<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Estimating Shadow Prices for Colombia in an&#13;
Input-Output Table Framework&#13;
SWP-357&#13;
;~~~~~. N.'&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No. 357&#13;
September 1979&#13;
Prepared by: Wolfgang W. Schohl&#13;
Latin America and the Caribbean Country Programs II Department&#13;
Latin America and the Caribbean Regional Office&#13;
Copyright © 1979&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D2C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
The views and interpretations in this document are those of the author&#13;
and should not be attributed to the World Bank, to its affiliated&#13;
organizations, or to any individual acting in their behialf.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The views and interpretations in this document are those of the author and&#13;
should not be attributed to the World Bank, to its affiliated organizations,&#13;
or to any individual acting in their behalf.&#13;
WORLD BANK&#13;
Staff Working Paper N° 357&#13;
September 1979&#13;
ESTIMATING SHADOW PRICES FOR COLOMBIA&#13;
IN AN INPUT-OUTPUT TABLE FRAMEWORK&#13;
The purpose of this paper is to explain the calculation of shadow&#13;
r- ices at the national level (so-called "National Accounting Prices") using&#13;
the so-called "Input-Output Table technique". In contrast to previous esti-&#13;
mates of shadow prices in World Bank work, which are limited to only a few&#13;
aggregate shadow prices for commodities and for labor, the new estimation&#13;
technique, herein applied to the Colombian economy, permits the easy calculation&#13;
of many more such prices. The larger set of pre-calculated National Accounting&#13;
Prices, derived on the basis of information contained in a country's Input-&#13;
Output Table, shonld save project economists' time while at the same time&#13;
improving appraisal results.&#13;
The Input-Output Approach as used here was mainly developed by a&#13;
research group in the "Interamerican Development Bank" in 1977. The present&#13;
paper follows largely this approach as far as efficiency pricing '.F concerned,&#13;
i.e., considering price distortions owing to export and import duties and&#13;
subsidies and distribution margins biased by them. In the case of sicial shadow&#13;
pricing, i.e., considering criteria of growth and income distribution, we follow&#13;
the approach developed by Lyn Squire and Herman G. van der Tak traditionally&#13;
used in World Bank work.&#13;
Prepared by: Wolfgang W. Schohl&#13;
Latin America and the Caribbean Country Programs II Department&#13;
Latin America and the Caribbean Regional Office&#13;
Copyright i 1979&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 2043. U.S..A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS&#13;
I am grateful to Mr. Jorge Tejada, who helped with all computational&#13;
work and valuable internal discussions, to Mr. Terry Powers and his team in the&#13;
"Interamerican Development Bank" who provided extensive conceptual help and&#13;
let us use his computer programs. I am particularly grateful to Mr. Alberto Favilla&#13;
who made the organizational arrangements to make this study possible; and to&#13;
Messrs. George GebharL and Fred Jaspersen who relieved me from many other duties&#13;
in ongoing country economic work. Also I am grateful to Messrs. Anandarup Ray&#13;
and Johannes Linn for valuable discussions on the methodology and clearness&#13;
of presentation; to Mr. John Holsen for helping to promote the use of the new&#13;
method in LAC Projects Department and to many other economists in the World&#13;
Bank for their comments on the draft paper. My thanks also go to Mr. Javier&#13;
Fernandez and his team of the National Planning Office (DNP) and various others&#13;
in Colombia who helped me shorten the time-consuming task of selecting the best&#13;
data for the study. It should, of course, be clear, that the specific methods&#13;
used and the results derived are my sole responsibility and do not necessarily&#13;
represent the views of all my collegues with whom I discussed them. Finally,&#13;
and by no means least, my thanks extend to Mrs. Lillian Ballivian and her&#13;
colleagues in Colombia Division, and to Mrs. Mary Brown and the LAC Word&#13;
Processing operators for their patience in the tedious task of typing and editing&#13;
the paper.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TABLE OF CONTENTS&#13;
Page No.&#13;
A.   Introduction. Summary and Table of Results&#13;
1.   Introduction ...............................   ...........        1&#13;
2.   Summary     ..................................................    3&#13;
3.   Summary of National Accounting Parameters for Colombia ...       18&#13;
B.   Conversion Factors for Sectors of the Input-Output Table&#13;
1.   The Input-Output Approach to Estimating Conversion Factors       24&#13;
2.   Deriving Weights for BPRs of the Traded Sectors ..........       29&#13;
3.   Deriving Border Price Ratios for Traded Sectors    ...........   30&#13;
4.   Efficiency Wage Analysis for Input-Output Table ..........       32&#13;
5.   Equations for Efficiency Wage Rate Ratios (EWRR) for&#13;
Non-Traded Sectors .....................................      34&#13;
a.   Unskilled  EWRR  ......................................    34&#13;
b.   S&amp;T-Skilled EWRR ....................................      37&#13;
c.   Academically-Skilled EWRR ...........................      41&#13;
d.   Resulting Vector of EWRRs for the Non-Traded Sectors       42&#13;
e.   Border-Pricing Other Primary Inputs ....       .............  42&#13;
6.   Border Price Ratios at Efficiency Prices for all Sectors..      43&#13;
7.   Multi-Sector-Conversion Factors and Their Meaning ........      49&#13;
8.   General Conversion Factors and Their Meaning .       ............  51&#13;
9.   How to use the Border Price Ratios in Project Appraisal ..      55&#13;
10.   Some Limitations of the Input-Output Approach ..     ..........  58&#13;
a. The problem of classification of input-output sectors&#13;
comprising goods with high and low tariffs ...........      58&#13;
b.  Partially traded goods ...............................       61&#13;
C.   General Efficiency Wage Rate Ratios&#13;
1.   Formulae and Assumptions Used in Efficiency Wage&#13;
Rate Ratios .......      .....................................  63&#13;
a.   EWRRUu for Urban Unskilled Workers        ..................  64&#13;
b.   EWRRru for Rural Unskilled Workers ....       ..............  65&#13;
2.   Special Assumptions Used in Basic Formulae on Efficiency&#13;
Wage Rate Ratios ...................  ....................     65&#13;
3.   Calculating Conversion Factors for the Marginal Product&#13;
of Labor ................      ...............................  70&#13;
4.   The Usefulness of Aggregate EWWRs ..........  ..    ............  74&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TABLE OF CONTENTS (Continued)&#13;
Page No.&#13;
D.   Conversion Factors at Social Prices&#13;
1.   Deriving Border Price Ratios for Traded Sectors ..........        75&#13;
2.   Social Wage Analysis for the Non-Traded Sectors ........   ..     75&#13;
3.   Unskilled Social Wage Rate Ratio .................   ........     76&#13;
4.   General Social Wage Rate Ratios .....      .....................  81&#13;
5.   Relationship between EWRRs and SWRRs in Colombia .........       82&#13;
6.   Differences between Conversion Factors for Commodities&#13;
at Efficiency and at Social Prices .....................       84&#13;
E.   The Opportunity Cost of Capital ..............................         86&#13;
F.   Social Pricing Parameters in Colombia&#13;
1.   The Consumption Rate of Interest       ......................    92&#13;
a.   The Rate of Pure Time Reference ( e ) .      ..............  92&#13;
b.   The Elasticity of Marginal Utility with Respect to&#13;
Consumption (n) ......      ......................  ......  93&#13;
c.   The Expected Growth of per Capita Consumption (g) ...       94&#13;
2.   The Consumption Distribution Weights (di) .....       ...........  94&#13;
3.   The Value of Public Income in Relation to Average&#13;
Consumption (v) ........................................       97&#13;
a.   Deriving the Marginal Propensity to Save (s) ........       97&#13;
b.   Deriving the Critical Consumption Level (CCL)      .......  100&#13;
c.   The Best Estimate of the Value of Public Income .....      101&#13;
4.   Accounting Rate of Interest (ARI) .........   ..    .............  102&#13;
ANNEXES&#13;
Annex 1: Methods Used for Estimating Conversion Factors in a&#13;
Trade-Data-Approach, and Reasons for Deviations from&#13;
Previous Estimates ....................................       104&#13;
Annex 2:   The Input-Output-Approach:   An Illustrative Example .....      109&#13;
Annex 3: Notes on the Input-Output-Tables Used and How to&#13;
Update  Them  ...........................................     122&#13;
Annex 4:   The Importance of Indirect Taxes and Subsidies ....     ......  125&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TABLE OF CONTENTS (Continued)&#13;
Page No.&#13;
Annex 5: General Notes on How to Obtain More Specific&#13;
Wage Rates in Colombia ................... . ............    127&#13;
Annex 6: The Extreme Lower Limit of the Opportunity Cost of Capital,&#13;
Estimated as Real Borrowing Rate from Commercial Banks       132&#13;
Annex 7:  Note on the Value of Public Income and Its Determinants .       135&#13;
Annex 8:  Note on the Estimation of the Opportunity Cost of Capital      139&#13;
Annex 9: How to Organize the Input-Output-Approach to Shadow&#13;
Pricing in World Bank Work .....       .......................  140&#13;
Annex 10: Detailed Definitions of the Sectors of the Colombian&#13;
Input-Output-Table ....................................      142&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
A.   INTRODUCTION, SUMMARY AND TABLE OF RESULTS&#13;
1.   Introduction&#13;
1.        Shadow pricing, as understood throughout this paper, is the&#13;
process of deriving the "true" prices of goods, services and productive&#13;
factors, by adjusting the market prices of cost and benefit items which&#13;
a project appraisal team would find in a country. The adjustment is&#13;
made for several distortions. These can be (a) of economic nature, such&#13;
as import duties, export taxes or subsidies, and indirect taxes of all&#13;
kinds, affecting goods and services which are an input into or an output&#13;
of a project; in the case of productive factors like labor, an economic&#13;
adjustment is made for imperfections in the labor markets.     An attempt is&#13;
made to measure the marginal output foregone of a worker in his "without-&#13;
the-project-employment", rather than the wage actually paid to the worker&#13;
in the project.   If there are, e.g., minimum wage laws that set wages&#13;
substantially higher than the marginal productivity of labor, such an&#13;
adjustment will become important. Adjustments of this kind are called&#13;
"economic" or, synonymously, "efficiency" shadow pricing.     Similarly,&#13;
"Shadow Pricing Parameters" are often, synonymously, called "Accounting&#13;
Parameters" or "Conversion Factors" in this and other studies. The main&#13;
thrust of this paper is on economic or efficiency pricing. The adjustment of&#13;
market prices may go further, however, and is then called (b) "social shadow&#13;
pricing, or simply "social pricing". It consists of two kinds of adjustments:&#13;
(1) The change in consumption of a poor man is generally given a higher weight&#13;
than the same change in consumption of a rich man derived from a project.&#13;
(2) Savings, investment and Government income are given some premium over&#13;
consumption in those countries, where investment levels and the provision of&#13;
public services are considered suboptimal.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-2-&#13;
2.        We use the term "shadow pricing" in the same way as done by&#13;
Squire and van der Tak in their book on the economic analysis of projects L1,&#13;
and as done in the basic book on project analysis by Little and Mirrless /2.&#13;
Our study basically uses the method and acronyms of Squire-van der Tak and&#13;
builds on thiem. For the sake of brevity, this paper does not explain the&#13;
fundamental theorems and definitions of the theory of shadow pricing. The&#13;
reader not familiar with the subject may, therefore, find it advisable&#13;
to get to know first the basic issues from Squire-van der tak, and a very&#13;
helpful illustration of the application of shadow pricing from J. Linn's&#13;
paper on the Ivory Coast .5, which includes various references to the&#13;
Squire-van der Tak book.&#13;
3.        In this paper we present the results of an efficiency and social&#13;
shadow .pricing exercise for Colombia. The exercise was first done in a&#13;
Stage I, which may be called a "Trade-Data-Approach" (T-D Approach) /4.&#13;
This is, within the Squire-van der Tak method, the approach most widely used&#13;
in the World Bank. It soon became obvious that this approach was not the&#13;
best one could do within reasonable time for a country like Colombia which&#13;
has relatively good statistics. Therefore, we tried to use what we call&#13;
an "Input-Output-Approach" (1-0 Approach) to deriving shadow prices for&#13;
/1   Squire, Lyn and van der Tak, Herman:   "Economic Analysis of Projects,"&#13;
LBRD, Johns Hopkins University Press, Baltimore and London, 1976.&#13;
/2   Little, J.M.D. and Mirrlees, J.A.:   "Proiect Appraisal and Plannin&amp;&#13;
for Developing Countries", New York, 1974.&#13;
/3   Linn, Johannes.   "Economic and Social Analysis of Projects:   A Case&#13;
Study of Ivory Coast". World Bank Staff Working Paper No. 253, p. 19.&#13;
/4   Described briefly in Annex 1.   More extensively illustrated in:   Bruce,&#13;
Colin: "Social Cost-Benefit Analysis: A Guide for Country and Project&#13;
Economists to the Derivation and ADP~'ication of Economic and Social&#13;
Accounting Prices, World Bank Staff Wc--king Paper No. 239, August 1976.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 3 -&#13;
commodities.  The basic di.ferences between the two methods are, in a very&#13;
short summary, the following:    - Trade Data Approach uses, as weights for&#13;
the rates of import duties and export subsidies (or taxes), the daca from&#13;
the trade balance only, rather than from an Input-Output-Ta3le. This leads&#13;
to certain distortions in the shadow prices for the so-called non-traded&#13;
sectors and in the so-called General Conversion Factors. In the Trade&#13;
Data Approach one simply "assumes away" the relevance of the non-traded&#13;
sectors. In the Input-Output-Approach, however, one can avoid these short-&#13;
comings. One may (a) readily derive shadow prices for many different sectors&#13;
of the economy, and (b) include the direct and indirect effects of protec-&#13;
tion on the Conversion Factors of typically non-traded goods and services.&#13;
4.        In this paper we present a relatively large set of shadow pricing&#13;
parameters for Colombia, estimated by the Input-Output Approach, and we&#13;
mnake a number of suggestions about:&#13;
-    how to use them efficiently and adequately;&#13;
-    how to improve the cooperation between country and&#13;
project economists in the field of shadow pricing; and&#13;
-    how to take advantage of existing computer routines in the&#13;
field of shadow pricing.&#13;
2.   Summary&#13;
5.        The following pages summarize the principal findings of the study,&#13;
following broadly the outline given in the table of contents, but focus-&#13;
sing on the use a project economist can make of the method and results of&#13;
the study.  Table I "Summary of National Accounting Parameters for Colombia'&#13;
at the end of this summary chapter, contains a list of all shadow pricing&#13;
parameters. In Part B of the paper we first explain the sequence of&#13;
calculating efficiency parameters by the 1-0-Approach. The broad steps are&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 4 -&#13;
(a) calculation of Conversion Factors for all traded sectors, by using data on&#13;
import duties and export taxes, classified by 31 1-0-Sectors; (b) calculation of&#13;
shadow prices for primary inputs, especially for labor, (c) calculation with&#13;
these inputs, through Input-Output-Matrix-techniques, of the Conversion Factors&#13;
for 9 sectors of the 1-0 Table which are considered non-traded; (d) iteration of&#13;
the process until the values of the CFs for non-traded sectors converge to a "best&#13;
value"; (e) derivation of "General Conversion Factors" and "Multi-Sector-Conversic&#13;
Factors."&#13;
The Pro's and Con's of the I-O-Approach to Shadow Pricing&#13;
6.        The main advantages of the I-0-Approach for calculating shadow prices&#13;
for commodities are the following: (a) the knowledge incorporated in a care-&#13;
fully done 1-0-Table can be used, and a country economist saves time for&#13;
other matters; 1-0-Tables in most less developed countries (LDCs) can be&#13;
expected to be created in the future where they do not exist yet; or will&#13;
probably regularly be updated and improved in countries where they exist&#13;
already. Therefore, the conversion factors can easily be updated when the&#13;
structure of an economy changes considerably; (b) the method allows to take&#13;
into account the impact of indirect inputs on the conversion factors of&#13;
non-traded sectors; (d) if an 1-0-Table is sufficiently well done and detailed&#13;
enough, conversion factors for many traded and non-traded sectors can readily&#13;
be calculated; also, they may easily be combined for any typical mix of inputs&#13;
which might go into a project. The malor disadvantage of the I-0-Approach is&#13;
the following: th-^ tables may be outdated and therefore only give a pseudo-&#13;
exact description of an economy; some updating of the tables can, however, be&#13;
done by relatively simple means with computer routines, starting from partial&#13;
data.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
7.        Additional benefits can be derived from a computerization of the&#13;
exercise of estimating National Accounting parameters. For the Input-Output-&#13;
Approach there already exists a computerized model in the Inter-American&#13;
Development Bank which both handles large matrices quickly, and aggregates&#13;
data on import and export values, on import duties, export subsidies, and&#13;
export taxes very easily, according to the classification of the I-0-sectors.&#13;
Therefore, two very important additional benefits accrue when one uses,&#13;
as done here, a computerized Input-Output-Approach: (a) any amount of&#13;
variants and sensitivity analyses can quickly be calculated; (b) similarly,&#13;
all national accounting parameters can be recalculated easily when a country&#13;
or project economist obtains additional data; e.g., on household propensities&#13;
to consume. Or if a country chooses to change its structure of import duties,&#13;
export subsidies or taxes etc. The model in its present form simply requires&#13;
some new entries into the data files which could be handled with a limited&#13;
number of computer commands on any of the Bank's terminals.&#13;
8.        One of the major conclusions of this study is, therefore, that the&#13;
I-0-Approach to Shadow Pricing should be used more often in World Bank work,&#13;
where 1-0-Tables are considered to be sufficiently well done.&#13;
Border Price Ratios for Traded Sectors of the Economy&#13;
9.        In section B.3 we derive "Border-Price-Ratios" (BPRs, i.e. a synonym&#13;
to Conversion Factors or Accounting Prices for commodities) for all 22 traded&#13;
sectors; i.e. sectors in which, if a project were implemented, on average, the&#13;
flow of imports and/or exports would change. The BPR's are the following&#13;
(Table A):&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 6 -&#13;
Table A: Border Price Ratios of Traded 1-0-Sectors. at Efficiency Prices&#13;
BPR with Petro-&#13;
BPR with High           leum Subsidies&#13;
Traded Sectors                        Petroleum Subsidies       Largely Removed L&#13;
1.   Agriculture                             .93&#13;
2.   Silviculture                             .93&#13;
3.   Fishing and hunting                     .92&#13;
4.   Mining                                 2.30                      1.44&#13;
5.   Coffee, processed                      1.21&#13;
6.   Meat                                    .90&#13;
7.   Cereal products                         .95&#13;
8.   Milk products                           .93&#13;
9.   Sugar                                  1.01&#13;
10.  Drinks                                  .66&#13;
11.  Tobacco, processed                      .92&#13;
12.  Other processed agriculture goods       .90&#13;
13.  Textiles, clothing and leather          .95&#13;
14.  Wood and wooden furniture              1.01&#13;
15.  Paper and printing                      .99&#13;
16.  Chemicals and rubber                    .89&#13;
17.  Refined petroleum                      3.00                      1.67&#13;
18.  Non-Metal products                      .94&#13;
19.  Metal products                          .89&#13;
20.  Machinery                               .86&#13;
21.  Transportation material                 .87&#13;
22.  Other manufactures                      .83&#13;
LI   Assuming that present subsidies on petroleum are reduced to 1/3 during&#13;
the next five years.&#13;
These figures were derived by taking into account: (a) trade distortions from&#13;
import duties, export taxes, and export subsidies; (b) distribution margins on&#13;
all goods, and their distortions; (c) indirect taxes and subsidies were&#13;
generally not taken into account because of data limitations, except in the&#13;
case of petroleum subsidies which are the most important subsidies. A project&#13;
economist must, tnerefore, assess for himself the amount of price distortions&#13;
for a sector or a product which come in through net indirect taxes/subsidies.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 7 -&#13;
10.       After Efficiency Wage Rates and a Standard Conversion Factor&#13;
(SCF) are calculated to border price the input of "Labor" and of "Interest,&#13;
Depreciation and Profits," respectively, into each of the non-traded sectors&#13;
(this is done in Chapters B.3-B.7), the BPRs of the nine non-traded sectors of&#13;
the economy are derived by input-output-matrix manipulation and iteration.&#13;
They are found to have the following values:&#13;
Table B: Border Price Ratios for Non-Traded 1-0 Sectors, at Efficiency Prices&#13;
BPR with Petro-&#13;
BPR with High              leum Subsidies&#13;
Non-Traded Sectors                    petroleum Subsidies         Largely Removed /&#13;
23.  Electricity, gas and water             1.10                        0.96&#13;
24.  Construction                           0.87                        0.84&#13;
25.  Commerce                               0.93                        0.90&#13;
26.  Transportation                         1.09                        0.96&#13;
27.  Communication                          0.83                        0.81&#13;
28.  Banking and insurance services         0.84                        0.84&#13;
29.  Housing Rental                         0.85                        0.86&#13;
30. Private services                        0.79                        0. 79&#13;
31. Public services                         0.76                        0.73&#13;
Li   Assuming that subsidies on petroleum are reduced to 1/3 during the next&#13;
five years.&#13;
Some sectors in the list of the 31 BPRs have remarkable results vhich are worth&#13;
mentioning: Sectors 4 and 17 reflect the traditionally high subsidy on crude&#13;
petroleum and gasoline. This affects the BPRs in the non-traded sectors&#13;
"electricity, gas and water" and "transportation" (Sectors 23 and 26) which&#13;
are large users of oil, and have thus BPRs around 1.10. The Government in&#13;
Colombia has taken steps to reduce these subsidies and announced that it will&#13;
continue to approximate Colombian petroleum prices to international levels.&#13;
If it proves realistic to assume that during the next years the subsidies can&#13;
be reduced to about 1/3 of their end 1977 levels, the second vector of BPRs in&#13;
Tables A and B should be used in proiect appraisal, which, for the non-traded&#13;
sectors, shows generally lower BPRs.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-8-&#13;
11.       Actually, the BPRc in Colombia show relatively little variance if&#13;
petroleum subsidies are removed. Also, they are not much under 1.0, i.e., net&#13;
import duties are not all too heavy. Finally, these BPRs should theoretically&#13;
not change very substantially since Colombia can modify her import duty and&#13;
export tax/subsidy structure only in coordination with her Andean Pact partners.&#13;
The Use of the Sectoral BPRs&#13;
12.       The 31 sectoral BPRs may be used:&#13;
(a) individually, for converting into foreign prices any single&#13;
minor input and/or output items in a project's final appraisal;&#13;
they may be even more valuable in case of preappraisal studies when&#13;
little time is available to obtain border prices directly which&#13;
mostly is a costly and time consuming task.&#13;
(b)  aggregated in the form of General Conversion Factors; they may&#13;
be applied to convert into border prices all highly aggregated&#13;
residuals of inputs and outputs which are not broken down further;&#13;
(c) they may be aggregated into what we may call "Multi-Sector-Conversion&#13;
Factors". Aggregates of this kind could, e.g., be made for all&#13;
sectors, like typically rural or urban sectors; of course they&#13;
would loose some specificity.&#13;
General Conversion Factors and Their Meanini&#13;
13.       General CFs were computed (in Chapter B.7) by taking weights largely&#13;
from the 1-0-Table.&#13;
(a) A set of marginal General Conversion Factors is calculated by weighing&#13;
each sector's BPR iith the ratio of the absolute change in expenditure that&#13;
took place within the corresponding sector between 1972 and 1975, over the&#13;
absolute change in expenditure on all sectors. Similarly, a set of average&#13;
General Conversion Factors is calculated by using the total expenditure&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 9 -&#13;
figures of each sector in 1975. The expenditure streams used are basically&#13;
the following and yield the corresponding General CFs:&#13;
(1) total intermediate and final demand (SCF);&#13;
(2) intermediate demand, i.e., raw materials and inter-&#13;
mediate goods (RMICF);&#13;
(3) total final consumption (CCF);&#13;
(4) public and private gross fixed investment (ICF).&#13;
The GCFs were also calculated (b) excluding the petroleum sectors altogether&#13;
in order to avoid considering distortions in petroleum subsidies in&#13;
sectors where there are none; and (c) in "social prices," i.e., basically:&#13;
using Social Wage Rate Ratios to border price labor inputs into the non-traded&#13;
sectors. In the case of Co;ou1 ia, the difference between marRinal and average&#13;
expenditure weights generally. are too small to matter; we, therefore, can&#13;
neglect them in practical work. The same is true for the difference between&#13;
social and efficiency GCFs.&#13;
14.       For the practical use of a project economist, we can, therefore,&#13;
limit ourselves to the list of most relevant GCFs presented on the following&#13;
page (the full set of GCFs is given in the Summary Table 1 at the end of&#13;
this Summary Chapter).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 10 -&#13;
Table C: General Conversion Factors for Practical Use&#13;
a          (SCF, Standard Conversion Factor, excluding&#13;
petroleum sectors)                                        =    0.93&#13;
aL         (SCF  , Standard Conversion Factor, including&#13;
ps        petpoleum sectors)                                             1.0&#13;
(CCF, Consumption Conversion Factor)                            0.93&#13;
ICF       (Investment Goods Conversion Factor)                            0.89&#13;
RMICF     (= RMICF , Conversion Factor for Raw Materials and&#13;
Intermediate Goods, excluding refined petroleum sector)        0.93&#13;
RMICF     (Conversion Factor for Raw Materials and Intermediate&#13;
Ps    Goods, including petroleum sectors)                            1.23&#13;
SERVCF    (Conversion Factor for all Services Sectors; this is&#13;
an example of a Multisector CF)                                0.82&#13;
1r        (RMPLCF, Conversion Factor for the Rural Marginal&#13;
Product of Labor)                                              0.93&#13;
iu       (UMPLCF, Conversion Factor for the Urban Marginal&#13;
Product of Labor)                                         a    0.88&#13;
1         (UMPLCF, Conversion Factor for the National Marginal&#13;
Product of Labor)                                              0.90&#13;
These GCFs should be used in the followinR way: In cases where neither&#13;
crude petroleum nor refined petroleum are significant in a group of miscella-&#13;
neous direct inputs into or outputs of a project, one should use the GCFs&#13;
which were calculated by excluding the petroleum sectors. Only where these&#13;
subsidized sectors make important direct contributions, should the SCFps and&#13;
RMICFpS be applied. 1/ The same is true for the calculation of Multi-Sector-&#13;
CFs: the second vector of BPRs in tables A and B should be used to calculate&#13;
Multi-Sector-CFs when sectors are concerned in which petroleum subsidies play&#13;
1/   These are mainly petroleum products themselves, or the sectors trans-&#13;
portation services, electricity, or fertilizers, either used as&#13;
miscellaneous project inputs themselves or being important indirect&#13;
inputs to other project inputs. In most cases this variant of the&#13;
General Conversion Factors will not apply.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 11 -&#13;
only a minor role or when it is expected that the subsidies will be&#13;
largely removed. The SERVCF was calculated including petroleum subsidies.&#13;
15.       Similar to the Multi-Sector-Conversion Factors, three so-called&#13;
'"arginal Product of Labor - CFs" were derived; however, employment was used&#13;
in each sector, rather than intermediate and/or final uses (see Chapter C.3.)&#13;
They are useful for the project economist to border price output foregone in&#13;
the context of deriving project specific Shadow Wage Rate Ratios. They are,&#13;
however, no substitute for the latter, but rather a special kind of Multi-&#13;
Sector-Conversion Factors.&#13;
Calculating Shadow Wage Rate Ratios&#13;
16.       In Chapter B.4 we had derived the Shadow Wage Rate Ratios (in efficiency&#13;
terms), for use within the I-0-Table calculations to derive the BPRs and GCFs.&#13;
Using similar general equations, we compute, in part C, four General Efficiency&#13;
Wage Rate Ratios (EWRRs). We specify rather carefully the formulae used and&#13;
assumptions made, because this type of shadow pricing is probably the most&#13;
important and sensitive to assumptions. Along with the presentation of our&#13;
methods for calculating both CFs for commodities and shadow wage rates, we aim&#13;
at demonstrating how improvements in the estimation of EWRRs can be made.&#13;
Also, we make suggestions how country and project economists can improve the&#13;
results by cooperating closely together. The formulae are stated in such a&#13;
way that a project economist can easily modify them for his specific purposes.&#13;
The complete set of EWRRs is listed in Summary Table 1, page 21.&#13;
17.       In Part D, we derive the corresponding sets of Social Wage Rate&#13;
Ratios (SWRRs), again both (a) for the non-traded sectors only, and to be used&#13;
in the I-0-Approach to derive our BPRs for Commodities, and (b) for the whole&#13;
economy.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 12 -&#13;
18.       Our results are summarized in the Summary Table 1, page 21.      In&#13;
general, SWRRs, as calculated here, are somewhat smaller than EWKRs, although&#13;
only by a small amount. The difference is somewhat bigger in the case of&#13;
urban unskilled labor (both across all sectors and for non-traded sectors&#13;
only), than for semi- and technically-skilled labor. This can mainly be&#13;
explained by the fact that the average income of unskilled urban labor is&#13;
somewhat lower than the Critical Consumption Level, although not very much /1.&#13;
It appears, therefore, that employing unskilled labor even in urban projects&#13;
becomes somewhat more attractive when a project is appraised in social terms,&#13;
than when appraised in efficiency terms. The same applies, of course, still&#13;
more to employing unskilled labor in rural projects.&#13;
19.       All Shadow Wage Rate Ratios have been derived under rather specific&#13;
conditions. Although they are differentiated by four skill-levels and many&#13;
sectors, they should be used cautiously taking into account the specific&#13;
assumptions and the limitations of their applicability.&#13;
The Opportunity Cost of Capital&#13;
20.        In Part E we calculate the Opportunity Cost of Capital (g) at border&#13;
prices, that is the cut-off economic internal rate of return below which projects&#13;
should not be executed. We adjust national accounts data and compare the result&#13;
in a strictly efficiency pricing context, (a) with what is considered the&#13;
cut-off rate for infrastructure projects in Colombia and (b) with the real&#13;
interest rate for public borrowing on international capital markets, which is&#13;
found to be around 3.5% (Annex 6). The compromise value of q recommended to be&#13;
used by Colombian planners in the medium term is 9%, whereas the rate actually&#13;
/1 For a more detailed explanation, see Chapter D.5 of main text.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 13 -&#13;
used is 11%, given their cautious policy on foreign borrowing. In a social&#13;
pricing context, this low real inerest rite of foreign borrowin, has to be&#13;
compared with the Accounting Rate of Interest (ARI - 6.3%), which also is well&#13;
above the borrowing rate. It appears that Colombian authorities, both in a&#13;
context of efficiency and of social pricing, are at present borrowing somewhat&#13;
less than optimally.&#13;
Basic Parameters for Social Shadow Pricing&#13;
21.       In Part F we derive the Basic Social Parameters, which we used here&#13;
as inputs into the Social Wage Rate Ratios and which should be used similarly&#13;
in all project appraisals in social terms. The methods used are exclusively&#13;
those of the Squire-van der Tak manual. We want to stress that all social&#13;
parameters are highly tentative because of the sometimes "heroic" assumptions&#13;
and the basic value judgements one has to make. They should be applied to&#13;
projects very cautiously and after consultation with the Colombian authorities.&#13;
22.       The best estimate for the Consumption Rate of Interest (i), used to&#13;
discount consumption streams, is found to be around 5.5%. This is based on&#13;
the assumptions that the Pure Rate of Time Preference is about e - 2%, and&#13;
that the elasticity of marginal utility with respect to consumption changes&#13;
n - 1.0. The expected growth of per capita consumption (g) is 3.5% p. a. in&#13;
the next 5 years.&#13;
23.       The Consumption Distribution Weights (di) are specified by deciles&#13;
for small changes in consumption, and again assuming n - 1.0, as shown in&#13;
Table 1, page 22. The average consumption c, derived from national accounts&#13;
data, is estimated to be around Col$ 15,800 in 1976 prices.&#13;
24.       With these background parameters, the Social Value of Public Income in&#13;
Relation to Average Consumption (v) is estimated. This is a parameter expressing&#13;
how much more valuable savings and investment are to the planner than private&#13;
consumption. Our best high estimate of v was 3.19, and our best low estimate was&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 14 -&#13;
2.13.  To arrive at a best center estimate, we calculated the Critical Consump-&#13;
tion Level (CCL) from data on tax-free income permitted by tax legislation, at&#13;
around Col$6,670 in 1976 current pesos. This figure is found to be roughly&#13;
consistent with independent estimates on the Relative and Absolute Poverty&#13;
Levels. About 38% of the total Colombian population fall under this CCL, and&#13;
a consumer at this level, can consume only about 42% of what the average&#13;
consumer can afford. With these inputs, our best center estimate for the&#13;
Social Value of Public Income is about v - 2.5.&#13;
25.       Finally, the Accounting Rate of Interest (ARI), used to discount all&#13;
future net benefits in a social appraisal context, is calculated to be ARI =&#13;
6.3%. If this cut-off rate is compared with the real interest rate for&#13;
borrowing abroad, which is 3.5%, it appears that even in social pricing,&#13;
Colombian planners could theoretically still increase their investment budgets.&#13;
Summary of Annexes&#13;
26.       Various annexes are attached to the main text of which the more&#13;
important ones are summarized below. Annex 1 demonstrates for what reasons&#13;
and to what extent National Accounting Parameters may vary when calculated via&#13;
the Trade-Data Approach, rather than an I-0-Approach. The results are&#13;
not greatly different when subsidies in the petroleum sectors are not taken&#13;
into account, and when, in the T-D-Approach, coffee is omitted. 1/ If the&#13;
coffee sector had received its full weight in exports rather than its weight&#13;
in total intermediate and/or final uses, the values of the SCFs and CCFs would&#13;
differ substantially between the two approaches.&#13;
27.       In Annex 4 the importance of adjustments for iadirect taxes and&#13;
subsidies is pointed out. Annex 5 explains how to obtain more specific&#13;
Shadow Wage Rates in Colombia, in conjunction with formulae and data given&#13;
1/   See Table 1, page 20.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 15 -&#13;
in the main text. In Annex 9 we make some suggestions on how the Input-Output-&#13;
Approach to shadow pricing could be or0anized in World Bank Work. Arnrex 10&#13;
lists the detailed definitions of all sectors of the Colombian Inp .-Ovutput-Table.&#13;
General Conclusions on the Value of Extensive Shadow Pricing Exercises&#13;
28.       On the whole efficiency pricing with the Input-Output-Approach&#13;
should be a useful tool both for the World Bank and the Colombian Government.&#13;
This is particularly so:&#13;
(a) if the exercise is considered a continuous process with relatively&#13;
frequent updating and recalculations;&#13;
(b) if country economists explain their assumptions and shortcut&#13;
procedures in a very detailed way to the project economists&#13;
who use them;&#13;
(c) if country, sector, and project economists in the World Bank,&#13;
and more so, if Colombian planning economists all work together&#13;
in the task of refinement and updating the conversion factors;&#13;
and&#13;
(d) if country economists are assigned more time than they usually&#13;
have or, even better, assistance through a specialized central&#13;
unit when doing their shadow pricing estimates.&#13;
29.       In order to facilitate the use of the I-0-approach it seems useful&#13;
to expand, at a later stage, that part of this paper, which deals with the&#13;
calculation steps used here, into a short manual, which would be detailed and&#13;
explicit enough to be easily readable by project economists from all back-&#13;
grounds, both in the World Bank and eventually in Colombia. The manual would&#13;
include instructions for handling the computer model which was used to calculate&#13;
the Border Price Ratios.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
16 -&#13;
30.        On Social Pricing, however, some work still needs to be done within&#13;
the World Bank in order to make social appraisals more acceptable. On the&#13;
one hand, some more standardization of the definitions and understandings of&#13;
such subjective parameters as the elasticity of marginal utility (n), and&#13;
the Rate of Pure Time Preference    e) could help to improve inter-country&#13;
comparisons of project appraisals.&#13;
31.       On the other hand, the amount of data necessary to be examined&#13;
and incorporated to arrive at a "solid" estimate of some of the basic&#13;
social parameters like "v" or "ARI", is often beyond the means of a country&#13;
economist. Therefore, a consultant or a centralized World Bank unit might&#13;
look, with more time than a country economist normally has, into the bases&#13;
for the calculation of the social parameters (see suggestions in Annex 7).&#13;
32.        In the case of Colombia, more work could be done in the following&#13;
fields. In discussions with Colombian planning authorities, one might&#13;
discuss what, in the light of the low rate of interest on foreign borrowing,&#13;
a feasible "optimal" size of the budget would be. More information should&#13;
be obtained on subsidy and tax policies and the main tax and subsidy&#13;
rates, and the implications of some of the shadow pricing parameters on&#13;
investment, tax and subsidy policies might be discussed. Finally, one&#13;
should get more information about income distribution data, consumer&#13;
surveys for both the urban and the rural population, and alternative sources&#13;
for approximating the Critical Consumption Level.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 17 -&#13;
Notes on Some Limitations of the Svr '.&#13;
33.       Some limitations of t-a I-O Approach are described ir ,hapter B.10.&#13;
They relate basically to the problem of classification of the I-O Table.&#13;
Since the table has been set up for purposes other than shadow pricing, some&#13;
distortions in the BPR's are unavoidable, especially in import substitution&#13;
sectors. The only way out would have been further disaggregation and reclassi-&#13;
fication, which, of course, would have increased manpower inputs for the&#13;
study.&#13;
34.       Also, if more time had been available, more could have been done&#13;
to determine the opportunity cost of capital in Colombia by alternative&#13;
approaches. Estimating the OCC from lending interest rates is not possible&#13;
in the case of Colombia because interest rates are all administered and were&#13;
often negative in real terms in recent years. Data on interest rates in the&#13;
"black" market are not available. A relatively promising approach would have&#13;
been to estimate economic rates of return on recent public sector projects,&#13;
and in various industrial sectors. However, to get a large enough and&#13;
representative sample of projects, considerable survey work seems to have been&#13;
necessary.&#13;
35.       Other possibilities for further refinement and a number of caveats&#13;
on the use of the parameters are noted in the text of the paper. In the&#13;
course of the study it became increasingly apparent that shadow pricing&#13;
is a field of economics with much room for improvement. Moreover, whenever&#13;
one tries to estimate national parameters, one has to sacrifice valuable&#13;
detailed information. As is the case with all statistics, working with means&#13;
only makes sense if one has a notion that the dispersion around the mean&#13;
is not "very" large. A project economist should have enough time to decide&#13;
in each individual case what "very" means in this context.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 18 -&#13;
Table I&#13;
Page 1 of 6&#13;
Table 1: SUMMARY OF NATIONAL ACCOUNTING PARAMETERS FOR COLOMBIA&#13;
1.   Border Price Ratios of 1-0-Sectors, at Efficiencv Prices&#13;
BPR with Petro-&#13;
BPR with High              leum Subsidies&#13;
Traded Sectors                         Petroleum Subsidies          Largely Removed /1&#13;
1.   Agriculture                             0.93&#13;
2.   Silviculture                            0.93&#13;
3.   Fishing and hunting                     0.92&#13;
4.   Mining                                  2.30                          1.44&#13;
5.   Coffee, processed                       1.21&#13;
6.   Meat                                    0.90&#13;
7.   Cereal products                         0.95&#13;
8.   Milk products                           0.93&#13;
9.   Sugar                                   1.01&#13;
10.  Drinks                                  0.66&#13;
11.  Tobacco, processed                      0.92&#13;
12.  Other processed agriculture goods       0.90&#13;
13.  Textiles, clothing and leather          0.95&#13;
14.  Wood and wooden furniture               1.01&#13;
15.  Paper and printing                      0.99&#13;
16.  Chemicals and rubber                    0.89&#13;
17.  Refined petroleum                       3.00                          1.67&#13;
18.  Non-metal products                      0.94&#13;
19.  Metal products                          0.89&#13;
20.  Machinery                               0.86&#13;
21.  Transportation material                 0.87&#13;
22.  Other manufactures                      0.83&#13;
Non-traded Sectors&#13;
23.  Electricity, gas and water              1.10                          0.96&#13;
24.  Construction                            0.87                          0.84&#13;
25.  Commerce                                0.93                          0.90&#13;
26.  Transportation                          1.09                          0.96&#13;
27.  Communication                           0.83                          0.81&#13;
28.  Banking and insurance services          0.84                          0.84&#13;
29.  Housing Rental                          0.85                          0.86&#13;
30.  Private services                        0.79                          0.79&#13;
31.  Public services                         0.76                          0.73&#13;
/1   Assuming that present subsidies on petroleum are reduced to 1/3 during&#13;
the next five years.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 19 -&#13;
Table 1&#13;
Page 2 of 6&#13;
2.   Efficiency Parameters (Input-Output-Table Approach)&#13;
a  -=SCF       (Standard Conversion Factor, Intermediate and&#13;
1      1      Final Uses, Average Weights Excluding Petroleum)          0.92&#13;
a2 =SCF        (Standard Conversion Factor, Final Uses, Average&#13;
2      2      Weights, Excluding Petroleum)                              0.92&#13;
a3= SCF3       (Average SCF + Urban Marginal Product of Labor&#13;
Conversion Factor)                                        0.94&#13;
a4= SCF4       (Standard Conversion Factor, Intermediate and&#13;
Final Uses, Average Weights Including petroleum)          0.98&#13;
a5= SCF5       (Standard Conversion Factor, Intermediate and Final Uses,&#13;
Marginal Weights, Including Petroleum)                    1.01&#13;
S  = CCF       (Consumption Conversion Factor, Marginal Weights&#13;
I  I   From I-O-Table)                                           0.94&#13;
2 = CCF2       (Consumption Conversion Factor, Marginal Weights&#13;
From Urban Consumer Survey)                               0.91&#13;
3 = CCF3       (Consumption Conversion Factor, Average Weights&#13;
From I-0-Table)                                           0.92&#13;
ICF1           (Investment Goods Conversion Factor, Marginal Weights)     0.91&#13;
ICF2           (Investment Goods Conversion Factor, Average Weights)      0.87&#13;
RMICF1          (Raw Materials and Intermediate Goods Conversion&#13;
Factor, Marginal Weights, Including Subsidized&#13;
Petroleum Sectors)                                        1.23&#13;
RMICF2          (Raw Materials and Intermediate Goods Conversions&#13;
Factor, Marginal Weights, Excluding Refined Petroleum)    0.93&#13;
SERVCF          (Conversion Factor for all Services Sectors)               0.82&#13;
RMPLCF          (Rural Marginal Product of Labor Conversion Factor)        0.93&#13;
UMPLCF          (Urban Marginal Product of Labor Conversion Factor)       0.88&#13;
NMPLCF          (National Marginal Product of Labor Conversion Factor)    0.90&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 20 -&#13;
Table I&#13;
Page 3 of 6&#13;
3.   Parameters Calculated in Trade Data Approach (Stage I) as Compared to&#13;
Input-Output-Approach (Stage II)&#13;
Trade        Input-&#13;
Data       Output&#13;
Approach    Approach&#13;
aL5         (SCF5, Standard CF, Including  Petroleum)                 1.01&#13;
a           (SCF1, Standard CF, Excluding Petroleum)      0.90        0.92&#13;
a           (CCF, Consumption Conversion Factor)          0.89        0.94&#13;
ICF        (Investment Conversion Factor)                 0.86        0.91&#13;
RMICF       (Raw Materials and Intermediate Goods CF&#13;
Including Petroleum)                        0.93 _       1.23&#13;
RMICF2      (Raw Materials and Intermediate Goods CF&#13;
Excluding Refined Petroleum)                             0.93&#13;
4.   Selected General Conversion Factors at Social Prices /2&#13;
Social   Efficienc&#13;
Prices     Prices&#13;
*3          (SCF3, Average SCF + Marginal Product of Labor&#13;
Conversion Factor)                                      0.94      0.94&#13;
*5          (SCF5, Standard Conversion Factor Including&#13;
Subsidized Petroleum Sectors)                           1.01      1.01&#13;
CCF1 (Consumption Conversion Factor)                    0.94      0.94&#13;
ICF  (Investment Conversion Factor)                    0.91       0.91&#13;
1&#13;
RMICF   (Raw Materials and Intermediate Goods&#13;
1   Conversion Factor, Including Petroleum)       1.22       1.23&#13;
RMICF2  (Raw Materials and Intermediate Goods CF,&#13;
Excluding Refined Petroleum)                   0.93      0.93&#13;
/1   Excluding construction in Trade Data Approach.&#13;
/2   For most General Conversion Factors, discrepancies between social&#13;
and efficiency pricing are unimportantly small; therefore, only a few&#13;
are shown here for illustration.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 21 -&#13;
Table 1&#13;
Page 4 of 6&#13;
5.   Shadow WaRe Rate Ratios at Efficiency and Social Prices&#13;
Type of Labor&#13;
(1)  Urban Unskilled Labor&#13;
in Non-traded Sectors                      EWRRui         SWRRLi&#13;
Electricity, gas and water                  0.66           0.61&#13;
Construction                                 0.72          0.68&#13;
Commerce                                    0.79           0.75&#13;
Transport                                    0.54          0.50&#13;
Communications                              0.54           0.50&#13;
Banks, insurance                            0.69           0.66&#13;
Other private services                       0.47          0.46&#13;
Public services                             0.47           0.46&#13;
(2)  Semi- and Technically Skilled&#13;
Labor in Non-traded Sectors                EWRR-i         SWRR5j&#13;
Electricity, gas and water                  0.81    )&#13;
Construction                                0.78    )&#13;
Commerce                                    0.75    )     assumed&#13;
Transport                                   0.71    )     the same&#13;
Communications                              0.71    )     as EWRRs&#13;
Banks, insurance                            0.68    )&#13;
Other private services                      0.74    )&#13;
Public services                             0.74    )&#13;
(3)  All Labor in Non-traded Sectors            EWRRnt.i      SWRRnt,i&#13;
Electricity, gas and water                  0.83           0.83&#13;
Construction                                0.78           0.76&#13;
Commerce                                     0.76          0.75&#13;
Transport                                    0.71          0.71&#13;
Communications                              0.71           0.71&#13;
Banks, insurance                            0.81           0.81&#13;
Other private services                       0.66          0.65&#13;
Public services                             0.66           0.65&#13;
(4)  Labor Across All Sectors,                 General        General&#13;
by Type of Skill                           EWRRs           SWRRs&#13;
Rural unskilled (EWRRuU)                    0.58           0.46&#13;
Urban unskilled (EWRRru)                   0.59            0.55&#13;
Urban semi and&#13;
technically skilled (EWRR.t.)              0.68           0.68&#13;
Academically skilled (EWRRas)              0.94            0.94&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 22. -&#13;
Table 1&#13;
Page 5 of 6&#13;
6.   Other Parameters Calculated&#13;
q     (Opportunity Cost of Capital at Border Prices)           0.11&#13;
i     (Consumption Rate of Interest)                           0.055&#13;
v     (Social Value of Public Income Relative to&#13;
Consumption)                                             2.5&#13;
ARI   (Accounting Rate of Interest)                            0.063&#13;
d     (Distribution Weight for Urban Receptors at&#13;
mean consumption level of Col$7,922)                     1.99&#13;
d     (Distribution Weight for Urban Employed, at&#13;
mean consumption level of Col$6,379)                     2.52&#13;
d     (Distribution Weight for Unemployed Urban Unskilled&#13;
uu Workers at mean consumption level of Col$5,379&#13;
per capita)                                              2.94&#13;
7.   Consumption Distribution Weights (d )&#13;
Percentage      Average per Capita            Marginal&#13;
Population            of Total       Consumption in Each         Distribution&#13;
Percentile           Consumption     Percentile Group, ci           Weight&#13;
(x)                               (1976 Current Pesos)          (n - 1.0)&#13;
Lowest 10               1.61                 2,563                   6.16&#13;
20              2.59                 4,107                    3.85&#13;
30              3.54                 5,599                    2.85&#13;
40              4.39                 6,951                    2.27&#13;
50              4.80                 7,603                    2.08&#13;
60              6.24                 8,876                    1.60&#13;
70              7.66                12,132                    1.30&#13;
80             10.48                16,601                    0.95&#13;
90              17.75               28,112                    0.56&#13;
100             40.93                64,827                    0.24&#13;
= 100          c   15,798  % 15,800&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 23 -&#13;
Table 1&#13;
Page 6 of 6&#13;
8.   Observed Parameters Used in Calculations /1&#13;
kI&amp;lasticity of Marginal Utility with&#13;
Respect to Consumption)                                  1.0 (assumed)&#13;
(Pure Rate of Time Preference)                          0.02 (assumed)&#13;
s        (Project Semi- and Technically-skilled Wage Rate)        60,127&#13;
u        (Project Unskilled Wage Rate for Urban Areas)            23,765&#13;
Wr         (Rural Average Wage Rate)                               14,616&#13;
Wm         (Rural Minimum Wage Rate)                               10,179&#13;
ue        (Per Capita Consumption of the Urban Unemployed)         5,046 (assumed)&#13;
Ya         (Per Capita Consumption of the Rural Population)         4,714.8&#13;
Er         (Employment Rate in Rural Areas)                         0.89&#13;
M          (Urban Labor Force i Urban Employed)                      1.15&#13;
Y          (Number of People Living on one Income, in Rural Areas) 3.1&#13;
e1         (Number of People Living on one Income, in Urban Areas) 3.5&#13;
2         (Number of Persons Living on one Income, in&#13;
Urban Areas, at CCL)                                      3.0&#13;
g          (Growth Rate of per Capita Income)                        0.035&#13;
s          (Marginal Propensity to Save out of Public&#13;
Project Yields;                                           0.25&#13;
c          (Per Capita Consumption national average)                15,800&#13;
CCL         (Critical per Capita Consumption Level)                  6,670&#13;
CCL/-       (CCL as percent of average consumption)                 42%&#13;
C&#13;
/1   All wage and consumption data are in 1976 current pesos.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 24 -&#13;
B.   CONVERSION FACTORS FOR SECTORS OF THE INPUT-OUTPUT TABLE&#13;
1.   The Input-Output-Approach to Estimating Conversion Factors&#13;
36.       The method used for the calculations of the Conversion Factors is&#13;
basically a computerized "Input-Output Table Approach" as developed by the&#13;
Inter-American Development Bank (IDB). /1    Where we develop our own equations&#13;
in the field of shadow wage rates, we follow largely the Squire-van der Tak-book,&#13;
thereby combining the two methods. For all other shadow pricing parameters,&#13;
too, we basically follow the Squire-van der Tak methods.&#13;
37.       In the 1-0-Approach, advantage is taken of the existence of an&#13;
Input-Output Table to calculate, by means of an iterative process, a number of&#13;
Conversion Factors for the non-traded sectors, plus the usual General Conver-&#13;
sion Factors, e.g. the Standard Conversion Factor or the Consumption Conversion&#13;
Factor. This is based on the assumption that a carefully set up Input-Output&#13;
Table gives more representative values of a sector's, e.g., transportation's,&#13;
typical input coefficients, than a quick analysis of a small sample of key&#13;
transport enterprises could yield. Also the expenditure weights used to&#13;
derive General Conversion Factors are readily available through the Input-&#13;
Output-Table.&#13;
38.       The advantages of the method, once one has decided to incur the&#13;
bigger initial costs, are the following: (a) the knowledge incorporated&#13;
in a carefully done Input-Output-Table can be used, and time saved for other&#13;
matters; 1-0-Tables in most LDCs can be expected to be created in the near&#13;
future where they do not exist yet; or will probably regularly be updated&#13;
/I   IDB, "Pilot Study on National Accounting Parameters, Their Estimation&#13;
and use in Chile, Costa Rica and Jamaica," Economic and Social Develop-&#13;
ment Department, October 1977. The approach is explained in detail&#13;
there, and we will limit ourselves here to a short overview in Chapter&#13;
B.1.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 25 -&#13;
and improved in countries where they exist already. LI Therefore, the conver-&#13;
sion factors can easily be updated when the structure of an economy changes&#13;
considerably; (b) the method allows one to take into account the impact of&#13;
indirect inputs on the conversion factors of non-traded sectors; (c) if an&#13;
I-0-Table is sufficiently well done and detailed enough, conversion factors&#13;
for many traded and non-traded sectors can readily be calculated; also, they&#13;
may easily be combined for any typical mix of inputs which might go into a&#13;
project.&#13;
39.       The maior disadvantages of the I-0-Approach are the following:&#13;
(a) the tables must be kept updated or they give a pseudo-exact&#13;
description of an economy; some updating can, however, be done&#13;
by relatively simple means (see Annex 3).&#13;
(b) the sectoral classification, into which the country's 1-0-Table&#13;
breaks the economy down, may not be the best for the purpose of&#13;
shadow pricing for project evaluation. For appraising agricultural&#13;
projects, for instance, the agricultural sector should often be&#13;
split into subsectors reflecting the main crops. (This also&#13;
applies for the Colombian 1-0-Table.) This is the reason why&#13;
some authors /2 prefer to construct their own highly disaggregated&#13;
I-0-Table, "tailor made" from agricultural and industrial surveys,&#13;
for the use in development projects. They enlarge those sectors&#13;
of a nationwide 1-0-Table which supply major inputs into or which&#13;
/1   Some institutions, like the University of Bradford, England, have large&#13;
collections of Input-Output-Tables for as many as 80 countries.&#13;
12   E.g. Scott, M.F.G.:   "Accounting Prices for Goods and Services in Kenya",&#13;
Oxford, 1972.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 26 -&#13;
represent major outputs of typical projects, and/or contain strong&#13;
trade distortions in them; and they may aggregate other sectors&#13;
which do not have these characteristics.&#13;
40.       Normally, country economists in the World Bank, however, do not&#13;
have the time to follow this procedure.   The second best solution is, there-&#13;
fore, to use the most up-to-date and disaggregated I-0-Table available,&#13;
calculate the BPRs for all sectors, and then (1) aggregate some less important&#13;
sectors (like in our calculations, a "Multi-Sector Conversion Factor".for all&#13;
services); and (2) disaggregate, with additional information from special&#13;
I-0-surveys or balance sheets on costs and revenues, those sectors which are&#13;
not sufficiently detailed yet.&#13;
41.       Finally, there is, in the I-0-Table approach of either form, an&#13;
inherent danger of "over-using" the numerous sectoral conversion factors in a&#13;
specific project. A project economist could, for lack of time, try to avoid&#13;
to a certain extent "direct pricing" of important project inputs and outputs&#13;
and use instead the ones derived by the nationwide 1-0-Table. To prevent&#13;
this, he should consider carefully to what extent the sectoral CFs can be&#13;
usefully applied to his project's cost and benefit items and make sure he uses&#13;
the complete list classifying which goods and services each sector of the&#13;
I-0-Table comprises. /I&#13;
42.       Additional benefits derive from a computerization of the exercise&#13;
of estimating National Accounting parameters. For the Input-Output-Approach&#13;
there already exists a computerized model in the Inter-American Development&#13;
Bank which both handles large matrices quickly, and easily aggregates data,&#13;
(1) on import and exrort values, and (2) on import duties, export subsidies&#13;
L/   Some useful comments in this regard may be found in Annex 4 "How to&#13;
use the Border Price Ratios in Project Appraisal"; the list of&#13;
definitions of the sectors is attached in Annex 10.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 27 -&#13;
and export taxes, according to the classification of the I-0-sectors.&#13;
Therefore, two very important additional benefits accrue when one uses,&#13;
as done here, a computerized Input-Output-Approach: (a) any amount of&#13;
variants and sensitivity analyses can be quickly calculated; (b) similarly,&#13;
all national accounting parameters can be recalculated easily and universally,&#13;
when additional data become available; e.g., on household propensities to&#13;
consume; or when a country changes its import duties, export subsidies or&#13;
taxes. The model, in its present form, simply requires some new entries&#13;
into the data files which could be handled with a limited number of computer&#13;
commands on any of the Bank's terminals.&#13;
43.       The Input-Output-Approach used here may conveniently be broken&#13;
down into about 10 steps. 1/ To begin, (1) the 1-0-sectors are initially&#13;
separated into traded and non-traded sectors and then into importable and&#13;
exportable parts of each traded sector. (2) Border price ratios (BPKs) 2/,&#13;
defined as the "international price divided by the domestic price of a goc'.,"&#13;
are then calculated for all traded sectors. (3) In addition, conversion&#13;
factors for converting domestic prices of primary inputs to border prices are&#13;
calculated. (4) The 1-0-Table is then used to derive direct-input coefficients&#13;
into each of the non-traded sectors.&#13;
1/   For readers not familiar with this method it may be very helpful to&#13;
consult the IDB report mentioned above, especially Volume I, pages&#13;
18 through 24. For the convenience of the reader we have reprinted,&#13;
in Annex 2, an illustrative example of the calculation steps taken from&#13;
the abovementioned report, pages 276 through 283.&#13;
2/   This is another wording for "Conversion Factors," mainly used to dis-&#13;
tinguish "individual conversion factors" of one sector from composite&#13;
conversion factors, which comprise several sectors.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- Lb -&#13;
44.        (5) The resulting set of equations are solved to yield both direct&#13;
and indirect input coefficients of all sectors into the non-traded sectors.&#13;
This is done by taking the Leontief Inverse of the submatrix of input coeffi-&#13;
cients from non-traded into the non-traded sectors, and premultiplying it with&#13;
the matrix of direct input coefficients from traded and primary sectors into&#13;
the non-traded sectors. (6) The resulting matrix of the direct plus indirect&#13;
coefficients is then multiplied by the vector of BPRs of the traded and&#13;
primary sectors, to yield the BPRs of each of the non-traded sectors.&#13;
45.        (7) To the extent that any of the "traded BPRs" or the "primary&#13;
input BPRs" were estimated with the help of any of the "non-traded BPRs,"&#13;
or if they contain any of the General Conversion Factors, they must be&#13;
recalculated in an iterative process. (8) This in turn requires reesti-&#13;
mation of the non-traded BPRs. This process is continued until the&#13;
"non-traded BPRs" converge.    (9) Then, by multiplying the expenditure vectors&#13;
from the 1-0-Table used as weights with the corresponding BPRs of each 1-0&#13;
category, it is possible to derive the General Conversion Factors. (10) Using&#13;
employment data, we may also derive what we call "Marginal Product of Labor&#13;
Conversion Factors."&#13;
46.       The steps of calculation and estimation are described largely&#13;
in this order in the following chapters. More time, relatively, is spent&#13;
on step (3), the derivation of the most important border price for primary&#13;
inputs, namely on the Shadow Wage Rates (in Chapters B.4 and B.5). This&#13;
is so because the equations used here also apply later to the General Shadow&#13;
Wage Rate Ratios (estimated in Part C), and because some new ways are tried&#13;
of estimating these in the Input-Output-Approach. Also, the data used are&#13;
described at some length so that a project economist can judge if they apply&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 29 -&#13;
in his case. Relatively little is said here about those steps which involve&#13;
basically standard computations (steps 4 through 8) because they are described&#13;
sufficiently in the IDB Research Paper mentioned above.&#13;
2.   Deriving Weights for BPRs of the Traded Sectors (Step 1)&#13;
47.       The 1972 I-0 table which we use consists of 31 sectors, 22 of which&#13;
were conside lJ traded and 9 non-traded /1. The separation into traded and&#13;
non-traded sectors was done by (1) inspection of the historical relative size&#13;
of exports and imports in gross value of production of each sector, and (2) by&#13;
considering indicators of capacity utilization, by which we tried to estimate&#13;
the likelihood that future public sector projects will change exports or&#13;
imports produced by, or used in, future public sector projects.&#13;
48.       For the calculation of Border Price Ratios, it is ideally required&#13;
to distinguish clearly between those sectors which are, at the margin. /2&#13;
importables, and those which are, at the margin, exportables. However,&#13;
most traded sectors of an I-0-Table represent fairly large aggregates of goods,&#13;
both importable and exportable, at the margin. Therefore, we calculated&#13;
a weight for each imported and each exported part of the traded share of&#13;
each sector's gross value. Using changes in imports of each sector between&#13;
1974 and 1976 and relating them to the change in boch imports and exports&#13;
in this sector, we obtained a weight for the imported part of a traded&#13;
sector; similarly, such a weight was calculated for the exported part.&#13;
/I The 1972 table is the latest available table which Departamento Adminis-&#13;
trativo Nacional de Estadisticas (DANE) has released. The flows are&#13;
expressed in purchasers prices. For details, see Annex 3.&#13;
/2   i.e., if one specific project is implemented and requires or produces&#13;
imports or exports of a certain commodity group.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 30 -&#13;
49.       Whenever one of these marginal trade weights within a sector&#13;
was below 0.10, it was considered negligible and thus, not taken into&#13;
account.   For the sectors "mining" (4) and "other processed agricultural&#13;
goods" (12), the average 1976 trade weights were used instead of marginal&#13;
ones because they seemed to be more representative of the future.&#13;
3.   Deriving Border Price Ratios for Traded Sectors (Step 2)&#13;
50.       The BPRs for the traded sectors, which are the adjusted ratios&#13;
of the c.i.f. - (for importables) or the f.o.b. (for exportables) price&#13;
over the domestic price, were estimated using the formula below:&#13;
Import    1 + D (BPR          Export  1- D (BPR)&#13;
BPR.          TiTrade        m           +  Trade &#13;
2.  ~   Weight    1    m+Dm            Wih          x   Dm]&#13;
where&#13;
1 + D  (BPR D)&#13;
I + t + D            is the BPRi of the marginally imported part&#13;
m    m&#13;
of each sector, and&#13;
1 - D   (BPRDm)      is the BPRi of the marginally exported part&#13;
m      Ur&#13;
1-t x-D m            of each sector&#13;
Dm         =     distribution margin of sector i in domestic prices (expressed&#13;
in % of gross value of sector i)&#13;
tm         =     import tariff rate of sector i, as % of peso import value of&#13;
each sector, before import tariff is levied&#13;
tx               export tax rate of sector i (negative tx implies subsidy), as&#13;
% of peso export value of each sector, before export tax is&#13;
levied&#13;
BPRDm             the BPR of the commercial sector (25)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 31 -&#13;
51.       Indirect taxes or subsidies were not taken into account in this&#13;
formula because adequate data fitting the 31 sectors of the I-0-Table were&#13;
not available, an exception is made with the important net subsidies in the&#13;
petroleum sectors. A project economist must, therefore, adjust additionally&#13;
for net indirect taxes if they are of importance. How to do this best is&#13;
further discussed in Chapter B.9 and in Annex 4. /I&#13;
52.       The distribution margin may be interpreted as the additional&#13;
expenditure of distributing domestically a marginal unit of a traded good.&#13;
The 1-0-Table used is expressed in purchasers' prices; therefore, one&#13;
should consider the distribution margins when border pricing. It also&#13;
follows that the Dm must be added to the price of imports and subtracted&#13;
from the price of exports in order to have the border prices reflect the&#13;
appropriate opportunity cost of importing and/or exporting.&#13;
53.       In general, the BPRs were calculated using 1976 DANE trade data&#13;
fitting the I-0 classification. The tm and tx were derived implicitly from&#13;
the corresponding actually paid peso values. It was felt chat the 1976 data&#13;
indicate, best of all data in recent years, the degree of protection which&#13;
would likely prevail in the medium term future. The values for Dm were&#13;
added to the formula in the I-0-Approach in order to reflect the impact that&#13;
distortions in prices of distribution can have on discrepancies between&#13;
domestic and foreign price levels of a commodity group. For the coffee sector&#13;
(5) and the petroleum related sectors (4) and (17), an alternative procedure&#13;
was followed /2. For the coffee sector a projected tax rate of 17% is&#13;
/1 Annex 4: "The Importance of Indirect Taxes and Subsidies."&#13;
/2 The "mineria" sector (4) includes crude petroleum.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 32 -&#13;
used, rather than a historical value LJ, and petroleum gets higher BPRs which&#13;
recognize the fact that petroleum in Colombia is heavily subsidized.&#13;
4.   Efficiency Wage Analysis for Input-Output Table (Step 3)&#13;
54.       Efficiency Wage Rate Ratios in this context are necessary to properly&#13;
price the direct and indirect wage input into all non-traded sectors of the&#13;
economy. They may be calculated in the same way for all different labor&#13;
markets.&#13;
55.       The direct labor input coefficient, as percent of total inputs&#13;
into each non-traded sector, was partitioned into the three labor categories&#13;
(1) unskilled, (2) semi-skilled and technically skilled (s &amp; t-skilled), and&#13;
(3) academically-skilled. To find the approximate proportion of each sector's&#13;
wage bill that corresponds to each of the three categories, we used the first&#13;
quarter 1977 "Encuesta de Hogares" data which break down the urban labor&#13;
force by wage level and iato nine sectors, six of which roughly correspond&#13;
to our non-traded sectors /2. The assumption is made that unskilled workers&#13;
earn up to Col$3,000 per month in current 1977 prices; semi- and technically-&#13;
skilled earn between Col$3,000 and Col$10,000, and academically-skilled employees&#13;
are paid over Col$10,000.   Below we present average wage levels Wi in each&#13;
sector, by skill category for the maior non-traded sectors:&#13;
/j   This is the estimated part of coffee export values which will be&#13;
taken away from the coffee sector through the coffee tax and the&#13;
"retention quota", and will not flow back into the sector.&#13;
2    These data may readily be used by a project economist for more&#13;
specific calculations on EWRRs and for other purposes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 33 -&#13;
Table 2:  COLOIBIA - ANNUAL WAGES PAID IN NON-TRADED SECTORS&#13;
(In 1976 Current Pesos)&#13;
8 &amp; L&#13;
Unskilled       Skilled     Skilled&#13;
Electricity, water and gas                   21,126         46,903      167,335&#13;
Construction                                  19,322        48,907      159,507&#13;
Commerce                                      17,660        51,825      175,331&#13;
Transport and communications                 25,660         53,300      170,569&#13;
Banks, insurance companies, etc.             20,034         55,916      183,307&#13;
Other services                               29,887         51,315      169,645&#13;
Arithmetic Average:                          22,383         51,411      170,949&#13;
With these wages, the Efficiency Wage Rate Ratios were then calculated as&#13;
follows: (The reader not interested in these details may go on to the&#13;
results in Chapter B.5.d.)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 34 -&#13;
5.   Equations for Efficiency Wage Rate Ratios (EWRR) for Non-Traded Sectors /&#13;
a.   Unskilled EWRR&#13;
1  * M * ¶r + pomo+ pO &#13;
EWRR      -           -                 -&#13;
U,i~~~~~U&#13;
where;&#13;
E RRU,i   -   Efficiency wage ratio for unskilled workers in&#13;
sector i.&#13;
1r        =   RMPLCF (Conversion Factor for Marginal Product of&#13;
Labor foregone in rural areas) - 0.93. /2&#13;
M              (Migration factor) - 1.15.&#13;
Wr             (Average agricultural wage, assumed to reflect the&#13;
marginal product of labor of the rural worker who,&#13;
without the project, was employed) - Col$14,616.00. /3&#13;
PO        =    (The probability of hiring a worker who formerly was&#13;
unemployed; in conservative case, p     - 0.11, which is&#13;
the average rate of unemployment inorural areas)./4&#13;
p1        -    (The probability of hiring a formerly employed&#13;
worker) - 0.89.&#13;
m         =    (Marginal product of labor of unemployed rural&#13;
°            workers)   -  0.&#13;
De             (A term reflecting the "disutility of effort"; because&#13;
of lack of data on a national average, it is here&#13;
assumed to be zero).&#13;
Wui       '   Average wage for unskilled labor in sector i (see Table 2).&#13;
This formula assumes that all unskilled labor going into the non-&#13;
traded sectors eventually comes from the agricultural sector earning average&#13;
/1   The rationale behind these formulae is further discussed in Section C&#13;
on the General Efficiency Wage Rate Ratios. The above formula could&#13;
be used for any sector or subsector of the economy where labor condi-&#13;
tions are sufficiently distinct from other labor markets.&#13;
/2   This is derived from Chapter C.3.&#13;
/3   Calculated from 1976 rural daily wage data - DANE.&#13;
/4   Calculated from CCRP employm_iic estimates of Corporacion Centro&#13;
12rni-1 H    PNl :ir,n (CRPP    Rnantn&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 35 -&#13;
wages. tl The marginal product of labor lost in rural areas is here approxi-&#13;
mated by a weighted average of (1) the average annual agricultural wage multiplied&#13;
with the share p1 of labor which comes into a project and was formerly employed&#13;
at average agricultural wage; and (2) the output mo of rural workers who&#13;
without the project would be unemployed (mo is assumed to be zero); this&#13;
output is weighted by the proportion po of unemployed workers in total workers&#13;
coming into the project. po is, in a conservative estimate, assumed here to&#13;
equal the average rate of open unemployment in rural areas, which is 11%. /2&#13;
56.       Other assumptions on the use of unemployed labor in urban non-&#13;
traded sectors may be useful, particularly so in a specific project context.&#13;
Our assumption is a "cautious" one. It presupposes that for all additional&#13;
jobs created in urban non-traded sectors there would come, out of the bulk&#13;
of the rural unemployed, only as ma &gt; s there are already, on average,&#13;
unemployed workers in the rural labor force, which supplies urban areas with&#13;
workers. If more were known about migration patterns, radius o6 migiation&#13;
around urban areas, and number of family members who, on average, accompany&#13;
a migrating wl:rker, one might assume alternatively the following:   of each&#13;
100 jobs created in urban non-traded sectors, 33 or 50 would be filled with&#13;
rural unemployed workers with some average rural skill level, rather than&#13;
only 11, as a.sumed here.   If this were found to be the case in a certain&#13;
context, our esults for the EWRRs for each non-traded sector, as given&#13;
in Table 3, could easily be adjusted. po would then assume the value&#13;
of 0.33 or 0.50, respectively, which would lower the EWRRs for unskilled&#13;
labor used he e.&#13;
LI   A simplifying assumption which may be tested empirically once more&#13;
work is done on labor markets in Colombia.&#13;
/2   It shoult be noted that, like in most LDC's and even in developed&#13;
countries, figures of rural unemployment do not allow inter-country&#13;
compari ans because of lack of uniform definitions.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 36 -&#13;
57.       We have, in the context of pricing labor in urban non-traded&#13;
sectors, chosen the "cautious" approach which avoids showing labor&#13;
as being extremely cheap, for the following reasons: (a) nothing specific&#13;
is known about the market of the specific labor force which typically comes&#13;
into the non-traded sectors. We do, however, assume that the unemployment&#13;
rate p  reflects, to a large extent, seasonal unemployment.     Therefore, the&#13;
employed labor force cannot, in most instances, be-withdrawn for an extended&#13;
period into urban non-traded sector production without sizeable output losses&#13;
in rural areas.   (b) We have some general information that in the past few&#13;
years, due to rising real wages in rural areas, it has no longer been easy to&#13;
attract rural labor into the cities within a relatively short period. (c) Also,&#13;
there may be parts of the family (wives, parents, etc.) following the migrating&#13;
workers which, in rural areas where they owned some land, had some output in&#13;
form of garden crops or farm maintenance, while in urban areas they have not.&#13;
Therefore, the loss in family output would be bigger than reflected by an EWRR&#13;
which only looks at worker's output.&#13;
58.       Some explanation may be useful concerning the migration factor&#13;
M. By putting this factor into the equation, it is assumed that for each&#13;
100 jobs created in the (mostly urban) non-traded industries, 115 workers&#13;
will leave their jobs in rural areas, of which 15 will remain unemployed.&#13;
If no adjustment by such a migration factor were made, the formula would&#13;
imply that urban unemployment rates are assumed to disappear in the long&#13;
run. However, Colombian labor market statisticians believe that, in recent&#13;
years, some magic minimum level of urban unemployment has been reached&#13;
which will not be lowered in the medium term. Therefore, we assume here,&#13;
that urban unemployment rates will remain at their average level of the&#13;
last years.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 37 -&#13;
b. S &amp; T-Skilled EWRR&#13;
59.       The EWRR for semi- and technically-skilled labor, employed addi-&#13;
tionally in non-traded sectors, was estimated by the following formula: /1&#13;
6&#13;
1 * E p W. + P     M  + P  D&#13;
EWERR        - &#13;
sts,i                   W&#13;
82.&#13;
EWRR stsi     -  Efficiency Wage Rate Ratio for semi- and technically-&#13;
'ts,i    skilled workers, employed in sector i.&#13;
1u - UMPLCF   -  (A conversion factor for average marginal product lost&#13;
in urban areas, discussed later) - 0.88.&#13;
W.            - Wage rate in domestic pricep of the employed worker&#13;
J               in non-traded sector j where labor is coming from.&#13;
To the extent workers are employed, their wage received&#13;
is assumed to reflect their marginal product of labor.&#13;
p.               Proportion of labor which at the margin would come&#13;
from each of the six non-traded sectors j into sector&#13;
i (approximated by share of employment in sector J, in&#13;
total non-traded-sector employment); p - proportion of&#13;
labor withdrawn from the bulk of the urban unemployed&#13;
labor force.&#13;
m0            = Marginal product of labor of the unemployed, here&#13;
assumed to be zero.&#13;
De            = A term reflecting the "disutility of effort"; because&#13;
of lack of reasonable average data on a national level,&#13;
it is assumed here to be zero.&#13;
W .           - Wage level for semi- and technically skilled workers in&#13;
sector i.&#13;
In the above formulation it is assumed that (i) skilled labor is paid its&#13;
marginal product to the extent that it is employed; (2) at the margin, skilled&#13;
labor is withdrawn only from within the urban economy /2; (3) it will be with-&#13;
drawn in the same proportion in which employment is presently distributed in&#13;
the non-traded sectors of the urban economy. On the following pages we explain&#13;
further the labor market model underlying this equation /3.&#13;
LI   This approach is conceptually similar to one used by N.F.G. Scott for&#13;
Kenya. M.F.G. Scott: Estimates of Shadow Wages in Kenya, Nuffield&#13;
College, Oxford, February 1973; Chapter 11.&#13;
/2   An assumption which could be changed easily if empirical evidence&#13;
were against it in a specific context.&#13;
3    The reader not interested in it may proceed to p. 41.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 38 -&#13;
60.       Assumption (2) seems justified as follows:     we suppose here that&#13;
schooling of rural labor to semi- and technically-skilled levels in urban&#13;
sectors, with high productivity and special skill requirements (like for&#13;
employment in communications and banking) would be too costly, and would&#13;
take longer than the preparation period needed for most projects. This&#13;
also takes account of the fact that the reservoir of rural labor in&#13;
Colombia is relatively limited, since only 35% is estimated to live in&#13;
the rural areas.   .oreover, as mentioned above, recent data have shown, that,&#13;
due to consecutive years of coffee boom and rising agricultural prices, real&#13;
wages in rural areas in the last couple of years increased more than real&#13;
wages in urban areas. Therefore, the rate of migration to the cities is&#13;
estimated to have slowed down somewhat. Finally, the creation of Jobs through&#13;
projects is often only temporary, like in the case of highway construction in&#13;
urban areas; this type of job creation might not induce rural workers to&#13;
migrate.&#13;
61.       Therefore, the usual "moving-up" theory, by which, in a long&#13;
series of jobs, the next higher step in the ladder will be filled by someone&#13;
from the next lower step - until finally only output in subsistence farming&#13;
is lost - may not apply in the case of urban s &amp; t-skilled labor. There may&#13;
be a bigger loss in production than just the one of an agricultural worker,&#13;
either because the semi-skilled worker in the highway project may be&#13;
temporarily unemployed after completion of the project (which would make&#13;
the total loss in output bigger), or because he would return to a job of&#13;
his former category, thereby moving someone else back a step "down the&#13;
ladder", but probably not affecting an agricultural worker if the project&#13;
is a typically urban one. Our formula takes account of these factors in a&#13;
simplified way.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 39 -&#13;
62.        Should a project economist, however, have evidence that:&#13;
(a) the period of withdrawal of labor through a project is&#13;
long enough or even permanent, so as to enable a long series&#13;
of changes in the hierarchy of skills, and&#13;
(b) that the type of semi-skilled and technically skilled labor&#13;
is not so sophisticated that additional training would have&#13;
to be added to the normal process of moving on along the&#13;
ladder - thereby creating extra costs -&#13;
then he may well introduce an agricultural wage into the formula as done in&#13;
the case of EWRR for rural unskilled labor. Or, he may use any weighted&#13;
average of output foregone in both rural and urban sectors, multiplying them&#13;
with one of the 31 Border Price Ratios calculated later. Also he may find it&#13;
useful to break the s &amp; t-skilled category up into (1) semi-skilled (without&#13;
considerable training costs), and (2) technically-skilled (with sizeable&#13;
training costs and time involved).&#13;
63.       Our third assumption was that labor would be withdrawn in the same&#13;
proportion pj in which it is presently distributed in the non-traded urban&#13;
economy, including the unemployed part of the labor force of all skill&#13;
levels. The unemployment rate for labor of all skill levels in non-traded&#13;
sectors is about 10% and slightly lower than the same unemployment rate&#13;
for the urban economy as a whole. To Justify this assumption, similar&#13;
is to be said as in the case of unskilled labor used in additional production&#13;
of urban non-traded sectors. Again, we have made a very cautious estimate,&#13;
using p0 = 0.10, for reasons similar to the above arguments as to why we did&#13;
not generally assume that s &amp; t-skilled labor comes from rural areas:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 40 -&#13;
(a) It may not appear very easy to attract, within a relatively&#13;
short period, a sizeable amount of labor out of the bulk of&#13;
the unemployed semi- and technically-skilled labor io0.ce,&#13;
because this sub-set of labor force of all three skill levels&#13;
working in non-traded urban sectors, may be rather small.&#13;
(b) Withdrawing a &amp; t-skilled labor out of the bulk of unskilled&#13;
labor, however, would require training costs and facilities.&#13;
At present, it appears that facilities for technical training&#13;
in Colombia are rather a bottleneck factor.&#13;
(c) Finally, semi- and technically-skilled labor, even in urban areas,&#13;
will probably have some "informal" output, even if they are&#13;
registered as unemployed; this may also be taken into account&#13;
indirectly by not choosing too high a value for p . 1/&#13;
64.       As will be seen later in part C, the whole discussion reduces largely&#13;
to (1) how much time and training facilities are available each year when a&#13;
set of additional government projects are implemented; (2) how many additional&#13;
workers do they demand; and (3) how many additional workers can a region or&#13;
city supply. To formulate these conditions in rather general terms, three&#13;
basic cases may conveniently be distinguished: (a) If quick implementation&#13;
of a project requires bringing in labor at very short notice and there is&#13;
little supply of unemployed s &amp; t-skilled labor in the immediate region, a&#13;
value for p of 0.10 may even be too high; (b) If, however, a set of projects&#13;
LI    Strictly speaking it should be explained by giving m    a value other than&#13;
zero. In the absence of general data on mo, however, one may incorporate&#13;
it in a low estimate of po.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 41 -&#13;
in a given area is either little labor intensive and/or if labor can&#13;
be hired and trained over some medium term period before the project needs&#13;
it, a value of q - 0.33 may be realistic; i.e. we may assume that, of all&#13;
s &amp; t-skilled workers hired for the additional projects, 1/3 may come out&#13;
of the bulk of the unemployed. (c) If, finally, there is empirical evidence&#13;
in a project context that: (1) there is ample supply of unemployed&#13;
s &amp; t-skilled labor, while (2) there is plenty of time and facilities to&#13;
hire and train labor in advance of the commencement of an additional project;&#13;
then the project economist may vary the "conservative" results in table 3 by&#13;
even using a value of po = 0.50 or higher.&#13;
c.   Academically-Skilled EWRR&#13;
65.       It is assumed here that the academically skilled workers earn&#13;
largely their marginal product, and that there is no unemployment. Middle&#13;
and higher management in government entities may even earn somewhat less&#13;
than their marginal product, but that may be assumed to be primarily compensated&#13;
through (a) income from participation or part time occupation in industry or&#13;
consulting that they gain simultaneously, and (b) by the relatively high&#13;
incomes that part of the academically trained elite earns in industry, as&#13;
reflected in the generally high income concentration in Colombia. No further&#13;
research has been done in this field since costs for academically skilled&#13;
labor are a relatively small component in most projects. For that same reason,&#13;
and since academically trained management is involved in the production of&#13;
all kinds of intermediate and final goods, the conversion factor used here&#13;
was the Standard Conversion Factor for intermediate and final demand combined&#13;
with the Urban Conversion Factcor for Marginal Product of Labor Foregone&#13;
(SCF3 = 0.94). Therefore, we have:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 42 -&#13;
EWRR     5    0.94        for i = 1, 2 ....... 9&#13;
as,i&#13;
for all nine non-traded sectors.&#13;
d.   Resulting Vector of EWRRs for the Non-Traded Sectors&#13;
(Step 3 continued)&#13;
'6.       Using the proportion of unskilled, s &amp; t-skilled and academically-&#13;
skilled employees in total employment in each non-traded sector as weights,&#13;
we obtained the vector of efficiency wage rate ratios for the nine non-traded&#13;
sectors shown in the following Table 3.&#13;
Table 3: COLOMBIA - EFFICIENCY WAGE RATE RATIOS AND OTHER PRIMARY INPUT RATIOS&#13;
CF for&#13;
Efficiency Wage Rate Ratios              Interest +&#13;
Un-        s &amp; t-  Academically Weighted     Depreciation +&#13;
Skilled    Skilled     Skilled    Average         Profits&#13;
Electricity,&#13;
gas and water        0.66        0.81       0.94       0.83           0.94&#13;
Construction          0.72        0.78       0.94       0.78           0.94&#13;
Commerce              0.79        0.75       0.94       0.76           0.94&#13;
Transport             0.54        0.71       0.94       0.71           0.94&#13;
Communication         0.54        0.71       0.94       0.71           0.94&#13;
Banking and&#13;
insurance services   0.69        0.68       0.94       0.81           0.94&#13;
Housing rental        ----        ----        ---       ----           0.94&#13;
Other private&#13;
services             0.47        0.74       0.94       0.66           0.94&#13;
Public services       0.47        0.74       0.94       0.66           0.94&#13;
e.   Border-Pricing Other Primary Inputs&#13;
67.        Finally, inputs from the primary sector "Interest, Depreciation&#13;
and Profits" which cannot easily be disaggregated into these three components&#13;
for the 31 sectors, were again converted to border prices by using the&#13;
SCF3 = 0.94. Depreciation and profit margins may vary considerably from&#13;
sector to sector. It would, therefore, have been desirable to split the&#13;
sector at least into two sub-sectors. This, however, requires a substantial&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 43 -&#13;
amount of time. (As it is, the aggregate used leads to some simplification&#13;
in sectors like renting of houses, (sector 29), where the share of interest,&#13;
depreciation and profits in total costs is extremely large, partly since&#13;
depreciation on the capital stock in form of buildings is an important item,&#13;
and partly because profits may be high.) In further analysis one might check&#13;
if some weighted average, in which the BPR24 for the construction sector plays&#13;
an important role, would not be a better approximation.(&#13;
58.       All these refinements would, however, require some sectoral data&#13;
which a project economist might find more easily available as he appraises&#13;
a project. It would then be easy enough to feed them into the model and&#13;
see to what extent BPRs of other non-traded sectors would be changed.&#13;
6. Border Price Ratios at Efficiency Prices for all Sectors (Steps 4&#13;
through 8)&#13;
69.        Feeding (a) the border price ratios of the traded sectors, (b) the&#13;
vectors of efficiency wage rates, and (c) the SCFs into the Input-Output&#13;
computer model, and multiplying them with the matrix of coefficients of&#13;
direct and indirect inputs into the nine non-traded sectors, we obtain a&#13;
Border Price Ratio for each non-traded sector (step 6). This process is&#13;
then iterated as described under steps (7) and (8). Table 4 presents&#13;
BPRs for all traded and non-traded sectors.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 44 -&#13;
Table 4: COLUMBIA - BORDER PRICE RATIOS OF ALL SECTORS AT EFFICIENCY PRICES&#13;
BPR with High   BPR with Petro-       Differenc&#13;
Petroleum      leum Subsidies     in PercentE&#13;
Traded Sectors                  Subsidies     LarRely Removed /1       PointE&#13;
1.   Agriculture                             .93&#13;
2.   Silviculture                            .93&#13;
3.   Fishing &amp; hunting                       .92&#13;
4.   Mining                                 2.30              1.44                -86&#13;
5.   Coffee, processed                      1.21&#13;
6.   Meat                                    .90&#13;
7.   Cereal products                         .95&#13;
8.   Milk products                           .93&#13;
9.   Sugar                                  1.01&#13;
10.  Drinks                                  .66&#13;
11.  Tobacco, processed                      .92&#13;
12.  Other processed agriculture goods       .90&#13;
13.  Textiles, clothing &amp; leather            .95&#13;
14.  Wood and wooden furniture              1.01&#13;
15.  Paper and printing                      .99&#13;
16.  Chemicals and rubber                    .89&#13;
17.  Refitted petroleum                     3.00              1.67               -133&#13;
18.  Non-metal products                      .94&#13;
19.  Metal products                          .89&#13;
20. Machinery                                .86&#13;
21.  Transportation material                 .87&#13;
22.  Other manufactures                      .83&#13;
Non-Traded Sectors&#13;
23.  Electricity, gas and water             1.10              0.96                -14&#13;
24.  Construction                            .87              0.84                - 3&#13;
25.  Commerce                                .93              0.90                - 3&#13;
26.  Transportation                         1.09              0.96                -13&#13;
27.  Communication                           .83              0.81                - 2&#13;
28.  Banking and insurance services          .84              0.84                  0&#13;
29.  Housing rental                          .85              0.86                + 1&#13;
30.  Other private services                  .79              0.79                  0&#13;
31.  Public services                         .76              0.73                - 3&#13;
/J   Assuming that present subsidies on petroleum are reduced to 1/3 during&#13;
the next five years.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 45 -&#13;
70.       A few sectors have remarkable results which shall be discussed&#13;
briefly in the following: In the sectors 4 and 17 which produce crude petro-&#13;
leum and refined petroleum, respectively, the net import duties a-d distri-&#13;
bution margins alone do by far not seem to explain fully the large difference&#13;
between international and domestic prices. Rather it is due to net subsidies&#13;
paid to petroleum and petroleum products. Since they are very substantial, we&#13;
took them into our calculations, although we generally left indirect taxes and&#13;
subsidies out because of lack of adequate data. Therefore the BPR4 (for mining,&#13;
including mining of petroleum which is about 2/3 of the sector's activity),&#13;
resulted in a BPR4 - 2.30, where otherwise, using only net import duties,&#13;
it would only have been minimally lower than 1.0; similar is true for sector&#13;
17 (Petroleum Refining).&#13;
71.       Another sector with a conversion factor relatively different from&#13;
1.0 is the coffee sector (sector 5). Deriving a Conversion Factor for this&#13;
sector is a rather complex task and would require more time than was avail-&#13;
able in this study. However, in the context of estimating a fully integrated&#13;
set of efficiency parameters, the limited amount of time spent on the coffee&#13;
sector does not affect overall results because;&#13;
(a) coffee plays no major role as an input into any domestic&#13;
production, but is largely exported;&#13;
(b) the question of the Conversion Factor for coffee would&#13;
become important if a project were appraised in Colombia&#13;
where coffee is a major output. This however, is very&#13;
unlikely since coffee areas generally are the relatively&#13;
well off amongst the rural areas.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 46 -&#13;
72.      We have, therefore, and because of the lack of good alteXnatives,&#13;
treated coffee in this study like all other export goods, namely assuming&#13;
infinite price elasticity of demand.&#13;
73.      The CF for coffee could only become somewhat important in one case:&#13;
if labor is withdrawn from coffee producing areas a coffee-CF for labor&#13;
would have to be calculated. This should then be undertaken by the project&#13;
economist, possibly along two lines: (1) According to Squire-van der Tak,&#13;
equation (A23) of the appendix. 1/ The difficulty in trying to arrive at&#13;
these figures would be to estimate reliable values for the elasticities of&#13;
world demand for Colombian coffee with respect to coffee prices, and supply&#13;
elasticities with respect to prices paid to Colombian producers. It is rathei&#13;
difficult to derive such elasticities meaningfully for the medium-term future&#13;
from past data when coffee prices, in real terms, varied widely, especially&#13;
in the last 3-4 years. (2) An alternative would be to proceed as done by&#13;
Linn in his study on Ivory Coast, 2/ i.e, to assume that the coffee tax is&#13;
optimal and that therefore the CF could be, under certain assumptions,&#13;
considered to be 1.0. This assumption, however, cannot be tested for the&#13;
reason stated above that elasticities estimates are not reliable.&#13;
74.      The export tax of 21% used here is an effective tax and is a result&#13;
of a somewhat complex calculation. It is relatively difficult to determine&#13;
the range of an effective coffee tax levied, given the extreme complexity&#13;
and variability of the Colombian coffee sector. The effective coffee tax&#13;
for shadow pricing purposes not only consists of the tax levied at the border&#13;
which was 12% in 1977 on the minimum exchange surrender price for coffee and&#13;
1/   L. Squire-H. van der Tak, op. cit., page 144&#13;
2/   J. Linn:  "Economic and Social Analysis of Prolects:    A Case Study&#13;
of Ivory Coast", World Bank Staff Working Paper No. 253, p. 19.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 47 -&#13;
went to the National Government budget; it also consists of a so-called&#13;
"retention quota" which is a tax paid in terms of real bags of coffee from&#13;
the producers to the Colombian Coffee Federation exporting for them, and&#13;
which is obviously more important than the first tax going to the govern-&#13;
ment. This "real" tax is changed whenever the world market price for&#13;
coffee rises substantially. It was raised in 1976 from 23% to 44% where&#13;
it was maintained throughout 1977 and 1978. Also there is no way to determine&#13;
more or less exactly the amount of how much of this second tax goes to the&#13;
government budget via a variety of measures imposed on the Coffee Federation,&#13;
and what part remains in the coffee sector by being invested in coffee&#13;
growing areas.&#13;
75.      Our best estimates, taking into account all these factors and&#13;
consulting with coffee experts in Colombia, is that the effective coffee&#13;
tax levied on the sector as a whole and being used by the Government for&#13;
general purposes is in the order of magnitude of 21%.&#13;
76.      We have attached the Conversion Factor of 1.21 to the sector.      "Coffee&#13;
Processing" because there is, unfortunately, no breakdown in the Input-Output&#13;
table of the agricultural sector into "coffee agriculture" and "non-coffee&#13;
agriculture", or even major individual non-coffee crops, which would be&#13;
desirable for rural projects. As can be seen from the foregoing, there is&#13;
room for improving the CF of coffee should this sector become important for&#13;
project appraisal.&#13;
77.      The BPRs for the non-traded sectors show relatively little variance,&#13;
with the exception of Electricity, Gas and Water (Sector 23), and Transportation&#13;
(sector 26). Again this can be explained through the petroleum subsidy; the&#13;
electricity sector uses partly fuel oil for power production, and the trans-&#13;
portation sector uses gasoline as a major input.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 48 -&#13;
78.       Since August 1978, the then elected Colombian Government raised&#13;
gasoline prices substantially and announced that it would aim at bringing&#13;
petroleum prices closer to international levels. Once that becomes true,&#13;
the BPRs of all non-traded sectors which use petroleum imports, will change.&#13;
We, therefore, adjusted, in a second round of calculations, the non-traded&#13;
BPRs. We assumed that within the next five years petroleum subsidies would&#13;
come down from their traditionally high levels of around 200% to a level of&#13;
only 1/3 of what they were before the price rises. The BPRs of sector (4)&#13;
would therefore reduce to 1.44, and those of sector (17) would be lowered to&#13;
1.67.&#13;
79.       With these new inputs, leaving everything else unchanged, we derived&#13;
a new set of BPRs for the sectors (23) through (31) (Table 4). The principal&#13;
changes, as can be expected, occur in the electricity and the transportation&#13;
sectors. The differences are 14 and 13 percentage points, respectively. No&#13;
changes occur in sectors like "Banking and insurance services" (sector 28) and&#13;
"Private services" (sector 30).&#13;
80.       So far, we have left the input coefficients of the non-traded sectors&#13;
unchanged. This, however, is not an ideal procedure; after the new prices&#13;
have been in effect for some time, downward chanxes in all crude petroleum&#13;
and gasoline input coefficient should be expected, which in turn should&#13;
lead to some major restructuring of the whole 1-0-Table. However, at the&#13;
present time, no projections about this can be made yet. It remains a&#13;
task to be done once a new stable level of relative petroleum prices has&#13;
been reached. (For the desirability of updating the I-0-Table, see Annex 3).&#13;
For the same reason, we have not calculated any new General Conversion&#13;
Factors so far. Rather we propose to (a) either use our General Conversion&#13;
Factors which exclude petroleum sectors, if they are no major input, or&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 49 -&#13;
(b) calculate specific Multi-Sector Conversion Factors which would use&#13;
weights for the petroleum sectors as specified by a project economist.&#13;
81.       The vector of 31 BPRs may now be used:&#13;
(a) individually, for converting into foreign prices any single&#13;
minor input and/or non-traded output items in a project&#13;
appraisal; this is especially valuable in case of prefeasibility&#13;
studies when little time is available to obtain border prices&#13;
directly;&#13;
(b) aggregated in the form of General Conversion Factors; they may&#13;
be applied to convert into border prices all highly aggregated&#13;
residuals of inputs and outputs which are not broken down&#13;
further;&#13;
(c) they may be aggregated into what we may call "Multi-Sector Conversion&#13;
Factors". Aggregates of this kind could, e.g., be made for all&#13;
typically&#13;
- rural sectors&#13;
- urban sectors&#13;
- raw material producing sectors&#13;
- intermediate goods producing sectors&#13;
- industrial sectors&#13;
- services sectors&#13;
or any other mix of the 31 sectors.&#13;
7.   Multi-Sector-Conversion Factors and their Meaning&#13;
82.       The "Multi-Sector CFs" may be the best use a project economist can&#13;
make from the Input-Output-Approach which incorporates many sectors. He would&#13;
not have to rely on only a few CFs for selected non-traded sectors, like&#13;
electricity, transport and construction only, but he could quickly calculate&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 50 -&#13;
any number of "tailor-made" conversion factors which would depend on the&#13;
varying degree of breakdown in which the input coefficients of a project are&#13;
available.&#13;
83.       Let us first calculate a "Multi-Sector-CF" in a practical example.&#13;
In order to show how easily this can be done in the 1-0-Approach, we may&#13;
calculate here a CF for services (SERVCF). Looking over Table 4 we find that&#13;
the BPRs for the typical services sectors (sectors 27 through 31) are very&#13;
similar and close to 0.8. We therefore weight these BPRs with their share&#13;
in the average value of total intermediate and final uses for all services,&#13;
using the data which we read off directly from the output of the computer&#13;
model (see Annex 2, Table 1):&#13;
Intermediate and                 Intermediate and&#13;
Final Uses of                    Final Uses of&#13;
Services at                      Services at&#13;
Domestic Prices       BPR of      Border Prices&#13;
(in Millions       Services      (in Millions&#13;
Sector                       of Pesos)        Sectors         of Pesos)&#13;
27.  Communication                  4,663            0.827           3,857&#13;
28. Banking and Insurance&#13;
Services                    38,961           0.841           32,760&#13;
29.  Housing Rental                18,303            0.855          15,644&#13;
30.  Private Services              42,438            0.788          33,454&#13;
31.  Public Services                2,872            0.758           2.176&#13;
Total Services               107.237                           87. 891&#13;
87,891&#13;
SERVCF                  0.82&#13;
107,237&#13;
84.       "Multi-Sector-Conversion Factors" should replace the General&#13;
Conversion Factors as fat as possible. For instance, when a project is set&#13;
up largely in an urban environment, most rural CFs should be excluded, among&#13;
cthers, the one on coffee; it greatly influences the Standard Conversion&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 51 -&#13;
Factors in Colombia, but, since it mostly accrues to a rural environment, it may&#13;
not matter for urban projects. Similarly, when a project uses aimost no raw&#13;
material inputs, certail iectors which have a BPR far from 1.0, like the one&#13;
on crude petroleum, would distort the average if they were not excluded.&#13;
Therefore, a "Multi-Sector-CF" would serve better than any of the conventional&#13;
General Conversion Factors. Used ini tfis way, the set of 31 BPRs becomes a&#13;
very versatile tool of any project economist.&#13;
85.       One may argue that even a break-down of intermediate inputs into 31&#13;
sectors still results in relatively crude sectors, i.e., commodity groups,&#13;
where one major commodity may have a rather high import duty, whereas another&#13;
may have a very low duty, both averaging out to some figure which is far off&#13;
the real protection of the specific imported commodity. However, fortunately,&#13;
Colombian import duties were harmonized in 1976 so that greater variances are&#13;
now avoided within a sector. Also, if a project economist wants to know the&#13;
variance within a sector, the Colombian National Planning Departmient can provide&#13;
him with data at a rather detailed level. In the future those variances and&#13;
the duty rates themselves may be expected to change relatively less than in&#13;
other LDCs, since Colombia is bound into the "Grupo Andino." Changes in duty&#13;
rates require a considerable degree of consensus between member countries ani&#13;
will therefore not happen very often. However, when they occur, they ould&#13;
without great effort, immediately be fed into the system, and its impact o.&#13;
all other BPRs and General Conversion Factors could be celcuiatt "ticklk&#13;
The same is true when project economists bring back better 1-O-coefficients&#13;
from detailed work in an appraisal.&#13;
8.   General Conversion Factors and their Meaning&#13;
86.       The set of General Conversion Factors we present in the following&#13;
Table 5 may be one that can most usefully be applied in practical work. Of&#13;
course, a project economist is free to produce any other set bv chanoinp thp&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 52 -&#13;
weights. We have, in some instances, presented a GCF both with marginal and&#13;
with average weights, in order to show that the differences are sometimes in&#13;
the order of magnitude of 3 to 4 percentage points. The results and the defini-&#13;
tions are in the table below.&#13;
TABLE 5: GENERAL CONVERSION FACTORS&#13;
a, (SCF1, Intermediate and Final Uses, Average Weights,&#13;
Excluding Petroleum)                                 -  0.92&#13;
a2 (SCF2, Final Uses, Average Weights, Excluding Petroleum)    =  0.92&#13;
a3 (SCF3, Average SCF + Urban Marginal Product of Labor&#13;
Conversion Factor)                                   -  0.94&#13;
a4 (SCF4, Intermediate and Final Uses, Average Weights,&#13;
Including Petroleum)                                 =  0.98&#13;
a5 (SCF59 Standard Conversion Factor, Intermediate and Final&#13;
Uses, Marginal Weights, Including Petroleum          =  1.01&#13;
el (CCF19 Consumption Conversion Factor, Marginal Weights&#13;
from 1-0-Table)                                      =  0.94&#13;
82 (CCF2, Consumption Conversion Factor, Marginal Weights&#13;
from Urban Consumer Survey)                          -  0.91&#13;
83 (CCF , Consumption Conversion Factor, Average Weights&#13;
from I-0-Table)                                      -  0.92&#13;
ICF (Investment Goods Conversion Factor, Marginal Weights)      -  0.91&#13;
ICF2(Investment Goods Conversion Factor, Average Weights)       =  0.87&#13;
RMICF     (Raw Materials and Intermediate Goods Conversion Factor,&#13;
Marginal Weights, Including Subsidized Petroleum Sectors) =   1.23&#13;
RMICF2     (Raw Materials and Intermediate Goods Conversion Factor,&#13;
Marginal Weights, Excluding Refined Petroleum)             =  0.93&#13;
SERVCF    (Conversion Factor for All Services Sectors)                =  0.82&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 53 -&#13;
87.       Looking through the table, the SCF5 immediately catches the reader's&#13;
eye. This Standard Conversion Factor for intermediate and final uses, using&#13;
marginal weights, is just over 1.0. This is to be explained by the relatively&#13;
strong subsidies in the petroleum and petroleum-based sectors (4) and (17).&#13;
Even if average weights are used, the value of the SCF is still relatively high&#13;
(SCF4= 0.98). In many cases a residual group of inputs into a project may not&#13;
use petroleum and petroleum-based products. Then the SCF, excluding the petro-&#13;
leum sectors, may be used (SCF1 = 0.92); this SCF is of a much more conventional&#13;
magnitude. As mentioned above, we have not calculated any GCFs with the pro-&#13;
jected low petroleum subsidies because too little is known about structural&#13;
changes in the economy which will result from relative price changes. This&#13;
should, however, be done at some later stage when the directions of significant&#13;
structural changes become apparent.&#13;
88.       A special standard conversion factor is calculated which is a simple&#13;
average between the urban MPL-Conversion Factor (UMPLCF) and the SCF for&#13;
intermediate and final uses including petroleum, named SCF3. It is used for&#13;
border-pricing inputs of academically trained labor in the iteration process&#13;
since this is mostly located in urban areas. In addition, we calculate a&#13;
second raw material and intermediate goods and conversion factor (RMICF2)&#13;
which excludes expenditures on the "refined petroleum" sector. This will&#13;
give us a conversion factor that will be useful in pricing miscellaneous&#13;
non-petroleum intermediate goods. The discrepancy between the RMICF1 and&#13;
RMICF2, including and excluding petroleum, is, of course, higher than&#13;
in any other General Conversion factor, since the petroleum sectors almost&#13;
exclusively sell to intermediate, rather than to final users.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 54 -&#13;
89.       We calculated the Consumption Conversion Factor basically ip, two&#13;
ways: CCFI (= 0.94) uses marginal weights from the I-0-Table while CCF2(= 0.91)&#13;
uses marginal weights derived from a consumer survey for urban households. The&#13;
results largely confirm each other. In our subsequent calculations, we used&#13;
CCF1 - 0.94, because it is a national average and stems from more recent data.&#13;
Also, for comparison of marginal and average weights, we calculated CCF3 = 0.92&#13;
which uses average weights derived from the Input-Output Table. The results&#13;
again largely confirm each other.&#13;
90.       On the whole, the variance between the different GCFs is not very big -&#13;
as was the case with the different BPRs - when the distortion through the&#13;
petroleum sectors is excluded. This is in contrast to some other LDCs, and it&#13;
is due to the above mentioned recent harmonization of import duties in Colombia.&#13;
Also, on average, protection on consumer goods is somewhat smaller than on&#13;
investment goods including construction, and about the same as on raw materials&#13;
and intermediate goods.&#13;
91.       For most practical purposes, in order to decide which of the General&#13;
Conversion factors to use, one has only to investigate if petroleum is a major&#13;
input into any of the residual groups of commodities one wants the GCF to&#13;
apply to. As an average Standard Conversion Factor, one may then use a value&#13;
of about SCF   0.93 in the case "without petroleum inputs," and a value of&#13;
SCF = 1.0 in the case "with petroleum inputs." The average value of the three&#13;
CCFs, on the other hand, is of course independent of these considerations and&#13;
can be considered to be in the same order of magnitude as the average value&#13;
of the SCF without petroleum distributions; we therefore recommend to use in&#13;
general CCF   0.93.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 55 -&#13;
92.       We did all of our calculations of GCFs also in a social pricing&#13;
context, as explained later. The cifferences between social and efficiency&#13;
priced GCFs were very small only. However, they may be more important in&#13;
other countries and in the multi-sector CFs. We therefore believe it is&#13;
worth the effort to describe in detail how this is done in an I-0-Approach.&#13;
We do this further below in part D, after having explained our General&#13;
Efficiency Wage Rate Ratios and the use of our conversion factors.&#13;
9.   How to use the border price ratios in project appraisal&#13;
93.       The applicability of the here derived BPRs depends mainly on the&#13;
importance of a commodity in a project. The following general rules may be&#13;
outlined.&#13;
(1) If a project is being preappraised, most of the BPRs calculated here&#13;
may be used. Only very few major inputs should be border priced directly.&#13;
(2) If a project is being appraised, the use of the 31 BPRs is more limited.&#13;
(a) All inputs or outputs which have a big weight in total inputs or&#13;
outputs of a project should be border-priced with extra information. This&#13;
may be done by finding the observed border price (from importers, etc.).&#13;
This "direct border pricing" is especially easy and useful if a good is&#13;
very homogeneous and has a different tax and duty treatment than similar&#13;
goods which are in the same economic sector. The BPRs may, however, always&#13;
be useful as a first guideline.&#13;
(b) For unimportant and/or typically miscellaneous inputs (and, occa-&#13;
sionally, outputs) the individual BPRs may be used. If that involves too&#13;
much detail work (like in the case of an item such as "maintenance costs" and&#13;
certain minor "operating costs"), the BPRs may be used in the form of Multi-&#13;
sector CFs, or even more time-saving, in the form of General CFs.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 56 -&#13;
94.        If the BPRs are used in case (1) or (2b), the following should be&#13;
observed: the BPRs as we calculated them are based on purchaser prices which&#13;
only include distribution margins. The full difference between purchaser&#13;
and producer prices, however, is: (a) distribution margins (mainly commerce&#13;
and transport costs); and (b) indirect taxes minus subsidies.&#13;
95.       Net indirect taxes are not considered in these calculations, except&#13;
for in the two petroleum sectors where subsidies seem to be very heavy, be-&#13;
cause of lack of reliable data by 1-0-Sectors. The project economist should&#13;
therefore ask for a statement, at least of the minor proiect costs and benefits,&#13;
in the following way:&#13;
(1) Broken down roughly by the classifications of our 31 sector&#13;
I-0-Table, unless he can get still more specific information&#13;
by some subsectors.&#13;
(2) Cost items may include distribution margins, i.e., need not&#13;
absolutely be at ex-factory costs. If distribution margins&#13;
can be separated out, however, it is all the better because&#13;
then he can replace a Dmi-value, which is a crude sector&#13;
average, by one specific to a major goods or services item in&#13;
the project, and border price it by the BPR of the commerce&#13;
sector.&#13;
(3) Separating out, however, all indirect taxes paid on the commodity&#13;
and, if possible, all subsidies received, because our BPRs are&#13;
not adjusted for these except in the petroleum related sectors.&#13;
This will be especially true for consumer goods for which indirect&#13;
excise taxes or subsidies may be substantial, and may vary&#13;
considerably amongst each other. It may also be true for&#13;
intermediate goods, but not in the case of gasoline, which&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 57 -&#13;
is already adjusted for Government subsidies. Separating&#13;
out indirect taxes both for the final product going into the&#13;
project, and its inputs, should not be too difficult because&#13;
Colombia since 1974 has introduced a value added tax system&#13;
with harmonized rates. The project economist should, where&#13;
net indirect taxes or net subsidies seem substantial, remove&#13;
them and then apply our BPRs.&#13;
96.       Also, the BPRs here calculated do not consider any monopoly profits&#13;
on domestic market prices. These may be important factors in some sectors,&#13;
especially where&#13;
(a) an importer of a good has the sole import license, or shares&#13;
it within a small group of importers who together set a monopoly&#13;
import price far higher than the sum of cif-price plus import duty&#13;
plus distribution margin;&#13;
(b) a manufacturer, e.g., of trucks or cars, assembles these&#13;
under a license extended by the Government, in cooperation&#13;
with a foreign automobile company. In order to achieve economies&#13;
of scale, the Government has only approved one license for such&#13;
cooperation.&#13;
97.       Such differences between border and domestic prices arising from&#13;
excess profits, of course, cannot be explained by the BPRs we provide here,&#13;
just as little as differences arising from differential indirect tax or&#13;
subsidy treatment, or manufacturing licenses can be explained. In cases&#13;
(b) of manufacturing licenses, the project economists has to try and make an&#13;
estimate of the excess profit margin by observing the actual border prices&#13;
of imported parts and applying BPRs to the domestic inputs, expecially&#13;
labor, so as to derive at a marginal cost estimate just as in the case of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 58 -&#13;
a non-traded sector. The border price thus calculated would then be used&#13;
for the subsector. If the excess profit were roughly known, one would treat&#13;
it like a transfer in form of an excise tax, deduct it from the domestic&#13;
market price and use one of our BPRs on the so corrected price.&#13;
98.       In case (a) of monopoly import licenses, the excess profit may be&#13;
considered a measure of the effect of an import quota, and thus be treated as&#13;
an additional import duty. In both of these cases, therefore, a project&#13;
economist must make "manual" adjustments to the BPRs given here; however,&#13;
they may be helpful as "base values" for the complete BPR of a commodity&#13;
group.&#13;
10. Some Limitations of the Input-Output Approach&#13;
a.   The Problem of Classification of In2ut-Output Sectors&#13;
comprising goods with high and low tariffs&#13;
99.       Some bias may be involved in the Input-Output Approach, especially&#13;
if the I-0 Table is not very disaggregated, due to the fact that imported&#13;
intermediate goods or capital goods pay lower import duties than consumer&#13;
goods, particularly luxury consumer goods; nevertheless, they are aggregated&#13;
into the same economic sector in the Input-Output Table. As an example, in our&#13;
Colombia study, the BPR for the "transport material" sector is 0.87, implying&#13;
a nominal protection of about 15%. 11 This is an average tariff composed&#13;
of (1) items like unassembled parts of cars, to be assembled in Colombia&#13;
and thus carrying a very low tariff, and (2) some finished cars, carrying a&#13;
very high tariff. However, by averaging, we lose this information in the&#13;
1-0 approach, and therefore some bias may come into the traded and non-traded&#13;
CFs.&#13;
LI   Calculated as           1.15&#13;
0.87&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 59 -&#13;
100.      The bias is probably towards too high CF's for: (a) a traded sectors,&#13;
and consequently for non-traded sectors; and (b) for General Conversion&#13;
Factors, for the following reason: project inputs will be final goods, for&#13;
which import duties are likely to be higher than for the average of final and&#13;
intermediate goods in that sector. However, to the extent that inputs into a&#13;
project are intermediate goods, the BPR may, in exceptional cases, also be too&#13;
low and the domestic price would actually be lower than suggested by the BPR.&#13;
What can be done about this problem? The general rule has of course to be to&#13;
use the CF's of the traded sectors only for minor inputs into a project. To&#13;
what extent further disaggregation is recommendable, is largely a question of&#13;
-the costs -for this task versus the marginal benefits of greater precision.&#13;
101.      To do this, one would have to obtain a matrix of imports for each&#13;
sector which disaggregates, at least, by (1) final consumer goods; (2) final&#13;
investment goods; (3) raw material and intermediate goods. If the share of&#13;
imports in sector i going into (1) consumption uses (which will prima-facie&#13;
have a high tariff) is almost as high as the share'of this good's import&#13;
going into (2) final investment use and (3) intermediate use (which will both&#13;
prima facie have a low tariff), then there will be good reason to disaggregate&#13;
further, because the variance around the weighted average import tariff&#13;
calculated or observed for sector i is likely to be very large. Alternatively,&#13;
if such a vector of variances is already calculated for all import items, it&#13;
should be used as the guideline for disaggregation.&#13;
102.      Since this is not the case for observed tariffs in Colombia, making&#13;
it would require some extra effort. There exists, however, a vector of&#13;
calculated standard deviations and maximum and minimum legal tariffs for&#13;
Colombian imports, as of December 1976. To the extent one can assume that&#13;
legal tariffs have similar variances as actually paid import tariffs,&#13;
project economists should use them.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 60 -&#13;
103.      It would then be the task of a project economist to break up the&#13;
I-0-sectors, according to the criterion of the variance in tariffs mentioned&#13;
above, and to calculate a BPR for each of the traded subsectors (if he does&#13;
not find out that a subsector should not rather be reclassified as non-&#13;
traded because of prohibitive import tariffs) with the disaggregated import&#13;
tariffs. In a first approximation a project economist would look through the&#13;
tariff structure in cases where he finds that a project input is likely to be&#13;
a luxury consumer good. It would be a matter of subjective decision what variance&#13;
is considered great enough to warrant and afford further breaking up of a sector.&#13;
104.      The whole problem mentioned above is, of course, a problem of&#13;
classification. If the I-0-Table had been made for the purpose of shadow&#13;
pricing, the problem would not arise. If one wants to get rid of a certain&#13;
systematic bias not only in the traded-sector-BPR's, but also in the ones&#13;
for non-traded sectors and GCF's, one will have to rebuild a whole new&#13;
1-0-Table, further disaggregated and reclassified. It would have to&#13;
comprise a new submatrix of final uses as well as of primary inputs. This&#13;
is, of course, a rather large additional task, which can only be undertaken&#13;
in exceptional cases. As it is, it seems worth while to limit oneself to&#13;
accepting the Colombian 1-0-Table for the purpose of estimating BPR's of the&#13;
non-traded goods and services, and the GCF's which anyway should not be used&#13;
often.&#13;
105.      The bias in the traded sector conversion factors of sectors with&#13;
import protection will have two further consequences for our estimates:&#13;
(1) Shadow Wage Rate Ratios will be somewhat biased to the extent project&#13;
labor is withdrawn from import substitution-sectors, since the Labor&#13;
Conversion Factors used in this paper would be somewhat biased, probably&#13;
on the high side. However, this bias may be considered to be relatively&#13;
small as compared to other biases which come into every SWR-calculation&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 61 -&#13;
through the fact that the marginal product of labor foregone is hard to&#13;
estimate, due to imperfect data on un- or under-employment, the sectors&#13;
from which labor is withdrawn, and the value of output in them. Only a&#13;
sensitivity analysis could decide this question, using as inputs a new,&#13;
further disaggregated and reclassified set of import duties and calculating&#13;
new Shadow     e laLts with the new labor conversion factors or the new&#13;
CF's for Lraded and non-traded sectors. (2) The Consumption Conversion&#13;
Factors will be somewhat too high to the extent that final goods from the&#13;
import substitution sectors enter the vector of coefficients for the CCF.&#13;
However, without very detailed disaggregation and reclassification as described&#13;
above, it is not possible to know of what order of magnitude the bias is.&#13;
b.   Partially Traded Goods&#13;
106.      If there is evidence that a good, being an input or an output of&#13;
the project, is "partially traded," 1/ a mixed procedure has ideally to be&#13;
followed: a commodity group is, in a first step, considered non-traded only,&#13;
and a "non-traded BPR" is calculated for it as done for the fully non-traded&#13;
sectors. Then it is considered traded only, and its "traded BPR" is calculated&#13;
with the standard formula. The two BPR's are finally weighted together accord-&#13;
ing to the likelyhood that they will be imported and domestically produced.&#13;
107.      This procedure was not followed in the present paper because the&#13;
classifications into only 31 sectors is relatively broad, and it is difficult&#13;
to estimate approximately if and to what extend goods in a sector will be&#13;
1/   This means (in the case of an import), it is partly imported, but not&#13;
fully because, e.g., of quantitive import restrictions; therefore partly&#13;
the project input has to be supplied by expanded production at home.&#13;
This case may not be too frequent in World Bank projects because often&#13;
import barriers will be lifted for such projects.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 62 -&#13;
partially imported and produced domestically. A project economist may, of&#13;
course, do this calculation, either by using the existing BPR's "exogenously",&#13;
or by rerunning the model for obtaining a more precise "endogenous" BPR for&#13;
the sector in question.&#13;
PART C. GENERAL EFFICIENCY WAGE RATE RATIOS&#13;
Introduction&#13;
108.      The General Efficiency Wage Rate Ratios calculated below differ&#13;
from those calculated in Section B in that they are no longer specific to&#13;
projects in the non-trad-d urban sectors only, but are meant to be applicable&#13;
to the labor component of an average project. To calculate such "General&#13;
Efficiency Wage Ratios," which have to be nationwide averages in every imagin-&#13;
able respect, seems to be a somewhat thankless task. What is difficult is not&#13;
so much the job of obtaining the data necessary to calculate the national&#13;
averages; rather it is not easy to specify a generally acceptable "average"&#13;
set of assumptions about the "average labor market," which, in a country like&#13;
Colombia, probably consists of a number of highly differentiated sub-markets.&#13;
They are, among other things, different by degree of mobility and migration&#13;
patterns, by wage levels, and unemployment rates. Therefore, it would be&#13;
only through a rather detailed study on labor markets that one could find out&#13;
what a "representative labor market" is.&#13;
109.      Much research work will still have to be done to give some guide-&#13;
lines about which short-cut procedures can be followed and what assumptions&#13;
can most safely be made. Given the importance of Economic and Social Wage&#13;
Rate Ratios, a project economist should be careful, when using any nationwide&#13;
General EWRRs and SWRRs, that he has studied their assumptions. For these&#13;
reasons, we discuss them at some length.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 63 -&#13;
110.      The formulae used here and the values of the parameters other than&#13;
the wage levels are very similar to those used as model inputs in Part B. The&#13;
average-project wage levels paid in projects in urban areas were estimated to&#13;
be the following:&#13;
Average wage for&#13;
urban unskilled workers       =  Col$23,765 (in 1976 current pesos)&#13;
Average wage for semi- and&#13;
technically skilled workers   -  Col$60,127 (in 1976 current pesos)&#13;
111.      The unskilled urban wage is an average between a wage level calculated&#13;
from ANIF-COLDATOS Data, /1 where a Col$3,000 (1976 prices) monthly income&#13;
was used as a cut-off, and the average wage paid to unskilled labor in&#13;
30 industrial projects. /2 The semi- and technically skilled wage is an&#13;
average between the wage paid to s&amp;t skilled construction workers, /3 and&#13;
the average wage paid to s&amp;t skilled workers in 30 industrial projects /4.&#13;
1.   Formulae and Assumptions Used in Efficiency Wage Rate Ratios&#13;
112.      We estimate here three general EWRRs:&#13;
(a) for urban unskilled workers (EWRR );&#13;
uu&#13;
(b)  for rural unskilled workers (EWRR   ); and&#13;
(c)  for semi- and technically skilled workers (EWRR t).&#13;
/1   ANIF-COLDATOS, Encuesta, 1976, unpublished figures.&#13;
/2   CEDE, Evaluacion Social de Treinta Proyectos Industriales, Bogota, 1975.&#13;
/3   DANE, Encuesta Industrial.&#13;
A4   The data used here for unskilled urban labor represent wages which are a&#13;
bit above the average of urban wages; they are characteristic for the&#13;
construction and the manufacturing sectors and have been collected in a&#13;
rather sophisticated manner; consequently, the EWRRs should be used&#13;
primarily for these, and sectors which would pay similar wages.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 64 -&#13;
The EWRR for academically skilled labor is taken to be the same for the whole&#13;
economy as derived above for the non-traded sectors, namely&#13;
EWRR      0.94&#13;
as&#13;
a.   EWRR    for Urban Unskilled Workers&#13;
u u_     _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _&#13;
1  * M *      Wr + p0 m+  P p0&#13;
EWRR                                            =0.59&#13;
uu                     W&#13;
u&#13;
1r   =  RMPLCF (Conversion Factor for Marginal Product of Labor&#13;
foregone in rural areas )     0.93&#13;
M    =   (Migration factor explained above) - 1.15&#13;
w    =   (Average agricultural wage, assumed to reflect the marginal&#13;
product of labor of the rural workers who, without the&#13;
project, would be employed) = Col$14,616 in 1976 current&#13;
pesos 1/&#13;
p    =   (The probability of hiring a worker who formerly was&#13;
°      unemployed).   In conservative case, p    = 0.11, which is&#13;
the average rate of unemployment in rural areas.&#13;
m    =   (Marginal product of labor of unemployed rural workers) = 0&#13;
0&#13;
W    =     (Average project wage for unskilled workers in urban&#13;
areas) = Col$23,765 in 1976 current pesos&#13;
D    =     (Disutility of effort, as in part B) assumed = 0&#13;
The assumptions included in this equation are the same as in the one used for&#13;
pricing labor in the non-traded sectors (see Chapter A.5). The basic differ-&#13;
ence between this efficiency wage rate and the one calculated for the non-traded&#13;
sectors is only the following: the wage paid in these urban projects is, in&#13;
1/   It should be borne in mind that these wage figures are not adjusted for&#13;
differences in purchasing power in rural versus urban areas, since no&#13;
representative data exist on consumer prices in rural areas in Colombia.&#13;
These differences may be important, as has been shown for the case of Peru&#13;
in a World Bank Study (Vinod Thomas: "The Measurement of Spatial&#13;
Differences in Poverty: The Case of Peru", World Bank staff Working&#13;
Paper No. 123, January 1978, p. 48). The price index for the capital&#13;
Lima was shown to be about twice ac high as the one for the rural sierra.&#13;
These differences should be taken into account in all those project&#13;
appraisals where incomes and changes in incomes are compared. It becomes,&#13;
therefore, especially important for social pricing.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 65 -&#13;
principle, an average of unskilled wages paid in all urban sectors jl,&#13;
whereas there it wa.- a wage specific to each urban, non-traded sector.&#13;
b.   EWRRru for Rural Unskilled Workers&#13;
Similarly, the unskilled Efficiency Wage Rate Ratio in&#13;
rural areas,- EWRRru, is calculated to be:&#13;
lr*      Wm + p0 mO + po0&#13;
EWRRru                   w&#13;
r&#13;
The variables Ir' mO and Wr are used under the same assumptions,&#13;
and have the same values as in the equation for the EWRRUu.&#13;
However, unskilled labor is now assumed to earn minimum agri-&#13;
cultural wages (Wm) only to the extent it is employed without a&#13;
rural development project /2; and it is assumed to earn average&#13;
agricultural wages (Wr) with the project. Also, no migration&#13;
factor is included in this formula, assuming that no important&#13;
migration flows occur.&#13;
2.   Special Assumptions Used in Basic Formulae on Efficiency Wage Rate Ratios&#13;
113.      Since wage costs are important items in most LDC-projects, and since&#13;
EWRRs are often remarkably lower than 1.0, a careful specification of the&#13;
EWRR is important. Therefore, we spell here in detail,for the use of a&#13;
project economist, some additional assumptions underlying these formulae,&#13;
and propose some ways of how to make them more project specific.&#13;
L1   Although, for specific use in public investment projects, they are&#13;
characteristic of the construction and manufacturing sectors.&#13;
/2   Source:  DANE, data on minimum wages.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 66 -&#13;
114.      (1) The formula for EWRRru assumes, that a project in a rural area&#13;
would pay the unskilled workers about 50% more than the minimum agricultural&#13;
wage, namely the average agricultural wage. This might be the case if:&#13;
-    the project is of high priority and therefore wants to pay an&#13;
incentive for people to give up other work quickly and at large&#13;
numbers.&#13;
-    the higher wage is meant to be a compensation for the inconve-&#13;
nience of dislocation or separation from their families of&#13;
workers from outside the immediate region Li. If this is&#13;
obviously not the case, e.g., there seems to be no or a much&#13;
smaller premium paid over the minimum wage, a project economist&#13;
can easily vary the formula.&#13;
115.      (2) As before, the agricultural wage paid to workers in&#13;
agriculture is considered to be the output foregone of the employed workers.&#13;
This may be some overstatement of the opportunity cost. However, it is&#13;
offset somewhat by assuming that po is only 0.11, which may be a low estimate&#13;
of absorption of unemployed workers into a project. Also, it is offset by the&#13;
fact that the output foregone of the so far unemployed (mo) and their disutility&#13;
of effort are, for lack of any representative data, assumed to be zero. In a&#13;
specific project context, all parameters may be adjusted somewhat.&#13;
116.      If a project economist finds that unemployment in a region is not&#13;
seasonal and so high that as good as all workers would come from the unemployed&#13;
labor force our EWRR-Formula would reduce to:&#13;
Ll   This is an implicit form of considering costs of replaclement of one&#13;
worker by another; it could be stated explicitly as shown below if&#13;
specific data were available.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 67 -&#13;
EWRRru,u = CCF * (Disutility of Effort + Replacement Costs)&#13;
Project Wage&#13;
The "disutility of effort" or "foregone leisure" will be a difficult estimate&#13;
item in a specific project, and it would be estimated by some indicators of&#13;
basic needs, like minimum nutrition, shelter and clothing.&#13;
117.      However, the "replacement costs" would be more easily tangible,&#13;
accounting for the fact that output is foregone during a time of adjustment&#13;
when the last worker who was so far unemployed, finds, moves and adjusts to&#13;
the job of the one working in agriculture at minimum wage, while the latter&#13;
adjusts to the work requirements in the project. The item "replacement costs"&#13;
would probably not be significant if the "chain of replacements" is rather&#13;
short. The replacement cost is an item similar to migration and training&#13;
costs; however, it is assumed that it is a relatively low cost. No migration&#13;
over a sizeable distance takes place, no new housing has to be provided for a&#13;
worker and his family; and the training component meant here is an informal,&#13;
quick training on the job. The project wage would in this cage probably be as&#13;
low as the agricultural minimum wage. We have not estimated any EWRR for such&#13;
a case, since this would vary too much from project to project.&#13;
118.      If migration costs. training costs or costs for reintegration of&#13;
the migrating workers arise while also output is foregone, the formula would&#13;
have to be somewhat different. These costs which would be using up real&#13;
resources, could then be incorporated into the formula in the following way:&#13;
1  *(p   W  + p  m   + p  D ) + (CF    *MTC)&#13;
EWRR    =    r     1 m     00      0  e        mtc&#13;
ru                            W&#13;
r&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 68 -&#13;
where, MTC      Marginal cost of migration and training,&#13;
CFmtc     A conversion factor for migration and training&#13;
costs; and&#13;
De        Disutility of effort.&#13;
The EWRR would then, ceteris paribus, become somewhat higher. This formula&#13;
may become especially important when migration over larger distances is&#13;
involved, and when housing in rural areas is abandoned while new housing in&#13;
urban areas has to be provided.&#13;
119.      (3) The output-foregone has finally to be converted into border&#13;
prices. The simplest way to do so is to use a Standard Conversion Factor.&#13;
This assumes that on average the output foregone is a mix of typical produc-&#13;
tion of urban and rural area. We have, however, decided that it is worth the&#13;
effort to distinguish between the typical urban and the typical rural economy.&#13;
Therefore, we converted the output foregone with a "Conversion Factor for&#13;
foregone marginal product of labor" which includes only BPRs of the typical&#13;
rural production, like agriculture, forestry and fishery. In the case of&#13;
Colombia these BPRs do not differ much from the average (excluding petroleum&#13;
sectors), but in other economies, with a bigger variance of the BPRs, this&#13;
distinction may matter. Protection rates in typical urban sectors, like all&#13;
subsectors of the manufacturing sector, may be significantly higher than in&#13;
typically rural sectors.&#13;
120.      (4) Similarly, if there appear to be significant differences in&#13;
purchasing power between rural and urban areas, these should be taken into&#13;
account in the EWRR-Formula. If the purchasing power of a wage was found&#13;
to be smaller in urban than in rural areas in a specific region in Colombia,&#13;
the EWRR would turn out to be somewhat smaller. We have not made such an&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 69 -&#13;
adjustment in our formulae where migration to the cities is assumed, since&#13;
there exist no nationwide representative data for Colombia.&#13;
EWRR    for Semi- and Technically Skilled Urban Workers&#13;
s ts&#13;
121.      Thie formula differs only little from the one used for the non-traded&#13;
sectors:&#13;
n&#13;
1 Z p. W. + p m + p D&#13;
u1           0 i  o0  o  e&#13;
EWRR                         0~~~~~~- .6e&#13;
sts             W&#13;
sts&#13;
The data used for this calculation are contained in Table 6. The denomina-&#13;
tions are basically the same as those for the non-traded sectors, except for&#13;
the following:&#13;
(1) There is only one general project wage called Wsts, not a set of&#13;
six urban non-traded wages. W3t. (average project wage for s &amp; t&#13;
skilled workers) - Col$60,127 in 1976 current pesos. Therefore,&#13;
we can calculate EWRR     for all urban semi- and technically-skilled&#13;
sts&#13;
labor with one summation over j only; we do not need a second&#13;
summation over i.&#13;
(2) Labor is withdrawn from the nine urban sectors (n - 9), where it is&#13;
paid a wage Wj, without the project (Table 6). It is additionally&#13;
withdrawn from the unemployed labor force, at a proportion of po,&#13;
out of total labor force hired to the project which is, as done&#13;
earlier, conservatively assumed to be equal to the average rate of&#13;
unemployment in the urban sectors for which we have these wage data;&#13;
that is p - 0.10. As mentioned in the calculation of the EWRR for&#13;
the non-traded sectors, p may assume alternative values depending&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 70 -&#13;
on findings in a project context. This would then change the&#13;
proportions pj in Table 6.   If po is assumed or found to be higher&#13;
than 10%, the EWRRStS would ceteris paribus be lower,&#13;
(3)  The marginal product of labor for workers which would be unemployed&#13;
without the job (mo) again is assumed to be zero. The same is&#13;
true for the disutility of effort (De = o), since we have no data&#13;
which allows us to estimate this item on an average for all urban&#13;
sectors.&#13;
Table 6: BACKGROUND DATA FOR THE EWRR FOR SEMI- AND TECHNICALLY SKILLED&#13;
LABOR IN COLOMBIA /1&#13;
Urban Sectors                           P-l                 W;&#13;
(In pesos of&#13;
First quarter 1977)&#13;
Agriculture (urban areas)                0.005                62,400&#13;
Mining (urban areas)                     0.002                 63,600&#13;
Industry                                 0.225                59,370&#13;
Electricity, gas, and water              0.012                55,350&#13;
Construction                             0.050                57,700&#13;
Comprce                                  0.178                61,150&#13;
Transportation and communication         0.088                62,900&#13;
Banking and insurance services           0.088                65,980&#13;
Public services                          0.253                60,550&#13;
Unemployed (sector 0)               po   0.100                     0&#13;
Total                               1.000&#13;
A    Data from DANE, Encuesta de Hogares, First quarter 1977.&#13;
3.   Calculating Conversion Factors for the Marginal Product of Labor&#13;
(Step 10)&#13;
122.      If rural labor were shadow priced in the Trade-Data-Approach   using&#13;
export and import data as weights, a uniform SCF of 0.90 would have been used&#13;
for converting marginal product of labor foregone into border prices /2. This&#13;
would have yielded the following results:&#13;
/2 Compare Annex I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 71 -&#13;
EWRR     = 0.59 *        = 0.57&#13;
uu            0.93&#13;
EWRR     = 0.58 * 0-90     0.56&#13;
ru            0.93&#13;
EWRR     = 0.68 * 0.90     0.70&#13;
sts           0.88&#13;
The differences are not very significant given the fact that these efficiency&#13;
wage rate ratios are considerably lower than 1.0, and since the trade data&#13;
estimate of the SCF is not too different from the one for the Conversion&#13;
Factors fur the Marsinai Product of Labur focegone (MPLCFs). However, the&#13;
difference may become significant in other countries, and that is why the&#13;
calculation of MPLCFs may be worthwhile, especially, if output foregone happens&#13;
in only a few specific sectors, where it is either heavily subsidized or taxed.&#13;
To show the concept and to find the order of magnitude of the differences, we&#13;
here calculated three MPL-Conversion Factors.&#13;
123.      MPLCFs differ from shadow wage rates in that they are an input into&#13;
them and are used in order to border price output foregone in labor intensive&#13;
sectors appropriately, rather than applying any of the General Conversion&#13;
Factors. Whereas GCFs are derived with output used as weights, the MPL-&#13;
Conversion Factors calculated here use employment figures as weights. The&#13;
more labor intensive a sector is, the bigger a weight would its BPR get and,&#13;
therefore, more appropriately reflect the loss in output through withdrawal&#13;
of workers into the project. Thus, a sector like commerce, which may be&#13;
highly labor intensive, would be treated differently from a sector like&#13;
electricity, gas and water, which is highly c:apital intensive, even if their&#13;
share in total urban output were the same.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 72 -&#13;
124.        In step 10, the final step in the iterative approach, we calculate&#13;
(1)  A rural MPL-Conversion Factor (RMPLCF) by taking an arithmetic&#13;
average of the BPRs of the activities in which a large amount&#13;
of rural labor is involved.&#13;
(2)  Similarly, an Urban MPL-Conversion Factor (UMPLCF) is calculated&#13;
by taking another weighted average of certain BPRs. The weights are&#13;
the relative quantity of labor in each of nine activities considered&#13;
to be largely urban, where manufacturing is composed of 19 sub-&#13;
sectors /l. The BPRs used are simple averages of the 1-0 BPRs&#13;
of sectors which belong to each of the nine activities.&#13;
(3) A National MPL-Conversion Factor (NMPLCF) is a weighted average&#13;
of the RMPLCF and the UMPLCF, where the weights are the share&#13;
of rural and urban population in total population, assuming&#13;
that participation rates are about the same in both areas /2.&#13;
These calculations yield the following results:&#13;
RMPLCF -lr     0.93    Average of I-0 sector BPRs 1, 2, 3&#13;
UMPLCF    lu - 0.89    Weighted average of BPRs of urban sectors&#13;
NMPLCF - 1 - 0.90&#13;
/    Calculated from DANE, "Encuesta de Hogares."&#13;
/2   Labor force is assumed to be distributed in proportions similar to the&#13;
population.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- l3 -&#13;
BPRs for the Urban MPLCF and Calculation of National MPI.CF&#13;
Average&#13;
Sector                                      BPRs&#13;
Urban agriculture                                  0.93&#13;
Mining                                             2.30&#13;
Industry                                          0.93&#13;
Electricity, gas and water                         1.10&#13;
Construction                                       0.87&#13;
Commerce                                           0.74&#13;
Ti insportation                                    0.97&#13;
Banks and insurance services                       0.85&#13;
Public services                                   0.80&#13;
NMPLCF  =  0.35 (RLCF + 0.65 (ULCF)   =  0.90&#13;
125.      The MPLCFs calculated here do not differ much from the SCF    for&#13;
intermediate and final goods, excluding petroleum, which is 0.92. However,&#13;
they differ somewhat more among each other, and they would differ yet more if&#13;
they were calculated in a more disagregated form. For instance, if it were&#13;
known that labor in a project A is withdrawn in specific sectors where the BPR&#13;
is considerably above 1.0 (like coffee or transport), and that their inpu&#13;
coefficient for labor is high, we would get an MPLCF for this loss in output&#13;
which is considerably higher than the one in a project B, withdrawing labor&#13;
from certain other sectors which have BPRs considerably smaller than 1.0&#13;
(like "Manufacturing," or "Transportation Material and Machinery"), or which&#13;
do not work labor intensive at all. Irrespective of the ratio between output&#13;
lost, unemployment and wages paid in the project, the shadow wage rate ratios&#13;
would look sizeably different only on account of the fact that domestic wage&#13;
ratios have to be converted to border prices. Also, since wages are important&#13;
inputs into most projects, and because shadow wage rates tend to be signifi-&#13;
cantly smaller than 1.0, the sophistication of using MPCLFs may contribute&#13;
sizeably to better shadow pricing results.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 74 -&#13;
4.   The Usefulness of Aggregate EWRRs&#13;
126.      Although EWRRs, as a country economist provides them, are based on&#13;
many averages of various determinants, which each may have very large variances&#13;
among each other, the calculation of these nationwide EWRRs is not altogether&#13;
futile. They may usefully be applied for:&#13;
(a) shadow pricing smaller and/or inhomegenous parts of the labor&#13;
cost of a project in an appraisal stage; and perhaps more&#13;
importantly,&#13;
(b) shadow pricing all labor costs in a preappraisal stage, which,&#13;
as World Bank work shows, should be done much more often. The&#13;
same applies here as for the Multi-Sector-Conversion Factors&#13;
for commodities mentioned above.&#13;
127.      Annex 5 provides some further suggestions how a project economist&#13;
may obtain more specific Shadow Wage Rates in the case of Colombia, and how&#13;
he should interprete the ones given here. These suggestions are based on&#13;
the assumption that in practice there exists a great many of different labor&#13;
markets between which a transition is not easy because of differences in&#13;
skills, migration costs and similar factors. With these qualifications in&#13;
mind, EWRR- and SWRR-calculations should already be quite useful when they&#13;
are calculated by a country economist. The more he breaks them down into&#13;
sectors and the more he uses additional information as provided in an Input-&#13;
Output-Approach, the more can his results be used fairly readily for most&#13;
preappraisals by various project economists, both inside and outside the&#13;
World Bank.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 75 -&#13;
PART D. CONVERSION FACTORS AT SOCIAL PRICES&#13;
128.      So far we have calculated a set of Border Price Ratios at the&#13;
efficiency level only. However, shadow pricing should not stop at that level,&#13;
but rather take distributive effects and different values of private consumption&#13;
and government income into account. We thuE describe in this chapter how a&#13;
set of "Social Border Price Ratios" has been calculated.&#13;
129.      The steps followed to derive the "Social BPRs" is largely analogous&#13;
to the ten steps used to derive "Efficiency BPRs." The only differences are&#13;
the following: (1) one of the primary inputs, labor, is initially converted&#13;
to social prices rather than efficiency prices. Therefore, we get a new vector&#13;
of nine Social Wage Rate Ratios. (2) Entrepreneurial income is, in a second&#13;
round, converted by a social Standard Conversion Factor. (3) To the extent&#13;
that the commerce sector's BPR is altered by the social analysis, the BPRs of&#13;
the traded sectors may also change somewhat, since commerce provides the&#13;
distribution margins. The process is iterative; however, only the final&#13;
conversion factors will be presented here.&#13;
1.   Deriving Border Price Ratios for Traded Sectors&#13;
130.      All 22 traded BPRs remain the same as before.   This is due to the&#13;
fact that the only element that might have altered them, the commerce sector's&#13;
BPR, remained equal to 0.94, as before in the efficiency analysis.&#13;
2.   Social Wage Analysis for Non-Traded Sectors&#13;
131.      The social wage analysis is meant to take into consideration the&#13;
distributive effects of changed consumption, and value the consumption in terms&#13;
of government income. The analysis below is identical to the efficiency wage&#13;
analysis with the exception that a social adjustment is made to the EWRR for&#13;
unskilled labor.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 76 -&#13;
132.       S &amp; t-skilled and academically-skilled labor are not thought to experiE&#13;
significant changes in consumption; therefore, a social analysis of these parts&#13;
of the labor sector would indicate only a negligible social adjustment to their&#13;
efficiency wage rate. Thus, for the non-traded sectors, the SWRRs are assumed&#13;
to equal the EWRRs for these sectors. In addition, the MPL-Conversion Factors&#13;
(1 , I ) remain as in the efficiency analysis.&#13;
3.   Unskilled Social Wage Rate Ratio&#13;
133.      The formula chosen here is similar to one used by Linn for the&#13;
Social Wage Rate in Ivory Coast /1, since we feel that this kind of model of&#13;
migration to the cities is also a good approximation for the unskilled urban&#13;
workers in Colombia:&#13;
SWRR   . -   EWRR  .                                      )   Efficiency wage&#13;
u,l          U,1                                      )  rate ratio&#13;
d.&#13;
+     (Wui  Wr       v     W(&#13;
(M-l)  (Y  y)        U     1Social&#13;
+@1 (M -l)   ue    a         v    Wui        adjustment          (2&#13;
d       13)&#13;
0 O (M - ) (Y e) ( B v 11&#13;
)&#13;
1        ~ue        v    W.i&#13;
The "social adjustment term" to an Efficiency Wage Rate, which in very simple&#13;
terms is written&#13;
d.&#13;
AC (a - v )&#13;
/I   Linn, Johannes F.:   "Economic and Social Analysis of Projects, A Case&#13;
Study for Ivory Coast." World Bank Staff Working Paper No. 253, 1977,&#13;
p. 48.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 77 -&#13;
conumpo  distribution&#13;
i.e., in words:     change in   *     consumption          weight&#13;
consumption          facnvers on    value of public&#13;
income in terms&#13;
of consumption&#13;
consists here of three components. which are each written out in a separate&#13;
line. /&#13;
134.      Each component reflects different changes of consumption which accrue&#13;
to the following three groups of persons: (1) a migrant worker and his dependents&#13;
who finds employment in the cities; (2) a migrant worker and his dependents who&#13;
does not; and (3) the rest of all urban unskilled workers who already live in&#13;
the urban area and sacrifice some of their own consumption by sharing it with&#13;
the migrants who stay unemployed.&#13;
135.      Each of these three income or consumption groups (the propensity to save&#13;
is here, for simplicity, assumed to be zero) also get a different distribu-&#13;
tion weight, depending upon&#13;
(a) if the change of their consumption is small or not, and&#13;
(b) what the consumption level without and with the project would&#13;
be. Let us consider each group of workers in turrn.&#13;
136.        (1) Migrant workers of the first consumption group enjoy an increase&#13;
from the average agricultural wage W    = Col$14,616 to a new level which is the&#13;
average wage W ui in each of the non-traded sectors (see Table 2 in part B).&#13;
This change in consumption is described as (W i - W ).     It has first to be&#13;
multiplied with the Consumption Conversion factor, which yields the net cost&#13;
to the economy which occurs since these workers "eat up" resources (W i - Wd)-&#13;
I                                  ~~~~~~uf&#13;
LI For the derivation of these variables, refer to part F; we follow, in&#13;
that part of the analysis, clearly the Squire-van der Tak method. The&#13;
values of the variables are summarized on page 23.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 78 -&#13;
It then is multiplied by the distribution weight di (which is one calculated&#13;
with the formula for non-marginal changes) for each change from the uniform&#13;
agricultural wage W  to the W i paid in all the different non-traded urban&#13;
sectors; and then divided by the parameter v to express the change in consump-&#13;
tion by government income, which is part of the definition of the numeraire in&#13;
our social shadow pricing method. We-thus arrive at the net value of addi-&#13;
tional consumption of the first income group, expressed as (W    - w ) * (   d -  i ).&#13;
ui    r         -r&#13;
This whole expression is then yet to be divided by each of the wages W 1 paid to&#13;
unskilled workers in the non-traded sectors, to make it compatible with the&#13;
fact that we always calculate a Shadow Wage Rate Ratio in one move, without&#13;
calculating the Shadow Wage Rate first and then making it a ratio in a second&#13;
step.&#13;
1-37.     (2) The second line of our equation values the increase in consump-&#13;
tion of the migrating unemployed workers and their families. There are&#13;
(H - 1) - 15% of the workers who move but remain without a job and live out of&#13;
other people's pockets. Their per capita consumption without the project is Yap&#13;
which is the average agricultural wage on which y = 3.1 people have to live on&#13;
average.  In the city, it is assumed that slightly more people, namely    01 = 3.5,&#13;
have to live on one income. (Some of the dependents will not find income as&#13;
they did in the rural areas with garden farming, etc.)&#13;
138.      It is now further assumed that the unemployed worker and his depen-&#13;
dents do not maintain the same low consumption level as before in rural areas,&#13;
but rather consume what they would earn in the lowest paying of all non-traded&#13;
urban sectors, that is Col$17,600; this amounts to a per capita consumption&#13;
level of Y   = Col$5,046, for each of the 3.5 dependents on this wage, and&#13;
ue&#13;
is not much higher than their consumption in rural areas. The total change in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 79 -&#13;
consumption of the unemployed worker and his dependents is therefore expressed as&#13;
e1 (M - 1) (Y - Y ).&#13;
1        ~~ue   a&#13;
139.      This change in consumption is now to be converted iLnto the&#13;
numeraire in the three steps mentioned above: (1) converted into border prices,&#13;
(2) valued in relation to the average consumer, and (3) converted to govern-&#13;
ment income.  The distribution factor d   ,again, is one for discrete consumption&#13;
changes (duu = 2.94).&#13;
140.      (3) So far we have had two positive changes in consumption; there&#13;
appears, in the third line of the equation, the valuation in social terms of&#13;
the negative change in consumption of the urban receptors, who are assumed&#13;
to pay for their unemployed friends or relatives. It is easily described as&#13;
e1 (M - 1) Y   ,as explained above.         -   r) is the corresponding&#13;
1       eu ueu)&#13;
v&#13;
social weight of the urban receptors, which is derived by assuming that urban&#13;
receptors suffer only a marginal change in consumption. They live at a per&#13;
capita consumption above the critical consumption level, whereas the mean&#13;
consumption (average between rural and urban incomes) of the migrants is only&#13;
slightly below the CCL, and the one for the unemployed migrants is clearly&#13;
below the CCL.&#13;
141.      Inserting the values of   p , the di, v, and the different consump-&#13;
tion levels into the equation, we obtain the following values for the social&#13;
adjustment for urban unskilled labor:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 80 -&#13;
Social Adlustment for Urban Unskilled Labor&#13;
Social&#13;
EWRRU i    Adiustment       WRRU i&#13;
Electricity, gas and water            0.66         - .05          0.61&#13;
Construction                          0.72         - .04          0.68&#13;
Commerce                              0.79         - .04          0.75&#13;
Transport                              0.54        - .04          0.50&#13;
Communication                         0.54         - .04          0.50&#13;
Banks and insurance services           0.69        - .03          0.66&#13;
Other private services                 0.47        - .01          0.46&#13;
Public services                       0.47        - .01           0.46&#13;
When the SWRRs for the urban unskilled are appropriately weighted and combined&#13;
with the s&amp;t-skilled and academically-skilled ratios, we obtain the overall SWRRS&#13;
for each of the non-traded sectors.&#13;
EWRRnt        SWRRnt&#13;
Electricity, gas and water           0.83          0.83&#13;
Construction                         0.78          0.76&#13;
Commerce                             0.76          0.75&#13;
Transport                            0.71           0.71&#13;
Communication                        0.71          0.71&#13;
Banks insurance services             0.81           0.81&#13;
Other private services               0.66           0.65&#13;
Public services                      0.66          0.65&#13;
In general, the SWRRs are slightly lower than the EWRRs. An explanation&#13;
for this is given in section D.5.&#13;
142.      The so derived Social Wage Rate Ratios for the non-traded sectors&#13;
are then used to border price the labor input coefficients in the same way&#13;
as done before with the EWRRs.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-81-&#13;
4.   General Social Wage Rate Ratios&#13;
143.      As in the case ot EWRR , the Gene ral Social Wage Rate Ratios ;.ippIy&#13;
to the urban and rural ec     ry a'; a whole.  They differ, thereiore, fromii the&#13;
previously calculated SWRRs for thie non-traded sectors in that they are&#13;
somewhat more general.   The formulae chosen are thus a generalization of the&#13;
ones for.the non-traded sectors and will not be explained in any further&#13;
detail.&#13;
(a) For the urban semi- and technically-skill.ed workers, the change in&#13;
consumption was thought to be minimal and hence no account was taken of it,&#13;
so that EWRR     = SWRR    = 0.68.&#13;
sts       sts&#13;
(b) For the urban unskilled worker, thie formul.a used is as stated&#13;
below:&#13;
SWRRU  = EWRR                                          Efficiency Ratio&#13;
uu       uu)&#13;
d&#13;
+ (W  -w )&#13;
d&#13;
+ Q2(M - 1)  (Yu  -             ue     1   )&#13;
ue    a          v  ) W      )   Social Adjustment&#13;
u&#13;
d                 )&#13;
- 9(M - 1)   (Y  )  (     u r      1&#13;
2           ue                 wJ&#13;
)&#13;
144.      As in the case of l.WRRs for all.the urban versus only the non-traded&#13;
sectors, the meanings and values of the parameters correspond to the ones for&#13;
non-traded sectors (Chapter D.3) and are given in Table I of the Summary (page&#13;
6 of 6). The meanings and values of the parameters correspond to the ones for&#13;
non-traded sectors and are given in Table 1 of the Summary.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 82 -&#13;
145.      The (W   - W ) represents the change in consumption which accrues&#13;
u    r&#13;
to the new worker and his dependents as they migrate.     (W  - W ) B represents&#13;
the efficiency cost at border prices of providing this additional consumption.&#13;
-W  - W )*  uu   represents the benefit of the additional consumption weighted&#13;
v&#13;
by an appropriate 'd'.&#13;
e2(M - 1) (Y    - Y )  is the change in consumption accruing to the additional&#13;
migrants. 02(M - 1) Y         is the negative change in consumption which the&#13;
urban receptors suffer as they are forced to support the additional migrants.&#13;
146.      Inserting all values into the equation, the SWRR for all urban&#13;
unskilled workers becomes&#13;
SWRR    = 0.55&#13;
uu&#13;
(c)  For the rural unskilled Social Wage Rate Ratio the formula used was:&#13;
SWRR   = EWRR                    )   Eficiency Wage Rate Ratio&#13;
+ (W1 -W) (B -    ru)     )   Social Adjustment&#13;
where ( W- W )is the change in consumption accruing to the new rural worker&#13;
and his family. As before, we assumed that the rural unskilled worker has a&#13;
marginal product equal to the minimum rural salary and that his wage in the&#13;
project will equal the average agricultural wage. SWR.Rru = 0.46.&#13;
5.   Relationship Between EWRRs and SWRRs in Colombia&#13;
147.      The Efficiency Wage Rate Ratio for unskilled labor in all non-traded&#13;
sectors in the urban economy is somewhat larger than the Social Wage Rate&#13;
Ratio; the value of a wage of an unskilled worker is worth about 3 percentage&#13;
points less, when appraised in social terms, than when calculated in efficiency&#13;
terms. The same is true for the General Social Wage Rate Ratios of all urban&#13;
unskilled workers, where the difference is 4 percentage points as the follow-&#13;
ing table shows.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 83 -&#13;
Colombia:  Relationshi.p Between EWRRs and SWRRs&#13;
1;eneral      Genera.1     Di ference&#13;
lype of Labor               EWRRs         SWRRs       EtR - ';WRR&#13;
Urban unskilled workers          (.59           0.55(&#13;
Rura.l uiLskiI led workers       0.58           ().46         0.12&#13;
Urban s-&amp;-t-skilled workers      Ii.68          ().68&#13;
This may seem somewliaLt surprising as compa Ied   ther- I.l Fis ( e * e.., I v r t  ms(t I /&#13;
where EWRR &lt; SWRR; btut for the case of Colombia it may he explaiited aS F(ell_Iws.&#13;
The average per capita income of utnskiLled irbanl workers, as we have defillod&#13;
them, is about Col$7,900 with the project, which is somewhat more ( bin lie&#13;
critical, consumption level, the level at whichi the government. valuIes addit (i11.1 1&#13;
consumption not less than investment., i.e., is prepared t(,) pay sisi dieS. But&#13;
it is only about Col$4,900 without the project.    li , for simplicity.  '1 tl!l--&#13;
weighited average is taken, the per capita (:onsumptiinn oE an urtibani woiket wou (ii&#13;
he around Col$6,400 and thus somewhlat helow the (CCI&#13;
14R.      While in other countries people whco consume only as mucIh &#13;
than the CCL would Predominantly 1ive in rural areasL in Goulombia hiey Live&#13;
partly in urban areas, since tbe share o)f ritral popiil aLn, with only 35% ot&#13;
a LI population, is extremnely sma I l.  Iherefori, while in oth er l,I(:s tn ily&#13;
for the rural unskilled workers wonl d F,WRR &gt; SWRR be trute, in Colombia it&#13;
not only holds for them, but also for urban ursk.i l.edl. Al so, as the table&#13;
shows, and consistent with the foregoinig, a social appraisal would make&#13;
rural unskilled labor in Colombia cheaper by a wider margin than urban&#13;
unskilled Labor, namely by 12 instead of 5 percentage points.&#13;
149.      The relationship between the order of magnittude of EWRR an(I SWRR&#13;
depends, of course, on many other variables. One prIncipal rule is the&#13;
1/   See Linn, Johannes:   "Economic and Social Analysis of Projects, A Case&#13;
Study for Ivory Coast." World Bank Staff Working Paper No. 253, 1977.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 84 -&#13;
following: whenever, at a given magnitude of change in consumption, the&#13;
Consumption (,oversion Factor for the respective income group is smaller than&#13;
the ratio of the distribution weight "d" and the value of public income&#13;
"v", i.e.,                          d.&#13;
If 8 ( l&#13;
v1 &#13;
the change in consumption will be a net benefit, and&#13;
EWRR &gt; SWRR&#13;
150.      This again is so whenever, ceteris paribus, the distribution weight&#13;
for the respective income class tends to be about as great or greater than the&#13;
value of public investment. I/ This means that the benefit of aivina hither&#13;
d.&#13;
consumption to relatively poor people, expressed by     AC *  I , is valued higher&#13;
V&#13;
than the cost to the economy, in border prices, which arises because people&#13;
consume more, (expressed as ACP) 2/. Since we have several terms for social&#13;
adjustment, this rule holds only under the ceteris paribus condition.&#13;
151.      In Colombia, given the values of the parameters and the formula&#13;
chosen, the consumption of the urban unskilled is low enough when compared to&#13;
average consumption, to make hiring unskilled labor coming from rural areas&#13;
slightly more attractive to the decision maker under the social appraisal&#13;
method, than under the efficiency method.&#13;
6.   Differences Between Conversion Factors for Commodities at&#13;
Efficiency and at Social Prices&#13;
152.      As mentioned above, all 22 BPR's for traded sectors remained the same&#13;
as before. The BPR's for nine non-traded sectors change only very little, too&#13;
little to really matter. The discrepancies are shown in the following table:&#13;
1/   This also implies the following     (if only a small change in consumption&#13;
occurs);whenever beneficiaries of a project have a consumption under the&#13;
CCL, the EWRR is greater than the SWRR.&#13;
2/   The sign of this item, although being a social cost, is positive because&#13;
it brings the accounting price of labor closer to the market price.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 85 -&#13;
TABLE 7: COLOMBIA - BORDER PRICE RATIOS FOR NON-TRADED SEC-JRS&#13;
Sector No.                   Cal½Uvr-.ed at         Calculated at     Difference,&#13;
F, K_.iency Prices     Social Price,      4r. erLcent.&#13;
23. Electricity, gas,&#13;
&amp; water                   1.096                  1.099             0.3&#13;
24.  Construction                0.868                  0.860             0.8&#13;
25.  Commerce                    0.932                  0.937             0.5&#13;
26.  Transport                   1.088                  1.092             0.4&#13;
27.  Communication               0.827                  0.830             0.3&#13;
28. Banking and insurance&#13;
services                  0.841                  0.841             0.0&#13;
29.  Housing rental              0.855                  0.863             0.7&#13;
30.  Other private services      0.788                  0.787             0.1&#13;
31.  Public services             0.758                  0.750             0.8&#13;
153.      This also implies that the differences in the General Conversion&#13;
Factors, calculated at social prices or efficiency prices, were negligibly&#13;
small (see Table I in the Summary). This means that, in the case of&#13;
Colombia, a project economist may work with only one set of Sectoral and&#13;
General Conversion Factors for commodities, whether he does an analysis at&#13;
social prices or at efficiency prices only. As we have seen before, thiq&#13;
was not the case with the Shadow Wage Rate Ratios.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 86 -&#13;
E. THE OPPORTUNITY COST OF CAPITAL (g)&#13;
154.      The formula below is used in the derivation of the marginal product&#13;
of capital 1/.&#13;
MPK   =FX    -                         SK*  *  SCF&#13;
[j~~  AK  ~~~JJ        ICF&#13;
Where:&#13;
MPK      Average marginal product of capital at efficiency&#13;
prices&#13;
AQ   =   Change in net domestic product (in millions of constant&#13;
1970 pesos)&#13;
AK       Net fixed investment (in millions of constant 1970 pesos)&#13;
AL       Change in employed labor force&#13;
MPL      Marginal product of labor (constant 1970 pesos per&#13;
employed worker)&#13;
To derive AQ/AK, AL/AK, and MPL, figures were used from years 1971 through&#13;
1974 2/.  The AK,    or net investment stream,was calculated by estimating&#13;
depreciation and subtracting it from gross investment. Depreciation was&#13;
calculated by multiplying the capital consumption, as stated in the National&#13;
Accounts, by 0.8 3/. The AQ is estimated by subtracting our depreciation&#13;
estimateN from gross domestic product. The AL is calculated from CCRP&#13;
estimates of employment in the whole economy 4/.&#13;
1/   Squire-van der Tak, op. cit., page 110.&#13;
2/   COLOMBIA:  Country Economic Memorandum, May 1977; Deflators Table 2.10;&#13;
more recent data were not used since investment in 1975, 1976 was&#13;
atypically low.&#13;
3/   Harberger has estimated that depreciation on average is overestimated&#13;
in the National Accounts by 20%, see "'La Tasa de Rendimiento de Capital&#13;
en Colombia", Revista de Planeacion y Desarrollo, Oct. 1969, p. 21.&#13;
4/   Corporacion Centro Regional de Poblacion (CCRP), Bogota, SERES Model.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 87 -&#13;
The marginal product of labor is calculated using the formula:&#13;
HPl, =   0.6 (change in Natic;0   Lncome t (change in Employed T.hor Force)&#13;
"Wages and salaries" taken from the National Accounts do, by far, not fully&#13;
describe the compensation of the labor force.     A large portion of .t is&#13;
contained in the component "income from entrepreneurship and profits."&#13;
This and "wages and salaries" taken together was estimated by Harberger&#13;
to be 60% of national income   1/.   We thus obtain the following basic valties&#13;
for  the macroeconomic estimate of the marginal product of capital in domestic&#13;
prices, which is then to be converted into border prices: 2/.&#13;
Values for Calculation of MPK&#13;
AQ           - AK              AL                         MPL&#13;
In Millions of            Employed             In constant Pesos per&#13;
Constant 1970 Pesos         Workers                  Employed Worker&#13;
1972           7,164        19,616        260,000                     16,341&#13;
1972          10,513        19,109        272,000                     21,653&#13;
1973          10,095        20,003        285,000                     22,iY80&#13;
1974           8,190        21,150        302,000                      15,369&#13;
1/   Arnold Harberger:   La Tasa de Rendimiento ....., op. cit. p. 15.&#13;
2/   Strictly speaking, each component in the above formula for MPK should&#13;
be converted separately into border prices. This would be done as&#13;
shown in Annex 8.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 88 -&#13;
Ihe SCF taken here is the one for final demand only, using average weights&#13;
and including export 1/, calculated with Efficiency Wage Rate Ratios 2/,&#13;
and excluding petroleum sectors. Petroleum is excluded in the SCF since&#13;
2&#13;
it is assumed that its prices will be raised in the medium-term future.&#13;
SCF2  -  0.92&#13;
ICFP  S  0.91&#13;
With the General Conversion Factors so chosen, MPK at domestic prices does&#13;
not differ from MPK at foreign prices.&#13;
155.      With these qualifications we arrive at a value for the MPK of about&#13;
13.5%. This is a relatively high estimate since (1) the marginal product&#13;
attributable to technical progress and land are in this approach attributed&#13;
to capital, and because (2) the estimate reflects the marginal product of&#13;
capital during the years of the average public and private sector investment&#13;
project, i.e. of the better and the worse projects. However, what is needed&#13;
is an approximation of the Economic Internal Rate of Return of the least&#13;
profitable public investment project in Colombia, which must be lower than&#13;
the average yield 3/. To approximate this rate, we look first at a lower&#13;
bound by taking an average of the real cost for the Colombian government&#13;
entities of borrowing abroad.&#13;
1/   To make it match the definitions of AQ and MPL, ideally marginal&#13;
weights should be taken. However, this yielded distorted results.&#13;
2/   For use in social analysis, this should be replaced by the Social&#13;
Wage Rate Ratios.&#13;
3/   It is assumed here   that the yields of the last public and private&#13;
investment projects are equal.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 89 -&#13;
156.      We do this comparison first strictly in a context of efficiency&#13;
pricing, although ,'e are aware that this is an arbitrary procedure 1/.&#13;
The real cost 2/ of Government borrowing on international comi jrcial&#13;
markets is found to be about 3.5%, if Colombia maintains its present conser-&#13;
vative policy of foreign borrowing. The derivation and interpretation of&#13;
the marginal cost of borrowing, based on past and projected figures, is laid&#13;
out in Annex 6.&#13;
157.      The cut-off economic rate of return for projects, at efficiency&#13;
prices, will be within these limits. Theoretically, the number of public&#13;
sector projects could be increased, and the amount of foreign borrowing&#13;
could be expanded until the Economic Rate of Return of the last project&#13;
equals the (probably rising) cost of borrowing abroad, which is somewhere&#13;
between these two interest rates. However, this will certainly not be as low&#13;
as anywhere near the present borrowing rate, since (a) this rate would increase&#13;
and, probably more importantly, (b) the Colombian public sector would have&#13;
neither enough administrative capacity, nor enough domestic counterpart funds&#13;
for loans from abroad which might be offered, even at a premium for increasing&#13;
risk, by international lenders.&#13;
158.      Colombian authorities have stated that they consider, for their&#13;
easy-to-quantify public sector investment projects, a rate of about 11% as&#13;
their economic cut-off rate. This rate can be considered relatively high,&#13;
too, if compared with the present and projected cost of marginal borrowing.&#13;
1/   In-a more complete context of shadow pricing, the real rate of foreign&#13;
borrowing can only be compared to the ARI, the cut-off rate at social&#13;
prices. This we shall do later on.&#13;
2/   Nominal U.S. dollar-denominated interest rates are deflated by the&#13;
World Bank's projected "International Price Deflator".&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 9u -&#13;
Leaving practical problems aside, it could, therefore, be considered a step&#13;
towards an optimal investment policy if the Government decided to lower the&#13;
cut-off rate and to expand the public sector investment program. Since&#13;
agencies for implementation and administration of public projects seem to&#13;
be bottleneck factors 1/, the Colombian Government might think of hiring a&#13;
larger number of foreign consulting firms and other contractors so long as&#13;
national agencies are too small. It might then seem economically reasonable&#13;
to lower the cut-off rate moderately to, say, 9%, so as to increase the number&#13;
of foreign financed projects.&#13;
159.      A much lower economic cut-off rate would, in a medium-term planning&#13;
horizon of about five years, probably not be feasible (a) because building&#13;
up the additional project implementation agencies would not work fast enough,&#13;
and (b) because the domestically produced part of the extra projects thus to&#13;
be implemented might have to create excess domestic demand in certain sectors&#13;
which could lead, under certain conditions, to changes in relative prices. We&#13;
therefore, consider a cut-off rate of 9% as a realistic lower limit of g,&#13;
expressed in border prices, in the short- to medium-run.&#13;
160.      Taking an arithmetic average between our higher bound and out&#13;
lower bound estimate for q, we would arrive at a central estimate for q of&#13;
around 11%, which coincides with the present practices of the Colombian&#13;
Government. We do not assume here that the Government will actually follow the&#13;
strategy of aggressively increasing public investment and foreign borrowing,&#13;
in the next five years, partly on the grounds of their traditionally conserva-&#13;
tive strategy in foreign borrowing.&#13;
1/ This could lower the EIRRs of additional projects rather rapidly.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 91 -&#13;
161.      We, therefore, take a value of q of 11% as our best estimate for&#13;
the OCC in _order prices.&#13;
162.      In a more complete ev-;. :tion, the borrowing rate of . %     s to&#13;
be compared to the Accounting Rate of Interest (ARI), which subsequently is&#13;
calculated to be around 6.3% (Chapter F.4). If all projects are appraised&#13;
in social terms, their Social Internal Rate of Return would still show a&#13;
gap between yield of the project and cost of funds, although the gap would&#13;
be smaller. Optimally, a planning agency would therefore tend to increase the&#13;
list of projects until the increasing cost of funds equals the decreasing&#13;
yield of the last projects.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 92 -&#13;
PART F. SOCIAL PRICING PARAMETERS IN COLOMBIA&#13;
163.      The Social Pricing parameters other than Social Wage Rate Ratios,&#13;
which we derived for Colombia, are ini the paper described in somewhat Less&#13;
detail than the efficiency parameters. This is done so mainly because we&#13;
follow very closely the Squire-van der Tak approach, which has been illustrated&#13;
very well and extensively by other authors 1/.&#13;
1.   The Consumption Rate of Interest (i)&#13;
164.      Our best estimate for the Consumption Rate of Interest (CRI or i) in&#13;
Colombia is 5.5Z. This interest rate measures how much less valuable a unit&#13;
of consumption received a year from now is, than a unit received today. The&#13;
CRI was estimated according to the commonly used formula:&#13;
CRI = i = ng + e    /2&#13;
The estimation of the various sub-parameters is described below.&#13;
(a) The Rate of Pure Time Preference ( e)&#13;
165.      The component     , the rate of pure time preference, was assumed to&#13;
be e = 2%.    If it is considered at all that e      , being the Rate of Pure Time&#13;
Preference as perceived by the Government, is a tangible variable, we propose&#13;
to justify this value as follows: the value of 2% is about one percentage point&#13;
lower than the real interest rate paid to foreign borrowers by the Colombian&#13;
public entities. This is an approximation for real market interest rates paid&#13;
1/   e.g., see Linn, Johannes:    Economic and Social Analysis of Projects,&#13;
. . . op. cit.&#13;
2/   See Squire-van der Tak, op. cit., p. 140.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 93 -&#13;
by the Government for savings in Colombia, where one percentage poin' allows&#13;
for the difference between the real .ate of borrowing and lending 1/.&#13;
166.      Although some auLilors Lave used values of e = 0%, we     dve not&#13;
considered a value significantly lower than 2% appropriate since interest rates&#13;
received by savers are probably slightly low anyway due to money illusion of&#13;
some of the savers 2/. Our value for e also assumes that the long-term rate&#13;
of Government savings reflects only the Rate of Pure Time Preference, and not&#13;
the CRI itself.&#13;
(b) The Elasticity of Marginal Utility with Respect to Consumption (n)&#13;
167.      The value of n, the elasticity of a marginal loss in utility due&#13;
to a marginal gain in consumption, was taken to be n = 1.0, as done in the&#13;
previous shadow pricing estimate in Colombia 3/. If at all any modification&#13;
might be used, one could assume n = 0.75 as an alternative. When the previous&#13;
estimate of shadow prices in Colombia was made, the then Colombian Covernment&#13;
had just taken office. At that time the public sector investment program&#13;
aimed at a significant redistribution of expenditures towards the poorer&#13;
population in form of social projects. Not all of these programs were indeed&#13;
implemented. Whether this was due to a lack of "absorptive capacity" or to&#13;
some basic change in the Government's intentions, cannot easily be evaluated.&#13;
1/   Taking international rates paid by the Government is necessary since&#13;
interest rates in Colombia are administered.&#13;
2/   Also, while the real market interest rate on financial savings may be 0%&#13;
in times of rising inflation, it may become significantly positive in&#13;
times of decelerating inflation.&#13;
3/   For some justification, see Conesa, Eduardo; Shadow Pricing Exercise&#13;
for Colombia, office memorandum, World Bank, December 1974.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 94 -&#13;
Only if the latter were the case, and if the previous assumption of n = 1.0 is&#13;
considered to be a generally acceptable standard, should this slight downward&#13;
actjiistmenit be macde.&#13;
168.      However, too little is known so far about some representative&#13;
values of n for LUCs with similar social policies, as expressed in income and&#13;
wealth taxes, minimum wages and subsidy policies. If inter-country comparison&#13;
is a desirable goal in World Bank social pricing exercises, some "absolute"&#13;
standards for hlighly subjective values like n might be agreed upon. In this&#13;
light, the value of n = 1.0 is a provisional number and should be refined in&#13;
further analysis.&#13;
(c) The Expected Crowth of per Capita Consumption (g)&#13;
169.      The value of g was projected to average about 3.5% in the next five&#13;
years. This compares with about 4% on average in the 1971-76 period, and&#13;
takes into account some deficiency of new investment in recent years. The&#13;
value g = 3.5% assumes a growth in consumption of about 6% and an increase&#13;
in population of around 2.5% per annum.&#13;
2.   The Consumption Distribution Weights (d.)&#13;
170.      The consumption distribution weight (di ) for a particular group&#13;
of beneficiaries will often have to be estimated in a specific project context,&#13;
when non-marginal changes in consumption occur. Examples of such distribution&#13;
weights are given in our Social Wage Rate Ratios, where projects are simulated&#13;
which lead to sizeable changes in consumption. For the calculation of the&#13;
specific d    and d  , therefore, consumption levels with and without the&#13;
uu      ue&#13;
project were taken into account.&#13;
171.      Only in cases where it may be assumed that small changes in con-&#13;
sumption are caused by the project, either on the input or the output side,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 95 -&#13;
can the marginal consumption distribution weight be applied. The following&#13;
Table 8 gives these weights for the copsumption distribution of the Colombian&#13;
economy, by decils.&#13;
172.      We already made some limited use of these distribution weights when&#13;
we calculated the Social Wage Rate Ratios, estimating dur* A project economist&#13;
would use the values for di in many more instances. Whenever, on the cost or&#13;
benefits side of the project, increases in consumption occur, which without the&#13;
project would not occur, they have to be valued just as in the case of the&#13;
SWRR calculations. This refers both to what might be labeled "direct"&#13;
consumption changes of the project, and to "indirect" changes. The latter,&#13;
typical "spillover effects," may extend over various income groups and are&#13;
often hard to assess. It is then left to the project economist's judgment&#13;
to decide where the marginal cost of social evaluation equals its marginal&#13;
benefits.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 96 -&#13;
Table 8:   COLOMBIA - CONSUMPTION DISTRIBUTION W(dl.T        ) Cd&#13;
Average per Capita&#13;
Percentage              Consumption in Each     Marginal&#13;
Population        of Total                Percentile Group, ci    Distribu-&#13;
Percentile        Consumption              (1976 Current          tion Weight&#13;
(M)                (X)                    Pesos)                (n=1.0)&#13;
Lowest     10              1.61                     2,563               6.16&#13;
20              '.59                     4,107                3.85&#13;
30              3.54                     5,599                2.85&#13;
40              4.39                      6,951               2.27&#13;
50              4.80                      7,603               2.08&#13;
60              6.24                      8,876               1.60&#13;
70              7.66                    12,132                1.30&#13;
80             10.48                     16,601               0.95&#13;
90             17.75                    28,112                0.56&#13;
100             40.93                    64,827               0.24&#13;
E = 100                   c = 15,798    15,800&#13;
Note:&#13;
1.   The base data for the underlying income distribution are adjusted from&#13;
Selowsky, Marcelo: "The Distribution of Public Services Across Income&#13;
Groups, A Case Study of Colombia," Unpublished Paper, LBRD, May 13, 1977.&#13;
The distribution percentiles are converted to absolute figures by&#13;
applying them to average household consumption taken from National&#13;
Accounts.&#13;
2.   The distribution weights are derived by applying the formula d      =&#13;
- n                                                              i&#13;
(c/ci) , where c   is the national average per capita consumption&#13;
(Col$15,800) and ci is the average per capita consumption in each&#13;
of the percentile groups.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 97 -&#13;
3.   The Value of Public Income in Relation to Average Consumption (v)&#13;
173.      The value of public income v was estimated with the following&#13;
equations: 1/&#13;
q   1&#13;
Minimum Value     V   . * -                  (1)&#13;
Maximum Value     v   (i   s) *q             (2)&#13;
(isq)     8&#13;
The minimum value equation assumes that no reinvestment of the annual yields&#13;
of the public project takes place, which makes the value of a public sector&#13;
project smaller. The second equation assumes that the private and/or the&#13;
public sector save and reinvest some of the profit of the project, which there-&#13;
fore yields ceteris paribus a higher value of v.&#13;
(a) Deriving the Marginal Propensity to Save (s)&#13;
174.      Theoretically, the marginal propensity to save should reflect&#13;
savings out of public net revenue resulting from a project. We have, however,&#13;
approximated a normative public marginal propensity to save by taking the&#13;
observed private MPS. This was done for the following reasons:&#13;
175.      The global MPS (for public plus private savings) equals, according&#13;
to National Accounts figures, only s = 0.185 (Average 1970-1976). The&#13;
private MPS, for the same period, equalled on average 0.25. The public MPS,&#13;
therefore, was sizeably below the global MPS and had a big variance. Had we&#13;
taken any value for the public MPS considerably below the global one, the&#13;
assumed small savings out of government project income would have resulted&#13;
in a very low value for ARI. This again would have implied a cut-off rate for&#13;
1/   From Squire-van der Tak, op. cit., pages 106, 195, respectively.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 98 -&#13;
the social evaluation well below 6%. A great number of low yielding projects&#13;
would then have to be included in the investment budget which otherwise would&#13;
not be undertaken.&#13;
176.      To avoid these implications, we postulate that, for planning reasons,&#13;
the MPS should be relatively high, i.e., the public MPS should be as high as&#13;
the historical private MPS. Estimating with equation (1) for alternative&#13;
values of q and i, we have the following lower bound results for v:&#13;
Table 9: LOWER BOUND VALUE OF PUBLIC INCOME&#13;
(no reinvestment case)&#13;
v = q/Bi       B = 0.94&#13;
q         9%            11%          13%&#13;
5.5%&#13;
f-2Z         1.74         2.13         2.51&#13;
3.5%&#13;
V_o%         2.74         3.34          3.95&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 99 -&#13;
For the upper bound value of v we have the following results:&#13;
Table 10 - UPPER BOUND VALUE OF PUBLIC INCOME WITH REINVESTMENT&#13;
(Partial Reinvestment Case)&#13;
1 - s)q    l         - 0.94&#13;
i -isq      B      s = 0.25&#13;
q         9%        11%         13Z&#13;
ix&#13;
;25%        2.20       3.19       4.61&#13;
3.5%        5.74      11.70       41.49&#13;
Formula (2) probably overestimates the true value of public income because&#13;
(a) the formula assumes that all parameters remain unchanged over time.&#13;
However, q, the opportunity cost of capital in border prices, can be assumed&#13;
in Colombia to decrease over time, as high yielding projects become scarce&#13;
and as the government increases its implementation capacity as recommended&#13;
above. (b) In Colombia the share of public investment in total public&#13;
expenditures appears to have decreased in recent years, partly due to restraint&#13;
on government investment expenditures during the years of the coffee boom,&#13;
1976 and 1977. The Colombian Government, therefore, seems to believe that&#13;
public investment should increase faster in the future than public consumption,&#13;
partly to finance large investments in the energy sector.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 100 -&#13;
This means that presently the value of public income (which should be looked&#13;
at as an average of the values v, for public investment and ve for public&#13;
consumption), must be somewhat below the value of public income estimated&#13;
here, where only the opportunity cost of public sector investment projects&#13;
was taken as input.&#13;
177.      Which of the alternative values of v seems most realistic is now a&#13;
matter of good judgement and testing for consistency. The values calculated&#13;
with a CRI = 3.5% in the upper bound formula seem to be too high. They were&#13;
calculated to show how sensitive v is to variations of      e  towards zero.   In&#13;
the calculation of q we considered 11 % as our best estimate. With e = 2%,&#13;
i   5.5% and q = 11%, our upper and lower limits of v would be 3.19 and&#13;
2.13, respectively. We shall now try to locate v with the help of an esti-&#13;
mate of the critical consumption level CCL.&#13;
(b) Deriving the Critical Consumption Level (CCL)&#13;
178.      Our best estimate of the CCL, that is the consumption of relatively&#13;
poor people in Colombia at which the government would start to consider&#13;
paying consumption subsidies rather than investing, was estimated to be&#13;
about Col$6,670. People who live at this critical consumption level can&#13;
only spend 42% of what the average consumer in Colombia can spend, and about&#13;
38% of the total population live under this consumption level, enjoying&#13;
only about 4.2% of total consumption.&#13;
179.       The CCL of about Col$6,670 in 1976 current pesos was derived as&#13;
follows: it takes into account the values of taxable income prevailing in&#13;
1977, at which the tax rate just equals zero. From the tax free net income,&#13;
gross figures were derived by working with a dependency ratio of 3.0 persons&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 101 -&#13;
living on one income in this income class in urban iri      and allowing for&#13;
the tax deductlons most commonly used by small income earners.&#13;
180.      The results so   -tained are, however, only tentative    just as&#13;
all calculations of relative poverty levels are somewhat hypothetic. Since&#13;
this study focuses mostly on deriving a large set of efficiency prices,&#13;
there was less time available for various other checks of the value of&#13;
v 1/. We have, however, checked it against estimates of both relative and&#13;
absolute poverty levels, and the results were positive.&#13;
181.      Our figure for the CCL is about one fourth (24%) higher than the&#13;
"relative poverty level" as defined by the World Bank, which is one third of&#13;
household income before direct taxes); and it is almost one third (31%) higher&#13;
than the absolute poverty level as calculated for 1976. Since the relative&#13;
poverty level .fn Colombia is not much higher than the absolute level, the&#13;
relative poverty line must not be considered as an approximation for the CCL,&#13;
but rather as a lower limit, and the estimate of around Col$6,670, as revealed&#13;
indirectly through the tax legislation, seems --easonable and consistent&#13;
with the poverty levels.&#13;
(c) The Best Estimate of the Value of Public Income&#13;
182.      Returning to our best estimate of v, we insert our CCL value into&#13;
the basic equation for the social pricing in the Squire-van der Tak method,&#13;
and arrive at a value of v=2.52. This is only a little bit lower than the&#13;
simple average between our lower and upper bound formula estimate. Given the&#13;
very crude way in which both the CCL and the values determining v, especially&#13;
1/ If more time were available, the CCL should be estimated and checked&#13;
through additional data. (Compare our note on the determinants of&#13;
"v" in Annex 7).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 102 -&#13;
n and q, have to be estimated or almost assumed 1/, we consider it&#13;
unreasonable to specify v for more than a decimal point and will use it as&#13;
v = 2.5. A project economist should be careful as to how to use this value.&#13;
Some interpretation and refinement is given in Annex 7.&#13;
4.   Accounting Rate of Interest (ARI)&#13;
183.      The ARI is used as a discount factor of future net benefits which&#13;
are expressed in the numeraire, that is, public income at border prices.&#13;
The ARI expresses the opportunity cost of capital "q" in terms of its social&#13;
value at border prices.&#13;
q&#13;
ARI = sq + (l    s)      0.063&#13;
Where s = marginal savings rate                                      =  0.25&#13;
q = opportunity cost of capital at border prices               =  0.11&#13;
v - social value of public income relative to consumption      =  2.5&#13;
= consumption conversion factor                                = 0.94&#13;
184.      We thus get a discount rate for all public income which is about&#13;
one percentage point higher than the discount rate used for all consumption&#13;
streams, the CRI; and about five percentage points lower than q, the discount&#13;
rate for public income, when no premium is placed on public income 2/. In&#13;
1/   See Annex 7:  "Note on the Value of Public Income and Its Determinants."&#13;
2/   Alternatively, if a strategy of investment were chosen which accepted&#13;
projects down to an Economic Internal Rate of Return at border prices&#13;
of 9% by borrowing more extensively abroad, the social discount rate&#13;
ARI, by which future public income streams would have to be discounted,&#13;
would be ARI = 3.2%.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 103 -&#13;
other words, the Social Internal Rate of Return on the marginal project&#13;
in the public sector can be as low as 6.3%.&#13;
185.      If this cutoff rate, again, is compared with the real cost of&#13;
foreign borrowing of 3.5%, it appears that,in a social pricing context,&#13;
Colombian planners could theoretically still increase their investment&#13;
budget, e.g., until the last project approved, at social prices, yields&#13;
only say 5%, and until the increasing cost of foreign borrowing abroad&#13;
has arrived at about this level.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 104 -&#13;
ANNEX I&#13;
METHODS USED FOR ESTIMATING CONVERSION FACTORS IN&#13;
TRADE-DATA APPROACH, AND REASONS FOR DEVIATIONS FROM PREVIOUS ESTIMATES&#13;
1.   Introduction&#13;
This Stage I estimate uses the "Trade Data Approach", i.e., takes&#13;
weights for the commodity conversion factors from trade data rather than from&#13;
data for the whole economy, as e.g., done in what we call the "Input-Output-&#13;
Table Approach". In that respect it is comparable to Conesa's calculations 1/.&#13;
In the second stage we used an input output table, and we contrasted the&#13;
results to the trade data approach in order to show to what extent results&#13;
are likely to differ purely by the method chosen. 2/ Also we used, in&#13;
Stage I, representative historical years or averages of them for the parameters,&#13;
whereas in Stage II we applied, to some extent, projected data. (The order of&#13;
magnitude of the discrepancies between these approaches would be of interest,&#13;
too).&#13;
The results obtained in the T-D-Approach differed in many instances&#13;
from those derived by Conesa. This is to be explained by three factors:&#13;
- slightly different methods for estimation;&#13;
- different definitions for the data used, like in the case of&#13;
shadow wage rate ratios; and&#13;
- updated data base.&#13;
1/   A first calculation of country parameters for Colombia was done in an&#13;
early study by Eduardo Conesa in December 1974 for the World Bank.&#13;
2/   See Table I in main text:    "Summary of National Accounting Parameters&#13;
in Colombia", page 20.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 105 -&#13;
ANNEX 1&#13;
2.   Conversion Factors for Commodities&#13;
These factors are used to convert values expressed in domestic&#13;
prices to those expressed at border prices, thus adjusting for distortions in&#13;
the domestic economy. The values for the General Conversion Factors are the&#13;
following:&#13;
- Standard Conversion Factor ( a or SCF) = 0.90&#13;
-  Consumption Conversion Factor ( R or CCF) = 0.89&#13;
- Raw Material and Intermediate Goods Conversion Factor (RMICF) = 0.93&#13;
- Investment Goods Conversion Factor (ICF) = 0.86&#13;
The formula used for the derivation of these factors is as follows:&#13;
K. t X.&#13;
C?:   M.                           1,2   ..., n&#13;
C: Mi-(l+toi  + X (1-ti)          ,...&#13;
where i denotes the type of conversion factor to be calculated, and Mi and Xi&#13;
are the imports and exports belonging to the ith class of goods, e.g., consump-&#13;
tion, investment, etc; tmi denotes the import tariff rate for each class (derived&#13;
implicity from actual collections), and t xi denotes export taxes or, more often,&#13;
export subsidies (derived implicitly from actual payments).&#13;
Coffee exports have been omitted in the above calculations because it&#13;
was felt that the value of coffee exports relative to total exports greatly&#13;
exaggerates the relative weight of coffee in marginal expenditures. In other&#13;
words, it would be imprecise to convert non-coffee goods and services into&#13;
border prices using a conversion factor derived with a high trade weight&#13;
of coffee. This is a kind of partial adjustment for the distortions implied&#13;
in the Trade-Data Approach, although a very imperfect one as compared to&#13;
taking weights from the 1-0-Table.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 106 -                           ANNEX I&#13;
The calculated conversion factors differ from Conesa's results.&#13;
Somewhat more sophisticated formulas were used by Conesa in his final results.&#13;
For the SCF and the CCF he used marginal figures as weights while ours are, in&#13;
stage I, average figures. In calculating the Capital Goods Conversion Factor,&#13;
Conesa used a breakdown of components into construction, imported capital&#13;
goods, and inventory, while we used imported machinery and equipment only, as&#13;
long as no CF for construction was available.&#13;
3.   Some Comments on the Data Base and Other Reasons for Discrepancies Between&#13;
Old and New Estimates in Trade Data Approach&#13;
Conversion Factors for Commodities&#13;
As done in the 1-0-Approach, import tariff rates t    , expressed in&#13;
m&#13;
percent of 1976 peso import values, are those prevailing in 1976. It was the&#13;
opinion in DNP 1/ and INCOMEX 2/ that this average rate structure is the best&#13;
approximation of the medium term future. Neither should it be as high as in&#13;
1974, when the Lopez Government decided to lower import protection, nor should&#13;
it be as low as in 1977 when some imports were freed to offset coffee export&#13;
receipts. Also 1976 is the most recent year with fairly complete and definite&#13;
sets for most data. Analogously, export subsidies and export taxes reflect&#13;
the effective structure of 1976, in percent of 1976 current peso exports. In&#13;
both cases, collected import duties and paid export subsidies (in form of&#13;
CATs) were used, as provided from treasury data. 3/&#13;
The alternative would have been to use import duty and export subsidy&#13;
rates as taken from the legal code, and apply them to the effective import/export&#13;
1/   Departamento Nacional de Planeacion (National Planning Department).&#13;
2/   Instituto Colombiano del Comercio Exterior (Colombian Foreign Trade&#13;
Agency).&#13;
3/   Obtained through DANE, National Accounts Division.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 107 -&#13;
ANNEX i&#13;
values of each CIIU or CUODE class. We decided to not use this alternative&#13;
in both the Trade Data and the 1-0-Approach because:&#13;
- we have no updated calculations on Plan Vallejo effective&#13;
export subsidies, therefore we accounted them as reductions&#13;
of the import duties.&#13;
- we do not know the extent of import duty exemptions for&#13;
Government imports and duty reductions for imports from&#13;
Andean Group Countries.&#13;
These three items should largely explain the difference between a received and&#13;
a calculated average import duty rate. On the exports side, while CATs are&#13;
included, export subsidies through PROEXPO credit could not be incorporated&#13;
because of lack of data.&#13;
Through the analysis of commodity-conversion factors in both the T-D&#13;
and I-0 approach it is assumed that Colombia in the medium term future wil]&#13;
maintain on average its present structure of protection, and will adjust all&#13;
discrepancies between domestic and foreign price levels which would affect&#13;
export and import competitiveness, via the exchange rate.&#13;
The investment conversion factor differs from the one calculated&#13;
in 1974 in that it does not account for (a) construction investment and not&#13;
for (b) inventory investment. Construction is largely a non-traded commodity&#13;
and was therefore properly to be calculated with the Input-Output-Table&#13;
Approach. Inventories should basically be converted by the Standard Conversion&#13;
Factor and may well be separated from fixed investment. We added a Conversion&#13;
Factor for Raw Materials and Intermediate Goods since this is useful in&#13;
practical evaluation and because it is already a component of the standard&#13;
conversion factor.&#13;
/I This is a relatively strong assumption, and the implications of relaxing&#13;
it are still to be researched in the theory of shadow pricing.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 108 -&#13;
ANNEX 1&#13;
Our new SCF was higher than the new ICF because import duties on raw&#13;
materials in 1976 are the lowest of the four categories, thus pulling the SCF&#13;
closer to one. Protection on consumer goods through import duties seems to&#13;
have been reduced since 1973.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 109 -&#13;
ANNEX 2&#13;
THE INPUT-OUTPUT-APPROACH: AN ILLUSTRATIVE EXAMPLE&#13;
For convenience of the reader, we here reprint an illustrative&#13;
example of the calculations performed in the Input-Output-Approach 1/. The&#13;
example is a simple version, done on a 4 by 4 inter-industry matrix, of what&#13;
we have done in Colombia on a 31 by 31 matrix.&#13;
Furthermore, in Tables 1 and 2 of this annex we present the actual&#13;
model printout for the Standard Conversion Factor SCF4 (average weights from&#13;
total intermediate and final demand, with petroleum subsidies) and for the&#13;
Consumption Conversion Factor CCF3 (average weights from I-0-Table). This&#13;
information can readily be used to calculate all kinds of Multi-sector CFs,&#13;
or General CFs excluding certain sectors.&#13;
Table 3 of this annex contains the printout of our Consumption&#13;
Conversion Factor CCF2, calculated with marginal propensities to consume out&#13;
of total expenditure which are derived from an urban consumer survey. Table 4&#13;
shows the Investment Conversion Factor ICFI which is calculated with "marginal&#13;
weights" obtained through the I-0-Tables. A large number of sectors, of course,&#13;
have an expenditure weight of zero since they do not produce investment goods.&#13;
1/   Reprinted, with permission of the authors, from:     "Pilot Study on National&#13;
Accounting Parameters: Their Estimation and Use in Chile, Costa Rica and&#13;
Jamaica, Volume 2, pages 277-283; by Pablo Guerrero, Eleanor Howard,&#13;
Deepak Lal, Terry Powers. Inter-American Development Bank, Economic and&#13;
Social Development Department, Country Studies Division, Project Methodo-&#13;
logy Unit; Washington, D.C., October 1977. I am indebted to the authors&#13;
and the IDB-Management for this reprint and the help they extended to me&#13;
when I was using their computer model.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 110 -&#13;
EXAMPLE USING INPUT-OUPUT ANALYSIS&#13;
TO CALCULATE NON-TRADED COMMODITY BORDER PRICE RATIOS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TABLE 1&#13;
InnUt-Out2ut Matrix&#13;
Surlanldia&#13;
(millions of pesos)&#13;
tputs to&#13;
sector&#13;
Inputs&#13;
from                              Ex-  House-   Profit  Invest-  Govern-&#13;
sector           A   B   C    D  port   holds    aPP.    ment      ment    Total&#13;
A     5  14   12   6   23     15       0        3        3      81&#13;
B    18   7   10   6    0     26       0        8        2      77&#13;
C    11  15   4   18    0     13       0        4        3      68&#13;
D    12  11  24    5    0      1       0        2        1      56&#13;
Imports           3   3   1.  4    0      2        0       0        0       13&#13;
Households       18  16  10  11    0       1       2       0        6       6,4&#13;
Operating&#13;
surplus       10    5   3   2    0      0        0       0        0      20&#13;
Depreciation      2   1   1   2    0      0        0       0        0        6&#13;
Government        2   5   3   2    2      12       0       2        1       29&#13;
Total            81  77  68  56   25      70       2      19       16      414&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 112 -&#13;
Table I shows the input output matrix of Surlandia. There are four&#13;
processing sectors of which two (A and B) produce traded output and two&#13;
(C and D) produce non-traded output. Sector A's output is exported at&#13;
the margin, while sector B's output is imported. Our objective is to&#13;
obtain a set of border price ratios for the four processing sectors. For&#13;
the sectors producing traded output (A and B), we calculate the border price&#13;
ratio according to the following formulas.&#13;
To simplify the exposition, we form the border price ratios for the&#13;
traded sectors taking account only of tariffs and assuming constant product&#13;
prices. The border price ratio for the exportable is:&#13;
p   ,    1&#13;
x          tx&#13;
and for the importable,&#13;
Pt     1 + t-&#13;
the  tx  is the marginal tax rate on exports and    tm  is the nominal tariff&#13;
on imports.&#13;
Sector A produces an exportable, which we asa.me has a 5 percent export tax.&#13;
The border prices ratio is thus:&#13;
1 &#13;
Px     1     - .05  1.053&#13;
Sector B produces an importable, which we assume has a 25 percent nominal&#13;
tariff so that:&#13;
1&#13;
P                -  .8000&#13;
1 + .25&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 113 -&#13;
The border price ratios for non-traded sectors (C and D) are obtained&#13;
in the following manner.&#13;
1. Determine the A matrix of technical coefficients per unit of gross&#13;
output, from the input output table.&#13;
5        14      12       6&#13;
81        77      68      56&#13;
18         7      10       6&#13;
81        77      68      56&#13;
A=&#13;
11        15       4      18&#13;
81        77      68      56&#13;
12        11      24       5&#13;
81        77      68      56&#13;
.06      .18     .18     .11&#13;
A       .22      .09     .15     .11&#13;
.14      .19     .06     .32&#13;
.15      .14     .36     .09&#13;
2. Partition the A matrix into four sectors&#13;
(A11     A12&#13;
A-&#13;
A21      A22&#13;
.06    .18l .18            .11 l14             .19          .06   .32&#13;
All     L ^ .22  .0   12     .15      .11  A21      5   .14  A22      36   .09&#13;
The four sub-matrixes describe the following activities:&#13;
All -   traded inputs into traded outputs&#13;
A12     traded inputs into non-traded outputs&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 114 -&#13;
A21 - Non-traded inputs into traded outputs&#13;
A22 = Non-traded inputs into non traded outputs&#13;
We have border priced the traded sectors directly; the border price&#13;
ratios for non-traded output is the sum of all factor inputs when these have&#13;
been valued at their border prices. The inputs into the non-traded sectors&#13;
are:&#13;
(1) home produced traded inputs as described by the sub matrix A12&#13;
(2) direct imports&#13;
(3) labor&#13;
(4) net operating surplus&#13;
(5) capital consumption&#13;
3. Form a new matrix H which describos the direct factor requirements&#13;
per unit of gross output. The A12 matrix is already expressed as such, so&#13;
we need only carry out the calculations on items 2 to 5 above.&#13;
.18      .11                     .18       .11&#13;
.15      .11                     .15       .11&#13;
1        4                      .01        .07&#13;
68       5&#13;
H       10        11 5                   .15       .20&#13;
368       2                     .04       .04&#13;
68       56                     .01       .04&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 115 -&#13;
4. The matrix of direct and indirect requirements of factor inputs&#13;
per unit of final demand (G) is:&#13;
G =  H (I-A22)f&#13;
(I-A 22)-    is the Leontief inverse of A22 and is obtained in the&#13;
following manner:&#13;
(I-A22) -  I-A22&#13;
01       F6      .3&#13;
1g        L6      .39&#13;
. 94       -.32&#13;
-.36      .61&#13;
The inverse of (I-A22) is:&#13;
-I     [.3313      .6981&#13;
.7857   2.0515&#13;
We get the G matrix of global factor requirements per unit of output&#13;
as:&#13;
G - H (I-A22) -1&#13;
.33   .35        .18   .11      [.3313       .698&#13;
.29   .33   .    .15   .11   x     .7857    2.0515&#13;
.07   .15        .01   .07&#13;
.36   .52        .15   .20&#13;
.08   .11        .04   .04&#13;
.04   .08        .01   .04&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 116 -&#13;
5. The vector of border price ratios for the non-traded sector B&#13;
is:&#13;
B - PG&#13;
Where P is a vector of border price ratios for the factor inputs, and&#13;
G is the matrix of global factor inputs required per unit of non-traded&#13;
output.&#13;
We assume the following factor border price ratios:&#13;
Factor                            Border Price&#13;
Input                                Ratio&#13;
Sector A                             1.053&#13;
Sector B                              .8&#13;
Direct Imports                       1.0&#13;
Wages                                 .5&#13;
Operating Surplus                     .8&#13;
Capital consumption                   .7&#13;
B - PG&#13;
.33        .35&#13;
B  .053       .8   1.0   .5     .8     j   x&#13;
]7  ~  .29       .33&#13;
.07        .15&#13;
.36        .52&#13;
.08        .11&#13;
.04        .08&#13;
B -   L2     1.]&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 117 -&#13;
Our sectoral border price ratios are:&#13;
Border&#13;
Sector                    Price Ratio&#13;
A                         1.053&#13;
B                          .8&#13;
C                          .92&#13;
D                         1.19&#13;
The general conversion factors would be a weighted average of these&#13;
sectoral border price ratios. We can use the expenditures from the input-&#13;
o;itput table as weights, or expenditure data from other sources.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 118 -                          Ajn4E 2 - Table I&#13;
sTAt;:;u,MP) COt4V IKS ION FACTOR&#13;
US INC Al nyIulRka'tlOITS&#13;
{ToLe1 1r.tciwp4.  nd Final Dead)                  PR for&#13;
UPRs for  Traded plus&#13;
Traded   Non-traded&#13;
9.ctors    Secto.u&#13;
EXP   LABOR    mi-URiC   INFU79   FROFITS   CAPlTAL    INPUTS   BP-CONT&#13;
CAT   (WL*)    (M*)      (P12*)   (52*)      (h2*)     (PI)      (U)&#13;
ttttgt**$Ftt*t .s tlit*t**tt*tt^ 9sstt**T*8999e**9*99999*9999*9*999**t&#13;
I                                                   0.93000   0.93000&#13;
2                                                   0.93000   0.93000&#13;
3                                                   0.92000   0.92000&#13;
4                                                   2.30000   2.30000&#13;
5                                                   1.21000   1.21000&#13;
6                                                   0.90000   0.90000&#13;
7                                                   0.95000   0.95000&#13;
a                                                   Q.93000   0.93000&#13;
9                                                   1.01000   1.01000&#13;
10                                                  0.66000    0.66000&#13;
11                                                   0.92000   0.92000&#13;
12                                                  0.90000    0.90000&#13;
13                                                  0.95000    0.95000&#13;
14                                                   1.01000   1.01000&#13;
15                                                  0.99000    0.99000&#13;
16                                                   0.09000   0.89000&#13;
17                                                  3.00000    3.00000&#13;
18                                                   0.94000   0.94000&#13;
19                                                  0.99000    0.99000&#13;
20                                                   0.86000   0.96000&#13;
21                                                   0.87000   0.87000&#13;
22                                                   0.83000   0.83000&#13;
23   0.33391  0.        0.43336  0.32847   0.                  1.09574&#13;
24   0.38495  0.        0.39979  0.08340   0.                  0.06814&#13;
25   0.20340  0.        0.12400  0.60430   0.                  0.93170&#13;
26   0.26277  0.        0.38967  0.4352S   0.                  1.00769&#13;
27   0.45847  0.        0.08722  0.28148   0.                  0.82717&#13;
28   0.68361  0.        0.10012  0.04911   0.                  0.84003&#13;
29   0.04466  0.        0.02056  0.78952   0.                  0.85474&#13;
Jo   o.261t)/ v.        0.256417  0.2/35/  0.                  0.78.30&#13;
31   0.51902  0.        0.22262  0.01596   0.                  0.75760&#13;
Tot.l .Intermdiate and Final&#13;
DUand by 31 Sectors&#13;
in Millions of pesos, at&#13;
EXP    DOMES.    DQ DER&#13;
CAT    PRICES    PRICES&#13;
asssasu****tsssss*t*s***&#13;
I    **99**99  t9**8**t&#13;
2     1872.00   1740.96.&#13;
3     2148.00    1976.16&#13;
4     7991.00  19379.30&#13;
5    27586.00   33379.06&#13;
a    36347.00  32712.30&#13;
7    2579/.00  24t501.lb&#13;
8     6917.00   6339.81&#13;
9     6165.00   6226.65&#13;
10    19302.00  12739.32&#13;
11     4442.00   4086.64&#13;
12    11940.00  10753.20&#13;
13    44255.00  42042.25&#13;
14     5118.00   5159.18&#13;
15    18571.00  103"5.29&#13;
16    56250.00  50062.50&#13;
17    160d2.00  481H.00&#13;
19     8615.00   8098.10&#13;
19    24273.00  :!1602.97&#13;
20'   22491.00   19342.26&#13;
21    18716.00   162U4.66&#13;
22     5537.00   4595.71&#13;
23     6406.00   7019.30&#13;
24    37592.00  32635.16&#13;
25     1021.00    951.26&#13;
26    49653.00  54007.17&#13;
27     4663.00   3h'i7.09&#13;
28    38961.00  32759.66&#13;
29    19303.00   15644.22&#13;
30    42438.00  33453.8Y&#13;
31     2872.00   21w5983&#13;
imp       0.        0.&#13;
TOT  696439.00 6n4/:35.28&#13;
THE CONVERSION FACTOR IS 0.9H305&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
..                                  4&#13;
-&lt; tOorro  .0 bOObOOOcOUm p  K&#13;
*  'j@  ~-,c,ooLDei VA0 Oe0 0  00O0 oo0hpiloq&#13;
aCt-     c0 C       .4  N144**&#13;
0 *&#13;
x-                    ......... x      r  4'4&#13;
0&#13;
I-  U  ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~1 410P- AN- &#13;
~..4 0**C~00000000000AMC 000                   '&#13;
ta  .Xt4 . ~04~0~S0000U   . m     .    .  . . . . ..&#13;
XC 4Nt"wnTrseoo-fMtesedrvttJobo-NN"fyrn*trM";tot"*   Ju _*Nl*-Lrx ZOo-elitLaxtbtt*toyt"&gt;*tt7"^^ttNtNt&gt;*rtw -t-* *&#13;
S  C  *~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~ ~ ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~r  ,U  D0r  Lz00L)I I- &#13;
-. 4 ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~~~~  r  ItlaP 0r &#13;
- ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~~~~~~~~  nC  C, AI :C.0t         ~ er 4  w4  -1N  l0L&#13;
1.1.                     000~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~A000000A                          CD  4&#13;
4                        4~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~M4&#13;
j                    Z~~~~~~~~00 0000 00* 4i&#13;
*              4~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ &#13;
Q.                                  .&#13;
*                                             *L4  00. 4TLI'   0   Z :00000000 000aC.4C  0000= 0-0&#13;
tii u                                  WU~~~000 00 04*  fl-               N 4  -&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 120 -                           ANNEX 2 - Table 3&#13;
CONSU?PTION C6ThLItSICO FACTOR (CCa2)&#13;
(Marginal Weight* from Urban Conuswer&#13;
Survey. Inputs In .ftijcimcy YrJce4)&#13;
EXP   LAOOI   I"PORTS    INPUTS   PROFITS   CAPITAL    INPUTS   3P-CONT&#13;
CAT   (ML*)     IN*)     WM2*)    (2*)      (K2*)      (P1)      (U)&#13;
$*$*ss$ess*ssnssssssssgss*Sssssss|ssseesgeessssast$gs*es,g$slss~gsagXss&#13;
1                                                  0.93000    0.93000&#13;
2                                        -          0.93000   0.93000&#13;
3                                                   0932000   0.92000&#13;
4                                                   2.30000   2.30000&#13;
3                                                   1.21000   1.21000&#13;
A                                                  0.90000    0.90000&#13;
0.95000   0.95000&#13;
*                                                  0.93000    0.93000&#13;
9                                                   1.01000   1.01000&#13;
10                                                  0.66000    0.66000&#13;
11                                                  0.92000    0.92000&#13;
12                                                  0.90000    0.90000&#13;
J3                                                  0.95000    0.95000&#13;
14                                                  1.01000    1.01000&#13;
15                                                  0.99000    0.99000&#13;
1I                                                  0.99000    0.09000&#13;
17                                                  3.00000    3.00000&#13;
lo                                                  0.?4000    0.94000&#13;
J9                                                  0   9000  0-89000&#13;
20                                                  0.-6000    0.06000&#13;
21                                                  0.07000    0.87000&#13;
22                                                  0.83000    0.83000&#13;
23   0.33391  0.        0.4333J  0.32847   0.                  1.09574&#13;
24   0.38495  0.        0.J 3"   0.09340   0.                  0.06314&#13;
25   0.20340  0.        0.12400  0.60430   0.                  0.93170&#13;
26   0.2&amp;277  0.        0.39967  0.43525   0.                  1.00769&#13;
27   0.45047  0.       0.08722   0.29148   0.                  0.92717&#13;
29   0.60341  0.        0.10912  0.04911   0.                  0.04083&#13;
29   0.04446  0.        0.02056  0.79932   0.                  0.95474&#13;
30   0.26157  0.        0.25317  0.27357   0.                  0.78030&#13;
31   0.51902  0.        0.22262  0.01596   0.                  0.75760&#13;
t**tStS$g*SSSSS******88*gg**3gS*SS****SSU*SS**S***t****s*Stgt$*ttgS*SS**s&#13;
EXP    DOwES.    BORDER&#13;
CAT    PRICES    PRICES&#13;
**S$**S****S*S3**S**SSS&#13;
1        0.07      0.07&#13;
2        0.00      0.00&#13;
3        0.00      0.00&#13;
4        0.        0-&#13;
S        0.00      0.00&#13;
6        0.00      0.07&#13;
7        0.0?      0.0?&#13;
8        0.02      0.02&#13;
9        0.00      0.00&#13;
10        0.02      0.01&#13;
it        0.01      0.01&#13;
12        0.02      0.02&#13;
13        0.12      0.11&#13;
14        0.01      0.01&#13;
1i        0.03      0.03&#13;
14        0.05      0.05&#13;
17        0.01      0.02&#13;
is        0.01      0.01&#13;
19        0.01      0.01&#13;
20        0.02      0.02&#13;
21        0.01      0.01&#13;
22        *0.01.    001&#13;
21        0.01      0.01&#13;
24        0.        0.&#13;
25        0.        0.&#13;
26        0.04      0.06&#13;
27        0.01      0.00&#13;
29        0.01      0.01&#13;
29        0.01      0.01&#13;
so        0.21      0.17&#13;
31        0.02      0.01&#13;
nip       O.        0.&#13;
TOT       0.85     0070&#13;
THE COWVERSION FACTOR IS 0.91341&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 121 -                          ANNEX 2 - Tobl 4&#13;
i1I7ED4NT GOODS CONVERSION FACTOR&#13;
Iff iciency BPRs  tnrpina1 Weinhza from 1-0 Table)&#13;
EXP   LABOR   IMPORTS    INPUTS   PROFIT$   CAPITAL   INUTS    BP-'ONT&#13;
£                                                    t0.3000  0.93  0&#13;
2                                                  0.93000   0.93000&#13;
3                                                  0.92000   0.92000&#13;
4                                                  2.30000   2.30000&#13;
5                                                  1.21000   1.21000&#13;
6                                                  0.90000   0.90000&#13;
7                                                  0.9SOOO   0.95000&#13;
8                                                  0.93000   0.93000&#13;
9                                                  1.01000   1.01000&#13;
10                                                  0.66000   0.66000&#13;
it                                                  O.92000   0.92000&#13;
12                                                  0.90000   0.90000&#13;
13                                                  0.95000   0.95000&#13;
14                                                  1.01000   1.01000&#13;
15                                                  0.99000   0.99000&#13;
16                                                  0.e9000   0.89000&#13;
17                                                  3.00000   3.00000&#13;
18                                                  0.94000   0.94000&#13;
19                                                  0.89000   0.89000&#13;
20                                                  0.66000   0.86000&#13;
21                                                  0.87000   0.87000&#13;
22                                                  0.63000   0.93000&#13;
23   0.33391  0.       0.43336   0.32847   0.                 1.09574&#13;
24   0.38495  0.       0.39979   0.08340   0.                 0.86014&#13;
25   0.20340  0.       0.12400   0.60430   0.                 0.93170&#13;
26   0.26277  0.       0.39967   0.43525   0.                 1.08769&#13;
27   0.45947  0.       0.09722   0.28140   0.                 0.02717&#13;
28   0.68361  0.       0.10812   0.04911   0.                 0.84083&#13;
29   0.04466  0.       0.02056   0.78992   0.                 0.65474&#13;
30   0.26157  0.       0.25317  0.27357    0.                 0.78930&#13;
31   0.51902  0.       0.22262   0.01596   O..                0.75760&#13;
S*$tStS***S**SS*S**SS*t*SS8SttJt**t***268t**SttS**SttStttttttSt*tSSStS**&#13;
Cbae in Expesditures&#13;
In&#13;
EXP    DOMES.    BeRDER&#13;
CAT    PRICES    PRICES&#13;
ssSSs,soossssSs**s**s***&#13;
I        0.        0.&#13;
2        0.        0.&#13;
3        0.        0.&#13;
4        0.        0.&#13;
5        0.        0.&#13;
6        0.        0.&#13;
7        0.       O0&#13;
8        0.        0.&#13;
9         0.       O.&#13;
10        0.        0.&#13;
11        0.        0.&#13;
12        0.        0.&#13;
13        0.        0.&#13;
14        0.        0.&#13;
15        0.        0.&#13;
16        0.        0.&#13;
17        0.        0.&#13;
16        0.        0.&#13;
19      945.00    752.05&#13;
20        0.        0.&#13;
21      605.00    700.35&#13;
22     1466.00   1216.78&#13;
23      115.00    126.01&#13;
24        0.        0.&#13;
25     4861.00   4528.99&#13;
26        0.        0.&#13;
27        0.        0.&#13;
26        0.        0.&#13;
29        0.        0.&#13;
30        0.        0.&#13;
31        0.        0.&#13;
IMP       0.        0.&#13;
TOT    9092.00   7324.19&#13;
THE CONVERSION FACinR IS 0.90511&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 122 -&#13;
ANNEX 3&#13;
NOTES ON THE INPUT-OUTPUT TABLES AND HOW TO UPDATE THEM&#13;
1.   Input-Output-Table&#13;
We used a 31-sector Input-Output Table of 1972, combined with&#13;
partial updates through 1975, in the case of vectors for changes in ex-&#13;
penditures which are used as weights for the General Conversion Factors.&#13;
There exists a more recent 99-sector I-0-Table which has a much more&#13;
detailed breakdown, to about 90 subsectors, for the industrial sector,&#13;
based on 1975 industrial survey data. Unfortunately we could not use it&#13;
for the following reasons: (a) There exists no corresponding 99-sector&#13;
breakdown of import duties and export subsidies actually paid, but only&#13;
data on theoretically payable duties and subsidies as calculated by taking&#13;
unweighted averages of rates established by law 1/; (b) also, data on ex-&#13;
port subsidies paid through reduction of import duties by "Plan Vallejo",&#13;
and through credit subsidies were not available by 99-sectors. The&#13;
"actually paid" import duty/export subsidy data, however, while not&#13;
containing export subsidies, at least reflect the important "Plan Vallejo"&#13;
subsidies; (c) the final demand matrix of the 1975 table was not available&#13;
and could have been estimated only by crude assumptions from national&#13;
accounts data; (d) the breakdown of typically non-traded sectors which are&#13;
an important reason for using the I-0-Approach was greater in the 1972&#13;
table. However, the 1975 data are available in a computer tape, and&#13;
they may be used by project economists for more detailed work with indus-&#13;
trial projects.&#13;
1/   This series of data produced different results from the one on 31&#13;
1-0-Sectors we used.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 123 -&#13;
ANNEX 3&#13;
2.   Updating the Input-Output-Table&#13;
The 1972 I-0-Table might be updated using a computer routine&#13;
employed, among others,by the Brookings Institution. Such updating is in the&#13;
process of being done in the LDB for countries with very outdated I-0-Tables.&#13;
For updating the 31-sector table of Colombia, the following data are available:&#13;
- the updated 90-sector information on the industrial sector, combined&#13;
with&#13;
-  national accounts data through 1976, broken down by eight sectors&#13;
-  updating sheets for the 31 sector 1972 Table through 1975, which&#13;
have complete data for the matrix of primary inputs, the final&#13;
demand matrix and the vector of total intermediate uses.&#13;
We have not done the updating routine in this exercise because&#13;
of time constraints. The bias, however, may not be all too biR for the&#13;
following reason: the rise of oil prices which led to major changes in&#13;
input coefficients in many countries, probably did not in Colombia so far.&#13;
.Colombia, on the one hand, was until 1975 on a net-basis only importing&#13;
unimportant amounts of petroleum, while before it was a net exporter. On the&#13;
other hand, even when net imports of petroleum increased in the last 2 years,&#13;
prices for petroleum and derivatives, as mentioned earlier, remained strongly&#13;
subsidized, thus preventing a thorough restructuring of the economy so&#13;
far.&#13;
However, if a country, sector or. project economist obtains updated&#13;
vectors of input coefficients through a special study, he may use them for&#13;
calculating his own updated BPRi. Also, if he obtains more specific input co-&#13;
efficients. e.R. for certain subsectors of the agricultural sector, he should&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 124 -&#13;
ANNEX 3&#13;
always calculate his specific BPRV rather than using an average BPR for the&#13;
whole agriculture sector, and add it to the list of our BPRs. This way the&#13;
list of shadow prices would become more sophisticated over time and could&#13;
serve for cross-checking the validity of our BPRs based on a somewhat outdated&#13;
1-0-Table.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 125 -&#13;
ANNEX 4&#13;
THE IMPORTANCE OF INDIRECT TAXES AND SUBSIDIES&#13;
1.         Indirect taxes and subsidies were not taken into account because no&#13;
data were available yet fitting the 31 sectors of the 1-0 Table, after the&#13;
1974-75 tax reform. Once these data will be available, the indirect tax or&#13;
subsidy rates should, of course, be added to the denominator of the formula&#13;
for the BPRs as shown below. Since they are not, there is, of course, a&#13;
systematic bias to the high side (since indirect taxes outweigh subsidies for&#13;
most sectors) of all (a) CFs of the non-traded sectors (b) General Conversion&#13;
Factors. The bias in the traded sectors themselves should, of course, be&#13;
corrected for by the project economist by adding in the term for indirect&#13;
taxes/subsidies for all sectors which constitute important project inputs or&#13;
outputs (see also Chapter B.9).&#13;
2.         The difference which the adjustment makes can be quite substantial,&#13;
as the following example may illustrate:&#13;
t.      (net indirect tax rate)   =  30%&#13;
1&#13;
t       (import duty rate)        =  20%&#13;
m&#13;
D       (distribution margin)     =  10%&#13;
m&#13;
BPRDM   (BPR of distribution sector)   =   0.93&#13;
(1)  If a good is imported and pays an indirect tax (e.g. retail sales tax),&#13;
the BPR would be:&#13;
BPR  ' 1 + 0.10 (0.193)       0.    6&#13;
1 1 +0.20 +0.10 +0.30&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 126 -&#13;
ANNEX 4&#13;
If the indirect tax is not considered, the BPR would be significantly higher:&#13;
BPR2   I + 0.093        -0.84&#13;
2   1 + 0.20 + 0.10&#13;
The difference here is 16 percentage points.&#13;
(2) If the good is a non-tradeable - therefore, no import duty is levied -&#13;
and an adjustment for the sales tax is not made, the difference in&#13;
percentage points would even be higher.&#13;
BPR  - 1 + 0.093        -0.78 as against&#13;
3   1 + 0.10 + 0.30&#13;
BPR '-1+ 0.093      0.99&#13;
4   1 +0.10&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 127 -&#13;
ANNEX 5&#13;
GENERAL NOTES ON HOW TO OBTAIN MORE SPECIFIC SHADOW WAGE RATES IN COLOMBIA&#13;
The classification of labor into any three categories only is&#13;
necessarily somewhat arbitrary. If more time is available, the breaKdown&#13;
could be made into more than three classes. The most rewarding first step&#13;
would probably be to break-up semi- and technically-skilled labor into&#13;
their two components. In order to distinguish all relevant different labor&#13;
markets between which "moving up" and "substituting" is not easily possible,&#13;
the classification should not only use wage data like done here, but also&#13;
criteria on educational and skill levels to complement the wage indicator.&#13;
For making shadow wage rates comparable between countries in&#13;
World Bank economic work, one might standardize these definitions somewhat&#13;
more, both by quantitative and qualitative indicators. Thus a project&#13;
economist working for the first time on a country like Colombia does not&#13;
have to familiarize himself with the whole tedious procedure of how SWRRs&#13;
have been derived in that specific country.&#13;
Also, generally, one should provide time to estimate a bigger set&#13;
of Shadow Wage Rate Ratios already on a national level, because there seem&#13;
to be some economies of scale involved in looking at relative wage data in&#13;
a country, which one should take advantage of. At least a country economist&#13;
could hold a larger quantity of base data for Shadow Wage Rate calculations&#13;
on file ready to be usable by a project economist. These are data which any-&#13;
way should have been reviewed by the country economist when doing his national&#13;
average EWRRs.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 128 -&#13;
ANNEX 5&#13;
If more work needs to be done on the EWRRs and SWRRs or if the broad&#13;
averages provided here can be used, depends largely on a sensitivity test: if&#13;
different assumptions on shadow wage rates change the net present value of a&#13;
project sizeably, more work is justified. When a project economist feels he&#13;
could use more specific Efficiency Wage Rate Ratios for certain labor costs,&#13;
he may refine the analysis efficiently in the following way. He may:&#13;
1.   adjust the wage rate Wi paid in the project according to his&#13;
knowledge about the labor market. E.g., the wage rate paid&#13;
for urban unskilled workers need not be the one based on data&#13;
in construction and industry. Indeed, we have made alternative&#13;
calculations based on a broader average of urban wages derived&#13;
from DANE, which differ somewhat from the above results (in&#13;
connection with the Trade-Data calculations);&#13;
2.   try to identify from what former activity labor might come into&#13;
the project, and make some appropriate estimate for the marginal&#13;
product of labor;&#13;
3.   similarly, he may try to project from which regions migrating&#13;
labor may come from, and use regional data on average and&#13;
minimum agricultural wages available in DANE, Colombia's&#13;
National Statistical Office. Rural wage levels differ sub-&#13;
stantially, especially between coffee growing and other areas,&#13;
hot and cold climates, and subsistence and "market crop" farming;&#13;
4.   try to get additional data on seasonal factors for employment&#13;
data in the project area; one formula for incorporating seasonal&#13;
fluctuations is given below.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 129 -&#13;
ANNEX 5&#13;
5.   for the social analysis, a rural consumption conversion factor&#13;
may be calculated to refine the valuation of consumption in-&#13;
creases in the rural sectors. However, in Colombia there&#13;
exists no representative nationwide rural consumption survey. Only&#13;
the Coffee Federation has made one for the coffee growing areas.&#13;
6.   Rural unemployment, of course, is very difficult to measure, and&#13;
inter-country comparisons are hardly meaningful. Moreover,&#13;
unemployment may not be the right measure at all, but rather&#13;
underemployment; the latter would be measured in some general form&#13;
as "hours worked per year over hours that can be worked", if rural&#13;
work could be organized in a form of an agro-industrial process,&#13;
avoiding seasonal underemployment. Any measure of a so-defined&#13;
underemployment is, of course, preferable to the cruder&#13;
unemployment measure, and all foregoing formulae for shadow&#13;
wage rates, especially those in rural areas, can easily be&#13;
adjusted accordingly.&#13;
7.   One final, more theoretical point is worth mentioning concerning&#13;
the valuation of the opportunity cost of labor. The valuation&#13;
of the marginal willingness to pay for labor must take account&#13;
of the cost of the complementary inputs, and therefore the&#13;
conversion factor appropriate for this purpose need not coincide&#13;
with the conversion factor for the specific type of output&#13;
produced by labor. The use of the output conversion factor will,&#13;
therefore, lead to an error which will be greater the greater the&#13;
share of non-labor inputs and/or the greater the difference between&#13;
the output conversion factor and the avetage conversion factor for&#13;
non-labor inputs is.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 130 -&#13;
ANNEX 5&#13;
ILLUSTRATIVE EXAMPLE FOR CALCULATING EFFICIENCY&#13;
WAGE RATE RATIOS IN A PROJECT CONTEXT&#13;
A.         Given a project in a rural area requiring semi-skilled rural labor.&#13;
Annual employment and wage data of average rural workers:&#13;
Duration&#13;
(% Of Days                       Daily&#13;
Type of            Spent per        Daily          Marginal&#13;
Production          Year = t )     Wage Paid      Product (m )     BPR&#13;
Foregone                            (Pesos)         (Pesos)&#13;
Coffee AgriC.          0.30            300             300         1.21&#13;
Other Domestic&#13;
Agriculture          0.55            200             150         0.93&#13;
Unemployed             0.15            -0-             -0-         ....&#13;
It is assumed here that the marginal product of small family plots is only&#13;
75% of the average wage.   The average daily wage Wp in the rural area thus&#13;
is 200 pesos.   The project pays 50% more than average wage in the rural area&#13;
which accounts for migration costs and separation allowances.&#13;
3&#13;
EWR  = m aue           t *m   * BPR&#13;
aue       1     ii         i&#13;
where i = 1,2,3 (the number of agricultural activities)&#13;
rMarginal product&#13;
EWR  =   of labor at border   = (0.30 * 300 * 1.21) + (0.55 * 200 * 0.93) = 211.2&#13;
prices, adjusted&#13;
Lfor unemployment&#13;
EWRR =    aue  =  211.2 = 0.70&#13;
w         300&#13;
p&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 131 -&#13;
ANNEX 5&#13;
B.        A somewhat more sophisticated way of calculating the EWR, requiring&#13;
data on seasonal fluctuations of unemployment in each foregone output activity,&#13;
is the following:&#13;
n&#13;
Employment in Seasonj    *  W    *  BPR&#13;
T     ,  Labor Force in Season       ij         i&#13;
i aue     =&#13;
n&#13;
where,    mi          Marginal product of labor foregone in output sector J,&#13;
mi,aue    adjusted for seasonal unemployment and converted into&#13;
border prices&#13;
W       =  Observed wage rate in season J, in output sector i&#13;
ij&#13;
This equation assumes that the difference between the marginal product of&#13;
labor and the actually paid wage rate in any season of the year is approxi-&#13;
mately proportional to the degree of underemployment down to a reasonable&#13;
lower limit.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 132 -&#13;
ANNEX 6&#13;
THE EXTREME LOWER LIMIT OF THE OPPORTUNITY COST OF CAPITAL,&#13;
ESTIMATED AS REAL BORROWING RATE FROM COMMERCIAL BANKS&#13;
A project econoAist may find it useful to have figures available on&#13;
borrowing rates from foreign commercial banks by types of borrowers (Central&#13;
Government, Local Government, public enterprises, public development banks,&#13;
etc.) or by sectors (borrowing for agricultural, manufacturing industries,&#13;
etc. purposes). These figures are available in World Bank files. For the&#13;
Durpose of finding an extreme lower bound of g, the OCC at border prices, we&#13;
here only estimate the aggregate rate for all public borrowing from foreign&#13;
commercial banks, in the period 1972-77. These are figures only for new&#13;
borrowing, committed in each one year, not effective interest paid which&#13;
contains interest on loans from previous years, when generally lower rates&#13;
were charged.&#13;
Table 1:  REAL INTEREST RATE ON FOREIGN PUBLIC BORROWING&#13;
Average&#13;
1972    1973    1974    1975   1976   1977  1972-77&#13;
(1)  Interest rate for total&#13;
new public sector borrow-&#13;
ing committed per year        7.5    10.1    10.4    8.5    7.2     7.2    8.5&#13;
(2)  LIBOR                         6.4     9.6     9.8    7.1    5.6     7.7    7.7&#13;
(3) Risk premium = (2)-(1)         1.1     0.5     0.6    1.4     1.6   -0.5    0.8&#13;
Source: IBRD: External Debt Division.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 133 -&#13;
ANNEX 6&#13;
The average interest rate on new borrowing over the six years is 8.5%, and&#13;
the development over time is shown in Table 1. 1/&#13;
For forecasting the lower limit of q, we start with the LIBOR-rate&#13;
of end 1977. We calculate the average risk premium on loans to Colombia by&#13;
comparing LIBOR with interest rates on new borrowing (Table 1). We assume some&#13;
further increase in the LIBOR rate, because of oil price increases, and a risk&#13;
premium like on average in 1972-75 (this is because on the one hand in the&#13;
1980-82 period Colombia's balance on current account may look less favorable&#13;
than in previous years which included the coffee boom, but on the other hand&#13;
there is a sufficient cushion of international reserves available).&#13;
The risk premium was on average about one percentage point. The&#13;
LIBOR-rate at the end of December 1977 stood at 7.7%. If in light of future&#13;
oil price increases it may rise somewhat, the interest ra, on new projects,&#13;
including the risk premium, to be paid by Colombia in the forecasting period&#13;
may be estimated to be around 9%.&#13;
This is the financial, nominal interest rate only. In order to&#13;
compare it to internal rates of return from Government projects, we have to&#13;
express it in real terms. If the US dollar inflation is assumed to be on&#13;
1/   Ideally one should try to estimate some marginal rate of borrowing.     It&#13;
is however, not easy to decide what marginal projects are, and even more&#13;
difficult to find out what their rate of borrowing would have been. We&#13;
therefore use the average rate of new borrowing. The average should be&#13;
relatively close to the marginal rate because Colombia has very good&#13;
creditworthiness ratios. Also, recent borrowing rates by public sector&#13;
enterprises borrowing for the first time in Eurodollar markets do not&#13;
seem to have been more above the LIBOR rate than they were on average for&#13;
all Colombian borrowers in recent years. If more time were available,&#13;
however, the analysis could be carried out in a more sophisticated way.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 134 -&#13;
ANNEX 6&#13;
average (1978-82) about J0 1/, the real interest rate for borrowing from&#13;
foreign commercial banks would be about 3%.&#13;
This would be an extreme lower limit even within this method of&#13;
calculation, because exchange rate risks for the Colombian Government are&#13;
not included, which occur to the extent that it borrows in currencies stronger&#13;
than the US dollar. If this is allowed for by a little premium the real&#13;
borrowing interest rate would be around 3.5%. No conversion to border&#13;
prices is required for this rate, because the cost is already expressed&#13;
in foreign exchange, i.e., the interest rate is calculated in US dollars&#13;
terms. We can therefore consider 3.5% to be an extreme lower limit of the&#13;
OCC at border prices (in efficiency analysis), and of the ARI (in social&#13;
analysis).&#13;
1/   See "Price Prospects for Major Primary Commodities, IBRD, Report&#13;
No. 814/78.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 135 -&#13;
ANNEX 7&#13;
NOTE ON THE VALUE OF PUBLIC INCOME AND ITS DETERMINANTS&#13;
1.        In a more sophisticated approach,the "v" should be estimated&#13;
not for public income as a whole, but for public investment and public&#13;
current expenditure separately. As it is estimated here, the assumption&#13;
is made that government current expenditures, like for teachers, officers&#13;
in the planning departments, etc., and military expenses have the same&#13;
value as investment projects in transportation, hydropower, or the industrial&#13;
public enterprises. This may sometimes not be the case, because current&#13;
expenditures may be fixed by institutional rigidities like labor unions&#13;
for government employees.&#13;
Also, the value of the "v" tells nothing ab -   the optimal size&#13;
of the public sector investment program as comparr' ro ,rivate sector invest-&#13;
ment because it is assumed that v   -  v . Ther_-.'re, "v" should not be&#13;
g P&#13;
judged in this light. In order to allow for such a judgment, "v" would&#13;
have to be calculated separately for public sector investment, e.g. as:&#13;
(1- sg) qg    l&#13;
V   =    &#13;
g     i -sg qg       8&#13;
and for private investment as:&#13;
(1 - sp) qp&#13;
p    i -s qs        B&#13;
and for public consumption as:&#13;
qc&#13;
c&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
136 -                      ANNEX 7&#13;
Where&#13;
s        is government marginal savings out of total marginal government&#13;
revenues and&#13;
s        is private marginal savings out of the marginal income of the&#13;
household and private enterprises sectors; and&#13;
q , q    would be the cut-off yields of government and private investment,&#13;
g   P   respectively.&#13;
This, however, creates data problems, since savings data are fairly un-&#13;
reliable, and EIRRs of many public sector projects, especially the social&#13;
sectors, have intangible elements which would make such a comparison&#13;
difficult.&#13;
A project economist should, therefore, be careful when using&#13;
v. If money in a project is spent on specific current government expendi-&#13;
tures whose productivity is clearly lower than the one of the average public&#13;
current and investment expenditures, he may chose a lower value for v.&#13;
2.        The value of public income as calculated here is, as can be&#13;
seen, somewhat preliminary. Most government authorities have not set up&#13;
their social policies according to an integrated scheme as the one presented&#13;
in the Squire-van der Tak and Little-Mirrlees Methods, and have therefore&#13;
no clear-cut idea of the meaning of the concept and the value of v in their&#13;
country. In Colombia, more should be done to arrive through alternative&#13;
approaches and with different assumptions at a value of v. If social pricing&#13;
is to be used meaningfully in project appraisal and in shaping sector policies,&#13;
the special effort of a consultant might be worthwhile who looks into all&#13;
aspects of social policies of the government, especially subsidies in various&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 137 -&#13;
ANNEX 7&#13;
fields in order to assess the CCL from different angles. If it is found&#13;
out that these policies are inconsistent (e.g., the minimum waL- rattq&#13;
policy yields another idea of the CCL than the majority of public subsidies)&#13;
the National Planning office might think of harmonizing these policies.&#13;
This is probably one of the very valuable side effects of&#13;
calculating a CCL, and of thinking in terms of social pricing. The&#13;
critical consumption level here estimated should, above all, be cross-&#13;
checked with data on subsidized rates in public utility enterprises. I/&#13;
Also, the CCL derived here from cutoff rates in the income tax may be&#13;
slightly downward adjusted to take account of the fact that relatively&#13;
high administrative costs are involved to collect taxes from citizens&#13;
earning close to the cutoff rate income; the "true" cutoff income level&#13;
aimed at by the Government for distributional reasons may therefore be&#13;
slightly lower than the level expressed in the tax rate tables.&#13;
Also, the World Bank and any other development institution might aim&#13;
at harmonizing the subjective values which are part of the calculation of v.&#13;
This is especially true for the parameters "n" and " q ".     The value of v is&#13;
very sensitive to both of them, and intercountry comparison of different&#13;
projects with social internal rates of return is not meaningful without&#13;
some minimum standardization. Similar is true for the value of q: as&#13;
long as country economists find a wide range between an actually used&#13;
cutoff rate (like 11% for Colombia), and a real rate of external borrowing&#13;
1/   For sources see, e.g.:   Linn, Johannes:   "The Distributive Effects of&#13;
Local Government Finances in Colombia: A Review of the Evidence" World&#13;
Bank Staff Working Paper No. 235, March 1976.     Also Selowsky, Marcelo:&#13;
"The Distribution of Public Services Across Income Groups..." op. cit.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 138 -&#13;
ANNEX 7&#13;
(3.5% for Colombia), a decision should be made about the following problem:&#13;
To which degree should the OCC at border prices or a value of ARI (in&#13;
social analysis) be set in a "normative sense," i.e., how far should it&#13;
be used to indicate that investment programs are too small. Should an&#13;
extensive foreign borrowing policy like in the case of Brazil be&#13;
considered better than a conservative policy used in Colombia? If yes,&#13;
the Colombian OCC and ARI should be lower than 11% and 6.3%, respectively.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 139 -&#13;
ANNEX 8&#13;
NOTE ON THE ESTIMATION OF THE OPPORTUNITY COST OF CAPITAL&#13;
A.   Note on the Conversion Factors for the MPK-Formula&#13;
Some sophistication to the Marginal Product of Capital calculation&#13;
could be achieved by using the following formula, where each element would&#13;
get a specific conversion factor:&#13;
MPK=     AQ *SCF -      IAL SWRR   R**MP&#13;
AK * ICF     AK *ICF         &#13;
The SCF would be the one calculated for final uses only, since it&#13;
is to be applied to final production. It would also be used for shadow&#13;
pricing MPL, since theoretically it is thought to be production, although&#13;
approximated by data on earnings. SWRR would be the Social Wage Rate Ratio&#13;
used in order to shadow price employment. All commodity conversion factors&#13;
would also be calculated as social conversion factors, not only efficiency&#13;
ones in order to use them in a complete social analysis of projects. We have,&#13;
however, not used this formula in order to make results easily comparable to&#13;
those estimated in other World Bank work.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 140 -&#13;
ANNEX 9&#13;
HOW TO ORGANIZE THE INPUT-OUTPUT-APPROACH TO SHADOW PRICING IN WORLD BANK WORK&#13;
Most data which are necessary to create the set of conversion&#13;
factors at efficiency Drices are by-products of any study on effective&#13;
protection of a country. If this study is undertaken e.g., by a sector&#13;
mission dealing with industrial export promotion, the task of the country&#13;
economist in a programs division is already greatly reduced. He then may&#13;
confine himself largely to estimating efficiency wage rate ratios and all&#13;
social parameters.&#13;
If effective protection rates are based on foreign trade data&#13;
already classified by the sectors of the I-0-Table, he mainly needs to prepare&#13;
them somewhat for insertion into the computer files. If not, he needs to&#13;
reclassify them to fit the 1-0-sector definitions. This can be done again&#13;
with computer routines.&#13;
If there is no specific study on effective protection available,&#13;
the shadow pricing exercise or its updating could be made part of a Basic&#13;
Economic Report Mlission. In this event, the mission members most prepared to&#13;
do the exercise would be the country economist in cooperation with a specialist&#13;
on export promotion or industrial sector analyst.&#13;
The exercise would be greatly supported if a centralized unit were&#13;
put together in the Bank to help country economists with the following&#13;
parts of the exercise:&#13;
-    with computational matters, like (a) aggregating foreign&#13;
trade data into the I-O-Sector classification and (b) manipulating&#13;
the 1-0-matrices and submatrices on the computer (steps 4 to 8);&#13;
and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 141 -&#13;
ANNEX 9&#13;
to give them some technical advice on shortcuts in case of&#13;
data problems, or for the interpretation of computer results.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 142 -&#13;
ANNEX 10&#13;
DEFINITION OF THE SECTORS AND SUBSECTORS OF THE COLOMBIAN INPUT-OUTPUT TABLE&#13;
Sector No.        Subsector No.&#13;
used in this       in Colombian&#13;
Study          National Accounts         Description of Sector&#13;
1                                     Agriculture&#13;
01                 Coffee (dry coffee grain)&#13;
02                 All other agricultural non-coffee&#13;
production&#13;
03                 Cattle production&#13;
2                  04                  Silviculture&#13;
3                  05                  Products from Fishing and hunting&#13;
4                  06                  Crude petroleum, natural gas and coal&#13;
07                 Other mining products, like:&#13;
07.1                  Iron&#13;
07.2                  Non-iron metals&#13;
5                  08                  Coffee, processed&#13;
6                  09                 Meat, like:&#13;
09.1                  Unprepared meat&#13;
09.2                  Prepared meat and subproducts&#13;
09.4                  Prepared fish products&#13;
7                  10                  Products from transformation of&#13;
cereals and food for animals, like:&#13;
10.1                  Flour&#13;
10.3                  Bread&#13;
8                  11                  Milk products&#13;
LI   Source:  DANE, Division of National Accounts Statistics&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 143 -&#13;
ANNEX 10&#13;
Sector No.        Subsector No.&#13;
used in this       in Colombian&#13;
Study          National Accounts         Description of Sector&#13;
9                  12                  Sugar, crude and refined&#13;
10                  13                 Drinks (prepared)&#13;
13.1                  Non-alcoholic drinks&#13;
13.2 - 13.5           Alcoholic drinks&#13;
11                  14                 Tobacco processed (like&#13;
cigarettes and cigars)&#13;
12                  15                 Other processed agricultural goods&#13;
like: oils, fats, products from&#13;
fruits and vegetables, chocolates&#13;
13                  16                 Textiles, clothing and leather&#13;
products, like:&#13;
16.1                  Fabrics&#13;
16.2                  Finished textile articles&#13;
16.3                  Clothing&#13;
and leather goods like shoes&#13;
14                  17                 Wood and wooden furniture&#13;
15                  18                 Paper and printing&#13;
18.1                  Paper pulp&#13;
18.2                  Paper&#13;
18.4                  Printed materials, newspapers etc.&#13;
16                  19                 Chemical products, plastics and&#13;
rubber, e.g.&#13;
19.1                  Chemical base materials&#13;
19.4                  Plastic products&#13;
19.5                  Processed rubber and rubber products&#13;
19.6                  Paints&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 144 -&#13;
ANNEX 10&#13;
Sector No.         Subsector No.&#13;
used in this        in Colombian&#13;
Study          National Accounts         Description of Sector&#13;
17                  20                  Products from petroleum refinery&#13;
(except gas), like:&#13;
20.1                  Refined petroleum (fuels like&#13;
gasoline and diesel)&#13;
20.2                   Other deriviates (like lubricants,&#13;
dissolvants, asphalt)&#13;
18                  21                  Non-metal processed products, like:&#13;
21.1                  Earthenwares, porcelain&#13;
21.2                  Glass products&#13;
19                  22                  Metal products, basic and processed&#13;
22.1                   Basic iron and steel industries&#13;
22.2                   Basic non-iron metal industries&#13;
22.3                  Manufacturing of metal products&#13;
except machinery and equipment&#13;
20                  23                  Machinery, equipment and electric&#13;
appliances like:&#13;
23.1                  Agricultural machinery and equipment&#13;
23.2                  Machinery and equipment for treating&#13;
metals and wood&#13;
23.3                  Machinery and special equipment for&#13;
manufacturing industries (like ovens,&#13;
kilns)&#13;
23.6                   Domestic appliances (non-electric)&#13;
23.7                   Electric appliances&#13;
21                  24                  Transportation materials and equipment&#13;
like:&#13;
24.1                   Ships and ship repair&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 145 -&#13;
ANNEX 10&#13;
Sector No.        Subsector No.&#13;
used in this       in Colombian&#13;
Study          National Accounts         Description of Sector&#13;
24.2                  Locomotives&#13;
24.3                  Automobiles&#13;
22                  25                 Other manufactured products, like:&#13;
25.1                  Measuring instruments&#13;
25.2                  Cameras and optical instruments&#13;
25.3                  Watches, jewelry&#13;
25.4                  Musical instruments&#13;
23                  26                  Electricity, gas and water&#13;
26.1                  Electricity&#13;
26.2                  Gas&#13;
26.3                  Water&#13;
24                  27                  Construction and Public Works&#13;
27.1                  Buildings, residential,&#13;
nonresidential and repairs&#13;
27.2                  Other civil construction&#13;
27.2.1                Transport infrastructure, like:&#13;
highways, airports, ports,&#13;
railways, and pipelines&#13;
27.2.2                Water and sewerage pipes&#13;
27.2.3                Water dams and irrigation systems&#13;
27.2.4                Distribution systems for&#13;
electricity and telephone&#13;
27.2.5                Land improvement&#13;
27.2.6                Well drilling for petroleum and&#13;
gas, and mining construction&#13;
27.2.7                Other civil construction&#13;
27.2.8                Repairs&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 146 -&#13;
ANNEX 10&#13;
Sector No.         Subsector No.&#13;
used in this        in Colombian&#13;
Study          National Accounts         Description of Sector&#13;
25                   28                 Commerce&#13;
26                  29                  Transport services&#13;
29.1                  Air transport&#13;
29.2                  Waterway transport&#13;
29.3                  Transport on land&#13;
29.4                   Transport by pipeline&#13;
29.5                  Auxiliary transport services,&#13;
like: storage, travel&#13;
agencies, ports services&#13;
27                  30                  Communication services&#13;
30.1                   Local telephone&#13;
30.2                   Long distance telephone&#13;
30.3                  Main service&#13;
30.4                  Radio and television service&#13;
28                  31                  Banking insurance and similar services&#13;
31.1                  Banking&#13;
31.2                   Insurance&#13;
31.3                  Services of other financial institu-&#13;
tions, like "Corporaciones Financie-&#13;
ras", stock exchanges, investment funds.&#13;
31.4                  Real estate services&#13;
31.5                   Services to the agricultural&#13;
sector, like technical assistance&#13;
31.6                  Leasing for machinery, equipment&#13;
and buildings&#13;
31.7                  Other services to enterprises,&#13;
like: engineering consulting,&#13;
consulting for advertising&#13;
and marketing, accounting,&#13;
computer services, news agencies,&#13;
legal services&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 147 -&#13;
ANNEX 10&#13;
Sector No.        Subsector No.&#13;
used in this       in Colombian&#13;
Study          National Accounts         Description of Sector&#13;
29                  32                  Housing rental&#13;
30                  33                  Personal services, like&#13;
33.1                  Recreation services&#13;
33.2                  Health services&#13;
33.3                  Hotels and restaurants&#13;
33.4                  Private education&#13;
33.5                  Repair services, like&#13;
automobile repairs&#13;
33.6                  Dry cleaning&#13;
31                  34                  Public services - These are all&#13;
services paid for by government&#13;
budgets, like administration,&#13;
defense, etc.&#13;
34.5                 Social security&#13;
34.6                  Urbanization, housing&#13;
34.7                  Sanitation&#13;
34.8                  Public education&#13;
34.9                  Research institutes&#13;
34.10                 Public health services&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
RECENT PAPERS IN THIS SERIES&#13;
No.                    TITLE OF PAPER                           AUT`OR&#13;
322    Ability in Pre-Schoolers, Earnings, and                R. Gr_we&#13;
Home-Environment&#13;
323    Priorities in Education:   Pre-School;                M. Smilansky&#13;
Evidence and Conclusions                               (consultant)&#13;
724    Tropical Root Crops and Rural Development             T. Goering&#13;
325    Costs and Scale of Bus Services                       A.A. Walters&#13;
326    Social and Cultural Dimensions of Tourism             R. Noronha&#13;
(consultant)&#13;
327    Investment in Indian Education:   Uneconomic?         S. Heyneman&#13;
328    Nutrition and Food Needs in Developing                0. Knudsen&#13;
Countries                                             P.L. Scandizzo&#13;
329    The Changing International Division of                B. Balassa&#13;
Labor in Manufactured Goods&#13;
330    Application of Shadow Pricing to Country              L. Squire&#13;
Economic Analysis with an Illustration from           I.M.D. Little&#13;
Pakistan&#13;
331    A Survey of the Fertilizer Sector in India            B. Bumb (consultant)&#13;
332    Monitoring and Evaluation in the PIDER                M. Cernea&#13;
Rural Development Project - Mexico&#13;
333    Determinants of Private Industrial                    A. Pinell-Siles&#13;
Investment in India&#13;
'434   The "Graduation" Issue in Trade Policy                I. Frank&#13;
Toward LDCs                                           (consultant)&#13;
J35    Balancing Trickle Down and Basic Needs                M. Selowsky&#13;
Strategies: Income Distribution Issues&#13;
in Large Middle-Income Countries with&#13;
Special Reference to Latin America&#13;
336    Labor Force, Employment and Labor Markets             L. Squire&#13;
in the Course of Economic Development&#13;
337    The Population of Thailand:   Its Growth              S. Cochrane&#13;
and Welfare&#13;
338    Capital Market Imperfections and Economic             V.V. Bhatt&#13;
Development                                           A.R. Roe&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 2-&#13;
No.                    TITLE OF PAPER                           AUTHOR&#13;
339    Behavior of Foodqrain Production                       J. Sarma&#13;
and Consumption in India, 19oO-77&#13;
340    Electric Power Pricing Policy                          M. Munasinghe&#13;
341    State Intervention in the Industrialization            A. Choksi&#13;
of Developing Countries: Selected Issues&#13;
342    Policies for Efficient and Equitable                  J. Lirn&#13;
Growth of Citites in Developing Countries&#13;
343    The Capital Goods Sector in LDCs:   A Case             J. Datta Mitra&#13;
for State Intervention?&#13;
344    International Technology Transfer:   Issues           F. Stewart&#13;
and Policy Options&#13;
345    Family Planning Programs:   An Evaluation             R. Cuca&#13;
of Experience&#13;
346    Prospects for Traditional and Non-                    D. Hughart&#13;
Conventional Energy Sources in&#13;
Developing Countries&#13;
347    National Urbanization Policies in Developing          B. Renaud&#13;
Countries&#13;
348    Private Direct Foreign Investment in                  K. Billerbeck&#13;
Developing Countries                                  Y. Yasugi (consultants:&#13;
349    Adjustment Policies and Problems in                   M. Wolf&#13;
Developing Countries&#13;
350    Energy Options and Policy Issues in                   T. Byer&#13;
Developing Countries                                  D. Fallen-Bailey&#13;
351    Growth and Equity in Semi-Industrialized              J. Bergsman&#13;
Countries&#13;
352    Capital Flows and Developing Country Debt              J. Katz&#13;
353    Trade Policy for Developing Countries                 D. Keesing&#13;
354    Development Problems of Mineral-Exporting             C. Nankani&#13;
Countries&#13;
355    The Global Framework                                   R. Cheetnam, S. Gupt.1&#13;
A. Schwartz&#13;
356    The Distribution of Income in Brazil                   C. Pfefferman&#13;
R. Webb&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1555088">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1979/09/1555088/estimating-shadow-prices-colombia-input-output-table-framework
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1979/09/1555088/estimating-shadow-prices-colombia-input-output-table-framework</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1979/09/1555088/estimating-shadow-prices-colombia-input-output-table-framework</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2002/11/16/000178830_9810190340346/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2002/11/16/000178830_9810190340346/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>1979-09-30T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2002-11-16T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Estimating shadow prices for Colombia in an
            input-output table framework
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The purpose of this paper is to explain
            the calculation of shadow prices at the national level using
            the so-called Input-Output Table technique. In contrast to
            previous estimates of shadow prices in World Bank work,
            which are limited to only a few aggregate shadow prices for
            commodities and for labor, the new estimation technique,
            herein applied to the Colombian economy, permits the easy
            calculation of many more such prices. The larger set of
            pre-calculated National Accounting Prices, derived on the
            basis of information contained in a country's
            Input-Output Table, should save project economists'
            time while at the same time improving appraisal results. The
            present paper follows largely this approach as far as
            efficiency pricing is concerned, i.e., considering price
            distortions owing to export and import duties and subsidies
            and distribution margins biased by them. In the case of
            social shadow pricing, i.e., considering criteria of growth
            and income distribution, we follow the approach developed by
            Lyn Squire and Herman G. van der Tak traditionally used in
            World Bank work.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Estimating shadow prices for Colombia in an
            input-output table framework
        </docna>
        <display_title>Estimating shadow prices for
            Colombia in an input-output table framework</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1979/09/1555088/estimating-shadow-prices-colombia-input-output-table-framework</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Banks &amp; Banking Reform,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Access to Markets,Markets and Market Access</subtopic>
        <teratopic>International Economics and Trade</teratopic>
        <count>Colombia</count>
        <authors>
            <author>SCHOHL, W.</author>
        </authors>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>South America!$!80469</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>America!$!80450</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_9810190340346</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>(Historic)Labor markets and employment</subsc>
        <admreg>Latin America &amp; Caribbean,Latin America &amp; Caribbean</admreg>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 357</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>International Economics and Trade</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Social Protection</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Accounting systems; Input output analysis;
            Pricing; Project appraisal; Shadow prices; Social prices
            Agriculture,Benefit Analysis,Border
            Price,Borrowing,capital markets,Commerce,Commercial
            Banks,Cost of Capital,country comparisons,developed
            countries,economic
            analysis,economists,Elasticity,employment,exports,Fishing,Housing,imports,income,income
            distribution,insurance,interest rates,Intermediate
            Goods,labor inputs,labor markets,laws,LDCs,legislation,less
            developed countries,low tariffs,Marginal Product,marginal
            productivity,Marginal Propensity to Save,Marginal
            Utility,market prices,National Accounting,oil,Opportunity
            Cost,petroleum prices,price distortions,private
            consumption,public services,real interest
            rate,Savings,shadow prices,shadow pricing,Social
            Prices,Social Pricing,streams,substitution,trade
            balance,Transport,Wage Rates,wages
        </keywd>
        <owner>LCS</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>South America</geo_region>
            <geo_region>America</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>SWP357</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Industry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics and Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crops</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance &amp; Risk Mitigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Assessment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Market Access</ml:concept><ml:concept>Employment and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Improving Labor Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Labor Market Interventions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Labor Markets, Job Creation and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wage Setting</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages, Compensation and Benefits</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Textiles</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Copyright</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Balance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Minimum Wages</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Social Impact Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Labor Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Americas</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Caribbean</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Colombia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>