<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Trends in Rural Savings and Private Capital&#13;
Formation in India&#13;
SWP382&#13;
World    Bank    Staff Working      Paper No. 382&#13;
April 1980&#13;
Prepared by: Raj Krishna and G.S. Raychaudhuri, Consultants&#13;
South Asia Programs Department&#13;
Copyright © 1980&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
1R, H Street, N.W.&#13;
iington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
views and interpretations in this document are those of t1          i7                            D&#13;
irs and should not be attributed to the World Bank, to ii           JI=J       fl lID) \\/7        r&#13;
,ed organizations, or to any individual acting in their beh U  UL  D      ((   ,t2J 1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The views and interpretations in this document are those of the authors and&#13;
should not be attributed to the World Bank, to its affiliated organizations,&#13;
or to any individual acting in their behalf.&#13;
WORLD BANK&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 382&#13;
April 1980&#13;
TRENDS IN RURAL SAVINGS AND PRIVATE CAPITAL FORMATION IN INDIA&#13;
This paper reports on trends in rural household savings, net private&#13;
capital formation in agriculture and the growth and composition of tangible&#13;
net wealth in rural India from 1950-1973. It also presents fresh estimates of&#13;
the marginal and average propensities to save and invest during the period&#13;
with respect to measured as well as permanent and transient income. The&#13;
results show that there has been an acceleration of saving and capital form-&#13;
ation in more recent years.&#13;
Prepared by: Raj Krishna and G. S. Raychaudhuri, Consultants.&#13;
South Asia Programs Department&#13;
Copyright (c) 1980&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TRENDS IN RURAL SAVINGS AND PRIVATE CAPITAL FORMATION IN INDIA&#13;
TABLE OF CONTENTS&#13;
Page No.&#13;
1.  Introduction .................................................            1&#13;
2.  Growth of Saving and Capital Formation .......................            3&#13;
3.  Marginal Propensities to Save and Invest .....................            9&#13;
4.  Propensities in the Fifties and Sixties ......................           14&#13;
5.  Saving Out of Permanent and Transient Income ....         .............  19&#13;
6.  Some Disaggregative Estimates ................................           23&#13;
7.  Tangible Wealth and Asset Composition ........................           26&#13;
Appendix A:   The Rural Household Savings Series ....        ..............  34&#13;
Appendix B:   Net Capital Formation in Agriculture Series        .........   38&#13;
Appendix C:   Tangible Wealth of Rural Households ....        .............  39&#13;
Bibliography          .....................................................  41&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TRENDS IN RURAL SAVINGS AND PRIVATE&#13;
CAPITAL FORMATION IN INDIA&#13;
1950-51 - 1973-74&#13;
by&#13;
Raj Krishna @&#13;
G. S. Raychaudhuri @&#13;
1. Introduction**&#13;
This paper reports on trends in (a) rural household savings,&#13;
(b) net private capital formation in agriculture and (c) the growth and&#13;
composition of tangible net wealth in rural India during the 24-year period&#13;
1950-51 to 1973-74. It also presents fresh estimates of marginal and average&#13;
propensities to save and invest during this period with respect to measured&#13;
as well as permanent and transient income. Previous time series studies have&#13;
covered the earlier period 1950-51/1962-63. (Gupta, 1970, and Datta Roy&#13;
Choudhury, 1968.) The saving propensities estimated in one of these studies&#13;
are comparable with our estimates for this earlier period. But there has been&#13;
an acceleration of saving and capital formation in more recent years, and,&#13;
therefore, the saving propensities estimated by us for the recent period&#13;
1960-61/1973-74 are distinctly higher.&#13;
*    The first draft of this paper was prepared for the World Bank.&#13;
**   Thanks are due to Chandra Mazumdar and Anil K. Gupta for competent&#13;
statistical assistance, and to Sartaj Alam Kidwai for computer&#13;
programming.&#13;
The authors are grateful to an anonymous reviewer for comments which&#13;
induced the addition of Section 6 to an earlier version.&#13;
@    Professor of Economics and Reader in Economics respectively in Delhi&#13;
School of Economics.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 2 -&#13;
The paper is organized as follows.&#13;
The next Section presents the basic data on the growth of saving&#13;
and private capital formation - aggregate and per capita - in different Plan&#13;
periods, and particularly in the period since the start of the Green Revolution&#13;
in 1967. Variations in the average saving rate and the average rate of private&#13;
capital formation are also analyzed.&#13;
Section 3 contains estimates of the marginal propensities to save&#13;
(MPS) and invest (MPI) 1/.&#13;
From the computed functions we have estimated the positive intercept&#13;
on the income axis which measures the income level at which positive saving&#13;
begins. We call it the "critical minimum income" necessary for income to ex-&#13;
ceed consumption. The relationship of this critical income to the poverty&#13;
line is very instructive.&#13;
The fourth Section compares our time series estimates of saving pro-&#13;
pensities with those of earlier time series studied. Some all-India cross-&#13;
section saving rates estimated on the basis of data collected by the National&#13;
Council of Applied Economic Research have also been reviewed.&#13;
The fifth Section separates savings out of permanent and transient&#13;
income. The MPS out of permanent income appears to be higher than out of&#13;
measured income. Transient saving seems to augment or reduce permanent saving&#13;
by 8 to 9 percent on the average.&#13;
Section 6 presents some evidence on variations in saving rates across&#13;
different regions and the returns to investment in modern inputs and assets.&#13;
1/   We shall hereafter use "investment" as an abbreviation for private&#13;
capital formation in agriculture.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Section 7 analyzes the growth of reproducible tangible net wealth&#13;
(RTW) in the rural areas on the basis of comparable estimates for 1950, 1961,&#13;
1966 and 1972 developed by the Central Statistical Organization (CSO) and the&#13;
Reserve Bank of India (RBI). Gini coefficients, available for 1961-62 and&#13;
1971-72, roughly measuring the degree of inequality in the distribution of&#13;
RTW, are also reported. They indicate no significant change in the degree&#13;
of inequality.&#13;
Livestock Census data contain considerable information on the asset-&#13;
composition of phiysical capital. Trends in this composition are also dis-&#13;
cussed in Section 6.&#13;
2. Growth of Saving and Capital Formation&#13;
Two basic time series - net rural household saving (S), and net&#13;
domestic private capital formation in agriculture (NDCFA) - for the period&#13;
1950-51 to 1973-74 have been developed in Table 13 and plotted in Figure 1.&#13;
The saving series includes RBI figures for rural household saving up to 1959-&#13;
60, and CSO figures for the remaining 14 years 1/. The NDCFA series is&#13;
obtained from the National Income/Accounts Statistics of the CSO 2/. Private&#13;
capital formation includes construction, machinery and equipment, livestock&#13;
and change in stocks.&#13;
1/   The latter have been computed so as to be comparable with the earlier&#13;
RBI figures. (See Appendix A.)&#13;
2/   Some adjustments have been made.    (See Appendix B.)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Rural Saving, Private Investment and Income&#13;
(Per capita in 1960-61 prices)&#13;
Rs.                                               I ndia, 1950-51/1973-74&#13;
35&#13;
yr   - Per capita rural income (Rs).&#13;
ndcfa - Per capita private invastment in agriculture (Rs).&#13;
s   - Per capita rural saving (Rs).&#13;
30                                                                                                                       y&#13;
-  -  -  -                        /~~~001- 00&#13;
25 &#13;
20&#13;
1 5                                                                                                              ndcfa   -&#13;
1 0                     _ _    _   _ _   _   _  _   _    _   _                          _ _    _    _&#13;
1950      1952       1954      1956      1958      1960      1962      1964      1966      1968       1970      1972     1974&#13;
Financial year beginning April&#13;
World Bank-20516&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The average rural saving rate series is shown in Table 1 and plotted&#13;
in Figure 2 (a). It will be seen that the saving ratio has recorded a dis-&#13;
appointingly modest upward trend. Over the whole 21 year period it averaged&#13;
only 2.8 percent. In the first two Five Year Plans it averaged 2.3 percent.&#13;
It rose to 2.5 percent in the Third Plan and then again to 3.8 percent in the&#13;
Fourth Plan period. A significant step-up in the ratio occurred in the years&#13;
beginning 1965-66 when price support and the new technology were introduced.&#13;
The ratio increased from 2.5 percent in the Third Plan to 3.5 percent in the&#13;
eight years beginning 1966-67. But even after this increase, the level of the&#13;
saving rate remains very low indeed. The rural sector is still apparently&#13;
unable to save even 5 percent of its income - the ratio which Arthus Lewis&#13;
(1954) characterized as the typical indicator of a backward pre-development&#13;
economy.&#13;
For an explanation of this low level we must recall the fact that&#13;
at least 41.4 percent of the rural population remained below the poverty line&#13;
(Rs 42.45 per capita per month) even in 1973-74 on the basis of consumption&#13;
(a) The income series used for calculating the saving ratio is the sum of&#13;
the long-period rural savings series constructed by us and the rural&#13;
component of the CSO estimate of aggregate consumption. Aggregate CSO&#13;
consumption is broken up into rural and urban consumption on the basis&#13;
of the rural: urban consumption ratio implicit in the National Sample&#13;
Survey data for each year.&#13;
Although the NSS consumption series are considered more satisfactory,&#13;
experiments with an alternative rural income concept in which this&#13;
series is used yielded inconsistent and incredible results for the two&#13;
periods 1950-51/1962-63 and 1960-61/1973-74. This outcome is clearly&#13;
due to the fact that the CSO and RBI saving estimates are related to&#13;
CSO income estimates and not to NSS data. Therefore, the choice was&#13;
made to use CSO consumption data to get the rural income series. This&#13;
choice has produced consistent and meaningful results for the whole&#13;
period 1950-51/1973-74. These results are also in harmony with other&#13;
bodies of independent cross-section data on rural saving, rural capital&#13;
formation etc.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 6 -&#13;
TABLE 1&#13;
RATIO OF RURAL SAVING AND INVESTNENT TO INCOME: INDIA&#13;
PER CAPITA (1960-61 PRICES)&#13;
Average&#13;
Net Saving/        of Plan            Net Investment/            Average of&#13;
Year         Rural Income       Periods               Rural Income           Plan Periods&#13;
(Percent)&#13;
1950-51        2.35              2.35                   1.07                  1.07&#13;
1951-52        2.40)                                    1.69)&#13;
1952-53        2.24)                                    0.91)&#13;
1953-54        2.36)             2.27                   1.56)                 1.58&#13;
1954-55        2.22)                                    1.67)&#13;
1955-56        2.11)                                    2.06)&#13;
1956-57        2.42)                                    3.30)&#13;
1957-58        2.03)                                    2.18)&#13;
1958-59        2.39)             2.32                   2.95)                 2.89&#13;
1959-60        2.37)                                    2.89)&#13;
1960-61        2.39)                                    3.14)&#13;
1961-62        2.02)                                    2.63)&#13;
1962-63        2.44)                                    2.87)&#13;
1963-64        2.51)             2.51                   3.18)                 3.29&#13;
1964-65         2.39)                                   3.49)&#13;
1965-66        3.18)                                    4.28)&#13;
1966-67         3.78)                )                  4.44)                     )&#13;
1967-68        3.07)             3.22)                  3.77)                 3.99)&#13;
1968-69        2.90)                 )                  3.75)                      )&#13;
)                                            )&#13;
1969-70         3.82)                )       3.50       4.18)                      )  4.35&#13;
1970-71        3.74)                 )                  4.64)                      )&#13;
1971-72        3.49)             3.79)                  4.47)                 4.57)&#13;
1972-73        4.10)                 )                  4.95)                      )&#13;
1973-74        3.80)                 )                  4.59)                      )&#13;
Average&#13;
(1950-51/&#13;
1973-74)      2.80                                     2.98&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Ratios of Rural Saving and Private Investment&#13;
to Rural Income, India, 1950-51/1973-74&#13;
(1960-61 prices)&#13;
6&#13;
S   - Rural saving&#13;
Yr -Rural income&#13;
ndcfa - Private agricultural investment&#13;
.+*-  *.   ...     *-,       nd~~~~_Udcf a&#13;
1 *&#13;
4                                                                                                                A&#13;
s/yr&#13;
3&#13;
2&#13;
1 **Ip S &#13;
1950     1952      1954      1956      1958      1960       1962      1964      1966      1968       1970      1972       1974&#13;
Financial year beginning April&#13;
World Bank-20517&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
expenditure data collected by the NSS. 1/ This population cannot afford any&#13;
positive saving. The capacity to save should also be negligible for millions&#13;
of people just above the poverty line. For as we shall see in the following&#13;
Section, saving bcomes significant only at levels of income much above the&#13;
poverty line. Thus only a fraction of the rural population are able to save.&#13;
And the saving ratio is significantly high for only a small minority of the&#13;
population. It is not surprising, therefore, that the average saving rate of&#13;
the rural economy as a whole should remain small even after some acceleration&#13;
of income growth in the last decade.&#13;
A comparison of trends in rural saving and rural investment ratios&#13;
cannot be properly made because the time series of rural investment is not&#13;
available. We have data only on private net capital formation in agriculture&#13;
(NDCFA) which excludes capital formation in rural non-agricultural sectors.&#13;
The ratio of NDCFA to rural income (YR) will:therefore be an underestimate of&#13;
the true rural investment/rural income ratio. But we find that over the whole&#13;
period of 24 years even this lower-limit ratio (NDCFA/YR) has averaged 2.98&#13;
percent which is slightly higher than the average rural saving ratio (2.80&#13;
percent).&#13;
The fact that the investment ratio is slightly higher than the&#13;
saving ratio is significant, for it implies that the urban sector has been&#13;
making a net contribution to capital formation in agriculture. In spite&#13;
of this contribution, however, the investment ratio exceeds the saving&#13;
ratio only by a small margin.&#13;
1/   Ministry of Planning reply to a question in Parliament, 29 June 1977.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The contribution of the urban sector also explains the fact that,&#13;
although the rural household saving growth rate (3.5 percent) has remained&#13;
below the all-India household saving growth rate (5.6 percent), the agri-&#13;
cultural investment growth rate (7.0 percent) has exceeded the all-India&#13;
investment growth rate (4.6 percent). As a result the share of net capital&#13;
formation in agriculture in net domestic capital formation has gone up from&#13;
11.5 percent to 19.7 percent between 1950-51 and 1973-74. The proportion&#13;
still remains low, but there is no basis for the common impression that the&#13;
share of rural areas in aggregate annual investment has been falling.&#13;
(Table 2.)&#13;
TABLE 2&#13;
GROWTH RATES OF SAVING &amp; INVESTMENT /a&#13;
1950-51/1973-74&#13;
Growth Rate&#13;
S1.               Items                             Rural     All-India&#13;
No.        (At 1960-61 prices)                          TPercent)&#13;
1.   Per Capita Household Saving                    3.55        5.60&#13;
2.   Per Capita Capital Formation /b                7.03        4.61&#13;
/a   Saving in current prices is deflated by the implicit national&#13;
income deflator, and NDCFA in current prices is deflated by the&#13;
investment cost index. (See Appendix B.)&#13;
/b   Agriculture only.&#13;
In spite of considerable investment in modern agricultural assets&#13;
the capital-output ratio in agriculture remained almost unchanged. It was&#13;
1.27 in 1950 and 1.28 in 1971. (Datta Roy Choundhury 1977.)&#13;
3. Marginal Propensities to Save and Invest&#13;
The marginal propensity to save has been derived with the basic&#13;
linear regression:&#13;
(1)   St       a   +   b YR   +   u&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 10 -&#13;
Here S is rural saving and YR rural income. This equation has been estimated&#13;
with S and YR measured as aggregates in current as well as in constant prices,&#13;
and as real quantities per capita. (Table 3.)&#13;
The results show that the marginal propernsity to save 1/ (MPS) has&#13;
been 11 percent (Table 3, Equation 3.4), which is substantially higher than&#13;
the average (2.80 percent). Therefore, the elasticity 2/ of saving with&#13;
respect to income is quite high (about 3.93).&#13;
The marginal and average net investment rates 3/ turn out to be&#13;
18.2 and 2.98 percent and the elasticity 2/ of NDCFA with respect to rural&#13;
income is also high (5.88). (Table 4, Equation 4.4).&#13;
These are promising results for they imply that real rural saving&#13;
per capita can grow nearly four times and agricultural capital formation per&#13;
capita can grow nearly six times the growth rate of real rural income per&#13;
capita. If government policy is effective in sustaining a satisfactory rate&#13;
of growth of rural income, rural saving and farm investment can be relied&#13;
upon to grow much more than income. But of course the spontaneous growth&#13;
of rural saving and investment can be accelerated still further if banking&#13;
facilities are expanded in the rural area, and more attractive physical and&#13;
financial assets are offered.&#13;
Although the estimated income elasticities of rural saving and farm&#13;
investment are encouraging, the fact remains that the average saving and invest-&#13;
ment rates (about 3 percent) are disconcertingly low. Until the incidence of&#13;
1/   Estimated with real quantities per capita.&#13;
2/   At the means of variables.&#13;
3/   Estimated with real quantities per capita.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TABLE 3&#13;
RURAL SAVINGS REGRESSIONS: INDIA&#13;
1950-51/1973-74&#13;
Serial    Dependent                                   Regression Coefficients             -2&#13;
Number    Variable           Constant         YR       YR/N     YR/NNPD    YR/NNPD/N      R         Elasticity&#13;
3.1       S                 -174.658           0.043                                      0.974       1.392&#13;
(7.438)        (29.412)&#13;
3.2       S/N                 -5.984                   0.047                              0.967       1.562&#13;
(8.622)               (25.922)&#13;
3.3       S/NNPD            -308.082                             0.059                    0.888       2.049&#13;
(-6.821)                         (13.543)&#13;
3.4       S/NNPD/N           -22.134                                        0.110         0.695       3.925&#13;
(-5.442)                                      (7.309)&#13;
S      : Rural Saving in Current Prices                          N     : Rural Population&#13;
YR     : Rural Income in Current Prices                          NNPD  : Net National Product Deflator&#13;
t-values are shown in the parentheses.&#13;
All equations are linear.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 12 -&#13;
poverty diminishes and income rises to a critical level, internal rural invest-&#13;
ment effort will have to be supplemented by resource flows from the urban non-&#13;
farm sector.&#13;
The sfving equation estimated by us enables us to compute the&#13;
"critical minimum" level of per capita income at which positive saving is&#13;
possible. The level is given by the horizontal intercept of the equation on&#13;
the income-axis (calculated by equating the estimated regression to zero).&#13;
Thus equation 3.4 yields Rs. 201.22 per annum as the critical per capita&#13;
rural income (in 1960-61 prices).&#13;
This figure may be compared to the Dandekar-Rath poverty line for&#13;
rural households: Rs 180 per annum in 1960-61 prices. Though it would have&#13;
been more appropriate to compare the poverty line with the intercept of a&#13;
cross-section regression, we can still draw the general inference that, on&#13;
the average, households in rural India can have positive saving only after&#13;
they have crossed the poverty line. The estimated intercept suggests that&#13;
real income per capita should rise at least 10 percent above the poverty line&#13;
before a typical household can afford to save.&#13;
We can even conceive of using the critical minimum income, esti-&#13;
mated from a saving regression, as a legitimate alternative way of defining&#13;
the poverty line itself, the logic being that a household may be properly&#13;
supposed to have risen above poverty only if and when its income exceeds&#13;
consumption.&#13;
There is another interesting question on which the estimated rural&#13;
saving equation throws some light. We can ask: how much will rural income&#13;
have to rise in order that higher rural saving ratios of the order of, say&#13;
5, 8 and 10 pereent may be achieved? This question can be answered if we&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TABLE 14&#13;
AGRICULTURAL INVESTMENT REGRESSIONS: INDIA&#13;
1950-51/1973-74&#13;
Serial    Dependent                                        Regression Coefficient                 -2&#13;
Number    Variable              Constant      YR          YR/N         YR/NNPD      YR/NNPD/N     R         Elasticity&#13;
4.1      NDCFA                -217.693        0.048                                              0.966     1.525&#13;
(7.741)     (25.104)&#13;
4.2      NDCFA/N                -7.758                    0.053                                  0.930     1.752&#13;
(6.876)                (17.059)                                                     I&#13;
4.3      NDCFA/IDW            -556.200                                 0.088                     0.932     2.717&#13;
(10.841)                             (17.453)&#13;
4.4      NDCFA/IDW/N           -40.480                                              0.182        0.689     5.876&#13;
(5.848)                                            (7.060)&#13;
NDCFA    : Net Domestic Capital Formation in Agriculture       N    : Rural Population&#13;
YR       : Rural Income in Current Prices                      NNPD : Net National Product Deflator&#13;
t-values are shown in the parentheses                         IDW   : Rural Investment Deflator (Weighted)&#13;
All equations are linear.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 14 -&#13;
rewrite the estimated saving function in the form&#13;
(2)  S/Y  =  0.11 -   22.13&#13;
y&#13;
This saving ratio function is pictured in Figure 3. In the Fourth Plan period&#13;
(1969-70/1973-74) the saving rate had risen to 3.8 percent while per capita&#13;
rural income averaged Rs 291.95 (in 1960-61 prices). The equation suggests&#13;
that a 5 percent saving rate would require income to rise to about Rs 369;&#13;
an 8 percent saving rate would require an income of Rs 738 and a 10 percent&#13;
rate Rs 2,213. In other words, the Fourth Plan level of rural income would&#13;
have to increase 2.5 times and 7.5 times for the rural saving rate to become&#13;
8 and 10 percent respectively. And even a 5 percent saving rate would require&#13;
a 26 percent increase in rural income. Since the rate of growth of rural in-&#13;
come per capita has averaged only 0.8 percent per annum over a long period,&#13;
it is clear that a substantial escalation of the rural income growth rate&#13;
will be necessary before the rural saving rate attains a reasonable level and&#13;
the rural growth process becomes self-sustained. Meanwhile, a net inflow&#13;
of resources from urban to the rural sector will continue to be necessary.&#13;
4. Propensities in the Fifties and Sixties&#13;
As stated in the beginning of Section 2, the foregoing results&#13;
have been derived with a 24-year time series of rural saving constructed by&#13;
pooling the Reserve Bank figures for the first 10 years and the CSO figures&#13;
for the latter 14 years. The pooled series has enabled us to get long-&#13;
period magnitudes of saving propensities. But there are some conceptual&#13;
differences between the RBI and CSO series. And there is reason to believe&#13;
that the saving propensity should have been higher in the second period which&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Average Rural Saving Function&#13;
India, 1952-53/1973-74&#13;
0.12&#13;
0...  . . .  . . .. . . . . . .. . .  . . . .  . . . . .  .................  ...  . . . . . .    .........-.------1......----1S--"-----&#13;
0.10-&#13;
~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~S0.0 =011 -22. 13 y-1&#13;
0.08&#13;
0.06-                   /     .1ll&#13;
0.04__                                                                                               _ _ _ _   _&#13;
0.02&#13;
0 &#13;
1 200           600               1000              1400               1800              2200 Y&#13;
-0.02-&#13;
s = Average saving rate&#13;
-0.04 -            r = Average saving rate out of ,er capita real income (per cent)&#13;
y = Per capita income in 1960-61 prices (Rs) (Rs.)&#13;
-0.06                                                                                              anl01&#13;
World Bank-20518&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 16 -&#13;
includes the years of the Green Revolution. Therefore, separate regressions&#13;
have also been estimated for the two periods. The key results are summarized&#13;
in Table 5.&#13;
TABLE 5&#13;
RURAL SAVING PROPENSITIES IN THE FIFTIES AND SIXTIES&#13;
Marginal      Average&#13;
Period             (Percent)     (Percent)   Elasticity&#13;
I      1950-51/1962-63            1.33        2.33         0.57&#13;
II      1960-61/1973-74           11.79        3.14         3.75&#13;
I + II    1950-51/1973-74           11.03        2.80         3.93&#13;
It is evident that the marginal propensity to save (MPS) (out of&#13;
real income per capita) in the second period is about 9 times what it was in&#13;
the first period. Some of this large difference is perhaps due to the under-&#13;
estimation of saving in the earlier period by the Reserve Bank. But even&#13;
allowing for this, it is clear that with the more rapid growth of rural income&#13;
per capita in the second period the incremental saving rate escalated 1/. And&#13;
the elasticity of saving with respect to rural income which was slightly more&#13;
than half in the early period increased to nearly 4 in the latter period. How-&#13;
ever, the average saving rate went up only moderately from 2.3 to 3.1 percent.&#13;
Our estimates of saving propensities for the earlier period are&#13;
comparable with those derived in an earlier study by Uma Datta Roy Choudhury&#13;
(1968). She estimated the marginal propensity to save out of per capita real&#13;
income in rural India to be 0.96 percent over the period 1950-51/1962-63. Our&#13;
estimate is 1.33 percent. Her estimate of the average propensity to save is&#13;
1/   Growth rates of real rural income per capita during 1950-51/1962-63&#13;
and 1960-61/1973-74 were 0.42 percent and 1.17 percent per annum&#13;
respectively.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 17 -&#13;
2.06 percent and ours 2.33 percent (Table 6). The difference is mainly due&#13;
to the different concepts of income used 1/. But in both studies the co-&#13;
efficient of determination of the saving function for the earlier period is&#13;
very low (0.11, 0.14) and the estimated marginal propensities to save are not&#13;
significant 2/.&#13;
TABLE 6&#13;
RURAL SAVING PROPENSITIES OBTAINED IN VARIOUS STUDIES: INDIA&#13;
(1950-51/1962-63)&#13;
MPS*     APS*                Elasticity   Deflator   Deflator&#13;
(Percent)         R2       of Saving    of Saving  of Income&#13;
Uma Datta&#13;
Roy                 0.96     2.06      0.14       0.14       Construc-   GNP&#13;
Choudhury /b       (1.32) /a                                 tion Cost   Deflator&#13;
of Rural&#13;
Buildings&#13;
K. L. Gupta /c      3.05      -        0.91        -         GNP         GNP&#13;
(10.80)                                    Deflator    Deflator&#13;
Krishna and&#13;
Raychaudhuri /b     1.33     2.33      0.11       0.57       NNP         NNP&#13;
(1.14)                                    Deflator    Deflator&#13;
/a   Parentheses show t-value.&#13;
/b   Real capita rural saving out of real per capita rural income.&#13;
/c   Real per capita rural saving as a function of real per capita dis-&#13;
posable agricultural income.&#13;
*    MPS = Marginal propensity to save.    APS = Average propensity to save.&#13;
1/   We have applied the NSS rural/urban consumption rato to CSO estimates&#13;
of aggregate consumption to get rural consumption. She has applied the&#13;
same ratio to aggregate national income to get rural income.&#13;
2/   There is one more study by K. L. Gupta, (1970), in which a much higher&#13;
and significant estimate of the marginal propensity to save (3.05 per-&#13;
cent) was obtained for the same period. (Table 6.) His results are&#13;
surprisingly different from and inconsistent with those of our study&#13;
and the Datta Roy Choudhury study. The saving data used are the same&#13;
in all the three studies. But income is defined by Gupta as real, dis-&#13;
posable agricutural income per capita, the deflator being the implicit&#13;
GNP deflator. Unfortunately his income series is not available for&#13;
comparison.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 18 -&#13;
A few all-India cross-section studies of rural saving have also&#13;
been completed with the National Council of Applied Economic Research (NCAER)&#13;
data for 1962, 1967-68 and 1968-71. The average and marginal propensities to&#13;
save estimated in these studies are summarized in Table 7. The MPS is avail-&#13;
able only for two years: 1962 which is the last year of our earlier period&#13;
(1950-51/1962-63), and 1967-68 which lies in the middle of our second period&#13;
(1960-61/1973-74) and was the first bumper crop year after the introduction&#13;
of the new hybrid-seed technology. The saving propensities in Tables 5 and 7&#13;
TABLE 7&#13;
ESTIMATES OF RURAL SAVING PROPENSITIES&#13;
Household Sample       MPS*    APS*       2&#13;
Year                  Size                (Percent)        R     Elasticity&#13;
NCAER Data (Cross-Section)&#13;
1962                  8,527              16.8    5.5     0.93       3.05&#13;
1967-68               2,380              36.0    8.2      -         4.39&#13;
1968-69 /a            4,118                -     3.0      -          -&#13;
1969-70 Ia            4,118                -     5.0      -          -&#13;
1970-71 /a            4,118                -     5.9      -          -&#13;
1970-71 /b            4,118              22.0    6.9     0.29        -&#13;
Time Series&#13;
Estimates&#13;
(This Paper)      Period II              11.8    3.1     0.60       3.75&#13;
/a   MPS were not estimated with data from these years.&#13;
/b   Bhalla (1976).   Measured Income.&#13;
*    MPS = Marginal propensity to save.&#13;
APS = Average propensity to save.&#13;
are not strictly comparable as they are derived from time series and cross-&#13;
section equations respectively. But it does seem that cross-section estimates&#13;
of saving propensities, regarded as long-period equilibrium parameters, tend&#13;
to be higher than time-series estimates. It is also clear that the cross-&#13;
section average saving rate fluctuates from year to year and, as we would&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 19 -&#13;
expect, it is higher in the good crop seasons such as 1967-68 and 1970-71&#13;
than in bad or average seasons.&#13;
In a recent study Bhalla (1976) has estimated alternative cross-&#13;
section saving equations with 1970-71 NCAER data. He defines saving as change&#13;
in net worth. Income is defined in three alternative ways: measured income&#13;
(Y) and two concepts of permanent income (Y      and Y   ).  Y   is estimated&#13;
p35      px      px&#13;
by adding up the returns to all household assets.    Y 35 is estimated   with&#13;
particular weights attached to the measured income of the current and two&#13;
preceding years. Transitory consumption occurs as an additional variable&#13;
in the Bhalla saving function besides the income variables. The marginal&#13;
propensity to save with respect to measured and permanent income turned out&#13;
to be 22 and 23 percent respectively. The APS was 6.9 percent with the net&#13;
worth concept of saving. Both these cross-section estimates are also higher&#13;
than our time series estimates.&#13;
5. Saving Out of Permanent and Transient Income&#13;
In another set of experiments an attempt has been made to differen-&#13;
tiate between transient and permanent income as contributors to saving. Per-&#13;
manent income in year 't' is defined as the average of measured income in the&#13;
current and two preceding years (t, t-l and t-2). Thus:&#13;
(3)   YPt     ( t     t-  +   t-2 )/3.&#13;
Transient income in period 't' is then the difference between measured income&#13;
and permanent income:&#13;
(4) YTt = yt     ( t    t-l    t-2)/3-&#13;
The saving function is&#13;
(5)  St   a + b YPt + c YTt + ut.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 20 -&#13;
The estimated function (5) with data for 24 years 1950-51/1973-74 in per&#13;
capita real terms is&#13;
(5')  St = - 29.587   +  0.139 YP,  -   0.026 YTt*&#13;
(-9.113)  (11.518)       (-0.884)&#13;
(-2 = 0.862)&#13;
(t-values are shown in the parentheses.)&#13;
The implicit elasticity of saving with respect to permanent income (at means&#13;
of variables) is 4.85.&#13;
The coefficient of transient income is non-significant. But the&#13;
marginal propensity to save out of permanent income turns out to be higher&#13;
(13.9 percent) than the MPS out of measured income (11.0 percent). (Regres-&#13;
sion 3.4 in Table 3.)&#13;
This implies that, if the growth of income was more stable, the pro-&#13;
pensity to save would be higher. But because income fluctuates widely from&#13;
year to year saving is also unstable and the propensity to save is reduced.&#13;
In order to study the effect of income fluctuations on saving we have com-&#13;
puted two components of measured saving: (1) saving out of permanent income&#13;
which may be called "permanent saving" and (2) "transient saving" computed&#13;
as measured saving minus permanent saving. These components are shown in&#13;
Table 8 and Figure 4. It is interesting to observe that in 6 out of 22 years&#13;
irregular saving out of windfall income augmented permanent saving by 8.2&#13;
percent on the average. But in the remaining 16 years windfall losses reduced&#13;
permanent saving by 9.2 percent on the average, the reduction ranging between&#13;
0.5 percent and 22.9 percent. Thus, income fluctuations produce measureable&#13;
variations in saving, from year to year, of the order of 8 to 9 percent on&#13;
the average above or below the normal level.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 21 -&#13;
TABLE 8&#13;
DECOMPOSITION OF MEASURED SAVING INTO "PERMANENT" AND "TRANSIENT"&#13;
SAVING: INDIA (1952-53/1973-74)&#13;
"Measured"     "Permanent"    "Transient"     Ratio of Transient&#13;
Year     Saving         Saving           Saving      to Permanent Saving&#13;
(Rs Per Capita in 1960-61 Prices)               (Percent)&#13;
1952-53       5.69           5.46             0.23               4.21&#13;
1953-54       6.12           5.99             0.13               2.17&#13;
1954-55       5.50           5.93            -0.43              -7.25&#13;
1955-56       5.50           5.73            -0.23              -4.01&#13;
1956-57       6.10           5.42             0.68              12.55&#13;
1957-58       5.62           6.76            -1.14             -16.86&#13;
1958-59       6.30           7.37            -1.07             -14.52&#13;
1959-60       6.12           7.65            -1.53             -20.00&#13;
1960-61       6.26           6.95            -0.69              -9.93&#13;
1961-62       5.23           6.78            -1.55             -22.86&#13;
1962-63       6.28           6.74            -0.46              -6.82&#13;
1963-64       6.47           6.56            -0.09              -1.37&#13;
1964-65       6.66           7.44            -0.78             -10.48&#13;
1965-66       8.60           8.04             0.56               6.97&#13;
1966-67      10.22           8.63             1.59              18.42&#13;
1967-68       8.92           9.21            -0.29              -3.15&#13;
1968-69      8.47           10.21            -1.74             -17.04&#13;
1969-70      11.05          11.11            -0.06              -0.54&#13;
1970-71      10.92          11.17            -0.25              -2.24&#13;
1971-72      10.31          11.33            -1.02              -9.00&#13;
1972-73      11.84          11.28             0.56               4.96&#13;
1973-74      11.20          11.39            -0.19              -1.67&#13;
Maximum      11.84           11.39            1.59        (a)  +18.4&#13;
(b)  - 0.5&#13;
Minimum       5.23           5.42            -1.74        (a)  + 2.2&#13;
(b)  -22.9&#13;
Mean          7.70           8.05            -0.35        (a)  + 8.21&#13;
(b)  - 9.23&#13;
(a)  For positive terms.&#13;
(b)  For negative terms.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Per Capita Rural Saving: India, 1952-53/1973-74&#13;
Rs.                                 (1960-61 prices)&#13;
1 2&#13;
12       ~~~~sr - Measured saving &#13;
sp   -Permanent savin-g. &#13;
10-          st - Transient saving                      /      /&#13;
6 ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~sr&#13;
4&#13;
2                                                     S&#13;
4~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ .&#13;
-2  -~~~~~ &#13;
O ,,                              * ,&#13;
-2~~9    0 '     *.,., 99-                ".  .,.- 9  9  9      9    9 - --. *  9'--*.,..,&#13;
195;2  1954    1956   1958    1960    1962   194     1966    1968   1970    1972  1974&#13;
Financial year beginning April&#13;
World Bank-20519&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 23 -&#13;
6. Some Disaggregative Estimates&#13;
The analysis presented here is basically "Keynesian" and&#13;
"aggregative" in the sense that income is the sole variable used to explain&#13;
saving, and the argument abstracts from variations in saving rates across&#13;
different classes of farmers, and different regions of the country. Ideally,&#13;
the influence of the varying returns to investment on the rates of saving&#13;
of various groups of farmers, in various regions, should be analyzed. But&#13;
disaggregated data on returns, and regional rural income and saving series,&#13;
are not available.&#13;
However, there are bits of evidence suggesting (1) that the rural&#13;
saving rate has been relatively higher in the irrigated, new technology&#13;
regions; (2) that, therefore, the increase in the saving rate in the late&#13;
sixties and early seventies should have been partly induced by the higher&#13;
returns expected from new technology; (3) that returns from working capital&#13;
as well as fixed investment in new technology have indeed been quite attrac-&#13;
tive; and (4) that the composition of rural capital has been changing pro-&#13;
gressively in favor of assets embodying more productive, modern technology.&#13;
Substantial data on this last point are presented in Section 7 below.&#13;
On the saving being higher in more irrigated progressive areas, we have the&#13;
results of some local cross-section studies. For the famous high-technology&#13;
district of Ludhiana in Punjab State the average saving rate in the first&#13;
five years of the introduction of HY seed varieties (1966-67/1970-71) was&#13;
found to range between 22 and 35 percent on a sample of 72 farms. (In this&#13;
district the irrigation ratio rose to 80 percent and the HYV area ratio to&#13;
nearly 60 percent in those years.) (Kahlon et.al. 1972). In the Nainital&#13;
district of U.P. State in 1967-68 the average investment/income ratio on a&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 24 -&#13;
sample of 156 farms is reported to have been as high as 17 to 44 percent.&#13;
And it was distinctly higher on innovating small and medium farms.&#13;
INVESTMENT RATIO ON A SAMPLE OF NAINITAL FARMS, 1967-68&#13;
Investment Ratio   Irrigation Ratio   HYV Area Ratio&#13;
(Percent)           (Percent)         (Percent)&#13;
Innovating Farms:&#13;
Small                28.14               74.0             28.1&#13;
Medium               44.3                75.0              24.1&#13;
Large                43.3                78.8              31.8&#13;
Other Farms:&#13;
Small                26.7                38.0              4.5&#13;
Medium               17.5                37.2               4.0&#13;
Large                43.7                48.7               6.2&#13;
Source: Shah and Singh 1969.&#13;
Similar evidence is available about some districts of South India. In a&#13;
sample of 36 farms the average investment ratio was 18 percent in Baptala&#13;
district and 31 percent in Chittoor district in Andhra Pradesh State in&#13;
1965-67. (The irrigation ratio was 30 percent in Baptala and 42 percent in&#13;
Chittoor.) (Misra and Mallick 1969). In the well-endowed district of&#13;
Coimbatore in Tamil Nadu State of South India the saving rate on a sample of&#13;
30 farms (with a 40 percent irrigation ratio) averaged 10 percent on small&#13;
and medium farms and 17.8 percent on large farms. (Rajagopalan and&#13;
Krishnamoorthy 1969.) For Western India a study of 87 Sangli farms in&#13;
Maharashtra State estimated saving rates averaging 12 to 16.6 percent for&#13;
four subgroups in 1970-71. (Chauhan et. al. 1972).&#13;
These estimates of saving/investment rates are not strictly com-&#13;
parable because different concepts of income, saving and investment have&#13;
been used by the authors. In general, they are gross magnitudes, whereas&#13;
our all-India time-series pertain to net quantities. However, the general&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 25 -&#13;
level of local, cross-section saving/investment ratios varying between 10&#13;
and 44 percent, is clearly far higher than (3 to 15 times) the all-India time&#13;
series ratios of the order of 3 percent (Table 1). Therefore, there can be&#13;
little doubt that in the better-irrigated, more rapidly innovating regions,&#13;
saving/investment rates tend to be much higher than in the country as a whole.&#13;
In part, the better irrigation/innovation situation should be influencing&#13;
saving by raising the level of income itself. But to some extent it may also&#13;
be inducing farmers directly to save/borrow/invest proportionately more at the&#13;
margin by raising expected returns. Unfortunately, the lack of data does not&#13;
allow the separation of these effects.&#13;
In spite of high saving/investment rates in some regions, the all-&#13;
India saving/investment rate remains low because the poorer, drier and less&#13;
dynamic regions (farms) dominate it. To cite an example, the average (net)&#13;
saving rate was found to be only 2.2 percent for a set of 72 farms in the&#13;
Hooghly district of West Bengal State in 1970. (Chakravarti 1970). This is&#13;
even less than the all-India average.&#13;
Just as the variation of the technological level underlies wide&#13;
cross-section differences in the saving rate, it is also the basic explana-&#13;
tion of the rise in the saving rate over time after the mid-sixties (already&#13;
noted in Section 4.)&#13;
As regards rates of return to modern input and assets it may be&#13;
noted, first, that physical yield increases of the order of 100 to 200 percent&#13;
above present levels are feasible with the modern seed-water-fertilizer&#13;
technology. (Singh 1978.) Cereal yields can be raised from less than 1,000&#13;
kgs. per hectare to 2,500 kgs. in the case of rice, and 4,000 to 5,000 kgs.&#13;
in the case of wheat. And pulses and oilseed yields can be raised from&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 26 -&#13;
600-700 kgs. per hectare to 1,000-1,500 kgs. per hectare. Second, under&#13;
irrigated conditions, marginal physical output-input ratios of the order of&#13;
10 or more, for fertilizer nutrient inputs, are quite common. Financial&#13;
return-cost ratios for fertilizer use lie between 2 and 3 for paddy and 2.9&#13;
to 4 for wheat. (FAI 1978). These facts make investments in modern seed-&#13;
water-fertilizer technology very attractive. When medium and long-term&#13;
investments are considered, the return prospects are equally attractive.&#13;
On the basis of a number of studies of returns to net farm investments, the&#13;
Agricultural Refinance and Development Corporation of India (ARDC) has found&#13;
that the financial return to minor irrigation investments ranges between 20&#13;
and 50 percent. The return to land development in command areas of irriga-&#13;
tion systems exceeds 50 percent. The return to dairy-buffalo units also&#13;
exceeds 50 percent. The return to mechanised fishing boats ranges between&#13;
20 and 25 percent and the return to investment in citrus, coconut, pepper,&#13;
cashew and rubber investments ranges between 18 and 49 percent. The social&#13;
return is of course much higher in all these cases. (ARDC 1978.)&#13;
These figures point to the existence of strong incentives for the&#13;
raltively higher rural saving/investment rates in the more dynamic, irrigated&#13;
regions, and in the recent decade of accelerated technical change.&#13;
7. Tangible Wealth and Asset Composition&#13;
In a recent paper Datta Roy Choudhury (1977) has presented revised&#13;
and comparable estimates of reproducible tangible wealth (RTW) in various&#13;
sectors of the Indian economy in 1950, 1961, 1966 and 1971. Her concept of RTW&#13;
in agriculture includes farm buildings, construction works, land improvement,&#13;
irrigation structures, livestock, machinery, transport and other equipment,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 27 -&#13;
and inventories. (The value of land and intangibles is excluded.) Her&#13;
estimates show that in constant (1960-61) prices the RTW in agriculture in-&#13;
creased from Rs 6,514 crores in 1950 to Rs 10,625 crores in 1971 at the&#13;
rate of 2.36 percent per annum. But the share of agriculture in the total&#13;
national RTW declined from 30 percent to 18 percent because the growth of&#13;
total RTW was faster (4.9 percent per annum). Thus it is clear that the&#13;
growth of RTW has been much slower in agriculture than in the whole economy.&#13;
This findings is not inconsistent with the fact noted in Section 2&#13;
that net capital formation in agriculture has been growing at a higher rate&#13;
(7.0 percent) than net capital formation in the whole economy (4.6 percent).&#13;
The explanation is that these latter figures refer to the growth of annual&#13;
investment and the figures in the preceding paragraph to the growth of the&#13;
total stock. It is quite possible that the share of agriculture in annual&#13;
investment increases and yet its share in the total stock falls if its initial&#13;
share in investment as well as in stock is very low.&#13;
As the figures in Table 9 show, this is, in fact, what really&#13;
happened. While the share of agriculture in the increment of RTW increased&#13;
from 7 percent in the decade 1951-61 to 15 percent in the decade 1961-71,&#13;
its share in the total stock of RTW fell steadily from 30 percent to 20 per-&#13;
cent in the first decade and 20 percent to 18 percent in the second decade.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 28 -&#13;
TABLE 9&#13;
SHARE OF AGRICULTURE IN REPRODUCIBLE TANGIBLE WEALTH (RTW)&#13;
AND IN THE INCREMENT OF RTW, 1950-51/1970-71&#13;
Decade          Decade&#13;
Increase        Increase&#13;
RTW            RTW        in RTW          in RTW&#13;
Agriculture      Total     Agriculture       Total&#13;
(Rupees Crores* in 1960-61 Prices)&#13;
1950-51              6,514        21,485           -              -&#13;
(30.3)&#13;
1960-61              7,685         38,990        1,171          17,505&#13;
(19.7)                        (6.7)&#13;
1970-71             10,625        58,546         2,940          19,556&#13;
(18.1)                       (15.0)&#13;
Figures in parentheses are percentage shares in the total.&#13;
*1 crore = 10 million.&#13;
Source: Datta Roy Choudhury (1977)&#13;
Another noteworthy finding of a study by Divatia (1976) is that&#13;
the concentration ratio for rural assets remained undiminished between 1961-62&#13;
and 1971-72. It was 0.65 in 1961-62 and 0.66 in 1971-72. The bottom 10 per-&#13;
cent of rural households owned 0.1 percent of total rural assets, and the top&#13;
10 percent owned 51 percent of rural assets both in 1961-62 and 1971-72.&#13;
This has the important implication that up to 1971-72 the land reform legis-&#13;
lation and other policies had no impact on the distribution of rural property.&#13;
In order to study the composition of assets (other than land) we&#13;
have calculated the aggregate value of the following aricultural assets in&#13;
constant 1960-61 prices: wooden and iron ploughs, carts, sugarcane crushers,&#13;
persian wheels, fishery equipment, electric and oil pump sets, tractors, oil-&#13;
crushers, other modern equipment, livestock, land improvement and irrigation&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 29 -&#13;
works, and residential and non-residential house property. 1/ (Table 10)&#13;
Figures for land improvement, irrigation works, house property and fishing&#13;
equipment have been obtained from Reserve Bank data and for other items from&#13;
the quinquennial Livestock Census data. The total value of these assets ex-&#13;
cluding residential house property (in 1960-61 prices) increased from 10,285&#13;
crores to Rs 15,591 crores, i.e., by 81 percent over the 21-year period 1951&#13;
to 1972. The implicit annual growth rate is 1.97 percent. 2/&#13;
When we examine trends in the composition of assets, we find that&#13;
livestock accounted for the largest share (66 percent) in the total value of&#13;
assets in 1951. But this share declined to 53 percent in 1972.&#13;
The second largest component of RTW, namely, land improvement and&#13;
irrigation works, accounted for 17 percent of the total reproducible tangible&#13;
wealth in 1951. 3/ But this proportion rose to nearly 25 percent in 1972.&#13;
1/   Some modern agricultural implements, viz., shellers, harvester combines,&#13;
planters, sprayers and dusters have not been included in our RTW esti-&#13;
mates for 1972 as data on their prices could not be obtained.&#13;
2/   The items covered and the sources of quantity and price data used by us&#13;
are given in Appendix C.   Our estimate of the total value of assets is&#13;
higher than the Datta Roy Choudhury (1977) estimate.     (Table 11).  The&#13;
difference is due to four factors.    First, we have valued the physical&#13;
stock in every Livestock Census year at the same price without allowing&#13;
for any depreciation of the depreciated part of the stock.     Secondly,&#13;
the prices used by us may be different from those used by Datta Roy&#13;
Choudhury in the case of some assets. Our price sources are given in&#13;
Appendix C; the Datta Roy Choudhury sources are not known to us. Third-&#13;
ly, the price deflation procedures used by us may be different from&#13;
Datta Roy Choudhury's. Fourthly, our estimates include private invest-&#13;
ment only. This makes a difference particularly in the case of land&#13;
improvement and irrigation works.&#13;
Our reason for developing independent estimates was the intention to&#13;
study the changes in the composition of assets. The Datta Roy Choudhury&#13;
study did not detail the composition.&#13;
3/   Public investment in land improvement and irrigation works, for 1949-50,&#13;
1960-61 and 1965-66, amounting to Rs 229 crores, Rs 1,158 crores and&#13;
Rs 2,300 crores respectively (in current prices) has not been included&#13;
here.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 30 -&#13;
The share of non-residential farm buildings declined from 12 to 9&#13;
percent.&#13;
TABLE 11&#13;
REPRODUCIBLE TANGIBLE WEALTH IN AGRICULTURE /a&#13;
Annual Compound&#13;
Value                    Growth Rate&#13;
(Rs Crores 1960-61 Prices)         (Percent)&#13;
Uma Datta             1950     1961       1971&#13;
Roy&#13;
Choudhury /b          6,514    7,685     10,625              2.36&#13;
Raj Krishna           1951     1961       1972&#13;
and&#13;
Raychaudhuri /c      10,285   12,124     15,591              1.97&#13;
/a   Excluding residential house property.&#13;
lb   Including public sector investment.&#13;
Ic   Excluding public sector investment.&#13;
But the share of machinery and equipment increased. In fact, it escalated from&#13;
5 percent to 13 percent during 1951-72.&#13;
Thus a significant modernization of the asset structure seems to have&#13;
occurred, with livestock growing at the low rate of 1 percent, non-residential&#13;
building stock too at the low rate of 0.6 percent, but land improvement and&#13;
irrigation facilities growing at the rate of 3.8 percent and machinery and&#13;
equipment more than 6 percent per annum for two decades.&#13;
In Table 12 we have analysed the growth in the stock of agricultural&#13;
equipment at a disaggregated level. It appears that two traditional items,&#13;
wooden ploughs and carts, accounted for 78 percent of the total value of equip-&#13;
ment in 1951. But their share fell to 43 percent in 1972. Thus the relative&#13;
importance of these traditional items in the stock of equipment declined&#13;
during the period. The number of wooden ploughs increased only 25 percent,&#13;
and carts only 33 percent; but on the other hand the number of improved iron&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 31 -&#13;
ploughs increased nearly 6 times, from less than 1 million to more than 5&#13;
million.&#13;
A similar trend is discernible in the case of irrigation equipment.&#13;
The number of traditional persian wheels increased only marginally by 4 per-&#13;
cent over the whole 21-year period. Their share in the total value of equip-&#13;
ment declined from 5.5 percent to 1.5 percent. On the other hand, the number&#13;
of oil and electric pumps increased more than 28 times, from about 96 thousand&#13;
in 1951 to nearly 2.8 million in 1972. In fact, in 1972 pumps became the&#13;
second largest component of farm equipment accounting for 30 percent of the&#13;
total value of equipment, next to carts accounting for 40 percent. Here we&#13;
have clear evidence of heavy private investment in irrigation during the two&#13;
decades.&#13;
The third most important component of farm equipment came to be&#13;
tractors. Their number grew more than 16 times from about 7,800 to 125,000.&#13;
And their share in the total value of equipment rose from 2 percent to 12&#13;
percent.&#13;
The investment in bullock-driven cane-crushers declined from Rs 30&#13;
crores to Rs 27 crores, while the investment in power crushers increased three&#13;
times, from Rs 4 crores to Rs 12 crores (in 1960-61 prices).&#13;
The investment in traditional oil crushers also declined from&#13;
about Rs 11 crores to Rs 4 crores. But the investment in fishery equipment&#13;
increased phenomenally: more than 8 times from Rs 15 crores to Rs 117 crores.&#13;
The overall picture that appears, then, is that the total value of&#13;
equipment increased 3.8 times from Rs 544 crores to Rs 2,072 crores; and the&#13;
composition of equipment underwent a radical transformation, with the share&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 32 -&#13;
of traditional items, e.g., carts, wooden ploughs, persian wheels, bullock-&#13;
driven cane-crushers and very small oil-crushers declining, and the relative&#13;
share of modern equipment including iron ploughs, oil and electric pumps,&#13;
tractors, power crushers and fishery equipment increasing.&#13;
Thus there can be no doubt that Indian farmers, especially medium&#13;
and large farmers, have been modernizing their asset structure to accommodate&#13;
more productive forms embodying the new technology. The constraints on the&#13;
growth of productive investment are obviously not due to any lack of adaptive-&#13;
ness on their part, but to the low overall saving rate, inadequacy of external&#13;
finance, lack of knowledge of profitable investment opportunities, and supply&#13;
bottlenecks.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 33 -&#13;
TABLE 13&#13;
RURAL SAVING, INCOME AND CAPITAL FORMATION, INDIA&#13;
1950-51/1973-74&#13;
Private Invest-&#13;
ment in&#13;
Rural Saving       Agriculture       Rural Income&#13;
(Rs Crores)&#13;
1950-51               166.30             59.35           7,088.60&#13;
1951-52               170.70             99.90           7,407.93&#13;
1952-53               163.50             57.15           7,306.39&#13;
1953-54               180.50            100.27           7,636.28&#13;
1954-55               147.90            104.84           6,672.79&#13;
1955-56               153.70            135.54           6,992.99&#13;
1956-57               187.70            233.36           7,763.85&#13;
1957-58               179.50            181.71           8,843.81&#13;
1958-59               212.20            246.10           8,870.73&#13;
1959-60               212.50            248.82           8,959.99&#13;
1960-61               225.30            295.65           9,422.11&#13;
1961-62               195.80            264.77           9,711.98&#13;
1962-63               248.30            303.45          10,195.37&#13;
1963-64               284.30            348.14          11,314.87&#13;
1964-65               326.80            434.01          13,668.12&#13;
1965-66               467.80            559.47          14,706.57&#13;
1966-67               649.50            630.07          17,170.65&#13;
1967-68               628.60            622.96          20,500.91&#13;
1968-69               603.00            672.26          20,790.97&#13;
1969-70               834.25            820.46          21,851.08&#13;
1970-71               864.75            967.56          23,131.05&#13;
1971-72               868.60            933.59          24,892.58&#13;
1972-73             1,125.00          1,152.09          27,400.01&#13;
1973-74             1,279.27          1,406.76          33,632.43&#13;
Annual Compound&#13;
Growth Rate&#13;
(Percent)              10.15             13.92                7.51&#13;
For sources and methods of estimation, see Appendices A and B.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 34 -&#13;
APPENDIX A&#13;
THE RURAL HOUSEHOLD SAVING SERIES 1950-51/1973-74&#13;
Estimates of net rural household saving in India for the period&#13;
1950-51 to 1962-63 are available in the Reserve Bank fo India (RBI) Bulletin,&#13;
March 1965. The RBI estimate is based mainly on data collected in the Bank's&#13;
All India Rural Credit Survey of 1951-52 (AIRCS), the Follow-Up Survey of&#13;
1956-57 and the Rural Debt and Investment Survey of 1961-62. Saving in the&#13;
form of physical assets and inventories was estimated with these bodies of&#13;
data for the three bench-mark years 1951-52, 1956-57 and 1961-62.&#13;
For the estimate of financial investments of the rural sector the&#13;
Reserve Bank used its own survey data as well as data collected in the Rural&#13;
Household Saving Survey (1962) by the National Council of Applied Economic&#13;
Research (NCAER). Adding financial investments to estimated saving in the&#13;
form of physical assets and deducting net borrowings from the urban sector&#13;
the Reserve Bank computes the net saving of the rural household sector.&#13;
The estimated saving for the three bench-mark years formed 3.3 per-&#13;
cent, 3.7 percent and 3.3 percent of agricultural income (including income&#13;
from animal husbandry, forestry and fishery). The average of these three&#13;
ratios, 3.4 percent, was applied by the Reserve Bank to the time series of&#13;
agricultural income to get the time series of saving for the whole period&#13;
1950-51/1962-63 because the variation in thle average saving as between bench-&#13;
march years was found to be very small.&#13;
For the period 1960-61 onwards the Central Statistical Organization&#13;
(CSO) has published estimates of net saving in the entire national household&#13;
sector in the National Accounts Statistics, October 1976. The breakup of total&#13;
household sector saving into rural and urban saving has not been given by the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 35 -&#13;
CSO. But since for the earlier period (1950-51/1962-63) Reserve Bank figures&#13;
for total as well as household saving are available, the time series of the&#13;
ratio of rural to total saving for this period was computed. The average for&#13;
the nine years 1954-55/1962-63 turned out to be 25 percent with a very small&#13;
coefficient of variation. Hence we have computed the rural saving series for&#13;
the recent period 1960-61/1973-74 by applying a constant ratio (25 percent)&#13;
to the total household saving series.&#13;
The combined time series of rural saving for the whole period&#13;
1950-51/1973-74 includes figures for 1950-51 to 1959-60 based on RBI data and&#13;
figures calculated for 1960-61/1973-74 on the basis of CSO data.&#13;
An alternative rural saving series for the later period 1960-61/&#13;
1973-74 was also generated without using a constant ratio between rural saving&#13;
and total household saving. Rural saving (RBI) was regressed on total house-&#13;
hold saving (RBI) for the period 1954-55/1962-63 and the estimated regression&#13;
was used to estimate rural saving (1960-61/1973-74) with the given CSO series&#13;
of total household saving. The two alternative rural saving series computed&#13;
by the "constant ratio method (CRM)" and the "regression method (RM)" are&#13;
shown in Table A.1. The RM estimates are consistently lower than CRM estimates,&#13;
the difference widening from Rs 4 crores in 1961-62 to Rs 248 crores in 1973-74.&#13;
The lower series also yields a lower marginal propensity to save for the whole&#13;
24-year peirod (6.9 percent) than the higher series (11.0 percent) used in&#13;
the text (equation 3.4).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 36 -&#13;
TABLE A.1&#13;
RURAL SAVING IN INDIA&#13;
(1960-61/1973-74)&#13;
Year            Saving CRM     Saving RM       CRM - RM&#13;
(Rs Crores)&#13;
1960-61             225.30           215.02        10.28&#13;
1961-62             195.80           192.17         3.63&#13;
1962-63             248.80          233.23         15.57&#13;
1963-64             284.30           260.74        23.56&#13;
1964-65             326.80           293.66        33.14&#13;
1965-66             467.80          402.91         64.89&#13;
1966-67             649.50           543.72       105.78&#13;
1967-68             628.50          527.45        101.05&#13;
1968-69             603.00          507.69         95.31&#13;
1969-70             834.25          686.86        147.39&#13;
1970-71             864.75           710.49       154.26&#13;
1971-72             868.50           713.39       155.11&#13;
1972-73           1,125.00          912.12        212.88&#13;
1973-74           1,279.25        1,031.63        247.62&#13;
Annual Coumpound&#13;
Growth Rate&#13;
(Percent)            15.67            13.97&#13;
The main reason for preferring the higher (CRM) series for the&#13;
analysis in the text is that the rate of growth of the CRM series in constant&#13;
prices (5.6 percent) is closer to the rate of growth of net domestic private&#13;
capital formation in agriculture (7.0 percent) than the lower RM series&#13;
(4.4 percent) (Table A.2). It is also closer to the rate of growth of the&#13;
deposits of primary agricultural credit cooperatives (11.4 percent). The RM&#13;
series does seem to underestimate real rural saving.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 37 -&#13;
TABLE A.2&#13;
GROWTH RATES OF RURAL SAVING,&#13;
INVESTMENT AND DEPOSITS&#13;
1950-51/1973-74&#13;
(1960-61 PRICES)&#13;
Rural Saving (CRM)                     5.61&#13;
Rural Saving (RM)                      4.38&#13;
Net Domestic Private Capital&#13;
Formation in Agriculture            9.17&#13;
Primary Agricultural Credit&#13;
Cooperative Deposits               11.37&#13;
An additional reason for using the CRM series is that for four years&#13;
for which independent cross-section data are available from the NCAER the&#13;
average saving ratio computed from the CRM series is nearer the cross-section&#13;
ratios. (Table A.3).&#13;
TABLE A.3&#13;
AVERAGE SAVING RATIOS&#13;
BENCHMARK YEARS&#13;
NCAER&#13;
Cross-Section       CRM Series      RM Series&#13;
Ratio             Ratio           Ratio&#13;
Year       (Percent)            (Percent)      (Percent)&#13;
1961-62          5.5                2.02           1.98&#13;
1968-69          3.0                2.90           2.45&#13;
1969-70          5.0                3.82           3.16&#13;
1970-71          5.9             _  3.74           3.09&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 38 -&#13;
APPENDIX B&#13;
NET CAPITAL FORMATION IN AGRICULTURE SERIES&#13;
1950-51/1973-74&#13;
Estimates of capital formation in the agricultural sector for the&#13;
period 1960-61/1972-73 are obtained directly from NAS, 1976 (National Accounts&#13;
Statistics 1960-61/1974-75, October 1976). They include capital formation in&#13;
agriculture proper, forestry and fishing, i.e., capital formation in the&#13;
primary sector minus capital formation in mining. For the earlier period&#13;
(1950-51/1959-60), estimates have been derived by extrapolating backwards the&#13;
share of the agricultural sector in total net capital formation.&#13;
Net capital formation in agriculture (NDCFA) in current prices has&#13;
been deflated to get NDCFA in 1960-61 prices. The deflator is the weighted&#13;
average of the real construction cost series prepared by R.N. Lal (1977) and&#13;
the machinery and equipment wholesale price series constructed by the authors.&#13;
The weights used are .9 and .1 respectively for the construction and equipment&#13;
indices. The weights are chosen on the basis of the average asset composition&#13;
of rural reproducible tangible wealth in 1951, 1961 and 1972.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 39 -&#13;
APPENDIX C&#13;
TANGIBLE WEALTH OF RURAL HOUSEHOLDS&#13;
The list of items included in our definition of tangible wealth&#13;
and the sources of quantity and price data used to evaluate them are shown&#13;
in the following table.&#13;
QUANTITY AND PRICE DATA USED FOR ESTIMATING TANGIBLE WEALTH&#13;
Source of&#13;
Source of      Price Data/           Source of&#13;
Item                      Quantity Data     Deflator               Value&#13;
Machinery and Equip-           Quinquennial     CSO for some       Reserve Bank&#13;
ment including items           Livestock        States.  Min-      of India (RBI)&#13;
1 to 7 in Table 12.            Census.          nistry of          Bulletin.&#13;
Item 8 in Table 12                              Agriculture&#13;
includes seed drills,                           for some items.&#13;
threshers and tractors-                         Wholesale Price&#13;
operated mould board                            Index for&#13;
and disc ploughs, disc                          Machinery and&#13;
harrows, tillers,                               Equipment&#13;
levellers, seed-cum-                            deflation.&#13;
fertilizer drills&#13;
and trailers.&#13;
Forestry and Fishery           Quinquennial     Wholesale Price    RBI Bulletin.&#13;
Equipment                      Livestock        Index for&#13;
Census.          Machinery and&#13;
Equipment.&#13;
Livestock                      Quinquennial     Agricultural       RBI Bulletin&#13;
Livestock        Situation in       and AIDIS*,&#13;
Census.          India (Ministry   RBI.&#13;
of Agriculture).&#13;
CSO for some&#13;
items.&#13;
Rural Buildings                                 R.N. Lal's         Mukherjee&#13;
(including Residen-                             Construction       and Shastry,&#13;
tial and Non-                                   Cost Index for     AIDIS, RBI.&#13;
Residential).                                   Deflation&#13;
Land Improvement                                R.N. Lal's         Mukherjee&#13;
and Irrigation                                  Construction       and Shastry.&#13;
Works.                                          Cost Index         RBI Bulletin.&#13;
Land                                                               RBI Bulletins.&#13;
AIDIS, RBI.&#13;
*    AIDIS:   All-India Debt and Investment Survey (1971-72), RBI.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 40 -&#13;
Some items could not be included, namely, certain types of equip-&#13;
ment and plantations because comparable quantity data and/or price data for&#13;
them were not available. Durable consumer goods have also not been included.&#13;
Details of extrapolations/intrapolations and deflations used are available&#13;
with the authors.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 41 -&#13;
REFERENCES&#13;
1.   ARDC 1978:   Agricultural Refinance and Development Corporation,&#13;
"Trends in Long Term Investment in Agriculture," Bombay, May 1978.&#13;
2.   Bhalla, Surjit S.:   Aspects of Savings Behaviour in Rural India,&#13;
Princeton University and Brooking Institution, 1976. (Mimeo).&#13;
3.   Central Statistical Organization:    National Income Statistics -&#13;
Estimates of Gross Capital Formation in India for 1948-49 to&#13;
1960-61, New Delhi, 1961.&#13;
4.   Central Statistical Organization:    Estimates of National Income&#13;
1948-49 to 1962-63, New Delhi, February 1964.&#13;
5.   Central Statisticsl Organization:    National Accounts Statistics&#13;
1960-61 -- 1974-75, New Delhi, October 1976.&#13;
6.   Chakravarty, S.K., "A Recent Change in Saving - Investment Direction&#13;
of the Small Cultivators in West Bengal (Case Studies of Hooghly&#13;
District)," Indian Journal of Agricultural Economics, Vol. XXVII,&#13;
October-December 1972, pp. 64-74.&#13;
7.   Chauhan, K.K.S., S. Mundle and D. Jadhav, "Income, Savings and&#13;
Investment Behaviour of Small Farmers," Indian Journal of Agricultural&#13;
Economics, Vol. XXVII, October-December 1972, pp. 43-50.&#13;
8.   Datta Roy Choudhury, Uma:    "Income, Consumption and Saving in Urban&#13;
and Rural India," The Review of Income and Wealth, Vol. 24, March 1968.&#13;
9.   Datta Roy Choudhury, Uma:   "Industrial Breakdown of Capital Stock in&#13;
India," The Journal of Income and Wealth, Vol. 1, No. 2, April 1977.&#13;
10. Directorate of Economics and Statistics, Ministry of Agriculture and&#13;
Irrigation: Seventh Livestock Census, New Delhi, 1951.&#13;
11. Directorate of Economics and Statistics, Ministry of Agriculture and&#13;
Irrigation: Eighth Livestock Census, New Delhi, 1956.&#13;
12. Directorate of Economics and Statistics, Ministry of Agriculture and&#13;
Irrigation: Ninth Livestock Census, New Delhi, 1961.&#13;
13. Directorate of Economics and Statistics, Ministry of Agriculture and&#13;
Irrigation: Tenth Livestock Census, New Delhi, 1966.&#13;
14. Directorate of Economics and Statistics, Ministry of Agriculture and&#13;
Irrigation: Eleventh Livestock Census, New Delhi, 1972.&#13;
15. Divatia, V.V.: "Inequalities in Asset Distribution of Rural Households,"&#13;
Reserve Bank Staff Occassional Papers, Vol. 1, Issue No. 1, June 1976.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 42 -&#13;
16. FAI 1978: Fertilizer Association of India, "Annual Review of Fertiliser&#13;
Consumption and Production 1977-78," New Delhi, July 1978.&#13;
17. Gupta, K. L.: "On Some Determinants of Rural and Urban Household Saving&#13;
Behaviour," Economic Record, Vol. 46, December 1970.&#13;
18. Kahlen, A. S., H.S. Bal and G. Singh: "Savings and Investment Patterns&#13;
in Farm Families in the Punjab (India)," Indian Journal of Agricultural&#13;
Economics, Vol. XXVII, October-December 1972, pp. 19-29.&#13;
19. Lal, Ram N.: Capital Formation and its Financing in India, Allied&#13;
Publishers, Bombay, 1977.&#13;
20. Lewis, W. Arthur: "Economic Development with Unlimited Supplies of&#13;
Labour," The Manchester School of Economic &amp; Social Studies, Vol. XXII,&#13;
1956.&#13;
21. Misra, B. and S. C. Mallick, "Factors Influencing Capital Formation in&#13;
Agriculture," Indian Journal of Agricultural Economics, Vol. XXIV,&#13;
October-December 1969, pp. 93-105.&#13;
22. Mukherjee, M. and N. S. R. Sastry: "An Estimate of the Tangible Wealth&#13;
of India" in Goldsmith, R and C. Saunders (ed.): The Measurement of&#13;
National Income, Income and Wealth Series VIII, Bowes &amp; Bowes, London,&#13;
1959.&#13;
23. National Council of Applied Economic Research: All India Rural House-&#13;
hold Survey 1962, Vol. II, New Delhi, 1965.&#13;
24. National Council of Applied Economic Research: All India Rural House-&#13;
hold Survey of Income, Saving and Consumer Expenditure (With Special&#13;
Reference to Middle Class Households), 1967-68, New Delhi, 1972.&#13;
25. National Council of Applied Economic Research: Changes in Rural Income&#13;
in India 1968-69, 1969-70, 1970-71, New Delhi, 1975.&#13;
26. Rajagopalan V. and S. Krishnamoorthy, "Savings Elasticities and&#13;
Strategies for Capital Formation - A Micro Analysis," Indian Journal of&#13;
Agricultural Economics, Vol. XXIV, October-December 1969, pp. 110-116.&#13;
27. Reserve Bank of India: "Estimates of Tangible Wealth in India,"&#13;
R.B.I. Bulletin, January 1963.&#13;
28. Reserve Bank of India: "Estimates of Saving and Investment in the Indian&#13;
Economy: 1950-51 to 1962-63," R.B.I. Bulletin, March 1965.&#13;
29. Reserve Bank of India: "Estimates of Tangible Wealth in India,"&#13;
R.B.I. Bulletin, October 1972.&#13;
30. Reserve Bank of India: All India Debt and Investment Survey 1971-72,&#13;
Vol I, Bombay, April 1975.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 43 -&#13;
31. Shah, S. L. and L. R. Singh, "Capital Formation in Agriculture of the&#13;
Terai Region of Uttar Pradesh," Indian Journal of Agricultural Economics,&#13;
Vol. XXIV, October-December 1969, pp. 87-92.&#13;
32. Singh 1978: Inderjit Singh, "Small Farmers and the Landless in South&#13;
Asia: Prospects and Problems," World Bank, Washington, August 1978.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
RECENT PAPERS IN THIS SERIES&#13;
No.                     TITLE OF PAPER                           AUTHOR&#13;
350     Energy Options and Policy Issues in                  D. Fallen-Bailey&#13;
Developing Countries                                  T. Byer&#13;
351     Growth and Equity in Semi-Industrialized              J. Bergsman&#13;
Countries&#13;
352     Capital Flows and Developing Country Debt            J. Katz&#13;
353     Trade Policy for Developing Countries                 D. Keesing&#13;
354     Development Problems of Mineral-Exporting            G. Nankani&#13;
Countries&#13;
355     The Global Framework                                  R. Cheetham, S. Gupta&#13;
A. Schwartz&#13;
356     The Distribution of Income in Brazil                 G. Pfefferman, R. Webb&#13;
357     Estimating Shadow Prices for Colombia in an          W. Schohl&#13;
Input-Output Table Framework&#13;
358     Inter-Country Comparison of "Real" (PPP)             P. Isenman&#13;
Incomes: Revised Estimates and Unresolved&#13;
Questions&#13;
359     Price Distortions in Agriculture and Their           E. Lutz&#13;
Effects:  An International Comparison                M. Bale&#13;
360     Costs and Benefits of Agricultural Research:          G.E. Schuh&#13;
The State of the Arts                                H. Tollini (consultants)&#13;
361     Investment in International Agricultural             G. Scobie&#13;
Research:  Some Economic Dimensions                   (consultant)&#13;
362     Identification and Appraisal of Rural Roads          H. Beenhakker&#13;
Projects                                             A. Chammari&#13;
363     Small Enterprises in African Development:             J. Page (consultant)&#13;
A Survey&#13;
364     Income, Consumption and Poverty in Thailand,         0. Meesook&#13;
1962/63 to 1975/76&#13;
365     A Survey and Critique of World Bank Supported        R. Marris&#13;
Research on International Comparisons of Real         (consultant)&#13;
Product&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 2-&#13;
No.                     TITLE OF PAPER                           AUTHOR&#13;
366     Paradigms in the Study of Urban Labor Markets        D. Mazumdar&#13;
in LDCs: A Reassessment in the Light of an&#13;
Empirical Survey in Bombay City&#13;
367     Incentives for Resource Allocation:                   S. Acharya&#13;
A Case Study of Sudan&#13;
368     Why the Emperor's New Clothes Are Not Made            D. Morawetz&#13;
in Colombia                                           (consultant)&#13;
369     Economic and Social Analysis of Projects             K. Cleaver&#13;
and of Price Policy: The Morocco Fourth&#13;
Agricultural Credit Project&#13;
370     The Tokyo Round and the Developing Countries         B. Balassa&#13;
371     Bus Ownership and Efficiency in Urban Areas          A. Walters&#13;
C. Feibel&#13;
372     The Tokyo Round:   Results and Implications           R. Kemper&#13;
for Developing Countries                              (consultant)&#13;
373     Malnutrition:   Some Measurement and Policy Issues    T.N. Srinivasan&#13;
374     The Prevalence of Calorie Deficient Diets            S. Reutlinger&#13;
in Developing Countries                              H. Alderman (consultant)&#13;
375     The Design of Organizations for Rural                F. Lethem, B. Thoolen&#13;
Development Projects - A Progress Report             W. Smith (consultant)&#13;
376     Fostering the Capital-Goods Sector in LDCs:          H. Pack (consultant)&#13;
A Survey of Evidence and Requirements&#13;
377     Macroeconomic Implications of Factor                 H. Pack (consultant)&#13;
Substitution in Industrial Processes&#13;
378     Household Income or Household Income per Capita       G. Datta&#13;
in Welfare Comparisons                               J. Meerman&#13;
379     Managing Information for Rural Development:          G. Deboeck&#13;
Lessons from Eastern Africa                           B. Kinsey&#13;
380     Women in the Urban Labor Markets of Africa:          N. Shields&#13;
The Case of Tanzania&#13;
381     Some Aspects of Wheat and Rice Price Policy          R. Krishna&#13;
in India                                             D.S. Raychaudhuri&#13;
(consultants)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
HG3881.5 .W57 W67 no.382 c.3&#13;
Krishna, Raj.&#13;
Trends in rural savings and&#13;
private capital formation in&#13;
India /&#13;
t~.~fATEj NAME AND EXTENSION   ROOM&#13;
NUMBER&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1555060">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1980/04/1555060/trends-rural-savings-private-capital-formation-india
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1980/04/1555060/trends-rural-savings-private-capital-formation-india</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1980/04/1555060/trends-rural-savings-private-capital-formation-india</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/07/26/000178830_98101903404134/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/07/26/000178830_98101903404134/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2003-07-26T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1980-04-30T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Trends in rural savings and private capital
            formation in India
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            This paper reports on trends in rural
            household savings, net private capital formation in
            agriculture and the growth and composition of tangible net
            wealth in rural India from 1950-1973. It also presents fresh
            estimates of the marginal and average propensities to save
            and invest during the period with respect to measured as
            well as permanent and transient income. The results show
            that there has been an acceleration of saving and capital
            formation in more recent years.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Trends in rural savings and private capital
            formation in India
        </docna>
        <display_title>Trends in rural savings and
            private capital formation in India</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1980/04/1555060/trends-rural-savings-private-capital-formation-india</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Banks &amp; Banking Reform,Economic Theory &amp; Research,International Terrorism &amp; Counterterrorism,Economic Investment &amp; Savings</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development</teratopic>
        <count>India</count>
        <authors>
            <author>KRISHNA, R.</author>
            <author>RAYCHAUDHURI, G.</author>
        </authors>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>South Asia!$!80470</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Asia!$!80451</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_98101903404134</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>(Historic)Other agriculture</subsc>
        <admreg>South Asia,South Asia</admreg>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 382</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development</historic_topic>
        <sectr>Agriculture, fishing, and forestry</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Agricultural investments; Capital formation;
            Households; Savings; Savings behavior
            affiliated
            organizations,agriculture,assets,capital formation,current
            prices,deflation,Economic
            Research,elasticities,elasticity,equilibrium,expected
            returns,farms,fishing,GNP,GNP deflator,growth
            rate,income,inventories,land development,marginal propensity
            to save,MPS,national income,net worth,oil,per capita
            income,permanent income,poverty line,real income,Reserve
            Bank of India,rural property,rural savings,savings,time
            series,transport,wealth,working capital
        </keywd>
        <owner>SAR</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>South Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Asia</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>SWP382</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fragility, Conflict and Violence</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics and Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Extension &amp; Research</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crops</ml:concept><ml:concept>Livestock</ml:concept><ml:concept>Livestock and Animal Husbandry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets and Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forest and Forestry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Market Access</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Lines</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Economics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Research</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Copyright</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fertilizers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Animal Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>Machinery and Equipment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Credit</ml:concept><ml:concept>Terrorism</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forestry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Social Impact Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Roads</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>India</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Southern Asia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>