<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>The Distribution of Income in Brazil&#13;
SWP356&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No. 356&#13;
September 1979&#13;
lhd by: Guy Pierre Pfeffermann&#13;
Country Programs Department II&#13;
Latin America and the Caribbean Regional Office&#13;
X     Richard Webb&#13;
Development Economics Department&#13;
|___ _  Development Policy Staff&#13;
Copyright © 1979&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.                                            !&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
The views and interpretations in this document are those of the authors;&#13;
and should not be attributed to the World Bank, to its affiliated&#13;
organizations, or to any individual acting in their behalf.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The views and interpretations in this document are those of the authors&#13;
and should not be attributed to the World Bank, to its affiliated&#13;
organizations, or to any individual acting in their behalf.&#13;
WORLD BANK&#13;
Working Paper No. 356&#13;
September 1979&#13;
THE DISTRIBUTION OF INCOME IN BRAZIL&#13;
This paper asks whether growth has been widely shared and,&#13;
*in particular, whether it has raised the absolute incomes of the&#13;
poorest groups in Brazil. The review of evidence covers the period&#13;
1960-1976/77. New sources, in particular a national household budget&#13;
survey (ENDEF) and the 1976 household employment survey,have made&#13;
possible both a re-examination of previous sources and a clearer&#13;
separation in the analysis of income trends before and during the&#13;
fast growth period between 1968 and 1974.&#13;
There is no set of comparable and accurate sources that pro-&#13;
vide a definite answer to questions regarding income trends since 1960.&#13;
There is, however, a great deal of fragmentary and imperfect evidence&#13;
which, when examined as a whole, suggests that (i) the extent of income&#13;
growth throughout the population, including many in the poorest groups,&#13;
has been underestimated in previous studies, and (ii) the rate of&#13;
poverty reduction was faster during the rapid growth years 1968-1974.&#13;
Prepared by: Guy Pierre Pfeffermann&#13;
Country Programs Department II&#13;
Latin America and the Caribbean Regional Office&#13;
Richard Webb&#13;
Development Economics Department&#13;
Development Policy Staff&#13;
JNTEMNATIONAL IMOlETARY FUND&#13;
Copyright ©   1979                             JOINT LIBRARY&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.                          [TE  2 '93&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
1-iTERhATIOPHAL BANi' rOR&#13;
rLEOlTF.-.ClCIOi LN:D-, LC', fOAENT&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TABLE OF CONTENTS&#13;
Page No.&#13;
I.  Introduction   . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .      1&#13;
II.  Overall Context . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .       2&#13;
III.  Trends in Inequality:   Census and Survey Data .   . .  . .   7&#13;
1.  The Available Data:   A Summary  . . . . . . . . . .      8&#13;
2.  ENDEF   .... .      .  .  .  .   ..... .  .  .  .  .  .  .   .  13&#13;
3.  Underreporting .... .       .  .   ..... .   .  .  .  .   .  15&#13;
4.  The 1960 Census    ....  .     .  .   .. .  .  .  .  .  .  .   .  24&#13;
5.  Other Years ............. -.------------ 29&#13;
6.  Censuses and Surveys:   Conclusions .   .   . . . . . .  32&#13;
IV.  Trends in Inequality:   Partial Data . .   . . . .  . . . .  38&#13;
1.  Education and Income Differentials .      .  . . . . . .  38&#13;
2.  Urban Modern Sector Differentials:   Law of 2/3          49&#13;
3.  Urban Modern Sector Differentials:   Wage Surveys        59&#13;
4.  Regional and Sectoral Differentials . . .    . . . . .   68&#13;
5.  Partial Data:   Conclusions . . . . . .. .   . . . .     77&#13;
V.  Trends in Employment and Incomes . . . . . . . . . . .       79&#13;
1.  The Structure of Employment   . . . . . . . . . . .      80&#13;
2.  The Structure of Incomes    . . . . . . . . . . . .      87&#13;
3.  Income Trends .... .       .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .   .  92&#13;
VT.  The Extent of Poverty in 1974/75    . . . . .                99&#13;
VII. Appendices    . . . . . . . . . . . . .                      103&#13;
Internal Terms of Trade   . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .     103&#13;
Wage Statistics .                                           107&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
LIST OF TABLES&#13;
Page No.&#13;
1. Estimated Family Income Shares . . . . . . . . . . .  10&#13;
2. Comparison of Estimates of Annual Personal Income&#13;
and  Consumption  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  16&#13;
3. Nonmonetary as a Proportion of Monetary Family Income 21&#13;
4. Educational and Occupational Income Differentials&#13;
1960-1976  .   .   .  .   .  .   .   .   .   .  .   .   .  .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .  41&#13;
5. Ske-wness in the Upper Tail of Income Distributions:&#13;
Ratios Between Mean Income in Open-Ended Class and&#13;
Lower Limit Income-, for Alternative Percentiles . . . 43&#13;
6. Population According to Grade Level . . . . . . . . . 48&#13;
7. Coverage of Law of 2/3 and 1959 Economic Census . . . 53&#13;
8. Trends in Modern Sector Wage Differentials:&#13;
Selected  Data  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  60&#13;
9. Trends in Regional and Sectoral Income Differentials  69&#13;
10. Life Expectancy by Regions (1950, 1970) . . . . . . . 74&#13;
11. The Structure of Employment 1960-1976 . . . . . . . . 81&#13;
12. Ranking of Occupational and Regional Groups by&#13;
Income Level (Household Heads and Household Income)&#13;
1974/75  .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .  89&#13;
13. Farm Household Incomes and Regional Agricultural&#13;
Productivity  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .   .  91&#13;
14.  Income and Wage Trends:  Indices . . . . . . . . . .  94&#13;
15. Comparison of Deflators . . . . . . . . . . . . . .  96&#13;
16. Proportion of Households Owning Durables . . . . . .  98&#13;
17. The Extent of Poverty: Families Under Two Minimum&#13;
Wages:  1974-1975 . . . . . ... . . . . . . . . . . . 100&#13;
Figure 1. Brazil - Percent of Average Life Expectancy&#13;
(1950,  1970)  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  75&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
THE DISTRIBUTION OF INCOME&#13;
IN BRAZIL&#13;
Guy Pfeffermann&#13;
and&#13;
Richard Webb&#13;
I. INTRODUCTION&#13;
The procedure we follow is to first examine data on trends in&#13;
the distribution of income. Since per capita income '.n Brazil doubled&#13;
between 1960 and 1976, substantial income growth for all groups will have&#13;
resulted unless it was offset by changes in distributive shares. The&#13;
analysis of changes in shares thus provides an ir:direct answer to the&#13;
question of income trends.   The evidence on trends -r. distribution consists&#13;
of aggregate data from censuses and surveys, and of partial data on income&#13;
differentials. The review of that information is then supplemented by a look&#13;
at direct evidence of change in emplcyment incomes occurring both through&#13;
the shift to better jobs and through increases in the incomes received in&#13;
specific types of employment.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-2-&#13;
II. THE OVERALL CONTEXT&#13;
Before entering into a discussion of income statistics, it will be&#13;
helpful to draw attention to certain features of the economy. The growth and&#13;
concentration of income can be expected to bear some relationship first to&#13;
the growth and concentration of output, and second, to the institutional&#13;
arrangements that affect the division of that output.     Though both&#13;
sets of factors contribute a great deal to explaining the income distri-&#13;
bution, it is easier to be quantitative about output than about&#13;
social and political behavior. Also, in the case of both output and&#13;
institutions, it is necessary to know something about the situation at the&#13;
starting point in 1960, and about how they have evolved since then. Again,&#13;
it is easier to provide numbers on trends in sectoral and regional output&#13;
and on the location of the population vis a vis that output, than&#13;
it is, for example,   to   quantify changes in share-cropping arrangements,&#13;
in the enforcement of minimum wage legislation, or in the extent to which&#13;
local monopoly powers of landlords, lenders and wholesalers are being&#13;
broken down by better roads and communications.&#13;
Since the issue of income distribution in Brazil is most often&#13;
posed as a case of "rapid growth with growing concentration" it is useful to&#13;
establish some facts on growth. These are first that growth rates have&#13;
been very variable, ranging from 3 consecutive years (1963-65) when per&#13;
capita growth was negative to 3 consecutive years (1971-73) when it sur-&#13;
passed 8.5% per year. At the same time this variability in real growth&#13;
was accompanied by high and also variable rates of inflation ranging from&#13;
91% in 1964 to 16% in 1972. Second, annual per capita growth in GDP was&#13;
relatively slow for over half the intercensal period; between 1962 and&#13;
1967 it averaged only 0.7%; for the intercensal period as a whole it&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
averaged about 3Z. The intercensal decade (1960-1970) therefore, is not&#13;
a convenient period for posing questions about distribution during rapid&#13;
growth.  Starting in 1968, per capita output grew by close to 8% per year&#13;
until 1974 and moderated to about 3% since then. Much of the debate about&#13;
distribution in Brazil took place in the early seventies and was based on&#13;
data for the sixties, particularly the censuses. The present is therefore&#13;
an opportune moment for reviewing the growth-distribution relationship&#13;
under the very different growth contexts of pre-1968 and post-1968.&#13;
Questions should also be raised about the impact of so much short-term price&#13;
and output variability on relative incomes and the responses of employers and&#13;
workers. Thus, the short-term behavior of incomes is likely to be.highly&#13;
variable, adding to the difficulty of discerning long-term trends.&#13;
A third feature of the growth record is the comparatively good&#13;
performance of agriculture which grew at 4.6% per year between. 1960-1977,&#13;
almost twice the rate for the rest of Latin America. Non-agricultural output grew&#13;
faster, but the substantial growth in agriculture satisfied a major necessary&#13;
condition for improvement in rural incomes. Furthermore, with the help of massive&#13;
rural-urban migration, which reduced the increase in farm families to about 0.6%&#13;
1/&#13;
per year, and of favorable terms of trade,     these output gains were trans-&#13;
lated into a growth in real agricultural value added per household of almost&#13;
4.0% per year. This poses the question of how productivity gains were dis-&#13;
tributed within agriculture.&#13;
It is difficult to evaluate income distribution in Brazil without&#13;
reference to the considerable degree of economic and social diversity. Some&#13;
1/ See Appendix on Internal Terms of Trade.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-4-&#13;
of this can be traced to the different origins of immigrants, but the most&#13;
powerful factors are probably ecological differences, and the speed and&#13;
uneven spread of technological change. A frequent but misleading expression&#13;
of this diversity is the description of Brazil as a dual economy, or a&#13;
1/&#13;
"Belindia",   stressing the contrast between modern and traditional technologies&#13;
and regions. This expression misleads in that structural differences are&#13;
important within the modern and traditional categories.&#13;
Thus the hourly wage for a bricklayer's assistant in Sao Paulo is twice that&#13;
in much of the North-East (Cr.$7.00 vs. 3.28); the rate of illiteracy amongst&#13;
male farm laborers in Sao Paulo 1973 was 25%, vs. 58% in the North-East.&#13;
There are powerful regional income differences within the North-East: in&#13;
1974/75 an index of average family income was 100 in rural areas, 200 in non-&#13;
metropolitan urban areas, 300 in Fortaleza and 590 in Salvador. Furthermore,&#13;
there are major income differences within rural society associated with ecology,&#13;
land tenure, and with a variety of contractual traditions in land, labor and&#13;
product markets.&#13;
The failure to notice this diversity underlies many oversimplifica-&#13;
tions about income distribution in Brazil. The population is frequently reduced&#13;
to a few categories that fit theories or paradigms, such as industrial labor,&#13;
the Northeast landless, and senior executives. But factory workers and the&#13;
Northeast landless together account for only 12% of the Brazilian labor&#13;
force, while the total income of senior managers is also a relatively&#13;
small proportion of total personal income. The great bulk of&#13;
income and employment is left out in discussions that center on those&#13;
categories. Within the Northeast, for example, there are as many owners and&#13;
self-employed in nonfarm businesses as there are landless farm families; the former&#13;
are growing much faster in number, and their average income is over three times&#13;
1/ From a juxtaposition of Belgium and India.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 5 -&#13;
that of the landless. There are almost as many domestic servants as factory&#13;
workers. In 1974, family employment on small and medium farms in the South&#13;
region alone-(States of Parana,      Santa Catarina, and Rio Grande do Sul)&#13;
was as large as that in all factories with 50 or more workers in Brazil, and&#13;
total income received by each group was similar. In 1976 there were twice as&#13;
many workers in Government and welfare services as in factories. Market&#13;
and institutional forces affecting employment and incomes in these other,&#13;
generally neglected components of the economy are thus, by far, the biggest&#13;
part of the story.&#13;
Finally, one cannot examine income distribution in Brazil without&#13;
noting the highly dynamic and mobile character of the population and its&#13;
economy. In such an environment, the traditional attention given to cross-&#13;
section or static measures of inequality needs to be complemented with measures&#13;
that reveal the income experience of individuals or groups over time. This&#13;
mobility has several aspects, the most familiar being the high rate of net&#13;
rural-urban migration. But less familiar is the extent of movement within&#13;
rural and urban areas, and the large urban-rural return migration. One&#13;
measure of all this locational change is the 1970 Census statistic that 25%&#13;
of all families had had less than two years' residence in their present home.&#13;
Another is the extent of labor turnover: in 1970, 60% of all manufacturing&#13;
employees in Sao Paulo State (the sample covers mostly medium and large firms)&#13;
had been employed less than two years in their current job. The extent of&#13;
turnover is related to the youth of the labor force: 1 in 3 workers were&#13;
less than 20 years old. A further aspect is that Brazil is still a frontier country:&#13;
cultivated acreage expanded by 35% between 1960 and 1975. The urban counter-&#13;
part is that around 1969-1970 about 15,000 manufacturing establishments of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-6-&#13;
1/&#13;
5 or more workers were being created annually.     So much movement leads one&#13;
to expect a great deal of individual income change with both upward and&#13;
downward mobility. Extensive movement could also have high pril_te costs,&#13;
particularly to groups such as casual farm and construction workers who move&#13;
frequently, and it may hamper the development of local and grassroots&#13;
organization and thus the capacity for communal self-help.&#13;
1/ Censo Industrial 1970, p. 270. The net increase in establishments of 5+&#13;
workers between 1960 and 1970 was only 28,000, implying considerable turn-&#13;
over of establishments.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-7-&#13;
III. TRENDS IN INEQUALITY: CENSUS AND SURVEY DATA&#13;
It is useful to begin the analysis by breaking down the issue&#13;
of overall inequality into two questions: First, what is the share of&#13;
the poorest 40%; and second, how is the remainder being distributed&#13;
between middle and top income groups. This distinction is helpful&#13;
because the questions have unequal priority, and because the causes&#13;
underlying changes in shares, and the corresponding policy implications,&#13;
1/&#13;
are likely to differ in each case. From the point of view of welfare,&#13;
the most important aspect of the aggregate distribution is the share&#13;
2/&#13;
accruing to the very poor. The extent of absolute poverty is the product&#13;
of that share and of the general level of development. The 3 to 4%&#13;
growth in per capita GDP since 1960 implies a substantial reduction in&#13;
the number of absolutely poor families and/or, in the size of the&#13;
21 This distinction is lost when a single measure of inequality, such&#13;
as the Gini coefficient, is used.&#13;
.] The choice of the bottom 40% as "the poor" is, of course, arbitrary.&#13;
However, it is probably close to the proportion of families falling&#13;
below the poverty line in 1960, using the two August 1974 minimum&#13;
wage poverty line that is the basis for the poverty estimates in&#13;
Table 6. Also, the statistical error in estimating income shares for&#13;
a smaller poverty group, e.g., bottom 20%, would have been even greater.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 8 -&#13;
poverty gap (the amount required to bring the poor up to some minimum&#13;
needs standard) unless there has been an offsetting fall in the income&#13;
share of the poor. A further methodological point: we assume that the&#13;
more meaningful unit for evaluating poverty and welfare is the household,&#13;
or consumption unit, rather than the individual income recipient.&#13;
Ideally, the analysis would be based on household income per adult&#13;
equivalent, but this information has not been published.&#13;
1.  The Available Data:  A Summaryi&#13;
The discussion of these questions has so far relied principally&#13;
on the 1960 and 1970 Demographic Census information on money income.&#13;
Some contributions have also referred to the 1972 and 1973 national household&#13;
Surveys (PNAD), and to partial sources, such as wage statistics for urban&#13;
2/&#13;
employees and household surveys in a few cities.    The recent publication&#13;
of the national household surveys for 1974-75 and 1976 provides an&#13;
opportunity for evaluating earlier sources, and for extending the data&#13;
to include the whole of the fast growth period between 1968-1974. The&#13;
1974-75 Estudo Nacional da Despesa Familiar (ENDEF) is the first household&#13;
expenditure survey with national coverage. Since there are strong&#13;
grounds for suspecting that direct queries on income, like those contained&#13;
in Census and employment survey questionnaires, tend to produce underestimates,&#13;
1/ The chief exception being Gary Fields' argument that "average real&#13;
incomes among families defined as poor by Brazilian standards&#13;
increased by as much as 60% while the comparable figure for non-poor&#13;
families is around 25%." "Who benefits from Economic Development? -&#13;
A Reexamination of Brazilian Growth in the 1960s," American Economic&#13;
Review, 67: 4 (Sept. 1977), pp. 570-582. Below (pp. 33-34) we argue that&#13;
this conclusion is statistically unsound.&#13;
2/ The most thorough attempt to draw on other sources is John Wells,&#13;
"Distribution of Earnings, Growth and the Structure of Demand in&#13;
Brazil during the 1960s," World Development 2:1 (Jan. 1974), pp. 9-24.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 9 -&#13;
(both through the unintentional omission of occasional and secondary&#13;
incomes, as well as through deliberate underreporting) the household&#13;
expenditure study is of particular interest as a check on previous&#13;
sources. The available data on household income shares, along with our&#13;
own adjusted estimates of the possible range for those shares are shown&#13;
in Table 1. "Our estimate" is the midpoint of the range in each year&#13;
and should be read as no more than an order of magnitude.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 10 -&#13;
Table 1:  ESTIMATED FAMILY INCOME SHARES&#13;
(Percentages of Total Family Income)&#13;
Percentile&#13;
Source                                Poorest            Top&#13;
40                10&#13;
1.  1960    Census                                    9.4           44.5&#13;
2.          Meesook-Fishlow adjustment               11.5           41.0&#13;
3.          Our estimate                              9.8           50.0&#13;
(Range)                              (8.0-11.5)      (41.0-59.0)&#13;
4.  1970    Census                                    8.1           46.2&#13;
5.          Our estimate                              8.4           51.5&#13;
(Range)                              (6.8-9.9)       (43.0-60.0)&#13;
6.  1972    PNAD: money income only                   7.4           50.5&#13;
7.          Our estimate                              8.9           53.6&#13;
(Range)                              (8.5-993)       (51.4-55.8)&#13;
8.  1974/75 ENDEF: Expenditures &amp; gross saving        9.4           46.0&#13;
9.          Our estimate                              8.5           51.9&#13;
(Range)                              (7.6-9.4)       (46.0-57.7)&#13;
10-. 1976    PNAD                                     7.5            N.A.&#13;
11.          Our estimate                             7.8            N.A.&#13;
(Range)                              (6.8-8.8)&#13;
Line&#13;
1.  Albert Fishlow and Astra Meesook, Technical Appendix, Brazilian Size&#13;
Distribution of Income, 1960, May 1972, Table B.5.1, p.54. Based on&#13;
one in 1,400 sample of Census, excluding North and Central-West&#13;
regions (about 7% of population). Principally money income (see fn. 1,&#13;
p. 25),       including transfers.  Original data were already grouped&#13;
by size classes so shares of bottom 40 and top 10 are sensitive to&#13;
assumed mean incomes for the bottom and the open-ended top size classes.&#13;
Fishlow-Meesook use a Pareto fit to estimate the mean for the top&#13;
open-ended size class (N.Cr.$50.0+) for individual recipients. Their&#13;
estimate is N.Cr.$108.7, (slightly higher than Langoni's N.Cr.$87.9).&#13;
After combining individuals into families, however, the resultant&#13;
open-ended class mean falls to N.Cr.$88.3 [Implicit in Table B.5.1,&#13;
p.54, op.cit.] This estimate appears to be low if compared with the&#13;
relationship between mean family income in. the open-ended class and&#13;
the class limit, in ENDEF and PNAD 1972, both of which publish the&#13;
actual means in the open-ended class. In both surveys, the ratio is&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 11 -&#13;
about 2.1 vs. Fishlow-Meesook's 1.75 (87.6 '. 50.0). These&#13;
relationships are shown in Table 5 below (p. 43). If the 1960&#13;
shares are reestimated using the ratio of 2.1, the Meesook-Fishlow&#13;
share for the top 10 rises by 3.6 percentage points, from 41.0 to&#13;
44.6, and that of the bottom 40 falls from 11.5.to 11.0. The esti-&#13;
mates in Line 3 would change in the same proportion.&#13;
2. Idem. Principal adjustment is imputation of value of direct consump-&#13;
tion of product by agricultural families. The imputation is a decreasing&#13;
proportion of money income and, on average, adds 39% to total farm&#13;
incomes. Other adjustments are imputations for owner-occupied homes,&#13;
and food and lodging received by domestic servants.&#13;
3.  Obtained by allocation of difference between Census income total (after&#13;
Meesook-Fishlow imputation of nonmonetary income) and national. accounts&#13;
total personal income (shown in Table 2). Range results frpm two extreme&#13;
assumptions regarding allocation by percentile: high figure assumes equal&#13;
proportional underreporting in each percentile; low figure allocates&#13;
entire difference to top decile. "Our estimate" is the midpoint of&#13;
range. See text pp. 35-36.&#13;
4.  Based on size distribution in Carlos Geraldo, Langoni, Distribu ao da&#13;
Renda E Desenvolvimento Economico do Brasil, (Rio de Janeiro, Editora&#13;
Expressao e Cultura, 1973), Table 1.2, p.26. Langoni's figures exclude&#13;
zero-income families (3.7% of total) but we re-included them for greater&#13;
comparability with 1960. Exclusion of zero-income families raises&#13;
share of bottom 40 to 9.5%. Presumably only monetary income is recorded&#13;
since Census questionnaire and coding procedures have no instructions&#13;
for imputation of nonmonetary income. Also, income at the top is&#13;
underestimated by a coding limitation: All incomes above Cr. 9997&#13;
were coded as equal to Cr. 9998 (Costa 1977, p.52).&#13;
5.  Includes three adjustments:   (a) addition of nonmonetary income using&#13;
ENDEF ratio of nonmonetary to monetary by percentile; (b) use of a Pareto&#13;
estimated mean income for open-ended income class, i.e., Cr.$4251 instead&#13;
of Langoni's Cr.$3245; and (c) allocation of difference between Census&#13;
income total (after adjustments (a) and (b)) and national accounts&#13;
disposable income as in Line 3.&#13;
6.  From Table 3.8 of PNAD-2, 1972 40 Trimestre, Todas Regioes, FIGBE,&#13;
p.54.  This table shows total income by income class and thus eliminates&#13;
the open-ended class problem. Includes monetary remuneration only&#13;
(Rendimento Monetario). A more comprehensive income concept (Renda&#13;
Global), including transfers and income in kind, is used in Table 6.1,&#13;
but distributed by individuals, not families. Renda Global is 34% larger&#13;
than Rendimento Monetario. PNAD 1972 excludes Regions VI and VII&#13;
(Federal District and North). Only 0.1% of all families are reported&#13;
with zero income, suggesting an element of incomparability with the&#13;
1960 and 1970 censuses,&#13;
7. Adjusted for nonmonetary income and for the shortfall of survey incomes&#13;
relative to national accounts (Table 2) as in Line 3 above.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 12 -&#13;
8.   Based on the Estudo Nacional da Despesa Familiar (ENDEF), Table 7,&#13;
for Regions I-V (excludes Distrito Federal &amp; North). Covers current&#13;
expenditures (including taxes) plus capital expenditures (principally&#13;
purchases of real estate) plus net increases in financial assets,&#13;
including retained earnings, plus debt payments. The financial&#13;
items, however, are not net of sales of assets or of borrowing, and&#13;
therefore exaggerate net saving.&#13;
9.  Adjusted to approximate current income by the arbitrary assumption&#13;
that net saving is 75% of gross saving in each income class, i.e.,&#13;
that sales of assets plus borrowing amount to 25% of gross savings&#13;
in each income class as recorded by ENDEF. Actual dissaving&#13;
(borrowing plus sales assets) is probably higher but (i) the value&#13;
of increases in bank accounts is already a net figure; and (ii) not&#13;
all dissaving needs to be included - only that which is reflected in&#13;
ENDEF's expenditure figures. Since ENDEF expenditure on durables and&#13;
real estate is understated by recording only the value of payments during&#13;
the reporting year,and not the full cost,there is no corresponding need&#13;
to deduct the value of consumer and mortgage debt incurred for those purchases.&#13;
Also adjusted for shortfall relative to national accounts (Table 2) as&#13;
in Line 3 above. All references in the text to ENDEF "income" refer to&#13;
this estimate of income based on reported expenditures and savings plus&#13;
our downward adjustment for unreported dissaving plus our upward adjust-&#13;
ment for unreported expenditures and/or savings.&#13;
10.  Table 3 (p.74) of the 1976 Pesquisa Nacional por Amostra de Domicilios&#13;
(PNAD). Excludes rural areas of Region VII (North) or about 1% of&#13;
National income according to national accounts Table XVIII. Share of&#13;
top 10% could not be estimated because the top open-ended class is&#13;
far too large: it contains 24% of all families. Includes nonmonetary&#13;
and transfer incomes. Only 1.0% families recorded with zero income.&#13;
Income in the open-ended class derived as a residual from total income&#13;
calculated from Table 14 of PNAD 1976. That table covers all individual&#13;
recipients and provides a more detailed set of income categories in&#13;
which the open-ended class comprises only 1.4% of all recipients. Mean&#13;
income for that class is based on a Pareto function fitted to the last&#13;
two income categories.&#13;
11. Same adjustment as Line 7.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 13 -&#13;
To the extent that any weight is placed on the estimates in Table 1&#13;
they support the view that inequality has probably increased. As will be&#13;
argued below, the margin for error in that data is very large and there is&#13;
no basis for a definite trend estimate. Nevertheless, it should be noted&#13;
that these estimates imply less deterioraticn than is usually alleged, and&#13;
allow for substantial growth in the absolute incomes of the poor.&#13;
A comparison of unadjusted figures (Lines 1 and 6, or 1 and 10)&#13;
shows some increase in inequality: between 1960 and 1976 the poor lose 21%&#13;
of their 1960 share and the rich gain 13%.   Adjustment, however, is necessary,&#13;
because there appears to be a great deal of unreported income in the original&#13;
sources.  The two main adjustments that are required have offsetting effects:&#13;
an imputation for no'amonetary income raises the share of the poor, while an&#13;
imputation for unreported money income probably increases concentration.&#13;
Though these imputations are largely arbitrary, explicit adjustments are&#13;
preferable to the implicit assumptions that are involved in using unadjusted&#13;
figures: Any comparison requires strong assumptions regarding the extent&#13;
and distribution of unreported income. The purpose of Table 1 is to set&#13;
out what we consider to be the most plausible statistical message provided&#13;
by the available data. The degree of uncertainty in these data will be&#13;
explored below.&#13;
2. ENDEF&#13;
The recently published 1974/75 national household expenditure&#13;
1/&#13;
and nutrition survey (ENDEF) provides the most reliable basis for statements&#13;
1/ By the Fundacao6 Instituto de Estatistica e Geografia (FIGBE). The&#13;
survey covered 55,000 households between August 1974 and August 1975.&#13;
The sampling framework was based on the 1970 Census updated in May&#13;
1974. Interviewers visited each household over a week.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 14 -&#13;
about the structure of incomes. Expenditure surveys usually achieve&#13;
better coverage of total income than employment surveys, and this was the&#13;
l/&#13;
case with ENDEF (Table 2). In part, coverage is higher because ENDEF con-&#13;
tains   the first carefully estimated measures of nonmonetary income at&#13;
a national level (Table 3). However, ENDEF also yields higher estimates&#13;
for monetary income, presumably because the additive procedure of listing&#13;
individual expenditures, along with the observation of a household over a&#13;
week served as checks on under-reporting. Another advantage of expenditure&#13;
surveys is that expenditure is more stable than income. The resulting&#13;
measures are therefore closer to an annual "normal" income, and there are&#13;
no cases of families with zero income.&#13;
One limitation of ENDEF is that the questionnaire data on incomes&#13;
have not yet been published. The estimates in Table 1 are based on published&#13;
figures for family expenditures and savings. The sum of these items in&#13;
principle equals income, but the published ENDEF data on financial trans-&#13;
actions are incomplete:    sales of assets and of some forms of borrowing&#13;
have not been netted out. Income is therefore overstated to the extent that&#13;
recorded consumption or investment has been financed by either borrowing&#13;
or sales of assets. In deriving the shares shown in Table 1, we made the&#13;
arbitrary assumption that true net savings in each income class were 75%&#13;
2/&#13;
of reported "gross savings."     Since saving as a proportion of current&#13;
1/ Cf. Altimir [1976], pp. 76 and 81.&#13;
2/ The term "Gross Savings" is inexact but is used to indicate that&#13;
ENDEF figures fail to deduct all debits. See footnotes to Lines 7&#13;
and 8, Table 1.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 15 -&#13;
expenditure is much higher in the top income brackets - 45% in the top&#13;
decile vs. 13% in the bottom 40% of families - the effect of this assump-&#13;
tion is to slightly reduce the degree of inequality, as indicated by&#13;
Lines 8 and 9 in Table 1. Furthermore, the discrepancy between ENDEF and&#13;
national accounts income shown in Table 2 suggests that income remains&#13;
underestimated, despite the overall high quality of ENDEF as a statistical&#13;
exercise, and despite the fact that ENDEF's coverage of personal income is high&#13;
in comparison with other Brazilian sources, and with most surveys in other&#13;
1/&#13;
countries (Table 2).&#13;
3. Underreporting&#13;
Some indication of the extent of underreporting in each source&#13;
is provided by the comparison with national accounts income and consumption&#13;
totals in Table 2. The national accounts figures have been adjusted to&#13;
approximate the Census/survey concepts. Crude assumptions were required&#13;
because there are no current estimates of corporate retained earnings&#13;
(missing in survey/census income), or of transfers within the private sector&#13;
(netted out in national accounts National Income). The adjustments, however,&#13;
are adequate to indicate orders of magnitude: the discrepancies between&#13;
Census/survey and national accounts figures are large and they differ over&#13;
2/&#13;
time.    They are surely the product of both unintentional omission of&#13;
occasional and secondary sources of income, and of deliberate underreporting.&#13;
This interpretation is supported by the fact that, by virtue of more&#13;
thorough questioning, both PNAD 1972 and ENDEF discover higher incomes.&#13;
It seems likely that even in the latter sources, much income remains&#13;
unreported: the obvious candidates are illegal incomes, reinvested profits&#13;
1/ See footnote 1, p. 17.&#13;
2/ An index of real income per household constructed from unadjusted&#13;
census and survey data rises as follows: 1970=100, 1972=170, 1974/75=232.&#13;
By contrast, the index of real GDP per capita is 1970=100, 1972"120,&#13;
1974/75=143.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 16 -&#13;
Table 2: COMPARISON OF ESTIMATES OF ANNUAL PERSONAL&#13;
INCOME AND CONSUMPTION&#13;
(in billions of current Cr.$)&#13;
Survey//   National       %&#13;
Census  a  Accountsb    Discrepancy&#13;
1.   1960      Census                          1.46         2.50       42&#13;
2.              (plus nonmonetary)             1.73         2.50       31&#13;
3.   1970      Census                          93.2         166        44&#13;
4.   1972      PNAD (money factor income)       164         290        43&#13;
5.              (plus nonmonetary and transfer&#13;
income)                        221         290         24&#13;
6.   1974-75   ENDEF (expenditures plus&#13;
saving)                        483         600         20&#13;
7.              (Consumption)                   395         480        18&#13;
8.   1976      PNAD                             916        1279        28&#13;
/a Total personal income figures of survey/censuses were adjusted (i) to&#13;
include Regions VI &amp; VII (Federal District and North) when coverage&#13;
was incomplete, using their share in NNP according to Table XVIII of&#13;
Contas Nacionais; (ii) to represent the calendar year, using Rio cost&#13;
of living index and real growth trend during the year: PNAD were&#13;
in fourth quarter, censuses in August (1960) and September (1970),&#13;
ENDEF was August 1974 - August 1975 but all ENDEF values are expressed&#13;
in August 1974 prices; and (iii) to deduct intra-family sector&#13;
transfers, estimated to equal 5% of total family income in all surveys,&#13;
and 3% in the Censuses (since less transfer income is reported in&#13;
Censuses). Figures are approximations based on 1972 PNAD figure of&#13;
12% for all transfer income, less social security transfers from&#13;
Sinopse Estatistico do Brasil 1977, pp. 511-518.&#13;
/b National accounts Personal Income estimated here as equal to National&#13;
Income plus Transfers and Subsidies, less Retained Earnings assumed&#13;
to equal 10% of National Income. No estimates of corporate retained&#13;
earnings are published, but the national accounts provides a ceiling&#13;
in the figure for private sector saving less depreciation, if one assumes&#13;
positive household sector saving. The latter assumption is strongly supported&#13;
by ENDEF, which slows household savings to be 16% of total income (after dbwn-&#13;
ward adjustment for unreported dissaving explained in Table 1, Line 9.)&#13;
Private sector saving less depreciation as a proportion of national&#13;
income was 6.2% in 1959, 8.3% in 1970, 9.7% in 1972, 11.5% in 1974 and&#13;
6.5% in 1976. These figures imply retained earnings well below 1/0%, but they&#13;
are subject to much error. Figures for other LDCs range between 5 and 10%.&#13;
Thus, the 10% used here is probably an upper bound for the seventies,&#13;
and too high for 1960 given the rapid growth of the corporate sector.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 17 -&#13;
Source: Contas Nacionais, Revisao e Atualizacao, July 1977. This&#13;
publication contains revised estimates for earlier years, including&#13;
the benchmark years 1949 and 1959. The revision implies a higher GNP&#13;
in 1960 than earlier estimates. Since Table VI does not contain an&#13;
estimate for 1960, the 1960 figure used here is a projection of 1959&#13;
using the implicit GDP deflator and real growth rate.&#13;
Line 1. From Fishlow and Meesook, Technical Appendix, p. 54. Census&#13;
reference month for income was August, but if August had not been a typical&#13;
month, a monthly average for the entire prior years was solicited. It&#13;
seems likely that a majority reported current (August) receipts.&#13;
Line 2. Same source as Line 1. Includes estimated nonmonetary income (imputed rent,&#13;
pay in kind of domestics, and own-consumption of agricultural output). The Fishlow-&#13;
Meesook original reconciliation with the national accounts obtained a maximum&#13;
discrepancy of 10%. Their comparison is with an earlier estimate of Personal&#13;
Income published in the Revista Brasileira    de Economia.  The figure for&#13;
Disposable Income used here is based on the recently revised Contas Nacionais&#13;
op.cit which revised 1959 NNP upwards by 28%.   About half sx thz increaae is&#13;
due to the revision of value added in Manufacturing and Commerce. The 1960&#13;
Economic Censuses, which provide the benchmarks for value added in those&#13;
sectors, appear to have classified several components of value added as forms&#13;
of intermediate purchases under the item "Other Expenditures." This became&#13;
apparent from a comparison of input-output ratios in the 1950 and 1960 censuses&#13;
and 1966-1970 annual establishment surveys by DEICOM/FIGBE. Thus, the ratio of&#13;
value added to total output in Manufacturing ranges between 39 and 40% in all&#13;
those years except 1960, when it was raported as only 30%.&#13;
AW discussed in the text (pp. 22-26) the 1960 discrepancies shown&#13;
here are probably minimum estimates.&#13;
Line 3. From Langoni, Carlos Geraldo, Distribuiga6 da Renda e Desenvolvimento&#13;
Economico do Brasil (Rio: Editora Expressao e Cultura, 1973), p. 64.&#13;
Langoni's mean income, however, was adjusted upwards by re-estimating the&#13;
upper open-class mean income with a Pareto fit to correct for the ceiling&#13;
income of Cr. 9998 imposed on his data.&#13;
Line 4. Table 3.7, PNAD-2, 1972, FIGBE. Defined as monetary remuneration,&#13;
including cash rents and other property income. (See footnote 6, Table 1,&#13;
above.)&#13;
Line 5. Table 6.1, PNAD-2, 1972. Defined as "global income" includes non-&#13;
monetary remuneration and transfer income from government (pensions, dis-&#13;
ability payments) from corporate sector (insurance payments, pensions) and&#13;
from other families (remittances to students, gifts, etc.). Nonmonetary&#13;
remuneration is 11.3% and transfers 13.4% of "global income." Rural non-&#13;
monetary income, however, appears to be underestimated (see text p. 29).&#13;
Unfortunately this table is a distribution by individual recipients; there&#13;
is no table which distributes "global income" by household income classes.&#13;
Thus the full and relative high coverage achieved by PNAD-1972 is not&#13;
available for comparison with household distributions in other years.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 18 -&#13;
Line 6. Estudo Nacional da Despesa Familiar 1974-75, FIGBE, Table 7.&#13;
Corresponds to our estimate of family income based on reported expenditure&#13;
and savings plus adjustment for unreported dissaving. (See footnotes&#13;
lines 8 &amp; 9, Table 1 above.)&#13;
Line 7. Idem. Consumption equals current Expenditures plus purchases of&#13;
vehicles classified under Increase in Assets.&#13;
Line 8. PNAD, FIGBE, Table 14. Pareto fit on upper two income categories&#13;
used to estimate mean income of top open-ended class, which comprises&#13;
1.4% of recipients. Includes imputed value income in kind, property&#13;
income, and transfers.&#13;
of family enterprises, corporate dividends and other property incomes,&#13;
and, in the case of ENDEF socially embarrassing expenditures.&#13;
Though the national accounts are also liable to large error, they deserve&#13;
greater credence as measures of the level of total income than replies to the brief&#13;
question used in Censuses, or even to the fuller questions in surveys. Moreover,&#13;
there is a variety of other evidence, reviewed below, which bears out the claim&#13;
that Census and survey incomes are too low. In this respect Brazil is similar to&#13;
other countries; it is a common experience that expenditure surveys yield lower&#13;
1/&#13;
incomes than the national accounts. Furthermore, the most plausible hypothesis&#13;
1/ Evidence for Latin America is provided by Oscar Altimir, "Income&#13;
Distribution Estimates from Household Surveys and Population Censuses&#13;
in Latin America: An Assessment of Reliability," IBRD/ECLA, Nov. 1976.&#13;
After reviewing 49 sources in 14 countries Altimir states that "very&#13;
.few of the surveys and censuses analyzed show income results which are&#13;
reasonably consistent with macroeconomic estimates," p. 95. Further&#13;
evidence is provided in the following percentages of&#13;
survey income to personal income or consumption according to the&#13;
national accounts:&#13;
73%    Mexico, Personal Income, 1963 (Navarrette 1970, p.68).&#13;
66%    Korea, Personal Income 1965 (Bhalla, 1979)&#13;
73%    Korea, Personal Income 1976 (Bhalla, 1979)&#13;
68-71% Philippines, Personal Income, 1970-71 (Berry, 1978, p.315)&#13;
80%    India, Rural Consumption 1970-71 (Ahluwalia, 1978, p. 21)&#13;
73%    Colombia, Personal Income (Berry, 1978, p. 22)&#13;
60%    Turkey, Non-agricultural Disposable Income (Dervis and Robinson,&#13;
1977, pp. 29 and 40).&#13;
All the above are expenditure surveys: employment and other non-&#13;
expenditure surveys usually yield even lower income figures.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 19 -&#13;
regarding Brazil's national accounts is that any net error is one of&#13;
underestimation, in part because several components of value added are&#13;
1/&#13;
themselves based on earnings levels reported by the 1970 census.    The&#13;
discrepancies noted in Table 2, therefore, are likely to be minimum&#13;
estimates of income not reported in censuses and surveys.&#13;
The most obvious component of underreporting is nonmonetary&#13;
income, chiefly own-consumption by farm households and imputed rents on&#13;
owner-occupied homes. Census and PNAD income data are commonly described&#13;
as being money income only. In fact, their income questions do not exclude&#13;
nonmonetary income, and further, the 1972, 1973 and 1976 PNAD's have explicit&#13;
questions for income in kind. The 1972 PNAD is particularly thorough in&#13;
its questionnaire on all forms of income. However, there is good reason to&#13;
believe that most nonmonetary income has been omitted by all sources except&#13;
PNAD 1972, and that even PNAD 1972 underreports the bulk of rural income in kind.&#13;
_/&#13;
This is an a priori to be expectation from reading the survey methodologies,&#13;
1/ Census earnings levels are applied to the self-employed outside agri-&#13;
culture, and to construction wage-earners. There are other components&#13;
of the national accounts methodology which raise questions of possible&#13;
underestimation, e.g., value of own-construction, and rural non-&#13;
monetary income. Also, total income of agricultural households according&#13;
to ENDEF is about 40% higher than national accounts value added in agri-&#13;
culture (Cr.$96 billion vs. 68 billion in 1974 prices). Presumably&#13;
agricultural households are receiving substantial amounts of income from&#13;
non-agricultural sources, e.g., construction labor, trading, social&#13;
security. Also their imputed rent should be deducted (about 7% of income).&#13;
On the other hand ENDEF probably omits much property income generated&#13;
in agriculture, but not attributed to "farm households," because the&#13;
proprietors are urban residents with other occupations. This comparison&#13;
thus definitely suggests underestimation of agricultural income in the&#13;
national accounts. At the same time, the national accounts probably&#13;
overestimate some items, but our view is that the net error is not likely&#13;
to be on the low side.&#13;
2/  In PNAD 1972, rural farm workers (mensalistas and diaristas) are not&#13;
asked the value of production for own-consumption. Landowners and&#13;
sharecroppers are asked to list quantity and price of up to six products&#13;
withdrawn for own use. Out of 107 foods listed by ENDEF in 67 cases&#13;
own-consumption accounted for half or more of total rural Northeast&#13;
consumption. Accurate recall on such a question would in any case be difficult&#13;
to achieve. PNAD 1976 has only a summary question on total income in kind.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 20 -&#13;
but the basic evidence is the much higher values of nonmonetary income&#13;
reported by ENDEF and by a set of rural family expenditure surveys carried&#13;
1/&#13;
out in 1962/63 bv the Funda;ico Getalin vargas.&#13;
ENDEF provides the first carefully estimated measures of non-&#13;
monetary income at a national level and confirms the earlier results of the&#13;
FGV: both sources report ratios of rural nonmonetary to monetary income of&#13;
about 50% (Table 3). The FGV ratio (46.5%) was used by Fishlow and Meesook&#13;
for their adjustment of the 1960 agricultural distribution.     Some doubt&#13;
was placed on the FGV ratio by two later studies that yielded much lower&#13;
figures. Langoni based his discussion of subsistence consumption on a relatively&#13;
2/&#13;
limited survey (597 farm households) which produced a ratio of only 15%. Fishlow,&#13;
in a more recent paper, cites the 1972 PNAD which also arrives at much lower figure&#13;
for rural households (17%), though its ratio for urban households is close&#13;
3/&#13;
to that of ENDEF (14 and 18% respectively).        We have assumed that, on&#13;
1/  The 1962/63 surveys were carried out by the Fundapao Getulio Vargas,&#13;
in rural areas of the States of Pernambuco, Ceara, Minas Gerais,&#13;
Espirito Santo, Sao Paulo, Santa Catarina and Rio Grande do Sul.&#13;
1816 families were interviewed. The 46.5% is for individual earners&#13;
and combines imputed rent (about 6%) and imputed consumption of farm&#13;
products (39%). Fishlow-Meesook's Tables B.0.1 and B.3.3 (pp. 25 and&#13;
45 in Technical Appendix, 1972) show a slightly higher ratio - 48% - for&#13;
families.&#13;
2/  Cited in Langoni, Distribuicao da Renda, pp. 28 and 40.    The survey was&#13;
by Carlos Langoni and Guilherme Dias, "Avaliaa-o Economica do Servico&#13;
de Extensao Rural," Convenio ABCAR-IPE, 1972. The ratio is strongly&#13;
progressive, rising from 1.2% for the top rural decile to 44.6% for the&#13;
poorest 40%, and 79.6% for the bottom decile.&#13;
31 Albert Fishlow was misled by these PNAD 1972 figures into     justifying&#13;
his comparison of unadjusted 1960 and 1970 Census and 1972 survey data.&#13;
From that comparison he concludes that there was a substantial&#13;
deterioration in the share of the poor. "These data [PNAD 1972 data on&#13;
nonmonetary income] therefore decisively reject the promise that a&#13;
properly calculated measure of real income would cast the Brazilian&#13;
size distribution in a more favorable light" in "Brazilian Income&#13;
Distribution: Does Trickle-Down Really Work?" unpublished paper pre-&#13;
sented to Workdhop on Analysis of Distributional Issues in Development&#13;
Planning, Bellagio, 1977.&#13;
Note that 62% of agricultural households are farmers, and that rural&#13;
wage-earners have several sources of nonmonetary income, viz. pay in&#13;
kind (both food and housing) small plots, wood and food gathering, and&#13;
home manufacture.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 21 -&#13;
methodological grounds, the two household budget surveys (FGV and ENDEF)&#13;
are more likely to measure both monetary and nonmonetary income adequately,&#13;
and therefore that the nonmonetary component is in the order of one-third&#13;
of total rural income.&#13;
Table 3: NONMONETARY AS A PROPORTION OF MONETARY FAMILY INCOME&#13;
All Families       Urban         Rural&#13;
ENDEF                            23             18             50&#13;
Rio                         19             18             36&#13;
Sao Paulo                   19             18             34&#13;
South                       27             18             50&#13;
Minas Gerais                26             18             52&#13;
Northeast                   30             20             57&#13;
FGV                              19                            47&#13;
PNAD 1972                        14              14            17&#13;
Rural laborers                                             9&#13;
Farmers                                                   17&#13;
Notes:  1.  ENDEF 1974/75, Despesas Das Familias.    Regions I-V, Table 4.&#13;
Total current and capital expenditure plus saving is used as&#13;
an estimate of income. Since savings are somewhat overstated&#13;
(see above p. 14) the above ratios are underestimated.&#13;
FCV. Food Consumption in Brazil, Family Budget Surveys in the&#13;
Earlv 1960s,  Data cited bv Fishlow-&lt;4eesook in  echnical&#13;
Appendix, pp, 25 and 45.&#13;
3. PNAD-2, 1972, Table 4.7 . Refers to farm and nonfarm rather&#13;
than urban-rural. The heavy weight of nonfarm plus decimal&#13;
rounding explain equality between national average and nonfarm&#13;
ratios.  Excludes rural areas of Region VII (North).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 22 -&#13;
There is also evidence that the nonmonetary proportion is much&#13;
higher for the poorest families. Within the Langoni-Dias sample the ratio&#13;
1/&#13;
rises from 1% in the top rural decile to 80% in the bottom decile.     The&#13;
more comprehensive FGV survey yields similar results: when income in kind&#13;
is added, mean income for the poorest quintile rises 100%, vs. about 40%&#13;
2/&#13;
for the top quintile.    The omission of nonmonetary income is therefore&#13;
particularly damaging to the measurement of poverty. This is corroborated&#13;
by differences in the estimates of families reported to earn one minimum&#13;
wage or less in different surveys. The proportion of such families&#13;
drops drastically and implausibly, from 47% in&#13;
1/ Langoni, Distribuicao, p. 28.&#13;
2/ Fishlow-Meesook, Technical Appendix, Tables B.0.1 and B.3.3.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 23 -&#13;
1/&#13;
1970, to 38% in 1972, to 12% in 1974/75. In 1976 it rises to 20%.&#13;
Though rapid income growth during this period may indeed have reduced&#13;
poverty, most of the reported change must be due to varying coverage of&#13;
nonmonetary income.  The intermediate 1976 figure can be explained by&#13;
its partial coverage of nonmonetary income. The 1976 income question&#13;
requested separate answers to monthly earnings in cash and in kind, but&#13;
as with the even more detailed 1972 question, it is likely that coverage&#13;
of nonmonetary income was incomplete, as might be expected from any similarly&#13;
direct and brief question on non-cash income, and as is suggested by the&#13;
fact that the PNAD proportion of families with one minimum wage or less is&#13;
almost double that of ENDEF.&#13;
There is evidence that monetary income is also underreported in&#13;
varying degrees in the different censuses and surveys. The 1960 census&#13;
figures, after the substantial Fishlow-Meesook adjustment for income in kind&#13;
are still 31% short of the national accounts estimate of personal income.&#13;
The ENDEF figure for Family Consumption Expenditure is about 18% short of&#13;
the national accounts Personal Consumption. The discrepancy between the&#13;
1976 PNAD and the national accounts (28%) is too large to be explained by&#13;
missing nonmonetary income, since some nonmonetary income is already included.&#13;
Another indication of missing income is provided by the higher coverage that resulted&#13;
1/  For 1970, Censo DemograZLi0 ,able 10, p.226.   Three-quarters of the&#13;
Cr. 151-200 class was assumed to earn up to one minimum wage (Cr. 187).&#13;
The 1972 figure is from Table 3.6 of PNAD-2 which excludes transfer and&#13;
nonmonetary income. (There is no table for families which includes&#13;
nonmonetary income, equivalent to Table 6.1 for individual recipients&#13;
though as argued in the text above even Table 6.1 probably underestimates&#13;
rural nonmonetary income). The 1976 figure is from Table 3, p.74.&#13;
The real minimum wage changed only slightly between 1970 and 1976.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 24 -&#13;
1/&#13;
from the much more detailed income questionnaire used in 1972.    As shown in&#13;
Table 2, overall coverage was close to that of ENDEF - the main difference&#13;
being the lesser coverage of rural nonmonetary income by PNAD 1972 - and&#13;
significantly higher than that of the Censuses. The composition of 1972&#13;
incomes is revealing: Transfers account for 13.4% of total income, income&#13;
in kind for 11.3% and monetary remuneration (including property income)&#13;
2/&#13;
for 75.3%.   It seems likely that the Censuses, and possibly, later PNAD's&#13;
were less complete in reporting transfer income.&#13;
4. The 1960 Census&#13;
The .1960 census deserves special attention .because it is the&#13;
sole basis for long-run comparisons of distribution. Furthermore, it is&#13;
the only source which shows a significantly different degree of inequality:&#13;
the income shares shown in Table 1 imply a better distribution in 1960&#13;
than in later years. It is clear from Table 2, however, that such com-&#13;
parisons will be subject to a high degree of uncertainty: about 42% of&#13;
personal income was not reported in the Census. Moreover, there is a&#13;
range of uncertainty associated with the amount that was "reported." Because&#13;
incomes were recorded by class intervals, the top and bottom shares are&#13;
sensitive to the assumptions regarding mean incomes in the extreme income&#13;
classes. But the more critical questions have to do with the allocation&#13;
of unreported income.&#13;
1/ The questionnaire listed six different categories of income or recipients&#13;
(wage-earners, self-employed, rural laborers, rural proprietors and&#13;
sharecroppers, property income, other monetary and nonmonetary income)&#13;
and then further listed various types or components of income within&#13;
each category, e.g., wage-earners were asked to report separately each&#13;
of the following: Cash wage, bonuses, overtime, paid holiday, severance&#13;
pay, and others. By contrast, the 1960 and 1970 Censuses simply asked&#13;
for average monthly earnings.&#13;
2/ Estimated from Tables 2.7 and 6.1, PNAD-2 1972. Transfers include&#13;
pensions, family remittances, lottery prizes, gifts, insurance payments, etc,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 25 -&#13;
The omission of nonmonetary income, which chiefly affects the&#13;
poorest deciles, was recognized by Fishlow and Meesook and was the subject&#13;
of a detailed adjustment procedure, but a comparison with ENDEF raises the&#13;
question whether Fishlow-Meesook adjusted enough: they arrive at a ratio&#13;
of nonmonetary to monetary income of 18%, which is lower than the 23%&#13;
1/&#13;
found by ENDEF.     For the poorest 40%, their ratio is also lower than&#13;
ENDEF's - 43% vs. 53%. The real value of nonmonetary income per poor&#13;
household in 1974/75 is exactly twice the amount imputed by Fishlow-Meesook&#13;
2/&#13;
in 1960.   Perhaps a third of the estimated difference is due to the&#13;
3/&#13;
relative increase in farm prices.    The remainder must represent either&#13;
growth in the quantity of nonmonetary consumption per household, or&#13;
underestimation in 1960. Growth in the quantity of own-consumption&#13;
may seem implausible, given the trend towards monetization, but (i) the&#13;
income elasticity of expenditure on housing - and therefore&#13;
imputed rents - is positive, and probably exceeds 1.0, and (ii) regional&#13;
cross-section evidence suggests that rural nonmonetary consumption rises&#13;
with income: in 1974-75, nonmonetary expenditure per household&#13;
was Cr.$6312 in the South, Cr.$4890 in Sao Paulo, and only Cr.$2742 in&#13;
4/&#13;
the Northeast.     Since there is evidence of some real income growth&#13;
1/ Fishlow and Meesook op.cit. One aspect of their method raises the&#13;
possibility of some compensating overadjustment in the lowest income&#13;
categories. Fishlow-Meesook assume that the Census reports money&#13;
income only.   (The Census question was "How much do you earn, on the&#13;
average, per month?") But in the Census, no farm families are reported&#13;
with zero income, though 5% of nonfarm families are reported with zero&#13;
income!  In the case of farm households, however, zero income would&#13;
imply no cash income during a whole year because variable-income families&#13;
were asked to report their mean income for the last 12 months. It seems&#13;
implausible that there were no pure subsistence families in 1960, this&#13;
statistic thus suggests that the Census is not pure money income.&#13;
2/  In 1974-75, nonmonietary income per family per annum, within the poorest&#13;
40% families, equalled Cr.$2130. The corresponding Fishlow-Meesook&#13;
value for 1960 (in 1974-75 prices) was Cr.$1056.&#13;
3/  The farm/nonfarm terms of trade rose about 40% over the period 1960-1974,&#13;
but an index that allows for own-consumption by farmers would rise less.&#13;
4/ ENDEF, Table 4.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 26 -&#13;
amongst the poor, some growth in own-consumption is likely.&#13;
Urbanization could have been expected to reduce nonmonetary consumption,&#13;
but the data show no urbanization of the poor: the urban-rural composition&#13;
1/&#13;
of the bottom 40 remained constant.     On the other hand, since the&#13;
elasticity of nonmonetary to total expenditure is less than 1.0, and some&#13;
degree of monetization is known to have occurred, the evidence still&#13;
points to some degree of uunderestimation of 1960 nonmonetary income of&#13;
the poor. Unfortunately, there is no basis for a more precise statement,&#13;
nor for an estimate of underreported cash income of the poor.&#13;
It is also difficult to gauge the error at the top of the 1960&#13;
distribution. One difficulty was noted above (notes to Table 1, Line 1):&#13;
data from ENDEF arnd P.'AD 1972 suggest that the Fishlow-Meesook mean income&#13;
for the open-ended class may be too low, in their household distribution.&#13;
In both these more recent surveys the ratio of the mean income&#13;
in the open-ended class to the limit of the class is higher (between&#13;
2/&#13;
2.0 and 2.1) than in Fishlow-Meesook's calculation (1.8).    This apparently&#13;
trivial difference is enough to raise the uncorrected share of the top&#13;
10 in 1960 (Table 1, Line 1) from 44.5 to 47.8%, i.e., it eliminates most&#13;
of the apparent increase in income concentration at the top since 1960.&#13;
In sum, there is an important margin of error in simply establishing what&#13;
the Census reports as the share of the rich. This is in addition to the&#13;
1/ In fact, the rural share appears to have grown. According to Fishlow-&#13;
Meesook, 60% of the bottom 40 in 1960 were agricultural families. In&#13;
1974-75, 66% were rural. This could be explained by a combination of&#13;
urbanization with faster poverty reduction within urban areas than in&#13;
rural. But it may be, to some extent, spurious - caused by a greater&#13;
underestimation of urban than rural incomes in 1960 (after the adjust-&#13;
ments for income in kind), thus overrepresenting urban poverty in 1960.&#13;
2/ See below, Table 5, p. 43. In their uncorrected household income distri-&#13;
bution, the implicit mean income for the Cr.$50.0+ class is Cr.$88.3&#13;
which is lower than Pareto fitted mean of Cr.$108.7 applied to the&#13;
distribution for individual recipients, and lower than the values (Cr.$100.0-&#13;
105.0) that would result from using the 1972 and ENDEF ratios of mean income&#13;
to limit income.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 27 -&#13;
margin of error associated with the allocation of unreported cash income,&#13;
which amounts to some 31% of personal income (Table 2, Line 2).&#13;
There is indirect evidence of considerable underreporting by the&#13;
rich in 1960. A set of family budget studies carried out'by the Fundaya6-&#13;
Getulio Vargas between 1961 and 1963, suggests that incomes at the top of&#13;
the distribution were much higher than reported by the Census. About 10%&#13;
of FGV's rural sample had family incomes over Cr.50 per month (1960 prices)&#13;
vs. only 0.5% in the Census, and 15% of the urban sample, vs. 3.0% in the&#13;
1/&#13;
Census.    Also, the top income category in the Census began at Cr.$50.0&#13;
2/&#13;
which in 1978 dollars represents about US$800 per month.     Only 1 in 6&#13;
professionals (doctors, dentists, judges, lawyers and engineers) reported&#13;
monthly incomes over that level. Half of all professionals declared&#13;
monthly incomes under US$500. Similarly, only 1 in 4 university graduates&#13;
3/&#13;
reported earning US$800 or more.     Again, the census reports only 32,000&#13;
r                                     4/&#13;
agricultural households with monthly incomes over that level.     Yet according&#13;
1/ A total of 9125 families were interviewed, 7,309 in the urban sector and&#13;
1,816 in the rural. The survey was not designed as a nationwide sample,&#13;
but had widespread regional coverage and was stratified to represent&#13;
state capitals, towns, and rural areas. The sample frame was drawn from&#13;
the 1960 census. Getulio Vargas Foundation, Food Consumption in Brazil,&#13;
Family Budget Surveys in the Early 1960s, p. 3. FGV data are for urban&#13;
and rural, census for agricultural and nonagricultural.&#13;
2/ This conversion uses the more realistic 1978 exchange rate of 18.07,&#13;
after reflating Cr.$50 by the adjusted Rio consumer price index'&#13;
Using the overvalued 1960 exchange rate (0.187) and US cost of living index&#13;
yields a lower dollar figure of $590. In 1960 dollars Cr.$50 was the&#13;
equivalent of only US$270.&#13;
3/ Graduates defined as having completed 5 or more years of superior&#13;
education. Only 0.6% of the labor force were university graduates.&#13;
4/ Fishlow and Meesook (op.cit, p. 25) report 0.5% households in agriculture&#13;
earning N.Cr.$50   or more per month.   Censo Demografico 1960, p. -14&#13;
gives 6.4 million households with head of household employed in agriculture.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 28 -&#13;
to the CIDA study of land tenure, there were 97,400 latifundios in Brazil&#13;
1/&#13;
in 1950 and over 100,000 in 1960.     The census income declarations by all "rich"&#13;
farm households, defined as those earning $670 or more per month, amount&#13;
2/&#13;
to only between 7 and 9% of 1960 agricultural value added.    Those&#13;
figures imply that the usual picture of income concentration drawn from land&#13;
tenure data is grossly exaggerated - or, that rich farmers underreported&#13;
3/&#13;
substantially in 1960.,&#13;
The margin of error in the 1960 income data is thus substantial&#13;
and limits any attempt to evaluate either the degree of inequality in&#13;
1960, or distributional trends over the sixties.&#13;
1/  Defined as farms employing 12 or more workers:   they range in size from&#13;
100 hectares up. CIDA, Land Tenure Conditions and Socio-Economic Develop-&#13;
ment of the Agricultural Sector, Brazil, Pan American Union, 1966,&#13;
pp. 82-90. Using size alone as a criterion, there were 190,000 farms&#13;
of 200 or more hectares in 1960, and 74,000 with 500 or more hectares.&#13;
2/ 1959 agricultural value added = 367 million Cr.$ (Table XVII Contas&#13;
Nacionais). 1960 value added was approximately Cr. 477 million. Total&#13;
income received by the richest 32,000 farm households was Cr.$34 million,&#13;
using Langoni's estimate of mean income in the open-ended income class&#13;
(Cr,$87.6 per month) or Cr. 43 million, using a Pareto fitted mean&#13;
income (Cr.$112 per month).&#13;
3/ The Census figures would also imply extraordinary mobility between 1960&#13;
and 1974/75 since ENDEF reports about 8 times as many rural households&#13;
(250,000 vs. 32,000) in that income categorv in 1974-75.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
5. Other Years&#13;
Most of the comments made about 1960 apply also to the 1970&#13;
1/&#13;
Census income data.  The income question was similar;    the discrepancy&#13;
with the national accounts is of about the same magnitude (44%): under-&#13;
reporting clearly includes omission of most income in kind as well as&#13;
underreporting of money incomes. In this case there is a better basis for&#13;
establishing at least a minimum estimate of underreporting by the rich:&#13;
1970 income tax data show twice as many persons in the census top income&#13;
bracket as are reported in the Census.     It is a minimum for the obvious&#13;
reason that income tax declarations are likely to underreport. Langoni&#13;
has provided minimum estimates of Census underreporting at the top of the&#13;
urban distribution: in 1970 non-agricultural tax-payers reported 84% more&#13;
income than Census income recipients with incomes equal to or higher than that&#13;
3/&#13;
of the poorest taxpayers (Cr.148 per month).    These findings also support&#13;
the argument that top percentile incomes were substantially underreported&#13;
in 1960.&#13;
The 1972 and 1976 surveys differ in their treatment of income,&#13;
between themselves and with respect to the Censuses.     The 1972 survey&#13;
was particularly thorough, as was noted above (p.19), and yields a&#13;
l/ The questionnaire provides for a single entry under "average monthly&#13;
income ; the Instruction Manual for interviewers specifies, as in 1960,&#13;
that fixed income recipients should state last month's income while&#13;
variable income recipients should average las;: year's income; it also&#13;
specifies that receipts from regular remittances, rents or dividends&#13;
should be included, and that loans, prizes, ir.heritances should be excluded.&#13;
2/ The Census (Table 26) reports 328,500 persons in the top bracket (Cr.$2001&#13;
or over per month) vs. 687,000 according to tax data&#13;
reported by Virgilio Horacio Samuel Gibbon, "DistribuiFio- de Renda e&#13;
Mobilidade Social: A Experiencia Brasileira," doctoral dissertation,&#13;
Fundasa-o Getulio Vargas.&#13;
3/ Langoni, Distribuicao da Renda, p. 276.&#13;
4/ The 1968 and 1973 surveys did not report the income of agricultural&#13;
employers or own-account farmers, who together made up 31% of the labor&#13;
force.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 30 -&#13;
coverage almost as high as ENDEF, though unfortunately the full income&#13;
results havenot been published in terms of household incomes. The published&#13;
data on household income covers monetary remuneration only, omitting&#13;
nonmonetary and transfer income which together amount to 25% of total&#13;
1/&#13;
income recorded by the survey, and 43% of national accounts total personal&#13;
income (Table 2).    The 1976 survey does include a household table based&#13;
2/&#13;
on total income as measured by the survey,    but its income data have the&#13;
disadvantage of being somewhat intermediate in coverage between the more&#13;
thorough ENDEF and 1972 PNAD,and the more casual censuses. Imputation&#13;
of missing income would be complicated by the uncertain degree of coverage&#13;
of transfer and nonmonetary incomes. Certainly the margin of error would&#13;
be far too large to infer changes during the seventies, while for comparison&#13;
with 1960, it would involve more uncertainty than a use nf ENDEF.&#13;
Comparisons based on individual recipients rather than households&#13;
face additional pitfalls. Bias may be introduced through both apparent&#13;
and real changes in the patterns of household structure and labor force&#13;
participation. A case of apparent changes arises because the more thorough&#13;
surveys of the 1970s not only improved the coverage of income, they also&#13;
appear to have found more income recipients than the censuses. This shows&#13;
up in a higher female participation ratio, and in a larger number of&#13;
1/ The 1972 household income shares presented by Albert Fishlow in&#13;
"Brazilian Income Distribution: Does Trickle-Down Really Work?" unpublished,&#13;
April 1977, p.6, are monetary remuneration only, based on Table 3.1 of&#13;
PNAD 1972, and thus omit about 43% of national accounts personal income.&#13;
This is also true of the 1972 data on individuals in his Table 1 (p.3).&#13;
Total survey income measured by PNAD 1972 has so far been published only&#13;
by income class of individual recipient, in Table 6.1, p.95 of PNAD-2, but&#13;
one hopes,    a household tabulation will be made available eventually.&#13;
2/ PNAD 1976, Table 3, p. 74. Unfortunately, the table shows only six&#13;
income categories and the open-ended top category includes 24% of all&#13;
families.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 31 -&#13;
pensioners and other inactive income recipients. Between 1970 and 1972&#13;
the female participation ratio (after deducting unpaid family workers)&#13;
1/&#13;
jumps from 16.5 to 22.9%.     The proportion of inactive income re-ipients&#13;
also rises sharply, from 3.4% in 1960, to 6.0% in 1970, 8.9% in 1972 and&#13;
11.4% in 1976. Some of this increase may be the effect of growing pension&#13;
coverage and disability payments; some is surely the effect of more intense&#13;
questioning in the surveys. The increased coverage of female and inactive&#13;
income recipients causes a major change in the structure -f 4.ncome&#13;
recipients: the proportion of males aged 20+ in the total falls from&#13;
64.4% in 1960 to 50.0% in 1976. Since women and the inactive (pensioners,&#13;
persons dependent on remittatices, etc.) are far more concentrated at the&#13;
bottom of the distribution, the effect is an apparent increase in poverty,&#13;
and probably, greater measured inequality. These biases will arise&#13;
particularly in any comparisons involving survey and census incomes.&#13;
Another pitfall results from a real demographic change: the&#13;
reduction in the proportion of unpaid family workers. This bias has&#13;
prejudiced the most widely cited conclusions drawn from the 1960 and 1970&#13;
censuses, in particular, those regarding the share of the poor. If the value&#13;
of income in kind is not imputed to these workers, the&#13;
reduction in their numbers creates an artificial impression of reduced&#13;
poverty, through a fall in the number of persons supposedly receiving&#13;
"zero income." This bias underlies Fields' and Morley-Williamson's (1977)&#13;
1/ There are numerous references in the literature to "rising female&#13;
participation." Comparisons of the 1960 and 1970 censuses, and of&#13;
the 1968 and 1973 surveys do show some rise, though at modest rates.&#13;
Reported female participation rates, especially in agriculture, are&#13;
notoriously sensitive to questionnaire wording and procedure and so&#13;
are subject to large margins of uncertainty.. The jump between 1970&#13;
and 1972 is clearly the product of questionnaire change. The rate is&#13;
constant between 1972 and 1976.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 32 -&#13;
conclusion that the poor fared much better between 1960-1970 than was&#13;
1/&#13;
commonly believed.   Langoni's calculation, which instead excludes unpaid&#13;
family workers from the comparison, creates an opposite error. The change&#13;
in job status of a large number of low productivity women and children -&#13;
from family helpers to paid wage-earners or self-employed - causes a spurious&#13;
growth in the number of persons employed in the lowest income categories&#13;
(they are exciuded in 1960 but included in 1970), and thus biases Langoni's&#13;
calculation towards underestimating income growth at the bottom. This particular&#13;
problem can be avoided by either imputing an income to family workers, or&#13;
2/&#13;
comparing hoUsehold rather than individual incomes.&#13;
6. Censuses and Surveys: Conclusions&#13;
We have argued that income distribution estimates based on&#13;
census and sUrvey income data carry a large margin of uncertainty. The&#13;
main reason is undercoverage.   A variety of evidence has been cited pointing&#13;
to the understatement of incomes in the censuses and surveys. But margin&#13;
for error arises not only from undercoverage; it is caused also by the&#13;
need to impUte mean incomes to the open-ended top class, by uncertainties&#13;
1/  Fishlow demonstrates that "Eliminating zero income workers from the&#13;
distribution fully reverses his [Fields'] resultg. Fields' claim to&#13;
the contrary (p.573, p7) is wrong, the result of arithmetic mis-&#13;
calculation,  When zero income wotkers are eliminated both in 1960 and&#13;
1970, the share of income received by "the poor".... declines from 8.9&#13;
to 8.0%, [between 1960 and 1970]. That translates into an average&#13;
growth of absolute income for those under the poverty line of 19%,&#13;
compared to 32% overall." Albert Fishlow, "The Fallacies of Decompo-&#13;
sition: A Comment dn Fields' Reexamination of Brazilian Income Distribution&#13;
in the 1960s,it unpublished, p.3.&#13;
2/ In fact, this problem is recognized and discussed by Langoni. He shows&#13;
that if one includes zero-income workers, the growth in the Gini&#13;
coefficient is reduced from 14% to 9%. (Langoni, op.cit, p.67).&#13;
He doesn't point out that the share of the poor, as distinct&#13;
from the Gini, is especially sensitive to the treatment of&#13;
unpaid family workers. The only statistics he presents on income shares&#13;
for 1960-1970 (in the much-cited Table 3.5) exclude the zero-income&#13;
labor force.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 33 -&#13;
regarding what is and is not covered in the sources, and by changing&#13;
methods and definitions. The main difficulty arises in trend comparisons;&#13;
ENDEF now provides a much improved cross-section measure of income levels&#13;
and of the extent and composition of poverty.&#13;
The degree of undercoverage severely qualifies the standard assertions&#13;
regarding trends in inequality in Brazil. The two most widely cited contributions&#13;
are those by Fishlow-Meesook (1972) and Langoni (1973). Both conclude,&#13;
from a comparison of uncorrected census data, and with no explicit assump-&#13;
tion regarding changes in the distribution of unreported income, that&#13;
inequality increased. Yet, if the estimates of undercoverage in Table 2&#13;
are approximately correct, the percentile shares and Gini coefficients&#13;
calculated by Fishlow-Meesook and Langoni are measuring dispersion of a&#13;
1/&#13;
subset covering only some 55 to 60% of personal income.    Also, as noted&#13;
above, these comparisons are prejudiced by being based on individual&#13;
recipient rather than household data. All other statements regarding&#13;
distribution during the sixties have been based on the abovementioned studies,&#13;
2/&#13;
or on independent calculations using the same uncorrected census data.&#13;
1/ As mentioned above, Fishlow-Meesook do correct the 1960 distribution&#13;
and use the corrected figures for an analysis of poverty and a decom-&#13;
position analysis of inequality in that year, but their 1960-1970 com-&#13;
parison is based on uncorrected data only.&#13;
2/ A study by Ramonaval Augusto Costa, DistribuicWto da Renda Pessoal   o&#13;
Brasil, 1970 (Rio de Janeiro: FIGBE, 1977) ail6s his own, independently&#13;
calculated Ginis for 1970, but using, again, the uncorrected census&#13;
data. Costa's presentation of the data, by the way, incorrectly&#13;
compares Fishlow-Meesook's adjusted 1960 Gini (0.52) with their unadjusted&#13;
1970 Gini (0.63); the unadjusted 1960 Gini is 0.59. Wells (1974) begins&#13;
his paper with references to Fishlow and Langoni and the statements&#13;
that "there was a considerable increase in the degree of inequality,"&#13;
(p.9) and "Now that it is generally accepted that a deterioration in&#13;
the distribution of personal income, as measured in the Census, has&#13;
occurred ......" (p.9). Bacha and Taylor (1978) in their review of the&#13;
debate on income distribution also take the worsening as adequately&#13;
(Continued on next page)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 34 -&#13;
And, to date, we have seen no attempt to compare the 1972 or 1976 surveys&#13;
with 1960 that recognizes and explicitly deals with the problems of under-&#13;
1/&#13;
coverage and change in methods.&#13;
What this implies has been stated succintly by Fishlow and Meesook:&#13;
. only to the extent that the approximation to a comparable national&#13;
accounts measure is close can the calculated distributions pretend to portray&#13;
the real distributions accurately. A large divergence allows scope for a&#13;
far different profile since the residual need not be distributed identically&#13;
2/&#13;
to that of the income segment included."&#13;
What should be added to this statement is first that census and survey income&#13;
data are weakest at the extremes of the distribution, thus magnifying the&#13;
uncertainty regarding the most important distributional statistic - the&#13;
share of the poor. And second, that the degree of uncertainty matters more&#13;
for estimates of how much income shares have changed rather than simply,&#13;
whether they have gone up or down.&#13;
2/ (Continued from p. 33)&#13;
proven; their discussion of the basic statistical evidence is limited&#13;
to a brief "dismissal"t of the Morley and Williamson (1975) and Fields&#13;
(1977) calculations which, because they include zero-income recipients,&#13;
show faster relative growth of income at the bottom (see below p. 32).&#13;
Independent calculations using uncorrected Census data were also carried&#13;
out by Rodolfo Hoffman and J.C. Duarte in "A Distribui,cao da Renda o&#13;
Brasil," Revista de Administracab de Empresas, 12(2): 46-66 (1972).&#13;
1/ Fishlow's comparison using 1972 household monetary remuneration data&#13;
only was referred to above p. 3Q, fn. 1. A study in progress by Regis Bonell&#13;
and Paulo Vieira da Cunha of INPES/IPEA, comparing 1960, 1970 and 1976&#13;
was cited in Jornal do Brasil, Oct. 22, 1978, p. 38. Their comparison&#13;
also uses unadjusted 1960 and 1970 data and compares these data with&#13;
1976 survey incomes that has partial coverage of income in kind and&#13;
fuller coverage of transfer and secondary incomes, as well as of income&#13;
recipients.&#13;
2/ Fishlow and Meesook, Technical Appendix, p. 55. This statement did not&#13;
inhibit their analysis of 1960 because their comparison with an earlier&#13;
estimate of Personal Income by the official national accounts office,&#13;
showed a iiuch smaller discrepancy than that obtained here (Table 2).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 35 -&#13;
In Table 1 (p. 10) we provide some orders of magnitude on the&#13;
margin of error that may result from undercoverage. The national accounts&#13;
provides a basis for estimating the amount of missing income, though the&#13;
size of the residual is subject to a large margin of error. The allocation&#13;
of that residual is crucial to the calculation of distributional trends, but&#13;
there is no information on which to base an allocation of that missing&#13;
income by income classes. At one extreme, for instance, the Fishlow-Meesook&#13;
procedure assumes that only nonmonetary income was omitted or, what is&#13;
equivalent, that the underreporting of money income is proportional to&#13;
income. Their adjustments, in consequence, raise the share of the poorest&#13;
40 from 9.4 to 11.5% (Table 1, Lines 1 and 2). At another extreme, one could&#13;
follow Navarrett' s procedure for Mexico; she assumed that all underreporting&#13;
of money income was by the rich, and therefore allocated the entire difference&#13;
1/&#13;
between survey and national accounts incomes to the upper income classes.&#13;
2/&#13;
The same procedure was used by Adelman and Morris.      This assumption can be&#13;
defended by noting that only the rich have an income tax incentive to&#13;
underreport, and that entrepreneurial incomes are more likely to be&#13;
underreported than wage incomes.&#13;
If the entire discrepancy in money income is allocated to the&#13;
top decile, the 1960 share of the poor (including nonmonetary income) is&#13;
reduced from the unadjusted census figure of 9.4% to 8.0%, while that of&#13;
the top decile is raised from 41% to 59%. Allocating the discrepancy in&#13;
money incomes to the rich increases measured inequality in any given year,&#13;
but the effect is greater in 1960 than in 1972, 1974/75 or 1976, because&#13;
1/  Ifigenia M. de Navarrette, "La Distribucion del Ingreso en Mexico&#13;
Tendencias y Perspectivas" in El Perfil de Mexico en 1980, (Mexico&#13;
DF: Siglo XXI Editores, 1970), p. 61.&#13;
2/ T. Adelman and C.T. Morris, An Anatomy of Income Distribution Patterns&#13;
in Developing Nations - A Summary of Findings, IBRD Economic Staff&#13;
Ulorking Paper No. 116, 1971.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 36 -&#13;
the size of the discrepancy is greater in 1960. The Fishlow-Meesook&#13;
assumption, which is equivalent to making no adjustment for the under-&#13;
reporting of money income, thus yields the least inequality in all years&#13;
but also the maximum increase in inequality between 1960 and 1974/75:&#13;
the share of the bottom 40 falls by 18% (from 11.5% to 9.4%: Lines 2 and&#13;
P., Tabl  1). Tbe Na.xRarrette-Adel-marn--Mcrris assumption yields the smallest&#13;
increase in inequality: the share of the bottom 40 falls by only 5%&#13;
1/&#13;
(from 8.0% in 1960 to 7.6% in 1974/75).&#13;
The true distributions in 1960 and other years, surely lie&#13;
somewhere between the limits produced by these extreme assumptions.&#13;
Altimir [1977] disaggregated the discrepancy between census/survey data&#13;
and the national accounts and found higher underreporting of urban&#13;
entrepreneurial incomes than of wages. His own adjustmenit procedure&#13;
therefore makes a proportionately greater allocation of the discrepancy&#13;
2/&#13;
to the rich.   Any such specific estimates, however, are highly arbitrary. In&#13;
Table 1 we have chosen instead to indicate the range of possible estimates&#13;
1J Comparison with 1972 and 1976 is more difficult because both years&#13;
include an undetermined amount of nonmonetary income. If PNAD 1972&#13;
monetary remuneration only is used (Line 6, Table 1), and if it is&#13;
assumed that the 1972 ratio of nonmonetary to total income in the&#13;
bottom 40 equals that in 1974/75, then the two extreme assumptions yield&#13;
bottom 40 shares of 9.2% and 6.4% which, if compared with the corresponding&#13;
shares for 1960 (11.5 and 8.0), both imply a reduction of 20%. Using&#13;
the same procedures for 1970 also yields equal though smaller (15%)&#13;
reductions in the share of the bottom 40. However, comparison with&#13;
1972 total survey income, or with 1976, both of which have better coverage&#13;
and smaller discrepancies, yields results similar to the comparison&#13;
with ENDEF, i.e., allocating the discrepancy to the rich results in a&#13;
smaller measured decline in the share of the poor than results from the&#13;
Fishlow-Meesook assumption. The range of variation in the share of the&#13;
bottom 40 produced by all these different comparisons (comparing 1960&#13;
with different years and using each of the extreme assumptions) is +6% to&#13;
-23%.&#13;
2/ Altimir [1977], pp. 82-88.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 37 -&#13;
that are made possible by different assumptions regarding the allocation&#13;
1/&#13;
of unreported monetary income.&#13;
Those ranges make it clear that there is no basis for definite&#13;
statements regarding the amount or even direction of change in distributive&#13;
shares. Most alternative comparisons indicate an increase in inequality,&#13;
particularly between 1960 and 1970. At the same time, most of those&#13;
comparisons indicate that the size of the change in distributive shares&#13;
was relatively small in relation to the growth in total per capita income:&#13;
between 1960 and the mid-seventies the share of the bottom 40 may have&#13;
fallen by about 15 to 20%; during the same period per capita income rose&#13;
about 90%. Despite the large margin of error attached to the estimates&#13;
of shares, and the probability of some increase in inequality, the data&#13;
imply substantial improvement in the real incomes of the poor.&#13;
1/ The margin of error implied in that range is in addition to that resulting&#13;
from Fishlow-Meesook's estimates of nonmonet.ry income and our own assump-&#13;
tion that the ratio of nonmonetary to monetary income as measured by&#13;
ENDEF is applicable to 1970, 1972 and 1976.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 38 -&#13;
IV.  TRENDS IN INEQUALITY: PARTIAL DATA&#13;
Numerous studies have examined trends in inequality within&#13;
one or another component of the Brazilian economy, both as corroboratory&#13;
evidence of trends in the aggregate distribution, and as a way to explain&#13;
overall trends. As evidence of overall trends, there is a temptation&#13;
to infer too much by making casual ceteris paribus assumptions. The&#13;
migration of a small farmer to a city may increase urban dispersion,&#13;
but reduce overall inequality. Partial analyses each make a limited&#13;
contribution towards a better aggregate picture, but one cannot extrapolate&#13;
from trends in any one component without strong assumptions about&#13;
associated changes in the rest of the economy. With this in mind, we&#13;
examine below income differentials by levels of education,&#13;
within the urban modern sector, and across regions and&#13;
sectors.&#13;
1. Education and Income Differentials&#13;
C3rowing income differentials by educational groups are fre-&#13;
quently cited to corroborate the view that inequality has increased, as&#13;
1/&#13;
well as to provide a causal explanation for that increase.     In fact,&#13;
Langoni's argument that growing skill differentials explained most of&#13;
the increase in inequality became the main issue in the debate on income&#13;
1/ Most notably by Langoni in Distribuicao da Renda, 1973.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 39 -&#13;
distribution.    The underlying statistical "fact", viz. that income&#13;
differentials by educational groups had widened sharply during the sixties,&#13;
was not questioned in that debate. Bacha and Taylor [1974] do point out&#13;
that the data are a "real puzzle," since schooling grew rapidly in the&#13;
sixties, and they cite the failure of attempts to specify plausible&#13;
2/&#13;
models that would reproduce the data.     Yet they also cite and implicitly&#13;
accept the Census statistics on educational differentials, as set out by&#13;
3/&#13;
Langoni.&#13;
The puzzle may be largely artificial:   our own estimates for&#13;
1960-1970 suggest that widening during the sixties has been exaggerated;&#13;
also, data for 1972 and 1976 suggest that incomes of the more educated may&#13;
have lagged behind most others since 1970. Furthermore, the most dramatic&#13;
figure cited by Langoni - an increase of 52% in college level incomes&#13;
between 1960-1970 - is an exceedingly arbitrary estimate. Arbitrariness&#13;
is unavoidable because of the large proportion (18.2%) of college level earners&#13;
1/ Wells [1974] provides a clear exposition of what he terms Langoni's&#13;
"neo-classical" or wage differential explanation, and of an alternative&#13;
"wage squeeze" or policy-based explanation, which he prefers. The&#13;
debate on this issue was reviewed recently by Bacha and Taylor [19781,&#13;
who also support the wage squeeze argument.&#13;
2/ Bacha and Taylor, JDS 1978, p. 282, "Widening skill differentials in&#13;
the face of increasing numbers of the skilled during the 1960s make up&#13;
the real puzzle in [Langoni's] Table 4." They cite four modelling&#13;
attempts, by Morley and Williamson [1975], Fishlow [1973], Cardoso&#13;
[1978] and Lysy and Taylor [1978].&#13;
31/ Langoni [1973]: Table 4.2, p.86. In fact, Bacha [1974(a); 1974(b)] along&#13;
with Fishlow [1977] have argued that widening differentials can be&#13;
explained by a link between managerial salaries and profits. They sup-&#13;
port   the argument with data showing growing wage differentials,&#13;
within the manufacturine sector and other laree establishments. These&#13;
data are discussed in the following Section IV.3, pp. 59-67.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 40 -&#13;
that fell into the open-ended income class in 1960; the average income of all&#13;
college graduates in that year is influenced heavily by whatever assumption&#13;
is made regarding the mean income in that class. Langoni's assumption, as&#13;
we argue below,    is    a point toward the low end of the range of possible&#13;
estimates of college level income in 1960 and, as a result, yields a&#13;
particularly high estimate of income growth between 1960 and 1970. Our&#13;
alternative results, including a range of arbitrariness for college level&#13;
earners, are shown in Table 4.&#13;
Our reestimates of college level incomes involve the following&#13;
changes:&#13;
(i) Langoni's figure for 1970 (Cr. 1706) is raised to correct for&#13;
the Cr.9998 problem: the 1970 census register of incomes was truncated&#13;
at Cr.9998 - all incomes above Cr. 9997 (slightly less than 1%) were&#13;
coded as Cr.9998. The Table 4 figure of Cr.1749 uses&#13;
a Pareto fit to the top 5% of the distribution, which yields a mean for the&#13;
top 1% equal to Ct. 14,000.&#13;
(ii) For all income classes except the top, we assume an average income&#13;
equal to the midpoint; this assumption is most important in the modal income&#13;
class (Cr. 20 to 50) since it contains almost half (47%) the distribution.&#13;
(iii) The rantge for 1960 college level income (1309 to 1438) is obtained&#13;
by using two alternative assumptions for the degree of skewness in the&#13;
upper tail, as measured by the ratio of mean income in the open-ended&#13;
class, to the tower limit of the class (Cr. 50 in 1960 prices, or Cr. 1769&#13;
in 1970 pricea). The low estimate (1309) uses a ratio of 1.8 which&#13;
corresponds to Langoni's college distribution for 1970 after correcting&#13;
for the Cit. 9998 problem as explained above. The original and corrected&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 41 -&#13;
Table 4:  EDUCATIONAL AND OCCUPATIONAL INCOME DIm ERENTIALS 1960-1976&#13;
Average Monthly Income                              /&#13;
Educational                   Percent of                  (in 1970 Crs.$)/d               Percentage Change -&#13;
Level La                   Labor Force's.            1960           1970       1972      1960-1970     1960-&#13;
1970    1972 Laborncb         *b      b     /b  7-&#13;
1960    1970    1972      Icl/- Excl -- Incl/- Excl/- Excl/-    Langoni Revised 1972&#13;
1.  No School              7.5     36.0   (25.3)       97,   111    104     112    150         0     7     35&#13;
2.  Primary                49.1    49.0   (56.3)      1i4    211            240    341        14    19     62&#13;
3.  Junior High             3.6     7.7     9.8        '     382            482    592        10    26     55&#13;
4.  Senior High             3.4     4.9     5.6              619            688    881        28     11    43&#13;
5.  College /f              1.3     2.3     3.1             1373           1749   1935        52    27     41&#13;
6.             (Range)                                   (1309-1438)      (1749) (1935)          (22-34)(35-48)&#13;
7.  Total (millions)       23.2    29.5    33.8&#13;
Occupational             Percent of Nonagricultural        Average Monthly Income           Percentage Change&#13;
Category                      Labor Force                     (in 1970 Crs.$)id          1960- 1970- 1960-   1960-&#13;
1960    1970    1972    1976      1960   1970   1972   1976        1970  1976  1972   1976&#13;
8. Administ. &amp; Technical 23.7     26.3     29.3    30.2      546    712    874    1317        30    85    60      141&#13;
9.  (Technical)            (6.6)   (8.3)   (8.2)   (9.5)     619    770    971    1417        24    84    57      129&#13;
10. Other Nonagricult.     76.3     73.7    70.7    69.8      219    250    341     461        14    84    56      111&#13;
Percentage Change&#13;
Income Differentials          in Income Differential&#13;
11. Lines 8 . 10                                             2.49   2.85   2.56    2.86       +14    0     +3    415&#13;
12.        9 . 10                                            2.83   3.08   2.85    3.07       + 9    0     +1    + 8&#13;
G_neral Note:  As noted in Table 2, the Censuses and the 1972 survey each appear to underreport personal&#13;
incoie by between 40 to 45%. Also, the questions and procedures used to measure income differ in the&#13;
Censuses and in each suTvey. The 1972 income data underlying this table exclude transfers and nonmenetary&#13;
Income, whlich increases their comparability with the census data, but also increases undercoverage.    The&#13;
1976 data used here also exclude transfers but include the imputed value of pay in kind in the principal&#13;
occupation. The greatest margins for error are probably in the No School and College categories, given&#13;
the importance of nunnonetary income to rural workers, and of entrepreneurial incomes to the more&#13;
educated.&#13;
Sources:&#13;
1.  Censo 1960.  Tables 20 and 22 for educational levels.   Table 24 for occulpational incomes.  2.  Censo 1970.&#13;
Tables 22 and 25 for educational levels.   Table 26 for occupational incomes.   3.  PNAD-2 1972. Table 2.6&#13;
for educational levels.  Table 2.4 for occupational incomes.   Income is monetary remuneration only.    The&#13;
1972 percent of nonagricultural labor force taken from Table 2.3.9 of PNAD 1972.    4.  PNAD 1976.&#13;
Table 29. 5. Langoni [1973, Table 4.2. p. 86].&#13;
Notes:&#13;
/a Definition of Educational Levels according to grade l,wel achieved:Primary (1-5). Junior High (6-9),&#13;
Senior High (10-12), College (13-17) except in 1972 wheni, aftcr a reform of the educational system,&#13;
College became 12-17. Definition of'Junior and Senior High seems to differ from Langoni's definitioni.&#13;
Nis 1960 percentages show twice as many at Junior High level (5.2%) than at Senior High level (2.7%).&#13;
This may explain the reversal of our iiicome trends for Junior and Senior High.&#13;
/b "Incl." and "Excl." mean inclusion or exclusion of unpaid family workers. Allocation of unpaid by&#13;
educational category was calculated from differen.e between Tables 20 and 22 in Censo 1960, anid&#13;
Tables 22 and 25 in Censo 1970.   Imputed nean income for unpaid eqial to that of lowest income class.&#13;
Adjustment applied only to No School and Primary due to small numbEr of unpaid family workers in higher&#13;
educational categories and greater margin for error in imputing incomc.    1972 data on unpaid family&#13;
workers by education not available.&#13;
/c Revised 1960-1970 comparison includes unpaid family workers, but 1960-1972 excludes them due to data&#13;
unavailability in 1972.&#13;
/d  For 1960 - 1970 we used Langoni's index:   1970 = 3537; 1960 = 100 (thc CDP implicit deflator) to&#13;
maintain comparability. For 1970-76 we deflated by Cuanabara Cost of Living Index, with an upward&#13;
adjustment in 1973,&#13;
/e  Includes unpaid familv workers.  Also includes a small number of illactive income recipients in 1960&#13;
and 1970 (0.6% in 1960, 2.6% in 1970).   Bracketed figures for 1972 No School and Primary are not&#13;
comparable with 1960 and 1970 since, in 1972, the bottom group was defined as Illiterate rather than&#13;
by lack of school attendance.   In 1972, persons with No Schooilng but who were literate were classified&#13;
as Primary.&#13;
/f Range of estimates of 1960 mean College level income explained in text.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 42 -&#13;
ratios are shown in Table 5. The high estimate (1438) uses a ratio of&#13;
2.2, which implies greater skew in 1960, but which, as may be seen in&#13;
Table 5, is entirely within the orders of magnitude of the various&#13;
distributions available for Brazil. Indeed that ratio, at the 18th per-&#13;
centile from the top (corresponding to the size of the open-ended class&#13;
in 1960) equals 2.5 or more in half the distributions.&#13;
(iv) Our point estimate for 1960 college income (1373) is&#13;
the midpoint of the range, and thus corresponds to a ratio of 2.0, thereby&#13;
giving some credit to the lower ratios shown for the 1970 (revised) and&#13;
1972 college level distributions. Langoni's 1960 college income (1123 or&#13;
Cr.80 in 1960 prices) is based on a ratio of only 1.6 (Table 5). On the&#13;
other hand, there is no compelling reason to assume a ratio as low as that&#13;
of the 1970 revised college distribution (1.8): the 1972 college distribution&#13;
has a higher ratio (2.1) than our point estimate; also, considerable change&#13;
in the shape of the college distribution could have occurred over a period&#13;
1/&#13;
of ten years during which the college earner population more than doubled.&#13;
Our estimates in Table 4 also involve a downward adjustment of 1960&#13;
incomes in the lowest educational categories.. The revision consists of&#13;
reintroducing unpaid family workers, with an imputed income equal to the&#13;
wage they could earn in agriculture. Because most unpaid family workers&#13;
are young or female workers in agriculture, their (imputed) earnings puts&#13;
them at the bottom of the income distributions for illiterates and primary&#13;
school leavers. Excluding them, therefore, tends to bias upward the 1960&#13;
1/ The use of a Pareto fit to estimate the 1960 mean income in the open&#13;
ended class had to be ruled out owing to the large percentage of the&#13;
distributions (65%) covered by the upper two income classes. The&#13;
Pareto fit is reliable only for much smaller upper tails.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 43 -&#13;
Table 5: SKEWNESS IN THE UPPER TAIL OF INCOME DISTRIBUTIONS: RATIOS BETWEEN&#13;
MEAN INCOME IN OPEN-ENDED CLASS AND LOWER LIMIT INCOME, FOR ALTERNATIVE PERCENTILES&#13;
Ratio of Mean to Lower Limit Income&#13;
of Top Percentile&#13;
Top Percent&#13;
Individual Income Recipients           2            5         10         18&#13;
1. 1960 Census-                      1.8          2.0        2.0        2.1&#13;
2. 1970 Census                       2.1         2.3         2.5        2.7&#13;
3. 1972 Survey                       2.1         2.3         2.5        2.8&#13;
4. 1976 Survey + Tax&#13;
Declarations                      1.9          2.1        2.5        2.8&#13;
5. 1972 Survey:  College Level       1.9         1.9         2.0        2.1&#13;
6. 1972 Survey:  Technicians         1.8         1.8         1.9        2.2&#13;
7. 1970 (and 1960) College&#13;
Level:  Langoni                   1.2          1.3        1.4        1.6&#13;
8. 1970 College Level: Revised       1.6         1.6         1.7        1.8&#13;
Households&#13;
9. 1960 Fishlow-Meesosk              1.8         1.8         2.0        2.2&#13;
10. 1970 Census                       2.1         2.1         2.3        2.7&#13;
11. 1972 Survey                       2.1         2.3         2.5        2.7&#13;
12. 1974-75 ENDEF                     2.0         2.2         2.3        2.5&#13;
Note:  Ratios were calculated by graphing each distribution and interpolating&#13;
to the above percentiles. The second percentile (top 2 percent) is&#13;
largely determined by the assumption made regarding the open-ended&#13;
class. For Lines 3, 11, and 12, however, published data included&#13;
total earnings so assumptions were not required.&#13;
Line&#13;
1. Langoni Table 23 page 60, Cash income only.&#13;
2. Censo Demografico 1970, Table 25. Cash income only.&#13;
3. PNAD-2 1972, Table 6.1. "Global Income": includes transfers and some&#13;
income in kind (see note to Table 1, Line 6).&#13;
4. PNAD 1976,  Table 14.   Top second and fifth percentiles taken&#13;
from income tax data published by V. Gibbon, Mobilidade Social, p. 31.&#13;
5. PNAD-2 1972. 1972. Table 2.6&#13;
6. PNAD-2 1972. 1972. Table 2.2&#13;
7. Langoni, Table A1.5 page 257.&#13;
8. Line 7 corrected at top of distribution by Pareto fit (see text).&#13;
9. Fishlow-Meesook Technical Appendix, page 54. Adjusted distribution.&#13;
10. Censo Demografico 1970, Table 9, page 225.&#13;
11. PNAD-2 1972 , Table 3.8. Cash income only.&#13;
12. Calculated from regional volumes of ENDEF, Table 7.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 44 -&#13;
mean income in each of those two educational categories and thus, to&#13;
1/&#13;
underestimate income growth between 1960 and 1970.     Stated differently,&#13;
their exclusion leaves out of the trend comparison the income growth that&#13;
is associated with moving out of family enterprises into paid employment.&#13;
The effect of this correction is minor, but it further offsets the initial&#13;
picture of widening differentials.&#13;
The comparison with 1972 presents a major problem because the&#13;
definition of the bottom group changed from "no formal schooling" to&#13;
"illiteracy." The sharp drop between 1970 and 1972 (36.0 to 25.3%) in the&#13;
No School category must mean that about 1 in 4 employed persons with no&#13;
2/&#13;
formal schooling have acquired literacy in some other way.     Those persons&#13;
were classified in Primary. The 1972 No School and Primary groups are&#13;
therefore less educated than the corresponding categories in earlier years:&#13;
the No School category in 1972 contains no literateg, whereas it does in&#13;
1960 and 1970; the 1972 Primary includes persons with no formal schooling&#13;
but who have taken an adult literacy course or acquired literacy on their&#13;
own. As a result, the 1972 mean incomes in the No School and Primary&#13;
categories are both biased downward, and the 1960-72 income growth rates&#13;
for these categories (35 and 62%) may therefore be higher than those shown&#13;
in Table 4.&#13;
1/ More precisely: exclusion occurs in both 1960 and 1970, but the bias&#13;
is greater in 1960 because the proportion of unpaid family workers is&#13;
larger.&#13;
2/ The 1972 PNAD instruction manual defines as illiterate persons who&#13;
cannot read, or write more than their own name. The definition for&#13;
primary level includes persons with at least one complete year of&#13;
school or an adult literacy course or who can write a "simple note."&#13;
In 1970, 11% of all persons 5 or more years old with no school were&#13;
classified as literate. The degree of literacy amongst the unschooled&#13;
can be expected to be higher in the employed population than in the&#13;
total.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 45 -&#13;
The 1972 results suggest a change in trends since 1970, but they&#13;
also add to the suspicion that the extent of widening of differentials&#13;
over the sixties l-s been exaggerated. The higher growth rates over 1960-1972&#13;
reflect better coverage of cash pay in 1972, as well as the rapid growth in&#13;
real incomes that occurred between 1970 and 1972. There is no basis for&#13;
allocating the improved coverage by schooling category, but the 1972 data&#13;
weaken the case for widening differentials. The striking result of the&#13;
1960-72 comparison is a substantial and roughly parallel growth of incomes&#13;
in the primary and secondary school categories relative to college level incomes.&#13;
To the extent that there is any pattern to the trends in differentials it is&#13;
one of slight narrowing. The lag by illiterates, however, is an important exception&#13;
(though the 1972 figure for illiterates is biased downwards, as pointed out above).&#13;
The behavior of occupational differentials supports the views&#13;
that widening has been exaggerated, and that trends improved after 1970.&#13;
Between 1960 and 1976 the mean income of technical and white collar&#13;
workers does rise relative to that of all other nonagricultural occupation,&#13;
but (i) the total increase, 15%, is modest; (ii) the increase is even&#13;
lower - 8% - for the most highly educated occupations, i.e., technical&#13;
workers; and (iii) all of the increase occurs between 1960-1970: there&#13;
is no widening after 1970. Furthermore, the small change in occupational&#13;
differentials actually suggests a falling premium for college education,&#13;
because a growing proportion of college graduates are probably being&#13;
forced into lower level jobs within the overall category of white collar&#13;
and technical occupations. This occupational downgrading is implied by&#13;
the much faster rate of increase in the number of college graduates than&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 46 -&#13;
in the number of white collar and technical jobs (12.6% vs. 7.1% per year&#13;
1/&#13;
since 1960).    There is also casual evidence of flooding in the market&#13;
for many categories of professionals. This trend was noted some time&#13;
ago by Pastore and Perosa [1971] and Pastore and Bianchi [1972]. The number of&#13;
medical doctors, for instance, doubled between 1971 and 1978 and, in&#13;
1978, doctors went on strike demanding a floor wage for hospital interns&#13;
of 5 minimum wages and alleging that the hourly wage of new doctors was&#13;
less than that of construction foremen working on the Rio subway.-&#13;
The relationship between education and inequality is determined&#13;
not only by income differentials, but also by the distribution of education&#13;
across the labor force. Indeed, independently of its role as a productive&#13;
asset, education is a value in itself, and should be studied as a component&#13;
in the distribution of welfare. Table 6, therefore, shows the entire popu-&#13;
lation aged 5 and over according to grade level achieved, while Table 4&#13;
shows the labor force according to schooling level.&#13;
1/ According to Censo DemQgrafico 1970, Table 14, 90% of all university&#13;
graduates, and 82% of all senior high school graduates were absorbed&#13;
by the Administrative and Technical occupational categories. Though&#13;
imperfect as proxies for higher educational classes, these categories&#13;
have a sufficient overlap with college and secondary schooling to&#13;
serve as tests of the widening differential argument. On the other&#13;
hand, these categories contain many persons with lower levels of&#13;
schooling: 45% of Administrators and 24% of Technicians had no more&#13;
than Primary school. Graduates are defined as persons who completed&#13;
college (grades 16-17) and high school (grades 12-15) respectively.&#13;
In Table 4, "college" includes persons who attended one or more years&#13;
of college, i.e., grades 13-17, and Senior High comprises grades&#13;
10-12. Sixty percent of the Table 4 college group had completed grades&#13;
16 or 17.&#13;
2/ Jornal do Brasil, July 16, 1978, p. 24.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 47 -&#13;
It is evident that the distribution of education is highly&#13;
unequal but that there is a trend towards equalization. Tables 4 and 6&#13;
show the impressive expansion of secondary and higher education. The&#13;
proportion of earners without schooling fell from 42.5% in 1960 to about&#13;
1/&#13;
28% in 1976.    The fall was less dramatic in the case of the total&#13;
population, however, and the absolute number of persons without schooling&#13;
actually rose around 10%.&#13;
To translate these figures into a single measure of equity in&#13;
the distribution of education one must first make a subjective judgment regarding&#13;
the consumption value of each level of schooling, and then choose some measure&#13;
of the productive value of schooling at each level. As a first approximation,&#13;
we have applied the simplest weighting system, which is self-weighting_&#13;
each grade is weighted according to its cardinal value (e.g., 0 for&#13;
those who never went to school, 8 for those who reached eighth grade).&#13;
These values are roughly parallel to the income differentials shown in&#13;
Table 4, which should be considered a maximum range since they do not&#13;
allow for consumption value and are not net of private costs of attendance.&#13;
The Gini coefficients so calculated for the total population are 0.69 in&#13;
1960, 0.65 in 1970 and 0.58 in 1976.&#13;
1/ Between 1970 and 1976 the proportion of earners with no schooling is&#13;
extrapolated on the basis of the trend in that ratio for (i) the total&#13;
population, which falls from 43.6 to 34.9% (Table 5); and (ii) heads of&#13;
households, which falls from 40.5% to 31.3% (Censo 1970, Table 5,&#13;
p. 214, and PNAD 1976, Table 7, p. 78.)&#13;
2/ Experiments with different weighting systems changed the level but&#13;
not the trend in the Gini's.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 48 -&#13;
Table 6: POPULATION ACCORDING TO GRADE LEVEL&#13;
(Persons 5 or more years old)&#13;
Cumulative&#13;
Number (Millions)            Percent             Percent&#13;
1960   1970   1976       1960   1970   1976      1960   1976&#13;
No formal schooling    30.1   34.5   32.1       51.0   43.6   34.9     100     100&#13;
Primary: Grades 1-3    16.6   22.1   24.2       28.1   27.9   26.3     49.0    65.0&#13;
4-5    8.6   13.3    19.6      14.6   16.8   21.3      20.9   38.7&#13;
High School             3.3    8.3    13.6       5.6   10.5   14.8       6.3   17.4&#13;
College                 0.4    0.9    2.4        0.7    1.1    2.6      0.7     2.6&#13;
Total                  59.0   79.1   91.9&#13;
Sources:  Censo 1960, Table 15.   Censo 1970, Table 15.   PNAD 1976, Table 11.&#13;
College level ("Superior") is defined in the 1960 and 1970 Censuses&#13;
as grades 13-17 but after the 1971 reform of the educational system,&#13;
College level is defined as grades 12-17.&#13;
Note:     The 1976 figures exclude the rural areas of Region VII (North) or&#13;
about 3.7% of the total population.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 49 -&#13;
In conclusion, the data relating education and income provide very&#13;
weak corroboratory evidence for the contention that inequality has increased&#13;
significantly in Brazil. They do suggest that income growth has lagged&#13;
for a poverty core, assuming that it is made up largely of illiterates. On&#13;
the other hand, this set of data indicates that income growth in the bottom&#13;
40 has not been insignificant: it includes modest improvement within the&#13;
category of illiterates, faster income growth for those amongst the poor who&#13;
have some primary schooling, and additional income growth through the reduc-&#13;
tion in the proportion of illiterates. For those with some schooling, the&#13;
trends in educational differentials are not clear; they are blurred by the&#13;
uncertainty regarding college incomes: also, a definite, though moderate&#13;
deterioration emerges only from the least favorable of our 1960-1970&#13;
assumptions.  The 1972 data instead imply    narrowing differentials between&#13;
1960-1972, except for a lag by illiterates (Table 4). The 1972 survey and 1970-76&#13;
occupational differentials suggest slower income growth for college graduates&#13;
since 1970. Other statistics on wage differentials - largely limited to&#13;
the urban modern sector - are discussed in the next section. But the more&#13;
general evidence from Census and survey data do not support the picture of&#13;
sharply increasing differentials during the sixties that are so often cited&#13;
in the literature, and in fact suggest a reverse trend during 1970-1976.&#13;
2. Urban Modern Sector Wage Differentials: Law of 2/3&#13;
Another set of statistics that are frequently cited to&#13;
corroborate as well as to explain growing inequality, are wage and&#13;
salary data for the modern urban sector. Two types of statistics&#13;
are involved. The first are chiefly the earnings figures for individual&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 50 -&#13;
workers reported by urban establishments under the Law of 2/3 and&#13;
available for the years 1965-1974. Also,the 1959 Economic Censuses&#13;
provide earnings data aggregated by income classes. These statistics&#13;
represent a large category of earners and lend themselves to the calcu-&#13;
lation of aggregate measures of dispersion. The second type of statistics&#13;
are occupational wage differentials derived from small samples of closely&#13;
specified occupations. Besides their use to support statements about&#13;
growing overall inequality, references to these statistics are generally&#13;
also part of an attempt to attribute that deterioration to either&#13;
or both a wage squeeze through wage policy, and the profits-managerial&#13;
salaries link referred to above.&#13;
Arguments based on these statistics suffer from two limitations&#13;
that have been largely overlooked in the literature. The first is limited&#13;
coverage: for most of the period the Law of 2/3 (the most comprehensive&#13;
of these data sets) covered less than 20% of employment, and less than&#13;
16% of personal income in Brazil. The second consists of problems of data&#13;
consistency and quality, particularly the bias introduced by growing&#13;
coverage. These limitations are examined more fully below, after a&#13;
description of the data and the way in which th7ey have been used.&#13;
The most comprehensive of these data sets is a consequence&#13;
of the Law of 2/3. The Law of 2/3 requires firms to employ a work force&#13;
in which two-thirds of the employees are Brazilian nationals. Under&#13;
this law, private sector firms in manufacturing, commerce and service&#13;
activities in urban areas are required to report to the Ministry of Labor&#13;
data on employment and earnings for the month of April of each year.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 51 -&#13;
In practice, coverage of smaller establishments is&#13;
partial. Comparisons of the Law of 2/3 earnings distributions have&#13;
been carried out by Wells [1974], and Morley [1976]; Morley's com-&#13;
parison was cited by Fishlow [1977]. Wells extends and supplements&#13;
the comparison by including the 1959 Economic Census results, and&#13;
1966 to 1970 earnings data from industrial establishment surveys.&#13;
Both Morley and Wells find increasing dispersion over time&#13;
in the earnings data. Wells calculates Gini coefficients for 1959&#13;
and 1965-1971. The Ginis show a general upward trend, with the biggest&#13;
1/&#13;
increase occurring during 1965-1966.     For those two years he also&#13;
presents decile shares showing sharp losses in the bottom decile, and&#13;
2/&#13;
the biggest gains in the top two deciles.     Morley compares only 1969&#13;
and 1973. He presents the frequency distributions for all earners&#13;
according to the Law of 2/3 in those years. Our calculations based on&#13;
those data show that the top decile share rises from 37.0 to 41.5%&#13;
while the bottom 40 share falls from 16.0 to 14.0%.&#13;
1/ To obviate changing sectoral coverage, Wells makes separate but&#13;
overlapping calculation for two and three year periods, but the&#13;
chain is broken, between 1968 and 1969, by a change in the timing&#13;
of the minimum wage adjustment. (The degree of dispersion in&#13;
earnings follows a cycle and is lowest immediately after a minimum&#13;
wage adjustment.) A chain index of Wells' Ginis for combined&#13;
industrial, commerce and service sector earnings is 1959=100,&#13;
1965=101.8, 1966=114.7, 1967=116.2, 1968=119.3. Then,starting&#13;
again,the index is 1969=100, 1970=104.4, 1971=104.9. Excluding the&#13;
unknown change between 1968-1969, the total increase in the Gini&#13;
between 1959 and 1971 is 25.1%, of which about half occurs between&#13;
1965-1966.&#13;
2/ The share of the bottom decile falls 44% in industry, and 30% in&#13;
commerce and services; the top 2 deciles gain 10% in industry and&#13;
5% in commerce and services.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 52 -&#13;
In interpreting these results, Wells is especially concerned&#13;
with the timing of the increased dispersion. He argues that the&#13;
especially strong increase in 1965-1966 conflicts with the human&#13;
capital supply and demand interpretation of growing inequality, and&#13;
instead supports a wage squeeze explanation:   "....... the major increase in&#13;
inequality can be ascribed to the period of most severe wage stabili-&#13;
1/&#13;
zation, 1965-6."    Morley notes that the "substantial increase in earnings&#13;
inequality" was accompanied by considerable job creating at middle&#13;
and high skill levels but that "there was virtually no real salary&#13;
increases for those who remained at the bottom." Both Wells and Morley&#13;
analyse these partial data sets side by side with comments about aggregate&#13;
inequality, without any explicit statistical consideration of the degree&#13;
of coverage of their data, and without discussing the necessary assump-&#13;
tions about associated changes in the rest of the economy that would&#13;
allow one to infer that an increase in dispersion within the urban modern&#13;
sector implies increased overall inequality. Neither author provides&#13;
data on the number of employees or on the amount of income covered.&#13;
The coverage of the 2/3 Law data is summarized in Table 7. In&#13;
1965, the initial year of Wells' analysis, it amounted to only 12.5% of&#13;
the labor force and 10% of personal income in Brazil. In 1969, the initial&#13;
year of Morley's comparison, the figures were 18.i and 15.2% respectively.&#13;
Even in relation to the 1969 nonagricultural sector, the 2/3 Law covered&#13;
1/ Wells (1974), p. 16.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 53 -&#13;
Table 7: COVERAGE OF LAW OF 2/3 AND 1959 ECONOMIC CENSUS&#13;
(1)         (2)            (3)         (4)            (5)         (6)          (7)&#13;
Reported Employment         Reported Earnings            Annual Earnings per Worker&#13;
(Millions)          Billions    Percent of            ('000 and Cruzeiros)&#13;
Percent        Current    Total Personal               Total         Ratio&#13;
Number     of Total       Cruzeiros    Income         Reported   Personal      (5) -(6)&#13;
Labor Force                                              Income&#13;
1959             2.41 (2.13) 10.8 (9.6)    0.21         11.6          0.087        0.082       1.07&#13;
1965             3.24        12.5           3.56        10.0           1.13        1.37        0.82&#13;
1966             3.46        13.0&#13;
1967             3.85        14.1&#13;
1968            4.51         16.1          13.6         14.1          3.02         3.45        0.88&#13;
1969            5.30         18.5          19.5         15.2          3.68&#13;
1970            5.73         19.4          26.4                       4.61&#13;
1971            6.03         19.8          33.4                       5.54&#13;
1972            6.88         22.1&#13;
1973             7.62        23.7          65.7         16.7          8.62         12.3        0.70&#13;
1974            8.80         26.7&#13;
Notes:&#13;
Sources: Reported data from 1959 lndustrial Census and 1959 Commerce and Services Census;&#13;
Atualidad e Estadfstica Brasil 1969; Anuario Estadfstico do Brasil 1972; Morley [1974].&#13;
Cols. (1) &amp; (2): Figures in brackets are coverage of data actually used by Wells, after&#13;
deductions of subsectors for comparability. Reported employment corresponds to employees whose&#13;
earnings were reported   in Table 5s Censo Industrial and Table 7.   Excludes proprietors and family&#13;
workers.&#13;
Col. (2):  Total Labor Force according to 1960 and 1970 Censuses and interpolation.     Use of PNAD labor&#13;
force definitions which result in higher participation rates, would yield even lower coverage, e.g.,&#13;
19.6Z for 1972 vs. 22.1Z.&#13;
Qol. (3):  1959 Censuses:   Total wages and salaries paid in 1959.   Other years:   April earnings X 12.&#13;
Col. (4): Total Personal Income defined as in Table 2 (Note 6).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- SI. -&#13;
only 1 in 3 employees and 19% of personal income. Because the number of&#13;
earners reported grew rapidly over the whole period, coverage grew, but&#13;
reached only 16.7% of personal income in the final year of Morle,'s comparison.&#13;
Any change in distribution within the 2/3 Law data is therefore a small part&#13;
of the income distribution story.&#13;
Aside from its limited coverage, the 2/3 data is liable to&#13;
significant biases. The most important is the result of growing coverage:&#13;
Between 1965 and 1973 the number of workers reported grew by 11.3% per year&#13;
and,   as  a proportion of the total labor force, coverage almost doubles.&#13;
It seems likely that most of the growth came from the incorporation of&#13;
smaller firms and workshops where wages are typically lower. Wells was&#13;
aware of this potential source of bias: "improved coverage should lead&#13;
to an increase in recorded dispersion," but he goes on to dismiss it:   ".....&#13;
1/&#13;
there is no strong indication that coverage has improved."     This dismissal&#13;
is surprising given the rapid growth shown in Table 7. Coverage grew 58%&#13;
over the period (1965-71) compared by Wells, and 29% over the shorter&#13;
period (1969-73) studied by Morley. The most likely result was a large&#13;
2/&#13;
relative increase of the population at the bottom of the distribution.&#13;
1/ Wells [1974], p. 12. He does not cite the numbers that led to this&#13;
judgment,&#13;
2/ The expectation that coverage is better amongst larger, higher-wage&#13;
firms is supported by Langoni who finds that the Law of 2/3 significantly&#13;
underrepresents employees who are illiterate, women, under 20 years old,&#13;
and resident in the North and Northeast regions. Distribuia-o da Renda,&#13;
pp. 272-274.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 55 -&#13;
Much of the increased dispersion, as measured by Wells and Morley, may&#13;
be explained by this change in the size and composition of the group&#13;
being studied. More obviously compromised is Morley's conclusion with&#13;
regard to the 1969-1973 comparison that "Wages at the very bottom actually&#13;
fell, those near the bottom rose .at a slow rate, and the number of people&#13;
1/&#13;
earning those wages rose as well."    All these trends are likely con-&#13;
sequences of growing coverage of lower-wage employees.&#13;
Wells points out a second possible bias but dismisses it, again&#13;
erroneously, in our opinion,        it is more than likely that employers&#13;
will overstate wages paid at' the lower end of the scale, so as not to&#13;
2_/&#13;
be seen to be breaking the minimum wage legislation."   But, he sees "no&#13;
reason why, over time, the degree of bias imparted to the results should&#13;
3/&#13;
be different."    A reason does exist, however, in the reduction of&#13;
the real minimum wage during the sixties.    Finally, the difficulty of inter-&#13;
preting the data is increased     by the fact that the incomes reported&#13;
are actual earnings during April, rather than monthly pay rates. Earnings&#13;
differ from monthly rates for-many obvious reasons: overtime, piece&#13;
rates, sickness, part-time work and high turnover, especially in the lower&#13;
occupational categories. It is no surprise therefore that, despite&#13;
inhibitions about reporting wage rates below the minimum wage, about 1 in&#13;
3 workers in  these  data have monthly earnings below the minimum wage.&#13;
1/ Morley [19761, p. 33.&#13;
21 Wells [19741, p. 12.&#13;
3/ Wells [19742, p. 12.&#13;
4/ An index of the real legal minimum wage (deflated bv FGV Guanabara cost of&#13;
living index) is 1959=100, 1965=79.4, 1966=73.4, 1969=68.5, 1971=67.2.&#13;
The real minimum fell by 10% between 3/65 and 3/66, the period that&#13;
registers the largest increase in inequality.&#13;
5/ Wells [1973], p. 12.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 56 -&#13;
The number involved is too large for a ceteris paribus assumption applied&#13;
to trends. The increase in coverage, for instance, could have led to&#13;
major changes in the composition of the sample, with different behavior&#13;
with respect to frequency of part-time work, piece-rates, turnover, etc.&#13;
In sum, though it is difficult to quantify the incidence of these various&#13;
potential biases, there are at least two sources of bias acting in the&#13;
direction of increasing measured inequality. The growth in coverage, in&#13;
particular,   is   large enough to cause    the observed increase in dispersion.&#13;
Limited coverage reduces the force of the argument, advanced by&#13;
several authors, that much of the growth in income concentration can be&#13;
1/&#13;
attributed to rising managerial salaries.      By its very nature, this&#13;
argument is about an extremely small group of persons - our ceiling&#13;
2/&#13;
estimate is 1% of the labor force.     A larger number would conflict&#13;
with the character of the argument, which turns on the link between&#13;
senior management salaries and profits, and on the power of senior govern-&#13;
3/&#13;
ment officials to set their own salaries.      Assuming that all private&#13;
1/ Bacha [1974(a)]; 1974(b)], Fishlow [1973], Wells [1974].&#13;
2/ Or about 300,000 persons in 1970, of which about one-third are in&#13;
government and therefore not covered by Law of 2/3 data. This is&#13;
an order of magnitude estimate based on following: (1) ENDEF reports&#13;
250,000 heads of families who are employees in "Cargos de Nivel&#13;
Superior" defined as employees with high-level responsibility requiring&#13;
university education or equivalent. Adjust upwards to 300,000 to allow&#13;
for non-heads of families and for North Region. (2) 1970 Census:&#13;
323,000 persons in Administrative, Technical and Defense occupa-&#13;
tions   (excluding proprietors) earning 8 or more minimum wages.    This&#13;
is a generous definition because senior managers normally earn more.&#13;
(3) Law of 2/3 data: in 1969 2.6% of earners, or 138,000 persons&#13;
earned 9.2 or more minimum wages. Criteria (1) to (3) are clearly&#13;
overestimating the concept of "senior managers" as implied by its&#13;
proponents, i.e., the true proportion is therefore well under the 1%&#13;
figure used here. A fourth criterion yields a much lower figure&#13;
(4) 1970 Industrial Census: 11,000 establishments with 20-49&#13;
workers, plus 10,000 with 50 or more workers. Assuming 1 senior&#13;
manager per establishment in 20-49 class and 3 per establishment in&#13;
50+ class yields only 41,000 senior managers in Manufacturing.&#13;
2/ Wells [1974], p. 16. "It would be more realistic to see these higher&#13;
paid employees, especially when they are executives, as paying them-&#13;
selves relatively higher salaries in spite of, and possibly as a&#13;
consequence of, strict control of the wages of manual workers."&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 57 -&#13;
sector managers are covered by the Law of 2/3 data, and that they are&#13;
at the top of the distribution, we can calculate that their share of&#13;
total personal income in Brazil rose from about 4.0% in 1969 to 4.7%&#13;
1/&#13;
in 1973.    The amount involved is minor, both as an absolute share and&#13;
as an increase. Managerial salaries may have risen much more than is&#13;
reflected in these data,through unreported payments in kind and bonuses,&#13;
and there is anecdotal evidence to that effect. But this cannot be&#13;
documented with the Law of 2/3 data. Those statistics do not support the&#13;
contention that the relative enrichment of the managerial class explains&#13;
much of the worsening income distribution. In fact, they weaken the&#13;
argument by establishing that only a relatively small proportion of total&#13;
income is involved. This negative conclusion applies as much to the&#13;
argument that relative enrichment was caused by the pulling up of high&#13;
salaries as to the argument that it resulted from compression of wages&#13;
at the bottom: either mechanism is summed up in the small percentages&#13;
noted above. If the wage squeeze did indeed cause a major redistribution&#13;
of total personal income, it is not demonstrated by the earnings data&#13;
reviewed here. These data imply that redistribution was minor,&#13;
1/ Assume 350,000 senior managers, in 1973. This equals 4.6% of all&#13;
reported earners. Their share is given by Morley [1974], Table 11,&#13;
as 28.0% of total earnings. Using our Table 6, Col. (4), this equals&#13;
(0.28 X 0.167) 4.7% of Personal Income. Assume a growth rate of&#13;
5.0% per year over 1969-1973: (slower than growth of all reported&#13;
earners due to growing coverage.)       Number of senior managers in&#13;
1969 therefore = 288,000 or 5.4% of 1969 reported earners. Their&#13;
of Personal Income is given by same tables. If this method is applied&#13;
to the Law of 2/3 data for 1965 calculate the share of senior managers&#13;
in that year the result implies a large fall in their share between&#13;
1965 and 1969.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 58 -&#13;
or that, if significant concentration did occur, it took the form chiefly&#13;
of a transfer from labor as a whole to profits, rather than of redistribu-&#13;
tion within labor.-/&#13;
1/ We have not reviewed the possibility of a major shift in the functional&#13;
distribution. Such a review would require a detailed examination of&#13;
the national accounts income estimates. Wells downplays this pos-&#13;
sibility [Wells 1974, pp. 10-11]. An analysis within the manufac-&#13;
turing sector was carried out by [Macedo 1977]. The national accounts&#13;
show relatively little change in the share o:- labor incomes in total&#13;
urban income; it falls from 55.4% in 1959 to 52.5% in 1975. (Contas&#13;
Nacionais, Revisao e Atualizacao 1977, Table IX).   Macedo finds a fall&#13;
in the manufacturing labor share between 1960 and 1970, from 26.1 to&#13;
23.1%, but argues that the measured fall may disappear if growing&#13;
social security payments are taken into account. Manufacturing in any&#13;
case accounted for only 31% of urban income in 1970. The national&#13;
accounts functional income data, however, are subject to large error,&#13;
and in fact, were dropped from the last publication of Contas Nacionais&#13;
in 1978, pending the results of a re-examination.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 59 -&#13;
3. Urban Modern Sector Differentials: Wage Surveys&#13;
The argument for growing inequality is also frequently&#13;
supported by references to a number of wage surveys. The most commonly&#13;
cited have been those published by Suplicy [1974; 1978] and Bacha [1974].&#13;
Both cite several wage surveys carried out by business associations&#13;
1/&#13;
and consulting firms.     These surveys appear to be limited to a rela-&#13;
tively modern, large-firm subset of the manufacturing industry. Two&#13;
additional studies, based on larger samples, have been published recently.&#13;
One, by DIESSE [1979], is based on wage data obtained from Sao Paulo&#13;
2/&#13;
unions.   The second, by Barbosa [1978] uses Law of 2/3 data.   Most of&#13;
these data, summarized in Table 8 show growing differentials, and&#13;
some of the figures have been used as dramatic illustrations of rising&#13;
3/&#13;
inequality. Thus Suplicy notes that "In 1969, the mean wage of the&#13;
general manager of a medium or large firm in Sao Paulo and Rio de Janeiro&#13;
was 65 times greater than that of a helper (servente) in civil construc-&#13;
tion in Sao Paulo; in 1973 it was 81 times greater and in 1975, 90 times&#13;
1/  The sources cited are (i) GRUPISA: a Rio based consortium of firms;&#13;
biannual surveys of about 180 job categories in some 50 large firms.&#13;
(ii) CSN: Personnel Department of National Steel Company, data for&#13;
15 large firms. (iii) GE: Payroll Department of General Electric,&#13;
survey managerial salaries in about 65 large competitors in Rio and&#13;
Sao Paulo. (iv) Morris and Morgan: Sao Paulo consulting firm, survey&#13;
of managerial salaries. (v) PRIL: Industrial relations firm: survey&#13;
of about 100 manual and administrative job categories in Sao Paulo.&#13;
2/  DIESSE (Inter-Union Department for Statistics and Socio-Economic Studies),&#13;
Distribuicao Salarial em Sao Paulo Segundo Guias da Contribui,cao Salarial&#13;
(Sao Paulo: December 1977). Data drawn from union fees, data for a&#13;
sample of Sao Paulo unions. Union contribution is obligatory, but&#13;
reporting is incomplete. Data for 1956, 1961, 1966, 1971 and 1976,&#13;
with skill breakdowns.&#13;
3/ Morley [1976], p.28, reproduces the PRIL and Morris and Morgan&#13;
statistics published by Suplicy referring to them as "startling data"&#13;
which "deserve far wider circulation."&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 60 -&#13;
Table 8: TRENDS IN MODERN SECTOR WACE DIFFERENTIALS: SELECTED DATA&#13;
Income&#13;
Range&#13;
(in .'971/72                                  Index of Real Wage&#13;
MinJl:Lm      1961     1966     1969     1970     1971     1972     1973     1974      1975     1976&#13;
_______    Wages)&#13;
CSN Sutrvey&#13;
Unskilled                        1-2                 100                                  92&#13;
Skilled                         2-7                  100                                 120&#13;
Marnagern                       14-32                100                                 153&#13;
San Paulo Industar  (PRIL and&#13;
Morris and Morgan)&#13;
Low                              1-4                          100      106      110      107       107      110      116      137&#13;
Middle                           4-9                          100      109      114      120       123      132      135      151&#13;
Middle                           9-19                         100      105      117      128      129       133      142      151&#13;
High                           19-66                          100      118      127      136      142       150      163      178&#13;
Very High                       66+                           100      123      128      137       148      148      182      190&#13;
Rio: Large Fir.vo (CRUPISA)&#13;
Skilled                         2-6                  100                                 115&#13;
Rio and Sao Paulo (GE)&#13;
Managers                        13-48                100                                 117&#13;
Sno Paulo Induitrly (DIESSE)&#13;
Unskilled                        1-2         100      70                         59                                            58&#13;
Serni-skilled                   1-3          100      74                         86                                            76&#13;
Skilled                          2-5         100      87                         94                                           108&#13;
Forerunf-                        3-1l        100      73                        104                                           102&#13;
Manager:c.                       5-i-        100      85                        11i                                           122&#13;
Sano l1'euo l..&gt;w ol 213 (Barbosa)&#13;
Unskilled                       -1.4                                            100                         107&#13;
SBon  ri,.J-'Ied              1.5-2.6                                           100                         100&#13;
Skilled and Whitc Collar      3.5-9.0                                           100                          89&#13;
Frofessionnls aind Managers     11-26                                           100                          93&#13;
Souirces&#13;
CSN: Bacha [1976]. Indices are weighted averages for different occupations calculated frori Table 1.&#13;
Pril and Morris ;i-d Morgan: Suplicy [1977], p.l46. Index is unweighted average..&#13;
GRUPISA and GE: Bacha [1976]. Indices are unweighted averages.&#13;
DlESSE:   1)iWriLuicaoSalarial em Sao Paulo segunedo (hnias da Contribuiecao Salarial;" Sao Paulo: Dec. 1977. Deflated by&#13;
DIESSE price index.&#13;
Barbora, Flilton, "Diferenciais de Snlarios entre 07.upacoes: Uma Analise das Variacoes Ocorridas no Periodo 1971-1974,"&#13;
tltiiversidade de Sao Paul.o, Tese de Mestre enr Econo-nia, Sao Paulo, 1978.&#13;
Note&#13;
/a  Defined to cover 70% or more.   The sources cited above use different deflators. DIESSE's deflator grows especial]y&#13;
fast; hence the much lower grouth in real wages. See below Table 15.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 61 -&#13;
greater.      Including the additional benefits received by a general&#13;
1/&#13;
manager, the differential in 1975 rose to close to 150 times." tHow&#13;
meaningful are such comparisons for the question of aggregate inequality?&#13;
A first observation about comparisons between servente and&#13;
managerial wages is that very few household heads in the modern sector&#13;
are serventes or unskilled workers. Of all blue-collar household heads&#13;
employed in manufacturing and construction in Belo Horizonte, only 14%&#13;
were classified as unskilled, in a 1972 survey; 86% were skilled&#13;
workers or foremen.     A nutrition survey in Sao Paulo classified 20%&#13;
of all (including informal sector) blue-collar fathers as unskilled,&#13;
and only 11% of the entire city sample of fathers were unskilled.&#13;
PNAD 1976 data for male employees in Sao Paulo manufacturing and con-&#13;
struction provide indirect support for this argument: 40% earned 2&#13;
21/&#13;
minimum wages or less but 35% were aged under 25.     These groups almost&#13;
3/&#13;
certainly overlap strongly.     Since only 7% of male household heads&#13;
were aged under 25, the large majority of employees who were heads must&#13;
have been earning over 2 minimum wages, implying skilled occupational&#13;
status. Further support comes from ENDEF: in 1974/75, the average household&#13;
income for manual employees in the State of Sao Paulo equalled 5.7 minimum&#13;
wages, implying that the heads of those households were earning between 4&#13;
4/&#13;
and 5 minimum wages.- Heads employed in the modern sector probably earned&#13;
5/&#13;
more.-   By contrast, wages for unskilled workers are generally between&#13;
1 and 2 minimum wages (Table 8). Part of this difference must result&#13;
1/ Suplicy [1977], p. 143. A similar observation is made by Paulo Renato&#13;
Souza in, La Segmentacion? del Mercado de Trabajo Urbano y las Disparidades&#13;
de Salarios en Economias Subdesarrolladas, (Santiago: PREALC, 1977), p.27.&#13;
2/ PNAD, 1976. Regiao II. Tables 21 and 30.&#13;
3/ As suggested by the age-earnings profile shown in PNAD 1976 (Table 28).&#13;
4/  ENDEF, Regiao II, Sao Paulo, Table 6.&#13;
5/ In 1974, the average wage of production workers in manufacturing firms&#13;
with 50 or more workers was 50% higher than that in firms with 5 to 19&#13;
workers, according to PescuisajludAustlDlil 147-4, FIBGE.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 62 -&#13;
from earnings from second jobs, and part from supplementary pay, in&#13;
cash and kind, not included in surveys such as those reported in Table 8.&#13;
But the large gap between unskilled wage rates and average earnings&#13;
according to ENDEF corroborates the survey findings cited above, that&#13;
few modern sector household heads are unskilled. The significant wage&#13;
from the point of view of poor households, therefore, is that for skilled&#13;
manual workers; the unskilled wage rate is of secondary relevance, since&#13;
it applies almost entirely to second earners, mostly young entrants into&#13;
1/&#13;
the labor market.&#13;
The relevance of the wage trend for managers must also be&#13;
questioned, not only because so small a fraction of the population is&#13;
involved, but because some of the increase in managerial wages is probably&#13;
attributable to a change in the nature of those positions. Managerial&#13;
positions are defined by the amount of responsibility they entail and,&#13;
in the case of senior executives, that amount is proportional to the size&#13;
of the firm. It is not clear whether the surveys reported in Table 8&#13;
have adjusted for the growth in firm size and degree of responsibility&#13;
associated with top executive positions. This bias probably does not&#13;
affect middle and lower level managerial positions whose degree of res-&#13;
ponsibility tends to be held constant as firms expand, with a growth&#13;
instead in the number of such positions. In the case of Table 8 data,&#13;
this possible bias is most likely to apply to the "very high" salaries&#13;
reported by Suplicy from a Morris and Morgan survey, covering positions&#13;
2/&#13;
with annual salaries over US$60,000.&#13;
1/ The average household in Sao Paulo has 1.6 earners (poorer households&#13;
usually have fewer earners). If the principal earner is a skilled&#13;
worker earning 3.5 minimum wages, the contribution of secondary workers&#13;
earning 1 minimum wage will on average amount to about 15% of family&#13;
income.&#13;
2/ In 1978 dollars, or, Cr.35,000 per month in 1975.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 63 -&#13;
A more meaningful wage differential therefore is that between&#13;
skilled workers and managers excluding the most senior. The data in&#13;
Table 8 are inadequate for a reliable test of this differential:&#13;
sampling procedures in all cases are unclear and may not be. appropriate&#13;
for trend analysis in the case of the public relations firm surveys,&#13;
periods covered differ, and only Barbosa's data appear to extend&#13;
beyond the largest and/or most modern sub-set of manufacturing firms.&#13;
The coverage  involved is thus       smaller and more "elite" than the&#13;
Law of 2/3 data reviewed above, and may therefore not represent trends&#13;
even within the whole of the urban modern sector.&#13;
Examining Table 8 with these qualifications in mind, the&#13;
differential between managerial and skilled manual wages rises as&#13;
follows:  CSN survey      (1966-72) 27.5%, PRIL survey (1969-76) 17.9%,&#13;
GRUPISA and GE surveys (1966-72) 1.7%, DIESSE (1961-76) 13.0%, Barbosa&#13;
(1971-74) 4.8%. The more systematic DIESSE study also covers the&#13;
longest period, and shows all the increase occurring between 1966-1971.&#13;
PRIL, Barbosa and DIESSE all show slower rates of widening during the&#13;
seventies. The DIESSE results are confused by the fact that foremen's wages&#13;
grow less than those of skilled manuals, while the semi-skilled category,&#13;
which overlaps somewhat with the skilled category in other surveys, lags&#13;
considerably. The Barbosa results, though they span only 4 years, add to&#13;
the confusion, by showing unskilled wages growing faster than managers',&#13;
and furthermore, a falling real wage for managers during the fast growth&#13;
1/&#13;
years 1971-1974.    Both results directly contradict the PRIL and Morris&#13;
1/ When deflated by the adjusted Rio cost of living index. Even DIESSE&#13;
whose deflator grows more rapidly, shows a rising real managerial wage&#13;
between 1971-1976.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 64 -&#13;
and Morgan datt cited by Suplicy. The overall impression, however, is&#13;
of support for the view that the wage gap increased, though the degree&#13;
of widening appears to be less dramatic than implied by most authors.&#13;
The question of how much is unsettled owing to the poQr quality of the&#13;
statistical evidence involved.&#13;
The evidence of widening within large scale manufacturing is&#13;
plausible, and there is a considerable literature offering competing&#13;
explanations. These arguments have been reviewed in a survey article&#13;
by Bacha and Taylor [1978]. One aspect of the trend in factory unskilled&#13;
wages that needs to be stressed here, because it bears on the question&#13;
of overall inequality in the economy, is the relationship between the&#13;
unskilled wage in large scale manufacturing and in the rest of the urban&#13;
economy. The stagnation or, possible fall in the factory unskilled&#13;
wage rate during the sixties is very likely a direct result of the falling&#13;
minimum wage. But a necessary condition for this policy impact was a&#13;
factory wage in 1961 that was relatively high in relation to the market&#13;
wage for unskilled labor. In 1959, 56% of all employees (white and blue&#13;
collar) reported by the Censuses of manufacturing, commerce and services&#13;
were earning one minimum wage or less.     Since white collar, foremen,&#13;
and skilled and semi-skilled manual workers comprise at least three quarters&#13;
of total reported employment, the unskilled (largely serventes and ajudantes)&#13;
must have been earning well under one minimum wage. Moreover, urban&#13;
employees not reported by the economic censuses (almost half of total&#13;
urban wage employment) probably earned less. By contrast, the 1966 servente&#13;
wage in those firms surveyed by CSN (Table 8) equalled 1.4 minimum wages,&#13;
while that in the other unskilled category, ajudantes, equalled 1.8 minimum&#13;
1/&#13;
wages.    The average unskilled wage in establishments surveyed by DIESSE.&#13;
1/ Bacha [1976], Table 1, p. 120. Calculated from Bacha's table by&#13;
applying his 1966-1972 (negative) growth rates to 1972 mean wages.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 65 -&#13;
equalled 1.2 minimum wages in both 1961 and 1966.- Both CSN and DIESSE&#13;
are therefore representative of a subclass of unskilled workers that&#13;
were relatively privileged in the early sixties: their wages were pro-&#13;
bably about twice the average urban unskilled wage rate. This is not&#13;
surprising since the large-scale, unionized firms surveyed by DIESSE&#13;
and CSN were the firms least likely to evade the minimum wage legislation in the&#13;
early sixties.&#13;
The narrowing differential between the legal minimum&#13;
and the going market wage for unskilled labor made it possible for large&#13;
firms to hold or lower their entry wage during the sixties, but there is&#13;
no evidence that this occurred for the majority of unskilled workers who are&#13;
employed outside the protected sector. Also, this process appears to have&#13;
reached its limit toward the end of the decade through the combined effect&#13;
of accelerated growth, and a narrower modern sector wage premium. During&#13;
the seventies, the minimum wage fell below the market wage in most urban&#13;
unskilled employment. By 1976, 93% of all nonfarm employees in the state&#13;
3/&#13;
of Sao Paulo reported earnings greater than the legal minimum.&#13;
Thus, the policy impact of minimum wage policy on unskilled wages in the&#13;
urban modern sector during the sixties cannot be extrapolated to wages&#13;
outside this relatively small (though highly visible) category of employ-&#13;
ment, nor to situations in which minimum wages can be overruled by the&#13;
market, as they were after 1970.&#13;
1/ DIESSE [1979].&#13;
2/ An alternative hypothesis is that these firms claimed to be paying the&#13;
minimum when in fact they were paying less. If true, this would imply&#13;
that part of the reported widening is artificial.&#13;
3/ PNAD 1976, Table 27. Figure excludes domestic servants whose pay&#13;
in kind is not included in the earnings data, and a small number (2%)&#13;
of part time workers earning the minimum or less.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 66 -&#13;
Suplicy's illustrative data on the range of incomes within the&#13;
modern sector also bears comment. Any statement about range is very&#13;
arbitrary unless it is interpreted in the most absolute sense: the&#13;
range" is highly sensitive to the extent of aggregation, i.e., 'rhether&#13;
one takes the top 0.1, 1.0 or 10%.    The closer to the&#13;
absolute end-points, the less interesting is the comparison, and also&#13;
the less reliable as a measure of shape of the rest of the distribution.&#13;
A somewhat more meaningful measure of range can be obtained from ENDEF&#13;
data on occupational incomes. ENDEF distinguishes a category of "high&#13;
level" employees which, in the State of Sao Paulo, comprise the top 4%&#13;
of the occupatidnal hierarchy. The range between their family income&#13;
and the average for all non-agricultural manual workers in the State is&#13;
1/&#13;
6.1 times (Cr.$150,479 vs. 24,606). If the comparison is made, not with&#13;
all manual workers, which are a large category (65% of families), but&#13;
with the poorest decile of all urban families in the State, the range is&#13;
21 times (Cr.150,479 vs. Cr.7,000). Even these are significant dif-&#13;
ferentials, though of a very different order of magnitude from Suplicy's&#13;
2/&#13;
illustrations.&#13;
Despite the attention that It has received, the evidence of wage&#13;
stretching reviewed in this section is limited to large scale manufacturing,&#13;
and is therefore of minor relevance from the point of view of aggregate&#13;
inequality in Brazil. In 1970, factories with 50 or more employees employed&#13;
only 1.7 million workers, or about 5% of the 31.5 million income recipients&#13;
in that year. The factory wage bill amounted to Cr. 9.9 billion or about&#13;
1/ Corrected for overestimation of savings and therefore income as&#13;
explained in text p. 14.&#13;
2/ ENDEF. Region II, Table 6.   The mean income for the poorest urban&#13;
decile is obtained by interpolation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 67 -&#13;
6% of personal income in Brazil. Furthermore, the forces acting&#13;
on wage structure in that sector, particularly wage policy and the effects&#13;
of large and growing organizations, cannot be generalized to the rest&#13;
of the economy. There is a need, therefore, for a much broader examination&#13;
of trends in differentials and their underlying mechanisms.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 68 -&#13;
4.    Regional .tnd Sectoral Income Differentials&#13;
A major support for the notion of growing inequality in Brazil&#13;
has been the -isible poverty and backwardness of the Northeast, and of&#13;
rural areas in general. This support has persisted as a popular notion,&#13;
despite e4idence fbom both the national accounts and the 1960 and 1970&#13;
censuses that regional ner capita income differentials were converging&#13;
1/&#13;
during the fiftie  and -ere relatively constant during the sixties.&#13;
Langoni finds al-i.tn r  change in the relative per capita income of the&#13;
Northeast between 1960 and 1970:   Northeast per capita income grew 34%&#13;
2/&#13;
vs. 37% for Brazil as a whole.     Similarly, the national accounts report&#13;
an almost constant differential between relative income per capita in the&#13;
Northeast and in all Brazil between 1960 and 1970: the differential&#13;
3/&#13;
grows 2% from 2.13 to 2.17.     Graham and Merrick calculate an  "aggregate&#13;
4/&#13;
measure of regional inequality" that improves slightly during that decade.&#13;
In Table 9 we-present additional evidence,including data through 1977,&#13;
that challenge the common presumption that per capita income growth was&#13;
concentrated in urban areas and in the Southeast.&#13;
1/ See Graham ai;d Mer-ric;; r1979h, Chapter VI. Also John Redwood III,&#13;
"Evolucao recente das disparidades de renda regional no Brasil,"&#13;
Pesquisa e Planejamento Economico 7:3 (Dec. 1977), pp. 485-549; and&#13;
Thompson Alineida Andrade "Desigualdades Regionais no Brasil: Uma&#13;
Selecao de Estudos Empiricos," Pesquisa e Planejamento Economico 7:1&#13;
(April 1977), pp. 205-226; Langoni [1973], pp. 84 and 113.&#13;
2/ Langoni [1973], Table 4.1. His statistical decomposition of the&#13;
sources of the increase in inequality finds that, holding other&#13;
factors constant (age, sex, education and activity) the regional&#13;
variable acts to reduce aggregate inequality (pp. 112-113).&#13;
3/ Based on national accounts data from Conjuntura Economica and reported&#13;
by Graham a-id Merrick [1979], Chapter VI.&#13;
4/ Grahamn and Merrick [19791.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 69 -&#13;
Table 9: TRENDS IN REGIONAL AND SECTORAL INCOME DIFFERENTIALS&#13;
1959    1960    1966    1968    1970     1972    1974    1976    1977&#13;
Regional per Canita Tncomea&#13;
1.  Urban - Rural:  Brazil                        2.17                    2.74    2.32   (2.93)   2.33&#13;
2.  S. Paulo , Northeast                         2.11                     1.98    2.64   (2.53)   2.00&#13;
3.  S. Paulo   Northeast (Urban)                 2.00                     1.93    1.96   (2.22)   1.96&#13;
4.  S. Paulo . Northeast (Rural)                  1.86                    2.15    2.83   (2.55)   2.17&#13;
5.  South   Northeast  (Rural)                   2.11                     1.98    2.64   (2.53)   2.00&#13;
6.  Brazil , Northeast                           1.76                     1.80    1.93   (2.02)   1.84&#13;
Regional-Sectoral Wages&#13;
7.  Construct.Unskilled - Rural Casual                            1.56    1.49    1.43    1.10    1.15    1.16&#13;
8.  Idem:  Sao Paulo                                              1.30    1.20    1.12    1.03    0.88    0.81&#13;
9.  Urban Minimum ,- Rural Casual                                 1.72    1.72    1.64    0.96    1.03    1.09&#13;
10.  Rural Casual: S.P. and South . NE                             1.71    1.81    1.81    1.52    1.58    1.57&#13;
11. Minimum:   Southeast 9 NE                     1.65     1.65    1.64    1.50    1.47    1.41    1.41    1.41&#13;
12.  Construct. Unskilled: Rio &amp; S.P. - NE                         1.59                                    1.74&#13;
13.  Construct. Skilled:  idem                                             1.59                            1.55&#13;
Occupational - Sectoral Wages&#13;
13.  Construct.'  Skilled ,' Unskilled                             1.97    1.91    1.92    1.68    1.64    1.60&#13;
14.  Manufac. (20+): Non-plant.   Plant   2.37                             2.69    2 46    2.59&#13;
15.  Manufac.: Large (20+)   Small (5-19) 1.40                             1.79    1.72    1.41&#13;
16.  Manufac.: Plant (20+) , Small (5-19) 1.16                             1.47    1.35    1.10&#13;
17.  Govt. , Private (Nonag. Employees)           1.64                     1.64                    1.41&#13;
Land Rent&#13;
18,  Cropland:  NE . Rio and South                         1.00                                    0.96&#13;
19.  Pasture: NE                                           1.00                                    1.11&#13;
Value Added per Household&#13;
20,  Nonagriculture , Agriculture         5.38                             7.70                    5.11&#13;
Line&#13;
1-6:   Sources:  Langoni (1973) for 1960 and 1970; PNAD 1972, Table 6.1; ENDEF; PNAD 1976 (Table 26).   See Notes&#13;
to Tables 1 and 2 for coverage. All data are for individual recipients except ENDEF (bracketed) which&#13;
are for households.&#13;
5:     South equals Region III Sul (Parana, Sta. Catarina and Rio Grande do Sul).&#13;
7-13: See Appendix on Wage Statistics.&#13;
14-16: Censo Industrial 1960; Censo Industrial 1970; Pesquisa Industrial 1972; Pesquisa Industrial 1974.&#13;
All by FIGBE.  Plant workers are "Pessoal ligado a Producab:"   covers plant engineers and supervisors,&#13;
skilled and unskilled plant workers.  Non-plant includes admin.strative and service workers.   This&#13;
breakdown was calculated here for firms with 20 or more worker:; only because of suspected poor quality&#13;
of this statistical distinction in smaller firms.&#13;
17:    1960 Census, 1970 Census and 1976 PNAD.&#13;
18-20: Conjuntura Economica, June 1977, p. 101.  States weighted by agricultural labor force.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 70 -&#13;
Between 1960 and 1976 per capita income in the Northeast kept&#13;
1/&#13;
pace with Sao Paulo (Line 2) and Brazil as a whole (Line 6).    This overall&#13;
performance shows up in both urban and rural areas. The Sao Paulo - North-&#13;
east urban differential is remarkably constant over the five different&#13;
years (and sources) shown (Line 3). As might be expected, the rural dif-&#13;
ferential is more variable: Northeast rural income lags behind rural income&#13;
in Sao Paulo (Line 4) but grows faster than the South (Line: 5). IOependett&#13;
support for these results is provided by trends in regional wage differentials:&#13;
both agricultural and skilled construction wage rates (Lines 10 and 13) rise&#13;
more rapidly in the Northeast than in the South and Southeast, between 1968&#13;
and 1977, though unskilled construction wages lag (Line 12). Finally, the&#13;
trend in agricultural land rents is consistent with the income and wage&#13;
data: the price of both rented cropland (Line 18) and pasture (Line 19)&#13;
2/&#13;
rose at almost the same rates in the Northeast and South. -&#13;
The overall urban-rural income ratio rises between 1960-1970, but&#13;
then falls between 1970-1976 to a level only 7% higher than in 1960 (Line 1).&#13;
Some improvement in the reporting of farm income in kind in the 1972 and&#13;
1976 surveys may contribute to this result, but coverage of urban cash&#13;
income also rose and there is no basis for knowing whether coverage improved&#13;
more in rural or urban areas. Wage statistics support the Census and PNAD&#13;
1/ The small changes in the ratios - a lag of 5% by the Northeast relative&#13;
to Brazil as a whole, a gain of 5% relative to Sao Paulo - are not&#13;
statistically significant, in view of the deficiencies of census and&#13;
survey income data discussed above, and in relation to the doubling&#13;
of income per capita over the period.&#13;
2/ In real terms the rental price of land in the Northeast rose 87% for&#13;
crops and 18% for pasture.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 71 -&#13;
income data: the gap between urban and rural unskilled wages falls from&#13;
1/&#13;
56% in 1968 to 16% in 1977 (Line 7).    Additional evidence is provided&#13;
by national accounts and demographic data. These show a net decline,&#13;
between 1959 and 1976/77, of the ratio between nonagricultural and&#13;
agricultural productivity (Line 20). The ratio rose substantially bet-&#13;
ween 1959 and 1970, but the increase was more than offset after 1970 by&#13;
a combination of real output growth, improved farm terms of trade, and&#13;
continuing rapid rural outmigration.&#13;
One measure of sectoral inequality, is provided by the&#13;
differential between the average wage in factories (20 or more workers) and&#13;
workshops (5-19 workers) (Line 15). This ratio, which can be interpreted&#13;
as a differential between protected and unprotected sectors, grows between&#13;
1960 and 1970, but then declines to its original level in 1959. This pat-&#13;
tern matches evidence from educational and occupational differentials&#13;
that some widening did occur between 1960 and 1970, but that this trend slowed&#13;
or was reversed after 1970. Another statistic that fits this pattern is the&#13;
wage ratio between non-plant and plant workers in factories (Line 14), which&#13;
follows a similar cycle between 1959 and 1974.&#13;
A related sectoral measure is the income ratio between govern-&#13;
ment and private nonagricultural employees (Line 17). Between 1960 and 1976,&#13;
government workers lose relative to private. Factories and government&#13;
together account for the bulk of what is usually considered the "modern&#13;
1/ The absolute size of this premium is not known exactly since reported&#13;
farm wage rates are on a daily basis, and reported construction rates&#13;
are hourly: the measured premium will turn 'on the assumption made&#13;
regarding average hours and days worked., Also, payments in both&#13;
these markets more often than not include pay in kind, piece rates,&#13;
and other incentive pay. The published rates are reportedly for&#13;
"pure!' cash contracts but-the frequency of "impure" contracts allows&#13;
considerable room for unmeasured differences in the average levels of&#13;
these two key wage rates, as well as in their trends.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 72 -&#13;
sector;" they are also the categories of employment most subject to direct&#13;
policy influence on wages. In both, wages are higher than in informal or&#13;
small-scale establishments, but that premium shows no net increase between&#13;
1959 and 1976. 1n fact, the average wage in the modern sector as a whole&#13;
appears i:o fall r .Jative to that in the urban informal sector.&#13;
The factory-workshop wage ratio (Line 15) raises questions about&#13;
wage determination. We noted above the arguments that wage policy tended&#13;
to depress manual wages during the sixties while organizational forces&#13;
pulled up supervisory and managerial salaries. These arguments imply&#13;
slow or no growth in the average factory wage (including manual and managerial&#13;
workers) starting up to about 1968, and faster growth after that year. The&#13;
factory wage series (Table 14) tends to bear out this prediction.&#13;
However, wages in the small-enterprise sector, which are determined in&#13;
relatively competitive markets for skilled and unskilled manual workers,&#13;
followed an even more pronounced cycle: the workshop wage lagged behind&#13;
factories in the sixties, but grew faster after 1970.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 73 -&#13;
This behavior suggests several, possible complementary explana-&#13;
tions. One is that the effects of policy have been exaggerated: sitall enterprise&#13;
wages, which are not likely to have been affected by wage policy, grew&#13;
even more slowly in the sixties than the wages of production workers in&#13;
factories (Line 16). Another is that labor market conditions changed&#13;
abruptly after 1968/70 and that the internal labor markets of factories&#13;
tended to dampen the effects of this change both before and after. A third&#13;
possibility is that the profits-wages link, that has been discussed solely&#13;
in connection with senior managerial wages, is equally powerful within&#13;
small enterprises. This is made plausible by general knowledge of the&#13;
importance of piece rates and other incentive pay, by the fact that many&#13;
employees are artisans using their own tools and often working on&#13;
a commission basis and the fact that workshop owners are generally on&#13;
the payroll paying themselves a combined salary and profit.&#13;
Another set of data that bears on the regional distribution&#13;
of income and welfare consists of life expectancy rates. These rates&#13;
are to some extent an indicator of economic improvement. But the achievement&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 74 -&#13;
of longer life expectancy is of course a fundamental objective of&#13;
development in itself. The following table analyzes the trend over&#13;
t--e and the distribution of life expectancy at birth by regions of&#13;
Brazil in 1950 and 1970:&#13;
Table I0; LIFE EXPECTANCY BY REGIONS&#13;
(1950, 1970)&#13;
1950            Life             1970            Life&#13;
Region          Population       Expectancy      Population       Expectancy&#13;
(1000)          (Years)          (1000)          (Years)&#13;
Amazonia                1,845            42.7             3,604           54.2&#13;
North                   2,629            43.7             4,673           50.4&#13;
Northeast               9,866            34.0            15,035           44.2&#13;
Bahia                   5,479            39.2             8,394           49.7&#13;
Minas Gerais            8,739            46.1            13,087           55.4&#13;
Rio-Guanabara           4,675            48.7             8,995           57.0&#13;
Sao Paulo               9,134            49.4            17,781           58.2&#13;
Parana                  2,116            45.9             6,930           56.6&#13;
South                   5,725            55.3             9,567           61.9&#13;
Central-West            1,737            49.8             5,073           57.5&#13;
Brazil                 51,945            43.6            93,139           53.4&#13;
Source:   Census, in Thomas W. Merrick:   "Interregional Differences in&#13;
Fertility in Brazil, 1950-1970" in Demography, August, 1974;&#13;
and Jose Alberto Magno de Carvalho and C.H. Wood: "Renda e&#13;
Concentracao da Mortalidade no Brazil," IPEA, Rio de Janeiro.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
C                                                                                      m~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~C &#13;
~~~~~~~~~~iI                                                               0~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~u&#13;
------------------------------...&#13;
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .   . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .   . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .&#13;
. . ..'  -.                                                                                       -~~~~~~~~~~~~ - - -  - - - &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 76 -&#13;
The poorest areas in 1970 have the same life expectancy as the country's&#13;
average in 1950 (about 44 years). In turn, life expectancy in the Nprtheast&#13;
in 1950 was only 34 years. Thus there is a 10-year span between the poorest&#13;
and the E .erage just as there is a 10-year improvement between the national&#13;
average for 1950 and that for 1970.&#13;
Ranking the ten regions in the table according to the life&#13;
expectancy of their populations and weighing the latter by the size of&#13;
each region's population, one arrives at Figure 1, which shows the&#13;
distribution of life expectancy in 1950 and 1970. If all persons had&#13;
had the same (average) life expectancy, the distribution curve would be a&#13;
vertical line rising at the- 100 index mark. Conversely, perfect inequality&#13;
would be represented on the Chart by a horizontal line. Thus, movement&#13;
toward the vertical between two observations reflects greater equality.&#13;
This is in fact what can be seen on the Chart. Perhaps partly because of&#13;
migration from poor to more affluent areas and the gradual assimilation of&#13;
migrants with the resident population, not only has life expectancy increased&#13;
substantially, but its distribution is more equal in 1970 than in 1950.&#13;
Moreover the absolute improvement at the top (61.9 minus 55.3 = 6.6 years), is&#13;
smaller than that at the bottom (44.2 minus 34.0 = 10.2 years) reflecting&#13;
"diminishing returns" to life-extending efforts as life expectancy and income&#13;
increase.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 77 -&#13;
5. Partial Data: Conclusions&#13;
The partial measures reviewed in this section do not support&#13;
the view that inequality grew significantly between 1960 and 1976. The&#13;
two sets of data that cover -the entire economy - educational and regional&#13;
income differentials - suggest little change in the structure-of incomes&#13;
since 1960. Educational and occupational differentials show a small&#13;
increase (Table 4), while regional differentials remain relatively constant&#13;
(Table 9). Law of 2/3 and some wage surveys show some widening in the&#13;
wage structure within the urban private modern sector. The Law of 2/3 data,&#13;
however, is subject to large margins of error and to biases that probably&#13;
overstate the increase in inequality. Also, that data cover a relatively&#13;
small proportion of total income and employment (Table 7). Wage surveys&#13;
also indicate widening differentials within large scale manufacturing&#13;
(Table 8), but the sector involved is an even smaller fraction of total&#13;
employment, and its wage structure was subject to forces that cannot be&#13;
generalized to the rest of the economy. Employees in the modern sector as&#13;
a whole, instead, tend to lose relative to those in the informal sector (Table 9).&#13;
A second conclusion is that distributive trends have been&#13;
more favorable since 1970, than during the sixties. This is true of&#13;
educational and occupational differentials, of large vs. small scale&#13;
manufacturing wages, and of regional income ratios.&#13;
Both conclusions support our analysis-of Census and survey&#13;
income data. We found no definite evidence of growing inequality in these&#13;
data, though a best guess regarding 1960 shares would imply some deteriora-&#13;
tion (Table 1). Also, whatever deterioration did occur probably took&#13;
place between 1960 and 1970.  This finding helps to reconcile our conclusions&#13;
*with the general view that inequality grew significantly. 'That view has&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 78 -&#13;
been based almost entirely on data for the sixties. On the other hand,&#13;
there has been a tendency to magnify the indicators of increase'.&#13;
inequality during the sixties, and to wrongly project t!,at trend into&#13;
the seventies.&#13;
The apparent improvement in distributive trends after 1970 is&#13;
especially interesting, because it implies that rapid growth had a double&#13;
effect on poverty reduction: during the boom, total inco-ne grew more rapidlv&#13;
and more evenly.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 79 -&#13;
V. TRENDS IN EMPLOYMENT AND INCOMES&#13;
For the most part, incomes rise in two ways: as people move to&#13;
better jobs, and as the mean income in specific jobs rises. The&#13;
following evidence on each of these sources of income growth thus&#13;
complements the indirect evidence obtained from trends in distribu-&#13;
tion. At the same time, it helps to explain those trends by providing a&#13;
more disaggregated, and less anonymous picture of the course of incomes&#13;
obtained from employment.&#13;
It is worth noting briefly, however, that property and transfer&#13;
income is probably larger than usually reported by the available sources,&#13;
and changes in the amount received by the poor may be an important compo-&#13;
nent of     trends in their overall income.   The main flows are likely to&#13;
be rents from agricultural holdings and urban real estate, and welfare&#13;
payments.-/ PNAD 1972 reported transfer, property and non-factor income&#13;
equal to 14% of total urban income, and 11% of rural income.- The propor-&#13;
tion of non-working income recipients grew from 7% to 11% of total reci-&#13;
pients between 1972 and 1976, according to the respective household surveys.&#13;
Since both surveys asked specific, separate questions on such income sources,&#13;
the increase probably reflects the rapid growth of welfare payments during&#13;
the seventies rather than changing statistical coverage. By 1974, the&#13;
number of persons receiving pensions from the two main welfare institutions&#13;
1/ Mixed property and labor income received by farmers, self-employed&#13;
workers and owners of small businesses is included in the data reported&#13;
below on income from "employment." The omission referred to here is of&#13;
pure property income and transfer payments.&#13;
2/ From comparison of Tables 2.8 and 6.1.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 80 -&#13;
1/&#13;
was larger than the number of factory workers.    In this paper we have not&#13;
attempted to measure the separate contribution of growing welfare payments&#13;
on poverty reduction, but their impact is reflected in the household&#13;
income levels re,orted by more recent surveys, and in the estimates of&#13;
poverty given below in Table 17.&#13;
The measurement of trends in income from employment poses&#13;
three statistical tasks: the measurement of (i) movement across jobs,&#13;
(ii) income differentials between jobs, and (iii) trends in mean earnings&#13;
in specific employment categories. Statistical gaps and imprecisions, partic-&#13;
ularly with respect to trends in wage rates and income in specific jobs, limit&#13;
the reliability of conclusions on these questions. Neverthe.less, the&#13;
conclusions obtained here tend to bear out the picture of widespread&#13;
income growth and upward mobility that is implied by the relatively small&#13;
changes in distributive shares and the substantial growth in per capita income.&#13;
1. The Structure of Employment&#13;
The two main features of the change in employment patterns&#13;
between 1960 and 1976 are a substantial move out of agriculture, and&#13;
an upgrading of the urban employment structure (Table 11). The absolute&#13;
number of farm households increased by only 11% over 16 years, and the rate&#13;
2/&#13;
of increase appears to have been slowing.     Thus, 4 out of every 5 farm&#13;
households that would have been created through natural population growth&#13;
1/ The two agencies are the National Institute for Social Welfare (INPS) and&#13;
FUNRURAL, the agencv of the Ministrv of Social Welfare in charge of administering&#13;
social welfare programs in the rural sector. By 1976, FUNRURAL's&#13;
receipts amounted to about 6% of total rural income.   In 1974 there&#13;
were 2.6 million workers in factories with 50 or more employees (Pe-squisa&#13;
Industrial 1974, p. 128, FIGBE), and 3.2 million INPS and FUNRURAL pen-&#13;
sioners (INPS_ Mensario Estatistico, and Boletin Estatistico do Funrural,&#13;
1977). One-thiird of the pensions were paid in rural areas, (by FUNRURAL).&#13;
Total welfare expenditure by these two agencies was about equal to total&#13;
wages and salaries paid by factories in 1974 (Cr.$38.5 billion).&#13;
2/  A comparison of 1970 Census and 1976 PNAD data shows a minimal change&#13;
between 1970 ind 1976 (an absolute growth of only 2%), but the margin&#13;
of error is larger than between Censuses.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 81 -&#13;
Table 1I: TIlF STRUC1URE OF 13iPLOYMENT 1960-1976&#13;
Labor Force                              Annual Percen-&#13;
(in Millions)                              tage_ . Crowth&#13;
Hlotiseihold 1leads          Total Labor Force /Ic    1960-1976&#13;
1960    1976/a          1960    1976            3960    1976     Heads Total&#13;
(Millions)                (_ )&#13;
Total                               12.06   19.25           100     100             22.75   39.72     3.0&#13;
Agriculture                          6.77    7.49           56.1    38.3                              0.6&#13;
Nonagriculture                       5.29   11.79           43.9    61.2                              5.3    5.7&#13;
Manufacture and Construction       1.50    4.67           12.4    24.2                              7.4&#13;
TransporL and Commerce             1.67    2.91           13.8    15.1                              3.5&#13;
Personal Services                  1.04    1.73            8.6     9.0                              3.2&#13;
Governsment and Social Services    0.67    1.65            5.6     8.6                              5.8&#13;
Others                             0.41    0.83            3.4     4.3                              4.5&#13;
Selected Subgroups&#13;
Activity&#13;
Construction                                                                       0.78    2.69            8.0&#13;
Factories (504 workers)                                                           (1.23)/b(2.95)/b         5.5&#13;
Women in Personal Services                                                         1.48    3.29            5.1&#13;
Occupation&#13;
Administrative and Technical                                                       2.53    7.61            7.1&#13;
Manual (nonagriculture)                                                            8.15   17.59            4.9&#13;
Status (Nonagricul ture)&#13;
Self-employed and Family                                                           2.97    5.29            3.7&#13;
E.j'1loyees                                                                        7.91   19.38            5.8&#13;
/5&#13;
Participation Rates d                       1960    1970    1972    1976&#13;
Population (10+)                          46.6    44.9    52.7    50.8&#13;
Women (10+)                               16.6    18.5    29.9    29.6&#13;
Men (10+)                                 77.2    71.8    76.1    73.6&#13;
Men (10-19)                               45.2    38.8    48.4    45.9&#13;
Sources: PNAD 1976. Censo Demografico 1960. Censo Industrial 1960. _esquisa Industrial 1974.      PNAD 1972.&#13;
Notes&#13;
/n  Adjusted upwards to include rural areas of North region esing 1970 CenslUs share of rural North in total&#13;
populationi (3.6%). Nonagriculture figures are slightly underestimated due to omission of nonagricultural&#13;
workers in rural areas of North.&#13;
lb  Estimated from 1959 and 1974 figures using the 5.5% annual growith rate recorded between 1959-1974.&#13;
/c As argtied in the text, thie comparisoni of total labor force structure between 1960 and 1976 is biased by&#13;
definitional changes which lead to higher participatlion rates in 1976. The change is especially large in&#13;
agriculture so only heads are compared in that sector.&#13;
/d  The purpose of showin g these datn is to demonst.rate the inconmparabilty between Censuses (1960 and 1970)&#13;
and surveys (1972 and 1976), particularly by shjbiIng the. jump between 1970 and 1972 in the rates for women&#13;
and young rnen.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 82 -&#13;
emigrated. As a result, the number of nonagricultural households more than&#13;
doubled, growing at 5.3% yearly over the whole period and at a slightly&#13;
faster rate since 1970. The contribution to income growth of that movement&#13;
is measured by the differential between agricultural and non-agricultural&#13;
.mean household incomes. The most reliable measure is provided by ENDEF:&#13;
for Brazil as a whole it was 2.5 times in 1974/75, and the size of the&#13;
differential appears to have remained roughly constant since 1960.1/ An&#13;
approximate adjustment for urban-rural cost of living diffeteices would&#13;
still leave a differential in the order of 2 times.-/&#13;
The constancy of the differential itself suggests that this&#13;
enormous absorption by urban areas occurred without a flooding of the&#13;
lower income categories. But more direct evidence is provided by the&#13;
favorable trends in the composition of non-agricultural employment. As may&#13;
be seen in Table 10, administrative and technical occupations gained rela-&#13;
tive to manual; secondary activities gained related to tertiary; within&#13;
tertiary, government and social services (mostly teachers and nurses) gained&#13;
relative to other services, and wage employment gained relative to self-&#13;
employment and unpaid family workers. Amongst heads, the slowest growth was&#13;
in personal services. One unfavorable trend appears to be a loss in the share&#13;
1/ Table 9, Lines 1 and 19. The urban-rural differential was 2.9 times&#13;
in 1974/75.&#13;
2/ Using the estimated cost of living differential of 25% explained in&#13;
Table 17, footnote 1.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 83 -&#13;
of factories relative to workshops or small-scale manufacturing but factory&#13;
employment grows almost as fast (5.5%) as total nonagricultural employment&#13;
1/&#13;
(5.7%).    Also. because the Dersonal services sector has a Particularly large&#13;
share of secondary earners, its growth is much understated by the household head&#13;
figures, but even the figure for all women in personal services, most of&#13;
whom are in domestic service, shows a slower rate of growth (5.1%) than that&#13;
for all non-agricultural workers (5.7%).&#13;
Those trends in some cases refer to household heads, and in&#13;
others to the total labor force. The more reliable comparison is that for&#13;
heads, because the post-1970 data are obtained from surveys which use dif-&#13;
ferent questions and definitions to define activity and, as a result, yield higher&#13;
levels of labor force participation than do censuses (Table 11). The rate for&#13;
women, for instance, jumps from 18.5% in 1970 to 29.9% in 1972. None of the&#13;
trends cited above, however, are significantly affected by this potential bias.&#13;
Our estimate that the rate of employment growth in agriculture was only&#13;
0.6% per year is based on the notion that households are a preferable basis for&#13;
defining employment trends in agriculture than individuals. This approach has&#13;
some obvious shortcomings: it will miss changes in the extent of wage-work&#13;
performed by women and children, or in the tendency for secondary earners&#13;
in farm households to work in construction or other nonagricultural activity.&#13;
1/ This statistic may be affected by changes in coverage. Factory employ-&#13;
ment (establishments with 50+.workers) is taken from Industrial Censuses&#13;
of 1960 and 1970 and Industrial Survey of 1974. The 5.5% growth rate&#13;
shown in Table 11 is that recorded between 1959 (1960 Census) and 1974.&#13;
In principle, all these sources cover all employment in firms of only 5&#13;
or more workers, so coverage of 50+ firms should not vary. As a test of&#13;
the Industrial Census data, the Census for 1972 yields 2.5 million&#13;
employees, vs. 2.7 million in SEPT data, and 3.7 million employees for&#13;
all size establishments according to PNAD 1972. The Census-PNAD residual&#13;
implies that about 30% of manufacturing employment was missed by the&#13;
Census, but the omission may all occur in firms of under 50 workers.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 64 -&#13;
This could be important, for instance, where access to land is declining,&#13;
or where school enrollment is increasing. On the other hand, the usual&#13;
definitions of labor force participation, where multiple and overlapping&#13;
forms of activity are the rule, and where much activity is&#13;
directed at production for own-consumption, can lead to large biases in&#13;
estimates of the volume of employment. In the context of rural households&#13;
in Brazil, standard definitions require highly arbitrary statistical&#13;
allocations, and the'resulting estimates are especially sensitive to changes&#13;
in definitions or procedures. Thus, the growth rate of total agricultural&#13;
employment obtained from a comparison of 1960 census and 1976 survey figures -&#13;
1.3% per year - is much higher than that of heads of households in agri-&#13;
culture, but the difference is largely attributable to the different treatment&#13;
of female activity. Thus, the difference arises only between censuses&#13;
and surveys: between 1960 and 1970 the census data record a growth rate&#13;
of total agricultural employment of only 0.5% per year, whereas, a&#13;
comparison of the 1970 census and 1976 survey yields a growth of 2.5% per&#13;
year. If women, and male unpaid family workers are excluded, the growth&#13;
of total agricultural employment between 1960 and 1976 is only 0.7%, similar&#13;
to that for household heads.&#13;
One aspect of employment change with negative implications for&#13;
income is an apparent reduction in access to land and parallel increases&#13;
in dependence on wage work and in the urbanization of the agricultural labor&#13;
1/&#13;
force.  Numerous studies claim the existence of such trends.     Some data&#13;
for the State of Sao Paulo show an increase in the category of volantes&#13;
1/ E.g. 0 Trabalho Volante na Agricultura.Paulista, Ministerio do Trabalho,&#13;
Secretaria de Emprego e Salario, Convenio SINE/SEMO, 1978. This was one&#13;
of a series of state-level studies. The literature generally refers to&#13;
boias-frias or volantes,terms applied to temporary wage workers.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 85 -&#13;
(temporary day workers), from around 17% in 1964 to 26% of total&#13;
1/&#13;
agricultural employment in 1975, but this phenomenon is particularly&#13;
pronounced in Sao Paulo. There are no available estimates for all Brazil.&#13;
Perhaps the most potentially negative component of this process&#13;
is urbanization, since it minimizes opportunities for own-production, and&#13;
entails higher living costs. Urbanization, of course, also carries&#13;
benefits, particularly in the form of greater access to services and to&#13;
a wider set of employment opportunities for all family members. In fact,&#13;
any trend to urbanization is surely, at least in part, voluntary. Some&#13;
data, however, suggest that the extent of urbanization of agricultural wage&#13;
earners     has been exaggerated in much of the discussion.    In 1976,&#13;
/2&#13;
19% of all agricultural households were urban. To approximate the increase,&#13;
between 1960 and 1976, in the proportion of farm household heads who were&#13;
both landless and urban it is necessary to deduct from that figure (i) farmers&#13;
who were urban residents, and (ii) agriciultural wage-earners who were urban&#13;
residents in 1960. These statistics are not available, but the net increase&#13;
is likely to have been well under that ceiling figure of 19% of farm&#13;
3/&#13;
households.&#13;
1/ Data fron Instituto de Economia Agricola, Secretaria de Agricultura,&#13;
State of Sao Paulo.&#13;
2/  The ratio was -37% in thp'eState-7bf Sao Paulo.  PNAD 1976, Table -7 (Familias).&#13;
3/  What may be concealed in that figure is a larger movement to urban areas&#13;
by the dependents of primary earners who are migrating to nonagricultural&#13;
jobs in towns and cities. Case studies suggest that a relatively large&#13;
proportion of volantes and boias frias are secondary earners.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 86 -&#13;
Changes in the proportion of landless, as distinct from urban&#13;
agricultural households are more difficult to estimate. The main&#13;
approximation to landlessness is the category of agricultural wage-earners.&#13;
In practice, there is enormous overlap between work on one's own land&#13;
and wage-employment. The frequency and variety of share-cropping arrange-&#13;
ments increase the difficulty of classification.&#13;
Since classification is normally by principal income source, the&#13;
number of wage-earners reported in censuses and surveys overestimates the&#13;
landless, because many "wage-earners" have some access to land, or are&#13;
members of households with land. On the other hand, changes in the amount&#13;
of land available to those with access, or in the terms of access in the&#13;
case of share-croppers and renters may be as important as changes in the&#13;
number of those who are strictly landless. The following data on wage-&#13;
earners are therefore open to several possible biases as indicators of&#13;
either the level or trend in the degree of access to land, but they are&#13;
presented as a first step towards better estimates.&#13;
A proxy for the number of landless households is the number of&#13;
men aged 24 and over classified as wage-earners. These grew only slightly&#13;
between 1960 and 1970, from 23.5% to 26.0% of all farm households, though&#13;
it is during this period, following the extension of protective labor&#13;
legislation to rural areas in 1963, that much of the increase should have&#13;
1/&#13;
occurred.    Figures for years after 1970 are not comparable owing to a&#13;
1/ The Estatuto do Trabalhador Rural. However, changing crops and&#13;
technologies may be a greater part of the explanation for the observed&#13;
increase in casual wage-employment in many areas.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 87 -&#13;
different treatment of sharecroppers (parceiros) who in 1960 and 1970 were&#13;
listed separately, but in 1976 were allocated between the categories of&#13;
employees and independents according to the nature of their relationship&#13;
with the landowner. In 1976, the proportion of heads in agriculture defined&#13;
as employees was 37% - a substantial jump over the 1970 figure of 26% - but&#13;
the definitional component of the change is not known. In summary, the aggregate&#13;
data suggest that inferences from case studies on localized trends have tended&#13;
to exaggerate the aggregate importance of urbanization and increased land-&#13;
lessness amongst the agricultural labor force. On the other hand, the&#13;
available aggregate data are very imperfect measures of those trends, and&#13;
the more definite evidence from case studies indicates that. in some areas,&#13;
at least, there has been a negative change in the agricultural employment&#13;
structure.&#13;
2. The Structure of Income&#13;
The broad occupational-regional hierarchy is provided in Table 12&#13;
using ENDEF data. The occupations are those of heads of families only,&#13;
while the incomes shown include the earnings of secondary workers and are&#13;
therefore higher than the earnings of any individual in those categories.&#13;
The table illustrates the power of both occupational and regional variables&#13;
in creating stratification. One point to note is the big differential&#13;
between farm and nonfarm manual labor ("Farm Laborer" and "Employee: Manual").&#13;
In all regions, the landless laborer doubles his income by moving to urban&#13;
manual employment within his own region. Allowance for urban-rural cost&#13;
of living differences would still leave increases of well over 50% since&#13;
the landless buy much of their food, while at least half of nonfarm manual&#13;
employment is in small cities and towns where cost of living differences&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 88 -&#13;
with rural areas are not as large as in metropolitan areas. The rural-Northeast&#13;
to urban-Rio move roughly triples income, while the family income of a Sao Paulo&#13;
manual workers is 4.7 times that of a Northeast farm laborer.&#13;
The size of these differences seems surprising in view of the&#13;
apparent extent of mobility and integration of unskilled labor markets.&#13;
Urban wage rates in entry jobs in construction, factories, small urban&#13;
establishments, and domestic services are generally between 1 and 2 minimum&#13;
wages, levels which are now close, in absolute terms, to daily wage rates&#13;
1/&#13;
in agriculture.    The observed higher mean earnings of urban manual workers&#13;
must therefore reflect the existence of a skill hierarchy. within urban manual&#13;
employment, as we noted in discussing wage differentials avove, and thus, the&#13;
potential for upward mobility within the category of manual employment. Another&#13;
factor may be the greater availability in urban areas of employment opportunities&#13;
for secondary workers.&#13;
The importance of access to land can also be measured in Table 12.&#13;
The term "laborer" must be interpreted as a matter of degree, since ENDEF&#13;
data show that "farm laborers" produce a substantial portion of their own&#13;
consumption. Small farmers in all regions receive, on average, about&#13;
twice the income of agricultural laborers in their region. A major exception&#13;
is the Northeast where the difference between farm laborers and small&#13;
farmers is minor. A more important qualification is that farm laborers&#13;
in all regions outside the Northeast earn more than small farmers in the&#13;
Northeast: the most striking difference is in Sao Paulo where the earnings&#13;
of a farm laborer's household are 70% higher than those of the Northeast&#13;
small farmer.&#13;
1/ As shown in Wage Statistics in Appendix.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- L,9&#13;
1T  * 1   l :  I       :;:( ( ' I(A; I(iNAI. fI ;:iI (-iAl. (:ROI:iS 1.V INCOME LIEVL&#13;
tI;EIiIffi l.   A ,:Nj hoU!Tt;f:OLD iN::OME) 19I141.5&#13;
Ccce.v-;&gt;ntls.nw -ar ion'Asil                    :    __          _AMNro uAltore        - ___tu&#13;
Category                              Ne.:n      Nudber                   Mean     Nwiuber&#13;
R    gieon  Income    Pre I i es    Region     Income    Fa m:: Jies&#13;
..   ____  ("'Ofl _  ('000)         ('CCC)    ('000)&#13;
Total                                              S,219                              6.263&#13;
Manager                      Rlo        169.1         78&#13;
SP         ]67.2         82&#13;
MG          143.4        19&#13;
NE          137.9        37&#13;
Employer or Professional.    Mr         136.3         62&#13;
SP         123.1        204&#13;
Rio        120.7         87&#13;
Manager                      South      120.4         34&#13;
F.nployer or Professional    South      108.5        117&#13;
MiddIle M1anagement          Sr          79.1        235&#13;
Shopkeeper                   SP          71.8        159&#13;
Em:ployer or Professional    NE          67.9         84&#13;
Middle Manacgement           Rio         67.7        139&#13;
South       57.6        116&#13;
Farmer                                                          SP          54.5       102&#13;
Middle Management            Mr          54.0         68&#13;
NE           52.1        96&#13;
Farmer                                                          MG          45.2        150&#13;
Rio          45.1        23&#13;
Shopkeeper                   South       44.4       117&#13;
Eraployce:  Nonmanual        SP          43.3        405&#13;
Shopkeeper                   Rio         42.9         57&#13;
Farmer                                                          South       42.5        286&#13;
Self-employed                SP          38.2       261&#13;
Workshop                     SP          36.8        121&#13;
Employee: Nonmanjal          Sout)i      35.7        179&#13;
Workshop                     South       35.5         96&#13;
Employee: Nonmanual          MG          34.4        123&#13;
Rio         34.2        254&#13;
Shopkeeper                   MG          34.0         96&#13;
Workshop                     Rio          31.0        49&#13;
MG           30.9        43&#13;
ELn;,loyee: .::inhuil        SP          25.6      1,337&#13;
Self-Cupio.td                RIo         24.9        169&#13;
South       24.5       Il5&#13;
Srail Farmer                                                    SP          23.2       174&#13;
Employee:  Nore.;:nual       NE          23.0        200&#13;
Emcployee:  Manual           Rio         21.0        685&#13;
Small Farmer                                                    South       20.2        930&#13;
Employee: Man,ial            Sourh       19.2        714&#13;
Self-cemployed               MG          17.8        180&#13;
Shiopkeeper                  NE          17.3        343&#13;
E.sployee:  Manual           MC          16.3        526&#13;
Sm.all Fanrer                                                   OG          16.0        439&#13;
Farrmer                                                         NE          15.9        487&#13;
Small Farmer                                                    Rio         14.8        41&#13;
Workshop                     NE          14.4        147&#13;
Farm Laborer                                                    SP          12.6        400&#13;
EaLplcyee: ;Ianual           NE          11.9       848&#13;
Self-e-mployed               NE          10.8       457&#13;
Farm Laborer                                                    South         9.9       329&#13;
Rio           9.0        71&#13;
MG            7.5       480&#13;
Small Farmer                                                    NE           7.3      1.239&#13;
Farm Laborer                                                    NE           5.5      1,112&#13;
Sources:  ENrMEF. Oceunation Is of he;ld of hou,sehold.  Ilco.ne is annual household I icome&#13;
in August 1974 cr-zviros.   Exchange rate - Cr.$/US$.&#13;
Definitions&#13;
1. Manager:   senior manngers, gencrally wit), professional qualificationA.&#13;
2.  Employe;r or professioena.: tar ldes:; self-emoloyed professionals.&#13;
3. Middle m!-snagerent:  includes supervisory pos!t, Ines requiring high school level.&#13;
4.  Shopkeeper: : nciUleCs   e raVe:S of service esit:d,lirlmeonts.&#13;
5.  farime: ridu!Le and largoye s: n  I:..0  moloc:. waye-l hor.&#13;
6.  Employee:  nonmamI l: low J--.    *.fflr 2ce rers, store and service employees.&#13;
7.  Wor-kberp:  a!d is;n. :-.;ir  l.; owl otlher veTI-al .activitles.&#13;
8.    Sf-t;..jM.:.-:  csi.  if inn :,Jst,r.,iI, cuafi irn establishlmert&#13;
9.  SnaI.al fa;vn r:  hL' I  lilt' inti':&#13;
10I.  I:   :.e-r: r i  n  .'.;r,--c-: I:..- :-&#13;
11. RE5I: j;ef: Sil: s;.c  tlc; -:  :        : I '   :...   ! .. :x .I e.ist&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 90 -&#13;
The data in Table 12 also indicate the size and composition of&#13;
middle income groups; 34% of all family, for instance, have family incomes&#13;
in the order of 5 to 20 minimum wages (Cr.$22,500 to 90,000). These include&#13;
a sizeable contingent of farmers who achieve incomes well above those of&#13;
agricultural laborers and who comprise a rural middle class. Much larger,&#13;
however, is the size of the urban middle-income groups made up of skilled&#13;
workers and a large number of small business owners.&#13;
Within agriculture, there is a strong relationship between&#13;
regional average productivity and the incomes of both small farmers and&#13;
farm laborer households. These relationships are shown in Table 13. The&#13;
comparison in that table is crude, owing chiefly to the lack of regional&#13;
value added data for 1974/75, but it serves to establish the relationships&#13;
between productivity and incomes. First, small farmer incomes are strongly&#13;
correlated with average regional productivity: the high productivity of&#13;
the South and Southeast is not limited to large farmers. Second, the&#13;
farm laborers also benefit substantially from higher regional productivity:&#13;
the elasticity of their household incomes to regional productivity is&#13;
between one-third and one-half. That elasticity is about twice that of&#13;
the rural wage rate. The Sao Paulo farm wage-earner's household income&#13;
is higher than in the Northeast only partly because the regional wage rate&#13;
is higher. Over half the higher family income of the Sao Paulo farm laborers&#13;
must be explained in other ways. One possibility is more days worked per year,&#13;
which may in turn be related   to more developed labor markets (better in-&#13;
formation, quicker transport, and more efficient intermediation). Another&#13;
is more and better paid work opportunities outside agriculture -- in towns&#13;
and cities during agricultural slack seasons.      These greater employment&#13;
opportunities apply as well to secondary earners. Finally, since many&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 91 -&#13;
Table 13: FARM HOUSEHOLD INCONES AND REGIONAL&#13;
AGRICULTURAL PRODUCTIVITY&#13;
Indices of&#13;
Household Income&#13;
Regional Agricultural      Seall       Farm          Rural&#13;
Value Added per Worker     Farmer     Laborer     Casual Wage&#13;
1970/1972                 1974/75              1974&#13;
Sao Paulo                        452               318         229            149&#13;
South                            306               277         180            146&#13;
Rio                              257               203         164            107&#13;
Minas Gerais                     174               219         136            121&#13;
Northeast                        100               100         100            100&#13;
Source:  ENDEF for household incomes.   National accounts for 1970 value added.&#13;
J.F. Graziano da Silva, coordinator, Estrutura Agraria e Producao de&#13;
Subsistencia na Agricultura Brasileira (Sao Paulo: Editora Hucitec.&#13;
1978), Table 51 for 1972 regional productivity per worker. For 1972&#13;
we used average of productivity per permanent and per maximum (peak&#13;
season) annual employment 1970/72 figure shown here is average of&#13;
those two years. FGV for rural casual wage.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 92 -&#13;
wage-earners have access to some land, they may enjoy higher productivity&#13;
on those plots than their counterparts in the Northeast.&#13;
What is most interesting about the cross-section relationship&#13;
between small farmer and wage-earner incomes and regional productivity is&#13;
that it suggests that the gains from productivity growth and improved terms&#13;
of trade have been widely shared within the agricultural sector.&#13;
3. Income Trends&#13;
The limited direct evidence on trends in the income of specific&#13;
occupational categories are the wage series summarized in Table 14 below&#13;
and the wage and income series discussed above and shown in Tables 8 and 9.&#13;
The broad conclusions that are suggested by those data are first&#13;
that most wages have been rising though at very variable rates. The general&#13;
picture is clearly not one of wage stagnation. A second conclusion is&#13;
that most wages grew faster during the period of accelerated economic&#13;
growth which began in 1968, though the pre-1970 data is scant. A third conclu-&#13;
sion is the lack of a clear relationship between the growth of skilled and&#13;
unskilled wages. Skilled categories gained relative to unskilled within&#13;
large-scale manufacturing, and there was some relative improvement for white-&#13;
collar workers over nonagricultural manual workers during the sixties, but the&#13;
unskilled fared better in construction, while unskilled casual farm labor&#13;
shows substantial growth in all regions of Brazil and a particularly rapid&#13;
increase in Sao Paulo. The single most striking and important feature of&#13;
those series is the marked increase after 1970 of real wage rates for casual&#13;
rural farm laborers. These wage rates went up by 61% in real terms between&#13;
1970 and 1977, Excluding the most advanced state of Sao Paulo, the average&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 93 -&#13;
wage rate for casual rural laborers still goes up by 56X for the rest of&#13;
Brazil. For comparison, per capita income went up by 57% during the period&#13;
1970-1977. Thus an important group of workers who are among the poorest&#13;
in the country experienced a substantial absolute improvement in their&#13;
1/&#13;
daily earnings.&#13;
Two qualifications must be made, however, with regard to these&#13;
statistics. One is that not enough is known regarding the precise manner&#13;
of measurement. Given the wide dispersion that characterizes wages even&#13;
for specific occupations, the accuracy of an index is usually sensitive to&#13;
the method of sampling, the moment of sampling, the coverage of the population&#13;
being sampled, and the extent to which various components of real remuneration&#13;
are included. The second qualification consists of the same set of&#13;
questions and degree of uncertainty with respect to the available price&#13;
indices. One price index in particular, estimated and published by DIESSE&#13;
shows a significantly faster rate of increase. A comparison of this&#13;
index with the more commonly used Cost of Living Index for Rio, (corrected&#13;
for underestimation in 1973) is shown in Table 15. Price indices for&#13;
other cities grow at variable rates, but the size of the differential between&#13;
the DIESSE index and others, especially since 1974, should be examined&#13;
further.&#13;
1/ The rural wage series refer to cash only. After the extension of labor&#13;
legislation to the rural areas in the mid-1960s the income in kind of&#13;
many rural workers was reduced; this reduction is unlikely to have had&#13;
much if any bearing on rural income trends in the 1970s.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 14:   INCOME AND WAGE TRENDS:  INDICES&#13;
Base&#13;
Year    1970    1971   1972   1973   1974    1975   1976   1977&#13;
=100&#13;
1.  Sao Paulo Casual Rural Wage                1960    112    121     128    145    180    184     193    210&#13;
2.  All Brazil:   Casual Rural Wage            1968     97    103     109    130    157    165     159    156&#13;
3.  Construction:   Unskilled                  1968     92     95      99    100    111    117     117    116&#13;
4.  Construction:   Skilled                    1968     89     91      97    103     94     99      97     94&#13;
5.  Construction:   Foremen                    1968     88     105    127    134    154    165     174    178&#13;
6.  Urban Employees (SEPT)                     1965    121    121            144&#13;
7.  Manufacturing Mean Wage (Central Bank)     1971           100     108    119    119     131    140&#13;
8.        to       (FI3GE/DEICOM)              1959    132    136     149    149    152    161&#13;
9.                 (Sao Paulo: 2/3 Law)        1972                   100                  128&#13;
10.         "       (Sao Paulo: DIESSE)         1961            92                                   97&#13;
11.                              *' (with FGV   1961           104                                  121&#13;
deflator)&#13;
12.  Car Industry                               1966    114    113     124    129    127    130&#13;
13.  Basic Industries (ABDIB)                   1971           100     108    119    119    131     140&#13;
Note:  All series deflated by Rio COL (adjusted upwards in 1973) unless otherwise indicated.&#13;
Line&#13;
1-5:   See Appendix on Wage Statistics.&#13;
6:   Law of 2/3, S PT, Ministry of Labor.&#13;
7:   Bolet.n do Barnco Central do Brasil.&#13;
8:   Mean remuneration of plant workers in manufacturing (includes plant supervisors and&#13;
foremen) ob..ained from industrial surveys.&#13;
9:   A weighted average of mean industry wages obtained from R. Macedo, Emprego e Salario&#13;
No Ciclo Economico 1972/75, Programa de Estudos, Secretaria de Emprego e Salario do MTG,&#13;
FIPE.&#13;
10:   DIESSE.  Deflated by DIESSE cost of living index.&#13;
12:   ANFAVEA.   Cited by Suplicy [1978).   DeflAted by FIPE/USP cost of living index.&#13;
13:   Conluntura Economica.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 95 -&#13;
The many questions that surround wage and price statistics make&#13;
it difficult to arrive at precise conclusions regarding the extent of&#13;
income growth in the important occupational categories covered by those&#13;
series. It does not seem plausible, however, that the variety of evidence&#13;
that has been cited on income trends in different regions and.occupations&#13;
.and sectors is providing a uniformly distorted picture, nor that the degree&#13;
of distortion would alter the broad conclusions cited above, i.e., that&#13;
real wages.and incomes in most employment categories have been growing at&#13;
significant rates, particularly since 1968.&#13;
The trend in rural wages is made plausible by the relationship&#13;
between regional farm incomes and agricultural productivity (Table 13).&#13;
And, as suggested by these data, the trend in wages may not capture the full&#13;
extent of income growth generated by rising productivity, since incomes may have&#13;
been affected also by increased opportunities for work during the year, and for&#13;
primary and secondary earners in both rural and urban.areas. The close&#13;
association between the trends in rural wage rate and farm productivity may&#13;
be seen in the following figures. An index of agricultural value added&#13;
in Brazil, deflated by the cost of living index to reflect consumer purchasing&#13;
power moves as follows: 1959=100, 1970=97, 1975=172, 1977=223. The rural&#13;
casual wage shown in Table 14 follows the same pattern closely: little&#13;
change during the sixties; sharp increase between 1970-1975. The falling&#13;
off in the rural wage since 1975 suggests that it was the exceptional&#13;
combination of an urban boom with sharp growth in agricultural value added&#13;
that generated so strong a response in wages, and that the slowing down of&#13;
urban growth has reduced pressure on the supply of rural labor.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 96 -&#13;
Table 15: COMPARISON OF DEFLATORS&#13;
Indices                      Index of&#13;
FGV              DIESSE           DIESSE.FGV&#13;
(Rio c.o.l.)&#13;
1964              100               100                100&#13;
1966              234               254                109&#13;
1971             673                761                113&#13;
1974           1,273              1,533                120&#13;
1977 (Dec.)    3,407              4,885                143&#13;
Index for 1974&#13;
Real Wage Rate Indices                   Deflator&#13;
(1968--'100)                        FGV              DIESSE&#13;
Sao Paulo:  Daily farm labor        150                125&#13;
Rest Brazil:   "    "     "         159                133&#13;
Sources:  1.  DIESSE, Dez Anos de Politica Salarial.    Measures&#13;
price changes for a typical consumption basket of&#13;
workers in Sao Paulo.&#13;
2.  FGV:   (Fundaca"o Getulio Vargas), Conjuntura, Corrected&#13;
for 1973 as explained in note to Appendix    Table II1.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 97 -&#13;
This review of statistical evidence on wage differentials, changing&#13;
employment structure, and wage trends has found evidence of widespread&#13;
income growth resulting from both movement to better jobs and rising incomes&#13;
within categories of employment. (Table 16 provides some corroboratory&#13;
evidence: it shows the substantial growth in the ownership of durables&#13;
1/&#13;
and use of electricity.) The data are stronger on the shift component of&#13;
income growth than on wage rates. Shifts in employment have clearly&#13;
contributed to income growth at many levels, including the poorest. The&#13;
wage trends also support the hypothesis suggested by other data reviewed&#13;
above, that income growth amongst poorer groups accelerated after 1970.&#13;
A proper statistical disaggregation of the sources of income growth would&#13;
perhaps find that mobility and employment change contributed more to&#13;
income growth during the intercensal decade than did rising wages, but&#13;
that the independent contribution of wage increases to income growth rose.&#13;
after 1970.&#13;
1/ See John Wells, "The Diffusion of Durables in Brazil and Its Implications&#13;
for Recent Controversies Concerning Brazilian Development," Cambridge&#13;
Journal of Economics 1 (3): 259-79. Wells argues that the growth in&#13;
consumption of durables was much broader in terms of income groups than&#13;
was believed.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 98 -&#13;
Table 16: PROPORTION OF HOUSEHOLDS OWNING DURABLES&#13;
1960      1970       1972     1974/75     1976&#13;
Brazil&#13;
Refrigerator           12        26         31        36         42&#13;
TV                      5         24        32        39         47&#13;
Electric Light         39        48        N.A.      N.A.        63&#13;
Radio                  35         59        73        69         76&#13;
Northeast&#13;
Refrigerator            3          9        11        13         17&#13;
TV                      0.3        8        10        13         18&#13;
Electric Light         16        23        N.A.      N.A.        34&#13;
Radio                  12        35         45        51         59&#13;
Sources: 1960 and 1970 Censuses; 1972-1976 PNAD; ENDEF.&#13;
N.A.:- Not available.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 99 -&#13;
VI. THE EXTENT OF POVERTY IN 1974/75&#13;
An approximate measure of the size and regional distribution of&#13;
poverty is presented in Table 16 using ENDEF. The main purpose of identi-&#13;
fying the poorest group in the population is, of course, to orient the&#13;
location and design of government efforts. The figures&#13;
also provide a benchmark for measuring progress in the reduction&#13;
of Doverty. These purposes can be served by the arbitrarily&#13;
defined poverty line use here. A further contribution could be made by&#13;
estimating an absolute poverty line based on nutritional requirements,&#13;
though more research is needed on the various dimensions of the relation-&#13;
ship between income levels and basic needs.&#13;
The publication of partial results of the national household&#13;
expenditure survey of 1974-75 (ENDEF) provides a      more reliable basis&#13;
for a measure of poverty than previously available statistics. As noted&#13;
above, the omission of both money and non-monetary income weakens the&#13;
value of the Census and PNAD as measures of income levels among the very&#13;
poor.&#13;
The poverty line chosen here - two Rio minimum wages per family&#13;
US$260 per capita - identifies 27% of the population as&#13;
poor.  A crude adjustment for regional cost of living differences was&#13;
carried out.   The regional distribution of these families corresponds to&#13;
common notions regarding Brazil: 61% of the poor are rural, and one half&#13;
are in the Northeast. A finding that is less generally known is that&#13;
almost three quarters of the urban poor are in smaller cities and towns&#13;
rather than in metropolitan areas. More precise measures would modify&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 100 -&#13;
Table 17: THF. EXTENT OF POVERTY: FAMILIES UNDER&#13;
TWO MINIMUM WAGES:/1 1974-1975&#13;
Total      Percent         Number   Regional Distri-&#13;
Regions               Families    Poor in          Poor    bution of Pcverty&#13;
('000)      Region          ('000)    (Percentage)&#13;
Rio                    2,169         11              244          4&#13;
Metropolitan           1,784          9              163          3&#13;
Other Urban              209         14               28          1&#13;
Rural                    176         30               53          1&#13;
Sao Paulo             4,168           9             385           7&#13;
Metropolitan           2,078          5              103          2&#13;
Other Urban            1,413         11             156           3&#13;
Rural                    677         19             126           2&#13;
South                 3,548          15             520           9&#13;
Metropolitan             601          8              48           1&#13;
Other Urban            1,162         13             147           3&#13;
Rural                  1,785         18             325           6&#13;
Minas G. &amp; E.S.        2,592         30              788         14&#13;
Metropolitan             367         14              52           1&#13;
Other Urban            1,034         25             260           5&#13;
Rural                  1,191         40             476           9&#13;
Northeast              5.791         52           3,008          54&#13;
Metropolitan             844         27             231           4&#13;
Other Urban            1,673         44             731          14&#13;
Rural                  3,274         62           2,046          37&#13;
North &amp; D.F.           2,032         30             619          11&#13;
Metropolitan             156          4                6          -&#13;
Other Urban              918         25             230           4&#13;
Rural                    958         40             383           7&#13;
Total                 20,300         27                         100&#13;
Metropolitan           5,830         10             603          11&#13;
Other Urban            6,409         24           1,554          28&#13;
Rural                  8,061         42           3,409          61&#13;
/1 Adjusted for regional cost of living differences. Income concept&#13;
is total family expenditure including nonmonetary and capital (real&#13;
estate, vehicles, stocks) expenditures. (From ENDEF, Table 7.)&#13;
Basis for poverty line was the highest regional minimum wage in&#13;
August 1974, or Cr.$376.80 per month. Adjustment for regional cost&#13;
of living differences is an arbitrary approximation. Differences&#13;
were assumed to equal 30% between rural and Metropolitan and 20%&#13;
between rural and other urban. The poverty line is Cr.$9,000 per&#13;
year (US$1,300) in Metropolitan areas, Cr.$7,500 in other urban areas&#13;
and Cr.$6,923 in rural areas. Assuming an average family of 5, this&#13;
amounts to a poverty line of US$260 per capita in metropolitan areas.&#13;
/2 Data for Ncrth are approximations guided by PNAD 1972 data on families&#13;
by income class and by regional unskilled wage differentials.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 101 -&#13;
these findings. The most important improvement that is required is the&#13;
estimation of more accurate regional cost of living differences.&#13;
A major finding here is that income levels of the poor have been&#13;
underestimated in the past. Estimates, based on PNAD 1972 money income only&#13;
data, for instance, place 62% of all households below the two minimum wage&#13;
line. A recent ECLA/IBRD study, using PNAD 1972 total income figures and&#13;
an almost identical poverty line, estimates that 47% of Brazilian families&#13;
were poor in 1972, a figure substantially higher than the 27% obtained&#13;
1/&#13;
from ENDEF.    Using a lower poverty line of US$130 per capita, which is&#13;
closer to figures normally used in other countries, would reduce the poverty&#13;
group to less than 15% of the population.&#13;
The most thorough previous measurement of poverty levels and&#13;
characteristics was carried out by Meesook and Fishlow for 1960, using&#13;
2/&#13;
Census data.    Their poverty line was equal to one Northeast urban minimum&#13;
3/&#13;
wage, or US$130 in 1974 prices.    After adjusting for non-monetary income,&#13;
they estimate that 31% of all families in 1960 fell below that level. If&#13;
we apply the same real poverty line to the ENDEF data, the share of the&#13;
4/&#13;
poor is in the order of 15%, or half of the 1960 level.     Since there is&#13;
a strong presumption that ENDEF figures are better approximations to true&#13;
1/  Oscar Altimir, CEPAL/BIRF, La Dimensioni de la Pobreza on America Latina&#13;
(March 1978). The poverty line was Cr.$890 per capita per year which,&#13;
in August 1974 prices, amounts to Cr.$9,700 vs. Cr.$9,000 used here.&#13;
2/  Albert Fishlow, "Brazilian Size Distribution of Income," AER 1972.&#13;
3/ Applying the Guanabara Retail Price index, plus an upward adjustment&#13;
for the rate of inflation in 1973 which government spokesmen now admit&#13;
to be closer to 22.5% than the official figure of 12.6%.&#13;
4/1 Reflated to 1974 prices using the Guanabara CQst of Living Index.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 102 -&#13;
income than Census-based estimates, this inconsistency has only two possible&#13;
explanations. One is that even the corrected Fishlow4Meesook income figures&#13;
are severe underestimates. Another is that poverty has been reduced. Since&#13;
it would require an implausibly large underestimation to explain the gap,&#13;
it seems probable that the much lower poverty share in 1974-75 is the result,&#13;
at least in part, of a real reduction- in poverty.&#13;
The discovery of higher income levels at the bottom of the&#13;
distribution is more a measure of the inaccuracy of earlier statistics than&#13;
of the adequacy of those income levels. There is much direct evidence on&#13;
the high levels of malnutrition, mortality rates and severely deficient&#13;
services and living conditions that correspond to income levels in the&#13;
vicinity of two minimum wages. In part this reflects high prices in Brazil&#13;
by international standards. More important perhaps is the fact that some&#13;
aspects of family welfare in Brazil have lagged behind the growth of money&#13;
incomes. This is most obvious with respect to the lag in public services&#13;
and relatively high levels of malnutrition, but it may also involve aspects&#13;
of welfare that are difficult to quantify, such as low levels of comunal&#13;
support and resources, and the costs associated with high degrees of&#13;
individual mobility.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 103 -&#13;
APPENDIX&#13;
Note on Internal Terms of Trade&#13;
An important factor in distribution change is the trend in internal&#13;
terms of trade between agriculture and the rest of the economy. Since the&#13;
poorer segments of the population include a high percentage of rural families,&#13;
the relationship between prices received by farmers for their products and&#13;
prices they pay for purchasing goods and services from the non-agricultural&#13;
sectors is significant for income distribution. The following table shows&#13;
three series: (a) changes in the relationship between wholesale prices&#13;
for agricultural output excluding export crops, and wholesale prices for&#13;
industrial goods; and (b) changes in the relationship between wholesale prices&#13;
for agricultural output excluding export crops, and wholesale prices for&#13;
textiles, shoes and clothing, three items of particular importance in the&#13;
budget of farmers who grow much of the food they consume. A third index (c)&#13;
shows changes in the relationship between wholesale prices for all agricultural&#13;
products (including export crops), and wholesale prices for textiles, shoes&#13;
and clothing. The table suggests that terms of trade have turned in favor&#13;
of agricultural products (whether food producers for the domestic market or&#13;
export producers) during the 1970s. While until the 1970s it took at least&#13;
one unit of agricultural production to buy a pair of shoes or a dress, it&#13;
now only takes 50 to 60% as much agricultural output to purchase these&#13;
manufactured goods.  For industrial goods as a whole the reduction is less&#13;
marked, but still in the order of 25% between 1970 and 1977. These trends&#13;
suggest that agricultural producers (who include a large proportion of&#13;
small poor farmers) have improved their purchasing power per unit produced&#13;
during the 1970s.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 104 -&#13;
Indicators of Internal Terms of Trade&#13;
(1965-67 = 100)&#13;
(a)                  (b)             (c)&#13;
1944-1950&#13;
average                    83.1                 77.9            82.7&#13;
1951-1959&#13;
average                    99.4                 93.9           112.0&#13;
1960                   101.2                 95.6            99.9&#13;
1961                    96.9                 85.0            87.7&#13;
1962                   107.2                 96.7            99.4&#13;
1963                   100.0                 91.4            91.0.&#13;
1964                    99.8                 96.1           104.3&#13;
1965                    91.0                 92.4            97.2&#13;
1966                   103.5                103.3           102.3&#13;
1967                   103.5                102.4           100.8&#13;
1968                    92.0                 89.3            88.7&#13;
1969                    94.4                102.8           100.6&#13;
1970                    99.6                108.6           111.0&#13;
1971                   108.9                117.7           117.3&#13;
1972                   112.8                121.4           123.1&#13;
1973                   113.4                119.8           125.4&#13;
1974                   112.3                135.8           143.6&#13;
1975                   111.5                159.8           163.2&#13;
1976                   120.5                165.7           182.4&#13;
1977                   124.1                178.5           204.8&#13;
Source:  Conjuntura Economica (Fundayao Getulio Vargas).&#13;
This impression is confirmed by looking at the relationship be-&#13;
tween farmgate prices for crops since 1970. These increased much faster&#13;
between 1970 and 1977 than either the Rio de Janeiro cost of living index or&#13;
its clothing and apparel component, as shown in the following table.&#13;
Furthermore, as the table shows, the improvement in terms of trade for the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 105 -&#13;
rural sector is not confined to export products but includes a wide range&#13;
of agricultural and livestock products. 1/&#13;
Increase in farm-gate prices as a multiple of increases&#13;
in (a) the Rio cost of living index and (b) its apparel component&#13;
(1970-1977) /1&#13;
(a)                (b)&#13;
Farm Products&#13;
Cotton                                    1.6                2.7&#13;
Peanuts                                   1.7                2.8&#13;
Rice                                      1.1                1.7&#13;
Bananas                                   1.7                2.9&#13;
Potatoes                                  1.3                2.2&#13;
Cocoa                                     4.0                6.7&#13;
Coffee                                    3.2                5.3&#13;
Sugar                                     1.2                2.0&#13;
Beans                                     1.4                2.4&#13;
Tobacco                                   1.7                2.7&#13;
Oranges                                   1.2                1.9&#13;
Manioc                                    3.5                5.9&#13;
Corn                                      1.0                1.7&#13;
Wheat                                     0.9                1.6&#13;
Beef                                      1.1                1.9&#13;
Hogs                                      1.3                2.1&#13;
Chicken                                   0.9                1.6&#13;
Milk                                      1.4                2.3&#13;
All Crops                                 2.3                3.9&#13;
Livestock Products                        1.2                2.0&#13;
All Farm Products                         2.1                3.5&#13;
Source: Conjuntura Economica.&#13;
/1   The cost of living in this table has been corrected for the likely&#13;
1973 under-estimate.&#13;
1/   The food and non-food components of the Rio de Janeiro cost of living&#13;
index have moved as follows between 1970 and 1977:&#13;
c.o.l.        Food       Non-food&#13;
1970:                   100           100          100&#13;
1977:                   529           590           486&#13;
Thus, if computed only over the non-food component of the c.o.1. index&#13;
the figures in column (a) in the table would-be increased by about&#13;
9 percent.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 106 -&#13;
In sum, the trend in the domestic terms of trade in favor of agri-&#13;
culture during the 1970's is fairly clear. The relationship between that&#13;
trend and rural incomes, particularly incomes of the poor rural population,&#13;
is, of course, very complex, and needs much further exploration.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 107 -&#13;
Appendix on Wage Statistics&#13;
The statistical series underlying the discussion of wage trends&#13;
are shown in Appendix Tables I to V. They contain the following information:&#13;
Appendix Table I: daily wage rate of unskilled rural laborers by states&#13;
except frontier states, for the period December 1968 - December 1977.&#13;
These rates are shown in current cruzeiros as well as in cruzeiros of&#13;
December 1977. States not shown on this table are in Appendix Table II,&#13;
as well as averages for all states. The average wage rate for all states&#13;
in Appendix   Table II reflects the 1972-76 weights of the Fundacao Getulio&#13;
Vargas, the source of these data.&#13;
Appendix Table II:   daily wage rates based on an 8-hour day for construction&#13;
workers in the principal city of each state. The table also shows the&#13;
legal urban minimum wage based on 27 days per month. 1/ Wages for&#13;
"lunskilled" workers are those for serventes; they do such jobs as&#13;
excavating without power tools or carrying loads on construction sites.&#13;
Wages for the "semi-skilled" are for armadores who have enough formal&#13;
or on-the-job training to shape and set metal rods into concrete;&#13;
they are the equivalent of skilled workers in manufacturing. Brick-&#13;
layers, painters, carpenters also fall into this category; their wage&#13;
rates are within 12 percent of those for armadores. "Skilled" workers&#13;
in the present context are foremen (mestres de obra) who typically have&#13;
either completed secondary school plus 2-3 years' vocational training,&#13;
or have an equivalent informal training. They are the equivalent of&#13;
technicians in manufacturing industry. The table also includes wage&#13;
1/   The legal wage is defined in Cr$ per month.   It is unclear whether the&#13;
daily rate should be based on 30 or 27 days, but since the data are used&#13;
principally for trends the possible error is immaterial.-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 108 -&#13;
statistics for Brazil, with and without Sao Paulo. These averages are&#13;
weighted, in the case of construction and in the case of the legal minimum&#13;
wage, by the 1970 population of the major cities listed in the Table.&#13;
Appendix Table III: the same as the previous table, but with all wage&#13;
rates brought forward into December 1977 cruzeiros. After checking&#13;
various regional deflators it was found that they do not differ enough&#13;
to warrant regional deflations. Nor is the difference between food&#13;
prices and other prices large or consistent enough to warrant separate&#13;
deflation. Therefore all current wage rates in this report are de-&#13;
flated by the Rio de Janeiro cost of living index, with an upward&#13;
adjustment of the rate of inflation in 1973, from the official figure&#13;
-of 12.6% to 22.5%, which government spokesmen now admit to be closer&#13;
to the true value for that year.&#13;
Appendix Table IV: the Fundacao Getulio Vargas collects from the agri-&#13;
cultural extension'service-statistics on monthly wages of permanent.&#13;
farm workers in each municipio. The table shows the trend in the&#13;
relationship between those monthly (money) wages on one hand and&#13;
daily wage rates for casual rural laborers on the other for 14 states&#13;
and Brazil (minus Sao Paulo and the frontier states), for the period&#13;
1966-1977.&#13;
Appendix Table V: Agricultural wage trend for the state of Sao Paulo.&#13;
The Instituto de Economia Agricola of the state of Sao Paulo collects&#13;
wage statistics through an annual survey of agricultural establishments&#13;
and thus provides an independent check to the FGV wages reported by&#13;
extensionists. Source for 1948-1968 data is IEA, "Modernization of&#13;
Agriculture in the State of Sao Paulo," 1973.   The figures after 1969&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 109 -&#13;
are drawn from earlier attachment Tables, assuming that the relation-&#13;
ship between December wages and annual averages obtains for 1975,&#13;
1976 and 1977. The deflator is the Sao Paulo cost of living index&#13;
adjusted in the same way as in Appendix Table III for inflation&#13;
in 1973. The wages concern only money income. Sundays and holidays&#13;
are incorporated in the attached series (which through 1969 is based&#13;
on monthly original aggregations). Therefore the daily wage between&#13;
1948 and 1963-64 is likely to be overstated. The series is shown in&#13;
graphic form in Figure 3 of the main text.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Appendix Table I&#13;
Daily Rural Unskilled Wages 1968-77&#13;
(in Cruzeiros)&#13;
Espirito      Sta.&#13;
Maranhao    Ceara   Paraiba    RGN     Alagoas   Sergipe    Santo      Catarina    RGS&#13;
Daily rural unskilled wages&#13;
1968          2.45     1.81     2.06      2.40     2.22      2.60        2.66       4.15      3.92&#13;
1969         2.71      2.30     2.40      2.58     2.42      3.00        3.28       4.89      4.89&#13;
1970         3.77      2.57     3.16      2.90     3.49      3.44        4.05       6.09      5.95&#13;
1971         4.63      3.62     4.07      3.50     3.81      4.61        4.85       7.42      7.08&#13;
1972         5.83      4.27     4.73      4.52     4.68      5.13        6.G1       9.07      8.94&#13;
1973          7.70     6.16     6.98      6.23     6.98      6.64        9.02      12.54     12.61&#13;
1974        11.64     10.65    13.27     10.79    12.55     13.10       14.51      20.25     17.76&#13;
1975         16.72    13.65    16.01     15.82    16.60     20.03       20.70      28.90     24.46&#13;
1976        23.12     19.56    23.46     21.49    24.42     23.90       30.65      38.17     34.08&#13;
1977        30.00     29.00    33.00     30.00    37.00     34.00       47.00      53.00     47.00&#13;
Daily rural unskilled wages deflated by C.O.L. index.&#13;
1968         20.42    15.08    17.17     20.00    18.50     21.67       22.17       34.58    32.67&#13;
1969        18.19     15.44    16.11     17.32    16.24     20.13       22.01      32.82     32.82&#13;
1970        20.94     14.28    17.56     16.11    19.39     19.11       22.50      33.83     33.06&#13;
1971        21.84     17-08    19.20     16.51    17.97     21.75       22.88      35.00     33.40&#13;
1972        24.09     17.64    19.55     18.68    19.34     21.20       26.07      37.48     36.94&#13;
1973        25.83     20.66    23.41     20.90    23.41     22.27       30.25      42.06     42.29&#13;
1974        29.07     26.60    33.14     26.95    31.34     32.72       36.24      50.57     44.35&#13;
1975        31.88     26.03    30.53     30.16    31.65     38.19       39.47      55.10     46.64&#13;
1976        30.40     25.72    30.84     28.25    32.11     31.42       40.30      50.19     44.81&#13;
1977        27.57     26.65    30.33     27.57    34.00     31.25       43.19      48.71     43.19&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- ill -&#13;
Appendix       Table II                              (paRs I of 2)&#13;
DIiy Vaga&#13;
(in Cruzeiroa)&#13;
crNsmRicrloN&#13;
Urban&#13;
Bural Unskilled        Skilled    Fre     n      Mlnlmm Wane&#13;
Natal (RON)&#13;
1968         1.97         2.64        4.00          *0.          2.93&#13;
1969         2.27         3.28        4.40         IA.00         3.614&#13;
1970         2.95        4.16         5.44         30.40        4.62&#13;
1971         3.65        5.04         6.80         30.40        5.6o&#13;
1972         4.89        6.08         8.32         30.40        6.76&#13;
1973         7.16        6.80        10.00         32.00        7.91&#13;
1974        13.13        10.72       16.00         32.00        9.87&#13;
1975        14.58       12.56        24.00         72.00       13.96&#13;
1976        21.51       21.04        40.00        132.00       20.18&#13;
1977        34.00       26.48        46.00        200.00       29.16&#13;
Salvador (Bahia)&#13;
1968         2.63        3.36         6.80         22.00         3.71&#13;
1969         3.03        4.00         9.60         24.00        4.44&#13;
1970         4.32        4.80        12.00         32.24         5.33&#13;
1971         5.01        5.76        13.60         52.00        6.40&#13;
1972         5.84        6.88        16.00         48.00         7.64&#13;
1973         8.33        8.00        17.60         80.00.       8.89&#13;
1974        14.83       10.80        23.20        123.20        10.93&#13;
1975        20.12       19.20        36.00        160.00       15.47&#13;
1976        28.10       24.00        47.20        240.00       22.31&#13;
1977        37.00       36.00        64.00        318.00       32.18&#13;
Rio de Janeiro (Rio)&#13;
1968         3.07        4.32         9.60         18.80        4.80&#13;
1969         3.54        5.20        11.20         24.00        5.78&#13;
1970         4.43        6.24        12.00         26.80        6.93&#13;
1971         5.16        7.52        14.80         39.84        8.36&#13;
1972         6.54        8.96        19.76         43.20        9.96&#13;
1973         9.16       10.40        21.60         60.00       11.56&#13;
1974        13.37       14.40        26.40         93.60        13.96&#13;
1975        19.98        20.00       36.00        120.00       19.73&#13;
1976        28.97       32.00        54.00        184.00       28. 44&#13;
1977        44.00       48.00        80.00        320.00       40.98&#13;
San Paulo (S.P.) 1/&#13;
S           1968         3.69        4.80         9.60         18.00        4.80&#13;
1969         4.36        5.20        11.52         18.40        5.78&#13;
1970         5.21        6.24        12.08         20.00        6.93&#13;
1971         6.61        7.60        14.80         26.56        *.36&#13;
1972         8.01        8.96        17.60         53.28        9.96&#13;
1973        11.18       12.00        24.80         55.84       11.56&#13;
1974        18.60       19.20        30.40         96.00       13.96&#13;
1975        25.00       24.00        38.40        132.00       19.73&#13;
1976        38.00       33.60        52.00        198.00        25.44&#13;
1977        59.00       48.00        72.00        256.32       40.98&#13;
Curitiba (Parana)&#13;
1968         3.42        4.16         6.88          8.24        4.36&#13;
1969         4.23        5.12         8.56         *2.e0        5.24&#13;
1970         5.32        6.32        10.96         13.12        6.31&#13;
1971         7.03        7.76        13.60         17.60        7.73&#13;
1972         7.69        9.36        16.32         21.36        9.24&#13;
1973        10.73       10.96        19.92         27.68        10.67&#13;
1974        16.74       16.00        26.00         48.00       12.98&#13;
1975        26.45       22.40        40.00         73.60        18.31&#13;
1976        32.52       32.00        59.60        112.00        26.40&#13;
1977        46.00       40.00        76.00        186.80       38.04&#13;
Balo Pori20nee (binas Cernia)&#13;
1968         2.72        4.16         7.12         14.40        4.62&#13;
1969         3.27        4.96         8.80         17.60        5.51&#13;
1970         3.86        5.92        10.08         20.24        6.58&#13;
1971         4.95        7.20        11.28         28.00        8.00&#13;
1972         6.12        8.96        12.32         28.80        9.96&#13;
1973        10.12       10.40        20.00         56.00       11.56&#13;
1974        15.17       14.40        24.00         64.00       13.96&#13;
1975        20.71       24.00        34.00        112.00       19.73&#13;
1976        28.23       35.20        56.00        176.00       28.44&#13;
1977        41.00       48.00        76.40        280.00       I0.98&#13;
I/ iaRe rates for 1975, 1976 and 1977 are for December. Earlier ratpet are annual rstes convertd to&#13;
December rates on tne basis of the :wlatlonship betwen anymal and December rat-s in 107c&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
(paRe 2 of 2)&#13;
Appendix Table II&#13;
Daily Wages - (cont'd)&#13;
(in Cruzeiros)&#13;
CONSTRUCTION&#13;
____________________________  Urban&#13;
Rural      Unskilled      Skilled       Foremen    Minimum Wage&#13;
Brazil (excl. Sao Paulo)&#13;
1968         2.64          4.05         7.90         16.28          4.57&#13;
1969         3.14          4.87         9.67         20.32          5.50&#13;
1970         3.86          5.86        11.06         24.11          6.60&#13;
1971         4.81          7.10        13.13         35.07          7.97&#13;
1972         5.86          8.59        16.13         36.48          9.57&#13;
1973         8.65          9.97        19.89         56.86         11.10&#13;
1974        13.97         13.92        24.77         81.42         13.45&#13;
1975        19.33         21.10        36.06        116.25         19.00&#13;
1976        26.48         31.35        53.75        179.39         27.40&#13;
1977        36.33         44.42        74.78        287.03         39.48&#13;
Brazil (cinc. Sao Paulo)&#13;
1968         2.79          4.36         8.60          17.00         4.67&#13;
1969          3.31         5.01        10.44          19.43         5.62&#13;
1970         4.05          6.02        11.48          22.41         6.74&#13;
1971         5.06          7.31        13.82          31.55         8.14&#13;
1972         6.16          8.74        16.74          43.44         9.73&#13;
1973         9.00         10.81        21.92          56.44        11.30&#13;
1974        14.62         16.10        27.10          87.45        13.67&#13;
1975        20.12         22.30        37.03         122.78        19.32&#13;
1976        28,09         32.28        53.03        187.10         27.84&#13;
1977        39.50         45.90        73.63        274.35         40.12&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-  113    -                 (a e 1 Of 2)&#13;
Appendix T-,;ie III&#13;
Daily Wages Deflated by the C.O.L. index&#13;
(in 1977 Cruzeiros)&#13;
CONSTRIICTION&#13;
-rban&#13;
Rua      Unskilled       Skilled       Foremen___         inims&#13;
Natal (RGN)&#13;
1968         16.42          22.00         33.33           U.67         24.42&#13;
1969         15.23         22.01          29.53         1C7.38         24.43&#13;
1970         16.39         23.11          30.22         168.89         2&lt;.67&#13;
1971         17.22         23.77          32.08         143.40&#13;
1972         20.21         25.12          34.38         125.62         27.9,-&#13;
1973         24.01         22.81         33.54          107.33         26.53&#13;
1974         32.79         26.77          39.96          79.92         24.65&#13;
1975         27.80         23.95         45.76          137.28         26.6i&#13;
1976         28.28         27.66         52.59          173.54         26.53&#13;
1977         31.25         24.34         42.27          183.80         26.80&#13;
Salvador (Bania)&#13;
1968         21.92         28.00          56.67         183.33         31.08&#13;
1969         20.34         26.85          64.43         161.07         29.80&#13;
1970         24.00         26.67          66.67         179.11         29.61&#13;
1971         23.63         27.17          64.15         245.28         30.19&#13;
1972         24.13         28.43          66.12         198.35         31.57&#13;
1973         27.94         26.83         59.02          268.32         29.82&#13;
1974         37.04         26.97         57.93          307.66         27.29&#13;
1975         38.36         36.60         68.56          305.06         29.50&#13;
1976         36.94         31.55         62.06         315.54          29.33&#13;
1977         34.00         33.08         58.82         292.24          29.57&#13;
Rio de Janeiro (Rio)&#13;
1968         25.58         36.00         80.00          156.67         40.00&#13;
1969         23.76         34.90          75.17         161.07         38.79&#13;
1970         24.61         34.67         66.67          148.89         38.50&#13;
1971         24.34        .35.47          69.81         187.92         39.43&#13;
1972         27.02         37.02         81.65          178.51         41.16&#13;
1973         30.72         34.89         72.44          201.24         38.77&#13;
1974         33.39         35.96         65.93          233.75         34.86&#13;
1975         38.09         38.13         68.64          228.79         37.61&#13;
1976         38.08         42.07         70.99          241.91         37.39&#13;
1977         40.44         44.11         73.52          294.08         37.66&#13;
Sao Pa,,In (S.P 1&#13;
1968         30.75         40.00          80.00         150.00         40.00&#13;
1969         29.26         34.90          77.32         123.49         38.79&#13;
1970         28.94         34.67         67.11          111.11         38.50&#13;
1971         31.18         35.85         69.81          125.28         39.43&#13;
1972         33.10         37.02          72.73         220.17         41.16&#13;
1973         37.50         40.25         83.18          187.29         38.77&#13;
1974         46.45         47.94          75.92         239.74         34.86&#13;
1975         47.67         45.76          73.22         251.68         37.61&#13;
1976         49.96         44.18         68.36          260.32         37.39&#13;
1977         54.22         44.11         66.17          235.56         37.66&#13;
Curitiba (Parana)&#13;
1968         28.50         34.67          57.33          68.67         36.33&#13;
1969         28.39         34.36         57.4!           80.54         35.17&#13;
1970         29.56         35.11         60.85           72.89         35.06&#13;
1971         33.16         36.60         64.15           83.02         36.46&#13;
1972         31.78         38.68         67.44           88.26         38.18&#13;
1973         35.99         36.76         66.81           92.84         35.79&#13;
1974         41.81         39.96         64.93          119.87         32.41&#13;
1975         50.43         42.71         76.27          140.33         34.9;&#13;
1976         42.75         42.07         78.35         147.25          34.71&#13;
1977         42.27         36.76         69.84         171.67          34.96&#13;
Belo Horizonte (Minas Gerais)&#13;
1968         22.67         34.67         59.33          120.00         38.50&#13;
1969         21.95         33.29         59.06          118.12         36.98&#13;
1970         21.44         32.88         56.00          112.44         36.56&#13;
1971         23.35         33.96         53.21          132.08         37.74&#13;
1972         25.29         37.02         50.91         119.G1          41.16&#13;
1973         33.94         34.89         67.08         187.83          38.77&#13;
1974         37.88         35.96         59.94         159.82          '* ^&#13;
1975         39.49         45.76         68.64         213.55          37.6i&#13;
1976         37.12         46.28         73.62         Z31.40          37.39&#13;
1977         37.68         44.11         70.21         257.32          37.66&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
(page 2 of 2)&#13;
Appendix Table III&#13;
Daily Wages Deflated by the C.O.L. index - (Cont'd)&#13;
(in 1977 Cruzeiros)&#13;
CONSTRUCTION&#13;
Urban&#13;
Rural       Unskilled    Skilled       Foremen     Minimum Wage&#13;
Brazil (excl. Sao Paulo)&#13;
1968         22.00         33.75        65.83        135.67         38.08&#13;
1969         21.07         32.68        64.90        136.38         36.91&#13;
1970         21.44         32.56        61.44         133.94        36.67&#13;
1971         22.69         33.49        61.93         165.42        37.59&#13;
1972         24.21         35.50        66.65         150.74        39.55&#13;
1973         29.01         33.44        66.71         190.71        37.23&#13;
1974         34.89         34.77        61.86         203.33        33.59&#13;
1975         36.85         40.23        68.75         221.64        36.23&#13;
1976         34.81         41.22        70.67         235.85        36.02&#13;
1977         33.39         40.82        68.72         263.78        36.28&#13;
Brazil (incl. Sao Paulo)&#13;
1968         23.25         36.33        71.67         141.67        38.92&#13;
1969         22.21         33.62        70.07        130.40         37.72&#13;
1970         22.50         33.44        63.78        124.50         37.44&#13;
1971         23.87         34.48        65.19        148.82         38.4o&#13;
1972         25.45         36.12        69.17        179.50         40.21&#13;
1973         30.19         36.25        73.52         189.30        37.90&#13;
1974         36.51         40.21        67.68         218.39        34.14&#13;
1975         38.36         42.52        70.61         234.10        36.83&#13;
1976          36.93        42.44        69.72         245.99        36.60&#13;
1977          36.30        42.18        67.67         252.13        36.87&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 115 -&#13;
Appendix Table IV&#13;
Ratio of wage per mDnth of permanent farm&#13;
workers to wage per day of casual workers&#13;
1966  1967   1968  1969   1970  1971  1972   1973  1974  1975   1976  1977&#13;
Maranhao                       32    28     30    32    30     31    28     29    25    23    23    24&#13;
Ceara                          33    27     31    28    29     27    27    27     24    24    25    25&#13;
Natal (RGN)                    28    29     31    28    29     30    25    25     20    24    23    24&#13;
Paraiba                        28    24     26    27    25     25    25    23     21    20    20    21&#13;
Pernambuco                     25    26     26    28    27     28    26     23    21    19    21    24&#13;
Alagoas                        28    25     26    31    30     34    32     26    22    23    20    19&#13;
Sergipe                        29    26     23    22    26     26    29    32     24    20    22    20&#13;
Bahia                          30    27     27    29    27     27    27    27     21    20    20    21&#13;
Minas Gerais                   31    31     29    27    28     27    27     26    24    24    25    24&#13;
Espirito Santo                 29    28     27    26    27     30    28    25     23    24    25    23&#13;
Rio de Janeiro                 29    27     27    26    29     30    29    29     26    24    25    25&#13;
Parana                         24    26     25    25    26     25    27    26     25    21    23    23&#13;
Santa Catarina                 24    25    24     25    25     23    25    23     19    19   21     21&#13;
R.G.S.                         26    29     26    26    26     28    26.   23     21    20    21    23&#13;
Brazil (excl. Sao Paulo)       30    30     29    29    30     29    29    28     24    24    24    26&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 116 -&#13;
Appendix Table V&#13;
Casual Rural Laborers' Wages, State of Sao Paulo: Daili Rates&#13;
(in 1977 cruzeiros)&#13;
1948        17.28                 1963         16.42&#13;
1949        19.87                 1964         22.29&#13;
1950        22.81                 1965        22.81&#13;
1951        25.75                 1966        19.87&#13;
1952        24.19                 1967        19.35&#13;
1953        21.08                 1968        19.70&#13;
1954        20.56                 1969        18.49&#13;
1955        21.25                 1970        18.66&#13;
1956        20.39                 1971        19.53&#13;
1957        19.35                 1972        20.05&#13;
1958        18.84                 1973        22.39&#13;
1959        17.11                 1974        29.54&#13;
1960        16.59                 1975        30.65&#13;
1961        16.42                 1976        34.28&#13;
1962        16.24                 1977        37.96&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
RECENT PAPERS IN THIS SERIES&#13;
No.                    TITLE OF PAPER                           AUTHOR&#13;
322    Ability in Pre-Schoolers, Earnings, and               R. Grawe&#13;
Home-Environment&#13;
323    Priorities in Education:   Pre-School;                 M. Smilansky&#13;
Evidence and Conclusions                               (consultant)&#13;
324    Tropical Root Crops and Rural Development             T. Goering&#13;
325    Costs and Scale of Bus Services                       A.A. Walters&#13;
326    Social and Cultural Dimensions of Tourism              R. Noronha&#13;
(consultant)&#13;
327    Investment in Indian Education:   Uneconomic?         S. Heyneman&#13;
328    Nutrition and Food Needs in Developing                0. Knudsen&#13;
Countries                                             P.L. Scandizzo&#13;
329    The Changing International Division of                B. Balassa&#13;
Labor in Manufactured Goods&#13;
330    Application of Shadow Pricing to Country              L. Squire&#13;
Economic Analysis with an Illustration from           I.M.D. Little&#13;
Pakistan&#13;
331    A Survey of the Fertilizer Sector in Ir.dia           B. Bumb (consultant)&#13;
332    Monitoring and Evaluation in the PIDER                M. Cernea&#13;
Rural Development Project - Mexico&#13;
333    Determinants of Private Industrial                    A. Pinell-Siles&#13;
Investment in India&#13;
334    The "Graduation" Issue in Trade Policy                I. Frank&#13;
Toward LDCs                                            (consultant)&#13;
335    Balancing Trickle Down and Basic Needs                M. Selowsky&#13;
Strategies: Income Distribution Issues&#13;
in Large Middle-Income Countries with&#13;
Special Reference to Latin America&#13;
336    Labor Force, Employment and Labor Markets             L. Squire&#13;
in the Course of Economic Development&#13;
337    The Population of Thailand:   Its Growth              S. Cochrane&#13;
and Welfare&#13;
338    Capital Market Imperfections and Economic             V.V. Bhatt&#13;
Development                                           A.R. Roe&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-2-&#13;
5No.                   TITLE OF PAPER                           AUTP.OR&#13;
339    Behavior of Foodgrain Production                       J. Sarma&#13;
and Consumption in India, 1960-77&#13;
340    Electric Power Pricing Policy                         NI. Munasinghe&#13;
341    State Intervention in the Industrialization           A. Chcksi&#13;
of Developing Countries: Selected Issues&#13;
342    Policies for Efficient and Equitable                  J. Linn&#13;
Growth of Citites in Developing Countries&#13;
343    The Capital Goods Sector in LDCs:   A Case             J. Datta Mitra&#13;
for State Intervention?&#13;
344    International Technology Transfer:   Issues            F. Stewart&#13;
and Policy Options&#13;
345    Family Planning Programs:   An Evaluation              R. Cuca&#13;
of Experience&#13;
346    Prospects for Traditional and Non-                     D. Hughart&#13;
Conventional Energy Sources in&#13;
Developing Countries&#13;
347-   National Urbanization Policies in Developing           B. Renaud&#13;
Countries&#13;
348    Private Direct Foreign Investment in                   K. Billerbeck&#13;
Developing Countries                                  Y. Yasugi (consultants)&#13;
349    Adjustment Policies and Problems in                    M4. Wolf&#13;
Developing Countries&#13;
350    Energy Options and Policy Issues in                    T. Byer&#13;
Developing Countries                                   D. Fallen-Bailey&#13;
351    Growth and Equity in Semi-Industrialized               J. Bergsnan&#13;
Countries&#13;
352    Capital Flows and Developing Country Debt              J. Katz&#13;
353    Trade Policy for Developing Countries                 D. Reesing&#13;
354    Development Problems of Mineral-Exporting             G. Nankani&#13;
Countries&#13;
355    The Global Framework                                   R. Cheetham, S. Gupta&#13;
A. Sch-wartz&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1555087">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1979/09/1555087/distribution-income-brazil
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1979/09/1555087/distribution-income-brazil</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1979/09/1555087/distribution-income-brazil</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/07/26/000178830_9810190340335/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/07/26/000178830_9810190340335/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2003-07-26T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1979-09-30T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            The distribution of income in Brazil
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            This paper asks whether growth has been
            widely shared and, in particular, whether it has raised the
            absolute incomes of the poorest groups in Brazil. The review
            of evidence covers the period 1960-1976/77. New sources, in
            particular a national household budget survey (ENDEF) and
            the 1976 household employment survey, have made possible
            both a re-examination of previous sources and a clearer
            separation in the analysis of income trends before and
            during the fast growth period between 1968 and 1974. There
            is no set of comparable and accurate sources that provide a
            definite answer to questions regarding income trends since
            1960. There is, however, a great deal of fragmentary and
            imperfect evidence which, when examined as a whole, suggests
            that: (i) the extent of income growth throughout the
            population, including many in the poorest groups, has been
            underestimated in previous studies; and (ii) the rate of
            poverty reduction was faster during the rapid growth years, 1968-1974.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            The distribution of income in Brazil
        </docna>
        <display_title>The distribution of income in Brazil</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1979/09/1555087/distribution-income-brazil</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Poverty Impact Evaluation,Inequality,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Economic Conditions and Volatility</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Poverty Reduction</teratopic>
        <count>Brazil</count>
        <authors>
            <author>PFEFFERMANN, G.</author>
            <author>WEBB, R.</author>
        </authors>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>South America!$!80469</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>America!$!80450</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_9810190340335</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>(Historic)Macro/non-trade</subsc>
        <admreg>Latin America &amp; Caribbean,Latin America &amp; Caribbean</admreg>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 356</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Poverty Reduction</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Economic Policy</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Educational level; Household budgets;
            Household income; Household surveys; Income levels; Per
            capita income; Wage rate; Wages
            absolute poverty,agricultural
            output,agriculture,assets,average
            income,benchmark,benchmarks,cost of living,cost of living
            index,debt,Deflators,Development Economics,disposable
            income,dividends,dual economy,earnings
            levels,ecology,Economic Censuses,Economic
            Development,Economic Review,employment,Expenditures,factor
            income,Family Budget,Family Budget Surveys,farms,GDP,GDP
            deflator,GDP per capita,Gini coefficient,GNP,growth
            period,growth rate,growth rates,household budget
            survey,Household Income,Household Incomes,household
            Surveys,income,income data,income differences,Income
            Differentials,income distribution,Income
            Distributions,income groups,Income Level,income share,Income
            Shares,income
            trends,incomes,Inequality,inflation,input-output,insurance,labor
            force,LDCs,legislation,Life Expectancy,Mean Income,mean
            incomes,Minimum Wages,money income,monopoly,national
            accounts,National income,pensions,per capita growth,per
            capita income,Personal Income,policy implications,poverty
            estimates,poverty gap,poverty line,poverty reduction,private
            sector,product
            markets,Productivity,Programs,questionnaires,rapid
            growth,real GDP,real growth,real income,reduced
            poverty,relative incomes,remittances,retained
            earnings,savings,secondary sources,technological
            change,Terms of Trade,total output,transfer
            income,underestimates,value added,Wage Differentials,Wages
        </keywd>
        <owner>LCS</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>South America</geo_region>
            <geo_region>America</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>SWP356</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics and Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Technological Change</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Birth Spacing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Impact Evaluations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Randomized Control Trials</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wage Bill</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wage Compression</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Market Access</ml:concept><ml:concept>Remittances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Migration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wage Setting</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages, Compensation and Benefits</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Lines</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Copyright</ml:concept><ml:concept>Technology Transfer and Diffusion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banking Institutional Set-up</ml:concept><ml:concept>Volatility</ml:concept><ml:concept>Impact Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Family Planning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Minimum Wages</ml:concept><ml:concept>Impact Assessment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Employment and Wage Data</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Movement of Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages</ml:concept><ml:concept>Tax Incentives</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>State Associations</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Americas</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Brazil</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Caribbean</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>