<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Identification and Appraisal&#13;
of Rural Roads Projects&#13;
SWP362&#13;
FIL E COPY§ Ft &#13;
w ^   ^ ^ ^   W                                           XY~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~A.U'NéGTOU4. D.C. ?(M31&#13;
World Bank Staff Working Paper No. 362|&#13;
October 1979&#13;
Prepared by: Henri L. Beenhakker&#13;
Europe, Middle East and North Africa&#13;
Projects Department&#13;
Abderraouf Chammari&#13;
Direction des Ponts et Chaussées&#13;
Ministère de l'Equipement&#13;
Republic of Tunisia&#13;
Copyright © 1979&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
The views and interpretations in this document are those of the authors&#13;
and should not be attributed to the World Bank, to its affiliated&#13;
organizations, or to any individual acting in their behalf.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The views and interpretations in this document are those of the author and&#13;
should not be attributed to the World Bank, to its affiliated organizations,&#13;
or to any individual acting in their behalf.&#13;
WORLD BANK&#13;
Staff Working Paper No. 362&#13;
October 1979&#13;
IDENTIFICATION AND APPRAISAL&#13;
OF RURAL ROADS PROJECTS&#13;
This paper describes an operational approach to the identification&#13;
and appraisal of projects consisting of rural roads and complementary&#13;
investments. The objective for such projects is to prepare and imple-&#13;
ment a comprehensive, multi-sectoral development program on the basis&#13;
of rural roads in their zones of influence.   The methodology can,&#13;
therefore, also be applied to rural development projects.&#13;
The principal purpose of the identification process is to ascertain&#13;
the development potential of a rural road's zone of influence. In many&#13;
instances this may depend on the potential of one or two crops, which,&#13;
therefore, should be examined with more care. The appraisal methodology&#13;
determines the appropriate scope and timing for road improvements or con-&#13;
struction, their maintenance needs, and the complementary investments in&#13;
other sectors, without which (in most cases) the road improvements or&#13;
construction would not be justified. In other words, the project attempts&#13;
to achieve an optimal development package for each road's zone of influ-&#13;
ence. The linkages between agricultural and transport compcnents are&#13;
emphasized.&#13;
Prepared by:  Henri L. Beenhakker&#13;
Europe, Middle East and North Africa&#13;
Projects Department&#13;
Abderraouf Chammari&#13;
Direction des Ponts et Chaussées&#13;
MinistEre de l'Equipement&#13;
Republic of Tunisia&#13;
Copyright (O 1979&#13;
The WVorld Bank&#13;
1818 H Street,-N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433&#13;
U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ACGOeLEDGEM&#13;
We have benefitted from discussing the subject matter&#13;
of this paper over the last few years wvth a great many people&#13;
inside and outulde the World Bank, and it is impossible to men-&#13;
tion them all. Special recognition should, however, be given to&#13;
Anandarup Ray, Victor Wouters, David Hodgkinson, Herbert Floyd,&#13;
and Peter Long, who collaborated with us in an earlier draft&#13;
paper. As the draft and. final version of the paper vere dev-&#13;
eloped, Aiko Muraki displayed a cheerful forbearance as she&#13;
produced efficient transcripts of illegible copy and incompre-&#13;
hensible symbole. None of the people credited is, however,&#13;
responsible for any errors or ommissions.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
IDENTIFICATION AND APPRAISAL&#13;
OF RURAL ROADS PROJECTS&#13;
Table of Contents&#13;
Page No.&#13;
I.  INTRODUCTION   ..........i .....................       1&#13;
II.  A SIMPLE EXAMPLE   ......      ......................  7&#13;
III.  IDENTIFICATION MET11OD   .....     ..................  22&#13;
IV.  RURAL ROADS PROGRAM ......       ....................  31&#13;
ANNEX&#13;
1. Economic Analysis of Road and Agricultural Investments&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
IDENTIFICATION AND APPRAISAL&#13;
OF RURAL ROADS PROJECTS&#13;
I. INTRODUCTION&#13;
1.        The Bank's experience indicates that, to achieve optimal benefits,&#13;
it is frequently necessary to integrate road improvements and agricultural&#13;
development; the main reason for not achieving forecast economic returns (ERs)&#13;
of road improvements in the past is the absence of a complementary agricul-&#13;
tural development program.    Thus rural road improvements often cannot be ex-&#13;
pected to raise agricultural production automatically. Vice versa, rural&#13;
development projects often require a rural roads component to complement&#13;
investments in agricultural production in order that the project achieve&#13;
its full development impact. The approach calls, therefore, for improvements&#13;
of rural roada and complementary agricultural investments.&#13;
2.        The main features of the approach to project preparation are: (i)&#13;
focus on individual rural roads and their specific zones of influence; (ii)&#13;
the development of an integrated investment package for each road's zone of&#13;
influence; and (iii) the integration of these investment packages into&#13;
regional and national development plans.&#13;
3.        Investment packages may consist of:   (i) rural road improvements;&#13;
(ii) equipment for improved rural road maintenance; (iii) land clearing,&#13;
planting of permanent crops, purchase of cattle, equipment and tool procure-&#13;
ment, and development of on-farm storage, which require on-farm investments&#13;
by participating farmers; (iv) inputs such as fertilizers, seeds, labor and&#13;
renting of equipment which require incremental working capital; (v) improved&#13;
extension services; and (vi) collection facilities, equipment maintenance&#13;
and rental facilities, etc. Recommendations with regard to the inclusion&#13;
of certain or all components in the investment package are based on an&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 2 -&#13;
analysis of the potential agricultural development and traffic requirements&#13;
in each rural road's zone of influence.&#13;
4.        The purpose of this paper is to describe an Identification Method&#13;
and a Rural Roads Programl/ whichhave been primarily developed to test alter-&#13;
native agricultural and road development strategies and to determine ERs&#13;
and net present values (NPVs) of the aforementioned investment packages.&#13;
It does not deal with at least equally important matters such as the organi-&#13;
zation necessary for successful implementation of a rural roads project,&#13;
the preparation of extension manuals and action programs indicating the&#13;
responsibilities of each concerned agency, indicators required to follow the&#13;
implementation of each component of the investment packages, and the develop-&#13;
ment of appropriate management information and monitoring systems. The Rural&#13;
Roads Program may be used for the appraisal of rural roads projects as well&#13;
as the appraisal of rural development projects.&#13;
5.        In order to obtain a balanced and optimal investment package, the&#13;
development of integrated investment packages is not only recommended for&#13;
those roads whose improvement could not be justified without complementary&#13;
agricultural investments, but also for those roads where road user savings&#13;
alone would warrant improvement. The availability of investment packages&#13;
for each road makes it possible, from the outset, to identify key crops and&#13;
actions to be taken for successful project implementation. As a result,&#13;
available extension and other support services can be focussed from the&#13;
start on these crops and actions and their effectiveness should therefore be&#13;
considerably improved.&#13;
6.        The zones of influence of the rural roads are determined by: (i)&#13;
the rural road network around the road being analyzed; (ii) the distances&#13;
1/ A detailed methodology for appraising investment packages of rural roads&#13;
and complementary agricultural investments.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 3 -&#13;
between farms and local markets; (iii) the-terrain; and (iv) the means of&#13;
transport used such as pack animals, animal-drawn carts, agricultural trac-&#13;
tors, pickups, trucks, passenger cars, and buses.&#13;
7.       In most situations benefits resulting from complementary agricul-&#13;
tural investments and investments for rural road improvements do not accrue&#13;
to final cons-prs of agricultural products since these investments are&#13;
normally not large enough to affect retail prices significantly.!J Benefits&#13;
stemming from agricultural investments accrue primarily to farmers, while&#13;
those from road improvements may accrue to farmers and/or transporters.&#13;
8.       Ignoring transport savings resulting from an improved rural road&#13;
which accrue to non-agricultural traffic, the benefits (B) to be had in a&#13;
specific year from an investment package of a rural road improvement and&#13;
complementary investments for one agricultural crop in its zone of influence&#13;
are:&#13;
value added of     ]    incremental costs     [10o8 in&#13;
B -  incremental agri-    -  of production and +    consumer&#13;
cultural production     transportation to      surplus&#13;
local markets&#13;
Annex 1 shows that&#13;
1&#13;
B   Pm (q2 - ql) - (R2 - Rl) - Pl(Hl - H2) - î&lt;lî - H2)(P2 - P1)&#13;
where:                                                                (1)&#13;
Pm    = local market price of a specific agricultural product&#13;
(tons)&#13;
qj,q2 = exports of this product from road's zone of influence&#13;
in the without- and with-project situation, respectively&#13;
(tons)&#13;
Rl,R2 - total economic cost of producing and transporting this&#13;
product to the local market, in the vithout- and with-&#13;
project situation, respectively ($)&#13;
PP,P2 = farm-gate price of this product in the vithout- and with-&#13;
project situation, respectively ($/ton)&#13;
1/ Section IV describes a situation with potential benefits accruing to&#13;
farmers, transporters and final consumera.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 4 -&#13;
H *H2 - home or on-farm consumption of this product in the&#13;
without- and with-project situation, respectively (tons)&#13;
The above-mentioned prices are efficiency prices. Assuming that salvage&#13;
values are negligible, expression (1) may be used to estimate the benefits&#13;
of any year during the expected life of the investment project. This&#13;
expression can also be applied to each crop of a zone of influence, if&#13;
there is more than one crop cultivated; the benefits are, in this situation,&#13;
obtained by addition of the benefits related to each crop.&#13;
9.        The last two terms of expression (1) represent the potential home&#13;
consumption loss due to larger exports in the with-project situation. The&#13;
term 2 (H1 - H2)(P2 - P1) is negligible if the farm-gate price elasticity&#13;
of the agricultural product considered, and the difference between Hl and&#13;
H2 are amall. Note that the local market price Pm of expression (1) is&#13;
assumed to remain constant in the without- and with-project situations, and&#13;
therefore the benefits accruing to final consumers are zero (para. 7).&#13;
10.       Annex 1 also shows that expression (1) can be rewritten as&#13;
B   B1 + B2&#13;
where&#13;
B1   benefits accruing to farmers&#13;
B2 = benefits accruing to transporters&#13;
or&#13;
B1  P2 q2 - P1 q1-P1(H1 - H2) - 2 (H1 - H2)(P2 - P1) - (C2 - C1)&#13;
........ *.(2)&#13;
and&#13;
B2  2     q2 -F1 q    (k2 q2 - k, ql)                  .... (3)&#13;
where P2, Pl, q2. ql. H1l H2 are as defined in para. 8, and&#13;
Cl,C2 = economic cost of producing the entire agricultural product&#13;
under consideration in the without- and with-project&#13;
situation, respectively (4)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
FJPF2 = fare for transporting one ton of exportable surplus over&#13;
the rural road in the without- and with-project situation,&#13;
respectively ($/ton)&#13;
ki,k2 = economic cost of transporting one ton of exportable&#13;
surplus over the rural road in the without- and with-&#13;
project situation, respectively ($/ton)&#13;
11.       Either expression (1) or expressions (2) and (3) may be used for&#13;
the identification and evaluation of an investment package. The choice&#13;
between these expressions is a matter of convenience and depends on which&#13;
required data are more easily available. The important point is not to&#13;
use expression (1) with expression (3) which would lead to double counting.&#13;
This paper employa expressions (2) and (3).&#13;
12.       The ER and NPV of an investment package are computed by comparing&#13;
total benefits, including transport savings accruing to non-agricultural&#13;
traffic (para. 8), with total costs of road construction and maintenance&#13;
and complementary agricultural investments. The computations become in-&#13;
volved and cumbersome if there are more than three different agricultural&#13;
outputs vith more than three inputs in a zone of influence, even if all&#13;
farms were of the same size so that differences in agricultural technologies&#13;
and yields could be ignored. To handle these more complex project situations,&#13;
a computer program called the Rural Roads Computer Program (RRCP) has been&#13;
developed in order to facilitate the computations and sensitivity annlyses.&#13;
With the exception of the establishment of a link between agricultural yields&#13;
and inputs, the RRCP does not determine links, such as those existing between&#13;
higher farm income and additional transport, additional consumption and&#13;
lover prices of agricultural products. These links have to be determined&#13;
separately by the analyst as an input for the RRCP.&#13;
13.       To further explain the methodology of the Identification Method&#13;
and the Rural Roads Program, Section II, A Simple Example, describes the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 6 -&#13;
evaluation of an over simplified case, i.e., one typical farm size, with&#13;
only two crops in a rural road's zone of influence. Section III describes&#13;
the Identification Method for rural roads projects. This method is based&#13;
upon the results of senaitivity testing of ERs and NPVs obtained during&#13;
the appraisal of about 60 individual rural roads and complementary agricul-&#13;
tural investments in the zones of influence of these roads in Tunisia.&#13;
The principles underlying the Identification Method and those underlying&#13;
the appraisal method (i.e., the Rural Roads Program) are the same. The&#13;
difference between these two methodologies is that a number of simplifications&#13;
has been introduced in the Identification Method. These simplifications&#13;
consist of the elimination of a number of input data which facilities the&#13;
computations. With the hope that it vill prove useful for other project&#13;
analysts, Section IV presents the analytical framçwork of the Rural Roads&#13;
Program, which is the logical basis of the RRCP. The RRCP has several unique&#13;
features that distinquish it from other programs available or under prepa-&#13;
ration for the analysis of rural development/roads projects. These features&#13;
include a road network analysis; links between savings in transportation&#13;
coste and farm-gate prices, traffic, and production; a generalized determina-&#13;
tion of the optimal investment year; an aggregation of benefits by beneficiary&#13;
groups, etc.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
II. A SIMPLE EXAMPLE&#13;
14.       The purpose of this example is to illustrate the practical steps&#13;
necessary for identifying and appraising an investment package consisting of&#13;
a rural road and complementary agricultural investments. The number of&#13;
outputs, inputs, agricultural investments, farm sizes and transport means is&#13;
kept to a minimum in order to facilitate the presentation.   Following a brief&#13;
description of the project components and data requirements (paras. 15 - 22)&#13;
a step-by-step analysis is given.&#13;
15.       A hypothetical 30 km rural road in flat terrain has been selected&#13;
for analysis. Improvement of the road from earth to al all-weather gravel&#13;
standard is proposed. The principal economic activity in the road's zone&#13;
of influence (para. 6) is the production of wheat and tomatoes for export&#13;
from this zone and for on-farm consumption. Most of the population of about&#13;
60,000 inhabitants in the zone of influence are farmers who own small lots&#13;
of land. Population growth is estimated at 2.5% per year. It is assumed&#13;
that the farms are all of the same size while used technologies and yields&#13;
are also the same in a specific project situation.&#13;
16.       The wheat and tomatoes are transported from the area by small&#13;
trucks and mules plus carts. Passenger transportation is by land-rover.&#13;
Traffic on the road averages four trucks, five carts and 4 land-rovers&#13;
per day. Non-agricultural traffic other than these land-rovers (general&#13;
freight, through traffic) is negligible. Average daily traffic by land-&#13;
rover, which is assumed to be constant without road improvements, is esti-&#13;
mated to grow at 5% per annum after the road improvement. Improvement of&#13;
the rural road is not expected to generate or divert other traffic in the area.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 8-&#13;
17.       The proposed investment package consists of:&#13;
(a)  Road improvement ........  costs  $1.20 million&#13;
(b)  Wells and pumps ......... costs   $0.20 million&#13;
(c)  Extension services ...... costs   $0.05 million.&#13;
The expected economic lives of all of these investments are, for simplicity&#13;
reasons, assumed to be ten years while salvage values are negligible. In&#13;
addition, it is assumed that these investments will be implemented over a&#13;
period of two years. Consequently, improvements in agricultural yields,&#13;
and savings in vehicle operating costs do not occur during these two years.&#13;
18.       Annual road maintenance expenditures, which are negligible in&#13;
the without-project situation, and annual agricultural production costs&#13;
(labor, equipment, fertilizers, water, etc.) in the without- and with-project&#13;
situations are given in Table II.1.&#13;
Table II.1: Annual Costs&#13;
Road Maintenance Costs    Agricultural Production Costs per Ha ($)&#13;
in With Situation        Without Situation        With Situation&#13;
Year           ($'000)               Wheat   Tomatoes      Wheat    Tomatoes&#13;
(1)              (2)                 (3)       (4)          (5)       (6)&#13;
1                0                   80      520           90       550&#13;
2                0                   80      520           90       550&#13;
3               25                   80      520           90       550&#13;
4               25                   80      520           90       550&#13;
5               25                   80      520           90       550&#13;
6               50                   80      520           90       550&#13;
7               25                   80      520           90       550&#13;
8               25                   80      520           90       550&#13;
9               25                   80      520           90       550&#13;
10               50                   80      520           90       550&#13;
il               25                   80      520           90       550&#13;
12               25                   80      520           90       350&#13;
19.       The crop area breakdown in the road's zone of influence and yields&#13;
in the vithout- and with-project situations are given in the table below.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 9 -&#13;
Table II.2: Crop Area Breakdown and Yields&#13;
Wheat                                Tomatoes&#13;
W/0        With Areas      Yield      W/o        With Areas      Yield&#13;
Areas        ('000 ha)      (t/ha)    Areas   _    (000 ha)       (t/ha)&#13;
Year ('000 ha) Unimprovet Improved W/0 With ('000 ha) Unimproved ioved V/O With&#13;
(1)    (2)       (3)      (4)    (5)  (6)    (7)       (8)       (9)  (1) 71TlT&#13;
1     5.0      5.0       0.0    0.6  1.0    0.5      0.5       0.0   10.0 20.0&#13;
2     5.0      5.0       0.0    0.6  1.0    0.5      0.5       0.0   10.0 20.0&#13;
3     5.0      4.0       1.0    0.6  1.0    0.5      0.3       0.2   10.0 20.0&#13;
4     5.0       3.0      2.0    0.6  1.0    0.5      0.2       0.3   10.0 20.0&#13;
5     5.0      1.0       4.0    0.6  1.0    0.5      0.0       0.5   10.0 20.0&#13;
6     5.0      0.5       4.5    0.6  1.0    0.5      0.0       0.5   10.0 20.0&#13;
7     5.0      0.5       4.5    0.6  1.0    0.5      0.0       0.5   10.0 20.0&#13;
8     5.0      0.5       4.5    0.6  1.0    0.5      0.0       0.5   10.0 20.0&#13;
9     5.0      0.5       4.5    0.6  1.0    0.5      0.0       0.5   10.0 20.0&#13;
10     5.0      0.5       4.5    0.6  1.0    0.5      0.0       0.5   10.0 20.0&#13;
il     5.0      0.5       4.3    0.6  1.0    0.5      0.0       0.5   10.0 20.0&#13;
12     5.0      0.5       4.5    0.6  1.0    0.5      0.0       0.5   10.0 20.0&#13;
The with-project situation distinguishes unimproved cultivated areas, i.e.,&#13;
areas where techniques (and yields) remain as in the the without-project situ-&#13;
ation, and improved cultivated areas. This distinction reflects the farmers'&#13;
adoptation of new techniques advocated under the extension services of the&#13;
with-project situation.&#13;
20.        The per-ton farm-gate prices of local consumption and exports from&#13;
the zone of influence are assumed to be the same in order to facilititate&#13;
the presentation. They amount to $150 and $60 in the without-project situ-&#13;
ation and $155 and $65 in the with-project situation for wheat and tomatoes,&#13;
respectively. The on-farm per-capita consumption of wheat and tomatoes in&#13;
the without-project situation is 15 kg and 0.5 kg, respectively; corresponding&#13;
values for the with-project situation are 12 kg and 0.3 kg.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 10 -&#13;
21.       Without- and with-project average fares and economic costs for&#13;
transporting agricultural products over the 30 km road are as follows:&#13;
Without         With&#13;
Average fare ($/ton)               0.36          0.20&#13;
Average cost ($/ton)               0.29          0.11&#13;
Note that:&#13;
(1)  the per ton-km transport savings amount to $0.29-$0.11 or $0.18;&#13;
(il)  the transporters' per ton-km profit   increases from $0.07 in the&#13;
without-project situation to $0.09 in the with-project situation,&#13;
or an increase of $0.02;&#13;
(iii) the difference between the aforementioned $0.18 and $0.02 or&#13;
$0.16 which equals the difference between average fares of the&#13;
vithout- and with-project situations, accrues to farmers;&#13;
(iv) the aforementioned $0.16 multiplied by the average road trip of&#13;
30 km equals $5.00 (rounded off), which is the amount by which the&#13;
without-project farm-gate prices are increased in the with-&#13;
project situation (para. 20); and&#13;
(v) the above fares and farm-gate prices imply that final consumers'&#13;
prices in the market are assumed to remain constant in the with-&#13;
out-and with-project situations.&#13;
The average fares and costs for transporting agricultural products are based&#13;
on vehicle operating costs of small trucks and mules plus carts (para. 16);&#13;
the with-project figures are lower due to savings in operating costs and&#13;
the partial substitution of small trucks for mules plus carts.&#13;
22.       The without- and with-project average vehicle operating costs of&#13;
land-rovers on the 30 km rural road amount to $0.70 and $0.40, per vehicle-&#13;
km, respecitvely.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- il -&#13;
23.       The step-by-step analysis consist of:&#13;
(a) the establishment of benefits accruing to farmers [expression (2)&#13;
of para. 10];&#13;
(b)  the determination of benefits accruing to transporters [expression&#13;
(3) of para. 10];&#13;
(c)  the computation of transport savings related to non-agricultural&#13;
traffic; and&#13;
(d) the determination of the ER and NPV of the investment package.&#13;
The annual wheat and tomatoe production, home (on-farm) consumption and&#13;
exports as well as annual agricultural production costs are first determined,&#13;
since they are required to establish the benefits accruing to farmers.&#13;
24.       Annual wheat and tomatoe production.   In the without-project situ-&#13;
ation, this production is obtained by multiplying the number of hectares&#13;
shown in Column (2) of Table II.2 by the yield of Column (5) of this table.&#13;
For instance, in year 3 the production of wheat is 5,000 ha times 0.6 ton/ha&#13;
or 3,000 tons, which is reported in Column (3) of Table II.3. In the wtth-&#13;
project situation, the agricultural production is obtained by taking the&#13;
sum of (i) number of unimproved hectares in Column (3) of Table II.2 times&#13;
the unimproved yield of Colunm (5) of this table, and (ii) number of improved&#13;
hectares ln Column (4) of Table II.2 times the improved yield of Column (6)&#13;
of this table. For instance, in year 5 the production of wheat is 1,000 ha&#13;
times 0.6 ton/ha plus 4,000 ha times 1.0 ton/ha,or 4,600 tons as shown in&#13;
Column (4) of Table II.3.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table I1.3:  Population ('000)&gt; Production, Home Consumtion ani Exorts-(1000 tons)&#13;
Wheat                                       Tomatoes&#13;
Home                                           Home&#13;
Production     Consumption      Eports        Production     Consution        Exports&#13;
Year Population   Without Wtth    Without With   Without With    W±thout With   Without Wîth   Without With&#13;
(1)      (2,        (3)    (4)     (5)     (6)    (7)     (8)     (9)    &lt;10)    (11)    (12)   (13)    (14)&#13;
1     60.00      3.00     3.00    0.90   0.90    2.10   2.10    5.00    5.00    0.03   0.03    4.97   4.97&#13;
2     61.50      3.00     3.00    0.92   0.92    2.-08  2.08    5o00    5.00    0.03   0.03    4.97   4.97&#13;
3     63.00      3.00    3.40    0.95    0.76    2.05   2.64    5.00    7.00    0.03  002     4.97   6.98&#13;
4     66.20      3.00     3.80    0.99   0.79    2.01   3.01    5.00    8.00    0.03   0.02    4.97    7.98&#13;
5     67.80      3.00     4.60    1.02   0.81    1.98   3.79    5.00   10.00    0.03   0.02    4.97    9.98&#13;
6     69.50      3.00    4.80     1.04   0.83    1.96   3.97    5.00   10.00    0.03   0.02     4.97   9.98&#13;
7     71.30      3.00    4.80     1.07   0.86    1.93   3.94    5.00   10.00    0.04   0.02     4.96   9.98&#13;
8     73.10      3.00    4.80     1.10   0.88    1.90   3.92    5.00   10.00    0.04   0.02    4.96    9.98&#13;
9     74.90      3.00    4.80     1.12   0.90    1.88   3.90    5.00   10.00    0.04   0.02     4.96   9.98&#13;
10     76.80      3.00     4,80    1.15   0.92    1.85   3.88    5.00   10.00    0.04   0,02     4.96   9.98&#13;
il     76.70      3.00     4.80    1.18   0.94    1.82   3.86    5.00   10.00    0.04    0.02    4.96   9.98&#13;
12     80.60      3.00     4.80    1.21   0.91    1.79   3.83    5.00   10.00    0.04    0.02    4.96   9.98&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 13 -&#13;
25.       Home consumption.  To determine this consumption, the population&#13;
in the road's zone of influence during the time of implementation and expected&#13;
life of the project, is first determined.  Column (2) of Table II.3 reports&#13;
these population statistics which are based on the base population of 60,000&#13;
and the 2.5Z growth rate (para. 15). The annual home consumption of wheat&#13;
and tomatoes is obtained by multiplying the corresponding annual population&#13;
statistic by the on-farm per-capita consumption of wheat and tomatoes,&#13;
respecitvely (para. 20). Columns (5), (6), (11) and (12) of Table II.3&#13;
show the aforementioned consumption.&#13;
26.       Annual exportable surplus.  The exportable surplus [Columns (7),&#13;
(8), (13) and (14) of Table II.31 in the without- and with-project situation&#13;
is obtained by deducting the corresponding home consumption from the produc-&#13;
tion in the without- and without-project situation, respectively.&#13;
27.       Annual value of wheat and tomatoe exports.  In the without- and&#13;
with-project situations these values are determined by multiplying the exports&#13;
from the zone of influence by the corresponding farm-gate price (para. 20).&#13;
For instance, in year 3 of the without-project situation, the value of the&#13;
wheat exports is 2,050 [Coluin (7), Table II.31 times $150/ton,or $308,000.&#13;
In year 5 of the with-project situation the value of wheat exports is 3,790&#13;
tons [Colunin (8), Table II.3] times $155/ton,or about $58,700. The export&#13;
values are shown in Colunmns(2), (3), (9) and (10) of Table II.4.&#13;
28.       Animal costs of wheat and tomatoe production.  These co0ts are&#13;
obtained by total number hectares times costs per ha. For instance,, in&#13;
year 3 of the without-project situation the costs of wheat production are&#13;
5,000 ha [Coluin (2), Table 11.2] times $80/ha [Colunin (3), Table II.l],or&#13;
$400,000 as shown in Coluni (5) of Table 11.4. The costs of wheat production&#13;
in the same year of the with-project situation amount to 4,000 ha [Column (3),&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 11.4s Vltlui of =zte. ?roduation Co3ta aQd G     Citc-      aaeau&#13;
Uheet                                                                          TuraLozî&#13;
rtriomet locrur_tal Production Costa Met luacretal        M_me Coompt1e     _    zt&gt;.     Lg          cl Production   mta   Me                  Coo_mt8an&#13;
Toit -rh              Eport Vl         I    t luth   treauctioo Cote        loue        Vithput  VLth   bort Vale_      Vithotat  Vtth       t    Cte     f     u*&#13;
|    315.0  315.0        0.0         400.0  400.0        0.0               0.0         2m)(    2903o.)     0.0         260.0  260.0         0.'              0.0&#13;
2    312.0  312.0        0.0         400.0  400.0        0.0               0.0         2.98.0  a020         0.0        260.0  260.0         0.0              0.0&#13;
3    308.0  409.0      101.0         400.0  410.0       10.0              28.1         20WO0   O15.G      116.0        260.0  266.0         6.0              0.6&#13;
ô    303.0  467.0       165.0        400.0  420.0       20.0              30.0         2C2,0  519.0       22t.0        260.0     .0         90               0.6&#13;
S    297.0  587.0      290.0         400.0  440.0       40.0              32.5         202.0   Gr&gt;o.      M1.0         260.0  2Ï5O0        \5.0              0.6&#13;
6    294.0  615.0       321.0        400.0  445.0       45.0              31.5         2£0.0   5G9.@      D51,0        260.0  2Y500         a5.0             0.6&#13;
7    Z90.0  611.0      321.0         400.0  445.0       45.0              31.5         290.0  6003V.Q     21.0         26000  275.U        R5.0              1.2&#13;
a    285.0  608.0       323.0        400.0  445.0       45.0              33.0         29o.0   54OOO      M51.0        260.0  2?5.0         25.0             1.2&#13;
9    282.0  605.0       323.0        400.0  445.0       45.0              33.0         298.0   040.G      311.0        260.0   275.0        15.0             1.2&#13;
10    278.0  601.0      323.0         400.0  445.0       45.0              34.5         2530e C69.0        251.0        260.0  275.0        15.0              1.2&#13;
Il    273.0  598.0      325.0         400.0  445.0       45.0              36.0         20.0    $490.0     S1e0        260.0  275.0         B500             1.2&#13;
12    269.0  594.0      325.0         400W.0  445.0      45.0              36.0         SWA1.   0M909      351.0        2O.o   275.0         15.0             1.2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 15 -&#13;
Table II.2] times $80/ha [Column (3), Table II.1] plus 1,000 ha [Column (4),&#13;
Table II.2] times $90/ha [Column (5), Table II.l],or $410,000 as shown in&#13;
Column (6) of Table II.3. The annual costs of tomatoe production are&#13;
shown in Column (12) and (13) of Table I1.4.&#13;
29.       Annual net incremental values.   Columns (4) and (11) of Table II.4&#13;
show the net incremental values of the annùal exports of wheat and those of&#13;
tomatoes, respectively. These values are the differences between the export&#13;
values in the with and those iu the without-project situation. The net&#13;
incremental production costs [Column (7) and (14) of Table II.41 are obtained&#13;
in a similar manner. For instance, the net incremental production costs of&#13;
tomatoes in year 5 is $275,000 [Column (13), Table II.4] minus $260,000&#13;
[Column (12), Table II.4] or $15,000 [Column (14), Table II.41.&#13;
30.       Home consumption lo0s.   This losa is determined by&#13;
Pl(Hl - H2) - -(H1 - H2)(P2 - P1)&#13;
2&#13;
of expression (2) of para. 10. The second term is not computed, since its&#13;
value is negligible. Columns(8) and (15) of Table II.4 present the loss&#13;
of home consumption of wheat and tomatoes. The loss of home consumption&#13;
of wheat in, for instance, year 5 is determined by multiplying $150 (para.20)&#13;
by the difference between the fifth-year values of Columns(6) and (5) of&#13;
Table 11.3 or 150(210) or $31,500.&#13;
31.       Note that in Table II.4:&#13;
(M) Columns (2) and (9) correspond to-the term P1 q1 of expression (2)&#13;
of para. 10;&#13;
(il)  Columns (3) and (10) cor_espond to the term P2 q2 of this&#13;
expression;&#13;
(iii)  Columns (4) and (11) correspond to (P2 q2 - P1 q1) of this&#13;
expression;&#13;
(iv) Columns (5) and (12) correspond to the term C1 of this expression;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 16 -&#13;
(v) Columns (6) and (13) correspond to the term C2 of this expression;&#13;
(vi) Columns (7) and (14) correspond to (C2 - C1) of this expression; and&#13;
(vii) Columns (8) and (15) correspond to Pl(Hl - H2) of this expression.&#13;
32.       Annual agricultural transport fares and costs.    In the without-&#13;
(with-) project situation the (i) annual agricultural transport fares and&#13;
(ii) costs and obtained by (i) the product of the average transport fare per&#13;
unit in the without- (with-) project situation (para. 21) times the distance&#13;
of the road times the exportable surplus in the without- (with-) project situ-&#13;
ation [Columns (7) and (13) or Columns (8) and (14) of Table II.3] and (ii)&#13;
the p.roduct of the average transport cost per unit (para. 21) in the without-&#13;
(with-) project situation times distance of the road times the exportable&#13;
surplus in the without- (with-) project situation. For instance, the fare for&#13;
transporting wheat in the fifth year of the with-project situation amounts to&#13;
$0.20/ton-km X 30 km X 3,790 tons, or about $22,740&#13;
as shown in Column (3) of Table II.5. The economic cost for transporting wheat&#13;
in the third year of the without-project situation is&#13;
$0.29/ton-km X 30 km X 2,050 tons, or about $17,840&#13;
as shown in Column (4) of Table II.5. Cost savings on transported agricul-&#13;
tural inputs are negligible in this example; hence similar computations&#13;
related to the transport of these inputs are not necessary.&#13;
33.       Transporters benefits.   These benefits are the difference between&#13;
the transporters' profit in the with-project situation and their profit in&#13;
the without-project situation. In other words, these benefits equal the&#13;
fare in the with-project situation, minus the fare in the without-project&#13;
situation minus the cost in the with-project situation plus the cost in the&#13;
without-project situation. The transporters' benefits related to the&#13;
transport of wheat and tomatoes are given in Columns (6) and (11) of Table II.5,&#13;
respectively. Note that in Table II.5:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table II.5: Transport Fares, Costa and Benefits ($'000)&#13;
Wheat                                            Tomatoes&#13;
Transportera'                                     Transportera'       Non-Agr.&#13;
Fares           Costs          Benefits           Fares            Costa           Benefits      Vehicle Costs&#13;
Year  Without   With   Without   With  (3)-(2)-(5)+(4)  Without    With  Without   With   (8)-(7)-(10)+(9)     Savings&#13;
(1)     (2)     (3)     (4)     (5)        (6)            (7)     (8)     (9)     (10)         (11)             (12)&#13;
1    22.68   22.68    18.27   18.27       0.00         53.68    53.68   43.24   43.24         0.00            0.00&#13;
2    22.46   22.46    18.10   18.10       0.00         53.68    53.68   43.24   43.24         0.00            0.00&#13;
3    22.14   15.84    17.84    8.71       2.83         53.68    41.88   43.24   23.03         8.41            6.57&#13;
4    21.71   18.06    17.49    9.93       3.91         53.68    47.88   43.24   26.33        11.11            6.90&#13;
5    21.38   22.74    17.23   12.51       6.08         53.68    59.88   43.24   32.93        16.51            7.24&#13;
6    21.17   23.82    17.05   13.10       6.60         53.68    59.88   43.24   32.93        16.51            7.61&#13;
7    20.84   23.64   16.79    13.00       6.59         53.57    59.88   43.15   32.93        16.53            7.99&#13;
8    20.52   23.52    16.53   12.94       6.59         53.57    59.88   43.15   32.93        16.53            8.39&#13;
9    20.30   23.40    16.36   12.87       6.59         53.57    59.88   43.15   32.93        16.53            8.80&#13;
10    19.98   23.28    16.10   12.80       6.60         53.57    59.88   43.15   32.93        16.53            9.24&#13;
il    19.66   23.16    15.83   12.74       6.59          53.57   59.88   43.15   32.93        16.53             9.71&#13;
12    19.33   22.98    15.57   12.64       6.58          53.57   59.88   43.15   32.93        16.53           10.19&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 11.5s Transport Fares. Costa and Benefits ($'000)&#13;
Wheat                                            Tomatoes&#13;
Transportera'                                     Transporters'       Non-Agr.&#13;
Fares           Costa          Benefits           Fares            Costs           Benefits      Vehicle Costs&#13;
Year  Without   With  Without    With  (3)-(2)-(5)+(4)  Without    With Without    With   (8)-(7)-(10)+(9)     Savings&#13;
(1)     (2)     (3)     (4)     (5)        (6)            (7)     (8)     (9)      (10)        (11)             (12)&#13;
1    22.68   22.68    18.27   18.27       0.00          53.68   53.68   43.24   43.24         0.00            0.00&#13;
2    22.46   22.46   18.10    18.10       0.00          53.68   53.68   43.24   43.24         0.00            0.00&#13;
3    22.14   15.84    17.84    8.71       2.83          53.68   41.88   43.24   23.03         8.41            6.57&#13;
4    21.71   18.06    17.49    9.93       3.91          53.68   47.88   43.24   26.33        11.11            6.90&#13;
5    21.38   22.74    17.23   12.51       6.08          53.68   59.88   43.24   32.93        16.51            7.24&#13;
6    21.17   23.82    17.05   13.10       6.60          53.68   59.88   43.24   32.93        16.51            7.61&#13;
7    20.84   23.64   16.79    13.00       6.59          53.57   59.88   43.15   32.93        16.53            7.99&#13;
8    20.52   23.52    16.53   12.94       6.59          53.57   59.88   43.15   32.93        16.53            8.39&#13;
9    20.30   23.40    16.36   12.87       6.59          53.57   59.88   43.15   32.93        16.53            8.80&#13;
10    19.98   23.28    16.10   12.80       6.60          53.57   59.88   43.15   32.93        16.53            9.24&#13;
il    19.66   23.16    15.83   12.74       6.59          53.57   59.88   43.15    32.93       16.53             9.71&#13;
12    19.33   22.98    15.57   12.64       6.58          53.57   59.88   43.15    32.93       16.53            10.19&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table II.6: Aggregation of Net Costs and Benefits Streams ($'000)&#13;
Road      Net Incremental        Net                                      Non-Agr.&#13;
Investment  Maintenance    Agricultural      Incremental       Home      Transporters'  Vehicle Cost&#13;
Year     Costs        Costs     Production Costs  Export Values   Consum tion    Benefits        Savinas&#13;
(1)      (2)          (3)             (4)              (5)           (6)           (7)            (8)&#13;
1     725.00           0.00         0.00             0.00           0.00          0.00          0.00&#13;
2     725.00           0.00         0.00             0.00           0.00          0.00          0.00&#13;
3       0.00          25.00        16.00           257.00         29.10           9.40          6.57&#13;
4       0.00          25.00        29.00           386.00          30.60         10.81          6.90&#13;
5       0.-0O         25.00        55.00           641.00          32.10         13.32          7.24&#13;
6       0.00          50.00        60.00           672.00          32.10         14.21          7.61&#13;
7       0.00         25.00         60.00           672.00         32.70          14.58          7.99&#13;
8       0.00          25.00        60.00           674.00          34.20         14.98          8.39&#13;
9       0.00          25.00        60.00           674.00          34.20         15.39          8.80&#13;
10       0.00          50.00        60.00           674.00          35.70         15.84          9.24&#13;
il       0.00          25.00        60.00           676.00          37.20         16.30          9.71&#13;
12       0.00          25.00        60.00           676.00          37.20         16.77         10.19&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 20 -&#13;
36.       It should be emphasized that the above example is based on a&#13;
number of simplifying assumptions, including:&#13;
(a)  no consideration of generated and/or diverted non-&#13;
agricultural traffic resulting from road improvement;&#13;
(b) negligible cost savings on transported agricultural&#13;
inputs;&#13;
(c) no distinction between costs of transport during the wet&#13;
and dry seasons;&#13;
(d) no distinction between normal and extreme deterioration&#13;
of the road;&#13;
(e) no detours when section(s) of the rural road are impassable&#13;
during the wet season;&#13;
(f)  the same expected economic lives and implementation&#13;
periods of all investments of the investment package;&#13;
(g) negligible salvage values of investments of the invest-&#13;
ment package;&#13;
(h) no benefits accruing to final consumera;&#13;
(i) no distinction between farm sizes in road's zone of&#13;
influence;&#13;
(j) no additional cultivated land in the with-project situation;&#13;
(k) no introduction of new agricultural outputs and no increase in&#13;
the number of crops per year in the with-project situation:&#13;
(1)  no distinction between farm gate prices of on-farm consum-&#13;
tion and exports from the road's zone of influence;&#13;
(m)  small or zero elasticity of per-capita on-farm consumption&#13;
as incomes increase;&#13;
(n)  no consideration of on-farm consumption by animals;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 21 -&#13;
(o) negligible road maintenance costS in the without-project&#13;
situation; and&#13;
(p) the price elasticity of on-farm home consumption [the term&#13;
-(H  - H)(P   - P)] is negligible (para. 30).&#13;
2i 1.  H2)2       î'J&#13;
With the possible exception of items (1), (m), (n) and (o), the effect of&#13;
the above assumptions on the ER and NPV criterla of an investment package&#13;
is to understate them.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 22 -&#13;
III. IDENTIFICATION METUOD&#13;
37.       The purpose of this method is two-fold:&#13;
(a) to provide an inexpensive and practical tool for determin-&#13;
ing which investment packages of rural roads and comple-&#13;
mentary agricultural investments, out of a total program&#13;
offered, warrant further consideration; and&#13;
(b)  to provide a practical tool for examining alternative&#13;
road and agricultural investment strategies of an&#13;
investment package.&#13;
Identification is not a substitute for the more comprehensive investment&#13;
package evaluation required in the final appraisal.&#13;
38.       The Identification Method should recognize the uncertainty attached&#13;
to the values of the various parameters and, in particular, to forecaste.&#13;
The estimated costs of investments are likely to be more accurate than&#13;
estimated future benefits accruing from them. Economic returns based on&#13;
the Identification Method should, therefore, be tested with sensitivity&#13;
analysis.&#13;
39.       The Identification Method described here is based on all of the&#13;
simplifying assumptions described in para. 36. The use of this method can&#13;
be further simplified by applying it only to the most important outputs (pro-&#13;
ducts) in the road's zone of influence rather than all outputs since in many&#13;
instances the development potential of the zone of influence may depend&#13;
primarily on the potential of one or two crops. In addition, rather than&#13;
the establishment of annual costs and benefits streams (para. 35), one may&#13;
calculate these streams for four representative years of the project imple-&#13;
mentation period and expected economic lfe (step 3 of para. 40) and obtain&#13;
values of these streams for other years through interpolation. The step-by-&#13;
step procedure of the following paragraph describes the Identification Method.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 23 -&#13;
40.       Step 1:  Estimate the costs of investments of the investment&#13;
package and their economic life.&#13;
Step 2: Estimate the annual road maintenance costs (routine and&#13;
periodic) in the with-project situation.&#13;
Step 3: For each (or each important) output in the road's&#13;
zone of influence, determine the agricultural production costs per ha of&#13;
the vithout- and with-project situations in the first year of project imple-&#13;
mentation, the first year after project implementation, and the mid and last&#13;
years of the expected project life.&#13;
Step 4: Fill out the following table for each (or each important)&#13;
output in the road's zone of influence.&#13;
Table III.1: Product X -- Areas and Yields&#13;
W/0 Areas     With Areas ('000 ha)              Yield (t/ha)&#13;
Year    ('000 ha)    Unimproved      improved         W/0           With&#13;
(Î1)       (2)           (3)           (4)            ()(6)&#13;
1&#13;
2&#13;
3&#13;
4&#13;
where, Year 1 = first year of project implementation&#13;
Year 2   first year after project implementation&#13;
Year 3 = mid-year of expected project life&#13;
Year 4   last year of expected project life&#13;
W/0 areas&#13;
total of areas in the road's zone of influence utilized&#13;
for the cultivation of product X in the without project&#13;
situation&#13;
With areas unimproved&#13;
total of areas in the road's zone of influence utilized-&#13;
for the cultivation of product X in the with-project&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 24 -&#13;
situation with techniques similar to those of the&#13;
.wtthout-project situation&#13;
With areas improved&#13;
- total of areas in the road's zone of influence utilized&#13;
for the cultivation of product X In the with-project&#13;
situation&#13;
Yield W/O&#13;
- yield of crop X with techniques similar to those of the&#13;
vithout project situation&#13;
Yield vith&#13;
- yield of crop X with techniques of the with praject&#13;
situation&#13;
Step 5: Estimate the road's zone of influence population for the&#13;
four yeare of Step 3.&#13;
Step 6: For each (or each important) agricultural produét of the&#13;
road's zone of influence, determine the on-farm per capita consumption&#13;
for the four years of Step 3 and the without- and with-project situations.&#13;
Step 7: Fill out the following table for each (or each important&gt;&#13;
output in the road's zone of influence.&#13;
Table I11.2: Product x - Production, Home Consumption&#13;
and Exports (1000 tons)&#13;
Production           Home Co  umption             Exp rts&#13;
ear      W/0        With        W/O         With         W/O         With&#13;
(1)       (2)        (3)         (4)         (5)          (6)         (7)&#13;
i&#13;
2&#13;
3&#13;
4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 25&#13;
where Year 1, 2, 3 and 4 are as defined in Step 4,&#13;
Production W/O  = number of ha of Column (2) of the Table III.1&#13;
times the yield of Column (5) of this table&#13;
Production with = number of ha of Column (3) of Table III.1 times&#13;
the yield of Column (5) of this table plus&#13;
number of ha of Column (4) of Table III.1&#13;
times the yield of Column (6) of this table&#13;
Home consumption W/O&#13;
= population (Step 5) times the corresponding&#13;
on-farm per-capita consumption in without&#13;
project situation (Step 6)&#13;
Home consumption with&#13;
= population (Step 5) times the corresponding&#13;
on-farm per-capita consumption in with&#13;
project situation (Step 6)&#13;
Exports W/O     = the difference between Columns (2) and (4) of&#13;
Table III.2&#13;
Exports with    = the difference between Columns (3) and (5) of&#13;
Table III.2&#13;
Step 8:  For each transport means, estimate the per passenger-km&#13;
and per ton-km fare and economic cost of transport in the without- and with-&#13;
project situations.&#13;
Step 9: For each agricultural transport means, determine the&#13;
average fare per ton-km and average transport cost per ton-km in the without-&#13;
and with-project situations.-&#13;
Step 10: For each (or each important) agricultural product of the&#13;
road's zone of influence, determine the farm-gate prices in the without- and&#13;
with-project situation. The farm-gate price in the with-project situation&#13;
equals that of the without-project situation plus the product of road dis-&#13;
tance and the difference between the fare in the without-project situation&#13;
and the fare of the with-project situation (para. 21).&#13;
1/ Taking into account transport savings due to reduction in vehicle&#13;
operating costs on the improved road and changes in traffic mix in&#13;
the with-project situation (para. 21).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 26 -&#13;
Step 11:   Fill out the following table for each (or each important)&#13;
output in the road's zone of influence.&#13;
Table III.3: Product x -- Values of Exports, Production Costs&#13;
and Home Consumption Loss ($'000)&#13;
Exports         Net            Production Costs     Net           Home&#13;
Year__         ______       mental                _____        mental&#13;
Year      W/0        With      Export       W/0         With    Production   Consump-&#13;
W,O   With     ~Values    _____       _____         Costs     tion Loss&#13;
(1)      (2)         (3)        (4)         (5)         (6)        (7)         (8)&#13;
i&#13;
2&#13;
3&#13;
4&#13;
where Year 1, 2, 3 and 4 are as defined in Step 4,&#13;
Exports W/0 = exports of Colu,mn (6) of Table III.2 times the&#13;
corresponding farm-gate price in the without-&#13;
project situation (Step 10)&#13;
Exports wïth - exports of Column (7) of Table III.2 times the&#13;
corresponding farm-gate price in the with-project&#13;
situation (Step 10)&#13;
Net incremental export values&#13;
the difference between Columns (3) and (2) of&#13;
Table III.3&#13;
Production costs W/0&#13;
= number of ha of Column (2) of Table III.1 times&#13;
the corresponding agricultural production costs&#13;
per ha in the without-project situation (Step 3)&#13;
Production costs with&#13;
number of ha of Column (3) of Table III.1 times&#13;
the corresponding agricultural production costs&#13;
per ha in the without-project situation plus&#13;
the number of ha of Column (4) of Table III.1&#13;
times the corresponding agricultural production&#13;
costs per ha (Step 3)&#13;
Net incremental production costs&#13;
= the difference between Columns (6) and (5) of&#13;
Table III.3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 27 -&#13;
Home consumption loss&#13;
= the product of the difference between Column (4)&#13;
and Column (5) of Table III.2 times the corres-&#13;
ponding farm-gate price of the without-project&#13;
situation [(Hi - H2)Pl]&#13;
Step 12: Fill out the following table for each (or each important)&#13;
output in the road's zone of influence.&#13;
Table III.4: Product x - Transport Fares, Costs&#13;
and Benefits ($'000)&#13;
Fares                          Coats              Transporters'&#13;
Year                                                                   Benefits&#13;
W/0            With            W/0            With      (3)-(2)-(5)+(4&#13;
(1)        (2)            (3)             (4)            (5)             (6)&#13;
1&#13;
2&#13;
3&#13;
4&#13;
where Year 1, 2, 3 and 4 are as defined in Step 4,&#13;
Fares W/0 = fares for transporting the exports over the rural&#13;
road under consideration in the without-project&#13;
situation,or Column (6) of Table III.2 times the&#13;
road distance times the corresponding average&#13;
fare per ton-km (Step 9)&#13;
Fares with = fares for transporting the exports over the rural&#13;
road under consideration in the with-project&#13;
situation,or Column (7) of Table III.2 times the&#13;
road distance times the corresponding average&#13;
fare per ton-km (Step 9)&#13;
Costs W/0 = economic costs of transporting the exports over&#13;
the rural road under consideration in the&#13;
without-project situation, or Column (6) of&#13;
Table 11.2 times the road distance times the&#13;
corresponding average transport cost per ton-km&#13;
(Step 9)&#13;
Costs with = economic costs of transporting the exports over&#13;
the rural road under consideration in the with-&#13;
project situation, or Column (7) of Table II.2&#13;
times the corresponding average transport cost&#13;
per ton-km (Step 9)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 28 -&#13;
Transportera' benefits&#13;
- [Columns(3) + (4)] minus [Colunmu (2) + (5)] of&#13;
Table III.4&#13;
Step 13: For each means of non-agricultural traffic, estimate&#13;
present and future (years 1, 2, 3 and 4 of Step 3) average daily traffic&#13;
in the without- and with-project situations.&#13;
Step 14: Based on per passenger-km and ton-km cost of transport&#13;
(Step 8) and present and future average daily trafflc (Step 13), determine&#13;
total cost of transport for each means of non-agricultural transport in&#13;
the without- and with-project situations.&#13;
Step 15: Determine for all non-agricultural transport means the&#13;
total cost savings for years 1, 2, 3 and 4 of Step 4 (difference between&#13;
these costs in the without-project situation and these costs in the with-&#13;
project situation).&#13;
Step 16: Based on the information established in Steps 1, 2, 11,&#13;
12 and 15, fill out the following table.&#13;
Table III.5: Aggregation of Net Costs and Benefits Streams&#13;
($,(O()&#13;
Net         Net                             Non-Agr.&#13;
Road     Incremental Ipcremental   Home                 Vehicle&#13;
Year  Investment  Maintenance Agricultural  Export  Consumption Transporters'  Cost&#13;
____    Costs       Costs    Prod.Costs   Values       Loss      Benefits    Savings&#13;
(1)     (2)         (3)         (4)        (5)         (6)         (7)        (8)&#13;
k&#13;
n&#13;
n&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 29 -&#13;
where&#13;
Year 1 = first-year of project implementation&#13;
Year k = first year after project implementation&#13;
Year m = mid-year of expected project life&#13;
Year n = last year of expected project life&#13;
Investment costs&#13;
= investment costs of road improvements (construction)&#13;
and agricultural complementary investments of invest-&#13;
ment package&#13;
Road maintenance costs&#13;
= costs of maintaining the improved (constructed) rural&#13;
road&#13;
Net incremental agricultural production costs&#13;
= for years 1, k, m and n the summation over all&#13;
agricultural products of the costs for years 1,&#13;
2, 3 and 4 of Column (7) of Table III.3,&#13;
respectively; the incremental costs for years 2,&#13;
3, .... (k - 1), (m + 1), (m + 2), ..., (n -1&#13;
are obtained through interpolation&#13;
Net incremental export values&#13;
= for years 1, k, m and n the sunmmation over all&#13;
agricultural products of the values for years 1,&#13;
2, 3 and 4 of Column (4) of Table III.3,&#13;
respectively; the incremental values for years&#13;
2, 3, ..., (k - 1), (m + 1), (m + 2), ..., (n - 1)&#13;
are obtained through interpolation&#13;
Home consumption loss&#13;
= for years 1, k, m, and n the summation over all&#13;
agricultural products of the losses for years 1,&#13;
2, 3 and 4 of Column (8) of Table III.3,&#13;
respectively; the losses for years 2, 3, ....&#13;
(k - 1), (m + 1), (m + 2), ..., (n - 1) are&#13;
obtained through interpolation&#13;
Transporters' benefits&#13;
= for years 1, k, m and n the summation over all&#13;
agriculturaL products of the benefits for years 1,&#13;
2, 3 and 4 of Column (6) of-Table I11.4, respectively;&#13;
the benefits for years 2, 3, ..., (k - 1), (m + 1),&#13;
(m + 2), ..., (n - 1) are obtained through interpolation&#13;
Non-agricultural vehicle cost savings&#13;
for years 1, k, m and n the summation over all&#13;
agricultural products of the savings for years 1,&#13;
2, 3 and 4 of Step 15, respectively; the savings&#13;
for years 2, 3, ..., (k - 1), (m + 1), (m + 2),&#13;
(n - 1) are obtained through interpolation&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 30 -&#13;
Step 17: With the costs and benefits streams of Table III.5,&#13;
determine the ER and NPV of the investment package.&#13;
41.       The techniques of ER and NPV computations are well known and,&#13;
therefore, not' illustrated here. Para.37 stated that one purpose of the&#13;
Identification Method is to provide a tool for examining alternative road&#13;
and agricultural investment strategies of an investment package. This&#13;
examination can be easily done by changing the investment costs of Column&#13;
(2) of Table III.5 and introducing consequent changes in, for instance,&#13;
agricultural yields, and therefore, modifications in the net incremental&#13;
agricultural production costs and export values [Columns (4) and (5) of&#13;
Table III.5]. In other words, the examination is done through a sensitivity&#13;
analysis. For rural roade (development) projects, it may be particularly&#13;
useful to test the sensitivîty of key crops in order to obtain better per-&#13;
spective on the development potential of the area and the viability of the&#13;
project.   The techniques of sensitivity analysis, which can also be employed&#13;
to test the sensitivity of the ER and NPV to estimated costs and benefits&#13;
(para. 39), are also well known.&#13;
42.       Many (or all) of the steps of the procedure of para. 40 could be&#13;
carried out by regional offices of Agricultural and Public Works Ministries.&#13;
Others may be better carried out by the central offices of these ministries.&#13;
In Tunisia, for instance, it was proposed to give the responsibility of&#13;
carrying out Steps 8, 9, 10 and 17 to the central offices and the remaining&#13;
steps to the regional offices.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 31 -&#13;
IV. RURAL ROADS PROGRAM&#13;
43.       The purpose of the Rural Roads Program is to provide a detailed&#13;
methodology for appraising investment packages of rural roads and comple-&#13;
mentary agricultural investments. None of the simplifying assumptions&#13;
made in the Identification Method (para. 36) are made in the Rural Roads&#13;
Program. The computations involved become, therefore, cumbersome if more&#13;
than three different agricultural outputs with more than three inputs&#13;
in a zone of influence are prevailing. A Rural Roads Computer Program&#13;
(RRCP) has been developed to assist vith the computations and sensitivity&#13;
analyses. RRCP and a manual describing the preparation and coding of&#13;
input data, the signing on to a time-sharing systems and the creation and&#13;
editing of data files are available at the EMENA Projects Department of&#13;
the World Bank.&#13;
44.       In addition to removing the assumptions of para. 36, the Rural&#13;
Roads Program differs from the Identification Method in that   it:&#13;
(a) apecifically recognizes existing interrelationships&#13;
between the various parameters;&#13;
(b) provides for the simultaneously testing of two alternative&#13;
road improvement situations and two alternative groups&#13;
of complementary agricultural investment components, and&#13;
combinations of these four alternatives (four "with-&#13;
project situations");&#13;
(c) establishes a link between annual agricultural inputs and&#13;
annual yields;&#13;
(d) computes for each transport means (agriculturally related&#13;
and non-agricultural related) future average daily traffic&#13;
on the rural road;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 32 -&#13;
(e) facilitates the economic analysis of livestock development&#13;
in the road's zone of influence;&#13;
(f) allows for the introduction of shadow prices; and&#13;
(g)  determines the optimal time for implementing the investment&#13;
package.&#13;
The following paragraphs describe the analytical framework of the Rural&#13;
Roads Program. Simple symbols and indices are used to express the inter-&#13;
relationships between the parameters.&#13;
45.       The program consists of the following six models:&#13;
(1) the Transport Model, which involves two sub-models,&#13;
(a) the Transport Costs and (b) the Farmer Benefits&#13;
sub-models;&#13;
(2) the Agricultural Revenue Model, which includes (a)&#13;
the Agricultural Production, (b) the Agricultural Inputs,&#13;
(c) the Agricultural Revenue and (d) the Agricultural&#13;
Investments sub-models;&#13;
(3) the Agricultural Traffic Model, including (a) the Local&#13;
Consumption and Exports, (b) the Agricultural Traffic and&#13;
(c) the Value of Local Consumption and Exports sub'models;&#13;
(4) the Distribution of Transport Savings Model, which involves&#13;
(a) the Consumers' Surplus and (b) the Transporters'&#13;
Surplus sub-models;&#13;
(5) the Non-Agricultural Traffic and Related Benefits Model,&#13;
which includes (a) the Non-Agricultural Traffic, (b) the&#13;
Related Benefits and (c) the Traffic sub-models; and&#13;
(6) the Economic Return Model, consisting of (a) the Costs and&#13;
Benefits, (b) the ER and NPV and (c) the Optimal Year&#13;
sub-models.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 33 -&#13;
46.       Indices.  Various input variables are indexed in parentheses&#13;
according to one or more of the following indices:&#13;
r   - index used to denote a link&#13;
s   - index used to denote two seasons (summer = 1, winter = 2)&#13;
rs  - index used to denote different road surface conditions;&#13;
a maximum of 7 road surface conditions can be used&#13;
sp - index used to denote different terrain types; a maximum&#13;
of 4 terrain types can be used, as for example:&#13;
sp=l represents flat terrain&#13;
sp=2 represents slightly undulating terrain&#13;
sp=3 represents-rolling terrain&#13;
sp=4 represents mountaineous terrain&#13;
h   - index used to denote the planning horizon where:&#13;
hl or h=l means the beginning of planning horizon&#13;
h2 or h=2 means the end of planning horizon&#13;
v   - index used to denote a means of transportation; a maximum&#13;
8 transport means can be used, as for example:&#13;
v=l represents transport by mule&#13;
v=2 represents transport by mule plus cart&#13;
v=3 represents transport by passenger car&#13;
v=4 represents transport by van&#13;
v=5 represents transport by truck&#13;
v=6 represents transport by mini-bus&#13;
v=7 represents transport by tractor&#13;
v=8 represents transport by motorcycle&#13;
t   - index used to denote different types of traffic; a maximum&#13;
of 4 traffic types can be used.&#13;
t=l represents passenger traffic using the project road&#13;
t=2 represents commodity traffic using the project road&#13;
t=3 represents passenger traffic diverted to the project&#13;
road in one of the with-project situations&#13;
t=4 represents commodity traffic diverted to the project&#13;
road in one of the with-project situations&#13;
e   - index used for a route on the project road&#13;
f   - index used for an alternative route if the project road is&#13;
impassable&#13;
n   - index to denote an external route or that portion of an&#13;
internal route that does not contain the project road;&#13;
an internal route is a route which contains the project&#13;
road (Note that an alternate route could be an external&#13;
route)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-34 -&#13;
OD - index used to denote an origin-destination pair on a route;&#13;
a maximum of 20 OD pairs can be used&#13;
ODe - index used to denote an origin-destination pair on route e&#13;
ODf - index used to denote an origin-destination pair on route f&#13;
ODn - index used to denote an origin-destination pair on route n&#13;
pt - index used to denote the degree of road improvements made&#13;
during the planning horizon where:&#13;
ptl or pt-i represents no road improvements in the road's&#13;
zone of influence&#13;
pt-2 represents a certain level of improvements in the&#13;
road's zone of influence&#13;
pt-3 represents another level of improvements in the road's&#13;
zone of influence&#13;
pa - index used to denote the degree of agricultural investments&#13;
made during the planning horizon where:&#13;
pal or pa=l represents no agricultural investments in the&#13;
zone of influence&#13;
pa=2 represents a certain level of agricultural investments&#13;
in the road's zone of influence&#13;
pa-3 represents another level of agricultural investments&#13;
in the road'a zone of influence&#13;
p   - index used to denote the degree of road improvements and/or&#13;
agricultural investments made during the planning horizon,&#13;
where:&#13;
pl or p=l represents no road improvements and no agricul-&#13;
tural investments in the road's zone of influence&#13;
p=2 represents a certain level of road improvements (pt=2)&#13;
and a certain level of agricultural investments (pa=2)&#13;
in the road's zone of influence&#13;
p=3 represents another level of road improvements (pt=3)&#13;
and a certain level of agricultural investments (pa=2)&#13;
in the road's zone of influence&#13;
p=4 represents a certain level of road improvements (pt=2)&#13;
and another level of agricultural investments (pa=3)&#13;
in the road's zone of influence&#13;
p=5 represents another level of road improvements (pt=3)&#13;
and another level of agricultural investments (pa=3)&#13;
in the road's zone of influence&#13;
The relation between pt, pa and p can be summarized as follows:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 35 -&#13;
p-                pa                Pt&#13;
1                 1                 1&#13;
2                 2                 2&#13;
3                 2                 3&#13;
4                 3                 2&#13;
5                 3                 3&#13;
I   - index to denote the agricultural input used; a maximum of&#13;
17 agricultural inputs can be used, as for example:&#13;
I=1 represents unspecialized labor (man-days/ha)&#13;
I=2 represents specialized labor (man-days/ha)&#13;
I=3 represents land used for the production of cereals (ha)&#13;
I=4 represents land used for the production of rainfed tree&#13;
products (olives, almonds) (ha)&#13;
I=5 represents pasture land (ha)&#13;
I=6 represents water (ton/ha)&#13;
I=7 represents animal labor (day/ha)&#13;
I=8 represents tractor use (hour/ha)&#13;
I=9 represents material use (hour/ha)&#13;
I=10 represents fodder (ton/ha)&#13;
I=11 represents seeds (ton/ha)&#13;
I=12 represents fertilizers (ton/ha)&#13;
I=13 represents insecticides (ton/ha)&#13;
I=14 represents credit requirements (monetary unit/ha)&#13;
I=15 represents herbicides (ton/ha)&#13;
I=16 represents fongicides (ton/ha)&#13;
I=17 represents combine use (hour/ha)&#13;
If - index used to denote fodder input for cattle and sheep in&#13;
the road's zone of influence&#13;
Note: The maximum number of agricultural inputs including&#13;
fodder inputs are 17 (i.e., "If" belongs to I).&#13;
c   - index to denote agricultural products; a maximum of 15&#13;
agricultural products can be used as for example:&#13;
c=l represents pasture land&#13;
c=2 represents meat from cows&#13;
c=3 represents milk from cows&#13;
c=4 represents meat from sheep&#13;
c=5 represents wheat&#13;
c=6 represents barley&#13;
c=7-represents fodder&#13;
c=8 represents olives&#13;
c=9 represents sunflower&#13;
c=10 represents cereals on irrigated land&#13;
c=ll represents tomatoes&#13;
c=12 represents fodder on irrigated land&#13;
c=13 represents vegetables&#13;
c=14 represents potatoes&#13;
c=15 represents corn&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-36 -&#13;
cf - index used to denote fodder products&#13;
Note: The maximum number of agricultural products including&#13;
fodder products is 15 (i.e., "cf" belongs to c).&#13;
x   - index used to denote farm sizes; a maximum of 4 farm sizes&#13;
can be used as for example:&#13;
x=l for very small farm size&#13;
x=2 for small farm size&#13;
x=3 for medium farm size&#13;
x=4 for large farm size&#13;
y   - index used to denote a year of the planning horizon&#13;
u   - index used to denote an activity by product and by farm&#13;
size, or u=cx; for example, VP(p,y,u) indicates VP is a&#13;
function of project situation p, year y, and u (farm size&#13;
x and product c)&#13;
TRANSPORT MODEL&#13;
47.       Transport Costs Sub-Model&#13;
47.1      The inputs to this model are:&#13;
1. For each transport type v, the operating cost per km (voc) as a&#13;
function of road surface condition rs and terrain sp (v-=l, 2, ..., 8;&#13;
rs=l, 2, ..., 7; sp=l, 2, ..., 4) (monetary unit)&#13;
2. The list of the OD's taken into consideration for the analysis of&#13;
the project road. OD's on route e are distinguished from those on route n.&#13;
3. The list of l'inks which lists each pair of OD's defining routes.&#13;
4. The matrix M which establishes the relation between each of the 8&#13;
transport means v and the four types t of traffic.&#13;
Note:  a.  M is a matrix indicating the fractions of transport&#13;
means (v) necessary to transport one ton of goods&#13;
(or one passenger) of traffic type t.&#13;
b. M is given for the beginning and end of planning&#13;
horizon (h=l and 2).&#13;
c. M is a function of pt and h; consequently, there are 6&#13;
different matrices M since pt=l, 2, 3 and h=l, 2.&#13;
5.  Characteristics related to road sections of extreme deterioration and&#13;
impassable road sections.&#13;
NSED(pt,r,s) = number of sections of extreme deterioration on link r&#13;
in each season of the without- and with project&#13;
situations&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 37 -&#13;
ED(rs,v)     = the distance on a link with road surface R, or a&#13;
road section of extreme deterioration (rs) which&#13;
is equivalent to a distance on a link with road&#13;
surface condition R (per means of transport v)&#13;
Note: The surface condition R is refined as the&#13;
average condition of the seven surface conditions rs.&#13;
PIOC(v)      = the portion of operating costs of a transport means,&#13;
which is proportional to distance&#13;
ANDI         = average annual number of days that a road is&#13;
impassable&#13;
ANDR         = average annual number of days of rain&#13;
The following information can be supplied for each link:&#13;
- identification number [number of province, number of rural road&#13;
(99), number of link (two digits)]&#13;
- number indicating the pt=l or pt=2 or pt=3 project situation&#13;
- length&#13;
- terrain&#13;
- season (summer s=l, winter s=2)&#13;
- status of the road surface condition (rs) for summer s=l and&#13;
winter s=2&#13;
- number of sections of extreme deterioration for s=l and s=2&#13;
The following information can.be supplied for each zone of influence&#13;
and for the without- or with-project situations (pt):&#13;
- the possible existence of impassable road sections during the&#13;
winter (rain) season&#13;
- the possible existence of an alternate route for the impassable&#13;
road section&#13;
- the links defining the alternate route (if existing)&#13;
47.2      The calculations of the Transport Cost Sub-Model are:&#13;
1. Cost of transport per means of transport v for each OD pair per&#13;
season of the without- and with-project situations (monetary unit), or&#13;
CTV(OD,pt,v,s)    =   E VOC(pt,r,v,s) X d(r)&#13;
rQOD&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 38 -&#13;
where&#13;
d(r)               - length of link r&#13;
VOC(pt,r,v,s)      - cost for transport means v, on link r&#13;
during each season of the without- and&#13;
with-project situations&#13;
2.  Costs of transport per traffie t for each OD pair, per season of the&#13;
without- and with-project situations and for the beginning and end of the&#13;
planning horizon (monetary unit), or&#13;
8&#13;
CTTR(OD,pt,t,h,s) = E M(pt,t,h,v)X CTV(OD,pt,v,s)&#13;
v=l&#13;
3. Cost of transport on sections of extreme deterioration per OD, per&#13;
means of transport (v) and per season of the without- and with-project&#13;
situations (monetary unit), or&#13;
CTEDV(OD,pt,v,s)       E NSED(pt,r,s,) X ED(rs,v) X PIOC(v)&#13;
reOD&#13;
4. Cost of transport on sections of extreme deterioration, per OD, per&#13;
means of traffic t, per season of the without- and with-project situations&#13;
(monetary unit), or&#13;
8&#13;
CTEDT(OD,pt,t,h,s) = E M(pt,t,h,v) X CTEDV(OD,pt,v,s)&#13;
v-l&#13;
5. Costs of transport per traffic type t including the sections of&#13;
extreme deterioration, per OD, per season of the without- and with-project&#13;
situations and for the beginning and end of planning horizon (monetary&#13;
unit), or&#13;
CTED(OD,pt,t,h,s) = CTTR(OD,pt,t,h,s) + CTEDT(OD,pt,t,h,s)&#13;
6. Cost of transport related to impassable section(s) (i.e., on route f)&#13;
per means of traffic in the winter (rain) season of the without- and with-&#13;
project situations and for the beginning and end of planning horizon&#13;
(monetary unit)&#13;
- if an alternate route f exists, compute first&#13;
CTED(ODf,pt,t,h,2) in a manner similar to the computation of CTED of&#13;
point 5 above and next&#13;
TTCT(OD,pt,t,h,2) =&#13;
(ANDR - ANDI)[CTED(OD,pt,t,h,2)]+ANDI[CTED(ODf,pt,t,h,2)]&#13;
ANDR&#13;
- if no alternate route f exists, reduce the yields of specific products&#13;
to reflect the loss in agricultural production due to impassable sections.&#13;
Note: The 2 in the CTED and TTCT formulas refer to s=2.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 39 -&#13;
7. Reduction in costs of transport (benefit) per traffic type,per OD,&#13;
per season of the two with-project situations and for the beginning and&#13;
end of planning horizon (monetary unit)&#13;
- for OD's on route e&#13;
DLTTCT(ODe,pt,t,h,s) = [TTCT(ODe,ptl,t,h,s)]-[TTCT(ODe,pt,t,h,s)]&#13;
- for OD's on route n&#13;
DLTTCT(ODn,pt,t,h,s) = CTED(ODf,ptl,t,h,s) - CTED(ODn,pt,t,h,s)&#13;
Note: (1) If DLTTCT(OD,pt,t,h,s) &lt; O for OD's on a route, then&#13;
DLTTCT(OD,pt,t,h,s) = O.&#13;
(2) pt in the second term of the above equations refers to one of&#13;
the two with-project situations.&#13;
48.       Farmer Benefits Sub-Model&#13;
48.1      This sub-model computes the portion of transport benefits accruing&#13;
to the farmer (which is reflected in a reduction in farm-gate prices of agri-&#13;
cultural inputs and an increase in farm-gate prices of agricultural outputs).&#13;
The inputs to this sub-model are:&#13;
1.  PIO(pt,h,s)     = percentage of agricultural inputs and outputs trans-&#13;
ported by the farmer himself per season for the&#13;
beginning and end of planning horizon of the without-&#13;
and with-project situations&#13;
2. A(pt) and B(pt) = two given parameters depending on pt and which&#13;
define the portion of transport benefits accruing&#13;
to farmers&#13;
48.2      The calculations are:&#13;
BF (pt,h,s)     = A(pt) X PIO(pt,h,s) + B(pt), or the&#13;
portion of transport benefits accruing to the farmer in a specific season&#13;
during the beginning and end of planning horizon of the with-project situations;&#13;
and&#13;
DLTCF(QDe,pt,h,s) = BF(pt,h,s) X DLTTCT(ODe,pt,t,h,s) or the&#13;
reduction in transport costs accruing to the farmer and corresponding to the&#13;
transport of agricultural inputs and outputs in the road's zone of influence&#13;
per season of the with-project situations, per ODe and during the beginning&#13;
and end of planning horizon (monetary unit).&#13;
49.       In summary, the outputs of the TRANSPORT MODEL are:&#13;
1.  Costs of transport per type of traffie and OD pair (monetary unit),&#13;
or TTCT(OD,pt,t,h,s)&#13;
2.  Reductions in costs of transport per type of traffic and OD pair&#13;
or DLTTCT(OD,pt,t,h,s)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 40 -&#13;
3. Portion of transport benefit accruing to the farmer, or BF(pt,h,s)&#13;
4. Reduction in transport cost accruing to the farmer (monetary unit),&#13;
or DLTCF(ODe,pt,h,s)&#13;
ACRICULTURAL REVENUE MODEL&#13;
50.       This model consists of four sub-models, i.e., Agricultural Production,&#13;
Agricultural Inputs, Agricultural Revenue, and Agricultural Investments.&#13;
51.       Agricultural Production Sub-Model&#13;
51.1      The inputs to this sub-model are:&#13;
1.  TCAl(x)       = total cultivated area in the zone of influence per&#13;
size of farm for the without-project situation (ha)&#13;
2. TAA(pa,y)      = total cultivable area per year (i.e., not cultivated&#13;
but with potential to be cultivated) in the zone of&#13;
influence for the without- and with project situations&#13;
3.  CABl(u)       = product area breakdown by farm size in the zone of.&#13;
influence for the without project situation (ha)&#13;
Note that u indicates an activity by product and&#13;
by farm size, or u = cx&#13;
4.  ACA(pa,y,c)   = additional cultivated area by product during each&#13;
year in the zone of influence for the without- and&#13;
with-project situations (pa= 1,2, 3) (ha)&#13;
5.. CICA(y,u)     = completely improved cultivated area by product and&#13;
farm size during each year in the zone of influence&#13;
(ha)&#13;
6. PCICA(pa,y,c) = percentage of CICA, indicative of the adoptation of&#13;
new techniques by farmers during each year in the&#13;
zone of influence for the without- and with-project&#13;
situations and by product&#13;
7.  YICL(y,u)     = yield on improved cultivated land, by farm size,&#13;
product and year (tons/ha)&#13;
B.  YACL(y,u)     = yield on additional cultivated land, by product,&#13;
farm size and year (tons/ha)&#13;
9. YUCL(y,u)      = yield on unimproved cultivated land, by farm size,&#13;
product and year (tons/ha)&#13;
51.2      The calculations of the Agricultural Production Sub-Model are:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 41 -&#13;
1. Product area breakdown after improvements have been introduced during&#13;
each year in the zone of influence for the without- and with-project&#13;
situations, by farm size and product (ha), or&#13;
CABI(pa,y,u)  = CABl(u) X [1- PCICA(pa,y,c)] + CICA(y,u) XPCICA(pa,y,c)&#13;
2. Percentage of improved area by product and farm size during each year&#13;
in the zone of influence and for the without- and with-project situations,&#13;
or&#13;
PRIA(pa.y,u) = CICA(y,u) X PCICA(pa,y,c)&#13;
CABI(pa,y,u)&#13;
3. Total variation in product area breakdown by product and farm size&#13;
during each year in the zone of influence and for the without- and with-&#13;
project situations (ha), or&#13;
TVCAB(pa,y,u) = CABI(pa,y,u) - CABI(pa,l,u)&#13;
4. Annual variation in product area breakdown (incremental) by product,&#13;
farm size and for the without- and with-project situations (ha), or&#13;
AVCICA(pa,y,u)= TVCAB(pa,y,u) - TVCAB(pa,y-l,u)&#13;
Note that E AVCICA(pa,y,u) = O&#13;
u&#13;
E TVCAB(pa,y,u)   O&#13;
u&#13;
5.  Improved cultivated area by product, farm size, and year of without-&#13;
and with-project situations (ha), or&#13;
ICAB(pa,y,u) = PRIA(pa,y,u) X CABI(pa,y,u)&#13;
6. Unimproved cultivated area by product, farm size and year of the&#13;
without- and with-project situations (ha), or&#13;
UCAB(pa,y,u) = CABI(pa,y,u) - ICAB(pa,y,u)&#13;
7.  Production on improved areas by product, farm size, and year of the&#13;
without- and with-project situations (tons), or&#13;
PIA(pa,y,u)   = ICAB(pa,y,u) X YICL(y,u)&#13;
8.  Production on unimproved cultivated areas by product, farm size, and year&#13;
of the without- and with-situations (tons), or&#13;
PUA(pa,y,u)   = UCAB(pa,y,u) X YUCL(y,u)&#13;
9. Production of additional cultivated areas by product, and year of the two&#13;
with-project situations (tons), or&#13;
PACA(pa,y,u) = ACA(pa,y,u) X YACL(y,u)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 42 -&#13;
10. Total production by product, farm size, and year of the without- and&#13;
with-project situations (tons), or&#13;
TPC(pa,y,u)   = PIA(pa,y,u) + PUA(pa,y,u) + PACA(pa,y,u)&#13;
11. Total production by product, and year of the without- and with-project&#13;
situations (tons), or&#13;
4&#13;
TP(pa,y,c)    =  E TPC[pa,y,(x,c)]&#13;
x=l&#13;
Note: The two principal input data are areas and yields. For cattle breed-&#13;
ing (cows and sheep) the area is assumed to be equal to one hectare and the&#13;
yield equal to total production. Product number 1 is always reserved for&#13;
pasture land (it cannot be used if there is no pasture land). If the pro-&#13;
duction of meat, milk and wool exists, the product numbers 2, 3 and 4 must&#13;
be assigned to the production of meat, milk and wool. Thus, CABI(pa,y,u)&#13;
are artificial areas for c=2, 3 and 4, and&#13;
E   CABI[pa,y,(c,x)] = TCA1(x) and&#13;
ce2,3,4&#13;
CABI[pa,y,(l,x)] = TCAl(x) -   E CABI[pa,y,(c,x)]&#13;
c_5&#13;
where product number 1 refers to pasture land.&#13;
52.       Agricultural Inputs Sub-Model&#13;
52.1      The inputs to this sub-model are:&#13;
1.  IICA(I,u)  = agricultural input I for improved cultivated areas&#13;
during the first year of the planning horizon (h=l),&#13;
by product and farm size (tons/ha)&#13;
2.  IUCA(I,u)  = agricultural input I for unimproved cultivated areas&#13;
during the first year of planning horizon (h=l), by&#13;
product and farm size (tons/ha)&#13;
3.  IACA(I,u)  = agricultural input I for additional, cultivated areas&#13;
during the first year of the planning horizon (h=l), by&#13;
product and farm size (tons/ha)&#13;
4.  GYICA(I,u) = parameter indicating the relation between growth of yield&#13;
and the use of an agricultural input I for improved&#13;
cultivated areas, by product and farm size&#13;
5.  GYUCA(I,u) = parameter indicating the relation between the growth&#13;
of yield and the use of an agricultural input I for&#13;
unimproved cultivated areas, by product and farm size&#13;
6.  GYACA(I,u) = parameter indicating the relation between the growth&#13;
of yield and use of an agricultural input I for&#13;
additional cultivated areas, by product and farm size&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 43 -&#13;
7.  IT(I,c)    = part of agricultural input I required for product&#13;
and transported during the summer (dry) seasor. over&#13;
the project road under consideration (tons/ha)&#13;
8.. WT(I,c)    = part of water input for product c transported over the&#13;
project road under consideration (tons/ha)&#13;
Note that WT(I,c) = 1 for I not equa' to water.&#13;
52.2      The calculations of the Agrieultural Inputs Sub-Model are:&#13;
1. AIICA(I,y,u) or the annual agricultural input I for improved cultivated&#13;
areas by farm size and product (tons/ha)&#13;
a.  If IICA(I,u) # O&#13;
AIICA(I,y,u)   GYICA(I,u)[     (Y'u&gt;- YICL(l'u)   IICA(I,u) + IICA(I,u)&#13;
YICL(l ,u)&#13;
b. If IICA(i,u)    O&#13;
AIICA(I,y,u) = GYICA(I,u)[YICL(y,u) - YICL(l,u)]&#13;
AIICA(I,y,u)            ~~YICL(l,u)&#13;
2. AIUCA(I,y,u) or the annual agricultural input I for unimproved culti-&#13;
vated areas by farm size and produet (tons/ha)&#13;
a.  If IUCA(I,u) $ O&#13;
AIUCA(I,y,u)   GYUCA(i,u)[ CL(y,u) - YUCL(Iu)] IUCA(I,u) + IUCA(I,u)&#13;
YUCL(l,u)&#13;
b.  If IUCA(I,u) = O&#13;
AIUCA(I y u) = GYUCA(I,u) YUCL(Y,u) - YUCL(l,u)]&#13;
AIUCA(I~~y,u)            YUCL(l,u)&#13;
3. AIACA(I,y,u) or the annual agricultural input for additional cultivated&#13;
areas by product (tons/ha)&#13;
a.  If IACA(I,u) # O&#13;
AIACA(I,y,u) = GYACA(I,u)[YACL(Y,u) - YACL(l,u)] LACA(I,u) +IACA(I,u)&#13;
YACL(l,u)&#13;
b.  If IACA(I,u)   O&#13;
AIACA(I,y,u) = GYACA(I,u)[YACL(y,u) - YACL(l,u)]&#13;
YACL(U)&#13;
4. TAI(pa,l,y,u) or total annual agricultural input I by product and&#13;
farm size in the without- and with-project situations (tons/ha)&#13;
TAI(pa,I,y,u) = AlICA(I,y,u) X ICAB(pa,y,u) +AIUCA(I,y,u) XUCAB(pa,y,u) +&#13;
+ AIACA(I,y,u) XACA(pa,y,c)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 44 -&#13;
5* ITS(pa,y,u,s=l) or the quantities (tons) of agricultural inputs to be&#13;
cransp(.rted during tae summer (dry) season, per year, per product, per&#13;
farm size and ir. the without- and with-project situations&#13;
ITS(pa,y,u,s=l) = E IT(I,c) WT(I,c)[AIICA(I,y,u) X ICAB(pa,y,u) +&#13;
IF-El&#13;
+ AIUCA(I,y,u) X UCAB(pa,y,u) + AIACA(I,y,u) XACA(pa,y,c)&#13;
where set El is the group of agricultural inputs to be transported (there&#13;
may also be agricultural inputs produced and consumed on the farm).&#13;
6. ITS(pa,y,u,s=2) or the quantities (tons) of agricultural inputs to be&#13;
transported during the winter (rain) season, per year, per product, per farm&#13;
size and in the without- and with-project situations&#13;
ITS(pa,y,u,s=2) -  E   [1  IT(I,c)] X WT(I,c)[AIICA(I,y,u) X ICAB(pa,y,u) +&#13;
IEEI&#13;
+ AIUCA(I,y,u) X UCAB(pa,y,u) + AIACA(I,y,u) X ACA(pa,y,c)&#13;
53.       Agricultural Revenue Sub-Model&#13;
53.1      The inputs to this sub-model are:&#13;
1.  FAC1(c)       = farm-gate efficiency price of agricultural product c&#13;
produced in the road's zone of influence in the without-&#13;
project situation (monetary unit/ton)&#13;
2. FAIFL(I,c)     = farm-gate efficiency price of agricultural input I&#13;
for product c (with no shadow price for family labor)&#13;
(monetary unit/ton)&#13;
3.  FAEFL(I,c)    = farm-gate price of agricultural input I for product c&#13;
(with a shadow price for family labor) (monetary unit/ton)&#13;
4.  K(c)          = part of agricultural product c transported during the&#13;
summer (dry) season&#13;
5.  L(c)          = part of agricultural product c transported during the&#13;
winter (rain) season; note that K(c) = 1 - L(c)&#13;
6.  SPI(I)        = coefficient which, when multiplied by the efficiency&#13;
price of an agricultural input I, gives its shadow price&#13;
7.  HL(x,I)       = parameter indicating the percentage of hired labor, by&#13;
farm size and agricultural input&#13;
53.2.     The computations of this sub-model are:&#13;
1.  Farm-gate shadow price of agricultural inputs by product (monetary unit/&#13;
ton), or&#13;
4&#13;
E TCAl(x)[HL(x,I)+ (1- HL(x,I)) SPI(I)]&#13;
FISPI(I,c)    = FAIFL(I,c)               4 =&#13;
E TCAl(x)&#13;
x=l&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 45 -&#13;
2. Value of production by type of agricultural product, farm size and&#13;
during each year of the planning horizon of the without-project situation&#13;
(monetary unit), or&#13;
VP(pl.y,u)    = TPC(pal,y,u) X FACl(c)&#13;
Note: pl represents the without project situation.&#13;
3. Costs of agricultural inputs per product, farm size and during each&#13;
year of the planning horizon of the without-project situation (monetary&#13;
unit), or&#13;
CIIFL(pl,y,u) = E TAI(pal,I,y,u) X FISPI(I,c)&#13;
I&#13;
4. Costs of agricultural inputs (with a shadow price for family labor)&#13;
per product, farm size and during each year of the planning horizon&#13;
the without-project situation (monetary unit), or&#13;
CIEFL(pl.y,u) = E TAI(pal,I,y,u) X FAEFL(I,c)&#13;
I&#13;
5. Revenue by product, farm size and during each year of the planning&#13;
horizon of the without-project situation (monetary unit), or&#13;
RIFL(pl,y,u) = VP(pl,y,u) - CIIFL(pl,y,u)&#13;
6. Revenue (with a shadow price for family labor) by product, farm size&#13;
and during each year of the planning horizon of the without-project situ-&#13;
ation (monetary unit), or&#13;
REFL(pl,y,u) = VP(pl.y,u) - CIEFL(pl,y,u)&#13;
7. Total revenue during each year of the planning horizon of the without-&#13;
project situation (monetary unit), or&#13;
TRIFL(pl,y)   = E RIFL(pl,y,u)&#13;
u&#13;
8.  Total revenue (with a shadow price for family labor) in the without-&#13;
project situation during each year of the planning horizon (monetary unit),&#13;
or&#13;
TREFL(pl,y)   = E REFL(pl,y,u)&#13;
u&#13;
9. Annual transport savings accruing to farmers in each season during&#13;
each year of the planning horizon of the with-project situations (monetary/&#13;
unit), or&#13;
DLTCF(ODe,pt,y,s) = DLTCF(ODe,pt,l,s)+ [DLTCF(ODe,pt,2,s) -&#13;
- DLTCF(ODe,pt,l,s)] X   Y-1&#13;
hl-h2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 46 -&#13;
lU. Farm-gate efficiency price of product c transported over the project&#13;
road during each year of the planning horizon of the without- and with-&#13;
project situations (monetary unit/ton), or&#13;
FP(pt,y,c)          FACl(c)+ K(c) DLTCF(ODe,pt,y,s=l)+&#13;
+ L(c) DLTCF(ODe,pt,y,s=2)&#13;
Note that DLTCF(ODe,pt,y,s) is the average over all ODe's on route e and&#13;
that FP(pt,y,c) - FACl(c) for agricultural products consumed on the farm&#13;
(products in group E2 or the group of fodder products).&#13;
11. Farm-gate efficiency price of agricultural input I transported over the&#13;
project road for product c during each year of the planning horizon of the&#13;
without- and with-project situations (monetary unit/ton), or&#13;
FIIFL(pt,I,y,c)   = FISPI(I,c) -IT(I,c) XWT(I,c) XDLTCF(ODe,pt,y,s=l) -&#13;
- [1 - IT(I,c)] WT(I,c) X DLTCF(ODe,pt,y,s=2)&#13;
12. Farm-gate price (with a shadow price for family labor) of an agricul-&#13;
tural input I being transported over the project road for product c during&#13;
each year of the planning horizon of the without- and with-project situ-&#13;
ations (monetary unit/ton), or&#13;
FIEFL(pt,I,y,c)   = FAEFL(I,c)- IT(I,c) WT(I,c)X DLTCF(ODe,pt,y,s=l) -&#13;
[(1 - IT(I,c)] WT(I,c) X DLTCF(ODe,pt,y,s=2)&#13;
13. Value of production by type of product and farm size and during each&#13;
year of the planning horizon of the with-project situations(monetary&#13;
unit), or&#13;
VP(p,y,u)         = TPC(pa,y,u) X FP(pt,y,c)&#13;
14. Costs of agricultural inputs per product, farm size and during each&#13;
year of the planning horizon of the with-project situations (monetary unit),&#13;
or&#13;
CIIFL(p,y,u)      = E TAI(pa,I,y,u) X FIIFL(pt,I,y,c)&#13;
I&#13;
15. Costs of agricultural inputs (with a shadow price for familv labor) per&#13;
project, farm size and during each year of the planning horizon of the&#13;
with-project situations(monetary unit), or&#13;
CIEFL(p,y,u)      = E TAI(pa,I,y,u) X FIEFL(pt,I,y,c)&#13;
I&#13;
16. Revenue by product, farm size and during each year of the planning&#13;
horizon of the with-project situations(monetary unit), or&#13;
RIFL(p,y,u)       = VP(p,y,u) - CIIFL(p,y,u)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 47 -&#13;
17. Revenue (with a shadow price for family labor) by product and farm&#13;
size and during each year of the planning horizon of the vith-project&#13;
situations (monetary unit/ton), or&#13;
REFL(p,y,u)   - VP(p,y,v) - CIEFL(p,y,u)&#13;
18. Total revenue during each year of planning horizon of the with-&#13;
project situations (monetary unit), or&#13;
TRIFL(p,y)    = E RIFL(p,y,u)&#13;
u&#13;
19. Total revenue (with a shadow price for family labor)during each year of&#13;
planning horizon of the with-project situations (monetary unit), or&#13;
TREFL(p,y)    - E REFL(p,y,u)&#13;
u&#13;
20. Change in annual revenue (monetary unit), or&#13;
DLRIFL(p,y)   - TRIFL(p,y) - TRIFL(pl,y)&#13;
21. Change in annual revenue (with a shadow price for fanmily labor;&#13;
monetary unit), or&#13;
DLREFL(p,y)   = TREFL(p,y) - TREFL(pl,y)&#13;
22. Change in the annual value of total production (monetary unit), or&#13;
DLVP(p,y)       E VP(p,y,u) - E VP(pl,y,u)&#13;
u             u&#13;
23. Change in annual costs of agricultural inputs (monetary unit), or&#13;
DLCIFL(p,y)   = E CIIFL(p,y,u) - E CIIFL(pl,y,u)&#13;
u                u&#13;
24. Change in annual costs of agricultural inputs (with a shadow price for&#13;
family labor; monetary unit), or&#13;
DLCEFL(p,y)   = E CIEFL(p,y,u) - E CIEFL(pl,y,u)&#13;
u                u&#13;
54.       Agricultural Investments Sub-Model&#13;
54.1      The inputs to this model are:&#13;
1.  CIIA(y,u)       = investment costs to significantly improve areas&#13;
for product c of farm size x during each year of the&#13;
planning horizon (monetary unit/ha)&#13;
2.  ICCL(y,u)       = investment costs to cultivate cultivable land for&#13;
product c of farm size x during each year of the&#13;
planning horizon (monetary unit/ha)&#13;
3.  INCNP(y,u)      = investment costs of new plantations for product c&#13;
of farm size x during each year of the planning&#13;
horizon (monetary unit/ha)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 48 -&#13;
54. 2      The calculations are:&#13;
1.  Variations in improved areas by type of product and farm size during&#13;
each year of the w:thc,it- and with-project situations (ha), or&#13;
AVICAB(pa,y9u)= ICAB(pa,y,u) - ICAB(pa,y-l,u)&#13;
2. Variations in additional cultivated areas by produet and farm size&#13;
during each year of the without- and with-project situations (ha), or&#13;
AVACA(pa,y,u) = ACA(pa,y,c) - ACA(pa,y-l,c)&#13;
3. Cost of investment to improve areas during year y for product c of farm&#13;
size x, for the without- and with-project situations (monetary unit), or&#13;
ICIA(p,y-l,u) = AVICAB(pa,y,u) X CIIA(y,u)&#13;
4.  Total costs of improving  areas during year y for all farm sizes and&#13;
products of the without- and with-project situations (monetary unit), or&#13;
TICIA(p,y)    = E ICIA(p,y,u)&#13;
u&#13;
5. Cost of investment to cultivate cultivable land during year y for&#13;
product c of farm size x, for the vithout- and with-project situations&#13;
(monetary unit), or&#13;
ICCA(p,y-l,u) - AVACA(pa,y,u) ICCL(y,u)&#13;
6. Total costs of cultivating cultivable land during year y for all farm&#13;
sizes and products of the without and with project situations (monetary&#13;
unit), or&#13;
TICCA(p,y)    = E ICCA(p,y,u)&#13;
u&#13;
7. Cost of investment for new plantations during year y for product c of&#13;
farm size x of without and wîth-project situations (monetary unit), or&#13;
ICNP(P,y-l,u) = AVCICA(pa,y,u) X INCNP(y,u)&#13;
8. Total costs of investments for new plantations during year y for all&#13;
farm sizes and products of the without- and with-project situations&#13;
(monetary unit), or&#13;
TICNP(p,y)    = E ICNP(p,y,u)&#13;
u&#13;
AGRICULTURAL TRAFFIC MODEL&#13;
55.       This model consists of three sub-models, i.e., Local Consumption&#13;
and Exports, Agricultural Traffic, and Value of Local Consumption and Exports.&#13;
Local consumption refers to agricultural products produced in the rural road's&#13;
zone of influence and consumed by people living in this zone. Exports refer&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 49 -&#13;
to agricultural products produced in the rural road's zone of influence and&#13;
exported outside this zone.&#13;
56.       Local Consumption and Exports Sub-Model&#13;
56.1      The inputs to this sub-model are:&#13;
1.  POP(pa,y)   = zone's population during year y of the without- or with-&#13;
project situation&#13;
2.  LCC(pl,l,c) = local per-capita consumption of product c during the&#13;
first year of the planning horizon (h=l) of the without-&#13;
project situation (tons/capita)&#13;
3.  ECC(c)      = elasticity of per-capita consumption of product c&#13;
4.  CF          = conversion factor between an animal-hour of transport&#13;
and on-farm services and the corresponding fodder intake&#13;
5. PEF(pa,If,y)= a zero-one integer to control the local consumption/&#13;
exports ôf fodder products during year y of the without-&#13;
and with-project situations&#13;
Note:  A zero value is assigned to ensure no exports of a fodder pro-&#13;
duct from the zone of influence; otherwise, one.&#13;
56.2      The calculations of the Local Consumption and Exports Sub-Models&#13;
are:&#13;
1. Average per-capita revenue for each year of the without- and with-&#13;
project situations (tons/capita), or&#13;
ACR(p,y)      T TREFL(p,y)&#13;
POP(pa,y)&#13;
2. Local per-capita consumption by product and year of the without- and&#13;
with-project situations (tons/capita), or&#13;
LCC(p,y,c)  = LCC(pl,l,c) X [ACR(P,l)]&#13;
3. Total consumption by product and year of the without- and with-project&#13;
situations (tons), or&#13;
TLCC(p,y,c) = POP(pa,y) X LCC(p,y,c)&#13;
4. Comparison of local production and local consumption of product c:&#13;
COMPI(p,y,c) = TP(pa,y,c) - PLCC(p,y,c)&#13;
If CCMPl(p,y,c) &lt; O, set TLCC(p,y,c) - TP(pa,y,c)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 50 -&#13;
5.  Total local consumption of all products locally produced during year y&#13;
of the without- and with-project situations (tons), or&#13;
TTLCC(p,y) = E TLCC(p,y,c)&#13;
c&#13;
Note: The above expressions deal with local consumption by people. The&#13;
following expressions deal with local consumption by animals.&#13;
6.  Local consumption of fodder products by animals bred for meat, milk&#13;
and wool production during each year of the planning horizon of the&#13;
without- and with-project situations (tons), or&#13;
LCFA(pa,y) = E E TAI(pa,If,y,u) X PEF(pa,If,y)&#13;
If u&#13;
7.  Local consumption by animals kept for transport and on-farm services&#13;
during each year of the planning horizon of the without-and with-project&#13;
situations (tons), or&#13;
LCFTA(pa,y) - E CF X E TAI(pa,If,y,u) XPEF(pa,If,y)&#13;
If      u&#13;
8. Total fodder inputs during each year of planning horizon of the without-&#13;
and with-project situations (tons), or&#13;
TFI(pa,y) = LCFA(pa9y) + LCFTA(pa,y)&#13;
9.  Comparison of local production and local consumption by animals during&#13;
each year of the planning horizon of the without- and with project situ-&#13;
ations (tons); or&#13;
COMP2(pa,y) = E TP(pa,y,c) PEFP(pa,y,c) - TFI(p,y)&#13;
ÉcE2&#13;
if COMP2(pa,y) &gt; 0, local consumption - TFI(p,y)&#13;
if COMP2(pa,y) &lt; 0, local consumption = TP(pa,y,c)&#13;
Note: E2 represents the group of fodder products.&#13;
10. Exportable surplus by product and year of the without- and with-project&#13;
situations for products other than fodder (tons), or&#13;
EXSU(p,y,c) - TP(pa,y,c) - TLCC(p,y,c)&#13;
11. Exportable surplus of fodder products during each year of the planning&#13;
horizon of the without- and with-project situations (tons), or&#13;
EXSUF(pa,y) = COMP2(pa,y), if COMP2(pa,y) &gt; 0, and&#13;
EXSUF(pa,y) = 0,if COMP2 (pa,y) &lt; O&#13;
12. Total exportable surplus during each year of the planning horizon of&#13;
the without- and with-project situations (tons), or&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TEXSU(p,y) - EXSUF(p,y) + E EXSU(p,y,c)&#13;
57.       Agricultural Traffic Sub-Model&#13;
57.1      This sub-model does not require any new input data.&#13;
57.2      The calculations are:&#13;
1. Matrices M on a year-to-year basis (by extrapolation), or&#13;
M(pt,t,y,v) = M(pt,t,hl,v)+ [M(pt,t,h2,v) - M(pt,t,hl,v)] (Y 1)&#13;
(h2-hl)&#13;
2. Average daily traffic by means of transport v and related to the&#13;
exports of agricultural products during each year of the planning horizon&#13;
of the without- and with-project situations (transport means/day), or&#13;
ADTE(p,y,v)  - 6 M(pt,t=2,y,v) X TEXSU(p,y)&#13;
3. Total imports of agricultural inputs during each year of the planning&#13;
horizon of the without- and with-project situations (tons), or&#13;
TIAI(pa,y)   = E [ITS(pa,y,u,s=l) +-ITS(pa,y,u,s=2)]&#13;
u&#13;
4. Average daily traffic by means of transport v and related to the imports&#13;
of agricultural inputs during each year of the planning horizon of the&#13;
without- and with-project situations (transport means/day), or&#13;
ADTI(p,y,v)  =  6 M(pt,t=2,y,v) TIAI(pa,y)&#13;
5.  Average daily traffic resulting from agricultural activities in zone&#13;
of influence, by means of transport v during each year of the planning&#13;
horizon of the without- and with-project situations (transport means/day),&#13;
or&#13;
ADTEI(p,y,v) = ADTE(p,y,v) +.ADTI(p,y,v)&#13;
6.  Average daily motorized traffic resulting from agricultural activities&#13;
in the zone of influence during each year of the planning horizon of the&#13;
without- and with-project situations (vehicles/day), or&#13;
8&#13;
ADTM(p,y)    =  E ADTEI(p,y,v)&#13;
vM3&#13;
Note: v=l and v=2 are assumed to be non=motorized means of transport;&#13;
all other v are assumed to be motorized means of transport.&#13;
7.  Average daily animal traffic resulting from agricultural activities&#13;
in the zone of influence during each year of the planning horizon of the&#13;
without- and with-project situations (animals or animal carts/day), or&#13;
2&#13;
ADTA(p,y)    =  E ADTEI(p,y,v)&#13;
v1=1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 52 -&#13;
58.       VaLue of Local Consumption and Exports Sub-Model&#13;
58.1      This sub-model requires only one input data:&#13;
FLCCl(c)       farm-gate efficiency price for locally consumed product c&#13;
of the without-project situation (monetary unit/tons)&#13;
58.2      The calculations of this sub-model are:&#13;
1. Farm-gate efficiency price of exports in the without-project situations&#13;
(monetary unit/ton)&#13;
a. For non-fodder products:&#13;
TP(pal,y=l,c) X FACl(c) - TLCC(p,y=l,c) FLCCl(c).&#13;
FEPl(c)      - [                   EXSU(pl,y=l,c)&#13;
if EXSU(pl,y=1,c) - O, then FEP1(c) = FLCCl(c).&#13;
b. For fodder products:&#13;
FEF1(c)      =      [TP(Pal,y=l,c) FAC1(c) - TLCC(pl,y=l,c) FLCC1(c)1&#13;
FEFi(e)  =ccE2                    EXSUIF(pl,y=1)&#13;
if EXSUF = O, then FEF1(c) = FLCCl(c).&#13;
2.  Farm-gate efficiency price of exports in with-project situations&#13;
(monetary unit/ton)&#13;
a. For non-fodder products:&#13;
FEP(pt,y,c) = FEPl(c) + K(c) DLTCF(ODe,pt,y,s=l) +&#13;
+ L(c) DLTCF(ODe,pt,y,s=2)&#13;
b. For fodder products:&#13;
FEF(p,y)     = FEF1(cf)+ K(cf) DLTCF(ODe,pt,y,s=l) +&#13;
+ L(cf) DLTCF(ODe,pt,y,s=2)&#13;
3.  Value of exports during each year of the without- and with-project&#13;
situations (monetary unit)&#13;
a.  For products other than fodder (by product):&#13;
VEC(p,y,c)   = EXSU(p,y,c) FEP(pt,y,c)&#13;
b.  For total of fodder products:&#13;
VECF(p,y)    = EXSUF(pa,y) FEF(p,y) +    E EXSU(p,y,c)&#13;
ccE2&#13;
4. Value of local consumption during each year of the without- and with-&#13;
project situations (monetary unit)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 53 -&#13;
a.  For products other,than fodder (by product):&#13;
VLCC(p,y,c) = VP(p,y,c) - VEC(p,y,c)&#13;
b.  For total of fodder products:&#13;
VLCCF(p,y,c) =   E VP(p,y,c) - VECF(p,y)&#13;
ceE2&#13;
5. Total value of exports (all products) during each year of the planning&#13;
horizon of the without- and with-project situations (monetary unit), or&#13;
TVE(p,y)     =   r VEC(p,y,c) + VECF(p,y)&#13;
ccE2&#13;
6. Total value of local consumption during each year of the planning&#13;
horizon of the without-and with-project situations (monetary unit), or&#13;
TVLC(p,y)    =   E VLCC(p,y,c) + VLCCF(p,y)&#13;
ccE2&#13;
DISTRIBUTION OF TRANSPORT SAVINGS MODEL&#13;
59.       This model treats increased values accruing to:    (i) consumers, and&#13;
(ii) transporters and other intermediate organizations. It consists of the&#13;
Consumers' Surplus Sub-Model and the Transporters' Surplus Sub-Model.&#13;
60.       Consumers' Surplus Sub-Model&#13;
60.1      The input to this sub-model is:&#13;
BC(pt)        = portion of the-transport savings accruing to the&#13;
consumer&#13;
60.2      The calculations are:&#13;
1. Annual transport savings for traffic type 2, per season and year of&#13;
the with-project situations(monetary unit), or&#13;
DLCT2(ODe,pt,y,s) = DLTTCT(ODe,pt,t=2,hl,s) + -[DLTTCT(ODe,pt,t=2,h2,s) -&#13;
- DLTTCT(ODe,pt,t=2,hl,s) X   y-l&#13;
h2-hl&#13;
Note:  Traffic type 2 is commodity traffic using the project road.&#13;
2.&#13;
2. Annual transport savings by product and year of the with-project&#13;
situations (monetary unit), or&#13;
DLCTC(pt,y,c) = K(c) DLCT2(pt,y,s=l) + L(c) DLCT2(pt,y,s=2)&#13;
3. Consumer surplus by product and year of the without- and with-project&#13;
situations (monetary Unit), or&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 54 -&#13;
- For all products other than fodder:&#13;
CSC(p,y,c) = BC(pt) X DLCTC(pt,y,c)[EXSUPpy,c) + EXSU(pl,y,c)]&#13;
- For fodder products:&#13;
CSC(p,y,cf) = BC(pt) DLCTC(pt,y,cf)[EXSU(P,Y,cf) + EXSU(pl,y,cf)1&#13;
2&#13;
4. Total consumer surplus of all fodder and non-fodder products by year&#13;
of the without- and with-project situations (monetary unit), or&#13;
TCSC(p,y)   = E CSC(p,y,c)&#13;
c&#13;
61.       Transporters' Surplus Sub-Model&#13;
61.1      The inputs to this model are:&#13;
1.  PBT         = the benefit (transport price minus transport cost)&#13;
accruing to the transporter (expressed as a percentage&#13;
of the transport cost)&#13;
2. AVL(v)       = average load of transport means v (tons)&#13;
61.2      The calculations are:&#13;
1.  BT(pt,h,s)   = 1 - BF(pt,h,s) - BC(pt)&#13;
BT(pt,y,s)  = BT(pt,hl,s) + [BT(pt,h2,s) -BT(pt,hl,s)] X 1  Y-&#13;
h2-hl&#13;
2. Motorized agricultural traffic in year y of the with-project situations&#13;
(transport means/day), or&#13;
8&#13;
MAT(pt,y)       E M(pt,t=l,y,v) X AVL(v) + M(pt,t=2,y,v) X AVL(v)]&#13;
v=3&#13;
3. Quantities transported during the summer (dry) season and related to&#13;
the agricultural activities in the road's zone of influence by product and&#13;
year of the without- and with-project situations (tons), or&#13;
- For all products other than fodder:&#13;
4&#13;
IQT(p,y,c,s=l)  =   E ITS(pa,y,u,s=l) + K(c) EXSU(p,y,c)&#13;
x=l&#13;
- For fodder products:&#13;
4&#13;
IQT(p,y,cf,s=l) =   E1ITS(pa,y,u,s=l) + K(cf)[EXSUF(pa,y)+ EXSU(p,y,cf)]&#13;
4.  Quantities transported during the winter (rainy) season and related to&#13;
the agricultural activities in the road's zone of influence by product and&#13;
year of the without- and with-project situations (tons), or&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 55 -&#13;
- For all products other than fodder:&#13;
4&#13;
IQT(p,y,c,s-2) - E ITS(pa,y,u,s=2) + K(c) EXSU(p,y,c)&#13;
x=l&#13;
- For fodder products:&#13;
IQT(p,y,cf,s=2) = ITS(pa,y,u,s=2) +-K(cf)[EXSUF(pa,y) + EXSU(p,y,cf)]&#13;
5. Annual benefits accruing to transporter in each season of the without-&#13;
and with-project situations for OD's on route e (monetary unit), or&#13;
First:&#13;
ABT(ODe,pt,h,s) = [1 - PIO(pt,h,s)] X [TTCT(ODe,pt,t=2,h,s)] X PBT&#13;
for h=1 and h=2&#13;
Next:&#13;
ABT(ODe,pt,y,s) = ABT(ODe,pt,hl,s) + [ABT(ODe,pt,h2,s) - ABT(ODe,pt,hl,s)] X&#13;
x  L-&#13;
X h2-hl&#13;
6. Transporters' surplus by product and year of the without- and with-&#13;
project situations (monetary unit), or&#13;
2&#13;
TSU(p,y,c)    E IQT(p,y,c,s) X BT(pt,y,s) X DLCT2(pt,y,s) + MAT(pt,y) X&#13;
s=l&#13;
X ABT(pt,y,s) X [IQT(p,y,c,s) - IQT(pl,y,c,s)1&#13;
if IQT(p,y,c,s) - IQT(pl,y,c,s) &gt; O&#13;
2&#13;
TSU(p,y,c) =  E IQT(p,y,c,s) X BT(pt,y,s) X DLCT2(pt,y,s)&#13;
s=l&#13;
if IQT(p,y,c,s) - IQT(pl,y,c,s) &lt; O&#13;
Note:  DLTC2(pt,y,s) is the average of DLTC2(ODe,pt.v,s) over all OD's on&#13;
route e (ODe).&#13;
7. Total transporters surplus by year of the without- and with-project&#13;
situations (monetary unit), or&#13;
TTSU(p,y) = E TSU(p,y,c)&#13;
c&#13;
NON-AGRICULTURAL TRAFFIC AND RELATED BENEFITS MODEL&#13;
62.       This model consists of three sub-models, i.e., the Non-Agricultural&#13;
Traffic, the Related Benefits and the Traffic Sub-Models.&#13;
63.       Non-Agricultural Traffic Sub-Model&#13;
63.1      The inputs to this sub-model are:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 56 -&#13;
= average daily traf fie of type t=l on each OD pair&#13;
of route e during each year of the planning&#13;
horizon of the without-project situation (passenger/&#13;
day)&#13;
ADT2'ODe,ptl,y)  = average daily non-agricultural traffic of type t=2&#13;
in each OD pair of route e during each year of the&#13;
planning horizon of the without-project situation&#13;
( tons/day)&#13;
3.  ADT3(ODr,y)      = average daily traffic of type t=3 on each OD pair&#13;
of route n during each year of the planning horizon&#13;
(passengers/day)&#13;
4. ADT4(ODn,y)       = average daily traffic of type t=4 on each OD pair&#13;
of route n during each year of the planning horizon&#13;
(tons/day)&#13;
5.  EL1              = elasticity coefficient for the calculation of&#13;
generated traffic of type t=l&#13;
6.  E'3              = elasticity coefficient for the calculation of&#13;
generated traffic of type t=3&#13;
63.2      The calculations of this sub-model are:&#13;
1. Generation factor for traffic type t=1 on OD's of route e during each&#13;
season of the without- and with-project situations and for the beginning&#13;
and end of the planning horizon, or&#13;
GFTl(ODe,pt,h,s) = [1 - DLTTCT(ODe,pt,l,h,s)       -EL1&#13;
2. Average generation factor for traffic type t=1 for OD's of route e&#13;
during the beginning and end of the planning horizon of the without- and&#13;
with-project situations, or&#13;
AGFTl(ODe,pt,h)  = (365- ANDR)GFTl(ODe,pt,h,l) +ANDRX GFTl(ODe,pt,h,2)&#13;
365&#13;
Note:  Generated commodity traffic is not considered.&#13;
3. Interpolation of the average generation factor for traffic type t=l, or&#13;
AGFTl(ODe,pt,y) = AFGTl(ODe,pt,hl) + [AGFTl(ODe,pt,h2) - AFGTl(ODe,pt,hl)] X&#13;
x y-1&#13;
h2-hl&#13;
4.  Average daily traffic of type t=l for OD's of route e during each year&#13;
of the planning horizon of the with-project situations (passengers/day),or&#13;
ADTl(ODe,pt,y)   = ADTl(ODe,ptl,y) X [l + AgFTl(ODe,pt,y)]&#13;
5. Average daily traffic of type t=3, during each year of the planning&#13;
horizon of the without- and with-project situations(passengers/day), or&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 57 -&#13;
(365 - ANDR) E ADT3(ODn,y) + ANDR E ADT3(ODn,y)&#13;
ADT03(pt,y)      =              ODnCE(3.1)             ODneE(3,2)&#13;
365&#13;
where ODncE(3,s) = group of OD's for which DLTTCT(ODn,pt,t=3,y,s) &gt; O&#13;
6. Average daily traffic of type t=4 during each year of the planning horiz&#13;
of the without- and with-project situations (tons/day), or&#13;
(365 - ANDR) E ADT4(ODn,y) + ANDR E ADT4(ODn,y)&#13;
ADT04(pt,y)      =             ODncE(4,1)              ODncE(4.2)&#13;
365&#13;
where ODneE(4,s) = group of OD's for which DLTTCT(ODn,pt,t=4,y,s) &gt; O&#13;
7. Generation factor for long distance passenger traffic on OD's belonging&#13;
to E(3,s) and route n in each season of the without- and with-project&#13;
situations and for the beginning and of planning horizon, or&#13;
DLTTCT(ODn,~pt,3,h,s)1 -'&#13;
GFT3(ODn,pt,h,s) - [1 - TTCT(ODn,pt,3,h,s)        - i&#13;
GFT3(ODn,pt,h,s) = O, if DLTTCT(ODn,pt,3,h,s) &lt; O&#13;
8. Average generation factor for long distance passenger traffic in the&#13;
vithout- and with-project situations and for the beginning and end of planning&#13;
horizon, or&#13;
AGFT3(ODn,pt,h) = (365- ANDR) GFT3(oDn,pt,h,l) + ANDR GFT3(ODn,pt,h,2)&#13;
365&#13;
9. Interpolation of the average generation factor for long distance traffic,&#13;
or&#13;
AGFT-3(ODn,pt,y) = AGFT3(ODn,pt,hl) + [AGFT3(ODn,pt,h2) - AGFT3(ODn,pt,hl)]X&#13;
X Y-1&#13;
h2-hl&#13;
10. Generated long-distance passenger traffic per OD and for the total of&#13;
OD's during each year of the planning horizon of the without- and with-&#13;
project situations (passenger/day), or&#13;
GT3(ODn,pt,y)    = ADT3(ODn,y) X AGFT3(ODn,pt,y)&#13;
TGT3(pt,y)       =  E GT3(ODn,pt,y)&#13;
ODn&#13;
64.       Related Benefits Sub-Model&#13;
64.1      No additional inputs are required.&#13;
64.2      The calculations of this sub-model are:&#13;
1. Reduction in costs of transport per OD, per traffic type, per season&#13;
and during each year of the planning horizon of the without- and with-&#13;
project situations (monetary unit), or&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 58 -&#13;
.  -r  j&amp;  Æ  3  .rc!  4:&#13;
r.,LrTCT(OD,pt,t,y,s) DLTTCT(OD,pt,t,hl,s) + [DLTTCT(OD,pt,t,h2,s) -&#13;
DLTTCT(OD,pt,t,hl,)] h2-'L&#13;
h 2-hl&#13;
2. Average reduction in daily transport costs, per OD, per traffic type&#13;
and during each year of the planning horizon of the without- and with-project&#13;
situations (monetary unit), or&#13;
For t-l, 2, 3 and 4:&#13;
DLTCM(OD,pt,t,y)      (365-ANDR) DLTTCT(OD,pt,t,y,l)+ANDR DLTTCT(OD,pt,t.y,2)&#13;
365&#13;
3. Annual benefits related to traffic type t-l for each and all OD's of route&#13;
e during each year of the planning horizon of the with-project situations&#13;
(monetary unit), or&#13;
ABTl(ODe,pt,y)      = 365 X ADTl(ODe,ptl,y) DLTCM(ODe,pt,l,y) and&#13;
TABTl(pt,y)         =  E ABTl(ODe,pt,y)&#13;
ODe&#13;
4. Annual benefits related to traffic type t-2 for each and all OD's of route&#13;
e during each year of the planning horizon of the with-project situations&#13;
(monetary-unit), or&#13;
ABTZ(ODe,pt,y)      - 365X ADT2(ODe,ptl,y) DLTCM(ODe,pt,2,y) and&#13;
TABT2(pt,y)         =  E ABT2(ODe,pt,y)&#13;
ODe&#13;
5. Annual benefits resulting from generated passenger traffic on each and&#13;
all OD's of route e during each year of the planning horizon of the with-&#13;
project situations (monetary unit), or&#13;
ABGTl(ODe,pt,y)     = 365 [ADTl(ODe,pt,y) - ADTl(ODe,ptl,y)] X&#13;
2&#13;
X DLTCM(ODe,pt,l,y) and&#13;
TABGTl(pt,y)        =  E ABGTl(ODe,pt,y)&#13;
ODe&#13;
6.  Annual benefits resulting from diverted passenger traffic during each&#13;
year of the planning horizon of the with-project situations (monetary unit),&#13;
or&#13;
ABDT3(pt,y)            (365 - ANDR)  E ADT3(oDn,y) X DLTTCT(ODn,pt,3,y,l) +&#13;
ODncE(3,sl)&#13;
+ ANDR E ADT3(ODn,y) X DLTTCT(ODn,pt,3,y,2)&#13;
ODncE(3,s=2)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 59 -&#13;
7. Annual benefits resulting from long distance generated passenger traffic&#13;
during each year of the planning horizon of the with-project situations&#13;
(monetary unit), or&#13;
ABGT3(pt,y)            365  E GT3(ODn,pt,y) X DLTCM(ODn,pt,3,y)&#13;
ABGT3(pt,y)2         ODn&#13;
8.  Annual benefits resulting from diverted commodity traffic during each&#13;
year of the planning horizon of the with-project situations (monetarv unit),&#13;
or&#13;
ABDT4(pt,y)            (365 - ANDR)  E ADT4(ODn,y) X DLTTCT(ODn,pt,4,y,1&#13;
ODncE(4,s-1)&#13;
+ ANDR E ADT4(ODn,y) X DLTTCT(ODn,pt,4,y,2)&#13;
ODnEE(4,s=2)&#13;
Note that E(3,s=l) and E(3,s=2) are the groups of OD's of route n for which&#13;
DLTTCT(ODn,pt,t=3,y,s) &gt; 0; E(4,s=1) and E(4,s=2) are the groups of OD's of&#13;
route n for which DLTTCT(ODn,pt,t=4,y,s) &gt; O.&#13;
65.       Traffic Sub-Model&#13;
65.1      No additional inputs are required.&#13;
65.2      The calculations of this model are as follows:&#13;
1.  For type 1 traffic:&#13;
ADTl(ODe,pt,y) or average daily traffic of type t=l on OD's of route e&#13;
during each year of the planning horizon of the without-&#13;
and with-project situations (passengers/day)&#13;
and&#13;
TTl(p,y)     =  E ADTl(ODe,pt,y), or traffic of type t=l on route e&#13;
ODe&#13;
during each year of the planning horizon of the without-&#13;
and with-project situations (passengers/day)&#13;
2. For type 2 traffic:&#13;
TT2(p,y)       TEXSU(p,y) + TIAI(pa,y) + ADT2(ODe.ptl,y)&#13;
365&#13;
or traffic of type t=2 during each year of the planning&#13;
horizon of the without- and with-project situations&#13;
(tons/day)&#13;
3. For type 3 traffic:&#13;
TT3(p,y)       ADT03(pt,y) + TGT3(pt,y)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 60 -&#13;
or traffic of type t-3 during each year of the planning&#13;
horizon of the without- and with-project situations&#13;
(passengers/day)&#13;
4. For type 4 traffic:&#13;
TT4(p,y)     = ADT04(pt,y)&#13;
or traffic of type t=4 during each year of the planning&#13;
horizon of the without- and with-project situations&#13;
(tons/day)&#13;
5. Average daily traffic on the rural road considered during each year of&#13;
the planning horizon of the without- and with-project situations (transport&#13;
means/day), or&#13;
ADTV(p,y,v) = [TTl(p,y) TT2(p,y) TT3(p,y) TT4(p,y)] X M(pt,t,y,v)&#13;
ECONOMIC RETURN MODEL&#13;
66.       This model consists of three sub-models, i.e., Costs and Benefits,&#13;
ER and NPV, and the Optimal Year. The inputs to these three sub-models are:&#13;
1.  CCONS(p,y)  = costs of improving or constructing the rural road, by year&#13;
of the with-project situations (monetary unit)&#13;
2.  CMAINT(p,y) = maintenance costs of the rural road (annual or periodic),&#13;
by year of the without- and with-project situations&#13;
(monetary unit)&#13;
3.  CES(p,y)    = costs of new techniques introduced to extension services,&#13;
by year of the with-project situations (monetary unit)&#13;
4.  CCRED(p,y)  = costs of making agricultural credit available, by year&#13;
of the without- and with-project situations (monetary unit)&#13;
5.  COTHR(p,y)  = other costs (e.g., for irrigation works or silos), by&#13;
year of the without- and with-project situations (monetary&#13;
unit)&#13;
6.  ELIIA       = expected life of investments to improve an area (TICIA;&#13;
year)&#13;
7.  ELICA       = expected life of investments to cultivate cultivable land&#13;
(TICCA; year)&#13;
8.  ELICNP      = expected life of plantations (TICNP; year)&#13;
9.  ELRR        = expected life of rural road (year)&#13;
10. ELES        = expected life of investments for extension services (CES;&#13;
year)&#13;
11. ELCRED      = expected life of agricultural credit facilities (CCRED;&#13;
year)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 61 -&#13;
12. ELOTHR       = expected life of other facilities (COTHR; year)&#13;
13. Seven replacement coefficients corresponding to Items 6 throug'; 12 above&#13;
[RC(1), RC(2), RC(3), RC(4), RC(5), RC(6), RC(7)]&#13;
67.       Costs and Benefits.   the costs of investments to be considered in&#13;
the ER and NPV calculations are the aforementioned five costs and the follcw-&#13;
ing three, which have already been computed in the AGRICULTURAL REVENUE MODEL,&#13;
viz, TICIA(p,y), TICCA(p,y) and TICNP(p,y). Naturally, costs of replacement&#13;
investments should be considered if these occur. The benefits to be considered&#13;
in the ER and NPV calculations are:&#13;
1. Benefits to farmers: DLRIFL(p,y) or DLREFL(p,y)&#13;
2. Benefits related to the agricultural development but not accruing to&#13;
the farmers: TCSC(p,y) and TTSU(p,y)&#13;
3. Benefits related to non-agricultural traffic:&#13;
TABT1(pt,y)&#13;
TABGT1&lt;pt,y)&#13;
TABT2(pt,y)&#13;
ABDT3(pt,y)&#13;
ABGT3(pt,y)&#13;
ABDT4(pt,y)&#13;
4. Other benefits [BOTHR(p,y)] to be introduced as an input to this model.&#13;
5. Salvage values: Certain agricultural investments can have an expected&#13;
life,which exceeds that of the rural road. Therefore, the following salvage&#13;
values (monetary value) should be introduced as a benefit at the end of the&#13;
planning horizon, if this is the case:&#13;
Salvage value of TICIA(p,y), or&#13;
h2 y ELIIA - (h2 + 1 -y)(p&#13;
SVIIA(p)  =  E [       -                X TICIA(p,y)&#13;
Salvage value of TICCA(p,y), or&#13;
SVICNP()   Eh2 [ELICA - (h2 + 1 - vY1   X TICCA(Âpy)&#13;
y=1         ELICA&#13;
Salvage value of TICNP(p,y), or&#13;
SVICNP(p) =  E~ [EIN       h2+i-v        X TIICNP(p,y)&#13;
y=l         ELICNP&#13;
Note that salvage values may also exist for investments related to CES, CCRED&#13;
and COTHR; the expected lives of these investments are, however, likely to&#13;
be smaller than the expected life of the rural road. Consequently, these&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 62 -&#13;
salvage values may be considered by introducing a salvage value for&#13;
the replacement investments corresponding to CES, CCRED and COTHR.&#13;
68.       ER and NPV.  Techniques for computing the ER and the NPV are well&#13;
known and, therefore, not described here. An ER, NPV and optimal year may&#13;
be computed for the following combinations:&#13;
Rural Roads                   Agricultural Investments&#13;
pt - 2                              pa - 2&#13;
Pt - 3                              pa - 2&#13;
pt - 2                              pa - 3&#13;
Pt - 3                              pa - 3&#13;
69.       Optimal Year.  The following symbols are introduced to facilitate the&#13;
determination of the optimal year of road and agricultural investments, which&#13;
are lnterdependent.&#13;
yc       - year of completing the road improvement (construction)&#13;
RHO(1)   - RHO(yc - l,l,yc)&#13;
- c(yc - 1) + c[yc - 2(1 + i)] + ... + c(yc - y)(1 + i),y - 1&#13;
- CCONS during year yc - y, yc - (y - 1), ..., yc - 2 and&#13;
yc - 1&#13;
RHO(2)   - stmilar formula for CES&#13;
RROM3)   - similar formula for CCRED&#13;
RHOM4)   - similar formula for COTHR&#13;
RHO(5)   - similar formula for TICIA&#13;
1110(6)  - similar formula for TICCA&#13;
THO(7)   - similar formula for TICNP&#13;
Di       .ELIR&#13;
D2       - ELES&#13;
D3       - ELCIED&#13;
D4         ELOTHR&#13;
D5       - ELIIA&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 63 -&#13;
D6       - ELICA&#13;
D7       - ELICNP&#13;
i        - opportunity cost of capital&#13;
Al(y)    - total net benefits during year y, which are independent&#13;
of yc&#13;
A2(y-yc) - total net benefits during year y which depend on (y-yc)&#13;
sî    - Dl    A2(n)&#13;
nml (1 + i)n&#13;
RC(1)    - replacement coefficient of rural road (1 - invage       colu )&#13;
investment cost&#13;
RC(2)    = replacement coefficient corresponding to CES&#13;
RC(3)    = replacement coefficient corresponding to CCRED&#13;
RC(4)    - replacement coefficient corresponding to COTHR&#13;
RC(5)    = replacement coefficient.corresponding to TICIA&#13;
RC(6)    - replacement coefficient corresponding to TICCA&#13;
RC(7)    - replacement coefficient corresponding to TICNP&#13;
L(2)     3        1&#13;
(1l+i)D   - 1&#13;
L(2)     =        1&#13;
(1 + i)D2 _ 1&#13;
L(3)              1&#13;
(1 + i)D3 - 1&#13;
L(4)     G1i&#13;
(+ i)     -1&#13;
L(5)              i &#13;
(1 + i)D5 - 1&#13;
L(6)     =        1&#13;
(1 + i)D6 -&#13;
L(7)     -        1&#13;
(1 + i)D7 -&#13;
The decision rule for determining the optimal year oy of the investment package&#13;
can now be formulated as follows:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
_ 64 -&#13;
7&#13;
a. If [ E RHO(J) {1 + RC(J) L(J)} - Sll &gt; O,&#13;
J=3.&#13;
oy is the first year for which&#13;
7         ~~Al(t)~&#13;
j-1 RHO(J) {i + RC(j) L(j)} - Si]&#13;
7&#13;
b. If [E RHO(J) {i + RC(J) L(J)} - Si] &lt; O, and if Al(t) &gt; O,&#13;
j-1&#13;
oy - as soon as possible&#13;
7&#13;
c.  If [E RHO(J) {i + RC(J) L(J)) - S1] &lt; O, and if Al(t) &lt; O,&#13;
ini&#13;
oy -infinite &lt;never implementation)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 65 -&#13;
ANNEX 1&#13;
ECONOMIC ANALYSIS OF ROAD AND AGRICULTURAL INVESTMENTSI/&#13;
1.        The following presentation pertains to the economic evaluation&#13;
of an investment package consisting of a rural road improvement (construc-&#13;
tion) and complementary agricultural investments in its zone of influence.&#13;
The prices on the local market of agricultural products produced in the rural&#13;
road's zone of influence and transported to the local market, which are called&#13;
the "local market prices", are assumed constant. In other words, the local&#13;
market is the importing area and the road's zone of influence is the&#13;
producing area. In addition to simplify the presentation non-agricultural&#13;
traffic is ignored. Thus, all benefits to be had from the investment package&#13;
accrue to farmers in the zone of influence and/or transporters of agricultural&#13;
products over the rural road under consideration.&#13;
No Home Consumption&#13;
2.        The benefits (B) accruing to farmers and transporters during a&#13;
specific year of the situation where only one agricultural crop in the zone&#13;
of influence is cultivated are graphically portrayed in Figure 1. This&#13;
presentation as well as expression (1) for these benefits ignore home con-&#13;
sumption in the with- and without-project situations.&#13;
1/ This form of presentation was auggested by Anandarup Ray. For extensive&#13;
analysis along similar lines, see H. G. van der Tak and A. Ray, "The&#13;
Economic Benefits of Road Transport Projects," World Bank Occasional&#13;
Paper No. 13.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 66 -&#13;
a    PM&#13;
4,&#13;
W1 t&#13;
A&#13;
B&#13;
q-           q2&#13;
exportable surplus (tons)&#13;
Figure 1&#13;
B      - (Pm q2    R2) - (Pm ql - R1)            ........... (1)&#13;
where&#13;
Pm     = local market price of a specific agricultural product ($/ton)&#13;
qj,q2 = exports of this product from tLle road's zone of influence&#13;
in the without- and with-project situation, respectively&#13;
(tons)&#13;
R1, R2 = economic cost of producing and transporting to the local&#13;
market (over the rural road under consideration) q1 and q2&#13;
tons, respectively ($)&#13;
Note that Pm is assumed to be constant in the without- and with-project situ-&#13;
ations (para. 1).&#13;
3.        The costs R1 and R2 can be divided into costs of production and&#13;
cost of transportation:&#13;
C1, C2 = economic cost of producing ql and q2, respectively ($)&#13;
K1, K2 = economic cost of transporting over the rural road the&#13;
exports q1 and q2, respectively ($)&#13;
Thus, expression (1) becomes&#13;
B      = (Pm q2 - C2 - K2) - (Pm q1 - C1 - K1)         ...... (2)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 67 -&#13;
4.        The following terms are introduced in order to divide E int&#13;
or benefits accruing to farmers and B2, or benefits accruing to treo.        :rs.&#13;
kl, k2 = economic coste of transporting over the rural rcad ;n&lt;»&#13;
ton of q1 and one ton of q2   respectively ($/ton)&#13;
F1, F  = fare of transporting over the rural road one ton of&#13;
1  2  and one ton q2, respectively ($/ton)&#13;
Thus,     K     K E   K    K    and&#13;
1   K1 q1, K2E Kq2,&#13;
K1 -K2 = k1 q1 - k2 q2 D (F1 q1 -F2 q2]          2 q2 -1 F  1q &#13;
- (k2 q2 - k1 ql)]&#13;
The term [F1 q1 - F2 q2] represents the difference between the farmer'8 trans-&#13;
port bill in the without-project situation and hie bill in the with-project&#13;
situation, while [(F2 q2 - F1 ql) - (k2 q2 - k1 ql)] represents the portion&#13;
of transport savinge accruing to transporters in the form of a higher profit.&#13;
Calling (F2~ q2 - F1 ql) the A transport revenues and (k2 q2 - k1 q1) the A&#13;
transport costs, we may also write:&#13;
K  - K2 = -[à transport revenues] +[à transport revenues -&#13;
1    2&#13;
- A transport costa]&#13;
Defining&#13;
P1, P2 = farm-gate price of a specific agricultural product ir. the&#13;
without- and with-project situation,    respective'L ($/ton)&#13;
results in Pm = P2 + F2 = P1 + F1&#13;
Thus, the farm-gate price increases in the with-project situation by (i,      f&#13;
5.        Expression (2) can now be rewritten as&#13;
B      ={B1} +(B2}-([(P2 + F2)q2 - C2] - [(P1 + Fl)ql - C1] +&#13;
+ [F1 q -F2 q2fl +f[F2 q2 - F1 ql] - [k2 q2 - k1 ql1&#13;
={[P2 q2 - C2] - [Plql - Cl1 +{[F2 q2 - F1 qlj -&#13;
- [k2 q2 - kl qlD                        .......... (3)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 68 -&#13;
Home Consum gption&#13;
6.        Expressions (1), (2) and (3) ignore the home consumption in the&#13;
without- and with-project sItuations (para. 2). Reference is made to&#13;
Figure 2 in order to examine the effect of   home consumption on B1.&#13;
_ P2                                      B/&#13;
4P1D&#13;
o&#13;
Qiuantïties of an agricuItural&#13;
product (tons)&#13;
Figure 2&#13;
The symbols Hl, H2, Ql1 Q2, Pl and, P2 in- Figure 2 denote:&#13;
Hl, H2 = on-farm (home) consumption of the agricultural product&#13;
with farm-gate price Pl and P2, respectively (tons)&#13;
Q1' Q2 = production of the' agricultural product with farm-gate&#13;
price Pl and P2, respectively (tons)&#13;
Pl' P 2 = as defined in para. 4&#13;
Note that q, = Q1   H   and q2   Q2&#13;
1 -    2 =Q2 -H2      Q &#13;
The benefits accruing to farmers (Bl) during a specific year of the situation&#13;
where one agricultural crop in the zone of influence is cultivated are&#13;
represented by area ABCD of Figure 2. Assuming that AD and BC of the demand&#13;
and supply curves of.igure 2 can be approximated by straight lines, gives:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 69 -&#13;
area ABCD= (P2-F)Q1 + 2 (P2 - P1) (Q2 - Ql) - [H1(P2 - P1&#13;
-1 (Hi - 2)     (P2 - Pl) &#13;
=P2 - Pl) (Q1      H I) + y (P2 - P1) I(Q2 - Q1) + (H1      -H2)&#13;
or, since q1 = (Q1 - H1) and q2 = (Q2 - H2)1&#13;
area ABCD    (P2 - Pl)q1 + 2 (P2 - Pl)[(q2 - q1) + (H1 - H2)]&#13;
=   (P2 - P1) (q2                            2 qj) + (P2 - P1)q1   - -(P2 - Pl)(q2 -  f)&#13;
Defining AP = (P2     P1) and Aq - (q2 - q1) results in&#13;
B1      -APq1 + j   PAq                                .      ...  (4)&#13;
Another way of expression B1 ls&#13;
i&#13;
B1        2 (F 1 -y2)(q2 + q.                               .    . (5)&#13;
since P2   -(Pm    F2) and P1     (Pm- F).&#13;
Expressions (4) and (5) are graphlcally represented by areas ABCD of Figure 3&#13;
and Figure 4, respectively. Note that areas ABED asd BEC of Figure 3 corres-&#13;
pond to APql and 1APAq respectively; areas AMCD and ECB of Figure 4 also&#13;
correspond to APql and 4 PAq respectively.&#13;
* c&#13;
2~~~~~~&#13;
Exportable srplus rtons:Exportable SrplUB (tonB&#13;
o&#13;
AJ&#13;
&lt;'v&#13;
4-.~~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
a' ~ ~   ~                 2                           ,q&#13;
Exportble srplus  tons)Exporable srplus(tons&#13;
'.4 ~       igr                                           Fgr       &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 70 -&#13;
7.        Another way of taking into consideration the effect of home&#13;
consumption on B1 is as follows.&#13;
Bl     ' (P2 Q2 - C2) - (Pl Ql - Cl) + (S2- S)        ..... (6)&#13;
where Pl, P2, Ql' Q2, Cl and C2 are as defined previously, ane&#13;
SV, S2 = consumer surplus on home consumption in the without- and&#13;
with-project situation, respectively ($)&#13;
Note that in Figure 2&#13;
area FBMJ = P2 Q2 - total income in the with-project situation&#13;
area ECNJ - P1 Ql - total income in the without-project situation&#13;
area GBMJ = agricultural production costs in the with-project situation&#13;
area GCNJ = agricultural production costs in the without-project situation&#13;
area OFA  - S2   consumer surplus in the with-project situation&#13;
area OED  = S1 = consumer surplus in the without-project situation&#13;
area ADEF = -(S2- S1) = los8 in consumer surplus&#13;
The term -(S2 - S1) is determined as follows:&#13;
(S- s) = - (area ADEF of Figure 2) = -APH1     + :1APH1=&#13;
2                              ~~~2  2&#13;
= -[(P2 - P1)H2 +-(P2 -Pl)(Hl - H2)] =&#13;
- -[P2 112-P~~1 21 -  1 H1 + P1 H1 + 2-(P2 - P1)(11  H 11)]=&#13;
= -[P2 H2 - Pl  H + Pl H1 - Pl H2 + 2(P2-Pl)(Hl - H2)] =&#13;
= -(P2 H2 - P1 Hi) - (P1 Hi  - Pl H2) - -(P2 - Pl)(Hl  - H2) =&#13;
= -(P2 H2 - P1 H1) - Pl(    -  Pl H2) -  2(P2 - P1) (H1  -H2)&#13;
................. .(7)&#13;
Substituting expression (;) for (S2 - Sl) of expression (6) gives:&#13;
B1     m(P 2 Q2   C2)- (Pl Q1- C1) - (P2 H2 - P1 Hl) -&#13;
- Pl(Hl - H2) - 4(P2 -P1)(H1    H H2) =&#13;
- P2 q2 - P  ql -pl(Hl - H2) - '(Hl - H2) (P2 - P1) -&#13;
- (C2 - C1)                       ................ (8)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 71 -&#13;
8.         Expressions (4), (5) and (8) are different ways of evaluating B,.&#13;
Expression (8) is preferred if one wishes to examine the influence of changes&#13;
in C1 and C2. In addition, a comparison between the first two terms of&#13;
expression (3), which represent B1, and expression (8) clearly shows the&#13;
impact of home consumption in the without- and with-project situations un B1.&#13;
This impact is represented by -P (Hl - H2) - 1(H1 - H2) (P2 - P1).       Thus,&#13;
these terms should be added to expression (1) if the aforementioned impact&#13;
is to be taken into consideration in this expression:&#13;
B      =[(P q2     R2) - (Pm q1 - RI)] + [- P(H- 2&#13;
--2 (Hl - H2)(P2 - P)]                   ........... (9)&#13;
Note that expression (9) may also be derived as follows:&#13;
1   B2    (P2 Q2 -C2)     (P1 Q1 - C1) + (S2 -S1) +&#13;
+ (F2 q2 - K2) - (F1 q1 - K1) =&#13;
= (P2 q2 + P2 H2 - C2) - (P1 q1 + P1 Hl - C1) +&#13;
+ (S2 - S) + (F2 q2 - K2) - (F1 q1 - K1)&#13;
= (P2 q2 + F2 q2 + P2 H2 - C2 - K2) -&#13;
- (P1 q1 + F1 q1 + P1 H1 - C1 - K1) + (S2 - S1)&#13;
or, since R2 = C2 + K2, R1 = C1 + K1, and Pm = P1 + F1 = P2 + F&#13;
B+B 2 =(Pm q2 + P2 H2 -      R2) - (Pm q   + P1 H1 - R1) + (S2 - S1)&#13;
= Pm(q2 - ql) - (R2 - R1) + (P2 H2 - P1 H1) + (S2 - SI) -&#13;
= Pm(q2 - ql) - (R2 - RI) - Pl(Hl - H2) - '(Hl - H2)(P2 - P1)&#13;
9.         Area ABCD of Figure 1 and area ABCD of Figure 5 represent the first&#13;
two and last two terms of expression (9), respectively.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 72 -&#13;
1XP2&#13;
a2            si_            _&#13;
On-farm consumption (tons)&#13;
Figure 5&#13;
10.        Naturally, an expression for B in terus of faru-gate prices 18&#13;
simply obtained by adding expression (8) to the la»t two terms of expression&#13;
(3):&#13;
B       -1 + B2 - P2 q2 - Pl ql - Pl(El -                 (2)(P2          Pl) &#13;
- (C2 - Cl) + (P2 q2 - P, ql) - (k2 q2 - kl ql) ... (10)&#13;
Figure 6 is a graphical presentation of expression (10).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 73 -&#13;
d           F m lP2                        /        /      /       Function of excess&#13;
v- I                                           _        _  __--    supply and trans&#13;
v&#156; P2                          L                            -  - / / -, ( port in without-&#13;
e  Fi                            /                  c /  /  C   project  situation&#13;
Function of excess&#13;
Pl A                    /       /   i !  --      - supply and transport&#13;
in with-project situation&#13;
Excess supply function&#13;
ql         q2&#13;
Exports (tons)&#13;
Figure 6&#13;
Note that in Figure 6:&#13;
Area ABCD represents the benefits accruing to farmers.&#13;
(Area AEFD - area ZXFD) represents the profit of transporters&#13;
in the without-project situation.&#13;
(Area BEGC - area YZGC) represents the profit of transporters&#13;
in the with-project situation.&#13;
(Area BEGC - area AEFD - area YZGC + area ZXFD) represents the&#13;
benefits accruing to transporters.&#13;
Line YC is the same as line BC of Figure 3.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 74 -&#13;
11.       Assuming that the prices used in the illustration are efficiency&#13;
prices and.that salvage values are negligible, successive application of&#13;
expression (9) or (10) to each crop of a zone of influence and the summation&#13;
of the results give the total benefits of any year during the expected lif e&#13;
of the investment project, if more than one crop is cultivated in a rural&#13;
road's zone of influence.&#13;
12.       The aforementioned discussion considers the one-to-one relationship&#13;
between farm production and agricultural transport over the improved (cons-&#13;
tructed) rural road. Specifically, substitution along the compensated (i.e.&#13;
excluding income effects) demand curve OD of Figure 2 will occur as the price&#13;
of the agricultural product considered rises; less of this product will be&#13;
consumed at home. Income effects can, of course, also be relevant. For&#13;
instance, if the agricultural product is an important one in farm production,&#13;
a price rise will increase farmers' income, which may result in increased&#13;
"home" demand. In this case, the aforementioned demand curve OD will slope&#13;
more steeply and the benefits evaluated by expression (9) or (10) will be&#13;
underestimated.&#13;
13.       Naturally, the demand curve OD may be more flat for an inferior&#13;
product of the farm production and in this case expression (9) or (10) would&#13;
overestimate the benefits B. The analysis of slopes of the compensated demand&#13;
curve OD of Figure 2 is complex and time consuming. Generally, the costs of&#13;
investments of a rural road improvement (construction) and complementary&#13;
agricultural components do not warrant such an analysis.&#13;
14.       Finally, it is noted that expresaion (9) corresponds to expression&#13;
(1) of the text of the INTRODUCTION (p. 1). Expression (10) relates to&#13;
expressions (2) and (3) of this text.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
HG3881.5 .W57 W67 no.362 c.3  |&#13;
Beenhakker, Henri L.&#13;
Identification and appraisal 1&#13;
of rural roads projects I&#13;
DATE   NAME AND EXTENSION   ROOM&#13;
_____________ ________________________________N_____ M BERI________ &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1555066">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1979/10/1555066/identification-appraisal-rural-roads-projects
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1979/10/1555066/identification-appraisal-rural-roads-projects</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1979/10/1555066/identification-appraisal-rural-roads-projects</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/10/03/000178830_98101903403512/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/10/03/000178830_98101903403512/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>1979-10-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2003-10-03T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Identification and appraisal of rural roads projects
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            This paper describes an operational
            approach to the identification and appraisal of projects
            consisting of rural roads and complementary investments. The
            objective for such projects is to prepare and implement a
            comprehensive, multi-sectoral development program on the
            basis of rural roads in their zones of influence. The
            methodology can, therefore, also be applied to rural
            development projects. The principal purpose of the
            identification process is to ascertain the development
            potential of a rural road's zone of influence. In many
            instances this may depend on the potential of one or two
            crops, which, therefore, should be examined with more care.
            The appraisal methodology determines the appropriate scope
            and timing for road improvements or construction, their
            maintenance needs, and the complementary investments in
            other sectors, without which (in most cases) the road
            improvements or construction would not be justified. In
            other words, the project attempts to achieve an optimal
            development package for each road's zone of influence.
            The linkages between agricultural and transport components
            are emphasized.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Identification and appraisal of rural roads projects
        </docna>
        <display_title>Identification and appraisal of
            rural roads projects</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1979/10/1555066/identification-appraisal-rural-roads-projects</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>Crops and Crop Management Systems,Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Roads &amp; Highways,Agricultural Knowledge and Information Systems</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Transport</teratopic>
        <authors>
            <author>BEENHAKKER, H.</author>
            <author>CHAMMARI, A.</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000178830_98101903403512</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>(Historic)Macro/non-trade</subsc>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 362</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Transport</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Economic Policy</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Agricultural investments; Agricultural
            production; Cattle; Construction; Cultivation; Extension
            services; Fertilizers; Improvement; Land clearing;
            Maintenance &amp; repair; Maintenance equipment; Project
            appraisal; Project identification; Roads &amp; highways;
            Rural roads; Seeds; Simulation; Transport costs
            agricultural development,agricultural
            inputs,agricultural investment,agricultural
            production,agricultural products,agricultural
            technologies,buses,capita consumption,consumers,Cost
            savings,crop,crops,cultivated land,cultivation,daily
            traffic,development projects,development strategies,dry
            seasons,economic activity,Economic Analysis,economic
            life,equipment,expenditures,exports,extension,extension
            services,fares,farm,farm income,farm
            storage,farmers,farms,fertilizers,gravel,growth
            rate,income,incomes,integration,M1,pack
            animals,passenger,passenger cars,pickups,planting,Population
            growth,price elasticity,production costs,road
            construction,road improvement,road improvements,road
            maintenance,rural development,rural
            roads,salvage,savings,seeds,Streams,terrain,through
            traffic,tomatoes,total
            costs,traffic,transport,transportation,trucks,value
            added,vehicle operating costs,wheat,yields,zero elasticity
        </keywd>
        <owner>DEC</owner>
        <repnb>SWP362</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crops</ml:concept><ml:concept>Livestock</ml:concept><ml:concept>Livestock and Animal Husbandry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Foreign Direct Investments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Linkages</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crops and Crop Management Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Growth and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Copyright</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Examinations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Support Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports &amp; Waterways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fertilizers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Animal Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Road Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Credit</ml:concept><ml:concept>On-Farm Storage</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Roads</ml:concept><ml:concept>FDI Spillovers</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>