<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>ï»¿                                                   57475&#13;
                        INTERNATIONAL BANK FOR 
&#13;
                    RECONSTRUCTION AND DEVELOPMENT 
&#13;
&#13;
.1&#13;
I, 	                           -   -   Â­&#13;
II&#13;
Ii&#13;
I' 	                105th Special Meeting&#13;
II&#13;
II&#13;
Ii&#13;
Ii&#13;
Ii&#13;
Ii&#13;
'I&#13;
Ii&#13;
d&#13;
"&#13;
II&#13;
'I&#13;
II&#13;
[!                                         Board Room&#13;
                                           International Bank Buildingi&#13;
[I                                         Washington, D. C. 
&#13;
I'                                         Tues day, February 21, 1956 
&#13;
I&#13;
II&#13;
Ii&#13;
III&#13;
!.	&#13;
           The meeting was convened at 10:00 otclock a.m.,&#13;
 I&#13;
I      Mr. Eugene R. Black, President, presiding.&#13;
II&#13;
II&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
II&#13;
II&#13;
&#13;
I
&#13;
II 
&#13;
I
&#13;
1\&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                    2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        Agenda Item&#13;
&#13;
        Proposed Loan to The Japan&#13;
          Development Bank   â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢   . . . . . . . . . â&#128;¢ 3
&#13;
:1                                                              
&#13;
II                    
&#13;
I!&#13;
                                                            
&#13;
I:I 
&#13;
 I&#13;
                                                                
&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                 3
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                THE CHAIRMAN:    The firs t item of business is the proposed!&#13;
                 6i&#13;
,           loan .iif' the Japan Deve lopmen t Bank.   This loan is to finance&#13;
"&#13;
!i&#13;
i:1l        the foreign exchange cos t of four equipment modernization&#13;
                                                                                      ,&#13;
Ii projects in the steel and shipbuilding and automotive industri~s.&#13;
II&#13;
I'&#13;
II&#13;
I&#13;
,               I would like to first calIon Mr. Dorr.&#13;
II     MR. DORR: This proposed loan would be for 8.1 million&#13;
!I&#13;
I: dollars for a term of 15 years at a rate of 4-3/4 percent withi!&#13;
,I&#13;
II a grace period of two years.&#13;
 Ii             As Mr. Black has said, it would be to the Japan Develop-&#13;
 I'&#13;
 ,I&#13;
 'I ment Bank which, as you all know, is a Japanese Government&#13;
 1;&#13;
  II&#13;
  Ii agency which is set up to conduct government financing of in-&#13;
  II&#13;
  !i dustry, both internal and through foreign loans.&#13;
       ,&#13;
  "&#13;
       ,&#13;
  'I&#13;
  ;i     The money would be reloaned by the Japan Development Bank i&#13;
  'I                                                               I&#13;
  I, to four Japanese companies, one a steel company, the Japan&#13;
  Ii                                                               I&#13;
                                                                   I&#13;
  Ii                                                               I&#13;
    \; Steel Tube Company, two shipbuilding companies, Mitshubishi an~&#13;
    "                                                                                     .&#13;
    I'                                                                                    :&#13;
    ,\&#13;
            Ishikawajima Heavy Industries, and one automobile and truck&#13;
    II manufacturing company, the Toyota Motor Company'.&#13;
    ,I&#13;
    ,I&#13;
    ilI,        The loan for steel would amount to 2.6 million, for shipÂ­&#13;
       II&#13;
       11&#13;
       I'&#13;
            building 3.1, and for trucl:cs 2.4.                                           â&#128;¢&#13;
       I&#13;
                The last loan the bank made to Japan was to the Yawata&#13;
                                                                        I&#13;
       II Steel Company, and I think the Board is fully familiar with th,&#13;
       II                                                               I&#13;
       II economic significance and necessity for the modernization of I&#13;
       II                                                               I&#13;
       II the steel industry in Japan.&#13;
       I'&#13;
       II&#13;
&#13;
       II&#13;
        I&#13;
        I&#13;
        I&#13;
        I&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                               4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                   I&#13;
    This is another project fundamentally along the same lines     I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
of modernizing, bringing up to date and replacing obsolete&#13;
equipment.&#13;
    The   ShiPbUild~ industry has become extremely important&#13;
        ~           ~&#13;
in Japan siRea tA&amp; importance, not only for replacing the&#13;
heavy 'War losses but also as a major export item, and today&#13;
it is one of the largest foreign exchange earners of Japan.&#13;
    The particular loan would go to financing equipment for&#13;
making an improved propulsion machinery.     The truck industry&#13;
                                                                   I&#13;
&#13;
is becoming of increasing importance in Japan with the developÂ­&#13;
ment of road transportation which is increasing very much&#13;
faster than any other form of transport in Japan.&#13;
    There is considerable scope for improving production    cost~&#13;
                                                                   .&#13;
                                                                   I&#13;
and thereby reducing the cost of the trucks and thereby the&#13;
cost of the transportation.&#13;
    The proposal is that in effect the four separate loans be :&#13;
                                                                       i&#13;
&#13;
combined into one.     There seem to be many good reasons on the&#13;
administrative Side, both from the Japanese point of view and&#13;
from the Bank's point of view, for combining these rather tha1&#13;
                                                                       I&#13;
&#13;
treating them as separate loans.&#13;
                                                                       1&#13;
    The pattern of the arrangements would be a loan agreement I&#13;
                                                                       I&#13;
with the Japan Development Bank, a guarantee agreement by the:I&#13;
                                                                       I&#13;
Japanese government, financial assurances by the individual&#13;
companies in favor of the bank, subsidiary loan agreements&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                    5&#13;
&#13;
                                                                        I&#13;
                                                                        i&#13;
     between the various companies, the fourcompanies, and the JaP4n&#13;
                                                                        i&#13;
     Development Bank, which would contain certain provisions    call~d&#13;
&#13;
     for by our agreement with the Japan Development Bank.&#13;
         Those subsidiary loan agreements have been informally&#13;
     agreed on with each of the four companies and do contain proviÂ­&#13;
     sions which ve believe adequately insure that the projects witl&#13;
     be carried out.&#13;
                                                                        I&#13;
        We are relying in essence on the undertaking of the Japan!&#13;
     Development Bank to cause the four companies to carry out the      I&#13;
                                                                        I&#13;
                                                                        I&#13;
     projects.   Of course, ve have the guarantee of the Japanese       I&#13;
                                                                        I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     government back or that obligation.&#13;
         The Japan Development Bank will charge one-half of one&#13;
     percent commission to the four sub borrowers.&#13;
                                                                        j&#13;
                                                                        !&#13;
                                                                        I&#13;
&#13;
         One important feature of this proposed loan as contrasted!&#13;
     with the earlier transactions is that we are proposing that        !&#13;
                                                                     I&#13;
     we do not take from the final borrowers any security.    In the I&#13;
     past we have asked that the Japan Development Bank pledge to       I&#13;
     us whatever security it got from the final borrower.               I&#13;
                                                                        I&#13;
         We have found that that involved us in a good many   negoti~-&#13;
                                                                        I&#13;
     tions and a good many questions which upon conSideration    seem~d&#13;
                                                                        !&#13;
                                                                        I&#13;
     to us to be unnecessary to get into.&#13;
                                                                        i&#13;
                                                                        I&#13;
         Here we are merely asking that the Japan Development Bank I&#13;
                                                                            i&#13;
                                                                            I&#13;
     should follow its normal practices in regard to security, that&#13;
     it will take security in accordance vith normal Japanese busii&#13;
                                                                        I&#13;
     ness practice but that it viII not be asked to pledge that         I&#13;
                                                                            I&#13;
                                                                            I&#13;
                                                                            i&#13;
,I&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                             6&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
             security to us.&#13;
                 I donlt think I need to add much to what was said last&#13;
             October in regard to the Japanese economic situation.    As&#13;
&#13;
ii&#13;
             noted in the Presidentts report, it has continued to be on an&#13;
I'&#13;
&#13;
II           improving trend, and the results for the calendar year 1955,&#13;
"&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
II&#13;
r)&#13;
II&#13;
I'&#13;
&#13;
" I think, can be regarded as quite encouraging.&#13;
II&#13;
II                                                                               ,&#13;
Ii&#13;
11               There is a balance of payment surplus of around 500 mil-        I&#13;
;1&#13;
I;                                                                               I&#13;
II&#13;
     I&#13;
             lion.   Industrial activity was up about 10 percent.    There   wa~&#13;
I'&#13;
,I                                                                               I&#13;
Ii           a bumper rice crop.    Despite some pressure the conservative       i&#13;
Ii,I&#13;
Ii'I:I 
 financial policy seems to be pretty well entrenched, and 1f&#13;
Ii                                                                               i
&#13;
             anyth1ng, more accepted than it has been at some times in the i&#13;
!i  ,I&#13;
&#13;
    :1       past.                                                               I&#13;
    :1&#13;
    II&#13;
    I&#13;
                 There are no new developments in regard to reparation.&#13;
    II                                                                           I&#13;
    !I       Negot1ations are continuing with the Philippines, and 1t is         i&#13;
    II                                                                           I&#13;
    II       expected or it is often stated that there will be a    settlemen~&#13;
    Ii very shortly.                                                             I&#13;
    il&#13;
                 As to the negotiations in regard to the French debt, I&#13;
    :iI, 
&#13;
    II&#13;
    ,I&#13;
             understand those are now proceeding and that the Japanese 
&#13;
    'I&#13;
    'I&#13;
    II&#13;
    II       government has offered to settle this dispute on the basis ot&#13;
    ,:&#13;
&#13;
             the recommendations ot the impartial expert whom the parties&#13;
    II&#13;
             called in sometime ago.&#13;
    II&#13;
                 THE CHAIRMAN:     Thank you very much.&#13;
                 Mr. Lipkowitz.&#13;
                                                                                     ,&#13;
                 MR. LIPKOWITZ:    Mr. Chairman, the loan proposal before    yo~&#13;
&#13;
             gentlemen comprises four separate projects.    The beneficiary          I&#13;
                                                                                     \&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                7&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
              enterprises are all companies which have a long history in&#13;
              Japanese industry, either directly or through affiliated con-&#13;
    I!&#13;
    II        cerns.    They are among the largest concerns in their separate&#13;
    :1&#13;
    ii&#13;
    il        branches of industry.   Each has shown a profit every year sinJe&#13;
    Ii                                                                              !&#13;
    I
&#13;
    !f&#13;
              1951 or earlier. 
&#13;
    :1&#13;
    'I&#13;
&#13;
    if&#13;
    II&#13;
                  Parenthetically, I might say that the record would have&#13;
    II&#13;
    II&#13;
              been much longer except for the war and the post-war policy&#13;
    IÂ·&#13;
    'i                                                                              I&#13;
    !I which has made a shambles of any continuity of financial his- I              I&#13;
&#13;
    il&#13;
        tory for most Japanese concerns. Their securities are all&#13;
    III&#13;
    .                                                                I&#13;
    II  traded on the Tokyo stock exchange. The companies are all co~Â­&#13;
                                                                     I&#13;
    iIl       petently managed.&#13;
    I&#13;
    II&#13;
                  The projects are essentially replacement in nature.       That i&#13;
    II&#13;
    ii        is, the expected benefits are to be derived mainly from&#13;
    II&#13;
    I'&#13;
    II&#13;
    [I&#13;
              reductions in unit costs, rather than from expected increases&#13;
    II        in volume.&#13;
     il&#13;
     Ii&#13;
     [i&#13;
     II           Estimated cost savings reflect increased productivity of ~he&#13;
     Ii                                                                             I&#13;
     I'&#13;
              new equipment and the labor, fuel, and material economies&#13;
     !I&#13;
     Ii&#13;
     II       arising from the utilization of this new equipment.       These&#13;
      I&#13;
     I savings have been calculated conservatively and would be grea~lY&#13;
                                                                                        I&#13;
&#13;
     Ii       increased if sales volumes rose suffiCiently to permit fuller I&#13;
          I&#13;
\             operations than has been assumed for the purposes of this&#13;
              report.&#13;
&#13;
                  In the case of the ~s~ng projects, Mitshubishi&#13;
              and Ishikawajima, the New   Eftel&amp;~8 tBB~8B8.   and   supercharge~~&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
              constitute only a small part of the total operations of these&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                               8
&#13;
&#13;
       firms.   In the case of Japan Steel Tube Company, the new&#13;
&#13;
       seamless pipe mill replaces two old mills with a net increase'&#13;
       in capacity of only five percent.&#13;
&#13;
           In the case of Toyota, the new equipment will tend to reÂ­&#13;
i'Il&#13;
III,   duce the unbalance between departments which has in past&#13;
II&#13;
II&#13;
II     periods of high demand required overtime work in departments&#13;
II&#13;
II&#13;
'I&#13;
II     whose facilities are now being modernized.&#13;
II&#13;
           The financia 1 pos i t ion of the bene fi ciary' en terpris es is&#13;
II&#13;
 I,&#13;
       good by current Japanese standards.       However, the enterprises&#13;
&#13;
       recognize that a further strengthening is desirable, and each&#13;
                                                                                ,&#13;
       has furnished the bank assurances of future improvement, alth6ugh&#13;
                                                                                I&#13;
       the measuring rods vary from case to case due to differing               I&#13;
                                                                                i&#13;
                                                                                I&#13;
       circumstances. 
&#13;
&#13;
           Staff members have reviewed with representatives of the 
&#13;
                                                                                I&#13;
&#13;
       beneficiary enterprises the quotations, offers and        specificat~ons&#13;
                                                                                i&#13;
       for the equipment to be purchased with the loan proceeds.&#13;
                                                                                I&#13;
           We are satisfied that diligent efforts have been made to i&#13;
                                                                                I&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                i&#13;
       procure the most favorable terms available in major supplying I&#13;
&#13;
       countries.                                                               J&#13;
           In view of the cost savings to be derived from the invest            I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       ments, the expected strengthenIng of Japan's competitive posi1&#13;
                                                                                I&#13;
                                                                                I&#13;
       tion in foreign markets, the prospective lowering of distribu-1&#13;
                                                                                    I&#13;
                                                                                    I&#13;
       tion costs within Japan, and the assurances received as to thi&#13;
       improvement of the finance of the beneficiary enterprises, I                 I&#13;
                                                                                    ,&#13;
&#13;
       have no hesitation in recommending approval of this combined&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                  9&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
project for bank financing.&#13;
    THE CHAIRMAN:     Thank you.&#13;
    Any questions?&#13;
                                                                      I&#13;
    MR. LIEFTI'VCK:    Mr. Chairman, what was the rate of   intere~t&#13;
&#13;
which the bank will charge to the final borrowers and how does&#13;
                                                                      I&#13;
&#13;
it compare with the rate of interest prevailing in Japan for&#13;
this kind of loan?&#13;
    MR. DORR:     The Japan Development Bank will charge a com-&#13;
                                                                      I&#13;
&#13;
mission of one-half of one percent over the rate that we char~e.&#13;
That is very considerably lower than commercial bank rates&#13;
which I would say would run around nine percent.&#13;
    The public utility industry gets from the bank, the Japan&#13;
                                                                      I&#13;
Development Bank, a rate of six percent.       But that is the onlt&#13;
industry that gets that preferred rate.&#13;
                       ~&#13;
    MR. BURY:     Thesellare in fact minute, aren't they, compare~&#13;
with the scale of operations of these companies?&#13;
                                                                      I&#13;
                                                                      I&#13;
                                                                      I&#13;
&#13;
    THE CHAIRMAN:     Yes. 
&#13;
    MR. DORR:     The foreign exchange risk is being borne by 
&#13;
the company. 
&#13;
    THE CHAIRMAN:     Any other questions? 
&#13;
    MR. OVERBY:     Mr. Chairman.&#13;
    THE CHAIRMAN:     Yes.&#13;
    MR. OVERBY:     I just assume that in this case as in others&#13;
the International Bank has made all reasonable efforts to&#13;
assure the maximum amount of private foreign capital particiÂ­&#13;
pation as well as domestiC, and I would hope that the Bank in&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                     10&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       this case as in others has had that in mind, as I am sure you&#13;
       have.&#13;
           THE CHAIRMAN:   Well, I don't report to the Board on that&#13;
       because I can assure the Board that they can take it for&#13;
       granted that we always do that.&#13;
           I think that it is a little early for Japan to be able to&#13;
       float a bond issue in this market, although I think they are&#13;
       going in that direction.&#13;
           These thinga sometimes happen sooner than you expect.     I&#13;
       think it could happen, but in this particular loan, I haven't&#13;
       advised the Board, but I vas just going to, that there vi11&#13;
       be a participation of 1,076,000 dollars in this loan by the        i&#13;
                                                                          I&#13;
       Chase Manhattan Bank.   They are taking the first four   maturit~es&#13;
                                                                          i&#13;
&#13;
       running from February 15, 1958 to August 15, 1959, and they&#13;
       are taking them to a four percent yield basis.&#13;
           So we do have participation, but I think it is a little        ,&#13;
                                                                          ,&#13;
       early to expect the private market to be able to float a bond!&#13;
       issue, although I think it may come.&#13;
           Any other questions?&#13;
Ii,I&#13;
,I&#13;
'[         If there are no other questions, no further disoussion,&#13;
'I 
                                                                      I&#13;
II may I have a motion to adopt the draft resolution. 
                       i&#13;
&#13;
                                                             unanlmou.~y
&#13;
I&#13;
[i         (Motion for adoption duly made and seconded and&#13;
   I&#13;
                                                                          !&#13;
1\&#13;
       carried.)&#13;
II&#13;
,&#13;
I&#13;
!I&#13;
&#13;
 !i&#13;
 II&#13;
  ,I&#13;
  Ii&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                   11&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    While it has taken a long time to conolude this loan, we&#13;
                                                                 I&#13;
are very glad to declare the loan of $8.1 million to the     Japa~&#13;
&#13;
Development Bank for industrial projects approved.&#13;
    Mr. Yumoto.&#13;
    MR. YUMOTO:    I wish to express the appreciation of the&#13;
Japanese government to the Directors for the approval of this&#13;
loan.&#13;
    I also wish to    express~appreciation     of the Japanese 	        i&#13;
                                                                        I&#13;
                                                              I&#13;
government to the management for the invention of the neW pr01&#13;
cedure of combining the several loans into one and giving it&#13;
to the Japan Development Bank.&#13;
    As Mr.   Do~   has explained, this will be a great help in&#13;
the administration of the loan not only' for the Bank but for&#13;
                                                                        i&#13;
the Japanese side as well. 	                                            i&#13;
                                                                        I&#13;
                                                                        I&#13;
    I Wish to thank personally the management for the     decisio~&#13;
&#13;
on this new procedure.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
project.&#13;
                                                                            I&#13;
    Although the amount may be small, however small the amount!&#13;
is, it requires as much work: for the staff.     So I also wish tol&#13;
                                                                            \&#13;
                                                                            I&#13;
express my appreciation to the staff.                                       t&#13;
                                                                            I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Thank: you.                                                             i&#13;
&#13;
    THE CHAIRMAN:     Thank you.&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="15936610">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1956/02/15936610/transcript-one-hundred-fifth-special-meeting-executive-directors-ibrd-held-tuesday-february-21-1956
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1956/02/15936610/transcript-one-hundred-fifth-special-meeting-executive-directors-ibrd-held-tuesday-february-21-1956</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1956/02/15936610/transcript-one-hundred-fifth-special-meeting-executive-directors-ibrd-held-tuesday-february-21-1956</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2012-03-14T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2016-01-14T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <docm_id>090224b0828d0b06</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b0828d0b06</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2012/03/15/000386194_20120315003424/Rendered/INDEX/6747500TRANS0B0losed0March014020120.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2012/03/15/000386194_20120315003424/Rendered/PDF/6747500TRANS0B0losed0March014020120.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2012-03-15T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1956-02-21T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Transcript of one hundred fifth special
            meeting of the Executive Directors of the IBRD, held on
            Tuesday, February 21, 1956
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            This transcript, from the session of the
            Executive Directors of the International Bank on
            Reconstruction and Development, held on Tuesday, February
            21, 1956 covers only the discussion about loan to the Japan
            Development Bank.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Transcript of one hundred fifth special
            meeting of the Executive Directors of the IBRD, held on
            Tuesday, February 21, 1956
        </docna>
        <display_title>Transcript of one hundred fifth
            special meeting of the Executive Directors of the IBRD, held
            on Tuesday, February 21, 1956</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/1956/02/15936610/transcript-one-hundred-fifth-special-meeting-executive-directors-ibrd-held-tuesday-february-21-1956</listing_relative_url>
        <projn>JP-Industrial Projects-294806 -- P037425</projn>
        <docty>Transcript</docty>
        <subtopic>Corporate Law,Education for the Knowledge Economy,Debt Markets,Banks &amp; Banking Reform,Microfinance</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Law and Development,Education</teratopic>
        <count>Japan</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!517191</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Asia!$!517198</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>East Asia and Pacific!$!119225</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000386194_20120315003424</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>(Historic)Industrial adjustment</subsc>
        <admreg>East Asia and Pacific,East Asia and Pacific</admreg>
        <colti>Board transcript</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Law and Development,Education</historic_topic>
        <prdln>IBRD/IDA</prdln>
        <sectr>(Historic)Industry</sectr>
        <majdocty>Board Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            balance of payment, bank financing, bank
            rates, beneficiary, bond, bond issue, borrower, branches,
            commercial bank, company, debt, Development Bank, equipment,
            firms, foreign capital, foreign exchange, foreign exchange
            risk, foreign loans, foreign markets, government financing,
            grace period, individual companies, INTERNATIONAL BANK,
            Loan, loan agreement, loan agreements, loan proceeds,
            productivity, savings, securities, stock exchange,
            subsidiary, transport
        </keywd>
        <owner>N/A</owner>
        <lndinstr>
            Sector Investment and Maintenance Loan
        </lndinstr>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>East Asia and Pacific</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>67475</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fragility, Conflict and Violence</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Banks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Retail Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crops</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corporate Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corporate Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enterprise Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enterprise and Commercial Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Knowledge Economy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fuels</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Reparations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Balance of Payments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enterprise and Corporate Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Eastern Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Japan</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>