<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>ï»¿                                                   67474&#13;
Bubley                        INTERNATIONAL BANK FOR&#13;
                          RECONSTRUCTION AND DEVELOPMENT&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                       TWO HUNDRED NINETIETH REGULAR MEETING&#13;
                                           of&#13;
&#13;
                             EXECUTIVE    DIRECTORS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         Board Room&#13;
                                         International Bank Building&#13;
                                         Washington, D. Co&#13;
                                         Thursday, August 8, 1957&#13;
              The meeting was convened at 10:00 a.m., Mr. Eugene R.&#13;
&#13;
         Black, President, presiding.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        ---&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                            2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                          CON TEN T S 
&#13;
&#13;
Agenda Item                                               Page 
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                
&#13;
                                                                
&#13;
Proposed   Loan     Japan 
&#13;
     Mr.   Quandt   - Loan Aspects â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢     4
&#13;
     Mr.   Tolley   - Economic Aspects â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢     5
&#13;
     Mr.   Reid -   The Project â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢     8
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                
&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                      3
&#13;
&#13;
                      PRO C E E DIN G S&#13;
&#13;
    MR. BLACK:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    The next item is the proposed loan to the Aichi IrrigaÂ­&#13;
tion Public Corporation.&#13;
&#13;
    I would like first to calIon Mr. Quandt.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                          4
&#13;
&#13;
     MR. QUANDT:   The project submitted to the Executive&#13;
Directors represents a noteworthy effort by Japan to respond&#13;
to one of the country's most urgent needs, to increase her&#13;
&#13;
domestic food production.&#13;
    With her territorial limitations, Japan must make every&#13;
effort to exploit all land that offers itself for food proÂ­&#13;
&#13;
duction of any kind, lest the burden of food imports on her&#13;
balance of payments will continue to increase with the food&#13;
demands of a growing population.   Consequently, Japan's efÂ­&#13;
forts to increase her cultivated areas must include marginal&#13;
&#13;
lands even at the expense of higher subsidies.&#13;
    The special significance of this project consists in the&#13;
&#13;
fact that it represents a promising attempt to introduce a&#13;
&#13;
novel type of land exploitation in Japan through the DrigaÂ­&#13;
tion of ridge land areas hitherto uncultivated or only cultiÂ­&#13;
vated to the extent of very limited natural possibilities.&#13;
The successful completion and operation of the project, by&#13;
demonstrating the technical and economic feasibility of the&#13;
&#13;
irrigation of ridge land areas, should open the way for the&#13;
exploitation in southern Japan of multiples of the area&#13;
&#13;
covered by the project and thus represent the first step&#13;
towards a new approach to a stlbstantial improvement of&#13;
Japan's food supply.&#13;
     However, the expected direct benefits of the project&#13;
&#13;
themselves are significant also, as they are expected to add&#13;
&amp;#12;'I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                5&#13;
&#13;
     food equivalent to about 100,000 tons of brown rice to the&#13;
     country's annual suppl1.es and also to improve considerably&#13;
     the standard of living of the agricultura.l population in the&#13;
&#13;
     Aichi area.&#13;
&#13;
          Subsidiary benefits, through the supply of much needed&#13;
     industrial and drinking 1'1ater to a numb,;?!, of municipalities&#13;
     and a noteworthy addition to the area IS poltler supply, wilJ.&#13;
&#13;
     8.1so contribute to increasing over-all productivity in the&#13;
     region.&#13;
&#13;
          The expectations for the success of the project appear&#13;
&#13;
     to be justified by the determination of the Japanese GovernÂ­&#13;
     ment to assist the completion a.nd operation of the project,&#13;
     by the competence of the prospective borrower's management&#13;
     which has been assisted by experienced consultants in every&#13;
     sector of planning, execution, and future operations where thei&#13;
&#13;
     novelty of the venture called for it.&#13;
&#13;
          Last but not least, the traditional skill and zeal of&#13;
     the Japanese farmer will be genuine motive powers on the&#13;
&#13;
     road to success.&#13;
          MR. BLACK:    Thank you, sir.&#13;
          Mr. Tolley.&#13;
&#13;
          MR. TOLLEY:     Mr. Chairman, gentlemen:   The economic proÂ­&#13;
     gress in Japan during the past few years has been truly reÂ­&#13;
     markable.     This progress can be attributed to a number of&#13;
&#13;
     factors:    the general prosperity in the world at large which&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                          6
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
has provided a good market for J a,panese exports; the conserÂ­&#13;
&#13;
vative financial policies on the part of the Japanese&#13;
Government; but most of all, the credit must go to the JapanÂ­&#13;
&#13;
ese people.     It was their lndustriousness, skill, and pruÂ­&#13;
dence which originated and fostered the rapid advance.&#13;
        However, the advance has been so rapid that it is not&#13;
&#13;
surprising that signs of strain have begun to appear in cerÂ­&#13;
tain sectors of the economy, and it has become clear that&#13;
&#13;
some slackening in the pace is unavoidable.&#13;
        As indicated in the economic report, a number of steps&#13;
have been taken to tighten credit and restrict imports.&#13;
These measures are being supplemented by others which give&#13;
further evidence of Japan's determination to control the&#13;
situation.    Government funds budgeted for lending to industry&#13;
during the current fiscal year are to be reduced by 15 per&#13;
cent.     Nine leading commercial banks were requested to hold&#13;
&#13;
their loans during July within the limit of repayments reÂ­&#13;
&#13;
ceived during that month.     The steel and electric power inÂ­&#13;
dustries, which have very large investment programs, have&#13;
been asked to revie"T their programs with a view to stretchÂ­&#13;
ing them out over a longer period.     Interest rat.es on savings&#13;
and time deposits are to be increased to encourage savings.&#13;
&#13;
        Most of these measures will require some time to proÂ­&#13;
duce visible effects.     The tightening of credit wan only&#13;
beg~~    about three months ago.   However, there are already&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                  1
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        some indications that the measures are proving effective.&#13;
&#13;
        Preliminary information indicates a drop in imports in July.&#13;
&#13;
il A number of important industries, such as textiles and autoÂ­&#13;
ii      mobiles, have announced cuts in production, and wholesale&#13;
II prices have begun to decline.&#13;
II 
&#13;
Iii 
&#13;
HI           It is, of course, much too soon to say that the corner&#13;
        has been turned.    However, there is good reason to expect&#13;
&#13;
        that equilibrium will be restored in the near future.     The&#13;
        newly appointed Finance Minister, Mr. Ichimada, is known for&#13;
        his conservative views on fiscal and monetary policies.        DurÂ­   I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        ing 1953 and 1954 he was one of the key figures in initiating&#13;
        and implementing the very tough but effective anti-inflationÂ­&#13;
        ary policy which brought stability within a fairly short&#13;
&#13;
        period and laid the groundwork for the subsequent rapid progÂ­&#13;
&#13;
        ress in Japan.     According to press reports, he is planning to&#13;
        follow a similar vigorous policy in the months ahead.     He&#13;
&#13;
        has stated that the Government has no intention of modifying&#13;
        the present tight money policy and that further retrenchment&#13;
&#13;
        is planned in next year's budget.&#13;
&#13;
             These restrictive policies should end the    inflationa~J&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        pressures and the balance of payments difficulties.     Once&#13;
        this is accomplished, there are good prospects that Japan will&#13;
        make further substantial progress under stable financial&#13;
&#13;
        conditions.&#13;
&#13;
             MR. BLACK:    Thank you.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                          8
&#13;
&#13;
     Mr. Reid.&#13;
     MR. REID:   Mr. Chairman and gentlemen:    The primary&#13;
purpose of this project is to irrigate 33,000 hectares or&#13;
83,000 acres, near Nagoya in southern Japan.    The secondary&#13;
objectives are to improve domestic and industrial water&#13;
supplies for the area and to make a modest contribution to&#13;
the power capacity of the region.&#13;
&#13;
     Now, this is by no means an orthodox irrigation project.&#13;
Apart from being large and costly, it is unusually compliÂ­&#13;
cated and involves technical difficulties which are somewhat&#13;
&#13;
unique.   These have been very thoroughly studied by Japanese&#13;
&#13;
and foreign technicians during the last three or four years,&#13;
&#13;
and have been solved to the extent that we think the project&#13;
should be supported.&#13;
&#13;
     NOW, we are well satisfied concerning engineering asÂ­&#13;
pects.    Consultants acceptable to us have been employed for&#13;
investigation and design and to supervise the construction.&#13;
&#13;
We accept their findings and recommendations, and we expect&#13;
they will do an equally good Job in the supervision.&#13;
&#13;
     We are also well satisfied concerning the competence of&#13;
&#13;
the borrower, the Aichi Company, to undertake the project and&#13;
operate it after completion. and the corporation has suffiÂ­&#13;
cient funds for these purposes.&#13;
     Agricultural aspects are less clear-cut.     In the first&#13;
&#13;
place, capital costs will be about $2,600 per hectare.        Now,&#13;
&amp;#12;'I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                               9&#13;
&#13;
     by way of comparison, this cost per hectare is $300 and $700&#13;
&#13;
     respectively more than the hectare costs for the irrigation&#13;
&#13;
     projects in Italy that we financed fairly recently.&#13;
&#13;
             In a country where land is used as intensively as in&#13;
&#13;
     Japan, it seems inevitable that costs of land development are&#13;
&#13;
     high.     Otherwise, the land would have been developed years&#13;
&#13;
     ago.     The Government proposes to meet these high costs by&#13;
&#13;
     subsidizing roughly 65 per cent of the over-all costs of the&#13;
&#13;
     development for agriculture included in the prOjected program.&#13;
&#13;
     This is the normal rate of subsidy for land development in&#13;
&#13;
     Japan.     It is considerably below the rate of subsidy on other&#13;
&#13;
     irrigation projects we have financed.    Given this rate of&#13;
&#13;
     subsidy, the operation of the project should be profitable.&#13;
&#13;
             The second agricultural feature is that operating the&#13;
&#13;
     system will be unusually complicated.    The 16,000 hectares of&#13;
&#13;
     the 33,000 which is rolling, upland country will not only be&#13;
&#13;
     the first irrigation in Japan of this sort of sloping country,&#13;
&#13;
     but it will be the largest operation of that nature in the&#13;
&#13;
     world, and will present many difficult technical problems in&#13;
&#13;
     getting the right amount of water at the right time to&#13;
&#13;
     twenty or thirty thousand small farms, and particularly so&#13;
     since if too much water gets there at any time, it can&#13;
&#13;
     seriously scour out the hillsides.&#13;
&#13;
             NOW, the Japanese are well aware of these problems, and&#13;
&#13;
     consequently they are employing experienced irrigation&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                              10 
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    consultants to advise them, and they are also sending some&#13;
I   of their own technicians abroad to study overseas practice&#13;
    in so far as they can.   We feel there may be initial diffiÂ­&#13;
    culties in operatXn, but we are very confident that they will     I&#13;
    be able to overcome them.&#13;
        Thirdly, since this again will be the first upland irriÂ­&#13;
    gation in Japan, it is a situation where there is not as yet&#13;
&#13;
    sufficient evidence to determine agricultural crop yield&#13;
    and agricultural benefits to be really firmly assessed.&#13;
         The Japanese have made an exceptionally thorough study&#13;
    of all the evidence they have got, which includes the results&#13;
    from two experimental farms that they have established in the&#13;
    area, and the estimates are in line with that evidence.     But&#13;
    what we cantt be sure of is Just what yields the Japanese&#13;
    farmers will be able to obtain, and how long it will take the&#13;
&#13;
    to get maximum yields.&#13;
         We are certain of one thing, however, and that is that&#13;
    Japanese farmers are among the most competent and diligent&#13;
    in the world, and they will spare no effort to get the best&#13;
    results on the resources they have been given.&#13;
         My remarks have pointed up the problems rather than the&#13;
    strong features of this proJect, and it is our firm belief&#13;
    that the competent Japanese technicians and farmers will be&#13;
&#13;
    able to overcome these problems.&#13;
         As Mr. Quandt pointed out, there is also wider&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                             11 
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
justification for this project because it is estimated there&#13;
&#13;
are about 200,000 hectares of similar upland country in&#13;
Japan, and hence this first attempt to develop it has an&#13;
experimental nature.       This doesnÂ·t mean that it is a hundredÂ­&#13;
&#13;
million-dollar experiment that is going to succeed or fail in&#13;
its own right.     It means, rather, that if results are a little&#13;
bit less than we anticipate, the project would still, we feel,&#13;
&#13;
be worth while.     On the other hand, if they are up to expectaÂ­&#13;
&#13;
tions or exceed expectations, they will demonstrate the&#13;
economic feasibility of developing a much greater area and&#13;
making a much greater contribution to Japan's food supply.&#13;
&#13;
     MR. BLACK:     Thank you, sir.&#13;
     Are there     any   questions?&#13;
&#13;
     Mr. Machado.&#13;
     MR. MACHADO:        I read with a great deal of interest the&#13;
report on this project, and I want to congratulate the staff&#13;
&#13;
not only for the excellent presentation, but also for the&#13;
excellent and to-the-point presentation at the meeting.&#13;
     I am   ve~J   much interested in the result of this experiÂ­&#13;
mental loan, if you want to call it that, because the success&#13;
&#13;
of this type of irrigation in Japan may be the answer to the&#13;
problems in some of the mountainous countries in Latin America&#13;
like Haiti and Chile, and perhaps part of Bolivia_ and I am&#13;
glad to see the Bank lend a hand in this loan.        I am sure the&#13;
loan will be a success, but the success obtained in Japan&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                  12 
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
will serve as a model that will enhance agriculture in the&#13;
more underdeveloped countries of the world, particularly&#13;
those I represent.&#13;
&#13;
        I    would be very happy to support this loan, Mr. PresiÂ­&#13;
dent.&#13;
&#13;
        MR. BLACK:     Thank you.&#13;
        Are there any other questions?&#13;
        Dr. Donner.&#13;
&#13;
        DR. DONNER:     Mr. Chairman, in reading the economic reÂ­&#13;
port and the project report, I, too, was greatly impressed&#13;
not only by the project but         by   the general features of the&#13;
recovery in Japan, which Japan has been able to achieve.&#13;
&#13;
        She has had, during recent years, a growth rate of more&#13;
than    ~o   per cent per annum, which, indeed, is a very high&#13;
&#13;
rate of development..       Although, as the staff also potnts out,&#13;
it can not be expected to continue in the future at that&#13;
rate, the expected rate of growth of 4 to 5 per cent per&#13;
&#13;
annum is neverth.s       ss again remarkable.&#13;
&#13;
       All this has been achieved and is expected to take&#13;
place on the basis of the response to what some people say&#13;
&#13;
is orthodox monetary '901icy, se,::;:lng to it tha,t there does not&#13;
take place any       inflationa~;   development, or that, as it&#13;
shows up it can be tC.ken under control.&#13;
       't'he JF.panese population, as is very neatly pointed out&#13;
in the economic report, page 14, has reacted to that&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                    13 
&#13;
&#13;
responsible policy of its Government in the best "lay, th:&#13;
'v-ia:y   one usually expects a government to react, namely, by&#13;
&#13;
responding with a high rate of savings.               Private savings as&#13;
a per cent of disposable income was previously up to a rate&#13;
of more than 12 per cent and is now in the neighborhood of&#13;
17 per cent, which is remarkable.&#13;
          And in order to put emphasis on the experiences of such&#13;
a country as Japan, what can be achieved by -- quote                    "or_&#13;
thodox monetary and fiscal methods;'           I add that the labor&#13;
&#13;
productivity has risen again in a very unusual way, 8.9 per&#13;
cent in a year.       That is a rather unique figure.&#13;
          I thought it 1n order to stress this, since very often&#13;
&#13;
there is a question in the minds of many people that what&#13;
&#13;
could be achieved with rigi.d monetary or fiscal policies is&#13;
doubted.       The question is asked    lii~1ether   a certain degree          1t&#13;
may be a bige;er degree:         of lnflationary pollctes might not,&#13;
in spite of all this advice, be better for a country, and&#13;
&#13;
particularly an underdeveloped country.&#13;
&#13;
          I have, to conclude, two little questions which are&#13;
more a matter of      my Olm   personal curiosity.&#13;
&#13;
          In the economic report on page 2 it is said -- no,&#13;
excuse me; it is on page 14            that the Japanese Government&#13;
has decided to cut income taxes by 100 billion yen since the&#13;
tax revenues were so buoyant.          But then it is added that they&#13;
&#13;
were setting against this tax decrease of 100 billion yen a&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                           14 
&#13;
&#13;
tax increase of 32 billion.&#13;
&#13;
     Now, I assume that behind this measure of raising taxes&#13;
&#13;
or decreasing taxes on the one hand, and raising taxes in&#13;
&#13;
other fields, there must stand some specific idea.     I would&#13;
&#13;
be interested in hearing what this was.&#13;
&#13;
     Then, the second point is also a matter of pure curiÂ­&#13;
osity.&#13;
&#13;
     On page 4 of the technical report, paragraph 17, it is&#13;
&#13;
said that Japan will send qualified technicians to the United&#13;
&#13;
states and elsewhere to inform themselves about the technique&#13;
&#13;
of irrigation \&gt;lork.&#13;
&#13;
     Now, what we heard here and what the technical report&#13;
&#13;
brings out is that the kind of irrigation work to be done in&#13;
&#13;
Japan at the Aichi Project seems to be of very singular&#13;
&#13;
character, of a kind quite different from the irrigation work&#13;
&#13;
to be done in other places.     So my curiosity makes me ask&#13;
&#13;
in which respect for such a singular project can techniques&#13;
&#13;
be learned other places?&#13;
&#13;
     MR. BLACK:    Do you want to answer that, Mr. Reid?&#13;
&#13;
     MR. REID:    Yes.   The proposals for training these techÂ­&#13;
&#13;
nicians will probably be in this country.     They are intending&#13;
to send at least six men over here, and their training will&#13;
&#13;
be arranged through ICA and the Bureau of Soil Conservation.&#13;
&#13;
     We realize that there is not another project exactly of&#13;
&#13;
this nature here or anywhere else, but what they intend to&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                          15 
&#13;
&#13;
study first is the operation and management, the actual&#13;
&#13;
management, of irrigation operation in the mountain states&#13;
where there are smaller schemes, but they have still got&#13;
similar problems.&#13;
&#13;
     Then they will study technical aspects of applying water&#13;
to soil, and soil conservation; and thirdly, the research&#13;
behind this sort of irrigation.&#13;
&#13;
     But the basic trend they are looking for is in the&#13;
operation and management of smaller-scale ones.&#13;
     DR. DONNER:    Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
     MR. BLACK:     Mr. Tolley.&#13;
&#13;
     MR. TOLLEY:     On the question of the reduction in taxes,&#13;
this reduction in general income taxes, I think this is on&#13;
the whole a political decision by a new government which had&#13;
recently come in.    There had been pressures before to reduce&#13;
taxes, and the new government felt that on the basis of reÂ­&#13;
cent experience, particularly in the last two or three years&#13;
where revenues had been running substantially above estimates,&#13;
this would be a good opportunity to put forth a reduction in&#13;
income taxes.&#13;
&#13;
     As to the specific taxes, the main increase in taxes was&#13;
on gasoline, and this was put forward to support another&#13;
&#13;
measure which the government wanted to get through, namely,&#13;
&#13;
the beginning of a highway development program.     So that they&#13;
&#13;
proposed this increase in gasoline taxes as support for their&#13;
&amp;#12;'. 
&#13;
                                                                 16 
&#13;
&#13;
       other proposal to get through a highway expenditure program.&#13;
           DR. DONNER:    I understand, then, that the revenue of&#13;
       the gasoline taxes would be applied to the financing of the&#13;
       highway project?&#13;
           MR. TOLLEY:    That is correct.&#13;
            MR. BLACK:    It's amazing how you find political considerÂ­&#13;
       ations popping up allover the world.      (Laughter)&#13;
&#13;
            Are there any other questions?&#13;
            Mr. Thurn.&#13;
            MR. THURN:    Mr. Chairman, I would also like to offer      my&#13;
&#13;
       congratulations to the staff on this very excellent economic&#13;
       report on the progress in Japan.&#13;
           We learned from this report that the real income in four&#13;
       years has risen 30 per cent in Japan, which is really a reÂ­&#13;
       markable achievement.     One naturally wonders how this has&#13;
       been brought about.     Well, the report gives the answers in&#13;
       paragraphs 3, 19, 22,and 27.&#13;
            I think the economic order established in Japan and the&#13;
       incentives created there promise even greater achievements&#13;
       and more impressive results than that.     I think it is a great&#13;
&#13;
       pleasure and privilege to be able to contribute to this good&#13;
       work by giving a loan of this type one's full and enthusiasti&#13;
       support.&#13;
            MR. BLACK:    Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
            MR. THURN:    Thank you.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                            17 
&#13;
&#13;
      MR. BLACK:   Mr. Mejia.&#13;
&#13;
      MR. MEJIA-PALACIO:   Mr. Chairman, I am also very greatly&#13;
 impressed by this project, this very important one, and I am&#13;
going to support it.&#13;
&#13;
     As a matter of curiosity, I want to ask a question.&#13;
It looks like the economic situation in Japan is like the&#13;
&#13;
other countries, a little difficult, inflation, and deficits,&#13;
and I am very glad that we are lending the money to them.&#13;
They will take pleasure in it.&#13;
&#13;
     But I read an article that even if the Japanese people&#13;
are very happy about the withdrawal of the American troops,&#13;
they expect some economic complications, first, because it&#13;
has been a source of foreign exchange, and second, because&#13;
80,000 Japanese who are working in the American Army are going&#13;
&#13;
to be out of their jobs.&#13;
&#13;
     I don't know if the staff has considered the consequences&#13;
of this withdrawal of the American troops.&#13;
     MR. BLACK:    They certainly have.&#13;
&#13;
     Mr. Tolley, would you like to comment on that?&#13;
     MR. TOLLEY:   Yes.&#13;
&#13;
     Of course, it is very difficult to project into the&#13;
&#13;
future just what will happen to these so-called special&#13;
United States expenditures in Japan.      I think we did have a&#13;
brief discussion in our report on the manner in which we&#13;
handled it.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                              18 
&#13;
&#13;
     Briefly, we expect that these expenditures are bound to&#13;
decline.   We don't think they will disappear for a numberof&#13;
&#13;
years, but we made what we believe to be a conservative&#13;
assumption on the drop in these expenditures of roughly&#13;
&#13;
150 million dollars below what they were in the past year.&#13;
&#13;
     Now, as to the current withdrawal which has been noted&#13;
in the papers, there is no precise estimate as to what reÂ­&#13;
duction in expenditure that might bring about, although I&#13;
have seen a figure which estimated it roughly at between 60&#13;
and 100 million dollars, roughly.        And then I did see a furÂ­&#13;
ther statement that the Government, after reconsidering,&#13;
&#13;
didn't feel that it would be as large as originally expected.&#13;
&#13;
     So, summing up, we feel that we have taken into account&#13;
an ample possiblity for decline in these expenditures when&#13;
we look to the future.&#13;
     MR. BLACK:    Any other questions?&#13;
&#13;
     If there are no other questions, no further discussion,&#13;
I would like to state that the First National City Bank in Ne&#13;
&#13;
York has agreed to buy the first five maturities of this&#13;
loan, amounting to $721,000.&#13;
&#13;
    So I would like to have a motion to adopt the draft&#13;
&#13;
resolution, including this National City Bank participation.&#13;
    MR. MACHADO:     I so move.&#13;
    MR. THURN:     Second.&#13;
&#13;
    MR. BLACK:     All in favor,   say   aye.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                          19 
&#13;
&#13;
     (Chorus of ayes.)&#13;
     Those opposed, no.&#13;
     (No response.)&#13;
&#13;
     The motion is carried.    The loan in various currencies&#13;
equivalent to $7 million to the Aichi Irrigation Public&#13;
Corporation is approved.&#13;
&#13;
     MR. TUN:    Mr. Chairman, in the absence of Mr. Watanabe..&#13;
&#13;
I would like to thank the Executive Directors for approving&#13;
the loan and the management and the staff for successfully&#13;
concluding the negotiations.&#13;
    MR. BLACK:    Thank you.&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="15936619">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1957/08/15936619/transcript-two-hundred-ninetieth-regular-meeting-executive-directors-ibrd-held-thursday-august-8-1957
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1957/08/15936619/transcript-two-hundred-ninetieth-regular-meeting-executive-directors-ibrd-held-thursday-august-8-1957</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1957/08/15936619/transcript-two-hundred-ninetieth-regular-meeting-executive-directors-ibrd-held-thursday-august-8-1957</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2012-03-14T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2016-01-14T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <docm_id>090224b0828b3e10</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b0828b3e10</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2012/03/15/000333038_20120315005210/Rendered/INDEX/6747400TRANS0B0losed0March014020120.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2012/03/15/000333038_20120315005210/Rendered/PDF/6747400TRANS0B0losed0March014020120.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2012-03-15T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1957-08-08T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Transcript of two hundred ninetieth regular
            meeting of the Executive Directors of the IBRD, held on
            Thursday, August 8, 1957
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            This transcript, from the session of the
            Executive Directors of the International Bank for
            Reconstruction and Development held on Thursday, August 8,
            1957, covers only the discussion in two hundred ninetieth
            regular meeting about loan to the Aichi Irrigation Public Corporation.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Transcript of two hundred ninetieth regular
            meeting of the Executive Directors of the IBRD, held on
            Thursday, August 8, 1957
        </docna>
        <display_title>Transcript of two hundred
            ninetieth regular meeting of the Executive Directors of the
            IBRD, held on Thursday, August 8, 1957</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/1957/08/15936619/transcript-two-hundred-ninetieth-regular-meeting-executive-directors-ibrd-held-thursday-august-8-1957</listing_relative_url>
        <projn>JP-Irrigation-294808 -- P037427</projn>
        <subtopic>Sustainable Land and Crop Management,Food &amp; Beverage Industry,Emerging Markets,Debt Markets,Taxation &amp; Subsidies</subtopic>
        <docty>Transcript</docty>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Rural Development,Private Sector Development,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth,Industry</teratopic>
        <count>Japan</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!517191</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Asia!$!517198</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>East Asia and Pacific!$!119225</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000333038_20120315005210</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Irrigation and drainage</subsc>
        <admreg>East Asia and Pacific,East Asia and Pacific</admreg>
        <colti>Board transcript</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Rural Development,Private Sector Development,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth,Industry</historic_topic>
        <prdln>IBRD/IDA</prdln>
        <sectr>Agriculture, fishing, and forestry</sectr>
        <majdocty>Board Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            agriculture, balance of payments, borrower,
            City Bank, commercial banks, deficits, disposable income,
            expenditure, expenditures, farmers, fiscal policies, food
            imports, food production, food supply, foreign exchange,
            Government funds, growth rate, income taxes, inflation,
            INTERNATIONAL BANK, Loan, maturities, monetary policies,
            Private savings, rate of growth, repayments, rice, savings,
            steel, tax, tax revenues, time deposits, underdeveloped
            countries, underdeveloped country, withdrawal
        </keywd>
        <owner>N/A</owner>
        <lndinstr>
            Specific Investment Loan
        </lndinstr>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>East Asia and Pacific</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>67474</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Industry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Science and Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sustainable Land and Crop Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Alternative Sentencing Options</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community based Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Correctional Services and Facilities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corrections</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime and Society</ml:concept><ml:concept>Defense Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Detention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enforcement Policies and Oversight Mechanism</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigative Task Force Police</ml:concept><ml:concept>Juvenile Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Law Enforcement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Offender Reintegration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Administration and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Problem solving Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Prosecution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Restorative Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Therapeutic Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Assistance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim-Offender Mediation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Banks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Retail Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crops</ml:concept><ml:concept>Asset Recovery</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monetary and Exchange Rate Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal &amp; Monetary Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Consolidation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Governance and Structural Fiscal Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Rules</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Sustainability</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macro-Fiscal Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Drainage Maintenance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Drainage Operations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Irrigation Maintenance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Irrigation Operations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Electric Power</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Textiles</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sustainable Land Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Engineering</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Criminal Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports &amp; Waterways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Highways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Mountains</ml:concept><ml:concept>Municipality</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Balance of Payments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inflation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monetary Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Irrigation and Drainage Operation and Maintenance</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Eastern Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Japan</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>