<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>ï»¿NOTE NUMBER 330                                                                                                                                                                 67806&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                       viewpoint                                  PUBLIC POLICY FOR THE PRIVATE SECTOR&#13;
FINANCIAL AND PRIVATE SECTOR DEVELOPMENT VICE PRESIDENCY DECEMBER 2011&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                       Reforming Business Taxes&#13;
                                                                         Miriam Bruhn                  What Is the Effect on Private Sector Development?&#13;
                                                                         Miriam Bruhn (mbruhn@         Tax rate s an d th e admi n i strati ve c osts of tax c ompl i an c e are ke y&#13;
                                                                         worldbank.org) is an&#13;
                                                                         economist in the World&#13;
                                                                                                       c on c e rn s of bu si n e ss. S tu di e s wi th i n an d ac ross c ou n tri e s su gge st th at&#13;
                                                                         Bankâ&#128;&#153;s Development            l owe ri n g c orporate tax rate s c an i n c re ase i n ve stme n t, re du c e tax&#13;
                                                                         Research Group.&#13;
                                                                                                       e vasi on by formal fi rms, promote th e c re ati on of formal fi rms, an d&#13;
                                                                         This Note was written as      u l ti mate l y rai se sal e s an d G DP. Th e se be n e fi ts, h owe ve r, n e e d to be&#13;
                                                                         part of the Investment        bal an c e d agai n st oth e r obj e c ti ve s of th e tax re gi me . A l th ou gh l e ss&#13;
                                                                         Climate Impact Project, a&#13;
                                                                         joint effort of the World     i s kn own abou t th e e ffe c ts of re du c i n g c ompl i an c e c osts, e vi de n c e&#13;
                                                                         Bank Groupâ&#128;&#153;s Investment       su gge sts th at th i s too c an l e ad to more formal fi rms an d h i gh e r sal e s.&#13;
                                                                         Climate Department, IFCâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
                                                                         Investment Climate Busi-&#13;
                                                                                                       The tax regime is one of the most prominent            tend to face disproportionately high compliance&#13;
                                                                         ness Line, and the World&#13;
                                                                                                       aspects of a countryâ&#128;&#153;s business environment. In        costs.1&#13;
                                                                         Bankâ&#128;&#153;s Development Re-&#13;
                                                                                                       many countries most formal firms are required to           Corporate tax rates have been almost univer-&#13;
                                                                         search Group, in collabora-&#13;
                                                                                                       file and pay taxes repeatedly throughout the year      sally reduced over the past decade as a result of&#13;
                                                                         tion with IFCâ&#128;&#153;s Develop-&#13;
                                                                         ment Impact Department,&#13;
                                                                                                       and must dedicate substantial staff time to the        the competition for increasingly mobile capital.&#13;
                                                                         the Development Impact&#13;
                                                                                                       process. Thus it is unsurprising that in the World     Yet important differences remain across coun-&#13;
                                                                         Evaluation Initiative, the    Bank Enterprise Surveys businesses consistently        tries.2 The World Bankâ&#128;&#153;s Doing Business report,&#13;
                                                                         FPD Chief Economistâ&#128;&#153;s         rank tax rates and the tax administrative process      which collects data on statutory tax rates around&#13;
                                                                         Office, and the Global        among the most important constraints they face         the world, finds significant variation, with rates&#13;
                                                                         Indicators and Analysis       (figure 1). Tax policy and administration are a        ranging from 0 percent in Moldova to 40 percent&#13;
THE WORLD BANK GROUP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                         Unit. The project is funded   key part of a countryâ&#128;&#153;s private sector development     in Chad in 2010 (World Bank 2011).&#13;
                                                                         by the U.S. Agency for        strategy. They are also often a political minefield,       But statutory tax rates do not necessarily rep-&#13;
                                                                         International Develop-        subject to conflicting objectives.                     resent the taxes that firms actually need to pay.&#13;
                                                                         ment and the World                The regulatory burden of taxation has been         The reason is that deductions, depreciation, and&#13;
                                                                         Bank Groupâ&#128;&#153;s Investment       increasingly highlighted in surveys on doing busi-     other factors influence how much of corporate&#13;
                                                                         Climate Department.           ness, and country case studies suggest that high       income is taxable. A more meaningful measure&#13;
                                                                                                       compliance costs can contribute to the decision        of corporate taxes is the effective tax rate, which&#13;
                                                                                                       of businesses to operate informallyâ&#128;&#148;that is, to        measures the actual taxes paid (after taking into&#13;
                                                                                                       not register with the tax authority at all (see,       account deductions, depreciation, and other&#13;
                                                                                                       for example, Thiessen 2003). This is particularly      factors) as a percentage of profits. Djankov and&#13;
                                                                                                       relevant for small and medium-size firms, which        others (2010) report both statutory and effec-&#13;
&amp;#12;REfORMING BUSINESS TAxES WhAT IS ThE EFFECT ON PRIVATE SECTOR DEVELOPMENT?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure Share of firms identifying issue as a major constraint&#13;
                                                                                                            Lower tax rates, higher investment&#13;
                                                                                                            While both tax rates and tax administration are&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
1          Percent                                                                                          key concerns of the business community, the lack&#13;
           50                                                                                               of comparable information on administrative&#13;
            40                                                                                              structures and, more important, administrative&#13;
            30                                                                                              and taxpayer compliance costs constrains cross-&#13;
            20                                                                                              country studies of tax administration.&#13;
            10                                                                                                  The tax component of the World Bankâ&#128;&#153;s Doing&#13;
              0                                                                                             Business survey is one of the few attempts to col-&#13;
                                                                                                            lect standardized information on tax compliance&#13;
                     s&#13;
&#13;
                                                         io n&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                           ty&#13;
&#13;
                                                          ns&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                            e&#13;
&#13;
                                                          on&#13;
&#13;
                                                          ce&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                            s&#13;
&#13;
                                                           ts&#13;
&#13;
                                                            g&#13;
&#13;
                                                         ion&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                           ls&#13;
&#13;
                                                          ns&#13;
                  ate&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                         or&#13;
                                                        im&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                       sin&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                       kil&#13;
                                                       ici&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                       ur&#13;
                                                      tio&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                      an&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                      tio&#13;
                                                      ati&#13;
                                                     pt&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                    tat&#13;
                                                     tit&#13;
                                                    Cr&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                   Co&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                   rs&#13;
                                                   ctr&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                   en&#13;
              xr&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 ula&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  fin&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 ula&#13;
                                                  str&#13;
                      rru&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 pe&#13;
                                                                                                            costs, though only for a single hypothetical firm.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 or&#13;
&#13;
                                               bo&#13;
                                               Lic&#13;
                                              Ele&#13;
            Ta&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              ini&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                             om&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              sp&#13;
                    Co&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                             eg&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                             eg&#13;
                                              to&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                            La&#13;
                                         dm&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                           an&#13;
                                          rr&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                          er&#13;
                                          ss&#13;
&#13;
                                         rc&#13;
                                                                                                            Using this database, Djankov and others (2010)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        Tr&#13;
                                       bo&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       ce&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       ad&#13;
                                      xa&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     cto&#13;
                                    La&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                    Ac&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                    Tr&#13;
                                   Ta&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   se&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                            examine the relationship between the complexity&#13;
                                al&#13;
                               m&#13;
                            or&#13;
                         Inf&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                            of paying taxes and investment. They find that&#13;
    Note: Data cover 128 countries and are the latest available for each country.                           neither the number of hours needed to comply&#13;
    Source: Authorâ&#128;&#153;s calculations based on data from World Bank Enterprise Surveys in 2005â&#128;&#147;10.&#13;
                                                                                                            with taxes nor the number of tax payments, as&#13;
                                                                                                            captured in the survey, is significantly correlated&#13;
                                                    tive tax rates for 85 countries.3 Effective tax rates   with investment across countries (table 1). But&#13;
                                                    tend to be lower (the average statutory tax rate        given the regressive nature of compliance costs,&#13;
                                                    is 29 percent, and the average effective tax rate       their effect can be expected to be more impor-&#13;
                                                    17.4 percent), but they still vary widely across        tant for firms that are smaller than the case study&#13;
                                                    countriesâ&#128;&#148;from 6.6 percent in Mongolia to 39.9          firm used by the Doing Business survey. Thus&#13;
                                                    percent in Bolivia.4                                    more research is needed to study the relation-&#13;
                                                        Measuring the effects of tax reforms on eco-        ship between tax simplification and investment&#13;
                                                    nomic outcomes such as investment is challeng-          across countries. There is no within-country study&#13;
                                                    ing. It involves extensive data requirements,           examining this relationship.&#13;
                                                    nonuniform reporting practices, identification              Most empirical papers on the private sector&#13;
                                                    problems, and a wide range of imperfect mea-            effect of tax reforms focus on the relationship&#13;
                                                    sures and methodologies to overcome these               between corporate income tax rates and invest-&#13;
                                                    challenges. Further complicating the task is            ment across countries. For example, one recent&#13;
                                                    that investment decisions usually are not based         study finds that a decrease in the statutory cor-&#13;
                                                    only on corporate income tax. Value added tax,          porate tax rate of 10 percentage points is associ-&#13;
                                                    depreciation, dividend tax, and capital taxes all       ated with an increase in foreign direct investment&#13;
                                                    play an important part as well, particularly for        equivalent to between 0.33 and 0.45 percent of&#13;
                                                    small domestic firms. Indeed, one reason why            GDP (Klemm and Van Parys 2009). The same&#13;
                                                    countries have lowered corporate income tax             study finds no significant relationship between&#13;
                                                    rates during the past decade is that they have          statutory tax rates and domestic investment.&#13;
                                                    also reduced tax incentives and have put more               Two cross-country studies using effective&#13;
                                                    emphasis on value added tax instead, raising the        tax rates find stronger results. They show that&#13;
                                                    rates and widening the coverage.                        a decrease in the effective corporate tax rate of 10&#13;
                                                        With these challenges in mind, this Note is         percentage points is associated with an increase in&#13;
                                                    aimed at providing an initial overview of the           foreign direct investment equivalent to between&#13;
                                                    empirical evidence on the effects of business tax       1.6 and 2.1 percent of GDP (Djankov and oth-&#13;
                                                    reforms that change the tax rate or administrative      ers 2010; Van Parys and James forthcoming).6&#13;
                                                    processes (particularly filing requirements and         Similarly, one shows that a decrease in the effec-&#13;
                                                    the time required to pay taxes) on investment,          tive corporate tax rate of 10 percentage points&#13;
                                                    tax evasion by formal firms, formal firm creation,      is associated with an increase in domestic invest-&#13;
                                                    and economic performance.5 Tax reforms clearly          ment equivalent to 2 percent of GDP (Djankov&#13;
                                                    have implications for other economic outcomes           and others 2010).7&#13;
                                                    as well, particularly government revenue. But the           A potential limitation of cross-country studies&#13;
                                                    focus here is on the effect of these reforms on         is that the estimated correlations between tax&#13;
                                                    private sector development.                             rates and investment are not necessarily causal,&#13;
&amp;#12;             since they can be driven by other country char-                                                    of 2000 increased tax evasion by formal firms by&#13;
             acteristics that are hard to control for (see also                                                 10.6 percent of sales (table 2).&#13;
             OECD 2007). Within-country studies can often                                                          A micro-level study successfully measures tax&#13;
             account for these factors, however, and can                                                        evasion by calculating the reporting gap between&#13;
             therefore identify a more reliable, causal rela-                                                   administrative data on exports from Hong Kong&#13;
             tionship. Two within-country studies examine                                                       SAR, China, to China and administrative data on&#13;
             the effect of effective tax rates on investment.                                                   imports by China from Hong Kong SAR, China&#13;
             An analysis of the U.S. Tax Reform Act of 1986                                                     (Fisman and Wei 2004). The study finds that a&#13;
             shows that for sole proprietors a 10 percentage                                                    10 percentage point increase in the tax rate on&#13;
             point decrease in the marginal tax rate led to a                                                   exports, defined as the import tariff plus value&#13;
             20 percent increase in investment (Carroll and                                                     added tax rate for each product, raises the report-&#13;
             others 1998). In contrast, a within-country study                                                  ing gap between exports and imports by 30 percent.&#13;
             in India finds that the Finance Act of 2000, which                                                    There are no studies that measure the effect of&#13;
             included a reduction in tax benefits for export                                                    compliance costs on tax evasion by formal firms.&#13;
             income (increasing the effective tax rate from&#13;
             0 to 18 percent), appears to have had no effect                                                    Lower and simpler taxes, more formal&#13;
             on firmsâ&#128;&#153; investment (James 2010). But further                                                     firm creation&#13;
             investigation suggests that firms were able to                                                     Another important outcome of tax reforms is&#13;
             avoid paying higher taxes after the reform by                                                      formal firm creation, encompassing both the&#13;
             overstating expenses.                                                                              formation of new firms and the formalization of&#13;
                                                                                                                previously informal firms. A cross-country study&#13;
             Higher tax rates, more tax evasion                                                                 shows that a 10 percentage point decrease in the&#13;
             by formal firms                                                                                    effective corporate tax rate is associated with an&#13;
             Estimating the effect of compliance costs and tax                                                  increase in the total number of registered busi-&#13;
             rates on tax evasion by formal firms is difficult                                                  nesses of 2 per 100 people of working age (Djankov&#13;
             because tax evasion is hard to measure empiri-                                                     and others 2010; table 3).8 The same study finds&#13;
             cally. Using detailed data from tax auditors to                                                    no significant correlation between the number&#13;
             capture tax evasion, the within-country study in                                                   of hours needed to comply with taxes and formal&#13;
             India (James 2010) shows that the increase in                                                      firm creation across countries. But a 10 percent&#13;
             effective tax rates ensuing from the Finance Act                                                   decrease in the number of tax payments is associ-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table     Effect of tax reforms on investment&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
1&#13;
                                                                                                                                       Increase in domestic                    Increase in foreign&#13;
           Country                  Study                    Reform                                                                    investment                              direct investment&#13;
           United States            Carroll and others 1998a Tax Reform Act of 1986: 10 percentage                                     20 percent&#13;
                                                             point decrease in marginal tax rate&#13;
           India                    James 2010               Finance Act of 2000 (marginal                                              None&#13;
                                                             effective tax rates)b&#13;
           Cross-country            Djankov and others 2010 10 percentage point decrease in effective                                   2 percent of GDP                       2 percent of GDP&#13;
                                                             corporate income tax ratec&#13;
                                                             10 percent decrease in number of                                           None&#13;
                                                             hours needed to comply with taxes&#13;
                                                             10 percent decrease in number of                                           None&#13;
                                                             tax payments&#13;
           Cross-country            Klemm and Van Parys      10 percentage point decrease in statutory                                  None                                   0.33â&#128;&#147;0.45 percent of GDP&#13;
                                    2009                     corporate income tax rated&#13;
            Cross-country           Van Parys and James      10 percentage point decrease in effective                                                                         1.6â&#128;&#147;2.1 percent of GDP&#13;
                                    forthcoming              corporate income tax rateb&#13;
        a. Examines the effect of sole proprietorsâ&#128;&#153; personal income taxes on their capital investment decisions. The measure of income taxes used is the marginal federal individual income tax rate, which&#13;
        accounts for both the statutory rate schedule and implicit tax rates that arise from special features of the tax code.&#13;
        b. Refers to the marginal effective tax rate on capital, defined as the amount of taxes paid as a percentage of the pretax return on investments that are marginal (that is, just sufficient to cover financing&#13;
        and tax costs).&#13;
        c. Refers to the first-year effective tax rate, defined as the actual first-year corporate income tax liability relative to pretax earnings, taking into account all available deductions.&#13;
        d. Tax data are from the PricewaterhouseCoopers worldwide summaries of statutory corporate tax rates.&#13;
&amp;#12;Table     Effect of tax reforms on tax evasion by formal firms&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
2&#13;
           Country                   Study               Reform                                                                                    Increase in tax evasion&#13;
           China                     Fisman and Wei 2004 10 percentage point increase in tax rate                                                  30 percent (in gap between&#13;
                                                         on exports from Hong Kong SAR, China,                                                     reported exports and imports)&#13;
                                                         to Chinaa&#13;
           India                     James 2010          Finance Act of 2000 (marginal                                                             10.6 percent of sales&#13;
                                                                       effective tax rates)&#13;
        a. Tax rate is import tariff plus value added tax rate.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                     4&#13;
&#13;
ated with an increase in business registrations of                                                    from tax reforms are also reflected in higher&#13;
1.6 per 100 people of working age.                                                                    sales and GDP. In the context of the U.S. Tax&#13;
    The study by Djankov and others (2010) does                                                       Reform Act of 1986, Carroll and others (2001)&#13;
not disentangle whether the increase in business                                                      find that a 10 percentage point decrease in the&#13;
registrations is due to the formalization of previ-                                                   marginal tax rate for sole proprietors led to an&#13;
ously unregistered firms or to new firm creation. But                                                 increase in firm sales of about 15 percent (table&#13;
within-country evidence from Brazil suggests that                                                     4). Similarly, Fisman and Svensson (2007) show&#13;
tax reforms can provide an incentive for informal                                                     that a 10 percentage point decrease in the effec-&#13;
firms to register. Fajnzylber, Maloney, and Montes-                                                   tive corporate tax rate in Uganda is associated&#13;
Rojas (forthcoming) show that the introduction                                                        with a 15 percentage point increase in annual&#13;
of the â&#128;&#156;SIMPLESâ&#128;? tax regimeâ&#128;&#148;which reduced the                                                         sales growth. The introduction of the SIMPLES&#13;
tax rate by up to 8 percent of annual revenue for                                                     tax regime in Brazil increased firm revenues by&#13;
both micro and small firms and consolidated six                                                       37 percent (Fajnzylber, Maloney, and Montes-&#13;
separate federal tax and social security payments                                                     Rojas forthcoming).&#13;
into a single monthly paymentâ&#128;&#148;increased the                                                               Only two papers examine how corporate tax&#13;
share of micro firms that are registered with the                                                     rates affect GDP growth across countries. The&#13;
tax authorities by 7.2 percentage points.9                                                            first, using statutory tax rates, finds no robust&#13;
    Since the SIMPLES reform in Brazil included                                                       correlation between these rates and GDP growth&#13;
both a simplification of payments and a reduction                                                     (Klemm and Van Parys 2009). The second uses&#13;
in tax rates, the effects cannot be clearly attrib-                                                   statutory top corporate tax rates and finds that&#13;
uted to either change. There is no within-country                                                     a 10 percentage point decrease in these rates&#13;
study that estimates the effects of simplifying pay-                                                  increases GDP per capita growth by 1.82 percent-&#13;
ments and reducing tax rates separately.                                                              age points (Lee and Gordon 2005). The results of&#13;
                                                                                                      the second paper may be more reliable, since this&#13;
Improved economic performance                                                                         paper includes a larger set of countries and uses&#13;
Several studies suggest that the increases in                                                         an instrumental variables strategy to capture the&#13;
investment and formal firm creation resulting                                                         causal effect of corporate tax rates on growth.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table     Effect of tax reforms on formal firm creation&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
3&#13;
           Country                   Study                             Reform                                                              Increase in formal firms&#13;
           Brazil                    Fajnzylber, Maloney,              Introduction of SIMPLES                                             7.2 percentage pointsa&#13;
                                     and Montes-Rojas&#13;
                                     forthcoming&#13;
           Cross-country             Djankov and others                10 percentage point decrease in                                     2 per 100 people of working age&#13;
                                     2010                              effective corporate income tax rateb&#13;
                                                                       10 percent decrease in number of                                    None&#13;
                                                                       hours needed to comply with taxes&#13;
                                                                       10 percent decrease in number                                       1.6 per 100 people of working age&#13;
                                                                       of tax payments&#13;
        a. Refers to the share of micro firms (urban self-employed and firms with at most five paid employees, excluding domestic workers) registered with the tax authorities.&#13;
        b. Refers to the first-year effective tax rate, defined as the actual first-year corporate income tax liability relative to pretax earnings, taking into account all available deductions.&#13;
&amp;#12;    Table    Effect of tax reforms on economic performance&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    4&#13;
                                                                                                                                        Increase in sales&#13;
               Country                 Study                           Reform                                                           (or GDP growth)&#13;
               United States           Carroll and others              Tax Reform Act of 1986: 10 percentage                            About 15 percent&#13;
                                       2001a                           point decrease in marginal tax rate&#13;
              Brazil                   Fajnzylber, Maloney,            Introduction of SIMPLES                                          37 percent&#13;
                                       and Montes-Rojas&#13;
                                       forthcoming&#13;
              Uganda                   Fisman and Svensson             10 percentage point decrease in effective                        15 percentage pointsc&#13;
5&#13;
                                       2007                            corporate income tax rateb&#13;
              Cross-country            Klemm and Van Parys             10 percentage point decrease in statutory                        None (GDP growth)&#13;
                                       2009                            corporate income tax rate&#13;
              Cross-country            Lee and Gordon                  10 percentage point decrease in statutory                        1.82 percentage points (GDP per&#13;
                                       2005                            top corporate tax rated                                          capita growth)&#13;
            a. Examines the effect of sole proprietorsâ&#128;&#153; personal income taxes on the sales growth of their enterprises. The measure of income taxes used is the marginal federal individual&#13;
            income tax rate, which accounts for both the statutory rate schedule and implicit tax rates that arise from special features of the tax code.&#13;
            b. Refers to firmsâ&#128;&#153; reported tax payment (all types of taxes) as a share of sales.&#13;
            c. Refers to sales growth, not the level of sales.&#13;
            d. Rates are from the World Tax Database of the Office of Tax Policy Research at the University of Michigan.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Conclusion                                                                                        4. Moldova and Chad, the countries with the lowest&#13;
    Both within- and cross-country studies suggest                                                    and highest statutory tax rates according to the World&#13;
    that lowering corporate tax rates can increase                                                    Bankâ&#128;&#153;s Doing Business 2012 (2011), are not in the sam-&#13;
    investment, reduce tax evasion by formal firms,                                                   ple of countries covered by Djankov and others (2010).&#13;
    promote the creation of formal firms, and ulti-                                                   5. A related literature examines the effects on invest-&#13;
    mately raise sales and GDP. These benefits,                                                       ment of tax incentives such as tax holidays and exemp-&#13;
    however, need to be balanced against other                                                        tions from import duties and consumption taxes on raw&#13;
    objectives of the overall tax regime. Less is                                                     materials and inputs (for an overview of this literature,&#13;
    known about the effects of reducing compliance                                                    see Zee, Stotsky, and Ley 2002). This literature sug-&#13;
    costs, largely because of a lack of comparable                                                    gests that tax incentives can stimulate investment (for&#13;
    information. The few completed papers on this                                                     example, Van Parys and James 2010). But a countryâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
    topic provide suggestive evidence that simplify-                                                  overall economic characteristics may be more impor-&#13;
    ing taxes can increase formal firm creation and                                                   tant for the success or failure of industries than any tax&#13;
    firmsâ&#128;&#153; sales. But more work, particularly at the                                                  incentive package (Zee, Stotsky, and Ley 2002). Several&#13;
    within-country level, is needed in this area to                                                   papers find that even if tax incentives stimulate invest-&#13;
    allow firm conclusions.                                                                           ment, they are not cost-effective, because they entail a&#13;
                                                                                                      revenue loss that is larger than the investment they cre-&#13;
                                                                                                      ate (Chai and Goyal 2008; Zee, Stotsky, and Ley 2002).&#13;
    Notes                                                                                             6. See OECD (2007) and Mooij and Ederveen (2008)&#13;
    The author would like to thank Jacqueline Coolidge,                                               for an overview of the earlier literature on corporate tax&#13;
    Sebastian S. James, Michael Keen, Jan Loeprick, Marialisa                                         rates and foreign direct investment.&#13;
    Motta, Massimiliano Santini, Richard Stern, and Uma                                               7. Using statutory rather than effective tax rates,&#13;
    Subramanian for their valuable inputs and comments.                                               Djankov and others (2010) find no significant effect&#13;
    1. These costs usually include the cost of preparing                                              on domestic investment and a slightly smaller effect on&#13;
    and paying taxes (above and beyond normal business                                                foreign direct investment.&#13;
    accounting) for profit tax, value added or sales tax, and                                         8. Using statutory rather than effective tax rates, Djank-&#13;
    payroll taxes (see also Engelschalk 2007 and Interna-                                             ov and others (2010) find a slightly smaller but positive&#13;
    tional Tax Dialogue 2007).                                                                        and significant effect on the number of registered busi-&#13;
    2. For an overview, see Deloitte (2011).                                                          nesses per 100 people of working age.&#13;
    3. The effective tax rates are calculated for a standard-                                         9. This corresponds to a 55 percent increase in the&#13;
    ized domestic enterprise operating in each country.                                               share of micro firms registered with the tax authorities,&#13;
&amp;#12;REfORMING BUSINESS TAxES WhAT IS ThE EFFECT ON PRIVATE SECTOR DEVELOPMENT?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
though from a low base (from only 13 percent before          the International Tax Dialogue Conference, Buenos&#13;
the reform to 20.2 percent after the reform).                Aires, October 17â&#128;&#147;19.&#13;
                                                          James, Sebastian S. 2010. â&#128;&#156;The Effect of Tax Incentives&#13;
References                                                   on Investment: Analysis of Exporters in India.â&#128;?&#13;
Carroll, Robert, Douglas Holtz-Eakin, Mark Rider, and        World Bank, Washington, DC.&#13;
   Harvey S. Rosen. 1998. â&#128;&#156;Entrepreneurs, Income Taxes,   Klemm, Alexander, and Stefan Van Parys. 2009. â&#128;&#156;Empir-&#13;
                                                                                                                       viewpoint&#13;
   and Investment.â&#128;? NBER Working Paper 6374, National        ical Evidence on the Effects of Tax Incentives.â&#128;? IMF&#13;
   Bureau of Economic Research, Cambridge, MA.               Working Paper WP/09/136, International Monetary&#13;
                                                                                                                       is an open forum to&#13;
â&#128;&#148;â&#128;&#148;â&#128;&#148;. 2001. â&#128;&#156;Personal Income Taxes and the Growth             Fund, Washington, DC.&#13;
                                                                                                                       encourage dissemination of&#13;
   of Small Firms.â&#128;? In Tax Policy and the Economy, vol.   Lee, Young, and Roger H. Gordon. 2005. â&#128;&#156;Tax&#13;
                                                                                                                       public policy innovations&#13;
   15, ed. James M. Poterba, 124â&#128;&#147;48. Cambridge, MA:          Structure and Economic Growth.â&#128;? Journal of Public&#13;
                                                                                                                       for private sectorâ&#128;&#147;led and&#13;
   MIT Press.                                                Economics 89: 1027â&#128;&#147;43.&#13;
                                                                                                                       market-based solutions for&#13;
Chai, Jingqing, and Rishi Goyal. 2008. â&#128;&#156;Tax Conces-       Mooij, Ruud A. de, and Sjef Ederveen. 2008. â&#128;&#156;Corporate&#13;
                                                                                                                       development. The views&#13;
   sions and Foreign Direct Investment in the Eastern        Tax Elasticities: A Readerâ&#128;&#153;s Guide to Empirical Find-&#13;
                                                                                                                       published are those of the&#13;
   Caribbean Currency Union.â&#128;? IMF Working Paper              ings.â&#128;? Oxford Review of Economic Policy 24 (4): 680â&#128;&#147;97.&#13;
                                                                                                                       authors and should not be&#13;
   WP/08/257, International Monetary Fund, Wash-          OECD (Organisation for Economic Co-operation and             attributed to the World&#13;
   ington, DC.                                               Development). 2007. Tax Effects on Foreign Direct         Bank or any other affiliated&#13;
Deloitte. 2011. â&#128;&#156;Global Tax Rates 2011.â&#128;? http://www          Investment: Recent Evidence and Policy Analysis. OECD     organizations. Nor do any&#13;
   .deloitte.com/.                                           Tax Policy Studies, no. 17. Paris: OECD.                  of the conclusions represent&#13;
Djankov, Simeon, Tim Ganser, Caralee McLiesh, Rita        Thiessen, Ulrich. 2003. â&#128;&#156;The Impact of Fiscal Policy and     official policy of the World&#13;
   Ramalho, and Andrei Shleifer. 2010. â&#128;&#156;The Effect of        Deregulation on Shadow Economies in Transition            Bank or of its Executive&#13;
   Corporate Taxes on Investment and Entrepreneur-           Countries: The Case of Ukraine.â&#128;? Public Choice 114        Directors or the countries&#13;
   ship.â&#128;? American Economic Journal: Macroeconomics 2        (3/4): 295â&#128;&#147;318.                                           they represent.&#13;
   (3): 31â&#128;&#147;64.                                            Van Parys, Stefan, and Sebastian S. James. 2010. â&#128;&#156;The Ef-&#13;
Engelschalk, Michael. 2007. Designing a Tax System for       fectiveness of Tax Incentives in Attracting Investment:   To order additional copies&#13;
   Micro and Small Businesses: Guide for Practitioners.      Panel Data Evidence from the CFA Franc Zone.â&#128;?             contact Ryan Hahn,&#13;
&#13;
   Washington, DC: International Finance Corpora-            International Tax and Public Finance 17 (4): 400â&#128;&#147;29.      managing editor,&#13;
&#13;
   tion.                                                  â&#128;&#148;â&#128;&#148;â&#128;&#148;. Forthcoming. â&#128;&#156;Why Tax Incentives May Be an              Room F 4P-252A,&#13;
&#13;
Fajnzylber, Pablo, William F. Maloney, and Gabriel V.        Ineffective Tool to Encouraging Investment? The           The World Bank,&#13;
&#13;
   Montes-Rojas. Forthcoming. â&#128;&#156;Does Formality Im-                                                                      1818 H Street, NW,&#13;
                                                             Role of Investment Climate.â&#128;? World Economy.&#13;
                                                                                                                       Washington, DC 20433.&#13;
   prove Micro-Firm Performance? Evidence from the        World Bank. 2011. Doing Business 2012: Doing Business&#13;
   Brazilian SIMPLES Program.â&#128;? Journal of Development        in a More Transparent World. Washington, DC: World&#13;
                                                                                                                       Telephone:&#13;
   Economics.                                                Bank.&#13;
                                                                                                                       001 202 473 4103&#13;
Fisman, Raymond, and Jakob Svensson. 2007. â&#128;&#156;Are Cor-      Zee, Howell H., Janet G. Stotsky, and Eduardo Ley.&#13;
                                                                                                                       Fax:&#13;
   ruption and Taxation Really Harmful to Growth?            2002. â&#128;&#156;Tax Incentives for Business Investment: A&#13;
                                                                                                                       001 202 522 3480&#13;
   Firm-Level Evidence.â&#128;? Journal of Development Econom-      Primer for Policy Makers in Developing Countries.â&#128;?&#13;
                                                                                                                       Email:&#13;
   ics 83 (1): 63â&#128;&#147;75.                                        World Development 30 (9): 1497â&#128;&#147;516.&#13;
                                                                                                                       rhahn@worldbank.org&#13;
Fisman, Raymond, and Shang-Jin Wei. 2004. â&#128;&#156;Tax Rates&#13;
   and Tax Evasion: Evidence from â&#128;&#152;Missing Importsâ&#128;&#153;&#13;
                                                                                                                       Produced by Carol Siegel&#13;
   in China.â&#128;? Journal of Political Economy 112 (2):&#13;
   471â&#128;&#147;96.                                                                                                             Printed on recycled paper&#13;
International Tax Dialogue. 2007. â&#128;&#156;Taxation of Small&#13;
   and Medium Enterprises.â&#128;? Background paper for&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                This Note is available online:&#13;
                                                             http://www.worldbank.org/fpd/publicpolicyjournal&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="16198906">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2011/12/16198906/reforming-business-taxes-effect-private-sector-development
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <virt_coll>Knowledge Notes</virt_coll>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2011/12/16198906/reforming-business-taxes-effect-private-sector-development</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2011/12/16198906/reforming-business-taxes-effect-private-sector-development</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2012-04-02T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2012-04-02T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2012/04/03/000333037_20120403005447/Rendered/INDEX/678060VP00PUBL0rming0Business0Taxes.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2012/04/03/000333037_20120403005447/Rendered/PDF/678060VP00PUBL0rming0Business0Taxes.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2012-04-03T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2011-12-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Reforming business taxes : what is the
            effect on private sector development?
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Tax rates and the administrative costs
            of tax compliance are key concerns of business. Studies
            within and across countries suggest that lowering corporate
            tax rates can increase investment, reduce tax evasion by
            formal firms, promote the creation of formal firms, and
            ultimately raise sales and Gross Domestic Product (GDP).
            These benefits, however, need to be balanced against other
            objectives of the tax regime. Although less is known about
            the effects of reducing compliance costs, evidence suggests
            that this too can lead to more formal firms and higher sales.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Reforming business taxes : what is the
            effect on private sector development?
        </docna>
        <display_title>Reforming business taxes : what
            is the effect on private sector development?</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2011/12/16198906/reforming-business-taxes-effect-private-sector-development</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Viewpoint</docty>
        <subtopic>Tax Law,Investment and Investment Climate,Emerging Markets,Debt Markets,Taxation &amp; Subsidies</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Private Sector Development,Law and Development,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth,Finance and Financial Sector Development</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Bruhn, Miriam</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000333037_20120403005447</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>Public policy for the private sector ; note
            no. 330</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Private Sector Development,Law and Development,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth,Finance and Financial Sector Development</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            accounting, affiliated organizations, annual
            sales, business environment, Business Investment, business
            tax, Business Taxes, capital investment, capital taxes,
            consumption taxes, corporate income tax, Corporate tax,
            corporate tax rate, Corporate tax rates, corporate taxes,
            Currency, deductions, Deregulation, Developing Countries,
            dividend, dividend tax, domestic investment, economic
            performance, Effective tax rates, export, Exporters,
            exports, federal tax, Finance Corporation, Firm Performance,
            Fiscal Policy, foreign direct investment, government
            revenue, implicit tax, income tax rate, International
            Development, International Finance, Investment Climate,
            investment decisions, Monetary Fund, payroll taxes, personal
            income, personal income taxes, Political Economy, PRIVATE
            SECTOR DEVELOPMENT, Public Finance, PUBLIC POLICY, public
            policy innovations, regulatory burden, return, return on
            investments, sales growth, sales tax, Small Businesses,
            statutory tax, statutory tax rate, statutory tax rates, Tax,
            tax administration, tax benefits, tax code, tax compliance,
            tax compliance costs, Tax Concessions, tax evasion, tax
            incentive, tax incentives, tax liability, tax payment, tax
            payments, Tax policy, Tax rate, tax rates, Tax Reform, tax
            reforms, tax regime, tax simplification, Tax Structure, Tax
            System, taxation, taxpayer, taxpayer compliance, Transition
            Countries, Value added tax, World Economy
        </keywd>
        <owner>DECRG: Finance &amp; Priv Sec Devt (DECFP)</owner>
        <repnb>67806</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sustainable Climate Business</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sustainable Energy Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Climate Change</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Alternative Sentencing Options</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community based Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Correctional Services and Facilities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corrections</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime and Society</ml:concept><ml:concept>Defense Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Detention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enforcement Policies and Oversight Mechanism</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigative Task Force Police</ml:concept><ml:concept>Juvenile Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Law Enforcement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Offender Reintegration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Administration and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Problem solving Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Prosecution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Restorative Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Therapeutic Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Assistance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim-Offender Mediation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Tax Exemption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Tax Giveaways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Tax Holiday</ml:concept><ml:concept>Tax Revenue Lost</ml:concept><ml:concept>Business Registration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Denationalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deregulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Destatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Divestiture of Ownership</ml:concept><ml:concept>Climate Impacts</ml:concept><ml:concept>Projected Climate Impacts</ml:concept><ml:concept>Asset Recovery</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investment and Investment Climate</ml:concept><ml:concept>Business Regulation for Enterprise Creation and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legal Regulation and Business Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Management of Public Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Finance Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Finances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Economics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Economics &amp; Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Tax Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Tax Compliance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Tax Self Assessment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Taxpayer Registry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Taxpayer Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Foreign Direct Investment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Foreign Direct Investments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Linkages</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Business Environments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Criminal Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Taxation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Tax Expenditures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Business Entry and Startup</ml:concept><ml:concept>Privatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Climate Change Impacts</ml:concept><ml:concept>Tax Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investment Climate</ml:concept><ml:concept>Business Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Tax and Revenue Policy and Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investment Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>FDI Spillovers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Tax Incentives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Tax Policy</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>