<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>ï»¿Report No. 51                                        67918&#13;
&#13;
South Asia Human Development Sector&#13;
&#13;
Enhancing the Quality of Education in the Maldives&#13;
Challenges and Prospects&#13;
&#13;
February 2012&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Discussion Paper Series&#13;
&amp;#12;Report No. 51&#13;
&#13;
South Asia: Human Development Unit&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Enhancing the Quality of Education in the&#13;
Maldives&#13;
Challenges and Prospects&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
February 2012&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Discussion Paper Series&#13;
&amp;#12;                                              TABLE OF CONTENTS&#13;
&#13;
Table of Contents ............................................................................................................................. i&#13;
Acknowledgements ........................................................................................................................ iv&#13;
Abbreviations and Acronyms ......................................................................................................... v&#13;
&#13;
Enhancing the Quality of Education ............................................................................................... 1&#13;
Introduction ..................................................................................................................................... 1&#13;
Education Quality and Performance ............................................................................................... 1&#13;
Raising Education Quality: Promise and Potential ......................................................................... 5&#13;
Enhancing the Skills and Performance of Teachers ....................................................................... 5&#13;
Quality Assurance ......................................................................................................................... 10&#13;
National Assessments of Learning Outcomes .............................................................................. 14&#13;
&#13;
Bibliography ................................................................................................................................. 18&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Tables&#13;
Table 1. Results of National Assessments of Learning Outcomes in Grade 4, English and&#13;
         Mathematics, 2008 ........................................................................................................... 1&#13;
Table 2. Results of National Assessments of Learning Outcomes in Grade 7, English and&#13;
         Mathematics, 2008 ........................................................................................................... 1&#13;
Table 3. Proportion of Students Passing the General Certificate of Examinations Ordinary&#13;
         Level (GCE O/L), 2007-2010 (percentage)...................................................................... 4&#13;
Table 4. Proportion of Students Passing the General Certificate of Examinations&#13;
         Advanced Level (GCE A/L), 2007-2010 (percentage) .................................................... 4&#13;
Table 5. Proportion of Untrained Teachers by Stage of Education, 2010 ...................................... 5&#13;
Table 6. Key Policy Options to Strengthen the Teacher System .................................................. 10&#13;
Table 7. Dimensions of Education Quality in CFBS .................................................................... 11&#13;
Table 8. Selected Countries That Used National Assessment Results in Reviewing the&#13;
         Education System ........................................................................................................... 14&#13;
Table 9. Differences between National Assessments and Public Examinations .......................... 15&#13;
Table 10. Options for Implementing a National Assessment ....................................................... 17&#13;
&#13;
Figures&#13;
Figure 1. Average English Language Learning Outcomes at Grade 4 by Atoll, 2008 ................... 2&#13;
Figure 2. Average English Language Learning Outcomes at Grade 7 by Atoll, 2008 ................... 2&#13;
Figure 3. Average Mathematics Learning Outcomes at Grade 4 by Atoll, 2008 ........................... 3&#13;
Figure 4. Average Mathematics Learning Outcomes at Grade 7 by Atoll, 2008 ........................... 3&#13;
Figure 5. Teacher Competencies..................................................................................................... 6&#13;
Figure 6. The Composition of the Teacher Stock, 2010 ................................................................. 7&#13;
Figure 7. Types of Teacher Incentives ............................................................................................ 9&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                         i&#13;
&amp;#12;Boxes&#13;
Box 1. Strengths of School-based Teacher Training/Support (SBT) Program in Egypt ................ 8&#13;
Box 2. Quality Assurance in Singapore Schools .......................................................................... 13&#13;
Box 3. Quality Assurance in Sri Lanka ........................................................................................ 13&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                               ii&#13;
&amp;#12;AUTHORS&#13;
Harsha Aturupane&#13;
&#13;
   Mari Shojo&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       iii&#13;
&amp;#12;                            ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS&#13;
The team acknowledges with sincere gratitude several officials in the Maldives who assisted and&#13;
provided valuable information for this study. The Minister of Education, the State Minister of&#13;
Education, the Deputy Ministers of Education, the Permanent Secretary of the Ministry of&#13;
Education; the Director-General of the Department of Higher Education and the Director-&#13;
General of the Department of Planning in the Ministry of Education; and the senior staff of the&#13;
Ministry of Education; the Minister and senior staff of the Ministry of Finance and Treasury; the&#13;
Department of National Planning; the Chancellor, Rector and staff of the Maldives National&#13;
University (MNU); the UN agencies; private higher education and training providers, including&#13;
from Clique College, Cyryx College, Focus Education Center, Mandhu College, Modern&#13;
Academy for Professional Studies, and Villa College; education officials from the Northern&#13;
Province, including from the Jalaaluddeen School, Afeefuddeen School and Atoll Education&#13;
Centre; education officials from the Southern Province, including from the MNU Campus and&#13;
the Polytechnic in Hethadoo, the Mohibudeen School and the Seenu Atoll Education Centre;&#13;
employers from the public and private sectors; participants at consultation workshops in Maleâ&#128;&#159;&#13;
and the Addu Atoll; and education officials from the Ameeniya School, Center for Higher&#13;
Secondary Education, and the Hiriyaa School, in Maleâ&#128;&#159;.&#13;
&#13;
The team also acknowledges the assistance of several World Bank colleagues in the preparation&#13;
of this report. In particular, Diaretou Gaye (Country Director for Sri Lanka and the Maldives),&#13;
Amit Dar (Education Sector Manager) and Deepa Sankar (Senior Economist).&#13;
&#13;
The team also thanks Anita Fernando (Team Assistant) and Mohammad Khalid Khan (Program&#13;
Assistant) of the World Bank for providing administrative and editorial assistance for the&#13;
production and dissemination of this paper.&#13;
&#13;
The financial assistance of the World Bank and the Education Program Development Fund&#13;
(Global and Regional Activities Program) of the Global Partnership for Education for this study&#13;
is acknowledged with gratitude.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                               iv&#13;
&amp;#12;             ABBREVIATIONS AND ACRONYMS&#13;
CCE       Centre for Continuing Education&#13;
CFBS      Child-Friendly Baraabaru Schools&#13;
ESDFP     Education Sector Development Framework and Program&#13;
GCE A/L   General Certificate of Education Advanced Level&#13;
GCE O/L   General Certificate of Education Ordinary Level&#13;
GOM       Government of Maldives&#13;
MNU       Maldives National University&#13;
MOE       Ministry of Education&#13;
SBT       School-based Teacher Training/Support&#13;
SEM       School Excellence Model&#13;
TA        Technical Assistance&#13;
TRC       Teacher Resource Center&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     v&#13;
&amp;#12;             ENHANCING THE QUALITY OF EDUCATION&#13;
                                       INTRODUCTION&#13;
The quality of education is a major policy challenge facing the Maldives. The country&#13;
achieved the first generation objective of providing universal access to basic education through&#13;
rapid expansion of enrollment. As is frequently the case with such countries, the second&#13;
generation challenge is to provide education of adequate quality. Evidence from a variety of&#13;
sources shows that education quality in the Maldives is weak, and needs urgent improvement.&#13;
&#13;
                    EDUCATION QUALITY AND PERFORMANCE&#13;
Learning outcomes in both primary and secondary education are modest. National&#13;
assessments of learning outcomes at Grade 4 and Grade 7 show that learning levels are&#13;
unsatisfactory [see Table 1 and Table 2]. The mean score for English among students at grade 4&#13;
is just 32 percent, and the mean score for mathematics is only 39 percent. At grade 7 the mean&#13;
score for English is merely 29 percent, and the mean score for mathematics is just 30 percent.&#13;
These are low average scores, and suggest that learning levels in both primary education and&#13;
lower secondary education are weak.&#13;
&#13;
Table 1. Results of National Assessments of Learning Outcomes in Grade 4, English and&#13;
Mathematics, 2008&#13;
                            Mean          Standard        Median        Number of&#13;
Grade and Subject            (%)          Deviation        (%)           Students&#13;
                                             (%)                          Tested&#13;
English                       32              18            29             5,503&#13;
Mathematics                   39              18            38             5,686&#13;
Source: Report of Achievement in English and Mathematics at Grades 4 and 7, Ministry of Education.&#13;
&#13;
Table 2. Results of National Assessments of Learning Outcomes in Grade 7, English and&#13;
Mathematics, 2008&#13;
                            Mean          Standard        Median        Number of&#13;
Grade and Subject            (%)          Deviation        (%)           Students&#13;
                                             (%)                          Tested&#13;
English                       29              19            22             7,808&#13;
Mathematics                   30              17            26             8,140&#13;
Source: Report of Achievement in English and Mathematics at Grades 4 and 7, Ministry of Education.&#13;
&#13;
There are wide regional disparities in learning outcomes. Cognitive achievement levels in&#13;
English language skills, at both grade 4 and grade 7, are considerably higher in the Maleâ&#128;&#159; atoll&#13;
than elsewhere in the Maldives [see Figure 1 and Figure 2]. The Seenu atoll and the Gnaviyani&#13;
atoll also possess English language skills well above the rest of the country. Most other atolls&#13;
perform poorly, with the Raa atoll at the bottom. The difference in average test scores among&#13;
students from the best and the weakest atolls, the Maleâ&#128;&#159; and Raa atolls respectively, is more than&#13;
double.&#13;
&#13;
                                                  1&#13;
&amp;#12;Figure 1. Average English Language Learning Outcomes at Grade 4 by Atoll, 2008&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Source: Achievement in English and Mathematics at Grades 4 and 7, Ministry of Education.&#13;
&#13;
Figure 2. Average English Language Learning Outcomes at Grade 7 by Atoll, 2008&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Source: Achievement in English and Mathematics at Grades 4 and 7, Ministry of Education.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  2&#13;
&amp;#12;Figure 3. Average Mathematics Learning Outcomes at Grade 4 by Atoll, 2008&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Source: Achievement in English and Mathematics at Grades 4 and 7, Ministry of Education.&#13;
&#13;
Figure 4. Average Mathematics Learning Outcomes at Grade 7 by Atoll, 2008&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Source: Achievement in English and Mathematics at Grades 4 and 7, Ministry of Education.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  3&#13;
&amp;#12;In mathematics the regional disparities are less, although gaps among atolls still exist [Figure 3&#13;
and Figure 4]. The Male, Seenu and Gnaviyani atolls display the best performance in&#13;
mathematics, along with other atolls such as Vaavu, Faafu and Baa. The Raa atoll shows the&#13;
lowest learning levels in mathematics, too.&#13;
&#13;
Examination pass rates at the General Certificate of Examination Ordinary Level (GCE&#13;
O/L) are poor. In 2010 only 33 percent of boys and 37 percent of girls who appeared for the&#13;
GCE O/L examination obtained five passes or more [Table 3]. This is a high failure rate, as it&#13;
suggests that two out of every three students is unable to pass the examination. The time trend,&#13;
however, has been positive. The GCE O/L pass rate among boys has risen from 26 percent in&#13;
2007 to 33 percent in 2010, and among girls from 25 percent in 2007 to 37 percent in 2010. 1&#13;
&#13;
Table 3. Proportion of Students Passing the General Certificate of Examinations Ordinary&#13;
Level (GCE O/L), 2007-2010 (percentage)&#13;
                        2007              2008               2009              2010&#13;
Maldives                 26                 27                32                35&#13;
Boys                     26                 25                31                33&#13;
Girls                    25                 29                33                37&#13;
Source: Department of Examinations.&#13;
Note: A student is considered to have passed the GCE O/L if he or she passes in at least 5 subjects.&#13;
&#13;
Examination pass rates at the General Certificate of Examination Advanced Level (GCE&#13;
A/L) are low. In 2010 only 35 percent of boys and 43 percent of girls who took the GCE A/L&#13;
examination were successful [Table 4]. This is an inadequate pass rate, as it suggests that two out&#13;
of every three boys and three out of every five girls is unsuccessful at the examination. Given&#13;
that the students who reach the GCE A/L stage are probably among the most intelligent in their&#13;
age cohorts, this is a disappointing level of performance. The time trend has been somewhat&#13;
positive among girls, with the GCE A/L pass rate among female students increasing from 38&#13;
percent in 2007 to 43 percent in 2010. However, among boys the time trend is less positive, with&#13;
the GCE O/L pass rate only rising marginally from 33 percent in 2007 to 35 percent in 2010.&#13;
&#13;
Table 4. Proportion of Students Passing the General Certificate of Examinations Advanced&#13;
Level (GCE A/L), 2007-2010 (percentage)&#13;
                        2007               2008              2009              2010&#13;
Boys                      33                33                 36               35&#13;
Girls                     38                39                 40               43&#13;
Source: Department of Examinations.&#13;
Note: Pass at the GCE A/L is defined as 2 Edexcel E's + 1 HSC C or 2 HSC C's + 1 Edexcel E or 3&#13;
Edexcel E's.&#13;
&#13;
The low level of learning outcomes and the wide regional disparities in learning are a&#13;
serious deficiency, as the cognitive achievement of students is central to the performance of&#13;
&#13;
1&#13;
 This increase in the GCE O/L pass rate over time may be over-estimated, as in recent years there appear to be some&#13;
schools which have kept back their weaker students from sitting the GCE O/L in order to raise their overall pass&#13;
rates. Such a practice would artificially increase the GCE O/L pass rate.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                        4&#13;
&amp;#12;an education system. Furthermore, the economic development of countries is closely related to&#13;
the cognitive skills of the labor force [Hanushek and Welch (2006), Hanushek and Woessmann&#13;
(2008)]. Hence, the poor cognitive performance of students, especially in the lagging atolls, will&#13;
hamper the future economic competitiveness and prospects of the country.&#13;
&#13;
        RAISING EDUCATION QUALITY: PROMISE AND POTENTIAL&#13;
There are several dimensions of education quality which Maldivian policy makers consider&#13;
to be of vital importance. Among these, the quality of school teachers is central to the&#13;
improvement of education quality. Hence, the Ministry of Education (MOE) is concerned to&#13;
develop the skills, motivation and performance of teachers. A second key policy initiative is the&#13;
establishment of a sound quality assurance framework for the school system. The MOE has&#13;
developed a quality assurance mechanism, which now needs to be pilot tested, refined and scaled&#13;
up throughout the country. A third strategic policy initiative is the development of a system of&#13;
regular national assessments of learning outcomes, which can then feed into policy formulation&#13;
and program development. These three strategic policy initiatives are discussed in the subsequent&#13;
sections of this report.&#13;
&#13;
       ENHANCING THE SKILLS AND PERFORMANCE OF TEACHERS&#13;
&#13;
The quality of teachers is of central importance to the performance of schools. Teachers&#13;
play a dominant role in what, how, and how much, students learn [OECD (2005), Hanushek&#13;
(2011)]. The performance of teachers depends on a variety of factors [Alemano et al (2011)]. A&#13;
three-level model of teacher competencies is presented in Figure 5 below. The first level covers&#13;
pre-service teacher education. The second level consists of teacher induction. The third level is&#13;
professional development. The latter can be divided into two further categories: off-site teacher&#13;
training opportunities, such as in teacher centers; and opportunities for on-site school based&#13;
teacher development.&#13;
&#13;
The Maldives has a high proportion of untrained primary school teachers. Approximately&#13;
23 percent of primary school teachers are untrained [Table 5]. Hence, the first level of an&#13;
adequate pre-service teacher education has not been completed in the country. Further, as these&#13;
untrained teachers are in primary schools any learning deficiencies of students will have a&#13;
cumulative effect further up into the secondary education system as well.&#13;
&#13;
Table 5. Proportion of Untrained Teachers by Stage of Education, 2010&#13;
                                         Lower        Secondary Higher                 Secondary&#13;
          Primary Education&#13;
                                         Education              Education&#13;
          Total       Untrained          Total     Untrained    Total              Untrained&#13;
          Teachers Teachers %            Teachers Teachers %    Teachers           Teachers %&#13;
 Male'    775         10                 570       5            140                0&#13;
 Atolls 2,817         27                 2,515     2            262                5&#13;
 Total    3,592       23                 3,085     2            402                3&#13;
Source: Ministry of Education Statistics.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                5&#13;
&amp;#12;Figure 5. Teacher Competencies&#13;
&#13;
                                                LEVEL 3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                LEVEL 2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                               LEVEL 1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Source: World Bank (2005), based on Martinet et al (2001).&#13;
Note: Level 1: Initial Teacher Education. Level 2: Teacher Induction. Level 3: Professional Development.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The proportion of untrained teachers in atolls is higher than in Maleâ&#128;&#153;. While 10 percent of&#13;
primary teachers in Maleâ&#128;&#159; are untrained, 27 percent of primary teachers in atolls are untrained.&#13;
Trained teachers are more interested in residing in Maleâ&#128;&#159; than in the outer atolls. However, this&#13;
creates an imbalance in the quality of education between Maleâ&#128;&#159; and the rest of the country. The&#13;
differences in teacher quality will be partly responsible for the weaker learning outcomes of&#13;
students in atolls compared to students in Maleâ&#128;&#159;.&#13;
&#13;
A shortage of adequately qualified teachers has necessitated the employment of a large&#13;
number of expatriate teachers for secondary education. Approximately 60 percent of teachers&#13;
at lower secondary and 67 percent of higher secondary teachers are expatriate teachers [Figure&#13;
6]. Most expatriate teachers are deployed in the atolls, especially as qualified Maldivians are&#13;
reluctant to take up positions in the remote islands. Among expatriate teachers, 87 percent at&#13;
lower secondary, and 64 percent at higher secondary level are deployed in the atolls.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                   6&#13;
&amp;#12;Figure 6. The Composition of the Teacher Stock, 2010&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Source: Ministry of Education Statistics.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The high dependence on expatriate teachers is controversial. Critics argue that expatriate&#13;
teachers are inadequately aware of the local culture, and that these teachers are not committed to&#13;
the Maldivian schools, resulting in rapid turnover. The cost of expatriate teachers, too, is higher.&#13;
The counter-arguments made against the critics are that: (a) there is a shortage of educated&#13;
Maldivians willing to become teachers; (b) foreign teachers are willing to serve in schools in&#13;
remote islands that Maldivians are not; and (c) expatriate teachers bring new ideas and cultural&#13;
diversity to the education system of the country.&#13;
&#13;
Policy Options for Teacher Development&#13;
&#13;
Successful achievement of a high quality of education will depend on the availability of&#13;
professionally educated and competent teachers at all levels. Pre-service teacher education is&#13;
offered by several institutions in the Maldives, including the Faculty of Education and the Centre&#13;
for Open Learning of the Maldives National University, as well as private higher education&#13;
institutions such as Mandhu College and Villa College. The number graduating from these&#13;
institutions, however, is too low to meet the needs of the system. Pre-service teacher education&#13;
opportunities need to be expanded sharply to ensure a fully trained cadre of school teacher. A&#13;
program to provide professional skills and competencies to the stock of untrained primary school&#13;
teachers is needed especially urgently.&#13;
&#13;
In-service teacher training needs to be further developed. The government has established a&#13;
professional development policy for teachers. The professional hubs for teacher development in&#13;
the Maldives are the Centre for Continuing Education (CCE) at the central level and Teacher&#13;
Resource Centers (TRCs) at regional levels, respectively. In-service teacher training is aimed at&#13;
the following categories of teachers: (a) unqualified teachers (mainly certification courses); (b)&#13;
teachers requiring skills upgrading: (c) teachers needing preparation for new roles, such as&#13;
                                                 7&#13;
&amp;#12;teacher educators or principals; and (d) curriculum related, particularly when there are&#13;
curriculum changes in the system, when teachers require refresher courses. The in-service&#13;
teacher training programs are mainly off-site programs, delivered through the TRCs or in Maleâ&#128;&#159;.&#13;
Off-site in-service teacher training is known to have limited impact internationally [Harris and&#13;
Sass (2011)]. Hence, off-site teacher training will need to be supplemented with other models of&#13;
teacher development.&#13;
&#13;
School-based teacher development is a promising initiative for policy makers to consider.&#13;
School-based teacher development has been noted globally for its effectiveness [Allemano et al&#13;
(2011)]. In the Maldives it would involve the active participation of school principals and&#13;
teachers, and atoll and island level officials. The range of activities under school-based teacher&#13;
development could cover school-based mentoring, peer learning, peer coaching, individual&#13;
consultations, and visits to classrooms in other schools and islands. It would also suit the&#13;
geography of the Maldives, with its widely dispersed small populations, as it would reduce travel&#13;
costs and minimize the time that teachers need to be away from their schools. Box 1 provides&#13;
examples of school-based teacher development, in the context of school-based management, in&#13;
Egypt.&#13;
&#13;
Box 1. Strengths of School-based Teacher Training/Support (SBT) Program in Egypt&#13;
Egypt has implemented school-based teacher training/support (SBT) program for English&#13;
teachers. This school-based teacher training and support takes place at the school site. The&#13;
strengths of this program include:&#13;
    ï&#130;· Teachers receive training without having to take time off work or travel long distances;&#13;
    ï&#130;· Teachers receive useful materials on teaching techniques and observe demonstrations;&#13;
    ï&#130;· Teachers can practice and discuss new techniques and new materials with colleagues and&#13;
        senior teachers on a daily basis;&#13;
    ï&#130;· The senior teachers can give classroom demonstrations using SBT activities;&#13;
    ï&#130;· The SBT activities increase communication and sharing of ideas among teachers;&#13;
    ï&#130;· The SBT provides a positive focus for inspectorsâ&#128;&#159; school visits, classroom observation,&#13;
        and meetings with teachers;&#13;
    ï&#130;· Senior teachers monitor teachers using SBT activities on a daily basis and can thus better&#13;
        assist inspectors on their observation visits; and&#13;
    ï&#130;· The SBT can serve as a link between a centralized type of in-service training program&#13;
        and specific teacher needs.&#13;
Source: Allemano et al (2011).&#13;
&#13;
Improving Teacher Motivation and Performance&#13;
&#13;
Attracting qualified individuals into the teacher profession field, retaining the qualified&#13;
teachers, and motivating them to work hard, is a critical challenge for the Maldives. Policy&#13;
makers in the MOE are keen to strengthen the motivation and incentives for teachers to perform&#13;
well. For instance, a hardship allowance was introduced in 2005 in order to promote local&#13;
teachers in the atolls. This incentive encouraged some local teachers and principals to work in&#13;
schools in remote atolls. The government now needs to develop a systematic set of policies to&#13;
strengthen teacher motivation and performance.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                8&#13;
&amp;#12;Countries around the world have tried a wide array of monetary and non-monetary&#13;
incentives to improve teacher quality and performance. These include internal motivation,&#13;
recognition and prestige, salary differentials, non-salary benefits, professional growth, adequate&#13;
school infrastructure and teaching materials, mastery, and responding to clients [see Figure 7].&#13;
The evidence from several studies suggests that a well-designed incentive system is important to&#13;
attract promising young people into the teaching profession, retain good quality teachers over the&#13;
career-cycle, and motivate teachers to perform well in classrooms [Bruns et al (2011)].&#13;
&#13;
Figure 7. Types of Teacher Incentives&#13;
&#13;
                                         Recognition&#13;
                                         and Prestige&#13;
                 Intrinsic                                                Salary&#13;
                Motivation                                             Differentials&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       Responding&#13;
                                                                               Job Stability&#13;
        to Clients                 Qualified, Motivated,&#13;
                                    Effective Teachers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          Mastery                                                            Pensions&#13;
                                                                            and Benefits&#13;
&#13;
                          Adequate&#13;
                        Infrastructure                  Professional&#13;
                         and Teaching                     Growth&#13;
                           Materials&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Source: Vegas (2005).&#13;
&#13;
In the Maldives the salaries of teachers have declined relative to the salaries of other government&#13;
services such as the civil service, and the private sector. In consequence, the most promising&#13;
school completers and young graduates are reluctant to enter the teaching profession. Also, in&#13;
mid-career capable teachers leave for more attractive jobs in the private sector and elsewhere in&#13;
the government.&#13;
&#13;
Policy Options for Improving Teacher Education and Training, Motivation and&#13;
Performance&#13;
&#13;
The Maldives needs to consider a package of policy initiatives to develop the teacher&#13;
system. This package should cover: (a) providing a benefit package that attracts bright young&#13;
people into the teaching profession and retains them over the career cycle; (b) producing a&#13;
sufficient number of qualified teachers over time; (c) the equitable deployment of teachers to the&#13;
atolls; and (d) the development of pre-service teacher education and professional development&#13;
&#13;
                                                        9&#13;
&amp;#12;opportunities during the career cycle. The main policy alternatives open to the Government of&#13;
Maldives (GOM) are summarized in Table 6.&#13;
&#13;
Table 6. Key Policy Options to Strengthen the Teacher System&#13;
       Policy Objectives                      Areas for Strategic Intervention&#13;
(a) Make teaching an          - Improve the competitiveness of teaching salaries&#13;
    attractive career choice  - Establishing professional standards for new teachers&#13;
    and increasing the        - Improve the image and status of teaching&#13;
    number of young           - Evaluate and reward effective teaching&#13;
    Maldivian teachers&#13;
(b) Extending and strengthen - Strengthen the relevant higher education institutions&#13;
    pre-service teacher          providing teacher education courses and programs,&#13;
    education                    especially in learner-centered teaching methods and subject&#13;
                                 content knowledge&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
(c) Upgrade the skills and           -    Develop and implement teacher training programs for these&#13;
    competencies of the                   teachers&#13;
    existing unqualified&#13;
    teachers&#13;
(d) Improve professional             -    Establish a program of School Based Teacher Development&#13;
    development                      -    Strengthen the off-site teacher training programs&#13;
    opportunities of teachers&#13;
&#13;
                                         QUALITY ASSURANCE&#13;
Quality assurance has assumed prominence among education policy makers around the&#13;
world in recent years. Quality assurance provides a framework for the systematic review and&#13;
monitoring of an education system to determine whether an acceptable standard of quality is&#13;
being achieved over the medium-term, and enhanced over the long-term in line with global&#13;
developments in education. Quality assurance reaches deep into the education system as the&#13;
standard of education in each school is open to evaluation through the protocols and processes of&#13;
the quality assurance framework [MOE (2010)]. The ultimate goal of a quality assurance system&#13;
is to assure every child of a high quality of education [Materu (2007)].&#13;
&#13;
The development of a quality assurance framework is an important recent policy initiative&#13;
in the Maldives. The MOE has introduced quality indicators for Child-Friendly Baraabaru&#13;
Schools (CFBS)2 [MOE (2010)]. CFBS is a new model that provides a comprehensive tool kit&#13;
for the evaluation of school performance. The main objectives of CFBS are to facilitate the&#13;
assessment of education processes by schools (self-assessment) and by provincial and national&#13;
level authorities (external assessments). The CFBS model helps to identify the strengths,&#13;
weaknesses and development needs of schools, and assists school-based development activities.&#13;
The CFBS indicators can be used for school self-assessments and for external assessments.&#13;
The CFBS quality indicators are categorized into five dimensions of education quality. These&#13;
&#13;
2&#13;
    Baraabaru means â&#128;&#158;goodâ&#128;&#159; in Dhivehi.&#13;
&#13;
                                                     10&#13;
&amp;#12;are: (a) inclusivity; (b) child-centered teaching and learning; (c) health and safety; (d) family and&#13;
community partnerships; and (e) leadership and management [Table 7]. For each dimension,&#13;
there are standards of quality. And for each standard, there are indicators that serve as criteria for&#13;
ratings within the standard. There are four levels of rating: emerging, procession, achieving, and&#13;
achieved. The indicators are used for both self-evaluation and monitoring. The quality assurance&#13;
evaluation processes can be implemented by schools, with the support of the provincial and&#13;
national level authorities.&#13;
&#13;
Table 7. Dimensions of Education Quality in CFBS&#13;
                  Child-centered                                Family and&#13;
                                    Health and                                      Leadership and&#13;
  Inclusivity      teaching and                                 community&#13;
                                        safety                                       management&#13;
                     learning                                   partnership&#13;
ï&#130;· Policy on      ï&#130;· Curriculum     ï&#130;· Health                  ï&#130;·   Family             ï&#130;·   Planning&#13;
   inclusivity       and syllabi      personnel                 participation      ï&#130;·   Professional&#13;
ï&#130;· Annual         ï&#130;· Lesson             and facilities        ï&#130;·   Communication          development&#13;
   enrolment         planning     ï&#130;· School                  ï&#130;·   Parental role      ï&#130;·   Professional&#13;
   and           ï&#130;· Teaching           health                ï&#130;·   Community              qualifications&#13;
   projections       and learning     policies                  involvement            and skills&#13;
ï&#130;· Inclusion          strategies   ï&#130;· Health and              ï&#130;·   Community          ï&#130;·   Human&#13;
   plan          ï&#130;· Teaching           nutrition                 resources              resources&#13;
ï&#130;· Children at        and learning     services                                         management&#13;
   risk              resources    ï&#130;· Health                                         ï&#130;·   Infrastructure&#13;
ï&#130;· Leadership     ï&#130;· Learning           education                                        and finance&#13;
   and               environment ï&#130;· Healthy                                         ï&#130;·   Leadership&#13;
   mentorship    ï&#130;· Learner-           physical                                         and&#13;
                     centered         environment                                      management&#13;
                     assessment   ï&#130;· Fitness                                        ï&#130;·   Community&#13;
                 ï&#130;· Co-                activities                                       collaboration&#13;
                     curricular                                                    ï&#130;·   Student&#13;
                     and extra â&#128;&#147;                                                       leadership&#13;
                     curricular&#13;
                     activities,&#13;
                     and career&#13;
                     guidance&#13;
Source: MOE (2010).&#13;
&#13;
Strategic Options for an Effective Quality Assurance Program&#13;
&#13;
While a conceptual framework for quality assurance in the Maldives has been prepared, it now&#13;
needs to be implemented effectively. In particular, the two dimensions of quality assessment, the&#13;
internal reviews or self-assessments by schools, and the external reviews through mechanisms&#13;
such as school inspections, need to be carefully developed and supported. Priority policy&#13;
attention is required for the program to be successful.&#13;
&#13;
Considerable capacity will need to be built to implement a sound quality assurance&#13;
program in the atolls and islands. The capacity of schools has to be developed to undertake&#13;
&#13;
                                                 11&#13;
&amp;#12;internal reviews and self-assessments. A significant degree of variation exists between and&#13;
within atolls in terms of the education levels and capabilities of parents and local communities.&#13;
In consequence, the MOE needs to clarify the roles and responsibilities of stakeholders from the&#13;
local communities in the quality assurance process. In addition, the capacity of atolls to&#13;
implement the protocols and procedures for external quality assurance activities has to be&#13;
developed. A geographic unit to function as the hub for the implementation of external reviews,&#13;
such as the provincial or atoll, has to be defined by the MOE and the necessary capacity built&#13;
within this geographical unit.&#13;
&#13;
Decentralized delivery of the quality assurance program will help to improve the cost-&#13;
effectiveness of implementation. Given the geography of the country with multiple and&#13;
scattered islands, centrally driven quality assurance processes such as quality assurance&#13;
inspections can be expensive. As such, the decentralized levels of the education system,&#13;
especially atolls and islands, will need to implement nearly all the activities for the quality&#13;
assurance program to be cost-effective. The program would also have to rely heavily on self-&#13;
assessments by schools, with external reviews taking place according to a time cycle that is&#13;
affordable. The MOE needs to develop on-line tools that can support the atolls, islands and&#13;
schools to implement the quality assurance program efficiently.&#13;
&#13;
Potential Innovations to Utilize the Quality Assurance Program&#13;
&#13;
The information from the quality assurance reviews can and should feed into policy&#13;
initiatives at the national level. An important national level policy measure could be the&#13;
classification and grouping of schools according to their performance, on quality assurance&#13;
reviews, such as in Singapore [Box 2]. Appropriate policy attention, including the allocation of&#13;
more resources, can then be directed at these groups of schools. Another policy use would be to&#13;
observe recurrent deficiencies or challenges across schools, which may require changes either in&#13;
academic programs (e.g. teacher education and training) or in the management of the education&#13;
system.&#13;
&#13;
The information from the quality assurance reviews need to feed into school improvement&#13;
activities at the local level. This would require schools to actively pursue measures to&#13;
strengthen areas in which they are diagnosed as weak through the quality assurance reviews. The&#13;
weaknesses identified can differ from school to school, and over time within the same school.&#13;
Hence, the quality assurance reviews have the advantage of being sensitive to the needs of&#13;
individual schools. However, there is considerable responsibility on schools to take the initiative&#13;
and design and implement performance improving actions. If schools fail to take initiative, the&#13;
potential of the quality assurance program will be under-utilized. Sri Lanka has developed and&#13;
implemented a system of quality assurance over the last decade or so [Box 3]. The feedback&#13;
from Sri Lankan schools which have utilized the quality assurance processes to improve school&#13;
performance is that the quality assurance system provides a very useful organizational&#13;
framework for school improvement activities.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                12&#13;
&amp;#12;Box 2. Quality Assurance in Singapore Schools&#13;
Quality assurance in education is of great concern in Singapore. The Ministry of Education in&#13;
Singapore has implemented a School Excellence Model (SEM), which provides a systematic&#13;
framework that enable schools to evaluate their practices by themselves, since 2000. Secondary&#13;
schools have been ranked based on performance criteria. The SEM was modified in 2004 so that&#13;
instead of ranking schools based on academic performance, schools with similar levels of academic&#13;
performance are classed together.&#13;
The SEM is a self-assessment model for schools adapted from various quality models. The SEM&#13;
aims to provide a means to objectively identify and measure the schoolsâ&#128;&#159; strengths and areas for&#13;
improvement, to allow benchmarking against similar schools, and to stimulate school improvement&#13;
activities. The SEM comprises nine quality criteria against which a school can be assessed: (a)&#13;
leadership of school leaders; (b) strategic planning; (c) staff management; (d) resources; (e) student-&#13;
focused processes; (f) efficiency and effectiveness on administrative and operational results; (g) staff&#13;
results; (h) partnership and society results; and (i) key performance results. Once in five years,&#13;
schools conduct an external validation exercise in which an external team of the Ministry of&#13;
Education visits the school for three days to validate the results of a self-assessment using the same&#13;
criteria. The assessment process is explicit in requiring evidence to justify a certain score. The SEM&#13;
is closely linked to a system of awards to schools based on broad criteria such as the extent of value-&#13;
added, good organizational practices, and performance in the arts and sports.&#13;
Source: Tan and Ng (2005).&#13;
Box 3. Quality Assurance in Sri Lanka&#13;
Sri Lanka has introduced a quality assurance system. The Ministry of Education has trained school&#13;
principals and teachers, and in-service advisors located in education zones and divisions, in quality&#13;
assurance activities. The conceptual model of the quality assurance systems contains eight themes.&#13;
These are: (a) general management; (b) physical and human resources management; (c) curriculum&#13;
management and classroom observation; (d) co-curricular activities; (e) student achievement; (f)&#13;
student welfare; (g) school and community; and (h) student development for a knowledge based&#13;
society.&#13;
The anticipated benefits of the Quality Assurance system are to:&#13;
   - improve accountability and capacity at the school level for performance improvement&#13;
       activities;&#13;
   - strengthen professional development through the improvement of competencies among&#13;
       school stakeholders;&#13;
   - utilize physical resources more efficiently;&#13;
   - identify the strengths and weakness of schools and introduce appropriate remedies ; and&#13;
   - improve the quality of schools.&#13;
The conceptual model of quality assurance has been organized and integrated within the overall&#13;
program of the government for the general education sector, the Education Sector Development&#13;
Framework and Program (ESDFP). This has given the quality assurance activities a prominent&#13;
position in the education policy framework of the country. The quality assurance system contains&#13;
both internal reviews by schools and external reviews by education administrators. Schools can use&#13;
the findings of the quality assurance reviews for the development of school plans and to monitor the&#13;
implementation of the school plans.&#13;
Source: MOE Sri Lanka (2010).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  13&#13;
&amp;#12;            NATIONAL ASSESSMENTS OF LEARNING OUTCOMES&#13;
The Maldives has conducted national assessments of learning outcomes in the past. These&#13;
national assessments have been useful to measure and understand the levels of cognitive&#13;
achievement in the country as a whole, as well as in the various atolls. However, institutional&#13;
capacity has not been developed in the Maldives to undertake regular national assessments of&#13;
learning outcomes that are technically rigorous and useful for policy purposes.&#13;
&#13;
The Maldives should develop institutional capacity to conduct national assessments of&#13;
learning outcomes on a regular cycle. National assessments have become the main tool for&#13;
policy analysis and policy development in the education systems of developed countries [see&#13;
Greaney and Kellaghan (2008)]. Many middle-income countries, and other countries in South&#13;
Asia such as Sri Lanka, Bangladesh, Nepal, Pakistan and India, are developing institutional&#13;
capacity to undertake national assessments according to a regular cycle and in line with the&#13;
requirements of policy makers.&#13;
&#13;
National assessments are useful for a variety of purposes. These include the following:&#13;
   ï&#130;· measuring the level of learning by students;&#13;
   ï&#130;· monitoring the level of student learning over time;&#13;
   ï&#130;· obtaining evidence on the strengths and weaknesses of studentsâ&#128;&#159; knowledge and skills;&#13;
   ï&#130;· examining disparities in learning between different sub-groups of students. e.g. regional&#13;
      disparities, gender disparities, or disparities among children from different economic&#13;
      groups;&#13;
   ï&#130;· analyzing the factors associated with student learning, such as school resources, teacher&#13;
      competence and preparation, and the home learning environments of students; and&#13;
   ï&#130;· developing policies and programs based on scientific information on learning levels and&#13;
      the covariates of learning outcomes.&#13;
&#13;
Examples of the uses of national assessments in several other countries are given in Table 8&#13;
below.&#13;
&#13;
Table 8. Selected Countries That Used National Assessment Results in Reviewing the&#13;
Education System&#13;
 Country               Examples of Some Claimed Uses&#13;
 Argentina             Instituted a program of school inspection&#13;
 Bolivia               Linked assessment data to a program for child nutrition&#13;
 Burkina Faso          Provided input for country analysis&#13;
 Cuba                  Strengthened preschool and early childhood care programs&#13;
 Kenya                 Led to benchmarks for providing facilities&#13;
 Kuwait                Provided support for the policy of introducing classroom libraries&#13;
 Malawi                Provided input for reform program&#13;
 Mauritius             Used data to support national sector study&#13;
 Namibia               Used by national commission&#13;
 Nepal                 Supported major government reform program&#13;
 Niger                 Provided input for country analysis&#13;
&#13;
                                              14&#13;
&amp;#12; Sri Lanka             Provided input for national sector strategy for education&#13;
 Uganda                Used to prepare educational reform program&#13;
                       Used to support a policy of expanding an equity program for full-&#13;
 Uruguay&#13;
                       time schools&#13;
                       Used to establish benchmarks for providing facilities (desks per&#13;
 Vietnam&#13;
                       pupil, books per pupil)&#13;
 Zanzibar (Tanzania)   Used in review of educational policies, standards, and benchmarks&#13;
 Zimbabwe              Used in commission review&#13;
Sources: Kellaghan, Greaney and Murray (2009).&#13;
&#13;
The national assessments can be designed to take into account the policy interests of&#13;
Maldivian policy makers. For instance, policy makers could benefit from a national assessment&#13;
which examined the factors associated with student learning, as such an information base does&#13;
not exist in the country. The findings of such an assessment can be used to develop policies in&#13;
areas such as teacher education and training, the implementation of the new curriculum, and&#13;
education resources.&#13;
&#13;
It is important to keep in mind that National Assessments of Learning Outcomes and Public&#13;
Examinations are different. These key differences are highlighted in Table 9 below.&#13;
&#13;
Table 9. Differences between National Assessments and Public Examinations&#13;
                                      National assessments           Public examinations&#13;
 Purpose                          To provide feedback to         To certify and select students&#13;
                                  policy makers&#13;
 Frequency                        For individual subjects        Annually and more often&#13;
                                  offered on a regular basis     where the system allows for&#13;
                                  (such as every four years)     repeats&#13;
 Duration                         One or two days                Can extend over a few weeks&#13;
 Who is tested?                   Usually a sample of students   All students who wish to take&#13;
                                  at a particular grade or age   this examination at the&#13;
                                  level                          examination grade level&#13;
 Format                           Usually multiple choice and    Usually multiple choices&#13;
                                  short answer&#13;
 Stakes: importance for           Low importance                 Great importance&#13;
 students, teachers, and others&#13;
 Coverage of curriculum           Generally confined to one or   Covers main subject areas&#13;
                                  two subjects&#13;
 Effect on teaching               Very little direct effect      Major effect: teacher&#13;
                                                                 tendency to teach what is&#13;
                                                                 expected on the examination&#13;
 Additional tuition sought for    Very unlikely                  Frequently&#13;
 students&#13;
 Do students get results?         Seldom                         Yes&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                               15&#13;
&amp;#12; Is additional information        Frequently, in student           Seldom&#13;
 collected from students?         questionnaires&#13;
 Scoring                          Usually involves statistically   Usually a simple process that&#13;
                                  sophisticated techniques         is based on a predetermined&#13;
                                                                   marking scheme&#13;
 Effect on level of student       Unlikely to have an effect       Poor results or the prospect&#13;
 attainment                                                        of failure, which can lead to&#13;
                                                                   early dropout&#13;
 Usefulness for monitoring        Appropriate if tests are         Not appropriate because&#13;
 trends in achievements levels    designed with monitoring in      examination questions and&#13;
 over time                        mind                             candidate populations change&#13;
                                                                   from year to year&#13;
Source: Greaney and Kellaghan (2008).&#13;
&#13;
The GOM needs to decide the institutional home for the national assessments of learning&#13;
outcomes, if the development of such institutional capacity is considered desirable. Some&#13;
countries use an external agency: for instance, Ireland has an Education Research Center in&#13;
Dublin; and Sri Lanka is building capacity for rigorous national assessments in the National&#13;
Education Research and Evaluation Center of the Faculty of Education in the University of&#13;
Colombo. Other countries use either their Department of Public Examinations, or staff in their&#13;
Ministries of Education. The various models have their advantages and disadvantages which are&#13;
summarized in Table 10.&#13;
&#13;
The Maldives in the past trained a small pool of officials in the MOE and conducted national&#13;
assessments from within the government. However, these officials were either promoted or&#13;
transferred elsewhere in a few years, and the capacity in the MOE weakened. A model that&#13;
policy makers could consider for the future is to develop the technical capacity for national&#13;
assessments in the Faculty of Education of the Maldives National University (MNU). This model&#13;
would have the advantage that the academic staff of the Faculty of Education will be available&#13;
over the long-term, as academics are not in a transferable service. The technical rigor of the&#13;
analysis is also likely to be strong when university researchers are involved. In addition, the&#13;
model would strengthen the capacity of the university for research. The role of the MOE in this&#13;
model would be to utilize the results of the national assessments for policy formulation and&#13;
program development.&#13;
&#13;
The Maldives could also consider participating in international assessments of learning outcomes&#13;
from time to time. The benefits would include assessing the performance of the education system&#13;
in relation to other middle-income and developing countries. This comparative assessment could&#13;
produce policy ideas for the further development of the system. The cost, of course, is that&#13;
participation in such studies can be very expensive. National policy makers would need to&#13;
measure the benefits and costs of such participation and choose.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                16&#13;
&amp;#12;Table 10. Options for Implementing a National Assessment&#13;
 Designated agency              Advantages                                 Disadvantages&#13;
Drawn from staff of - Likely to be trusted by ministry. -         Findings might be subject to&#13;
ministry of          - Enjoys ready access to key                 political manipulation including&#13;
education               personnel, materials, and data            suppression.&#13;
                        (for example, school population -         May be viewed sceptically by other&#13;
                        data).                                    stakeholders.&#13;
                     - Funds that may not have to be    -         Staff may be required to undertake&#13;
                        secured for staff time.                   many other tasks.&#13;
                                                        -         Technical capacity may be lacking.&#13;
&#13;
Drawn from staff of    -   Usually is credible.               -   Staff who may be required to&#13;
public examination     -   Has experience in running              undertake many other tasks.&#13;
unit                       secure assessments.                -   Technical capacity that may be&#13;
                       -   Funds that may not have to be          weak.&#13;
                           secured for staff time.            -   May lack ready access to data.&#13;
                       -   Some skills (for example, test     -   Public examination experience that&#13;
                           development) that can be               may result in test items that are too&#13;
                           transferred to enhance the             difficult.&#13;
                           examination unit.&#13;
                       -   More likely to be sustainable&#13;
                           than some other models.&#13;
Drawn from             -   Findings that may be more          -   Have to raise funds to cover staff&#13;
research/                  credible with stakeholders.            costs.&#13;
university sector      -   Greater likelihood of some         -   May be less sustainable than some&#13;
                           technical competence.                  other models.&#13;
                       -   May use data for further studies   -   May come into conflict with&#13;
                           of the education system.               education ministry.&#13;
Recruited as foreign   -   More likely to be technically      -   Likely to be expensive.&#13;
technical assistance       competent.                         -   May not be sensitive to educational&#13;
(TA)                   -   Nature of funding that can help        context.&#13;
                           ensure timely completion.          -   Difficult to ensure assessment&#13;
                                                                  sustainability.&#13;
                                                              -   Possibly little national capacity&#13;
                                                                  enhancement.&#13;
Made up of a           -   Can improve technical capacity     -   Possibly difficult to coordinate&#13;
national team              of nationals.                          work of national team members&#13;
supported with some    -   May ensure timely completion.          and TA.&#13;
international TA       -   May add credibility to the         -   Might be difficult to ensure skill&#13;
                           results.                               transfer to nationals.&#13;
Ministry team          -   Can ensure ministry support        -   National TA that may lack the&#13;
supported with             while obtaining national TA.           necessary technical capacity.&#13;
national TA            -   Less expensive than                -   Other potential disadvantages that&#13;
                           international TA.                      are listed under ministry of&#13;
                                                                  education and that may apply.&#13;
Source: Greaney and Kellaghan (2008).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 17&#13;
&amp;#12;                                       BIBLIOGRAPHY&#13;
Allemano, E., N. Baumgart, D. Chapman, H. Craig, R. Kraft, R. Rawlinson, and H. Thornton. (2011).&#13;
Teacher Development and Management. The World Bank, Washington D.C., U.S.A. Processed.&#13;
&#13;
Bruns, B., D. Filmer, and H. Patrinos. (2011). Making Schools Work: Mew Evidence on Accountability&#13;
Reforms. The World Bank, Washington D.C., U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
Greaney, V. and T. Kellaghan. (2008). Assessing National Achievement Levels in Education. Vol. 1. The&#13;
World Bank, Washington D.C., U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
Greaney, V., T. Kellaghan, and T. S. Murray. (2009). Using the Results of a National Assessment of&#13;
Educational Achievement. Vol. 5. The World Bank, Washington D.C., U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
Hanushek, E. (2011). â&#128;&#156;The Economic Value of Higher Teacher Quality.â&#128;? Economics of Education&#13;
Review, 30: 466-479.&#13;
&#13;
Hanushek, E., and F. Welch. (2006). Handbook of the Economics of Education. Vol. 1. Elsevier Science&#13;
and Technology Books.&#13;
&#13;
Hanushek, E., and L. Woessmann. (2008). â&#128;&#156;The Role of Cognitive Skills in Economic Development.â&#128;?&#13;
Journal of Economic Literature, 46 (3): 607-668.&#13;
&#13;
Harris, D., and T. Sass. (2011). â&#128;&#156;Teacher Training, Teacher Quality, and Student Achievement.â&#128;? Journal&#13;
of Public Economics. 95: 798-812.&#13;
&#13;
OECD (2005). Teachers Matter: Attracting, Developing and Retaining Effective Teachers, OECD, Paris.&#13;
&#13;
Martinet, M., A. Raymond, D. and C. Gauthier. (2001). La Formation Ã  lâ&#128;&#153;enseignement: Les&#13;
Orientations; Les CompÃ©tences Professionnelles. MinistÃ¨re de lâ&#128;&#159;Ã©ducation, QuÃ©bec.&#13;
&#13;
Materu, P. (2007). â&#128;&#156;Higher Education Quality Assurance in Sub-Saharan Africa: Status, Challenges,&#13;
Opportunities, and Promising Practicesâ&#128;?. World Bank Working Paper, 124.&#13;
&#13;
Ministry of Education, Maldives (MOE). School Statistics, various years. Maleâ&#128;&#159;, Maldives.&#13;
&#13;
Ministry of Education, Maldives (MOE). (2010). Introduction: Quality Indicators Child Friendly&#13;
Baraabaru Schools. Maleâ&#128;&#159;, Maldives.&#13;
&#13;
Ministry of Education, Sri Lanka (MOE). (2010). Guidelines on National Educational Standards and ISA&#13;
Competencies, Colombo, Sri Lanka.&#13;
&#13;
Tan, E. T. J., and P. T. Ng. (eds.) (2005). Shaping Singaporeâ&#128;&#153;s Future: Thinking Schools and Learning&#13;
Nation. Prentice Hall, Singapore.&#13;
&#13;
Vegas, E. (ed.) (2005). Incentives to Improve Teaching: Lessons from Latin America, The World Bank,&#13;
Washington D.C., U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
World Bank (2005). Expanding Opportunities and Building Competencies for Young People: A New&#13;
Agenda for Secondary Education, The World Bank, Washington D.C., U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  18&#13;
&amp;#12;&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="16209857">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2012/02/16209857/enhancing-quality-education-maldives-challenges-prospects
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2012/02/16209857/enhancing-quality-education-maldives-challenges-prospects</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2012/02/16209857/enhancing-quality-education-maldives-challenges-prospects</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2012-04-05T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2012-04-05T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2012/04/05/000406484_20120405155733/Rendered/INDEX/679180NWP00PUB07903B0Report00No.510.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2012/04/05/000406484_20120405155733/Rendered/PDF/679180NWP00PUB07903B0Report00No.510.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2012-04-05T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2012-02-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Enhancing the Quality of Education in the
            Maldives : Challenges and prospects
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The quality of education is a major
            policy challenge facing the Maldives. The country achieved
            the first generation objective of providing universal access
            to basic education through rapid expansion of enrollment. As
            is frequently the case with such countries, the second
            generation challenge is to provide education of adequate
            quality. Evidence from a variety of sources shows that
            education quality in the Maldives is weak, and needs urgent
            improvement. Learning outcomes in both primary and secondary
            education are modest. National assessments of learning
            outcomes at Grade 4 and Grade 7 show that learning levels
            are unsatisfactory. The low average scores suggest that
            learning levels in both primary education and lower
            secondary education are weak. There are several dimensions
            of education quality which Maldivian policy makers consider
            to be of vital importance. Among these, the quality of
            school teachers is central to the improvement of education
            quality. Hence, the Ministry of Education (MOE) is concerned
            to develop the skills, motivation and performance of
            teachers. A second key policy initiative is the
            establishment of a sound quality assurance framework for the
            school system. The MOE has developed a quality assurance
            mechanism, which now needs to be pilot tested, refined and
            scaled up throughout the country. A third strategic policy
            initiative is the development of a system of regular
            national assessments of learning outcomes, which can then
            feed into policy formulation and program development. These
            three strategic policy initiatives are discussed in the
            subsequent sections of this report.&lt;BR&gt;
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Enhancing the Quality of Education in the
            Maldives : Challenges and prospects
        </docna>
        <display_title>Enhancing the Quality of
            Education in the Maldives : Challenges and prospects</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2012/02/16209857/enhancing-quality-education-maldives-challenges-prospects</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Working Paper (Numbered Series)</docty>
        <subtopic>Teaching and Learning,Access &amp; Equity in Basic Education,Primary Education,Education For All,Tertiary Education</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Education</teratopic>
        <count>Maldives</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Aturupane, Harsha; Shojo, Mari</author>
        </authors>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Asia!$!80451</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>South Asia!$!80470</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000406484_20120405155733</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>South Asia,South Asia</admreg>
        <colti>South Asia Human Development Sector report
            no. 51</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Education</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            academic performance, academic programs,
            academic staff, acceptable standard, access to data,
            achievements, Adequate Infrastructure, assessment of
            education, assessment process, basic education, career,
            career choice, career guidance, civil service, classroom,
            classroom libraries, Cognitive achievement, cognitive
            performance, cognitive skills, Community involvement,
            comparative assessment, Continuing Education, curricular
            activities, curriculum, curriculum changes, early childhood,
            early childhood care, early dropout, Economics of Education,
            education courses, education Leadership, education
            officials, education personnel, education policy, Education
            Sector, Education Sector Development, Education Statistics,
            Education System, education systems, Educational
            Achievement, educational policies, educational reform,
            Effective Teachers, effective teaching, employment,
            Examination pass rates, expatriate teachers, Faculty of
            Education, female students, foreign technical assistance,
            gender disparities, general education, girls, Health
            education, Higher Education, Higher Education Quality, home
            learning, Human Development, Human resources, improvement of
            education, improvement of education quality, incentives for
            teachers, labor force, Learning, learning environments,
            learning levels, Learning Outcomes, learning strategies,
            Literature, local teachers, lower secondary education,
            Ministers of Education, Ministries of Education, Ministry of
            Education, National Assessment, National Assessments,
            National Education, National Educational Standards, National
            University, nutrition, Open Learning, pass rate, performance
            in mathematics, performance of students, primary education,
            Primary Education Education, primary school, primary school
            teachers, primary schools, primary teachers, private higher
            education, private higher education institutions,
            professional development, professional growth, Professional
            qualifications, professional standards, qualified teachers,
            quality assessment, Quality Assurance, quality assurance
            systems, Quality of Education, quality of teachers, quality
            teachers, rapid expansion of enrollment, refresher courses,
            researchers, Resource Center, Resource Centers, school
            improvement, school infrastructure, school inspections,
            school leaders, school level, school performance, school
            population, school principals, school site, School
            Statistics, school system, school teacher, school teachers,
            school visits, Schools, Secondary Education, Secondary
            schools, senior teachers, service training, sports, standard
            of education, student achievement, student attainment,
            student learning, student welfare, subject areas, syllabi,
            Teacher, teacher competence, Teacher Competencies, teacher
            development, teacher education, teacher education
            opportunities, teacher educators, Teacher Incentives,
            Teacher Motivation, teacher quality, teacher training,
            teacher training programs, Teachers, teaching, teaching
            materials, teaching methods, teaching techniques, Technical
            Assistance, test development, test scores, training needs,
            training opportunities, training programs, tuition,
            universal access, Untrained Teachers, visits to classrooms,
            young people
        </keywd>
        <owner>Education (SASED)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>South Asia</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>67918</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teacher Professional Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education for All Fast Track Initiative, MDG</ml:concept><ml:concept>Strategic Planning</ml:concept><ml:concept>School Based Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Basic Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Higher Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Tertiary Education – Enhancing Access, Equity and Quality</ml:concept><ml:concept>Adult Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Adult Education, Literacy, and Lifelong Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Continuing Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education Quality</ml:concept><ml:concept>Quality and Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pensions &amp; Retirement Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition – Community Based Interventions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition – Raising Awareness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition – Training</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civil Service Employment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civil Service Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Capital</ml:concept><ml:concept>Managing People</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Employment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Treasury</ml:concept><ml:concept>Examinations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teacher Training</ml:concept><ml:concept>Global Partnership for Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Policy Framework</ml:concept><ml:concept>Strategic Policy Planning</ml:concept><ml:concept>School-Based Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>School Inspection</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Primary Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Secondary Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Tertiary Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Lifelong Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Quality of Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pensions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resources Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Maldives</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Southern Asia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>