<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>ï»¿72204&#13;
&amp;#12;Horizontal Learning for Strengthening Capacities of&#13;
   Local Government Institutions in Bangladesh&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                          REPORT ON&#13;
   THE NATIONAL DISSEMINATION WORKSHOP&#13;
&#13;
                      Dhaka, October 30, 2008&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                      Local Government Division&#13;
     Ministry of LGRD &amp; Cooperatives, Government of Bangladesh&#13;
                                   and&#13;
            Water and Sanitation Program, World Bank, Dhaka&#13;
&amp;#12;&amp;#12;Table of Content&#13;
&#13;
                                                                            Page&#13;
      Glossary of abbreviations and terms                                   iv&#13;
      Preface                                                               v&#13;
 1.   Introduction                                                          7&#13;
 2.   Inaugural session                                                     9&#13;
 3.   Display on top eight good practices                                   13&#13;
 4.   Thematic Session-I: Flashback on experiences of horizontal learning   18&#13;
      Background of preparing the pata song                                 22&#13;
 5.   Thematic Session-II: Talk show                                        22&#13;
      Summary of the talk show                                              23&#13;
 6.   Summing up and closing - Recommendations for the future               25&#13;
      Annexures&#13;
      Annexure A: Background                                                27&#13;
      Annexure B: Workshop program                                          31&#13;
      Annexure C: Participants and resource persons                         32&#13;
      Annexure D: Presentation on thematic session-I                        33&#13;
&amp;#12;GLOSSARY OF ABBREVIATIONS AND TERMS&#13;
AI             Appreciative Inquiry&#13;
ASEH           Advancing Sustainable Environmental Health&#13;
BDT            Bangladesh Taka&#13;
BUET           Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology&#13;
CBO            Community-based organization&#13;
DASCOH         Development Association for Self-Reliance, Communication and Health&#13;
Danida         Danish International Development Agency&#13;
Dishari        Decentralized Total Sanitation Project&#13;
DPHE           Department of Public Health Engineering&#13;
Eco-friendly   Environment-friendly&#13;
Gambhira       Style of traditional folk song and traditional communication technique&#13;
               ('Alkap',' jari', 'shari', and 'bhatiali' are also some examples of the same thing)&#13;
Gan            Translates as 'song'&#13;
GoB            Government of Bangladesh&#13;
HL             Horizontal Learning&#13;
JICA           Japan International Cooperation Agency&#13;
LG             Commission Local Government Commission&#13;
LGD             Local Government Division&#13;
LGI            Local Government Institution&#13;
LGRD&amp;C         Local Government, Rural Development and Cooperatives&#13;
MDG            Millennium Development Goal&#13;
MJSKS          Mohideb Jubo Samaj Kallyan Somity&#13;
NGO            Non-governmental organization&#13;
NILG           National Institute of Local Government&#13;
Nirbahi        Translates as 'executive'&#13;
Para           Translates as 'a section of the village'&#13;
Pata song      Local genre of folk songs&#13;
Patuas         Rural canvas painters (also known as 'gains' in Jessore and Khulna regions)&#13;
Pir, fakir     A saintly man&#13;
PRDP-2         Participatory Rural Development Project-2&#13;
Pucca          Translates as 'permanent'&#13;
Q/A            Question/Answer&#13;
Sangit         Translates as 'music'&#13;
SDC            Swiss Agency for Development and Cooperation&#13;
SDSD           Sustainable Solutions for the Delivery of Safe Drinking Water&#13;
SLGDFP         Sirajganj Local Governance Development Fund Project&#13;
UNO            Upazila Nirbahi Officer&#13;
UP             Union parishad&#13;
Upazila        Subdistrict&#13;
WSP-SA         Water and Sanitation Program - South Asia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
iv&#13;
&amp;#12;PREFACE&#13;
          T  he report of the 'National Dissemination Workshop on&#13;
             Horizontal Learning for Strengthening Capacities of&#13;
          Local Government Institutions' summarizes the workshop&#13;
          proceedings and final recommendations for the horizontal&#13;
          learning program. This report is prepared in consultation&#13;
          with all the participating agencies including LGIs (Unions),&#13;
          which will be eventually prepared in both Bangla and&#13;
          English languages.&#13;
&#13;
          The final recommendations were shared with the Ministry of&#13;
          Local Government, Rural Development and Cooperatives&#13;
          (LGRD&amp;C) and necessary steps have already planned to&#13;
          turn the recommendations into action.&#13;
&#13;
          On behalf of the Local Government Division, Ministry of&#13;
          LGRD&amp;C, we would like to convey our sincere thanks to&#13;
          the Water and Sanitation Program (WSP) of the World Bank&#13;
          and other partners for helping us prepare this report, and&#13;
          appreciate their support for our horizontal learning program&#13;
          for enhancing capacities of local government institutions.&#13;
&#13;
          The horizontal learning program is an evolving process;&#13;
          therefore, any comments or suggestions related to horizontal&#13;
          learning will be welcomed. All comments or feedback on&#13;
          this report, and on the horizontal learning program, should&#13;
          be addressed to any of the resource persons mentioned on&#13;
          the back cover of this report.&#13;
&#13;
          We hope readers will find this report useful towards further&#13;
          enhancing the capacities of local government institutions in&#13;
          Bangladesh.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                             Shams Uddin Ahmed&#13;
                                           Deputy Secretary (WS),&#13;
                          Local Government Division and Focal Point&#13;
                                              -Horizontal Learning&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                  v&#13;
&amp;#12;vi&#13;
&amp;#12;1. INTRODUCTION&#13;
The horizontal learning program is a peer-to-peer learning process that was initiated in&#13;
Bangladesh by local government institutions (LGIs) in November 2007, aiming to strengthen&#13;
the capacity of union parishads. The initiative is being facilitated by the Local Government&#13;
Division, Ministry of Local Government, Rural Development and Cooperatives (LGRD&amp;C),&#13;
Government of Bangladesh, and supported by the Water and Sanitation Program (WSP) of&#13;
the World Bank. Other partners are:&#13;
      Development Association for Self-Reliance, Communication and Health (DASCOH);&#13;
      Japan International Cooperation Agency (JICA);&#13;
      Plan Bangladesh;&#13;
      WaterAid Bangladesh through its local NGOs- Shushilon, Green Hill and Mohideb&#13;
      Jubo Samaj Kallyan Somiti (MJSKS);&#13;
      Dhaka Ahsania Mission,&#13;
      NGO Forum&#13;
Different programs and projects in 10 upazilas under the horizontal leraning program are&#13;
being supported through various funding agencies, such as, Government of Bangladesh&#13;
(GoB), Swiss Agency for Development and Cooperation (SDC), Department for International&#13;
Development (DfID), World Bank, and Danish International Development Agency (Danida).&#13;
The program commenced with the selection of the best performing upazilas (subdistricts) by&#13;
each partner agency within the horizontal learning program, followed by the identification of&#13;
best practices in water supply and sanitation activities and gradually expanded for inclusion&#13;
of a broader range of good governance initiatives in each participating upazila. This approach&#13;
offers union parishads the opportunity to learn about, and replicate, good practices. The&#13;
program was initially started in 66 unions of six upazilas and gradually expanded to 93&#13;
unions under 10 upazilas covering about 2.2 million people.&#13;
Through the process of horizontal learning, 21 good practices and relevant indicators were&#13;
identified for verification. Sixty-two out of 93 participating union parishads allocated BDT&#13;
24,198,732 (approx. US$355,865) during the financial year FY 09 (July 2008 - June 2009)&#13;
for replicating 17 good practices.&#13;
As part of dissemination of learning, the Local Government Division, Ministry of LGRD&amp;C&#13;
with support from partners under the horizontal learning program, organized a national&#13;
dissemination workshop on October 30, 2008, at the Winter Garden of the Sheraton Hotel,&#13;
Dhaka. The purpose of the workshop was to: (a) share the lessons learned from the first year&#13;
of the horizontal learning program among a larger audience; and (b) formulate a roadmap for&#13;
the future, with the consensus of potential players in the sector, to strengthen capacities of&#13;
local government institutions through the horizontal learning program. More than 300&#13;
participants representing government, local government institutions, non-governmental&#13;
organizations, and development partners participated in the workshop.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                          7&#13;
&amp;#12;Overall objective&#13;
The overall objective of the workshop was to disseminate the lessons learned on best&#13;
practices under the horizontal learning program, which would facilitate its replication on a&#13;
larger scale.&#13;
&#13;
Specific objectives&#13;
   To share the experiences and lessons learned under the horizontal learning program by&#13;
   LGIs (union parishads) and other stakeholders.&#13;
   To formulate a roadmap for horizontal learning program to strengthen the capacities of&#13;
   LGIs.&#13;
   To design an effective communication strategy for dissemination of lessons learned.&#13;
   To reach consensus for further aid-harmonization for strengthening capacities for local&#13;
government institutions.&#13;
&#13;
Workshop design&#13;
The workshop was designed in three sessions:&#13;
Part I : Inaugural session.&#13;
Part II : Thematic Session I, covering presentations and discussions on experiences of the&#13;
horizontal learning program, followed by questions and answers from the floor. Session I&#13;
included a pata song, based on the top eight good practices, with a brief introduction on the&#13;
background of the pata song preparation.&#13;
Part III : Thematic Session II was on 'Talk Show' to share experiences of the replication of&#13;
good practices and highlight the way forward for the horizontal learning program in&#13;
Bangladesh.&#13;
&#13;
Workshop methodologies&#13;
The workshop methodologies included a combination of video screenings, power point&#13;
presentations, performance of pata song, holding of talk show and plenary session, followed&#13;
by question-answer sessions.&#13;
The national dissemination workshop resulted in a series of recommendations, which will be&#13;
discussed at the informal core team meeting, followed by their submission to the government&#13;
for onward action.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
1&#13;
  BDT is Bangladeshi Taka. US$1 = BDT 68 (as of April 7, 2009). Conversions rates are&#13;
from http://coinmill.com; all conversions in the text are approximations&#13;
&#13;
    8&#13;
&amp;#12;2. INAUGURAL SESSION&#13;
The workshop was inaugurated by the Chief Guest,&#13;
Shaikh Khurshid Alam, Secretary, Ministry of Local&#13;
Government, Rural Development and Cooperation;&#13;
Mr. Vinaya Swaroop, Acting Country Director,&#13;
World Bank, Dhaka Office, addressed the function as&#13;
Special Guest. The opening session was chaired by&#13;
Md. Lukman Hakim Talukder, Joint Secretary (WS),&#13;
LGD; and the welcome speech was made by Mr.&#13;
Shams Uddin Ahmed, Deputy Secretary (WS-1),&#13;
LGD and Focal Point Horizontal Learning. Mr.&#13;
Glenn Pearce-Oroz, Country Team Leader, Water&#13;
and Sanitation Program, Bangladesh (WSP) of&#13;
World Bank, made the opening remarks on behalf of&#13;
participating and developing partners of the&#13;
horizontal learning program. A colorful video&#13;
presentation was screened on overall activities of the&#13;
horizontal learning program at the beginning of the&#13;
inaugural session to appraise the audience. Mr.&#13;
Oaliar Rahman, Chairman, Jagdal Union Parishad&#13;
(Magura Sadar, Magura) presented the vote of thanks&#13;
on behalf of LGIs under the horizontal learning&#13;
program.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  9&#13;
&amp;#12;Chief Guest Shaikh Khurshid Alam appreciated the&#13;
initiation of horizontal learning for building capacity of&#13;
LGIs, for improving water supply and sanitation services&#13;
in Bangladesh. Union parishads in Bangladesh have&#13;
always had the potential for implementing good works.&#13;
What this horizontal learning program has shown us is&#13;
that with a little more organization and coordination,&#13;
union parishads in Bangladesh can make an even bigger&#13;
impact with the successful home-grown practices that&#13;
                                                             Shaikh Khurshid Alam&#13;
otherwise might have been limited to only one or a           Secretary, LGD, Ministry of LGRD&amp;C&#13;
handful of union parishads. For instance, the good&#13;
practices in water quality testing in Chowgacha, or the&#13;
Chapai Nawabganj Sadar approach of receiving funding&#13;
directly from NGOs, should not remain limited to just&#13;
their respective areas. Even if only half of all union&#13;
parishads could contribute with good practices, that&#13;
would be over 2,000 proven ideas that could be made&#13;
available to all. The potential of having in place a&#13;
horizontal learning network among union parishads, felt&#13;
Mr. Alam, is extremely important for other reasons as&#13;
well. The Local Government Division currently has the&#13;
Local Governance Support Program (LGSP) that&#13;
provides funds directly to union parishads. Good&#13;
practices and good uses of these funds by one union&#13;
parishad could now be effectively and efficiently&#13;
communicated to other parishads as well, thereby&#13;
increasing the effectiveness of the entire program. He&#13;
stressed the need for replication of identified good&#13;
practices; they should be streamlined in different&#13;
projects/programs, incorporated at the policy level, and&#13;
translated into practice. Local level communication is&#13;
important to share information about good practices.&#13;
More existing good practices should be identified and&#13;
disseminated through horizontal learning to speed up&#13;
development activities in rural areas. Supply of safe&#13;
water and sanitation is one of the big challenges in&#13;
Bangladesh-there is no other alternative to face this&#13;
challenge then capacity building of local government&#13;
institutions. A pragmatic plan for scaling up the&#13;
horizontal learning program should be prepared for a&#13;
longer period. He thanked all the LGI representatives,&#13;
government officials, supporting partners, and NGOs for&#13;
initiating and carrying forward the horizontal learning&#13;
program in Bangladesh.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 10&#13;
&amp;#12;                                          Lukman Hakim Talukder mentioned that horizontal&#13;
                                          learning is a peer-to-peer learning process initiated by the&#13;
                                          LGIs in Bangladesh in November 2007. The initiative is&#13;
                                          being facilitated by the Local Government Division of the&#13;
                                          Ministry of Local Government, Rural Development and&#13;
                                          Cooperatives, and supported by the Water and Sanitation&#13;
                                          Program - South Asia of the World Bank. Other partners&#13;
                                          are DASCOH, JICA, WaterAid, Plan Bangladesh, Dhaka&#13;
                                          Ahsania Mission and supporting local NGOs such as&#13;
Lukman Hakim Talukder                     Shushilon, MJSKS and Green Hills. The main objective of&#13;
Joint Secretary (Water Supply),- LGD      the program is building capacity of the LGIs for&#13;
Ministry of LGR&amp;D                         improving water supply and sanitation services in&#13;
                                          Bangladesh. The program has now expanded to 93 union&#13;
                                          parishads of 10 upazilas covering 2.2 million people. Two&#13;
                                          more upazilas will join soon under this learning process.&#13;
                                          The achievements of the horizontal learning program&#13;
                                          would also help in achieving Millennium Development&#13;
                                          Goals (MDGs). He appreciated the achievements made&#13;
                                          due to horizontal learning in the short span of one year. He&#13;
                                          also emphasized the need for scaling up and sustainability&#13;
                                          of horizontal learning. He expressed his gratitude to the&#13;
                                          representatives of LGIs and supporting partners for their&#13;
                                          contribution to the horizontal learning program.&#13;
                                          Mr. Vinaya Swaroop highlighted the fact that the&#13;
                                          horizontal learning program is an innovative initiative for&#13;
                                          building the base of development at the grassroots level.&#13;
                                          He congratulated the Local Government Division for&#13;
                                          taking the lead in opening a space for local governments&#13;
                                          in union parishads where they could acknowledge the&#13;
                                          good practices that are taking place among them. The&#13;
                                          encouragement and support provided by the Local&#13;
                                          Government Division, and the important constructive&#13;
                                          relationship facilitated between UNOs and union&#13;
Vinaya Swaroop                            parishads, Mr. Swaroop felt, was a very important step for&#13;
Acting Country Director, the World Bank   acknowledging that local governments possess the&#13;
                                          capacity to implement activities that are requested by their&#13;
                                          communities, and that union parishads can become trusted&#13;
                                          leaders in the development of the country. He mentioned&#13;
                                          that this process was initiated by the LGIs to fulfill their&#13;
                                          needs depending on their own resources-they are trying to&#13;
                                          expand their resource base through collecting taxes and&#13;
                                          unveiling untapped resources along with capacity building&#13;
                                          for improving water and sanitation services in&#13;
                                          Bangladesh. He expressed his hope that horizontal&#13;
                                          learning practices that have been so successful during this&#13;
                                          initial year would continue to provide helpful support for&#13;
                                          sharing improved decision-making practices and sharing&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                 11&#13;
&amp;#12;mechanisms for promoting increased responsiveness and&#13;
accountability of local governments. Programs such as&#13;
LGSP would benefit clearly from these types of effective&#13;
practices. He mentioned that, as development partners, we&#13;
will continue to stand ready to support improved and&#13;
innovative practices for strengthening decentralized&#13;
systems of government. More collective efforts are needed&#13;
on our part, to coordinate our own efforts to better support&#13;
the local government institutions as they face ongoing&#13;
challenges, and to support the central government as it&#13;
stays on course for continuing to advance policies and&#13;
programs that make decentralized systems more effective.&#13;
&#13;
Mr. Shams Uddin Ahmed, on behalf of the government,&#13;
welcomed the distinguished participants from different&#13;
spheres, from the government, development partners,&#13;
representatives from LGIs, NGOs, media and other&#13;
organizations and commended them for their participation&#13;
in the 'National Dissemination Workshop on Horizontal&#13;
Learning for Strengthening Capacities of the Local&#13;
Government Institutions on Improving Water Supply and&#13;
Sanitation Services in Bangladesh'. He said the positive&#13;
impact of the horizontal learning program had contributed      Mr. Shams Uddin Ahmed&#13;
towards achieving Sanitation for All by 2010. He made          Deputy Secretary (WS-1), LGD and&#13;
                                                               Focal Point Horizontal Learning&#13;
especial mention of the bottom-up approach of the&#13;
horizontal learning program and said that it has created an&#13;
enabling environment of cooperation, sharing, and&#13;
confidence-building among the LGIs, development&#13;
partners, NGOs and different projects. Mr. Ahmed also&#13;
expressed his satisfaction over tremendous outcome of&#13;
this learning process-within one year of its inception-&#13;
which complements other existing capacity-building&#13;
projects. The Government, development partners, and&#13;
NGOs render invaluable support, also for the LGIs, he&#13;
said.&#13;
Mr. Glenn Pearce-Oroz mentioned that the horizontal&#13;
learning process had been initiated by LGI representatives&#13;
about one year ago and is being facilitated by the Local&#13;
Government Division of the Ministry of Local&#13;
Government, Rural Development and Cooperatives and&#13;
supported by the Water and Sanitation Program of the&#13;
World Bank and other partner organizations. He hoped&#13;
that the workshop would enrich future planning by&#13;
gathering multi-sectoral and institutional experiences&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 12&#13;
&amp;#12;                                          through the active participation of relevant stakeholders.&#13;
                                          Mr. Pearce-Oroz also expected that the findings of the&#13;
                                          workshop would help disseminate that learning across the&#13;
                                          sector, horizontally, and also contribute to the further&#13;
                                          development of the sector. Local government institutions&#13;
                                          have already shown their innovative ideas and confidence&#13;
                                          regarding implementation of development activities&#13;
                                          within this short period. This initiative has opened new&#13;
                                          opportunities for harmonizing development partners,&#13;
Glenn Pearce-Oroz&#13;
Country Team Leader, Bangladesh           enabling bottom-up planning, as well as ensuring people's&#13;
Water and Sanitation Program South Asia   participation, transparency, and accountability at the&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
                                          grassroots level. This process might be useful in other&#13;
                                          sectors also. Mr. Pearce-Oroz also hoped that all the&#13;
                                          remaining unions of the country would gradually be&#13;
                                          covered by this initiative.&#13;
                                          On behalf of the union parishads of the horizontal&#13;
                                          learning program, Mr. Oaliar Rahman, Chairman,&#13;
                                          Jagdal union parishad, Magura Sadar Upazila, gave the&#13;
                                          vote of thanks to the guests, resource persons and&#13;
                                          participants for their inputs for the workshop. He said the&#13;
                                          set of recommendations made in the workshop would&#13;
                                          help scaling up the horizontal learning program&#13;
                                          throughout the country.&#13;
                                          3. DISPLAY ON TOP EIGHT GOOD PRACTICES&#13;
Oaliar Rahman&#13;
Chairman, Jagdal Union                    Display tables were arranged to share the best eight good&#13;
Magura Sadar Upazila                      practices, selected by 93 union parishads. The display was&#13;
                                          inaugurated by Shaikh Khurshid Alam, Secretary, Local&#13;
                                          Government Division, Ministry of LGRD&amp;C. The salient&#13;
                                          features of each are highlighted here.&#13;
                                          3.1 Water quality surveillance: Arsenic testing,&#13;
                                          bacteriological testing and sanitary survey:&#13;
                                          Water quality testing is imperative for more than 9.75&#13;
                                          million household tubewells and 93,000 community-&#13;
                                          based water sources in Bangladesh. It is a matter of&#13;
                                          concern that water quality monitoring of a huge number&#13;
                                          of tubewells in the rural areas of Bangladesh is&#13;
                                          inadequate.&#13;
                                          To address the inadequacy in water testing, all union&#13;
                                          parishads under Chowgacha upazila have started arsenic&#13;
                                          test with field kits (under the leadership of union&#13;
                                          parishads). The approach is self-sustaining; the villagers&#13;
                                          pay BDT 50 for each test and the union parishads are able&#13;
                                          to purchase reagents for field kits. Union parishads keep&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                13&#13;
&amp;#12;records of test results and review them in their monthly meetings. They paint the outer surface of each&#13;
tubewell spout either green (for safe water) or red (for unsafe water), which creates further awareness&#13;
in the community about the current situation regarding arsenic contamination. Nearly 2,762 tubewells&#13;
have been tested so far by the union parishads under Chowgacha upazila in the last two years. The&#13;
Arsenic Mitigation Project provided training for carrying out water testing to volunteers and village&#13;
police (also the chowkidar, who conducts arsenic test).&#13;
The union parishads involved within the horizontal learning program identified this initiative as one&#13;
of the good practices. They therefore visited this upazila to learn more from their peers and then&#13;
replicate this good practice in their own areas. Twenty-two unions in five upazilas from five districts&#13;
have already introduced arsenic testing of tubewell water in their own areas. Within six months (May&#13;
to October 2008) an incredible 3,322 arsenic tests were conducted by these unions.&#13;
There are nearly 38,000 arsenicosis patients in Bangladesh, but they were without any means of&#13;
support till the Arsenic Mitigation Project piloted the purchase and provision of medicines to patients&#13;
by utilizing the Annual Development Budget Grants. This learning was discussed with government&#13;
and a gazette was issued by the government on January 14, 2008, which then permitted all union&#13;
parishads to utilize their Annual Budget for buying medicines for arsenicosis patients. Union&#13;
parishads outside Chowgacha and Sharsha upazilas (outside the Arsenic Mitigation Project), first&#13;
came to know about this from horizontal learning and have applied the learning in their own areas. As&#13;
a result, eight unions of Chapai Nawabganj Sadar and Shyamnagar have allocated BDT 4,72,180 for&#13;
arsenicosis patients.&#13;
&#13;
3.2 Community ignition to achieve 100% sanitary latrine coverage:&#13;
Union parishads under Shreepur upazila in Gazipur district achieved 100 percent sanitary latrines&#13;
without subsidy or providing any support towards&#13;
materials' costs. This was possible through community&#13;
ignition. This unique initiative has been identified as one&#13;
of the good practices under the horizontal learning&#13;
program. Union parishads implemented this good practice&#13;
with support from the Dishari project. The achievement&#13;
was possible through activating different taskforces at&#13;
upazila, union, village, and para levels. Educational&#13;
institutions, teachers, students, religious leaders, and&#13;
members of the local elite and civil society were mobilized&#13;
to achieve the target. Different types of promotional&#13;
activities and cultural events using local folk media motivated people to want their own latrine and&#13;
towards positive behavioral changes relating to sanitation.&#13;
Participatory monitoring, documentation, and record keeping system at para and union levels were&#13;
introduced to help the community participate effectively in the entire process. A child-to-child&#13;
approach for community ignition to achieve 100 percent sanitation coverage was found to be very&#13;
effective for community mobilization.&#13;
This learning has been identified as one of the good practices, which is being led by union parishads&#13;
of Shreepur upazila, with support from Dhaka Ahsania Mission in collaboration with Plan&#13;
Bangladesh.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 14&#13;
&amp;#12;This learning is now being implemented in 13 unions of three upazilas under the horizontal learning&#13;
program. Besides unions within the horizontal learning program, another 30 unions in Jamalpur&#13;
Sadar, Malandaha and Bakshiganj upazila are also replicating this initiative.&#13;
3.3 Environment-friendly village:&#13;
Implementing the activities meant for achieving 100 percent sanitation in their village brought the&#13;
                                                          people of Baladangi village (of Bharbhary&#13;
                                                          union parishad under Khansama upazila in&#13;
                                                          Dinajpur district) closer as a community.&#13;
                                                          The common understanding among villagers&#13;
                                                          ignited them taking more development&#13;
                                                          initiatives. Their success in achieving 100&#13;
                                                          percent sanitation inspired them to also&#13;
                                                          make their village environment-friendly. To&#13;
                                                          achieve their target, they organized&#13;
                                                          discussions, courtyard meetings, rallies, etc.&#13;
                                                          The major achievements illustrating the&#13;
                                                          environment-friendly village are:&#13;
                                                          Drainage management: The people built a&#13;
                                     Eco-friendly Village 380-foot drain for the disposal of waste.&#13;
Everybody participated in the implementation process; some also contributed bamboo, polythene, etc.&#13;
The union parishad welcomed the initiative. It allocated BDT 30,000 for constructing a 60-foot pucca&#13;
drain and also earmarked allocations for other development activities during the financial year 2008-&#13;
09.&#13;
&#13;
Waste management and organic fertilizer: The people disposed their waste in a specific pit to make&#13;
their environment cleaner. They are also producing organic fertilizer, by composting organic waste&#13;
accumulated in a specific pit, using scientific methods. This fertilizer is then used for increased&#13;
agricultural production.&#13;
&#13;
Hygiene and behavioral change: All households in this village have their sanitary latrines. The&#13;
people-very much aware about personal hygiene-use and maintenance them properly. For instance,&#13;
they wash their hands after using the latrines. The use and maintenance of latrines are demonstrated to&#13;
school students. The village was declared 100 percent sanitized in 2006. Incidents of diarrheal&#13;
diseases have not been found since 2006 in the village, according to the local Upazila Health&#13;
Complex report.&#13;
&#13;
Recent Initiatives: Villagers are planting plants along a 2.5-kilometer road. In addition, they are&#13;
repairing roads and abandoned ponds in the village. All villagers have their birth registration&#13;
certificates. They have declared their village free of child labor, dowry, child marriage, multiple&#13;
marriage, and separation in conjugal life. Slogans on rights, environment protection, and so on, are&#13;
displayed at public places to generate awareness among the people.&#13;
The good practices of Baladangi village are being replicated in five villages, of five unions in&#13;
Khansama upazila, with support from Plan Bangladesh. They are now implementing a series of&#13;
activities to make their village environment friendly. Partners under horizontal learning have also&#13;
visited the village. This initiative is now replicated in many upazilas including Chapai Nawabganj&#13;
Sadar upazila, Tarash in Sirajganj, Rajarhat in Kurigram, Shreepur in Gazipur and Magura Sadar in&#13;
Magura districts.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                   15&#13;
&amp;#12;3.4 Implementation of development activities through private entrepreneurs:&#13;
Representatives of LGIs, under horizontal learning, visited the development activities implemented&#13;
by different union parishads under Chapai Nawabganj Sadar upazila. The visiting team identified the&#13;
implementation of development activities through private entrepreneurs as a good practice. Union&#13;
parishads under Chapai Nawabganj Sadar upazila practice community-based planning through CBOs&#13;
and implement water supply facilities through private entrepreneurs following all government&#13;
procedures. DASCOH disburses development funds directly to the union parishads' accounts; the&#13;
CBO collects and deposits users' contributions into the same accounts. Users and CBOs are also&#13;
taking part for monitoring the quality of the facilities being implemented by the private entrepreneurs.&#13;
As a result, many private entrepreneurs have evolved-from nil in 2003 to more than 150 in 2008. This&#13;
has further helped union parishads to delineate their roles and step back from being involved in actual&#13;
implementation, which has strengthened transparencies, accountability, and good governance in the&#13;
respective unions.&#13;
When the LGI representatives of nine upazilas (Shreepur, Khansama, Rajarhat, Tarash, Shyamnagar,&#13;
Chowgacha, Karimganj, Magura, and Rangamati) under the horizontal learning program visited the&#13;
area, they were motivated to replicate this initiative in their areas. Chowgacha (in Jessore) and&#13;
Khansama (in Dinajpur) district already started replicating this initiative; the latter, in fact, has&#13;
replicated this good practice in six union parishads.&#13;
3.5 Open budget meeting:&#13;
Open budget meetings in union parishads under Tarash&#13;
upazila in Sirajganj district, involving people from all&#13;
walks of life, has been identified as another good&#13;
practice under the horizontal learning program. Open&#13;
budget meetings-which Tarash union parishads have&#13;
been practicing for the last five years-were initiated&#13;
under the Sirajganj Local Governance Development&#13;
Fund Project (SLGDFP). The union parishads prepare a&#13;
draft plan and budget for the financial year, along&#13;
consultations with the community at ward level&#13;
meetings. This plan is shared with the people in an open&#13;
budget meeting, organized in the presence of upazila level officials, and NGO and CBO&#13;
representatives. People can raise questions, get explanations, and give suggestions on the draft budget&#13;
and plan. After considering all the comments and suggestions, union parishads then prepare the final&#13;
plan and budget. During budget meetings, budget books are distributed to the people at the meet.&#13;
The outcome has been an improvement in the governance situation, and in the relationships between&#13;
the people and the union parishad.&#13;
Union parishads under eight upazilas (Chapai Nawabganj Sadar, Shreepur, Rajarhat, Shyamnagar,&#13;
Chowgacha, Karimganj, Magura, and Rangamati Sadar) are now replicating open budget meetings.&#13;
Despite no involvement in the horizontal learning program, the Auch para union parishad (in&#13;
Bagmara upazila in Rajshahi district) has also visited Tarash upazila and is now replicating open&#13;
budget meetings.&#13;
3.6 Increased collection of holding tax:&#13;
This is the good practice of Tarash upazila of Sirajganj district. It was initiated under the SLGDFP to&#13;
increase the own resource base of the union parishads, so that dependency on the central government&#13;
&#13;
 16&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                       and supporting projects/organizations could be&#13;
                                                       reduced.&#13;
                                                       In 2002, the elected chairmen and members&#13;
                                                       had initiated new assessment after many years;&#13;
                                                       they raised the rate of holding tax to&#13;
                                                       reasonable levels and made concerted efforts&#13;
                                                       to increase collection. People did not respond&#13;
                                                       in the beginning. However, through open&#13;
                                                       budgets, introduction of passbooks,&#13;
                                                       community-based planning, and motivational&#13;
                                                       meetings, as well as by showing that they&#13;
                                                       could fulfill peoples' needs, they succeeded in&#13;
convincing the people about the new initiative. Finally, they achieved their target of increasing&#13;
collection of holding tax. Before 2003, average holding tax of a union parishad was BDT 60,000-&#13;
80,000. Now, in the changing situation, the average tax collection rose to BDT 300,000-400,000. This&#13;
is more than 300 percent collection than that in 2003.&#13;
Nine upazilas (Chapai Nawabganj Sadar, Shreepur, Khansama, Rajarhat, Shyamnagar, Chowgacha,&#13;
Karimganj, Magura and Rangamati Sadar) are now replicating this good initiative.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
3.7 Upazila Womenâ&#128;&#153;s Forum:&#13;
Elected female members have to face some inconvenience in the exercise of their role and&#13;
responsibilities. Upazila Women's Forum was formed in Tarash Upazila in Sirajganj district to&#13;
                                             empower its female members to work efficiently,&#13;
                                             and help them exercise their rights according to the&#13;
                                             rules and regulations of the Government of&#13;
                                             Bangladesh. The implementation of this particular&#13;
                                             good practice in the union parishads has brought&#13;
                                             about tremendous positive changes in the&#13;
                                             communities in terms of empowerment of women-&#13;
                                             both socio-politically and economically.&#13;
&#13;
                                                 The Upazila Women's Forum is non-profit, non-&#13;
                                                 governmental voluntary organization. The overall&#13;
Upazila Women's Forum                            objective of the organization is to conduct&#13;
advocacy programs at the policy level to resolve the problems usually faced by female members.&#13;
Former as well as current union parishad female members are eligible to be members of the Forum.&#13;
The activities of the Forum also help build the confidence of the local people towards female&#13;
members of Tarash upazila who are consequently well aware of their role, responsibilities, rights,&#13;
obligations and government policies. Their social status has been upgraded. They are now able to&#13;
champion the cause of destitute women to the union parishad. They provide income-generating&#13;
training and micro-credit to poor women without interest (from their savings fund); they also&#13;
contribute to eliminating dowry, early marriage, oppression on women, etc.&#13;
This good practice is being replicated at Karimganj upazila of Kishoreganj district.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                 17&#13;
&amp;#12;3.8 Local Government Association:&#13;
Elected representatives of all eight union parishads under Tarash upazila in Sirajganj district formed&#13;
a Local Government Association to implement their activities in a coordinated manner; avoid&#13;
unwanted intervention from outside; involve the community in union parishad activities; establish&#13;
inter-relationships among elected representatives; exchange views; and uphold the image of union&#13;
parishads.&#13;
The outcomes of the activities of the association include:&#13;
 - Enhancing the capacity of elected representatives for delivering quality services;&#13;
 - Increasing Community participation, transparency, and accountability;&#13;
 - Replicating the good practices of one union in others;&#13;
 - Strengthening cooperation with local administration;&#13;
 - Addressing different types of natural disaster with concerted efforts;&#13;
 - Distributing resources rationally; and&#13;
 - Protecting the union parishads' interests and activities from outside interference.&#13;
Karimganj Upazila of Kishoreganj and Khansama upazila in Dinajpur district are replicating this&#13;
good practice.&#13;
&#13;
4. THEMATIC SESSION I: FLASHBACK ON EXPERIENCES OF HORIZONTAL&#13;
LEARNING&#13;
Thematic Session I stressed revisiting the potential achievements made so far under the horizontal&#13;
learning process. Moderated by Professor Mujibur Rahman, Civil Engineering Department, BUET,&#13;
this session was attended by:&#13;
 Mr. Shafiqul Islam, Deputy Secretary (Fisheries), Ministry of Fisheries and Livestock.&#13;
 Mr. Atiqur Rahman, UNO, Karimganj, Kishoreganj.&#13;
 Mr. Mansoor Rahman Bachhu, Chairman, Tarash Sadar union parishad, Tarash, Sirajganj.&#13;
 Mr. Asjadur Rahman, Chairman, Gobratola union parishad, Chapai Nawabganj Sadar.&#13;
 Mr. Md. Khalilur Rahman, Chairman, Alokjhari union parishad, Khansama, Dinajpur.&#13;
 Mr. M.A. Salam, Chairman, Chowgacha union parishad, Chowgacha, Jessore.&#13;
 Mr. Md. Nur Mohammad Fakir, Chairman, Goshinga union parishad, Shreepur, Gazipur.&#13;
In this session participants presented their lessons learnt. Question answer and views were shared on&#13;
the basis of presentation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Summary of presentations:&#13;
Mr. Shafiqul Islam initiated the presentation, which was then supported by the other presenters. He&#13;
remarked that whereas any capacity-building program starts with the notion that there is a lack of&#13;
capacity, the horizontal learning program, on the other hand, builds on activities which are working&#13;
well, that is, where there are capacities existing on the ground. These lessons are being identified by&#13;
the unions for replication. This peer learning process follows appreciative inquiry which focuses on&#13;
positive factors and helps to identify, acknowledge, and appreciate achievements. Through holding&#13;
hands, union parishads learn from their peers and replicate those learnings. This has created a virtual&#13;
movement within the participating union parishads in Bangladesh-in six upazilas, the horizontal&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
18&#13;
&amp;#12;learning program has been able to identify 21 good practices and, if this process continues, in 507&#13;
upazilas there may be thousands of good practices revealed for replication. The horizontal learning&#13;
program thus has unveiled untapped resources in Bangladesh; it has helped in growing confidence&#13;
and credibility within local government institutions and creating a harmonization among aid partners.&#13;
Mr. Islam invited each of the local government representatives from various participating upazilas to&#13;
highlight some of the key findings of the horizontal learning program.&#13;
Mr. Atiqur Rahman praised the active participation of LGI representatives in Karimganj upazila. He&#13;
mentioned that the LGI representatives are leading the activities for eradication of open defecation&#13;
and use of sanitary latrines, formation of Karimganj Development Committee (KDC) to implement&#13;
different development activities in a coordinated manner, formation of Women's Forum to uphold the&#13;
rights of disadvantaged female members, holding of open budget meetings, increase collection of&#13;
holding tax, and the construction of bamboo bridge over a river with the contribution of he local&#13;
people, commonly known as Swapner Satu (that is, 'Bridge of our dreams').&#13;
Mr. Md. Mansoor Rahman Bachhu, Chairman, Tarash Sadar union parishad, said that he learned&#13;
about increased tax collection mechanisms. Sirajganj Local Governance Development Fund Project&#13;
(SLGDFP) facilitated them in this regard, he mentioned. He said that when he started his tenure in&#13;
2003, people were not aware of the tax and its assessment, and were very reluctant to pay tax at that&#13;
time. However, when he educated the community-through consultations and ward level meetings-that&#13;
the tax would be used for the development of the union itself, such as constructing roads or culverts,&#13;
renovating public properties, etc, the attitude of the people changed. Mr. Bachhu said open budget&#13;
meetings with people from the community ensured the transparency and accountability of LGI&#13;
activities and also improved the quality of the budget. While various upazilas learned open budget&#13;
and increase in collection of holding tax from Tarash, they also learned many new best practices from&#13;
Chowgacha, Khansama and others, which they are now replicating.&#13;
Mr. Khalilur Rahman, Chairman, Alokjhari union parishad, Khansama, was motivated by Plan&#13;
Bangladesh for implementing sanitation activities. Describing the process, he said that he discussed&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                 19&#13;
&amp;#12;the importance of practicing improved sanitation facilities with parishad members and formed ward-&#13;
wise committees. He involved the community in the whole implementation process by conducting&#13;
social mobilization activities. He recalled the concerted efforts of LGIs, the community and&#13;
development partners for achieving 100 percent sanitation in his union. To ensure the effective&#13;
participation and provide ownership of the program to the people in the community, they introduced&#13;
participatory planning and monitoring systems. They are also working towards making their villages&#13;
eco-friendly and have already declared six villages as 'Eco-friendly Model Village' in six unions. As&#13;
part of ensuring a healthy environment, they initiated plantation activities; three varieties of trees,&#13;
including fruits, timber and harval, have been planted. Many upazilas have liked their approach and&#13;
are now replicating their good practices, while they have also learned other good practices from&#13;
Chowgacha, Tarash, etc, and are replicating&#13;
them.&#13;
Mr. Abdus Salam, Chairman, Chowgacha&#13;
union parishad, described his experiences&#13;
regarding identifying arsenic and arsenicosis&#13;
patients, and techniques of testing of arsenic.&#13;
JICA provided technical and financial&#13;
support for strengthening the capacity of&#13;
LGIs and the community in this regard. He&#13;
pointed out that JICA helped them form&#13;
committees to implement arsenic-related&#13;
activities. The committee members&#13;
disseminated the messages in various&#13;
institutions such as schools, mosques, etc. Mr. Salam said that JICA also provided them and LGI&#13;
representatives arsenic test kit boxes free of cost. They are thus able to conduct arsenic tests on&#13;
tubewell water. The charge of BDT 50 for each test was given to the local hospital for purchasing&#13;
medicines. People could collect medicine from the hospital free of cost. Safe water options are also&#13;
installed to address the arsenic problem. This learning is now being replicated by other upazilas and&#13;
the horizontal learning program is helping them replicate other good practices in their own areas.&#13;
Mr. Md. Asjadur Rahman, Chairman, Gobratola union parishad, Chapai Nawabganj Sadar, described&#13;
the implementation of development activities through private enterprises, an initiative that is being&#13;
implemented with support from DASCOH. He told that the people in the community assessed the&#13;
need and submitted the demand to the union parishad. Accordingly, DASCOH transferred the funds to&#13;
the parishad. The latter selects the contractor, manages the contract, maintains government procedures&#13;
and issues work orders. The union parishad pays the bills upon satisfactory completion of work. Mr.&#13;
Rahman said the union parishad is always ready to implement all sort of development activities.&#13;
Therefore, more opportunities should be created for parishads to carry out such activities.&#13;
&#13;
Short discussion of question and answer session:&#13;
Mr. Shajahan Siraj, Chairman, Kaikhali Union Parishad, Shyamnagar, pointed out that 21 good&#13;
practices had been identified so far. But only eight good practices were being discussed in this&#13;
national forum. He suggested arranging another forum to discuss all the 21 good practices. Union&#13;
parishad chairman Mr. Liakot Ali wanted to know from the Bachhu chairman whether the union&#13;
parishad had any provision to allocate money for marriage purposes. If it was not possible, he&#13;
suggested opening a separate social head to meet such requirements. Chairman Mohsin Reza wanted&#13;
to know what the safe distance between a safe water source and sanitary latrine would be.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 20&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                      Mr. Saiful Islam, a veterinary doctor from&#13;
                                                      Tarash, suggested that the respective&#13;
                                                      ministries of the government should identify&#13;
                                                      good practices and should also initiate&#13;
                                                      replication on a larger scale. Mr. Rashedul&#13;
                                                      Islam, Sub-Assistant Engineer, DPHE of&#13;
                                                      Karimganj upazila, pointed out that increased&#13;
                                                      collection of tax would help create&#13;
                                                      confidence among the community but, at the&#13;
                                                      same time, it might be exactly the opposite if&#13;
                                                      the tax amount was misused. He also&#13;
suggested an expansion of the network of horizontal learning program in all union parishads, in&#13;
phases. Mr. Naimur Rahman, a school student from Shreepur upazila, highlighted that 100 percent&#13;
sanitation has been achieved in Shreepur due to the active participation of school children and the&#13;
community in the sanitation program.&#13;
Mr. Abdul Kader, Chairman, Pashapole union parishad, Chowgacha, suggested organizing workshops&#13;
for people in the community at a village level to orient them about lessons learned under the&#13;
horizontal learning program. Mr. Md. Yanus Ali, Chairman, Singhhozul union parishad, Chowgacha,&#13;
suggested using surface water instead of extracting groundwater. Amin Kuddus from Plan Bangladesh&#13;
suggested support for bottom-up planning, people's participation, and change of attitudes&#13;
Professor Mujibur Rahman summarized the salient features of the thematic discussions:&#13;
  Updating of the union parishad manual in line with developments made under the horizontal&#13;
  learning program.&#13;
  Proper open budget meetings create incentive for increased tax collection.&#13;
  More emphasis should be given to: (a) objective settings; (b) capacity-building regarding technic&#13;
  knowhow; and (c) appreciation of good work.&#13;
  Declaration of model union based on best performance.&#13;
  Good practices will be replicated considering socio-economic conditions.&#13;
  Need to prepare local resource policy.&#13;
  Hardcore list should be prepared permanently.&#13;
  Need media and other channel partnerships for disseminating the learnings.&#13;
  Encourage other development agencies to transfer funds directly to union parishads.&#13;
  Award to LGIs for good performance.&#13;
  Policy advocacy.&#13;
  Program approach.&#13;
  Acknowledge LGIs for replication of good practices.&#13;
  Include new upazilas in the horizontal learning network.&#13;
  Horizontal learning should be incorporated in the union parishad manual.&#13;
  Increase people's involvement.&#13;
  Provide incentives for the higher tax-collecting union parishads.&#13;
  Documentation of replicated best practices.&#13;
  Dissemination through television, community radio, etc.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                21&#13;
&amp;#12;    Communications using local tools/methods like pata song.&#13;
    Sharing of experience on horizontal learning at the national and international levels.&#13;
    Horizontal learning program should continue for a minimum of three more years.&#13;
BACKGROUND OF PREPARING THE PATA SONG&#13;
Pata gan or Patua sangit is a genre of folk song performed by patuas (rural canvas painters) who&#13;
paint stories on canvas based on myth and folklore. The illustrated canvas is unrolled as the patua&#13;
narrates the story through dance and song. The stories of the pats (paintings) and their accompanying&#13;
songs are very diverse in subject matter. Patua reflects the ordinary traditional folk painters who are&#13;
adept in drawing images connected to folk beliefs. Their drawings are generally known as pata&#13;
paintings (patachitras). Normally, they draw on a piece of cloth with figures of Hindu gods and&#13;
goddesses or Muslim pirs and fakirs. At one time patua songs were very popular in many areas of&#13;
Bangladesh, among both Hindus and Muslims, as they dealt with issues of religious reforms and&#13;
social change. Though the popularity of these folk songs has lessened in many areas, they still survive&#13;
and are the main occupation of a particular sect or group of people. Patuas earn their livelihood by&#13;
displaying their work, with accompanying music. They hold sessions where they display patachitras&#13;
and narrate the stories in song. They were known as gains in the Jessore and Khulna regions.&#13;
Local level communication is important to share information effectively. It was agreed by LGIs&#13;
within the horizontal learning program that traditional communication techniques, such as, pata song,&#13;
gambhira, alkap, jari, shari, and bhatiali songs, etc, would be used for effective communication&#13;
between the LGIs and rural people. Pata song was given a high priority because it is a strong&#13;
communication tool for mass awareness, accepted by the community, and cost effective.&#13;
The pata song on horizontal learning was performed by Shushilon, a local NGO. The script of the&#13;
pata song was prepared by Shushilon with support from Water and Sanitation Program (WSP) of the&#13;
World Bank under the overall guidance of a core group consisting of various support agencies. The&#13;
pata song described the horizontal learning process-appreciative inquiry, holding hands for&#13;
identification, learning, replication and peer review including highlighting eight good practices. The&#13;
performance was well received and appreciated by the national and international participants.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
5. THEMATIC SESSION-II: TALK SHOW&#13;
The talk show was moderated by Mr. Mohammad Jahangir and attended by eight LGI representatives&#13;
including six chairmen and two women members; two deputy secretaries and two upazila nirbahi&#13;
officers of the government, and one representative from a partner organization. This session was&#13;
specifically designed to provide an opportunity to LGI representatives to share their lessons learned&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 22&#13;
&amp;#12;from the horizontal learning process. The maximum number of participants were drawn from LGIs to&#13;
showcase the learning at the grassroots level. LGI representatives were enthusiastic about sharing&#13;
their views.&#13;
The participants in the talk show were:&#13;
       Mr. Shams Uddin Ahmed, Deputy Secretary, Local Government Division,&#13;
       M. Shafiqul Islam, Deputy Secretary, Ministry of Fisheries and Livestock;&#13;
       Md. Atiqur Rahman, UNO, Karimganj Kishoreganj;&#13;
       Md. Fazlul Kabir, UNO, Khansama, Dinajpur;&#13;
       Azahar Ali, Director, Governance and Strategic Support, WaterAid Bangladesh;&#13;
       Md. Sahadat Hossain Bablu, Chairman, Goaldehi Union Parishad Khansama, Dinajpur;&#13;
       Md. Abdul Hakim Khondaker, Chairman, Omarmajid Union Parishad, Rajarhat, Kurigram;&#13;
       Mr. Arun Kumar Chakma, Chairman, Makban Union Parishad, Rangamati Sadar, Rangamati;&#13;
       Mr. Amirul Islam Groho, Chairman, Naogaon Union Parishad, Tarash, Naogaon,&#13;
       Alhaj Alamgir Haider, Chairman, Ramjannagar Union Parishad, Shyamnagar, Satkhira,&#13;
       Ms. Monowara Begum, Female Member, Baruhas Union Parishad, Tarash, Sirajganj,&#13;
       Ms. Shuktara Yasmin, Female Member, Baliadanga Union Parishad, Nawabganj Sadar&#13;
        D.M. Ziaur Rahman, Chairman, Auspara Union Parishad, Bagmara, Rajshahi,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
SUMMARY OF THE TALK SHOW.&#13;
The talk show discussed the chronological development of the horizontal learning process. The&#13;
concept of this peer-to-peer learning was evolved at an experience-sharing workshop of LGI&#13;
representatives in June 2007 in Elenga, Tangail, and started its journey in November 2007. The talk&#13;
show highlighted the differences between a normal development process and the horizontal learning&#13;
process. The discussants pointed out that a normal development process maintains a top-down,&#13;
project-based, and target-oriented approach where involvement of primary beneficiaries usually&#13;
remains absent. The horizontal learning process, however, maintains bottom-up and program-based&#13;
approaches. Beneficiaries are directly involved in identifying their capacity building needs and also in&#13;
implementing activities according to local priorities.&#13;
The participants identified confidence-building through 'appreciative inquiry' as the most important&#13;
element under the horizontal learning process. About the benefits of the process, the LGI&#13;
representatives unanimously acknowledged that the horizontal learning process contributed to&#13;
strengthening the capacity of LGIs in all respects.&#13;
When the moderator wanted to know how the philosophy of 'appreciative inquiry' had influenced&#13;
them, LGI representatives said the philosophy of 'appreciative inquiry' helped them change old mind-&#13;
sets towards positive dimensions that reflect in their behavioral patterns. One of the major strengths&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                   23&#13;
&amp;#12;of such inquiry is to learn how to respect other people's opinions. It also helps ensure the involvement&#13;
of the community in the implementation of development activities and also ensure transparency,&#13;
accountability, and good governance.&#13;
&#13;
When a participant was invited to explain how they were replicating good practices, a participant&#13;
from Karimganj said on the basis of the good practices, a preliminary replication plan had been&#13;
developed with communities at ward level and then shared with the union parishad and Upazila&#13;
Development Coordination Committee meetings. The final draft replication plan, along with the&#13;
budget, is also shared with people in the community. Through holding meetings and consultations at&#13;
different levels, the final draft plan had been finalized to go for replication. Already positive results&#13;
are already happening, they admitted.&#13;
&#13;
The participants of the talk show said good practices have been shared among larger audiences&#13;
through holding meetings, briefings, and personal contacts. Monitoring of replication is done through&#13;
peer review by a team from the initiator of the good practice. The process helps strengthen the&#13;
capacity of women for effective participation in development activities. The implementation of&#13;
horizontal learning is possible without external support by using untapped resources, involving&#13;
community in the implementation process. However, some external support is initially required to&#13;
facilitate this process. The large-scale implementation of this learning process is also possible with&#13;
coordinated efforts of LGI representatives, government, development partners, NGOs and private&#13;
entrepreneurs.&#13;
&#13;
One LGI representative mentioned how his union had initiated replication of good practice though his&#13;
union had not yet joined in the horizontal learning program. Representative of the supporting partners&#13;
mentioned that supporting partners and projects may benefit by initiating replication of good&#13;
practices and horizontal learning process within their own working areas. He also stressed the need&#13;
for policy support for the scaling up of the horizontal learning program.&#13;
The talk show pointed out that horizontal learning contributes to the betterment of local people&#13;
through replication of identified good practices. People get direct benefits from activities such as&#13;
improvements in sanitation, arsenic testing of tubewell water and arrangement of alternative safe&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 24&#13;
&amp;#12;water devices, eco-friendly model villages, community based-planning, open budgets, livelihood&#13;
activities, upgradation of tubewells through construction of platforms and introduction of safer pump&#13;
heads, etc. The community plays a pivotal role in implementing this process.&#13;
&#13;
The talk show discussed the expansion of the horizontal learning process in all union parishads in&#13;
Bangladesh. The participants stressed the need for scaling up the program on a priority basis.&#13;
&#13;
6. SUMMING UP AND CLOSING â&#128;&#147; RECOMMENDATIONS FOR THE FUTURE&#13;
The workshop presented a set of recommendations for the consideration of the government and&#13;
partners under the horizontal learning program:&#13;
Creating an enabling environment&#13;
      Need to expand the horizontal learning process across all union parishads in Bangladesh.&#13;
      The union parishad manual, LGSP, and other national modules need to be modified to include the best&#13;
      practices identified by the LGIs under horizontal learning.&#13;
      LGIs from the horizontal learning program can be included in the committee responsible for the&#13;
      oversight of curriculum development at the national level.&#13;
      LGIs should identify those best practices that should be included in the national curriculum.&#13;
      Representatives from 'good practice' union parishads can be co-opted into curriculum revision.&#13;
      Representatives from 'best practice' union parishads can sell their training services to other parishads.&#13;
      The provision of orientation for newly elected representatives of local government institutions should be&#13;
      kept under the horizontal learning program.&#13;
      The horizontal learning program will continue to support union parishads to move towards programmatic&#13;
      approaches through showcasing 'bottom-up' approaches to aid-harmonization.&#13;
      A four-year business plan for the horizontal learning program needs to be planned to ensure an enabling&#13;
      environment for replicating and scaling-up of good practices in union parishads in Bangladesh.&#13;
Pomoting improved service delivery&#13;
   Exposure visits and peer reviews should be continued to assist in the replication of good practices&#13;
   within the horizontal learning program.&#13;
   Lessons learned during successful replication and scaling-up of good practices need to be&#13;
   documented and disseminated, using both Bangla and English languages.&#13;
   A special emphasis is required on deepening the horizontal learning process within the&#13;
   participating unions to ensure strengthened downward accountability to citizen stakeholders.&#13;
   Linkages with national institutions are essential to integrate the lessons learned in their regular&#13;
   course curricula.&#13;
   Periodic events to share the lessons learned from the horizontal learning program within all&#13;
   participating upazila and unions are essential.&#13;
   Periodic regional events could disseminate the lessons learned from the horizontal learning&#13;
   program.&#13;
   Incentive mechanisms need to be designed to acknowledge LGIs for the replication of good&#13;
   practices.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                              25&#13;
&amp;#12;Improving effective communication&#13;
      Need to utilize the independent media and other communication channels for disseminating the key&#13;
      horizontal learning messages.&#13;
      Need to utilize local and traditional forms of communication for disseminating horizontal learning&#13;
      messages within the participating and non-participating unions.&#13;
      Successful stories from the horizontal learning program could be telecast on television programs.&#13;
      The preparation and dissemination of various analytic learning products could strengthen the bottom-up&#13;
      teaching and lobbying power of the horizontal learning program.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Challenges ahead&#13;
      The initial success of horizontal learning created interest among many partners and central agencies. The&#13;
      challenge is to maintain the bottom-up spirit of this horizontal learning and protecting against the&#13;
      imposition of external wisdom that tends to erode the confidence of union parishads.&#13;
&#13;
      People's participation is the key for replicating good practices. Therefore, as LGIs learn new ideas and&#13;
      seek to replicate these approaches, they need to ensure that their citizens have ownership of these new and&#13;
      sometimes conflicting new initiatives.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Finally, it was also agreed in the workshop that the government would review these&#13;
 recommendations and take necessary actions for further development of the pace of the horizontal&#13;
 learning program.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 26&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                   ANNEXURE A: BACKGROUND&#13;
An innovative challenge to learn, share, empowerment and work together&#13;
for better results: A background&#13;
The horizontal learning program is a peer-to-peer learning process that was initiated by Local&#13;
Government Institutions (LGIs) in Bangladesh in November 2007. The initiative is being facilitated&#13;
by the Local Government Division, Ministry of Local Government, Rural Development and&#13;
Cooperatives (LGRD&amp;C) and supported by the Water and Sanitation Program - South Asia (WSP-&#13;
SA) of the World Bank, in partnership with Development Association for Self-Reliance,&#13;
Communication and Health (DASCOH) with financial support from Swiss Agency for Development&#13;
Cooperation (SDC); Japan International Cooperation Agency; WaterAid Bangladesh with assistance&#13;
from its local NGOs-Shushilon, Green Hill and Mohideb Jubo Samaj Kallyan Somiti (MJSKS); with&#13;
financial support from Department for International&#13;
Development (DfID); Plan Bangladesh; Dhaka Ahsania&#13;
Mission, and NGO Forum with financial support from&#13;
Danish International Development Agency (Danida).&#13;
The program was initially started in 66 unions of six upazilas&#13;
(subdistricts) to enhance the capacities of local water and&#13;
sanitation service delivery, and has been expanded to 10&#13;
upazilas (see map) with the potential to benefit&#13;
approximately 2.2 million people in 93 unions with improved&#13;
water and sanitation and good governance practices.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Introduction of horizontal learning in LGIs&#13;
In June 2007, WSP-SA organized a two-and-a-half day&#13;
participatory workshop for union parishad (UP) chairmen&#13;
and members from 29 UPs with support from SDC. The main&#13;
purpose of the workshop was to review, identify and&#13;
understand the existing capacities of the LGIs and to agree&#13;
on a roadmap for improving UPs' capacities to manage for&#13;
sustainable water supply, sanitation, and hygiene practices.&#13;
During the workshop the participants conceptualized and recommended a collective mutual learning&#13;
approach for strengthening the capacities of the UPs to create positive impact in planning and&#13;
implementing improved water supply, sanitation, and hygiene activities. As a follow-up of the June&#13;
workshop, stakeholders' meetings were held between July and November 2007 and the horizontal&#13;
learning approach was launched. This approach is intended to complement conventional methods of&#13;
capacity building.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Horizontal Learning is an initiative undertaken by Local Government Institutions with support from the Local Government&#13;
  Division, Ministry of LGRD&amp;C, Water and Sanitation Program â&#128;&#147; South Asia of the World Bank in partnership with JICA,&#13;
  DASCOH, WaterAid Bangladesh, Plan Bangladesh, Dhaka Ahsania Mission, NGO Forum, Shushilon, MJSKS and Green Hill.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                      27&#13;
&amp;#12;Horizontal learning in Bangladesh&#13;
The traditional capacity building program usually starts with assumption that "there is a lack of&#13;
capacity" that has to be addressed. What, how, and when these deficiencies will be delivered are&#13;
generally decided upon by experts. In contrast, the basic assumption in the horizontal learning&#13;
program is that "there are existing capacities, which are working well at grassroots level". What, how,&#13;
and when learning will be undertaken is decided by a peer group. Therefore, though the horizontal&#13;
learning program is not replacing conventional capacity building efforts, it aims to reinforce the target&#13;
groups' commitment for enhancing its own capacities. Similarly, capacity building efforts are also&#13;
adding values to horizontal learning program.&#13;
Horizontal learning: The implementation process&#13;
A draft learning framework was developed, discussed, and later shared with development partners and&#13;
the Local Government Division (Ministry of LGRD&amp;C) to agree upon the operationalization of this&#13;
horizontal learning program. All the&#13;
participating partner agencies agreed to&#13;
                                                                    Adding value to capacity building processes&#13;
collectively support this initiative with LGD&#13;
leadership (a Deputy Secretary was&#13;
subsequently designated as Focal Person) and                                  Capacity Building     Horizontal Learning&#13;
&#13;
coordination from WSP-SA. As per the learning         Starting Point          Deficiency            Capacity&#13;
&#13;
framework, several workshops were held with           What                    Should beâ&#128;¦..          Is workingâ&#128;¦.&#13;
&#13;
representatives from the five selected upazilas       Who   teaches           Experts               Peers&#13;
&#13;
to undertake the horizontal learning by union         Who   decides           Program               Self selection&#13;
&#13;
parishads. In the FIRST PHASE, the UPs                Why                     To meet standards     To address my needs&#13;
&#13;
identified through an appreciative inquiry            Where                   Classroom             Field based&#13;
&#13;
process 26 'good practices' and their respective      Result                  Increased capacity    Increased confidence&#13;
&#13;
indicators of verification. It was agreed that&#13;
development partner agencies would pre-visit&#13;
these 'good practices' and help each upazila to validate them as well as help them plan for upcoming&#13;
exposure visits. In a SECOND PHASE, network workshops were organized to summarize the&#13;
learning from the exposure visits and, most importantly, to plan for replicating these good practices.&#13;
Each union parishads selected many 'good practices' for replication. However, it was also agreed&#13;
among LGIs that if any union parishad will go for replicating 'good practices' it would need to&#13;
incorporate necessary support in its own annual plans and budgets, which would be shared with&#13;
partners. From the final list of 21 good practices, 16 are being picked up by UPs for replication,&#13;
through integration in their individual annual plan and budget.&#13;
                                                                                    16 good practices are now&#13;
         Initially, 26 good pr actices         After field validation jointly         being replicated after&#13;
             wer e indicated by                  by LGIs and par tner s, 21             exposure visits and&#13;
          par ticipating upazilas.                 good pr actices wer e                  integratedin&#13;
                                                     finalized.                     Annual Development Plan.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
By the end of September 2008, in the THIRD PHASE, 54 out of 93 participating union parishads had&#13;
allocated BDT 24,198,732.00 (around US$355,865) in their union budgets (July 2008 - June 2009) for&#13;
the purpose of replicating 16 good practices. Another eight UPs have begun replicating good practices&#13;
without explicit budget allocations. In addition to the horizontal learning field work, an Executive&#13;
Briefing was organized by LGI representatives and partner agencies for the Secretary, LGD, Ministry&#13;
of LGRD&amp;C and other senior officials. Linking good local practices to policy-makers and senior level&#13;
decision-makers has helped them to develop a greater awareness of local governments' potential to&#13;
implement demand-responsive development activities.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 28&#13;
&amp;#12;        Twenty-one good practices identified by LGIs in the first year of horizontal learning&#13;
  Upazila                                                        Good Practices&#13;
                 Water quality surveillance - arsenic testing, bacteriological testing, sanitary survey&#13;
 Chowgacha       Allocation of money for providing medicine to the arsenicosis patients from ADP allocation&#13;
                 Installation of water sources based on the demand of villagers and offering informed choices&#13;
                 Women's Forum for empowerment of women and creating environment for income generation&#13;
                 Formation of Local Government Association&#13;
  Tarash         Open budget meeting&#13;
                 Enhancement of holding tax assessment and increase of collection&#13;
                 Moving towards total sanitation (community ignition to achieve 100 percent sanitary latrine coverage)&#13;
  Sreepur        Initiated process for activation of the Task Forces at upazila, union and ward level&#13;
                 Childrenâ&#128;&#153;s leadership in hygienic behavioral change programme through educational institutions&#13;
                 Eco-friendly villages&#13;
                 Establishment of village sanitation centers and its effective operation&#13;
 Khansama        Effective communication with UPs, VDCs, upazila parishads and NGOs&#13;
                 Integration of sanitation and education programme&#13;
&#13;
                 Up-gradation of tube wells&#13;
  Rajarhat       Introduction of different low cost durable latrine options&#13;
&#13;
                 Performance monitoring for improving watsan services â&#128;&#147; social map, inventory, ward summary, action plan,&#13;
 Shyamnagar      Resolutions, actions applied, review of social map&#13;
                 Alternate technology options â&#128;&#147; pond sand filter (type-1), pond sand filter (type-2), rain water harvesting&#13;
                 Community based planning and monitoring&#13;
 Nawabganj       Implementation of development activities through small scale (local) private entrepreneurs&#13;
                 Disbursement of project grants directly to the union parishads and implementation of development projects&#13;
                 through union parishads&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
During this first year of horizontal learning, seven pre-visits and seven exposure visits were organized. About&#13;
300 representatives from LGIs, upazilas, local leaders, school teachers, and partner agencies participated&#13;
from the concerned UPs. In addition, many separate field missions aimed at 'good practice' verification and&#13;
replication assistance were supported by individual partners.&#13;
Replicating good practices: Some examples&#13;
Enhancement of holding tax assessment and increase of collection&#13;
Gazipur UP (Shreepur upazila) has initiated the replication and has&#13;
collected BDT 240,000 against a new tax assessment of BDT 316,000.&#13;
Tax collection increased from 25 percent the previous year to&#13;
approximately 76 percent.&#13;
Pashapol UP (Chowgacha upazila) collected BDT 55,000 against an&#13;
assessment of BDT 70,000. Tax collection increased from 15 percent the&#13;
previous year to approximately 79 percent.&#13;
Dehunda UP (Karimganj) was able to adopt similar methods and in the&#13;
first year secure a 20 percent increase in its annual holding tax collection.&#13;
Water Quality Surveillance (Arsenic Testing)&#13;
Once UPs learned through exposure visits to Chowgacha how to test water samples for arsenic, the&#13;
Naogaon UP and Tarash Sadar UP (Tarash upazila), Ranihati and Moharajpur UPs (Nawabganj&#13;
upazila) and Omarmajid UP (of Rajarhat upazila) also undertook systematic testing of water samples&#13;
for arsenic.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                              29&#13;
&amp;#12;Moving towards total sanitation&#13;
The success of UPs in Khansama and Shreepur upazilas for 100 percent sanitation coverage inspired&#13;
union parishad of Dehunda (Karimganj) to reduce open defecation by 45 percent (from an estimated&#13;
55 percent to 10 percent) in five months.&#13;
&#13;
Eco-friendly villages&#13;
Learning from Khansama UP, Tarash Sadar and&#13;
Naogoan UPs (Tarash upazila) and Omarmajid UP&#13;
(Rajarhat upazila) have already initiated similar&#13;
approaches to effectively manage excreta disposal,&#13;
wastewater disposal and solid waste disposal at union&#13;
level.&#13;
&#13;
Women's Forum&#13;
Formation of an upazila Women's Forum has been&#13;
replicated in two upazilas (Karimganj and Shreepur).&#13;
&#13;
Future challenges&#13;
The horizontal learning process has just begun in Bangladesh. The immediate results are encouraging&#13;
and there is an ongoing demand from various union parishads and upazilas to join the process of&#13;
horizontal learning. However, some challenges also remain in order to fully internalize this approach:&#13;
Deepening of the horizontal learning: To deepen the concept and practice of horizontal learning, it&#13;
was agreed that each ward within each upazila would start to peer review other wards replication of&#13;
good practices. Union parishads of Tarash upazila has already embarked on this process.&#13;
&#13;
 Communication to internalize the horizontal learning: Local level communication is quite&#13;
 important to share the information effectively. It was agreed by LGIs within the horizontal learning&#13;
 program that traditional communication techniques, such as, pata song, alkap, Bhatiali songs, etc,&#13;
 would be used for effective communication within LGIs. However, for dealing with official&#13;
 communication local display boards, sharing information in radios and official announcements will&#13;
 be further strengthened.&#13;
&#13;
 Maintaining the 'bottom-up' spirit: Maintaining the bottom-up spirit of this initiative and protecting&#13;
 against the imposition of external wisdom that tends to erode the self-respect and confidence of&#13;
 union parishads is essential. Therefore, broader capacity-building programs should take measures&#13;
 to protect this spirit in the horizontal learning, even as they complement this approach.&#13;
&#13;
 Ensuring people's participation in the process for sustainable development: People's participation is&#13;
 the key for replicating good practices and therefore, carrying out an open budget meeting,&#13;
 dialoguing with people and then integrating the replication plan within the ADP is mandatory for&#13;
 LGIs to continue to incorporate their citizens' opinions.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
30&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                    ANNEXURE B: WORKSHOP PROGRAM&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
08:00 â&#128;&#147; 09:30       Registration&#13;
&#13;
Inaugura Session:&#13;
&#13;
09:30 - 09:35       Welcome Speech by Mr. Shams Uddin Ahmed, Deputy Secretary (WS), LGD,&#13;
                    Ministry of LGRD&amp;C&#13;
&#13;
09:35 â&#128;&#147; 09:50       Presentation on horizontal learning: A process for enhancing capacities of union&#13;
                    parishads&#13;
&#13;
09:50 â&#128;&#147; 10:00       Opening remarks by Mr. Glenn Pearce-Oroz, Country Team Leader and Senior WSS&#13;
                    Specialist, WSP- SA, World Bank&#13;
&#13;
10:00 â&#128;&#147; 10:10       Speech by Special Guest â&#128;&#147; Mr. Vinaya Swaroop, Acting Country Director, WB, Dhaka Office&#13;
&#13;
10:10 â&#128;&#147; 10:25       Speech by Chief Guest â&#128;&#147;Shaikh Khurshid Alam, Secretary, LGD, Ministry of&#13;
                    LGRD&amp;C&#13;
&#13;
10:25 â&#128;&#147; 10:35       Speech by the Chairperson â&#128;&#147; Mr. Md. Lukman Hakim Talukder, Joint Secretary (WS),&#13;
                    LGD, Ministry of LGRD&amp;C&#13;
&#13;
10:35 â&#128;&#147; 10:40       Vote of thanks by Mr. Oaliar Rahman, Chairman, Jagdal union parishad, Magura Sadar upazila&#13;
&#13;
10:40 â&#128;&#147; 11:00       Refreshment&#13;
&#13;
Thematic Session:&#13;
&#13;
11:00 â&#128;&#147; 11:40       Flashback on field exposure experiences under horizontal learning - moderated by&#13;
                    Prof. Dr. Md. Mojibur Rahman, Dept. of Civil Engineering, BUET&#13;
&#13;
11:40 â&#128;&#147; 12:20       Floor participation&#13;
&#13;
12:20 â&#128;&#147; 01:15       Pata song on horizontal learning in Bangladesh â&#128;&#147; by Shushilan&#13;
&#13;
01:15 â&#128;&#147; 02:30       Prayer and lunch&#13;
&#13;
02:30 â&#128;&#147; 04:00       Talk show: Experiences on replication of good practices under horizontal learning&#13;
&#13;
04:00 â&#128;&#147; 04:30       Summing-up&#13;
&#13;
04:30 â&#128;&#147; 05:00       Closing tea&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                          31&#13;
&amp;#12;                    ANNEXURE C: PARTICIPANTS AND RESOURCE PERSONS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Sl.                   Category of participants          Number of participants&#13;
&#13;
1.     LGI representatives                                        115&#13;
&#13;
2.     Upazila administration                                     37&#13;
&#13;
3.     Supporting agencies                                        42&#13;
&#13;
4.     Government agencies                                        35&#13;
&#13;
5.     Special guests and others                                  75&#13;
&#13;
6.     Informal working team members                              37&#13;
&#13;
7.     Media persons                                              64&#13;
&#13;
8.     Pata song group members                                    15&#13;
&#13;
9.     Volunteers                                                 20&#13;
&#13;
10     WSP-SA                                                     10&#13;
&#13;
                                    TOTAL PARTICIPANTS            450&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
32&#13;
&amp;#12;ANNEXURE D: PRESENTATION ON THEMATIC SESSION-I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 33&#13;
&amp;#12;34&#13;
&amp;#12;35&#13;
&amp;#12;36&#13;
&amp;#12; Horizontal Learning in Bangladesh&#13;
   Open Budget Declaration&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Horizontal Learning in Bangladesh&#13;
Local Governments Association&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     37&#13;
&amp;#12;38&#13;
&amp;#12;39&#13;
&amp;#12;40&#13;
&amp;#12;41&#13;
&amp;#12;&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="16659427">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2008/10/16659427/bangladesh-horizontal-learning-strengthening-capacities-local-government-institutions-bangladesh
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2008/10/16659427/bangladesh-horizontal-learning-strengthening-capacities-local-government-institutions-bangladesh</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2008/10/16659427/bangladesh-horizontal-learning-strengthening-capacities-local-government-institutions-bangladesh</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2012-08-30T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2012-08-30T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2012/08/30/000425962_20120830162354/Rendered/INDEX/722040WP0Box370enthening0capacities.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2012/08/30/000425962_20120830162354/Rendered/PDF/722040WP0Box370enthening0capacities.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2012-08-30T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2008-10-30T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Bangladesh - Horizontal learning for
            strengthening capacities of local government institutions in Bangladesh
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The report of the 'National
            Dissemination Workshop on Horizontal Learning for
            Strengthening Capacities of Local Government
            Institutions' summarizes the workshop proceedings and
            final recommendations for the horizontal learning program.
            The horizontal learning program is a peer-to-peer learning
            process that was initiated in Bangladesh by local government
            institutions (LGIs) in November 2007, aiming to strengthen
            the capacity of union parishads. The overall objective of
            the workshop was to disseminate the lessons learned on best
            practices under the horizontal learning program, which would
            facilitate its replication on a larger scale. The
            workshop's specific objectives are to share the
            experiences and lessons learned under the horizontal
            learning program by LGIs (union parishads) and other
            stakeholders; to formulate a roadmap for horizontal learning
            program to strengthen the capacities of LGIs; to design an
            effective communication strategy for dissemination of
            lessons learned; and to reach consensus for further aid
            harmonization for strengthening capacities for local
            government institutions.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Bangladesh - Horizontal learning for
            strengthening capacities of local government institutions in Bangladesh
        </docna>
        <display_title>Bangladesh - Horizontal learning
            for strengthening capacities of local government
            institutions in Bangladesh</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2008/10/16659427/bangladesh-horizontal-learning-strengthening-capacities-local-government-institutions-bangladesh</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>UNDP-Water &amp; Sanitation Program</docty>
        <subtopic>Knowledge for Development,Teaching and Learning,Educational Sciences,Debt Markets,ICT Policy and Strategies</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Information and Communication Technologies,Education</teratopic>
        <count>Bangladesh</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Asia!$!80451</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>South Asia!$!80470</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000425962_20120830162354</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>South Asia,South Asia</admreg>
        <colti>Proceedings</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Information and Communication Technologies,Education</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            achievement, achievements, beliefs,
            beneficiaries, best practice, best practices, capacity
            building, child labor, collaboration, communities,
            Conversions, core group, credibility, curricula, curriculum,
            curriculum development, decision-making, deposits,
            Disbursement, discussion, discussions, durable, enabling
            environment, financial support, good practice, government
            policies, holding, ideas, integration, International
            Development, inventory, leadership, leading, Learning,
            learning approach, learning practices, learning process,
            Local Government, local governments, media, medicine,
            micro-credit, national curriculum, natural disaster, partner
            organizations, peer review, programs, radio, readers,
            schools, speech, target groups, tax, tax collection,
            teachers, teaching, television, tenure, transparencies,
            transparency, wisdom
        </keywd>
        <owner>Water - Water &amp; Sant. Prgrm-SAR (GWASS)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>South Asia</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>72204</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Science and Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Arts and Culture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Livestock</ml:concept><ml:concept>Livestock and Animal Husbandry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Basic Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>On-site Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Marketing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen's Budgets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal and Budgetary Transparency</ml:concept><ml:concept>Open Budget</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Knowledge for Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Disasters</ml:concept><ml:concept>Engineering</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Growth and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Media</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water, Sanitation and Hygiene</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fertilizers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Micro-Credit</ml:concept><ml:concept>Animal Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Local Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Transparency</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Local Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Drainage</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Bangladesh</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Southern Asia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>