<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>ï»¿WATER AND SANITATION PROGRAM: RESEARCH BRIEF&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                  72258&#13;
WSP Sanitation Global Practice Team&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Financing Household On-Site&#13;
Sanitation for the Poor&#13;
April 2011&#13;
                                                                                   KEY MESSAGES&#13;
&#13;
INTRODUCTION                                                                       â&#128;¢ Public financing for â&#128;&#156;softwareâ&#128;? has a significant role&#13;
Forty percent of the worldâ&#128;&#153;s people do not have access to a basic                    to play in creating demand for improved sanitation&#13;
level of sanitation; one in five of us practices open defecation.1 This              and changing community and household behaviors.&#13;
crisis in sanitation has clear consequences. Diarrhea kills more than                However, the amount and way such public support is&#13;
1.5 million children each year, and 88 percent of these deaths are at-               financed can significantly affect the performance of&#13;
tributed to fecal contamination from inadequate sanitation, hygiene,                 sanitation projects and their impact.&#13;
and water supply.2 The cost of these problems is high in economic                  â&#128;¢ Project designers should look beyond the seman-&#13;
as well as human terms. In a series of studies, the Water and Sani-                  tics of simplistic â&#128;&#156;subsidy vs. no subsidyâ&#128;? debates&#13;
tation Program (WSP) estimated that inadequate sanitation costs                      to define an appropriate level and form of public&#13;
the economies of four Southeast Asian countries the equivalent of                    investment in sanitation. The design of the financing&#13;
approximately 2 percent of their GDP3; these results echo similar                    approach at the outset of on-site sanitation programs is&#13;
findings elsewhere about both the costs and benefits of sanitation.4                 too often not given sufficient critical thinking. Answers&#13;
                                                                                     to basic financial questionsâ&#128;&#148;â&#128;&#156;Who pays for what, when,&#13;
Sanitation solutions are not cheap for the poor, who make up the                     and how?â&#128;?â&#128;&#148;can determine the extent to which projects&#13;
vast majority of those without sanitation. Like housing, on-site sani-               can replicate, expand sanitation, be sustainable, and&#13;
tation is often viewed as a private good and the basic responsibility                meet household needs.&#13;
of the beneficiaries themselves. Yet sector professionals have long                â&#128;¢ Well-targeted hardware subsidies can provide a&#13;
argued that some public finance of sanitation can be justified by                    critical safety net for the poor. Such subsidies should&#13;
its inherent externalities: construction and use of a family latrine                 not be used as a substitute for hardware investments&#13;
protects others at least as much as it reduces disease transmission                  by households. Hardware subsidies that were most&#13;
within the family. However, the large number of poor households                      effective were provided after demand was createdâ&#128;&#148;and&#13;
without sanitation makes it difficult for strained government bud-                   especially after outputs and/or outcomes were achieved.&#13;
gets to contribute a large fraction of the cost. In addition, econo-&#13;
mists and sector professionals are generally skeptical of subsidy&#13;
schemes, having seen how inefficient and counterproductive some&#13;
poorly designed programs can be.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
1&#13;
  UNICEF/WHO JMP (Joint Monitoring Programme for Water Supply and&#13;
  Sanitation). 2008. Progress on Drinking Water and Sanitation: Special Focus on&#13;
  Sanitation. Geneva: WHO.&#13;
2&#13;
  A. Lopez et al. 2006. Global Burden of Disease and Risk Factors. Washington,&#13;
  DC: The World Bank, Disease Control Priorities Project.&#13;
3&#13;
  See the reports available through the WSP Economic Impacts of Sanitation&#13;
  Initiative website at www.wsp.org/wsp/content/economic-impacts-sanitation.&#13;
4&#13;
  G. Hutton and L. Haller. 2004. Evaluation of the Costs and Benefits of Water&#13;
  and Sanitation Improvements at the Global Level. WHO/SDE/WSH Report&#13;
  04.04. Geneva: WHO. Additional background information is derived from&#13;
  roughly 30 country reports, both published and unpublished, completed&#13;
  between 2004 and 2007 and made available to the authors by Bjorn Larsen.&#13;
&amp;#12;2     Financing Household On-Site Sanitation for the Poor                                                                  WSP Sanitation Global Practice Team&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Table 1. Approaches Used in the Six Case Studies&#13;
    Country                 Program Name                              Approach&#13;
    Bangladesh               DISHARI                                  Community-Led Total Sanitation (CLTS), reward for outcome and upfront subsidy for poorest&#13;
    Ecuador                  PRAGUAS                                  Hardware subsidy to users in rural areas&#13;
    Maharashtra (India)      Total Sanitation Campaign (TSC)          Community-Led Total Sanitation (CLTS), sanitation-linked reward for outcome and hardware&#13;
                                                                      subsidy for poorest after success&#13;
    Mozambique               Improved Latrines Program (PLM)          Hardware subsidy to providers in urban areas&#13;
    Senegal                  PAQPUD                                   Hardware subsidy to users in urban areas&#13;
    Vietnam                  Sanitation Revolving Fund (SRF)          Subsidized revolving loan fund for hardware in urban areas&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The challenges of financeâ&#128;&#148;the practical decisions about who                                 the best way to ensure that they reach their intended recipients&#13;
pays how much for what, when, and howâ&#128;&#148;thus lie at the heart                                 and are sustainable and scalable?&#13;
of the worldâ&#128;&#153;s efforts to promote health, dignity, and a cleaner                          â&#128;¢ What innovative mechanisms (such as credit or revolving funds)&#13;
environment through sanitation. In 2010, WSP and the World Bank                             can be used to promote household sanitation financing?&#13;
conducted a study to improve understanding of the financing of&#13;
on-site sanitation at the household level through careful analysis                      The study reviewed alternative financing approaches from programs&#13;
of practical field experiences in a wide range of programs. This                        representing a range of approaches, from those that combined&#13;
Research Brief summarizes findings from the full report, available                      support for software activities with limited targeted hardware sub-&#13;
online.5                                                                                sidies for poor households to approaches with a relatively high&#13;
                                                                                        hardware subsidy (Table 1). The diversity in financing approaches&#13;
PURPOSE AND METHODOLOGY                                                                 was also reflected in different approaches to program design,&#13;
Many people without sanitation live in rural areas or on the fringe of                  with programs ranging from community-led programs for invest-&#13;
cities beyond the reach of sewerage networks. The first step up the                     ment in basic sanitation to programs providing a well-defined set of&#13;
â&#128;&#156;sanitation ladderâ&#128;? for those without access will be on-site sanita-                    improved sanitation solutions.&#13;
tion. The institutional and financial structures of sewerage and on-site&#13;
sanitation are so different that it was decided to focus first on the                   In addition to summarizing the mechanics of each approach, all&#13;
issue of basic on-site sanitation.                                                      projects were evaluated against a common set of criteria:&#13;
&#13;
The study formulated a set of basic questions to help identify the                        â&#128;¢ Impact on sustainable access to services: Did the financial&#13;
best-performing approaches and the relevant factors and issues                              approach leverage increased sanitation access?&#13;
to consider in designing a sanitation financing strategy. These&#13;
                                                                                          â&#128;¢ Costs: Are the costs of the resulting sanitation facilities reason-&#13;
included:&#13;
                                                                                            able and affordable to the beneficiaries?&#13;
&#13;
    â&#128;¢ How much does provision of access to on-site sanitation cost                        â&#128;¢ Effectiveness of the use of public funds: Were public funds&#13;
      once all costs (hardware and software) are accounted for?                             used in a way that maximized impact?&#13;
&#13;
    â&#128;¢ Do the type and scale of sanitation subsidy affect provision and                    â&#128;¢ Poverty targeting: Did the program seek to target the poor and&#13;
      uptake? How?                                                                          was the program effective at doing so?&#13;
&#13;
    â&#128;¢ How can the public sector most effectively support household                        â&#128;¢ Financial sustainability: Could the financial approach be sus-&#13;
      investment in on-site sanitation?                                                     tained over time without external support?&#13;
&#13;
    â&#128;¢ Should support be via investment in demand stimulation, sub-                        â&#128;¢ Scalability: Could the financial approach be scaled up to cover&#13;
      sidies to households or suppliers, credit schemes, or by other                        those who are not yet covered in the country at a reasonable cost?&#13;
      means?&#13;
                                                                                        Two principles guided the data-collection phase. First, all costs&#13;
    â&#128;¢ Should hardware subsidies be provided or should public spend-&#13;
                                                                                        for both hardware (including the initial capital expenditure and the&#13;
      ing focus on promoting demand or supporting the supply side&#13;
                                                                                        estimated ongoing maintenance costs) and software (such as de-&#13;
      of the market? Where hardware subsidies are adopted, what is&#13;
                                                                                        mand promotion and media campaigns) were counted. Second, all&#13;
                                                                                        sources of funds (governments, the households themselves, and&#13;
5&#13;
    The full report is available at www.wsp.org/wsp/sites/wsp.org/files/publications/&#13;
                                                                                        international transfers from, for example, NGOs and donors) were&#13;
    financing_analysis.pdf.                                                             included.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                     www.wsp.org&#13;
&amp;#12;WSP Sanitation Global Practice Team                                                                            Financing Household On-Site Sanitation for the Poor                           3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ANALYSIS                                                                             Figure 2: Total Initial Costs per Household Sanitation&#13;
Key characteristics of the financing approaches used in the projects                 Facility (Actual US$ Exchange Rate)&#13;
studied are represented in Figure 1. The horizontal axis shows the                              800&#13;
level of public sector finance as a proportion of the initial hardware                          700&#13;
and software costs of sanitation, whereas the vertical axis reflects                            600&#13;
the percentage of such public support that was spent on hardware&#13;
                                                                                                500&#13;
subsidies. Although there are important differences, the financing&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                          US$&#13;
                                                                                                400                                                                       Key&#13;
approaches broadly fit into three groups:                                                                                                                                 Software support&#13;
                                                                                                300&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                          (public)&#13;
                                                                                                200                                                                       Hardware subsidy&#13;
At one end of the spectrum, Vietnam, Bangladesh, and Maha-                                                                                                                (public)&#13;
rashtra primarily relied on households to invest in their own facili-                           100                                                                       Household investment&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                          (private)&#13;
ties. Public support was provided to promote and create demand                                    0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                         e&#13;
                                                                                                                                 ra&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                             m&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                     sh&#13;
                                                                                                                     r&#13;
                                                                                                           l&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                      qu&#13;
                                                                                                       ga&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                    do&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                           a&#13;
                                                                                                                               ht&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                  de&#13;
                                                                                                                                        tn&#13;
for sanitation. Hardware subsidies were fairly limited overall, al-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                    bi&#13;
                                                                                                      ne&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                ua&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                              as&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                la&#13;
                                                                                                                                         e&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                 am&#13;
                                                                                                  Se&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                               Ec&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                          ar&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                      Vi&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                             ng&#13;
                                                                                                                         ah&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                               oz&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                           Ba&#13;
though targeted subsidies were given to poor households to ad-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                             M&#13;
                                                                                                                     M&#13;
dress affordability issues in Bangladesh and Maharashtra.&#13;
&#13;
At the other end of the spectrum, Senegal and Ecuador provided&#13;
substantial public support, primarily in the form of hardware subsidies.             subsidy component and the household investment component. The&#13;
                                                                                     figure shows substantial differences in the initial costs per house-&#13;
Mozambique was somewhere in the middle, relying on partial                           hold for accessing sanitation, from more than US$700 in Senegal7&#13;
hardware subsidies provided to local suppliers to build improved                     to US$24 dollars in Bangladesh. These substantial cost variations&#13;
latrines.6                                                                           largely reflect the difference in levels of service provided by different&#13;
                                                                                     projects. The choice of financing approach also appears to have&#13;
The average costs of providing household sanitation were com-                        a substantial impact on costs. On the whole, the higher the level&#13;
puted by taking into account all costs (including software) and all                  of service, the higher public subsidies are as a percentage of the&#13;
sources of finance. Figure 2 shows the average initial costs of the                  total cost of sanitation adoption. The software support costs per&#13;
sanitation â&#128;&#156;packageâ&#128;? that households accessed in each project                        household varied considerably. Software costs as a percentage of&#13;
and breaks down the initial hardware costs between the hardware                      total initial costs varied from 29 percent in Bangladesh to 7 percent&#13;
                                                                                     in Maharashtra. Finally, when compared to household incomes,&#13;
                                                                                     hardware costs ranged from 2.7 percent of average income in Ban-&#13;
Figure 1: Characterizing Financing Approaches                                        gladesh to just over 30 percent of income for below-poverty-level&#13;
to On-Site Sanitation                                                                (BPL) household in Vietnam. These projects and their financing ap-&#13;
                                                                                     proaches are presented in Table 2 in the increasing percentage of&#13;
                90&#13;
                                                                                     the total costs of sanitation adoption coming from public funds.&#13;
                80&#13;
                                                                           Ecuador&#13;
&#13;
                                                                           Senegal   Table 2 provides a summary evaluation of how the different case&#13;
                70&#13;
                                                                                     studies performed with respect to the six criteria: impact on sus-&#13;
                60                             Mozambique                            tainable access to services, costs, effectiveness in the use of public&#13;
 Hardware 50                                                                         funds, poverty targeting, financial sustainability, and scalability.&#13;
subsidies as&#13;
 % of public 40&#13;
investment                                                                           Some approaches, such as those in Maharashtra and Bangla-&#13;
                30           Vietnam                                                 desh, did very well on all parameters and appeared highly replica-&#13;
                              Maharashtra                                            ble. They are applicable in certain settings, such as rural settings in&#13;
                20&#13;
                                                                                     South Asia and probably on other continents as well, but might be&#13;
                10&#13;
                                        Bangladesh                                   less successful in areas with less community cohesion and higher&#13;
                 0                                                                   expectations in terms of service levels. The approach used in Ma-&#13;
                        10      20     30    40      50     60   70   80    90       harashtra, where households receive a subsidy to cover a basic&#13;
                                       Public investment as % of total&#13;
                                     investment in household sanitation              level of service and are encouraged to invest in higher service levels&#13;
&#13;
6                                                                                    7&#13;
    Data for Mozambique were estimated for the situation in the late 1990s (the          For Senegal, the average costs were calculated by dividing the total costs of&#13;
    â&#128;&#156;heydayâ&#128;? of the program), given that actual data were not available and could        providing on-site sanitation facilities by the number of households reached, to&#13;
    no longer be collected for that period.                                              reflect the fact that households served received 1.56 facilities on average.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
www.wsp.org&#13;
&amp;#12;4   Financing Household On-Site Sanitation for the Poor                                                       WSP Sanitation Global Practice Team&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Table 2. Case Studies: Summary Evaluation&#13;
 Project context level of service, population that adopted&#13;
 sanitation during the project, study period                     Financing approach&#13;
 Vietnam: Sanitation Revolving Fund (SRF)                        â&#128;¢ Public funds = 7% of total costs of sanitation adoption&#13;
 â&#128;¢ Urban areas                                                   â&#128;¢ Software support for sanitation promotion and hygiene education&#13;
 â&#128;¢ Mostly bathrooms and septic tanks                             â&#128;¢ Facilitated access to credit via sanitation revolving funds&#13;
 â&#128;¢ 194,000 people                                                â&#128;¢ Subsidized interest rates on loans for hardware construction&#13;
 â&#128;¢ 2001 to 2008                                                    (accounting for about 3% of hardware costs)&#13;
 Maharashtra (India): Total Sanitation Campaign (TSC)            â&#128;¢ Public funds = 9% of total costs of sanitation adoption&#13;
 â&#128;¢ Rural areas                                                   â&#128;¢ Software support for community mobilization, including outcome-based financial&#13;
 â&#128;¢ Community-Led Total Sanitation (CLTS) approaches                rewards to villages reaching Open Defecation Free (ODF) status to be spent on&#13;
 â&#128;¢ Improved latrines                                               sanitation investments&#13;
 â&#128;¢ 21,200,000 people                                             â&#128;¢ Outcome-based hardware subsidies for below-poverty-line households (covering&#13;
 â&#128;¢ July 2000 to November 2008                                      about 22% of hardware costs for beneficiaries)&#13;
                                                                 â&#128;¢ Access to credit in some districts only&#13;
 Bangladesh: DISHARI                                             â&#128;¢ Public funds = 31% of total costs of sanitation adoption&#13;
 â&#128;¢ Rural areas                                                   â&#128;¢ Software support for community mobilization, sanitation promotion, and local&#13;
 â&#128;¢ Based on Community-Led Total Sanitation                         government strengthening, including outcome-based financial rewards to villages&#13;
 â&#128;¢ Basic latrines                                                  that are 100% sanitized. Rewards come with no strings attached and do not&#13;
 â&#128;¢ 1,631,000 people                                                necessarily need to be spent on sanitation.&#13;
 â&#128;¢ 2004 to 2008                                                  â&#128;¢ Up-front in-kind hardware subsidies targeted to the poorest (covering about 42%&#13;
                                                                   of hardware costs for beneficiaries)&#13;
 Mozambique: Improved Latrines Program (PLM)                     â&#128;¢ Public funds = 58% of total costs of sanitation adoption (estimated)&#13;
 â&#128;¢ Urban areas                                                   â&#128;¢ Software support for sanitation promotion and establishment of local workshops&#13;
 â&#128;¢ Improved latrines                                               building slabs and latrines&#13;
 â&#128;¢ 1,888,000 people                                              â&#128;¢ Output-based subsidies to local sanitation providers for each slab or latrine sold&#13;
 â&#128;¢ 1980 to 2007                                                    (intended to cover 40% to 60% of hardware costs)&#13;
 Ecuador: PRAGUAS                                                â&#128;¢ Public funds = 85% of total costs of sanitation adoption&#13;
 â&#128;¢ Rural areas                                                   â&#128;¢ Software support to strengthen municipalities to work in sanitation, for technical&#13;
 â&#128;¢ Sanitation units (toilet, septic tank, sink, shower)            designs and monitoring&#13;
 â&#128;¢ 143,000 people                                                â&#128;¢ Up-front fixed hardware subsidies (covering about 60% of hardware costs)&#13;
 â&#128;¢ 2001 to 2006                                                    provided to communities&#13;
 Senegal: PAQPUD                                                 â&#128;¢ Public funds = 89% of total costs of sanitation adoption&#13;
 â&#128;¢ Urban areas                                                   â&#128;¢ Software support for sanitation promotion, including hygiene promotion and&#13;
 â&#128;¢ Range of options: improved latrines to septic tanks             education, community organization, technical support&#13;
 â&#128;¢ 411,000 people                                                â&#128;¢ Output-based hardware subsidies to local sanitation providers for each sanitation&#13;
 â&#128;¢ 2002 to 2005 (not including extensions via GPOBA)               solution built (covering about 75% of hardware costs)&#13;
                                                                 â&#128;¢ Limited schemes to facilitate access to credit&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
if they so wish, could potentially be adapted to scenarios where          By contrast, the financing approach in Senegal does not fare well&#13;
service expectations are high. The mechanisms for targeting subsi-        when measured against these criteria, even though the project as a&#13;
dies in Maharashtra could probably be improved, however, as they          whole has been successful at putting on-site sanitation on the map&#13;
suffer from a relatively high exclusion error due to disputed criteria    in Senegal and in neighboring countries. The adopted approach has&#13;
for poverty targeting.                                                    led to high costs that are not affordable to the local population with-&#13;
                                                                          out substantial external support. As a result, the financial sustain-&#13;
The sanitation revolving fund approach in Vietnam was very effec-         ability of the scheme is very fragile. Scaling up such an approach&#13;
tive at leveraging household investments and proved highly sustain-       to reach the countryâ&#128;&#153;s MDGs would simply be beyond Senegalâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
able and scalable. A potential drawback is that the most indigent         means. Elements of this approach could nevertheless be adopted&#13;
are excluded, so they might need to receive direct support, as was        in other settings, such as the provision of output-based subsidies to&#13;
done through several benefit schemes in Vietnam. This approach,           local producers, which was practiced in Mozambique as well.&#13;
based on microcredit, could be replicated in densely populated&#13;
urban areas on the condition that a strong microfinance institution       Finally, the approach in Ecuador worked well, but given the relative&#13;
can be identified and that the credit scheme does not compete with        wealth of the country it might prove too expensive to replicate in&#13;
high subsidies available to all.                                          countries with more limited public funds.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                            www.wsp.org&#13;
&amp;#12;WSP Sanitation Global Practice Team                                                               Financing Household On-Site Sanitation for the Poor                5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Table 3. Case Studies: Summary Evaluation&#13;
 Criteria               Bangladesh            Ecuador                 Maharashtra            Mozambique               Senegal                Vietnam&#13;
 Impact on              Substantial and       Substantial             Very rapid increases   Rapid increases in       Speed of coverage      Rapid extension of&#13;
 sustainable access     rapid increase in     increases in            in coverage (with      coverage only when       increased when         coverage&#13;
                        coverage, mostly      coverage with good      some cases of          software support         required household&#13;
                        sustained             evidence of use         relapse)               was also provided        contribution was&#13;
                                                                                                                      reduced&#13;
 Costs                  Basic sanitation      Comprehensive           Improved sanitation,   Affordable basic         Comprehensive          Costs moderate&#13;
                        costs reasonable      sanitation solutions:   households invest      sanitation solutions,    sanitation solutions   compared to other&#13;
                        when compared to      costly but meet         based on what they     reduced demand           but expensive          programs but high&#13;
                        household income      existing demand         can afford             when incomes grow        by both national       when compared to&#13;
                        (3% to 4%)                                                                                    and international      household incomes&#13;
                                                                                                                      standards&#13;
 Effectiveness in use   High leverage         Low leverage            High leverage          Medium                   Low leverage           Very high&#13;
 of public funds                                                                             leverage                                        leverage&#13;
 Poverty                Effective targeting   Geographical            Means-tested           Self-selection via       Geographical           Effective targeting,&#13;
 targeting              through community     targeting reached       targeting effective    level of service, with   targeting reached      although lowest&#13;
                        involvement           intended recipients     although some are      limited inclusion        intended recipients    income excluded&#13;
                                                                      excluded               error&#13;
 Financial              Sustainable as long   Highly dependent        Low demands on         Dependent on             Highly dependent       Financially&#13;
 sustainability         as public sector      on external             external public        external financing       on external            sustainable: initial&#13;
                        continues to          financing               funds                  (with a marked           financing              public funds have&#13;
                        contribute                                                           decline when                                    revolved many&#13;
                                                                                             subsidies drop)                                 times&#13;
 Scalability            Scale-up achievable   Scale-up could          Has been scaled        Was scaled up in         Too expensive to       Scale-up has been&#13;
                        at a reasonable       be achieved given       up at federal level    major urban centers      scale up nationwide    achieved in country&#13;
                        cost                  relatively high         (coverage still        but further scale-up&#13;
                                              national income         needs to improve)      unlikely&#13;
 Summary                Efficient use of      Only useful for         Efficient use of       Efficient use of         Limited use: high      Very efficient use of&#13;
 evaluation             public funds for      countries willing       public funds, which    public funds with        demand on public       limited public funds&#13;
                        rural settings with   and able to fund        are provided on an     simple and effective     funds and limited      but may be hard to&#13;
                        strong demand for     high levels of          outcome basis          targeting                leverage               replicate&#13;
                        low-cost solutions    service&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table 3 presents a summary of the evaluation based on the six                      it is hard to imagine a sanitation program that does not involve some&#13;
criteria described above.                                                          public or external investment, if only to share information or stimulate&#13;
                                                                                   demand. Given the wide spectrum of options, from a minimal invest-&#13;
KEY LESSONS                                                                        ment in start-up of a revolving fund, to significant community mobiliza-&#13;
The study revealed important lessons about on-site sanitation                      tion and demand stimulation, all the way to hardware subsidies of up&#13;
financing.                                                                         to 75 percent of capital costs in addition to community mobilization,&#13;
                                                                                   the choice is not â&#128;&#156;Subsidy or no subsidy?â&#128;? but, â&#128;&#156;What form and level&#13;
Public funding can trigger significantly increased access to                       of public funding makes sense in a specific context?â&#128;?&#13;
household sanitation. Public investments of varying forms en-&#13;
abled an absolute increase in the fraction of the target population                The different financing strategies adopted had a profound influ-&#13;
gaining access to sanitation, which varied between 20 and 70 per-                  ence on equity, scale, sustainability, levels of service, and costs.&#13;
cent. Each of the programs enabled significant numbers of people                   No project represented a â&#128;&#156;silver bulletâ&#128;? approach that can be repli-&#13;
to improve their sanitationâ&#128;&#148;from the largest (more than 21 million                 cated globally: different models will be more appropriate based on&#13;
gained access in Maharashtra) to the smallest (more than 140,000                   specific project objectives. One indicator of the effectiveness of public&#13;
in Ecuador). Although sanitation projects have earned a reputation                 finance use is the number of households gaining basic access per&#13;
as difficult and often ineffective, there is compelling evidence that              US$1,000 of public funding. Like most indicators, this ration cannot&#13;
government investment can yield results.                                           tell the whole story by itself because both the levels of service offered&#13;
                                                                                   and the costs varied between projects. Nevertheless, it is revealing&#13;
The most relevant question to ask is not â&#128;&#156;Are subsidies good                       that in rural Bangladesh, US$1,000 of public investments resulted in&#13;
or bad?â&#128;? but rather â&#128;&#156;How best can we invest public funds?â&#128;? Al-                     improved sanitation for 135 households, while in Senegal the same&#13;
though much has been written on the dangers of sanitation subsidies,               public funding only served 1.6 households with improved sanitation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
www.wsp.org&#13;
&amp;#12;6   Financing Household On-Site Sanitation for the Poor                                                    WSP Sanitation Global Practice Team&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Households are key investors in on-site sanitation and care-               The provision of hardware subsidies on an output basis rather&#13;
ful project design and implementation can maximize their                   than an input basis can be effective at stimulating demand and&#13;
involvement, satisfaction, and financial investment. All of the            leveraging private investment. Several projects used an output-&#13;
reviewed projects assumed that the poor can contribute to their            based method to deliver subsidies (e.g., Mozambique and Maha-&#13;
own sanitation facilities, and in several cases they paid the bulk of      rashtra). Providing a subsidy on an output basis can ensure that the&#13;
the hardware costs. Poor households can make substantial sanita-           subsidized activity is actually delivered. It can also give incentives&#13;
tion investments (up to 25 or 30 percent of their annual income, as        to producers to reduce costs and to serve areas that they might&#13;
in Vietnam) if they see the need and potential benefits. Leverage of       otherwise not consider. From a donor perspective, output-based&#13;
household investment also varied. In Vietnam, the household con-           subsidies can mitigate some of the risk of low uptake of a subsidy&#13;
tribution to sanitation was 20 times greater than the public invest-       program: If there is no demand (if the product is not appropriate,&#13;
ment, whereas in three other projects public investment exceeded           if it is incorrectly priced, etc.), there is no output and therefore no&#13;
the household investment. The Vietnam example also shows that              payment. The provision of financial rewards based on outcomes&#13;
access to household credit (and thus the opportunity to spread the         acted as a strong motivator for villages in Bangladesh and Maha-&#13;
investment over time) can be an effective mechanism to make basic          rashtra and helped mobilize energies around the achievement of&#13;
sanitation affordable.                                                     clear goals.&#13;
&#13;
Hardware subsidies of some form played a critical role in all              All of the projects included a significant publicly funded soft-&#13;
six case studies. Subsidies varied from a subsidized interest rate         ware component (sanitation and hygiene promotion and com-&#13;
yielding US$6 per septic tank in Vietnam to subsidies between              munity mobilization). The Maharashtra and Bangladesh projects&#13;
US$200 and US$1,000 in Senegal, depending on the techni-                   invested heavily in software (with targeted hardware subsidies for&#13;
cal options selected. On the one hand, subsidies targeted within           the poorest) and had some of the highest leverage and basic-&#13;
communities to the very poorest have enabled the achievement of            access-to-investment ratios of all projects studied. The Mozam-&#13;
Open Defecation Free (ODF) status by communities in the DISHARI            bique project was most effective when the government also&#13;
project in Bangladesh; on the other hand, when a high proportion           financed community animators for demand promotion. The decline&#13;
of substantial hardware costs are subsidized, as in Senegal and            of the program was closely linked to the withdrawal of such soft-&#13;
Ecuador, a higher level of service is achieved, but this might limit the   ware support following decentralization.&#13;
potential scale of interventions to a relatively limited set of people&#13;
given a restricted budget.                                                 IMPLICATIONS FOR PRACTITIONERS&#13;
                                                                           The findings from this study present strong evidence to support&#13;
Subsidy targeting methods must be tailored to country cir-                 appropriate public investment in sanitation. Given the range of pos-&#13;
cumstances. There was a range of targeting methods for hardware            sible approaches to financing sanitation (Table 4), the challenge is&#13;
subsidies, including geographic targeting, means-tested target-            to choose an approach that matches the local context. Going for-&#13;
ing, community-based targeting, and self-selection. Community-             ward, some points to consider include:&#13;
based targeting (in which the community itself manages the identi-&#13;
fication and support of its poorest members) and self-selection (in        Early planning and careful design of financial arrangements&#13;
which only in-kind support for the most basic sanitation is offered,       for sanitation at the start can go a long way toward promot-&#13;
leading to self-selection among potential subsidy applicants) ap-          ing project realism and sustainability. Financial arrangements&#13;
pear to be more effective than means-tested systems, which can             probably shape the success or failure of sanitation projects more&#13;
be costly and generate perverse incentives. Community-based                than any other factor. Answers to the basic questions of financeâ&#128;&#148;&#13;
selection appears to be a more flexible, better targeted, and prob-        â&#128;&#156;Who pays for what, when, and how?â&#128;?â&#128;&#148;determine the extent to&#13;
ably less costly way to identify poor households, but it requires          which projects can replicate, expand sanitation, and meet house-&#13;
the right type of community mobilization and solidarity. Although          hold needs. Projects with financial designs that match local needs&#13;
no precise data were available to confirm whether self-selection is        and capacities can take off, while projects with poor or unrealistic&#13;
an effective targeting approach, this method appeared to be the            financial designs will stall at the end of the project cycle. Sanitation&#13;
cheapest and easiest to implement. This would seem most ap-                finance is thus a key element of project design, yet one that often&#13;
propriate for those countries that have limited means to introduce         lags because of the paucity of information, options, and sound&#13;
either means-tested or community-based targeting approaches                analysis rooted in local conditions. In most urban water supply and&#13;
but seek to reach a large population through a basic sanitation            sanitation (WSS) projects, for example, there has inevitably been&#13;
program (such as in Mozambique, where improved latrines are                some experience with water tariffs, and often some experience with&#13;
subsidized).                                                               sewer connection charges. With some important exceptions, utility&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                      www.wsp.org&#13;
&amp;#12;WSP Sanitation Global Practice Team                                                                  Financing Household On-Site Sanitation for the Poor               7&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Table 4. Potential Financing Approaches for On-Site Sanitation&#13;
Financing approach                         Potential advantages                                       Potential risks&#13;
Financing sources: Purely private (households)&#13;
Self-financing: Households invest in       â&#128;¢ Majority of latrines are currently financed privately    â&#128;¢ Risk of poor quality infrastructure&#13;
their own facilities and pay for sludge-     this way                                                 â&#128;¢ Does not fully consider environmental impact&#13;
emptying servicesâ&#128;&#148;no subsidy               â&#128;¢ Reflects existing demand                                 â&#128;¢ Suppliers may not exist&#13;
                                           â&#128;¢ No use of public funds                                   â&#128;¢ Unaffordable for the very poor&#13;
Sanitation surcharge: Cross-subsidy to     â&#128;¢ Use of cross-subsidies                                   â&#128;¢ Available funds may be limited due to affordability&#13;
finance on-site sanitation                                                                              constraints&#13;
Financing sources: Combination of private (household) and public funds (taxpayer monies and external sources)&#13;
Loans to households, including             â&#128;¢ Particularly useful in cohesive communities              â&#128;¢ Demand for sanitation needs to be stimulated&#13;
microcredit for sanitation or home           aiming at 100% sanitation                                â&#128;¢ Requires a solid institution to manage funds&#13;
improvement (e.g., revolving funds)        â&#128;¢ Limits initial outlay of public funds                    â&#128;¢ May be unaffordable for the very poor&#13;
                                           â&#128;¢ Subsidy linked to outcome&#13;
Software support, with low/no subsidy      â&#128;¢ Focuses subsidies on creating demand                     â&#128;¢ Sustainability at risk once the initial attention / champion&#13;
for hardware                               â&#128;¢ Relies on community cohesion/ solidarity                   or other motivating factor disappears&#13;
Loans to private-sector providers          â&#128;¢ Lift constraints for small scale independent             â&#128;¢ Services may not reach the very poor&#13;
                                             providers (SSIPs) to expand their services               â&#128;¢ Not sufficient demand to keep the business running if not&#13;
                                                                                                        combined with hygiene &amp; sanitation promotion&#13;
Non-financial support to providers         â&#128;¢ Boosts private-sector development so that                â&#128;¢ Services may not reach the very poor&#13;
(training, demand creation)                  supply can meet demand for sanitation facilities&#13;
Output-based aid: Grants to households     â&#128;¢ Subsidy linked to actual outputs delivered               â&#128;¢ Requires private sector prefinancing, which may not be&#13;
or SSIPs based on outputs or outcomes                                                                   forthcoming&#13;
Partial hardware subsidy: Users            â&#128;¢ Enhances ownership of facility                           â&#128;¢ May be unaffordable for the very poor&#13;
contribute in kind or in cash              â&#128;¢ Improves affordability                                   â&#128;¢ May be an unsustainable drain on resources&#13;
Financing source: Purely public (taxpayer monies and external sources)&#13;
Full subsidy: Households receive facilities â&#128;¢ Removes affordability constraint for the very poor â&#128;¢ Can crowd out household resources&#13;
as a gift                                     (if they capture the subsidy)                      â&#128;¢ No demand test, so facilities often not used&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
or government policies promoting or financing on-site sanitation                   level and form of public investment in sanitation. Many sector&#13;
are often nonexistent or, at best, ad hoc. In rural areas, the lack of             specialists are frustrated after decades of unrealistic, poorly de-&#13;
documented examples and options has until now often limited the                    signed and administered subsidy programs. They have noted that&#13;
scope to â&#128;&#156;what weâ&#128;&#153;ve always done.â&#128;?                                                 such programs are unsustainable, and have the perverse effect of&#13;
                                                                                   stifling the development of real sanitation markets for the poor, as&#13;
It is important to monitor financial approaches during imple-                      both suppliers and consumers waited for the next round of subsi-&#13;
mentation. Good real-time data is needed to help governments                       dies before investing. This frustration has recently been expressed&#13;
improve their sanitation programs and financing approaches and                     by some who have taken a simplistic â&#128;&#156;no subsidyâ&#128;? position, arguing&#13;
learn from experience. This means collecting basic data on the                     from the correct observation that hardware subsidies can some-&#13;
costs of promotion, the costs of hardware subsidies, the contribu-                 times limit sustainability to the invalid conclusion that hardware sub-&#13;
tions made by households, and so on. Building in such data col-                    sidies are always unjustified and counterproductive.&#13;
lection and analysis from the outset will improve project monitoring&#13;
and the supervision of these crucial elements of implementation                    This study showed that a wide spectrum of finance arrangements&#13;
during the projectâ&#128;&#153;s lifetime.                                                     has been used with varying degrees of success. Experience teaches&#13;
                                                                                   that sanitation, like other goods with significant externalities, does&#13;
Operational staff must look beyond the semantics of simplis-                       not â&#128;&#156;take care of itself,â&#128;? especially among the poor. The study makes&#13;
tic â&#128;&#156;subsidy vs. no subsidyâ&#128;? debates to define an appropriate                      a strong argument for the benefits of appropriate public investment&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
www.wsp.org&#13;
&amp;#12;8   Financing Household On-Site Sanitation for the Poor                                                  WSP Sanitation Global Practice Team&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
in sanitation. The challenge is to define ap-         Hawkins (WSP), Guy Hutton (WSP), Bill&#13;
propriate approaches, shares, and mecha-              Kingdom (World Bank), Andreas Knapp&#13;
                                                                                                         Full Report&#13;
                                                                                                         See Financing On-Site Sanitation for&#13;
nisms to finance sanitation for the poor that         (UNICEF), Yogita Mumssem (World Bank),&#13;
                                                                                                         the Poor: A Six Country Comparative&#13;
match the specific local context.                     Jan-Willem Rosenboom (Bill and Melinda             Review and Analysis (WSP 2010), by&#13;
                                                      Gates Foundation), David Schaub-Jones              Sophie TrÃ©molet with Pete Kolsky and&#13;
               â&#128;&#148;By Sophie TrÃ©molet with               (Building Partnerships for Development),           Eddy Perez&#13;
              Pete Kolsky and Eddy Perez              Maria-Angelica Sotomayor (World Bank),             www.wsp.org/wsp/sites/wsp.org/files/&#13;
                                                                                                         publications/financing_analysis.pdf&#13;
                                                      Caroline Van den Berg (World Bank), and&#13;
Acknowledgements                                      Almud Weitz (WSP). The following authors&#13;
The following people peer-reviewed the                contributed the research and writing for           Additional Reading&#13;
methodological approach underlying the                the country case studies: Shafiul Azam             Sanitation Finance in Rural Cambodia:&#13;
report and/or peer reviewed the original              Ahmed (Bangladesh), Patricio Arrata,               Review and Recommendations (WSP&#13;
study: Oscar Alvarado (World Bank),                   ICA Consultores (Ecuador), ChimÃ¨re                 2010), by Andy Robinson&#13;
                                                                                                         www.wsscc.org/sites/default/files/&#13;
Isabel Blackett (WSP), Ousseynou Diop                 Diop and Ousseynou GuÃ¨ne (Senegal),&#13;
                                                                                                         publications/wsp_adb_sanitation_finance_&#13;
(WSP), Barbara Evans (independent                     Alan Malina (Mozambique), Rajiv Raman              rural_cambodia_2010.pdf&#13;
consultant), Vivien Foster (World Bank),              (Maharashtra), and Cu Thuy and Mai Van&#13;
                                                                                                         Output-Based Aid and Sustainable&#13;
Jonathan Halpern (World Bank), Peter                  Huyen (Vietnam).&#13;
                                                                                                         Sanitation (WSP 2010), by Sophie&#13;
                                                                                                         TrÃ©molet and Barbara Evans&#13;
                                                                                                         www.wsp.org/wsp/sites/wsp.org/files/&#13;
                                                                                                         publications/WSP_OBA_sanitation.pdf&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                         Output-Based Aid and Sustainable&#13;
                                                                                                         Sanitation (WSP 2010), by Sophie&#13;
                                                                                                         TrÃ©molet and Barbara Evans&#13;
                                                                                                         www.wsp.org/wsp/sites/wsp.org/files/&#13;
                                                                                                         publications/WSP_OBA_sanitation.pdf&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                         Contact Us&#13;
                                                                                                         For more information please visit&#13;
                                                                                                         www.wsp.org or email Eddy Perez&#13;
                                                                                                         at wsp@worldbank.org.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
WSP is a multi-donor partnership created in 1978 and administered by the World Bank to support&#13;
poor people in obtaining affordable, safe, and sustainable access to water and sanitation services.&#13;
WSPâ&#128;&#153;s donors include Australia, Austria, Canada, Denmark, Finland, France, the Bill &amp; Melinda Gates&#13;
Foundation, Ireland, Luxembourg, Netherlands, Norway, Sweden, Switzerland, United Kingdom,&#13;
United States, and the World Bank.&#13;
&#13;
The findings, interpretations, and conclusions expressed herein are entirely those of the author and&#13;
should not be attributed to the World Bank or its affiliated organizations, or to members of the Board&#13;
of Executive Directors of the World Bank or the governments they represent.&#13;
&#13;
Â© 2011 Water and Sanitation Program&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="16711979">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2011/04/16711979/financing-household-on-site-sanitation-poor
        </url>
        <availablein>Spanish,English</availablein>
        <fullavailablein>
            <available_in lang="Spanish" entityid="000356161_20130409160135" node_id="16711979"/>
        </fullavailablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2011/04/16711979/financing-household-on-site-sanitation-poor</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2011/04/16711979/financing-household-on-site-sanitation-poor</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2012-09-07T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2012-09-07T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2012/09/07/000425962_20120907102445/Rendered/INDEX/722580BRI0Box30ite0Sanitation0Brief.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2012/09/07/000425962_20120907102445/Rendered/PDF/722580BRI0Box30ite0Sanitation0Brief.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2012-09-07T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2011-04-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Financing household on-site sanitation for
            the poor
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            In 2010, WSP and the World Bank
            conducted a study to improve understanding of the financing
            of on-site sanitation at the household level through careful
            analysis of practical field experiences in a wide range of
            programs. This Research Brief summarizes findings from the
            full report. The study formulated a set of basic questions
            to help identify the best-performing approaches and the
            relevant factors and issues to consider in designing a
            sanitation financing strategy. These included: How much does
            provision of access to on-site sanitation cost once all
            costs (hardware and software) are accounted for? Do the type
            and scale of sanitation subsidy affect provision and uptake?
            How? How can the public sector most effectively support
            household investment in on-site sanitation? Should support
            be via investment in demand stimulation, subsidies to
            households or suppliers, credit schemes, or by other means?
            Should hardware subsidies be provided or should public
            spending focus on promoting demand or supporting the supply
            side of the market? Where hardware subsidies are adopted,
            what is the best way to ensure that they reach their
            intended recipients and are sustainable and scalable? What
            innovative mechanisms (such as credit or revolving funds)
            can be used to promote household sanitation financing? The
            study reviewed alternative financing approaches from
            programs representing a range of approaches, from those that
            combined support for software activities with limited
            targeted hardware subsidies for poor households to
            approaches with a relatively high hardware subsidy. The
            diversity in financing approaches was also reflected in
            different approaches to program design, with programs
            ranging from community-led programs for investment in basic
            sanitation to programs providing a well-defined set of
            improved sanitation solutions.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Financing household on-site sanitation for
            the poor
        </docna>
        <display_title>Financing household on-site
            sanitation for the poor</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2011/04/16711979/financing-household-on-site-sanitation-poor</listing_relative_url>
        <subtopic>Rural Poverty Reduction,Access to Finance,Urban Water Supply and Sanitation,Health and Sanitation,Hygiene Promotion and Social Marketing</subtopic>
        <docty>UNDP-Water &amp; Sanitation Program</docty>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Poverty Reduction,Water Supply and Sanitation,Health, Nutrition and Population</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000425962_20120907102445</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>Water and Sanitation Program : Research Brief</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Poverty Reduction,Water Supply and Sanitation,Health, Nutrition and Population</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            access to credit, access to sanitation,
            access to services, access to water, affordability,
            alternative financing, benefits of sanitation, capital
            costs, credit scheme, credit schemes, cross-subsidies,
            demand for sanitation, Diarrhea, disease transmission,
            drain, Drinking Water, Evaluation Criteria, Exchange Rate,
            exclusion, expenditure, external financing, financial
            support, Financial sustainability, government policies, home
            improvement, household income, household incomes, household
            investment, household investments, household needs,
            household sanitation, households, hygiene, hygiene
            education, hygiene promotion, inadequate sanitation,
            interest rate, interest rates, latrine, Latrines, loan fund,
            media campaigns, microcredit, microfinance, microfinance
            institution, Poor, poor households, poor people, private
            investment, provision of access, public finance, public
            funds, public investment, Public investments, public
            spending, public subsidies, Revolving Fund, revolving funds,
            revolving loan, rural, rural areas, rural settings, safety,
            safety net, SANITATION, sanitation access, sanitation
            facilities, Sanitation Facility, Sanitation Improvements,
            SANITATION PROGRAM, sanitation projects, sanitation
            promotion, sanitation services, Sanitation solutions,
            Self-financing, septic tank, septic tanks, sewer connection,
            sewerage, sewerage networks, Site Sanitation, sources of
            finance, sources of funds, start-up, Subsidy targeting,
            targeting, technical support, toilet, Total Sanitation,
            urban areas, urban centers, urban water, urban water supply,
            users, villages, water tariffs
        </keywd>
        <owner>Water- Water and Sanit Prgrm (GWASP)</owner>
        <repnb>72258</repnb>
        <alt_title>
            Financiando el saneamiento in situ para
            los pobres
        </alt_title>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Arts and Culture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Gender</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Poverty Reduction Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>BoD</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Cost of Disease</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Impact of Disease</ml:concept><ml:concept>Safety Nets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Safety Nets and Transfers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Safety Nets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wastewater Collection and Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Basic Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>On-site Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Marketing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Basic Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Management of Public Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Finance Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Finances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Economics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Economics &amp; Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Efficiency of Public Expenditures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Expenditures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Financial Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Spending</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Expenditures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Investment Plan</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Media</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Structures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply</ml:concept><ml:concept>Diseases</ml:concept><ml:concept>Burden of Disease</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water, Sanitation and Hygiene</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Assistance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sewerage</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Onsite Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Managing Public Finances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Investment Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Services</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>