<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>ï»¿WATER AND SANITATION PROGRAM: LEARNING NOTE&#13;
                                                                                                                             64855&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Global Scaling Up Handwashing Project&#13;
                                                                                                            Key findings&#13;
Tanzania: A Handwashing                                                                                     â&#128;¢ While designing a behavior change&#13;
                                                                                                              intervention from an evidence base is&#13;
Behavior Change Journey                                                                                       critical, limited formative research can&#13;
                                                                                                              be analyzed in the FOAM framework&#13;
October 2011                                                                                                  and information gaps can be filled&#13;
                                                                                                              with small-scale spot research.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                            â&#128;¢ Designing a behavior change&#13;
                                                                                                              communication campaign across&#13;
                                                                                                              mutually reinforcing channels may&#13;
INTRODUCTION                                                                                                  prove to be a particularly effective&#13;
In Tanzania, nearly 30,000 people die                   rural districts5 with end-of-project tar-             approach to changing behaviors.&#13;
annually due to diarrheal diseases1 and                 gets that included 1.25 million women&#13;
an estimated 12.6 percent of children                   and children practicing improved hand-              â&#128;¢ Behavior change often takes place&#13;
suffer from diarrheal diseases.2 There                  washing behaviors; 14.5 million women                 through an evolving process;&#13;
is a widespread and deep-rooted belief                  and children ages 5 to 14 exposed to                  programs designed to be multi-&#13;
that diarrhea is part of growing up and                 behavior change messaging through                     phased, with evolving objectives, may&#13;
cannot be prevented. Working with the                   the radio; 300,000 women and children                 help support behavior shifts.&#13;
government and with non-governmen-                      reached through Interpersonal Com-&#13;
tal organizations, the Water and Sanita-                munication (IPC) activities; and the at-&#13;
tion Program (WSP) sought to increase                   tendance of 170,000 people at Direct&#13;
rates of handwashing with soap among                    Consumer Contact (DCC) events. To&#13;
women and children, especially at criti-                analyze the health and poverty im-&#13;
cal junctures.                                          pacts, intervention areas were selected&#13;
                                                        to produce a representative sample of&#13;
Initial support started in 2005 with                    the general population.&#13;
the development of the Public-Private&#13;
Partnership for Handwashing3 and                        This Learning Note documents the de-&#13;
small-scale formative research which                    velopment of the project, with a focus&#13;
showed that while knowledge of the                      on how it was designed, implemented,&#13;
reasons to wash hands was high, the                     and monitored. Challenges and lessons&#13;
practice was low, with just four percent                learned are highlighted to assist program&#13;
of mothers and five percent of children                 managers in designing and manag-&#13;
reporting that they wash hands with                     ing evidence-based handwashing with&#13;
soap.4 In 2006, WSP began to scale up                   soap and/or other hygiene promotion&#13;
the handwashing program across ten                      programs.&#13;
&#13;
1&#13;
  WHO. 2006 Mortality Fact Sheet, http://www.who.int/whosis/mort/profiles/mort_afro_tza_tanzania.pdf&#13;
2&#13;
  Tanzania DHS. 2004-05 Final Report, http://www.measuredhs.com/pubs/pub_details.cfm?ID=566&amp;ctry_&#13;
  id=39&amp;SrchTp=ctry&#13;
3&#13;
  For more information, see http://www.globalhandwashing.org&#13;
4&#13;
  TMS International. 2006. Understanding the Tanzanian Consumer in Respect to Handwashing with Soap.&#13;
5&#13;
  The ten districts are Masasi, Rufiji, Iringa, Sumbawanga, Mpwapwa, Kiteto, Kondoa, Karagwe, Igunga, and&#13;
  Musoma.&#13;
&amp;#12;2    Tanzania: A Handwashing Behavior Change Journey                                                                 Global Scaling Up Handwashing Project&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 1: FOAM Framework                                                                handwashing behavior (Figure 1). Communication objectives&#13;
                                                                                        were identified based on the identification of determinants&#13;
         Focus           pp       y&#13;
                        Opportunity           Ability         Motivation                (Figure 2) and these were shared with the Government of&#13;
                           Access/                             Belief and               Tanzania and key stakeholders to facilitate engagement&#13;
         Target           availability                         attitudes&#13;
                                            Knowledge&#13;
        behavior                                                                        throughout the process.&#13;
                                                               Outcome&#13;
                           Product                            expectations&#13;
                          attributes                                                    Additional research was conducted to test preliminary cre-&#13;
         Target                                Social            Threat                 ative concepts developed at a multi-sectoral workshop. In&#13;
       population           Social            support&#13;
                            norms                               Intention&#13;
                                                                                        order to identify the â&#128;&#156;triggerâ&#128;? that would motivate women to&#13;
                                                                                        improve their handwashing behavior, representatives from the&#13;
                                                                                        hygiene sector generated several creative concepts based on&#13;
                                                                                        the results of the formative research, their own experience,&#13;
ACTION                                                                                  and a field visit. These were tested with rural women at focus&#13;
Research                                                                                group sessions led by marketing research specialists who&#13;
The teamâ&#128;&#153;s first steps toward developing an evidence-based                              worked at a private sector soap company providing tech-&#13;
behavior change program focused on gathering and con-                                   nical support to the partnership. An important insight was&#13;
ducting research to better understand the target audienceâ&#128;&#148;                              that mothers felt burdened with responsibility for raising chil-&#13;
including current understandings, feelings, and actions                                 dren, but were rarely thanked or rewarded, and asking them&#13;
toward handwashing.                                                                     to focus on handwashing with soap was felt to be an extra&#13;
                                                                                        burden. Two ideas emerged from this experience, â&#128;&#156;Mother is&#13;
Initial formative research indicated that people would tend to                          the Pillar of the Homeâ&#128;? (â&#128;&#156;Mama Nguzoâ&#128;?) and â&#128;&#156;Heroes Make&#13;
rinse hands when they were visibly dirty, but that the use                              Heroes.â&#128;? Both concepts acknowledged mothers for all they&#13;
of soap for handwashing was not widespread. Additionally,                               didâ&#128;&#148;including teaching handwashing with soapâ&#128;&#148;rather than&#13;
respondents indicated that handwashing with soap was an                                 rebuking them for what was not done.&#13;
extra burden and many of those surveyed felt they were too&#13;
busy to wash their hands with soap.&#13;
                                                                                        Design&#13;
Findings from the formative research were analyzed using                                Following testing, a creative brief was developed at a multi-sec-&#13;
FOAM,6 a framework designed to identify behavioral deter-                               toral workshop (Figure 3). The brief was provided to an advertis-&#13;
minants for handwashing, and their relative role in shaping                             ing agency that ultimately developed the communications idea&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 2: Mapping Formative Research Findings to FOAM Determinants and Communication Objectives&#13;
&#13;
                                                                        FOAM&#13;
                                      g&#13;
                       Research Finding                               Determinant                              Communication Objectives&#13;
         Soap and water are not often located near the                                               Have mothers believe it is easy to ensure that soap&#13;
                                                                            Access&#13;
                   latrine or cooking area                                                             and water are easily available for handwashing&#13;
&#13;
                                                                             Social              Everyone routinely uses soap when washing hands and that&#13;
       Low prioritization of using soap while handwashing&#13;
                                                                             Norms                washing hands without soap is not effective handwashing.&#13;
&#13;
            Low practice of handwashing with soap&#13;
                                                                        Knowledge                  Have mothers understand the danger of invisible germs&#13;
                        after defecation&#13;
&#13;
                There are no visual cues to make                                                  Have mothers construct handwashing stations to act as&#13;
                                                                            Intention&#13;
                     handwashing habitual                                                                  reminders to wash hands with soap&#13;
&#13;
                                                                             Social                  Have mothers believe that by washing their hands,&#13;
            People who do not wash hands are filthy&#13;
                                                                             Beliefs                       they are a good community member&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
6&#13;
    See Y. Coombes and J. Devine, Introducing FOAM: A Framework to Analyze Handwashing Behaviors to Design Effective Handwashing Programs. Available at http://&#13;
    www.wsp.org/wsp/sites/wsp.org/files/publications/WSP_IntroducingFOAM_HWWS.pdf&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                    www.wsp.org&#13;
&amp;#12;Global Scaling Up Handwashing Project                                                      Tanzania: A Handwashing Behavior Change Journey     3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 3: Summary of Creative Brief&#13;
&#13;
     The job to be done:      To have mothers believe in their hearts that handwashing with soap is a critical part of their role as strong,&#13;
                              resourceful caregivers of the family and that it is simple and easy to do&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
              What the Audience Does, Thinks, Feels Today                          What We Want Them to Do, Think, Feel Tomorrow&#13;
&#13;
     Does&#13;
     If hands are visibly dirty, they will wash hands with water (no soap)      Always wash hands with soap after defecation and before&#13;
     or else just wipe hands on clothes                                         handling food&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Thinks&#13;
     â&#128;¢ Handwashing with soap is an extra burdenâ&#128;&#148;too busy to do it              â&#128;¢ Handwashing with soap is simple and quick&#13;
     â&#128;¢ Diarrhea is part of growing up                                          â&#128;¢ Handwashing with soap makes life easierâ&#128;&#148;saves money&#13;
     â&#128;¢ Generations before have survived without soap                           â&#128;¢ Handwashing with soap will have an impact on a childâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
                                                                                 wellbeing&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Feels&#13;
     â&#128;¢ They are surviving                                                      â&#128;¢ Finally, my role as a mother is recognized&#13;
     â&#128;¢ Their family trusts them when it comes to managing the                  â&#128;¢ Empowered that handwashing with soap can help care for&#13;
       household and hygiene issues                                              their children&#13;
     â&#128;¢ They feel nobody notices their efforts                                  â&#128;¢ Feel proud about the role they play&#13;
                                                                               â&#128;¢ We have found a solution and are less burdened&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
â&#128;&#156;Mikono Yenye Fahariâ&#128;? (â&#128;&#156;Hands To Be Proud Ofâ&#128;?). This concept                 health centersâ&#128;&#148;were carried out by Front-Line Activators&#13;
formed the backbone of the campaign: it tapped into mothersâ&#128;&#153;                 (FLAs). Village Executive Officers selected this unpaid, vol-&#13;
aspirations for recognition, their pride in the work they do for their       unteer, community-based cadre of women (and occasionally&#13;
families, and their role as the central pillar of the family. The de-        men) for their self-motivation. Working through FLAs ensured&#13;
sign went through several iterations and was pre-tested through              not only that skills acquired through the training would remain&#13;
focus groups and key informant interviews. Spot research was                 in the community but also that messages would be delivered&#13;
also undertaken to close gaps in the evidence base, particularly             by a source respected by the community. The vision for this&#13;
around beliefs and knowledge about the link between hand-                    volunteer cadre was that they would serve their immediate&#13;
washing with soap and acute respiratory infection.                           communities and take advantage of day-to-day activities to&#13;
                                                                             promote handwashing with soap. Because they would be&#13;
IMPLEMENTATION                                                               disassociated from an institutional structure, it would also be&#13;
Integrated Channels                                                          more possible to avoid nepotism and to ensure the hand-&#13;
Key messages were promoted through multiple integrated chan-                 washing with soap duties were not lost in the list of duties&#13;
nels, which has been shown to be effective for behavior change in            assigned to village level officials. Working with local govern-&#13;
other sectors such as HIV/AIDS, malaria, and reproductive health.            ment authorities, 45 FLAs were selected and trained in each&#13;
When an individual receives a consistent message through multi-              district, reaching a total of 450 trained. While FLAs are not&#13;
ple channels it reinforces social norms around the behavior. Mes-            part of any institution or government structure, they served&#13;
saging across three channels, mass media, Direct Consumer                    as a resource to promote hygiene to Village Executive Of-&#13;
Contact (DCC) and Interpersonal Communication (IPC) was har-                 ficers, Ward Executive Officers, and district-level officials.&#13;
monized by the development of a single creative brief.&#13;
                                                                             Direct Consumer Contact events complemented IPC ac-&#13;
Mass media offers constant reminders and cues to action.                     tivities with a goal of improving their audiencesâ&#128;&#153; knowledge,&#13;
Radio was selected as the mass media carrier based on re-                    especially their knowledge of the ease of handwashing with&#13;
search that indicated that television coverage was low and                   soap. DCC was chosen because public events have been&#13;
radio influence high in rural areas.                                         effective in commercial marketing to raise the enthusiasm of&#13;
                                                                             participants for a topic and help shifts social norms. Addi-&#13;
Interpersonal Communication can target building knowledge                    tionally, these events were a logical channel to improve the&#13;
and skills. Activitiesâ&#128;&#148;including visits to homes, schools, and               access portion of the opportunity determinant by introducing&#13;
www.wsp.org&#13;
&amp;#12;4   Tanzania: A Handwashing Behavior Change Journey                                                                   Global Scaling Up Handwashing Project&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
the tippy-tap, an enabling technology for handwashing7,                              on Sustain (Stage 5) began in June 2011 through radio com-&#13;
which many audience members had not seen before.                                     munication and IPC and will be maintained as the Global&#13;
                                                                                     Scaling Up Handwashing Project is integrated into Scaling&#13;
Arrangement and Strategy                                                             Up Rural Sanitation, a large-scale initiative that is being im-&#13;
The implementation arrangement, led by WSP, included gov-                            plemented by the Government of Tanzania with technical as-&#13;
ernment representatives, private firms, and community mem-                           sistance from WSP.8&#13;
bers (see Box 1). From the early planning stages, stakeholders&#13;
were considered part of the team, and their input and buy-in                         Phase I: Awaken and Inspire&#13;
was considered crucial. Introducing a behavior-change in-&#13;
                                                                                     Phase I focused on increasing knowledge about the impor-&#13;
tervention of this type required stakeholders to adopt a new&#13;
                                                                                     tance of using soap, critical times for handwashing, and inspir-&#13;
approach to hygiene interventions. In Tanzania, previous initia-&#13;
                                                                                     ing women to prioritize handwashing. This phase targeted the&#13;
tives had been largely didactic, education-driven approaches,&#13;
                                                                                     knowledge portion of the ability determinant, based on forma-&#13;
and it required considerable time to get stakeholders to accept&#13;
                                                                                     tive research that showed key gaps in understanding about the&#13;
a new approach. Efforts to engage stakeholders throughout&#13;
                                                                                     importance of handwashing with soap.&#13;
the process strengthened support, increasing opportunities&#13;
for both scale-up and sustainability.                                                Mass media, including radio spots, call-in shows, and DJ-&#13;
                                                                                     mentions,9 focused on when to wash hands with soap. Pro-&#13;
A marketing team from a private soap company developed a&#13;
                                                                                     grams aired on national stations and one regional station&#13;
five-stage, phased approach to help carry the target audience&#13;
                                                                                     between February and April 2009. Handwashing posters&#13;
from an initial stage, becoming aware of the importance of&#13;
                                                                                     were also produced and distributed.&#13;
handwashing, to building skills to conduct improved handwash-&#13;
ing, to sustaining handwashing with soap behavior (Figure 4).                        IPC focused on building knowledge and skills to build tippy-&#13;
Phase I, including Awaken (Stage 1) and Inspire (Stage 2)                            taps, managing availability of soap and water, and hand-&#13;
was implemented from February 2009 to March 2010; Phase                              washing at critical times.&#13;
2, including Empower (Stage 3) and Amplify (Stage 4) was&#13;
conducted from July 2010 to June 2011. Phase 3, focusing                             DCC events focused on improving knowledge around the&#13;
                                                                                     ease of handwashing with soap and introducing the tippy-&#13;
    BOX 1: IMPLEMENTATION ARRANGEMENT                                                tap, which many participants had not seen before. Events&#13;
                                                                                     were carried out by two teams: â&#128;&#156;Pathfindersâ&#128;? targeted&#13;
    Activity                                Implementing Agency                      smaller communities with a program that included a sound&#13;
    Formative research                      Research firm                            truck, master of ceremonies, and dancers; â&#128;?Handwashersâ&#128;?&#13;
    Research analysis                       WSP                                      targeted larger villages with a program that included music,&#13;
                                                                                     dancers, skits, and tippy-tap demonstrations. Events lasted&#13;
    Communications concept                  Private firm&#13;
                                                                                     a couple of hours, but were filmed, quickly edited, and then&#13;
    Mass media production and               Private firm&#13;
                                                                                     shown again at night to reach a wider audience. An esti-&#13;
    planning&#13;
                                                                                     mated 161,000 women and children (95 percent of the tar-&#13;
    DCC development and                     Private firm&#13;
                                                                                     get figure) were reached in just seven months, starting in&#13;
    execution&#13;
                                                                                     August 2009.&#13;
    IPC materials                           WSP&#13;
    IPC training (Training of               WSP and private firm                     Several learnings emerged during this phase. First, FLAs were&#13;
    Trainers)                                                                        trained to deliver messages using an emotive approach. Re-&#13;
    IPC delivery                            Community volunteers                     ports began to indicate, however, that FLAs were experiencing&#13;
    Monitoring                              WSP and private firms                    difficulties conveying knowledge and skills using an emotive&#13;
                                                                                     approach. Messages were refined to create a more pragmatic&#13;
&#13;
7&#13;
  For more information on tippy-taps and other enabling technologies for handwashing with soap, see WSPâ&#128;&#153;s Enabling Technologies for Handwashing Database at&#13;
  www.wsp.org/scalinguphandwashing/enablingtechnologies.&#13;
8&#13;
  For more information, see www.wsp.org/scalingupsanitation&#13;
9&#13;
  â&#128;&#156;DJ-mentionsâ&#128;? are a subtle way to convey the handwashing message. For example, DJs invite callers to explain why their mothers are heroes. The caller might&#13;
  mention that their mother made sure they were well dressed every day, or that their mother took care of them when they were sick. The DJ might then segue to the&#13;
  handwashing message by mentioning, â&#128;&#156;Isnâ&#128;&#153;t in wonderful how mothers do so much for us, like teaching us to wash our hands with soap?â&#128;?&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                       www.wsp.org&#13;
&amp;#12;              Figure 4: Campaign Stages&#13;
                              Advertising            Public Relations              Partnerships                  Experiential            Response          Consumer Promotions&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
www.wsp.org&#13;
              Purpose             Salience                 Credibility                Association                 Engagement              Relationship             Conversion&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                     Relevance via               Engagement via         Relationship via&#13;
                Role       Persuasion via salience   Inï¬&#130;uence via credibility                                                                                Conversion via incentive&#13;
                                                                                      association                  experience             recognition&#13;
&#13;
                                   Image                     Trust                      Values                     Interaction                Trial                   Trial&#13;
              Channel            Immediacy              Rapid Response                 Content                     Immersion                 Loyalty                Urgency&#13;
                Use             Reassurance                  News                    Endorsement                      Depth              Personiï¬?cations            Proximity&#13;
                                   Stature               Endorsement                   Prestige                   Participation              Reward                  Reward&#13;
&#13;
                Stage&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                        Global Scaling Up Handwashing Project&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                           Radio and print on        News coverage              Promoting buy-in;          DCC and IPC on&#13;
                           key junctures for         of campaign                training local, national   key junctures and&#13;
                 1         handwashing with          in newspapers              government on              importance of soap&#13;
               Awaken      soap and the                                         handwashing with soap&#13;
                           importance of soap                                                              DCC and IPCâ&#128;&#148;&#13;
                                                                                                           constructing tippy-taps&#13;
                           Wall branding                                                                   and washing hands&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                     Radio phone-in with        Soap packaging with        Radio phone-in with       Promotional items      DCC and IPCâ&#128;&#148;&#13;
                   2                                 handwashing with           messages                   handwashing with soap                            constructing tippy-taps&#13;
                Inspire                              soap experts                                          experts                                          and washing hands and&#13;
                                                                                                                                                            winning promotional items&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                           Radio soap opera                                                                IPC and DCC promoting     Tippy-taps comic        DCC events for mothers&#13;
                  3                                                                                        mother as heroes ready                            as heroes ready for&#13;
               Empower                                                                                     for competition           Radio soap opera        competition&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                           Tippy-taps comic&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                           Radio sponsorship for     News coverage              Radio spots of Famous      Engagement through        Asante Mama through     Asante Mama through&#13;
                           Asante Mama               of Asante Mama             people saying why their    media, DCC and IPC        media, DCC and IPC      media, DCC and IPC&#13;
                  4                                                             mothers are heroes as      on Asante Mamaâ&#128;&#148;&#13;
                Amplify                                                         part of Asante Mama.       nominating mothers&#13;
                                                                                                           as heroes&#13;
                                                                                Handwashing with&#13;
                                                                                soap ambassador&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                  5        Radio spots and soap                                 Soap packaging             IPC&#13;
                Sustain    opera&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                        Tanzania: A Handwashing Behavior Change Journey&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                        5&#13;
&amp;#12;6   Tanzania: A Handwashing Behavior Change Journey                                               Global Scaling Up Handwashing Project&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
approach. Second, the interventions were effective at target-          (motivation determinant). Asante Mama was integrated into the&#13;
ing opportunity determinants (including access, availability,          soap opera through the character of a hero-mother who is rec-&#13;
and product), and ability determinants (knowledge, including           ognized for her importance in the family, including handwash-&#13;
awareness of tippy-taps and the critical times for handwash-           ing with soap. Radio spots aired five times daily from July 2010&#13;
ing), but were less effective in addressing the motivation de-         to June 2011; the soap opera aired two times per week from&#13;
terminant (intention to wash hands with soap). In early 2010,          November 2010 to June 2011. In addition to the radio spots&#13;
WSP held a learning event to review the intervention and it was        and soap opera, sponsorship hours were piloted in which DJs&#13;
determined that, while IPC messages needed a more prag-                asked listeners to call in and tell a story about why their mother&#13;
matic approach, DCC and mass media should be adjusted to               is hero. The DJs were tasked to link that story to handwashing&#13;
emphasize more emotive messages. For example, a rational               with soap. However, after one month, the sponsorships were&#13;
benefit is that washing hands with soap can save money and             cancelled because the DJs focused on rational reasons to&#13;
prevent disease. An emotional benefit of handwashing with              wash hands with soap rather than the Asante Mama concept,&#13;
soap is to be a good mother and to be recognized as a hero.            praising mothers for washing their hands with soap.&#13;
&#13;
Phase II: Empower and Amplify                                          IPC included the development and distribution of a â&#128;&#152;comic&#13;
To increase the emotive impact of the campaign, the team               bookâ&#128;&#153; that illustrated, step-by-step, how to build a tippy-tap.&#13;
developed a creative brief centered on the concept of Asante           A graphic approach was selected due to the low rates of lit-&#13;
Mama, which acknowledged, praised, and thanked mothers for             eracy in Tanzania. The storyline incorporated characters from&#13;
the things they did every day for their family and children, includ-   the soap opera, thereby integrating with mass media, and&#13;
ing washing hands with soap. This phase of the campaign fo-            was distributed by FLAs in 30 wards.&#13;
cused on making handwashing an intrinsic behavior, increasing&#13;
                                                                       DCC targeted attitudes and beliefs, outcome expectations, and&#13;
womenâ&#128;&#153;s understanding of the tippy-tap, and building skills to&#13;
                                                                       intention (all part of the motivation determinant), social norms&#13;
better manage soap and water.&#13;
                                                                       (opportunity determinant), and social support (ability determi-&#13;
Mass media targeted social support (ability determinant), and          nant). A competition was held in ten districts in which audience&#13;
beliefs and attitudes outcome expectations, and intentions             members were invited to go on stage to share why their mother&#13;
                                                                       was their hero, with the winner selected by audience response.&#13;
                                                                       Each district winner won a trip to participate in Global Hand-&#13;
Illustration 1: DCC Event in Igunga&#13;
                                                                       washing Day. DCC was integrated with IPC and mass media&#13;
                                                                       through skits that focused on how to build a tippy-tap; skits&#13;
                                                                       based on the radio soap operas; and playing radio jingles at&#13;
                                                                       events. At events, district and community officials were invited&#13;
                                                                       onstage and recognized, helping to strengthen political buy-in.&#13;
                                                                       DCC events reached an additional 166,000 women and chil-&#13;
                                                                       dren during this phase (Illustration 1). Wall paintings executed&#13;
                                                                       on community buildings depicted a woman teaching her child&#13;
                                                                       to wash hands using a tippy-tap. The painting reinforced the&#13;
                                                                       theme of Asante Mama to integrate with mass media and DCC,&#13;
                                                                       and served as permanent billboards.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                       MONITORING&#13;
                                                                       WSP hired four District Coordinators to support district gov-&#13;
                                                                       ernments in carrying out the implementation. The District&#13;
                                                                       Coordinators supervised and monitored the intervention to&#13;
                                                                       make sure that activities were delivered as planned and that&#13;
                                                                       messaging stayed on topic.&#13;
During Phase II, DCC roadshow events included tippy-tap&#13;
demonstrations to help improve two determinantsâ&#128;&#148;opportunity            Mass Media was monitored by a local media monitoring firm&#13;
and ability. Above, women in Nanga, Igunga District use a tippy-       that produced monthly reports showing when radio spots&#13;
tap to wash hands with soap.                                           and soap operas actually aired.&#13;
                                                                                                                             www.wsp.org&#13;
&amp;#12;Global Scaling Up Handwashing Project                                                      Tanzania: A Handwashing Behavior Change Journey            7&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
IPC monitoring was done through FLAâ&#128;&#153;s, on a self-reported          Figure 5: Knowledge of Key Junctures for&#13;
basis, using paper forms that were distributed to local gov-       Handwashing with Soap&#13;
ernment authorities. The forms were designed to record the&#13;
                                                                                    100&#13;
number and type of meetings held (e.g., household, commu-&#13;
                                                                                     80&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                       Percentage&#13;
nity, market, and so forth); who was reached (women ages&#13;
                                                                                     60&#13;
15â&#128;&#147;49, women over age 49, men, children); and how many&#13;
                                                                                     40&#13;
people were reached on a monthly basis. However, perhaps&#13;
                                                                                     20&#13;
because FLAs were unpaid community volunteers, only 67&#13;
                                                                                      0&#13;
percent of FLAs submitted forms, and data was not always                                  After the   Before      Before        Before      After&#13;
                                                                                            toilet    eating     preparing     feeding    cleaning&#13;
complete. Additionally, there was a challenge validating re-                                                       food         a child   a childâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
ported data. Interestingly, the FLAs who submitted forms                                                                                  bottom&#13;
                                                                                                               Key Junctures&#13;
to local governments viewed it a means to demonstrate re-&#13;
                                                                                      Before Event       After Event&#13;
sults of the work, and this helped to motivate them to record&#13;
data. Additionally, WSP monitored FLA activities through&#13;
spot-checks.&#13;
&#13;
DCC monitoring tracked progress in implementation and the          Strengthening the Motivation of FLAs. Since FLAs are&#13;
quality of the interventions. Implementing agencies also com-      not paid, there is also less motivation for preferential selection.&#13;
pleted a form after each event to record the size and compo-       However, without compensation or an institutional structure,&#13;
sition of the audience, topics covered, type of location, and      ongoing volunteerism has lagged. Several challenges have&#13;
prizes given away. Local government authorities and WSP staff      emerged. First, FLAs feel that they should be compensated or&#13;
monitored activities conducted by firms. Additionally, WSP         at least better recognized by local authorities for their efforts.&#13;
validated event data through spot checks and event impact          The government cannot afford to provide the volunteersâ&#128;&#153; trans-&#13;
surveys (EISs), developed by WSP, and undertaken to assess         portation or reimbursement for their time. Second, volunteers&#13;
how well the DCC firm transmitted messages. EISs assess the        are constrained by transportation and limited geographic influ-&#13;
impact of live behavior change communication events by mea-        ence. The question then becomes how many volunteers are&#13;
suring reception to the communication among members of the         needed to train at scale, and the costs associated with train-&#13;
target audience and changes in knowledge and intention.            ing. More analysis is needed to understand scalability, costs,&#13;
                                                                   and what is financially viable for the government.&#13;
The DCC firm administered the EIS before and after a random&#13;
sample of 28 DCC events (25 percent of end-of-project target       An alternative approach may be to develop a health-product&#13;
for DCC events) in five districts. Results suggest that the tar-   sales force with basic sales training and to provision them&#13;
geted behavioral determinants, knowledge (ability determinant)     with an initial batch of products such as soap, water treat-&#13;
and intention (motivation determinant), had improved among         ment tablets, and condoms. This would help build income&#13;
those exposed to a DCC event (Figure 5). It is hoped that a gain   and could promote FLAsâ&#128;&#153; status in the community. Another&#13;
in these determinants will be reflected in improved behavior.      option is to find other ways to motivate and provide incen-&#13;
                                                                   tives to FLAs. For example, in some villages, FLAs have been&#13;
CHALLENGES                                                         elected as village representative because of their raised pro-&#13;
Geographic Arrangement of the Intervention. Because                file as an FLA. Overall, expectations must be managed up&#13;
of poor transportation, the dispersed project areas created        front about what is expected of a volunteer, and how they will&#13;
many challenges, from delivering trainings to implementing         be recognized for their work&#13;
DCC events to supervising progress.&#13;
                                                                   Monitoring FLAs. Collecting data through the local govern-&#13;
Developing the Creative Concept. The time needed to                ment structure has proven challenging and it is likely that the&#13;
develop a positive, professional, communications campaign          figures reported are an underestimate of work conducted by&#13;
was underestimated. It took over six months of working with        FLAs. An estimated 67 percent of trained FLAs have submit-&#13;
the advertising firm to develop a concept that met the criteria    ted and delivered at least one form to the district government,&#13;
in the creative brief and established emotive messages. This       either directly or through their village and ward leaders. Due&#13;
delay impacted the development of communication materi-            to issues such as transportation, it is possible that an addi-&#13;
als and timing of intervention across all channels.                tional 20 percent of trained FLAs conducted work, but were&#13;
www.wsp.org&#13;
&amp;#12;8   Tanzania: A Handwashing Behavior Change Journey                                                      Global Scaling Up Handwashing Project&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Table 1: Project Reach in Tanzania Through December 2010                                                About the project&#13;
                                                                    Reported                             Global Scaling Up Handwashing is a&#13;
 Intervention                                      Target            Reach              Percent&#13;
                                                                                                         Water and Sanitation (WSP) project&#13;
 Mass media                                     14.5 million       14.5 million          100%            focused on applying innovative&#13;
 Direct Consumer Contact (DCC)                    170,000            327,000             191%            behavior change approaches&#13;
 Interpersonal Communication (IPC)                320,000            165,000              52%            to improve handwashing with&#13;
                                                                                                         soap behavior among women of&#13;
not able to submit forms to the district             from government officials on their report-          reproductive age (ages 15â&#128;&#147;49) and&#13;
government. Furthermore, FLAs who                    ing as well as site visits to see progress.         primary school-age children (ages&#13;
have submitted forms may submit only                 Without this feedback FLAs are unlikely             5â&#128;&#147;9). It is being implemented by&#13;
a small portion of their forms. Anec-                to maintain motivation.                             local and national governments&#13;
dotal evidence from discussions with                                                                     with technical support from WSP&#13;
FLAs suggests that the majority try to               Message Creep. During DCC events,                   in four countries: Peru, Senegal,&#13;
achieve their target to reach 75 women               the implementing firm would naturally               Tanzania, and Vietnam. For more&#13;
a month. To rectify the situation, the               start to play for laughs and key messages           information, please visit www.wsp&#13;
team planned a follow-up training with               would gradually drop away. This can be              .org/scalinguphandwashing.&#13;
FLAs to review target numbers and ac-                mitigated through independent supervi-&#13;
tual reach. FLAs completed a report on               sion by either the local government or              Contact us&#13;
the number of targets reached in the                 the hiring entity, through Event Impact             For more information, please visit&#13;
past month, and compared this against                Survey results, which will show if the firm         www.wsp.org or email Yolande&#13;
previous months.                                     is not delivering the message effectively,          Coombes at wsp@worldbank.org&#13;
                                                     and through message checklists.&#13;
Value of Data. FLA monitoring forms&#13;
record process indicators such as num-               Results&#13;
ber of people reached, location, and du-             As of December 2010, the project has&#13;
ration of visits but many officials place            exceeded project targets for mass&#13;
a low value on this data. This situation             media and DCC, and reached 52 per-&#13;
impedes the process of collecting the                cent of the target for IPC (Table 1).&#13;
forms at each level, decreasing the likeli-&#13;
hood that FLA forms will be institution-                               â&#128;&#148;By Yolande Coombes&#13;
alized. FLAs have requested feedback                                         and Nat Paynter&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
WSP is a multi-donor partnership created in 1978 and administered by the World Bank to support&#13;
poor people in obtaining affordable, safe, and sustainable access to water and sanitation services.&#13;
WSPâ&#128;&#153;s donors include Australia, Austria, Canada, Denmark, Finland, France, the Bill &amp; Melinda Gates&#13;
Foundation, Ireland, Luxembourg, Netherlands, Norway, Sweden, Switzerland, United Kingdom,&#13;
United States, and the World Bank.&#13;
&#13;
The findings, interpretations, and conclusions expressed herein are entirely those of the author and&#13;
should not be attributed to the World Bank or its affiliated organizations, or to members of the Board&#13;
of Executive Directors of the World Bank or the governments they represent.&#13;
&#13;
Â© 2011 Water and Sanitation Program&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="16769062">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2011/10/16769062/tanzania-handwashing-behavior-change-journey
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <virt_coll>Knowledge Notes</virt_coll>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2011/10/16769062/tanzania-handwashing-behavior-change-journey</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2011/10/16769062/tanzania-handwashing-behavior-change-journey</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2012-09-26T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2012-09-26T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2012/09/26/000356161_20120926034819/Rendered/INDEX/648550REPLACEM00Change0Journey0HWWS.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2012/09/26/000356161_20120926034819/Rendered/PDF/648550REPLACEM00Change0Journey0HWWS.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2012-09-26T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2011-10-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Revised</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309936</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Tanzania - A handwashing behavior change journey
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            In Tanzania, nearly 30,000 people die
            annually due to diarrheal diseases and an estimated 12.6
            percent of children suffer from diarrheal diseases. There is
            a widespread and deep-rooted belief that diarrhea is part of
            growing up and cannot be prevented. Working with the
            government and with non-governmental organizations, the
            Water and Sanitation Program (WSP) sought to increase rates
            of handwashing with soap among women and children,
            especially at critical junctures. This learning note
            documents the development of the project, with a focus on
            how it was designed, implemented, and monitored. Challenges
            and lessons learned are highlighted to assist program
            managers in designing and managing evidence-based
            handwashing with soap and other hygiene promotion programs.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Tanzania - A handwashing behavior change journey
        </docna>
        <display_title>Tanzania - A handwashing behavior
            change journey</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2011/10/16769062/tanzania-handwashing-behavior-change-journey</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>UNDP-Water &amp; Sanitation Program</docty>
        <subtopic>Hygiene Promotion and Social Marketing,Water and Human Health,E-Business,Population Policies,ICT Policy and Strategies</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Private Sector Development,Water Resources,Information and Communication Technologies,Water Supply and Sanitation,Health, Nutrition and Population</teratopic>
        <count>Tanzania</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>East Africa!$!80458</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Sub-Saharan Africa!$!80473</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000356161_20120926034819</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>Africa,Africa</admreg>
        <colti>Water and sanitation program learning note ; WSP</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Private Sector Development,Water Resources,Information and Communication Technologies,Water Supply and Sanitation,Health, Nutrition and Population</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            advertising, backbone, behavior change,
            caregivers, communication campaign, condoms, diarrhea,
            diarrheal diseases, Fact Sheet, general population,
            Handwashing, health centers, hygiene, hygiene interventions,
            hygiene issues, hygiene promotion, hygiene promotion
            programs, id, Image, Implementing agencies, Implementing
            Agency, information gaps, institution, Interpersonal
            Communication, LEARNING, literacy, local authorities, local
            governments, malaria, marketing, mass media, Mortality,
            Mother, national government, national governments, number of
            people, phone, posters, primary school, primary school-age
            children, Private Partnership, private sector, progress,
            radio, radio communication, reproductive age, reproductive
            health, Respect, results, rural areas, rural women,
            SANITATION, sanitation services, school-age children, soap,
            Social norms, Social support, supervision, sustainable
            access, targets, technical assistance, technical support,
            television, transportation, uses, using soap, wash hands
            with soap, washing hands, woman
        </keywd>
        <owner>Water- Water and Sanit Prgrm (GWASP)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>East Africa</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Sub-Saharan Africa</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>64855</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Arts and Culture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>AIDS HIV</ml:concept><ml:concept>HIV AIDS</ml:concept><ml:concept>HIV/AIDS</ml:concept><ml:concept>Behavior Change Communication</ml:concept><ml:concept>Handwashing Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Reproductive Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Reproductive and Women's Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Hygiene Promotion and Social Marketing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health and Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Media</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Diseases</ml:concept><ml:concept>HIV and AIDS</ml:concept><ml:concept>Malaria</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water, Sanitation and Hygiene</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Hygiene Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports &amp; Waterways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Local Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Reproductive and Maternal Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Africa</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Tanzania</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>