<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>ï»¿Report No. 39                                       74170&#13;
&#13;
South Asia Human Development Sector&#13;
&#13;
National Transfer Accounts Analysis For Sri Lanka&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
October 2012&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Discussion Paper Series&#13;
&amp;#12;Report No. 39&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
South Asia: Human Development Unit&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
National Transfer Accounts Analysis For Sri Lanka&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
October 2012&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Discussion Paper Series&#13;
&amp;#12;Discussion Papers are published to communicate the results of the World Bankâ&#128;&#153;s work to the&#13;
development community with the least possible delay. The typescript manuscript of this paper&#13;
therefore has not been prepared in accordance with the procedures appropriate to the formally&#13;
edited texts. Some sources cited in the paper may be informal documents that are not readily&#13;
available.&#13;
&#13;
The findings, interpretations, and conclusions expressed herein do not necessarily reflect the&#13;
views of the International Bank for Reconstruction and Development / The World Bank and its&#13;
affiliated organizations, or those of the Executive Directors of the World Bank or the&#13;
government they represent.&#13;
&#13;
The World Bank does not guarantee the accuracy of the data included in this work. The&#13;
boundaries, colors, denominations, and other information shown on any map in this work do not&#13;
imply any judgment on the part of the World Bank concerning the legal status of any territory or&#13;
the endorsement or acceptance of such boundaries.&#13;
&amp;#12;Contents&#13;
&#13;
   Acknowledgements ................................................................................................................................... v&#13;
      1.      Background and Motivation.......................................................................................................... 1&#13;
      2.      Brief Summary of the National Transfer Accounts Methodology ................................................ 2&#13;
      3.      Discussion of Results .................................................................................................................... 3&#13;
      4.      Projections................................................................................................................................... 17&#13;
      5.      Conclusion .................................................................................................................................. 19&#13;
   Appendix A: Estimation of NTA components for Sri Lanka ................................................................. 20&#13;
   References ............................................................................................................................................... 26&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figures&#13;
Figure 1: Total Labor Income and Consumption .......................................................................................... 3&#13;
Figure 2: Total Life Cycle Deficit (C-YL).................................................................................................... 5&#13;
Figure 3: Sri Lanka NTA: Life cycle deficit ................................................................................................. 6&#13;
Figure 4: Mean Labor Income and Consumption ......................................................................................... 7&#13;
Figure 5: Private health and education consumption .................................................................................... 7&#13;
Figure 6: Private expenditure on health and education ................................................................................. 8&#13;
Figure 7: Share of the elderly population and total fertility rate ................................................................... 9&#13;
Figure 8: Share of elderly population and total fertility rate (expanded view) ........................................... 10&#13;
Figure 9: Sri Lanka versus Developed Countries ....................................................................................... 12&#13;
Figure 10: Sri Lanka versus Developing Countries at Similar Stage of Demographic ............................... 13&#13;
Figure 11: Sri Lanka versus Developing Countries at Earlier Stages of Demographic Transition and&#13;
           Economic Development ............................................................................................................ 14&#13;
Figure 12: Private and public transfers, % private consumption ................................................................ 15&#13;
Figure 13: Private and Public transfers, % labor income ............................................................................ 16&#13;
Figure 14: Observed and Projected Total Labor Income and Total Consumption ..................................... 17&#13;
Figure 15: Observed and Projected Total Life Cycle Deficit (C-YL)......................................................... 18&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Tables&#13;
Table 1: Aggregate Control Parameters for Income, 2007, Millions Rs..................................................... 20&#13;
Table 2: Aggregate Control Parameters for Taxes, 2007, Millions Rs. ...................................................... 21&#13;
Table 3: Private Consumption Aggregate Controls, Millions Rs ............................................................... 22&#13;
Table 4: Aggregate Control Parameters for Current Public Expenditure on Education in Primary,&#13;
Secondary and Tertiary Education, 2007, Millions Rs. .............................................................................. 23&#13;
Table 5: Aggregate Controls on Public Expenditure, 2007, Millions Rs.................................................... 24&#13;
Table 6: Aggregate Control Parameters for Transfers, 2007, Millions Rs. ................................................ 25&#13;
&amp;#12;                      Authors&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Denis Nikitin, Indralal de Silva, and Tissa Jayasekara&#13;
&#13;
                    World Bank&#13;
&amp;#12;                                     Acknowledgements&#13;
&#13;
This paper was written under the overall direction of Cem Mete (Lead Economist, World Bank). Authors&#13;
thank Cem Mete, Susrutha Goonasekara, Nistha Sinha, and Stefania Rodica Cnobloch for insightful&#13;
comments on the working drafts of this paper. Gretchen Donehower has provided invaluable advice on&#13;
the National Transfers Accounts methodology.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 v&#13;
&amp;#12;                                      1. Background and Motivation&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sri Lanka has been going through a demographic transition triggered by decreasing fertility and&#13;
increasing life expectancy. The demographic transition is marked by two stages. During the first&#13;
stage, the drop in new births reduces the under-age dependency ratio, while the proportion of&#13;
working age population expands. This reduction in dependency ratio due to declining fertility,&#13;
frequently referred to as the demographic bonus, is associated with an increased pace of&#13;
economic development due to the larger share of working age population relative to the total&#13;
population, and the smaller pool of dependents that workers have to support. In the second stage&#13;
of the demographic transition, the consistently low fertility rates in combination with increased&#13;
life expectancy for the elderly, lead to the relative expansion of the old-age dependency ratio. As&#13;
the demographic transition enters the second stage, the demographic bonus deteriorates.&#13;
&#13;
The extent to which Sri Lanka can benefit from the demographic transition depends in many&#13;
ways on labor policies. In the first stage, the demographic transition naturally creates a larger&#13;
labor force which â&#128;&#147; other things constant â&#128;&#147; will increase the output in the economy as a whole.&#13;
However, policies that promote labor productivity will augment the magnitude of the&#13;
demographic bonus, e.g., investment in education, vocational and skills training, incentives to&#13;
households to invest in childrenâ&#128;&#153;s education etc.&#13;
&#13;
As Sri Lanka is going through a demographic transition, it is important to take stock of the ways&#13;
labor income is produced and consumed by different age groups. Similarly, when a deficit or a&#13;
gap between consumption and labor income emerges, it is important to know what type of&#13;
expenditures drive it and how it is financed. This paper documents labor income and&#13;
consumption patterns by age group in Sri Lanka, in a manner that is comparable to work carried&#13;
out for other countries that participate in the National Transfer Accounts Project.1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
1&#13;
    Seethe documentation provided by www.ntaccounts.org&#13;
                                                     1&#13;
&amp;#12;              2. Brief Summary of the National Transfer Accounts Methodology&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
This paper relies on the National Transfer Accounts (NTA) methodology (Lee and Mason, 2004;&#13;
Mason, Lee et al, 2006) in assigning expenditure and income to different age groups. This&#13;
methodology makes it possible to evaluate the magnitude of difference between the amount of&#13;
labor income earned by each age group and its consumption level, or the â&#128;&#156;life cycle deficit.â&#128;? For&#13;
working age adults, the lifecycle deficit is usually positive because their age group receives more&#13;
income from labor than it consumes. Age cohorts unable to work â&#128;&#147; usually the very young and&#13;
the very old â&#128;&#147; run a negative deficit, consuming more than their labor earnings. Their lifecycle&#13;
deficit is then financed through a combination of public and private transfers and asset&#13;
reallocation, consisting of income from assets (rents, dividends) and dissaving (e.g., sale of&#13;
properties).&#13;
&#13;
Following the NTA methodology, the flow of age reallocations can be described as follows:&#13;
&#13;
(1)     YL + YA + TGIN + TFIN = C + S + TGOUT + TFOUT .&#13;
On the left-hand side, YL stands for labor income; YA represents asset income; while TGIN and&#13;
TFIN denote incoming government and private transfers. On the right-hand side C is household&#13;
consumption, S stands for savings and TGOUT and TFOUT represent outgoing government (i.e.,&#13;
taxes) and private transfers. Private transfers in and out include inter- and intra-household&#13;
reallocations.&#13;
&#13;
Life-cycle deficit, or the difference between labor income and consumption can be written as&#13;
&#13;
(2)    LCD = YL â&#128;&#147; C .&#13;
&#13;
However, rearranging (1), LCD can be defined as&#13;
&#13;
(3)    LCD = S + TGOUT + TFOUT â&#128;&#147; YA â&#128;&#147; TGIN â&#128;&#147; TFIN = S â&#128;&#147; YA + TGNET + TFNET .&#13;
&#13;
Essentially, the life-cycle deficit is the sum of net asset reallocations (savings minus net asset&#13;
income) and net total transfers.&#13;
&#13;
Calculations of age-specific reallocations involve two key steps: (i) calculation of age profiles â&#128;&#147;&#13;
or the distribution of each NTA component (consumption, labor income, transfers) by age group&#13;
â&#128;&#147; and (2) application of macro controls. While the calculation of age profiles routinely relies on&#13;
household surveys, macro controls come from national accounts data.&#13;
&#13;
In the case of Sri Lanka, we construct age profiles for income, household consumption, and&#13;
transfers using the data from the 2007 Sri Lanka Household Income and Expenditure Survey&#13;
(HIES 2007), the most recent representative household dataset. The details of creation of specific&#13;
NTA components are discussed in Appendix A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                2&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                            3. Discussion of Results&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
              Life cycle deficit aggregate view&#13;
&#13;
              The vast majority of the labor income is earned by working age individuals 19 to 59 years old,&#13;
              who earn nearly 85 percent of all labor income. In the aggregate, consumption is heavily skewed&#13;
              toward the younger cohorts (see Figure 1). Children and youth under 19 account for 22 percent&#13;
              of private and 26 percent of total (private plus public) consumption, while contributing 2.5&#13;
              percent of labor income.&#13;
&#13;
                                        Figure 1: Total Labor Income and Consumption&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                             Total Labor Income and Consumption&#13;
                  80000&#13;
                  60000&#13;
Rs millions&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   40000&#13;
                   20000&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                           0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                               0   5   10   15   20   25   30      35   40   45   50    55     60   65   70   75   80    85     90   95   100&#13;
                                                                                  Age&#13;
                                                       Labor inc                   Priv cons                  Priv + pub cons&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
              Thus, Sri Lankaâ&#128;&#153;s aggregate age reallocation exhibits a strong downward trend with&#13;
              greater proportion of resources flowing toward children. This pattern reflects the large share&#13;
              of children in consumption, reflects their large proportion in Sri Lankaâ&#128;&#153;s total population, as well&#13;
              as the fact that Sri Lanka is in the relatively early stage of demographic transition. Economies&#13;
              that have reached advanced stages of demographic transition, such as the United States or Japan,&#13;
              are characterized by the net upward flow of resources toward the elderly, who represent a larger&#13;
              proportion of population in developed countries and whose benefits are rather costly (Lee 2002).&#13;
&#13;
              By comparison with other countries, Sri Lankaâ&#128;&#153;s life cycle is characterized by a relatively&#13;
              early age of negative life cycle deficit. In Sri Lanka, the total life cycle deficit remains positive&#13;
              (i.e., total consumption exceeding labor income) through age 21 (see Figure 2). In Germany and&#13;
              the Philippines, for example, labor income begins to exceed consumption only by the age 27,&#13;
                                                                             3&#13;
&amp;#12;versus 22 in Sri Lanka (Mason et al., 2009). In a series of cross-country comparisons, Austria in&#13;
2000, China in 2002, Korea in 2000 and Kenya in 1994 display comparably early age thresholds&#13;
at which youth LCD disappeared (Tung, forthcoming, in Mason, 2009). For majority of the&#13;
countries, the life-cycle deficit turns into surplus between the ages of 24 and 27. In some extreme&#13;
cases â&#128;&#147; Mexico in 2004 and Brazil in 1996 â&#128;&#147; the surplus emerges around the age of 30.&#13;
&#13;
On the income side, this pattern is driven by the relatively early age of labor force entry. On the&#13;
consumption side, it is likely linked to a relatively low enrolment rate in local institutions of&#13;
higher learning. Public education expenditure accounts for a sizable share of total consumption at&#13;
younger ages, yet the low supply of opportunities leads Sri Lankan students to seek enrolment at&#13;
colleges and universities abroad.&#13;
&#13;
The total income of persons age 22 to 56 remains higher than their total consumption, but after&#13;
age 57, the life deficit turns positive again. The timing of the old-age deficit is similar to that&#13;
found in Germany and the Philippines.&#13;
&#13;
Notably, the aggregate LCD for the elderly is small, corresponding to the relatively low level of&#13;
old-dependency due to the small share of the elderly in total population. However, as the fertility&#13;
rates decline and life expectancy increases, the childrenâ&#128;&#153;s share in life cycle deficit will decline&#13;
and the share of the elderly will grow. The relative expansion of the elderly age group will put&#13;
pressure on the working age population to finance the upward transfers, which will require&#13;
considerable improvements in labor force productivity, or â&#128;&#147; should productivity remain the same&#13;
â&#128;&#147; expansion of the labor force, for instance through the increase participation of women, or&#13;
increasing the amount of time one works.&#13;
&#13;
The latter two options are less attractive, from the economic point of view, than the first one.&#13;
Expanding labor force participation only provides a short- to medium-term solution to the&#13;
increasing old-dependency problem, since eventually even a labor force with 100 percent&#13;
participation would have to increase productivity to finance the benefits of a continuously aging&#13;
population. Expanding the amount of work is also problematic; Figure 2 indicates that the life&#13;
cycle deficit already turns negative earlier than in a number of comparator economies reflecting&#13;
the fact that an average Sri Lankan starts to work relatively early. Even earlier entry into the&#13;
labor force is often associated with underinvestment in human capital (due to foregone&#13;
schooling), leading to a less skilled labor force, unless complemented by work-study&#13;
arrangements, and loss of productivity since a low-skilled labor force would be unlikely to&#13;
engage in high-value added activities.&#13;
&#13;
Extending the effective time of retirement from the labor force can â&#128;&#156;transferâ&#128;? the burden of&#13;
financing the old-age benefits to the elderly themselves. In fact, we already see some of this in&#13;
Sri Lanka: the life-cycle deficit of individuals over 72 begins to shrink â&#128;&#147; to some extent due to&#13;
continued participation of the elderly in self-employment, which generates moderate income&#13;
flow for some of them while their consumption declines.2 However, delaying retirement from the&#13;
labor force can put a considerable stress on the elderly and lead to adverse health outcomes. It is&#13;
likely to be a more viable option when there are robust social safety nets for the elderly already&#13;
in place, e.g., health care, retraining, etc.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
2&#13;
    Another contribution comes from civil service pension payment to former civil servants.&#13;
                                                           4&#13;
&amp;#12;              Thus, from the economic point of view, increasing productivity of the labor force offers the best&#13;
              way to address increasing old-dependency, but it requires additional investment in education and&#13;
              vocational training.&#13;
&#13;
                                                      Figure 2: Total Life Cycle Deficit (C-YL)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                           Total Life Cycle Deficit (C-YL)&#13;
                        40000&#13;
                        30000&#13;
                        20000&#13;
                        10000&#13;
Rs Millions&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                0&#13;
                     -10000&#13;
                     -20000&#13;
                     -30000&#13;
                     -40000&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                    0   5   10   15   20   25   30   35   40   45   50    55   60   65   70   75   80   85   90   95   100&#13;
                                                                                    Age&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
              Lifecycle deficit - per capita view&#13;
&#13;
              The per capita life cycle deficit reveals a different picture. The deficit for children and youth&#13;
              under 19 is still high, reflecting the fact that the per capita total consumption at lower ages is still&#13;
              high due to higher large private and public spending on health, and especially on education.&#13;
              However, the per capita value of the life cycle deficit of the elderly is much higher than the&#13;
              aggregate view of the life cycle deficit would suggest, driven in large part by the low numbers&#13;
              of the elderly. Even though the elderly are able to earn income from their labor activities, their&#13;
              per capita expenditures (public and private) are higher as well. Thus in per capita terms,&#13;
              consumption by the elderly far exceeds their income and the older they are the greater the deficit.&#13;
&#13;
              Figures 3 through 6 illustrate these trends in per capita deficit, consumption and labor. Note that&#13;
              to facilitate the cross-country comparisons the y-axis reports the monetary value of per capita&#13;
              deficit scaled by the mean labor income of mature working age adults 30 to 49 year old. The&#13;
              same scaling adjustment, commonly used in NTA studies, is applied to all figures depicting per&#13;
              capita trends.&#13;
&#13;
              The high per capita deficit of the elderly implies that as the population ages and old-&#13;
              dependency ratio grows, the aggregate old-dependency burden will expand more than&#13;
              proportionately, assuming the levels of labor income and consumption remain constant.&#13;
                                                                                5&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                     Figure 3: Sri Lanka NTA: Life cycle deficit&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                           Sri Lanka NTA: Life cycle deficit&#13;
&#13;
                                  .5&#13;
                                  .3&#13;
of 30-49 year olds&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  .1&#13;
                                    0&#13;
                                  -.1&#13;
                                  -.3&#13;
                                  -.5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        0   5   10   15   20   25   30   35   40   45   50    55   60   65   70   75   80   85   90   95   100&#13;
                                                                                        Age&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     The per capita life cycle deficit of the younger population under 20 reflects their high&#13;
                     consumption of public services (Figure 4). The nutritional needs of children are lower than&#13;
                     those of adults, which are reflected in the use of adult equivalence scales in allocating&#13;
                     consumption between household members. Consequently childrenâ&#128;&#153;s total level of private&#13;
                     consumption is low; notwithstanding the fact that their private consumption of health and&#13;
                     education is relatively high (see Figure 5). Yet their consumption of public education â&#128;&#147; and to a&#13;
                     lesser extent public health â&#128;&#147; is disproportionately high, which accounts for the high total&#13;
                     consumption of children and youth.&#13;
&#13;
                     Total consumption increases with age until the mid-60s, despite higher public consumption of&#13;
                     persons under 25 as a result of continuous growth of private consumption and increasing public&#13;
                     spending on health after the age of 17.&#13;
&#13;
                     Increased private consumption reflects the progressively higher private healthcare faced by&#13;
                     people as they age. This is understandable since aging is associated with more serious health&#13;
                     problems. Specifically, Figure 6 indicates that per capita private expenditure on healthcare&#13;
                     rapidly rises in absolute terms for people age 25 and older, reaching 6 percent of median labor&#13;
                     income of 30 to 49 year olds.&#13;
&#13;
                     The trend for private healthcare costs to rise in age is observed in many economies. Governments&#13;
                     usually seek to offset the climbing cost through public provision and or financing health services,&#13;
                     and Sri Lanka is no exception: per capita public spending on health steadily increases for persons&#13;
                     17 years of age and older. An important policy question is whether the government spending on&#13;
                     health is sufficient to control the rising private costs as people age. Figure 6 seems to suggest that&#13;
                                                                                   6&#13;
&amp;#12;public health spending grows in age, but fails to keep pace with the increasing cost of&#13;
healthcare. After the age of 47, private expenditure accounts for more than half of total&#13;
spending on health; and the private share in financing health care costs is even higher for older&#13;
individuals.&#13;
&#13;
                              Figure 4: Mean Labor Income and Consumption&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                Mean Labor Income and Consumption&#13;
           1.2&#13;
             1&#13;
           .8&#13;
           .6&#13;
           .4&#13;
           .2&#13;
             0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                 0   5   10    15   20   25   30      35   40   45   50    55     60   65   70   75   80    85     90   95   100&#13;
                                                                     Age&#13;
                                          Labor inc                   Priv cons                  Priv + pub cons&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                         Figure 5: Private health and education consumption&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                 7&#13;
&amp;#12;                     Another driver of private expenditure is private spending on education. Unsurprisingly, private&#13;
                     spending on education is high among school-age children and young adults; but what is more&#13;
                     interesting is that adults age 40 to 55 have the highest per capita private education expenditures&#13;
                     (Figure 6). The trend reflects the fact that childrenâ&#128;&#153;s education is heavily subsidized by public&#13;
                     sources, while very little public support is available for adult education, mostly in the form of&#13;
                     informal and vocational training. Figure 6 suggests that there is demand for adult learning&#13;
                     that is currently being met by private expenditure; however, there may be scope for&#13;
                     additional public investment in adult and informal learning as a way to increase the quality&#13;
                     and productivity of the labor force.&#13;
&#13;
                                             Figure 6: Private expenditure on health and education&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  Private expenditure on health and education&#13;
                               .08&#13;
                               .06&#13;
of 30-49 year olds&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                               .04&#13;
                               .02&#13;
                                     0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         0    5   10   15   20   25   30   35     40    45      50   55   60   65      70    75   80   85   90   95   100&#13;
                                                                                             Age&#13;
                                                                           Priv exp on health                       Priv exp on educ&#13;
&#13;
                                                                           Pub exp on health                        Pub exp on educ&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     Our model of private education expenditure estimates that the elderly also report an increased&#13;
                     spending on education. Recall that the allocation of private education expenditure is estimated&#13;
                     indirectly by regressing total household education expenditure on the number of persons of a&#13;
                     given age group associated with change in education consumption. Higher consumption&#13;
                     spending in households with more elderly members may reflect contributions of grandparents to&#13;
                     the schooling costs of their grandchildren.&#13;
&#13;
                     Cross-country comparisons of per capita life cycle deficit&#13;
&#13;
                     One of the benefits of the NTA methodology is the ability to draw cross-country comparisons.&#13;
                     Comparator countries, divided into three sets according to the stage of demographic transition,&#13;
                     are reported in Figures 9 through 11. The comparator graphs of labor income and public and&#13;
                     private consumption are expressed, as in Figure 3, in scaled units. The available graphs cover a&#13;
                     wide range of countries and periods corresponding to various stages of economic development&#13;
                                                                                       8&#13;
&amp;#12;and demographic transition. Figure 7 plots the available countries with respect to their total&#13;
fertility rate and proportion of the elderly (65 and older).&#13;
&#13;
European economies (during 2000-2005), USA (2003), and Uruguay (1994) are obviously at&#13;
more advanced stages of the demographic transition. On the other hand, Kenya in 1994 and&#13;
Nigeria in 2004 are at much earlier stages of demographic transition.&#13;
&#13;
In terms of demographic trends, Sri Lanka is closest to Chile in 1997, China in 2002, Costa Rica&#13;
in 2004 and Indonesia in 2005; Brazil in 1996 is also reasonably close. India in 2004 and&#13;
Philippines in 1999 have considerably higher fertility and a lower share of elderly population.&#13;
Despite the fact that Korea is often seen as a relevant example of successful demographic&#13;
transition applicable to Sri Lanka, Korea (2000) is a bit of an outlier in that it has a relatively low&#13;
proportion of the elderly (7.3 percent) for its low fertility rate (1.47). The elderly represent the&#13;
same proportion of the population in Sri Lanka (7.1 percent), but its fertility rate is much higher&#13;
(2.34).&#13;
&#13;
                          Figure 7: Share of the elderly population and total fertility rate&#13;
                               20&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        JPN04&#13;
&#13;
                                         DEU03&#13;
                                        ESP00 SWE03&#13;
                                          AUT00 FIN04&#13;
                                         HUN05&#13;
                                        SVN04&#13;
                               15&#13;
Population 65 and older&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                     USA03   URY94&#13;
                                                                           Sri Lanka 2007&#13;
                               10&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                           KOR00&#13;
                                               CHN02&#13;
                                               THA04 CHL97&#13;
                                                        CRI04&#13;
                                                         MEX04&#13;
                                                         IDN05&#13;
                                                             BRA96&#13;
                                5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                         IND04&#13;
                                                                                   PHL99&#13;
                                                                                                       NGA04&#13;
                                                                                                   KEN94&#13;
                                0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                    1            2                   3                     4   5         6&#13;
                                                                         Total fertility&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
However, even economies at comparable stages of demographic transition dramatically differ in&#13;
terms of economic performance and characteristics of the labor force. Figure 8 plots only&#13;
countries with TFR below 3.5 and less than 10 percent of the elderly; the size of the circle&#13;
corresponds to per capita income expressed in constant 2005 PPP dollars. Thus, even though Sri&#13;
Lanka is comparable to Chile (1997) in terms of the elderly share in population and the total&#13;
fertility rate, its GDP per capita is less than one half of Chileâ&#128;&#153;s. Per capita income, in turn, has&#13;
important implications for the allocation of public and private resources to health, education, and&#13;
social protection.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                           9&#13;
&amp;#12;                          Figure 8: Share of elderly population and total fertility rate (expanded view)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       8&#13;
                                                                                              Sri Lanka 2007&#13;
&#13;
                                                    KOR00&#13;
                                                            CHN02              LKA07&#13;
                                                             THA04&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       7&#13;
                                                                             CHL97&#13;
Population 65 and older&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       6&#13;
                                                                          CRI04&#13;
                                                                            MEX04&#13;
                                                                              IDN05&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                      BRA96&#13;
                                       5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                       IND04&#13;
                                       4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                   1.5           2                  2.5            3&#13;
                                                                     Total fertility&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
International comparisons â&#128;&#147; presented in Figures 9 through 11 â&#128;&#147; point to several patterns.&#13;
&#13;
Sri Lankans start earning income earlier than their peers in other countries and become&#13;
net earners relatively early as well. As one would expect, labor income remains effectively&#13;
zero in the early ages since relatively few children work for pay, and when they do, they are paid&#13;
little. Labor income increases beyond the negligible levels around the age of 15 in most&#13;
countries, even later in developed countries where schooling is close to universal, returns to&#13;
schooling are sizable, and the average household income is high, making the opportunity cost of&#13;
early entry in the labor force an unattractive option. But even compared to most comparable&#13;
countries or even poorer countries at earlier stages of the demographic transition, Sri Lanka&#13;
stands out in terms of the relatively young age of earners. China in 2002 comes closest to Sri&#13;
Lanka; in China, labor income becomes non-negligible relatively early too, around 12 years old.&#13;
&#13;
In Sri Lankaâ&#128;&#153;s case, children 10-11 years old already earn 3 to 4 percent of the wages of prime&#13;
working age adults. Many of these are not wageworkers but work in their familiesâ&#128;&#153; businesses or&#13;
farming. According to the NTA methodology, all household members who report working are&#13;
imputed labor income based on the average wage for their age group, even if they did not&#13;
explicitly report wages. Variation in household surveys may also affect the comparability of data&#13;
across countries since the age threshold for asking labor related questions varies from survey to&#13;
survey and from country to country. Some surveys are better at picking up child and youth&#13;
employment than others.&#13;
&#13;
Similar to other countries, the labor income curve in Sri Lanka shows a steep increase around the&#13;
age of fifteen, as a considerable proportion of young people enter the labor force in low-skilled&#13;
occupations after completing primary and lower secondary schooling. Mexico, Brazil, Costa&#13;
Rica and Indonesia, among others, display a similar pattern. Yet Sri Lankan youth still remain&#13;
net total consumers until the age of 21, a relatively young age by international standards, an&#13;
outcome of early age of labor market entry (on the labor income side), and low secondary and&#13;
especially tertiary enrolment rates (on the consumption side).&#13;
The elderly Sri Lankans work longer and earn considerable amounts of labor income well&#13;
into their seventies and eighties. In most other countries, for which national transfer accounts&#13;
graphs are available, labor income declines more drastically for the people after 65. This is&#13;
                                                                      10&#13;
&amp;#12;especially true of developed countries, where generous public spending on the elderly substitutes&#13;
for the declining labor income. In Sri Lanka, however, public spending flows upward toward the&#13;
young and is centered on education, while persons of advanced age receive little public support.&#13;
Additionally, government and semi-government sectors are large in Sri Lanka, accounting for&#13;
approximately 30 percent of formal labor force; high labor income after 65 reflects a large&#13;
number of relatively high pension payments to public sector retirees.&#13;
&#13;
Among countries of comparable demographic stage and level of income, Brazil (1996), China&#13;
(2002), and less so India (2004) report significant labor income among the seventy and eighty&#13;
year olds; but still they earn less (as proportion of earnings of prime working age adults) than&#13;
their Sri Lankan peers. However, Brazil has nearly double the per capita income of Sri Lanka&#13;
and favors the elderly in public expenditure allocations. Only Nigeriaâ&#128;&#153;s elderly (in 2004) worked&#13;
as long as their peers in Sri Lanka and earned similar levels of income. Notably, Nigeriaâ&#128;&#153;s public&#13;
spending on the elderly was virtually non-existent.&#13;
&#13;
Sri Lankaâ&#128;&#153;s overall level of public spending is low, but similar to many countries in its&#13;
comparator group: India (2004), China (2002), Thailand (2004), Indonesia (2005), Chile&#13;
(1997), Uruguay (1994). Only Brazil (1996) and Taiwan (1998) have markedly higher public&#13;
spending across all age groups.&#13;
&#13;
Education is the biggest public expenditure item and the greatest source of public assistance&#13;
Sri Lankans receive during their life course. It is concentrated around the primary and&#13;
secondary levels with relatively small per capita expenditure on tertiary schooling. In this,&#13;
Sri Lankaâ&#128;&#153;s early age profile of consumption resembles that of the Philippines (1999) most&#13;
closely: in both cases, education expenditure is lumped around primary schooling. Other&#13;
countries of comparable demographic stage and per capita income allocate more public resources&#13;
toward tertiary schooling, including Thailand (2004), Indonesia (2005), China (2002), India&#13;
(2004), Mexico (2004), and Korea (2000).&#13;
&#13;
However, the general shape of the consumption curve for age 0 through 25 is similar to those of&#13;
many other developing countries, in that past the school age, public expenditure remains&#13;
constant and rather low. By contrast, in OECD and some middle income economies (Brazil in&#13;
1996, Costa Rica in 2004) public per capita consumption is higher at both tails of the age&#13;
distribution: both the young and the elderly receive higher levels of public allocation. For the&#13;
young, public spending is predominantly focused on schooling, while for the elderly on&#13;
healthcare.&#13;
&#13;
What accounts for the small size of public spending relative to private expenditure in Sri Lanka?&#13;
It does not appear that the level of consumption is inordinately large, making the public share&#13;
appear small in comparison. In fact, private consumption levels between 40 and 60 percent of&#13;
labor income among 20 to 60 year olds in Sri Lanka prove to be on the low side. Among other&#13;
countries, only Kenya and China have private consumption significantly lower than Sri Lankaâ&#128;&#153;s.&#13;
So public consumption is low either because of low supply or weak demand for public services,&#13;
or both. On the supply side, the evidence suggests that there exists demand for skills and training&#13;
among 40 to 55 year olds, which is presently met through only private financing. The provision&#13;
of higher education slots also does not meet the demand for tertiary schooling. Similarly, the&#13;
results reported above indicate that public financing of health, especially for the elderly, was not&#13;
keeping pace with the growing cost of healthcare, which had to be absorbed by out-of-pocket&#13;
                                                11&#13;
&amp;#12;  expenditures. On the demand side, problems of access and quality of publicly provided services&#13;
  in health and education discourage people from using them.&#13;
&#13;
                                   Figure 9: Sri Lanka versus Developed Countries&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
GDPPC=40565; TFR=2.0; % Elderly=12.3      GDPPC=31697; TFR=1.4; % Elderly= 15.5               GDPPC= 30654; TFR=1.7; % Elderly=17.1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
GDPPC=30731; TFR=1.3; % Elderly=17.8      GDPPC=29738; TFR=1.3 ; % Elderly=19.4&#13;
                                                                                              GDPPC=29917; TFR=1.8; % Elderly=15.7&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
GDPPC=25129; TFR=1.2; % Elderly=16.8      GDPPC=22527; TFR=1.2; % Elderly=15.3                GDPPC=16955; TFR=1.3; % Elderly=15.6&#13;
                                                                                              Shaded area = labor income&#13;
                                          Sri Lanka 2007                                      Top curve = total consumption (public + private)&#13;
                                         1.5&#13;
                                                                                              Second from top curve = private consumption&#13;
                                         1.2                                                  Bottom curve = public consumption&#13;
&#13;
                                          .9&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                          .6&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                          .3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                           0&#13;
                                               0     10   20   30   40   50   60   70   80   90&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                   GDPPC=4008; TFR=2.3; % Elderly=7.1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                    12&#13;
&amp;#12;            Figure 10: Sri Lanka versus Developing Countries at Similar Stage of Demographic&#13;
                                  Transition and Economic Development&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
GDPPC=18730; TFR=1.5; % Elderly=7.3   GDPPC=12326; TFR=2.3; % Elderly=5.6     GDPPC=10162; TFR=2.3; % Elderly=6.9&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
GDPPC=8645; TFR=2.2; % Elderly=5.7    GDPPC= 8746; TFR=2.6; % Elderly=12.3    GDPPC=7771; TFR=2.5; % Elderly=5.1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                      GDPPC= 6519.7; TFR=1.8; % Elderly=7     GDPPC=3217; TFR=2.3; % Elderly=5.5&#13;
GDPPC= 6520; TFR=1.8; % Elderly=7&#13;
&#13;
                                                                              Sri Lanka 2007&#13;
                                                                              1.5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                              1.2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                               .9&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                               .6&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                               .3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                               0&#13;
                                                                                    0   10   20   30   40    50    60   70       80   90&#13;
                                      GDPPC=2141; TFR=3.0; % Elderly=4.5&#13;
GDPPC=3108; TFR=1.8; % Elderly=7.1                                           GDPPC=4008; TFR=2.3; % Elderly=7.1&#13;
                                                                              Shaded area = labor income&#13;
                                                                              Top curve = total consumption (public + private)&#13;
                                                                              Second from top curve = private consumption&#13;
                                                                              Bottom curve = public consumption&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                           13&#13;
&amp;#12;   Figure 11: Sri Lanka versus Developing Countries at Earlier Stages of Demographic Transition&#13;
                                   and Economic Development&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
GDPPC=2491; TFR=3.6; % Elderly=3.4     GDPPC=1687; TFR=5.7; % Elderly=3                   GDPPC=1294; TFR=5.4; % Elderly=2.7&#13;
                                                                                          Shaded area = labor income&#13;
                                        Sri Lanka 2007                                    Top curve = total consumption (public + private)&#13;
                                       1.5&#13;
                                                                                          Second from top curve = private consumption&#13;
                                       1.2                                                Bottom curve = public consumption&#13;
&#13;
                                        .9&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        .6&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        .3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         0&#13;
                                             0   10   20   30    40   50   60   70   80     90&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     GDPPC=4008; TFR=2.3; % Elderly=7.1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Transfers&#13;
&#13;
  Within the national transfer accounts, the life cycle deficit is financed either by transfers or by&#13;
  asset reallocation (saving and drawing on savings, or purchasing a house and selling it). In Sri&#13;
  Lankaâ&#128;&#153;s context, it is especially important to consider the role of transfers. On the one hand, as a&#13;
  matter of policy, the Sri Lankan government pursues an ambitious agenda of social investments.&#13;
  On the other, Sri Lanka is a big exporter of labor force, and remittances from Sri Lankan&#13;
  residents working abroad represent a significant amount. In the tables below, we consider the&#13;
  role of private and public welfare transfer sources, first relative to labor income and then in&#13;
  relation to private consumption.&#13;
&#13;
  Before considering transfers, two remarks are in order. First, note that public transfers refer to&#13;
  social welfare transfers only (dominated by Samurdhi, and disability benefits to soldiers, and&#13;
  other household welfare transfers, such programs as Triposha); they do not include flows of&#13;
  subsidized health or education services already included under health or education spending&#13;
  (e.g., transportation subsidies to students, school meals, textbooks or free checkups).&#13;
&#13;
  Secondly, private transfers are by and large recorded as household headâ&#128;&#153;s income, even when the&#13;
  intended beneficiary is another household member. Therefore, their age distribution does not&#13;
  adequately reflect the age distribution of final consumers of transfers. This is, for instance, true&#13;
  of children who legally cannot be recipients of some transfers (e.g., money wired from abroad).&#13;
  For this reason, private transfers have been assigned to the household head across the board. This&#13;
  explains the zero level of remittance income before the age of 15, and the abrupt increase in&#13;
  private remittance after the age of 20. Misallocation of transfers away from the elderly presents&#13;
  less of a problem since in the HIES, transfers are recorded at the individual level.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                14&#13;
&amp;#12;Following the NTA methodology, however, public transfers are assigned to the intended&#13;
beneficiary, who in our case is the recipient reported in the HIES. Consequently, Figure 12&#13;
shows that public transfers play a greater role up to the age of 20 than private transfers.&#13;
&#13;
In light of this pattern of assignment of transfers, it is not surprising that both public and private&#13;
transfers play a much smaller role among the younger age groups, with one exception â&#128;&#147; relative&#13;
to labor income, public transfers prove high among 10 to 15 year olds. The importance of public&#13;
transfers for that age group is due to the low labor income of 10 to 15 year olds. Apart from this&#13;
exception, the contribution of public and private transfers to labor income and&#13;
consumption is greater among older age cohorts (see Figure 13).&#13;
&#13;
                 Figure 12: Private and public transfers, % private consumption&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 15&#13;
&amp;#12;                    Figure 13: Private and Public transfers, % labor income&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Despite the fact that Sri Lanka is a net receiver of remittances from abroad, the role played&#13;
by remittances is rather modest. They contribute between 4 and 7 percent of labor income after&#13;
the age of 56 and 2.5 percent to 4.5 percent of consumption for the same age group. But the&#13;
relative importance of remittances increases as the labor income declines and the old-age&#13;
life deficit turns positive after the age of 56.&#13;
&#13;
Remittances also record a spike relative to consumption and labor income for the working age&#13;
group of 25 to 40 year olds, whose income from labor is high - the fact that does not fit the logic&#13;
of substitution between transfers and labor income. This is likely an artifact of assigning&#13;
remittances to household heads, who are often the biggest earners in the household.&#13;
&#13;
Public transfers are also modest in size relative to consumption and labor income; even for&#13;
the elderly over the age of 60, they range from just over 2 percent to just under 5 percent of&#13;
labor income and around 2 percent of consumption. This is hardly surprising given that&#13;
schemes included in public transfers tend to target underprivileged groups and do not have large&#13;
coverage. Another reason for low public transfers has to do with the social assistance strategy Sri&#13;
Lanka pursues: it centers on health and education services and some of the education and health&#13;
programs, while programs explicitly designated as public transfers are â&#128;&#156;top upsâ&#128;? to them. Yet&#13;
after the age of 40, the share of transfers relative to consumption plateaus at about 2 percent,&#13;
despite the intuition that poverty is more prevalent among the elderly.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                16&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                              4. Projections&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
              Population growth and aging have serious implications for the size and distribution of the life&#13;
              cycle deficit. On the one hand, the growing share of the working age population will expand the&#13;
              amount of labor income; on the other, expansion of the elderly share of the population will&#13;
              augment the deficit among the elderly.&#13;
&#13;
              Projections, based on expected age specific population growth trends,3 illustrate the growth of&#13;
              total labor income and consumption for different age groups (Figure 14). These projections&#13;
              assume that the current age profile of labor income and consumption remains constant; the only&#13;
              variable that drives the differences between the observed and projected curves is the differential&#13;
              population growth for different age groups. Thus, the total labor income expands as the share of&#13;
              working persons grows. Since the elderly earn a considerable amount of income, their income&#13;
              would also expand, but the total consumption of the elderly will increase even faster.&#13;
&#13;
                               Figure 14: Observed and Projected Total Labor Income and Total Consumption&#13;
                                                           (Public and Private)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                             Observed and Projected Total Labor Income and&#13;
                                                 Total Consumption (Public and Private)&#13;
                       80000&#13;
                       60000&#13;
Rs millions&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                       40000&#13;
                       20000&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        0    5     10   15   20    25    30   35    40      45   50   55   60    65     70     75   80   85   90&#13;
                                                                                           Age&#13;
                                                                         Observed YL 2007                  Projected YL 2040&#13;
&#13;
                                                                         Observed C 2007                   Projected C 2040&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
              As a result, the total life cycle deficit will expand substantially for the elderly, especially for the&#13;
              60 to 75 year olds (Figure 15). For people over 60 years old, demographic change will increase&#13;
              the life cycle deficit by more than three fold. The deficit of the young will also grow, but to a&#13;
              much smaller extent (9 percent for people under 20) due to low fertility.&#13;
&#13;
              3&#13;
                  Projections are based on UN estimates of age specific population growth for 5-year age groups between 2007 and 2040.&#13;
                                                                                     17&#13;
&amp;#12;                               Figure 15: Observed and Projected Total Life Cycle Deficit (C-YL)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   40000&#13;
                   20000&#13;
                               Observed and Projected Total Life Cycle Deficit (C-YL)&#13;
Rs Millions&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                           0&#13;
                -20000&#13;
                -40000&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                               0   5   10   15   20   25   30   35   40   45    50   55   60   65   70   75   80   85   90&#13;
                                                                          Age&#13;
&#13;
                                                      Observed 2007                       Projected 2040&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
              It is important to reiterate that these projections do not attempt to take into account possible&#13;
              changes in the cost of services, such as health, which â&#128;&#147; if they were to change â&#128;&#147; would impact&#13;
              the biggest users of health services, the elderly and the very young disproportionately, and would&#13;
              alter the projected deficit at the old age. Similarly, no possible additional effects on labor&#13;
              income, e.g., due to increased worker productivity, are accounted for.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                     18&#13;
&amp;#12;                                           5. Conclusion&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sri Lankaâ&#128;&#153;s aggregate age reallocation exhibits a strong downward trend with greater proportion&#13;
of resources flowing toward children than the elderly, reflecting the large share of children in Sri&#13;
Lankaâ&#128;&#153;s total population. Yet as the demographic transition continues, the share of the elderly in&#13;
the aggregate consumption will increase dramatically to reflect the greater number of the elderly&#13;
surviving to older ages and the higher cost of health care in old age. The life cycle deficit&#13;
projections support this view and predict the deficit for the elderly (65 and older) would grow by&#13;
246 percent, assuming the current pattern of distribution of total labor income and consumption.&#13;
&#13;
Naturally, the expected expansion of old-age deficit will have to be financed one way or another.&#13;
Contrary to expectations, the role played by remittances in financing the life cycle deficit is&#13;
rather limited overall. Even though the transfers play a greater role in financing consumption&#13;
among the elderly, they only account for 2.5 to 4.5 percent of consumption of the elderly.&#13;
&#13;
The contributions of public transfers are also low, even though they do play a greater role for&#13;
people in higher age brackets.&#13;
&#13;
Despite the progressive pattern of remittances and public transfers with age, there are reasons to&#13;
believe that these may be inadequate to offset the growing costs associated with aging, especially&#13;
the cost of healthcare. Given the low public spending on the elderly and modest public transfers&#13;
and remittances, household members have to finance the deficit through a combination of intra-&#13;
household transfers, and asset reallocation (dissaving, sale of assets). Sri Lankaâ&#128;&#153;s elderly also&#13;
seek to reduce the deficit by working well past their retirement age.&#13;
&#13;
However, regardless of the nature of the reallocation mechanism, the solution to the problem of&#13;
financing the projected growing numbers of the elderly must center on increasing the&#13;
productivity of the labor force. Income must be generated before it is allocated. Productivity, in&#13;
turn, could be stimulated through increased investment in education and vocational training, both&#13;
for the younger cohorts of low-skilled workers just entering the labor force and for those middle-&#13;
aged workers who require retraining.&#13;
&#13;
At the current stage, the lifecycle deficit financing seems to rely less on productivity and more&#13;
on early entry into the labor force and late retirement (driven by informal sector employment,&#13;
since formal sector retirement ages are low) with a non-trivial proportion of the elderly&#13;
continuing to work into their seventies. This is not a sustainable arrangement and efforts to&#13;
increase labor productivity should be made. Public investment in education and vocational&#13;
training is a key means toward this end.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                19&#13;
&amp;#12;                 Appendix A: Estimation of NTA components for Sri Lanka&#13;
&#13;
Labor income&#13;
&#13;
The age profile for labor income is calculated from the HIES survey data. It includes income&#13;
from wage employment and agricultural and non-agricultural self-employment, as well as civil&#13;
servantsâ&#128;&#153; pensions.4 Consistently with the NTA methodology, 1/3 of self-employment income is&#13;
attributed to labor, and the remaining 2/3 are attributed to assets.&#13;
&#13;
Macro controls on labor income were calculated as follows: compensation to employees plus&#13;
laborâ&#128;&#153;s share of income taxes and taxes on good and services. While the large part of the taxes on&#13;
goods and services (VAT and import taxes) is assigned to consumption, other taxes on&#13;
production should be assigned to labor in proportion to labor incomeâ&#128;&#153;s share in taxable income.5&#13;
The latter share is calculated from the survey data and is equal to 61 percent.&#13;
&#13;
Table A1 summarizes the macro-control parameters used for aggregate controls on income.&#13;
Labor income should also be adjusted upward to account for some taxes on production and&#13;
income, which are passed on to workers in the form of lower wage rates.&#13;
&#13;
                   Table 1: Aggregate Control Parameters for Income, 2007, Millions Rs.&#13;
&#13;
Labor income aggregate controls                                            Millions Rs.&#13;
Compensation to employees (a)                                                 1869325&#13;
Development subsidies (b)                                                        11239&#13;
Sources: (a) CEIC dataset of SL National accounts.&#13;
(b) Treasury of GoSL (2008) Financial Statements for the Year Ending on December 31,&#13;
2007.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
4&#13;
  In HIES, social pensions are not distinguished from civil servant pensions. To distinguish between the two we applied the cutoff value of 7200&#13;
rupees per year. The cutoff was calculated as follows: since there are two social pensions, which pay approximately 200 to 300 rupees per&#13;
month, any given individual is unlikely to receive more than 600 rupees per month in social pensions; the annual cutoff amount for the two&#13;
pensions is 600*12=7200 rupees.&#13;
5&#13;
  Taxable income is defined as income from all sources, except welfare payments (but including civil servants' pensions).&#13;
                                                                      20&#13;
&amp;#12;The following aggregate controls were applied to the calculation of taxes (Table A2).&#13;
&#13;
                       Table 2: Aggregate Control Parameters for Taxes, 2007, Millions Rs.&#13;
TAXES&#13;
Taxes related to consumption                                                            324273&#13;
  (1) VAT/G&amp;S                                                                           187452&#13;
     Alcohol                                                                             23723&#13;
     Tobacco                                                                             31437&#13;
     Petrol                                                                              17126&#13;
  (2) Stamp Duties/ Cess Levy/ Social Responsibility                                     25715&#13;
  (3) Port and AirPort Development Levy&#13;
Levy/RIDL/SCL                                                                            26700&#13;
  Taxes on foreign trade                                                                 84406&#13;
Tax related to both labor and assets&#13;
  Other taxes on production                                                              46290&#13;
     of these the labor part is 60.691%                                                  28094&#13;
  Income tax                                                                            107168&#13;
     of these the labor part is 60.691%                                                  65041&#13;
Taxes related to labor only&#13;
  Social security contributions                                                           8777&#13;
  TOTAL TAXES FOR ADJUSTING LABOR INCOME                                                101912&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Consumption&#13;
&#13;
We distinguish between private and public consumption, and within each of these, three distinct&#13;
components are identified: expenditure on health, expenditure on education, and other&#13;
expenditure. Separate age profiles are calculated for each of these components.&#13;
&#13;
Private consumption. To calculate private health expenditure age profile, we assign household-&#13;
level health expenditure to individual members based on their health service utilization rate from&#13;
the HIES data. The total household health expenditure is regressed on the number of household&#13;
members within a given age group, which used inpatient and outpatient services.&#13;
&#13;
Private expenditure on education - collected at the household level - is allocated to individual&#13;
household members indirectly using and OLS regression analysis. Household expenditure on&#13;
education is modeled as a function of the number of household members enrolled at each level of&#13;
schooling (primary, secondary, tertiary, not-enrolled6) by age category. The regression&#13;
coefficient in then interpreted as the cost associated with attendance at a given level of schooling&#13;
of an additional household member of a given age.&#13;
&#13;
Other private consumption is allocated according to the consumption age profile based on adult&#13;
equivalency weights.&#13;
&#13;
Aggregate controls on private consumption are summarized in Table A3. Because the&#13;
disaggregation of household consumption into health and education was not available for 2007,&#13;
2006 values were used to make 2007 projections.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
6&#13;
    Non-enrolled members can still have education expenditures on informal schooling.&#13;
                                                                      21&#13;
&amp;#12;                         Table 3: Private Consumption Aggregate Controls, Millions Rs&#13;
&#13;
Total household consumption (2007)                                                                       2403167&#13;
Household consumption, health (2006)                                                                       72827&#13;
Household consumption, education (2006)                                                                    30346&#13;
Total household consumption (2006)                                                                       1988378&#13;
Adjustment to 2006 levels of private consumption of health                                       2403167/1988378&#13;
servicesconsumption,&#13;
Private  and education  (a) (2007)&#13;
                       health                                                                              88019&#13;
Private consumption, education (2007)                                                                      36676&#13;
(a) Proportionate to increase in total private consumption&#13;
&#13;
Sources: Sri Lanka National Accounts from CEIC database&#13;
Public consumption. Public health expenditure age profile is based on age-specific utilization&#13;
rates of inpatient and outpatient care, which were then applied to the current public spending on&#13;
inpatient and outpatient services. Public preventative services expenditures were allocated&#13;
proportionately to population size; while expenditures on medical goods and other health&#13;
expenditures are allocated proportionately to the utilization rates of inpatient and outpatient&#13;
services.&#13;
&#13;
Public education is financed from the central government budget at the tertiary level, while&#13;
primary and secondary schooling is financed from central and provincial government budgets.&#13;
Thus, we consider general government spending, the total of central and provincial expenditures,&#13;
allocated to age groups based on the age profile for enrolment at each age.&#13;
&#13;
Public expenditure on education includes the cost of tuition, subsidized transportation,7 and - for&#13;
primary and secondary students - supplies, and uniforms, and nutritional support for&#13;
underprivileged children. Free uniforms and nutritional support could also be classified as&#13;
transfers; however, we consider them together with educational spending because they are&#13;
financed by the ministry of education and counted as part of education expenditure; furthermore,&#13;
their allocation is consistent with the age profile for enrolment.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
7&#13;
 School transportation is subsidized at 90 percent of regular transportation costs for primary and secondary students and at 70 percent for&#13;
university students.&#13;
                                                                      22&#13;
&amp;#12;Table 4: Aggregate Control Parameters for Current Public Expenditure on Education in&#13;
            Primary, Secondary and Tertiary Education, 2007, Millions Rs.&#13;
&#13;
          Category                                                                      Millions Rs.&#13;
         Personal Emoluments                                                                 58,467&#13;
          Welfare programs                                                                    13886&#13;
                 Text books                                                                    2,250&#13;
                 Uniforms                                                                      1,067&#13;
                 Scholarships                                                                    185&#13;
                 Nutritional food                                                              1,925&#13;
                 Season tickets                                                                  250&#13;
                 Other                                                                         8,209&#13;
          Total                                                                              72,353&#13;
          Source: Sri Lanka Ministry of Finance and Planning (2007). Annual Report 2007. Page 121.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                        23&#13;
&amp;#12;Detailed macro-level inputs for calculating public expenditure are reported in Table A5.&#13;
&#13;
               Table 5: Aggregate Controls on Public Expenditure, 2007, Millions Rs.&#13;
&#13;
       Total current expenditure of general government (a)                                                           622758&#13;
&#13;
         Public spending on education (b)                                                                             76343&#13;
           Primary                                                                                                    22304&#13;
              Central                                                                                                 20475&#13;
              Provincial                                                                                               1829&#13;
           Secondary                                                                                                  39584&#13;
              Central                                                                                                 31643&#13;
              Provincial                                                                                               7942&#13;
           Special education                                                                                           2231&#13;
              Central                                                                                                   129&#13;
              Provincial                                                                                               2102&#13;
           Vocational                                                                                                  1867&#13;
           Tertiary                                                                                                   10357&#13;
       Public spending on health (2007) (a)                                                                           54737&#13;
         Total current spending (public and private) on health (2005) (c)&#13;
            inpatient                                                                                                 39864&#13;
            outpatient                                                                                                24869&#13;
            medical goods                                                                                             26139&#13;
            preventive care                                                                                            6476&#13;
           other                                                                                                       7653&#13;
           Overall                                                                                                   105001&#13;
         Share of public by type of health services (2005) (c)&#13;
            inpatient                                                                                                  0.72&#13;
            outpatient                                                                                                 0.35&#13;
            medical goods                                                                                               0.1&#13;
            preventive care                                                                                            0.86&#13;
           other                                                                                                       0.24&#13;
         Public spending on health by type of health service, imputed for 2007&#13;
            inpatient                                                                                                 14962&#13;
            outpatient                                                                                                 4537&#13;
            medical goods                                                                                              1363&#13;
            preventive care                                                                                            2903&#13;
           other                                                                                                        957&#13;
       Source: (a) Ministry of Finance and Planning (2007) Annual report 2007;&#13;
       (b) Provided by Sri Lanka team, but consistent with Annual report 2007;&#13;
       (c) Health Policy Research Institute (2007). Population Ageing and Health Expenditure: Sri Lanka 2001-2101.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Transfers: public, private&#13;
&#13;
Private transfers are calculated as a total of foreign and domestic remittances, as well as in-kind&#13;
gifts.&#13;
Domestic and foreign remittances data are collected in the income section of the HIES survey;&#13;
the values of the two types of remittances is collected separately. The aggregate controls for&#13;
&#13;
                                                                 24&#13;
&amp;#12;foreign remittances come from the Sri Lanka national accounts and are allocated based on the&#13;
age profile of heads of households receiving such remittances.&#13;
&#13;
In-kind gifts exclude â&#128;&#156;giftedâ&#128;? material for uniforms, because the latter is publicly provided and&#13;
should be considered a public transfer. However, gifted ready-made uniforms and free uniform&#13;
tailoring services are counted in private transfers, because they fall outside of the scope of public&#13;
transfers to school children. The value of publicly provided uniforms is included in education&#13;
expenditure.&#13;
&#13;
Public transfers are dominated by Samurdhi benefit payments (Rs. 9200 million), and disability&#13;
payments (to disabled soldiers) at Rs. 7428 million; other welfare benefits amount to Rs. 5726&#13;
million. These transfers do not include development subsidies (agriculture, fuel, etc.). To allocate&#13;
welfare transfers we use the age-specific expenditure profile obtained from HIES, which is an&#13;
aggregate of Samurdhi, disability, and social pensions (pensions other than civil servant&#13;
pensions).&#13;
&#13;
            Table 6: Aggregate Control Parameters for Transfers, 2007, Millions Rs.&#13;
                Transfers, Millions Rs.&#13;
                Public welfare transfers&#13;
                   Samurdhi                                                    9200&#13;
                   Disabled soldiers                                           7428&#13;
                   Other                                                       5746&#13;
                Private transfers&#13;
                   Total foreign remittances                              276771.24&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 25&#13;
&amp;#12;                                        References&#13;
&#13;
Health Policy Research Institute (2007). Population Ageing and Health Expenditure: Sri Lanka&#13;
2001-2101.&#13;
&#13;
Lee, Ronald (2002). â&#128;&#156;Demographic Change, Welfare, and Intergenerational Transfers: A Global&#13;
Overview,â&#128;? http://www.ceda.berkeley.edu/papers/rlee/Text-Figs-Rome2.pdf&#13;
&#13;
Lee, Ronald, and Andrew Mason (2004). Macroeconomic Demography of International&#13;
Transfers. Washington, DC: National Institute of Aging.&#13;
&#13;
Mason, Andrew (2009). National Transfer Accounts: Introduction to Concepts. Presentation.&#13;
&#13;
Mason, Andrew, Ronald Lee, A. Tung, M. Lai, and Tim Miller (2006). â&#128;&#156;Population Aging and&#13;
Intergenerational Transfers: Introducing Age into National Accounts,â&#128;? National Bureau of&#13;
Economic Research, Working Paper 12770.&#13;
&#13;
Mason, Andrew, Ronald Lee, Gretchen Donehower, Sang-Hyop Lee, Tim Miller, An-Chi Tung,&#13;
and Amonthep Chawla (2009). â&#128;&#156;National Transfer Accounts Manual, Draft Version 1.0.â&#128;?&#13;
&#13;
Sri Lanka Ministry of Finance and Planning (2007). Annual Report 2007.&#13;
&#13;
Treasury of Government of Sri Lanka (2008). Financial Statements for the Year Ending on&#13;
December 31, 2007.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                             26&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="17036783">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2012/10/17036783/national-transfer-accounts-analysis-sri-lanka
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2012/10/17036783/national-transfer-accounts-analysis-sri-lanka</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2012/10/17036783/national-transfer-accounts-analysis-sri-lanka</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2012-12-05T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2012-12-05T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2012/12/05/000333037_20121205003445/Rendered/INDEX/NonAsciiFileName0.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2012/12/05/000333037_20121205003445/Rendered/PDF/NonAsciiFileName0.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2012-10-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2012-12-05T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            National transfer accounts analysis for Sri Lanka
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Sri Lanka has been going through a
            demographic transition triggered by decreasing fertility and
            increasing life expectancy. The demographic transition is
            marked by two stages. During the first stage, the drop in
            new births reduces the under-age dependency ratio, while the
            proportion of working age population expands. This reduction
            in dependency ratio due to declining fertility, frequently
            referred to as the demographic bonus, is associated with an
            increased pace of economic development due to the larger
            share of working age population relative to the total
            population, and the smaller pool of dependents that workers
            have to support. In the second stage of the demographic
            transition, the consistently low fertility rates in
            combination with increased life expectancy for the elderly,
            lead to the relative expansion of the old-age dependency
            ratio. As the demographic transition enters the second
            stage, the demographic bonus deteriorates. As Sri Lanka is
            going through a demographic transition, it is important to
            take stock of the ways labor income is produced and consumed
            by different age groups. Similarly, when a deficit or a gap
            between consumption and labor income emerges, it is
            important to know what type of expenditures drive it and how
            it is financed. This paper documents labor income and
            consumption patterns by age group in Sri Lanka, in a manner
            that is comparable to work carried out for other countries
            that participate in the National Transfer Accounts Project.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            National transfer accounts analysis for Sri Lanka
        </docna>
        <display_title>National transfer accounts
            analysis for Sri Lanka</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2012/10/17036783/national-transfer-accounts-analysis-sri-lanka</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Working Paper (Numbered Series)</docty>
        <subtopic>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation,Public Sector Economics,Inequality,Labor Policies,Population Policies</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Social Protections and Labor,Poverty Reduction,Public Sector Development,Health, Nutrition and Population</teratopic>
        <count>South Asia</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Nikitin, Denis</author>
            <author>Silva, Indralal de</author>
            <author>Jayasekara, Tissa</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000333037_20121205003445</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>South Asia,South Asia</admreg>
        <colti>South Asia Human Development Sector report
            no. 39</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Social Protections and Labor,Poverty Reduction,Public Sector Development,Health, Nutrition and Population</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            accounting, adult education, age
            distribution, aging, cross-country comparisons, decreasing
            fertility, deficit financing, demand side, demographic
            change, Demographic Transition, demographic trends,
            dependency burden, dependency ratio, Developed Countries,
            Developing Countries, disability, Economic Development,
            economic performance, Economic Research, elderly, elderly
            population, employment, families, fertility, fertility rate,
            fertility rates, foreign trade, government spending, health
            care, health outcomes, Health Policy, health problems,
            health services, health spending, Household Income,
            household level, household members, household surveys, human
            capital, Human Development, important policy, income taxes,
            individual members, International comparisons, investment in
            education, labor force, labor force participation, labor
            market, labor policies, labor productivity, legal status,
            life expectancy, low fertility, ministry of education,
            Motivation, number of persons, nutritional needs,
            occupations, old age, old-age, opportunity cost, outpatient
            care, participation of women, pensions, per capita
            consumption, per capita income, Policy Research, Population
            growth, population growth trends, population size, primary
            schooling, private consumption, public, public consumption,
            Public education, Public Expenditure, public health, Public
            health expenditure, public investment, Public investment in
            education, public provision, public resources, public
            sector, public services, public spending, public support,
            public transfer, public transfers, regression analysis,
            relative importance, remittance, remittances, rents,
            respect, retirement, safety, safety nets, savings, school
            age, school children, school-age children, secondary
            schooling, sector employment, serious implications,
            servants, service utilization, skilled labor, skilled
            workers, social safety, social safety nets, Social security,
            social welfare, Tax, Tertiary Education, tertiary level,
            transportation, Treasury, vocational training, wages, worker
            productivity, young adults, young age, young people, youth employment
        </keywd>
        <owner>Social Protection - East/South (AFTSE)</owner>
        <repnb>74170</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Expenditure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographic Transition</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Investment in Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Provision of Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Provision of Education Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private School</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Funds</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Funds and Pensions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Zero Pillar</ml:concept><ml:concept>Higher Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Tertiary Education – Enhancing Access, Equity and Quality</ml:concept><ml:concept>Continuous Vocational Training (CVT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Lifelong Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Strengthening Technical Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Strengthening Vocational Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Technical Vocational Education and Training Policies and Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Technical and Vocational Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Vocational Education and Training</ml:concept><ml:concept>Vocational Training</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pensions &amp; Retirement Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Efficiency of Public Expenditures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Expenditures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Financial Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Spending</ml:concept><ml:concept>Remittances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Migration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wage Setting</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages, Compensation and Benefits</ml:concept><ml:concept>Children and Youth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Boundaries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government Expenditure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographic Change</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Elderly</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Pensions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Youth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Tertiary Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pensions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Managing Public Finances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Movement of Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Southern Asia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>