<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>﻿OFFICIAL f&#13;
CUMENTS&#13;
The World Bank                                   1818 H Street N.W.      (202) 473-1000&#13;
INTERNATIONAL BANK FOR RECONSTRUCTION AND DEVELOPMENT  Washington, D.C. 20433  Cable Address: INTBAFRAD&#13;
INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPMENT ASSOCIATION            U.S.A.                 Cable Address: INDEVAS&#13;
Dated,6c%t),9xM1   9 16,L&#13;
Mr. Michel Mordasini&#13;
Head of Corporate Domain Global Cooperation&#13;
Swiss Agency for Development and Cooperation SDC&#13;
Freiburgstrasse 130&#13;
CH - 3003 Bern&#13;
Switzerland&#13;
Trust Fund Administration Agreement between Switzerland, acting&#13;
through the Swiss Federal Department of Foreign Affairs and the&#13;
International Bank for Reconstruction and Development and the&#13;
International Development Association concerning the Umbrella&#13;
Facility for Gender Equality (UFGE) Multi-Donor Trust Fund&#13;
(No.TFO71893)&#13;
Dear Mr. Mordasini:&#13;
1.    We are pleased to acknowledge on behalf of the International Bank for&#13;
Reconstruction and Development ("IBRD") and the International Development&#13;
Association ("IDA") (collectively, the "Bank") that the Government of Switzerland,&#13;
acting through the Swiss Federal Department of Foreign Affairs (the "Donor") hereby&#13;
approves to transfer to the Umbrella Facility for Gender Equality (UFGE) Multi-Donor&#13;
Trust Fund (the "Trust Fund") the unused amounts in the Multi-donor Trust Fund for the&#13;
Gender Action Plan TF070751 attributable to the Donor and United States Dollars One&#13;
Million (USD 1,000,000) from the Swiss Donor Balance Account TF029056&#13;
(the "Contribution") in accordance with the terms of this Agreement. Other donors are&#13;
also expected to contribute to the Trust Fund on the terms and conditions specified in the&#13;
Annexes to this Agreement.&#13;
2.    The Contribution shall be used to finance the activities and the categories of&#13;
expenditure set forth in the "Description of Activities, Allocation of Funds and&#13;
Expenditures under the UFGE Multi-Donor Trust Fund" attached hereto as Annex 1, and&#13;
shall be administered by the Bank on behalf of the Donor in accordance with the terms of&#13;
this Agreement including the "Standard Provisions Applicable to the UFGE Multi-Donor&#13;
Trust Fund" (the "Standard Provisions") attached hereto as Annex 2 and "Governance&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-2-&#13;
and Other Terms Applicable to the UFGE Multi Donor Trust Fund" attached hereto as&#13;
Annex 3.&#13;
3.    The first portion of the Contribution will use funds from the Gender Action Plan&#13;
(GAP) TF070751 Multi-Donor Trust Fund. Accordingly, the Donor hereby authorizes the&#13;
Bank, to promptly following countersignature of this Agreement, transfer the sum of&#13;
Sixty-one thousand four hundred and ninety six United States Dollars and two cents&#13;
(USD 61,496.02) plus the Donor's pro-rata share of any investment income that may&#13;
have accrued until the date of transfer from the GAP Trust Fund (TF07075 1) to the&#13;
Umbrella Facility for Gender Equality (UFGE) Multi-Donor Trust Fund TF071893.&#13;
4.    The second portion of the Contribution will use funds from the Swiss Donor&#13;
Balance Account TF029056. Accordingly, the Donor hereby authorizes the Bank, to&#13;
promptly following countersignature of this Agreement, transfer the sum of one million&#13;
United States Dollars (USD 1,000,000) from the Swiss Donor Balance Account&#13;
TF029056 to the Umbrella Facility for Gender Equality (UFGE) Multi-Donor Trust Fund&#13;
TFO71893.&#13;
6.    Any notice, request or other communication to be given or made under this&#13;
Agreement shall be in writing and delivered by mail, facsimile or e-mail to the respective&#13;
party's address specified below or at such other address as such party notifies in writing&#13;
to the other party from time to time:&#13;
For the Bank:&#13;
Sarah Nedolast&#13;
Senior Program Coordinator&#13;
Gender and Development&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
1818 H Street, NW&#13;
Washington, DC 20433&#13;
Tel: 202-473-2890&#13;
Fax: 202-522-3237&#13;
E-mail: snedolast@worldbank.org&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-3-&#13;
For the Donor:&#13;
Ursula Funk&#13;
Senior Advisor&#13;
Division Global Institutions&#13;
Swiss Agency for Development and Cooperation SDC&#13;
Freiburgstrasse 130&#13;
CH - 3003 Bern&#13;
Tel: (0)31 324 83 66&#13;
Fax: (0)31 324 13 47&#13;
E-mail: ursula.funk@deza.admin.ch&#13;
7.    Notwithstanding section 3.1 of Annex 2 of this Administration Agreement, the&#13;
Bank will not deduct and will not retain for its own account, the amount of 2% referred to&#13;
in such section, from the funds that are being transferred upon the Donor's instructions&#13;
from the GAP Trust Fund (TF07075 1), as Contribution to this UFGE TFO71893.&#13;
8.    All annexes hereto constitute an integral part of this Agreement. This Agreement&#13;
may be amended only in writing between the Bank and the Donor; provided, however,&#13;
that such annexes may be amended only with the agreement of all donors contributing to&#13;
the Trust Fund.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-4-&#13;
9.    Please confirm your agreement with the foregoing, on behalf of the Donor, by&#13;
signing, dating, and returning to us the enclosed copy of this Agreement. Upon receipt by&#13;
the Bank of the copy of this Agreement countersigned by you, this Agreement will&#13;
become effective as of the date of the countersignature.&#13;
Sincerely,&#13;
INTERNATIONAL BANK FOR RECONSTRUCTION AND DEVELOPMENT&#13;
INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPMENT ASSOCIATION&#13;
Jen Klugma&#13;
Director, Gen eir and  eeomn&#13;
AGREED:&#13;
Swiss Agency for Development and Cooperation (SDC)&#13;
By:                                           Date:&#13;
Name: Michel Mordasini&#13;
Title: Head Corporate Domain Global Cooperation&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-5-&#13;
ANNEX 1&#13;
Description of Activities, Criteria for Allocation of Funds, and Expenditures under&#13;
the UFGE Multi-Donor Trust Fund&#13;
This Annex will be applicable to and form an integral part of all agreements&#13;
entered into between the Bank and entities (collectively, the "Donors") that provide&#13;
contributions (the aggregate of all contributions from the Donors, the "Contributions") to&#13;
be administered by the Bank for the Trust Fund.&#13;
A. DESCRIPTION OF ACTIVITIES&#13;
The main objective of the Trust Fund is to strengthen awareness, knowledge, and&#13;
capacity for gender-informed policy making and programs. The Trust Fund will support&#13;
activities that contribute to better gender-informed policy making at the country level by&#13;
increasing the availability of gender-relevant data and evidence; contribute to global&#13;
knowledge by road testing new evidence; and help raise awareness of and demand for&#13;
gender equality interventions by working in partnership with client governments, civil&#13;
society, research institutes, academia, the private sector, and development partners.&#13;
Activities&#13;
The Trust Fund will finance activities with a strong 'public good' element, as well as&#13;
those that are innovative and push the frontiers of gender equality work. Activities to be&#13;
financed by the Trust Fund will fall under three main priority areas:&#13;
I.      Increasing availability of gender-relevant data and evidence. Activities will&#13;
include addressing data gaps, making existing data more accessible and building&#13;
evidence in frontier areas and those where gender gaps persist.&#13;
II.     Road testing new evidence. Activities will include identifying relevant lessons&#13;
on how development practitioners can effectively translate new evidence into&#13;
results on the ground, such as strengthening and expanding successful&#13;
approaches.&#13;
III.    Leveraging partnerships to help advance gender equality. Under this&#13;
activity the Bank will engage civil society and private sector, especially from&#13;
developing client countries to identify, disseminate and implement innovative&#13;
gender equality initiatives.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-6-&#13;
The implementation of the activities to be financed by the Trust Fund is as follows:&#13;
(I)   Bank-Executed Trust Fund Activities:&#13;
(a)   Activities related to priority areas I (Increasing availability of gender-&#13;
relevant data and evidence) II (Road testing new evidence), and III&#13;
(Leveraging partnerships) mentioned above.&#13;
(b)   Program   Management, Program    Administration  and  Knowledge&#13;
Management: The PREM Gender and Development Group (PRMGE) will&#13;
coordinate the day to day activities including leveraging global&#13;
partnerships,  aggregate  knowledge  management  activities  and&#13;
administering the Trust Fund, working in close collaboration with regions&#13;
and networks.&#13;
(II)  Recipient-Executed Trust Fund Activities:&#13;
(a)   Activities related to priority areas I (Increasing availability of gender-&#13;
relevant data and evidence), and II (Road testing new evidence).&#13;
B. CRITERIA FOR ALLOCATION OF FUNDS&#13;
The Gender and Development (GAD) Board is responsible for allocation decisions, and&#13;
ensuring that such allocations are aligned with the objectives of the UFGE and the&#13;
strategy for gender mainstreaming in the Bank.&#13;
The GAD Board will make allocation decisions based on the following general criteria:&#13;
* Alignment with the Bank's strategy for gender mainstreaming.&#13;
* Alignment with Regional needs and priorities, as laid out in the Regional Gender&#13;
Action Plans.&#13;
* Alignment with the overall objectives of the UFGE: to strengthen awareness,&#13;
knowledge and capacity for gender-informed policy making.&#13;
* Extent to which activities have a strong public-good rationale and/or are catalysts&#13;
for innovation and investment in frontier issues and persistent gaps.&#13;
Funds under the UFGE will mainly be allocated through:&#13;
B. 1. Strategic Allocations&#13;
a)     Strategic Activities: Activities related to priority areas I (Increasing&#13;
availability of gender-relevant data and evidence) II (Road testing new&#13;
evidence), and III (Leveraging partnerships) mentioned above.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-7-&#13;
b)      Regional Block Grants (for both, Bank and Recipient execution):&#13;
These will cover a three-year period and be considered once every 18&#13;
months, depending on funding availability. Proposals must be endorsed&#13;
by the Regional Vice President. The GAD Board will review and&#13;
approve proposals based on the criteria above.&#13;
B. 2. Competitive Calls for Proposals&#13;
A portion of the Trust Fund may be used for competitive calls for proposals for&#13;
Bank executed activities. The intent of this mechanism is to incentivize Bank teams to&#13;
undertake activities in areas where the agenda on gender equality needs a push. It might&#13;
also be used to address areas where the implementation of the 2012 WDR is lagging.&#13;
A Technical Review Committee, consisting of World Bank experts, would be&#13;
convened to establish criteria for a call for proposals and to review and rank those that are&#13;
submitted. The GAD Board will endorse the criteria and clear the selection of proposals.&#13;
B. 3. PRMGE Managed Allocation&#13;
The focus under this allocation is priority area III (leveraging partnerships) as&#13;
described above, as well as activities that will include aggregate knowledge management&#13;
and UFGE's Program management and administration, to be carried out by PRMGE.&#13;
C.     ELIGIBLE CATEGORIES OF EXPENDITURE&#13;
For Bank-Executed activities the Contributions may be used to finance:&#13;
(a)   consultants' services (individuals and firms);&#13;
(b)   extended term consultants;&#13;
(c)   associated overheads (e.g., telephone, fax, internet connection expenses&#13;
during mission travel, telecommunications for learning events, etc.);&#13;
(d)   contractual services;&#13;
(e)   staff costs, benefits and indirects (e.g., communications, use of office&#13;
space and IT equipment by staff, etc.);&#13;
(f)   travel expenses (including travel related charges and subsistence for staff,&#13;
consultants and workshop participants, etc.);&#13;
(g)   media, workshop, conference and meeting expenses (including external&#13;
participant costs, honoraria, facilities for events, etc.); and&#13;
(h)   temporary support staff costs.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-8-&#13;
For Recipient-Executed activities, the Contributions may be used to finance eligible&#13;
expenditures in accordance with the Bank's applicable policies and procedures.&#13;
The foregoing categories of expenditures may include the financing of taxes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-9-&#13;
ANNEX 2&#13;
Standard Provisions Applicable to the UFGE Multi-Donor Trust Fund&#13;
This Annex will be applicable to and form an integral part of all agreements&#13;
entered into between the Bank and the Donors that provide Contributions to be&#13;
administered by the Bank for the Trust Fund.&#13;
1.    Administration of the Contributions&#13;
1.1.  The Bank will be responsible only for performing those functions specifically set&#13;
forth in this Arrangement and will not be subject to any other duties or responsibilities to&#13;
the Donors, including, without limitation, any duties or obligations that might otherwise&#13;
apply to a fiduciary or trustee under general principles of trust or fiduciary law. Nothing&#13;
in this Arrangement will be considered a waiver of any privileges or immunities of the&#13;
IBRD and IDA under their Articles of Agreement or any applicable law, all of which are&#13;
expressly reserved.&#13;
1.2.  The Contribution will be administered in accordance with the Bank's applicable&#13;
policies and procedures, as the same may be amended from time to time, including its&#13;
framework to prevent and combat fraud and corruption and its screening procedures to&#13;
prevent the use of Bank resources to finance terrorist activity, in line with the Bank's&#13;
obligations to give effect to the relevant decisions of the Security Council, taken under&#13;
Chapter VII of the of Charter of the United Nations. The Donor acknowledges that this&#13;
provision does not create any obligations of the Bank under the anti-terrorist financing&#13;
and asset control laws, regulations, rules and executive orders of an individual member&#13;
country that may apply to the Donor, nor will it be deemed a waiver, express or implied,&#13;
of any of the privileges and immunities of the Bank.&#13;
2.    Commingling, Exchange and Investment of the Contributions&#13;
2.1.  The Contributions will be accounted for as a single trust fund and will be kept&#13;
separate and apart from the funds of the Bank. The Contributions may be commingled&#13;
with other trust fund assets maintained by the Bank.&#13;
2.2.  The Contributions may be freely exchanged by the Bank into other currencies as&#13;
may facilitate their disbursement.&#13;
2.3.  The Bank will invest and reinvest the Contributions pending their disbursement in&#13;
accordance with the Bank's policies and procedures for the investment of trust funds&#13;
administered by the Bank. The Bank will credit all income from such investment to the&#13;
Trust Fund to be used for the same purposes as the Contributions.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿- 10 -&#13;
3.    Administrative Cost Recovery&#13;
3.1   the Bank may deduct and retain for its own account, as a deduction from each&#13;
Installment, an amount equal to two percent (2%) per Installment as an administrative fee&#13;
for the Trust Fund.&#13;
3.2   In addition, costs incurred by the Bank for other expenses, such as for program&#13;
management and Trust Fund administration will be charged to the Trust Fund on an&#13;
actual basis up to a maximum of three percent (3%) of the total Contributions under all&#13;
Administration Agreements.&#13;
3.3   Each Donor acknowledges and agrees that the percentage deductions for fees in&#13;
this Trust Fund Fees and Costs section are estimated on the basis of anticipated&#13;
Contributions. If actual Contributions significantly differ from what was originally&#13;
anticipated at the time of signature of the first Administration Agreement, or if other&#13;
circumstances affecting Trust Fund fees or costs change, the Bank reserves the right to&#13;
request a change to the terms of this Trust Fund Fees and Costs section, which would be&#13;
effectuated by amendments made to the Administration Agreements of all Donors and&#13;
which would thereafter be applicable to all new Contributions that are provided either as&#13;
amendments to supplement existing Administration Agreements or from new Donors&#13;
under new Administration Agreements.&#13;
4.    Grants to Recipients&#13;
4.1.  The Bank will, as administrator of the Trust Fund on behalf of the Donors, enter&#13;
into grant agreements (the "Grant Agreements") with eligible recipients selected in&#13;
accordance with the Criteria for Allocation of Funds under Annex 1 (the "Recipients")&#13;
consistent with the purposes of this Arrangement and on the terms and conditions set&#13;
forth in the Grant Agreements. Grant Agreements may be entered into up to the&#13;
maximum amount of the Contributions that all Donors have agreed to make available&#13;
under the Administration Agreements between the Bank and the Donors. Upon request&#13;
by a Donor, the Bank will furnish a copy of the Grant Agreements to the Donors.&#13;
4.2.  The Bank will be responsible for the supervision of the activities financed under&#13;
the Grant Agreements. Subject to the consent of the relevant Recipients, representatives&#13;
of the Donors may be invited by the Bank to participate in Bank supervision missions&#13;
related to the Trust Fund.&#13;
4.3.  The Bank will promptly inform the Donors of any significant modification to the&#13;
terms of any Grant Agreements and of any contractual remedies that are exercised by the&#13;
Bank under any Grant Agreements. To the extent practicable, the Bank will afford the&#13;
Donors the opportunity to exchange views before effecting any such modification or&#13;
exercising any such remedy.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿- 11 -&#13;
5.    Procurement&#13;
5.1.  For Recipient-executed activities, the Grant Agreements will provide that the&#13;
Contributions will be used by the Recipients to finance expenditures for goods and&#13;
services, as the case may be, in accordance with the Bank's Guidelines on "Procurement&#13;
under IBRD Loans and IDA Credits" and the Bank's Guidelines on the "Selection and&#13;
Employment of Consultants by World Bank Borrowers," as in effect at the date of entry&#13;
into the respective Grant Agreements.&#13;
5.2.  For Bank-executed activities, the employment and supervision of any consultants&#13;
and the procurement of any goods financed by the Contributions will be the responsibility&#13;
of the Bank and will be carried out in accordance with its applicable policies and&#13;
procedures.&#13;
6.    Accounting and Financial Reporting&#13;
6.1.  The Bank will maintain separate records and ledger accounts in respect of the&#13;
Contributions deposited in the Trust Fund account and disbursements made therefrom.&#13;
6.2.  The Bank will furnish to the Donors current financial information relating to&#13;
receipts, disbursements and fund balance in the holding currency of the Trust Fund with&#13;
respect to the Contributions via the World Bank's Trust Funds Donor Center secure&#13;
website. Within six (6) months after all commitments and liabilities under the Trust Fund&#13;
have been satisfied and the Trust Fund has been closed, the final financial information&#13;
relating to receipts, disbursements and fund balance in the holding currency of the Trust&#13;
Fund with respect to the Contributions will be made available to the Donors via the&#13;
World Bank's Trust Funds Donor Center secure website.&#13;
6.3.  The Bank will provide to the Donors, within six (6) months following the end of&#13;
each Bank fiscal year, an annual single audit report, comprising (1) a management&#13;
assertion together with an attestation from the Bank's external auditors concerning the&#13;
adequacy of internal control over cash-based financial reporting for all cash-based trust&#13;
funds as a whole; and (2) a combined financial statement for all cash-based trust funds&#13;
together with the Bank's external auditor's opinion thereon. The cost of the single audit&#13;
will be bome by the Bank.&#13;
6.4.  If a Donor wishes to request, on an exceptional basis, a financial statement audit&#13;
by the Bank's external auditors of the Trust Fund, the Donor and the Bank will first&#13;
consult as to whether such an external audit is necessary. The Bank and the Donor will&#13;
agree on the appropriate scope and terms of reference of such audit. Following&#13;
acceptance on the scope and terms of reference, the Bank will arrange for such external&#13;
audit. The costs of any such audit, including the internal costs of the Bank with respect to&#13;
such audit, will be paid by the requesting Donor.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿- 12 -&#13;
6.5.  The Bank will provide the Donors with copies of all financial statements and&#13;
auditors' reports received by the Bank from the Recipient(s) pursuant to the Grant&#13;
Agreements.&#13;
7.    Progress Reporting&#13;
7.1.  The Bank will provide the Donors with an annual report on the progress of&#13;
activities financed by the Contributions. Within six (6) months of the final disbursement&#13;
date specified in paragraph 8.2, the Bank will furnish to the Donors a final report on the&#13;
activities financed by the Trust Fund.&#13;
7.2   Any Donor may review or evaluate activities financed by the Trust Fund. The&#13;
Donor and the Bank will agree on the scope and conduct of such review or evaluation,&#13;
and the Bank will provide all relevant information within the limits of its policies and&#13;
procedures. All associated costs will be borne by the Donor. It is understood that any&#13;
such review or evaluation will not constitute a financial, compliance or other audit of the&#13;
Trust Fund.&#13;
8.    Disbursement; Cancellation: Refund&#13;
8.1.   The Contributions may be used to retroactively finance payments made as of&#13;
June 01, 2012 for eligible expenditures in accordance with the Bank's policies and&#13;
procedures.&#13;
8.2   It is expected that the Contributions will be fully disbursed by the Bank by&#13;
June 30, 2017. The Bank will only disburse Contributions for the purposes of this&#13;
Arrangement after such date with the written approval of the Donors.&#13;
8.3   Any Donor or the Bank may, upon three (3) months' prior written notice, cancel&#13;
all or part of the Donor's pro rata share, of any remaining balance of the Contributions&#13;
that is not committed pursuant to any agreements entered into between the Bank and any&#13;
consultants and/or other third parties for the purposes of this Arrangement prior to the&#13;
receipt of such notice, including the Grant Agreements.&#13;
8.4.  Following the final disbursement date specified in paragraph 8.2, the Bank will&#13;
return any remaining balance of the Contributions to the Donors or to the relevant Donor&#13;
Balance Account on a pro rata basis based on the Donors' paid Contributions. In the&#13;
event of a cancellation the Bank will promptly return to the relevant Donor or Donors or&#13;
to the relevant Donor Balance Account the Donor's pro rata share of uncommitted&#13;
Contributions in accordance with paragraph 8.3.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿- 13 -&#13;
9.    Disclosure; Dispute Resolution&#13;
9.1   The Bank shall disclose the Administration Agreements and related information&#13;
on this Trust Fund in accordance with the Bank's Policy on Access to Information. By&#13;
entering into Administration Agreements, the Donors consent to such disclosure of their&#13;
respective Administration Agreements and such related information.&#13;
9.2   The Donors and the Bank shall use their best efforts to amicably settle any&#13;
dispute, controversy, or claim arising out of or relating to the Administration&#13;
Agreements.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿- 14 -&#13;
ANNEX 3&#13;
Governance and Other Terms Applicable to the UFGE Multi-Donor Trust Fund&#13;
The following governance terms will apply to the Gender Equality (UFGE) Trust Fund:&#13;
1.    The Donors agree that the Bank has responsibility for Trust Fund operations&#13;
under the terms of this Administration Arrangement, including with respect to the&#13;
allocation of funds, the implementation of Bank-executed activities and the supervision&#13;
of Recipient-executed activities. For clarity, decisions on work programs and allocation&#13;
of funds will be made by the Bank.&#13;
2.    The Bank agrees to convene annual meetings to which all Donors are invited&#13;
("Annual Consultations"). The purpose of the Annual Consultations is for the Bank and&#13;
the Donors to discuss:&#13;
a) Results (as defined below) presented by the Bank;&#13;
b) future program plans presented by the Bank;&#13;
c) broad strategic guidance reflective of (a) and (b).&#13;
3.    "Results" will be reported by the Bank and reviewed at the Annual Consultations&#13;
on the basis of a results framework for the Trust Fund issued by the Bank upon&#13;
establishment of the Trust Fund, derived from the results framework of the relevant&#13;
Bank-endorsed sector / thematic strategy and providing sufficient granularity to reflect&#13;
the anticipated contribution of the Trust Fund, as may be modified over time to reflect&#13;
actual Contributions and other external factors.&#13;
4.    Progress reporting will occur on a unified, common basis for all Donors.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="17040837">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2012/11/17040837/official-documents--administration-agreement-switzerland-contribution-tf071893
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2012/11/17040837/official-documents--administration-agreement-switzerland-contribution-tf071893</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2012/11/17040837/official-documents--administration-agreement-switzerland-contribution-tf071893</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2012-12-05T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2012-12-05T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <docm_id>090224b0817dc3d4</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b0817dc3d4</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/PREM/2012/12/05/090224b0817dc3d4/1_0/Rendered/INDEX/Official0Docum0ribution0to0TF071893.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/PREM/2012/12/05/090224b0817dc3d4/1_0/Rendered/PDF/Official0Docum0ribution0to0TF071893.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2012-11-09T16:58:16Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2012-12-05T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docna>
            Official Documents- Administration Agreement
            with Switzerland for Contribution to TF071893
        </docna>
        <display_title>Official Documents-
            Administration Agreement with Switzerland for Contribution
            to TF071893</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/2012/11/17040837/official-documents--administration-agreement-switzerland-contribution-tf071893</listing_relative_url>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <docty>Trust Fund Administrative Agreement</docty>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Akerova,Anarkan</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>HQBOCS</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <owner>Gender and Development (PRMGE)</owner>
        <trustfund>TF071893-Umbrella Facility for Gender
            Equality (UFGE)</trustfund>
        <lang>English</lang>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT for Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies (ICT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Arts and Culture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Gender</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutritional supplements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Vitamins</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>Freedom of Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure and Networks (National; State; Local)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunication and Network Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunications</ml:concept><ml:concept>Bank Supervision</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enforcement of Judgements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Informal Dispute Resolution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Gender and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civil Society</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Media</ml:concept><ml:concept>Privileges and Immunities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supplements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Right to Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>External Audit</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunications and Broadband Access</ml:concept><ml:concept>Bank Regulation and Supervision</ml:concept><ml:concept>Knowledge Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Dispute Resolution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Gender and Human Development</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>