<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>﻿OFFICIAL&#13;
DOCUMENTS1&#13;
The World Bank                                 1818 H Street N.W.  (202) 473-1000&#13;
INTERNATIONAL BANK FOR RECONSTRUCTION AND DEVELOPMENT  Washington, D.C. 20433  Cable Address: INTBAFRAD&#13;
INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPMENT ASSOCIATION          U.S.A.              Cable Address: INDEVAS&#13;
Date: NW       1,2,,01-&#13;
Mr. Marc Trouyet&#13;
Chef de la Mission de la Gouvernance D6mocratique&#13;
Direction de l'Economie Globale et des Strat6gies de D6veloppement&#13;
Direction G6n6rale de la Mondialisation, du D6veloppement et des Partenariats&#13;
Ministere des Affaires Etrangeres&#13;
27 Rue de la Convention&#13;
CS91533 - 75732 Paris - Cedex 15&#13;
France&#13;
Trust Fund Administration Agreement between the French Republic,&#13;
acting through its Ministry of Foreign Affairs and the International&#13;
Bank for Reconstruction and Development and the International&#13;
Development Association concerning the Public Expenditure and&#13;
Financial Accountability Program, Phase IV Multi-Donor Trust Fund&#13;
(TFO71895)&#13;
Dear Mr. Trouyet:&#13;
1.    We are pleased to acknowledge on behalf of the International Bank for&#13;
Reconstruction and Development ("IBRD") and the International Development Association&#13;
("IDA") (collectively, the "Bank") that the French Republic, acting through its Ministry of&#13;
Foreign Affairs (the "Donor") has agreed to make available as a grant the sum of seventy&#13;
thousand Euro (E70,OOO) (the "Contribution") for the Public Expenditure and Financial&#13;
Accountability Program ("PEFA"), Phase IV Multi-Donor Trust Fund (the "Trust Fund") in&#13;
accordance with the terms of this Agreement. Other donors are also expected to contribute&#13;
to the Trust Fund on the terms and conditions specified in the Annexes to this Agreement.&#13;
2.    The Contribution shall be used to finance the activities and the categories of&#13;
expenditure set forth in the "Description of Activities, Expenditures and Governance&#13;
Arrangements under the Public Expenditure and Financial Accountability Program, Phase&#13;
IV Multi-Donor Trust Fund" attached hereto as Annex 1, and shall be administered by the&#13;
Bank on behalf of the Donor in accordance with the terms of this Agreement including the&#13;
"Standard Provisions Applicable to the Public Expenditure and Financial Accountability&#13;
Program, Phase IV Multi-Donor Trust Fund" (the "Standard Provisions") attached hereto as&#13;
Annex 2.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-2-&#13;
3.    The Donor shall deposit the Contribution into such bank account designated by the&#13;
Bank promptly following countersignature of this Agreement by the Donor and submission&#13;
of a payment request by the Bank.&#13;
4.    When making such deposit, the Donor shall instruct its bank to include in its&#13;
payment details information (remittance advice) field of its SWIFT payment message,&#13;
information indicating: the amount paid, that the payment is made by the Donor for the&#13;
Public Expenditure and Financial Accountability Program, Phase IV Trust Fund, and the&#13;
date of the deposit (the "Deposit Instruction"). In addition, the Donor shall provide a copy&#13;
of the Donor's Deposit Instruction to the Bank's Accounting Trust Funds Division by e-mail&#13;
sent to tfremitadvice@worldbank.org or by fax sent to (202) 614-1315.&#13;
5.    The Bank shall convert the Contribution funds into the holding currency of the Trust&#13;
Fund, namely United States Dollars, promptly upon receipt of the Contribution funds and&#13;
the Deposit Instruction containing the information specified in paragraph 4 at the exchange&#13;
rate obtained by the Bank on the date of the conversion. Where the Contribution proves to&#13;
be insufficient to complete the activities as a result of an exchange rate fluctuation, neither&#13;
the Bank nor the Donor shall bear any responsibility for providing any additional financing.&#13;
6.    Except as provided for in paragraph 4 above, any notice, request or other&#13;
communication to be given or made under this Agreement shall be in writing and delivered&#13;
by mail, facsimile or e-mail to the respective party's address specified below or at such other&#13;
address as such party notifies in writing to the other party from time to time:&#13;
For the Bank:&#13;
Mr. Nick Manning&#13;
Director&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
1818 H Street, NW&#13;
Washington, DC 20433&#13;
U.S.A.&#13;
Tel: 1-202-473-1202&#13;
Fax: 1-202-522-7132&#13;
E-mail: nmanning@worldbank.org&#13;
and&#13;
Mr. Phil Sinnett&#13;
Program Manager, PRMPS&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
1818 H Street, NW&#13;
Washington, DC 20433&#13;
U.S.A.&#13;
Tel: 1-202-473-8619&#13;
Fax: 1-202-522-7132&#13;
E-mail: psinnett2pefa.or&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-3-&#13;
For the Donor:&#13;
Mr. Marc Trouyet&#13;
Chef de la mission de la gouvernance démocratique&#13;
Direction générale de la mondialisation, du développement et des partenariats&#13;
Direction de l'Economie Globale et des Stratégies du Développement&#13;
27 Rue de la Convention&#13;
CS91533 - 75732 Paris Cedex 15&#13;
France&#13;
Tel: +33 1 43 17 66 65&#13;
Fax: +33 1 43 17 73 91&#13;
e-mail: marc.trouyet@diplomatie.gouv.fr&#13;
and&#13;
Mr. Patrick Buzaud&#13;
Ministère des Affaires étrangères&#13;
Direction générale de la mondialisation, du développement et des partenariats&#13;
Direction de l'Economie Globale et des Stratégies du Développement&#13;
Mission de la Gouvernance Démocratique&#13;
27 Rue de la Convention&#13;
CS91533 - 75732 Paris Cedex 15&#13;
France&#13;
Tel: +33 143 17 67 27&#13;
Fax: +33 1 43 17 69 24&#13;
E-mail: patrick.buzaud@diplomatie.gouv.fr&#13;
and&#13;
Ms. Audrey Perraud&#13;
Ministère des Affaires étrangères&#13;
Direction générale de la mondialisation, du développement et des partenariats&#13;
Direction de l'Economie Globale et des Stratégies du Développement&#13;
Mission de la Gouvernance Démocratique&#13;
27 Rue de la Convention&#13;
CS91533 - 75732 Paris Cedex 15&#13;
France&#13;
Tel: +33 1 43 17 67 27&#13;
Fax: +33 1 43 17 73 91&#13;
E-mail: audrey.peraud@diplomatie.gouv.fr&#13;
7.    All annexes hereto constitute an integral part of this Agreement. This Agreement&#13;
may be amended only in writing between the Bank and the Donor; provided, however, that&#13;
such annexes may be amended only with the agreement of all donors contributing to the&#13;
Trust Fund.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-4-&#13;
8.     Please confirm your agreement with the foregoing, on behalf of the Donor, by&#13;
signing, dating, and returning to us the enclosed copy of this Agreement. Upon receipt by&#13;
the Bank of the copy of this Agreement countersigned by you, this Agreement will become&#13;
effective as of the date of the countersignature.&#13;
Sincerely,&#13;
INTERNATIONAL BANK FOR RECONSTRUCTION AND DEVELOPMENT&#13;
INTERNAT NAL DEVELOPMENT ASSOCIATION&#13;
-V V     Lind  aq/elder&#13;
Sector Ohector&#13;
Public Sector Governance&#13;
Poverty Reduction and Economic Management Network&#13;
AGREED:&#13;
FRENCH REPUBLIC, ACTING THROUGH ITS&#13;
MINISTRY OF FOREIGN AFFAIRS&#13;
By:                                           Date:        N&#13;
Marc    u&#13;
Chef de la Mission de la Gouvernance Democratique&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-5-&#13;
ANNEX 1&#13;
Description of Activities, Expenditures and Governance Arrangements under the&#13;
Public Expenditure and Financial Accountability Program, Phase IV&#13;
Multi-Donor Trust Fund&#13;
This Annex shall be applicable to and form an integral part of all agreements entered&#13;
into between the Bank and entities (collectively, the "Donors") that provide contributions&#13;
(the aggregate of all contributions from the Donors, the "Contributions") to be administered&#13;
by the Bank for the Trust Fund.&#13;
A.    DESCRIPTION OF ACTIVITIES&#13;
1.    Purpose and Objective&#13;
The strengthening of public expenditure, procurement and financial accountability systems&#13;
is a key element in the efforts towards the promotion of economic development, poverty&#13;
reduction and good governance. The Public Expenditure and Financial Accountability&#13;
Program ("PEFA Program") was established in December, 2001 to support the development&#13;
of integrated and coordinated approaches to assessment and reform in the field of public&#13;
expenditure, procurement and financial accountability, with the particular goals to:&#13;
(a)   develop an approach to improve public financial management ("PFM")&#13;
system reform outcomes and learn lessons of successful and unsuccessful&#13;
PFM reforms; and&#13;
(b)   reduce transaction costs to countries from duplicative and overlapping&#13;
diagnostics while ensuring that the information needs of donors can still be&#13;
met.&#13;
Following the development of the PFM Performance Measurement Framework (the "PFM&#13;
Framework") and the Strengthened Approach to supporting PFM reform (the "Strengthened&#13;
Approach") during the first four years (under the PEFA Program, Phase I), the PEFA&#13;
Program has, during Phases II and III aimed to monitor and provide technical support on the&#13;
application of the PFM Framework, to provide a common information pool on PFM systems&#13;
based on completed PEFA Program assessments, to fine-tune the PFM Framework and to&#13;
support dissemination, training and lesson learning on the PFM Framework and the&#13;
Strengthened Approach, in order to meet its goals. Phase IV of the PEFA Program will&#13;
continue to support these activities while expanding its focus on the use of assessments for&#13;
multiple purposes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-6-&#13;
The Public Expenditure and Financial Accountability Program, Phase IV Multi-Donor Trust&#13;
Fund supports the strengthening of partnerships between development agencies that&#13;
contribute to the achievements of the goals of the PEFA Program mentioned above. The&#13;
Trust Fund's global, intermediate and direct objectives are as follows:&#13;
(a)   to improve PFM system performance for strengthened economic growth and&#13;
government service delivery (global objective);&#13;
(b)   to have PEFA assessments used for PFM reform formulation, donor support&#13;
decisions and research (intermediate objective); and&#13;
(c)   to expand and update the global, common and credible information pool on&#13;
PFM systems performance (direct objective).&#13;
2.    Eligible Activities&#13;
The Trust Fund will finance the activities set forth in Section V.4 of the Program Document&#13;
for the PEFA Program, Phase IV (2012-2017) approved by the Steering Committee of the&#13;
PEFA Program on April 25, 2012 (the "Program Document"), as amended from time to time&#13;
by decision of the Steering Committee in accordance with the Governance Arrangements (as&#13;
defined below) (the "Eligible Activities").&#13;
B.    CATEGORIES OF EXPENDITURE&#13;
All activities financed by the Trust Fund shall be Bank-executed. The eligible categories of&#13;
expenditures for such Bank-executed activities are:&#13;
(a)   consultant fees (individuals and firms);&#13;
(b)   equipment and office premises lease cost;&#13;
(c)   media, workshop, conference and meeting expenses;&#13;
(d)   staff costs with indirects;&#13;
(e)   travel expenses;&#13;
(f)   contractual services;&#13;
(g)   associated overheads;&#13;
(h)   extended term consultants&#13;
(i)   temporary support staff costs; and&#13;
(j)   equipment purchases.&#13;
For clarity: (i) staff costs with indirects and travel expenses may be financed by the Trust&#13;
Fund only for staff employed by the Bank specifically for the PEFA Secretariat; and (ii)&#13;
associated overheads includes the translation of policy documents and substantive reports&#13;
approved by the Steering Committee.&#13;
The foregoing categories of expenditures may include the financing of taxes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-7-&#13;
C.    GOVERNANCE ARRANGEMENTS&#13;
The "Program Governance Arrangements" set forth in Section VI of the Program Document,&#13;
as amended from time to time by decision of the Steering Committee, shall apply to the&#13;
Trust Fund (the "Governance Arrangements").&#13;
Any amendments to the Eligible Activities or the Governance Arrangements shall become&#13;
applicable to this Administration Agreement as such amendments take effect without further&#13;
need to amend this Administration Agreement; provided that such amendments do not&#13;
conflict with applicable Bank policies and procedures and provided further that in the event&#13;
of any conflict with other parts of this Administration Agreement, the terms of this&#13;
Administration Agreement shall prevail.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-8-&#13;
ANNEX 2&#13;
Standard Provisions Applicable to the Public Expenditure and Financial&#13;
Accountability Program, Phase IV Multi-Donor Trust Fund&#13;
This Annex shall be applicable to and form an integral part of all agreements entered&#13;
into between the Bank and the Donors that provide Contributions to be administered by the&#13;
Bank for the Trust Fund.&#13;
1 .   Administration of the Contributions&#13;
1.1.  The Bank shall be responsible only for performing those functions specifically set&#13;
forth in this Agreement and shall not be subject to any other duties or responsibilities to the&#13;
Donors, including, without limitation, any duties or obligations that might otherwise apply&#13;
to a fiduciary or trustee under general principles of trust or fiduciary law. Nothing in this&#13;
Agreement shall be considered a waiver of any privileges or immunities of the IBRD and&#13;
IDA under their Articles of Agreement or any applicable law, all of which are expressly&#13;
reserved.&#13;
1.2.  The Contribution shall be administered in accordance with the Bank's applicable&#13;
policies and procedures, as the same may be amended from time to time, including its&#13;
framework to prevent and combat fraud and corruption and its screening procedures to&#13;
prevent the use of Bank resources to finance terrorist activity, in line with the Bank's&#13;
obligations to give effect to the relevant decisions of the Security Council, taken under&#13;
Chapter VII of the of Charter of the United Nations. The Donor acknowledges that this&#13;
provision does not create any obligations of the Bank under the anti-terrorist financing and&#13;
asset control laws, regulations, rules and executive orders of an individual member country&#13;
that may apply to the Donor, nor shall it be deemed a waiver, express or implied, of any of&#13;
the privileges and immunities of the Bank.&#13;
2.    Commingling, Exchange and Investment of the Contributions&#13;
2.1.  The Contributions shall be accounted for as a single trust fund and shall be kept&#13;
separate and apart from the funds of the Bank. The Contributions may be commingled with&#13;
other trust fund assets maintained by the Bank.&#13;
2.2.  The Contributions may be freely exchanged by the Bank into other currencies as may&#13;
facilitate their disbursement.&#13;
2.3.  The Bank shall invest and reinvest the Contributions pending their disbursement in&#13;
accordance with the Bank's policies and procedures for the investment of trust funds&#13;
administered by the Bank. The Bank shall credit all income from such investment to the&#13;
Trust Fund to be used for the same purposes as the Contributions.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-9-&#13;
3.    Administrative Cost Recovery&#13;
3.1.  In order to assist in the defrayment of the costs associated with the establishment of&#13;
the Trust Fund, the Bank may, following deposit of the first Contribution from any Donor to&#13;
the Trust Fund, deduct and retain for its own account from that Contribution an amount&#13;
equal to and not greater than thirty-five thousand United States Dollars (US$35,000).&#13;
3.2.  In order to assist in the defrayment of the costs of administration and other expenses&#13;
incurred by the Bank under this Agreement, the Bank may deduct and retain for its own&#13;
account an amount equal to five percent (5%) of each Contribution. If the contributions&#13;
increase beyond what was originally expected at the time of counter-signature of the first&#13;
administration agreement, and the administrative costs increase as a result, the Donors&#13;
acknowledge that an additional administrative fee may be applied to such new contributions.&#13;
4.    Procurement&#13;
4.1.  The employment and supervision of any consultants and the procurement of any&#13;
goods financed by the Contributions shall be the responsibility of the Bank and shall be&#13;
carried out in accordance with its applicable policies and procedures.&#13;
5.    Accounting and Financial Reporting&#13;
5.1.  The Bank shall maintain separate records and ledger accounts in respect of the&#13;
Contributions deposited in the Trust Fund account and disbursements made therefrom.&#13;
5.2.  The Bank shall furnish to the Donors current financial information relating to&#13;
receipts, disbursements and fund balance in the holding currency of the Trust Fund with&#13;
respect to the Contributions via the World Bank's Trust Funds Donor Center secure website.&#13;
Within six (6) months after all commitments and liabilities under the Trust Fund have been&#13;
satisfied and the Trust Fund has been closed, the final financial information relating to&#13;
receipts, disbursements and fund balance in the holding currency of the Trust Fund with&#13;
respect to the Contributions will be made available to the Donors via the World Bank's&#13;
Trust Funds Donor Center secure website.&#13;
5.3.  The Bank shall provide to the Donors, within six (6) months following the end of&#13;
each Bank fiscal year, an annual single audit report, comprising (1) a management assertion&#13;
together with an attestation from the Bank's external auditors concerning the adequacy of&#13;
internal control over cash-based financial reporting for all cash-based trust funds as a whole;&#13;
and (2) a combined financial statement for all cash-based trust funds together with the&#13;
Bank's external auditor's opinion thereon. The cost of the single audit shall be borne by the&#13;
Bank.&#13;
5.4.  If a Donor wishes to request, on an exceptional basis, a financial statement audit by&#13;
the Bank's external auditors of the Trust Fund, the Donor and the Bank shall first consult as&#13;
to whether such an external audit is necessary. The Bank and the Donor shall agree on the&#13;
appropriate scope and terms of reference of such audit. Following agreement on the scope&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿- 10 -&#13;
and terms of reference, the Bank shall arrange for such external audit. The costs of any such&#13;
audit, including the internal costs of the Bank with respect to such audit, shall be paid by the&#13;
requesting Donor.&#13;
6.    Progress Reporting&#13;
6.1.  The Bank shall provide the Donors with an annual report on the progress of activities&#13;
financed by the Contributions. Within six (6) months of the final disbursement date&#13;
specified in paragraph 7.1, the Bank shall furnish to the Donors a final report on the&#13;
activities financed by the Trust Fund.&#13;
6.2.  Any Donor may review or evaluate activities financed by the Trust Fund. The Donor&#13;
and the Bank shall agree on the scope and conduct of such review or evaluation, and the&#13;
Bank shall provide all relevant information within the limits of its policies and procedures.&#13;
All associated costs shall be borne by the Donor. It is understood that any such review or&#13;
evaluation will not constitute a financial, compliance or other audit of the Trust Fund.&#13;
7.    Disbursement; Cancellation; Refund&#13;
7.1.  It is expected that the Contributions will be fully disbursed by the Bank by October&#13;
31, 2017. The Bank shall only disburse Contributions for the purposes of this Agreement&#13;
after such date with the written approval of the Donors.&#13;
7.2.  Any Donor or the Bank may, upon three (3) months' prior written notice, cancel all&#13;
or part of the Donor's pro rata share, of any remaining balance of the Contributions that is&#13;
not committed pursuant to any agreements entered into between the Bank and any&#13;
consultants and/or other third parties for the purposes of this Agreement prior to the receipt&#13;
of such notice.&#13;
7.3.  Following the final disbursement date specified in paragraph 7.1, the Bank shall&#13;
return any remaining balance of the Contributions to the Donors or to the relevant Donor&#13;
Balance Account on a pro rata basis based on the Donors' paid Contributions. In the event&#13;
of a cancellation the Bank shall promptly return to the relevant Donor or Donors, or to the&#13;
relevant Donor Balance Account, the Donor's pro rata share of uncommitted Contributions&#13;
in accordance with paragraph 7.2.&#13;
8.    Disclosure&#13;
The Bank will disclose this Agreement and related information on this Trust Fund in&#13;
accordance with the World Bank Policy on Access to Information. By entering into this&#13;
Agreement, Donors consent to disclosure of this Agreement and related information on this&#13;
Trust Fund.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="17040937">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2012/11/17040937/official-documents--administration-agreement-french-republic-contribution-tf071895
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2012/11/17040937/official-documents--administration-agreement-french-republic-contribution-tf071895</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2012/11/17040937/official-documents--administration-agreement-french-republic-contribution-tf071895</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2012-12-05T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2012-12-05T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <docm_id>090224b0817dc441</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b0817dc441</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/PREM/2012/12/05/090224b0817dc441/1_0/Rendered/INDEX/Official0Docum0ribution0to0TF071895.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/PREM/2012/12/05/090224b0817dc441/1_0/Rendered/PDF/Official0Docum0ribution0to0TF071895.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2012-11-12T17:08:06Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2012-12-05T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docna>
            Official Documents- Administration Agreement
            with French Republic for Contribution to TF071895
        </docna>
        <display_title>Official Documents-
            Administration Agreement with French Republic for
            Contribution to TF071895</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/2012/11/17040937/official-documents--administration-agreement-french-republic-contribution-tf071895</listing_relative_url>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <docty>Trust Fund Administrative Agreement</docty>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Gonzalez Rodriguez,Pilar Elisa</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>HQBOCS</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <owner>Public Sector Governance (PRMPS)</owner>
        <trustfund>TF071895-Public Expenditure and
            Financial Accountability (PEFA) Phase IV Multi-D</trustfund>
        <lang>English</lang>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Arts and Culture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Expenditure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>Freedom of Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>Leasing law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Efficiency of Public Expenditures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Expenditures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Financial Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Spending</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Remittances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Migration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Media</ml:concept><ml:concept>Privileges and Immunities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government Expenditure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Right to Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>External Audit</ml:concept><ml:concept>Leasing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Managing Public Finances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Movement of Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>