<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>﻿OFFICIAL                        T      oqeZ&#13;
DOCUMENTS&#13;
Administration Arrangement&#13;
Between the Government of Canada&#13;
as Represented by the Minister for International Cooperation&#13;
Acting Through the Canadian International Development Agency&#13;
and the International Bank for Reconstruction and Development&#13;
Concerning the Transition Fund (MTO 069024) Dated Noeb 4   2-1, Ll 2-&#13;
WHEREAS, this Administration Arrangement is acknowledged by the Government of Canada (the&#13;
"Donor") and the International Bank for Reconstruction aid Development, as Trustee (the "World&#13;
Bank," and together with the Donor, the "Participants") for the purpose of receiving funds for the&#13;
Trust Fund, MTO 069024, supporting the Transition Fund, and for which capitalized terms used&#13;
herein are used as defined in the Glossary in the Operations Manual;&#13;
WHEREAS, the governance structure and operating principles, guidelines and procedures for the&#13;
day-to-day operations of the Transition Fund are set forth in the Operations Manual; and&#13;
WHEREAS, it is understood that the term "Contribution Agreement" as defined in the Glossary of&#13;
the Operations Manual and used in Annex 1 attached hereto includes this Administration&#13;
Arrangement, and that the Participants' intention is for the use of "Administration Arrangement" to&#13;
reflect an internal Donor characterization without treating this Administrative Arrangement&#13;
differently from all other Contribution Agreements, of which this Administration Arrangement&#13;
constitutes a part;&#13;
NOW THEREFORE, the Parties hereto agree as follows:&#13;
1.     The Donor has decided to contribute, as a Canadian grant, a total amount of CAD&#13;
15,000,000 (fifteen million Canadian Dollars) (the "Contribution") to the Trust Fund as specified in&#13;
paragraph 3 below.&#13;
2.     The Contribution will be administered by the Trustee on behalf of the Donor in accordance&#13;
with the terms and conditions specified (i) in this Administration Arrangement, including Annex 1&#13;
(Standard Provisions), which constitutes an integral part of this Administration Arrangement, and&#13;
(ii) the Operations Manual (including the Glossary) whose terms will apply hereto. Other&#13;
contributors may contribute to the Trust Fund on such terms and conditions. In the event of&#13;
conflict, the terms of this Administration Arrangement will prevail over the Operations Manual.&#13;
3.     The Donor will deposit the Contribution through a bank transfer into such account with&#13;
such bank designated by the Trustee in accordance with the following payment schedule and&#13;
currency, in each case upon submission of a payment request by the Trustee:&#13;
Payment Due                      Contribution Currency     Amount Due&#13;
Upon effectiveness of this       Canadian Dollars          15,000,000    for   the&#13;
Administration Arrangement                                 Donor's    fiscal  year&#13;
2012/2013&#13;
4. When making the deposit, the Donor will instruct its bank to include in its payment details&#13;
information (remittance advice) field of its SWIFT payment message, information indicating: the&#13;
1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿amount paid, that the payment is made by the Donor for the Trust Fund (MTO 069024) for the&#13;
Transition Fund, and the date of the deposit.&#13;
5.     The offices responsible for coordination of all matters related to the implementation of this&#13;
Administration Arrangement are, except as may be notified in writing to the other Contact:&#13;
For the Trustee (the 'Trustee Contact"):&#13;
Director&#13;
Multilateral Trusteeship and Innovative Financing&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
1818 H Street, NW&#13;
Washington, DC 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
Tel: + 1 202 458 0019&#13;
Fax: + 1 202 614 0249&#13;
For the Donor (the 'Donor Contact"):&#13;
Project Team Leader&#13;
Middle East and North Africa Program&#13;
Canadian International Development Agency&#13;
200 Promenade du Portage&#13;
Gatineau, Qu6bec KIA 0G4 Canada&#13;
Tel: +1 819-956-8322&#13;
Fax: +1819-994-7161&#13;
6.     No offer, gift or payment, consideration or benefit of any kind, which constitutes an illegal&#13;
or corrupt practice, has or will be made to anyone, either directly or indirectly, as an inducement or&#13;
reward for the execution of this Administration Arrangement.&#13;
7.     No member of the House of Commons of Canada will be admitted to any share or part of&#13;
this Administration Arrangement or to any benefit to arise therefrom.&#13;
8.     No current or former public office holder or public servant of the Government of Canada&#13;
who is not in compliance with Canada's Conflict of Interest and Post-Employment Code for Public&#13;
Office Holders or the Values and Ethics Code for the Public Service will derive a direct benefit&#13;
from this Administration Arrangement. Any such practice will be grounds for terminating this&#13;
Administration Arrangement or taking any other corrective action as required.&#13;
9.     With respect to any payment to be made under this Administration Arrangement that is&#13;
subject to there being an appropriation by the Parliament of Canada for the fiscal year in which the&#13;
payment is to be made, including for any supplemental contribution, if CIDA's appropriation is&#13;
changed by the Parliament of Canada, CIDA may reduce or terminate the relevant portion of the&#13;
Contribution in respect of that fiscal year by signing a modification to this Administration&#13;
Arrangement with the Trustee.&#13;
10.    This Administration Arrangement may be amended by written agreement between the&#13;
Trustee and the Donor; provided, however, that (i) Annex 1 attached hereto may be amended only&#13;
by written agreement between the Trustee and all Donors contributing to the Trust Fund, and (ii)&#13;
the Operations Manual may be amended by the Steering Committee according to its terms with&#13;
such amendment becoming automatically applicable to this Administration Arrangement as and&#13;
2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿when such amendment becomes effective without the need for further written agreement between&#13;
the Trustee and the Donor; in both cases (i) and (ii) provided further that any such amendment does&#13;
not conflict with other terms of the Administration Arrangements and is consistent with the World&#13;
Bank's Articles, policies and procedures, as determined by the World Bank, and the ISAs'&#13;
applicable policies and procedures.&#13;
11.    This Administration Arrangement constitutes the entire agreement of the Participants with&#13;
respect to its subject matter and supersedes all oral communication and prior writings with respect&#13;
thereto.&#13;
12.    This Administration Arrangement may be executed in separate counterparts, all of which&#13;
taken together will constitute one and the same instrument.&#13;
13.    It is understood that this Administration Arrangement, including Annex 1, is not an&#13;
international treaty and is not eligible for registration as a treaty under Article 102 of the UN&#13;
Charter. It is an administrative arrangement between the Trustee and the Donor.&#13;
14.    This Administration Arrangement will be carried out as of the date of the last signature of&#13;
the Participants hereto, acting through their duly authorized representatives.&#13;
INTERNATIONAL BANK FOR RECONSTRUCTION AND DEVELOPMENT,&#13;
as Trustee of   Transit'    nd Trust Fund&#13;
Axel van Trotsenburg,     resi&#13;
Concessional Finance          artnerships&#13;
Date:      O     /&#13;
THE GOVERNMENT OF CANADA&#13;
CANADIAN INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPMENT AGENCY&#13;
Bob Johnston, R/gional Director General&#13;
Europe, Maghreb, Middle East, Afghanistan and Pakistan Directorate&#13;
Date:&#13;
Attachments:&#13;
Annex 1 (Standard Provisions)&#13;
3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿ANNEX 1&#13;
Standard Provisions&#13;
This Annex will be applicable to and form an integral part of each Contribution Agreement&#13;
entered into between the World Bank as Trustee, acting not for its own account, but solely in its&#13;
capacity as trustee of the Trust Fund for the Transition Fund, and each Donor with respect to its&#13;
respective Contribution to the Trust Fund.&#13;
1.     Role of the Trustee&#13;
1.1    The Trustee will be responsible only for performing those functions specifically set forth in&#13;
the Contribution Agreements and Financial Procedures Agreements and will not be subject to any&#13;
other duties or responsibilities to the Donors, ISAs or Transition Countries, including, without&#13;
limitation, any duties or obligations that might otherwise apply to a fiduciary or trustee under&#13;
general principles of trust or fiduciary law. Nothing in the Contribution Agreements or the&#13;
Financial Procedures Agreements will be considered a waiver of any privileges or immunities of&#13;
the World Bank under its Articles of Agreement or any applicable law, all of which are expressly&#13;
reserved.&#13;
2.     Receipt of Contributions&#13;
2.1    Contributions to the Trust Fund may be received from donor countries, as specified in the&#13;
Operations Manual, that enter into a Contribution Agreement with the Trustee (each a Donor),&#13;
consistent with the Trustee's policies and procedures and the Contribution Agreements.&#13;
2.2    Contributions will be provided to the Trustee for deposit into the Trust Fund in the&#13;
currency stated in the Contribution Agreement or an amendment thereto. With respect to each&#13;
Contribution, funds provided to the Trustee in a currency other than the Holding Currency will be&#13;
promptly converted by the Trustee to the Holding Currency.&#13;
2.3    Donors may make Contributions to the Trust Fund by means of payment in cash or, with&#13;
agreement of the Trustee, by the delivery to the Trustee of instruments payable on demand or&#13;
similar obligations in a form acceptable to the Trustee. Contributions may be paid in one lump&#13;
sum or in installments on the terms agreed with the Trustee and specified in the respective&#13;
Contribution Agreement.&#13;
3.     Administration of Contributions&#13;
3.1    The Trustee will account for Contributions as a single trust fund and keep them separate&#13;
and apart from the funds of the World Bank. The Contributions may be commingled with other&#13;
trust fund assets maintained by the World Bank.&#13;
3.2    The Contributions may be freely exchanged by the Trustee into other currencies to&#13;
facilitate operations.&#13;
3.3    The World Bank will invest and reinvest the funds in the Trust Fund pending their transfer&#13;
in accordance with the World Bank's applicable policies and procedures for the investment of trust&#13;
funds administered by the World Bank. The Trustee will deposit all income from such investment&#13;
in the Trust Fund to be used for the purposes of the Trust Fund.&#13;
4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿3.4    Funds may be approved by the Steering Committee only to the extent funds are available in&#13;
the Trust Fund, meaning throughout the Contribution Agreements available cash and promissory&#13;
notes net of any funds already allocated but not yet disbursed, as determined by the Trustee.&#13;
Subject to the availability of cash and investments held in the Trust Fund as determined by the&#13;
Trustee, the Trustee will commit, transfer or use such funds for any purpose approved and in the&#13;
amounts allocated by the Steering Committee in accordance with the terms of the Contribution&#13;
Agreements and the Financial Procedures Agreements.&#13;
3.5    Upon the transfer of funds from the Trust Fund to an ISA or the Coordination Unit, the&#13;
Trustee will have no responsibility, fiduciary or otherwise, for the use of such funds or activities&#13;
carried out therewith. The Donors acknowledge and agree that the Trustee will transfer funds&#13;
without requiring pre- or post-fund transfer review by the Trustee of any funding proposals&#13;
submitted to the Steering Committee or any activities implemented thereunder.&#13;
4.     Costs of the Trustee and Coordination Unit&#13;
4.1    Costs incurred by the Trustee and the Coordination Unit will at all times be covered in&#13;
their entirety by the Trust Fund. For the purposes of funding such costs, the Trustee and the&#13;
Coordination Unit will submit to the Steering Committee annual Budgets. The first annual Budget&#13;
will include reimbursement for costs incurred prior to Budget approval. Upon approval by the&#13;
Steering Committee of any Budget proposal from the Trustee or Coordination Unit, the Trustee&#13;
may transfer to the Trustee or the Coordination Unit, as the case may be, the respective amount&#13;
approved. The Donors acknowledge and agree that any Trustee or Coordination Unit Budget&#13;
amounts approved by the Steering Committee will be adjusted as necessary at the end of each&#13;
Fiscal Year based on actual costs incurred for activities performed in accordance with the Trustee's&#13;
and the Coordination Unit's respective roles and responsibilities. To the extent actual costs&#13;
incurred are lower than the transferred Budget amount, funds will be returned for deposit in the&#13;
Trust Fund.&#13;
5.     Use of Funds&#13;
5.1    Funds from the Trust Fund may be used by ISAs for Projects and by the Trustee and&#13;
Coordination Unit for Budgets, in each case in accordance with the purposes approved by the&#13;
Steering Committee and in accordance with the Operations Manual.&#13;
6.     Records and Reporting&#13;
6.1    The Trustee will maintain separate records and ledger accounts with respect to the funds in&#13;
the Transition Fund and transfers made therefrom. The Trustee will maintain books, records,&#13;
documents, and other evidence in accordance with the Trustee's usual accounting procedures to&#13;
substantiate the management of funds in the Trust Fund.&#13;
6.2    The Trustee will report to the Steering Committee semi-annually on the financial status of&#13;
the Transition Fund, including information on the status of Contributions, investment income,&#13;
commitments, transfers and funds available for allocation by the Steering Committee.&#13;
6.3    The Trustee will provide to the Donors, within six (6) months following the end of each&#13;
Fiscal Year, an annual single audit report, comprising (i) a management assertion together with an&#13;
attestation from the World Bank's external auditors concerning the adequacy of internal control&#13;
over cash-based financial reporting for all cash-based trust funds as a whole; and (ii) a combined&#13;
5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿financial statement for all cash-based trust funds together with the World Bank's external auditors'&#13;
opinion thereon. The cost of the single audit will be borne by the World Bank.&#13;
6.4   If a Donor wishes to request, on an exceptional basis, an audit of the financial statements&#13;
of the Trust Fund by the World Bank's external auditors, the Donor may seek such audit through&#13;
the Steering Committee. If the Steering Committee agrees to request such an audit, the Steering&#13;
Committee will designate one of its members to act on the Steering Committee's behalf for the&#13;
specific purpose. The designated representative and the World Bank will first consult as to&#13;
whether such an external audit is necessary, in which case the World Bank and the designated&#13;
representative will agree on the appropriate scope and terms of reference of such audit. Following&#13;
agreement on the scope and terms of reference, the World Bank will arrange for such external&#13;
audit. The costs of any such audit, including the internal costs of the World Bank with respect to&#13;
such audit, will be borne by the requesting Donor, unless the Steering Committee agrees to instruct&#13;
the Trustee to pay the costs of any such audit from available funds in the Trust Fund. In the event&#13;
the Steering Committee does not agree to request such an audit, and the Donor has a statutory,&#13;
regulatory or policy environment requiring such Donor's ability to make such a request&#13;
unilaterally, such Donor may proceed in lieu of the designated representative as specified above.&#13;
6.5    The Donors acknowledge and agree that the provision of any financial statements and&#13;
progress reports from ISAs is the responsibility of the respective ISA.&#13;
7.     Dispute Resolution&#13;
7.1    The Donors and the Trustee, in coordination with the Steering Committee and the&#13;
Coordination Unit, as applicable, agree to make every effort to settle amicably, by way of&#13;
consultation and other remedies as set out below, any dispute or controversy arising out of or&#13;
relating to the Contribution Agreements.&#13;
7.2    To the extent feasible, any dispute or controversy between a Donor and an ISA under a&#13;
Financial Procedures Agreement with respect to ISA Funds will, in the first instance, be resolved&#13;
amicably directly between the Steering Committee and the ISA without requiring involvement of&#13;
the Trustee or individual Donors. The Donors agree that they may collectively through the&#13;
Steering Committee, as undertaken by one of its members specifically designated to act on the&#13;
Steering Committee's behalf for the specific purpose, address to the ISA a request to settle&#13;
amicably such dispute or controversy with respect to any breach of a Financial Procedures&#13;
Agreement.&#13;
7.3   In the event a request to settle amicably a dispute or controversy is not approved by the&#13;
Steering Committee under Section 7.2 in a manner satisfactory to a requesting Donor, and the&#13;
requesting Donor has a statutory, regulatory or policy environment requiring such Donor's ability&#13;
to make such a request unilaterally, such Donor may address a request for amicable settlement, in&#13;
accordance with the terms and in the manner provided for in this Contribution Agreement, directly&#13;
to the ISA.&#13;
7.4    Each Donor will be considered an interested party under each Financial Procedures&#13;
Agreement and will have the option to address a request to the respective ISA to settle amicably, in&#13;
accordance with the terms and in the manner provided for in the respective Financial Procedures&#13;
Agreement, a dispute or controversy regarding any breach by the ISA thereof, whether for itself&#13;
under Section 7.3 or on behalf of the Steering Committee under Section 7.2.&#13;
6&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿8.     End Dates and Termination&#13;
8.1   It is expected that no new Projects will be approved by the Steering Committee after the&#13;
End Approval Date and no new transfers to ISAs will be made from the Trust Fund after the End&#13;
Transfer Date. The Trustee may transfer funds after the End Transfer Date only with the approval&#13;
of the Steering Committee.&#13;
8.2    Any Donor may, upon 90 days' advance written notice, cancel all or part of its Donor&#13;
Share as calculated at the end of the notice period. In the event of such cancellation, the Trustee&#13;
will return to such Donor the amount of its Donor Share by transferring the funds directly to (i)&#13;
such Donor, (ii) such Donor's donor balance account held by the World Bank or (iii) another trust&#13;
fund administered by the World Bank, as instructed in writing by the Donor Contact.&#13;
8.3    The Trustee may terminate its role as Trustee of the Trust Fund for the Transition Fund at&#13;
any time after providing the Steering Committee, all the Donors and all the ISAs 90 days' advance&#13;
notice in writing. Following termination, the Trustee will carry on no business for the Transition&#13;
Fund except for the purpose of winding up its affairs. The Trustee will, in consultation with the&#13;
Steering Committee and the IFI Coordination Platform, take all necessary action for winding up its&#13;
affairs in an expeditious manner.&#13;
8.4    Following the date when all funds committed by the Trustee have been fully transferred,&#13;
the Trustee will return to each Donor the amount of its respective Donor Share by transferring the&#13;
funds directly to (i) such Donor, (ii) such Donor's donor balance account held by the World Bank&#13;
or (iii) another trust fund administered by the World Bank, as instructed in writing by the Donor&#13;
Contact.&#13;
9.     Disclosure&#13;
9.1    The World Bank may disclose the Contribution Agreements and information on the&#13;
Transition Fund in accordance with the World Bank's policy on access to information in effect at&#13;
the time of such disclosure. By agreeing to these terms, each Donor consents to such disclosure of&#13;
its Contribution Agreement and such information. This provision will continue in full force and&#13;
effect following completion of all Trust Fund transfers or termination of the Trust Fund.&#13;
7&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="17141679">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2012/11/17141679/official-documents--administration-arrangement-cida-tf069024
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2012/11/17141679/official-documents--administration-arrangement-cida-tf069024</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2012/11/17141679/official-documents--administration-arrangement-cida-tf069024</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2013-01-03T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2013-01-03T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <docm_id>090224b08185ced2</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b08185ced2</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/CFP/2013/01/05/090224b08185ced2/1_0/Rendered/INDEX/Official0Docum0th0CIDA0for0TF069024.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/CFP/2013/01/05/090224b08185ced2/1_0/Rendered/PDF/Official0Docum0th0CIDA0for0TF069024.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2012-11-21T14:37:16Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2013-01-03T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docna>
            Official Documents- Administration
            Arrangement with CIDA for TF069024
        </docna>
        <display_title>Official Documents-
            Administration Arrangement with CIDA for TF069024</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/2012/11/17141679/official-documents--administration-arrangement-cida-tf069024</listing_relative_url>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <docty>Trust Fund Administrative Agreement</docty>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Stumpf,Andrea E.</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>HQBOCS</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <owner>Multilateral Trustee/Innov Fin (CFPMI)</owner>
        <trustfund>TF069024-Middle East and North Africa
            Transition Fund</trustfund>
        <lang>English</lang>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Organisational Structures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Organizational Assessments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>Freedom of Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>Remittances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Migration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Checks on Executive Power</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen User Satisfaction Survey</ml:concept><ml:concept>Independent Commissions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ombudsmen</ml:concept><ml:concept>Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Parliament</ml:concept><ml:concept>Procurement Complaints Review Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supreme Audit Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enforcement of Judgements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Informal Dispute Resolution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Treaties</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance Structures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Right to Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>External Audit</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Movement of Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Accountability Mechanisms</ml:concept><ml:concept>Dispute Resolution</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>