<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>ï»¿                                                                    75002&#13;
                      Improving Universal Primary&#13;
                      Health Care by Kenya&#13;
                      A Case Study of the Health&#13;
                      Sector Services Fund&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Gandham NV Ramana,&#13;
Rose Chepkoech, and&#13;
Netsanet Walelign&#13;
Workie&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                      Universal Health Coverage Studies Series (UNICO)&#13;
                      UNICO Studies Series No. 5&#13;
&amp;#12;&amp;#12;UNICO Studies Series 5&#13;
Improving Universal Primary Health Care by Kenya&#13;
A Case Study of the Health Sector Services Fund 1&#13;
Gandham NV Ramana, Rose Chepkoech, and Netsanet Walelign&#13;
Workie 2&#13;
&#13;
The World Bank, Washington DC, January 2013&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
1&#13;
  The Health Sector Services Fund is Kenyaâ&#128;&#153;s response to expand the supply and strengthen primary health care.&#13;
The program empowers communities to take charge of addressing their health needs and set priorities responsive to&#13;
local needs.&#13;
2&#13;
  We would to thank Dr. S. K. Sharif, Director Public Health; Dr. Jackson Songa, Head of the Health Sector Services&#13;
Fund (HSSF) Secretariat, and colleagues from the Royal Danish Embassy for their constant support of this important&#13;
initiative. We would also like to place on record the commitment shown by Facility Management Committees and&#13;
the staff of the Health Centers and Dispensaries for their constant efforts to improve services by making the best use&#13;
of HSSF grants.&#13;
&amp;#12;           The World Bankâ&#128;&#153;s Universal Health Coverage Studies Series (UNICO)&#13;
&#13;
All people aspire to receive quality, affordable health care. In recent years, this aspiration has&#13;
spurred calls for universal health coverage (UHC) and has given birth to a global UHC&#13;
movement. In 2005, this movement led the World Health Assembly to call on governments to&#13;
â&#128;&#156;develop their health systems, so that all people have access to services and do not suffer&#13;
financial hardship paying for them.â&#128;? In December 2012, the movement prompted the United&#13;
Nations General Assembly to call on governments to â&#128;&#156;urgently and significantly scale-up efforts&#13;
to accelerate the transition towards universal access to affordable and quality healthcare&#13;
services.â&#128;? Today, some 30 middle-income countries are implementing programs that aim to&#13;
advance the transition to UHC, and many other low- and middle-income countries are&#13;
considering launching similar programs.&#13;
The World Bank supports the efforts of countries to share prosperity by transitioning toward&#13;
UHC with the objectives of improving health outcomes, reducing the financial risks associated&#13;
with ill health, and increasing equity. The Bank recognizes that there are many paths toward&#13;
UHC and does not endorse a particular path or set of organizational or financial arrangements to&#13;
reach it. Regardless of the path chosen, successful implementation requires that many&#13;
instruments and institutions be in place. While different paths can be taken to expand coverage,&#13;
all paths involve implementation challenges. With that in mind, the World Bank launched the&#13;
Universal Health Coverage Studies Series (UNICO Study Series) to develop knowledge and&#13;
operational tools designed to help countries tackle these implementation challenges in ways that&#13;
are fiscally sustainable and that enhance equity and efficiency. The UNICO Studies Series&#13;
consists of technical papers and country case studies that analyze different issues related to the&#13;
challenges of UHC policy implementation.&#13;
The case studies in the series are based on the use of a standardized protocol to analyze the nuts&#13;
and bolts of programs that have expanded coverage from the bottom upâ&#128;&#148;programs that have&#13;
started with the poor and vulnerable rather than those initiated in a trickle-down fashion. The&#13;
protocol consists of nine modules with over 300 questions that are designed to elicit a detailed&#13;
understanding of how countries are implementing five sets of policies to accomplish the&#13;
following: (a) manage the benefits package, (b) manage processes to include the poor and&#13;
vulnerable, (c) nudge efficiency reforms to the provision of care, (d) address new challenges in&#13;
primary care, and (e) tweak financing mechanisms to align the incentives of different&#13;
stakeholders in the health sector. To date, the nuts and bolts protocol has been used for two&#13;
purposes: to create a database comparing programs implemented in different countries, and to&#13;
produce case studies of programs in 24 developing countries and one high-income â&#128;&#156;comparator,â&#128;?&#13;
the state of Massachusetts in the United States. The protocol and case studies are being published&#13;
as part of the UNICO Studies Series, and a comparative analysis will be available in 2013.&#13;
We trust that the protocol, case studies, and technical papers will provide UHC implementers&#13;
with an expanded toolbox, make a contribution to discussions about UHC implementation, and&#13;
that they will inform the UHC movement as it continues to expand worldwide.&#13;
                                                                               Daniel Cotlear&#13;
                                                       UNICO Studies Series Task Team Leader&#13;
                                                                             The World Bank&#13;
                                                                             Washington, DC&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                ii&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                          TABLE OF CONTENTS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Abbreviations ............................................................................................................................................... iv&#13;
Executive Summary ...................................................................................................................................... v&#13;
1. Introduction ............................................................................................................................................ 1&#13;
2. HSSF Institutional Architecture and Interaction with the Rest of the Health System ............................ 2&#13;
3. Targeting, Identification, and Enrolment of Beneficiaries ..................................................................... 5&#13;
4. Special Topics Related to the Management of Public Funds in HCP..................................................... 6&#13;
5. Management of the HCPâ&#128;&#153;s Benefits Package ......................................................................................... 8&#13;
6. The Information Environment of the HCP ........................................................................................... 12&#13;
7. Key Conclusions................................................................................................................................... 13&#13;
8. Pending Agenda .................................................................................................................................... 15&#13;
9. Proposed Way Forward ........................................................................................................................ 16&#13;
Annex 1 General Health System Overview of Financing and Delivery ..................................................... 17&#13;
Annex 2 HSSF Activity Planning ............................................................................................................... 20&#13;
Annex 3 Spider Web ................................................................................................................................... 22&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
FIGURES&#13;
Figure 1 Average Clinical Quality Scores in Health Facilities under PBF ................................................... 4&#13;
Figure 2 Average Cross-cutting Quality Score Improvements in Health Facilities under PBF.................... 5&#13;
Figure 3 Funding and Disbursement Pathways for HSSF ............................................................................ 7&#13;
Figure 4 HSSF Reporting Process ................................................................................................................ 8&#13;
Figure 5 Conceptual Frameworks of HSSF ................................................................................................ 10&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
TABLES&#13;
Table 1 Kenya Essential Package of Health Services ................................................................................... 9&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                            iii&#13;
&amp;#12;                                 Abbreviations&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CBHF            Community Based Health Financing&#13;
DANIDA          Danish International Development Agency&#13;
DHMT            District Health Management Teams&#13;
ESP             Economic Stimulus Package&#13;
HCP             Health Care for the Poor&#13;
HFMC            Health Facility Management Committee&#13;
HMIS            Health Management Information System&#13;
HSSF            Health Sector Services Fund&#13;
K Sh            Kenya shillings&#13;
KEMSA           Kenya Medical Supplies Agency&#13;
KEPH Services   Kenya Essential Package of Health Services&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                             iv&#13;
&amp;#12;Executive Summary&#13;
&#13;
This case study describes the Government of Kenyaâ&#128;&#153;s initiative to expand the supply of health&#13;
care and strengthen primary health care through implementation of the Health Sector Services&#13;
Fund (HSSF), which provides direct cash transfers to primary health facilities. This initiative,&#13;
launched in 2010, is a direct response to challenges identified by the Public Expenditure&#13;
Tracking Surveys in making funds for operation and maintenance available to the health&#13;
facilities, and builds on lessons from initiatives supported by the Danish International&#13;
Development Agency (DANIDA) in the Coastal Region.&#13;
&#13;
The local communities, represented by the facility management committee, manage the funds&#13;
received, and work closely with the facility staff to improve delivery of primary health services.&#13;
Currently, the Government of Kenya, DANIDA, and the World Bank are supporting this&#13;
initiative, which is complemented by ongoing sector reforms to improve the availability of health&#13;
human resources and essential medicines to further expand service delivery. The program also&#13;
helps in improving accountability for the use of resources received from different sources,&#13;
including cost sharing involving local community representatives monitored by independent&#13;
agencies on a periodic basis. The HSSF initiative is well aligned with the principles of&#13;
devolution as envisaged by Kenyaâ&#128;&#153;s new constitution.&#13;
&#13;
This initiative has so far been expanded to nearly 3,000 primary health facilities in the public&#13;
sector. The administrative data of ministries of health suggest increased utilization of the primary&#13;
health facilities (from 25.8 million in 2010/11 to 27.0 million 2011/12). The health facilities&#13;
were able to improve their overall upkeep with the local contractual staff and were able to buy&#13;
consumables to improve quality of care. A pilot undertaken in applying the principles of&#13;
performance-based financing suggests that such an approach can help further strengthen the&#13;
monitoring and evaluation systems and contribute to improvements in quality.&#13;
&#13;
There are, however, some operational challenges that were faced during the first two years of&#13;
implementation. The most important ones include issuing timely authorizations for incurring&#13;
expenditures, need for more hands-on support for accounting, and further simplification of&#13;
accounting at the facility level. These issues are being addressed by the government. The&#13;
authorization is now done annually, district health management teams are being complemented&#13;
with accountants to provide better hands-on support, and program accounting requirements at the&#13;
facility level are being simplified ensuring, full compliance with the government procedures. The&#13;
ongoing Public Expenditure Tracking Survey Plus will provide more quantitative information,&#13;
which will help to further fine-tune this initiative and make it responsive to the new dispensation&#13;
wherein counties will be responsible for the delivery of primary health services.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                  v&#13;
&amp;#12;vi&#13;
&amp;#12;1.   Introduction&#13;
&#13;
This case study describes the Government of Kenyaâ&#128;&#153;s initiative to expand the supply of health&#13;
care and strengthen primary health care through implementation of the Health Sector Services&#13;
Fund (HSSF) launched in 2010. Specifically, the paper presents the key health sector and&#13;
financing issues, the institutional and implementation arrangements of the HSSF, and&#13;
complementary reforms in the sector to support the HSSF. It also shares early implementation&#13;
experiences and ongoing innovations, highlights the pending agenda, and proposes options to&#13;
enhance on-the-ground effectiveness of the HSSF.&#13;
&#13;
The HSSF is an innovative financing approach to improve the delivery of primary health services&#13;
in Kenya. It is a revolving fund providing direct cash transfers to primary health care facilities&#13;
that include dispensaries and health centers. The local communities represented by the Health&#13;
Facility Management Committee (HFMC) manage the funds received and prioritize their use&#13;
responsive to their health needs.&#13;
&#13;
The HSSF aims to improve the delivery of quality essential health services in an equitable and&#13;
efficient manner as envisaged by Kenya Vision 2030 (Kenyaâ&#128;&#153;s development program covering&#13;
2008 to 2030), the Kenya Health Policy framework 1994â&#128;&#147;2010, and the Ministry of Public&#13;
Health and Sanitation Strategic Plan 2008â&#128;&#147;2012. This initiative was a direct policy response by&#13;
the Government of Kenya to the findings of the Public Expenditure Tracking Survey of 2005 that&#13;
little or no funds provided for the operation and maintenance of primary health facilities actually&#13;
reach them and, as a result, the delivery of health services is adversely affected.&#13;
&#13;
The HSSF mobilizes additional resources from the government and its development partners to&#13;
improve service delivery. It envisages expeditious and direct cash transfers to primary health&#13;
facilities run by the government and faith-based organizations, and supports an equitable&#13;
distribution of resources. More importantly, the HSSF empowers local communities to take&#13;
charge of their health by actively involving them through the HFMCs in the identification of&#13;
their health priorities, and in planning and implementation of initiatives responsive to the&#13;
identified priorities. The program also helps in improving accountability for the use of resources&#13;
received by the facility through both grants and cost sharing.&#13;
&#13;
Thus, the HSSF is well aligned with the principles of devolution and access to services as&#13;
described in Kenyaâ&#128;&#153;s new constitution, which expects the state to ensure reasonable access to its&#13;
services to all parts of the republic.&#13;
&#13;
The Government of Kenya is complementing HSSF with other reforms required to improve&#13;
service delivery for the rural poor. These include reforms in human resources and procurement,&#13;
and introducing a pull system 3 of distributing medical products.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
3&#13;
   A pull system is a â&#128;&#156;Manufacturing system in which production is based on actual daily demandâ&#128;¦â&#128;?&#13;
(http://www.businessdictionary.com/definition/pull-system.html).&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                 1&#13;
&amp;#12;2. HSSF Institutional Architecture and Interaction with the Rest of the Health System&#13;
Brief Description of HSSF&#13;
&#13;
The HSSF is an important initiative under the National Health Sector Strategic Plan II (2005â&#128;&#147;&#13;
2012) and the Community Strategy to expand the supply and strengthen primary health care. The&#13;
specific objectives of the HSSF are to (a) support and empower communities to take charge of&#13;
improving their health, (b) support capacity building in management of health facilities, and (c)&#13;
provide financial resources to meet critical gaps for improving quality of health service delivery&#13;
at the facility level.&#13;
&#13;
The HSSF is a government-led response to effectively address the operational challenges&#13;
encountered in making funds available to health facilities. It builds on lessons learned from a&#13;
Danish International Development Agency (DANIDA)-supported program that provided direct&#13;
funding to health facilities in the Coast and North-Eastern Provinces of Kenya. While the&#13;
approved scope for HSSF includes public primary health facilities and facilities operated by&#13;
faith-based organizations, the scale-up is taking longer than the originally envisaged time to&#13;
ensure adequate fiduciary and accountability mechanisms. The program hitherto has been&#13;
expanded only to the government primary health facilities, first starting with 722 health centers.&#13;
Subsequently, the program was scaled up to over 2,000 government dispensaries in FY 2012,&#13;
and the government is currently in the process of evolving implementation details, including the&#13;
option of using performance-based financing, for expanding the fund to facilities managed by the&#13;
faith-based organizations.&#13;
&#13;
The program was formally launched in 2010 by the Government of Kenya and is being financed&#13;
through domestic resources and support from DANIDA and the International Development&#13;
Association (IDA) through the Health Sector-Wide Approach (SWAp).&#13;
&#13;
Institutional Architecture of Health Care for the Poor (HCP)&#13;
&#13;
The HSSF has a formal governance structure and is regulated by the legal notice â&#128;&#156;The&#13;
Government Financial Management (HSSF) Regulations,â&#128;? 2007, Legislative Supplement No. 67,&#13;
gazetted on December 21, 2007, and subsequently updated in June 2009.&#13;
&#13;
HSSF resources consist of funds allocated to the facility from the national level and appropriated&#13;
by parliament, grants and donations received locally, and user charges generated by the facility.&#13;
The funds provided from the national level include the resources allocated by Government of&#13;
Kenya and the development partners supporting HSSF. These funds are credited directly to the&#13;
bank account of each facility that is eligible to receive HSSF grants 4, and are managed by the&#13;
Health Facility Management Committee (HFMC) according to the Financial Guidelines&#13;
approved by the Ministry of Public Health and Sanitation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
4&#13;
  These eligibility criteria include (a) the health facility has been gazetted formally by the government; (b) HFMC&#13;
members have been trained; (c) the health facility has an operational bank account; (d) adequate technical staff are&#13;
available at the facility; (e) an Annual Operational Plan has been prepared; and (f) an accountant would have been&#13;
appointed for the cluster of facilities where the facility is located, to carry out or oversee the required financial&#13;
accounting functions.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                   2&#13;
&amp;#12;At the national level, the oversight for HSSF is provided by a seven-member National Health&#13;
Sector Committee that includes representatives of civil society, the private sector, and the&#13;
Permanent Secretaries of Public Health and Finance. The Director of Public Health Services&#13;
functions as the Secretary for the National Health Sector Committee. The eight Provincial Health&#13;
Teams provide strategic oversight for the fund in their respective jurisdictions including the&#13;
capacity building for fund management and reporting. With the proposed devolution in the heath&#13;
sector guided by Kenyaâ&#128;&#153;s new constitution, the counties are expected to take over this function&#13;
and play a more proactive role.&#13;
&#13;
The District Health Management Teams (DHMT) provide technical and operational oversight at&#13;
the district level by approving the Annual Operational Plans and Quarterly Implementation Plans&#13;
prepared by the facilities, and the monitoring the implementation of these plans through&#13;
integrated supportive supervision. The DHMTs are to consolidate the performance and&#13;
expenditures reported by facilities in their respective districts and forward them to the national&#13;
level with a copy to the provincial health team.&#13;
&#13;
The governance at the facility level is ensured by the HFMC. Every facility has seven to nine&#13;
members (with at least four members selected from the community and four women) that have&#13;
the responsibility for preparing and implementing the Annual Operational Plans and Quarterly&#13;
Implementation Plans with budgets. The HFMC will also oversee implementation including&#13;
supervision and control of all resources raised, received, and managed by the health facility,&#13;
including HSSF resources.&#13;
&#13;
The planning and monitoring are integrated with regular supportive supervision of primary&#13;
health services from the district, provincial, and national levels.&#13;
&#13;
Spillover Effects on the Rest of the Public System&#13;
&#13;
                                                     The HSSF offers a vehicle for&#13;
                                                     channeling resources directly to the&#13;
                                                     health facilities for the first time in&#13;
                                                     Kenya, using country systems compliant&#13;
                                                     with Government of Kenya fiduciary&#13;
                                                     guidelines. The program promotes&#13;
                                                     transparency,         participation       of&#13;
                                                     communities in decision making, and&#13;
                                                     better accountability for funds and&#13;
                                                     results. While it is too early to assess the&#13;
                                                     impact, an important initial spillover&#13;
                                                     effect observed was the improved&#13;
                                                     reporting and accounting for the user fee&#13;
                                                     being collected by facilities. Some&#13;
                                                     facilities effectively used the funds to&#13;
improve service delivery such as providing electricity to maternity wards to provide much&#13;
needed 24-hour delivery services and improve facility upkeep by hiring local staff. Also, the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                3&#13;
&amp;#12;overall accountability is beginning to improve and facilities are disclosing the client charters and&#13;
services offered free of charge.&#13;
&#13;
The partners supporting the health sector are&#13;
showing keen interest in using HSSF for&#13;
improving service delivery, and UNICEF&#13;
has already started using HSSF to improve&#13;
delivery of maternal and child health&#13;
services in a few provinces.&#13;
&#13;
The     HSSF       design     also    includes&#13;
performance-based financing, and the Bank&#13;
is currently supporting a pilot in Samburu&#13;
County to test the feasibility of this&#13;
approach, building on the systems&#13;
established under the program. The&#13;
preliminary results from validation of&#13;
project facilities suggest improvements in&#13;
prenatal care, deliveries by skilled&#13;
attendants, and children fully immunized. More importantly, the Health Management&#13;
Information System (HMIS) reporting has improved from 71 percent to 88 percent and both&#13;
clinical and overall quality/governance scores have shown steady improvement, highlighting&#13;
potential benefits of overall systems strengthening (figures 1 and 2).&#13;
&#13;
             Figure 1 Average Clinical Quality Scores in Health Facilities under PBF&#13;
&#13;
            5                                             4.77                    4.23&#13;
          4.5        3.92&#13;
            4&#13;
          3.5&#13;
            3                    2.46&#13;
          2.5                                1.81                     1.73&#13;
            2&#13;
          1.5&#13;
            1&#13;
          0.5&#13;
            0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                  Oct-Dec 2011          Jan-March 2012           April-June 2012&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                  4&#13;
&amp;#12;   Figure 2 Average Cross-cutting Quality Score Improvements in Health Facilities under PBF&#13;
&#13;
             85                                               80.69&#13;
             80&#13;
             75                                70.79&#13;
             70&#13;
             65                 63.15&#13;
             60&#13;
             55&#13;
             50&#13;
                               Cross-cutting quality scores (%)&#13;
                   Oct-Dec 2011         Jan-March 2012         April-June 2012&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
This initiative also noted the weaknesses and inconsistencies in the HMISs and the opportunity&#13;
for using implementing partners present in the district for verification of data reported by&#13;
facilities, which will be external to the system and will not significantly add to the costs. The&#13;
government is contemplating using this approach to contract faith-based organizations, and also&#13;
to scale-up performance-based financing through other sources of financing including support&#13;
for health systems strengthening from the Global Alliance for Vaccines and Immunization and&#13;
Health Results Innovation Trust Fund established at the World Bank with support from the UKâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
Department for International Development (DfID) and the Government of Norway.&#13;
&#13;
3. Targeting, Identification, and Enrolment of Beneficiaries&#13;
&#13;
Addressing inequities in the access to and utilization of health services is the central goal of the&#13;
National Health Sector Strategic Plan II. The HSSF supports this goal by targeting services and&#13;
levels of care where there are still huge inequities. The focus of HSSF is on the first three levels&#13;
of health careâ&#128;&#148;community, dispensary, and health centerâ&#128;&#148;which are most critical for delivering&#13;
the Kenya Essential Package of Health Services. In addition to supporting improvement of&#13;
service delivery at the facility level, the HSSF provides resources for the staff to plan regular&#13;
outreach sessions to address special needs of the underserved populations who do not visit the&#13;
facilities.&#13;
&#13;
The HSSF design envisaged equity-based resource allocation criteria to provide additional&#13;
funding to areas where poverty levels are high, population density low, and costs of providing&#13;
services relatively high. Despite being approved by the parliament, the equity-based resource&#13;
allocation has still not been made operational due to time taken to ensure adequate accountability&#13;
mechanisms in the program and improve reporting of expenditures. Meanwhile, Kenyaâ&#128;&#153;s new&#13;
Constitution mandated devolution of responsibility to deliver essential health services to counties&#13;
and introduced equity-based resource allocations for counties covering all sectors. The HSSF&#13;
program now needs to revisit the originally envisaged equity formula in light of these&#13;
developments.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                  5&#13;
&amp;#12;The HSSF also aims to support the primary health facilities being operated by the faith-based&#13;
organizations that still remain the sole providers of health services in some of the poorest and&#13;
hard-to-reach communities. Channeling HSSF resources to such facilities will help increase&#13;
access for the poor. Building on the implementation experiences so far, the program is now&#13;
exploring specific modalities for contracting faith-based organizations, including the option of&#13;
using performance-based financing.&#13;
&#13;
4. Special Topics Related to the Management of Public Funds in HCP&#13;
&#13;
The financial transfers under HSSF are expected to influence the behavior of the two Ministries&#13;
of Health, development partners, and primary health service providers. The HSSF was set up as a&#13;
mechanism for pooling resources from the government and development partners through the&#13;
SWAp and through transferring the resources directly to health facilities to improve the upkeep&#13;
of facilities and implement locally relevant activities for improving service delivery. All&#13;
decisions to use the HSSF are expected to be endorsed by the HFMC, which improved&#13;
participation of users in decisions related to delivery of health services and enhanced&#13;
accountability in the use of HSSF money to deliver agreed results. More importantly, the HSSF&#13;
minimized the risk of loss of funds noted in the past when transfers were made through regions&#13;
and districts, and provided more predictable financing to primary health facilities.&#13;
Each facility receives HSSF funds directly into its bank account. At the facility level, the HSSF&#13;
funds help to improve coverage, quality, and their responsiveness by providing basic operational&#13;
costs. These costs include supporting staff for facility upkeep and recordkeeping, and operation&#13;
and maintenance of the facility, equipment, and vehicles. In addition, the fund also supports&#13;
outreach and community-based services to promote equity and cross-sector linkages.&#13;
&#13;
The planning process is facilitated by a facility stakeholderâ&#128;&#153;s forum organized by the facility in&#13;
charge, consisting of the HFMC, development partners supporting the health sector in the&#13;
locality, representatives of the constituency development fund, the divisional water officer, the&#13;
agricultural extension officer, and the head teachers of the primary school. This forum reviews&#13;
the performance of the facility during the previous year, discusses the implementation challenges&#13;
and how the facility tackled them, and the governmentâ&#128;&#153;s identified priorities in the sector, and&#13;
lists the key issues to be addressed by the facility during the next financial year. These key issues&#13;
guide the Annual Operational Plan prepared by the facility in charge together with the HFMC.&#13;
After the Annual Operational Plan has been approved by the DHMT, the HFMC prepares the&#13;
Quarterly Implementation Plan, which describes specific activities to be implemented during&#13;
each quarter. The Quarterly Implementation Plans are approved by the HFMC and submitted to&#13;
DHMT.&#13;
&#13;
The facilities requisition funds on a quarterly basis; however, the first two quarters for a new&#13;
facility participating in the program are released in one installment, and releases for the third and&#13;
fourth quarters are released only after the facilities prepare and share their quarterly financial&#13;
reports. After the reports have been approved by the National Health Sector Committee, the&#13;
money for the next quarter is transferred to the facility bank account (figure 3).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                   6&#13;
&amp;#12;                     Figure 3 Funding and Disbursement Pathways for HSSF&#13;
&#13;
                                                                    Thus, the HSSF allows the&#13;
                                                                    community to have a strong&#13;
                                                                    role in the planning and&#13;
                                                                    implementation of health&#13;
                                                                    services responsive to their&#13;
                                                                    local needs, and ensures&#13;
                                                                    provision of funds directly&#13;
                                                                    to health facilities. More&#13;
                                                                    attention is being paid to&#13;
                                                                    compliance with guidelines&#13;
                                                                    for community participation&#13;
                                                                    in the program and the&#13;
                                                                    performance of providers&#13;
                                                                    using    new     tools   for&#13;
                                                                    supportive supervision.&#13;
&#13;
The HFMCs have the full responsibility for preparing and implementing the Annual Operational&#13;
Plans and Quarterly Implementation Plans, including their budgets to oversee implementation&#13;
and supervise and control all the resources raised, received, and managed by the Officer in&#13;
Charge, including HSSF resources. The HSSF has a well-developed results chain, which links&#13;
the inputs from HSSF to services and intermediate health outcomes and uses selected indicators&#13;
to assess the performance of a facility in order to reward performance. Intensified supervision of&#13;
services is provided under the HSSF program whereby every quarter, all facilities are visited by&#13;
the DHMT at least once.&#13;
&#13;
The Service Delivery reports compiled monthly by the officer in charge of the facility on behalf&#13;
of the Health Center/Dispensary Management Committee are sent to the DHMT. All spending&#13;
units of the program (HSSF secretariat, Provincial Health Management Team, DHMT, and&#13;
facilities) prepare and submit a Monthly Expenditure Return and a Quarterly Financial Report.&#13;
&#13;
Each facility receiving HSSF grants prepares a monthly financial report using the standard&#13;
format and shares it with the DHMT within the prescribed deadline for review and consolidation.&#13;
The DHMT submits the consolidated monthly financial report, which includes reports from both&#13;
the facilities and the DHMT to the Ministry of Public Health and Sanitation head of accounting&#13;
unit through the HSSF secretariat. The HSSF secretariat, in turn, produces a summarized and&#13;
consolidated HSSF-wide financial report, which it uses to prepare its interim financial reports&#13;
and annual accounts. Copies of these reports are submitted to the Health SWAp for monitoring&#13;
purposes (figure 4).&#13;
&#13;
The fund has facilitated improvement in the delivery of quality essential health services in an&#13;
equitable and efficient manner. The HFMCs at the health center and dispensary levels have&#13;
proved that these funds can be managed fairly well in low-resource settings and that the impact is&#13;
perceived to be highly positive. Further, HSSF also helped eliminate operational bottlenecks in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                7&#13;
&amp;#12;providing financial resources to the primary health facilities that predominantly faced delays in&#13;
receiving funds from the Ministry of Health.&#13;
&#13;
                                Figure 4 HSSF Reporting Process&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
5. Management of the HCPâ&#128;&#153;s Benefits Package&#13;
&#13;
Despite Kenyaâ&#128;&#153;s strong commitment to achieving universal coverage with the Kenya Essential&#13;
Package of Health (KEPH) Services, several supply-side constraints still exist in its health&#13;
system. (See Annex 2 for the plan to improve delivery of KEPH Services.) The three most&#13;
important challenges in delivering the KEPH Services for all Kenyans are:&#13;
&#13;
   â&#128;¢   Access to resources to maintain facilities and deliver quality services&#13;
   â&#128;¢   Availability of competent human resources to deliver the package&#13;
   â&#128;¢   Availability of an adequate supply of essential medicines and medical supplies.&#13;
&#13;
While the HSSF is aiming to addresses the first challenge, the Government of Kenya has&#13;
initiated efforts to address the remaining two challenges.&#13;
&#13;
The HSSF supports improved delivery of the KEPH Services. The KEPH is organized by birth&#13;
cohorts, as shown in table 1.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                               8&#13;
&amp;#12;                          Table 1 Kenya Essential Package of Health Services&#13;
&#13;
 Cohort                                                         Service Package&#13;
 Cohort 1                        ï&#130;§   ANC and nutritional care, Intermittent Prophylactic Treatment for&#13;
 Pregnancy and newborn               Malaria, Tetanus Toxoid Immunization&#13;
 (up to 2 weeks of age)          ï&#130;§   Use of skilled birth attendants, clean delivery, BCG vaccination&#13;
                                 ï&#130;§   Postnatal care, breastfeeding support, supplementary feeding&#13;
                                 ï&#130;§   Family planning services&#13;
                                 ï&#130;§   Insecticide Treated Net promotion and use&#13;
                                 ï&#130;§   Indoor Residual spraying&#13;
                                 ï&#130;§   Prevention of Mother to Child Transmission of HIV&#13;
                                 ï&#130;§   Micronutrient supplements (iron)&#13;
                                 ï&#130;§   Hygiene, water and sanitation&#13;
 Cohort 2                        ï&#130;§   Community integrated management of childhood illnesses and&#13;
 Early childhood                     insecticide treated net promotion and use&#13;
 (2 weeks to 5 years)            ï&#130;§   Appropriate nutrition, extended breastfeeding, growth monitoring,&#13;
                                     Expanded Program for Immunization, provision of vitamin A, zinc&#13;
                                 ï&#130;§   Psychological stimulation, physical/cognitive development&#13;
                                 ï&#130;§   Exercise and recreation&#13;
 Cohort 3                        ï&#130;§   Essential school health program&#13;
 Late childhood                  ï&#130;§   Adequate nutritional care&#13;
 (6â&#128;&#147;12 years)                    ï&#130;§   ITN promotion and use&#13;
                                 ï&#130;§   Exercise and recreation&#13;
 Cohort 4                        ï&#130;§   TT2 in schools&#13;
 Adolescents                     ï&#130;§   Reproductive Health and HIV/AIDS/STI (sexually transmitted&#13;
 (13â&#128;&#147;24 years)                       infections) counseling&#13;
                                 ï&#130;§   Substance abuse counseling&#13;
                                 ï&#130;§   Adequate nutritional care&#13;
                                 ï&#130;§   Accident prevention&#13;
                                 ï&#130;§   Reproductive Health and Family Planning services&#13;
                                 ï&#130;§   Exercise and recreation&#13;
 Cohort 5                        ï&#130;§   Annual screening and medical examinations&#13;
 Adults                          ï&#130;§   Accident prevention&#13;
 (25â&#128;&#147;59 years)                   ï&#130;§   Reproductive Health and Family Planning services&#13;
                                 ï&#130;§   Healthy lifestyles (exercise, recreation, nutrition, etc.)&#13;
 Cohort 6                        ï&#130;§   Annual screening and medical examinations&#13;
 Elderly                         ï&#130;§   Exercise and the promotion of general hygiene&#13;
                                 ï&#130;§   Social/emotional/community support&#13;
&#13;
The HSSF alone will not be able to improve service delivery in isolation. However, it addresses&#13;
one of the important bottlenecks in service delivery. The program, therefore, requires&#13;
complementary reforms and actions to improve availability of human resources for health and&#13;
improved supply of essential health products. The conceptual framework of HSSF presented in&#13;
figure 5 considers these issues.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                     9&#13;
&amp;#12;                                          Figure 5 Conceptual Frameworks of HSSF&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 Conceptual Framework for HSSF&#13;
                     Supply side                                                                             Demand side&#13;
                                                                    HEALTH                                COMMUNITY         CBOs/NGOs&#13;
          CRITICAL          INFRA-                                                     FACILITY&#13;
                                                                    SECTOR                              1. Aware of        1. Sensitize&#13;
           STAFF          STRUCTURE                                                 MANAGEMENT&#13;
                                            ESSENTIAL              SERVICES                                HSSF and its       the&#13;
       1. Available      1. Basic                                                    COMMITTEES&#13;
                                            MEDICINES                FUND                                  support to         communiti&#13;
       2. Have              infrastruct                                             1. Represent&#13;
                                                AND           1.   Empowers                                improve            es about&#13;
          required          ure for                                                    the interest&#13;
                                              MEDICAL              local                                   service            HSSF&#13;
          Competenci        service                                                    of&#13;
                                             SUPPLIES              communities                             delivery        2. Ensure&#13;
          es                delivery                                                   community&#13;
                                           1. Supplied        2.   Linked to                            2. Know the           adequate&#13;
          (Technical,       and client                                              2. Play an&#13;
                                              and                  Annual                                  services           consultatio&#13;
          Planning          privacy                                                    active role in&#13;
                                              replenished          Operational                             exempted           ns with&#13;
          and            2. Functional                                                 decentralize&#13;
                                              in time              Plans                                   from user fee      communiti&#13;
          Fiduciary)        equipment                                                  d planning&#13;
                                           2. Are of good     3.   Reaches in                           3. Familiar with      es&#13;
       3. Have           3. Electricity                                             3. Provide&#13;
                                              quality              time                                    HFMC role       3. Enhance&#13;
          incentive to      and water                                                  required&#13;
                                           3. Used            4.   Used                                    and where to       consumer&#13;
          sustain           Supply                                                     oversight for&#13;
                                              properly             effectively in                          complain if        voice and&#13;
          motivation        services                                                   HSSF&#13;
                                                                   accordance                              deficiency in      provider&#13;
                            functional                                                 implementat&#13;
                                                                   with the                                services           accountabil&#13;
                                                                                       ion&#13;
                                                                   guidelines                              /corruption        ity&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         Inputs Supported                                   Inputs Supported by                                  Inputs Supported&#13;
         by GoK and other                                     the Health SWAp                                    by GoK and other&#13;
             Partners                                                                                                Partners&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  Increased Use of Kenya Essential&#13;
                                                     Package of Health Services&#13;
&#13;
                 HSSF requires both supply- and demand-side inputs for delivering the results&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
A health sector Community Strategy has also been developed and launched. The main objective&#13;
of this strategy is to â&#128;&#156;strengthen the community to progressively realize their right to accessible&#13;
and quality care and to seek accountability from facility based health services.â&#128;? In addition, the&#13;
strategy proposes strengthened linkages and dialogue with the formal health sector through&#13;
Community Health Workers, who are volunteers supervised and supported by Community&#13;
Health Extension Workers. In principle, the full implementation of the community strategy&#13;
would need 4,000 extension workers and 70,000 Community Health Extension Workers, but the&#13;
Community Strategy will be implemented only gradually due to financial constraints (box 1).&#13;
&#13;
Reforms are also underway in human resources for health. In particular, new human resources&#13;
for the health strategic plan have been launched, and the Ministry of Public Health and Sanitation&#13;
has undertaken a devolved recruitment exercise, with the resources made available through the&#13;
governmentâ&#128;&#153;s fiscal stimulus package. In recent years, the shortfall of staff in the health services&#13;
has been ameliorated by employing contract staff under a funding arrangement with&#13;
Development Partners. Many of the staff hired on contract have been posted to the most&#13;
deprived, underserved provinces. The contract health workers have helped improve the service&#13;
coverage and quality of care. However, shortfalls still remain, especially among nurses, clinical&#13;
officers, and laboratory technicians in many deprived districts. Although current human&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                            10&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                     resources       management       is&#13;
                                                                     overcentralized, there are ongoing&#13;
    Box 1 Recruitment of Health Workers under the Economic&#13;
    Stimulus Package (ESP) Program                                   efforts to devolve human resources&#13;
                                                                     management to the counties.&#13;
    The Kenya ESP was initiated by the Government of Kenya to&#13;
    boost its economic growth. It was introduced in the&#13;
    2009/2010 Budget Speech and its aim was to jump-start the        Discussions are also ongoing to&#13;
    Kenyan economy toward long-term growth and development,          introduce new allowances for health&#13;
    after the 2007/2008 postelection violence that affected the      workers in remote areas, and there&#13;
    Kenyan economy, a prolonged drought, and an escalation in&#13;
    oil and food prices. Investment in health was one of the major&#13;
                                                                     are plans to set up campuses for&#13;
    elements of the ESP, and the budget allocation was envisaged     postgraduate training programs in&#13;
    to cover, among others, public health centers in all 210         the provinces to retain health&#13;
    constituencies. Employment of 20 nurses on a contract basis&#13;
    per constituency was one of the aims of the project.&#13;
                                                                     professionals   in    their   work&#13;
                                                                     locations.&#13;
    The process is decentralized, with recruitment panels at the&#13;
    district level and the management of the data centered at the&#13;
                                                                Progress has also been made in&#13;
    Ministry of Public Health and Sanitation headquarters. After&#13;
    interviews are conducted in the districts, the lists are    reforming      and      strengthening&#13;
    forwarded to the headquarters where they are compiled and   governance of the Kenya Medical&#13;
    the names forwarded to the Public Service Commission for    Supplies Agency (KEMSA). There&#13;
    approval and issuance of appointment letters.&#13;
                                                                are already signs of efficiency&#13;
   The staff hired under the package include nurses, Community  improvements in KEMSA. In&#13;
   Health Extension Workers, Public Health Officers, and Public particular, KEMSAâ&#128;&#153;s procurement&#13;
   Health Technicians.&#13;
                                                                function is now generally in&#13;
   ESP Phase 1: In 2010, under the ESP program, the initiative  compliance with the Public&#13;
   set out to employ 4,200 nurses (20 for each of the 210       Procurement        and        Disposal&#13;
   constituencies) under contract. The total number recruited&#13;
   was 3,776, of which 3,497 reported to stations.&#13;
                                                                Authority  provisions, and   the prices&#13;
                                                                for health commodities obtained by&#13;
   ESP Phase 2: In 2011, under ESP Phase II, 6,300 health       KEMSA compare favorably with&#13;
   workers were earmarked for recruitment. Under Phase II, the  other suppliers, mainly due to high&#13;
   numbers of health staff authorized were 3,150 nurses, 2,100&#13;
   Community Health Extension Workers, and 1,050 Public         volumes         and         improving&#13;
   Health Officers/Public Health Technicians. The total number  procurement standards. KEMSAâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
   of health workers recruited in this phase was 4,827, which   throughput also increased by almost&#13;
   included 2,129 nurses, 2,099 Community Health Extension&#13;
   Workers, and 599 Public Health Officers/Public Health        37 percent in 2009 compared to&#13;
   Technicians.                                                 2008, with only a marginal increase&#13;
                                                                of 9 percent in supply chain costs.&#13;
                                                                KEMSA        has     improved        its&#13;
coordination with Development Partners including through a major review meeting in March&#13;
2010.&#13;
&#13;
However, there are still challenges in ensuring effective distribution of procured commodities&#13;
and institutionalizing the pull system. With support from the development partners, KEMSA is&#13;
currently focusing on strengthening and integrating its logistic systems to ensure timely&#13;
availability of all supplies (including those supplies made through national programs) based on&#13;
the facility drawing rights established and disease burden. The existing centralized procurement&#13;
and distribution arrangements need to be revisited in light of the ongoing devolution, ensuring&#13;
that facilities and counties have autonomy to order essential medicines based on their needs and&#13;
have alternate options to do so while ensuring principles of economy, quality, and rational use.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                     11&#13;
&amp;#12;6. The Information Environment of the HCP&#13;
&#13;
Health information systems at the Ministries of Health collect routine health data through a&#13;
network of community units comprising 6,190 health facilities (government, faith-based,&#13;
nongovernmental, and private). Other key contributors to health information are the Civil&#13;
Registration Department of the Ministry of Immigration, the Kenya National Bureau of&#13;
Statistics, research institutions, and the African Network for Health Management.&#13;
&#13;
A core set of process and governance indicators has been identified to monitor the&#13;
implementation of HSSF. HSSF uses information from two sources to assess the performance of&#13;
a facility: the HMIS and a quantifiable supervision checklist. Both the HMIS and supportive&#13;
supervision by the DHMTs are well-established strategies of the Ministry of Public Health and&#13;
Sanitation to assess facility performance.&#13;
&#13;
The HMIS remains the main source of information for the Annual Operational Plan. However,&#13;
like most developing countries, there are challenges in getting reliable information in time from&#13;
the HMIS. The major challenges include inconsistencies in data reported compared to actual&#13;
sources of data, weak capacities of HMIS staff, lack of integration among the many parallel data&#13;
collection systems, and inadequate coordination. While HSSF resources can be used for the&#13;
recruitment of records clerks, depending on need, the supportive supervision role of DHMT can&#13;
be more effectively used building on the new checklist introduced by the Department of Primary&#13;
Health Care, which helps to objectively assess the performance of facilities.&#13;
&#13;
In addition, an independent integrated fiduciary review agency has been contracted to monitor on&#13;
a quarterly basis HSSFâ&#128;&#153;s fiduciary compliance, performance, governance arrangements, and&#13;
value for money covering a nationally representative sample. Some of the positive findings from&#13;
the first two reviews are that (a) the program funds were generally well used and there were&#13;
visible improvements in overall service delivery at the sampled health facilities; (b) the HFMCs&#13;
were generally well constituted and involved in decision making and oversight functions; and (c)&#13;
the sampled facilities received Essential Medicines and Medical Supplies from KEMSA,&#13;
quarterly. Reported instances of Essential Medicines and Medical Supplies stock-out decreased&#13;
from 49 percent in September 2011 to 46 percent in December 2011.&#13;
&#13;
The key challenges identified are (a) delays in the release of HSSF funds and authorizations to&#13;
incur expenditures, thereby adversely affecting the implementation of planned program&#13;
activities; (b) poor recordkeeping at facilities due to heavy workload, capacity constraints, and&#13;
inadequate support from accountants; (c) despite having adequate storage and inventory records,&#13;
updating of bin cards used for recording pharmaceutical stocks was not being done regularly; and&#13;
(d) 27 instances of inappropriate use of HSSF funds were reported.&#13;
&#13;
The Ministry of Public Health and Sanitation has started measures to address the identified&#13;
weaknesses of the program. All cases of inappropriate use of HSSF funds reported were&#13;
investigated and acted upon, and feedback is being provided to facilities on their specific areas of&#13;
weakness. The HSSF fiduciary records are being further simplified while maintaining&#13;
compliance with Government of Kenya requirements. The authorization to incur expenditure is&#13;
now being issued on an annual basis, which allows facilities to readily access available funding.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                 12&#13;
&amp;#12;Finally, DANIDA has agreed to support government efforts to have one accountant in each&#13;
district to provide sustained handholding and capacity building of health facilities as a full&#13;
member of the DHMT.&#13;
&#13;
7. Key Conclusions&#13;
&#13;
Health centers and dispensaries are the major source of primary-level care for communities,&#13;
particularly in the rural areas of Kenya, where over 80 percent of the population resides. Public&#13;
health services at these lower levels of care where the poor mainly seek their care are particularly&#13;
weak. Unreliable funds flow and unavailability of essential medicines and medical products are&#13;
known common weakness in public primary health care facilities. According to a 2009 client&#13;
satisfaction report by the Ministry of Medical Services, a majority of public health facility clients&#13;
reported unavailability of essential drugs and medicines. In addition, the findings of the 2005&#13;
Public Expenditure Tracking Survey revealed that little or no funds actually reach primary health&#13;
care facilities. The manifestations of such weakness at the service provision level have included,&#13;
among others, inadequate and poorly maintained equipment and infrastructure.&#13;
&#13;
The Government of Kenya regards primary health care facilities as a critical pillar of the health&#13;
system for delivering the essential package of health services for all Kenyans. In an effort to&#13;
address the challenges faced by these facilities, various reforms have been implemented to&#13;
ensure that primary health care facilities offer quality services. One of the key reforms has been&#13;
the establishment of the HSSF, which helps to transfer funds expeditiously and directly to rural&#13;
health facilities, particularly Level 1, 2, and 3 facilities, to enable them to improve services to&#13;
local communities. In addition, strategies to remove the supply-side constraints and expand&#13;
primary health care have been developed. The introduction of the demand-based pull system&#13;
approach (box 2) of supplying essential medicines and medical supplies has ensured reliable&#13;
availability of health commodities at the lower-level health facilities. In addition, to address the&#13;
shortages in health workers, a devolved recruitment exercise was undertaken under the&#13;
Economic Stimulus Package. This helped in locally recruiting and deploying nurses, community&#13;
health extension workers, and public health officers and technicians to work in the rural and&#13;
undeserved areas.&#13;
&#13;
Since its rollout in 2010, the HSSF has proved to be a successful strategy for ensuring that funds&#13;
reach the periphery of the health system, with minimal bureaucratic interference. An early&#13;
evaluation of the HSSF program by the Kenya Medical Research Institute highlighted the fact&#13;
that direct financing made an important contribution of facility funding, and was also perceived&#13;
to have a positive impact on staff motivation, use, and quality of care. Notably, there has been&#13;
remarkable improvement in the quality of services provided at the primary health care facilities.&#13;
One of the most recent key finding on the implementation of the HSSF program by DANIDA&#13;
and the World Bank is the significant number of people visiting the health centers.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                  13&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                           The HSSF is currently&#13;
                                                                           covering 721 health centers&#13;
Box 2 The Pull System of Supplying Essential Medicines and&#13;
                                                                           and 2,296 dispensaries in the&#13;
Medical Supplies&#13;
                                                                           public        sector.        The&#13;
The â&#128;&#156;pull systemâ&#128;? is a demand-based approach for ensuring the              administrative data of the&#13;
reliable availability of health commodities at all service delivery        Ministries of Health suggest an&#13;
points within a health system. In Kenya, under the National Health&#13;
Sector Strategic Plan II (2005â&#128;&#147;2012) the government (Ministry of           increase in utilization rates of&#13;
Health) has established virtual â&#128;&#156;drawing rightsâ&#128;? for health facilities     health facilities. During the&#13;
to move toward the â&#128;&#156;pullâ&#128;? system of supply in which facilities order       first nine months of fiscal&#13;
their required supplies and commodities based on actual need&#13;
rather than receiving centrally determined numbers of medicine             2011/12, nearly 27.9 million&#13;
kits (referred to as the â&#128;&#156;pushâ&#128;? system of supply).                         individuals     used     primary&#13;
                                                                           health services compared to&#13;
Drawing rights for Level 2 and 3 facilities: Each public rural health&#13;
facility has annual drawing rights established by the ministry&#13;
                                                                           25.8 million in fiscal 2010/11.&#13;
through the above-mentioned resource allocation criteria. In 2011â&#128;&#147;         Over half of these users (16.3&#13;
12, new resource allocation criteria for rural health facilities were      million) were female. In&#13;
developed, and the allocation of drawing rights is done at two&#13;
levelsâ&#128;&#148;national to district and district to health facilities&#13;
                                                                           addition, nearly 0.8 million&#13;
                                                                           eligible children were fully&#13;
National to district: Allocation criteria are based on district            immunized, with marginal&#13;
workload, district population, number of Rural Health Facilities in        improvements in coverage&#13;
the district, and the district poverty index. Each component has&#13;
individual weights.                                                        levels in the North Eastern&#13;
                                                                           province. Other early benefits&#13;
District to facility: The allocation criterion is primarily based on the   of the HSSF noted are that&#13;
facility workload.&#13;
                                                                           facilities were able to improve&#13;
The process of transition from the push to the pull system for the         their     upkeep     and     buy&#13;
Rural Health Facilities began at the end of 2005, and pilot projects       consumables       to    improve&#13;
were undertaken in the Coast and North Eastern provinces. The&#13;
pilot ended in December 2006. In 2007, a phased rollout for the rest&#13;
                                                                           quality of care, and HFMC&#13;
of the country was planned, with Nairobi province and its environs         members         are      actively&#13;
brought on board. The next counties to be included in the system           participating     in    decision&#13;
were the Lower Eastern, including Machakos, Makueni, and Kitui&#13;
counties. However, there were challenges on the supply side,&#13;
                                                                           making and are supporting the&#13;
particularly in the processing of orders, since the processing was         facilities.&#13;
based on individual orders. During the same period, the KEMSA&#13;
board was dissolved and a task force formed to investigate the             Early results from the pull&#13;
matter.&#13;
                                                                           system indicate that in the&#13;
With these developments, the enrollment of Rural Health Facilities         districts currently using the&#13;
in the system was stopped. In late 2009, a new board was formed            new pull system, wastage and&#13;
and a new road map on KEMSA drawn.&#13;
In the first quarter of 2011, KEMSA put more facilities into the pull      expiry of drugs have been&#13;
system for the remainder of the Central and Eastern provinces.             reduced. Furthermore, there is&#13;
Between October 2011 and February 2012, two provinces were                 reliable availability of health&#13;
placed onto the pull, namely Western and Nyanza provinces. The&#13;
entire country is expected to move to pull system by the end of FY&#13;
                                                                           commodities as reflected in&#13;
2012 from accounting departments.                                          reduced stock-outs at health&#13;
                                                                           facilities.&#13;
Early results from the pull system include: (1) wastage and&#13;
expiry of drugs has been reduced; (2) stock-out reduced and there&#13;
is reliable availability of health commodities, and (3) equity in          The HSSF aims to improve&#13;
resource allocation improved.                                              delivery of quality essential&#13;
                                                                           health services at the sub-&#13;
                                                                           district and community levels,&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                         14&#13;
&amp;#12;in an equitable and efficient manner through (a) generating and providing sufficient resources for&#13;
implementing each facilityâ&#128;&#153;s Annual Operational Plan to address preventive, promotive, and&#13;
curative services at Levels, 1, 2, and 3 and to account for them in an efficient and transparent&#13;
manner according to the government systems; and (b) supporting capacity building in the&#13;
management of health facilities.&#13;
&#13;
Each facility receives funds four times every financial year, and the funds are credited directly to&#13;
the beneficiaryâ&#128;&#153;s bank account. At Level 2 and 3 health facilities, the HSSF funds help in&#13;
improving coverage, quality, and responsiveness by providing basic operational costs. These&#13;
costs include supporting staff for facility upkeep and recordkeeping; and operation and&#13;
maintenance of the facility, equipment, and vehicles. The fund is also used to ensure&#13;
uninterrupted electricity and water, communication, and supply of consumables and stationery.&#13;
&#13;
In addition, the fund improves services at Level 1 through outreach and community-based&#13;
services to promote equity and cross-sector linkages by applying resource allocation criteria. The&#13;
specific activities it supports include outreach services such as reproductive and child health&#13;
provided by facility staff; mobilizing communities, and promoting cross-sector linkages and&#13;
other community-based innovative activities including maintenance of water sources and&#13;
sanitation (Annex 1).&#13;
&#13;
To ensure proper management of the fund, management committees have been established and&#13;
trained at the district, provincial, and national level. The committees provide oversight functions,&#13;
but day-to-day management is in the hands of facility committees.&#13;
&#13;
8. Pending Agenda&#13;
&#13;
Like most developing countries, Kenya faces major challenges in ensuring universal health care&#13;
coverage. Access to affordable and quality health care remains a major challenge for most&#13;
Kenyans. Income and geographic inequalities still predominate in accessing and using health&#13;
services, with low utilization of essential services among the poor and those residing in arid and&#13;
semi-arid areas.&#13;
&#13;
The poor benefit far less from government subsidies to health care. Ill health is concentrated&#13;
among the poor, but the poorest 20 percent lay claim to just 14 percent of government health care&#13;
expenditure compared to 27 percent of the benefit received by the richest 20 percent. Both the&#13;
quality and efficiency of public health services remain low. While many guidelines and policies&#13;
exist, there is no systematic approach to assessing, monitoring, and improving the performance&#13;
of health services, at least not according to consistent, defined standards.&#13;
&#13;
Health workers are unevenly distributed around the country, with greater numbers in hospitals&#13;
and in urban and non-arid areas. Further, there is a general decline in the number of health&#13;
workers in all provinces. Although the recruitment of health workers under the ESP addressed&#13;
the shortfalls in human resources, polices to attract them to underserved areas mostly remain&#13;
ineffective. Moreover, it is still unclear how the status of more than 3,000 staff recruited under&#13;
the ESP program will be regularized.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                 15&#13;
&amp;#12;Significant progress in efficiency has been observed in KEMSA, but stock-outs of essential&#13;
medicines, and in particular medical supplies, are still frequent. The overall government&#13;
allocation for pharmaceuticals remains low and this, coupled with poor supply chain&#13;
management, forces medicines and medical supplies to be bought locally, as a result of which&#13;
prices are higher and effective quality oversight suffers.&#13;
&#13;
Despite recent improvements, the health sector continues to face governance challenges.&#13;
Accountability needs to improve at all levels of the health system, in terms of both service&#13;
delivery and financial management. Community ownership and involvement in the planning and&#13;
monitoring of health services have improved following the establishment of community HFMCs,&#13;
but the complaint redress mechanisms that give voice to citizens remain weak and lack efficiency&#13;
and transparency.&#13;
&#13;
9. Proposed Way Forward&#13;
The way forward could include the following:&#13;
&#13;
â&#128;¢   Improving delivery of the Kenya Essential Package of Health Services and strengthening&#13;
    systems will be critical for further improvements in health status, especially for poor people.&#13;
    The money being spent on health care could deliver better health outcomes by improving the&#13;
    efficiency of existing systems. Kenya Vision 2030 recommends scaling up output-based&#13;
    approaches that would enable disadvantaged groups to access health care from preferred&#13;
    institutions. The ongoing supply-side innovations such as the HSSF need to be&#13;
    complemented by innovations that more strongly focus on results, such as performance-based&#13;
    financing and demand-side innovations. The Government of Kenya is currently working with&#13;
    its partners to study the applicability of performance-based financing and vouchers in the&#13;
    health sector, building on the successful foundation provided by the HSSF.&#13;
â&#128;¢   The devolved health care system envisaged by the new constitution provides a huge&#13;
    opportunity for offering more responsive and accountable health services, addressing some of&#13;
    the equity and efficiency concerns about the centralized system. However, it is also important&#13;
    to ensure that countries sustain successful initiatives such as the HSSF and pull system. This&#13;
    requires more stringent assessment of the impact of these initiatives on service delivery,&#13;
    covering both equity and quality dimensions.&#13;
â&#128;¢   Ongoing reforms need to be further deepened to enhance the citizenâ&#128;&#153;s role in health service&#13;
    delivery, through active participation in planning, facility management, complaint redress,&#13;
    and validation of reported results.&#13;
â&#128;¢   A strong national commitment is required to support counties in addressing the unequal&#13;
    distribution of human resources. While incentives linked to performance remain critical, the&#13;
    creation of an enabling work environment for health care staff in underserved areas remains&#13;
    equally important.&#13;
â&#128;¢   There is also a need to focus on sustained commodity supply by scaling up the pull system.&#13;
    This involves building on the economic and efficiency benefits of centralized procurement,&#13;
    while improving facility-level commodity management and rational use, led by county and&#13;
    facility health management teams and creating strong competition.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                16&#13;
&amp;#12;            Annex 1 General Health System Overview of Financing and Delivery&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
General Health System&#13;
&#13;
Health services in Kenya are provided by a wide range of players, and the public services (see&#13;
figure below), which mainly cater to the poor, are particularly weak at the lower levels. Health&#13;
care providers include the government, faith-based organizations, other not-for-profit&#13;
organizations, for-profit service providers, and traditional healers. About 40 percent of the&#13;
services are provided by the private sector, which is broadly defined.&#13;
&#13;
                                                               Health services in Kenya are&#13;
                                                               provided through a network of over&#13;
                                                               4,700 health facilities countrywide,&#13;
                                                               with the public sector system&#13;
                                                               accounting for about 51 percent of&#13;
                                                               these facilities. At present, the&#13;
                                                               public health system consists of the&#13;
                                                               six levels, as shown in figure A1.1:&#13;
                                                               the national referral hospitals&#13;
                                                               (Level      6),     which     provide&#13;
                                                               sophisticated              diagnostic,&#13;
                                                               therapeutic, and rehabilitative&#13;
                                                               services;       provincial    general&#13;
                                                               hospitals,        which       provide&#13;
                                                               specialized referral care (level 5);&#13;
                                                               district hospitals, which provide&#13;
referral care in priority areas for the district (Level 4); health centers offering a well-defined&#13;
package of preventive and curative services including delivery (Level 3); dispensaries, which are&#13;
the first point of contact with the formal health system with priority focus on preventive and&#13;
promotive care (Level 2); and the community (Level 1).&#13;
&#13;
Basic primary care is provided at the lowest levels of care, including health centers and&#13;
dispensaries. The main programs in primary care settings include malaria, HIV/AIDS, TB, child&#13;
health including immunization and birth deliveries, and reproductive health programs. For these&#13;
programs, health workers use a population-based list of names to monitor program&#13;
implementation. These programs have earmarked funding, which is more predictable than for the&#13;
rest of the public health system, although the recent reduction of financing from the Global Fund&#13;
for HIV/AIDS, Tuberculosis and Malaria could affect the predictability of commodities. There is&#13;
a small user fee for primary care services (10 K Sh for a dispensary and 20 K Sh for a health&#13;
center). However, all services for children under five, pregnant women, and national priority&#13;
health programs are exempted from a user fee. Generally, HIV/AIDS, malaria, TB, and child&#13;
health are very strong programs. However, for various reasons, they still tend to get implemented&#13;
vertically, especially to meet donor requirements, resulting in unnecessary duplication.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                  17&#13;
&amp;#12;Health Financing&#13;
&#13;
The sources of health financing include government, households, the private sector, and donors&#13;
that pool resources and pay for services provided by public and private providers. The main&#13;
players of health financing in Kenya are:&#13;
&#13;
â&#128;¢   General tax financing: This mainly consists of tax-financed â&#128;&#156;freeâ&#128;? health care services in&#13;
    public health facilities, later modified by the introduction of user fees.&#13;
â&#128;¢   National Hospital Insurance Fund: This was established in 1966 to finance health care in&#13;
    public and private facilities. The scheme is mandatory for formal sector workers earning&#13;
    more than K Sh 1,000 per month. As of June 2010, the National Health Insurance Fund was&#13;
    able to reach 6.6 million beneficiaries (about 18 percent of Kenyans), with 2.8 million&#13;
    principle members, which makes it by far the largest health insurer in the country.&#13;
â&#128;¢   Private health insurance: This has developed over the years, becoming more visible in the&#13;
    early 1980s, with the introduction of health maintenance organizations and the growth in&#13;
    health insurance portfolios for insurance companies.&#13;
â&#128;¢   Employer self-funded schemes: Employers provide health benefits as incentives to their&#13;
    workers and dependents through self-insured in-house medical schemes.&#13;
â&#128;¢   Community Based Health Financing (CBHF) schemes: These have emerged over time to&#13;
    meet the health care financing needs of low-income earners who traditionally have been&#13;
    largely left out of private insurance and the National Health Insurance Fund. There is no&#13;
    specific regulation for CBHF, and most are registered by the Ministry of Gender and Youth&#13;
    Affairs.&#13;
â&#128;¢   Out-of-pocket health spending: Like many developing countries, out-of-pocket spending&#13;
    has been very high in Kenya. Out-of-pocket spending is a major barrier to accessing health&#13;
    care services and drives households into poverty through the sale of assets and the diversion&#13;
    of meager income into health services.&#13;
â&#128;¢   Development partners and nongovernmental organizations: Various development&#13;
    partners and nongovernmental organizations have traditionally contributed significantly to&#13;
    health care financing and provision.&#13;
â&#128;¢   Other mechanisms: These include HSSF, which is a form of supply-side is financing to&#13;
    lower-level health facilities and the Output-Based Approach Reproductive Health Voucher,&#13;
    which is a form of demand-side financing that targets the poor. The poor buy the health&#13;
    vouchers at token prices and the voucher is redeemed with a specific service provider&#13;
    network for specified health services.â&#128;&#153;&#13;
&#13;
Funding for the health sector is increasing but still falls short of the needed amount. According to&#13;
the National Health Accounts undertaken in 2009â&#128;&#147;10, the Total Health Expenditure in absolute&#13;
value increased from K Sh 82.2 billion (US$1,046 million) in 2001/02 to K Sh 122.9 billion&#13;
(US$1,620 million), in 2009/10, an increase of 49 percent. Total Health Expenditure per capita&#13;
increased from K Sh 2,636 (US$34) in 2001/02 to K Sh 3,203 (US$42) in 2009/10, a 24 percent&#13;
increase. However, the Total Health Expenditure as a percentage of gross domestic product has&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                 18&#13;
&amp;#12;remained nearly constant, at 5 percent since 2001/02. What is more worrisome is the decline of&#13;
government health expenditures as a percentage of total government expenditures from 8 percent&#13;
in 2001/02 to 4.6 percent in 2009/10 (figure A1.2).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        Figure A1.2 Distrubution of Financing Sources, 2001/02, 2005/06, and 2009/10, Kenya&#13;
&#13;
 100%&#13;
&#13;
  90%               16.4&#13;
                                                 31.0                         34.5&#13;
  80%&#13;
&#13;
  70%&#13;
&#13;
  60%&#13;
                    54.0&#13;
  50%                                            39.3                         36.7&#13;
  40%&#13;
&#13;
  30%&#13;
&#13;
  20%&#13;
                    29.6                         29.3                         28.8&#13;
  10%&#13;
&#13;
   0%&#13;
                   2001/02                      2005/06                      2009/10&#13;
                           Public               Private                 Donors&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The health sector continues to be predominantly financed by private sector sources (including by&#13;
household out-of-pocket spending), as depicted in figure A1.2. However, the private sector share&#13;
has decreased from a high of 54 percent in 2001/02 to 37 percent in 2009/10, while public sector&#13;
financing has remained constant over the last decade, at about 29 percent. The contribution from&#13;
donors has more than doubled, from 16 percent in 2001/02 to 35 percent in 2009/10 (figure&#13;
A1.3).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                              19&#13;
&amp;#12;          Figure A1.3 Distribution of Financing Agents, 2001/02, 2005/06, and 2009/10, Kenya&#13;
100%                      3.1                                              2.6                                                 1.8&#13;
                          1.2                                              1.9                                                 2.7&#13;
                          1%&#13;
&#13;
90%                      6.0&#13;
                                                                          18.2&#13;
80%                                                                                                                          27.8&#13;
&#13;
70%&#13;
                        43.4&#13;
                                                                          29.1&#13;
60%&#13;
                                                                                                                             24.5&#13;
50%&#13;
                                                                            5.4&#13;
                          3.8&#13;
                                                                            1.3&#13;
40%                       2.8                                               3.7                                                6.7&#13;
                          3.9                                                0.6&#13;
                                                                           1.7%&#13;
                          1.0                                                                                                  2.4&#13;
                         0.1                                                                                                   4.7&#13;
30%                                                                                                                           0.9%&#13;
                                                                                                                              0.2&#13;
                                                                                                                              1.1%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
20%&#13;
                        33.7                                              35.4&#13;
                                                                                                                             27.2&#13;
10%&#13;
                                                                     \&#13;
 0%              Ministries of Health       NACC                           Other ministries             Local Authorities&#13;
                      2001/02                                            2005/06                                            2009/10&#13;
                 NHIF                       Parastatals                    Private Employer Insurance   OOP&#13;
&#13;
                 NGOs                       Private Firms                  Rest of the World            Others&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  In terms of uses, the public sector entities are estimated to have managed 37 percent of Total&#13;
  Health Expenditure in 2009/10 compared to 43 percent in 2001/02. Similarly, resources&#13;
  managed by the private sector decreased from nearly 50 percent in 2001/02 to almost 30 percent&#13;
  in 2009/10. There has been a steep increase in resources managed by nongovernmental&#13;
  organizations and donors, which nearly quadrupled from 2001/02 (figure A1.4).&#13;
&#13;
                 Figure A1.4 Distribtion of Providers, 2001/02, 2005/06, and 2009/10, Kenya&#13;
       100%                       2.7                                      0.5&#13;
&#13;
                                  5.4                                     10.9                                        8.4&#13;
       90%&#13;
                                  8.4&#13;
                                                                                                                     13.8&#13;
       80%                        7.4                                     15.2&#13;
                                                                           0.7&#13;
                                                                          2.5%                                        8.2&#13;
       70%                       10.5&#13;
                                  1.2&#13;
                                                                           6.0                                        2.8&#13;
                                                                           1.0                                        3.1&#13;
       60%                       10.1                                      8.5                                        2.1&#13;
&#13;
                                  3.1                                      5.3&#13;
                                                                                                                     10.3&#13;
       50%&#13;
                                 11.9                                                                                 4.9&#13;
                                                                          13.6&#13;
       40%                                                                                                            7.6&#13;
&#13;
       30%&#13;
&#13;
       20%                       39.3                                     35.8                                       36.3&#13;
&#13;
       10%&#13;
&#13;
        0%&#13;
                                2001/02                              2005/06                                      2009/10&#13;
&#13;
         Public Hospitals                 Private for Profit Hospitals           NFP Hospitals                   Public HCs and Dispensaries&#13;
         NFP HCs and Dispensaries         FP HCs and Dispesaries                 Private Clincs                  Private Pharmacies&#13;
         CHWs                             Providers of Health Programs           General Health Admin            Others&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                               20&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                Annex 2 HSSF Activity Planning&#13;
&#13;
        Objective: To improve the delivery of Kenya Essential Package of Health (KEPH) Services at the&#13;
        facility and community levels, especially for the poor.&#13;
Purpose and                  Activities                        Inputs           Indicative                 Output&#13;
Expenditure                                         (with intermediate-level      Share&#13;
Category                                                 account codes)&#13;
Improving            â&#128;¢ Support staff for facility   â&#128;¢ Casual wages for           20â&#128;&#147;40%      â&#128;¢ Fully functional Level 2 and 3&#13;
coverage, quality,     upkeep, recordkeeping,         temporary staff                          facilities delivering KEPH Services&#13;
and                    security, etc.                 (f2110200)                               and responsive to clients&#13;
responsiveness       â&#128;¢ Operation and                â&#128;¢ Utilitiesâ&#128;&#148;electricity,     10â&#128;&#147;20%      â&#128;¢ Increased use of facilities for&#13;
of Level 2 and 3       maintenance of facility,       water (h2210100)                         preventive health services&#13;
health facilities      equipment, and               â&#128;¢ Communication, supplies    5â&#128;&#147;10%         (immunization, Intermittent&#13;
by providing           vehicles                       and servicesâ&#128;&#148; mobile,                    Preventive Treatment, pre- and&#13;
basic operational    â&#128;¢ Uninterrupted                  Internet, and courier                    postnatal care, Voluntary&#13;
costs (K Sh            electricity and water          services (h2210200)                      Counselling and Testing,&#13;
450,000 per          â&#128;¢ Communication                â&#128;¢ General office supplies    5â&#128;&#147;10%         Prevention of mother to child&#13;
health center/K      â&#128;¢ Supply of consumables          and services (h2211100)                  transmission), promotive health&#13;
Sh 110,000 per         and stationery               â&#128;¢ Repairs and routine        10â&#128;&#147;20%        services (skilled birth care,&#13;
dispensary)                                           maintenanceâ&#128;&#148;vehicles                     growth monitoring, vitamin A,&#13;
                                                      and other transport                      contraceptive promotion),&#13;
                                                      equipment (h2220100)                     curative care (treatment of the&#13;
                                                    â&#128;¢ Repairs and routine                      sick child, TB diagnosis and DOTS&#13;
                                                      maintenance of                           [directly observed treatment,&#13;
                                                      equipment and other                      short-course], and outpatient and&#13;
                                                      assets (h2220200)                        inpatient care, referrals)&#13;
                                                    â&#128;¢ Fuel and lubricants                    â&#128;¢ Enhanced transparency and&#13;
                                                      (h2211200)                               accountability (decentralized&#13;
                                                    â&#128;¢ Other operating                          planning involving Health Facility&#13;
                                                      expensesâ&#128;&#148;bank services,                  Management Committees,&#13;
                                                      contracted guard, and                    disclosure of information on&#13;
                                                      clearing and transport                   funds received and used, timely&#13;
                                                      costs (h2211300)                         expenditure reporting)&#13;
&#13;
Improving Level      â&#128;¢ Outreach services      â&#128;¢       Accommodation and                      â&#128;¢ Planned outreach activities held&#13;
1 services             provided by facility           domestic travel            20â&#128;&#147;30%      â&#128;¢ Improved coverage for&#13;
through outreach       staff:                         (g2210300)                               community-based services&#13;
and community-          ï&#131;&#152; reproductive and â&#128;¢          Advertising, awareness,                  (immunization, prenatal care,&#13;
based services to             child health            and publicity campaigns                  vitamin A distribution, use of&#13;
promote equity          ï&#131;&#152; nutrition                   (h2210500)                               Long Lasting Insecticidal Nets,&#13;
and cross-sector        ï&#131;&#152; communicable        â&#128;¢       Fuel and lubricants                      community management of&#13;
linkages by                   disease and             (h2211200)                               diarrhoea, malaria and acute&#13;
applying                      noncommuni-                                                      respiratory infection, nutrition&#13;
resource                      cable diseases                                                   rehabilitation,&#13;
allocation              ï&#131;&#152; school health                                                        contraceptive/condom&#13;
criteria (K Sh                clinics                                                          distribution)&#13;
225,000 per          â&#128;¢ Mobilizing                                                            â&#128;¢ Enhanced cross-sector linkagesâ&#128;&#148;&#13;
health centre/K        communities and                                                         access to safe drinking water,&#13;
Sh 55,000 per          promoting cross-                                                        sanitary latrines, school health&#13;
dispensary)            sector linkages       â&#128;¢        Performance incentives     30â&#128;&#147;70%      â&#128;¢ Linked improved coverage of&#13;
                     â&#128;¢ Other community-                                                        KEPH Servicesâ&#128;&#148;initially to&#13;
                       based innovative                                                        facilities (based on scorecards)&#13;
                       activities (e.g.,                                                       and subsequently to communities&#13;
                       maintenance of water                                                    and Community Health Extension&#13;
                       sources, sanitation)                                                    Workers after the community&#13;
                                                                                               strategy is implemented&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                      21&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                             Annex 3 Spider Web&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        I. Outcomes comparisons:&#13;
                                     Kenya and Low Income Countries&#13;
                                                                                          Note on interpretation:&#13;
                                                                                          In this plot â&#128;&#152;higherâ&#128;&#153; is â&#128;&#152;worseâ&#128;&#153; â&#128;&#147; since&#13;
                                                                                          these indicators are positive measures&#13;
                                                                                          of mortality / morbidity. Life&#13;
                                                                                          expectancy is converted to be an&#13;
                                                                                          inverse measure.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                          The values on the radar plot have&#13;
                                                                                          been standardized with respect to the&#13;
                                                                                          average low income country value.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                          The table below summarizes outcome&#13;
                                                                                          comparisons with the average low&#13;
                                                                                          income country (LIC).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  IMR: Infant mortality rate (2010). U5MR: Under-5 mortality rate (2010). Stunting: prevalence of low height-for-age among children under 5 (2010). MMR: Maternal&#13;
  mortality rate (2010) per 100 000 live births. Adult mortality: Adult mortality rate per 1000 male adults (2010). [100-(life expectancy)]: Life expectancy at birth&#13;
  (2010) subtracted from maximum of 100. Neonatal mortality: Neonatal mortality per 1000 living births. CD as cause of death: Communicable diseases as cause of&#13;
  death (% total). All data from World Bank's World Development Indicators. Income averages for stunting calculated by Bank staff and are unweighted.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        II. Inputs comparisons&#13;
                                   Kenya and Low Income Countries&#13;
                                                                                           Note on interpretation:&#13;
                                                                                           This plot shows indicators which&#13;
                                                                                           measure spending on health or the&#13;
                                                                                           number of health workers per&#13;
                                                                                           population.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                           The values on the radar plot have&#13;
                                                                                           been standardized with respect to&#13;
                                                                                           the average low income country&#13;
                                                                                           value.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                           The table below summarizes inputs&#13;
                                                                                           comparisons with the average low&#13;
                                                                                           income country (LIC).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
THE as % of GDP: Health expenditure, total (% of GDP) (2010). Hospital bed density: Hospital beds per 1,000 people (latest available year). Physician density: Physicians&#13;
per 1,000 people (latest available year). Nurse/midwife density: Nurses and midwives per 1,000 people (latest available year). GHE as % of THE/10: Public health&#13;
expenditure (% of total expenditure on health) (2010). All data from World Bank's World Development Indicators.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                            22&#13;
&amp;#12;                                      III. Coverage comparisons&#13;
                                   Kenya and Low Income Countries&#13;
                                                                                           Note on interpretation:&#13;
                                                                                           In this plot â&#128;&#152;higherâ&#128;&#153; is â&#128;&#152;betterâ&#128;&#153; â&#128;&#147; since&#13;
                                                                                           these     indicators      are    positive&#13;
                                                                                           measures. In this case, all are percent&#13;
                                                                                           of the population receiving or having&#13;
                                                                                           access to a certain health related&#13;
                                                                                           service.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                           The values on the radar plot have&#13;
                                                                                           been standardized with respect to&#13;
                                                                                           the average low income country&#13;
                                                                                           value.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                           The table below summarizes&#13;
                                                                                           coverage comparisons with the&#13;
                                                                                           average low income country (LIC).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
DPT immunization: % of children aged 12-23 months with DPT immunization (2010). Prenatal services: % of pregnant women receiving prenatal care (latest available&#13;
year). Contraceptive prevalence: % of women ages 15-49 using contraception (latest available year). Skilled birth attendance: % of all births attended by skilled health&#13;
staff (latest available year). Improved sanitation: % of population with access to improved sanitation facilities (2010). TB treatment success: Tuberculosis treatment&#13;
success rate (% of registered cases). All data from World Bank's World Development Indicators.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     IV. Infrastructure comparisons&#13;
                                    Kenya and Low Income Countries&#13;
                                                                                           Note on interpretation:&#13;
                                                                                           In this plot â&#128;&#152;higherâ&#128;&#153; is â&#128;&#152;betterâ&#128;&#153; â&#128;&#147; since&#13;
                                                                                           these     indicators      are    positive&#13;
                                                                                           measures of provision of certain&#13;
                                                                                           good / service, and a measure of&#13;
                                                                                           urban development.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                           The values on the radar plot have&#13;
                                                                                           been standardized with respect to&#13;
                                                                                           the average low income country&#13;
                                                                                           value.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                           The table below summarizes&#13;
                                                                                           infrastructure comparisons with the&#13;
                                                                                           average low income country (LIC).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Paved roads: % of total roads paved (most recent). Internet users: users per 100 people (2010, with some estimates from prior years). Mobile phone users: mobile&#13;
 cellular subscriptions per 100 people (2010). Access to improved water: % of population with access to improved water source (2010). All data from World Bank's&#13;
 World Development Indicators.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                           23&#13;
&amp;#12;                                       V. Demography comparisons&#13;
                                     Kenya and Low Income Countries&#13;
                                                                                               Note on interpretation:&#13;
                                                                                               Indicators here measure births per&#13;
                                                                                               woman, the extent of rurality, and&#13;
                                                                                               the number of dependents.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                               The values on the radar plot have&#13;
                                                                                               been standardized with respect to&#13;
                                                                                               the average low income country&#13;
                                                                                               value.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                               The table below summarizes&#13;
                                                                                               demographic indicators comparisons&#13;
                                                                                               with the average low income country&#13;
                                                                                               (LIC).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
TFR: total fertility rate (births per woman), 2009. Dependency ratio: % of working-age population (2010) aged less than 15 or more than 64. Youth dependency: % of&#13;
working-age population (2010) aged less than 15. Rurality: % of total population in rural areas (2010). All data from World Bank's World Development Indicators.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                          VI. Inequality comparisons&#13;
                                       Kenya and Low Income Countries&#13;
                                                                                               Note on interpretation:&#13;
                                                                                               In this plot â&#128;&#152;higherâ&#128;&#153; is â&#128;&#152;inequalâ&#128;&#153; and&#13;
                                                                                               indicators here measure inequalities&#13;
                                                                                               in selected health outcomes by&#13;
                                                                                               taking the ratio of prevalence&#13;
                                                                                               between Q1 and Q5.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                               The values on the radar plot have&#13;
                                                                                               been standardized with respect to&#13;
                                                                                               the average low income country&#13;
                                                                                               value.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                               The table below summarizes&#13;
                                                                                               inequality indicators comparisons&#13;
                                                                                               with the average low income country&#13;
                                                                                               (LIC).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   All indicators measure the ratio of prevalence between the poorest (in Q1, the first wealth distribution quintile) and the richest (in Q5, the fifth wealth distribution&#13;
   quintile). The data (latest data available) are taken from HNPstats (http://data.worldbank.org/data-catalog/HNPquintile).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                              24&#13;
&amp;#12;25&#13;
&amp;#12;The World Bank supports the efforts of countries to share prosperity by&#13;
transitioning toward universal health coverage (UHC) with the objectives of&#13;
improving health outcomes, reducing the financial risks associated with ill&#13;
health, and increasing equity. The Bank recognizes that there are many paths&#13;
toward UHC and does not endorse a particular path or set of organizational or&#13;
financial arrangements to reach it. Regardless of the path chosen, the quality of&#13;
the instruments and institutions countries establish to implement UHC are&#13;
essential to its success. Countries will face a variety of challenges during the&#13;
implementation phase as they strive to expand health coverage. With that in&#13;
mind, the World Bank launched the Universal Health Coverage Studies Series&#13;
(UNICO Studies Series) to develop knowledge and operational tools designed&#13;
to help countries tackle these implementation challenges in ways that are&#13;
fiscally sustainable and that enhance equity and efficiency. The UNICO Studies&#13;
Series consists of technical papers and country case studies that analyze&#13;
different issues related to the challenges of UHC policy implementation.&#13;
&#13;
The case studies in the series are based on the use of a standardized protocol&#13;
to analyze the nuts and bolts of 27 programs in 25 countries that have&#13;
expanded coverage from the bottom up, starting with the poor and vulnerable.&#13;
The protocol consists of 300 questions designed to elicit a detailed&#13;
understanding of how countries are implementing five sets of policies to&#13;
accomplish the following:&#13;
&#13;
â&#128;¢   Manage the benefits package&#13;
â&#128;¢   Manage processes to include the poor and vulnerable&#13;
â&#128;¢   Nudge efficiency reforms to the provision of care&#13;
â&#128;¢   Address new challenges in primary care&#13;
â&#128;¢   Tweak financing mechanisms to align the incentives of different stakeholders&#13;
    in the health sector&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The UNICO Studies Series aims to provide UHC implementers with an expanded toolbox.&#13;
The protocol, case studies and technical papers are being published as part of the Series. A&#13;
comparative analysis of the case studies will be available in 2013.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                               26&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="17210384">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2013/01/17210384/kenya-improving-universal-primary-health-care-kenya-case-study-health-sector-services-fund
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2013/01/17210384/kenya-improving-universal-primary-health-care-kenya-case-study-health-sector-services-fund</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2013/01/17210384/kenya-improving-universal-primary-health-care-kenya-case-study-health-sector-services-fund</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2013-02-04T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2013-02-04T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2013/02/04/000425962_20130204110301/Rendered/INDEX/750020NWP0Box30ry0Health0Care0KENYA.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2013/02/04/000425962_20130204110301/Rendered/PDF/750020NWP0Box30ry0Health0Care0KENYA.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2013-01-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2013-02-04T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Kenya - Improving universal primary health
            care by Kenya : a case study of the Health Sector Services Fund
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            This case study describes the Government
            of Kenya's initiative to expand the supply of health
            care and strengthen primary health care through
            implementation of the Health Sector Services Fund (HSSF),
            which provides direct cash transfers to primary health
            facilities. This initiative, launched in 2010, is a direct
            response to challenges identified by the Public Expenditure
            Tracking Surveys in making funds for operation and
            maintenance available to the health facilities, and builds
            on lessons from initiatives supported by the Danish
            International Development Agency (DANIDA) in the Coastal Region.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Kenya - Improving universal primary health
            care by Kenya : a case study of the Health Sector Services Fund
        </docna>
        <display_title>Kenya - Improving universal
            primary health care by Kenya : a case study of the Health
            Sector Services Fund</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2013/01/17210384/kenya-improving-universal-primary-health-care-kenya-case-study-health-sector-services-fund</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Working Paper (Numbered Series)</docty>
        <subtopic>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation,Population Policies,Housing &amp; Human Habitats,Health Economics &amp; Finance,Health Systems Development &amp; Reform</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Health, Nutrition and Population,Communities and Human Settlements</teratopic>
        <count>Kenya</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Ramana, Gandham NV</author>
            <author>Chepkoech, Rose</author>
            <author>Workie, Netsanet Walelign</author>
        </authors>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>East Africa!$!80458</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Sub-Saharan Africa!$!80473</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000425962_20130204110301</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>Africa,Africa</admreg>
        <colti>Universal Health Coverage (UNICO) studies
            series ; no. 5</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Health, Nutrition and Population,Communities and Human Settlements</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            access to services, accountability
            mechanisms, Adolescents, Adult mortality, Adult mortality
            rate, aged, birth attendants, breastfeeding, budget
            allocation, capacity building, child health, child health
            services, citizen, citizens, Clinical Quality, clinics,
            Communicable diseases, Community Health, community
            participation, cost sharing, counseling, Counselling,
            decision making, delivery of health services, developing
            countries, disadvantaged groups, Dispensaries, Early
            childhood, economic growth, Elderly, Employment, equitable
            distribution of resources, essential drugs, essential health
            services, essential medicines, expenditures, Family
            planning, Family planning services, financial constraints,
            Financial Management, financial resources, financial risks,
            General Health System, health care coverage, health care
            expenditure, health care facilities, health care financing,
            Health care providers, health care services, health care
            system, Health Centers, health clinics, Health Coverage,
            health data, Health Expenditure, Health Expenditure per
            capita, health expenditures, Health Extension, Health
            Facilities, Health Financing, Health information, Health
            information systems, health maintenance, health maintenance
            organizations, Health Management, health needs, health
            outcomes, Health Policy, health professionals, health
            programs, Health Results, Health Sector, health service,
            health service delivery, health service providers, Health
            Services, health spending, health status, Health System,
            health systems, health systems strengthening, Health
            Workers, healthcare services, Healthy lifestyles, HIV,
            HIV/AIDS, Hospital, Hospital beds, hospitals, human
            resources, human resources management, Hygiene, ill health,
            Immigration, Immunization, income, income countries,
            inequities, Infant mortality, Infant mortality rate,
            Information System, inpatient care, Insurance, insurance
            companies, integrated management of childhood illnesses,
            integration, iron, isolation, Life expectancy, Life
            expectancy at birth, local communities, local community, Low
            Income, Malaria, management of health, medical examinations,
            Medical Research, Medical Services, Medical Supplies,
            medicines, ministries of health, Ministry of Health,
            morbidity, mortality, Mother, National Health, National
            Health Insurance, National Health Insurance Fund, national
            level, national levels, national priority, newborn,
            nongovernmental organizations, number of people, nurses,
            nutrition, participation of communities, Physician,
            Physicians, pilot projects, Policy framework, policy
            response, Poor Health, population density, Postnatal care,
            Pregnancy, pregnant women, prenatal care, preventive health
            services, Preventive Treatment, primary care, Primary Health
            Care, primary health care facilities, primary health
            facilities, primary health services, primary school, Private
            health insurance, private insurance, Private Pharmacies,
            private sector, Progress, providers of health services,
            provision of care, Public Expenditure, Public Health, Public
            Health Services, public health system, Public Hospitals,
            public sector, Public Service, public services, quality
            care, quality of care, quality of health, quality of
            services, quality services, recreation, rehabilitation,
            Reproductive Health, reproductive health programs, research
            institutions, resource allocation, resource allocations,
            rural areas, Sanitation, school health, screening, service
            delivery points, service provider, service provision,
            services for children, sexually transmitted infections,
            skilled attendants, skilled birth attendants, Spillover,
            Substance abuse, supply of health care, Tetanus, traditional
            healers, Tuberculosis, universal access, use of resources,
            user fees, vaccination, Vaccines, violence, work
            environment, Workers
        </keywd>
        <owner>Health, Nutrition &amp; Popultn Team (HDNHE)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>East Africa</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Sub-Saharan Africa</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>75002</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Expenditure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Capacities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Staffing Needs Assessments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery of Health Care</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Care Delivery</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Service Management and Delivery</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Basic Drugs</ml:concept><ml:concept>Essential Medicines List</ml:concept><ml:concept>Lists of Essential Medicines</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutritional supplements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Vitamins</ml:concept><ml:concept>Vaccines</ml:concept><ml:concept>Strategic Planning</ml:concept><ml:concept>HRH</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Workers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Reproductive Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Reproductive and Women's Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Electronic Medical Records</ml:concept><ml:concept>HMIS</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Information Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Efficiency of Public Expenditures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Expenditures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Financial Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Spending</ml:concept><ml:concept>Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deconcentration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delegation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Devolution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sub-National Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subnational Government and Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Checks on Executive Power</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen User Satisfaction Survey</ml:concept><ml:concept>Independent Commissions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ombudsmen</ml:concept><ml:concept>Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Parliament</ml:concept><ml:concept>Procurement Complaints Review Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supreme Audit Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Foreign Direct Investments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Linkages</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government Expenditure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Services Delivery</ml:concept><ml:concept>Essential Medicines</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supplements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Immunizations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Cash Transfers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Strategic Policy Planning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Essential Package of Health Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resources for Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Reproductive and Maternal Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Management Information Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Managing Public Finances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Administrative Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Accountability Mechanisms</ml:concept><ml:concept>FDI Spillovers</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Africa</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Kenya</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>