<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>﻿DOCUMENTS&#13;
December 13, 2012&#13;
Ms. Emma Donnelly&#13;
1 lead of DFID Yerr.en&#13;
Department for Intcrnational Development&#13;
1 Palace Street&#13;
London, SWIE 5H.E&#13;
United Kingdom&#13;
Trust Fund Administration Arrangement between the Government of&#13;
the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland acting&#13;
thiough the Departm?nt for International Development (DFID) and&#13;
the International Bar, k for Reconstruction and Development and the&#13;
International Develcpment Association concerning the Mutual&#13;
Accountability Framework (MAF) Multi-Donor Trust Fund for&#13;
Yemen (YMAFTF) (TF No.TF072002) - DFIDARIES Component&#13;
No.203756-101&#13;
Dear Ms. Donnelly:&#13;
1     We are pleased to acknowledge on behalf of the International Bank for&#13;
REconstruction and Development ("IBRD") and the International Development&#13;
I' sociation ("IDA") (collectively, the "Bank") that the that the Government of the United&#13;
K ingdom of Greal. Britain and Northern Ireland acting through the Department for&#13;
Iliernational Development (the "Donor") will make available as a grant the sum of three&#13;
rr illion one hundred and fifty thousand Pounds Sterling (f3,150,000.00) (the&#13;
"C ontribution") for MAF M ilti-Donor Trust Fund for Yemen (the "Trust Fund") in&#13;
accordance with the provisions of this Arrangement. Other donors are also expected to&#13;
cotribute to the Trust Fund in accordance with the provisions specified in the Annexes&#13;
to&gt; this Arrangemen.&#13;
The Contribution wil' be used to finance the activities and the categories of&#13;
cx9enditure set forth in the "Description of Activities, Expenditures and Governance&#13;
n rangements under the MA. Multi-Donor Trust Fund for Yemen" attached hereto as&#13;
inex 1, and will be administered by the Bank on behalf of the Donor in accordance with&#13;
th.e terms of this Arangement including the "Standard Provisions Applicable to the MAF&#13;
M,I jlti-Donor Trust Fund for Yemen" (the "Standard Provisions") attached hereto as&#13;
A niex 2.&#13;
The Donor will deposit the Contribution into such bank account designated by the&#13;
Bank in installments in accordance with the following schedule:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-2-&#13;
(a) promptly following countersignature of this Arrangement by the Donor and&#13;
upon submission o:'a payment request by the Bank, £1,100,000.00.&#13;
(b) on or before August 14, 2013 and upon submission of a payment request by&#13;
the Bank, £683,332.00.&#13;
(c) on or before Febrt ary 14, 2014 and upon submission of a payment request by&#13;
the Bank, £683,332 .00.&#13;
(d) on or before August 15, 2014 and upon submission of a payment request by&#13;
the Bank, f683,334.00.&#13;
4.    When making each such deposit, the Donor will instruct its bank to include in its&#13;
payment details inlormation iremittance advice) field of its SWIFT payment message,&#13;
information indicaling: the amount paid, that the payment is made by the Donor for&#13;
TF072002 (MAF Multi-Donor Trust Fund for Yemen), and the date of the deposit (the&#13;
"I)eposit Instruction"). In addition, the Donor will provide a copy of the Donor's Deposit&#13;
Ir struction to the Bank's Accounting Trust Funds Division by e-mail sent to&#13;
tfremitadvice@worldbank.org or by fax sent to (202) 614-1315.&#13;
5.     The Bank will convert the Contribution funds into the holding currency of the&#13;
T,ust Fund, namely the United States Dollars, promptly upon receipt of the Contribution&#13;
funds and the Deposit Instruction containing the information specified in paragraph 4 at&#13;
the exchange rate obtained )y the Bank on the date of the conversion. Where the&#13;
C' ntribution proves to be insufficient to complete the activities as a result of an exchange&#13;
r: te fluctuation, neither the BE nk nor the Donor will bear any responsibility for providing&#13;
aiiv additional financing.&#13;
( Except as provided for in paragraph 4 above, any notice, request or other&#13;
communication to be given Dr made under this Arrangement will be in writing and&#13;
delivered by mail, facsimile o:- e-mail to the respective party's address specified below or&#13;
at such other address as such r arty notifies in writing to the other party from time to time:&#13;
For the Ban,:&#13;
Name: Ipek Alkan&#13;
Title: Senior Country Officer&#13;
Unit/Departme it: MNCA3, J-2-061&#13;
The World Bark&#13;
1818 H Street, \4W&#13;
Washington, DC 20433&#13;
U.S.A.&#13;
Tel:202-458-5106&#13;
Fax:202-477-1603&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-3-&#13;
E-mail:lalkan@ worldbank.org&#13;
For the Donor:&#13;
Name: Ross Hilton&#13;
Title: Deputy Pmgram Manager&#13;
Office: Departrent for International Development&#13;
Add-ess: 1 Palace Street&#13;
London, SWIE 5HE&#13;
United Kingdom&#13;
Tel:+44(0) 20 7023 0867&#13;
Fax:+44 (0) 20 7023 0744&#13;
E-mail:r-hilton@dfid.gov.uk&#13;
All annexes hereto constitute an integral part of this Arrangement. This&#13;
Arrangement may be amenced only in writing between the Bank and the Donor;&#13;
r:ovided, however, that such annexes may be amended only with the agreement of all&#13;
donors contributing to the Trust Fund.&#13;
Please confirm your acceptance with the foregoing, on behalf of the Donor, by&#13;
signing and dating the two or ginals, retaining one original for your record and returning&#13;
tlhv other original to the Bank. Upon receipt by the Bank of the original Arrangement,&#13;
coantersigned by you, this Arrangement will become effective as of the date of the&#13;
cointersignature. It is undersiood that this Arrangement is not an international Treaty. It&#13;
i; in administrative Arrangement between DFID and the Bank.&#13;
Sincerely,&#13;
INTERNATIONAL BANK FOR RECONSTRUCTION AND DEVELOPMENT/&#13;
INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPMENT ASSOCIATION&#13;
Hartwig Sc afer&#13;
Director&#13;
Yemen, Egypt and Djibouti Country Department&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-4-&#13;
AGREED:&#13;
UNITED KINGDOM OF GREAT BRITAIN AND NORTHERN IRELAND&#13;
ACTING THROUGH '[HE DEPARTMENT FOR INTERNATIONAL&#13;
DEVELOPMENT (DFID)&#13;
By:                 ______&#13;
Name: EMf t     0j4  E LL&#13;
Title: FI OYFFL/ME/N&#13;
Date: 1h / 2- Z2.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-5-&#13;
ANNEX 1&#13;
Description of Ativities, Expenditures and Governance Arrangements under the&#13;
MAF Multi-Donor Trust Fund for Yemen&#13;
This Annex will be applicable to and form an integral part of all agreements&#13;
eniered into between the Bank and entities (collectively, the "Donors") that provide&#13;
contributions (the aggregate o "all contributions from the Donors, the "Contributions") to&#13;
be administered by the Bank for the Trust Fund.&#13;
A. DESCRIPTION OF ACTIVITIES&#13;
The overarching objective of the YMAFTF is to strengthen the capacity of the&#13;
government to coordinate and monitor commitments made under the six pillars of the&#13;
MAF and by donors at the Riyadh and New York Meetings.&#13;
(i)   Bank-Executed Trust Fund Activities:&#13;
(a)   provisic n of advisory support to the MAF Coordination Secretariat&#13;
in order to build and strengthen its capacities and competencies; (b)&#13;
program management and Trust Fund administration; and (c) supervision&#13;
of Recipient Ex.ecuted activities.&#13;
(ii)  Recipient-Executed Trust Fund Activities:&#13;
(a)   setting up MAF Coordination Secretariat, equipped with high level&#13;
professional ar.d administrative staff; (b) provision of office equipment&#13;
and furniture "or the MAF Secretariat; (c) organizing and conducting&#13;
consultation workshops and study visits on key policy issues; and (d)&#13;
provision of on-demand technical assistance on various areas of the MAF.&#13;
B. CATEGORIES OF EXI ENDITURE&#13;
For Bank-Executed activities, the Contributions may be used to finance: (a)&#13;
associated overheads; (b) consultant fees individuals and firms; (c) contractual&#13;
services; (d) extended tcrm consultants; (e) media, workshops, conferences and&#13;
meetings; (f) staff costs - with indirect costs; (g) temporary support staff costs; and&#13;
(h) travel expenses.&#13;
For Recipient-Executed E.ctivities, the Contributions may be used to finance: (a)&#13;
consultant services; (b) go)ds; (c) operating costs; and (d) training.&#13;
The foregoing categories of expenditures may include the financing of taxes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-6-&#13;
C( GOVERNANCE ARRANGEMENTS&#13;
The World Bank will be solely responsible and accountable for the administration of&#13;
MAF Multi-Donor Trust Fund for Yemen, as well as the supervision of recipient-executed&#13;
tasks financed under YMAFTF, within the context of its operational policies and guidelines,&#13;
and as stipulated in the respective Administration and Grant Agreements. A World Bank&#13;
Task Team Leader (TTL) will oversee implementation of this Trust Fund. In addition, a&#13;
fie,ld-based YMAFTF coord nator will be selected to oversee the broader program&#13;
requirements, and coordinate and facilitate day-to-day operations of YMAFTF.  The&#13;
Y\4AFTF coordinaor will work in close coordination with the TTL as well as the World&#13;
Bank Country Manager located in Sana'a. The World Bank policy of full cost recovery for&#13;
hy brid TFs (both B ank-executed activities and Recipient-executed activities) will apply. As&#13;
part of the MAF arrangement, there will be quarterly meetings in Sana'a at the Head of the&#13;
Agency level for monitoring of the commitment made. These meetings will be co-chaired by&#13;
the Government of Yemen (G(oY) and the WB, and will provide status update on the progress&#13;
against the results framework and give opportunity to the representatives of the MG to&#13;
provide suggestions on adjustnents in direction or scope of the YMAF. High level meetings&#13;
ircluding representatives of th. Donors will take place every six months to take forward the&#13;
di scussion on MAF implemenlation.&#13;
D. PROGRAM CIUTERIA&#13;
The allocation decisions of specific grants and activities will be made based on the needs&#13;
ard priorities identified by the Bank in consultation with Government and which meet the&#13;
overall objective of implementing and operationalizing the Mutual Accountability&#13;
Ftamework (MAF).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-7-&#13;
ANNEX 2&#13;
Standard Provisions Applicable to the&#13;
MAF Multi-Donor Trust Fund for Yemen&#13;
This Annex will be applicable to and form an integral part of all agreements&#13;
etered into between the Bank and the Donors that provide Contributions to be&#13;
administered by the Bank for the Trust Fund.&#13;
1.    Administration of the Contributions&#13;
1.1.  The Bank will be responsible only for performing those functions specifically set&#13;
f.orth in this Arrangement and will not be subject to any other duties or responsibilities to&#13;
the Donors, including, without limitation, any duties or obligations that might otherwise&#13;
apply to a fiduciary or trustee under general principles of trust or fiduciary law. Nothing&#13;
i! this Arrangement will be considered a waiver of any privileges or immunities of the&#13;
IBRD and IDA under their Articles of Agreement or any applicable law, all of which are&#13;
ex pressly reserved.&#13;
1.2.  The Contribution will be administered in accordance with the Bank's applicable&#13;
policies and procedures, as tle same may be amended from time to time, including its&#13;
framework to prevent and combat fraud and corruption and its screening procedures to&#13;
prevent the use of Bank resources to finance terrorist activity, in line with the Bank's&#13;
obligations to give effect to t ie relevant decisions of the Security Council, taken under&#13;
Chapter VII of the of Charter of the United Nations. The Donor acknowledges that this&#13;
provision does not create any obligations of the Bank under the anti-terrorist financing&#13;
and asset control laws, regulations, rules and executive orders of an individual member&#13;
country that may apply to the Donor, nor will it be deemed a waiver, express or implied,&#13;
c- any of the privileges and immunities of the Bank.&#13;
2.    Commingling, Exchan e and Investment of the Contributions&#13;
2 I.  The Contributions will be accounted for as a single trust fund and will be kept&#13;
s.parate and apart from the funds of the Bank. The Contributions may be commingled&#13;
with other trust fund assets maintained by the Bank.&#13;
2 :.  The Contributions ma,1 be freely exchanged by the Bank into other currencies as&#13;
ri-,y facilitate their disbursement.&#13;
2. 3. The Bank will invest and reinvest the Contributions pending their disbursement in&#13;
accordance with tl-e Bank's )olicies and procedures for the investment of trust funds&#13;
administered by the Bank. The Bank will credit all income from such investment to the&#13;
Trust Fund to be used for the ame purposes as the Contributions.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-8-&#13;
3     Administrative Cost R-covery&#13;
3 1.  In order to assist in the defrayment of the costs of administration and other&#13;
expenses incurred by the Ban.-, under this Arrangement, the Bank may deduct and retain&#13;
f:-r its own account an amount equal to two percent (2%) of each Contribution. In&#13;
addition, costs for program management and trust fund administration as defined in&#13;
Annex 1 up to a maximum of 9.66% will be charged to the Trust Fund on an actual basis.&#13;
It the contributions increase beyond what was originally expected at the time of counter-&#13;
signature of the first administration arrangement, and the administrative costs increase as&#13;
a result, the Donors acknowledge that an additional administrative fee may be applied to&#13;
such new contributions.&#13;
4     Grants to Recipient&#13;
4. 1.  The Bank will, as administrator of the Trust Fund on behalf of the Donors, enter&#13;
irtto a grant agreement (the "Grant Agreement") with the "Recipient" selected in&#13;
accordance with the governance terms of Annex 1 (the "Recipients") consistent with the&#13;
purposes of this Arrangement and on the terms and conditions set forth in the Grant&#13;
Agreement. The Grant Agreement may be entered into up to the maximum amount of the&#13;
Contributions that all Donors have agreed to make available under the Administration&#13;
Arrangement between the Bark and the Donors. Upon request by a Donor, the Bank will&#13;
farnish a copy of the Grant Ag reement to the Donors.&#13;
4 2.  The Bank will be responsible for the supervision of the activities financed under&#13;
the Grant Agreement. Subject to the consent of the Recipient, representatives of the&#13;
D, onors may be invited by the Bank to participate in Bank supervision missions related to&#13;
the Trust Fund.&#13;
4 3.  The Bank will promptly inform the Donors of any significant modification to the&#13;
ti:rms of any Grant Agreement and of any contractual remedies that are exercised by the&#13;
flank under any G-ant Agreement. To the extent practicable, the Bank will afford the&#13;
Eonors the opportunity to exchange views before effecting any such modification or&#13;
exercising any such remedy.&#13;
Procuremert&#13;
For Recipient-executed activities, the Grant Agreement will provide that the&#13;
Contributions will be used )y the Recipient to finance expenditures for goods and&#13;
services, as the case may be, n accordance with the Bank's Guidelines on "Procurement&#13;
u-ider IBRD Loans and IDA Credits" and the Bank's Guidelines on the "Selection and&#13;
Employment of Consultants ty World Bank Borrowers," as in effect at the date of entry&#13;
iAlo the respective Grant Agreement.&#13;
5 2.  For Bank-executed aclivities, the employment and supervision of any consultants&#13;
and the procurement of any goods financed by the Contributions will be the responsibility&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-9-&#13;
c the Bank and will be carried out in accordance with its applicable policies and&#13;
! -ocedures.&#13;
Accounting and Financial Reporting&#13;
6.1.  The Bank will maintain separate records and ledger accounts in respect of the&#13;
Contributions deposited in the Trust Fund account and disbursements made therefrom.&#13;
6.2. The Bank will furnish to the Donors current financial information relating to&#13;
receipts, disbursements and fLnd balance in the holding currency of the Trust Fund with&#13;
ri spect to the Contributions via the World Bank's Trust Funds Donor Center secure&#13;
Nwebsite. Within six (6) montd s after all commitments and liabilities under the Trust Fund&#13;
have been satisfied and the Trust Fund has been closed, the final financial information&#13;
r lating to receipts, disbursements and fund balance in the holding currency of the Trust&#13;
f ind with respect to the Co itributions will be made available to the Donors via the&#13;
World Bank's Trus: Funds Donor Center secure website.&#13;
6.3.  The Bank will provide to the Donors, within six (6) months following the end of&#13;
each Bank fiscal vear, an annual single audit report, comprising (1) a management&#13;
assertion together with an att,,station from the Bank's external auditors concerning the&#13;
adequacy of internal control over cash-based financial reporting for all cash-based trust&#13;
funds as a whole; and (2) a combined financial statement for all cash-based trust funds&#13;
tgether with the Bank's external auditor's opinion thereon. The cost of the single audit&#13;
vill be borne by the Bank.&#13;
6.4.  If a Donor wishes to request, on an exceptional basis, a financial statement audit&#13;
by the Bank's external auditors of the Trust Fund, the Donor and the Bank will first&#13;
consult as to whether such an external audit is necessary. The Bank and the Donor will&#13;
a iree on the appropriate scope and terms of reference of such audit. Following agreement&#13;
ci the scope and terms of ref -rence, the Bank will arrange for such external audit. The&#13;
c,)sts of any such audit, includ Ing the internal costs of the Bank with respect to such audit,&#13;
vill be paid by the requesting Donor.&#13;
6.I.  The Bank will provide the Donors with copies of all financial statements and&#13;
auditors' reports received by the Bank from the Recipient pursuant to the Grant&#13;
I L reement.&#13;
'7.   Proaress Reporting&#13;
7.1.  The Bank will provido the Donors with semi-annual reports on the progress of&#13;
activities financed by the Con:ributions. Within six (6) months of the final disbursement&#13;
date specified in paragraph 8.2, the Bank will furnish to the Donors a final report on the&#13;
activities financed by the Trus: Fund.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-10-&#13;
7.2   Any Donor may review or evaluate activities financed by the Trust Fund. The&#13;
E:nor and the Bank will agrce on the scope and conduct of such review or evaluation,&#13;
and the Bank will provide all relevant information within the limits of its policies and&#13;
procedures. All associated ccsts will be borne by the Donor. It is understood that any&#13;
such review or evaluation will not constitute a financial, compliance or other audit of the&#13;
Trust Fund.&#13;
8.    Disbursement Cancellation; Refund&#13;
8.1.   It is expected that the Contributions will be fully disbursed by the Bank by&#13;
DE.cember 31, 2015. The Bank will only disburse Contributions for the purposes of this&#13;
Arrangement after such date with the written approval of the Donors.&#13;
8.2    Any Donor or the Bank may, upon three (3) months' prior written notice, cancel&#13;
al I or part of the Donor's pro rata share, of any remaining balance of the Contributions&#13;
that is not committed pursuani to any agreements entered into between the Bank and any&#13;
crnsultants and/or other third parties for the purposes of this Arrangement prior to the&#13;
receipt of such notice, including the Grant Agreement.&#13;
83.   Following the final disbursement date specified in paragraph 8.1, the Bank will&#13;
return any remaining balance of the Contributions to the Donors or to the relevant Donor&#13;
Balance Account on a pro rala basis based on the Donors' paid Contributions. In the&#13;
e,.ent of a cancellatlon the Bank will promptly return to the relevant Donor or Donors or&#13;
to the relevant Donor Balance Account the Donor's pro rata share of uncommitted&#13;
Contributions in accordance with paragraph 8.2.&#13;
9     Disclosure&#13;
The Bank will disclose this Arrangement and related information on this Trust&#13;
Fund in accordance with the World Bank Policy on Access to Information. By entering&#13;
into this Arrangement, Donors consent to disclosure of this Arrangement and related&#13;
information on this Trust Fund.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="17303813">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2012/12/17303813/official-documents--administration-agreement-dfid-tf072002
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2012/12/17303813/official-documents--administration-agreement-dfid-tf072002</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2012/12/17303813/official-documents--administration-agreement-dfid-tf072002</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2013-01-11T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2013-01-11T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <docm_id>090224b0818833e1</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b0818833e1</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/MNA/2013/01/11/090224b0818833e1/1_0/Rendered/INDEX/Official0Docum0h0DFID0for0TF0720020.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/MNA/2013/01/11/090224b0818833e1/1_0/Rendered/PDF/Official0Docum0h0DFID0for0TF0720020.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2012-12-13T11:58:01Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2013-01-11T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docna>
            Official Documents- Administration Agreement
            with DFID for TF072002
        </docna>
        <display_title>Official Documents-
            Administration Agreement with DFID for TF072002</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/2012/12/17303813/official-documents--administration-agreement-dfid-tf072002</listing_relative_url>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <docty>Trust Fund Administrative Agreement</docty>
        <count>Yemen</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Mwenda,Edith Ruguru</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>HQBOCS</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <owner>Anchr:Djibouti/Egypt/Yemen (MNCA3)</owner>
        <trustfund>TF072002-Mutual Accountability Framework
            (MAF) Multi-Donor Trust Fund for Yemen</trustfund>
        <lang>English</lang>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Arts and Culture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>Freedom of Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>Bank Supervision</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Media</ml:concept><ml:concept>Treaties</ml:concept><ml:concept>Privileges and Immunities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Right to Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>External Audit</ml:concept><ml:concept>Bank Regulation and Supervision</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Yemen</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>