<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>﻿[OCUMIEKT9.&#13;
The World Bark                                    1818 H Stree) N.W.      (202) 473-1000&#13;
INTERNATIONAL BANIK FOR RECONSTRUCTIOIN AND DEV WLOPMEN  ,9s ,D.C. 20433  Cable Address: INTBAFRAD&#13;
INTERNATIONAL DEVI*LOPMENT ASSOCIATION            U.S.A.                  Cable Address: INDEVAS&#13;
November 27, 2012&#13;
Mr. Scott Dawson&#13;
First Assistant Director Genei-al&#13;
South and West Asia Divisio!i&#13;
AusAID&#13;
255 London Circuit&#13;
Canberra, ACT 2600&#13;
Australia&#13;
Trust Fund Administration Agreement between the Government of&#13;
Australia, acting through the Australian Agency for International&#13;
Development and tL e International Bank for Reconstruction and&#13;
Development and the Inter national Development Association concerning the&#13;
Multi-Donor Trust Fund for the South Asia Water Initiative Phase-2 (Trust&#13;
Fund No.TF071929), A1sA D Agreement 63224&#13;
Dear Mr. Dawson:&#13;
1.    We are pleased to acknowledge on behalf of the International Bank for&#13;
Reconstruction and Devel,praent ("IBRD") and the International Development&#13;
Association ("IDA") (collective Ly, t le "Bank") that the Government of Australia, acting&#13;
through the Australian Ager cy for International Development (AusAID) (the "Donor")&#13;
shall make available as i :,ran: the sum of eight million Australian Dollars&#13;
(AUD8,000,000.00) (the "Contribut ion") for the Multi-Donor Trust Fund for the South&#13;
Asia Water Initiative Phase-: Tiust . 'und (the "Trust Fund") in accordance with the terms&#13;
of this Agreement, Other doiors ar: also expected to contribute to the Trust Fund on the&#13;
terms and conditions specified in the Annexes to this Agreement.&#13;
2.    The Contribution shall be used to finance the activities and the categories of&#13;
expenditure set forth in the "Desc -iption of Activities, Expenditures and Governance&#13;
Arrangements under the Multi- Dor or Trust Fund for the South Asia Water Initiative&#13;
Pha;e-2 Trust Fund" attache, I h-ereto as Annex 1, and shall be administered by the Bank&#13;
on I:ehalf of the Donor in z ccorda ice with the terms of this Agreement including the&#13;
"Staidard Provisions Applicable to 1 he Multi-Donor Trust Fund for the South Asia Water&#13;
Initiative Phase-2 Trust Fund" (the "Standard Provisions") attached hereto as Annex 2.&#13;
3.    The Donor shall dep )sil the Contribution into such bank account designated by&#13;
the Bank in installments in a(cordan-:e with the following schedule:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-2-&#13;
(a) promptly 'ollowinig countersignature of this Agreement by the Donor and&#13;
submission of a payment request by the Bank, two million Australian Dollars&#13;
(AUD 2,000,000),&#13;
(b) on or before 15 Febru iry 2014, three million Australian Dollars (AUD&#13;
3,000,000) and submissic n of a payment request by the Bank; and&#13;
(c) on or before 15 F ,bru ry 2015 three million Australian Dollars (AUD&#13;
3,000,000) and su6missic n of a payment request by the Bank.&#13;
4.    When making each deposit, the Donor shall instruct its bank to include in its&#13;
payment details information (rcmitiance advice) field of its SWIFT payment message,&#13;
information indicating: the imount paid, that the payment is made by the Donor for&#13;
TFO71929 (the South Asia Weter nitiative Phase-2 Trust Fund), and the date of the&#13;
deposit (the "Deposit Instru(tion"). In addition, the Donor shall provide a copy of the&#13;
Donor's Deposit Instruction to the Bank's Accounting Trust Funds Division by e-mail&#13;
sent to tfremitadvide@worldlhank.or:; or by fax sent to (202) 614-1315.&#13;
5.     The Bank shall conNert the Contribution funds into the holding currency of the&#13;
Trust Fund, namely United States Dollars, promptly upon receipt of the Contribution&#13;
funds and the Deposit Instruction containing the information specified in paragraph 4 at&#13;
the exchange rate obtained by the Bank on the date of the conversion. Where the&#13;
Coriiribution proves to be ins uff [ciet t to complete the activities as a result of an exchange&#13;
rate fluctuation, neither the B anl: noi the Donor shall bear any responsibility for providing&#13;
any additional financi:ag.&#13;
6.    Except as provided foi in paragraph 4 above, any notice, request or other&#13;
communication to be given or m!de under this Agreement shall be in writing and&#13;
delivered by mail, facsimile or c-ma .1 to the respective party's address specified below or&#13;
at such other address as such party n )tifies in writing to the other party from time to time:&#13;
For the Bank:&#13;
Ms. Geneviev, Connors&#13;
Senior Water Re,,ources Specialist, SASDI&#13;
The World Banik&#13;
HT (H' ndusta 1 T [me.) House&#13;
Ground Floor&#13;
18-20 Kasturt a (rand ai Marg&#13;
New Delhi - 110)01&#13;
India&#13;
Tel: +91 11 4924 7732&#13;
Email: gconnrs@Ow)rldbank.org&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-3-&#13;
For the Donor&#13;
Mr. Russell RAhson&#13;
First Secretar)&#13;
AusAID New Delhi&#13;
Austraian High Commission&#13;
1/50 G Shanti-ath, Clianakyapuri&#13;
New Delhi 11 )K1 IDIA&#13;
Tel: +9111 449 4465&#13;
Fax: +9111 2688 7492&#13;
E-mail: Russe .l.rollas on@dfat.gov.au&#13;
7.    All annexes hereto conslitut( an integral part of this Agreement. This Agreement&#13;
may be amended only in writing b tween the Bank and the Donor; provided, however,&#13;
that such annexes may be amenled )nly with the agreement of all donors contributing to&#13;
the Trust Fund.&#13;
8.    Please confirm your agieem ent with the foregoing, on behalf of the Donor, by&#13;
signing, dating, and retuminj to us t 4e enclosed copy of this Agreement. Upon receipt by&#13;
the Bank of the copy of t1lis Agr :ement countersigned by you, this Agreement will&#13;
become effective as of the dai:e of thi countersignature.&#13;
Sincerely,&#13;
INTERNATIONAL BAN K FOR RECONSTRUCTION AND DEVELOPMENT/&#13;
INTERNATI ONAL DEVELOPMENT ASSOCIATION&#13;
3 label . Luerrero&#13;
Vice President&#13;
5 outh Asia Region&#13;
AGREED:&#13;
AUSTRAAN AGENCY FOR INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPMENT (AUSAID)&#13;
By:&#13;
Date:       '&#13;
Nari e: Scott Dawson&#13;
Titl: IFADG, South and W:st Asia Divisionl&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-4-&#13;
ANNEX 1&#13;
Descriptionof ctivities and Ext enditures and Governance Arrangements under&#13;
the Souih Asia Wite r In tiative Phase-2 Multi-Donor Trust Fund&#13;
This Annex s'lall be ap plic ble to and form an integral part of all agreements&#13;
entered into between the Banl&lt; an I entities (collectively, the "Donors") that provide&#13;
contributions (the aggregate of  11 c.ntributions from the Donors, the "Contributions") to&#13;
be administered by the Bank bar the Trust Fund.&#13;
A. DESCRIPTION OF ACTIVI IES&#13;
The Project Developne at (lbjective is to increase regional cooperation in the&#13;
mariagement of the Himalayan Riv:-r systems to deliver sustainable, fair and inclusive&#13;
development and climate resilience.&#13;
(i)   Ba k-Execut,-d,Tru!,t Fund Activities:&#13;
SAWI will support activities relating to the management of river basins rising in&#13;
the Greater Himalayas, in the co intr: es of Afghanistan, Bangladesh, Bhutan, China, India,&#13;
Nepal and Pakistan. The program will be structured around five key Focus Areas: the&#13;
Ganges Basin, the Brahmaputra Ba. in, the Indus Basin, the Sundarbans Landscape, and&#13;
Regional Cooperation. Speci:ic outp its and the outcomes to which they contribute will be&#13;
iderlified in the Focus AreE Sirate)ries at the basin, sub-basin/landscape, and regional&#13;
levels. At the Program level there will be two inter-related components:&#13;
Component 1: Building Coof erztion and Governance&#13;
Systematic dialogue (e.g., policy aiid practice debates engaging governments, opinion-&#13;
makers, civil society, privale ,ectc r and media) will be facilitated on transboundary&#13;
opportunities and policy developm nt at the regional and national levels, and among&#13;
development partners. Effor s will :e made to reach out to women and disadvantaged&#13;
groups in order to ensure that c )ncerns and opportunities relating to gender and&#13;
inclusiveness are identifie. The se dialogues will lead to improved common&#13;
understanding, better priority ,ettig, greater stakeholder ownership of interventions,&#13;
enabled policy environments. and ca.1s for action.&#13;
Learning: Capacity Building. Prioritized shared learning activities will be delivered to&#13;
build capacity and skills, and tc off,-r opportunities for regional practitioners to develop&#13;
de f1acto networks of practice. F articularly in fragile states, SAWI will support activities&#13;
to enhance the capacity of officials and other stakeholders to manage water (e.g., flood&#13;
forecasting, institutional deve-lopment, basin modeling) and to engage in transboundary&#13;
activities (e.g., international water law, negotiations.) These efforts will contribute to&#13;
more effective engagement on trar sboundary issues, better management practices and&#13;
more successful implementation of r elated activities.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-5-&#13;
Component 2: Supporting KrowledEe and Investments&#13;
Knowledge: Analysis and Pc licy Dt velopment. High quality, policy relevant knowledge&#13;
bases will be built in at least thrce important basins or landscapes. The process of&#13;
knowledge developirent and Jisscmination will be emphasized to ensure quality,&#13;
ownership and uptake, and S kVWI di alogues will be used as key platforms for knowledge&#13;
sharing. Accessibility (e.g., cpe:i ac.ess data platforms) will also be emphasized. These&#13;
effoits will contribute to m:re informed policy debates, greater legitimacy of&#13;
positions/decision taken and betier d,-signed interventions.&#13;
Action: Investment Design, Five genuine transboundary reform processes and/or&#13;
investments will be supportOd. Gr( at potential exists in the region for transboundary&#13;
cooperation on water resources rela:ed opportunities and risks at different levels: at the&#13;
regional (e.g., hydro meteorcilot:ical information, disaster risk management, hydropower&#13;
development), river basin (e.g., intcgrated river basin management, conjunctive use of&#13;
surface and groundwater, se dirent management) and landscape levels (e.g., glaciers,&#13;
mangroves). These actions m ou .d contribute to greater sustainability and productivity of&#13;
rivers and ecosystems, the prctect on of lives and livelihoods against disasters, and&#13;
enhanced resilience to climal e c hani ;e. Potentially, these efforts could also help diminish&#13;
regional tensions around tran.,;bounda Lry waters.&#13;
(ii)   Re$ipient-Exocuted [rust Fund Activities:&#13;
Supporting the client cointri -s in specific activities to be carried out in line with&#13;
enhancing their capacity and in coniributing to the SAWI-2 objectives, including: pilots,&#13;
capacity building, study tours, resezrch grants, show cases, exchange of knowledge and&#13;
best practice on specific issues relev; nt to SAWI-2.&#13;
B. CATEGORIES OF EXPE NDI TURE&#13;
(i)    For Bank-Exe zuted at.tivities the Contributions may be used to finance: (a)&#13;
associated overhead; (b) consultant fees individuals and firms; (c) contractual services;&#13;
(d) equipment and office prei nis es kase cost; (e) extended term consultants-No indirects;&#13;
(f) extended terms consultents; (g) field assignment benefits; (h) media, workshop,&#13;
conference and meeting; (i) staff costs - with indirect costs; (j) staff costs - no indirect&#13;
costs; (k) temporary support !taff cots; and (1) travel expenses.&#13;
(ii)  For Recipier -Execu ted activities, the Contributions may be used to&#13;
finance: (a) civil works; (1) consliltant services; (c) goods; (d) operating costs; (e)&#13;
training; and (f) grants.&#13;
The foregoing categories of expe aditures may include the financing of taxes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-6-&#13;
C.    GOVERNANCE ST RL CT JRE&#13;
An annual meeting of the MDTF Committee (SAWI Partners) will review&#13;
progress, update and approve the Fo,,us Area Strategies, and finalize an Annual Report. It&#13;
will assess progress against phanne i results and consider what changes are needed to&#13;
max'mize the likelihood that Lng term outcome indicators are achieved. Within the&#13;
components, the decision on allocalion of funds will be based on Focal Area Strategies&#13;
and understandings reached c uriag tie annual meeting of the MDTF Committee.&#13;
The World Bank wi 1 lie rmsponsible for the day-to-day administration of the&#13;
MDTF in accordance with admit istration arrangements with SAWI partners. The&#13;
responsibility of 'no-objectioi i' to act vities rests with the World Bank. The overall MDTF&#13;
will be supervised by the EAVI 'eam Leader/TF Manager, reporting directly to the&#13;
SASDI Sector Manager. The SAWI Team Leader/TF Manager and SASDI Sector&#13;
Manager will process all pro osals in accordance with required fiduciary procedures and&#13;
the objectives of the Trust Ftind Individual Focus Area Leaders will be appointed and be&#13;
responsible for the developnient of the Focus Area Strategy and for reporting on&#13;
implementation progress. Inc ividual Task Team Leaders will manage each grant funded&#13;
acti1ity supported by Ihe Tru!:t Fund&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-7-&#13;
ANNEX 2&#13;
Standard Provision s Applica ble Io the South Asia Water Initiative Phase-2 Multi-&#13;
]Donor Trust Fund&#13;
This Annex s'all be ap plicable to and form an integral part of all agreements&#13;
entered into between the 3ark and the Donors that provide Contributions to be&#13;
administered by the Bank for the TIL st Fund.&#13;
1.    Administration of the Contril iutions&#13;
1.1.  The Bank shall be res poiisibl e only for performing those functions specifically set&#13;
forti in this Agreement and ;hall nc t be subject to any other duties or responsibilities to&#13;
the Donors, including, witho at I imil ation, any duties or obligations that might otherwise&#13;
apply to a fiduciary or trustee under general principles of trust or fiduciary law. Nothing&#13;
in this Agreement shall be con3ide:ed a waiver of any privileges or immunities of the&#13;
IBR) and IDA under their A rticles f Agreement or any applicable law, all of which are&#13;
exp:essly reserved.&#13;
1.2.  The Contribution shal1 be administered in accordance with the Bank's applicable&#13;
policies and procedures, as 1 he sarr e may be amended from time to time, including its&#13;
framework to preveni and combat I raud and corruption and its screening procedures to&#13;
prevent the use of Bank resources to finance terrorist activity, in line with the Bank's&#13;
obligations to give effect to the relevant decisions of the Security Council, taken under&#13;
Chapter VII of the of Charte o:' the United Nations. The Donor acknowledges that this&#13;
provision does not create any cblig itions of the Bank under the anti-terrorist financing&#13;
and asset control laws, regulations, rules and executive orders of an individual member&#13;
country that may apply to the Donor, nor shall it be deemed a waiver, express or implied,&#13;
of any of the privileges and iiamunit es of the Bank.&#13;
2.    Commingling, Excha ige and Investment of the Contributions&#13;
2.1.  The Contributions shll be accounted for as a single trust fund and shall be kept&#13;
separate and apart from the 'unIs of the Bank. The Contributions may be commingled&#13;
with other trust fund assets r aintain d by the Bank.&#13;
2.2.  The Contributions may be fi eely exchanged by the Bank into other currencies as&#13;
may facilitate their disbursenien.&#13;
2.3. The Bank sha.1 invest and rminvest the Contributions pending their disbursement&#13;
in accordance with the Bank's policies and procedures for the investment of trust funds&#13;
administered by the Bank. The Bank shall credit all income from such investment to the&#13;
Trust Fund to be used for the same p arposes as the Contributions.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-8-&#13;
3.    Administr4tive Cost Lecover y&#13;
3.1   In order to assist in the- dc frayment of the costs of administration and other&#13;
expenses incurred by the Bar k t nde - this Agreement, the Bank may deduct and retain for&#13;
its own account an amount equal 1o two percent (2%) of each Contribution from the&#13;
Contributions. In addition, costs for program management and administration up to a&#13;
max1mum of 7% will be char,zec. to I [e Trust Fund on an actual basis. If the contributions&#13;
increase beyond what was or ginally expected at the time of counter-signature of the first&#13;
administration agreement, arid 1he administrative costs increase as a result, the Donors&#13;
acknowledge that an additional ,dministrative fee may be applied to such new&#13;
coniributions.&#13;
4.    Grants to Recipients&#13;
4.1.  The Bank shall, as ad miiistr itor of the Trust Fund on behalf of the Donors, enter&#13;
into grant agreements (the "Grant Agreements") 'with eligible recipients selected in&#13;
accordance with the governa ce ten.is of Annex 1 (the "Recipients") consistent with the&#13;
purposes of this Agieement and on the terms and conditions set forth in the Grant&#13;
Agreements. Grant Agreemcnt,, may be entered into up to the maximum amount of the&#13;
Contributions that all Donois have agreed to make available under the Administration&#13;
Agreements between :he Bark and tie Donors. Upon request by a Donor, the Bank shall&#13;
furnish a copy of the Grant Agreeme 'it to the Donors.&#13;
4.2.  The Bank shall be respo:isib e for the supervision of the activities financed under&#13;
the Grant Agreements. Sub ecl to he consent of the Recipients, representatives of the&#13;
Donors may be invited by thc B ink :o participate in Bank supervision missions related to&#13;
the Trust Fund.&#13;
4.3.  The Bank shall promptly infi irm the Donors of any significant modification to the&#13;
terms of any Grant Agreeme its and of any contractual remedies that are exercised by the&#13;
Bank under any Grant Agrectments. To the extent practicable, the Bank shall afford the&#13;
Donors the opportunity to exciange views before effecting any such modification or&#13;
exercising any such remedy.&#13;
4.4.  The Bank shall include a pr )vision in each Grant Agreement that the Recipient&#13;
will: (i) not use the proceeds of the grant for the purposes of any payment to persons or&#13;
entities, or for the import of goo Is, if such payment or import, to the Recipient's&#13;
knowledge or belief, is prohibiled by decisions of the United Nations Security Council&#13;
take under Chapter V] I of the Cliarte r of the United Nations, and if applicable, (b) include&#13;
a corresponding provision in any sul b-grant agreements that the Recipient enters into with&#13;
entities to which the Recipienit make; the grant funding available.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-9-&#13;
5.    Procurement&#13;
5.1.  For Recipient.-execut,l acti,rities, the Grant Agreements shall provide that the&#13;
Contributions shall be used by the Recipients to finance expenditures for goods and&#13;
services, as the case may be, in accordance with the Bank's Guidelines on "Procurement&#13;
under IBRD Loans and IDA Credit ;" and the Bank's Guidelines on the "Selection and&#13;
Employment of Cons-iltants by Woild Bank Borrowers," as in effect at the date of entry&#13;
into the respective Grnmt Agr,,enent;.&#13;
5.2.  For Bank-executed activities, the employment and supervision of any consultants&#13;
and the procurement of zny goods financed by the Contributions shall be the&#13;
resrionsibility of the Bank ind shall be carried out in accordance with its applicable&#13;
policies and procedures.&#13;
6.    Accounting and Finarcial Reporting&#13;
6.1.  The Bank shall main tain separate records and ledger accounts in respect of the&#13;
Contributions deposited in th - Trust Fund account and disbursements made therefrom.&#13;
6.2.  The Bank shall furn sh to the Donors current financial information relating to&#13;
receipts, disbursements and fUnd ba ance in the holding currency of the Trust Fund with&#13;
respect to the Contributions via th . World Bank's Trust Funds Donor Center secure&#13;
website. Within six (6) moni hs aftei all commitments and liabilities under the Trust Fund&#13;
have been satisfied and the Frust Fund has been closed, the final financial information&#13;
relating to receipts, di sbursei nr ts a id fund balance in the holding currency of the Trust&#13;
Fund with respect to the Cont-ibulions will be made available to the Donors via the&#13;
World Bank's Trust Funds Donor Cnter secure website.&#13;
6.3.  The Bank shall provide 10 th - Donors, within six (6) months following the end of&#13;
each Bank fiscal year, an annual single audit report, comprising (1) a management&#13;
assertion together with an a testatic n from the Bank's external auditors concerning the&#13;
adequacy of internal control ov -r cash-based financial reporting for all cash-based trust&#13;
funds as a whole; and (2) a coinbir ed financial statement for all cash-based trust funds&#13;
together with the f3ank's ext,.rnal at ditor's opinion thereon. The cost of the single audit&#13;
shall be borne by the Bank.&#13;
6.4.  If a Donor wishes to request, on an exceptional basis, a financial statement audit&#13;
by the Bank's external audi:orr of the Trust Fund, the Donor and the Bank shall first&#13;
consult as to whether such an eterr al audit is necessary. The Bank and the Donor shall&#13;
agree on the appropriate score aid trms of reference of such audit. Following agreement&#13;
on the scope and terms of rei2erence the Bank shall arrange for such external audit. The&#13;
costs of any such audit, inclu Jing thc internal costs of the Bank with respect to such audit,&#13;
shall be paid by the requesting lono r.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-10-&#13;
6.5.  The Bank shall provide thd Donors with copies of all financial statements and&#13;
auditors' reports received hy the Bank from the Recipients pursuant to the Grant&#13;
Agreements.&#13;
7.    Progress Reporting&#13;
7.1.  The Bank shall proNide the Donors with an annual report on the progress of&#13;
activities financed by the Co:itributi,)ns. Within six (6) months of the final disbursement&#13;
date specified in paragraph 8. 1, the 3ank shall furnish to the Donors a final report on the&#13;
activities financed by the Trust Fund.&#13;
7.2   Any Donor may revie,w or (valuate activities financed by the Trust Fund. The&#13;
Donor and the Bank shall a&amp;ree on the scope and conduct of such review or evaluation,&#13;
and the Bank shall provide all -elevant information within the limits of its policies and&#13;
procedures. All associated costs shill be borne by the Donor. It is understood that any&#13;
such review or evaluation will rot c )nstitute a financial, compliance or other audit of the&#13;
Trust Fund.&#13;
8.    Disbursement: Cance lat on; Refund&#13;
8.1   It is expected that the Cor tributions will be fully disbursed by the Bank by&#13;
December 31, 2017. The Bank shall only disburse Contributions for the purposes of this&#13;
Agreement after such date with 1 he  iritten approval of the Donors.&#13;
8.2   Any Donor or the Bank ma3, upon three (3) months' prior written notice, cancel&#13;
all or part of the Donor's pr) rata share, of any remaining balance of the Contributions&#13;
that is not committed pursuait to ar y agreements entered into between the Bank and any&#13;
consultants and/or other thi: d -arti .s for the purposes of this Agreement prior to the&#13;
receipt of such notice, includ ng the irant Agreements.&#13;
8.3.  Following the final disburse nent date specified in paragraph 8.1, the Bank shall&#13;
return any remaining balance of the Contributions to the Donors or to the relevant Donor&#13;
Balance Account on a pro lata bas [s based on the Donors' paid Contributions. In the&#13;
event of a cancellation the B ink sha 11 promptly return to the relevant Donor or Donors or&#13;
to the relevant Donor Balance Ac count the Donor's pro rata share of uncommitted&#13;
Contributions in accordance vit 1 pa -agraph 8.2.&#13;
9.    Disclosure&#13;
The Bank will disclo.e t iis ) kgreement and related information on this Trust Fund&#13;
in accordance with the World' B,nk "olicy on Access to Information. By entering into this&#13;
Agreement, Donors consent to disc osure of this Agreement and related information on&#13;
this Trust Fund.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="17398045">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2012/11/17398045/official-documents--administration-agreement-ausaid-contribution-tf071929
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2012/11/17398045/official-documents--administration-agreement-ausaid-contribution-tf071929</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2012/11/17398045/official-documents--administration-agreement-ausaid-contribution-tf071929</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2013-02-28T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2013-02-28T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <docm_id>090224b08196f7d5</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b08196f7d5</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/SAR/2013/02/28/090224b08196f7d5/1_0/Rendered/INDEX/Official0Docum0ribution0to0TF071929.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/SAR/2013/02/28/090224b08196f7d5/1_0/Rendered/PDF/Official0Docum0ribution0to0TF071929.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2012-11-27T14:26:08Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2013-02-28T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docna>
            Official Documents- Administration Agreement
            with AusAID for Contribution to TF071929
        </docna>
        <display_title>Official Documents-
            Administration Agreement with AusAID for Contribution to TF071929</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/2012/11/17398045/official-documents--administration-agreement-ausaid-contribution-tf071929</listing_relative_url>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <docty>Trust Fund Administrative Agreement</docty>
        <count>South Asia</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Kane,Minneh Mary</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>HQBOCS</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <owner>Environment &amp; Water Resources (SASDI)</owner>
        <trustfund>TF071929-South Asia Water Initiative Phase-2</trustfund>
        <lang>English</lang>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Arts and Culture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shared Rivers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Diplomacy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>Freedom of Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>Bank Supervision</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Hydro Power</ml:concept><ml:concept>Hydroelectric Power</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ecosystems and Natural Habitats</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Climate Resilience</ml:concept><ml:concept>Disaster Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Hazard Risk Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>River Basin Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civil Society</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Media</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transboundary Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>Right to Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>External Audit</ml:concept><ml:concept>Bank Regulation and Supervision</ml:concept><ml:concept>Hydropower</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ecosystems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Resilience and Climate Change</ml:concept><ml:concept>Disaster Risk Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Southern Asia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>