<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Case Studya23&#13;
23722&#13;
January 2001&#13;
Water and                                       B&#13;
Sanitation                       The Buenos Aires&#13;
Program&#13;
An international                 concession&#13;
partnership to help&#13;
the poor gain sustained&#13;
access to improved&#13;
water supply and&#13;
sanitation services&#13;
This paper is part of a research           -&#13;
and dissemination initiative&#13;
which the Water and Sanitation          t &#13;
Program-South Asia (WSP-SA) is&#13;
carrying out into private sector&#13;
participation and the poor in the&#13;
urban water sector. Proposals to&#13;
involve the private sector in water&#13;
supply and sanitation sometimes&#13;
raise fears that the poor will be&#13;
priced out through higher tariffs&#13;
and costly connection fees or&#13;
overlooked because they live in&#13;
hard-to-reach locations. The&#13;
reality is that the private sector&#13;
has the capacity and the interest&#13;
to serve the poor, is willing to        jt.-.+z-ofJ5 )&#13;
experiment with low-cost options                # ~n           -&#13;
and different levels of service,          .     -                                                    -&#13;
and with greater efficiency, can         h     I r&#13;
benefit all consumers. There are&#13;
examples of this in other parts of&#13;
the world but not as yet in any of&#13;
the countries of South Asia. This                                                                          , -&#13;
series   will  document     best&#13;
practices and show how service to&#13;
the poor can be addressed by&#13;
the skillful design of private&#13;
sector contracts; by strengthening           Summary&#13;
the regulatory system and&#13;
making sure it protects the                  In May 1993, a 30-year concession cont-act was awarded to a private company to operate the&#13;
interests of the poor; and by               water and sewerage services in Buenos Aires. At the time, tariffs barely covered the costs of the&#13;
creating partnerships between                inefficient utility running the system, and water had been made artificially scarce by poor&#13;
civil society, local authorities and         management, despite an abundant and easily tapped source. The concession attracted three bidders&#13;
private operators.                          who offered lower tariffs and annual investments of US$ 240 million over the first five years;&#13;
The   series also   analyzes              annual investment over the previous decade had been only US$ 10 million.&#13;
lessons learnt and explores how             Those consumers who were already connected to the system initiially benefitted from a significant&#13;
international experiences can                drop in tariffs and an improvement in the quality and reliohility of service. Expansion targets set by&#13;
be adapted to this region.                   geographical area, with poor areas prioritized, has resulted in large numbers of new households&#13;
being connected. However, affordability for the poor has been a serious concern, and it appears&#13;
that the benefits have accrued largely to the middle-class consumers already connected at the time&#13;
of contract award. An unpopular decision to pass the cost of system expansion on to new consumers&#13;
; ..                   '           ."::. . in the form of a hehy infrastructure charge was one of the issues leading to early contract&#13;
renegotiations. Regulation has been weak and ineffective, and this has led to some erosion of&#13;
public confidence in the process. The Buenos Aires concession demonstrates the importance of&#13;
effective regulation in maintaining transparency and public trust, and in an understanding of the&#13;
impact of concession design, pricing policy and regulatory decisions on the poor.&#13;
W A T E R  &amp;   SANITATION&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Historical         and          the Rio de la Plata and has an eas-  The  M ain&#13;
ioy tapped, ample supply of rela-&#13;
Political                       tively clean raw water. Despite this,  Features   of&#13;
Background                      the state-owned water utility, OSN  the  Contract&#13;
(Obras San itarias de la Nacion) was&#13;
providing limited and poor quality&#13;
In 1 989 Argentina was on the  service and, with very low levels of  Preference was given to a conces-&#13;
verge of bankruptcy, with a rapidly  investment, was unable to expand  sion format over a management or&#13;
deteriorating economy and spiraling  connections to the rapidly growing,  lease contract because the govern-&#13;
hyperinflation. The newly elected  poorer, areas of the city. Revenues  ment wanted the private investor to&#13;
government of Carlos Menem was   had shrunk, partly because of a  take responsibility for the mas-&#13;
able to take advantage of a rare  declining tariff in reol terms, and  sive investments needed to expand&#13;
political consensus on the need for  the network had deteriorated due  the system. Selling the assets could&#13;
reform and to introduce wide rang-  to poor maintenance. Water had  have posed legal problems and the&#13;
ing economic measures, including  become artificially scarce due to  concession arrangement has the&#13;
the restructuring and privatization of  mismanagement and poor policy  advantage of keeping ownership of&#13;
inefficient public utilities, of which the  and losses were estimated at 45%  fixed assets in the public domain.&#13;
water industry was one. In Decem-  of the total volume supplied. Only  The number of likely bidders was&#13;
ber 1992 a 30-year concession con-  70% of the population were con-  limited by pre-qualification&#13;
tract for water and sanitation provi-  nected to the water system and 58%  requirements that operators had&#13;
sion in the Buenos Aires metropoli-  to the sewerage system. The short-  experience in operating very large-&#13;
tan area was awarded to a private  fall was concentrated almost exclu-  scale systems. However the bid was&#13;
sector consortium who assumed    sively in the poorer, suburban  competitive, with three consortia&#13;
responsibility for operations in May  areas, where only 55% of the 5.6  passing the technical pre-qualifica-&#13;
1993; it remains the largest con-  million inhabitants had water con-  tion stage. The 30-year concession&#13;
cession in the world given to a  nections and 35% sewerage con-  wasawardedtotheconsortiumthat&#13;
single operator.                 nections. By contrast almost all the  offered the largest tariff reduction.&#13;
Buenos Aires is situated beside  three million people in the city cen-  The winner was Aguas Argentinas,&#13;
ter were connected to the munici-  headed by Lyonnaise des Eaux; they&#13;
pal system. Of the 30% of the    proposed a tariff reduction of&#13;
population without connections,  26.9%, their nearest competitors&#13;
most relied on well water. They suf-  offered a reduction of 26.1% and&#13;
fered higher rates of water-borne  the third bidder 10.1%. The contract&#13;
9  s -   I   disease than the rest of the city  was awarded in December 1992,&#13;
because of contamination of     with a takeover date of May 1993.&#13;
A- +   F^GENTN  groundwater by untreated indus-  An    independent regulatory&#13;
trial waste and raw sewerage seep-  agency ETOSS (Ente Tripartite de&#13;
ing from cesspools of households  Obras de Servicios de Sanea-miento)&#13;
that were not connected to the   was created in May 1993 to enforce&#13;
sewer system. OSN did not cover  compliance with the terms of the con-&#13;
operating costs for three of the five  cession contract, monitor the&#13;
years leading up to privatization  concessionaire'sfive-yearinvestment&#13;
I/ X , /          and the utility was widely regarded  plans, determine tariff provisions and&#13;
as unresponsive to customer com-  investigate customer complaints. The&#13;
plaints with a backlog of breaks  agency was partly financed by a sur-&#13;
awaiting repair.                charge of 2.7% levied on the consum-&#13;
2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Addressing&#13;
Contract obligations specify:                                  the    Needs&#13;
guaranteed standards for water quality, continuity of service, water  of the  Poor&#13;
pressure and flow;&#13;
targets for metering (only 1 % of connections were metered at the start&#13;
of the concession), loss reduction and network rehabilitation;  the concessine eater   thac&#13;
of the 150,000 new water connec-&#13;
development of sewage treatment plants;                      t&#13;
expansion mandates for water supply from 70% coverage at the start,  t6ons tte stem hehoyear,&#13;
expansion                                    ~~~~~~~~~~~~~(60%) are to poor househiolds, and&#13;
to 100% at the end of the concession;                        t&#13;
expansion mandates for the sewerage system from 58% coverage at the  at this sevesion bsorbs&#13;
about 15% of investment but contrib-&#13;
start, to 85% at the end of the concession;&#13;
expansion mandates planned on a five-year basis for each of the four  u y  1%eofyincrease revu&#13;
geographical zones into which the concession is divided (see Table !);  By specifying precise geo-&#13;
five-yearly review of the tariff regime with renegotiation permissible  contract attempted to enforce&#13;
in the event of unforeseen circumstances outside the control of the&#13;
concessionaire;                                              service provision to areas of low&#13;
employee contracts to be negotiated with the unions (the workforce  coverage, which are largely poor&#13;
had been reduced by 1,600 immediately prior to privatization);  neighborhoods. For example, the&#13;
investments of about US$ 4 billion over the life of the contract with  first five-year expansion targets for&#13;
a significant proportion, US$ 1.2 billion, being disbursed in the first&#13;
five years.&#13;
ers' bills. ETOSS was staffed mainly  the network. The new clients,&#13;
by former employees of OSN who  mainly the suburban poor, were ex-   Population of Greater Buenos&#13;
were poorly qualified for the respon-  pected to pay for much of the sec-  peoule&#13;
sibility of tariff setting and had no  ondary expansion network through  people&#13;
experience of regulating a com-  a so-called infrastructure charge;  Poverty line: average monthly&#13;
mercial venture. In addition, the  it was assumed that the poor could  income US$ 500&#13;
contract was drafted in a manner  afford this charge since the con-  Number of poor: 2 million&#13;
that allowed undue intervention by  cession required the concession-  Average monthly income below&#13;
ETOSS in the operational decisions  aire to provide financing assistance  US$ 240: 0.8 million&#13;
of the concessionaire, including  at 12% interest for two years. This  Three types of dwellings for&#13;
small details like maintaining  proved a serious misjudgment and  the poor:&#13;
valves and hydrants.            affordability of access remains a    Group housing societies:&#13;
To raise confidence among     contentious issue.                   1.5 million&#13;
potential bidders for the conces-  Labor opposition to reform was    Poor quality public housing&#13;
sion, tariffs had been increased by  reduced by the promise of shares in  units (relocation colonies):&#13;
25% in February 1991 and a fur-  Aguas Argentina and a volunteer     0.25 million&#13;
ther 29% in April 1991. The sub-  departure scheme. The close involve-&#13;
sequent tariff reduction of 26.9%  ment of union officials in the process  Slums or "Villas miserias°:&#13;
(May 1993) and early improve-   alsohelpedwinagreement(thehead       0.25 million&#13;
ments in service mainly benefitted  of the Union of Argentine Sanitation  Population density in poor areas:&#13;
middle   a n d  u pp e r - i n come  Workers was part of the privatization  10,000 inhabitants per sq km&#13;
households already connected to  committee).&#13;
3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
% of Population Connected to Services&#13;
Year 0            Year 5             Year 15            Year 30&#13;
, Region              Water Sewerage    Water   Sewerage   Water Sewerage     Water   Sewerage&#13;
a .               ~   ~   ~    ~   ~~%  %  %  %        %        %         %        %     i&#13;
I Capital Federal       99       99      100       99       100      100       100      100&#13;
North Zone            69       44       88       65        95       92        I00      100&#13;
West Zone             54       45       76       51        92       69        100      85&#13;
South Zone            49       21       79       40        92       77        100      100&#13;
Total Served as %&#13;
of Total Population   70       58       86       66        95       83        100      85&#13;
... -   .-   ..  . ,  .... s.  .._ 1 - _   - - - - .  ... .  -  - - - .   .......... ......   .... - ---------.... - . . . . . .   -- -- - .   ......   - .- -   ....... ............. ... . ~.. ... .. . .......9...... &#13;
Total Served Population&#13;
(millions)           6,000   4,950     7,700    5,900     9,100   8,000     10,250    9,750&#13;
the poorly served South Zone aimed  priority areas defined by each  low-income areas helped to shape&#13;
to increase the number of house-  municipality. The low-income house-  the Service Expansion Plan.&#13;
holds connected to services from 49%  holds without water and sewerage  In addition to serving the poor&#13;
to 79% for water and from 21% to  connections were scattered through-  through the SEP, the concessionaire&#13;
40% for sewerage (see Table 1 and  out the three suburban zones, but at  has developed a range of innovative&#13;
Figure 1). Although it will still take  the start of the concession socio-eco-  arrangements which are designed to&#13;
15 years for water to reach a full  nomic data was unreliable; to  accelerateserviceprovisiontohouse-&#13;
92% of the population, the targets  address the challenge of hard-to-  holds in areas not included in the first&#13;
underline the attempts being    reach households the concessionaire  five-year plan, and at the same time&#13;
made to prioritize service provision  engaged an NGO, IIED-AL, (Interna-  to bring down connection costs for&#13;
to poor households.              tional Institute for Environment and  low-income households. These are:&#13;
To meet these targets the conces-  Development - Latin America),&#13;
sionaire developed a five-yearly Ser-  whose research into housing char-  a collaboration between the conces-&#13;
vice Expansion Plan (SEP), based on  acteristics and service demand in  sionaire,whodesignsandsupervises&#13;
the works and provides training and&#13;
technical assistance; the municipality,&#13;
which provides construction material&#13;
J§e  *  | -   and facilitates legal requirements;&#13;
and individual communities who&#13;
build and maintain the infrastructure&#13;
-        w      in lieu of connection charges. So far&#13;
around 30,000 inhabitants in 15&#13;
j   neighborhoods, who would other-&#13;
wise not have been able to afford&#13;
_5 -1 connections, have benefitted from&#13;
-.  the scheme.&#13;
-     -   NGO intervention; a collaboration&#13;
-    _     TX between NGOs, the concessionaire&#13;
FIGURE 1: Buenos Aires concesSiotarea showing percentfge        and individual neighborhoods. For&#13;
of population with connections at the start of the concession contract  example, one NGO, Fandation&#13;
4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Riachuelo, was already working on  internal restructuring and training to  Under Argentinian law, consumers&#13;
urban renewal schemes in Lanus, an  facilitate their pro-poor expansion  must connect to a water or sewer net-&#13;
area not included in the first Service  plans. Each zonal office now has a  work, when it is extended to within a&#13;
Expansion Plan. The concessionaire  dedicated employee specifically  certain distance to their premises.&#13;
was approached to explore cost shar-  responsible for coordinating service  This means that the concessionaire&#13;
ing options to expand services ear-  provision to the poor. A specialist in  can, in principle, install networks&#13;
lier than planned and as a result an  water supply for low-income areas in  without consumers' consent, and&#13;
agreement was reached (November  developing countries funded by the  without a need to determine their&#13;
1997) betweentheNGO,themunici-   Inter American Development Bank  willingness to pay for services.&#13;
pality, the concessionaire, the regu-  (IADB), co-ordinates all pro-poor  Under the terms of the original con-&#13;
lator, and the residents with costs split  activities throughout the concession.  tract, expansion of the secondary&#13;
as follows: 54% Fondation Riachuelo,  Four local NGOs, lIED-AL, Fondation  network in Buenos Aires was to be&#13;
35% households and 11% conces-   Riachuelo, Alma and Adeso, have   financed through an "infrastructure&#13;
sionaire. This collaborative approach  been engaged by the concessionaire  charge" on new consumers costing&#13;
has benefitted an additional 5,000  to strengthen their capacity to respond  US$ 415 for water and US$ 606 for&#13;
inhabitants so far.              to the specific needs of the poor.  sewerage. This charge affected&#13;
The Employment Generation        This includes organizing relevant  mainly low-income households liv-&#13;
Unit: a collaboration between the  training programs for employees,  ing in the poor suburban areas and&#13;
province, the concessionaire and  developing a management manual  was a source of resentment. The&#13;
the users which employs local  for services to the poor, and monitor-  monthly repayments of up to US $ 48&#13;
the users which employs local &#13;
ing response to coverage, consump-  represented about 20% of the fam-&#13;
tion, level of satisfaction and security.  ily income of the poorest households,&#13;
very suitable for expanding ser-                                   who in addition had to find the&#13;
vices into areas of h igh unemploy-' &#13;
iesnt. Theaoncessionahir designsuContaet-                          money for internal plumbing fixtures.&#13;
aend. supervisessthenwork aesignd pro-ractDespite low interest loans, extended&#13;
Revisions          and           over a two-year period by the con-&#13;
vides appropriate training but a&#13;
vidscalpporopriater tresponsingbility  Renegotiat          s      cessionaire, the charges were sim-&#13;
local contractor has responsibility  Renegotiations                ply not affordable and an increasing&#13;
for construction. The province&#13;
finances the equipment and mate-    Since the contract became opera-  number of people refused to pay&#13;
rial an laor ontibuionredces  lnc th cotrat bcom  opra- them. By the end of 1996 arrears&#13;
rials and labor contribution reduces  live in May 1993, several major  had reached US$ 30 million, forc-&#13;
the cost of connections. So far, over  changes have been implemented and  ing the concessionaire to suspend&#13;
100r000 thisheoe havebenefitted  some of the terms of the concession  service expansion to poor areas&#13;
from this scheme.                have been renegotiated.           and leading to the renegotiation of&#13;
The Tax Compensation Agreement     The first revision occurred in 1994  the contract.&#13;
is a financial arrangement, whereby  when the concessionaire was    In February 1997 Aguas Argen-&#13;
the municipality waives the excava-  granted a 13.4% tariff increase,  tinas and the regulatory agency,&#13;
tion tax normally payable to dig  about half the original reduction on  ETOSS, began negotiations but the&#13;
trenches and the notional savings are  which the contract was awarded. It  process was quickly bogged down.&#13;
invested by the concessionaire in  had quickly become clear that the  Problems were due in part to politi-&#13;
expanding water connections to   infrastructure was in worse shape  cal pressure brought to bear on&#13;
poor areas not included under the  than estimated; to improve water  members of the ETOSS board, many&#13;
SEP This scheme has so for enabled  quality, investment plans had to be  of whom were political appointees.&#13;
an additional 50,000 people to   speeded up and the resulting cost  The regulator was bypassed and two&#13;
have water access.               increase triggered a contract clause  federal agencies, the Public Works&#13;
The concessionaire has introduced  allowing for tariff adjustment.  Secretariat and the Natural Resources&#13;
5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
April to the end of December&#13;
1998; and (c) canceling the fines&#13;
The existing tariff structure was passed on to the concessionaire. The  imposed by the regulator for failure&#13;
tariff structure is complicated; it is based on the type of consumer,  to reach agreed investment targets.&#13;
(residential, non-residential or real-estate); the service (water  As a result of these changes the&#13;
only or water and sewerage); and the kind of building involved  average bimonthly bill for existing&#13;
(location, age and size of the house, total area and type of prop-  consumers increased by 19% from&#13;
erty). These are then multiplied by a k factor, an adjustable figure  US$ 37 to US$ 45. For new consum-&#13;
fixed by the regulator and linked to an index of the operating costs  ers, the majority of whom were liv-&#13;
of the concessionaire. The concessionaire can change the tariff: by  inginthepoorer reas, average bills&#13;
negotiating an increase in k, by reclassifying consumers to more ex-   Howea  e r it is   to&#13;
pensive non-residential blocks, or by proposing adjustments in build-  US$16. However it is debatable&#13;
ing type, size or criteria for age and location.               weerdeven ahl the         rates&#13;
There are many weaknesses in the tariff system:                are affordable for the poor.&#13;
The tariff is not linked to consumption and there. is no incentive to  me  renesoiationade funda&#13;
curb usage. The majority of domestic connections are unmetered;  mental changes in the nature of the&#13;
metering was made mandatory for non-residential customers but  concession contract. Under the&#13;
optional for residential connections,                               or cnrace firm received&#13;
Given the complexity of the tariff system and the lack of metering it is  payment for service expansion only&#13;
almost impossible for consumers to understand or monitor their bill.  when the work was done; the intro-&#13;
There is no explicit subsidy scheme for poor consumers.       con   of SUMA        be pat in&#13;
The tariff structure has serious, inherent, inequities: for example,  concessionaire would be paid in&#13;
a consumer living in a new house in a new area will pay seven times the  advance. In addition, while the&#13;
rate of someone in a similar sized, but older house, in an older district,  decision not to penalize he efirm for&#13;
regardless of consumption patterns.                            delayed investment may have been&#13;
As tariff is linked to property characteristics and as many poor areas  a recognition that the original tar-&#13;
have no proper titles to their dwellings the concessionaire is often  gets were ambitious, it also estab-&#13;
unable to collect revenues. This creates a considerable disincentive to  lished a precedent that the conces-&#13;
expand services to poor areas.                            sionaire would not be held account-&#13;
expand services to poor areas.&#13;
able for delays. Thus a weak and&#13;
politicized regulator, combined with&#13;
and Human Development Secre-     improvements that were not included  hard-to-achieve contractual targets&#13;
tariat, reached an agreement     in the original contract. This change  for service expansion resulted in a&#13;
directly with the concessionaire.  was unpopular among middle class  regulatory failure; a failure that is&#13;
The renegotiation, agreed in     consumers who saw their bills rise.  likely to disproportionately affect the&#13;
August 1997, introduced the fol-   Reduced connection charges to  poor by slowing down the rate of&#13;
lowing main changes:             US$ 120 for water or sanitation;  coverage and diluting contractual&#13;
Replaced the infrastructure charge  repayable overfive-years in interest-  obligations  which  are  the&#13;
for new users with a bimonthly   free installments averaging US$ 4  concessionaire's strongest incentive&#13;
Universal Service and Environ-   per month.                      for serving the poor.&#13;
mental Improvement fee (SUMA)      ReducedsomeofAguasArgentinas'   In 1 998 the concessionaire&#13;
payable by all consumers, irrespec-  contractual obligations by: (a) cutting  requested a further 11 .7% tariff&#13;
tive of the date of the connection.  expansion targets for the first five-  increase. This caused public opposi-&#13;
Part of the charge was to replace the  year plan by 15% for water and 13%  tion, coming as it did on top of ear-&#13;
revenue loss of the concessionaire  for sewerage; (b) postponing the  lier increases and at a time when&#13;
and part was to fund environmental  completion of the first phase from  economic growth was slowing. In the&#13;
6&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
FIGURE 2: BUENOS AIRES PRICE INCREASES                    concessionaire and the renegotia-&#13;
tion of the contract have stimu-&#13;
lated the emergence of a more&#13;
4.6%       vocal civil society. Municipalities are&#13;
I pre-concession                   19.0%1998 price isf&#13;
1.6I creae;                s. :1             s,     above   being forced to respond to the needs&#13;
c                               1.6 .. eI.zr1 0^ 1 5 - q , I1O ' price  of the urban poor and to address the&#13;
o 14                      e 20 e icomplex issue of property rights. The&#13;
1.2-1                                                       new political administration has&#13;
*°  .0 'ieel;1 -    '                                      decided to encourage wider public&#13;
'r  O   _   _   i_ X            &lt;        L L          participation and for the first time in&#13;
o  0.8-     ill,                                               Argentina a public hearing called by&#13;
0.6 -                                                          the regulator was held in June 2000&#13;
o  04-                            ' _               _          to discuss the concessionaire's new&#13;
r° 0.2 4-                    .     .           ~~~~~~~~~~~~~five-year investment plan. A consul-&#13;
0.2               1                                      tative forum, funded by the regula-&#13;
0                            .9.   -          i .        tor and composed of consumer&#13;
organizations has now been estab-&#13;
endafigureof4.6%wasagreed(see   ing low-income households. This  lished. Though a step in the right&#13;
Figure 2).                      situation is now changing but    direction, some people consider the&#13;
affordability of the connection charge  forum to be lacking in either influ-&#13;
Outcomes                        remains an issue.                ence or bite. One NGO, Interna-&#13;
Increased investment has been  tional Institute for Environment and&#13;
dramatic. Before privatization the  Development, America Latina, has&#13;
Despite institutional weaknesses  . .i. . u                   commented:&#13;
and prblemswith he orginal inefficient utility running the system&#13;
and problems with the original   ha'enivetn'navrg            f   "By having aforum it seems 'civil&#13;
negoiatins, herehavebeen had been Investing an average of&#13;
negotiations, there have been   o    US$ 20  illi         Thi    society' has a seat at the table&#13;
major benefits in service delivery  increased to over US$ 250 million  but what kind of table is it? It is&#13;
water quality since the concession  between     US$ 250 mill     just for appetizers because the big&#13;
was granted. The drop in tariff at the  betmen 193 9   when (less  meal is cooked and eaten with-&#13;
start of the concession has been  investment wasoUS$1.04biliaono (ess  out this incomplete representative&#13;
eroded by subsequent increases,  than The o atagt    ofius       of civil society. And another cru-&#13;
but after five years consumers are  billion). The latest available figures  cial aspect is the capacity of those&#13;
paying only 3.3% more than they  (July 2000) indicate that water ser-  who sit at the table. They are&#13;
were before the private sector  viceshavebeenextendedto1.2mil-  'convidados de piedra' (guests of&#13;
operator took over (66.3% more   lion poor people and sewerage ser-  stone) who do not have the&#13;
than they were in 1990) (see Fig-  vices to 0.3 million poor people.  capacity nor funds to process the&#13;
ure 2). However, the gains dis-  The majority of these connec-   thousands of maps and papers&#13;
proportionately benefit high    tions (around 60%) have been    they are asked to analyze and&#13;
and middle-income users already  funded by the concessionaire's  advise on."&#13;
connected at the time of the     regular expansion program. The    The NGO acknowledges that a&#13;
concession. Infrastructure charges  balance was funded through the  more transparent process is begin-&#13;
were initially unaffordable for the  tax credit agreement and the  ning but stress that fair representa-&#13;
poor and these created problems  innovative institutional arrange-  tion and sensible capacity building&#13;
during the first few years after  ments described above, which mix  are vital for an effective pro-poor&#13;
privatization when the concession-  public and private funds.    consultative forum.&#13;
aire made slow headway in reach-   It is significant that criticism of the  Improved channels of commu-&#13;
7&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
nication have seen the number of  domentally flawed then adjustments  Lessons     for&#13;
registered complaints increase but  in tariff rates, however well inten-&#13;
response time to leakages and    tioned, will also be flawed. If the  South   Asia&#13;
breakdowns has dropped, demon-   tariff and incentive structure is&#13;
strating greater responsiveness  transferred from public to private  The contract was awarded on the&#13;
to consumer demands by the pri-  management without any modi-     basis of the highest tariff reduction,&#13;
vate operator.                   fications it can be difficult to pro-  a process which benefitted already&#13;
The concession contract explicitly  vide services effectively, particu-  connected households in more afflu-&#13;
stated that none of the government  larly to the poor; reform in insti-  ent areas and penalized those with-&#13;
signatories assumed responsibility  tutional arrangements must pre-  out access by introducing costly con-&#13;
for the quality or accuracy of the con-  cede private sector participation.  nection fees. Cost of access was not&#13;
tents and the winning bidder com-  The adjustments and renego-    addressed in the bidding process.&#13;
mented on the serious lack of infor-  tiations also created some pub-  The concession could have been&#13;
mation. This information gap led  lic disillusionment with the con-  awarded based on investment plans&#13;
to problems which have dogged    cession. There have been accusa-  within a specified tariff. As it was, the&#13;
the early years of the concession  tions that the concessionaire acted  tariff reduction was based on unre-&#13;
and led to disagreements about   opportunistically from the start,  alistic assumptions about the willing-&#13;
issues which should have been    accepting unreliable information in  ness and ability of new, poor con-&#13;
very clear from the start. In fact,  the confident expectation that tar-  sumers to pay large connection fees.&#13;
low-quality and unreliable informa-  iffs could be renegotiated later.  Inadditiontotheissueofaffordability&#13;
tion was a defining feature of the  There were clear risks and lack of  there was resentment at a system&#13;
tender process.                  information in the original bid pro-  which seemed unfair and unjustified&#13;
The weakness of the regula-    cess, problems compounded by a   in placing the financial burdens of&#13;
tory structure raises serious con-  weak and inexperienced regulator  expansion of the system on those&#13;
cerns. The six-member board of   subjected to constant political inter-  who could least afford to pay them.&#13;
ETOSS are political appointees and  ference and pressure.         The experience of Buenos Aires sug-&#13;
there have been instances of politi-&#13;
cally motivated decisions being   K&#13;
foisted on the concessionaire. Dur-&#13;
ing the renegotiation of the contract&#13;
the regulatory agency was bypassed&#13;
when the board became deadlocked&#13;
and the central government was&#13;
forced to resolve the issues. This v&#13;
regulatory failure has fed consumer&#13;
doubts that their interests are not  f&#13;
being protected and is likely to have      - -&#13;
disproportionately affected the poor.&#13;
The inherited tariff structure is      _&#13;
inefficient and complicated and         ,      &#13;
makes it difficult for consumers  ,&#13;
to understand how they are charged.&#13;
This underlines the fact that&#13;
privatization without reform can have =&#13;
only limited benefits for poor con-&#13;
sumers. If the tariff structure is fun-&#13;
8&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
gests that for the poor affordability  dissatisfaction with the inefficient  with respect to issues affecting&#13;
of access is for more important than  water industry were catalysts for  the poor.&#13;
reduction in water tariffs. The intro-  change but it was political circum-  The vocal opposition to the per-&#13;
duction of a system favorable to  stances that made the concession  ceived unfairness of the heavy con-&#13;
existing users and skewed against  feasible. The Menem government  nection charges on new consumers&#13;
new connections created difficulties  was able to exploit an unprecedented  and the subsequent process of con-&#13;
in expanding services to the poor and  political consensus; a coalition of  tract renegotiations has stimulated a&#13;
ultimately required a renegotiation  political factions representing  new, and important, role for civil&#13;
of the contract. Insufficient atten-  middle-income voters formed the  society. Wider public participation is&#13;
tion has been given to the cost of  core support base for Menem's  being encouraged and discussion on&#13;
access in South Asia, where heavy  reform program in Congress. They  the second expansion plan has been&#13;
consumption subsidies are com-    approved a water concession that  much more transparent and open to&#13;
mon; but connection costs are     effectively benefitted people who  all stakeholders. The role of civil&#13;
often unaffordable for the poor.  were already connected to the sys-  society has emerged late in&#13;
The experience in Buenos Aires  tem. In South Asia it is clear that  Buenos Aires; but in South Asia,&#13;
underlines the need to start from a  political support needs to be  civil society already enjoys a&#13;
secure information base. Shifting all  carefully built among all stake-  more influential profile, and can&#13;
information risks to the bidder, as  holders, including the poor - and  be involved from the start.&#13;
happened in this case, is not sensible.  this will be helped if consumers  The concessionaire worked closely&#13;
Taking more time to get information  are clearly informed of the inef-  with  union  officials in the&#13;
on the system and rationalizing the  ficiencies and high costs of the  privatization process and organized&#13;
pricing policy can reduce many of  current system. There is already  labor opposition to the reform was&#13;
these problems. However, experi-  one documented example of a      reduced by the pledge of shares in&#13;
ences from other cities indicate that  project failing through loss of  the privatized firm. Working closely&#13;
delays have ended up derailing    political support (see the WSP case  with labor leaders and securing&#13;
planned privafization ventures which  study of the cancellation of the Pune  support for private sector in-&#13;
are dependent on a "political win-  water supply project).         volvement will be crucial for&#13;
dow". Argentina's quick action on the  Transparent, rule-based decision  successful reform. In South Asia&#13;
Buenos Aires concession is in con-  making is important in gaining and  labor issues are even more con-&#13;
trast to two regional neighbors, Chile  maintaining public confidence. This  tentious as utilities are heavily&#13;
and Peru. Both governments delayed  requires a good regulatory frame-  over-staffed (it is estimated that&#13;
planned private sector participation  work, an independent regulator and  India has 10 times more employ-&#13;
for water services and although the  a strong political commitment to  ees for each water connection&#13;
Santiago water company was even-  allow the regulator to function with-  than what is considered current&#13;
tually sold in 1999, Peru ultimately  out political interference. Argentina  best practice in South America).&#13;
failed to privatize. South Asian  didnothavegoodregulationand      Overstaffing and patronage&#13;
governments who may be con-       this is having a negative impact  should not be left to the opera-&#13;
templating private sector part-   on the success of this concession.  tor to resolve alone; they are&#13;
nerships to expand service pro-   South Asia has veryfew examples  policy issues which need to be&#13;
vision to the poor should ensure  of good regulators in any sector,  addressed within the context of&#13;
they have a reliable informa-     and it is imperative to start build-  broader sector reforms.&#13;
tion base which will allow risks  ing an effective regulatory sys-   In Buenos Aires two serious prob-&#13;
and responsibilities, as well as  tem which can draw on the les-   lems with public policy affected the&#13;
grounds for renegotiation, to be  sons emerging from    interna-   concessionaire's operation and acted&#13;
spelled out clearly.              tional experience, and which can  as disincentives to serving the poor.&#13;
An economic crisis and growing  be well informed from the outset  One was a legacy of populist poli-&#13;
9&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
cies advocating the "canilla libre"    For all its faults, the project has&#13;
(free tap) in poor neighborhoods and  provided important lessons for the       Water and Sanitation&#13;
creating a dependency on free       Argentiniangovernmentwhoisseek-            W   at  a    Sanitation&#13;
water and an unwillingness to pay   ing to expand water and sanitation         Program - South Asia&#13;
for services. The second concerned   services in poor areas across the         55 Lodi Estate&#13;
land tenure issues in makeshift      country within private concessions.       New Delhi 110 003&#13;
areas where property rights were not  The experience has been instrumen-       I&#13;
defined and cost recovery was very  tal in clarifying issues and drawing       India&#13;
low. Both these problems are         up policies for future concession con-&#13;
common to many South Asian           tracts. In South Asia, an initial,        Phn: (91-11) 4690&#13;
countries and will need to be        successfully bid and negotiated           Fax: (91-11) 4628250&#13;
addressed if poor communities        concession, would go a long way           Web site: http://wwwwsp.org&#13;
are to benefit from    access to    towards providing a role model&#13;
safe water.                          for the region.&#13;
Other publications in this series:&#13;
Case Studies from El Alto; Manila;&#13;
Jakarta; Durban&#13;
References                                                                       Overview Paper - Private Sector&#13;
Participation in Water and Sanitation:&#13;
Alcazar, Lorena, Abdala, Manuel A.  et latino-americaine. Comment penser       Serving Poor Consumers in&#13;
and Shirley, Marie M., April 2000. The  le probleme?." Presented at research     South Asian Cities&#13;
Buenos Aires Water Concession. Policy  seminar: (( Faire parler les reseaux &gt;&#13;
Research Working Paper No.2311. The  l'eau (Europe - Amerique latine).&#13;
World Bank, Washington D.C.            Lyonnaise des Eaux, 1998. Alterna-&#13;
Campes, Claude, September 1996.   tives Solutions for Low-Income House-&#13;
"Regulating Water Concessions. Les-  holds in Deprived Urban Areas. Suez       Prepored  by Marie-Ha sene Zerdh,&#13;
sons from the Buenos Aires conces-   Lyonnaise des Eaux. Paris.                L   a   ser a de  Eauio  secon  to&#13;
sion." Notes No. 91. Public Policy for  Murawski, Murielle and Hauswald,       Water and Sanitation Program-South&#13;
the Private Sector. The World Bank,  Roland, January 2000. "Le programme       Asia, Kathleen Graham-Harrison,&#13;
Washington D.C.                      Riachuelo : une cooperation franco-       Editorial  Conuant, Wat        and&#13;
Faudry, Daniel, 1995. "La conces-  argentine pour favoriser l'emergence      Clarissa Brocklehurst, WSP-SA.&#13;
sion des services de l'eau potable et  d'un operateur urbain." Presented at&#13;
de I'assainissement de Buenos Aires."  research seminar: (( Faire parler les   Series Coordinator:&#13;
In Gestions Urbaines de I'Eau, edited  reseaux ) : 1'eau (Europe - Amerique    Clarissa Brocklehurst&#13;
byDominiqueLorroin. Economica. Paris.  latine). Paris.&#13;
pp.1 17-133.                           Schneier-Madanes, Graciela, Janu-&#13;
Idelovitch, Emanuel and Ringskog,  ary 2000. "Systemes techniques            January 2001&#13;
Klas, 1997. "Private Sector Participation  urbains: les conflits de l'eau a Buenos  The Water and Sanitation Program is&#13;
in Water Supply and Sanitation in Latin  Aires." CREDAL, STU. Polygraph. Paris.  an international partnership to help the&#13;
America." Directions in Development,   Schusterman , Ricardo, lIED-AL, per-    poor gain sustained access to improved&#13;
The World Bank, Washington D.C.      sonal communication, 2000.                water supply and sanitation services.&#13;
The World'Bank, Washington D.C.  sonal communication, 2000.       The Program's funding partners are the&#13;
Lentini, Emilio, January 2000. "Di-  Van Den Berg, Caroline, 2000.           Governments of Australia, Belgium,&#13;
agnostic et solutions pour la regula-  "Who Wins, Who Loses, and What to       Canada, Denmark, Germany, Italy,&#13;
tion du service d'eau potable du Grand  do about it", Viewpoint Note 217, The  Japan, Luxembourg, the Netherlands,&#13;
Buenos Aires. Perspectives argentines  World Bank, Washington D.C.             Norway, Sweden, Switzerland, and the&#13;
United Kingdom; the United Nations&#13;
Development Programme, and&#13;
The World Bank.&#13;
Created by Write Media&#13;
E-mall: writemedla@vsnl.com&#13;
Printed at PS Press Services Pvt Ltd&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1743977">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2001/01/1743977/buenos-aires-concession-private-sector-serving-poor
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2001/01/1743977/buenos-aires-concession-private-sector-serving-poor</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2001/01/1743977/buenos-aires-concession-private-sector-serving-poor</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2002/04/12/000094946_02040304022171/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2002/04/12/000094946_02040304022171/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2002-04-03T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2001-01-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            The Buenos Aires concession - the private
            sector serving the poor
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            In 1993, a 30-year concession contract
            was awarded to a private company, to operate the water, and
            sewerage services in Buenos Aires, Argentina. At the time,
            tariffs barely covered the costs of the inefficient utility
            running the system, and water had been made artificially
            scarce by poor management, despite an abundant, and easily
            tapped source. The concession attracted three bidders who
            offered lower tariffs, and annual investments of U$S 240
            million over the first five years; annual investment over
            the previous decade had been only U$S 10 million. Those
            consumers who were already connected to the system,
            initially benefited from a significant drop in tariffs, and
            improvements in the quality and reliability of service.
            Expansion targets, set by geographical area, with poor areas
            prioritized, resulted in large numbers of new households
            being connected. However, affordability for the poor has
            been a concern, and seemingly, the benefits have accrued
            largely to the middle-class consumers. An unpopular decision
            to pass the cost of system expansion on to new consumers in
            the form of a hefty infrastructure charge, was one of the
            issues leading to early contract renegotiations. Weak, and
            ineffective regulation led to erosion of public confidence,
            but the Buenos Aires concession demonstrates the importance
            of effective regulation, and of understanding the impact of
            concession design, and pricing policy decisions on the poor.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            The Buenos Aires concession - the private
            sector serving the poor
        </docna>
        <display_title>The Buenos Aires concession - the
            private sector serving the poor</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2001/01/1743977/buenos-aires-concession-private-sector-serving-poor</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>UNDP-Water &amp; Sanitation Program</docty>
        <subtopic>Town Water Supply and Sanitation,Water and Industry,Urban Water Supply and Sanitation,Health Economics &amp; Finance,Water Supply and Sanitation Governance
            and Institutions</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Water Resources</teratopic>
        <count>Argentina</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Zerah, Marie-Helene</author>
            <author>Graham-Harrison, Kathleen [editor]</author>
            <author>Brocklehurst, Clarissa</author>
        </authors>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>South America!$!80469</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>America!$!80450</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000094946_02040304022171</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Urban Water Supply</subsc>
        <admreg>Latin America &amp; Caribbean,Latin America &amp; Caribbean</admreg>
        <colti>Water and Sanitation Program case study</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Water Resources</historic_topic>
        <sectr>Water, sanitation and flood protection</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Concession award; Water supply &amp;
            sanitation; Urban infrastructure; Private sector
            participation; Poverty reduction strategies; Water tariffs;
            Operating costs; Management problems; Tariff reductions;
            Investments; Water delivery; Household consumption; Targeted
            assistance; Affordable access services; Consumer confidence;
            Regulatory framework; Pricing strategy; Poverty incidence
            capacity building,central government,civil
            society,concession contract,connected
            households,connection,connection charge,connection
            charges,connection fees,construction,continuity of
            service,contract award,cost recovery,domestic
            connections,groundwater,households,income,internal
            plumbing,land tenure,land tenure issues,local
            authorities,low-income
            households,metering,Municipalities,Natural
            Resources,Population density,private concessions,private
            operators,private sector,public participation,public
            trust,public utilities,Public Works,raw sewerage,raw
            water,regulatory agency,residential blocks,residential
            connections,residential customers,safe
            water,Sanitation,sanitation Program,sanitation
            services,Sanitation water,service delivery,service
            demand,service provision,sewage treatment,sewer
            system,sewerage,sewerage services,sewerage system,tariff
            adjustment,tariff increase,tariff rates,tariff
            setting,tariff structure,Urban Areas,urban water,urban water
            sector,users,water company,water connection,water
            industry,water quality,water sector,water services,water
            supply,water system,water tariffs,water utility
        </keywd>
        <owner>Anchor: India (SACIA)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>South America</geo_region>
            <geo_region>America</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>23722</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Denationalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deregulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Destatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Divestiture of Ownership</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Infrastructure (Water and Wastewater)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Water and Small Town Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wastewater Collection and Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Basic Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>On-site Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Marketing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Leasing law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Town Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Lines</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civil Society</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Middle-class</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Privatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply</ml:concept><ml:concept>Diseases</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water, Sanitation and Hygiene</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sewerage</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Municipality</ml:concept><ml:concept>Leasing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>State Associations</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Americas</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Argentina</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Caribbean</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>