<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>﻿OFFICIAL&#13;
The World Bank                              1818 H Street N.W.       (202) 477-1234&#13;
INTERNATIONAL BANK FOR RECONSTRUCTION AND DEVELOPMENT  Washington, D.C. 20433  Cable Address: INTBAFRAD&#13;
INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPMENT ASSOCIATION       U.S.A.                   Cable Address: INDEVAS&#13;
March 13, 2013&#13;
Ms. Melanie Robinson&#13;
Head of Office&#13;
DFID Ethiopia&#13;
c/o British Embassy&#13;
Comoros Road&#13;
PO Box 858&#13;
Addis Ababa&#13;
Ethiopia&#13;
Trust Fund Administration Arrangement between the Government of&#13;
the United Kingdom and Northern Ireland, acting through the&#13;
Department for International Development and the International&#13;
Bank for Reconstruction and Development as trustee of BioCarbon&#13;
Fund concerning the BioCF Technical Assistance Trust Fund (TF&#13;
No.052033, ARIES component codes 202957-105 and 202957-106)&#13;
Dear Ms. Robinson,&#13;
I.    We are pleased to acknowledge on behalf of the International Bank for&#13;
Reconstruction and Development ("IBRD" or the "Bank") as trustee of the BioCarbon&#13;
Fund ("BioCF") that the Government of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and&#13;
Northern Ireland, acting through the Department for International Development (DFID)&#13;
(the "Donor") will make available as a grant the sum of three million five hundred&#13;
thousand Pounds Sterling (3,500,000) (the "Contribution") for the BioCF Technical&#13;
Assistance Trust Fund, TF No.052033 (the "Trust Fund") in accordance with the terms of&#13;
this Administration Arrangement (the 'Arrangement'). Other donors are also expected to&#13;
contribute to the Trust Fund on the terms and conditions specified in the Annexes to this&#13;
Arrangement.&#13;
2.    The Contribution will be used to finance the activities and the categories of&#13;
expenditure set forth in the "Description of Activities and Expenditures under the BioCF&#13;
Technical Assistance Trust Fund" attached hereto as Annex 1, and will be administered&#13;
by the Bank on behalf of the Donor in accordance with the terms of this Arrangement&#13;
including the "Standard Provisions Applicable to the BioCF Technical Assistance Trust&#13;
Fund" (the "Standard Provisions") attached hereto as Annex 2.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-3-&#13;
For the Bank:&#13;
Jodlle Chassard&#13;
Manager&#13;
Carbon Finance Unit&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
1818 H Street, NW&#13;
Washington, DC 20433&#13;
U.S.A.&#13;
Tel: (202) 458-1873&#13;
Fax: (202) 522-7432&#13;
E-mail:Jchassard@worldbank.org&#13;
For the Donor:&#13;
Yasmin Abubeker&#13;
Deputy Programme Manager&#13;
Wealth Creation and Climate Change Team&#13;
DFID Ethiopia&#13;
c/o British Embassy&#13;
Comoros Road&#13;
PO Box 858&#13;
Addis Ababa&#13;
Ethiopia&#13;
Telephone: +251 116 180601 Ext. 5572&#13;
Facsimile: +251 116 180635&#13;
E-mail: y-abdulwassie@dfid.gov.uk&#13;
7.    All annexes hereto constitute an integral part of this Arrangement. This&#13;
Arrangement may be amended only in writing between the Bank and the Donor;&#13;
provided, however, that such annexes may be amended only with the agreement of all&#13;
donors contributing to the Trust Fund.&#13;
8.    It is understood that this Administration Arrangement, including any annexes, is&#13;
not an international treaty and is not eligible for registration as a treaty under Article 102&#13;
of the UN Charter. It is an administrative arrangement between the Trustee and the&#13;
Donor.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-5 -&#13;
ANNEX 1&#13;
Descrintion of Activities and Expenditures under the BioCF Technical Assistance&#13;
Trust Fund&#13;
This Annex will be applicable to and form an integral part of all Arrangements entered&#13;
into between the Bank and entities (collectively, the "Donors") that provide contributions&#13;
(the aggregate of all contributions from the Donors, the "Contributions") to be&#13;
administered by the Bank for the Trust Fund.&#13;
A. DESCRIPTION OF ACTIVITIES&#13;
The Trust Fund is established for the purposes of funding capacity building activities&#13;
designed to support the BioCarbon Fund ("BioCF").&#13;
The Fund Manager will consult with the donors on the type of technical assistance&#13;
activities to be undertaken, the countries where these activities could be undertaken, and&#13;
the technology focus. An annual work program will be prepared by the management,&#13;
taking into account the outcome of these consultations, and to be approved by the donors&#13;
meeting to be held at least once a year.&#13;
(i)   Bank-Executed Trust Fund Activities:&#13;
(a) Support of Project Development;&#13;
(b) Capacity Building of Local Intermediaries;&#13;
(c) Development of Monitoring Methodologies;&#13;
(d) Trust Fund Administration; and&#13;
(e) Technical Assistance to the National and Sub-national Structures&#13;
managing climate change funds.&#13;
(ii)  Recipient-Executed Trust Fund Activities&#13;
(a) Conducting readiness activities and capacity building related to carbon&#13;
emission reduction activities in the land use sector;&#13;
(b) Preparation of pilot activities for BioCF projects and programs; and&#13;
(c) Development of monitoring, reporting and verification systems and&#13;
reference emissions level for land use activities.&#13;
B. CATEGORIES OF EXPENDITURE&#13;
(i)   For Bank-Executed activities the Contributions may be used to finance (a)&#13;
Travel Expenses; (b) Staff Costs; (c) Consultant Fees; (d) Associated&#13;
Overheads; (e) Contractual Services; and (f) Media &amp; Workshop Costs.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-7-&#13;
ANNEX 2&#13;
Standard Provisions Applicable to the BloCF Technical Assistance Trust Fund&#13;
This Annex will be applicable to and form an integral part of all Arrangements&#13;
entered into between the Bank and the Donors that provide Contributions to be&#13;
administered by the Bank for the Trust Fund.&#13;
I.    Administration of the Contributions&#13;
1.1.  The Bank will be responsible only for performing those functions specifically set&#13;
forth in this Arrangement and will not be subject to any other duties or responsibilities to&#13;
the Donors, including, without limitation, any duties or obligations that might otherwise&#13;
apply to a fiduciary or trustee under general principles of trust or fiduciary law. Nothing&#13;
in this Arrangement will be considered a waiver of any privileges or immunities of the&#13;
IBRD under its Articles of Agreement or any applicable law, all of which are expressly&#13;
reserved.&#13;
1.2.  The Contribution will be administered in accordance with the Bank's applicable&#13;
policies and procedures, as the same may be amended from time to time, including its&#13;
framework to prevent and combat fraud and corruption and its screening procedures to&#13;
prevent the use of Bank resources to finance terrorist activity, in line with the Bank's&#13;
obligations to give effect to the relevant decisions of the Security Council, taken under&#13;
Chapter VII of the of Charter of the United Nations. The Donor acknowledges that this&#13;
provision does not create any obligations of the Bank under the anti-terrorist financing&#13;
and asset control laws, regulations, rules and executive orders of an individual member&#13;
country that may apply to the Donor, nor will it be deemed a waiver, express or implied,&#13;
of any of the privileges and immunities of the Bank.&#13;
2.    Commingling. Exchane and Investment of the Contributions&#13;
2.1.  The Contributions will be accounted for as a single trust fund and will be kept&#13;
separate and apart from the funds of the Bank. The Contributions may be commingled&#13;
with other trust fund assets maintained by the Bank.&#13;
2.2.  The Contributions may be freely exchanged by the Bank into other currencies as&#13;
may facilitate their disbursement.&#13;
2.3.  The Bank will invest and reinvest the Contributions pending their disbursement in&#13;
accordance with the Bank's policies and procedures for the investment of trust funds&#13;
administered by the Bank. The Bank will credit all income from such investment to the&#13;
Trust Fund to be used for the same purposes as the Contributions.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿date specified in paragraph 6.1, the Bank will furnish to the Donors a final report on the&#13;
activities financed by the Trust Fund.&#13;
5.2   Any Donor may review or evaluate activities financed by the Trust Fund. The&#13;
Donor and the Bank will agree on the scope and conduct of such review or evaluation,&#13;
and the Bank will provide all relevant information within the limits of its policies and&#13;
procedures. All associated costs will be borne by the Donor. It is understood that any&#13;
such review or evaluation will not constitute a financial, compliance or other audit of the&#13;
Trust Fund.&#13;
6.    Disbursement: Cancellation: Refund&#13;
6.1   It is expected that the Contributions will be fully disbursed by the Bank by&#13;
December 31, 2020. The Bank will only disburse Contributions for the purposes of this&#13;
Arrangement after such date with the written approval of the Donors.&#13;
6.2    Any Donor or the Bank may, upon three (3) months' prior written notice, cancel&#13;
all or part of the Donor's pro rata share, of any remaining balance of the Contributions&#13;
that is not committed pursuant to any agreements entered into between the Bank and any&#13;
consultants and/or other third parties for the purposes of this Arrangement prior to the&#13;
receipt of such notice.&#13;
6.3.  Following the final disbursement date specified in paragraph 6.1, the Bank will&#13;
return any remaining balance of the Contributions to the Donors or to the relevant Donor&#13;
Balance Account on a ro rata basis based on the Donors' paid Contributions. In the&#13;
event of a cancellation the Bank will promptly return to the relevant Donor or Donors or&#13;
to the relevant Donor Balance Account the Donor's pro rata share of uncommitted&#13;
Contributions in accordance with paragraph 6.2.&#13;
7.    Disclosure&#13;
The Bank will disclose this Arrangement and related information on this Trust&#13;
Fund in accordance with the World Bank Policy on Access to Information. By entering&#13;
into this Arrangement, Donors consent to disclosure of this Arrangement and related&#13;
information on this Trust Fund.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="17476751">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2013/03/17476751/official-documents--administration-agreement-dfid-tf052033
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2013/03/17476751/official-documents--administration-agreement-dfid-tf052033</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2013/03/17476751/official-documents--administration-agreement-dfid-tf052033</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2013-03-22T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2013-03-22T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <docm_id>090224b081a10d96</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b081a10d96</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/SDN/2013/03/22/090224b081a10d96/1_0/Rendered/INDEX/Official0Docum0th0DFID0for0TF052033.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/SDN/2013/03/22/090224b081a10d96/1_0/Rendered/PDF/Official0Docum0th0DFID0for0TF052033.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2013-03-22T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2013-03-13T16:26:02Z</docdt>
        <docna>
            Official Documents- Administration Agreement
            with DFID for TF052033
        </docna>
        <display_title>Official Documents-
            Administration Agreement with DFID for TF052033</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/2013/03/17476751/official-documents--administration-agreement-dfid-tf052033</listing_relative_url>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <docty>Trust Fund Administrative Agreement</docty>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Rosembuj,Flavia</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>HQBOCS</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <owner>Carbon Finance (CPFCF)</owner>
        <trustfund>TF052033-BIOCARBON TECHNICAL ASSISTANCE
            TRUST FUND</trustfund>
        <lang>English</lang>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sustainable Climate Business</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sustainable Energy Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Arts and Culture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Climate Change</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Biosequestration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Carbon sequestration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>Freedom of Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Media</ml:concept><ml:concept>Treaties</ml:concept><ml:concept>Privileges and Immunities</ml:concept><ml:concept>BioCarbon</ml:concept><ml:concept>Right to Information</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>