<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>﻿DOCUMENTS&#13;
The World Bank                                 1818 H Street N.W.        (202) 477-1234&#13;
INTERNATIONAL BANK FOR RECONSTRUCTION AND DEVELOPMENT  Washington, D.C. 20433  Cable Address: INTBAFRAD&#13;
INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPMENT ASSOCIATION          U.S.A.                    Cable Address: INDEVAS&#13;
Administration Arrangement between the Department for International Development (DFID) and the&#13;
International Bank for Reconstruction and Development and the International Development Association&#13;
concerning the Ghana Living Standards Survey 6 Single Donor Trust Fund (No. TFO72036)&#13;
1.     We are pleased to acknowledge on behalf of the International Development Association (the "Bank")&#13;
the intention of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland, acting through the Department&#13;
for International Development (DFID), (the "Donor", and together with the Bank, the "Parties" and each a&#13;
"Party") to make available as a grant the sum of three million Pound Sterling (3,000,000) (the&#13;
"Contribution") for the Ghana Living Standards Survey 6 Single Donor Trust Fund, No. TF072036&#13;
(the "GLSS6" or "Trust Fund") in accordance with the terms of this Administration Arrangement.&#13;
2.     The Contribution will be used to finance the activities set forth in the "Ghana Living Standards&#13;
Survey 6 Single Donor Trust Fund" attached hereto as Annex 1, and will be administered by the Bank on&#13;
behalf of the Donor in accordance with the terms of this Administration Arrangement, including the&#13;
"Standard Provisions" attached hereto as Annex 2.&#13;
3.     The Donor will deposit the Contribution in accordance with the currency specified in Section I&#13;
above ("Contribution Currency") into such bank account designated by the Bank upon submission of a&#13;
payment request by the Bank: Promptly following countersignature by March 31, 2013, three million&#13;
Pound Sterling (f3,000,000).&#13;
4.     When making any deposit, the Donor will instruct its bank to include in its deposit details&#13;
information (remittance advice) field of its SWIFT deposit message, information indicating: the amount&#13;
deposited, that the deposit is made by the Donor for TF072036 (the Ghana Living Standards Survey 6 Single&#13;
Donor Trust Fund), and the date of the deposit (the "Deposit Instructions"). In addition, the Donor will&#13;
provide a copy of the Deposit Instructions to the Bank's Accounting Trust Funds Division by e-mail sent to&#13;
tfremitadvice@worldbank.org or by fax sent to +1 (202) 614-1315.&#13;
5.     Except with respect to the Deposit Instructions, any notice, request or other communication to be&#13;
given or made under this Administration Arrangement will be in writing and delivered by mail, fax or e-mail&#13;
to the respective Party's address specified below or at such other address as such Party notifies in writing to&#13;
the other Party from time to time:&#13;
For the Bank&#13;
Smile Kwawukume&#13;
Senior Public Sector Specialist&#13;
AFTP3&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
69 Dr. Isert Street, North Ridge, Accra&#13;
Tel: +233-302-214100&#13;
Fax: +233-302-227887&#13;
E-mail: skwawukume@worldbank.org&#13;
1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿For the Donor&#13;
Ms. Sally Taylor&#13;
Country Director for Ghana&#13;
DFID Ghana Country Office&#13;
c/o British High Commission, Osu link. Off Gamel Abdul Nasser Ave.&#13;
Box 296, Accra&#13;
Tel: +233-302-211490&#13;
Fax: +233-302-211491&#13;
E-mail: s-taylor@dfid.gov.uk&#13;
6.    In the event any amounts are to be returned to the Donor under this Administration Arrangement, the&#13;
Bank will transfer such amounts to the Donor's applicable donor balance account with the Bank, unless&#13;
otherwise agreed with the Bank.&#13;
7.     All references made in Annexes and related documents to "Administration Agreement" and "shall"&#13;
will have the same meaning as the terms "Administration Arrangement" and "will" herein.&#13;
8.     All annexes hereto constitute an integral part of this Administration Arrangement, whose terms taken&#13;
together will constitute the entire agreement and understanding between the Donor and the Bank. Unless&#13;
otherwise specified in an annex hereto, this Administration Arrangement may be amended only by written&#13;
amendment between the Bank and the Donor.&#13;
[remainder of page intentionally left blank]&#13;
2&#13;
( Y&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿9.     Each of the undersigned represents, by confirming its acceptance below, that it is authorized to enter&#13;
into this Administration Arrangement and act in accordance with its provisions. The Bank and the Donor are&#13;
each requested to sign and date this Administration Arrangement, and upon possession by the Bank of this&#13;
fully signed Administration Arrangement, this Administration Arrangement will become carried out as of the&#13;
date of the last signature. It is understood that this Arrangement, including any annexes, is not an&#13;
international treaty and is not eligible for registration as a treaty under Article 102 of the UN Charter. It is an&#13;
administrative arrangement between the Trustee and the Donor.&#13;
INTERNATIONAL BANK FOR RECONSTRUCTION AND DEVELOPMENT&#13;
INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPMENT ASSOCIATION&#13;
By:&#13;
Name: Yusupha B. Crookes&#13;
Title: Country Director for Ghana&#13;
Date: /5- &lt;.- -29/g&#13;
THE UNITED KINGDOM OF GREAT BRITAIN AND NORTHERN IRELAND, ACTING&#13;
THROUGH THE DEPARTMENT FOR INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPMENT (DFID)&#13;
By:&#13;
Name: Sally Taylo-&#13;
Title: Country Director for Ghana&#13;
Date:&#13;
3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿ANNEX I&#13;
Ghana Living Standards Survey 6 Single Donor Trust Fund (No.TF072036)&#13;
Trust Fund Description&#13;
This Annex shall be applicable to and form an integral part of the Administration Arrangement for the Trust&#13;
Fund between the Bank and the Donor.&#13;
1. Objectives&#13;
The objective of the GLSS6 Trust Fund is field data collection and data capture, processing, editing and&#13;
tables completed.&#13;
2. Recipient Executed Activities&#13;
The activities (which may be described as "components" of activities) to be financed by the Trust Fund are:&#13;
(a) GLSS6 data collection (including cleaning and validation) and monitoring of field work.&#13;
(b) Production and dissemination of labor force statistics.&#13;
(c) Development of a dissemination strategy and operational support for implementation of GLSS6.&#13;
3. Eligible Expenditures&#13;
The Trust Fund funds may be used to finance Goods, Consultant Services, and Operating Costs.&#13;
4. Taxes&#13;
The foregoing activities and categories of expenditures may include the financing of taxes in accordance with&#13;
the Bank's applicable policies and procedures.&#13;
4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿ANNEX 2&#13;
Standard Provisions&#13;
This Annex shall be applicable to and form an integral part of the Administration Arrangement between the&#13;
Bank and the Donor.&#13;
1.     Administration of the Contributions&#13;
1.1   The Bank shall be responsible only for performing those functions specifically set forth in this&#13;
Administration Arrangement and shall not be subject to any other duties or responsibilities to the Donor,&#13;
including, without limitation, any duties or obligations that might otherwise apply to a fiduciary or trustee&#13;
under general principles of trust or fiduciary law. Nothing in this Administration Arrangement shall be&#13;
considered a waiver of any privileges or immunities of the Bank under its Articles of Agreement or any&#13;
applicable law, all of which are expressly reserved.&#13;
1.2   The Donor's Contribution (collectively, the "Contributions") shall be administered in accordance&#13;
with the Bank's applicable policies and procedures, as the same may be amended from time to time,&#13;
including its procurement, financial management, disbursement and safeguard policies, its framework to&#13;
prevent and combat fraud and corruption and its screening procedures to prevent the use of Bank resources to&#13;
finance terrorist activity, in line with the Bank's obligations to give effect to the relevant decisions of the&#13;
Security Council taken under Chapter VII of the of Charter of the United Nations. The Donor acknowledges&#13;
that this provision does not create any obligations of the Bank under the anti-terrorist financing and asset&#13;
control laws, regulations, rules and executive orders of an individual member country that may apply to a&#13;
Donor.&#13;
2.     Management of the Contributions&#13;
2.1    The funds deposited in the Trust Fund shall be accounted for as a single trust fund and shall be kept&#13;
separate and apart from the funds of the Bank. The funds deposited in the Trust Fund may be commingled&#13;
with other trust fund assets maintained by the Bank. The Bank, in its capacity as trustee, has legal title to the&#13;
funds deposited in the Trust Fund.&#13;
2.2    The currency in which the funds in the Trust Fund shall be held is United States Dollars (the&#13;
"Holding Currency").&#13;
2.3    Donor agrees to deposit its Contributions in the Contribution Currency stated in the Administration&#13;
Arrangement. In the case of deposits received in a Contribution Currency other than the Holding Currency,&#13;
promptly upon the receipt of such amounts and the accompanying Deposit Instructions, the Bank shall&#13;
convert such amounts into the Holding Currency at the exchange rate obtained by the Bank on the date of the&#13;
conversion. Where deposits prove to be insufficient to complete activities as a result of exchange rate&#13;
fluctuations, neither the Bank nor the Donor shall bear any responsibility for providing any additional&#13;
financing.&#13;
2.4    The funds deposited in the Trust Fund may be freely exchanged by the Bank into other currencies as&#13;
may facilitate their disbursement at the exchange rate obtained by the Bank on the date of the conversion.&#13;
2.5    The Bank shall invest and reinvest the funds deposited in the Trust Fund pending their disbursement&#13;
in accordance with the Bank's applicable policies and procedures for the investment of trust funds&#13;
5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿administered by the Bank. The Bank shall credit all income from such investment to the Trust Fund to be&#13;
used for the same purposes as the Contributions.&#13;
3.     Trust Fund Fees and Costs&#13;
3.1    The Bank shall deduct and retain for its own account, as a one-time deduction from the funds in the&#13;
Trust Fund, an amount equal to and not greater than thirty-five thousand United States Dollars (US$35,000)&#13;
as a set-up fee for the Trust Fund upon receipt of funds in the Trust Fund.&#13;
3.2    The Bank shall additionally deduct and retain for its own account, as a deduction from the&#13;
Contribution, an amount equal to five percent (5%) as an administrative fee for the Trust Fund.&#13;
3.3    The Donor acknowledges and agrees that the percentage deductions for fees in this Trust Fund Fees&#13;
and Costs section are estimated on the basis of anticipated Contributions. If actual Contributions significantly&#13;
differ from what was originally anticipated at the time of signature of the first Administration Arrangement,&#13;
or if other circumstances affecting Trust Fund fees or costs change, the Bank reserves the right to request a&#13;
change to the terms of this Trust Fund Fees and Costs section, which would be effectuated by amendments&#13;
made to the Administration Arrangement and which would thereafter be applicable to all new Contributions&#13;
that are provided as amendments to supplement existing Administration Arrangements.&#13;
4.     Accounting and Financial Reporting&#13;
4.1    The Bank shall maintain separate records and ledger accounts in respect of the funds deposited in the&#13;
Trust Fund and disbursements made therefrom.&#13;
4.2    The Bank shall furnish to the Donor current financial information relating to receipts, disbursements&#13;
and fund balance in the Holding Currency with respect to the Contributions via the World Bank's Trust&#13;
Funds Donor Center secure website. Within six (6) months after all commitments and liabilities under the&#13;
Trust Fund have been satisfied and the Trust Fund has been closed, the final financial information relating to&#13;
receipts, disbursements and fund balance in the Holding Currency with respect to the Contributions shall be&#13;
made available to the Donor via the World Bank's Trust Funds Donor Center secure website.&#13;
4.3    The Bank shall provide to the Donor via the World Bank's Trust Fund Donor Center secure website,&#13;
within six (6) months following the end of each Bank fiscal year, an annual single audit report, comprising&#13;
(i) a management assertion together with an attestation from the Bank's external auditors concerning the&#13;
adequacy of internal control over cash-based financial reporting for all cash-based trust funds as a whole; and&#13;
(ii) a combined financial statement for all cash-based trust funds together with the Bank's external auditor's&#13;
opinion thereon. The cost of the single audit shall be borne by the Bank.&#13;
4.4   If the Donor wishes to request, on an exceptional basis, a financial statement audit by the Bank's&#13;
external auditors of the Trust Fund, the Donor and the Bank shall first consult as to whether such an external&#13;
audit is necessary. The Bank and the Donor shall agree on the appropriate scope and terms of reference of&#13;
such audit. Following agreement on the scope and terms of reference, the Bank shall arrange for such&#13;
external audit. The costs of any such audit, including the internal costs of the Bank with respect to such&#13;
audit, shall be borne by the Donor.&#13;
4.5    The Bank shall make available to the Donor copies of all financial statements and auditors' reports&#13;
received by the Bank from Recipients pursuant to any Grant Agreements (as defined below) in accordance&#13;
with the Bank's Access to Information Policy.&#13;
6&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿5.     Progress Reporting&#13;
5.1    The Bank shall provide the Donor with annual reports on the progress of activities financed by the&#13;
Contributions. Within six (6) months of the End Disbursement Date (as defined below), the Bank shall&#13;
furnish to the Donor a final report on the activities financed by the Trust Fund.&#13;
5.2    The Donor may review or evaluate activities financed by the Trust Fund at any time up to six (6)&#13;
months following the End Disbursement Date. The Donor and the Bank shall agree on the scope and conduct&#13;
of such review or evaluation, and the Bank shall provide all relevant information within the limits of the&#13;
Bank's applicable policies and procedures. All associated costs, including any costs incurred by the Bank,&#13;
shall be borne by the Donor. It is understood that any such review or evaluation will not constitute a&#13;
financial, compliance or other audit of the Trust Fund.&#13;
6.     Disbursement; Cancellation; Refund&#13;
6.1   It is expected that the funds deposited in the Trust Fund will be fully disbursed by the Bank by&#13;
August 31, 2014 (the "End Disbursement Date"). The Bank shall only disburse funds deposited in the Trust&#13;
Fund for the purposes of this Administration Arrangement (other than returns to Donor) after such date to the&#13;
extent such date is changed in accordance with amendments made to the Administration Arrangement with&#13;
the Donor. Following the End Disbursement Date, the Bank shall return any remaining balance of the Trust&#13;
Fund to the Donor in the Holding Currency in the manner specified in the Administration Arrangement, all&#13;
calculated as Holding Currency amounts.&#13;
6.2    The Donor may cancel all or part of such Contribution, and the Bank may cancel all or any Donor&#13;
share, upon three (3) months' prior written notice, of any Contributions (paid and not yet paid) that are not&#13;
committed pursuant to any agreements entered into between the Bank and any consultants and/or other third&#13;
parties for the purposes of this Administration Arrangement, including any Grant Agreements, prior to the&#13;
receipt of such notice. In the event of a cancellation, the Bank shall return to the Donor in the Holding&#13;
Currency in the manner specified by the Donor in the Administration Arrangement such uncommitted&#13;
balance of the Trust Fund, in accordance with any additional terms that may be agreed between the Bank and&#13;
the Donor.&#13;
7.     Disclosure; Dispute Resolution&#13;
7.1    The Bank shall disclose the Administration Arrangement and related information on this Trust Fund&#13;
in accordance with the Bank's Policy on Access to Information. By entering into Administration&#13;
Arrangement, the Donor consent to such disclosure of this Administration Arrangement and such related&#13;
information.&#13;
7.2    The Donor and the Bank shall use their best efforts to amicably settle any dispute, controversy, or&#13;
claim arising out of or relating to the Administration Arrangement.&#13;
8.     Grants to Recipients&#13;
8.1    The Bank shall, as administrator of the Trust Fund on behalf of the Donor, enter into one or more&#13;
grant agreements (the "Grant Agreements") with recipients (the "Recipients") consistent with the purposes of&#13;
this Administration Arrangement and on the terms and conditions set forth in the Grant Agreements. Grant&#13;
Agreements may be entered into up to the maximum amount of the Contributions that the Donor have agreed&#13;
to make available under the Administration Arrangement between the Bank and the Donor.&#13;
7&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿8.2    The Bank shall be responsible for the supervision of the activities financed under any Grant&#13;
Agreements. Subject to the consent of any relevant Recipients, representatives of the Donor may be invited&#13;
by the Bank to participate in Bank supervision missions related to the Trust Fund.&#13;
8.3    The Bank shall promptly inform the Donor of any significant modification to the terms of any Grant&#13;
Agreements and of any contractual remedies that are exercised by the Bank under any Grant Agreements.&#13;
To the extent practicable, the Bank shall afford the Donor the opportunity to exchange views before effecting&#13;
any such modification or exercising any such remedy.&#13;
8&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="17489733">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2013/03/17489733/official-documents--administration-agreement-dfid-tf072036
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2013/03/17489733/official-documents--administration-agreement-dfid-tf072036</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2013/03/17489733/official-documents--administration-agreement-dfid-tf072036</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2013-03-26T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2013-03-26T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <docm_id>090224b081a20355</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b081a20355</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/AFR/2013/03/26/090224b081a20355/1_0/Rendered/INDEX/Official0Docum0th0DFID0for0TF072036.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/AFR/2013/03/26/090224b081a20355/1_0/Rendered/PDF/Official0Docum0th0DFID0for0TF072036.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2013-03-26T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2013-03-15T16:47:35Z</docdt>
        <docna>
            Official Documents- Administration Agreement
            with DFID for TF072036
        </docna>
        <display_title>Official Documents-
            Administration Agreement with DFID for TF072036</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/2013/03/17489733/official-documents--administration-agreement-dfid-tf072036</listing_relative_url>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <docty>Trust Fund Administrative Agreement</docty>
        <count>Ghana</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Mwenda,Edith Ruguru</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>HQBOCS</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <owner>AFT: PREM 3 (AFTP3)</owner>
        <trustfund>TF072036-Ghana Living Standards Survey 6</trustfund>
        <lang>English</lang>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutritional supplements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Vitamins</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>Freedom of Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>Bank Supervision</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Remittances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Migration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enforcement of Judgements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Informal Dispute Resolution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Treaties</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supplements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Right to Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>External Audit</ml:concept><ml:concept>Bank Regulation and Supervision</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Movement of Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Dispute Resolution</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Africa</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Ghana</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>