<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>﻿11 PR  13 OFFICIAL        I&#13;
DOCUMENTS,&#13;
IFC TF071837&#13;
IBRD/IDA TF071823&#13;
CIDA PO#: 7059710&#13;
ADMINISTRATION ARRANGEMENT&#13;
AMONG&#13;
THE GOVERNMENT OF CANADA AS REPRESENTED BY&#13;
THE MINISTER FOR INTERNATIONAL COOPERATION ACTING THROUGH&#13;
THE CANADIAN INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPMENT AGENCY&#13;
AND&#13;
INTERNATIONAL FINANCE CORPORATION&#13;
AND&#13;
INTERNATIONAL BANK FOR RECONSTRUCTION AND DEVELOPMENT&#13;
INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPMENT ASSOCIATION&#13;
FOR&#13;
THE FINANCIAL SUPPORT&#13;
RELATING TO&#13;
THE MICRO, SMALL AND MEDIUM ENTERPRISES TECHNICAL ASSISTANCE FACILITY&#13;
FOR THE MIDDLE EAST AND NORTH AFRICA PROJECT&#13;
ARRANGEMENT dated - 3/31/ , 2013 among:&#13;
1. THE GOVERNMENT OF CANADA AS REPRESENTED BY THE MINISTER FOR&#13;
INTERNATIONAL COOPERATION, acting through the CANADIAN INTERNATIONAL&#13;
DEVELOPMENT AGENCY("CIDA") (the "Donor");&#13;
2. INTERNATIONAL FINANCE CORPORATION        ("IFC"), an international organization&#13;
established by Articles of Agreement among its member countries (including Canada) and a&#13;
member of the World Bank Group ("WBG"); and&#13;
3. INTERNATIONAL BANK FOR RECONSTRUCTION AND DEVELOPMENT ("IBRD") and&#13;
INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPMENT ASSOCIATION ("IDA", and together with IBRD, the&#13;
"Bank"), each an international organization established by Articles of Agreement among its&#13;
member countries (including Canada), and each a member of the WBG (The Donor, IFC and the&#13;
Bank collectively, the "Signatories" and, individually, a "Signatory").&#13;
IFC Project Related Doc's\all\trufunOO\agr\00264596.DOC;I 3\l\2012 09:23 PM l llFC Project Related Doc's\all\tutfunOO\agr\00264596.DOC;1 2\27\2012 11:56 AM I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-2-&#13;
WHEREAS:&#13;
(A)    IFC and the Bank have agreed to coordinate their support in Egypt, Jordan, Lebanon, Libya,&#13;
Morocco, Tunisia and West Bank and Gaza (collectively, the "Region") in the area of micro, small, and&#13;
medium enterprises ("MSME"), as a comprehensive package of technical assistance, analytical and&#13;
advisory services and policy support ("TA Facility"), under the umbrella of the MENA MSME Facility&#13;
approved by IBRD in 2011.  The Donor and IFC may later agree to add Syria to the definition of the&#13;
Region, subject to the approval that may be also required from any other donors also contributing to the&#13;
TA Facility through the same trust funds as the Donor. The objectives of the TA Facility are:&#13;
i.    to improve the business environment for MSME finance;&#13;
ii.    to build the capacity of financial institutions for sustainable financing; and&#13;
iii.  to support MSME business development services.&#13;
(B)    The TA Facility is not a separate legal entity, but rather is a coordination mechanism of IFC and&#13;
the Bank currently administered by IFC's Middle East &amp; North Africa Department and by the Bank's&#13;
MENA Finance and Private Sector Development Department. Nothing in this Arrangement is intended to&#13;
create or imply a legal partnership between or among the Donor, IFC and the Bank, and any other donor&#13;
and/or any other person.&#13;
(C)    The Donor has expressed strong support for the TA Facility and wishes to provide funding for the&#13;
activities undertaken by IFC and the Bank under such TA Facility.&#13;
(D)    Each of IFC and the Bank is prepared to utilize funds provided by the Donor for the purpose of&#13;
financing activities undertaken by IFC (the "IFC Activities") and activities undertaken by the Bank (the&#13;
"Bank Activities", and collectively with the IFC Activities, the "Activities") within the framework of the&#13;
TA Facility.&#13;
(E)    For the above purpose, IFC and the Bank will set up on the provisions set forth below two trust&#13;
funds, identified by: (i) the number TFO71837 (the "IFC Donors' Trust Fund") to administer the funds&#13;
allocated for the lFC Activities; and (ii) the number TFO71823 (the "WB Multi-Donor Trust Fund"; and&#13;
collectively with the lFC Donors' Trust Fund, the "Trust Funds") to administer the funds allocated for the&#13;
Bank Activities.&#13;
NOW THEREFORE, the Signatories hereto decide as follows:&#13;
1      The Contributions&#13;
1.1  The initial contribution of the Donor under this Arrangement is ten million Canadian dollars&#13;
(CAD10,000,000) (the "Contribution") of which:&#13;
(a)    five million Canadian dollars (CAD5,000,000) is for the IFC Activities and is to&#13;
be credited to the IFC Donors' Trust Fund TFO71837; and&#13;
(b)    five million Canadian dollars (CAD5,000,000) is for the IBRD Activities and is&#13;
to be credited to the WB Multi-Donor Trust Fund TFO71823.&#13;
EDRMS# 6573047 mh(I IFC Project Related Doc's\all\trufunOO\agr\00264596.DOC;I 3\l\2012 09 23 PM ) IFC Project Related Doc's\all\trmfunOO\agr\00264596.DOC;I 2\27\2012 11:56 AM&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-3-&#13;
1.2  The Contributions will be used to finance the Activities in the Region and the categories of&#13;
expenditure set forth in the "Description of Activities and Expenditures under the IFC Donors&#13;
Trust Fund" attached hereto as Annex A ("IFC Activities"), and in the "Description of Activities&#13;
and Expenditures under the WB Multi-Donor Trust Fund" attached hereto as Annex B ("Bank&#13;
Activities"), respectively. The "Coordination Arrangements" for the Trust Funds are attached&#13;
hereto as Annex C. While the Donor understands that the Contribution may not be earmarked for&#13;
specific Activities or specific allocations, the Donor wishes that the Contribution be applied to&#13;
fund Activities in Jordan, Morocco and Egypt as described in Annex A and B of this&#13;
Arrangement. However, since the Contribution will be commingled with the other donors'&#13;
contributions to fund all the Activities, each of IFC and the Bank will endeavor to apply an&#13;
amount equivalent to five million Canadian dollars (CAD 5,000,000) from each of the IFC's&#13;
Donors' Trust Fund and the WB Multi-Donor Trust Fund to finance the IFC Activities and the&#13;
Bank Activities, respectively, in Jordan, Morocco and Egypt in accordance with such preference&#13;
of the Donor. Neither IFC nor the Bank will be in a position to guarantee that the Contribution&#13;
will be used in accordance with the Donor's preference, and IFC and the Bank will have no&#13;
obligation to the Donor if such preference cannot be achieved&#13;
1.3  The Contribution will be administered by IFC in relation to the IFC Donors Trust Fund and the&#13;
Bank in relation to the WB Multi-Donor Trust Fund for the account of the Donor in accordance&#13;
with the provisions of this Arrangement including the "Standard Provisions Applicable to the&#13;
IFC Donors' Trust Fund (TF071837) and the WB MSME Multi-Donor Trust Fund&#13;
(TF071823)" (the "Standard Provisions") attached hereto as Annex D.&#13;
1.4  The Donor may later decide jointly with IFC and/or the Bank to contribute additional funds to&#13;
support the IFC Activities or the Bank Activities, as the case may be, which will be governed in&#13;
all respects by this Arrangement unless otherwise decided jointly. Notwithstanding the provisions&#13;
of this paragraph, it is understood between the Donor, the IFC and the Bank that any additional&#13;
funding will be subject to an amendment to this Arrangement, written and signed between the&#13;
Donor, the IFC and the Bank.&#13;
1.5  Other donors are also expected to contribute to the Trust Funds on the provisions specified in the&#13;
Annexes to this Arrangement. When other donors contribute funds to the IFC Donors' Trust&#13;
Fund and/or to the WB MSME Regional Multi-Donor Trust Fund, the aggregate of all the&#13;
Donors' contributions to either Trust Fund will be commingled in each Trust Fund and are&#13;
referred to in this Arrangement as the "Contributions".&#13;
2      Deposit of the Contribution&#13;
2.1    The Donor's initial Contribution under this Arrangement will be provided to:&#13;
(a) the IFC Donors' Trust Fund (TF071837) as follows:&#13;
Amounts              Payment to be made to IFC on/or before:&#13;
CADI,875,000           Upon signature, for the Donor's fiscal year 2012/2013&#13;
CADI,375,000           March 3 1st, 2014, for the Donor's fiscal year 2013/2014&#13;
CADI,750,000           March 3 1st, 2015 for the Donor's fiscal year 2014/2015&#13;
TOTAL CAD5,000,000&#13;
EDRMS#: 6573047 mh{IFC Project Related Doc's\all\trufunOO\agr\00264596.DOC;J 3\1\2012 09 23 PM ) (IFC Project Related Doc's\all\trufunO\agr\00264596.DOC,l 2\27\2012 1156 AM&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-4-&#13;
b) the WB Multi-Donor Trust Fund (TF071823) as follows:&#13;
Amounts         Payment to be made to the Bank on/ or before:&#13;
CADI,875,000      Upon signature, for the Donor's fiscal year 2012/2013&#13;
CADI,375,000      March 31st, 2014, for the Donor's fiscal year 2013/2014&#13;
CADI,750,000      March 31st, 2015 for the Donor's fiscal year 2014/2015&#13;
TOTAL CAD5,000,000&#13;
2.2    Either the IFC or the Bank will submit a written payment request before each payment.&#13;
2.3    The amounts will be deposited by the Donor into such account with such bank designated in the&#13;
corresponding payment request submitted by IFC or the Bank.&#13;
2.4    When making each such deposit, the Donor will instruct its bank to include in its payment details&#13;
information (remittance advice) field of their SWIFT payment message, information indicating:&#13;
a. the amount paid;&#13;
b. that the payment is from the Donor and specifying what portion of the amount paid is to&#13;
be allocated to each of(or entirely to either of):&#13;
(i)   the MENA MSME Facility IFC Donors' Trust Fund, TFO71837; and&#13;
(ii)  the MENA MSME Facility WB Multi-Donor Trust Fund, TFO71823; and&#13;
c. the date of the deposit;&#13;
(the "Deposit Instruction")&#13;
In addition, the Donor will provide a copy of its Deposit Instructions to the IBRD's Accounting&#13;
Department,  Trust  Funds   Division  (by  fax  to   +1-202-614-1315   or  by   email to&#13;
tfremitadvice@worldbank.org) and, in case of any deposit to the IFC Donors' Trust Fund, also to the&#13;
General Manager, Advisory Services in MENA (Egypt, Cairo), by fax to +20-2-2461-9130.&#13;
2.5    Promptly upon receipt of the Contribution funds and the Deposit Instructions, if funds are&#13;
received in a currency other than United States dollars, the funds will be converted into United States&#13;
dollars at the exchange rate obtained by the Bank, on the date of the conversion. Where the Contribution&#13;
funds prove to be insufficient to complete the Activities as a result of any exchange rate fluctuation,&#13;
neither IFC, nor the Bank, nor the Donor will bear any responsibility for providing any additional&#13;
financing.&#13;
3      Other Provisions&#13;
3.1    Annexes A, B, C and D to this Arrangement constitute an integral part of this Arrangement and&#13;
the entire understanding between the Signatories.&#13;
EDRMS#: 6573047 mh{IFC Project Related Doc's\all\trufunOO\agr\00264596.DOC;I 3\l\2012 09.23 PM  )IFC Project Related Doc's\all\trufunOO\agr\00264596.DOC;I 2\27\2012 11:56 AM&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-5-&#13;
3.2    This Arrangement may be amended only by written mutual consent between the IFC, the Bank&#13;
and the Donor; provided, however, that the annexes may be amended only with the understanding of all&#13;
donors contributing to the IFC Donors' Trust Fund or WB MSME Multi-Donor Trust Fund.&#13;
3.3    This Arrangement will become effective on the date it is signed by all Signatories.&#13;
3.4    The Donor will not be responsible for the activities of any person employed by IFC or the Bank&#13;
as a result of this Administration Arrangement, nor will the Donor be liable for any costs incurred by IFC&#13;
or the Bank in terminating the engagement of any such person.&#13;
3.5    It is understood that this Arrangement is not an international treaty. It is an administrative&#13;
arrangement among the Donor, IFC and the Bank.&#13;
3.6    All   references  made    in  Annexes    and   related  documents   to   "Administration&#13;
Agreement" will have the same meaning as the term "Administration Arrangement" used herein.&#13;
3.7    No member of the House of Commons of Canada will be admitted to any share or part of this&#13;
Administration Arrangement, or to any benefit arising therefrom.&#13;
3.9    Any subsequent funding, if any made under this Arrangement is subject to there being an&#13;
appropriation by the Parliament of Canada for the fiscal year in which the payment is to be made. If the&#13;
Donor's appropriation is changed by the Parliament of Canada, the Donor may reduce the funding, or&#13;
cancel this Arrangement. If the Donor's appropriation is changed by the Parliament of Canada or if funds&#13;
are not available for any other reason, the Donor will promptly inform IFC and the Bank accordingly in&#13;
writing and the Donor will have no obligation to provide under this Arrangement such portion of the&#13;
funds that are not available.&#13;
3.10   In compliance with IFC's program to combat fraud and corruption which is available at&#13;
http:/www.ifc.org/anticorruption, no offer, gift or payment, consideration or benefit of any kind, which&#13;
constitutes an illegal or corrupt practice, has or will be made to anyone by IFC and/or the Bank, either&#13;
directly or indirectly, as an inducement or reward for the award or execution of this Arrangement. Any&#13;
such practice will be grounds for terminating this Arrangement or taking any other corrective action as&#13;
required.&#13;
4      Communications&#13;
4.1    Any notice, request or other communication required or permitted to be given under this&#13;
Arrangement will be in writing and will be delivered by mail, courier service, email or facsimile to the&#13;
respective party's address specified below or at such other address as such party notifies in writing to the&#13;
other parties from time to time:&#13;
EDRMS#. 6573047 mh(IFC Project Related Doc's\all\trufunOO\agr\00264596.DOC;I 3\l\2012 09.23 PM ) (IFC Project Related Doc's\all\trufunOO\agr\00264596.DOC;1 2\27\2012 11.56 AM&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-6-&#13;
For the Donor:&#13;
Canadian International Development Agency (CIDA)&#13;
200 Promenade du Portage, II 11th Floor&#13;
Gatineau, Quebec&#13;
CANADA K14 064&#13;
Attention: Deputy Director, Middle East &amp; North Africa Division&#13;
Fax:      + (819) 994-7161&#13;
For IFC:Intemational Finance Corporation&#13;
2121 Pennsylvania Ave., N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433&#13;
United States of America&#13;
Attention: Director, Middle East and North Africa Department&#13;
Fax: +1-202-974-4396&#13;
With copy to:&#13;
The Director, Partnerships and Advisory Services Operations Department&#13;
International Finance Corporation&#13;
2121 Pennsylvania Ave., N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433&#13;
United States of America&#13;
Fax: +1-202-974-4344&#13;
For the Bank:&#13;
THE WORLD BANK&#13;
Middle East &amp; North Africa Region&#13;
1191 Corniche el Nil Street, World Trade Center, 15th Floor,&#13;
Cairo, Egypt&#13;
Tel: 202-2574 1188 ext. 215&#13;
Fax: 202-2574 1676&#13;
Attention: Sahar Nasr, Lead Financial Economist&#13;
Email: snasr@worldbank.org&#13;
EDRMS#: 6573047 mh{IFC Project Related Doc's\all\trufunOO\agr\00264596.DOC;1 3\l\2012 09 23 PM  ){IFC Project Related Doc's\all\trufunOO\agr\00264596.DOC;I 2\27\2012 11 56 AM&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-7-&#13;
IN WITNESS WHEREOF, the authorized representatives of the parties hereto have signed this&#13;
Arrangement.&#13;
THE GOVERNMENT OF CANADA&#13;
as represented by&#13;
THE MINISTER FOR INTERNATIONAL&#13;
COOPERATION, acting through the&#13;
CANADIAN INTERNATIONAL&#13;
DEVELOPMENT AGENCY&#13;
By: ____&#13;
Name:     4~/&amp;           ,&#13;
Ti tlIe:          61&amp;        /&#13;
Date:  / /t'/&#13;
INTERNATIONAL FINANCE         INTERNATIONAL BANK FOR&#13;
CORPORATION                   RECONSTRICTION AND DEVELOPEMENT/&#13;
INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPMENT&#13;
ASSOCIATION&#13;
By:   :    _    _     _       By:JAQ            k   j&#13;
Name: M])r SW)U.S\A-          Name:   1tAi oE1\&#13;
Title:          UAAA CEP      Title:              1%M;Nc MWFT"&#13;
Date:                         Date:&#13;
EDRMS#. 6573047 mh(IFC Project Related Doc's\all\trufunOO\agr\00264596.DOC,I 3\l\2012 09:23 PM I (IFC Project Related Doc's\all\trufun00\agr\00264596. DOC,l 2\27\2012 11:56AM&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-8-&#13;
ANNEX A&#13;
DESCRIPTION OF IFC ACTIVITIES AND EXPENDITURES UNDER THE IFC DONORS'&#13;
TRUST FUND (TF071837)&#13;
This Annex will be applicable to, and form an integral part of, all agreements entered into between IFC,&#13;
the Bank and entities that provide contributions (collectively, the "Donors") (the aggregate of all&#13;
contributions from the Donors, the "Contributions") to be administered by IFC for the IFC Donors' Trust&#13;
Fund (TF071837).&#13;
IFC Activities will cover financial infrastructure improvements, advisory services to financial&#13;
institutions and corporate governance and training program for MSMEs&#13;
Financial infrastructure program&#13;
IFC will extend its work on credit bureaus, secured transaction reforms and collateral registries as well as&#13;
mobile payment in the Region with a focus on MSME finance. IFC has a dedicated team of 3 senior&#13;
experts for this program. The objective of program is to increase the private sector's access to credit in&#13;
the Region by strengthening lenders' rights in movable assets, supporting the development of leasing as a&#13;
new financing tool for SMEs, developing effective credit reporting environment and enhancing the&#13;
framework for effective branchless banking solutions. This objective is achieved through legislative&#13;
reform resulting in enactment/amendment of laws, and awareness raising and capacity building activities&#13;
to increase knowledge among stakeholders' (both government and private sector) about the benefits of&#13;
well-functioning financial infrastructure.&#13;
The program is expected to leverage IFC partnership with the Arab Monetary Fund to improve the&#13;
financial infrastructure for lending to MSMEs. IFC currently has a team of four staff fully dedicated to&#13;
this financial infrastructure program.&#13;
Advisory to Financial Institutions&#13;
IFC will lead on advisory services to financial institutions to strengthen their capacity for sustainable and&#13;
innovative MSME banking. Of particular emphasis is building capacity of financial institutions to better&#13;
serve women entrepreneurs and youth. IFC has hired an experienced gender specialist for marketing and&#13;
designing banking products serving women enterprises.&#13;
Over the course of the program, IFC expects to advise 15 to 20 Arab banks on market analysis and&#13;
product development, underwriting policy, risk management and women entrepreneur finance. This&#13;
program is expected to have a significant impact on the volume and quality of banking services to SMEs&#13;
in the Arab world.&#13;
IFC will also provide advisory services to at least 15 microfinance institutions in priority countries. It&#13;
currently has a portfolio of 5 microfinance projects in the region supported by a team of 5 microfinance&#13;
experts with good experience in the region and fluency in Arabic or French. This program is expected to&#13;
have an impact on the sustainability and quality of products offering of MFIs in the Arab world. IFC&#13;
technical support to MFIs will focus on three areas:&#13;
1. Strengthening the institutional capacity of MFIs with a focus on risk management to better cope with&#13;
the ongoing crises.&#13;
2. Diversifying products, most MFIs are still focusing on microcredit, while savings and insurance&#13;
services are very important and require scaling up in the context of MENA.&#13;
EDRMS#: 6573047 mh(IFC Project Related Doc's\all\trufunOO\agr\00264596.DOC;1 3\l\2012 09:23 PM  } llFC Project Related Doc's\all\trfunOO\agr\00264596.DOC;I 2\27\2012 11:56 AM&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-9-&#13;
3. Responsible finance, by facilitating the integration of MFIs in credit bureaus (already ongoing in&#13;
Morocco and Egypt) and providing TA support to MFIs on responsible lending practices and&#13;
financial literacy programs to clients.&#13;
MSME capacity building&#13;
IFC will deploy its flagship management training program for SMEs (Business Edge) as well as its web&#13;
based SME training program in the Region. IFC will ramp up its existing corporate governance program&#13;
with a focus on the Region.&#13;
Monitoring and Evaluation&#13;
IFC has built a strong in house management and evaluation system to monitor project performance and&#13;
evaluate impacts. Each project has clear outputs, outcomes and impact objectives and is supervised&#13;
biannually (June and December) by management and the M&amp;E unit.&#13;
Categories of Expenditures&#13;
Expenditures will include those of WBG's consultants and staff dedicated to the implementation of the&#13;
IFC Activities, equipment, workshops/training, grants, office space and furniture, travel and&#13;
communications, public relations and business development expenses, and any other costs, all to the&#13;
extent incurred for the implementation of the IFC Activities. IFC will utilize the Donors' Funds for the&#13;
payment of salaries and benefits for WBG's staff and consultants only to the extent that their work is&#13;
dedicated to the implementation of the IFC Activities.&#13;
Start of Implementation of the IFC Activities&#13;
Funds from the IFC Donors' Trust Fund may be used by lFC to pay for any expenditure incurred in&#13;
connection with the implementation of the IFC Activities on or after January 1, 2012 until the date&#13;
determined in accordance with paragraph 7.1 of the Standard Provisions (Annex D).&#13;
EDRMS#: 6573047 mhJlFC Project Related Doc's\all\trufunOO\agr\00264596.DOC;I 3\1\2012 09:23 PM  ) {IFC Project Related Doc's\all\trufUnO\agr\00264596 DOC;1 2\27\2012 11:56 AM&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿- 10 -&#13;
ANNEX B&#13;
DESCRIPTION OF ACTIVITIES AND EXPENDITURES UNDER THE WB MSME MULTI-&#13;
DONOR TRUST FUND (TFO71823)&#13;
This Annex will be applicable to, and form an integral part of, all agreements entered into between IFC,&#13;
the Bank and entities that provide contributions (collectively, the "Donors") (the aggregate of all&#13;
contributions from the Donors, the "Contributions") to be administered by the Bank for the WB MSME&#13;
Regional Multi-Donor Trust Fund (TFO71823).&#13;
A. DESCRIPTION OF BANK ACTIVITIES&#13;
A. 1   The Bank Activities will consist of a variety of activities, selected in accordance with the&#13;
selection mechanism set forth in Section B (Selection of Activities) below, with a focus on the following&#13;
three areas:&#13;
1.     Enabling the environment to promote MSME finance&#13;
(a)    Support on policy, legal and regulatory reforms to develop an enabling environment for MSMEs.&#13;
(b)    Capacity building of financial regulators and government agencies supporting MSME&#13;
development.&#13;
(c)    Support on strengthening the institutional financial infrastructure of MSME institutions payments&#13;
systems, innovative technology, transparency and corporate governance.&#13;
(d)    Support on carrying out customized country diagnostics of demand and supply of MSME finance,&#13;
including identifying gaps and constraints.&#13;
2.     Advisory services to Financial Institutions&#13;
(a)    Strengthening the capacity of state-owned banks and microfinance non-governmental&#13;
organizations in order to improve access to finance for MSMEs.&#13;
(b)    In coordination with IFC, provide technical assistance and advisory services to public banks and&#13;
microfinance non-governmental organizations involved in MSME financing, with emphasis on&#13;
strengthening risk management, market analysis, product development, underwriting policies and&#13;
corporate governance.&#13;
(c)    Support the design of innovative financial products for MSMEs, aimed at catering for&#13;
underserved groups.&#13;
3.     Supporting and training to MSMEs&#13;
(a)    Support to selected enterprises through entrepreneur networks, mentoring and business incubator&#13;
services.&#13;
(b)    Capacity building of entrepreneurs in accounting, marketing and business plan development, and&#13;
corporate governance.&#13;
(c)    Strengthening small, medium enterprises (SMEs) in innovation and technological advancement,&#13;
including through support on development of information technology skills, email and internet&#13;
access, website development, and qualifying for international certification.&#13;
A.2    As part of the Bank Activities, the Bank will coordinate among donors and SME agencies, as well&#13;
as project management and monitoring and evaluation of selected activities.&#13;
EDRMS#: 6573047 mh(IFC Project Related Doc's\all\trufunOO\agr\00264596.DOC,l 3\l\2012 09:23 PM } lIFC Project Related Doc's\all\trfunOO\agr\00264596.DOC;I 2\27\2012 11:56 AM&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿- 11 -&#13;
B. CATEGORIES OF EXPENDITURE&#13;
The Contributions may be used to finance (a) associated overheads; (b) consultant fees (individuals and&#13;
firms); (c) contractual services; (d) equipment and office premises lease cost; (d) extended term&#13;
consultants; (e) field assignment benefits; (f) media, workshop, conference and meeting costs; (g) staff&#13;
costs (with and without indirect cost); (h) temporary support staff costs; and (i) travel expenses.&#13;
EDRMS#: 6573047 mh{lFC Project Related Doc's\all\trufUnO0\agr\00264596 DOC;l 3\l\2012 09:23 PM  l {IFC Project Related Doc's\all\trufunOO\agr\00264596.DOC;I 2\27\2012 11:56 AM&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿- 12 -&#13;
ANNEX C&#13;
COORDINATION ARRANGEMENTS&#13;
IFC and the Bank will coordinate as follows under the Trust Funds:&#13;
(a) The Bank and IFC will form a Coordination Committee comprising of the team leader&#13;
responsible for the IFC Donor's Trust Fund and the team leader responsible for the WB&#13;
MSME Multi-Donor Trust Fund and relevant subject matter experts as needed;&#13;
(b) The Coordination Committee will be responsible for the general coordination of the&#13;
implementation of the Activities, including monitoring the progress of such implementation&#13;
and reporting to the donors;&#13;
(c) Unless otherwise notified to the Donor in writing, the Coordination Committee will meet, at&#13;
least once a year, with representatives of the donors contributing to the IFC Donors' Trust&#13;
Fund and the WB Multi-Donor Trust Fund for the purpose of seeking strategic guidance in&#13;
the implementation of the Activities and coordinating donor funding.&#13;
EDRMS#: 6573047 mhJlFC Project Related Doc's\all\trufunO\agr\00264596.DOC;I 3\l\2012 09:23 PM  } J1FC Project Related Doc's\all\tuftnOO\agr\00264596.DOC;I 2\27\2012 11:56 AM&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿- 13 -&#13;
ANNEX D&#13;
STANDARD PROVISIONS APPLICABLE TO THE IFC DONORS' TRUST FUND (TF071837)&#13;
AND THE WB MSME MULTI-DONOR TRUST FUND (TF071823)&#13;
This Annex will be applicable to, and form an integral part of, all agreements entered into between IFC,&#13;
the Bank and entities (collectively, the "Donors") that provide contributions (the aggregate of all&#13;
contributions from the Donors, the "Contributions") to be administered by IFC or the Bank, as applicable,&#13;
for the IFC Donors' Trust Fund and the WB MSME Multi-Donor Trust Fund.&#13;
1.    Administration of the Contributions&#13;
1.1 IFC and the Bank will be responsible only for performing those functions specifically set forth in this&#13;
Agreement for its respective trust fund and will not be subject to any other duties or responsibilities to&#13;
the Donor including, without limitation, any duties or obligations that might otherwise apply to a&#13;
fiduciary or trustee under general principles of trust or fiduciary law. Nothing in this Agreement will&#13;
be considered a waiver of any of the privileges and immunities of IFC, IBRD and IDA under their&#13;
Articles of Agreement or any applicable law, all of which are expressly reserved.&#13;
1.2 The Contributions in each of the IFC Donors' Trust Fund and the WB Multi-Donor Trust Fund will&#13;
be administered in each case in accordance with the applicable policies and procedures of IFC or the&#13;
Bank, as the case may be, as the same may be amended from time to time, including IFC's or the&#13;
Bank's framework to prevent and combat fraud and corruption and their respective screening&#13;
procedures to prevent the use of lFC or Bank resources to finance terrorist activity, in line with IFC's&#13;
and the Bank's obligations to give effect to the relevant decisions of the Security Council, taken under&#13;
Chapter VII of the of Charter of the United Nations. The Donor acknowledges that this provision&#13;
does not create any obligations of IFC and the Bank under the anti-terrorist financing and asset&#13;
control laws, regulations, rules and executive orders of an individual member country that may apply&#13;
to the Donor nor will it be deemed a waiver, express or implied, of any of the privileges and&#13;
immunities of the Bank.&#13;
2.     Commingling, Exchange and Investment of the Contributions&#13;
2.1    The Contributions in either of the IFC Donors' Trust Fund and the WB Multi-Donor Trust Fund&#13;
will be accounted for as a single trust fund in each case. Each of IFC and the Bank will have the right to&#13;
commingle the funds in the trust fund administered by it with other trust funds assets maintained by IFC&#13;
and the Bank, provided however that all such assets will be kept separate and apart from those of IFC and&#13;
the Bank.&#13;
2.2    The Contributions may be freely exchanged into other currencies as may facilitate their&#13;
disbursement by [FC or the Bank.&#13;
2.3   IBRD, acting for the Bank or on behalf of IFC, may invest and reinvest the Contributions in&#13;
either of the Trust Funds pending their disbursement in accordance with its policies and procedures for&#13;
the investment of trust funds administered by IBRD on behalf of IFC or IBRD on behalf of the Bank.&#13;
The income earned by each trust fund from such investment and reinvestment will be credited&#13;
respectively to the IFC Donors' Trust Fund for use for the implementation of the IFC Activities, and to&#13;
the WB Multi-Donor Trust Fund for use for the implementation of the Bank Activities.&#13;
EDRMS#: 6573047 mhJlFC Project Related Doc's\all\trufun00\agr\00264596.DOC;I 3\l\2012 09.23 PM l JIFC Project Related Doc's\all\trufunOO\agr\00264596.DOC;I 2\27\2012 11:56 AM&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿- 14 -&#13;
3.     Administrative Cost Recovery&#13;
3.1   In order to assist in the defrayment of the costs of administration and other expenses incurred by&#13;
IFC and the Bank under this Agreement:&#13;
(a)    IFC may deduct and retain for its own account an amount equal to five percent (5%) of&#13;
each Contribution from a Donor to the IFC Donors' Trust Fund; and&#13;
(b)    the Bank may deduct and retain for its own account an amount equal to five percent (5%)&#13;
of each Contribution from a Donor to the WB Multi-Donor Trust Fund.&#13;
3.2   In addition, in order to assist in the defrayment of the costs associated with the establishment of&#13;
the WB Multi-Donor Trust Fund, the Bank may following deposit of the first Contribution from any&#13;
Donor to the WB MSME Multi-Donor Trust Fund, deduct and retain for its own account an amount equal&#13;
to and not greater than thirty-five thousand United States dollars (US$35,000).&#13;
3.3   If the donor contributions increase beyond what was originally expected at the time of counter-&#13;
signature of this Agreement, and the administrative costs increase as a result, the Donor acknowledges&#13;
that an additional administrative fee may be applied by the Bank to such new contributions.&#13;
4.     Procurement&#13;
The employment and supervision of any consultants and the procurement of any goods financed&#13;
by the Contributions for each respective Trust Fund will be the responsibility of IFC or the Bank, as&#13;
applicable, and will be carried out in accordance with their respective applicable policies and procedures.&#13;
5.     Accounting and Financial Reporting&#13;
5.1   IBRD, acting for the Bank and on behalf of IFC, will maintain separate records and accounts in&#13;
respect of the Contributions in the IFC Donors' Trust Fund and in the WB Multi-Donor Trust Fund, and&#13;
funds disbursed from either of them by IFC or the Bank, respectively.&#13;
5.2   IBRD, acting for the Bank and on behalf of IFC, will make available to the Donor current&#13;
financial information relating to receipts, disbursements and fund balance in United States dollars with&#13;
respect to the Donors' Funds in the IFC Donors' Trust Fund and the WB Multi-Donor Trust Fund&#13;
separately  via  the   World    Bank's   Trust  Funds   Donor    Center   secure  website&#13;
(https://clientconnection.worldbank.org). Within six (6) months after all commitments and liabilities&#13;
under either of the IFC Donors' Trust Fund and the WB Multi-Donor Trust Fund have been satisfied and&#13;
such trust fund has been closed, the final financial information relating to receipts, disbursements and&#13;
fund balance in United States dollars with respect to such trust fund will be made available to the Donor&#13;
via the World Bank's Trust Funds Donor Center secure website.&#13;
5.3   IBRD, acting for the Bank and on behalf IFC, will provide to the Donor, within six (6) months&#13;
following the end of each IFC's and the Bank's fiscal year, an annual single audit report, comprising (1) a&#13;
management assertion together with an attestation from the WBG's external auditors concerning the&#13;
adequacy of internal control over cash-based financial reporting for all cash-based trust funds as a whole;&#13;
and (2) a combined financial statement for all cash-based trust funds together with the WBG's external&#13;
auditor's opinion thereon. The cost of the single audit will be borne by the WBG.&#13;
5.4   In addition, if the Donor wishes to request, on an exceptional basis, a financial statement audit of&#13;
the IFC Donors' Trust Fund or the WB Multi-Donor Trust Fund by WBG's external auditors, the Donor&#13;
EDRMS#: 6573047 mh{IFC Project Related Doc's\all\trufunOO\agr\00264596.DOC,l 3\l\2012 09:23 PM } (1FC Project Related Doc's\all\trufunOO\agr\00264596.DOC,l 2\27\2012 11 56AM&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿- 15 -&#13;
and IFC or the Bank, as the case may be, will first consult as to whether such an external audit is&#13;
necessary with respect to its trust fund. The Donor and IFC or the Bank, as the case may be, will agree on&#13;
the most appropriate scope and terms of reference of such audit. Following agreement on the scope and&#13;
terms of reference, IFC or the Bank, as the case may be, will arrange for such external audit. The cost of&#13;
such an audit, including the internal costs of IFC or the Bank, as the case may be, with respect to such&#13;
audit, will be borne by the Donor.&#13;
6.     Progress Reporting&#13;
6.1    IFC and the Bank will coordinate to provide the Donors with consolidated semi-annual reports&#13;
covering the progress of both the IFC Activities and the Bank Activities financed from the Contributions.&#13;
Within six (6) months of the final disbursement date specified in paragraph 7.1, IFC and the Bank will&#13;
furnish to the Donors a final consolidated report on the activities financed under the IFC Donors' Trust&#13;
Fund or the WB Multi-Donor Trust Fund.&#13;
7.     Disbursement; Cancellation: Refund&#13;
7.1    It is expected that the Contributions will be fully disbursed by IFC and the Bank for their&#13;
respective Trust Funds by June 30, 2017. IFC and/or the Bank will only disburse Contribution funds for&#13;
the purposes of this Agreement after such date with the written approval of the Donors.&#13;
7.2    (a)    Any Donor or the Bank may, upon three (3) months' prior written notice, cancel all or&#13;
part of the Donor's pro rata share of any remaining balance of the Contributions on the WB Multi-Donor&#13;
Trust Fund that is not committed pursuant to any agreements entered into between the Bank and any&#13;
consultants and/or other third parties for the purposes of this Agreement prior to the receipt of such&#13;
notice.&#13;
(b)    Any Donor or IFC may, upon three (3) months' prior written notice, cancel all or part of&#13;
the Donor's pro rata share of any remaining balance of the Contributions on the IFC Donors' Trust Fund&#13;
that is not committed pursuant to any agreements entered into between IFC and any consultants and/or&#13;
other third parties for the purposes of this Agreement prior to the receipt of such notice.&#13;
7.3.   Following the final disbursement date specified in paragraph 7.1 above, each of IFC and the Bank&#13;
shall return any remaining balance of the Contributions on its Trust Fund to the Donors or to the relevant&#13;
Donor Balance Account on a pro rata basis based on the Donors' paid Contributions to that Trust Fund.&#13;
In the event of a cancellation, IFC and/or the Bank, as the case may be, shall promptly return to the&#13;
relevant Donor or Donors or to the relevant Donor Balance Account such Donor's pro rata share of&#13;
uncommitted Contributions in its Trust Fund in accordance with paragraph 7.2.&#13;
8.     Disclosure&#13;
The Bank will disclose this Agreement and related information on the WB Multi-Donor Trust Fund in&#13;
accordance with the World Bank Policy on Access to Information. By entering into this Agreement, the&#13;
Donor consents to disclosure of this Agreement and related information on the WB Multi-Donor Trust&#13;
Fund.&#13;
EDRMS# 6573047 mh(IFC Project Related Doc's\all\trufunOO\agr\00264596.DOC;1 3\1\2012 09 23 PM } {IFC Project Related Doc's\all\trufunOO\agr\00264596.DOC;I 2\27\2012 11:56 AM&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="17632873">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2013/03/17632873/official-documents--administration-arrangement-cida-ifc-tf071837-ibrd-ida-tf071823
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2013/03/17632873/official-documents--administration-arrangement-cida-ifc-tf071837-ibrd-ida-tf071823</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2013/03/17632873/official-documents--administration-arrangement-cida-ifc-tf071837-ibrd-ida-tf071823</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2013-04-25T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2013-04-25T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <docm_id>090224b081b088b6</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b081b088b6</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/MNA/2013/04/25/090224b081b088b6/1_0/Rendered/INDEX/Official0Docum00IBRD000IDA0TF071823.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/MNA/2013/04/25/090224b081b088b6/1_0/Rendered/PDF/Official0Docum00IBRD000IDA0TF071823.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2013-04-25T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2013-03-31T14:45:04Z</docdt>
        <docna>
            Official Documents- Administration
            Arrangement with CIDA for IFC TF071837 and IBRD / IDA TF071823
        </docna>
        <display_title>Official Documents-
            Administration Arrangement with CIDA for IFC TF071837 and
            IBRD / IDA TF071823</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/2013/03/17632873/official-documents--administration-arrangement-cida-ifc-tf071837-ibrd-ida-tf071823</listing_relative_url>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <docty>Trust Fund Administrative Agreement</docty>
        <count>Middle East and North Africa</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Ahmed,Syed</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>HQBOCS</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <owner>Finance &amp; Private Sector Dev. (MNSF1)</owner>
        <trustfund>TF071823-Middle East and North Africa -
            Micro, Small and Medium Enterprises (MSM</trustfund>
        <lang>English</lang>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Business in Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Business Regulation for Enterprise Creation and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legal Regulation and Business Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civic Participation and Corporate Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corporate Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nationalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Enterprise Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>State Owned Enterprise Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>State-Owned Enterprise Restructuring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Remittances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Migration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Mobile Money</ml:concept><ml:concept>Mobile Payments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Checks on Executive Power</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen User Satisfaction Survey</ml:concept><ml:concept>Independent Commissions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ombudsmen</ml:concept><ml:concept>Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Parliament</ml:concept><ml:concept>Procurement Complaints Review Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supreme Audit Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Bankruptcy Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insolvency and creditor/debtor regimes</ml:concept><ml:concept>Secured Transactions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corporate Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enterprise Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enterprise and Commercial Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>SME Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Business Development Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Business Environments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Treaties</ml:concept><ml:concept>Youth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Collateral Registries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Credit Reporting</ml:concept><ml:concept>Microfinance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Branchless Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Business Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>State Owned Enterprises</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Movement of Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Electronic Payments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Accountability Mechanisms</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insolvency and Creditor Rights</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enterprise and Corporate Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>MSME Finance</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>