<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>z                                                               0                                        0&#13;
I-&#13;
Primary Health Services&#13;
CristianVladescuand      Output-Based        Contracting       to   Lift Performance         in  Romania&#13;
Silviut Radulescu&#13;
In  1994 the Romanian government introduced                a pilot scheme of&#13;
Cristian Vladescu is&#13;
exectiae praesident of   output-based     contracts to develop the independent provision                of&#13;
executtive president of the&#13;
Centerfor Health Policy  primary health      services, to   increase the share of health         spending&#13;
and Services in Bucharest&#13;
aod an associate         going to   preventive care, and to improve access to health services,&#13;
3        and an assoaate&#13;
professor at Bucharest   especially in rural areas. To achieve these objectives, the scheme&#13;
University. Silviu       relied  on output-based       financial incentives and competition           between&#13;
Radulescu is a health&#13;
= specialistat the World  doctors for patients. With modifications based on lessons from                  the&#13;
Bank. Both authors were  pilot, the scheme has now         been extended across the entire country.&#13;
involved in the early&#13;
design ofhealth reforms  Under Romania's old health care system pri-      In the early l990s Romania started to reform&#13;
-a      in some of the Romanian&#13;
districts .~ '/"'~v' the new  mary care doctors faced few incentives to pro-  its health sector-to shift the balance from hos-&#13;
ec  districts pd,d,l,,g the new&#13;
cec      approach to primarV     vide  preventive  care  or  ensure   patient   pital services toward primary care, and from cur-&#13;
F   health care. The pilot  satisfaction. Patients were simply assigned to  ative  care toward  preventive; to  address&#13;
was part of a major      practitioners on the basis of their residence or  inequities in access to basic services resulting&#13;
project to restructure   employment. Doctors' incomes (low compared    from inadequate staffing (especially in rural&#13;
=-       health sectorfinanicing  with the average income) were determined by   areas) and funding; and to give patients choice&#13;
and management. Begun    seniority and.length of service, with no link to  over their doctor. As part of the reform a pilot&#13;
in 1991, the project was  quality or volume of care. Public health spend-  scheme introduced output-based contracts for&#13;
O        supported by a US$150    ing was low, averaging around 3 percent of GDP  primary care in 8 of the country's 40 districts,&#13;
million World Bank loan.  in  1990-97. Decisionmaking   power over      covering about 4 million people, between 1994&#13;
resources was centered in hospitals, with the  and 1996. This new contracting system would&#13;
z                                 result that primary care centers were starved of  use competition backed by financial incentives&#13;
drugs and equipment. The end result of this sys-  as a mechanism for shifting resources. The con-&#13;
tem: patients often bypassed primary health   tract design had to strike a balance among spec-&#13;
_J                               services, seeking care directly from specialist  ifying service requirements, allowing flexibility&#13;
O                                 physicians and hospitals. Treatment was free, in  to respond to demand, setting workable per-&#13;
theory, at the point of service for all levels of  formance targets, and protecting the system&#13;
'a                                care-though many paid under the table for      against abuse and budget blowouts. The&#13;
better service, especially for specialist care.  contracts also had to anticipate moves to set up&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
PRIMARY    HEALTH   SERVICES OUTPUT-BASED CONTRACTING TO LIFT PERFORMANCE IN ROMANIA&#13;
an autonomous national health insurance fund  pregnancy and child development monitoring,&#13;
(financed by a 7 percent tax on salaries and a 7  cancer and tuberculosis detection, and public&#13;
percent levy on1 employers) and develop an   health activities. But the fee-for-service require-&#13;
accreditation system for health care providers to  ments were defined only in general terms.&#13;
improve the quality of care.                    To calculate payments to doctors, their out-&#13;
puts were converted into points. To discourage&#13;
Designing the payment system                 doctors from  registering too many patients,&#13;
In the eight pilot districts one-year service con-  points for services were progressively reduced&#13;
tracts were concluded between doctors and dis-  above two thresholds-by 50 percent above&#13;
trict health authorities, ending the doctors'  1,500 registered patients and by 70 percent over&#13;
status as hospital employees. Doctors had to be  2,000. And to take into account the higher&#13;
accredited, but the criteria were very basic. To  demand for services by infants and the elderly,&#13;
hold a contract, a family doctor had to have at  these patients were assigned three to four times&#13;
least 500 registered patients (fewer would sug-  as many points as a young adult. The monetary&#13;
gest poor service and would result in an ineffi-  value of a point was determined quarterly by&#13;
cient allocation of funds to cover the fixed costs  dividing the budget for paying family doctors in&#13;
of running a medical practice). The optimum  the eight districts by the points reported. The&#13;
number of patients was deemed to be 1,500.   contract required doctors to submit monthly&#13;
Patients were allowed to choose their family  reports on changes in their patient list and on&#13;
doctor and to switch after three months.     the number of fee-for-service items provided.&#13;
The contracts covered curative and preven-  District health authorities had the right to audit&#13;
tive primary services for the patients registered  the doctors' records.&#13;
with each doctor. Services continued to be free&#13;
to patients. The payments from  the health   Assessing the results&#13;
authorities to doctors combined a capitation  The small number of indicators collected for&#13;
adjusted for patients' ages (about 60 percent of  routine monitoring has limited analysis of the&#13;
the total) and reimbursement for about 30 fee-  pilot's results. The data that are available show&#13;
for-service items (about 40 percent).        steady growth in the share of the population&#13;
A capitation is a fixed payment for providing  registered wvith family doctors-from  72 per-&#13;
a list of services for a set period to an enrolled  cent in the first quarter to 82 percent after one&#13;
patient. Providers receive the payment whether  year and 86 percent after two years-with regis-&#13;
or not the patient used the services, so in prin-  tration averaging 8 percentage points higher in&#13;
ciple they had an incentive to keep their     urban than in rural areas. Few patients have&#13;
patients healthy. The capitation was also meant  changed doctors, though the number differed&#13;
to give physicians in areas with a surplus of  significantly among districts.&#13;
providers an incentive to move to areas with a  Two years after the pilot started the average&#13;
deficit, where it would be easier to build up  patient lists in urban and rural areas were roughly&#13;
patient lists. The capitation was increased for  the same (about 1,740), although there were&#13;
work in remote areas or difficult conditions (by  more people per physician in rural areas (2,125)&#13;
20-60 percent) and for professional qualifica-  than in urban (1,929).Thesmallestlists (the high-&#13;
tions (5 percent for specialists, 10 percent for  est density of physicians) occurred in the urban&#13;
senior specialists)-and reduced for not pro-  areas of a poorer district (about 1,200) and the&#13;
viding coverage at night (5 percent) or on week-  rural areas of relatively well-off districts (1,300-&#13;
ends (10 percent). (The contract required     1,400)-and the largest lists in the rural areas of&#13;
24-hour availability for emergencies.) The con-  a poorer district (nearly 2,500). This pattern sug-&#13;
tract provided no clear guidelines on what was  gests that in poorer districts family doctors prefer&#13;
expected for the capitation, however.        to practice in urban settings, even though that&#13;
The fee-for-service payments covered pri-  means a lower income, and that better-offdistricts&#13;
mary and secondary clinical preventive care,  attract more doctors, who have to build up rural&#13;
including periodic checkups, immunizations,  practices even if they live in towns.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Family doctors increased their output, pro-  to hospitals, reducing health care costs. Family&#13;
viding 21 percent more consultations and 40  doctors do report fewer referrals, but as noted,&#13;
percent more home visits, and at the end of  there has been no significant change in hospital&#13;
1996, 87 percent were providing emergency    admissions. In urban areas with an adequate sup-&#13;
coverage at night or on weekends. The doctors  ply of doctors, however, competition does seem&#13;
identified higher patient expectations as a  to be producing the desired results. Still, a lack&#13;
major factor in their increased workload.    of influence on the utilization of hospitals and&#13;
Surveys revealed that family doctors had     specialist care would not be surprising, since no&#13;
become more client oriented. And interviews of  disincentives to unnecessary referrals were built&#13;
both doctors and patients provided some evi-  into the payment system. Moreover, most&#13;
dence of a reduction in informal payments    patients still expect to be easily referred to spe-&#13;
(already relatively low at this level of care).  cialists, and therefore would find family doctors&#13;
In the first months there was a tendency   responsive to that expectation more attractive.&#13;
toward "inflation" of fee-for-service items. Pay-  The new delivery and payment arrange-&#13;
ments for these exceeded the 40 percent initially  ments had a positive effect on the quality of ser-&#13;
estimated as a maximum, so payment rules were  vices. But the effect was limited by doctors' lack&#13;
changed and monitoring mechanisms strength-  of control over medical practice resources-&#13;
ened. When fee-for-service points exceeded 65  which prevented them from influencing nurses'&#13;
percent of the capitation points, they were reim-  performance  and  improving  the  physical&#13;
bursed at only 50 percent of their value. Auditing  conditions of practice-and by the lack of&#13;
reports for reimbursement became a major task  incentives and facilities for professional devel-&#13;
for the inspectors hired by district health author-  opment. Although the regulations for the pilot&#13;
ities. Feedback from doctors suggests that the  provided for a practice budget that would have&#13;
audits were uneven and erratic, reducing the  allowed doctors to make their own decisions&#13;
credibility of the payment scheme.           about spending on new equipment or mainte-&#13;
For an average family doctor with a specialist  nance, in reality they had no possibilities for&#13;
qualification, caring for about 1,700 patients,  doing so because of budgetary constraints.&#13;
the capitation accounted for about 65-70 per-  Attendance by family doctors at training courses&#13;
cent of income and fee-for-service for the rest.  was poor, in part because of the lack of financial&#13;
Incomes increased by 15 percent on average (to  resources and a good system for ensuring that a&#13;
about US$180-200 a month), with more than 80  backup doctor would be available.&#13;
percent of participating doctors experiencing   The "optimum" list size of 1,500 patients&#13;
an increase. The range of incomes also       proved too small to improve the distribution of&#13;
increased, with the top 5 percent earning more  family doctors, providing insufficient competi-&#13;
than four times as much as the bottom 5 percent.  tion, and the disincentives over the threshold of&#13;
Technical efficiency has increased in primary  1,500 proved too steep. Further undermining&#13;
care, with output growing more than payments  competition, district health authorities turned&#13;
to service providers. But an effect on the overall  out to be unwilling to make the "hard" decision&#13;
efficiency of health services is difficult to prove.  of denying contracts to family doctors with small&#13;
Although referrals to hospitals and polyclinics  lists. Moreover, no mechanisms were designed&#13;
reportedly declined (by 8 percent in 1996), there  to provide financial support for physicians mov-&#13;
are doubts about the quality of the data. There  ing to underserved areas, and the incentives&#13;
seemed to be no effect on hospital admissions,  from bonuses proved too weak.&#13;
which increased by 3.6 percent in 1996, in line  The underspecification of requirements for&#13;
with the national trend (a 4 percent increase).  the capitation led doctors to see it as an entitle-&#13;
ment. Among fee-for-service items, the techni-&#13;
Weighing the prognosis                       cal quality of some was questionable and&#13;
By introducing competition for patients, the  difficult to monitor (such as cervical screening,&#13;
scheme was expected to encourage doctors to  routine examinations, and detection of breast&#13;
expand their services rather than refer patients  and prostate cancer), and the frequency with&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
PRIMARY    HEALTH    SERVICES OUTPUT-BASED CONTRACTING TO LIFT PERFORMANCE IN ROMANIA&#13;
which they were provided varied widely. This is  * The College of Physicians, established in&#13;
unsurprising, given the lack of clear guidelines    1997, has started to develop practice guide-&#13;
for these services, the inadequate equipment,      lines and requires doctors to participate in&#13;
and the uneven training of physicians.              continuous medical education as a condition&#13;
for periodic recertification.                  viewpoint&#13;
Moving along                                        The new health insurance system led to a 25    Vi_WpOl_t&#13;
After a new health insurance law came into       percent (real) increase in health spending in&#13;
effect in 1998, payment mechanisms similar to    1999  compared    with the   mid-1990s. This&#13;
those piloted in the eight districts were intro-  increase allowed a significant rise in doctors'  encope forum t&#13;
duced for general practitioners throughout       incomes, the main element in primary care        public policy innovations for&#13;
the country for services contracted by newly     costs. But by the end of 2000 pressures from the  private sector-led and&#13;
established district health insurance funds.     increasing costs of drugs and hospital care were  market-based solutions for&#13;
Lessons from the pilot led to some changes,      reversing the initial shift in resources toward  development. The views&#13;
however:                                         primary care.                                    published are those of the&#13;
* To reduce the complexity of the capitation,                                                     authors and should not be&#13;
the number of age groups and rates was        Conclusion                                       attributed to the World&#13;
reduced.                                      By combining per capita payments with limited    Bank or any other affiliated&#13;
* Regulations on the capitation describe more    fee-for-service and other incentives, the output-  organizations. Nor do any of&#13;
clearly the services that need to be provided.  based contract developed in Romania seeks to   the conclusions represent&#13;
* The threshold above which the capitation is    encourage responsiveness to patients and key     official policy of the World&#13;
reduced was set at 2,000 patients (3,000 in   public health outcomes such as immunization      Bank or of its Executive&#13;
localities with insufficient family doctors).  and expanded access to health care-while still  Directors or the countries&#13;
* A 100 percent bonus was added to the capi-     avoiding the problems of unconstrained fee-for-  they represent.&#13;
tation for family doctors practicing in remote  service remuneration seen in some OECD&#13;
or low-income areas.                          countries.                                       To order additional copies&#13;
* For vaccinations, fee-for-service payments        But purchasing authorities operating    in    contact Suzanne Smith,&#13;
were simplified (awarding all vaccinations    Romania's weak regulatory environment, with       managing editor,&#13;
the same number of points), and family doc-   insufficient capacity and experience, have faced  Room 19-017,&#13;
tors can claim  payments for vaccinating      serious difficulties in monitoring both the num-  The World Bank,&#13;
patients not on their lists (such as children  ber and   the quality of services reported.      1818 H Street, NW,&#13;
attending schools in their practice area).    Moreover, the changes have notyet significantly  Washington, DC 20433.&#13;
* Requirements for routine checkups are          reduced the use of hospital services or redis-&#13;
more clearly defined.                         tributed providers to improve access to health   Telephone:&#13;
00 1 202 458 728 1&#13;
* To reward effective intervention    (rather    services in rural areas. The system may need to  Fax:&#13;
than mere reporting of clinical activities of  establish more credibility before it can persuade  001 202 522 3181&#13;
uncertain quality), more points are awarded   patients to change their behavior and doctors to  Email:&#13;
for screening and detection of cancer and     move to underserved areas.                       ssmith7@worldbank.org&#13;
tuberculosis, but only after confirmation by&#13;
a specialist physician.&#13;
* An allowance based on the number of                                                             Printed on recycled paper&#13;
registered patients was introduced to cover   Cristian  Vladescu  (cvladescu@buc.osfro)  and  Silviu&#13;
all practice costs. This allowance is managed  Radulescu (sradulescu@warldbank.org).&#13;
by the doctors, who have gained significant&#13;
discretion  over spending   on   staff and&#13;
maintenance.                                     U&#13;
* Rather than setting a cap on individual doc-&#13;
tors' fee-for-service payments, the new system&#13;
splits the primary care budget into alloca-&#13;
tions for capitation, fee-for-service, and prac-&#13;
tice budgets.&#13;
This Note is available online:&#13;
www.worldbank.org/html/fpd/notes/&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1764496">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2001/09/1764496/primary-health-services-output-based-contracting-lift-performance-romania
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <virt_coll>Knowledge Notes</virt_coll>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2001/09/1764496/primary-health-services-output-based-contracting-lift-performance-romania</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2001/09/1764496/primary-health-services-output-based-contracting-lift-performance-romania</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2002/05/03/000094946_02042504020053/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2002/05/03/000094946_02042504020053/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2002-05-15T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2001-09-30T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Primary health services : output-based
            contracting to lift performance in Romania
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            In 1994 the Romanian government
            introduced a pilot scheme of output-based contracts to
            develop the independent provision of primary health
            services, to increase the share of health spending going to
            preventive care, and to improve access to health services,
            especially in rural areas. To achieve these objectives, the
            scheme relied on output-based financial incentives and
            competition between doctors for patients. With modifications
            based on lessons from the pilot, the scheme has now been
            extended across the entire country.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Primary health services : output-based
            contracting to lift performance in Romania
        </docna>
        <display_title>Primary health services :
            output-based contracting to lift performance in Romania</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2001/09/1764496/primary-health-services-output-based-contracting-lift-performance-romania</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Viewpoint</docty>
        <subtopic>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation,Health Systems Development &amp; Reform,Housing &amp; Human Habitats,Gender and Health,Health Economics &amp; Finance</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Gender,Health, Nutrition and Population,Communities and Human Settlements</teratopic>
        <count>Romania</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Vladescu, Cristian</author>
            <author>Radulescu, Silviu</author>
        </authors>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Eastern Europe!$!107233</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Europe!$!80461</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000094946_02042504020053</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Primary Health, Including Reproductive
            Health, Chi</subsc>
        <admreg>Europe and Central Asia,Europe and Central Asia</admreg>
        <colti>Public policy for the private sector ; Note
            no. 239</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Gender,Health, Nutrition and Population,Communities and Human Settlements</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Health, Nutrition &amp; Population</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Primary health care costs; Primary health
            care evaluation; Primary health care management; Preventive
            health care; Access to health care; Financial incentives;
            Competitiveness; Payments systems; Immunization costs;
            Service quality
            cancer,capitation,child
            development,districts,doctors,employment,fixed costs,general
            practitioners,health care,health care costs,health care
            providers,health insurance,health outcomes,Health
            Policy,health sector,health services,hospital
            admissions,hospital care,hospital
            services,hospitals,immunization,income,infants,intervention,medical
            education,monitoring
            mechanisms,nurses,patients,physicians,pregnancy,primary
            care,private sector,prognosis,prostate cancer,Public
            health,rural areas,schools,screening,specialists,towns,urban areas,vaccinations
        </keywd>
        <owner>Private Sctr Devel &amp; Infrastr VP (PSI)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Eastern Europe</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Europe</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>23941</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT for Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies (ICT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Preventive Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Primary and Secondary Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Hospital Care</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inpatient  and Outpatient Care</ml:concept><ml:concept>Secondary Health Care</ml:concept><ml:concept>Specialized Care</ml:concept><ml:concept>Neoplasms</ml:concept><ml:concept>Vaccines</ml:concept><ml:concept>Payment Instruments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Payment Systems &amp; Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Securities Settlement Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Settlement Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Servers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Switches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance Regulation and Supervision</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Insurance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Preventive Care</ml:concept><ml:concept>Primary Care</ml:concept><ml:concept>Secondary Care</ml:concept><ml:concept>Tuberculosis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Cancer</ml:concept><ml:concept>Immunizations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Examinations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Elderly</ml:concept><ml:concept>Payment Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inflation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Network Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance Law and Regulation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Europe</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Central Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Romania</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>