<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>﻿THE WORLD BANK I BANK DUNIA                                 OFFICIAL       1-r     0    o   4 7&#13;
Sharing Development Solutions                               OCUMENTS&#13;
for an Emerging Indonesia&#13;
April 24, 2013&#13;
Mr. Lukita Dinarsyah Tuwo&#13;
Vice Minister of the National Development Planning as the&#13;
Chairman of the Board of Trustee&#13;
Millennium Challenge Account - Indonesia&#13;
Jalan Subang No. 10&#13;
Jakarta Pusat 10310&#13;
Dear Mr. Tuwo:&#13;
Trust Fund Administration Agreement between the Millennium Challenge Account -&#13;
Indonesia and the International Bank for Reconstruction and Development concerning&#13;
the Support Facility for National Program for Community&#13;
Empowerment (PSF) (TF No. 070967)&#13;
1.    We are pleased to acknowledge on behalf of the International Bank for Reconstruction and&#13;
Development ("IBRD" or the "Bank") that the Millennium Challenge Account - Indonesia ("MCA-I"&#13;
or the "Provider") shall allocate, from the grant provided by the United States of America, acting&#13;
through the Millennium Challenge Corporation, as set out in the Millennium Challenge Compact dated&#13;
November 19th, 2011, the sum of eighty nine million four hundred eighty five thousand United States&#13;
dollars (US$89,485,000) (the "Allocation") for the Support Facility for National Program for&#13;
Community Empowerment ("PSF") Trust Fund (the "Trust Fund") in accordance with the terms of&#13;
this Agreement. Other Providers are also expected to contribute to the Trust Fund on the terms and&#13;
conditions specified in the Annexes to this Agreement.&#13;
2.     The Allocation shall be used to finance the activities and the categories of expenditure set forth&#13;
in the "Description of Activities and Expenditures under the PSF Trust Fund" attached hereto as&#13;
Annex 1, and shall be administered by the Bank on behalf of the Provider in accordance with the terms&#13;
of this Agreement including the "Standard Provisions Applicable to the Trust Fund" (the "Standard&#13;
Provisions") attached hereto as Annex 2.&#13;
3.     The Provider shall, using the disbursement mechanism set forth in Section 2.4(b) of the&#13;
Compact between the United States of America, acting through the Millennium Challenge Corporation,&#13;
and the Republic of Indonesia, dated November 19, 2011, ensure that a deposit of the Allocation, in&#13;
installments, is made directly from the United States Treasury Account into such bank account&#13;
designated by the Bank promptly: (a) following countersignature of this Agreement by the Provider and&#13;
submission by the Bank of a payment request which shall be no greater than the accompanying six&#13;
month expenditure forecast of the categories of expenditures set forth in Annex I.C below; and (b) at&#13;
least every 6 months thereafter following submission by the Bank of the relevant payment request&#13;
which shall be no greater than the accompanying six month expenditure forecast of the categories of&#13;
expenditures set forth in Annex I.C below.&#13;
ISEB Tower 2, 121h Floor, JL Jend. Sudirman Kay. 52-53, Jakarta 12190 8 +6221 5299 3000 0+6221 5299 3111 ( www.worldbank.org/id&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿TF070967                                 2 of 12                      April 24, 2013&#13;
4.     When making each such deposit, the Provider shall instruct its bank to include in its payment&#13;
details information (remittance advice) field of its SWIFT payment message, information indicating:&#13;
the amount paid, that the payment is made by the Provider for TF070967 (the Support Facility for&#13;
National Program for Community Empowerment (PSF) Trust Fund), and the date of the deposit (the&#13;
"Deposit Instruction"). In addition, the Provider shall provide a copy of the Provider Deposit&#13;
Instruction  to  the  Bank's  Accounting   Trust  Funds   Division  by   e-mail  sent  to&#13;
tfremitadvice()worldbank.org or by fax sent to (202) 614-1315.&#13;
5.     The Bank shall convert the Allocation funds into the holding currency of the Trust Fund,&#13;
namely United States Dollars, promptly upon receipt of the Allocation funds and the Deposit&#13;
Instruction containing the information specified in paragraph 4 at the exchange rate obtained by the&#13;
Bank on the date of the conversion. Where the Allocation proves to be insufficient to complete the&#13;
activities as a result of an exchange rate fluctuation, neither the Bank nor the Provider shall bear any&#13;
responsibility for providing any additional financing.&#13;
6.     Except as provided for in paragraph 4 above, any notice, request or other communication to be&#13;
given or made under this Agreement shall be in writing and delivered by mail, facsimile or e-mail to&#13;
the respective party's address specified below or at such other address as such party notifies in writing&#13;
to the other party from time to time:&#13;
For the Bank:&#13;
Mr. Jan Weetjens&#13;
Sector Manager, Social Development - EASID&#13;
The World Bank Office Jakarta&#13;
Indonesia Stock Exchange Building Tower 2, 12 Floor&#13;
Jl. Jendral Sudirman Kay. 52-53&#13;
Jakarta 12190&#13;
Tel: (62) (21) 314-8175&#13;
Fax: (62) (21) 529-93111&#13;
E-mail: jweetiens(aworldbank.org&#13;
For the Provider:&#13;
J.W. Saputro&#13;
Executive Director&#13;
MCA-Indonesia&#13;
Jl. Subang No. 10&#13;
Jakarta Pusat 10310&#13;
Tel: (62) (21) 390-9850&#13;
Fax: (62) (21) 392-6425&#13;
E-mail: saputro@mca-indonesia.go.id&#13;
ISEB Tower 2, 121h Floor, JI. Jend. Sudirman Kay. 52-53, Jakarta 12190  I+6221 5299 3000  0 +6221 5299 3111  0 www.worldbank.org/id&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿TF070967                                 3 of 12                       April 24, 2013&#13;
7.     All annexes hereto constitute an integral part of this Agreement. This Agreement may be&#13;
amended only in writing between the Bank and the Provider; provided, however, that such annexes&#13;
may be amended only with the agreement of all Providers contributing to the Trust Fund.&#13;
8.     Please confirm your agreement with the foregoing, on behalf of the Provider, by signing,&#13;
dating, and returning to us the enclosed copy of this Agreement. Upon receipt by the Bank of the copy&#13;
of this Agreement countersigned by you, this Agreement will become effective as of the date of the&#13;
countersignature.&#13;
Sincerely,&#13;
INTERNATIONAL BANK FOR RECONSTRUCTION AND DEVELOPMENT&#13;
Yogana Prasta&#13;
Acting Country Director, Indonesia&#13;
AGREED:&#13;
MILLENNIUM'P LLENGE ACCOUNT - INDONESIA&#13;
By:&#13;
Name: Lukita Dinarsyah Tuwo&#13;
Title: Vice Minister of National Development Planning as the&#13;
Chairman of the Board of Trustee&#13;
Date: April 24, 2013&#13;
ISEB Tower 2, 12th Floor, JI. Jend. Sudirman Kay. 52-53, Jakarta 12190 X+6221 5299 3000 &amp;+6221 5299 3111 Owww.worldbank.org/id&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿TF070967                                4 of 12                      April 24, 2013&#13;
ANNEX 1&#13;
Description of Activities and Expenditures under the PSF Trust Fund&#13;
This Annex shall be applicable to and form an integral part of all agreements entered into&#13;
between the Bank and entities (collectively, the "Providers") that provide allocations (the aggregate of&#13;
all allocations from the Providers, the "Allocations") to be administered by the Bank for the Trust&#13;
Fund.&#13;
A.     DEFINITIONS&#13;
Unless the context otherwise requires, the several terms defined in the Trust Fund Administration&#13;
Agreement have the respective meanings therein set forth, and the following additional terms and&#13;
expressions have the following meanings:&#13;
(a)    "Advisory Panel" means the Advisory Panel referred to in paragraph 7.4 of this Annex;&#13;
(b)    "Bank-Executed Activities" means activities included in a Project, and to be executed&#13;
by the Bank;&#13;
(c)    "BAPPENAS" means Badan Perencanaan Pembangunan Nasional, the Republic of&#13;
Indonesia's National Development Planning Agency, and any successor thereto;&#13;
(d)    "Allocation" means any allocation to the Trust Fund made by the Provider pursuant to&#13;
an agreement between the Bank acting as trustee of the Trust Fund and the Provider;&#13;
(e)    "Dollar" or "$" means the United States dollar;&#13;
(f)    "Provider" means each Provider making a Allocation to the Trust Fund;&#13;
(g)    "GOI" means Government of Indonesia;&#13;
(h)    "Grant" means a grant made or proposed to be made by the Bank out of the resources&#13;
of the Trust Fund to support a Recipient-Executed Activity;&#13;
(i)    "Grant Agreement" means an agreement entered into, or proposed to be entered into,&#13;
between the Bank and a Grant Recipient governing a Grant;&#13;
(j)    "Grant Recipient" means the Republic of Indonesia or any agency of the Republic of&#13;
Indonesia or any NGO or other entity, for the benefit of which any Grant has been, or is proposed to be,&#13;
made;&#13;
(k)    "Joint Management Committee" and "JMC" means the Joint Management Committee&#13;
referred to in paragraph 7.1 of this Annex.&#13;
(1)    "NGO" means non-governmental organization;&#13;
ISEB Tower 2, 12m Floor, JI. Jend. Sudirman Kay. 52-53, Jakarta 12190 S +6221 5299 3000 0+6221 52993111 O www.worldbank.org/id&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿TF070967                                5 of 12                      April 24, 2013&#13;
(m)    "Operational Manual" means the Operational Manual to be approved and adopted by&#13;
the JMC, giving details of operational guidelines and procedures governing the eligibility of funding&#13;
under the Trust Fund, approval process, terms and conditions of Grants, transfer of funds, monitoring&#13;
and supervision, and reporting obligations, as such Operational Manual may be amended from time to&#13;
time with the agreement of the JMC;&#13;
(n)    "PNPM" and "PNPM Mandiri" means Program Nasional Pemberdayaan Masyarakat&#13;
Mandiri, the GOI's National Program for Community Empowerment;&#13;
(0)    "Project" means one or more PSF Trust Fund activities grouped in the form of a&#13;
project which is the subject matter of a Proposal, and which has been, or is expected to be, endorsed by&#13;
the Joint Management Committee, either specifically as a Project or as part of the funding for a group&#13;
of Projects or "windows" for financing under the Trust Fund;&#13;
(p)    "Proposal" means a proposal for Project, meeting the requirements set out in the&#13;
Operations Manual;&#13;
(q)    "PSF" means the PSF facility consisting of this Trust Fund and any other trust funds&#13;
administered by the Bank and agreed by the Providers to be subject to the governance arrangements set&#13;
out in the Operations Manual;&#13;
(r)    "PSF Trust Fund Activity" means each activity for which an allocation is made out of&#13;
the Trust Fund either specifically as a Project or as part of the funding for a group of Projects or&#13;
"windows", and may be Bank-Executed or Recipient-Executed;&#13;
(s)    "Recipient-Executed Activities" means activities included in a Project, and to be&#13;
executed by an entity other than the Bank;&#13;
(t)    "Technical Committee" means the Technical Committee referred to in paragraph 7.2 of&#13;
this Annex;&#13;
(u)    "Technical Secretariat" means the Technical Secretariat referred to in paragraph 7.3 of&#13;
this Annex; and&#13;
(v)    "Trustee" means the Bank acting as Trustee of the Trust Fund.&#13;
B.     DESCRIPTION OF ACTIVITIES&#13;
1.    The purpose of the Trust Fund is to establish a common platform to mobilize Provider&#13;
resources and channel financial assistance in support of the Republic of Indonesia's efforts to reduce&#13;
poverty through PNPM, through: (a) provision of strategic oversight of PNPM and related poverty&#13;
reduction programs, and (b) coordination of Provider-provided grant funds.&#13;
ISEB Tower 2, 12th Floor, JI. Jend. Sudirman Kay. 52-53, Jakarta 12190 a +6221 5299 3000 &amp; +6221 5299 3111 O www.worldbank.org/id&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿TF070967                                  6 of 12                       April 24, 2013&#13;
2.     The activities ("Activities") for which the Allocation is provided are as follows:&#13;
(a)    Provision of support for small infrastructure investment works, social services projects&#13;
and other community-led poverty reduction activities, through co-financing of Bank and International&#13;
Development Association operations, and other investments, including provision of block grants for the&#13;
benefit of communities.&#13;
(b)    Provision of grants to intermediary NGOs and other civil society groups which engage&#13;
in poverty reduction activities at grassroots level to be on-granted to groups which provide special&#13;
services to poor communities, or to develop the capacity of such intermediary NGOs or groups to&#13;
engage in such on-granting activities.&#13;
(c)    Provision of technical advisory services and other material assistance to agencies of the&#13;
Republic of Indonesia to support their long-term capacity to engage in the long-term management of&#13;
the PNPM.&#13;
(d)    Provision of technical advisory services to support PNPM-related special studies and&#13;
programs, including establishment and operation of a partnership office for harmonization and&#13;
coordination of PNPM-related programs and technical advisory services, monitoring and evaluation&#13;
activities, special activities, workshops and facilitated comparative studies, as well as activities in&#13;
support of national and local government poverty reduction programs or to develop the capacities of&#13;
universities, think-tanks and other organizations likely to contribute to achievement of the purposes of&#13;
the PNPM.&#13;
C.     CATEGORIES OF EXPENDITURE&#13;
1.     The Allocation will be used exclusively for the financing of the following categories:&#13;
(a)    For Recipient-Executed Activities: consultants' services, other services, goods, works,&#13;
block grants (sub-grants), non-government organization/entity staff costs (excludes civil servant&#13;
salaries), non-government organization/entity management fees (not to exceed 10% of the total amount&#13;
of the grant to the recipient), training and workshop costs and operating costs; and&#13;
(b)    For Bank-Executed Activities: communications and translation; consultants' fees&#13;
(individuals and firms); contractual services; equipment purchase; leased office premises and&#13;
equipment; extended term consultants; field benefits; media, workshops/conferences and meetings;&#13;
staff costs (salary + benefits + indirect costs); staff costs (salary + benefits); temporary staff costs; and&#13;
travel expenses.&#13;
2.     The foregoing categories of expenditures may include the financing of taxes.&#13;
ISEB Tower 2,12th Floor, JI. Jend. Sudirman Kay. 52-53, Jakarta 12190  g+6221 5299 3000  0+6221 5299 3111  O www.worldbank.org/id&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿TF070967                                 7 of 12                      April 24, 2013&#13;
D.     Management of Trust Fund Operations&#13;
1.    Joint Management Committee (JMC).&#13;
(a)    There shall be established a Joint Management Committee (JMC) to be chaired by&#13;
BAPPENAS.     Voting members of the JMC shall be BAPPENAS, the Bank, each Provider&#13;
contributing at least US$1 million, and representatives from GOI agencies appointed from time to time&#13;
by BAPPENAS.&#13;
(b)    The JMC is responsible for: (i) providing strategy development direction; (ii)&#13;
supporting the GOI in promoting harmonization and coordination among all Indonesian poverty-&#13;
reduction programs; (iii) reviewing and approving Project proposals concerning PSF Trust Fund&#13;
Activity budget allocations; (iv) overall review of progress; and (v) adoption of the Operations Manual&#13;
and any changes to it.&#13;
(c)    The JMC will determine its procedures and regulate its proceedings as set out in the&#13;
Operations Manual.&#13;
2.     Technical Committee.&#13;
(a)    There shall also be established a Technical Committee to be co-chaired by a&#13;
representative of BAPPENAS and the chair of the Technical Secretariat. The co-chairs may invite&#13;
additional individuals to participate as members of the Technical Committee for particular PSF Trust&#13;
Fund Activity discussions, depending on the agenda of a specific meeting. Decisions regarding&#13;
recommendations proposed to the Joint Management Committee will be made on a consensus basis&#13;
among the co-chairs of the Technical Committee.&#13;
(b)    The Technical Committee will be responsible for: (i) designing appropriate&#13;
interventions; (ii) monitoring/ analyzing the findings of programmatic/technical evaluations of PNPM&#13;
Mandiri activities and preparing associated recommendations for the Joint Management Committee's&#13;
consideration; (iii) contributing to the development of Project Proposals and endorsing them prior to the&#13;
Joint Management Committee's review; and (iv) updating the Operations Manual from time to time for&#13;
approval by the Joint Management Committee and other PNPM Mandiri publications.&#13;
(c)    The Technical Committee will determine its procedures and regulate its proceedings as&#13;
set out in the Operations Manual.&#13;
3.     Technical Secretariat.&#13;
(a)    The Technical Committee will be supported by a Technical Secretariat at the World&#13;
Bank Office Jakarta, consisting of a team of suitably qualified and experienced administrative and&#13;
technical experts. The chair of the Technical Secretariat is appointed by the Joint Management&#13;
Committee.&#13;
ISEB Tower 2, 12th Floor, JI. Jend. Sudirman Kay. 52-53, Jakarta 12190  X+6221 5299 3000  0+6221 52993111  O www.worldbank.org/id&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿TF070967                                  8 of 12                       April 24, 2013&#13;
(b)    The Technical Secretariat will be responsible for: (i) administering Grant Agreements&#13;
issued through both the Trust Fund and any other PSF trust funds; (ii) developing/conducting&#13;
evaluations and analytical work; (iii) coordinating program supervision missions and appraisals; (iv)&#13;
providing operational and technical assistance to GOI agencies managing PNPM Mandiri programs;&#13;
(v) preparing reports in accordance with the Operations Manual; (vi) preparing PSF annual work plans;&#13;
and (vii) administering the Joint Management Committee meetings.&#13;
(c)    The Technical Secretariat will determine its procedures and regulate its proceedings as&#13;
set out in the Operations Manual.&#13;
4.     Advisory Panel.&#13;
(a)    The JMC may from time to time appoint an Advisory Panel consisting of Indonesian&#13;
professionals noted for their expertise in poverty reduction and/or community empowerment issues to&#13;
serve as individual advisors to the JMC.&#13;
(b)    The terms of reference for the Advisory Panel will be developed by the Technical&#13;
Committee with the support of the Technical Secretariat and will be approved by the JMC.&#13;
(c)    The Advisory Panel will determine its procedures and regulate its proceedings as set&#13;
out in the Operations Manual.&#13;
5.     Endorsement of PSF Trust Fund Activities Proposals&#13;
(a)    The resources of the Trust Fund shall be applied to provide funding for PSF Trust&#13;
Fund Activities approved and allocated in accordance with the Operations Manual to finance activities&#13;
which are of high priority, relevant to the development needs of Republic of Indonesia and consistent&#13;
with the objectives of the PSF.&#13;
(b)    Each PSF Trust Fund Activity or any modification thereto will be prepared and&#13;
approved by the appropriate approving authority as set out in the Operations Manual.&#13;
ISEB Tower 2,12th Floor, JI. Jend. Sudirman Kay. 52-53, Jakarta 12190  2+6221 5299 3000  6 +6221 5299 3111  O www.worldbank.org/id&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿TF070967                                 9 of 12                      April 24, 2013&#13;
ANNEX 2&#13;
Standard Provisions Applicable to the PSF Trust Fund&#13;
As Amended and Restated&#13;
This Annex shall be applicable to and form an integral part of all agreements entered into&#13;
between the Bank and the Providers that provide Allocations to be administered by the Bank for the&#13;
Trust Fund.&#13;
1.    Administration of the Allocation&#13;
1.1.   The Bank will be responsible only for performing those functions specifically set forth in this&#13;
Trust Fund Administration Agreement and will not be subject to any other duties or responsibilities to&#13;
the Provider, including, without limitation, any duties or obligations that might otherwise apply to a&#13;
fiduciary or trustee under general principles of trust or fiduciary law. Nothing in this Trust Fund&#13;
Administration Agreement will be considered a waiver of any privileges or immunities of the Bank&#13;
under its Articles of Agreement or any applicable law, all of which are expressly reserved.&#13;
1.2.   The Allocation shall be administered in accordance with the Bank's applicable policies and&#13;
procedures, as the same may be amended from time to time, including its framework to prevent and&#13;
combat fraud and corruption and its screening procedures to prevent the use of Bank resources to&#13;
finance terrorist activity, in line with the Bank's obligations to give effect to the relevant decisions of the&#13;
Security Council, taken under Chapter VII of the of Charter of the United Nations. The Provider&#13;
acknowledges that this provision does not create any obligations of the Bank under the anti-terrorist&#13;
financing and asset control laws, regulations, rules and executive orders of an individual member&#13;
country that may apply to the Provider, nor shall it be deemed a waiver, express or implied, of any of&#13;
the privileges and immunities of the Bank.&#13;
2.     Commingling, Exchanie and Investment of the Allocation&#13;
2.1.   The Allocation funds may be commingled with other trust fund assets maintained by the Bank,&#13;
but will be kept separate and apart from the funds of Bank.&#13;
2.2.   The Allocation funds may be freely exchanged by the Bank into other currencies as may&#13;
facilitate their disbursement.&#13;
2.3.   The Bank will invest and reinvest the Allocation funds pending their disbursement in&#13;
accordance with the Bank's policies and procedures for the investment of trust funds administered by&#13;
the Bank. The Bank will credit all income from such investment to the Trust Fund to be used for the&#13;
same purposes as the Allocation funds.&#13;
ISEB Tower 2, 12th Floor, JI. Jend. Sudirman Kay. 52-53, Jakarta 12190  X+6221 52993000  ib+6221 52993111  Owww.worldbank.org/id&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿TF070967                                 10 of 12                            April 24, 2013&#13;
3.     Administrative Cost Recovery&#13;
In order to assist in the defrayment of the costs of administration of the Allocation funds and&#13;
other expenses incurred by the Bank pursuant to this Trust Fund Administration Agreement, the Bank&#13;
may, following deposit of the Allocation by the Provider, deduct from the Allocation and retain for the&#13;
Bank's own account an amount equal to one percent (%) of the Allocation. In addition, costs for (a)&#13;
incremental supervision activities and fiduciary and operational reviews; and (b) program management,&#13;
including the operating costs of the Technical Secretariat up to a maximum of 5.24%% will be charged&#13;
to the Trust Fund on an actual basis. If the allocations increase beyond what was originally expected at&#13;
the time of counter-signature of the first administration agreement, and the administrative costs&#13;
increase as a result, the Providers acknowledge that an additional administrative fee may be applied to&#13;
such new allocations.&#13;
4.     Grants to Recipients&#13;
4.1.   The Bank shall, as administrator of the Trust Fund on behalf of the Providers, enter into grant&#13;
agreements (the "Grant Agreements") with eligible recipients selected in accordance with the&#13;
governance terms of Annex 1 (the "Recipients") consistent with the purposes of this Agreement and on&#13;
the terms and conditions set forth in the Grant Agreements. Grant Agreements may be entered into up&#13;
to the maximum amount of the Allocations that all Providers have agreed to make available under the&#13;
Administration Agreements between the Bank and the Providers. Upon request by a Provider, the&#13;
Bank shall furnish a copy of the Grant Agreements to the Providers.&#13;
4.2.   The Bank shall be responsible for the supervision of the activities financed under the Grant&#13;
Agreements. Subject to the consent of the relevant Recipients, representatives of the Providers may be&#13;
invited by the Bank to participate in Bank supervision missions related to the Trust Fund.&#13;
4.3.   The Bank shall promptly inform the Providers of any significant modification to the terms of&#13;
any Grant Agreements and of any contractual remedies that are exercised by the Bank under any Grant&#13;
Agreements. To the extent practicable, the Bank shall afford the Providers the opportunity to exchange&#13;
views before effecting any such modification or exercising any such remedy.&#13;
5.     Procurement&#13;
5.1.   For Recipient-executed activities, the Grant Agreements shall provide that the Allocations shall&#13;
be used by the Recipients to finance expenditures for goods and services, as the case may be, in&#13;
accordance with the Bank's Guidelines on "Procurement under IBRD Loans and IDA Credits" and the&#13;
Bank's Guidelines on the "Selection and Employment of Consultants by World Bank Borrowers," as in&#13;
effect at the date of entry into the respective Grant Agreements.&#13;
5.2.   For Bank-executed activities, the employment and supervision of any consultants and the&#13;
procurement of any goods financed by the Allocations shall be the responsibility of the Bank and shall&#13;
be carried out in accordance with its applicable policies and procedures.&#13;
ISEB Tower 2, 12th Floor, J1. Jend. Sudirman Kay. 52-53, Jakarta 12190 2 +6221 5299 3000 0 +6221 5299 3111 0 www.worldbank.org/id&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿TF070967                                 11 of 12                            April 24. 2013&#13;
6.     Accounting and Financial Reporting&#13;
6.1.   The Bank will maintain separate records and ledger accounts in respect of the Allocation funds&#13;
deposited by the Providers in the Trust Fund account and disbursements made therefrom. Separate&#13;
records and ledger accounts shall be kept for the Trust Fund account and each PSF Facility trust fund.&#13;
6.2.   The Bank shall furnish to the Providers current financial information relating to receipts,&#13;
disbursements and fund balance in United States Dollars with respect to the Allocation funds via the&#13;
World Bank's Trust Funds Donor Center secure website. Within six (6) months after all commitments&#13;
and liabilities under the trust fund have been satisfied and the trust fund has been closed, the final&#13;
financial information relating to receipts, disbursements and fund balance in the United States Dollars&#13;
with respect to the Allocation funds will be made available to the Providers via the Bank's Trust Funds&#13;
Donor Center secure website.&#13;
6.3.   The Bank will provide to the Provider within six (6) months following the end of each World&#13;
Bank Group fiscal year, the annual single audit, comprising (1) a management assertion together with&#13;
an attestation from the World Bank Group's external auditors concerning the adequacy of internal&#13;
control over cash-based financial reporting for trust funds as a whole; and (2) a combined financial&#13;
statement for all cash-based trust funds together with the external auditor's opinion thereon. The cost&#13;
of such attestations will be borne by the World Bank Group.&#13;
6.4.   If the Provider wishes to request, on an exceptional basis, a financial statement audit by the&#13;
Bank's external auditors of the trust fund established under this Trust Fund Administration Agreement,&#13;
the Provider and the Bank will first consult as to whether such an external audit is necessary. The Bank&#13;
and the Provider will agree on the most appropriate scope and terms of reference of such audit.&#13;
Following agreement on the scope and terms of reference, the Bank will arrange for such external&#13;
audit. The costs of any such audit, including the internal costs of the Bank with respect to such audit,&#13;
will be paid by the Provider.&#13;
6.5.   The Bank will also provide the Provider with copies of all financial statements and auditors'&#13;
reports received by the Bank from the Recipients pursuant to the Grant Agreements.&#13;
7.     Progress Reporting&#13;
7.1.   The Bank will provide the Provider with an annual report on the progress of activities financed&#13;
by the Allocation. Within six (6) months of the final disbursement date specified in paragraph 13.1 of&#13;
this Annex, the Bank will furnish to the Provider a final report on activities supported under the Trust&#13;
Fund.&#13;
7.2.   The Bank may prepare a single report covering both this Trust Fund and other PSF facility&#13;
trust funds.&#13;
7.3.   The Bank will promptly inform the Provider of any significant modification to the terms of the&#13;
Grant Agreements and of any contractual remedy that is exercised by the Bank under the Grant&#13;
Agreements. To the extent practicable, the Bank will afford the Provider the opportunity to exchange&#13;
views before effecting any such modification or exercising any such remedy.&#13;
ISEB Tower 2, 12m Floor, JI. Jend. Sudirman Kay. 52-53, Jakarta 12190  3+6221 5299 3000  *+6221 5299 3111  0 www.worldbank.org/id&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿TF070967                                  12 of 12                             April 24, 2013&#13;
7.4.   Any Provider may review or evaluate activities financed by the Trust Fund. The Provider and&#13;
the Bank shall agree on the scope and conduct of such review or evaluation, and the Bank shall provide&#13;
all relevant information within the limits of its policies and procedures. All associated costs shall be&#13;
borne by the Provider. It is understood that any such review or evaluation will not constitute a&#13;
financial, compliance or other audit of the Trust Fund.&#13;
8.     Disbursement; Cancellation; Refund&#13;
8.1.   The Allocations may be used to retroactively finance payments for eligible expenditures in&#13;
accordance with the Bank's policies and procedures.&#13;
8.2.   It is expected that the Allocation funds will be fully disbursed by the Bank in accordance with&#13;
the provisions of this Trust Fund Administration Agreement by June 30, 2014. The Bank will only&#13;
disburse Allocation funds for the purposes of this Trust Fund Administration Agreement after such&#13;
date with the written approval of the Provider.&#13;
8.3.   Either party may, upon giving three (3) months' prior notice in writing to the other, cancel all or&#13;
part of any remaining balance of the Allocation that is not committed pursuant to the Grant Agreement&#13;
or any other agreement entered into between the Bank and any consultants and/or other third parties for&#13;
the purposes of this Trust Fund Administration Agreement prior to the receipt of such notice.&#13;
8.4.    Following the final disbursement date specified in paragraph 8.2, the Bank shall return any&#13;
remaining balance of the Allocations to the Providers or to the relevant Provider Balance Account on a&#13;
pro rata basis based on the Providers' paid Allocations. In the event of cancellation the Bank shall&#13;
promptly return to the relevant Provider or Providers or to the relevant Provider Balance Account the&#13;
Provider's pro rata share of uncommitted Allocations in accordance with paragraph 8.3.&#13;
9.   Disclosure&#13;
The Bank will disclose this Agreement and related information on this Trust Fund in accordance with&#13;
the World Bank Policy on Access to Information. By entering into this Agreement, Providers consent to&#13;
disclosure of this Agreement and related information on this Trust Fund.&#13;
ISEB Tower 2, 12m Floor, J1. Jend. Sudirman Kay. 52-53, Jakarta 12190 Z+6221 5299 3000 *+6221 5299 3111 Owww.worldbank.org/id&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="17706536">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2013/04/17706536/official-documents--administration-agreement-millenium-challenge-account-indonesia-tf070967
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2013/04/17706536/official-documents--administration-agreement-millenium-challenge-account-indonesia-tf070967</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2013/04/17706536/official-documents--administration-agreement-millenium-challenge-account-indonesia-tf070967</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2013-05-13T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2013-05-13T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <docm_id>090224b081baada3</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b081baada3</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/EAP/2013/05/13/090224b081baada3/1_0/Rendered/INDEX/Official0Docum0donesia0to0TF0709670.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/EAP/2013/05/13/090224b081baada3/1_0/Rendered/PDF/Official0Docum0donesia0to0TF0709670.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2013-04-24T16:44:35Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2013-05-13T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docna>
            Official Documents- Administration Agreement
            with Millenium Challenge Account - Indonesia to TF070967
        </docna>
        <display_title>Official Documents-
            Administration Agreement with Millenium Challenge Account -
            Indonesia to TF070967</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/2013/04/17706536/official-documents--administration-agreement-millenium-challenge-account-indonesia-tf070967</listing_relative_url>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <docty>Trust Fund Administrative Agreement</docty>
        <count>Indonesia</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Mpundu,Marjorie</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>HQBOCS</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <owner>Social Development - Indonesia (EASID)</owner>
        <trustfund>TF070967-Support Facility for the
            National Program for Community Empowerment</trustfund>
        <lang>English</lang>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Arts and Culture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>Freedom of Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>Bank Supervision</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Remittances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Migration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Checks on Executive Power</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen User Satisfaction Survey</ml:concept><ml:concept>Independent Commissions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ombudsmen</ml:concept><ml:concept>Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Parliament</ml:concept><ml:concept>Procurement Complaints Review Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supreme Audit Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civil Society</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Media</ml:concept><ml:concept>Privileges and Immunities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Treasury</ml:concept><ml:concept>Right to Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>External Audit</ml:concept><ml:concept>Local Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Bank Regulation and Supervision</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Movement of Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Accountability Mechanisms</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Indonesia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>