<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>﻿                                                                   78942&#13;
                  Summary of Oral History Transcript               v1&#13;
                             Black, Eugene R.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Interview conducted by Professor Robert W. Oliver, Brookings&#13;
Institution, on 1961-08-06&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Eugene R. Black, in his third term as President of the Bank from&#13;
July 1, 1949 to December 31, 1962, talks about how he first came to&#13;
the Bank from the Chase National Bank in New York in response to&#13;
McCloy's request, as American Director for two years. The conditions&#13;
under which McCloy accepted the presidency of the Bank, and how until&#13;
their arrival in March '47 the Bank had made no loans and sold no&#13;
bonds, McCloy bringing down R. Garner as Vice President, and their&#13;
work as a team in getting the Bank to be a functional organization. He&#13;
talks about the initial task of acquainting people with the Bank's&#13;
intentions and the policies it was proposing to follow, setting up&#13;
policies to safeguard the Bank against defaults on foreign loans,&#13;
obtaining the required legislation to be passed through the U.S.&#13;
Congress; giving institutional investors permission to deal in Bank&#13;
bonds, his decision to sell Bank bonds outside the U.S, and the&#13;
Chilean Government as the first to apply for a sizeable loan.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Black elaborates on the function of the American Director in the&#13;
Bank. Talks about the Bank maintaining its objectivity in remaining&#13;
independent from the political influences of various member&#13;
governments and, therefore, not inclined to make loans for political&#13;
advantages. The governments' veto power in preventing the Bank from&#13;
making loans such as in the case of the Czech and Polish loans, when&#13;
both countries declined from becoming members of the Marshall Plan&#13;
after receiving orders from the Russians not to. In the case of the&#13;
Yugoslav loan--the only case in which the Bank had ever made a loan to&#13;
a Communist country-the U.S. government did not react against it as it&#13;
had with the Polish loan because the Yugoslavs had broken with the&#13;
&amp;#12;Russians. Management's lukewarm attitude towards a prospective loan&#13;
when a) a government is thought not to be following sound policies, b)&#13;
it had failed to do what was agreed upon with the Bank, or c) that the&#13;
project is not good. The importance of a country's creditworthiness in&#13;
loan negotiations as in the case of Brazil and Turkey, and the&#13;
technical assistance services offered by the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Black mentions how he was able to double the Bank's capital, why&#13;
he favors multilateral aid, and the great emphasis placed on making&#13;
high-quality loans to a country.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Also, his personal experiences in involving himself in&#13;
mediations, limited to when situations reached an impasse and/or a&#13;
breaking point, such as in the case of the Indus River-dispute between&#13;
India and Pakistan; the settlement of the Suez Canal dispute and his&#13;
relationship with Nasser-dispute between the British and the Egyptian&#13;
governments; and a mediation--of a personal nature--between the French&#13;
bondholders' committee and the city of Tokyo.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Black discusses the circumstances which led to him becoming&#13;
President. Coming to the Bank initially for two years on leave of&#13;
absence from the Chase Bank and serving as American Director in a&#13;
rather unusual capacity--spending his time on management issues and&#13;
trying to establish a bond market. And, when soon after his return to&#13;
the Chase Bank in March'49, McCloy was offered the High Commissionship&#13;
to Germany and pressured him into accepting the Presidency of the Bank&#13;
which he had initially refused.&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="17968857">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1961/08/17968857/transcript-oral-history-interview-eugene-r-black-held-august-06-1961-vol-1-2-summary-oral-history-transcript
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1961/08/17968857/transcript-oral-history-interview-eugene-r-black-held-august-06-1961-vol-1-2-summary-oral-history-transcript</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1961/08/17968857/transcript-oral-history-interview-eugene-r-black-held-august-06-1961-vol-1-2-summary-oral-history-transcript</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2008-12-02T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2008-12-02T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2013/07/05/000442464_20130705143601/Rendered/INDEX/789420v10TRN0B0mmary0August06001961.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2013/07/05/000442464_20130705143601/Rendered/PDF/789420v10TRN0B0mmary0August06001961.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2013-07-05T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1961-08-06T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>2</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>2</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Transcript of oral history interview with
            Eugene R. Black held on August 06, 1961
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            In August 1961, Eugene R. Black was
            interviewed on behalf of the World Bank Group Archives oral
            history program by Robert W. Oliver. During his tenure at
            the Bank from 1947 to 1962, Mr. Black worked in the
            following areas: as executive director (United States) of
            the World Bank Group (1947-1949); as president of the World
            Bank Group (1949-1962); and as president of the
            International Finance Corporation (IFC) (1961-1962). He
            focused policies to safeguard the World Bank against
            defaults on foreign loans, offered institutional investors
            permission to deal in World Bank bonds, and collaborated on
            the decision to sell World Bank bonds outside the United
            States. His transcript concerns his ideal to maintain an
            objective of remaining independent from the political
            influences of various member governments and, therefore, not
            inclined to make loans for political advantages.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Summary
        </docna>
        <display_title>Transcript of oral history
            interview with Eugene R. Black held on August 06, 1961 (Vol.
            2) : Summary</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/1961/08/17968857/transcript-oral-history-interview-eugene-r-black-held-august-06-1961-vol-2-summary</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Transcript</docty>
        <subtopic>Public Sector Corruption &amp;
            Anticorruption Measures,Banks &amp; Banking Reform,Corporate Law,Debt Markets,Hazard Risk Management</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Law and Development,Public Sector Development,Urban Development</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000442464_20130705143601</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>World Bank Group Archives oral history program</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Law and Development,Public Sector Development,Urban Development</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Board Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Bank bonds, bond, bond market, bondholders,
            bonds, creditworthiness, defaults, foreign loans,
            institutional investors, legislation, limited, loan,
            National Bank, negotiations, return, settlement, technical assistance
        </keywd>
        <owner>Knowledge &amp; Information Services (ITSKI)</owner>
        <repnb>78942</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation and Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Mediation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>