<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>ï»¿                                                                              78944&#13;
&#13;
Memorialist's name:     Kenneth Bohr&#13;
Date of interview:     July 13, 1986&#13;
Place:     The airport, Portland, Maine&#13;
Interviewer's name:     Robert W. Oliver&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     I think we might begin our conversation, if we may, Ken, by your&#13;
telling a bit about how you came to the Bank in the first place.       Perhaps&#13;
you would summarize your general career before we get down to some specific&#13;
things.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     I graduated in engineering, went into the Army, and spent four years&#13;
in the Army in the Second World War.       When I came back, I went back to&#13;
school under the G.I. Bill.     I went to MIT as an undergraduate and also as&#13;
a graduate.     I got interested in economics.   After the war I did some work&#13;
in engineering and then switched to economics and completed all my&#13;
requirements for an advanced degree, except the thesis, at MIT and looked&#13;
for a job.     I went to the economics meetings in New York and a friend of&#13;
mine who was then at the Fund and had been a graduate student with me&#13;
introduced me to [PaulJ Rosenstein-Rodan, I believe it was, and he was&#13;
interested in the fact that I had studied both engineering and economics.&#13;
Out of that, one thing led to another and I joined the Bank in 1950.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     I think that was his background, too.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     Yes and he was interested in the technical ratios of industry.      In&#13;
fact, one of the first jobs I did for the Bank was a study of investment&#13;
criteria which classified industries in various ways.      I had been working&#13;
on the steel industry as a graduate student and I also wrote a paper in the&#13;
Bank on the steel industry.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Briefly, my career in the Bank started in the Research Department.         I&#13;
was an industrial economist.     From that I got involved in sector work.     I&#13;
did sector work on industry in a number of countries, then also on electric&#13;
&#13;
NOTE: This partially edited transcript has been reviewed by and&#13;
incorporates changes made by the memorialist, and is made available for the&#13;
sole use of the World Bank History Project, 10/21/91.&#13;
&amp;#12;BOHR                                   -2-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
power in one case.     Then I went from sectors, general analysis of a sector,&#13;
to project work.     I worked on a preliminary mission for a project in&#13;
electric power.     And then at a critical time, I suppose, I went to India.&#13;
I was involved in the Bell Mission, which was six months in India, and&#13;
later I served in the Bank's office in India for four years.     That came out&#13;
of my experience with sector work; I wrote the report on Indian public&#13;
sector industry for the Bell Mission.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    After leaving India in 1970, I had a problem adjusting to the Bank; it&#13;
had changed and I had changed.     The most important thing that happened&#13;
after that was my involvment with urban work.     I was in urban work rather&#13;
early.     I had a hand in some of the early thinking about it, but my main&#13;
contribution was to organize and set up the first loan to Calcutta.        I was&#13;
in a very fortunate position, having been in Calcutta earlier, having known&#13;
something about the situation and having been able to see the opportunity&#13;
that existed in 1972.     This was the first multi-sector urban project loan&#13;
made by the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    I stayed with urban work, and then there was a reorganization.     I was&#13;
put in an awkward position bureaucratically.     I left urban work after a&#13;
number of years and went to the Operations Evaluation Department.     I spent&#13;
the last six years at the Bank reviewing the work of the Bank and ge post&#13;
evaluation of project experience.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:    Just to clarify what you've been telling me, when you were in&#13;
sector work, was that in the Research Department or in the Projects&#13;
Department?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     I was always in the Economics Department in its various forms.     I&#13;
was never in the Projects Department until I got into urban work.     In the&#13;
early days, as an industrial economist, I was lent to other departments for&#13;
certain missions.     I did work with project people on the preliminaries of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NOTE: This partially edited transcript has been reviewed by and&#13;
incorporates changes made by the memorialist, and is made available for the&#13;
sole use of the World Bank History Project, 10/21/91.&#13;
&amp;#12;BOHR                                      -3-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
the power project in Venezuela.        I worked on a sector study of power in&#13;
Yugoslavia.        In those days the economics group was a source of economists&#13;
for long-term work, missions of, say, four to six weeks.          I was involved in&#13;
two survey missions, one to Spain and one to what was then British Guiana,&#13;
and they took a long period of time.          From the early days of the Bank, the&#13;
operating people could not assign their own people for that long a period,&#13;
so they would gather their staff, some from the Economics Department, some&#13;
from outside.        So my missions up to 1970 were not very frequent, but they&#13;
were long by Bank standards.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     When you were doing the urban work you went to the Projects&#13;
Department.        Was that Urban Projects?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     At first it was called Special Projects.      Bob [Robert A.) Sadove was&#13;
the Director.       He and I were old friends, had worked together in the study&#13;
of demand for power back in the early 1960s.         This was the beginning.    At&#13;
that time the Bank seemed to have the idea that to lend for a new field, it&#13;
was necessary to set up a new department,         That was the approach; if you're&#13;
going to go in to tourism, you establish a department making tourism&#13;
projects.     You defined your projects in terms of what the department can&#13;
do.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      The Special Projects Department changed to the Urban Department,          Later&#13;
it was reorganized and combined with the Transportation Department.            Sadove&#13;
left and a new boss came in and the younger generation took over.          I was in&#13;
urban work for four to five years.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     Just before you went in that department, when you were still in&#13;
Economics, you were doing work in industry, were you not?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     Right.    When I carne back to the Bank I was given a place as Division&#13;
Chief of the Industrial Economics Division of the Economics Department.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NOTE: This partially edited transcript has been reviewed by and&#13;
incorporates changes made by the memorialist, and is made available for the&#13;
sole use of the World Bank History Project, 10/21/91.&#13;
&amp;#12;BOHR                                    -4-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     You worked with Helen Hughes?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     Right.   Helen Hughes was the deputy.     She had been very active in&#13;
this.     I had a point of view from the field and it was hard for me to move&#13;
back into the Bank.      I didn't see the relation of some of the work we were&#13;
doing to the work in the field.      The style of the work was different from&#13;
what I had thought; I didn't find it very satisfactory.         I would have&#13;
rather been in a project department, and I left when I had a chance to go&#13;
to Special Projects in urban work.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     Can you expand on that a bit and categorize the differences of&#13;
outlook of people in the field, on the one hand, and people in, let's say,&#13;
theoretical economics, on the other hand?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     Well, the field experience was very interesting.      A great deal of&#13;
the problem was finding out facts, finding out what was really happening.&#13;
For example, the need to know details about the experience of the&#13;
fertilizer industry was really important.         I always found, particularly in&#13;
India, there were plenty of theorists.         There were people who had theories&#13;
about everything, but you couldn't often find someone who really knew what&#13;
was going on or just how things worked.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    I found the concern with getting things done, the concern with doing&#13;
things, was very compatible to me, perhaps because I originally started out&#13;
in a technical field.      Economics was a kind of veneer in my case, and it&#13;
was always a means to something else.         When I came back to the Bank I had&#13;
the feeling that the economists had gotten a pretty strong position, and&#13;
there was a lot of effort which was a logical extension of theory about&#13;
various things, including the way they were going to apply shadow prices&#13;
and all that.      And, as one who had struggled with how to find out what the&#13;
price actually was, I was conscious of the gap between what was being done&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NOTE: This partially edited transcript has been reviewed by and&#13;
incorporates changes made by the memorialist, and is made available for the&#13;
sole use of the World Bank History Project, 10/21/91.&#13;
&amp;#12;BOHR                                     -5-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
in the Bank and what was done in the field.        I was always conscious of&#13;
this.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     I understand.     Can we go backwards in history from the time you&#13;
started in urban work and have you tell what you care to about your&#13;
experiences in India?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     Yes.   That was quite an experience.    My first trip to India was in&#13;
1963.     It was one of those "point trips", and I took my wife.     People said,&#13;
"Oh, what a terrible thing.        You've got this points trip and you have to&#13;
take your wife to India".        Well, it wasn't easy, but her father was born&#13;
there; she had grandparents who were missionaries, so her interest was not&#13;
just normal, it was unusual.        That was a short trip that introduced us to&#13;
the place a little bit.        I was concerned with following up on a power&#13;
study, actually.      It was after that, in 1964, that the Bell mission was set&#13;
up and the Economics Department, I think Drag [Dragoslav] Avramovic was&#13;
then the Director, was more or less divided: a bunch went to Brazil and a&#13;
bunch went to India.        We left may be some secretaries and a few staff&#13;
people at home.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       I was assigned to the Bell mission and it was quite an experience.        We&#13;
moved out families.     We moved out to India after school had started, pulled&#13;
our children out, put them into school in India, were there six months, and&#13;
then went back into school in the States.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       We had a large mission with very distinguished people--Sir John&#13;
Crawford was the head of the agricultural group, David Hopper was assisting&#13;
him.    He was then with the Rockefeller Foundation, in India.      [Professor]&#13;
Ed (EdwardS.] Mason came out to review the part-time work.         Jean Baneth&#13;
was a member, Stanley Please was a member.       Ben [Benjamin B. ] King, the&#13;
Rresident Representative in India, was a member ...&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NOTE: This partially edited transcript has been reviewed by and&#13;
incorporates changes made by the memorialist, and is made available for the&#13;
sole use of the World Bank History Project, 10/21/91.&#13;
&amp;#12;BOHR                                      -6-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     Did Stanley Please stay four years also?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     No, no.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     These were just on the Bell mission.       I see.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     Baneth and I stayed four years afterwards.       Well, it was a hard&#13;
mission, because we were to find out what was wrong with the Indian&#13;
economy.     Why didn't the Third Five Year Plan give the planned results.          No&#13;
one appreciates a bunch of people coming in to tell one where he has gone&#13;
wrong.     It was slow.     I did travel around quite a bit and got some sort of&#13;
feel for things.     We had a long time to write the report, I wrote three&#13;
versions of my report, I know.        I was reasonably pleased with what we&#13;
finished up with, and I think Bernie [Bernard R. Bell) was.          It was an&#13;
interesting experience because we did see quite a lot.          I went to lots of&#13;
companies and places, and we lived in the country.          It was a very unusual&#13;
job.     It was to report to the President of the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       I believe one of the outcomes of the report was the devaluation which&#13;
the Indians felt was forced on them by the Bank and the Fund, and there was&#13;
some bad feeling about it.        But the result for me was that the Bank decided&#13;
to enlarge the office in India, which had been a two or three-man office in&#13;
the back of the Reserve Bank building.          Bob Sadove was selected to be the&#13;
representative and he selected me as his deputy.          I went to India and he&#13;
did not actually come at all, so I was in charge for a year.         We enlarged&#13;
the office from two people to about six I think.         We were put in new&#13;
quarters.     We had to furnish the quarters, hire local staff.      All this was&#13;
done in the field.        At that time there wasn't a system, there wasn't&#13;
someone from Washington telling you what to do.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     Did you take your family back out with you?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NOTE: This partially edited transcript has been reviewed by and&#13;
incorporates changes made by the memorialist, and is made available for the&#13;
sole use of the World Bank History Project, 10/21/91.&#13;
&amp;#12;BOHR                                    -7-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     We took our family, yes.   This was in 1966 and we left India in&#13;
1970.     Well it was a lot of work and it was quite interesting because I was&#13;
in charge of something.      I had quite a bit to do.     John Baneth came out.&#13;
He had been on the Bell mission.      So we knew something about India;     we&#13;
weren't coming cold to this job.      Bob [Robert] Picciotto was in the office.&#13;
Peter Naylor was in the office.      We had responsibility for running the&#13;
office and reporting and handling     ~issions   that came through and being&#13;
intermediaries with the Indian officials.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     Were you involved in writing a second report, or was this ... ?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     We wrote pieces of annual reports there.      After a year, [William M.]&#13;
Gilmartin came as the head of the mission.       He was Head of the Mission&#13;
until I left and he stayed on for several more years, I believe.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     By this time the Bell report was totally finished?&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     Oh, yes, this was after the Bell report.      We had submitted it to&#13;
them.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     I just had one other question about the Bell report.      Yours was&#13;
the volume that dealt with industry?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     Yes.   It was a special focus on public sector industry.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     Could you quickly summarize a recommendation of this report?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     Well, we tried to see the difficulties that the Indians were&#13;
encountering in running public sector industry.         We saw the dilemma they&#13;
were in, how they got involved in it, and we were concerned with the&#13;
difficulty of running these industries effectively.         I don't remember the&#13;
specific problems, but I remember this, that we were able to use studies&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NOTE: This partially edited transcript has been reviewed by and&#13;
incorporates changes made by the memorialist, and is made available for the&#13;
sole use of the World Bank History Project, 10/21/91.&#13;
&amp;#12;BOHR                                   -8-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
that they had done themselves which were very critical of how some&#13;
industries were run.     We weren't just bringing our ideas from the outside;&#13;
we were able to use published material from the Indian Government.          They&#13;
had a commission that reviewed the operation of industries, and I made&#13;
quite good use of that material to comment on the difficulties they were&#13;
having.     They had difficulties with management, they had difficulties not&#13;
having managers that were familiar with particular industries; they used&#13;
generalists and switched them around a lot.        It gave me an impression of&#13;
how difficult it was.     I hadn't started out being against public sector&#13;
industry; I didn't go with that prejudice, but I ended up with a feeling&#13;
that it was really a very, very difficult job.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:    Well, was one of your recommendations that some of the public&#13;
industry should be privatized?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     I don't think we got to that point.     I think we really talked about&#13;
improving planning and management of projects.       We also noted that in some&#13;
areas public sector projects worked well.       We were seeking some reason why&#13;
it worked well in some sectors and not well in others.       For instance, the&#13;
machine tool industry seemed to be easily adapted; they had a success story&#13;
in the machine tool industry.     They had a great deal of difficulty with&#13;
large electrical equipment, where everything was done piece by piece on&#13;
special order; it wasn't repetitive, and it involved a different kind of&#13;
labor force.     It was a different experience.    I think if we had gone&#13;
further we could have pointed out that the adaptation problem was quite&#13;
different with different kinds of processes.       If the process was, say,&#13;
fertilizer, they had some very good public industries.       They had some bad&#13;
and good, but certain processes were much easier to adapt than other&#13;
processes.     I think that was one thing I will compare.    They had trouble&#13;
with the job shop, which was the great big electrical generators and&#13;
turbines and stuff that they made on order.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NOTE: This partially edited transcript has been reviewed by and&#13;
incorporates changes made by the memorialist, and is made available for the&#13;
sole use of the World Bank History Project, 10/21/91.&#13;
&amp;#12;BOHR                                   -9-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     Did you comment on the pricing system?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     I don't think we did much in that report.     Other reports dealt with&#13;
administrative controls of which we were quite critical.       We had some case&#13;
studies.     I remember one case study about the Neyveli lignite project,&#13;
where the idea was to mine lignite in the south.       The south had no coal,&#13;
and power could be produced from the lignite.        Briquettes for cooking could&#13;
also he produced as well as fertilizer.      Nitrogeneous fertilizer was made&#13;
by many different processes in India, but this was one of the most&#13;
difficult: gasification of lignite.      Well, what was revealed by looking&#13;
into this case was: you had this grand idea of the multipurpose project,&#13;
but as it went along, it took a long time, and there was no way of&#13;
adjusting when you saw that the market shifted.       You saw things had changed&#13;
but you couldn't adjust to what was really happening.       They could have used&#13;
more power, probably less of the briquettes.      I'm not recalling exactly,&#13;
but they weren't ableÂ· to adjust to a shifting situation over a period of&#13;
time.     Of course, the period of time tends to be twice what you expect and&#13;
investment costs were well over original estimates.       That I remember&#13;
particularly.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     Was your industry report reasonably well received by the Indian&#13;
Government?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     Yes, I think so.   If I do say so, it was very carefully done.    It&#13;
was carefully done by trying to explain that we understood what they were&#13;
trying to do but here were problems.     Also the criticism was mostly&#13;
criticism which was not new; it had been put out by their own people.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     The overall Bell report, the summary report, did receive a fair&#13;
amount of criticism in the Indian press, I think.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NOTE: This partially edited transcript has been reviewed by and&#13;
incorporates changes made by the memorialist, and is made available for the&#13;
sole use of the World Bank History Project, 10/21/91.&#13;
&amp;#12;BOHR                                       -10-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR;     Certainly the issue of devaluation received criticism.         Of the&#13;
sector reports that we did, the one that was criticised was Ben King's on&#13;
planning, which was a little sharp.          They objected to some of the comments,&#13;
or some of the ways it was done.          They said it was fine for a university,&#13;
but they didn't like it as a public document.            That was a very readable,&#13;
very interesting piece, but it was an analysis of why planning was done so&#13;
poorly or why planning wasn't effective.            It had a little bit of sociology&#13;
and other things that they objected to in our meetings.             I think that it&#13;
was not distributed as part of the main report, but was kept aside.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     I understand that at one time or another, George Woods when he was&#13;
President, and Robert McNamara later, when he was President, actually&#13;
visited India.          Could you comment on those visits?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     Yes.    Th~   Woods visit came while I was in charge of the Resident&#13;
Mission.     We didn't know what to do.      What should we do?    The President of&#13;
the Bank was coming, and Romano Pantanal!, who had been in the Delhi office&#13;
for some time- -he was still on the staff- -said, "We ought to have a big&#13;
cocktail party and get all the Indian officials together and let them meet&#13;
Mr. Woods.       This is what we should do."&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    We had no word from Woods as to his plans or desires.             I think we may&#13;
have tried to correspond and find out what Woods' plans were, but we didn't&#13;
get any information.         We set up this cocktail party.     It was the biggest&#13;
cocktail party that we had ever given.            It was in our house, and we hadn't&#13;
done this before.         We invited the working level of the government that we&#13;
knew and people from the foundations, from AID and other embassies--the&#13;
people that were concerned with the assistance business. And when Woods&#13;
came, we were told that he would only go to one public event a day, and he&#13;
wasn't sure he would come.         We were kind of nervous about that, but he did&#13;
come.     He came to the party and actually had a very good time.         It was&#13;
quite a success.         There was quite a bit of tension before, but it was quite&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NOTE: This partially edited transcript has been reviewed by and&#13;
incorporates changes made by the memorialist, and is made available for the&#13;
sole use of the World Bank History Project, 10/21/91.&#13;
&amp;#12;BOHR                                     -11-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
successful.     It counted as a success.        Then he stayed at a hotel nearby.       I&#13;
remember a couple of things.        I remember him calling up my wife.       He had&#13;
some homey issue that he asked her about.          And he was very gracious.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    The other thing I remember was that he came to the office.           This was&#13;
very helpful.     When I was in the Army, I knew what how it was when the&#13;
generals came around and how you could use the visit to help support your&#13;
staff and so forth.        So I was able to take him around the office.      He had&#13;
never been in this office.        It was a private house that we had fixed up,&#13;
and I could say that Ursula [Zieschang] was the one in charge of all this;&#13;
she did this, and somebody did that, and so on--this person did that.              He&#13;
was very appreciative because he had seen the office the Bank had had&#13;
previously which was in the back of the Reserve Bank building where, in the&#13;
summer, you'd have to step over some reclining, sleeping bodies to get in&#13;
the office,     He was very appreciative of what we had done, and he spoke to&#13;
the people there.        I remember that it was very satisfactory.     Our&#13;
relationship with him was friendly and warm.           I also accompanied him to the&#13;
Punjab.     At that time, the Punjab had two governments, Haryana and Punjab,&#13;
and he was able to talk to the Governors.          The Governors knew all about the&#13;
problems of these governments.        I was also there when he gave his press&#13;
conference at the airport.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Generally it was a pleasant experience for us.          My wife remembers it.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     Was Mrs. Woods with him on this trip?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     Yes she was.    We were very relieved that things had gone off well,&#13;
because this was all a new experience for us.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    McNamara visited shortly after he became President of the Bank.            I&#13;
think he became President April 1, 1968.          So he was very new when he came.&#13;
His public relations man came to Delhi first.          It was William Clark, and he&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NOTE: This partially edited transcript has been reviewed by and&#13;
incorporates changes made by the memorialist, and is made available for the&#13;
sole use of the World Bank History Project, 10/21/91.&#13;
&amp;#12;BOHR                                  -12-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
came to scout out things and find out what was happening.        The next thing,&#13;
McNamara came in by chartered airplane from Pakistan on a Sunday, and, as&#13;
soon as he landed, he had something to say to the press right at the&#13;
airport.     Then he didn't stay in a hotel, he went to stay in the&#13;
President's Palace.     This was a Sunday.   Gilmartin was then the Chief of&#13;
the Mission.     I was the Deputy of the Mission.   We had our staff all on&#13;
duty in the office because we expected McNamara would come to visit.           But&#13;
he didn't ever visit the office; we had to go to the Palace--! guess it was&#13;
the Palace, the President's residence--and brief him there.        That's an&#13;
incident.     I hadn't read The Best and the Brightest, and I didn't know his&#13;
penchant for figures.     I briefed him on the fertilizer industry.     I gave&#13;
him the total production of the industry, the market, the surplus, of&#13;
demand and what they were expecting to do,     He wanted to know how many&#13;
individual plants were involved in this expansion, how many individual&#13;
units,     Well, I had done a paper on the thing, but I couldn't remember that&#13;
figure at the time.     I should have just given him a figure, I realize.        I&#13;
had to back off, go and figure it out and give him a figure later.        But I&#13;
remember that incident because when I read the stories about the colonels&#13;
who gave him figures and the people who didn't and how he behaved, I could&#13;
understand that,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Well, he was very good to brief.     He absorbed things very quickly and&#13;
very well, and he complemented us.     "It was a great briefing."     Maybe he&#13;
says that to many people, but it was a good briefing.        We were quite a&#13;
competent group there, I think.     That was one instance.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    The other thing we noticed was that he spent a lot of time in Delhi&#13;
with the Americans, with the Embassy and the Ford Foundation, and he did&#13;
not give much attention to the UN people.     We felt that, because we were in&#13;
the Bank, sitting in a foreign country, trying to establish that we are not&#13;
an arm of the American government, trying to be what we thought we were,&#13;
which was independent.     Well, we noticed, and the UN people noted, that he&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NOTE: This partially edited transcript has been reviewed by and&#13;
incorporates changes made by the memorialist, and is made available for the&#13;
sole use of the World Bank History Project, 10/21/91.&#13;
&amp;#12;BOHR                                       -13-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
spent a lot of time with the Americans and not much with the others.              But&#13;
he was new at the job ...&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     Were the two visits, the Woods visit first and the McNamara visit&#13;
second, roughly comparable in length of time?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     I think so.      I think McNamara went to more places.     Woods used to&#13;
plan fewer things         a day.   But the big thing that I remember was the visit&#13;
to Calcutta.      We had to be taken in by helicopter because there was a riot&#13;
in Calcutta during McNamara's visit,          They burned a streetcar in his honor,&#13;
you might say.      There were crowds and crowds because he was then considered&#13;
the Secretary of Defense and Vietnam was a hot issue in Calcutta and that's&#13;
how they treated him in Calcutta.          It was all kind of exciting and kind of&#13;
scary.     There were mobs in the streets.         We couldn't get through certain&#13;
places, had to go around.          And we did come in by helicopter.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     The mobs were antagonistic, I take it?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     Yes.   Right.    Antagonistic.    Well, it didn't seem to faze him, I&#13;
must say.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     He'd seen antagonists in the United States.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     He'd seen worse than that.       Yes.    But there was another interesting&#13;
incident there.      He was very interested in Calcutta.        I believe he had been&#13;
there during the war, when he was in the Air Force.           We had a series of&#13;
meetings on Calcutta and its problems.            There were meetings with the&#13;
Planning Commission; there were meetings with businessmen; there were&#13;
meetings with individual groups of citizens.           One I got a sense of how&#13;
difficult things were.         There was nobody to deal with.     I mean, there&#13;
wasn't an organization you could tell, "We'll lend you something.            You can&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NOTE: This partially edited transcript has been reviewed by and&#13;
incorporates changes made by the memorialist, and is made available for the&#13;
sole use of the World Bank History Project, 10/21/91.&#13;
&amp;#12;BOHR                                  ~14-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
do something.â&#128;¢â&#128;¢   Things were in quite a disarray.     I think there was&#13;
President's rule at that time, that is the governor was in charge.         I was&#13;
very impressed with all that.    I took notes.    I was the one who did notes&#13;
from the meetings and there was a lot of discussion about the Calcutta&#13;
urban problems and the impossibility of providing the kind of homes that&#13;
Nehru said each Indian should have.    In Calcutta you had to deal with what&#13;
you could, fix up the slums, do this and that, improve the slums.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    I heard the first serious presentation of that issue by Colin Rosser,&#13;
an anthropologist, I believe.    He was an advisor paid by the Ford&#13;
Foundation.   He was very eloquent in the meetings.     That meeting had&#13;
consequences for me, because when I went to Calcutta in 1972, as a member&#13;
of the Urban Projects Department, they'd had President's Rule and they'd&#13;
set up an organization to do something, and I had always in my mind the&#13;
memory of these early meetings and how difficult it was to get a hold on&#13;
the situation.    In 1972 there was an organization.    There was a very&#13;
dynamic--it's kind of a hackneyed word--but a very able fellow in charge,&#13;
Sivarama Krishnan, who had worked with the Ford Foundation before and had&#13;
experience.   He was the Secretary of the Calcutta Metropolitan Development&#13;
Authority.    I could see that if there was going to the any chance to move,&#13;
it was there, while there was momentum.      There was help from the center.&#13;
This was a complicated business.    The center had set the whole thing up.&#13;
They had brought in money; they had set up this development authority over&#13;
the whole area to disburse funds for the development program.      So I was&#13;
very strong on acting at the time, while you had a chance, because knowing&#13;
how things go, you didn't know how long euphoria would last; and, if you're&#13;
going to get into a problem, you have to get into it at a good time.        The&#13;
McNamara visit was very helpful for me because I had a perspective that&#13;
nobody else involved in that project had.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:   Both Woods and McNamara's visits were successes but in different&#13;
ways, so to speak.   At least the character of each was different.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NOTE: This partially edited transcript has been reviewed by and&#13;
incorporates changes made by the memorialist, and is made available for the&#13;
sole use of the World Bank History Project, 10/21/91.&#13;
&amp;#12;BOHR&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     Yes, the character was very different.   And, of course a personal&#13;
thing was that we really appreciated Woods coming to the office.        This was&#13;
not a practice of McNamara's in other places either;        I always thought that&#13;
it was a little puzzling for someone who had been in military service,&#13;
because that's where I got the first taste of that kind of thing.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     May I ask one other question about the Bell mission?    The Bell&#13;
mission was put together and went around the existing chain of command in&#13;
the Bank, so to speak.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     Yes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     I take it Mr. Woods felt very strongly that he wanted to give a&#13;
fair amount of attention to India, wanted to speed things up, and was&#13;
concerned about the way the Indian Government was going.       Can you comment&#13;
on that and how the people in the Asia Department felt about having this&#13;
special mission go out kind of around them?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     It certainly was that way.   However, Ben King, who was in the&#13;
Department and the resident, was certainly a very important member of the&#13;
mission; and Pantanali, who was also in the office, was a member of the&#13;
mission.     I wasn't aware of awkwardness at that point.    Normally, the Bank&#13;
was not staffed to do any operation of that size.     You just couldn't do&#13;
that.     The thing that I found satisfactory about this was that we followed&#13;
up; we put people in the Delhi office who had been through the exercise,&#13;
and I thought that was very, very good.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    My feeling about India was: You spend a year just learning about things&#13;
and maybe after another year you may be able to say something useful.          It's&#13;
a very complicated system.     You think you know it because it's in English,&#13;
but you don't know as much about how it works as you think you do.         To have&#13;
any kind of effectiveness in the field, you've got to spend time.       Often it&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NOTE: This partially edited transcript has been reviewed by and&#13;
incorporates changes made by the memorialist, and is made available for the&#13;
sole use of the World Bank History Project, 10/21/91.&#13;
&amp;#12;BOHR                                   -16-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
has been the practice of putting people in the field who didn't know&#13;
anything about the country: putting them in cold.      When I sat in India, I&#13;
used to comment on the missions that came over.      People that had never been&#13;
in India before and had never been in the Bank before were sent out to do&#13;
project business.     Maybe this couldn't be avoided, but it's a difficult way&#13;
to do business.     The Indians would sometimes ask me, "Now what's the&#13;
qualification of these people?"&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     When someone came through who knew enough about the field and who&#13;
wasn't just a Young Professional who had learned it in the Bank, they would&#13;
really appreciate it--someone who could say: "Look, that is very good."&#13;
Young people could be critical much more easily because they were comparing&#13;
what they saw with some kind of standard they were trying to reach and&#13;
which might not be very realistic in the circumstance.      But there were some&#13;
mission people I thought were very helpful,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     Did you have a feeling that real progress was made in India during&#13;
the time you were there?     Some have commented that India is so enormous,&#13;
the problems so great, that it's really almost beyond the capacity of an&#13;
organization even as big as the World Bank to have a lot of effect on it.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     Yes, when I was on the Bell miss ion, I thought, tâ&#128;¢How in the world&#13;
could you ever expect that this country could change the way these plans&#13;
said?'t   You could see how the change has to be slow.    I mean, it was sort&#13;
of unreasonable, some of the things they're expecting, but I felt there was&#13;
some change. Certainly one could see the change.      We were aware of the&#13;
change in agriculture.     The Bell mission did quite a bit on that because it&#13;
took something that was started and pressed it.      It wasn't critical of&#13;
Indian agriculture practices like the Bank had been previously.      Mainly due&#13;
to Sir John Crawford, the mission saw that changes were coming--new seeds-&#13;
-and it just pushed and pushed along the way things were going and, I&#13;
think, gave them more support in the direction they were going.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NOTE: This partially edited transcript has been reviewed by and&#13;
incorporates changes made by the memorialist, and is made available for the&#13;
sole use of the World Bank History Project, 10/21/91.&#13;
&amp;#12;BOHR                                     -17-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    On a small scale, you could see progress as one living there.           Ye were&#13;
told what we had to bring in 1965.        Yell, we didn't have to bring all that.&#13;
The people who told us that had been there before.           Now you don't have to&#13;
bring much of anything.        You are aware of the growth of the middle class&#13;
economy in Delhi.       Yhat that means for the country, I don't know.      I am a&#13;
little partial to my friend in Calcutta who said every time he went to&#13;
Delhi he felt like crying to see all the money spent in Delhi while they're&#13;
trying to do things with their bare hands, in Calcutta so to speak.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     I think Bernie Bell feels that the World Bank is over-centralized&#13;
in Washington and that there ought to be more missions abroad for long&#13;
periods of time like the one that you were a part of and like he&#13;
subsequently was a part of in Indonesia.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     In Indonesia.    Yes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     Yould you comment on that?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     Yes.   I was very much aware of the centralization of the Bank.       When&#13;
I came back, I was hit with it particularly because in 1970 the Bank had&#13;
changed a lot.     There were layers on layers of people, and it was even more&#13;
strongly, not just centralized, but it was also saying at the top what&#13;
people were supposed to do.        It was much more authoritarian, I felt, coming&#13;
down through.      I always went through a difficulty of moving back and forth.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     Is part of the authoritarian appearance due to the change of&#13;
presidents, do you think, between 1965 and 1970?           Was it a matter of style&#13;
to some degree?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     I think so.     It seems like the idea for all this poverty business&#13;
came from the top.        It didn't come from the field.     I know I felt at the&#13;
time, well, people were talking about delivery systems for the urban poor.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NOTE: This partially edited transcript has been reviewed by and&#13;
incorporates changes made by the memorialist, and is made available for the&#13;
sole use of the World Bank History Project, 10/21/91.&#13;
&amp;#12;BOHR                                    -18-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
I was working in Calcutta.       Nobody came to Calcutta.    This was a subject&#13;
you talked about or you read about.       The interplay of the politics and&#13;
economics and all that kind of stuff, which was evident in the field, was&#13;
something that wasn't really tackled very much.       Maybe it could have been.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     Well, I've interrupted you several times.       I don't think I ever&#13;
let you finish!&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     Okay.    I had another point, because I was thinking about the Bell&#13;
mission.     To me this was characteristic of the Woods period:       the Bell&#13;
mission, big effort, and some follow-up.       The other big thing was the Indus&#13;
Basin study, which was another large effort set apart from normal&#13;
operations.       I did some work on that recently, doing a review of the energy&#13;
program in Pakistan, and I had the distinct feeling there was not much&#13;
follow-up in that case.      After this great study of the use of waters of the&#13;
Indus and all this business, the Bank reorganized to some extent, and the&#13;
Central Projects Department was cut out and the responsibility for&#13;
following up on this big work was left to small pieces of a Central&#13;
Projects Staff.      I don't know whether this is true, but in the McNamara&#13;
time it seems there was greater use of regular channels and focusing on&#13;
lending.     These unusual things of the Woods time, I'm not aware of them&#13;
being repeated.      Maybe they have been but ... They were so big--these two&#13;
studies, and they both took a long time.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     Would you back up just a little and say a bit about the Indus&#13;
Basin study itself?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     Well, I wasn't a participant in this study but I have read about it.&#13;
It started in trying to settle the water dispute between India and&#13;
Pakistan.     This was in Eugene Black's time, and his Vice President, Sir&#13;
William Iliff, was the negotiator for water agreement.         It was a six-year&#13;
negotiation to settle the water problem.       It was one of the outstanding&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NOTE: This partially edited transcript has been reviewed by and&#13;
incorporates changes made by the memorialist, and is made available for the&#13;
sole use of the World Bank History Project, 10/21/91.&#13;
&amp;#12;BOHR                                 -19-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
things the Bank did back in that time.      It was a very patient, long&#13;
negotiation by a man who had been a negotiator.      I mean, he was a U.K civil&#13;
servant and had some experience in this sort of thing.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Well, as an outcome of this negotiation, the waters could be divided;&#13;
but Pakistan wanted made up in storage what they would lose by shifting it,&#13;
and a little more, so there was a lot of money involved in this.      You had&#13;
to raise the money to make the thing work.      It was under Woods that the&#13;
study was done, which was to determine how best to use the additional water&#13;
in Pakistan.   This was a big study with consultant firms.     [Pieter]&#13;
Lieftinck was the head of it, and a lot of Bank staff were involved.&#13;
Sadove was the deputy on that.    They worked a number of years.    There were&#13;
a number of consulting firms and Pakistan counterparts, so forth.         This was&#13;
also a part of justifying the Tarbela Dam.      It was a big thing, whether it&#13;
was needed, how the water would be used.      It was that kind of a thing.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Well, the Tarbela Dam was financed by the Bank.      The study showed that&#13;
it would be justified.    The study went on to talk about how best to use the&#13;
irrigation and power, the difference between using water for two purposes&#13;
and all that--about setting up models and scheduling everything.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:   Then, after the study was completed, there were changes in the&#13;
Bank's relation with Pakistan.   There was the fall of [President] Ayub; a&#13;
number of things happened.   The work that was suggested wasn't really&#13;
carried out, and actually there was a period of not much action by the Bank&#13;
in Pakistan for a period in the 1970s.      I had a sense, reading the history,&#13;
that this was a big piece of work that was finished, and that was it.         It&#13;
was like the Bell mission was a big piece of work, except the Bell mission&#13;
was a different kind of work, and there was follow-up in the sense that&#13;
there was continuity in the Bank's staff involved in it.      The continuity&#13;
was lost in the other case because of the reorganization of the Bank.&#13;
Everyone was dispersed.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NOTE: This partially edited transcript has been reviewed by and&#13;
incorporates changes made by the memorialist, and is made available for the&#13;
sole use of the World Bank History Project, 10/21/91.&#13;
&amp;#12;BOHR                                     -20-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     You mean to imply that some sort of a permanent Bank team should&#13;
have been left in Karachi, let's say, or somewhere in Pakistan to oversee&#13;
the continuation of the project?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     No, I wouldn't say that.     It's easy to talk about it afterwards, but&#13;
it seemed to me the aim of the study was the study itself.           Whereas you&#13;
could have said that the aim might be to prepare the local bodies to carry&#13;
on, and not be so elaborate with the study.           But there were a lot of&#13;
problems.        There were problems between states in Pakistan, as to their&#13;
control of water and so forth.        So I had the impression, trying to look&#13;
back at it a bit, that it wasn't really focused on action in the same way&#13;
as it might have been.        I don't know, that may be ambiguous.     But there was&#13;
a study and it stood.        It was three volumes.*     But there was no real&#13;
expectation that you could follow up.           First of all, it took too much&#13;
money, and there was a great problem of the overrun cost of the Tarbela&#13;
Dam.    There were other things that meant that the level of investment was&#13;
such that they couldn't reach it and so forth.           But I'm thinking of it as&#13;
kind of parallel to the Bell mission--that these were big things.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     I understand.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     Afterwards the concern was much more regular dealing.       You dealt&#13;
through the existing Bank structure of departments.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     Was there a series of sub-projects, so to speak: irrigation&#13;
projects, aqueducts, what have you, that followed on from the Tarbela Dam?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     Yes.    Well, there certainly was a lot done following on, but my&#13;
impression was that the focus ...      Well, for instance, the focus was on&#13;
&#13;
*Pieter Lieftinck, Robert A. Sadove, and Thomas C. Creyke, Water and Power&#13;
Resources in West Pakistan: A Study in Sector Planning, 3 vols., Baltimore,&#13;
Johns Hopkins Press, 1969.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NOTE: This partially edited transcript has been reviewed by and&#13;
incorporates changes made by the memorialist, and is made available for the&#13;
sole use of the World Bank History Project, 10/21/91.&#13;
&amp;#12;BOHR                                     -21-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
WAPDA (Water and Power Development Authority], which was the big&#13;
organization.      The Bank was concerned about improving WAPDA's operation,&#13;
but it wasn't lending very much in the 1970s, so the contact was loose and&#13;
the impact was not as strong as it might have been.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     It may have been one of George Woods' frustrations in the middle&#13;
1960s that he was not able to raise more money for IDA Replenishments, some&#13;
of which might have gone for doing what you are suggesting.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:       I was a member of the mission that reexamined the lending for&#13;
Pakistan over 20 years.        The report was done last year, and John Lewis was&#13;
the head of that mission.        It's more clear about the things than I am&#13;
suggesting.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     You mean John Lewis was in charge of the report?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     Right.   I did the power part and there were other people doing other&#13;
parts.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     This is a report that is available in the Bank?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     Yes, that's right.     In the Operations Evaluation Department.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     What other events of the 1960s, as far as your own personal&#13;
connection with the Bank, stand out in your memory?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     Well, for me the 1960s were pretty much taken up by India.        There&#13;
was some reorganization that took place at that time of the economics work.&#13;
While we were in India [Irving] Friedman became economic head and Avramovic&#13;
was put in charge of another group.       That happened while I was there.      It&#13;
never worked very smoothly, that arrangement.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NOTE: This partially edited transcript has been reviewed by and&#13;
incorporates changes made by the memorialist, and is made available for the&#13;
sole use of the World Bank History Project, 10/21/91.&#13;
&amp;#12;BOHR                                   -22-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Now I associate Woods with a number of things in the Bank.         One was&#13;
enlarging the economics work, building it up in size and so forth.         The&#13;
other was connections, making agreements with FAO and other UN agencies to&#13;
operate together.     He had this phrase, "A horse and rabbit pie," and he&#13;
expected a little bit of rabbit at least; he wanted some contribution from&#13;
FAO in the joint things.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     I'm not sure I totally understand the horse and rabbit part.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     One horse, one rabbit.   It's the size of the ingredients.     The Bank&#13;
would be putting in most but the FAO has to put in something, I mean not&#13;
nothing, not just a plain horse pie.       It's going to be ...&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     Yes, I understand.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     He had a salty way of talking.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    I also remember something in the attempt to get the Bank involved in&#13;
fertilizer.     This is an issue we were concerned with on the Bell mission.&#13;
The Bank had a position of only going into private sector fertilizer.          But&#13;
a lot of Indian plants were some kind of public sector, some were state,&#13;
some were different public companies.         I was involved in some work on&#13;
fertilizer, together with David Dodd, who came out from the Bank, who was a&#13;
very able engineer.     We did a study of the fertilizer industry and where&#13;
the new plants should come and so forth.        We felt that if the Bank was&#13;
really going to help with fertilizer, it had to get involved with the&#13;
public sector.     I know one reason I felt was that fertilizer was almost&#13;
like a public utility; you can't get into the country and make a lot of&#13;
money off the farmers.     You're going to be held down for one reason or&#13;
another.     Well, Bernie was involved in this, and Bernie had some dealings&#13;
with Woods on this.     He would be the one to say about it, but that was an&#13;
issue at that time and eventually the Bank did get involved in the public&#13;
sector.&#13;
&#13;
NOTE: This partially edited transcript has been reviewed by and&#13;
incorporates changes made by the memorialist, and is made available for the&#13;
sole use of the World Bank History Project, 10/21/91.&#13;
&amp;#12;BOHR                                     -23-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       I was in India when the fertilizer mission came out.     These fellows&#13;
were originally from the private part of the Bank, IFC [International&#13;
Finance Corporation], and they wrote a report which was pretty critical.&#13;
In fact the Indians said, "Are these people serious about wanting to make a&#13;
loan?"     I remember being involved in this and it was difficult because some&#13;
of the Bank people expected the public sector could just shift and change&#13;
quickly because they said so.      But the public sector in this case had been&#13;
through a recent reorganization, had been through a lot of stuff, and I&#13;
knew what they were telling our people, but our people didn't understand&#13;
what they were being told.      But eventually we did get into the public&#13;
sector.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:    Well, do you feel that the work of the Bank, in part of the 1960s&#13;
at least, was impeded by Woods' own predilection towards private ownership&#13;
and operation, as I know he was.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     I don't think so.   I think he was the one that shifted finally.      He&#13;
was a little reluctant, and I think now this shift should be cautious.          I'm&#13;
more aware of the problems of public sector than I was before I got&#13;
involved with it.     But when I'm thinking of things, the Bank did quite a&#13;
bit in India over the period that I know.       I think some of the fertilizer&#13;
projects came out all right.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:    How about the IFC?   Was it very much involved in India?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     I don't know, I really had little contact with IFC.    I think they&#13;
were involved in one fertilizer plant in Uttar Pradesh but I don't know.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:    You recall Marty [Martin M.] Rosen ever being in your office, for&#13;
example?     Or anybody else from IFC?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NOTE: This partially edited transcript has been reviewed by and&#13;
incorporates changes made by the memorialist, and is made available for the&#13;
sole use of the World Bank History Project, 10/21/91.&#13;
&amp;#12;BOHR                                  -24-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     Well I remember dealing with IFC on some of the stuff that we'd done&#13;
on fertilizer, because they were interested.       They were involved in this&#13;
plant in Uttar Pradesh, which was a British subsidiary firm that made&#13;
explosives as well, I forget the company.       Maybe they became more involved&#13;
later.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     How about other industries besides fertilizer?    Was the Bank much&#13;
involved in industry in India?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     Well, one of their large involvements was through what they call&#13;
maintenance imports.     And this came out of the Bell mission.    The argument&#13;
was that the reason the industry isn't growing, is they have a shortage of&#13;
spare parts and all kinds of odds and ends.       So we don't need new projects,&#13;
we need financing for the things to make the existing plants go.        The first&#13;
mission on this, the maintenance import mission, was a very interesting one&#13;
let by Hans Fuchs.     It was very thorough.    They went around to all these&#13;
industries and they rated companies as to how good they were, what their&#13;
problems were, and so forth.     You sort of got the Good Housekeeping Seal of&#13;
Approval so you could have access to imports.      Well, I always felt this&#13;
work was not followed up enough because I remember seeing these early&#13;
reports, and I think it would have been exciting to see what happened to&#13;
these companies.     At the time, the Bank was pressing to loosen the&#13;
regulations, cut down on the constraints and the allocation of materials&#13;
and so forth.     It would be interesting to see how the economy responded to&#13;
that.     I always thought that was a missed opportunity.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    We had missions come out looking at industry in general and then&#13;
lending for maintenance imports.     But later on they became rather&#13;
perfunctory.    They didn't have the capacity to look at the industries and&#13;
see what was happening.     But I know one of the Indian officials, S. S.&#13;
Marathe, who we worked with very much.       We both thought, "Gee, if you get&#13;
those old reports and see what happened, you'd begin to understand."        I had&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NOTE: This partially edited transcript has been reviewed by and&#13;
incorporates changes made by the memorialist, and is made available for the&#13;
sole use of the World Bank History Project, 10/21/91.&#13;
&amp;#12;BOHR                                  -25-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
felt that we did not do a good job in analyzing industry in India.         Ye'd do&#13;
pieces and then the cast would change and we'd do another piece.       I&#13;
remember reading reports after I came back, in 1972, maybe, and I'd think,&#13;
"My gosh, the same old stuff, the same old ideas that the problem is a need&#13;
for private management.     Some of the cliches of what we always said, but&#13;
not really deep enough to be really helpful," I thought.      And I felt that&#13;
the continuity was not what it might have been.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    You've got to get somebody excited about it that's in position for a&#13;
long period of time.    Yhile I was in India there was a survey of industry&#13;
made with Bevan Waide and a group.     I remember at the time saying, "Well we&#13;
don't need that; this is what we need.       We're at this point in&#13;
understanding industry."    This was for the Fourth Plan.     "Yhat we really&#13;
need to know are these things here.    Yhy not concentrate on that?"       But,&#13;
Gil [William L Gilmartin] would say, "Look, it's a big country.       There's&#13;
room for everybody."    Well, they come in and they go over the whole thing&#13;
and massage the data again and come up with something else, but it's very&#13;
hard to build on stuff in an organization.       That's been my experience in&#13;
the Bank.     I did feel that we could have known more about industry, and we&#13;
could have contributed more by being tougher on certain things, but knowing&#13;
why we were tough and building support in the country.      There were very&#13;
able guys in the Indian government and they would have the same feeling.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Yhen I was in Delhi, I remember the Secretary concerned with industry&#13;
and regulations saying, "Look, when you go out in the country, tell us what&#13;
things are like, we can't get out of the office, you know.      Tell us how it&#13;
is out there."    We were in a working partnership to some extent, and I&#13;
guess that can go too far and there seemed to the a policy to change field&#13;
staff every so often.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     It sounds like you personally had quite good relationships with&#13;
your counterparts in the Indian Government.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NOTE: This partially edited transcript has been reviewed by and&#13;
incorporates changes made by the memorialist, and is made available for the&#13;
sole use of the World Bank History Project, 10/21/91.&#13;
&amp;#12;BOHR                                     -26-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     Yes, I did.    Yes, I had good relationships with them.     I had a time&#13;
not knowing who was the most difficult to deal with, the Indian Government&#13;
or the Bank.     We had our problems with delays in shipping stuff.      We were&#13;
out there, moved to India, and they never shipped our stuff until quite&#13;
late.     Luckily we had brought enough with us so we didn't freeze.       It gets&#13;
quite cold in Delhi in the winter, but we had a feeling of dealing with two&#13;
kind of bureaucracies.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     Can you comment on the reputation within the Indian Government of&#13;
the World Bank?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     I think in my time, when Gil was there--Gil was a very able fellow&#13;
and very intelligent and not excitable--we had good relations.         I think we&#13;
had good relations.       And I think that office which we built up at that time&#13;
has done well.      Now there've been variations in the people that they're had&#13;
there, but generally they've had good people.         I was back last year for a&#13;
few days, and people said the present fellow, who is Bevan Waide, whom I&#13;
knew, was great.        I mean, the Government really comes to him.   I think they&#13;
have put good people in that office.         Now it's considered a plum, but when&#13;
we first went there people wanted to avoid going to India because of health&#13;
reasons and other things.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     I think there was a time shortly after the Bell report became&#13;
semi-public, at least, when both Bell and Woods had relatively bad press in&#13;
India.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     Yes.   I think that's true, yes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     Can you comment on that period and whether it passed fairly&#13;
quickly?     Were there some lingering overtones?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NOTE: This partially edited transcript has been reviewed by and&#13;
incorporates changes made by the memorialist, and is made available for the&#13;
sole use of the World Bank History Project, 10/21/91.&#13;
&amp;#12;BOHR                                     Â·27Â·&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     I can't say much except that I knew, and other people had said, that&#13;
Gil being there and contributed to improved relations.        I wasn't raising&#13;
any fights and I didn't get involved in this thing very much.          I know Gil&#13;
was very highly respected.        I think that we weathered that.   Ve also had&#13;
people we knew there a long time, a long time.        I'd known I.G. Patel when&#13;
he was with the Monetary Fund many, many years ago.        When we first came to&#13;
Washington, he lived with a classmate of mine and used to come to the&#13;
house.     My little children used to talk about Bob and I.G.       This was back&#13;
in the 1950s.       Well, I.G. is way up there now.   I knew him, he knew me.       It&#13;
wasn't that we were strangers, and that didn't hurt.        The Bell mission&#13;
threw us very closely in with a lot of people in the government.          It was a&#13;
great introduction to being in the office.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     Was your training as an engineer sufficient in detail to permit&#13;
you to make detailed investigations of individual plants, let's say?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     No, no.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     Accounting systems?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     No.   The only thing I would say is that my training made me less&#13;
reluctant to tackle technical subjects and made me very sensitive to data.&#13;
I've never quite gotten used to the cavalier way economists use data&#13;
without any concern for the significance of the figures or anything.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     May I say, neither have I.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     Okay, okay.    I've often felt I'm really not an economist.     I listen&#13;
to these chaps talk, but I have a hangÂ·up on significance of data.         If you&#13;
add two things together you don't add things that are vastly different in&#13;
their accuracy and expect that the total means anythingÂ·Â·or multiply them.&#13;
I'm sort of cautious in that sort of thing.       Otherwise, the training was&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NOTE: This partially edited transcript has been reviewed by and&#13;
incorporates changes made by the memorialist, and is made available for the&#13;
sole use of the World Bank History Project, 10/21/91.&#13;
&amp;#12;BOHR                                    -28-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
more theoretical.       Actually, metallurgical engineering is what my degree&#13;
was in.     I can appreciate steel plants and things like that.      I know a&#13;
little bit about it, but it didn't really do much.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     Well, have we said as much about India as you would like to say?&#13;
Today at least?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     I think so.    It was a good experience.    For a period of about ten&#13;
years, I spent about half the time in India.         This was, say from 1965 to&#13;
1975.     When I was involved in Calcutta it was three missions a year.         I&#13;
spent a lot of time in India.       There was a long period after which I went&#13;
to the Operations Evaluation Department.       Then I was back in India again,&#13;
in Calcutta, on an evaluation assignment once.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     I would appreciate it if you would say a bit about that phase of&#13;
your career also.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     Well, the way it happened, I reached the job that I wanted in the&#13;
Bank, which was economic advisor.       When I was young in the Bank, or in the&#13;
early days, that was the chief economic position in the different&#13;
departments.      I was Economic Advisor in the Urban Projects Department.&#13;
Then there was the reorganization and ...&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     This was the McNamara reorganization?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     Yes.   But there were some others.   There was that, but there was&#13;
something else, too, because Sadove was moved out and [Edward V.K.] Jatcox,&#13;
a young man, came in as head of the department with his people.         There was&#13;
one other guy about my age, but most of them were young people.         I was at&#13;
the level of a division chief.       Suddenly, they abolished my job.    Usually&#13;
you abolish the job and then later on you put the guy in that you want, but&#13;
meanwhile the fellow whose job is abolished is sent someplace.          I had done&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NOTE: This partially edited transcript has been reviewed by and&#13;
incorporates changes made by the memorialist, and is made available for the&#13;
sole use of the World Bank History Project, 10/21/91.&#13;
&amp;#12;BOHR                                  -29-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
the Calcutta work as the economic advisor to the department.       I was not in&#13;
a division.     This turned out to be a little awkward because I didn't have&#13;
the command of any people, I had to go around begging people.       It was&#13;
difficult to work like that.     I needed more help and I had to find out how&#13;
to get it.     I wasn't the division chief, but I was in the division.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      Well, when Jaycox came and said: "Look, you can keep your position, but&#13;
do you want to go into another division, or something?"       I saw that the&#13;
time was limited, but I decided to stay.     I stayed with it until I thought&#13;
we were getting close to the second phase of Calcutta.       Then I bowed out of&#13;
it.     One place that I could go that sounded interesting was Operations&#13;
Evaluation.     This sort of completes a cycle.   Here you're looking at&#13;
projects from the back, ex post.     I found this an intriguing thing, an&#13;
interesting thing, because I had my own comments and criticisms on how&#13;
things were done.     Now you could do it in a formal sense; you could look&#13;
back.    Well, I was hired by [Christopher] Willoughby.     At that time&#13;
[Mohamed] Shoaib was in Mervyn's [Weiner] position as Director General&#13;
Operations Evaluation, but Shoaib died, or before he died I think Mervyn&#13;
took over and Willoughby left and [ShivS.] Kapur came in as head of that&#13;
department.     I was the senior person.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      Well, in Operations Evaluation the subject was interesting, but the&#13;
work was difficult.     It was difficult because we were not organized in&#13;
divisions.     We had all kinds of charts and how many things you had to keep&#13;
track of and how many things to turn out.     I ended up doing an awful lot of&#13;
writing of lousy stuff.     You couldn't make it first class but you could get&#13;
it through, a lot of that.     I was not the head and I wasn't doing the work&#13;
in the field, I was in the impossible position of being at that&#13;
intermediate level concerned with editing papers.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      Two interesting things happened during that period.     One, I took over a&#13;
study which someone else had started on delays in implementation.          Well, I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NOTE: This partially edited transcript has been reviewed by and&#13;
incorporates changes made by the memorialist, and is made available for the&#13;
sole use of the World Bank History Project, 10/21/91.&#13;
&amp;#12;BOHR                                  -30-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
got terribly involved in this study; I guess too much involved,      I had felt&#13;
that I was the research fellow and I was in this department where people&#13;
didn't understand how to deal with data and all this stuff.      I must say I&#13;
tried too hard on this.     But it was fascinating, why projects were delayed&#13;
and why projects didn't work out as you expected.      You could trace it to&#13;
poor preparation in the sense of not realistically knowing the reaction of&#13;
people who have to react to make the project work, like farmers.      You've&#13;
got a big project and you're assuming a whole lot of things are going to&#13;
happen but you don't have control; it's a whole area that you don't have&#13;
control of and you just assume, you don't really know.     A lot of it had to&#13;
do with preparation, unreality in the Bank, things that I had another way&#13;
of feeling about.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Well we had a little trouble with that project because Kapur didn't&#13;
like the way I had dealt with it.     I was tired.   Finally, he rewrote a big&#13;
long beginning to it.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    One of the points of criticism was my treatment of time.      I had a&#13;
little part saying that the Bank thinks of time in a very continous way,&#13;
but to the borrower time is often seen differently.     There is a time to do&#13;
things.    Also, if you're executing a project and you're going to execute it&#13;
in a certain place, you could be concerned with the reaction of those&#13;
people.     The Bank isn't concerned with that.   The Bank wants to get it done&#13;
in a hurry, but you've got to live in this situation, so the concepts of&#13;
time are different.     There also is a kind of a corning and going, the kind&#13;
of a circular sense of time, corning back, going to the village, corning&#13;
back.     Change comes little by little by little, and the concept of time in&#13;
the world is not the concept that the Bank works with, this linear time.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Well that couldn't go, I assume, because McNamara is stickler on time.&#13;
He says, "Look, if you're late, you're losing."      I could say, "No, you're&#13;
not necessarily losing.     You may have something else that's more important&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NOTE: This partially edited transcript has been reviewed by and&#13;
incorporates changes made by the memorialist, and is made available for the&#13;
sole use of the World Bank History Project, 10/21/91.&#13;
&amp;#12;BOHR                                     -31-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
to push ahead."        This issue of time was taken out.   This was one of the&#13;
issues where the department felt we couldn't be critical, because if you&#13;
took what I was trying to say, the whole idea of scheduling was affected,&#13;
gets loosened up more.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     Can that sort of difference in looking at time be taken into&#13;
account when programming the evolution of the process?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     I thought so.     One of the things we found, was that the average time&#13;
was very different by sectors.        Nobody seemed to know this.   The project&#13;
director thought the difference among sectors averaged out.         No, the&#13;
slowest are the education projects, and you know why when you look at them.&#13;
They are projects that average this long to implement this and this and&#13;
this.     There's a whole different pattern.      I think since that study people&#13;
have been more conscious of this.        There's been more sensitivity to that.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    But I had difficulty because here I was with all this material that I&#13;
would have loved to have had when I started out in the Bank, and we're not&#13;
able to exploit it as far as I think it should be exploited,         I was just&#13;
thinking of how you learn about what happens.         That was one characteristic,&#13;
one frustration of that period.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     Did you convince Kapur eventually of your point of view?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     No, not particularly.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     No?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     No.     This was a tenuous thing.   McNamara was sitting up there&#13;
looking, and you had to figure out rates of returns for everything, and you&#13;
had to write an annual report.        I also had troubles with style.   There is a&#13;
bureaucratic way to operate.        You want to write a report that gives the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NOTE: This partially edited transcript has been reviewed by and&#13;
incorporates changes made by the memorialist, and is made available for the&#13;
sole use of the World Bank History Project, 10/21/91.&#13;
&amp;#12;BOHR                                   -32-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
impression that you as an evaluation department have done lots of work and&#13;
see lots of trouble but still, things are pretty good.        That's a technique,&#13;
and Kapur was a very excellent writer.        I was trying to get it clear and it&#13;
didn't work.     I was trying to clarify a complicated system.     I was trying&#13;
to bring it down.     Our styles were not compatible, so there was some&#13;
trouble there.     I mean, I felt that I was ... Sometimes when you collaborate&#13;
the result is better; sometimes when you collaborate the result isn't&#13;
improved because the points of view and styles of the collaborators don't&#13;
go well together.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Anyway, one of the things I did, I went to Berkeley.        I took a study&#13;
leave for three months, four months.      That was about the best thing I did&#13;
during that period.     I found that what I was really excited about was&#13;
political science.     I read.   I wrote a paper, "Seeking Perspective".    I was&#13;
concerned about the process of projects, how projects get done.        I read a&#13;
whole literature I didn't know existed.       I read something called The&#13;
Implementation Game by a chap up in Berkeley, and I read Wildavsky and&#13;
Hirschman, who I've always been reading, and Lindblom's stuff on politics&#13;
and Usable Knowledge, by Lindblom and Cohen, things like that.        I got very&#13;
excited about the work that's been done and is being done on the process of&#13;
change, how change takes place, which is what projects are about.        I got&#13;
much more of interest from the political scientists who were working in the&#13;
field than from the economists; the economists, I've heard all they have to&#13;
say, and it's rather limited.     I got excited about this.    I got very&#13;
interested in it.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     Economists do not handle time very well in their models.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     No.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     What period is it that you're now talking about?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NOTE: This partially edited transcript has been reviewed by and&#13;
incorporates changes made by the memorialist, and is made available for the&#13;
sole use of the World Bank History Project, 10/21/91.&#13;
&amp;#12;BOHR                                    Â·33-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     I went to Berkeley in 1980.   And I retired in 1982.    I had to pay&#13;
the Bank back something, but by 1982 I had been in the Bank 32 years.          I&#13;
was 62.     And I had to figure, I don't really need this; I'm not enjoying&#13;
this editing work, and I would rather do contract work, do a complete piece&#13;
of work.     So I retired in 1982 and did some work afterwards.    I did a piece&#13;
on evaluation for the EDI which they didn't like or, at best to my&#13;
knowledge, didn't use.      I read more about evaluation after I left the&#13;
department, about what had been done by the GAO (General Accounting Office]&#13;
and the American experience and so forth.      I tried to relate evaluation on&#13;
a personal level to things you can evaluate and things you can't, like you&#13;
can't evaluate how well you raise your children, there's no way to measure;&#13;
but you can evaluate a test.      The same thing with these projects.   Some&#13;
projects are set up so it's easy; some projects are not easy to evaluate.&#13;
And also why you need an outsider, because you can't judge your own work&#13;
objectively.     I tried to relate evaluation to how it is as a personal&#13;
thing, because it isn't just bureaucratic.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    I also did an evaluation of a planning project in the Philippines and&#13;
this stuff in Pakistan, and then I just finished doing a project completion&#13;
report on another Calcutta project.      I don't do very much, just a couple of&#13;
weeks a year.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     So you're still doing consulting for the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     Yes, a little, right.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     I'm relieved.   It sounds to me like the experience that you had&#13;
should be very valuable to the Bank, particularly in special cases.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     Well, maybe.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NOTE: This partially edited transcript has been reviewed by and&#13;
incorporates changes made by the memorialist, and is made available for the&#13;
sole use of the World Bank History Project, 10/21/91.&#13;
&amp;#12;BOHR                                  -34-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     May we go full circle and come back again now at the end of our&#13;
conversation to your beginnings in the Bank?     What were some of the initial&#13;
assignments that you had when you were in the Research or Economics&#13;
Departments?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     Well, Rosenstein-Rodan wanted me to work on criteria for projects,&#13;
for the selection of industrial projects, and I did a paper.      That's the&#13;
paper that was published in the Review of Economic Statistics.       It started&#13;
with things he'd done, and then I got other kinds of criteria, not just&#13;
capital, but size and skills and things like that, and locational patterns.&#13;
There was some very interesting stuff done in this country on locational&#13;
patterns: which activities are spread and which activities are&#13;
concentrated.    You can infer from that a lot about industrial cost.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Then there was a period in economics when lots of little odds and ends&#13;
jobs used to come in.    We weren't a really high class operation.    We did&#13;
what had to be done.     We would look up different industries.   The next&#13;
thing I spent time on, if I remember, was the aluminum industry.      I did a&#13;
study of the world aluminum industry which was meant as a back-up thing for&#13;
a loan for an aluminum smelter in Africa.     This was quite good, I mean, it&#13;
was a lot.     I had to make estimates of the Russians, the Africans, the&#13;
Europeans, assuming how long it takes and how much lead time.      I felt&#13;
pretty good about it, and people who really knew the stuff in the Bank said&#13;
it was okay, so that was all right.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Then there was a period on electric power.     We were concerned that&#13;
people were using a simple, double-every-ten-years estimate for the growth&#13;
in electric power consumption.     Sadove had come to the department at that&#13;
point.    This was around 1960.   And we put together a paper on the demand&#13;
for electric power which the project people didn't want to have published.&#13;
They thought somebody could get it and quote it back at them.      It wasn't&#13;
their work, although their people did use it.     We had put together a lot of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NOTE: This partially edited transcript has been reviewed by and&#13;
incorporates changes made by the memorialist, and is made available for the&#13;
sole use of the World Bank History Project, 10/21/91.&#13;
&amp;#12;BOHR                                   -35-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
information on levels of consumption relating it to different kinds of&#13;
situations.     We had little formulas and stuff like that.    It was a big&#13;
effort, a pioneering effort, but it never ended up as a final paper.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       Then I got involved in survey missions.    The first survey mission was&#13;
1953.     I wasn't in the Bank long.   I went to British Guiana and I did the&#13;
piece on industry, mining and power, which wasn't much.       It's a little&#13;
bitty country, but it was exciting to go there.       Next after the power work,&#13;
I went to Yugoslavia with Andy (Andrew M.] Kamarck--the second mission to&#13;
Yugoslavia in 1960 after they'd been involved and then the Bank had been&#13;
out.     I did a price on the power industry in Yugoslavia, background for a&#13;
lending operation--a very nice mission with Andy.       He's a very good mission&#13;
leader, and it was a very nice mission.       In 1961 I was called in late to do&#13;
the industry piece for the Spanish survey mission.       The man they had was an&#13;
industrialist, and he didn't quite grasp what they wanted.       I had to come&#13;
in late and sort of pick up the pieces.       I was there for about two months.&#13;
It's a book: The Economic Development of Spain.*&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       After that there was a job in the Philippines with Drag [Dragoslav&#13;
Avramovic] on industrial criteria, a part of his mission.       And there was a&#13;
job in Venezuela.     This was interesting.   We were asked about the appraisal&#13;
of a big hydroelectric project, and this was the first time where I had&#13;
been on a mission where we had two from the Economics Department and two&#13;
from the Projects Department; two engineers, Fred [Frederick] Howell and&#13;
John Lithgow, two economists, Herman van der Tak and I.       We had the problem&#13;
of how to appraise a big dam where the power won't come in for 20 years.&#13;
We got into discounting and, in our hotel room, with an adding machine--we&#13;
didn't have a computer--worked out the flows from alternative ways of&#13;
developing this power source using gas or hydro, what is the price of gas,&#13;
all that kind of stuff.     No one had actually dealt with this tremendous&#13;
&#13;
*The Economic Development of Spain. Baltimore:      The Johns Hopkins&#13;
University Press, 1963.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NOTE: This partially edited transcript has been reviewed by and&#13;
incorporates changes made by the memorialist, and is made available for the&#13;
sole use of the World Bank History Project, 10/21/91.&#13;
&amp;#12;BOHR&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
issue of time in this kind of a project, to my knowledge, in the Bank.             The&#13;
question the head of the Projects Department asked was, "Well, what's it&#13;
like in ten years?"       Ten years, nothing.     I mean, the problem is it takes&#13;
so long to build it, if you use a high discount rate you're gone.          You&#13;
forget about it.     But we got an eight percent discount.       Out of that&#13;
project came a paper which van der Tak wrote.          He was in my division. and&#13;
he wrote the paper on evaluation of hydroelectric projects, which was a&#13;
theoretical kind of a treatment of what we did.         After that it was into the&#13;
Indian stuff.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     Well, you've had a wide variety of experiences in the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     Yes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     Are there some questions about your total experience in the Bank&#13;
that I should have asked you and I haven't asked?&#13;
BOHR:     I don't know.   When we came it was pretty small.      I came in 1950.&#13;
It's clear in my mind and I noted in the notes that I had tried to write,&#13;
when I came back to the Bank from India in 1970 that I had a hard time&#13;
coming back into the Bank.       I don't think I ever came back into it very&#13;
well.     I was 50 in 1970 when I came back.      Economics was flying much&#13;
higher, and I have a kind of a reservation about this.         The thing that&#13;
interested me in my last years of the Bank were the process of change and&#13;
how you really look at the process.       That is interesting, and it's&#13;
certainly not something that you can get from just looking at economics.&#13;
And the Bank has been doing that, too.          I remember thinking about something&#13;
and then running into Francis Lethem, who was once a trainee with me.            I've&#13;
known him a long time, and he was working on the same thing and thinking in&#13;
a similar way.     This was a paper on the designing of rural projects,!&#13;
believe.     Some of the same ideas, the same approach, was starting to come&#13;
out from the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NOTE: This partially edited transcript has been reviewed by and&#13;
incorporates changes made by the memorialist, and is made available for the&#13;
sole use of the World Bank History Project, 10/21/91.&#13;
&amp;#12;BOHR                                     -37-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     When you say the process of change, are you talking about the&#13;
process of change in the developing countries?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     No.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     You're not talking about the process of change in the Bank itself?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     No, I'm not.     I find it difficult even to clearly comprehend how the&#13;
bureaucracy works.        I know I found it when I came back to the Bank.   I&#13;
remember writing a memo to [Hollis] Chenery, a big discussion of policy.&#13;
My point was really, isn't the issue of policy something for the people&#13;
that are going to have the policy?        I mean that we not just sort of decide&#13;
what's right policy.        I have trouble with that.   I have trouble with the&#13;
concept which I sensed in the Bank during the McNamara period, that there's&#13;
no problem that we can't solve if we put the brains to it.         We can deal&#13;
with any problem if we think about it and get the smartest people to deal&#13;
with it.        I just don't believe that at all.   I found that philosophically I&#13;
was out of touch with the general trend in the Bank and people seemed to&#13;
have followed general trends.        Where I was in the Bank, I found it&#13;
intellectually not very exciting toward the last period.         People were so&#13;
busy doing things or seeing what the boss wants or carrying out the&#13;
program.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     Are you implying amongst other things that the Bank became too&#13;
much involved in trying to impose programs and conditions on the member&#13;
countries rather than working with situations in the countries?         If so, it&#13;
sounds similar to what Bernie Bell was saying.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     I would say so, yes.     I have been places where the local officials&#13;
told me that they had had missions that never listened.        They just talked&#13;
the whole time.       Others have been told, "Why, you're the first person to&#13;
ever listen to us."        This kind of issue.   For one thing, the Bank was tied&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NOTE: This partially edited transcript has been reviewed by and&#13;
incorporates changes made by the memorialist, and is made available for the&#13;
sole use of the World Bank History Project, 10/21/91.&#13;
&amp;#12;BOHR                                  -38-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
up with these schedules, and time is a big thing in this.      If you go out&#13;
you can't play around. you've got to get the project.      In the early days&#13;
you didn't have to get a project.     If they didn't have a good project, you&#13;
wouldn't make a loan, but once we're tied into programs the whole game&#13;
changes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     Once you got a five-year schedule pushing the money out, you have&#13;
to get the project ready on time.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     Yes, I also sense another thing.   I have the feeling that I never&#13;
completely understood some aspects of the Bank's operations.      I saw a real&#13;
conflict between project lending and the goal of transferring funds.         This&#13;
was clear.     You had Chenery and his people talking at one level, and the&#13;
projects prople talking at another level.     In the old days we used to say,&#13;
"Well, you want a project, you send Joe out; he's easy an appraisals.         If&#13;
you want no project you send Jim because he'll be much more tough."        But&#13;
there is a conflict between whether you were concerned with transferring&#13;
funds or doing project work.     Then you look at the projects, as I did in&#13;
the delay study and the money isn't moving.     If projects aren't good,&#13;
nothing happens.     The project is committed but there's no money going at&#13;
all.    This is very slow.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     Did this point that you're now making ever get considered by the&#13;
Operations Evaluation people?     Can it be shown by studying projects that&#13;
some of them turn out less well than had been hoped because they were&#13;
pushed too fast and too soon?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     We tried to do that with this delay study.   I think we did.   We had&#13;
a list of things that we thought were contributing factors, and a lot of it&#13;
implied that.     I think maybe some of that got edited out of the paper, but&#13;
I had the feeling that there was a conflict always in this.      Sometimes you&#13;
swing too far one way and sometimes too far the other.      I think I even&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NOTE: This partially edited transcript has been reviewed by and&#13;
incorporates changes made by the memorialist, and is made available for the&#13;
sole use of the World Bank History Project, 10/21/91.&#13;
&amp;#12;BOHR                                     -39-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
stated it, but our people weren't ready to talk about conflicts or that&#13;
kind of thing.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     If I wanted to find this paper another time, how would I identify&#13;
it?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     The delay study?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     Yes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     OED, Delay in Project Implementation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     What date approximately?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     Oh it must be 1980.    Oh, yes around 1980.    There is a list of all&#13;
the papers done by the Operations Evaluation Department, the whole thing,&#13;
there's a list of everything.       They bring out a catalog, and it would be&#13;
there.     I don't say it's a great paper.      It's not a very long paper.&#13;
That's the thing.      It's quite brief.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     Something to be said for that.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     Oh, yes, I tell you.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     Well I appreciate ever so much your going so far out of your way&#13;
today to make our conversation possible.        I have enjoyed it and profited&#13;
from it very much.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BOHR:     Well, I appreciate that you are interested enough to come up.       It's&#13;
nice to see you again, and I kind of enjoy talking about this.         It helps to&#13;
get one's mind straightened out.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     Sure.   Thank you so much.&#13;
&#13;
NOTE: This partially edited transcript has been reviewed by and&#13;
incorporates changes made by the memorialist, and is made available for the&#13;
sole use of the World Bank History Project, 10/21/91.&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="17968845">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1986/07/17968845/transcript-oral-history-interview-kenneth-bohr-held-july-13-1986
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1986/07/17968845/transcript-oral-history-interview-kenneth-bohr-held-july-13-1986</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1986/07/17968845/transcript-oral-history-interview-kenneth-bohr-held-july-13-1986</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2013-07-05T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2013-07-05T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2013/07/05/000442464_20130705151546/Rendered/INDEX/789440TRN0Bohr0erview0July013001986.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2013/07/05/000442464_20130705151546/Rendered/PDF/789440TRN0Bohr0erview0July013001986.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2013-07-05T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1986-07-13T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Transcript of oral history interview with
            Kenneth Bohr held on July 13, 1986
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            In July 1986, Kenneth Bohr was
            interviewed on behalf of the World Bank Group Archives oral
            history program by Robert W. Oliver. During his tenure at
            the Bank from 1950 to 1982, Mr. Bohr worked in the following
            areas: in India as a deputy resident representative of
            resident mission (1950-1970); in the economics department,
            industry division, as chief (1970-1971); in the urban
            projects department as an urban economics advisor
            (1972-1973); in the transportation and urban projects
            department as a senior urban specialist (1973-1975); and in
            the operations evaluation department as chief evaluations
            officer (1975-1982). After serving in the office of the
            World Bank in India, he wrote a paper that was published as
            a review of the economic statistics of the country for the
            public sector for the economics department. He is working as
            consultant to the World Bank. His transcript focuses on his
            discussion about industry privatization in India.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Transcript of oral history interview with
            Kenneth Bohr held on July 13, 1986
        </docna>
        <display_title>Transcript of oral history
            interview with Kenneth Bohr held on July 13, 1986</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/1986/07/17968845/transcript-oral-history-interview-kenneth-bohr-held-july-13-1986</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Transcript</docty>
        <subtopic>Public Sector Corruption &amp;
            Anticorruption Measures,Banks &amp; Banking Reform,Corporate Law,Sustainable Land and Crop Management,Hazard Risk Management</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Rural Development,Law and Development,Public Sector Development,Urban Development</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000442464_20130705151546</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>World Bank Group Archives oral history program</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Rural Development,Law and Development,Public Sector Development,Urban Development</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Board Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Accounting, Accounting systems, businessmen,
            chain of command, company, Corporation, economics, ex post,
            explosives, farmers, generators, investigations, limited,
            managers, negotiation, partnership, private ownership,
            public companies, reorganization, riot, slums, subsidiary, war
        </keywd>
        <owner>Knowledge &amp; Information Services (ITSKI)</owner>
        <repnb>78944</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Industry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Science and Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Alternative Sentencing Options</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community based Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Correctional Services and Facilities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corrections</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime and Society</ml:concept><ml:concept>Defense Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Detention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enforcement Policies and Oversight Mechanism</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigative Task Force Police</ml:concept><ml:concept>Juvenile Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Law Enforcement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Offender Reintegration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Administration and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Problem solving Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Prosecution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Restorative Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Therapeutic Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Assistance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim-Offender Mediation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crops</ml:concept><ml:concept>Asset Recovery</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Electric Power</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Engineering</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Industrial Economics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Criminal Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Middle-class</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fertilizers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Airports</ml:concept><ml:concept>Adaptation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>