<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>ï»¿                                                        Copy_ o f _ Copies&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                        Classification: OH/_ __&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                78964&#13;
                                                                v2&#13;
&#13;
      The World Bank/IFC Archives&#13;
&#13;
                 Oral History Program&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                  Transcript of interview with&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                           WILLIAM CLARK&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                  lJate:   October 4. 1983&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
B;v&#13;
 r&#13;
      _____________~Pallt~r~ic~iaa~B~laa,uÂ·r~----------------&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            PRINfED AND REPRODUCED ON ACID FREE PAPER&#13;
&amp;#12;BLAIR: Today is Tuesday, October 4, 1983.     My name is Patricia Blair, and I&#13;
&#13;
have with me William Clark, who retired from the Bank in April 1980, after&#13;
&#13;
twelve years, first as Director of Information and Public Affairs, and then as&#13;
&#13;
Director and Vice President for External Relations.     Before joining the Bank,&#13;
&#13;
Mr. Clark, who is British, was Director of the Overseas Development Institute&#13;
&#13;
in London.    He is now President of the International Institute for Environment&#13;
&#13;
and Development, also in London.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          Today we will focus on the significance for the Bank of two major&#13;
&#13;
international commissions: the Pearson Commission of 1968-69, and the Brandt&#13;
&#13;
Commission a decade later.     Both Commissions were created at the suggestion of&#13;
&#13;
Bank Presidents, although the connection with the Pearson Commission was&#13;
&#13;
rather closer than that with the Brandt Commission.     Let's begin with the&#13;
&#13;
Pearson Commission.     Back in your days as head of the ODI, I gather that you&#13;
&#13;
had something to do with George Woods' original suggestion for a Grand&#13;
&#13;
Assize.    Did that have something to do with the week-end you spent with Woods&#13;
&#13;
and others at Sir Edward Boyle's house?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CLARK: Yes, to get right back to that period, 1967, Barbara Ward and Hans&#13;
&#13;
Singer had been writing the mid-term review of the First Development Decade,&#13;
&#13;
which was then known as the Development Decade and not the First Development&#13;
&#13;
Decade.     It became very apparent to them and to myself, who was advising&#13;
&#13;
Barbara on this, in part, that there was a great deal of 'aid fatigue', as&#13;
&#13;
it's now known, and that it was going to be difficult to get a second&#13;
&#13;
Development Decade going.    Parenthetically, I have always been against the&#13;
&#13;
phrase 'Development Decade,' because it's like saying 'The Fortnight for the&#13;
&amp;#12;                                           - 2 -&#13;
&#13;
 Revolution of the World'.     Things don't happen that way; they happen over a&#13;
&#13;
much longer period.     It would have been better if we had talked about the end&#13;
&#13;
of the 'Development Century', or something of that sort.        Now, this is&#13;
&#13;
relevant because, when the mid-term review was completed, I had some long&#13;
&#13;
conversations at the Overseas Development Institute with Barbara to discuss&#13;
&#13;
what we could do to help overcome the 'aid fatigue', which was most apparent&#13;
&#13;
in America but quite apparent in Britain, too, and what we could do to create&#13;
&#13;
some feeling that aid was a worthwhile endeavor.        As a result, I asked a few&#13;
&#13;
friends to meet with me at Edward Boyle's capacious house down in Sussex.            He,&#13;
&#13;
having been the Financial Secretary to the Treasury, was really responsible&#13;
&#13;
for getting the first Aid Department in the British Government set up.         (He&#13;
&#13;
was not made head of it, as many of us had hoped, but he was always&#13;
&#13;
interested.)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            As I was saying, we had this meeting to discuss what could be done,&#13;
&#13;
and I invited George Woods, whom I had got to know quite well through his&#13;
&#13;
coming to one of our annual ODI meetings in 1965; he was already in Europe, I&#13;
&#13;
think I'm right in saying, for an ACC (Administrative Committee on&#13;
&#13;
Coordination) meeting in Geneva.       I got both George Woods and Rene Maheu, then&#13;
                             van J,r   /(f.t &gt;sell~&#13;
head of UNESCO, and Axsel WanderhuscQeF, a German friend of mine much&#13;
&#13;
concerned with the equivalent to a Peace Corps in Germany, and Andrzej&#13;
/(r(Jff&amp;I&lt;/Tky&#13;
Krosefeloy, who was then the member of my staff at the ODI who was particularly&#13;
&#13;
concerned with rural development, which I had just started plugging, and who&#13;
&#13;
is now in the United Nations.     I think there were one or two others and of&#13;
&#13;
course, Barbara Ward, Lady Jackson.        We all met over a week-end in order to&#13;
&#13;
see what could be done by way of reviving interest in aid and development.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                       - 3 -&#13;
&#13;
           The suggestion which emerged from the conference as a whole was that&#13;
&#13;
we should try and move back to the enthusiasm of the Marshall Plan days.          All&#13;
&#13;
of us - myself and Barbara and George Woods, and less Rene Maheu, Axsel&#13;
&#13;
Wanderbuscher, who were from a somewhat younger generation - all had been&#13;
&#13;
touched enormously by the Marshall Plan, and our enthusiasm for something&#13;
&#13;
similar was really one of the prime things in our approach.         As a result, we&#13;
&#13;
agreed that what was necessary was to have something like the Franks&#13;
&#13;
Commission, which was set up in 1948 in Paris and which grew into the OECD.&#13;
&#13;
That is to say, we wanted a commission that would look into the broad&#13;
&#13;
possibilities and problems of the development scene: what is needed, how it is&#13;
&#13;
to be allocated among people, and so on.         And that was what we agreed.   Rather&#13;
&#13;
typically of many conferences I run, we did not actually agree on a course of&#13;
&#13;
action, but we left the seed in the ground, and, as I think I can also say of&#13;
&#13;
many conferences I run, the seed did germinate and grow.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          About six weeks later, I was rung by George Woods and asked if I was&#13;
&#13;
going to be in America in the near future, which I was.         He said would I come&#13;
&#13;
and see him, so I went and saw him, and he said, "I'm going to make a speech&#13;
&#13;
in Stockholm to the bankers.   I'll write the banker's part, but I wonder if&#13;
&#13;
you would write the part suggesting a Franks Commission, preparatory to a&#13;
&#13;
surge of effort in the development field."         I agreed to do that.   When I got&#13;
                               Lor/.rJVCIN"'A.&#13;
back to England, I went in to Tudoni.tlo, where Barbara Ward then lived.        She&#13;
&#13;
and I had been friends since the 'forties and I saw her regularly.         We spent a&#13;
&#13;
day and an evening discussing the speech, and it is in that speech, which was&#13;
&#13;
the actual origin of the Pearson Commission, that we used the name Grand&#13;
&#13;
Assize.   I don't know which of us thought of that particular name; it sounds&#13;
&amp;#12;                                       - 4 -&#13;
&#13;
more like me as a historian, but Barbara had such a fertile mind that it may&#13;
&#13;
have been hers.    Anyway, we thought of this.     I still think it was quite an&#13;
&#13;
interesting name, and that was the speech that George Woods delivered to the&#13;
&#13;
Swedish bankers.    We had really, sort of almost automatically, decided that&#13;
&#13;
the person to run the Grand Assize would be Oliver Franks, Lord Franks, as he&#13;
&#13;
had become, who was then Provost of Worcester College, Oxford.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
           What happened then was curious.     I don't think altogether expectedly,&#13;
&#13;
the changes in the Bank took place.     George Woods retired, Robert McNamara&#13;
&#13;
came in.     Incidentally, I was asked by George Woods to come across and meet&#13;
&#13;
McNamara a day or two after the announcement of his coming to the Bank.       It&#13;
&#13;
was a joint Woods/McNamara appointment of myself to the World Bank.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BLAIR:     Specifically to implement the Grand Assize?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CLARK:     No.   It was simply to be the Director of Information and Public&#13;
&#13;
Affairs.    But I was conscious that this would be one of the things that I&#13;
&#13;
wanted to do.     In fact, on April 2, 1968, on my second day in the Bank, after&#13;
&#13;
I came on board full time - and more important, McNamara's second day in the&#13;
&#13;
Bank he gave (in a very George Woodsian way, and not a very McNamara way)&#13;
tlcAib~Ura&#13;
George Woods allocated the whole morning to discussing with Oliver Franks the&#13;
&#13;
problems of a Franks Commission and what what should be done, etc., etc. and&#13;
&#13;
then we had lunch afterwards.     It was a very long meeting.    I don't have much&#13;
&#13;
recollection of it.    Oliver, who was incidentally a very old friend of mine,&#13;
&#13;
even from before the war when he and I were at the University of Chicago&#13;
&#13;
together, was clearly interested, but worried equally clearly about whether he&#13;
&amp;#12;                                      - 5 -&#13;
&#13;
could combine this with his work at Oxford, where he was trying to revise the&#13;
&#13;
University statutes to make it a rather more modern university.    To cut a long&#13;
&#13;
period short, after about three months or more, Lord Franks sent us a very&#13;
&#13;
apologetic letter saying he felt he really couldn't do this.    I remember that&#13;
&#13;
both Mr. McNamara and myself were rather peeved, because it had taken so long,&#13;
&#13;
and because it was negative.    Nothing was known in public about this, I think,&#13;
&#13;
at all.   But McNamara and I had a discussion and agreed that Lester Pearson,&#13;
&#13;
who had ceased to be Prime Minister of Canada about four months before, might&#13;
&#13;
be the ideal person.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BLAIR:    I remember finding in the files a complimentary letter from Lester&#13;
&#13;
Pearson, as well as, I think, from the Foreign Minister of Canada, sent just&#13;
&#13;
after the original Woods speech.   As he reacted almost immediately, I wonder&#13;
&#13;
if he was volunteering.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CLARK:    I wonder, too.   It's interesting, because it is also true that I&#13;
&#13;
suggested Lester Pearson to George Woods, and he said, "No, I think someone&#13;
&#13;
who has just lost office is not the ideal person."    So I put it aside.&#13;
&#13;
Anyway, McNamara and myself discussed this.   McNamara had had some dealings,&#13;
&#13;
not terribly friendly, with Lester Pearson during the Johnson presidency.      I&#13;
&#13;
can't remember the details and it doesn't matter.    I had worked with him for a&#13;
&#13;
long time during the 'sixties on a series of development programs, financed by&#13;
&#13;
the Ford Foundation, called "The Council on World Tensions", which had&#13;
&#13;
meetings around the world of the newly developing countries, particularly the&#13;
&#13;
newly independent countries.    So Mike had got a lot of experience of meeting&#13;
&#13;
these people.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                        - 6 -&#13;
&#13;
         I went up to Ottawa, twice actually, and without a great deal of&#13;
&#13;
difficulty persuaded Mike Pearson.    I can remember him saying, "You caught me&#13;
&#13;
at just the right moment.    My wife is beginning to say that I needed to have&#13;
&#13;
something to do after breakfast."    He agreed to do it, and he came down to&#13;
&#13;
Washington.   We went over the proposals, went to eat dinner in Tracy Place&#13;
&#13;
with McNamara, just the three of us, with Mrs. McNamara as hostess.     We agreed&#13;
&#13;
to make the announcement on the Saturday for the Sunday papers.     Of course, it&#13;
&#13;
leaked and got into the Saturday papers, which meant that the appointment&#13;
&#13;
didn't get proper coverage on Sunday.     (That sort of thing alway happens and&#13;
&#13;
it never matters twopence.    But it did so occur.)   Then we started the buildup&#13;
&#13;
of the Commission.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BLAIR:   Before we go on, before the Commission began, indeed before you came&#13;
&#13;
to the Bank, was there an attempt to orchestrate a positive response in Europe&#13;
&#13;
and in this country to the general idea of a Commission?     I gather you talked&#13;
&#13;
to a number of people in Europe, and I wondered whether someone was doing that&#13;
&#13;
in the United States as well, or in other donor countries?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CLARK:   I don't think so.    My own recollection is that I only started trying&#13;
&#13;
to get support for this after I had come to the Bank in April, which was quite&#13;
&#13;
a long time after the Stockholm speech.     I remember feeling that this hadn't&#13;
&#13;
been followed up properly, but I don't know; it would perhaps be worth trying&#13;
&#13;
to talk to Harold Graves, who was my predecessor, about that.     He might know.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BLAIR:   Did the idea for the Commission change, did the concept change at&#13;
&#13;
all, between Woods and McNamara?&#13;
&amp;#12;                                      - 7 -&#13;
&#13;
CLARK:    Yes, I think it did.   I think that Woods was really anxious to have&#13;
&#13;
an investigation to see what was going well and what wasn't.     McNamara,&#13;
&#13;
typically, was more intent on having a report which would shove things forward&#13;
&#13;
and give them a great deal more impetus.      In our conversation that evening, we&#13;
&#13;
agreed that the crucial matter was to get movement in the United States.&#13;
&#13;
McNamara then proposed the ex-Secretary of the Treasury, Doug Dillon, as the&#13;
&#13;
American representative.    He said he could deliver him to Mike Pearson, and&#13;
&#13;
did so the very next day before Pearson left town.      I'm not certain whether it&#13;
&#13;
was finalized, but he did do that.    A great deal of the thinking was to&#13;
&#13;
stimulate the United States on this particular issue.     Even at that time, it&#13;
&#13;
was my particular interest to think how to publicize, etc., the report when it&#13;
&#13;
came.    I had some talks with Mike and I went on seeing him throughout this&#13;
&#13;
period in order to discuss how to have maximum impact.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BLAIR:    What other kinds of planning and preparation did you do?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CLARK:    Very little, because we were quite anxious not to preempt Mike&#13;
&#13;
Pearson's real freedom of choice.    We did not - I did not, and McNamara even&#13;
&#13;
more did not - bring much influence to bear.     He suggested Doug Dillon, and&#13;
&#13;
that pleased Mike Pearson immensely, so he accepted him at once.      I suggested&#13;
&#13;
Edward Boyle as the British member, but Mike Pearson in fact tried to get&#13;
&#13;
Geoffrey Crowther, who was then editor of The Economist.     It was only when he&#13;
&#13;
failed that he fell back on Edward Boyle.     I think the fact that he went for&#13;
&#13;
Geoffrey Crowther was at least in part because he felt that Crowther would be&#13;
&#13;
immensely helpful in publicizing the final recommendations, not just through&#13;
&#13;
The Economist, but through his extraordinary abilities as a publicist and as a&#13;
&amp;#12;                                        - 8 -&#13;
&#13;
writer.     I think that is what we did in the remaining day.   Mike came down for&#13;
&#13;
dinner and stayed throughout the next day and left on the, I think, Saturday&#13;
&#13;
morning.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            We agreed at the dinner that, roughly speaking, there would be six or&#13;
&#13;
eight members.     I think we rather unconsciously assumed that they would be&#13;
&#13;
essentially from the developed countries, though there was an idea that there&#13;
&#13;
should be at least one person from what we now call the "NICS", the Newly&#13;
&#13;
Industrializing Countries of the South, and it eventually turned out to be the&#13;
&#13;
Brazilian, Roberto Campos, who was a fairly old friend of both Robert's and&#13;
&#13;
mine.     But that was left to Mike.   I think, though, that it was clear that our&#13;
&#13;
thinking was essentially a conference about the donors' side of aid, and not&#13;
&#13;
really about the recipients' side.     Looking back at it, that was in the spirit&#13;
&#13;
of the times, but it was very different from Brandt.      I'll come to that later&#13;
&#13;
on.     Anyway, on the head table in the dining room over lunch, I did introduce&#13;
&#13;
Ed Hamilton from the White House to Mike Pearson, who offered him the job of&#13;
&#13;
being Secretary of the new commission.     And he accepted.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BLAIR:      Had you known Ed ?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CLARK:      Yes, I had met him through Doug Cater, who was an old friend.   I'd&#13;
&#13;
lunched with him a couple of times in the White House canteen, and was very&#13;
&#13;
impressed with him.     I had talked with him a lot about the Overseas&#13;
&#13;
Development Institute and was trying to get something similar going in this&#13;
&#13;
country.     Incidentally, though this is very much a side issue, it was at this&#13;
&#13;
time that, with a lot encouragement from Gene Black, and working through&#13;
&amp;#12;                                          - 9 -&#13;
&#13;
Dick Demuth, we got the ODC going.     And it was in relation to that that I had&#13;
&#13;
really been talking to Ed Hamilton.       Anyway, he was intrigued by the offer&#13;
&#13;
from Pearson.     I'm sure, though I really don't know this, that he got a call&#13;
&#13;
from McNamara encouraging him to accept.          The result was that he said yes, and&#13;
&#13;
Bob McNamara got a blast from President LBJ for stealing his brightest young&#13;
&#13;
man.     I saw McNamara just afterwards, and he was still quite shaken by it.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            However, we kept Ed, and I can remember, he came 'round a few days&#13;
&#13;
later and saw McNamara, discussed it.       He said, "I will want only one&#13;
&#13;
appointee of my own, and that would be a fellow American, Ernest Stern.             He's&#13;
&#13;
by far the best man in the AID and I do need him."          And that was the only&#13;
&#13;
person that he himself, I think, chose.       The rest of the Secretariat was&#13;
&#13;
chosen with very little influence from me, but with the World Bank's expertise&#13;
&#13;
in who was good, young.    One or two, I think, came out of the World Bank for a&#13;
&#13;
time.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BLAIR:     I think almost half were seconded from the Bank Group.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CLARK:     It was as much as that, yes.     I was too fresh to know even who was&#13;
&#13;
what.    But that is how we got it set up.        The assumption was that the&#13;
&#13;
Commission could be financed quite easily by the Bank on a sort of petty cash&#13;
&#13;
account.    I remember McNamara saying, "Well, I think that we can provide the&#13;
&#13;
cash for this, and we could probably provide housing.          I would like it to be&#13;
&#13;
nearer to a quarter of a million dollars than half a million dollars.''            It&#13;
&#13;
was, I think, two million in the end.       But that's all right.     One of the&#13;
&#13;
curious things was that, moving down from the billions of the US Defense&#13;
&#13;
Department, McNamara really always thought in what for the Bank were quite big&#13;
&amp;#12;                                         - 10 -&#13;
&#13;
terms, but which turned out to be small terms compared with what emerged,&#13;
&#13;
partly because of inflation but not by any means wholly.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
           The Commission was chosen by Mike Pearson and was announced, as I&#13;
&#13;
remember, during the Annual Meeting of 1968, which was very quick.       I would&#13;
&#13;
also say, with considerable respect and pleasure, that Pearson produced his&#13;
                                                                           1&#13;
report in a printed version for distribution at the Annual Meeting of          69.   I&#13;
&#13;
can remember, it was brought down from the printing works, which I think was&#13;
&#13;
in Philadelphia, in a vast truck.       It came down through the night, and broke&#13;
&#13;
down â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BLAIR:     As a former staff member I can tell you, we worked very hard to get&#13;
&#13;
that report out on time.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CLARK:     Yes.   Yes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BLAIR:     Did you have much contact with the Commission, either through Pearson&#13;
&#13;
or Ed Hamilton while it was working?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CLARK:     Yes and no.    We agreed at the very beginning that neither McNamara,&#13;
&#13;
nor myself, nor any other member of the Bank staff, except those seconded,&#13;
&#13;
would go to the meetings or have anything to do with the Commission.       But I&#13;
&#13;
was liaison, and I did keep in constant liaison with Ed Hamilton, and I kept&#13;
&#13;
McNamara informed.       We did not interfere almost at all.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                       - 11 -&#13;
&#13;
          There is one exception to that, and I think it would be a good idea&#13;
&#13;
if I mentioned that now.     It was the suggestion that IDA should be separated&#13;
&#13;
from the Bank, and should have a separate Board and even perhaps a separate&#13;
&#13;
Secretariat or group of operating officers.     It was Arthur Lewis' suggestion,&#13;
&#13;
I understand, and the reasoning was that it was necessary to make the&#13;
&#13;
proposals for action amongst the poorest of a different sort from those&#13;
&#13;
amongst richer countries.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          I remember extremely well.    Though Bob did not interfere, he did tell&#13;
&#13;
me what he thought, and I did pass that on.     It was an interference, if you&#13;
&#13;
like, but it was not an overt one, nor was it a backstairs one; it was known&#13;
&#13;
what he thought, and why he thought it.     What he said was, "If there is going&#13;
&#13;
to have to be a move towards dealing with the poorest, the change should come&#13;
&#13;
on the part of the Bank, not on the part of IDA."     That is a very significant&#13;
&#13;
fact.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          This is said with a certain amount of personal vanity, but it had&#13;
&#13;
been my main conclusion from seven years work in the Overseas Development&#13;
&#13;
Institute, writing quite a lot of policy papers for the new British Ministry&#13;
&#13;
of Overseas Development, that aid should be poverty-oriented, to use the&#13;
&#13;
modern phrase.     It wasn't called that in those days. I don't think I&#13;
&#13;
particularly sold this to McNamara, but it was something on which we very&#13;
&#13;
strongly agreed.    There was this attempt to make IDA a poverty-oriented&#13;
&#13;
program and therefore detach it from the Bank.     McNamara said, in effect,&#13;
&#13;
"Don't detach IDA from the Bank; rather, let IDA lead the Bank into right&#13;
&#13;
paths."   Looking back, that was a very significant move.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                       - 12 -&#13;
&#13;
         I must say that the Pearson Report itself was a conservative report&#13;
&#13;
saying, roughly speaking, we are on the right lines and what we need to do is&#13;
&#13;
move faster and to concentrate more on development and less on fringe&#13;
&#13;
benefits, so to speak, with which I think everyone agreed.      It did have this&#13;
&#13;
element of poverty orientation in its discussion of IDA      and there were some&#13;
&#13;
recommendations that underlined this, but mostly I think it said, "more of the&#13;
&#13;
same," and I think it said it very effectively.      When the report came out,&#13;
&#13;
McNamara's immediate reaction was, first, to praise it in his speech at the&#13;
&#13;
Annusl Meeting--though it was not released till the following day; in fact, it&#13;
&#13;
didn't arrive till the following day.     (I was going to tell you, the truck&#13;
&#13;
came down and broke down in the driveway of the hotel; some 2-4,000 copies of&#13;
&#13;
the report had to be manhandled the last four or five hundred yards.      Quite a&#13;
&#13;
difficult thing to do.)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BLAIR:   On this question of poverty orientation.      As I remember, shortly&#13;
&#13;
after the report was released, Barbara Ward organized a conference â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CLARK:   Yes, indeed.     We'll go into that.   But, first, I was just going to&#13;
&#13;
say, when the report came out, McNamara praised it and particularly fastened&#13;
&#13;
on to and loudly supported the recommendation that 0.7% of GNP should go to&#13;
&#13;
development, and particularly a smaller figure which was to go through the&#13;
&#13;
multilaterals.   Typically, he saw what was in it for the Bank and stressed&#13;
&#13;
that, while very genuinely regarding the report as an enlightened attempt to&#13;
&#13;
put the case for aid in a way that was really appealing.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                       - 13 -&#13;
&#13;
            Now, I must say something about my disappointment with this.       I&#13;
&#13;
thought the report was very good and I did not think, as I now do, that it was&#13;
&#13;
the last shout of the traditional values.       I had no great wisdom.   I had&#13;
&#13;
thought it might be a bit stronger on the poverty orientation, but that didn't&#13;
&#13;
upset me.     Instead, I has two very great disappointments.    One, the report had&#13;
&#13;
really no impact in the US and I was too fresh to the US to understand that.&#13;
&#13;
Its impact on Congress was minimal.     Secondly, I was and remain terribly&#13;
&#13;
disappointed by the Bank's own official reaction.       As you may remember, Mr.&#13;
&#13;
McNamara told the Board and the country in his speech that he was going to&#13;
&#13;
have every item that referred to the Bank in any way studied, discussed in the&#13;
&#13;
Board, and acted on in some way or other.       Well, we looked it through, with&#13;
&#13;
Dick Demuth and Shirley Boskey doing the work, and came to the conclusion that&#13;
&#13;
on the whole we had it right and changes were not strictly necessary.          I was&#13;
&#13;
at the time not aware enough of the Bank's history and practice to know&#13;
&#13;
whether that was absolutely correct, but I thought it made a poor impression.&#13;
&#13;
I know that it did make a poor impression on several members of the Commission&#13;
&#13;
and on several members of the Secretariat.       It was, I think, rather a sad&#13;
&#13;
showing, and I'll say something rather similar when we get round to Brandt,&#13;
&#13;
too.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            It was in part in an attempt to remedy this that Barbara Ward and I&#13;
&#13;
       Barbara had written some of Pearson's introduction to the Report and&#13;
&#13;
worked with him on his speech presenting it, I think, to the US.         I think she&#13;
&#13;
felt that, if the report had been picked up and run with, it could have gone&#13;
&#13;
further and perhaps have excited more interest in the US,       As a result,&#13;
&amp;#12;                                      - 14 -&#13;
&#13;
though, of the relative failure to interest the US, and perhaps to move as&#13;
&#13;
fast as both Barbara and I may have wished towards a more poverty-oriented&#13;
&#13;
program, we arranged with her Schweitzer professorship at Columbia University&#13;
&#13;
a meeting, first at Williamsburg and then up in New York, at which McNamara&#13;
&#13;
spoke, and in which, incidentally, he began to talk about the bottom forty&#13;
&#13;
percent.    That speech was the first hint of that sort of interest on&#13;
&#13;
McNamara's part.     It was at that a conference that Richard Jolly, from the&#13;
&#13;
University of Sussex, played a rather major part in emphasizing the role of&#13;
&#13;
poverty.    I happen to remember, anecdotally and self-regardingly, coming back&#13;
&#13;
and giving a talk to about two hundred members of the staff in the Boardroom&#13;
&#13;
on the results of the Pearson Commission and of this conference and saying,&#13;
&#13;
"You're going to hear a lot more about the bottom 40% and about development&#13;
&#13;
from the bottom up."     I got a very cool response from the older members of the&#13;
&#13;
Bank and a puzzled but very friendly response from what was then called the&#13;
&#13;
530 Club, or maybe it was the 630 Club; it met in Room 530 or 630 and involved&#13;
&#13;
the younger people in the Bank.    Bob Kassen was a member and so on.    The Club&#13;
&#13;
was to be a sort of ginger group and was somewhat frowned on by the senior&#13;
&#13;
staff until McNamara went and talked to them and managed to make them all feel&#13;
&#13;
that they were terrible old conservatives.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BLAIR:     As I remember, at that conference, the majority of the people there&#13;
&#13;
signed the Columbia Declaration, which recommended that aid should focus&#13;
&#13;
specifically on poverty.    Had you expected that to come out of the conference?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CLARK:     Yes.   I'd hoped, and Barbara and I and Richard Jolly had worked on&#13;
&#13;
that a bit.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                       - 15 -&#13;
&#13;
BLAIR:      I once heard Hollis Chenery trace the poverty orientation of Bank&#13;
&#13;
policy back to that conference.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CLARK:      I think that isn't quite correct.    I would trace it back really to&#13;
&#13;
the response to Arthur Lewis' attempt to break IDA off from the Bank, whereas&#13;
&#13;
McNamara wanted to break the Bank off from its traditions.       But I do think it&#13;
&#13;
was a very important conference in that way and his speech was a very&#13;
&#13;
important speech - and not one, though it's in the canon, that's looked at as&#13;
&#13;
much as it might be.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BLAIR:      In terms of the impact of the Pearson Report outside the US, do you&#13;
&#13;
think it had any effect?     I remember hearing at the time that the Japanese and&#13;
&#13;
the Scandinavian countries, who were surprisingly low aid-givers at the time,&#13;
&#13;
were perhaps more forthcoming as a result of the report.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CLARK:      I think the Pearson Report had an impact almost everywhere except the&#13;
&#13;
US.     It had a large influence in Britain.    That was in Wilson Government&#13;
&#13;
days.     It was a period of rapid growth in British development assistance and&#13;
&#13;
the poverty line was adopted by the British more or less officially and pushed&#13;
&#13;
through, quite largely by Britain, at the Commonwealth conference.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            I think that this was also the beginning of the changearound in the&#13;
&#13;
Third World attitude towards the Bank.     No, actually it was just after the '68&#13;
&#13;
speech and before Pearson.     Remember that the Third World regarded McNamara as&#13;
&#13;
an intrusion for American political purposes.       During that first year, when we&#13;
&#13;
visited all three developing continents, I regarded my main duty, though it's&#13;
&amp;#12;                                       - 16 -&#13;
&#13;
not really relevant to the Pearson Report, as being to try and make these&#13;
&#13;
people come to understand and trust McNamara's Bank.        (I don't like using that&#13;
&#13;
phrase, but in this case it is the right phrase to use because each time there&#13;
&#13;
is a change of persons there is a change of focus and attitudes, and there was&#13;
&#13;
a great deal of suspicion at that time.)        I think the greatest impact we had&#13;
&#13;
was in India, where McNamara made a long broadcast on All India Radio and one&#13;
&#13;
or two speeches.     The broadcast made an impact on the government which was&#13;
&#13;
enormous.     It wasn't then quite so clear what we were doing in way of the&#13;
&#13;
poverty orientation but we were concerned, as we said in the 1968 speech, with&#13;
&#13;
the development aspects of the release of poor people into productivity.         That&#13;
&#13;
was really what was important at that time.        In was on the basis of that&#13;
&#13;
speech that we tried to make our case.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BLAIR:      Do you think Pearson made negotiation for IDA replenishment any&#13;
&#13;
easier?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
C~K:        Yes, I think so.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            During the whole of my twelve years in the Bank, with four&#13;
&#13;
replenishments, I think, it was always the same game.        It was always&#13;
&#13;
mobilizing the eighteen or so donors against the United States, which was&#13;
&#13;
trying to cut back.     (Things haven't changed.)&#13;
&#13;
            I think Pearson particularly helped with two new stars in the&#13;
&#13;
firmament: Germany, where Wilfred Guth, who was a Commission member, was very&#13;
&#13;
influential; indeed, very helpful to us, though it was really later, when one&#13;
&#13;
got a Socialist coalition and in the Brandt Government, that Germany began to&#13;
&amp;#12;                                       - 17 -&#13;
&#13;
become a really active member.     And Japan, though it was more dubious in&#13;
&#13;
Japan.   It was less easy, then as now, to know really what they were after.&#13;
&#13;
In addition, what are now called the "like-minded countries": - the Low&#13;
&#13;
Countries and Scandinavia, and sometimes, incidentally, oddly, Australia -&#13;
&#13;
were for a time very, very strongly pro-Pearson and were moved to try and&#13;
&#13;
increase the IDA contributions.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BLAIR:   To get back to the discussions within the Bank, the Executive&#13;
&#13;
Directors did have some discussions on the Report.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CLARK:   Yes, they did.     They discussed each recommendation, on the basis of&#13;
&#13;
somewhat negative reports put to them, I thought.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BLAIR:   Well, do you think that the recommendations of the Pearson Commission&#13;
&#13;
made any difference at all in the Bank?     Would Bank policy be the same today,&#13;
&#13;
say, on program lending, which was one recommendation that Pearson was quite&#13;
&#13;
strong on?   Also, the questions of allocation, where, as I remember, Pearson&#13;
&#13;
suggested that IDA fill in the gaps of bilateral aid that were skewed for&#13;
&#13;
political reasons, that sort of thing.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CLARK:   I think that they made an impact on McNamara, and that in the course&#13;
&#13;
of the years, he used that book, which he often used to travel with, as a&#13;
&#13;
guideline and as support.     I regret that I do not really think they formally&#13;
&#13;
made much difference.     For instance, on that matter of allocation, to fill in&#13;
&#13;
the gaps, so to speak.     For reasonable political considerations, it was turned&#13;
&#13;
down completely by Dick Demuth's recommendations and by the Board.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                       - 18 -&#13;
&#13;
BLAIR:      There were a number of more limited recommendations, things like&#13;
&#13;
being in favor of joint financing, being in favor of local cost financing, and&#13;
&#13;
so on.     Were these trends under way at the Bank already?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CLARK:      I don't know, and I don't think I'm the person to question about&#13;
&#13;
Ohat.    I was concerned nearly always with the broadest and the rather public&#13;
&#13;
policies, and I was disappointed that we weren't more enthusiastic about some&#13;
&#13;
of these changes, for which I felt Pearson had made a good case.      On the other&#13;
&#13;
hand, the Bank did change out of all recognition between the time of the&#13;
&#13;
Pearson report and 1973.     It's my view that quite a lot of that was due to the&#13;
&#13;
careful work of the Secretariat and of the final report.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BLAIR:      Let's move on to the Brandt Commission.   You were in at the beginning&#13;
&#13;
of that?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CLARK:     Yes.   Brandt had oddly similar origins.   In 1976, when the Annual&#13;
&#13;
Meeting was in Manila, there was one part of McNamara's speech which I was&#13;
&#13;
particularly interested in, which McNamara was not quite certain about, but&#13;
&#13;
which eventually got in.     That was the recommendation that we should have a&#13;
&#13;
Global Compact.    We should know how much was needed, where it should be&#13;
&#13;
allocated, and by whom it should be raised.     That was the thing.   If only we&#13;
&#13;
could arrive at a Global Compact on who did what, we could move forward at the&#13;
&#13;
necessary speed.     The recommendation went down like a lead balloon.     I had&#13;
&#13;
with considerable effort lobbied Dennis Healey on my pre-Annual Meeting visit&#13;
&#13;
to England, and he had agreed that he would use his personal efforts, and&#13;
&#13;
perhaps his speech, to support the proposal, and actually he did.        But he&#13;
&amp;#12;                                       - 19 -&#13;
&#13;
didn't come to the meeting, because the British pound dropped through the&#13;
&#13;
floor, and he got off the plane from Manila and went back to Number 11 Downing&#13;
&#13;
Street.   That was a disappointment.    I don't think I'd asked anyone else to&#13;
&#13;
follow it up.   My folly.   It didn't do well.   McNamara thought that it wasn't&#13;
&#13;
necessarily a very good idea, and I think quite a lot of people close to him&#13;
&#13;
didn't.   I'm not, by the way, saying that I'm sure that it was, either.     But&#13;
&#13;
towards the end of '76 we did begin to realize that there was a sort of&#13;
&#13;
deadlock between the OPEC countries who had a lot of money and the countries&#13;
&#13;
which were feeling hurt by OPEC, particularly Bill Simon and the US Treasury,&#13;
&#13;
the poorer countries, and some of the richer developing countries who were&#13;
&#13;
being more being more or less ruined by the rising oil prices, inflation,&#13;
&#13;
etc.   We realized that we were going nowhere.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          If I may just interpose something.     On the whole, the years to 1973&#13;
&#13;
and the Nairobi speech were all forward for McNamara.      The years after the&#13;
&#13;
Nairobi speech and the official proclamation, as it were, of the rural&#13;
&#13;
development/poverty-oriented program were almost all backwards, because of the&#13;
&#13;
oil price hike, and the general distaste of the Americans and most of the&#13;
&#13;
Western world for the rather successful tactics of the Third World in&#13;
&#13;
blackmailing the developed world through its oil weapon.     So by '76 we were&#13;
&#13;
really dead in the water, we felt.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          That was the background for a new attempt, towards the end of the&#13;
&#13;
decade, a little bit earlier this time, to produce a report which would send&#13;
&#13;
us on our way again.    I can remember, I talked about a repetition of the&#13;
&#13;
Pearson Commission.    Indeed it was known in our notes as Pearson II.    I can&#13;
&#13;
remember again that, on one of Barbara Ward's visits to stay with Bob, we had&#13;
&amp;#12;                                       - 20 -&#13;
&#13;
spent the evening discussing this, and she had said "Why don't you find&#13;
&#13;
something for Willy Brandt to do.     He's out of power, and is finding it&#13;
&#13;
difficult to adjust to that, and is rattling around.     Why don't we try and use&#13;
&#13;
him on this."    Bob said nothing at that time, and when I spoke to him about it&#13;
&#13;
later he seemed rather negative.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         Then, as often happens, suddenly one morning, at a small group of&#13;
&#13;
five or six of us: Ernest Stern, Hollis Chenery, myself, I can't remember what&#13;
&#13;
we were doing, but he said, "Well, there's one other thing I should say&#13;
&#13;
something about.     If we're going to have what I'll call a Brandt Commission,&#13;
&#13;
then we've got to do something about it fairly soon." That was the first any&#13;
&#13;
of us had heard.     I jumped in and made a simple practical suggestion, which&#13;
&#13;
was that he might announce this in a speech that he was going to make in&#13;
&#13;
Boston, receiving an award from Cabot Lodge.     We just took an old speech and&#13;
&#13;
puttied it in.     We made the suggestion that there should be a commission to&#13;
&#13;
study, essentially, the Global Compact.     Having consulted Brandt privately and&#13;
&#13;
through third parties, so he didn't have to give a yes or no, we put into the&#13;
&#13;
speech, as I remember, the phrase, "If some world leader of the stature, say,&#13;
&#13;
of Willy Brandt were to â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢ "      And that was the beginning of that.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         It took a very long time to get Willy Brandt to bite on this&#13;
&#13;
particular thing, though.     I went and saw him in Bonn almost immediately after&#13;
&#13;
this speech, and found him very interested.     I found an old friend of mine,&#13;
&#13;
Egon Bahr, who had been Brandt's spokesman in Berlin when he was mayor and&#13;
&#13;
whom I'd known as a journalist (we're still good friends).     Egon Bahr&#13;
&#13;
encouraged him, and Willy gave me an answer which I interpreted as being&#13;
&amp;#12;                                       - 21 -&#13;
&#13;
definite and positive.     Bob McNamara said, "That isn't a promise," and I said,&#13;
&#13;
"No, but it is a promise to try," and he said, "Well, it's difficult to go&#13;
&#13;
ahead on the basis of that," so there were more weeks of negotiation, more&#13;
&#13;
months of negotiation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          What Brandt was determined on, and he said this to me very frankly,&#13;
&#13;
was to be more independent of the Bank than the Pearson Commission had been.&#13;
&#13;
He said, "I'm afraid that some of my recommendations will probably be&#13;
&#13;
unwelcome to your boss."     I think he was thinking of was his Socialist past&#13;
&#13;
and a poverty-oriented program.     I think he was wrong.     The three of us,&#13;
&#13;
McNamara, Brandt and myself, had a conversation perhaps two months later, in&#13;
&#13;
which Brandt was saying some things very tentatively, saying, "I don't want to&#13;
&#13;
suggest we'll go too far," and McNamara said, 11 Yes, yes, no, you must go much&#13;
&#13;
farther than that."     This rather suprised him.     Secondly, and interestingly,&#13;
&#13;
Brandt said, "Of course, I feel that we cannot detach this entirely from the&#13;
&#13;
disarmament issue, and I know that that will be awkward for you".        "Awkward?"&#13;
&#13;
said McNamara, "I can't think how any sane man can imagine we can not do&#13;
&#13;
that."   But, as I say, Brandt was anxious to be independent, and to appear&#13;
&#13;
independent, with which I very much agreed.       He was determined, therefore,&#13;
&#13;
that he would finance it himself, which in a sense he did.        I'll say more of&#13;
&#13;
that in a moment.     He was determined that he would not go ahead unless he had&#13;
&#13;
the good will of the Third World.     Thereby hangs a very long tale, the number&#13;
&#13;
of troubles we had with the Third World.        I simply can't go into it from&#13;
&#13;
memory in detail.     I just would add here that I think I have a lot of notes on&#13;
&#13;
this, and sometime I may try and put this down on a tape and send it to you.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                       - 22 -&#13;
&#13;
          But we had a great deal of opposition.    I can remember talking after&#13;
&#13;
the event to the Pakistani who was then Chairman of the Group of 77, and his&#13;
&#13;
telling me that he simply couldn't persuade his colleagues to go ahead and&#13;
&#13;
endorse this, because they were all sure - "and so was I," he said - "that all&#13;
&#13;
we would get would be another lecture on how we ought to behave."     They never&#13;
&#13;
really did endorse it, but they did say that, sort of nihil obstat.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          Secondly, there was a curious episode with Perez Guerrero, the&#13;
&#13;
Development Minister, I think he was called, or Finance Minister of&#13;
&#13;
Venezuela.   Yes, Perez Guerrero was a key figure in this.    I don't quite&#13;
&#13;
remember why.   Absolutely refused to go along, saying no, this ought to be&#13;
&#13;
dealt with through the United Nations, and only through the United Nations,&#13;
&#13;
which has always been his view.   He is, in my opinion one of the people who&#13;
&#13;
has really wrecked most of the attempts to produce a working body of North and&#13;
&#13;
South that would not be a hundred-and-fifty-nine nations.     His last effort was&#13;
&#13;
at the Cancu 0 n Conference, where he said that a furthur Cancu 0 n Conference&#13;
&#13;
would undoubtedly be a derogation of the rights of the United Nations, since&#13;
&#13;
neither the summits of the developing countries nor the United Nations had&#13;
&#13;
been heard from effectively.   There we are.    I'm bitter about that, because he&#13;
&#13;
held things up for a very long time.    He did not have anything to put in its&#13;
&#13;
place.   Eventually, he agreed, though very reluctantly.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          In the meanwhile, Willy Brandt had decided that, as the world's&#13;
&#13;
population is heavily weighted towards the poorer countries, so his Commission&#13;
&#13;
should be.   He put a large number of Third World personalities, all of whom&#13;
&#13;
are individually good, I think, onto the Commission.    But that did unbalance&#13;
&amp;#12;                                       - 23 -&#13;
&#13;
it somewhat as an active organization.     I worked with him very closely on the&#13;
&#13;
membership, though less closely, in a way, on the Third World members.       I&#13;
&#13;
confess, I had thought McNamara had thought of two or three or four Third&#13;
&#13;
World people, and four or five or six people from developed countries, the&#13;
&#13;
bias being again in favor of those who were going to have to take the majority&#13;
&#13;
of action.     Brandt had other views; in a very real sense, I think he was more&#13;
&#13;
up-to-date than we were, and that this is what a Commission ought to be that&#13;
&#13;
is looking at the developing world.     I think such a commission should have,&#13;
&#13;
roughly speaking, proportional representation for the Third World.      But the&#13;
&#13;
net result for Brandt was to slow its proceedings very, very much and lead to&#13;
&#13;
a great deal of trouble.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
           I can remember that McNamara and myself suggested two from the Third&#13;
&#13;
World who were adopted at once, which were L.K. Jha, who became Deputy&#13;
&#13;
Chairman, and Amir Jamal, from Tanzania, who couldn't, by any means, be&#13;
&#13;
regarded as a conservative or a pushover for the North.     I also suggested&#13;
&#13;
personally Sonny Ramphal, the Commonwealth Secretary.     Oddly enough, because&#13;
&#13;
he wasn't known in Germany at all, we had to push quite hard for him, which I&#13;
&#13;
didn't hesitate to do.     I also suggested Ted Heath, to which Willy Brandt&#13;
&#13;
agreed absolutely at once.     I think that the eventual report was written more&#13;
&#13;
by Ted Heath and Sonny Ramphal than it was really by Willy Brandt,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
           I attended the first meeting, which was in Schlossgymnich, in&#13;
&#13;
Germany, in December of '77.     I made a small speech.   I also drafted, with&#13;
&#13;
Willy Brandt, his speech.     (I don't mean I wrote it; I worked with him,&#13;
&#13;
though.)     We decided, with myself enthusiastic and himself somewhat reluctant,&#13;
&#13;
but it was his idea, to make the idea of mutual benefit one of the key&#13;
&amp;#12;                                       - 24 -&#13;
&#13;
factors.     That was one of the key factors, perhaps the key factor, in the&#13;
&#13;
eventual report.     But at that meeting I could see that the Third World already&#13;
&#13;
was organizing itself around Ramphal to try and push the NIEO, the New&#13;
&#13;
International Economic Order, onto the Commission.       And I can remember, in the&#13;
&#13;
period when we were trying to finance the organization -because, although the&#13;
&#13;
Bank didn't do it, we did play a considerable part in raising the finance - I&#13;
&#13;
went and saw Jan Pronk, who was then the Minister of Aid of the Dutch.         I got&#13;
&#13;
him to agree to put up a million dollars for the Commission, which was what&#13;
&#13;
they built on.     He, Jan Pronk said, "I think that the Commission ought to&#13;
&#13;
accept that the New International Economic Order is what is desired by the&#13;
&#13;
Third World; it must be considered the basis on which discussions will take&#13;
&#13;
place. 11&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            I carried this to Willy Brandt, with my heart in my mouth, and was&#13;
&#13;
prepared to argue with him i f he said Pronk's view should prevail.      Luckily,&#13;
&#13;
he gave it long thought and went away for an hour and came back and said no.&#13;
&#13;
I think it would have been quite fatal i f he had said yes on that.      But I&#13;
&#13;
could see that there was going to be the usual global-negotiations pressure to&#13;
&#13;
try and get the NIEO in.     And so there was.    The Brandt Commission very nearly&#13;
&#13;
broke down in the final stages, because Brandt saw the folly, if I dare say&#13;
&#13;
so, of the NIEO.     At the same time, to get a unanimous report, something of it&#13;
&#13;
really had to appear.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            Personally, I feel that the report, which was excellent in some ways,&#13;
&#13;
was of two parts.     There was a first part, which was an accelerated emergency&#13;
&#13;
program.     That was, I think, just excellent.    then there was, really to&#13;
&amp;#12;                                       - 25 -&#13;
&#13;
comfort the Third World, a long-term program with     massive transfers of&#13;
&#13;
resources, etc., run through a World Development Fund and administered&#13;
&#13;
essentially by the United Nations.     That was a second phase.   I'd heard about&#13;
&#13;
this quite a lot, and I'd talked to Ted Heath about it quite a lot, and he'd&#13;
&#13;
nodded his head sagely but not said anything.     The eventual compromise was&#13;
&#13;
that these two rather incompatible programs were put in, except that the&#13;
&#13;
second one was to take place later.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BLAIR:   But that was really the basis for the reaction to the report.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CLARK:   That's right, and that was the difficulty, because the report didn't&#13;
&#13;
come out in October of '79, as it should have.     When it was launched, by 1980,&#13;
&#13;
there had been the second oil shock.     There was a plunging recession, and the&#13;
&#13;
report was lucky to survive.   I think that a very good job was done in selling&#13;
&#13;
the report in most countries, particularly Britain, where it is still regarded&#13;
&#13;
as a sort of gospel by a lot of people.     But the fact of the matter is that&#13;
&#13;
the report got launched at a time when greater efficiency in aid giving,&#13;
&#13;
smaller amounts, and greater accountability and control by the North - none of&#13;
&#13;
which I'm particularly in favor of - were becoming the order of the day.        By&#13;
&#13;
1981, when the thing was published, there was a Conservative government in&#13;
&#13;
Britain which dismissed it as a lot of arrant nonsense.     It's greatly to the&#13;
&#13;
credit of the British Parliament and the British people that they managed to&#13;
&#13;
force the government to drop that stance, but they only dropped it verbally.&#13;
&#13;
The fact of the matter is that the administration in Great Britain will never&#13;
&#13;
do anything about the Brandt Report, and the administration in this country,&#13;
&#13;
which accepted it with considerable reluctance under Carter, has not accepted&#13;
&amp;#12;                                       - 26 -&#13;
&#13;
it one bit under Reagan.     The report has had no real positive impact.     I think&#13;
&#13;
that is very sad.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BLAIR:      Would you go so far as to say it was counter-productive in some sense?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CLARK       No, I wouldn't, though a lot of people would.    I think anything would&#13;
&#13;
have been counter-productive, so to speak, if it was any good at all.        I do&#13;
&#13;
think that the four-hundred-billion-dollar World Development Fund was a "red&#13;
&#13;
rag".    And in that sense, it was perhaps little counter-productive.      But it&#13;
&#13;
was mainly counter-productive against the report itself, rather than against&#13;
&#13;
the institutions.     Perhaps it is true to say that the report added a little&#13;
&#13;
fuel to what I'll call the anti-McNamara theory of growth of assistance and&#13;
&#13;
growth in the world.     Anyway, it has fallen on completely stony ground in the&#13;
&#13;
developed world at large.     And because it has not had any impact in the&#13;
&#13;
developed world, it has not really been very popular in the developing world.&#13;
&#13;
The report is something which is lauded and praised, but it has not had the&#13;
&#13;
desired result.     After leaving the Bank, I got back to England in time to do a&#13;
&#13;
little lobbying for the report itself, and      I'm glad to think that, through&#13;
&#13;
publishing it with people who had published some novels of mine, we at least&#13;
&#13;
sold more copies in Britain than in any other country.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            I think, though, that the report's impact within the Bank was&#13;
&#13;
negative.     It was published, as I remember, in January.   We had a lunch on the&#13;
&#13;
day of publication in McNamara's office, with Mahbub ul Haq, Kay Graham, Willy&#13;
&#13;
Brandt, myself, Ernie Stern and Hollis Chenery, I think, and Sonny Ramphal,&#13;
&#13;
who was here.     McNamara's first response, this was private, was to turn to&#13;
&amp;#12;                                     - 27 -&#13;
&#13;
Sonny and say, "Why did you have to be so critical of the Bank as you are.&#13;
&#13;
It'll do us nothing but harm.   It'll make the capital increase more&#13;
&#13;
difficult.   It'll make our efforts more difficult.''    Sonny justified himself&#13;
&#13;
and said, "Well, this is the view of the Third World.      ~don't      you teach&#13;
&#13;
them better?" McNamara said, "Is it your view?," and he said it wasn't.        I&#13;
&#13;
think that McNamara was very disappointed indeed by the report.       I was much&#13;
&#13;
less so, though I do feel that it was an effort that was mistimed, and I don't&#13;
&#13;
think that the second report, which came out this year, has had any impact.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BLAIR:   I was just going to say, I see they're still in business, and still&#13;
&#13;
trying to influence policy in some ways.      Do you think that's a good idea?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CLARK:   Willy Brandt was terribly opposed to it, though I said to him, "I&#13;
&#13;
don't think you'll be able to stop having some further meetings".       I went to&#13;
&#13;
the final meeting, in December of '78; he said there, "We will not meet&#13;
&#13;
again," but they met again within a year.      I wasn 1 t invited to that meeting,&#13;
&#13;
and I don't think it was a frightfully good idea, because now, I think, we&#13;
&#13;
really have to try and cope with a different cast of mind.       But this has not&#13;
&#13;
much to do with the Bank.   I would just say that I think the current views of&#13;
&#13;
US, UK, and Germany are deadly for the future of a united world.       And I am&#13;
&#13;
very unhappy.   To some extent I am happy that the Brandt Commission provided a&#13;
&#13;
flag for the old ship "Development" to go down with.      But that isn't saying a&#13;
&#13;
very great deal.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BLAIR:   That's very pessimistic, I must say.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                       - 28&#13;
&#13;
CLARK:   It is very pessimistic.     What is wrong with my analogy, of course, is&#13;
&#13;
that ships stay sunk and political movements don't stay sunk, especially when&#13;
&#13;
they are essential.     But we are going to miss five years, at least, of&#13;
&#13;
development.    And we are probably are going to divide the world more&#13;
&#13;
completely than it has been divided since colonial days.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BLAIR:   At least in the last few months, I have heard calls for a new Bretton&#13;
&#13;
Woods-type conference.     Is it possible that the Brandt Commission, by staying&#13;
&#13;
in existence, is preempting the possibility of new thinking along those lines?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CLARK:   No.     I think that the only real effort for a new Bretton Woods&#13;
&#13;
Conference is the Commonwealth Report, of which, by the way, I was a&#13;
&#13;
signatory.     And I'll just add two little personal postscripts.    In the last&#13;
&#13;
two years, I have been associated with the Commonwealth in producing two&#13;
&#13;
pamphlets.     The one that I was mainly concerned with was one called "The&#13;
&#13;
North-South Dialogue: Making it Work", in which I took a lot of the Brandt&#13;
&#13;
ideas and put them into some of the proposals that were made.       Oddly enough,&#13;
&#13;
the pamphlet's recommendations have been endorsed by the present Conservative&#13;
&#13;
government in Britain.    As for the new Bretton Woods proposal, which was the&#13;
&#13;
second part of this Commonwealth Secretariat's effort, I played a small part&#13;
&#13;
in setting it up, but did not take part in the discussions, which I think that&#13;
&#13;
has produced the best proposals for a new Bretton Woods that exist.       The&#13;
&#13;
difficulty about the Brandt Commission was that it didn't look to a revised&#13;
&#13;
World Bank, it looked to a new Heaven and a new Earth, and one that is&#13;
&#13;
extremely unattractive to the present monetarists and conservative governments.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                       - 29 -&#13;
&#13;
BLAIR:   Do you think some of the Brandt proposals might rise again?         I mean,&#13;
&#13;
I know Mahbub was pushing automaticity in one way or another, for example, and&#13;
&#13;
Brandt seems to have endorsed that notion.      Is that likely to come up?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CLARK:   Not in the next four or five years, unless we have something that is&#13;
&#13;
more or less like a revolution as a result of the continuing recession.         By&#13;
&#13;
revolution, I don't mean a Red revolution, but I mean a real swing to a&#13;
&#13;
different attitude.     I don't happen to think that all likely.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         The difficulty is this: As long as aid was regarded as cream on the&#13;
&#13;
coffee, as something on top of the effort, so long was it more or less&#13;
&#13;
impossible to get people to recognize that they ought to maintain their aid&#13;
&#13;
effort even when they were going through hard times.      I don't believe there is&#13;
&#13;
any way in which harder times are going to make people feel that they ought to&#13;
&#13;
do something big for the Third World, and I don't think that a move out of the&#13;
&#13;
recession is going move us fast enough to get a change of view, that people&#13;
&#13;
will feel, "Well, now we're rich again, we can really do something about&#13;
&#13;
development".    I happen to think it is plain sense that we should do so.       But&#13;
&#13;
I am not, at this stage of my life, prepared to believe that popular opinion&#13;
&#13;
will shift very fast.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BLAIR:   In retrospect, do you think these exercises were worthwhile from the&#13;
&#13;
point of view of the Bank?    If you had it to do again, would you do it a&#13;
&#13;
different way?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CLARK:   In retrospect, I think that both Pearson and Brandt contributed to a&#13;
&#13;
forward motion on the part of the Bank.     I think particularly the idea of&#13;
&amp;#12;                                        - 30 -&#13;
&#13;
moving out of the one-to-one gearing ratio was an idea that was very helpful&#13;
&#13;
to the Bank, and was plain common sense.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            A lot of what I call the 'Phase I' of Brandtery is useful advice to&#13;
&#13;
the Bank.     The trouble is this: what we, the Bank, really wanted was political&#13;
&#13;
support, rousing political support.      I personally think that if the Brandt&#13;
&#13;
report if had come out a year earlier, if it had been done in one year instead&#13;
&#13;
of two-and-a-half, it might have had a very real impact.      It might have been&#13;
&#13;
picked up by the Jim Callaghans and Dennis Healeys in Britain, might have been&#13;
&#13;
picked up by the Carter regime easily and have begun something which would&#13;
&#13;
have been quite difficult to stop.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BLAIR:      If someone proposes a new commission in the next decade, would you&#13;
&#13;
recommend the Bank be involved again?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CLARK:      Certainly, in some way.   The Bank is the main force for development&#13;
&#13;
in the world.     If there is a commission to look at North-South relations, the&#13;
&#13;
Bank must be involved in the sense that it must give its testimony and try and&#13;
&#13;
convince the group, whatever it is, that it has something very substantial to&#13;
&#13;
contribute, and that a lot of progress can be added by doing more with the&#13;
&#13;
Bank.     I would not actually recommend that the Bank set anything up at this&#13;
&#13;
moment.     Much better to get something like the Commonwealth, or the Trilateral&#13;
&#13;
Commission or, at this moment, something North-South in the Americas, in the&#13;
&#13;
Western Hemisphere, to look at this.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                       - 31 -&#13;
&#13;
BLAIR:      I notice you don't mention the United Nations, at all. Have you given&#13;
&#13;
up on that?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CLARK:      I don't mention the United Nations at all because I think that it is,&#13;
&#13;
at this moment, showing no signs of having a constructive approach towards the&#13;
&#13;
North.   I think it is very remiss of the North to be so unwilling to discuss&#13;
&#13;
issues at the UN, but as long as the Third World thinks that its majority of&#13;
&#13;
votes in the UN will win it concessions, so long are they dealing with an arid&#13;
&#13;
prospect.     They are not, really not, going to get anywhere that way.     Now, it&#13;
&#13;
may well be, that within the remainder of the century, push will come to&#13;
&#13;
shove, and we will have more violent methods of achieving something.        The&#13;
&#13;
possiblity of a major debt default by collusion, by intent, might well create&#13;
&#13;
a situation in which the North had to do something about the South, but I&#13;
&#13;
don't think any of the things that would be done that way would be&#13;
&#13;
constructive.     They would be done in a damage-limitation way, essentially&#13;
&#13;
trying to isolate the North from the South.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BLAIR:      Well, I realize that you have lots better things to do than talk&#13;
&#13;
about Bank history.     I do want to thank you for your time, and ask you if&#13;
&#13;
there's anything else that you think of to say by way of summing up, or that&#13;
&#13;
we've not talked about?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CLARK:      No, I think that is really all.     I am doing another talk with Bob&#13;
&#13;
Asher.   Eventually, I shall perhaps have some thoughts which I have not had.&#13;
&#13;
May I just add one thing, to go on the record, which is that I hope you may&#13;
&#13;
put into your files the article I wrote in December of '81, on the McNamara&#13;
&amp;#12;                                        - 32 -&#13;
&#13;
years at the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BLAIR:      Yes, that appeared in Foreign Affairs ("Reconsiderations: Robert&#13;
&#13;
McNamara at the World Bank", Foreign Affairs, Fall, 1981).      Actually I was&#13;
&#13;
interested to see that in that article you barely mentioned either Pearson or&#13;
&#13;
Brandt as an influence on McNamara, on his thinking.      Would you say that's&#13;
&#13;
accurate?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CLARK:      When one talks about influencing McNamara, what one's got to realize&#13;
&#13;
is that he usually has his own strategy, and he picks up support where he can&#13;
&#13;
find it.     He does not easily get pushed off course, but he gets pushed along&#13;
&#13;
courses.     I think that, focussing on the Pearson Commission as I have this&#13;
&#13;
morning, I've realized the extent to which that and the immediate post-Pearson&#13;
&#13;
events were rather the beginning of a lot of his poverty-oriented thinking.&#13;
&#13;
But, although the Pearson Commission enlarged his mind, as his travels have&#13;
&#13;
done, it didn't really make a right-angle bend in his thinking.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BLAIR:      Good.   Well, thank you very, very much.   I know Bob is looking&#13;
&#13;
forward to talking to you tomorrow.&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="17968920">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1983/10/17968920/transcript-oral-history-interview-clark-william-d-held-october-4-5-1983-vol-2-3-main-report
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1983/10/17968920/transcript-oral-history-interview-clark-william-d-held-october-4-5-1983-vol-2-3-main-report</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1983/10/17968920/transcript-oral-history-interview-clark-william-d-held-october-4-5-1983-vol-2-3-main-report</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2008-03-18T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2008-03-18T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2013/07/05/000356161_20130705151823/Rendered/INDEX/789640v20TRN0C0on010October04001983.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2013/07/05/000356161_20130705151823/Rendered/PDF/789640v20TRN0C0on010October04001983.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>1983-10-05T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2013-07-05T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>3</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Transcript of oral history interview with
            William D. Clark held on October 4 and 5, 1983
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            In October 1983, William D. Clark was
            interviewed on behalf of the World Bank Group Archives oral
            history program by Robert E. Asher and Patricia Blair.
            During his tenure at the Bank from 1968 to 1980, Mr. Clark
            joined the World Bank upon appointment by both presidents
            George Woods and Robert McNamara. He served as director for
            the information and public affairs department (1968-1973)
            and for external relations (1973-1974), where he concluded
            his tenure as vice president (1974-1980). His transcript
            concerns the high priority task of working closely with
            Robert McNamara, the specific facets of his responsibilities
            in public relations and the publications office, the
            importance of the Economic Development Institute (EDI), the
            contribution of the World Bank to the environment, and
            foundation of the Consultative Group for International
            Agricultural Research (CGIAR).
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            First interview session
        </docna>
        <display_title>Transcript of oral history
            interview with William D. Clark held on October 4 and 5,
            1983 : First interview session</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/1983/10/17968920/transcript-oral-history-interview-william-d-clark-held-october-4-5-1983-first-interview-session</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Transcript</docty>
        <subtopic>Access to Finance,Public Sector Corruption &amp;
            Anticorruption Measures,Corporate Law,Sustainable Land and Crop Management,Banks &amp; Banking Reform</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Law and Development,Public Sector Development,Rural Development</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000356161_20130705151823</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>World Bank Group Archives oral history program</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Law and Development,Public Sector Development,Rural Development</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Board Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            accountability, appointee, cash account,
            collusion, debt, development assistance, housing, inflation,
            investigation, limited, lobbying, majority of votes,
            Minister, persons, political movements, productivity, public
            policies, recession, remedy
        </keywd>
        <owner>Knowledge &amp; Information Services (ITSKI)</owner>
        <repnb>78964</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Alternative Sentencing Options</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community based Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Correctional Services and Facilities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corrections</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime and Society</ml:concept><ml:concept>Defense Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Detention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enforcement Policies and Oversight Mechanism</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigative Task Force Police</ml:concept><ml:concept>Juvenile Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Law Enforcement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Offender Reintegration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Administration and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Problem solving Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Prosecution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Restorative Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Therapeutic Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Assistance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim-Offender Mediation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shocks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crops</ml:concept><ml:concept>Asset Recovery</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Checks on Executive Power</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen User Satisfaction Survey</ml:concept><ml:concept>Independent Commissions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ombudsmen</ml:concept><ml:concept>Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Parliament</ml:concept><ml:concept>Procurement Complaints Review Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supreme Audit Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Lines</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fuels</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Growth and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Criminal Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Treasury</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shocks and Vulnerability</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inflation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Accountability Mechanisms</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>