<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>﻿                                                                 78928&#13;
                  Summary of Oral History Transcript             v1&#13;
                           Baum, Warren C.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Interview conducted by Professor Robert W. Oliver, on 1986-07-23&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Baum earned a PhD in economics from Harvard University. In 1959&#13;
he joined the Bank after working in the Marshall Plan of the US&#13;
Government for four years as the French desk officer and writing a&#13;
book for the Rand Corporation on the French economy. As a country&#13;
economist in the Department of Operations (Europe, Africa and&#13;
Australasia), he worked on France, Algeria, Spain, and Portugal. He&#13;
became a Programs Division Chief, then was invited by Aldewereld&#13;
(Director of Projects) to join the Projects Department as head of the&#13;
Transportation Division in 1964, thus becoming the first economist in&#13;
a managerial position of an Area Department to bridge the chasm which&#13;
separated the Area and Projects departments.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Baum elaborates on the organizational structure and separate&#13;
functions of both the Area and Projects departments within the&#13;
division of responsibility. Their separate management resulting in&#13;
poor relationships, due to the inherent tension in Bank operations&#13;
between the country and project focus and, the many issues having to&#13;
be resolved either in the Office of the Vice President (B. Knapp) or&#13;
in the Loan Committee deliberations. Baum moved from head of the&#13;
Transportation Division to Associate Director of the Projects&#13;
Department under Bernard Chadenet, when Aldewereld became Vice&#13;
President of Projects and Finance. He discusses McNamara's&#13;
introduction of the five-year projection plan soon after becoming&#13;
President (April 1968); his interpretation of McNamara's motives for&#13;
the '72 reorganization; the introduction of the Country Program Paper&#13;
(CPP); the organizational structure of the newly-formed regions; the&#13;
structure and function of the Loan Committee; and the existence and&#13;
function of the Economic Committee.&#13;
&amp;#12;     Baum depicts in detail the McNamara era in terms of its more&#13;
ambitious and expansionary concept of the role of the institution than&#13;
during either of his predecessors; the increase in capital&#13;
subscriptions and IDA Replenishments; and the effect of the five-year&#13;
programming increasing not only the volume but the quality of lending,&#13;
thus generating tremendous pressure within the institution to reach&#13;
lending targets which were not only met but were exceeded. During the&#13;
'72 reorganization, Aldewereld who had been Vice President of both&#13;
Finance and Projects became Vice President of Finance only, and Baum&#13;
became Vice president of Projects. He covers in detail the staffing&#13;
structure and functions within the new organization.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Baum talks about McNamara as the quintessential leader, but a&#13;
poor and indifferent manager and, in that context, describes the&#13;
management and leadership styles of the presidents he served under&#13;
mainly Black, Woods, and McNamara. He covers briefly their&#13;
relationship with the Board and in detail McNamara's relationship with&#13;
the Board and attributes the strains that developed, aside from his&#13;
personality and management style, to the increased complexity of Bank&#13;
operations as well as the increasing importance of IDA Replenishments&#13;
requiring government approval. When Clausen came the continued strains&#13;
had already reinforced the Board's desire to be more independent of&#13;
Management.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     According to Baum, in contrast with McNamara the quintessential&#13;
leader, Clausen was the quintessential manager, given that he did not&#13;
lead the institution on the operational side leaving it in the hands&#13;
of the senior operational management, he was, however, a leader on&#13;
finance. Clausen established the Managing Committee early on in his&#13;
tenure--a concept believed to have been imported from the Bank of&#13;
America--comprised of the vice presidents reporting directly to him.&#13;
Baum elaborates on the structure and function of the Managing&#13;
Committee; the President's Council under Woods, McNamara, an dClausen&#13;
who renamed it the Senior Management Council; the discontinuation of&#13;
the senior staff meetings; McNamara giving the Regional vice&#13;
&amp;#12;presidents sole responsibility for the working party and negotiation&#13;
teams at the operational level; Clausen's relationship with the Board,&#13;
specifically, in prolonging the polarization with Management.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Baum gives a brief description of specific personality traits of&#13;
the Presidents he served under: Black, Woods, McNamara, and Clausen.&#13;
He then covers his own personal career in the Bank including the major&#13;
projects he was closely involved in. Mainly, the Spanish railways and&#13;
the innovation he introduced to a covenant in highway projects, his&#13;
great emphasis on the quality of Bank operations and his active&#13;
participation to the broadening of the whole project approach. He&#13;
discusses cost-benefit analysis, methods for ordering projects, the&#13;
Bank's increased review of a country's investment program as a whole,&#13;
structural and sector adjustment lending, Irving Friedman and the&#13;
proposal from UNCTAD, and serving as the Chairman of the Consultative&#13;
Group on International Agricultural Research for 10 years as the thing&#13;
he enjoyed most and the Group's function in relation to the Green&#13;
Revolution. Finally, his appreciation of the unique experience given&#13;
him to write two books on the work of the Bank: Investing in&#13;
Development: Lessons of World Bank Experience; and Partners Against&#13;
Hunger.&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="17968665">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1986/07/17968665/transcript-oral-history-interview-warren-c-baum-held-july-23-1986-vol-1-2-summary-oral-history-transcript
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1986/07/17968665/transcript-oral-history-interview-warren-c-baum-held-july-23-1986-vol-1-2-summary-oral-history-transcript</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1986/07/17968665/transcript-oral-history-interview-warren-c-baum-held-july-23-1986-vol-1-2-summary-oral-history-transcript</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2008-12-02T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2008-12-02T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2013/07/05/000356161_20130705131440/Rendered/INDEX/789280v10TRN0B0ummary0July023001986.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2013/07/05/000356161_20130705131440/Rendered/PDF/789280v10TRN0B0ummary0July023001986.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2013-07-05T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1986-07-23T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>2</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>2</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Transcript of oral history interview with
            Warren C. Baum held on July 23, 1986
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            In July 1986, Warren C. Baum was
            interviewed on behalf of the World Bank Group Archives oral
            history program by Robert W. Oliver. Mr. Baum earned a PhD
            in economics from Harvard University, and he joined the
            World Bank after working on the Marshall Plan with the US
            Government, During his tenure at the Bank from 1959 to 1986,
            Mr. Baum worked in the following areas: in the Europe,
            Africa and Australasia department as an economist/loan
            officer (1959-1962); in the department of operations,
            Europe, as a loan officer (1962-1964); in the projects
            department, transportation, as an assistant director
            (1964-1968) and associate director (1968-1972); as vice
            president of projects staff (1972-1974); as chairman of the
            consultative group on international agricultural research
            (1974-1984); and in operations policy as a vice president
            (1982-1986). His transcript concerns his time working on
            projects for France, Algeria, Spain, and Portugal, as well
            as becoming a liaison between the projects department and
            the transportation division. His appreciation of the unique
            experience inspired him to write two books on the work of
            the World Bank, Investing in Development: Lessons of World
            Bank Experience and Partners Against Hunger.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Summary
        </docna>
        <display_title>Transcript of oral history
            interview with Warren C. Baum held on July 23, 1986 (Vol. 2)
            : Summary</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/1986/07/17968665/transcript-oral-history-interview-warren-c-baum-held-july-23-1986-vol-2-summary</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Transcript</docty>
        <subtopic>Access to Finance,Post Conflict Reconstruction,Rural Portfolio Improvement,Labor Policies,Poverty Monitoring &amp; Analysis</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Rural Development,Poverty Reduction,Conflict and Development,Social Protections and Labor</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000356161_20130705131440</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>World Bank Group Archives oral history program</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Rural Development,Poverty Reduction,Conflict and Development,Social Protections and Labor</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Board Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            economics, Green Revolution, innovation,
            Loan, meetings, negotiation, Operations, organizational
            structure, polarization, Programs
        </keywd>
        <owner>Knowledge &amp; Information Services (ITSKI)</owner>
        <repnb>78928</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Extension &amp; Research</ml:concept><ml:concept>Railways Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Research and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Research</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Railways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Highways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>