<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>﻿                                                                 78969&#13;
                                                                 v1&#13;
                Summary of Oral History Transcript&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                          Cosgrove, John H.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Interview conducted by Jochen Kraske and William Becker, on 1995-05-03&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Cosgrove covers his educational and professional background prior&#13;
to coming to the Bank in 1991 as Executive Director (ED) representing&#13;
the Western Pacific constituency numbering 12 countries. Starting at&#13;
the Australian Treasury in the early 60's, he worked mostly on&#13;
domestic economic analysis and policy issues which subsequently took&#13;
him to the Australian Mission to the European Community in Brussels in&#13;
1973, the OECD in Paris in 1974, back in Canberra in 1976 working on&#13;
international issues, a second posting overseas to the High Commission&#13;
in London (1982-1985), then back to the Treasury in Canberra until he&#13;
was appointed ED at the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Cosgrove discusses briefly the structure of the Australian&#13;
Government, its membership in the multilateral financial institutions,&#13;
and the Treasury's philosophical perspective and Australia's evolving&#13;
philosophical position on economic matters. According to Cosgrove, in&#13;
spite of the Treasury's orthodoxy it has undertaken quite a few&#13;
important reforms over the years, especially, in the area of&#13;
microeconomics which saw the removal of quite a few structural&#13;
barriers to economic growth and freeing up the market to the rest of&#13;
the world.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Cosgrove discusses his objectives and accomplishments as ED, his&#13;
chair's firm approach on the Bank's budget in general, and balancing&#13;
the various interests of the constituencies he represents. He stresses&#13;
the distinction between finance and development assistance, and&#13;
maintains that the Bank is more focused on financial transfers and not&#13;
sufficiently focused on economic development. In line with the&#13;
&amp;#12;Australian Treasury's underlying economic philosophy, he strongly&#13;
feels that self-help goes a long way; a principle that applies to&#13;
almost any country. To that effect, he talks of the Bank and Fund's&#13;
crucial role in bringing about a sound economic framework with&#13;
emphasis on capacity building, and points to the lack of effective&#13;
technical assistance.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     In light of the general tendency of Board members to act as&#13;
Ambassadors, he stresses the specific role of an ED as a member of the&#13;
Bank's Executive Board as well as an official of the Bank. In that&#13;
context, he talks of his rapport with the shareholders and Canberra&#13;
specifically. He discusses Australia's weightier role as a bigger&#13;
stakeholder in the Asian Development Bank than in the Bank, at the&#13;
same time, cites the reasons for Australia's declining financial input&#13;
in both institutions and specifically in its IDA contributions, and&#13;
Australia's two major export markets in Asia, Japan and Korea, and the&#13;
Association of the Asia-Pacific Economic Corporation (APEC).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Cosgrove addresses the workings of the Board, his relationship&#13;
with its members, and the impediment of frequent turnovers. The review&#13;
of Board procedures, and his support of the recommendations of the&#13;
Haralz-Naim report. He elaborates on the ensuing reforms resulting in,&#13;
among other things, improved Board/Management relations but with still&#13;
rather limited informal contact, the Board's increased influence in&#13;
covering policy issues even though he still feels that the Board is&#13;
weak and should be more determined about its role as the decision-&#13;
making body of this organization. He opines on certain remedial steps&#13;
that he would like to see put into effect, offers a rationale of the&#13;
underlying tension between Management and the Board and, in that&#13;
context, assesses the roles of Presidents Conable and Preston.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     On Board representation, he talks of the advantages in having a&#13;
smaller Board and mentions the postponement of reviewing the Board's&#13;
structure and composition. Again, he discusses the need for effective&#13;
technical assistance, argues against the Bank's involvement in areas&#13;
&amp;#12;that lie outside of its comparative advantage, such as granting money&#13;
to U.N. agencies to help them finance their own operations, and&#13;
getting involved in micro-credit type facilities. He praises the&#13;
Bank's achievements on environmental issues, and the pivotal role of&#13;
the U.S. chair in easing pressures from environmentalists associated&#13;
with the execution of some Bank projects.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Cosgrove discusses the reasons why he does not favor an&#13;
inspection panel, the Bank's progress on the issue of women in&#13;
development, opines on the notion of the Bank as a 'bloated&#13;
bureaucracy' including its over generous remuneration, Management's&#13;
handling of staff reductions, his disappointment in seeing less coming&#13;
in the way of savings from higher productivity per employee-on which&#13;
he elaborates--than from lowering the number of employees, and&#13;
concludes in stressing the crucial role of the shareholders in&#13;
affecting change in terms of cost consciousness and accountability in&#13;
the Bank.&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="17969303">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1995/05/17969303/transcript-oral-history-interview-cosgrove-john-h-held-may-3-1995-vol-1-2-summary-oral-history-transcript
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1995/05/17969303/transcript-oral-history-interview-cosgrove-john-h-held-may-3-1995-vol-1-2-summary-oral-history-transcript</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1995/05/17969303/transcript-oral-history-interview-cosgrove-john-h-held-may-3-1995-vol-1-2-summary-oral-history-transcript</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2008-12-02T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2008-12-02T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2013/07/05/000356161_20130705173920/Rendered/INDEX/789690v10TRN0C00Summary0May03001995.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2013/07/05/000356161_20130705173920/Rendered/PDF/789690v10TRN0C00Summary0May03001995.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>1995-05-03T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2013-07-05T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>2</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>2</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Transcript of oral history interview with
            John H. Cosgrove held on May 3, 1995
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            In May 1995, John H. Cosgrove was
            interviewed on behalf of the World Bank Group Archives oral
            history program by Jochen Kraske and William Becker. During
            his World Bank tenure from 1991 to 1995, Mr. Cosgrove served
            as executive director representing the Western Pacific
            states. Cosgrove discusses his objectives and
            accomplishments as executive director. His transcript
            concerns his relationship with the board and its members,
            the progress of the World Bank on the issue of women in
            development, and its handling of staff reductions. He
            concludes his discussion by stressing the crucial role of
            shareholders in affecting change in terms of cost
            consciousness and accountability in the World Bank.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Summary
        </docna>
        <display_title>Transcript of oral history
            interview with John H. Cosgrove held on May 3, 1995 (Vol. 2)
            : Summary</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/1995/05/17969303/transcript-oral-history-interview-john-h-cosgrove-held-may-3-1995-vol-2-summary</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Transcript</docty>
        <subtopic>Public Sector Corruption &amp;
            Anticorruption Measures,Hazard Risk Management,Emerging Markets,Corporate Law,Debt Markets</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Private Sector Development,Law and Development,Public Sector Development,Urban Development</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000356161_20130705173920</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>World Bank Group Archives oral history program</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Private Sector Development,Law and Development,Public Sector Development,Urban Development</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Board Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            accountability, Board members, capacity
            building, Corporation, Development Bank, economic
            development, environmental issues, export markets, financial
            institutions, limited, micro-credit, savings, shareholders,
            stakeholder, technical assistance, Treasury, turnovers
        </keywd>
        <owner>Knowledge &amp; Information Services (ITSKI)</owner>
        <repnb>78969</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Treasury</ml:concept><ml:concept>Micro-Credit</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>