<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>ï»¿                                                   Copy_ o f _ Copies&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                   Classification: OH/_ _ __&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                         78951&#13;
                                                         v2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       The World Bank/IFC Archives&#13;
&#13;
               Oral Histmy Program&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                Transcript of interview with&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                 SIR ALEXANDER CAIRNCRQSS&#13;
&#13;
                              and&#13;
                        'WILLIAM DIAMOND&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
               lJate:     January 10. 1985&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
B)r.                    Charles zjegler&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          PRINI'ED AND REPRODUCED ON ACID FREE PAPER&#13;
&amp;#12;INTERVIEWEE:     SIR ALEC CAIRNCROSS&#13;
INTERVIEWER:     CHARLES ZIEGLER&#13;
January 10, 1985&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:        Today is January 10, 1985.   My name is Charles Ziegler, and&#13;
I have with me here at the Headquarters of the World Bank the&#13;
distinguished economist Sir Alec Cairncross who, in 1954, undertook a&#13;
study on behalf of the World Bank which lead directly to the&#13;
establishment of the Economic Development Institute, or EDI, and who&#13;
served as its first Director from July, 1955 until December, 1956.         I'm&#13;
privileged to have with me also during this interview Mr. William Diamond&#13;
who, during a long and illustrious career with the Bank, served as a&#13;
staff member of the Economic Development Institute during Sir Alec's&#13;
directorship.     Sir Alec, may I begin by asking you to describe how you&#13;
first became involved with EDI.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CAIRNCROSS:     I was asked in 1954 if I would prepare a report for the Bank&#13;
on the question of whether there should be an Institute or not.      It&#13;
hadn't been decided at that stage whether to have an Institute, and what&#13;
form it should take if it were decided to go ahead.      I was asked, if I&#13;
remember correctly, by Mr. Demuth, with whom I had an association going&#13;
back some years.     I agreed to come out and spent the summer of 1954&#13;
inquiring of academics, members of the Bank, various people to whom I&#13;
talked, what they thought about the project.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    I remember in particular going to see Jacob Viner.     Viner took the&#13;
view that it wouldn't really do much good to bring people away from their&#13;
administrative duties here to Washington.      It was preferable to have&#13;
somebody who'd go out and more or less sit opposite the men who were&#13;
being trained, see what problems were coming to them across the desk, and&#13;
teach them how to handle them on the spot.     That was his view.   Now he&#13;
was a very experienced man, and I was very much struck by this thought&#13;
that you could only teach people in terms of the actual problems that&#13;
they were handling.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                     -2-&#13;
&#13;
CAIRNCROSS&#13;
&#13;
    (Cairncross) However, when I talked with other people, and&#13;
particularly two or three people in the Bank, I came to the conclusion&#13;
that an EDI should be started.    I was very hesitant about it.    It was not&#13;
a conclusion which I put forward very dogmatically, but it did seem to me&#13;
that there was scope for something more in the nature of a staff college&#13;
than a purely academic body, that the Bank had a great deal of experience&#13;
to be drawn on, and that it should be possible to communicate that to men&#13;
brought here.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    It was also a very important point in my mind that the Bank had a&#13;
feeling that what was holding up development in the countries they were&#13;
lending to was not capital.    They could provide the capital.    But it was&#13;
more other difficulties of a managerial character--there were various&#13;
impediments--and that until they had people adequately trained in the&#13;
handling of projects, in thinking about how to run an economy, the&#13;
business that they were trying to engage in--of accelerating&#13;
development--would not succeed.    So I could see the importance of an&#13;
educational role in a body attached to the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Unfortunately, my university took the view that, if I were released,&#13;
they could only spare me for one year.     I'd only recently taken up my&#13;
duties in a quite new department there, and after a little further&#13;
discussion it was agreed that I could be released for eighteen months.         I&#13;
came here in the middle to 1955, knowing that I would have to wind up at&#13;
the end of 1956.    That meant, therefore, that my involvement with EDI&#13;
consisted, a, in submitting a report in 1954; b, in preparing for and&#13;
running a first course; and, c, running the first half of the second&#13;
course.   It was therefore a very limited participation, in terms of time,&#13;
over that period.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                      -3-&#13;
&#13;
CAIRN CROSS&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:        Could you describe the process by which you were selected?&#13;
Do you know anything about how it came to be that you were the one chosen?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CAIRNCROSS:     No, I don't think I could tell you much about that.       I had&#13;
written virtually nothing on development.     When I came to ask myself what&#13;
I knew about the subject, I decided that I was very ignorant.       The&#13;
literature on it didn't seem to me to be very illuminating, but it was&#13;
quite extensive, and I thought that the people who knew about development&#13;
were probably in the Bank.     That was an illusion, as I discovered, but I&#13;
think that most of us were really very ignorant about development in the&#13;
middle 1950's.     The question wasn't how to handle an economy to get full&#13;
employment.     We all thought we knew about that.    But if you asked what do&#13;
you do to get faster growth in an economy, although economists wrote a&#13;
lot about it, much of what they wrote seemed to me to be beside the&#13;
point, and very little of what they wrote really bore on what you did as&#13;
a government.     So I didn't feel that I was necessarily very much&#13;
handicapped.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    As to why I was picked on, I think the answer must be largely that&#13;
Mr. Black was guided by Dick Demuth.     Dick had known me in Berlin in&#13;
1945-46, and we had had contact at various places later.       I was at the&#13;
Merrill Center in 1953, and I saw Mr. Black and others there, so they may&#13;
have thought that, from their personal knowledge, I might be able to&#13;
tackle this job.     But I didn't appear for an interview, I didn't submit&#13;
an application.     There was nothing of that kind.    I simply was asked if I&#13;
would be prepared to do it.     And I was asked that question after I had&#13;
submitted my report, so that the primary question is, why did they pick&#13;
on me to write the report?     Once that was done, as so often happens, I&#13;
was asked why I couldn't come and follow up the recommendations and put&#13;
them into practice myself.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                         -4-&#13;
&#13;
CAIRNCROSS&#13;
&#13;
DIAMOND:        May I ask you a question?      Aside from your personal&#13;
connection with Dick, do you see any tie-in between your selection and&#13;
your involvement in planning during the war, and in the reconstruction of&#13;
Germany?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CAIRNCROSS:     I don't think so.     I had, in fact, a long association with&#13;
various departments in Whitehall, where I was involved in economic&#13;
management and planning at first hand, and when it came to running the&#13;
Institute I found that that was my biggest single advantage.         I drew far&#13;
more heavily on what I knew about the way in which governments behave&#13;
than on any theoretical understanding of the process of development.            I&#13;
think that was probably a sounder base.         But I don't know that it was&#13;
very much in the minds of the Board or Mr. Black when I was approached.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:        Sir Alec, what were your expectations when you undertook to&#13;
become the first Director of the Economic Development Institute?          How did&#13;
you believe that it was going to evolve?        What was your idea in that&#13;
respect?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CAIRNCROSS:     Well, I was full of trepidation, I suppose.      I was not at&#13;
all certain how it would go.        I could see the obstacles very clearly.&#13;
There were problems in selecting participants who would form a&#13;
homogeneous group.     They might not be able to speak English adequately.&#13;
They might not have studied any economics at all, or some might and the&#13;
others not, so that you got a very heterogeneous scatter between the&#13;
participants.     Some might take to study, and others might be completely&#13;
incapable of settling down to study, given the duties they'd been&#13;
performing.     Some might be in senior positions, others from very junior&#13;
positions.    And looking at that side of things, I could see that there&#13;
would be problems in making them give their energies to pursuing the&#13;
course and preserving a level of discourse that was taxing and yet was&#13;
&amp;#12;                                      -5-&#13;
&#13;
CAIRN CROSS&#13;
&#13;
(Cairncross) within the competence of all those taking part.     We had to&#13;
set a high standard, and yet it had to be one that was within the grasp&#13;
of those who were trying to achieve it.     That was one source of problem.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       Then, I did not foresee many of the difficulties that we encountered&#13;
in practice.     We had thought at the beginning that it would be nice to&#13;
have all the men in one place, leaving their wives behind, leaving their&#13;
families, housed together so that they could engage in discussion with&#13;
one another on the same kind of footing as I recall from the Merrill&#13;
Center, where I spent the summer of 1953, or as, for instance, at Henley,&#13;
at the Administrative Staff College there, or at various other places&#13;
that I'd seen where men come to be trained, and put in their time in that&#13;
way.    And I had earlier suggested that we should try to find a country&#13;
house where we would be a little remote from the Bank, not too close to&#13;
it, but still within striking distance, so that we wouldn't be forgotten,&#13;
and would be really able to tap people from the Bank who could come out&#13;
and take part.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       In fact we didn't find a house of that kind, and I think it was just&#13;
as well.    We found a house at 1620 Belmont Street, which seemed, at first&#13;
sight, to be within the parameters that I had in mind.     And we took great&#13;
trouble over the furnishing of it, and the decoration of it, to make sure&#13;
that it was comfortable, and elegant in its way, and that people living&#13;
there would have no grounds for complaint.     But in fact the mechanics of&#13;
housing and looking after the participants was a very imporant issue&#13;
which I had not taken sufficient account of.     I think we all felt that&#13;
the first course would have been much more successful if we had run it&#13;
differently, if we had had something like the accommodation there is now,&#13;
and if families could have been brought over at the expense of the&#13;
participants.     There were those who foresaw this.   I remember Monsieur&#13;
Hoppenot, the French Executive Director, regarded me as quite inhuman&#13;
&amp;#12;                                      -6-&#13;
&#13;
CAIRN CROSS&#13;
&#13;
(Cairncross) when I was proposing that wives should be left behind and&#13;
spoke to me indignantly about this proposal.     He forecast what proved to&#13;
be true, that this was not the ideal way to run things.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       When we came to the second course, we remedied most of that.     We put&#13;
the participants in a hotel at 2400 16th Street.     They didn't have to&#13;
have just one room which was both a study and a bedroom.     They didn't&#13;
have to share bathrooms, which caused some of them a good deal of&#13;
indignation.     They were living in different circumstances, and I think&#13;
they were rather more relaxed.     We were trying too hard on the first&#13;
course.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       But you asked me what did I foresee at the beginning, what did I hope&#13;
for?     Well, one thing I hoped for very much was that if people came into&#13;
association with the Bank through studying here, they would carry with&#13;
them ideas that were more congenial to the Bank when they went back to&#13;
their own country, would be more understanding of what the problem was&#13;
that the Bank was trying to assist in solving, and would build up over&#13;
the years a cadre of qualified experts in economic management who could&#13;
begin to have a genuine impact on the development of their countries.        It&#13;
wasn't a question of just educating a random fifteen to twenty&#13;
participants in the problems of development.     It was more building up a&#13;
core of people who would, together, have an impact.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       I thought also that it would do the Bank a great deal of good.     I had&#13;
in mind that the Institute would be a kind of think tank for the Bank.&#13;
It would not necessarily do a great deal of research but it would think&#13;
out issues, think out policies, see the objections to them, and, by&#13;
tapping the Bank's experience, see where that experience pointed to&#13;
courses of action that were not being pursued, or avoiding action of a&#13;
kind which was not very helpful from the point of view of development.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                      -7-&#13;
&#13;
CAIRN CROSS&#13;
&#13;
       (Cairncross) Thirdly, I thought that the Institute could be a link&#13;
between the universities and academics generally, and the Bank.      I felt&#13;
that there was not enough dialogue between the Bank, in its very&#13;
practical activities, and the people engaged in thinking about the&#13;
problems of development in the universities and elsewhere.     I thought&#13;
that there could be a group who would serve as that bridge.     I've always&#13;
been sorry that in a way the EDI didn't quite succeed in fulfilling&#13;
this.    We certainly tried in the first course to bring in as many eminent&#13;
academics who'd worked on any aspect of development as we could, so that&#13;
they knew of the existence of the EDI, so that they contributed to the&#13;
work we were doing, and took away from it whatever we could offer.       But I&#13;
somehow feel that that conception didn't go down much with the Bank.&#13;
They felt more self-sufficient than I think they should have felt, and&#13;
didn't encourage this aspect of things.     My experience of other&#13;
institutions of the same kind is that this does tend to happen.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       I was subsequently involved in setting up a rather similar body&#13;
attached to the British civil service where people went for training for&#13;
six months, and were released from their duties.     There, too, I thought&#13;
something could grow which would be intermediary between the academic&#13;
community and government servants.    But, again, it didn't work out that&#13;
way.    That side of things died, and I think it died partly through lack&#13;
of imagination on the part of the government departments concerned.&#13;
Maybe it's very difficult to make it grow.     There is a resistance.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:       Sir Alec, how did you and your colleagues go about&#13;
establishing a curriculum?    How did you come to decide what it was that&#13;
the individuals involved in the Economic Development Institute were going&#13;
to actually sit down, study, and discuss?&#13;
&amp;#12;                                     -8-&#13;
&#13;
CAIRN CROSS&#13;
&#13;
CAIRNCROSS:    That was one of the most difficult problems of all.   It came&#13;
rather late in the agenda.    We had to think up how we were going to get&#13;
participants at all long before we brought that up.    There was a whole&#13;
series of problems about how we established contact with the countries&#13;
concerned, how we were going to house the participants when they came,&#13;
what the terms were, how we arranged finance, and so on.    A hundred and&#13;
one problems, but the curriculum came rather well down the list.     But&#13;
when we got to it--there were only the three of us: Bill Diamond, John&#13;
Adler and myself--and we gave a great deal of thought to what we should&#13;
do.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      The first effort, again, was experimental and differed very&#13;
substantially from the second.    We wanted to start by taking them through&#13;
the whole intellectual process of thinking out what they meant by&#13;
development, what was involved in it, how you knew whether you were&#13;
developing, and then running through a whole series of policies: monetary&#13;
policy, fiscal policy, investment, agricultural policy, anything that was&#13;
involved in development, principally with the aim of showing the&#13;
interconnection between different things.    We rather felt that somebody&#13;
who's been in a government department sees the problems of that&#13;
department quite clearly, just from experience and from handling them,&#13;
but doesn't always see how what they're doing links into the rest of the&#13;
work of the government.    Therefore, we felt that they should at least be&#13;
made familiar with the interconnection between different policies.    We&#13;
also felt that the curriculum should provide for some work being done by&#13;
each participant on his own, induce him to write a bit about some problem&#13;
that he knew of.   We felt that they should not be studying all the time.&#13;
Six months would be just too rich a diet, and in fact it did prove too&#13;
rich a diet.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                       -9-&#13;
&#13;
CAIRN CROSS&#13;
&#13;
    (Cairncross) I felt that they should be taken on trips to look at&#13;
things, and I particularly felt that, since they were in the United&#13;
States, there was a great deal that they could see.       They would certainly&#13;
look at the Bank, because all the participants wanted to find out how the&#13;
Bank worked and were bound to give time to getting around the Bank,&#13;
whatever we did.      That was one of the bonuses that they could see in&#13;
coming to Washington, that they were making contact with the Bank.         But I&#13;
also thought that they should see something of American business,&#13;
American methods, American technology, and I wanted to take them to&#13;
different institutions like TVA, or to Pittsburgh to let them see some of&#13;
the factories there, or to various other places, the Port Authority of&#13;
New York, to see how a subordinate authority operated in America.        The&#13;
problem of central control and the relationships between different public&#13;
authorities: how did it work?      How did a nationalized industry, or&#13;
whatever you like to call it, work?      That didn't always work out as I had&#13;
thought.      For example, we went to Sparrows Point, and at Sparrows Point,&#13;
though I wasn't aware of it at the time, you had in Bethlehem Steel&#13;
pretty well the largest steel works in the world.       And they felt when&#13;
they were shown the Bethlehem Steel works that I was showing them a steel&#13;
works so that they would not build any steel works when they went back,&#13;
because they could see it was clearly beyond the scope of their country.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    On the other hand, I sometimes tried to go to the opposite extreme,&#13;
and say, well now, where is something small?       I found there was still a&#13;
factory in Washington--there weren't very many--which made iron work, and&#13;
we went to look at that factory, the smallest one I could think of.          It&#13;
had been a very rapidly developing factory because by the time we got&#13;
there we found they were also making large aluminium containers for&#13;
putting on trucks, for transport, so that they had developed from what&#13;
they did when the founder of the firm came from Austria about the&#13;
beginning of the century.     But when they were shown that they said, well,&#13;
why do you show us this kind of thing?       We have iron works, cast iron,&#13;
&amp;#12;                                     -10-&#13;
&#13;
CAIRN CROSS&#13;
&#13;
(Cairncross) all over the place.     We know all about that, it's nothing&#13;
new.     Or when they were taken to the railway workshops at Baltimore,&#13;
again, I remember the comment: we have railway workshops in our country.&#13;
Why do you want to show us all this?     Clearly, you are showing us things&#13;
we already have, or things we can never have.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       But it was worse than that because, to take two illustrations, when&#13;
they went to Sparrows Point I gave them quite a long talk on the&#13;
technology of steel making, and I remember enlarging on twenty-six foot&#13;
hearths and twenty-eight foot hearths, and I thought they would perhaps&#13;
acquire something from it all.     But the Nigerian participant, who was a&#13;
very intelligent man--he had a first in law from King's College,&#13;
Cambridge--came to me in the middle of it all and said, "Mr. Cairncross,&#13;
they keep talking to me about iron or, iron or.     Iron or what?"     I&#13;
thought, well, if they can't get that one right what's the good of going&#13;
on with this?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       Then when we went down to Knoxville to look at TVA, I remember that&#13;
they were given a talk which seemed to me to be not a very creditable&#13;
performance by somebody I felt should not have been put in the scheme at&#13;
all, and the Pakistani participant came up to me afterwards and said,&#13;
"Now, that was exactly what we should have been told."     It   was a talk&#13;
involving     references to input-output studies, and he had found that&#13;
input-output was not included in the curriculum.     He thought that this&#13;
was a great mistake, and that he would like to go and pursue the matter&#13;
in TVA.     I may say that, although we made appropriate arrangements, he&#13;
never did.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       But it did bring home to me this much about the curriculum.    First,&#13;
that you shouldn't have too much theoretical economics in it.        It had to&#13;
be pretty practical.     They were interested in specific issues.     Second,&#13;
you could forget about teaching them much about technology, because their&#13;
&amp;#12;                                     -11-&#13;
&#13;
CAIRNCROSS&#13;
&#13;
(Cairncross) minds weren't attuned to that, and they weren't really&#13;
interested in the purely technical aspects.     Third, they were really&#13;
looking very often for gimmicks.     Fundamentally, they were looking for&#13;
certainties.     They had come hoping to be given cut and dried answers to&#13;
cut and dried questions, and that isn't the nature of the animal.       There&#13;
are no cut and dried answers.     What they had to be taught was to exercise&#13;
their judgement in a more sophisticated way than before.      Teaching people&#13;
to improve their powers of judgement is not a simple operation.      They had&#13;
to understand the nature of the choices they were engaging in, the way in&#13;
which action taken in one place would have repercussions on policy&#13;
elsewhere.     So, I finally concluded that the curriculum, although it made&#13;
quite good intellectual sense, was not working very satisfactorily.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       At the end of the course we did what went rather against the grain&#13;
with me, but what probably was more sensible as an approach to the&#13;
teaching.     They all came thinking that somehow development must be&#13;
planned.     I had certain views about planning, having spent years of my&#13;
life engaged in it, and become rather sceptical about what plans were and&#13;
did.    And we decided that the thing to do was to start from the question:&#13;
How do you draw up a development program?     What is the nature of the&#13;
program?     What are the problems that would emerge in the course of the&#13;
program?     That appeared to be much more congenial from their point of&#13;
view.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       There was a certain element of deception in proceeding in this way, I&#13;
must confess, because it was certainly not my view that a development&#13;
program was necessarily the right starting point for thinking about&#13;
development.     But there were undoubtedly many things that did need&#13;
careful planning.     You had to see into the future.   You had to take a&#13;
view of the future in considering what was to be done.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                     -12-&#13;
&#13;
CAIRN CROSS&#13;
&#13;
    (Cairncross) My problem was to convey to them the way in which you&#13;
link together what we would call the price mechanism--the way in which&#13;
price signals operate on the market, the way in which market forces&#13;
operate--and the way in which government operates, and that one couldn't&#13;
really just regard it as a question of government doing all the job.&#13;
That would be nonsense.     Nor could one regard it as a problem of the&#13;
market, purely.   You had somehow to get over to them the nature of the&#13;
relationship between these two different forces.     And we did conceive of&#13;
it in that way.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Now--if I can just conclude on the curriculum--now that EDI has grown&#13;
and expanded to a very much greater extent, and is no longer concerned&#13;
simply with a general course of the kind that we were concerned with, I&#13;
think the same preoccupation with gimmicks and certainty is almost&#13;
certainly in the minds of the people coming from these countries to&#13;
Washington thinking that here is superior widsom, superior knowledge of&#13;
exactly what is to be done in a given situation.     But, I think one thing&#13;
that makes this more difficult now is that many of the courses are on a&#13;
specific limited area, such as investment appraisal, which came to&#13;
dominate the work of the Institute.    And I think if you're doing&#13;
investment appraisal, it gives you sometimes a wrong perspective, because&#13;
it obliges you to concentrate on one single project, and to do certain&#13;
sums in relation to that project, when in fact the big projects that&#13;
one's considering have to fit in to a program for the economy as a&#13;
whole.   I'm not really sure that a system under which your attention is&#13;
forced rigidly on doing, say, discounted cash flow calculations, is&#13;
fundamentally helpful in getting investment rightly programmed in&#13;
relation to a collection of projects, which is what is involved.     So, I&#13;
think that some of the problems from which we set out are still there,&#13;
and will always be there.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                     -13-&#13;
&#13;
CAIRN CROSS&#13;
&#13;
    (Cairncross) One other thing that has changed, of course, in relation&#13;
to the curriculum, and has made a very big difference, is that, when we&#13;
started, very few of the participants had done much in the way of&#13;
economics, and what they had done was often very limited and didn't&#13;
necessarily take them very far.     Now, I think it is possible to count on&#13;
at least some degree of sophistication in the participants and therefore&#13;
a rather larger element of homogeneity in the group which you're&#13;
teaching.     If you've got, say, fourteen people, all of whom are quite&#13;
different, and all of whom are of different ages and backgrounds, and&#13;
they're all there in the same room morning, noon and night, you have a&#13;
problem, because you can't easily find teaching materials that strike the&#13;
right level and are satisfactory for them all.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    One last footnote.     I think it was Joe Willits (Rockefeller&#13;
Foundation) who was responsible for guiding us to limit the first course&#13;
to fourteen.    We had earlier thought of twenty-five to thirty as the&#13;
appropriate number, and we came back to that, when we came to the second&#13;
course.     But it was put to me, and I think he was the one who said it,&#13;
that perhaps the first course would be better if we had fewer people.&#13;
I'm not certain he was right, because the very fact that you had fourteen&#13;
meant you couldn't break them up.     We'd only three on the staff.     We were&#13;
all frantically busy.     You had to have them all together, and that&#13;
constant discussion with the same people there all the time was not, I&#13;
think, altogether healthy.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:        What was the relationship between EDI and the Bank?     Of&#13;
course, by this I mean more than just the strictly institutional&#13;
relationship.    Also, could you perhaps reflect on whether this attitude,&#13;
in terms of the relationship, evolved from when EDI was being considered&#13;
to the time when you left the directorship?&#13;
&amp;#12;                                     -14-&#13;
&#13;
CAIRN CROSS&#13;
&#13;
CAIRNCROSS:   I think that there was a change, as you would gather from&#13;
what I've said.    The original concept was that the EDI would be somewhat&#13;
self-contained--certainly not right inside the Bank, more detached than&#13;
that--and would be able to form its own views, which would not&#13;
necessarily coincide with the kind of philosophy and thinking that&#13;
permeated the Bank.    We did want to have a degree of independence from&#13;
the Bank, in other words.    On the other hand, we also wanted to draw on&#13;
Bank staff freely, so that they could come and deal with particular&#13;
projects or particular problems, and give us their views.    That was the&#13;
basis on which we were proceeding.    I had thought that we were going to&#13;
rely on case studies which we could take ready-made from the Bank, and it&#13;
was a great shock to me when I found out there were no case studies.&#13;
Indeed, when we tried to embark on them, they turned out to be something&#13;
very different, again and again, from what the Bank staff thought they&#13;
were, because they had often missed the whole point in the episode that&#13;
we were asking them to enlarge on.    The situation changed through time,&#13;
and, as you can see, we were first drawn physically towards the Bank by&#13;
coming to Belmont Street, and then by the time Bill (Diamond) was&#13;
leaving--I should think by about 1958--we were beginning to move&#13;
physically further and further in, and it is now â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
DIAMOND:      Not yet, not while I was there, but shortly thereafter.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CAIRNCROSS:   It's now become another department of the Bank.    The&#13;
detachment has gone completely.    It's simply run as part of the Bank.&#13;
Now, it's arguable whether that is the most satisfactory way of running&#13;
it, given what happened, given that certain things didn't take root,&#13;
given that, as an institution, it didn't develop quite along the lines&#13;
that I had foreseen.    Maybe this was inevitable, but this is partly&#13;
because it didn't develop that other root in the academic community that&#13;
I had thought it would, which would have given it some kind of balance&#13;
between the two.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                    -15-&#13;
&#13;
CAIRN CROSS&#13;
&#13;
    (Cairncross) The relations with the Bank were very close.       The&#13;
directors took an interest, and came to some of the seminars.       The staff&#13;
of the Bank were always free to come in and meet the participants, and&#13;
did in fact often respond in that way.       There was frequent contact.   The&#13;
staff of the Bank were also drawn on to conduct seminars.       So that the&#13;
comings and goings between the EDI and the Bank were a very material aid&#13;
to the work of the EDI.    We made big demands on the time of the staff of&#13;
the Bank, and I doubt whether it would be possible to have continued&#13;
demands on quite that scale, but at the start we did really draw very&#13;
heavily because, as I have pointed out, we only had three people and we&#13;
had to have some others to help us, not just in individual seminars but&#13;
also in running a whole series of seminars.        Mr. Prasad, for instance,&#13;
who was I think at that time the Indian executive director (for the IMF),&#13;
conducted some courses for us and later was very helpful, too.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    On other relationships with the Bank, looking back, I'm a little&#13;
puzzled at the relationship we had with the Economic Staff of the Bank&#13;
because, when I think of it now, it would seem to me that there were many&#13;
economists in the Bank, and that it would have been natural to have had a&#13;
very close tie with the economists.    I don't think that our relationship&#13;
with the economists was really, fundamentally, any closer than with other&#13;
operating divisions of the Bank, the loan officers and projects people or&#13;
many, many different divisions.    That's one question that I'm a little&#13;
bit puzzled by.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
DIAMOND:       May I jog your memory, or your thoughts, on this.     First of&#13;
all, with respect to the relationship at the top level, I always like to&#13;
pay my respects to the president and vice president in that context.&#13;
First of all, there was no question of their support, but this wasn't&#13;
support on paper alone.    Black came, talked, not in a formal way, but in&#13;
the evening.    Every year he gave a talk.    But the vice president, Garner,&#13;
actually took a formal part in conducting a seminar which was part of the&#13;
&amp;#12;                                     -16-&#13;
&#13;
CAIRN CROSS&#13;
&#13;
(Diamond) regular curriculum.     He gave the seminar on management, if you&#13;
remember, in the course on administration and management, and this was&#13;
the kind of support which tended, I think, to fritter away with the&#13;
passage of time.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       But on the economists point, Alec, the economic work of the World&#13;
Bank in the late 1940's, and up until the period you're talking about,&#13;
the middle 1950's, had nowhere near the standing in the World Bank which&#13;
it does today.     Today the economic complex is a big affair; some think&#13;
too big; but it was of rather secondary importance at that time.        I don't&#13;
want to detract from Leonard Rist, but in Leonard Rist's days it just&#13;
wasn't all that important, or under his successors, and really didn't&#13;
become important again until McNamara and Chenery.     So I think the&#13;
relative absence of the economists as such from an active role in the&#13;
curriculum in those days is related to the place of economics in the&#13;
World Bank as a whole.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CAIRNCROSS:     Well, I'd like just to endorse, first of all, what Bill said&#13;
just now about Mr. Black and Mr. Garner.     I've no doubt that their&#13;
enthusiasm for the idea of an Institute was cardinal.     They were more&#13;
enthusiastic than I was, to tell the truth.     I can recall the occasion on&#13;
which Bob Garner really made up his mind about the Institute, when he&#13;
stood by the window looking out.     At that point it had registered with&#13;
him that we were not dealing with a single course and a single group of&#13;
people; we were dealing with the building up of a group, in each of the&#13;
countries with which the Bank dealt, who would be familiar with the&#13;
Bank's practices, who would have been in Washington and discussed what&#13;
went into successful development, and that group could really have a big&#13;
influence on the subsequent development of the country.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       Mr. Black, through thick and thin, was a very strong supporter of the&#13;
EDI.     I think that very much of the credit for anything that was done&#13;
should be with him.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                   -17-&#13;
&#13;
CAIRNCROSS&#13;
&#13;
    (Cairncross) On the second point, about the Economic Staff, my&#13;
recollection is that the Economic Staff was quite largely engaged in&#13;
helping to assess the prospects for particular countries.     They were&#13;
doing the economic aspect of reports on individual countries, and&#13;
therefore they had a practical job to do which in a way conflicted with&#13;
thinking in more general terms about the nature of the development&#13;
process.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
DIAMOND:      If I may exaggerate slightly, there wasn't much&#13;
macro-economics around the Bank at that time.     What I see, running down&#13;
the list, is economists who were country economists, but very narrowly&#13;
focused on a country or two, or project economists, which is what you're&#13;
talking about.   I see Sam Lipkowitz lecturing that first year on mining,&#13;
specifically on mining problems.   Douwe Groenveld was involved in&#13;
irrigation, but irrigation, period.   Murray Ross lectured on the Cassa&#13;
Program in southern Italy, and there are very few who were involved in a&#13;
world view.   One of them was (Dragoslav) Avramovic.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CAIRNCROSS:   But he was an outstanding case, I think, an exceptional case.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
DIAMOND:      But you were quite right in your analysis that these were&#13;
narrowly focused--and I don't mean that in any invidious way--on a&#13;
specific country or a specific type of project.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CAIRNCROSS:   When you date the development of the economists in the Bank&#13;
from Hollis Chenery, you may like to know that I was asked in 1964 to&#13;
come out and take charge of the economists as vice president, but I&#13;
couldn't do that.   Had I come back to the Bank, I would have certainly&#13;
been interested in bringing together EDI and the economists, and I think&#13;
there has been a rather closer association than the one â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢&#13;
&amp;#12;                                     -18-&#13;
&#13;
CAIRN CROSS&#13;
&#13;
DIAMOND:       And there were exceptions to that generalization I made.&#13;
After all, Paul (Rosenstein-) Rodan is one of the fathers of the EDI, but&#13;
he left the Bank in early 1952.     And there were a few others of some&#13;
eminence, but I suppose a reason they left is precisely because of the&#13;
role to which economics was relegated in those earlier years.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CAIRNCROSS:    There were very few who were looking at macro-economic&#13;
questions, that was quite true.     This is rather a diversion from what you&#13;
were asking.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:        It's all very interesting, actually.     The next point is&#13;
slightly different but it does again have an impact on EDI.        What was the&#13;
view of the member governments toward EDI?     Obviously, you were&#13;
approaching governments for suitable candidates.       What sort of reaction&#13;
did you get to the idea of EDI from the different governments?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CAIRNCROSS:     I think most governments were quite enthusiastic about the&#13;
idea.   They were getting it on the cheap, remember.       I seem to recall&#13;
that some governments who felt they were paying the bill weren't quite&#13;
happy that it should be possible to buy into EDI at fifteen-hundred&#13;
dollars a time and wanted to put that up a bit.        But it was expensive&#13;
from the point of view of the other governments in the sense that they&#13;
were losing the services of one their key members of staff for six&#13;
months, so that one had to look at it from that point of view, too.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      I think the directors of the Bank, in general, were initially rather&#13;
sceptical.     I don't think that the enthusiasm of Mr. Black and Mr. Garner&#13;
was shared right through the directorate.     That's not my impression.&#13;
They changed their minds.     I think they became much more interested once&#13;
they saw what was going on, but initially they were rather doubtful about&#13;
it.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                     -19-&#13;
&#13;
CAIRN CROSS&#13;
&#13;
       (Cairncross) Now, I don't think that was quite so true of the&#13;
governments.     I think that the governments could see the virtue of having&#13;
an Institute in Washington to which their men could come and learn about&#13;
development.     We wondered about the reaction in terms of what kind of&#13;
candidate they would choose.     Would they really send their best men for&#13;
six months?     I don't think they did send their best men for six months&#13;
but they did send many quite able candidates, and their interest grew&#13;
over time.     Once they had seen what was going on, I think they felt it&#13;
was worth pursuing.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       Some countries were very enthusiastic.    I can take Korea, for&#13;
example, because I was there about six or seven years ago.       It was&#13;
perfectly clear to me that in Korea the old school tie meant the old&#13;
members of EDI.     They more or less ran the country and were conscious&#13;
that they had been trained in EDI.       And I think there were other&#13;
countries.     Pakistan had a great many ex-EDI men who quite consciously&#13;
were pulling together and having an influence on development.       The&#13;
initial reaction was necessarily less enthusiastic than the later&#13;
reaction, because they weren't quite clear what they were buying and how&#13;
it would work out.     Once they had begun to see the reaction of those who&#13;
were sent, they were more confident about continuing to work in this&#13;
way.     But if you take--I'm looking at those who took part in the first&#13;
course here--some of them, for instance Mr. (Mushtaq) Ahmad, he ran the&#13;
railways in his country, and he was sent from Pakistan.       Sunthorn&#13;
Hongladarom (from Thailand) at one stage became the President of the IBRD&#13;
Annual Meeting.     He took the chair.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
DIAMOND:        He was director general of SEATO, minister of finance,&#13;
ambassador to the United States, to the Court of St. James, etcetera,&#13;
etcetera.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                     -20-&#13;
&#13;
CAIRN CROSS&#13;
&#13;
CAIRNCROSS:     There was varied experience.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
DIAMOND:        Director general of the Nacional Financiera of Mexico--this&#13;
is Jorge Espinosa de los Reyes--and now ambassador to Washington.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CAIRNCROSS:    And Udoji was permanent secretary of a department when he&#13;
came.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
DIAMOND:        He still is very eminent, very eminent in Nigeria, highly&#13;
thought of.     The man, the way he developed, doesn't fit your story about&#13;
iron ore.     He learned.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CAIRNCROSS:     He learned, but I don't know whether he learned about iron&#13;
ore.    They were a mixed bunch.   I could tell you other stories about some&#13;
of the other participants.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
DIAMOND:        (Abdel Moneim Ahmed Mohamed) El Banna became quite important&#13;
in Egypt for a period.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CAIRNCROSS:    One or two went back and went to prison, not necessarily for&#13;
bad reasons.     One, for instance, on the second course, Mr. In Sang Song,&#13;
who was the Korean representative, was initially imprisoned, but later&#13;
became head of the Export-Import Bank, and did all kinds of things in his&#13;
country, and very successfully.     He made a big contribution, I think, to&#13;
Korean development.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
DIAMOND:        If a story about In Sang Song is permitted, maybe this would&#13;
give you a chance to catch your breath.        He has said that after his six&#13;
months in EDI, to which he was sent in the days of Syngman Rhee, he went&#13;
back to Korea and Syngman Rhee said to him, good Mr. Song, you know all&#13;
about planning.     You are now minister of reconstruction.     Prepare a&#13;
plan.   So he spent two years, or something like that, as minister of&#13;
&amp;#12;                                     -21-&#13;
&#13;
CAIRN CROSS&#13;
&#13;
(Diamond) reconstruction, and prepared the first Five Year Plan for&#13;
Korea, after which Syngman Rhee called him in and said, good Mr. Song, I&#13;
like your plan.    You are now finance minister.   Please finance it.     And&#13;
he became finance minister.     I don't know how well he did, but he was&#13;
involved in many others things involving Syngman Rhee, so he was put in&#13;
prison, where he languished for about three years before emerging.        But&#13;
at the end of this he said he had spent six years in the service of his&#13;
country: three years as minister and three years as jail bird.     Then&#13;
after some years of rehabilitation he became, as you say, ambassador to&#13;
EEC first, and then after this--I saw him in Brussels, as a matter of&#13;
fact--became head of the Export-Import Bank, and is a man of great&#13;
eminence.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    If I may say, what you said about the Korean government being unique&#13;
in many respects in its attitude towards EDI and the role of EDI in Korea&#13;
being much more important there, is in part attributable to the fact that&#13;
they chose as their first man In Sang Song, who is not only a very able&#13;
fellow but a first class publicist.     In Sang Song was responsible to a&#13;
great extent for putting the EDI on the map in Korea.     He deserves some&#13;
personal credit for that.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CAIRNCROSS:   Well, he does.    I don't know whether you want me to recount&#13;
any story about In Sang Song, but I remember his intervention in one of&#13;
the seminars, when we were talking about investment.     He told a story&#13;
which has remained in my mind as a very interesting illustration of a&#13;
general principle.     He said that when Seoul was still flat on the ground,&#13;
and they were busy reconstructing, they had to decide what to do about&#13;
the brewery, which had been bombed.     They called in a group of American&#13;
experts who looked at the brewery, decided it was a write-off, and&#13;
submitted proposals for building a new brewery at a cost of about two&#13;
million dollars.     The government hesitated about finding two million&#13;
dollars for a new brewery and first called in a group of German experts.&#13;
The German experts looked at the demolished brewery and said it's really&#13;
&amp;#12;                                     -22-&#13;
&#13;
CAIRN CROSS&#13;
&#13;
(Cairncross) in reasonably good trim.       We could, for a very moderate&#13;
expenditure, get it back into working order.       They went ahead on this,&#13;
and simultaneously the Americans, who had made proposals, embarked on the&#13;
construction of a new brewery in conformity with their ideas.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    When the two breweries were complete and were competing with one&#13;
another, the interesting thing, Mr. Song pointed out, was that the&#13;
reconstructed brewery appeared to be out-selling the other.        He explained&#13;
that that was for a very simple reason.      That if you built something&#13;
which was too highly capital-intensive and too automatic, you were forced&#13;
to accept whatever product emerged at the end of the day.        It was often a&#13;
very standard product, not necessarily an acceptable one.        In the case of&#13;
the brewery that had been reconstructed, you could, while the process of&#13;
brewing was in progress, still test, add a little if you didn't think it&#13;
was to your taste, and end up with a product that was much more saleable&#13;
than if you just let it go on.     And he was citing this to show that&#13;
increasing investment didn't always improve your chance of selling&#13;
things.    You might find that there were other more economical ways of&#13;
setting about it.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    To come back to what was said by Bill about those who came on these&#13;
early courses, you really didn't know whether somebody was going back to&#13;
be a minister, or was going back to be arrested.        We had both.   I&#13;
remember that one man called Tomas Calix Moncada was recalled by his&#13;
government to become minister of labour and abandoned the course after&#13;
the first few weeks.    On the other hand, there was at least one member of&#13;
the first course who, within a short time after she had returned, was put&#13;
in prison.    You had a mixture.   You couldn't tell.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
DIAMOND:       That's right.   I forgot the Jordanian was also withdrawn&#13;
after a few months to become a minister, (Hamad El-)Farhan.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                        -23-&#13;
&#13;
CAIRN CROSS&#13;
&#13;
CAIRNCROSS:     There have been cases on both sides.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:        As we're talking about the members of the course, perhaps&#13;
you could shed some light on the selection process which the candidates&#13;
underwent to be admitted to the first, and even the second, class of EDI.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CAIRNCROSS:     I don't think that we in Washington had very much influence&#13;
on the selection, though we had to approve all the candidates.        In the&#13;
case of the first course, our anxiety was concentrated more on getting&#13;
the necessary numbers.     There was some member of the Bank staff who&#13;
personally interviewed anyone who was put forward as a candidate, and&#13;
therefore had to vouch for them.        He'd certainly to vouch for their&#13;
knowledge of English, because that was a very material condition. There&#13;
was no point in having somebody who didn't understand what was being said&#13;
or couldn't join in the discussion.        He had to vouch for their seniority&#13;
in the administration.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    I don't remember that there were many that were turned down at the&#13;
beginning.     There were one or two.    For instance, Ethiopia was anxious&#13;
that we should take young members of about twenty-five.        I thought that&#13;
it would be rather undesirable at the beginning to take men quite as&#13;
young and inexperienced as that.        They had to have some knowledge of how&#13;
a government functioned and what the problems were that governments had&#13;
to deal with.     But I could see that eventually we ought to be taking&#13;
young men of that kind since, if we didn't, we'd never have anybody from&#13;
Ethiopia.     They had no really senior people who were likely to be sent on&#13;
any of our courses.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    This was a dilemma.     At that time it was hard to be sure that you&#13;
would find an appropriate candidate from the very countries that you most&#13;
wanted to help.     The countries that had a good administration could&#13;
generally find somebody who qualified, and we could easily have staffed&#13;
&amp;#12;                                        -24-&#13;
&#13;
CAIRN CROSS&#13;
&#13;
(Cairncross) an entire course with people from India, Pakistan, and other&#13;
countries like that.        But these were not the countries that we were&#13;
aiming to help.        We were aiming to help the ones that had the most&#13;
difficulty in supplying us with candidates.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    There was a selection process, but the selection process was rather a&#13;
process through which the man on the spot, in the country concerned, was&#13;
asked to notify us as to the quality of the candidate.        And there were&#13;
one or two who got through who I think should not have got through, who&#13;
were not really up to it, who were not fulfilling really difficult duties&#13;
of the kind that we had in mind.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
DIAMOND:        You were also influential in one respect, or you had a hand&#13;
in the selection process.       You made a conscious effort, Alec, to get a&#13;
geographical spread.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CAIRNCROSS:     We did that, yes.    We did not want to have people all drawn&#13;
from one country.       We limited the numbers from any one country.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
DIAMOND:        If I look at the photograph of the second course--that's a&#13;
larger group, twenty-odd--there is a proportionately higher number of&#13;
people who came to positions of eminence thereafter, such as (Jose C.)&#13;
Cardenas in Ecuador who became minister of economy and finance minister,&#13;
and (Denio Chagas) Nogueira in Brazil, who became the first head of the&#13;
Central Bank.     There were others as well.    But this diversity was the&#13;
point that I wanted to make, that is, geographical diversity.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CAIRNCROSS:     Yes.    We did feel, I think, that the Middle East and Latin&#13;
America were rather poorly represented, initially.        There was a tendency&#13;
for Latin American governments to send their people to ECLA, and we felt&#13;
that they had some reluctance about sending anybody to Washington.&#13;
Chile, I think, was almost a write-off throughout.        I don't believe they&#13;
ever sent more than one single representative.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                      -25-&#13;
&#13;
CAIRN CROSS&#13;
&#13;
DIAMOND:        (Alvaro) Marfan, from the "long country".   Do you remember?&#13;
The top ones who strike me from this early course are Nogueira and Pepe&#13;
Cardenas, who really did get close to the top in their countries.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CAIRNCROSS:     Could I come back on a point?   It really relates more to&#13;
your earlier question about the curriculum, but deals with the&#13;
development of EDI.     We were giving only a general course and we did not&#13;
run special courses on, say, agriculture, or transport, and power, and so&#13;
forth.     But even at the beginning we included nearly all of the sectoral&#13;
studies in the curriculum, since we wanted to make sure that there was at&#13;
least some understanding of the problems of each sector before the course&#13;
was complete.     When special courses were prepared, they were&#13;
fundamentally elaborations of what had been part of the original&#13;
curriculum, such as transport, or power, or agriculture, or whatever it&#13;
might be.     These were all covered in the original curriculum, because we&#13;
wanted to give a rounded view of the process of development.      But later,&#13;
when shorter courses of a more specialized character began, they built on&#13;
that part of the curriculum.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:        Earlier you alluded to the physical process of setting up&#13;
EDI.     Could you elaborate a little more on that?   I remember reading that&#13;
there were some problems in actually physically setting up the&#13;
Institute.    Would you care to perhaps cite a few examples of some&#13;
difficulties you encountered?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CAIRNCROSS:     Yes indeed.   The first course was the one on which I was&#13;
most conscious of this because, since they were all housed in the one&#13;
building, it was important that they should be able to get in and out.&#13;
And we found infinite difficulties with the front door.      Now, this&#13;
doesn't seem to be an important impediment to development, but first the&#13;
key wouldn't turn, or else the door wouldn't close.     We had somebody&#13;
coming in dealing with that front door for weeks and weeks.       If it wasn't&#13;
one thing it was another.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                   -26-&#13;
&#13;
CAIRN CROSS&#13;
&#13;
    (Cairncross) That was only part of the problem.     I remember also that&#13;
on the very first day, just when I was due to give my inaugural address&#13;
in January, 1956, I arrived to discover that the water had been flooding&#13;
down from the bathroom above through the ceiling onto the carpet in the&#13;
room we were to meet in.   The Yugoslav participant had arrived rather&#13;
late, and had had a bath, and gone to bed.    However, he had forgotten to&#13;
turn the water off, and therefore the water flowed over and came down.&#13;
These may seem very trivial problems, but they certainly loomed very&#13;
large in the minds of the three of us at the beginning, because they&#13;
affected the morale of the participants.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    You found also that people like the Pakistani participant was very&#13;
curious that he should have come to a developed country where you&#13;
couldn't have a cup of tea in bed in the morning.     This seemed to him&#13;
extraordinary.   Nobody brushed his boots.   He had a room where he shared&#13;
a bathroom with another participant and explained to us that he'd never&#13;
shared a bathroom with his wife since he was married, so why should he&#13;
now share a bathroom with somebody else when he came to Washington?        All&#13;
that aspect of things which, as I say, may seem almost comic and&#13;
certainly subordinate, was in fact very important.     These mechanical&#13;
problems of making people feel relaxed and at home and not worried about&#13;
what's going on were of great importance.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:      As a follow-on to some of the things you've just said, would&#13;
you care to discuss the professional and social integration of the first&#13;
class, and of course you can extend that to the second class if you wish?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CAIRNCROSS:   Well, it would be greater in the second case.    In the first&#13;
case, I don't think there were many personal animosities.     There were&#13;
people who got impatient with one another.    They didn't like listening to&#13;
those members of the course who talked at greatest length and knew least&#13;
about what they were talking about.   There was a certain amount of&#13;
&amp;#12;                                     -27-&#13;
&#13;
CAIRN CROSS&#13;
&#13;
(Cairncross) friction.     There was only one woman on the course, and I&#13;
think in a way, as Bill would say, she was the surrogate wife.      She did&#13;
help to keep the peace, I think, to some extent, between the men.      They&#13;
did talk to one another.     They did form a group and, probably more than&#13;
we realized, learned from one another.      We were not always present when&#13;
they were having discussions with one another, but I think there's no&#13;
doubt that they did influence each other by the mere fact of having a&#13;
different approach to any question that we cared to raise.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    The professional association I would say was not great.      They didn't&#13;
talk much in terms of any background knowledge.      They might talk a bit&#13;
about running a big investment program or something of that kind, but&#13;
there were rather few issues that they really â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
DIAMOND:        I don't recall about specific issues, frankly, or specific&#13;
conversations.    But I have felt, whether it's the result of the personal&#13;
pleasure I derived, or the professional satisfaction of having been&#13;
involved, I've always attributed a great deal of importance to the&#13;
after-hours hour, when the group got together.      It was not required, but&#13;
the opportunity was made available to them.     And most of them did&#13;
afterwards spend an hour or so with one or more of the staff members,&#13;
having a drink and a bite to eat and talking for anywhere up to about two&#13;
hours.     I'm afraid I can't pinpoint any special subject, but it could not&#13;
all have been completely small talk, considering the fact that it went on&#13;
five days a week, every day.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CAIRNCROSS:    And the field trips, I think, were much the same.    We had a&#13;
break, to go to Pittsburgh or wherever it might be, and that brought them&#13;
together.     Just traveling by bus or by train wherever we went, they were&#13;
able to relax and talk about things.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                     -28-&#13;
&#13;
CAIRN CROSS&#13;
&#13;
    (Cairncross) I think there was a reasonable degree of integration.&#13;
These annoyances about the accommodation and conditions of living came&#13;
out from time to time, particularly at the beginning, but I didn't think&#13;
that this prevented them from deriving very considerable advantage from&#13;
the course.     This is borne out by what happened at the end, because when&#13;
they had an opportunity to say exactly what they thought, they spent the&#13;
morning tearing the course to bits and speaking in such terms that made&#13;
one think that it was madness to continue.      But when you got them in the&#13;
evening and asked them the question, shall we carry on with this or ought&#13;
we to abandon it? they were horrified at the thought that it should be&#13;
abandoned.    They all uniformly said, of course, you must go on.    And when&#13;
it came to the second course, there was no question at all about it.&#13;
There were these teething troubles at the beginning, and one can make too&#13;
much of them.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    They're interesting, I think, to anybody who is thinking of starting&#13;
an institute of this kind.     I know that very much the same problems have&#13;
been encountered by other bodies at the early stages, so that if one is&#13;
simply interested in running an institute, one ought to know what to be&#13;
prepared for.     But, once one gets past that stage and gets on to the&#13;
later courses, I think most of these things are minor.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
DIAMOND:        It occurs to me that you may not know that there remains one&#13;
person on the staff of the EDI who was there from day one, and this is&#13;
one of the two maids who you hired.      Myrtle is still there.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CAIRNCROSS:     Is Myrtle still there?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
DIAMOND:        And she would be a subject for interview on a totally&#13;
different level, but nonetheless interesting, because her memory is&#13;
pretty vivid.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                      -29-&#13;
&#13;
CAIRN CROSS&#13;
&#13;
CAIRNCROSS:     Well, I talked as if there were only three people around,&#13;
and that of course is not true.      Mrs. Fraser (mother of a staff member),&#13;
who acted as a kind of hostess, was there and handled a great many&#13;
things.    There was Mrs. (Myrtle) Timmins, who was a secretary and who did&#13;
a lot of work.      Jane Henley was there at the beginning, also doing some&#13;
of the secretarial and other work.      There was a librarian (Patricia&#13;
Taylor).      There was the lady who helped us originally with the decoration&#13;
and interior design of the building.      There were a good many other people&#13;
attached to us.      The Bank certainly did us proud in terms of the help&#13;
that they offered.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    In laying stress on the fact that there were only three of us, I am&#13;
speaking of course only of the professional staff, and there the pressure&#13;
was intense.      There was no time to spare for anything because, given the&#13;
way in which we worked, each member of the staff had to prepare an&#13;
outline of the discussion that was going to take place, so that the&#13;
members were supplied with a summary that he could read before and take&#13;
away with him afterwards to refresh his memory.      There was also the time&#13;
spent in the seminar itself, and that tended to go on every day.      There&#13;
was time in the evening when you had to be there.      So one had a pretty&#13;
long and continuous immersion in the Institute, probably more than would&#13;
have been sustainable in all future courses.      I think there had to be&#13;
some relaxation from that later on, but initially the effort of the first&#13;
course is something that one found pretty telling.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:        At this point, would you care to perhaps focus on some of&#13;
the most significant problems which you encountered in setting up EDI,&#13;
and the lessons you learned as a result of encountering them?      In other&#13;
words, if you had to do it all over again, what would you do differently?&#13;
&amp;#12;                                      -30-&#13;
&#13;
CAIRN CROSS&#13;
&#13;
CAIRNCROSS:      I think I would probably go for a rather shorter course.       We&#13;
had some hesitation about six months from the start, but we did satisfy&#13;
ourselves that governments were releasing men to go to other courses that&#13;
seemed to us to be much inferior for periods of up to six months.         And we&#13;
did feel that if you didn't have quite a long do, you would really get&#13;
very little across.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    It's difficult to say how I would do it if I were starting again,&#13;
because, of course, today conditions are quite different.      Starting&#13;
today, in 1985, you could take for granted a range of participation which&#13;
wasn't available then.     We were right at the beginning of the expansion&#13;
in training in economic management.      I think I would still go for&#13;
founding an institute rather than sending people to an academic body,&#13;
which was the alternative at that time.      There were many people who said&#13;
to us, it's really silly to think that you can teach effectively in an&#13;
institute rather than go for ordinary academic instruction, where you can&#13;
count on very high quality of staff to begin with, you can count on&#13;
adequate company, there is a large body of students.      They all fit in&#13;
readily.      You've got economies of scale, whereas this is a rather&#13;
intensive course which makes heavy demands on staff.      Are you quite sure&#13;
that these demands will be met year in, year out?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    I think I would still choose the course that we took, and I think I&#13;
would also still begin with a general course, rather than take specific&#13;
issues like agriculture, or transport, or power, or whatever it might be,&#13;
partly because, being an economist, I'm more anxious to get over the&#13;
general view than to get over the specific problems of one sector.         In&#13;
those days it would have been impossible, I think, to lay down the&#13;
requirement that they should all have taken at least an elementary course&#13;
in economics, but it would have helped if we could have laid that&#13;
condition down.      I would certainly have cut out the attempt to get them&#13;
all into one building under the conditions that we did start with.         I&#13;
&amp;#12;                                     -31-&#13;
&#13;
CAIRN CROSS&#13;
&#13;
(Cairncross) would have started nearer to what we had in the second&#13;
course, and I don't think I would have done anything very different.          I&#13;
think by the time we came to run the second course, we were fairly&#13;
satisfied that that was alright.     That was in keeping with what would be&#13;
successful.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
DIAMOND:        This implies a view towards physical integration with the&#13;
World Bank.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CAIRNCROSS:     It does imply that, but it does also imply, Bill, that the&#13;
Bank would be prepared to do what it did on the first course: give first&#13;
rate staff to the job.     The Bank, I think, made a quite substantial&#13;
sacrifice in letting you and John come to me and take part in that&#13;
course, and I'm not certain that in later years they were really willing&#13;
to let people of that caliber go to the EDI.     All I'm saying is that in&#13;
the second course I had people who were seasoned by the first year's&#13;
experience, who were of the caliber that was required, who were really&#13;
interested in teaching, who had something to convey and, although we had&#13;
rather a small number, I felt that that went down better.     A rather&#13;
over-taxed, small staff was better than too large a group who really&#13;
didn't know one another and didn't work as a team.     I think the&#13;
enlargement of the Institute has had penalties attached to it.       It was&#13;
easier to do the job well when you were only dealing with twenty-five or&#13;
thirty people, than when you had decided you were going to get through a&#13;
thousand people, to some extent, each year.     That's a very different&#13;
proposition.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:       As you see it, what has been the effect over time of&#13;
increasing numbers of EDI graduates working in the less-developed&#13;
countries?     I know you've mentioned Korea as a particular case in point,&#13;
but do you have any views, other specific countries perhaps, or even a&#13;
broader overview, over time?&#13;
&amp;#12;                                     -32-&#13;
&#13;
CAIRN CROSS&#13;
&#13;
CAIRNCROSS:     It's very difficult for me to say, because I haven't&#13;
encountered a great many of the participants in my life since 1955-56.          I&#13;
met a number of them in Korea, and that's why I instanced that as a&#13;
case.     I could speak from first-hand experience there.    You would really&#13;
need to turn to other directors who attempted to evaluate the course.&#13;
Anything I say has to be based rather on a priori judgement.       I did ask&#13;
myself constantly, during the first and second courses, how does one know&#13;
whether one is doing a good job?     How can you decide?    And I knew that&#13;
the fundamental test is whether, when the man goes back to his country,&#13;
he looks at a problem in a different way, puts into practice policies&#13;
that he would not have thought about if he hadn't been submitted to the&#13;
course.     And that is something that is very difficult to say unless&#13;
you're in immediate contact with the man.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    There is a simple academic way of judging these things, and that is&#13;
you make them sit examinations.     There always were people who wanted us&#13;
to make the participants take an examination.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
DIAMOND:        Including members of your Universities Advisory Committee.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CAIRNCROSS:     I didn't feel that this was appropriate.    I think it's true&#13;
of all education that one has to ask how you know whether you've done a&#13;
good job.     While it may be that for some purposes an examination supplies&#13;
you with an answer, where you're dealing with mature people engaged in&#13;
administrative duties, where, for instance, if you're conducting courses&#13;
in business management, you have exactly the same problem.       How do you&#13;
know whether you're doing a good job?       To some extent you're dependent on&#13;
the judgement of the man himself.     If he comes back and says I want more,&#13;
it's possible that he's really benefited, it's possible that he's doing&#13;
better.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                    -33-&#13;
&#13;
CAIRN CROSS&#13;
&#13;
    (Cairncross) I think one of the things that you can convey--certainly&#13;
it's been my experience in business management when I've had this problem&#13;
and had to build up from scratch, and to train men already in business to&#13;
do the job better--one of the things that you were anxious to do is to&#13;
build up more self-confidence, because people feel ill-at-ease in&#13;
handling a different set of problems.       Often the association with other&#13;
people doing the same thing is very important.       The bringing of these men&#13;
together, in other words, to a single course, affects their judgement of&#13;
whether they're doing their job well, because they meet other people&#13;
doing a similar job, and they think perhaps, well, I seem to be as good&#13;
as he is, where if they're only in their own job, in their own country,&#13;
they haven't got necessarily a good standard of comparison.       That's been&#13;
my experience with businessmen, at an rate, that often the biggest&#13;
service you can render them is not teaching them to do new calculations,&#13;
or look at investment appraisal in a different way, or anything of that&#13;
sort.   It's often a quite general thing. It's making them feel that they&#13;
may be wrong, but anybody else might be wrong too, and that therefore&#13;
they can approach their problems with a little more confidence, instead&#13;
of just withdrawing from them and not really attacking them at all.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:      Would you care to cite any of the more outstanding or&#13;
memorable personalities whom you encountered in EDI during these early&#13;
days?   I don't just mean the people in the course, but members of the&#13;
staff of the World Bank also.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CAIRNCROSS:    Oh, there's an enormous range of people.     If you look at the&#13;
list of those, for instance, who came as guest speakers it is quite&#13;
fantastic.    We had Nobel prize winners.     You had chiefs, like (Obafami)&#13;
Awolowo from Nigeria coming in.    (M.) Cuaderno, who was the Governor of&#13;
the Central Bank of the Philippines.    When I look through that kind of&#13;
list, it really is a parade of talent that is almost unimaginable today.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                      -34-&#13;
CAIRN CROSS&#13;
&#13;
    (Cairncross) But, leaving aside those who came in from outside, there&#13;
were also the people who came from the Bank.        There were among them many&#13;
striking personalities.      Mr. Black to start with.    To have the president&#13;
of the World Bank come and give a seminar, and take part in discussion&#13;
for these men must have been very impressive, because he treated banking&#13;
as most people would treat running a small store.        You could understand&#13;
what it was about when he talked, whereas most bankers talk in a way that&#13;
makes you think you'll never understand it.        That was one example.   Dick&#13;
Demuth was a very strong personality, and, for my money, I relied very&#13;
heavily on his judgement on any issue connected with the Bank.        I would&#13;
come to him for new ideas, too.      He was very much somebody who might be&#13;
sceptical of what you said, but he'd think it over and he'd always come&#13;
up with new, constructive ideas.      Now these people are rare.    But he had&#13;
them constantly.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
DIAMOND:         (Edward M.) Bernstein and (Irving S.) Friedman.    They were&#13;
IMF but they were practically â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CAIRNCROSS:     Well, we had Bernstein in as the very first speaker from&#13;
outside.      He's still at it, writing away at Brookings to this day.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
DIAMOND:        Pieter Lieftinck.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CAIRNCROSS:     We had Pieter Lieftinck.     That's another director of the&#13;
Bank.   Yes, many of the directors of the Bank were interesting&#13;
personalities in their own right, no question.        Monsieur Hoppenot, whom I&#13;
spoke of before.      I don't think we ever got him to give a seminar, but&#13;
Lieftinck did, and Prasad gave several seminars.        Then, remember, we did&#13;
make use of some pretty eminent people to run courses that we felt we&#13;
couldn't take on ourselves.      (Ragnar) Nurske, for instance, came up from&#13;
Columbia University and conducted a course for us.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                     -35-&#13;
&#13;
CAIRN CROSS&#13;
&#13;
DIAMOND:      (Simon) Kuznets.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CAIRNCROSS:   Kuznets came for one evening, leading a discussion on&#13;
inequality, which I still â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
DIAMOND:      (Frank W.) Notestein came to speak on population.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CAIRNCROSS:   We had Notestein, yes, who gave a very interesting talk on&#13;
population growth.    Whether he got it right I don't know, because always&#13;
demographers seem to get it wrong, and he started off by telling us that,&#13;
if I remember.   It's hard to do justice to all this, because there must&#13;
be many names that don't occur to me as I talk, of people who did a great&#13;
service by coming and speaking.     I think it spoke well for the reputation&#13;
of the Bank that, if we wanted to get somebody to come from&#13;
elsewhere--say, Ed (Edwards.) Mason to come down--they came.        They gave&#13;
us these services willingly.     I don't think that we were ever turned down&#13;
when we asked somebody to come.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Now, I can't believe that once you've been in business for some&#13;
years, you can count on that going on.      We had the advantage of being&#13;
new, and a lot of people were curious to see what it was like.       So they&#13;
came.   I hope they still come back.    But we had an unusual collection.&#13;
Similarly with the Bank.    I think the Bank, at the beginning, was very&#13;
anxious to see what it was like, and we could count on enthusiastic&#13;
collaboration.   People did give their time, did spend a lot of time&#13;
helping us.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Now, when I try to think of others who came, we mentioned Avramovic,&#13;
for instance, as somebody who helped.       There were many, many people who&#13;
came to give talks.    Marty (Martin M.) Rosen.     George Martin, I remember&#13;
speaking on how to get a bond market going.       Some people came who were a&#13;
bit disappointing.    There was always a mixture.     Some of the engineers&#13;
&amp;#12;                                    -36-&#13;
&#13;
CAIRN CROSS&#13;
&#13;
(Cairncross) were not quite as hot as I thought they should be.      We had&#13;
Al (Albert) Waterson, Tony (Antonin) Basch, (Siem) Alderwereld of course&#13;
came and spoke, I remember when he was there.    Simmy (Reynold E.) Carlson&#13;
came too, I remember.    Inside six months, you got so many people that it&#13;
must have been a bit of a whirl.    I was a bit worried that we'd overegged&#13;
the pudding, and that the unfortunate participants couldn't possibly&#13;
absorb from day to day the whole of the riches which were being poured&#13;
out in front of them.    It was just too rich a bag, as I said earlier on.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:      In closing, Sir Alec, is there anything which we've not&#13;
covered which you'd like to discuss, or anything else which you'd like to&#13;
add?   Mr. Diamond, also, if there's anything you'd care to add or&#13;
elaborate on, I'd be most happy to hear it.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CAIRNCROSS:   Well, there are one or two things that stick in my mind.        I&#13;
mentioned earlier that we're dealing with issues which are partly&#13;
theoretical, that is, partly have been the subject of economic analysis&#13;
and on which economists think they know an awful lot, and partly issues&#13;
which are governmental, so that they have to be looked at in terms of the&#13;
way governments act.    I have always had the feeling that the theorists&#13;
don't always understand the problem from the governmental point of view,&#13;
and the people in government are not always familiar with what the&#13;
theorists have to contribute.    There is in every situation of this kind a&#13;
need to draw from both experiences: the theorist and the practical man.&#13;
And I saw the EDI as one of the places where these two things could be&#13;
mixed, where you could draw on both.    I felt that probably, as I&#13;
indicated, my own contribution would be more in terms of recollections of&#13;
how administrative procedures and administrative problems are handled,&#13;
and can be handled, and the limitations of leaving things to sort&#13;
themselves out through market forces, or in some other way, than in terms&#13;
of knowledge of the finer points of economic theory.    I was doubtful&#13;
whether, beyond a certain point, economic theory really did help to&#13;
answer the questions.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                     -37-&#13;
&#13;
CAIRN CROSS&#13;
&#13;
    (Cairncross) If somebody asked me how much can we safely borrow&#13;
abroad, or what is the most appropriate tax system for an underdeveloped&#13;
country, or what we should do about inflation, I don't think that you&#13;
would necessarily get very far by reading the textbooks on these issues.&#13;
I think these are broad judgements that need to rely as much on your&#13;
knowledge of what would happen in a given political system and a given&#13;
political situation; that we have to pay regard to the balance of power&#13;
in any economy, and not just to the economic forces at work.     So, the&#13;
first thing I would say is that in any institution of this kind teaching&#13;
administrators, teaching people who have responsibility for action, it's&#13;
necessary not to lean too far in either direction, either the direction&#13;
of pure theory, or in terms simply of all the forms of government&#13;
control, and all the ways in which governments intervene and act to get a&#13;
solution to their problems.     For that purpose, you ought to have on the&#13;
staff some people who have had experience of government, and I am rather&#13;
worried when I see the Institute expand on the basis of bringing in&#13;
people, many of whom have a purely academic approach to the issues that&#13;
they're dealing with.   That's one point.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    There's a second point that is in a sense associated with it.      That&#13;
is that in people who come on courses of this kind--and I would judge&#13;
that probably the same is true of people who come on business management&#13;
courses, though not always, it's slightly different--there is a hunger&#13;
for certainty, a hunger for being given the prepared answer to the&#13;
question, the feeling that some people know the answer, and, if the Bank&#13;
doesn't know it, well, the Bank can't be doing its job well.     When in&#13;
fact we all know that that isn't the nature of the beast, that in all key&#13;
decisions you're in the dark.     You don't know the facts, you don't really&#13;
know where you are, you really don't know how the system's working, and&#13;
so on.   Of course, in theory you pretend you know all these things.    You&#13;
know exactly where you are.     You have a theory which starts from&#13;
assumptions, quite definite assumptions.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                     -38-&#13;
&#13;
CAIRN CROSS&#13;
&#13;
    (Cairncross) So when people come to you and ask you questions like&#13;
the ones I've given earlier, they are looking to some curious oracle that&#13;
is going to give them precise answers to their questions.       I think they&#13;
have to be taught that you're always handling uncertainty.       You're always&#13;
dealing with uncertain situations.     What you're trying to see&#13;
fundamentally is what are the options in front of you, what possible&#13;
lines of action can be taken, and what are the risks that you run in&#13;
taking this line rather than that line?       Maybe you have also to open your&#13;
mind to possibilities that never crossed it, and you ought to know more&#13;
about the background of the subject.     You ought to have experts there who&#13;
can tell you that you may not realize it, but knowledge has expanded&#13;
since your time, and there are all these new ways of doing things.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    But very often, certainly when you're dealing with ministerial&#13;
action, the minister says he's got to decide anyhow.       All you can do to&#13;
help him is to make clear to him the precise nature of the choices in&#13;
front of him, and what will happen, or what you think will happen, if he&#13;
follows one course or another, so that he's warned against taking one&#13;
line.   You may recommend to him to take another, but you really can't&#13;
recommend as if it were the only thing he could do.       Often, there's only&#13;
a little margin in it between the two courses that you're suggesting.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    But I come back to this point about certainty.       I think that it means&#13;
that the people who come on courses here almost certainly undergo a&#13;
process of disillusionment at some point, and unless the teacher is&#13;
prepared for that, unless he appreciates that they're coming with certain&#13;
expectations that he can't possibly fulfill, he's in trouble.       I was&#13;
bothered by this at the time because I couldn't profess that I knew the&#13;
answer to any questions.     I still don't.    And I thought myself, you see,&#13;
rather like them.   There must be some chaps who understand all of this,&#13;
and who could tell me.     But when I read the books, I thought they really&#13;
&amp;#12;                                     -39-&#13;
&#13;
CAIRN CROSS&#13;
&#13;
(Cairncross) didn't know any more, and they were often, to my mind, quite&#13;
wrong.     They were laying emphasis on factors that seemed to me&#13;
subsidiary, and often getting things the wrong way round, thinking that A&#13;
caused B when it was perfectly plain that it was, as often as not, the&#13;
other way round.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       The fact is that the whole problem of development is a difficult&#13;
one.     It has tended in the theories to be greatly simplified, and because&#13;
it's greatly simplified, it's thought that you can communicate it in a&#13;
course easily.     But when you run a course like the one we had, you find&#13;
it's not like that at all.     You're really trying to bring out just how&#13;
complex it is, that there is no simple solution, and that you've got to&#13;
take into account the whole social context in which you're talking.          And&#13;
that's different from one country to another.      So you hesitate to&#13;
enunciate general propositions.     There are some, but you've got to be&#13;
rather careful.     These are the two things I think I would lay emphasis&#13;
on, looking back.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       There may be other reflections.   There is a reflection as to scale,&#13;
and that worries me quite a bit.     There's a reflection as to whether you&#13;
do the job here or there.     We felt that what we were trying to do had to&#13;
be done here, but perhaps now more emphasis is necessary--and I think&#13;
that would be my judgement--on what you can do on the spot.      But then&#13;
there are a hundred and fifty different countries, and to get around them&#13;
is difficult.     All you can do in a way is to lend a hand to the ones that&#13;
ask for help.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       Lastly, perhaps I should just say a word about publications.     We&#13;
thought that something could be done if the reading material that we&#13;
prepared and the bibliographies that we had. in mind were disseminated all&#13;
over, and I think probably that has been useful.      I would like to know&#13;
more about the evaluation that the EDI puts on all that.      It still does&#13;
it.     I thought that there ought to come from the EDI--it may have been an&#13;
&amp;#12;                                     -40-&#13;
&#13;
CAIRN CROSS&#13;
&#13;
(Cairncross) impossible ambition--a series of quite short and rather&#13;
rough treatments, for teaching purposes, of some key issues.      And Bill,&#13;
bless him, managed to prepare a book on development banks which I thought&#13;
was absolutely the right kind of thing, the kind of thing EDI should have&#13;
been doing.     I think, had it not been published, had it simply gone round&#13;
as a series of readings, it would not have had the same influence.         I&#13;
think publication was indispensible.      It was always a great regret to me&#13;
that I wasn't there long enough to jog John Adler into doing even a rough&#13;
little book on fiscal problems in the less developed countries, because&#13;
there was absolutely nothing on that available.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
DIAMOND:        I jogged him for years without success.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CAIRNCROSS:     You jogged him, and he didn't do it, but even what he had&#13;
put down on paper, with a very little editing, and published, not sent&#13;
round in mimeograph form, published--people look at it differently when&#13;
it's published--would, I think, have made quite a difference, because&#13;
these are very big problems and, as I say, there was nothing.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    I'm not saying that we should have done research.      Research is a&#13;
different issue.     There was that question sometimes raised.   I'm thinking&#13;
of teaching materials.     I think the preparation of teaching material is a&#13;
very difficult operation.     I very much doubt whether it's being done by&#13;
EDI in the way in which I would be happy now, because it has to be done&#13;
by people who have really seen the problem, who've been involved in the&#13;
problem, and are writing for other people involved in the problem.         It&#13;
can be done.     It's not a question of the kind of teaching materials for&#13;
universities.     It's quite different.   It's a very skilled job and has to&#13;
be done probably by people who know that this is one thing that's going&#13;
to be asked of them at the end of any course they give.      I think that a&#13;
little more could have been done there, but maybe that's inhuman too.           I&#13;
asked for a lot of inhuman things, sometimes I was wrong, and I may have&#13;
been asking too much.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                      -41-&#13;
&#13;
CAIRN CROSS&#13;
&#13;
    (Cairncross) I think even on development, if I had only put together&#13;
some of the things that I thought strongly about, I might have influenced&#13;
some of the arguments about development theory that went on which were,&#13;
to my mind, absolutely beside the point, absolutely useless, but were&#13;
still regarded as great contributions to knowledge.        I mean, most of the&#13;
literature, I think, on development is not really helpful to a man in&#13;
government, or the stuff the people think is helpful to them in&#13;
government, like input-output, or ICOR's, and all that kind of thing.          I&#13;
just wonder how they persuade themselves that it's useful.        If they do&#13;
use it, God help them!     But there are real things that need to be thought&#13;
about.     I mean, the budget.   Everybody has a budget.   How do you do the&#13;
budget?    How do you control expenditure?    What do you do about taxation?&#13;
All these things are very real.      And for the less developed countries,&#13;
particularly, where the problem looks a little different, there were&#13;
things to be done.     There were publications that would have been&#13;
helpful.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:       Mr. Diamond, is there anything you would care to add?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
DIAMOND;       No.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:       Well, I want to thank both of you gentlemen for this most&#13;
illuminating ninety-some minutes, and thank you very much for&#13;
contributing so freely of your time to the Oral History Program of The&#13;
World Bank.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Kristi Cruzat, Transcriptionist&#13;
&amp;#12;             NOTE:   This item was transmitted to the Oral History Program&#13;
&#13;
in August, 1985, by Sir Alec Cairncross in the hope that it might be&#13;
&#13;
a useful supplement to his Oral History interview,      Sir Alec noted that&#13;
&#13;
it ,.,as written some years ago, and that John Adler had seen it before&#13;
&#13;
his death,&#13;
&amp;#12;                                      -1-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   THE ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT INSTITUTE 1955-6&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    In the late spring of 1954 I was approached by Dick Demuth, whom I&#13;
had first met in Berlin in 1945-6, to act as a Consultant to the World&#13;
Bank in Washington.     He asked me to review a proposal that the Bank&#13;
should provide some form of training for senior administrators from the&#13;
less developed countries.     This proposal had been put forward originally&#13;
by Paul Rosenstein-Rodan and had strong support from some of the Bank&#13;
staff who were keenly aware that many of these countries lacked&#13;
administrators with the skill and understanding to evaluate large capital&#13;
projects.     It was hoped to make the task of Bank loan officers easier&#13;
(and perhaps increase the flow of capital to creditworthy countries) by a&#13;
form of management education aimed Â·at key members of staff in these&#13;
countries.     The question was not so much whether there was something that&#13;
needed doing as whether it might be better done by existing educational&#13;
institutions.     There was a further question, how such a proposal would be&#13;
viewed in the countries concerned:     would there be enough applications&#13;
from men of the necessary seniority?     And might they not prove too&#13;
heterogeneous in command of English, familiarity with economics, age,&#13;
seniority, and so on, to form a coherent group for simultaneous&#13;
instruction?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    I was intrigued by the proposal;     all the more because it came&#13;
shortly after we had launched our experiment in management education in&#13;
Glasgow and followed a visit I had recently made to the Administrative&#13;
Staff College in Henley.     The prospect of spending some weeks in July and&#13;
August in America was also very enticing in the wake of my very agreeable&#13;
stay at the Merrill Centre the previous year.     I was not as conscious&#13;
then as I am now how uncomfortable the Washington climate can be in&#13;
mid-summer.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                     -2-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    So once more I left wife and family behind and headed west.         I&#13;
discussed the proposal with as many members of the staff of the Bank as&#13;
possible and went in search of academic opinion to Harvard and&#13;
elsewhere.    I had a particularly interesting talk with Jacob Viner who&#13;
put it to me that an administrator might gain far less from a course of&#13;
study in Washington than from someone looking over his shoulder and&#13;
commenting on successive problems as they landed on his desk.      It seemed&#13;
to me, however, that there was no immediate possibility of following this&#13;
recipe and that if the Bank meant to educate its customers it had better&#13;
put over its ideas and draw on its experience where its own staff was at&#13;
work, i.e. in Washington.    I had Henley in mind as a guide to what might&#13;
be attempted;   and for this reason thought first in terms of a country&#13;
house in the vicinity of Washington, but sufficiently removed from the&#13;
Bank to force the participants to concentrate on their studies,&#13;
undisturbed by the diversions of a large city.      The amenities of the&#13;
Merrill Centre also coloured my initial thinking and even made me&#13;
contemplate Southampton, Long Island, as a possible site in spite of its&#13;
distance from Washington.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    What I suggested in the end was a staff college to consider case&#13;
studies drawn from the wealth of material which must exist in the Bank; a&#13;
maximum of 25 participants; and a course lasting 6 months.      These&#13;
recommendations were found acceptable.      The President, Eugene Black,&#13;
needed little persuasion but the Vice President, Bob Garner, was more&#13;
doubtful.    It was the idea of a staff college that overcame his doubts;&#13;
as he meditated on the proposal he grew increasingly enthusiastic at the&#13;
prospect of a growing number of administrators throughout the world who&#13;
had shared a common training at the Bank and would come to be a kind of&#13;
corps d'elite in the world of economic development.      It was a vision that&#13;
was at least to some extent realized.      When I visited Korea in 1977, for&#13;
example, I found that a very large proportion of the top administrative&#13;
&amp;#12;                                      -3-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
jobs were filled by former participants, proud of their association with&#13;
the Institute that the Bank created, and grateful for the training they&#13;
had received there.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    There were other recommendations in my report that created more&#13;
difficulty.     It was simply not possible to find accommodation of the kind&#13;
I had suggested and the Bank in the end settled for a mansion house in&#13;
Belmont Street that had belonged to its first President, Eugene Meyer.&#13;
On grounds of cost I had also made no allowance for the transport and&#13;
housing of wives and families.     But as the French Executive Director, Mr.&#13;
Roger Hoppenot, was quick to point out, this Anglo-Saxon view of life was&#13;
somewhat unrealistic and less than human.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    However, the scheme was approved and the Ford and Rockefeller&#13;
Foundations offered to meet a substantial part of the cost, which worked&#13;
out at $10,000 per participant exclusive of the cost to his government of&#13;
releasing him.     The new institution was christened the Economic&#13;
Development Institute and was scheduled to begin operations in January&#13;
1956.   The first requirement was to find staff and the Bank enquired&#13;
whether I would be willing to accept appointment as the first Director.&#13;
Since I had no wish to abandon my career at Glasgow after only four years&#13;
as head of a new department, I suggested that I should ask for leave of&#13;
absence from my university for two years and see the first two courses at&#13;
the Institute to completion before turning the Directorship over to&#13;
someone else.    This suggestion, however, met with resistance from my&#13;
Vice-Chancellor and I began to reconsider the Bank's original offer.     In&#13;
the end, however, I submitted a compromise that was acceptable both to&#13;
the Bank and the University:     that I should go for eighteen months from 1&#13;
July 1955 to 31 December 1956, returning briefly from consultation&#13;
half-way through, to deal with any urgent matters affecting my&#13;
Department.     The effect of this curtailment from the proposed two years&#13;
&amp;#12;                                    -4-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
was that the second course had to be advanced from January 1957 to&#13;
October 1956 so that I could at least launch it during my term of office&#13;
and leave only when it was well under way.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    When I reached Washington my first task was to find a house where the&#13;
family could live; and on this I had great good luck for I was able to&#13;
rent a convenient house in Cleveland Park which, being in a cul-de-sac,&#13;
was free of traffic so that young children could play out-of-doors.        I&#13;
was even luckier in finding staff, since the Bank made available to me&#13;
two very able men, John Adler and Bill Diamond, who combined&#13;
administrative and teaching ability and undertook their duties with a&#13;
zest that never dwindled.   The redecoration and furnishing of 1620&#13;
Belmont Street was left to a skilled interior decorator and the Bank also&#13;
took charge of the organization and sifting of applications for the first&#13;
course.   This still left plenty of time-consuming administrative chores&#13;
among which the selection of a table of the right shape for seminar&#13;
discussions stands out in my memory as a prime example (we settled in the&#13;
end for a U-shaped table of light construction divisible into five&#13;
sections that could be used separately when required).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Although fourteen participants from as many different countries were&#13;
selected for the first course, only one had arrived by the beginning of&#13;
1956, and there was great uncertaintly as the days went by, how many&#13;
could eventually show up.   By January 4, when two more arrived, I had my&#13;
first experience of consumer resistance.     The Pakistani member of the&#13;
course was in a great rage and demanding to see the President:       there was&#13;
no morning tea, no one polished his shoes, and he felt insulted by "the&#13;
attic which has been assigned to me".     From then on I had ample&#13;
opportunity to observe how the living conditions that I had hoped would&#13;
foster study bred grievances instead.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                    -5-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    On Monday when the course opened I noted some of our housekeeping&#13;
difficulties in my diary:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    The front door was repaired endlessly, keys cut three times, finally&#13;
    a new lock fixed; yet the handle came off at the first pull. Table&#13;
    not installed until yesterday. Only nine participants arrived in&#13;
    Washington by dinner time on Friday. Icy weather for today's&#13;
    inaugural address at 10 a.m. with practically no audience at the&#13;
    start and Executive Directors drifting in one by one for the next&#13;
    hour. Fuses all the time. No cupboards in two of the rooms. No&#13;
    keys for any of the rooms. No maps for the front hall. No&#13;
    pigeonholes (my instructions countermanded). Notice board far too&#13;
    big and had to be taken down - in fact no new board up yet. No light&#13;
    in library except one that is badly placed. No chess, scrabble, or&#13;
    other diversions even now.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Most of these difficulties were soon sorted out but others remained.&#13;
The front door continued to give trouble; it would not shut or shut too&#13;
noisily.   Two men had rooms at what we might call garden level, which to&#13;
them was simply the basement; bathrooms had to be shared and as they were&#13;
often located between two bedrooms, there were plenty of opportunities&#13;
for absentmindedly locking the other fellow out.   Nobody had their own&#13;
car, or telephone, or personal servant.   And so on, and so on.   The&#13;
trouble was that while the house was rather a splended nineteenth century&#13;
mansion with over twenty rooms, it was ill adapted for use simultaneously&#13;
as a dormitory, office and seminar centre.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    At the same time the men felt cut off from their families and from&#13;
female company.   They might even feel some frustration because they knew&#13;
that their wives suspected them of having a high old time while they were&#13;
unable to justify the suspicion.   The one young woman among them (from&#13;
the Philippines) might be a dead loss from the training point of view -&#13;
although she needed no training in the use of the opportunities open to&#13;
her and took back some nineteen trunk full of clothes and other purchases&#13;
- but she certainly worked her passage in helping to restore morale, and&#13;
was an unfailing source of good humour and high spirits.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                      -6-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Virginia made no bones about how she had come on the course.           She&#13;
cultivated the President's wife with great diligence and had prevailed on&#13;
her to use her influence in the right quarters.        She had clearly little&#13;
to learn about public relations; and the fact that she had accumulated a&#13;
large dollar balance in New York while carrying out duties in the import&#13;
licensing department of her central bank must have struck the authorities&#13;
as evidence of this talent since she was arrested and imprisoned not long&#13;
after her return to the Philippines.        However, she was subsequently&#13;
released.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Other members of the course were at least as colourful.        There was,&#13;
for example, the Belgian who had some vague responsibility for the Congo&#13;
but came from Brussels and once admitted to me that he had agreed to join&#13;
the course because he understood that it was much easier in the United&#13;
States to obtain the drugs his condition required.        He drank large&#13;
quantities of beer and enjoyed nothing so much as taking cans from the&#13;
refrigerator, opening them in large numbers, and leaving them for others&#13;
to drink without actually offering them to anybody.        I was startled one&#13;
day to hear a distinguished guest exclaim, as he watched this&#13;
performance:     "Doesn't he know he's drinking poison?"     I asked what he&#13;
meant.     "That fat chap", he said, "suffers from a disease I know only too&#13;
well and the last thing he should be drinking is beer.        He's killing&#13;
himself."     Sure enough, within a week or two we had to send the Belgian&#13;
to a hospital and he took no further part in the course.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    The participants were a mixed bunch:       mixed in age, in seniority, in&#13;
educational achievements, in command of English, in garrulity.        We had a&#13;
few PhD's but that was no guarantee of intellectual depth, nor even- I&#13;
should say not least - in the case of a doctorate in economics from&#13;
Harvard.     One or two were clearly accustomed to throwing their weight&#13;
around but the large majority were neither very assertive nor unduly&#13;
demanding.     Tbey did not, however, take readily to what approximated to&#13;
undergraduate life.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                    -7-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    I had imagined that they would want to exchange experiences and talk&#13;
shop like old Whitehall addicts.   It hardly every happened.     One of the&#13;
few occasions on this course when I heard one participant cite his&#13;
experience for the benefit of another occurred in an exposition by the&#13;
Egyptian member of the case for the High Dam.      "I can tell you," said his&#13;
Yugoslavian colleague, "what the result will be.     We have had very&#13;
ambitious investment programmes too.      And what is sure to happen is that&#13;
you will have a riproaring inflation."&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    If one participant was asked to introduce a discussion of the&#13;
problems of his country, the others would protest.      "We don't want to&#13;
know all about Ceylon, or Nigeria or Mexico.      Besides, it's all so&#13;
boring.   We came to listen to what you could tell us and hear how the&#13;
Bank sets about development."   There were two difficulties about this.&#13;
One was that if they didn't get a chance to expound their own views and&#13;
undergo the criticism this would provoke, they might go back none the&#13;
wiser, to listen and make occasional comments was no way to learn.       We&#13;
could put before them the most outstanding thinkers in North America but&#13;
if they merely listened there was no guarantee that any new ideas would&#13;
lodge and develop in their minds and only too often it was evident that&#13;
the nub of what was said had escaped them.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    The second difficulty was the greater.      Like them, I had conceived of&#13;
the Bank as a storehouse of development experience readily available as&#13;
teaching material.   I had seen enough to satisfy myself that the Bank's&#13;
thinking was not always abreast of current theory and that in some&#13;
respects it was decidedly obscurantist.      But I was confident that it&#13;
could make up for this in case studies illustrating what was liable to go&#13;
wrong, and what was calculated to make a success of things.      Instead, we&#13;
found ourselves having to dig up our own case material and sometimes&#13;
putting a totally different complexion on cases where members of the&#13;
&amp;#12;                                     -8-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Bank's staff seemed to us to be emphasizing quite the wrong things.      As I&#13;
should have known from past experience, most people know only part of the&#13;
story even when they have been working on it all along.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    The construction of a suitable curriculum was by no means&#13;
straight-forward.   Apart from the difficulty of finding time to give the&#13;
matter thought in the middle of pressing administrative duties (and in&#13;
the intervals between those gin-soaked social evenings that sabotaged&#13;
attempts to think things out in Washington), there was an absence of any&#13;
adequate theory of economic development.    On the other hand, the&#13;
developing countries were infatuated with the construction of development&#13;
programmes.    I knew very little about developing countries, having hardly&#13;
ever set foot in one, and was almost totally unfamiliar with the&#13;
literature.   Most of the theory, so far as I could make out, had nothing&#13;
to do with developing countries:    it took development for granted.    So I&#13;
had to work out my own theory, such as it was.    I was very conscious that&#13;
the blind were about to be led by the, at best, half-blind.     Yet I had&#13;
one great and unforeseen advantage in preparing the curriculum.      I had&#13;
been an administrator and I had been a planner.    I knew what went wrong&#13;
with plans and I could imagine what went wrong with development&#13;
programmes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    What we ultimately devised was a course consisting of over a dozen&#13;
seminars, each on a different topic and spread over several weeks, some&#13;
chaired by myself, some by John or Bill or Professor Prasad (the Indian&#13;
Executive Director of the IMF), or by Ragnar Nurske (who came up from New&#13;
York once a week to lend a hand).    Before each session of any seminar a&#13;
brief (and sometimes not so brief) outline of the argument was&#13;
circulated, prefaced by a reading list:    where the articles cited were&#13;
difficult to procure we had them photocopied without undue attention to&#13;
copyright.    At half or more of the sessions we had a guest speaker,&#13;
carefully chosen, sometimes from the Bank, sometimes from business,&#13;
&amp;#12;                                               -9-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
government or academic life.              Other speakers such as Simon Kuznets or&#13;
Wallace Notestein came for an evening talk.              It was a rich diet and you&#13;
needed a good digestion.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    In order to afford some respite from everlasting seminars we went on&#13;
field trips from time to time to see factories, and other enterprises,&#13;
mainly for a day or two at a time but in the middle of the course for an&#13;
entire week on a visit to TVA.              It was not always easy in those days for&#13;
a group including coloured participants to find hotel accommodation,&#13;
especially in Tennessee and there were some embarrassing moments, even in&#13;
a northern state like Maryland.              But we had no difficulty in getting&#13;
access to a wide variety of places of interest from Oak Ridge to Sparrows&#13;
Point.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Many incidents on those trips come back to me vididly.               I assumed&#13;
that the participants would want to see examples of American industry and&#13;
took them to Bethlehem Steel plant at Sparrows Point, the only plant of&#13;
its kind within easy reach of Washington.              Some of them were deeply&#13;
suspicious of this choice and after a brief peregrination of the blast&#13;
furnaces assured me that I must be trying to dishearten them by showing&#13;
them what they could never copy:              it was one more attempt to discourage&#13;
them from building up a steel industry.              On the other hand, when they&#13;
went round the railway workshops in Baltimore, I was asked why they&#13;
should spend time looking at such a plant when they had railway workshops&#13;
in their own country.              At Sparrows Point, just after I had been expanding&#13;
on 28 foot hearths, the Nigerian participant, a graduate of King's&#13;
College, Cambridge with first class honours in law, came up to me.                  "Mr.&#13;
              11              11&#13;
Cairncross,        he said,        they keep talking about 'Iron or', 'iron or' :&#13;
iron or what?"&#13;
&amp;#12;                                   -10-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Whatever the participants learned from these field trips, I found&#13;
them very illuminating.   They gave me an insight into the flexibility of&#13;
industrial organization in the United States that was just as valuable as&#13;
the earlier education in industrial technology I acquired in my visit to&#13;
the United States in 1936.   I found, for example, that Safeway had a&#13;
separate company inside its large Washington warehouse for the&#13;
maintenance and operation of its forklift trucks.   At Pittsburgh when we&#13;
saw over a nail-making plant, there turned out to be a small independent&#13;
cooperage business in the middle of it, making containers.    When we&#13;
visited TVA, we met a farmer who was already being supplied with a&#13;
formula for the mix of his feeding stuffs derived by linear programming&#13;
methods.   On this visit, too, we saw what was then the largest power&#13;
station in the world at Kingston, in a building that looked no bigger&#13;
than a moderate-sized warehouse.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    I had seen something of TVA in 1936 and was familiar with the claims&#13;
made for it by David Lilienthal and others.   It was therefore something&#13;
of a shock to find that the dams had become a comparatively insignificant&#13;
part of its activities and that, in terms of its financial operations at&#13;
least, TVA was now largely a supplier of electric power, generated from&#13;
upriver coal, to the thermonuclear diffusion plant at Oak Ridge.       This&#13;
was not, however, the picture that the participants took away:     most of&#13;
them seemed dazzled by the spectacle of multi-purpose planning that was&#13;
put on for them.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    On the way to Oak Ridge I happened to read in The Times of the&#13;
opening that week of Calder Hall; and as the lectures we were given&#13;
seemed to dwell exclusively on the enrichment of uranium I asked whether&#13;
this was indispensable to the generation of nuclear energy.    I was&#13;
assured that this was so and took some satisfaction in producing my&#13;
evidence that in Britain at least, we were able to get by on raw&#13;
uranium.   It is strange to reflect that nearly a quarter of a century ago&#13;
&amp;#12;                                   -11-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
the merits of different kinds of nuclear reactor, including BWR's, and&#13;
PWR's but not AGR's, were already being canvassed by the World Bank and&#13;
that the layman felt just as lost then as now in the debate between the&#13;
experts.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    As the first course drew to its end, the question that kept recurring&#13;
in my mind was how one could judge its success.    As an educator I was&#13;
accustomed to the simple tests of examinations but examinations were&#13;
irrelevant to the objects of a course which was designed to make the&#13;
participants better administrators.    How could one tell whether they&#13;
would do their job better or return?    For that matter, how did a grown&#13;
man learn and what contribution could a teacher make to his progress?      We&#13;
had not been trying to communicate lumps of information or tricks and&#13;
techniques of action.   Our purpose was to educate:   to improve their&#13;
judgement by improving their understanding of the background to the&#13;
judgements they were asked to make.    What they had learned, whether&#13;
through our efforts or not, would only show over the years in their&#13;
future careers.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   When I invited frank criticisms at the end of the course, I was not&#13;
altogether prepared for the vehemence with which they were delivered.       It&#13;
was obvious that many were deeply disappointed, both with their living&#13;
conditions and with the course itself. Â·The seminars had gone on too&#13;
long; the questions had been too elementary; the discussion had been too&#13;
inconclusive; they had spent too much time looking round factories.       They&#13;
assured me that their criticisms were meant to be constructive and that&#13;
they wanted to see the Institute continue.    It was obvious also that&#13;
there were at least some of them whose one idea seemed to be to set up a&#13;
similar course in their own country, much as schoolboys think of becoming&#13;
teachers, and they were taking back as much of our teaching material as&#13;
they could pack.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                    -12-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Eugene Black was rather shocked and indignant when he heard of these&#13;
reactions but I saw no harm in some escape of steam.     It was clear that&#13;
we must provide separate living accommodation for all future courses and&#13;
this was found initially at the Hotel 2400, a short distance away, where&#13;
meals had been served to those on the first course.     This change by&#13;
itself worked wonders and the atmosphere in October when the second&#13;
course began was altogether different.     There was also a question mark&#13;
against the length of the course.   We had picked on six months rather&#13;
hesitantly, afraid that it might seriously curtail the number and&#13;
seniority of applicants, but recognising that it would be easier to&#13;
contract than to extend the initial period.     I concluded that we should&#13;
continue to offer a six months course and in the end we had no difficulty&#13;
in attracting twenty-five good candidates to the second course - a more&#13;
homogeneous and less eccentric group as it happened.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    So far as the course itself was concerned we made no radical changes&#13;
but tightened it up and revised our seminar outlines in order to take&#13;
advantage of what we ourselves had learnt.     It was agreed that we should&#13;
add to our staff someone from a less developed country and were joined by&#13;
K.S. Krishnaswani, later Deputy Governor of the Reserve Bank of India&#13;
who, like John Adler, was later to serve as Director of the Institute.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Throughout the first course and such part of the second as I&#13;
directed, we had the unstinting support of the staff of the Bank.        Senior&#13;
staff members took part in many of the seminars; the Executive Directors&#13;
showed a keen interest; the administrative arrangements were excellent.&#13;
From the point of view of the participants, their contact with the Bank&#13;
was regarded as perhaps the most fruitful part of the entire course.        It&#13;
gave them access to staff and knowledge of Bank procedures which could be&#13;
extremely valuable in any future loan negotiations.     Study at a&#13;
university, for this reason alone, would have been regarded as a poor&#13;
substitute for the ED! course.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                     -13-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    When I originally recommended in favour of a Bank Institute this&#13;
development had seemed to me inevitable.     But there were other&#13;
developments which I had not so clearly foreseen in encouraging the Bank&#13;
to enter the educational business.     I began to see the Institution as a&#13;
link between the Bank and the academic community from which it was&#13;
largely cut off.     I saw advantages to both sides if economists, for&#13;
example, could be attached for a year or two to the Institute, since this&#13;
would bring the theory and practice of economic development closer&#13;
together.   The Bank might learn a thing or two from the economists and&#13;
they in turn might form a more realistic view of the problems of&#13;
development or of the practices of the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    For the same reason I was anxious that we should make a start on&#13;
publishing our teaching material.     If the Bank did have more experience&#13;
of development than any other institution then we ought to make the&#13;
experience widely available.     In the end, however, we were too pressed&#13;
for time to give much thought to publication; and the one volume which&#13;
did eventually appear- Bill Diamond's book on Development Banks            owed&#13;
at least as much to reading and study of material already in print as to&#13;
anything gleaned from the experience of the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    There were various other links with the academic community that I&#13;
tried to build up.    For example, there was an academic advisory committee&#13;
of distinguished economists like Ed Mason.     I also agreed to give a&#13;
public lecture on the Bank on the tenth anniversary of the opening of the&#13;
Institute in the hope that this might encourage the establishment of an&#13;
annual lecture there on some aspect of economic development.        Some&#13;
professional economists continued to take part as members of the staff,&#13;
and not just as guest speakers, in subsequent courses at the Institute.&#13;
But, with the exception of Krishnaswami, no one from outside the Bank was&#13;
invited to direct the work of the Institute.     The bridge I had hoped to&#13;
build never really came into existence.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                     -14-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Nevertheless the Institute itself grew and flourished.      The number of&#13;
courses multiplied:     the courses were given in more languages and more&#13;
countries; the modest professional staff of three grew to one of nearly&#13;
forty.   Watching these developments, Dick Demuth thought that they should&#13;
be reviewed periodically from outside and I was twice invited to report&#13;
on them, once in 19 â&#128;¢â&#128;¢ and again in 19 â&#128;¢â&#128;¢ , shortly after Mr. MacNamara took&#13;
office as President.     Neither of these reports merits extended discussion&#13;
here.    Not only would it be out of place;   any criticisms would also be&#13;
out-of-date.     All I need say is that I encouraged further growth but was&#13;
a little concerned at the scaling down of the general course with which&#13;
EDI had started.     There seemed to me an undue concentration on matters of&#13;
technique in the numerous project evaluation courses which have come to&#13;
dominate its work.     I put this impression to the test when I was invited&#13;
to attend the concluding session of one such course which had spent much&#13;
of its time on discounted cash flow calculations.      I asked what rate of&#13;
discount they would apply when they got back to their own countries.&#13;
There was a long and embarassing silence.     It was finally broken by a&#13;
young Mexican:     "I would use Bank Rate", he said.   This incident did&#13;
nothing to dispel my doubts.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    The founding of ED! had not only a deep personal interest for me - it&#13;
might have been the beginning of an entirely different career - but it&#13;
provided a case study in the creation of new educational institutions.&#13;
At the final session of the first course I pointed out that much could be&#13;
learned about economic development from reflection on that case study.&#13;
The establishment of the Institute had been itself an effort of&#13;
development in which one could observe as through a microscope the&#13;
elements that made for success and failure.     The theories that economists&#13;
had devised in order to explain development could be brought to the test&#13;
of their own recent experience.     If they imagined that it would be easier&#13;
to develop their countries than to develop the Institute they would find&#13;
themselves mistaken.    To make a success of the Institute meant that&#13;
&amp;#12;                                     -15-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
everybody had to be emotionally involved in making it work; and in the&#13;
same way successful development of a country called for a general feeling&#13;
of participation in the process.     That process, moreover, was essentially&#13;
educational;   at the root of the problem of development was the need to&#13;
organize the transfer of knowledge and experience.     This could be done in&#13;
many different ways;    and the best way to do it preoccupied many&#13;
different institutions from the World Bank to the various national&#13;
planning agencies.     It was the essential concern of the EDI.   The&#13;
experience of the EDI might have lessons, therefore, of much wider&#13;
significance than its own immediate future.&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="17968907">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1985/01/17968907/transcript-oral-history-interview-cairncross-sir-alexander-k-held-january-10-1985-vol-2-2-main-report
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1985/01/17968907/transcript-oral-history-interview-cairncross-sir-alexander-k-held-january-10-1985-vol-2-2-main-report</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1985/01/17968907/transcript-oral-history-interview-cairncross-sir-alexander-k-held-january-10-1985-vol-2-2-main-report</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2007-07-26T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2007-07-26T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <docm_id>090224b0828b4a15</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b0828b4a15</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2013/07/05/000356161_20130705145014/Rendered/INDEX/789510v20TRN0C0iew0January010001985.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2013/07/05/000356161_20130705145014/Rendered/PDF/789510v20TRN0C0iew0January010001985.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2013-07-05T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1985-01-10T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>2</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Transcript of oral history interview with
            Sir Alexander K. Cairncross and William Diamond held on
            January 10, 1985
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            In January 1985 Sir Alexander K.
            Cairncross and William Diamond were jointly interviewed on
            behalf of the World Bank Group Archives oral history program
            by Charles Ziegler. This transcript includes the paper
            "The Economic Development Institute, 1955-1956" by
            Alexander Cairncross. During Sir Cairncross's tenure at
            the Bank from 1955 to 1956, he worked as the founding
            director of the Economic Development Institute (EDI). He
            questioned the fulfillment of the World Bank on both its
            research and training needs. His transcript concerns the
            relationship between the Economic Development Institute
            (EDI) and the World Bank, aiming to maintain a degree of
            independence while at the same time drawing from the
            economic staff. Sir Cairncross opines the view of the World
            Bank on development and macro-economics in the 1950s. During
            Mr. Diamond's tenure at the Bank from 1947 to 1978, he
            worked in the following areas: in the Europe, Africa, and
            Australasia department of operations (1947-1960); in the
            department of operations as assistant director for the
            western hemisphere (1960-1962); at the International Finance
            Corporation (IFC) department of development bank services as
            director (1962-1964); in the development finance companies
            department as director (1968-1972); in the Asia region as
            director of country department 2 (1972-1975); as special
            assistant to the vice president of finance (1975-1977); and
            at the Economic Development Institute (EDI) as a senior
            fellow (1977-1978).
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Main transcript
        </docna>
        <display_title>Transcript of oral history
            interview with Sir Alexander K. Cairncross and William
            Diamond held on January 10, 1985 : Main transcript</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/1985/01/17968907/transcript-oral-history-interview-sir-alexander-k-cairncross-william-diamond-held-january-10-1985-main-transcript</listing_relative_url>
        <subtopic>Technology Industry,Sustainable Land and Crop Management,Public Sector Corruption &amp;
            Anticorruption Measures,Access to Finance,Banks &amp; Banking Reform</subtopic>
        <docty>Transcript</docty>
        <teratopic>Rural Development,Public Sector Development,Industry,Finance and Financial Sector Development</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000356161_20130705145014</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>World Bank Group Archives oral history program</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Rural Development,Public Sector Development,Industry,Finance and Financial Sector Development</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Board Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Bank loan, Bank loan officers, bond market,
            business management, businessmen, capital projects, civil
            service, complaint, confidence, development banks,
            discounted cash flow, Economic Development, economies of
            scale, EDI, employment, expenditure, families, farmer,
            fiscal policy, flow of capital, geographical spread,
            housing, inequality, inflation, jail, justice, loan, loan
            officers, management education, minister, monetary policy,
            penalties, personal credit, programming, subsidiary,
            taxation, technical aspects, transport, warehouse, woman
        </keywd>
        <owner>Knowledge &amp; Information Services (ITSKI)</owner>
        <repnb>78951</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Industry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shocks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Textbooks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Railways Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Policy, Strategy and Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crops</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal &amp; Monetary Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Consolidation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Governance and Structural Fiscal Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Rules</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Sustainability</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macro-Fiscal Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Technology Industry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Copyright</ml:concept><ml:concept>Taxation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banking Institutional Set-up</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shocks and Vulnerability</ml:concept><ml:concept>Examinations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning Materials</ml:concept><ml:concept>Railways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports &amp; Waterways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>