<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>﻿                                                                   78945&#13;
                Summary of Oral History Transcript                 v1&#13;
&#13;
                          Boskey, Shirley E.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Interview conducted by Professor Robert W. Oliver, on 1986-07-14&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Boskey joined the Bank after serving for about nine years in the&#13;
U.S. Government as Assistant General Counsel of the Office of&#13;
Territories in the Interior Department. Boskey knew Dick Demuth who,&#13;
at one point, needed an assistant in his department. Boskey briefly&#13;
runs a comparison of the Presidents during whose tenure she served,&#13;
covering mainly their interaction with the staff.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Boskey began as a staff assistant, in the Technical Assistance&#13;
and Liaison Department, where she stayed--through its many&#13;
departmental name changes--until her retirement from the Bank 29 years&#13;
later. She became the first woman Department Director in 1975;&#13;
succeeding M. Hoffman who became director after Demuth's departure.&#13;
According to Boskey, Demuth was a man of ideas and the new&#13;
organizations created as Bank affiliates either originated with him,&#13;
or were confided to him to work over. Demuth also wrote the speeches&#13;
for the Annual Meeting. The principal responsibility of the department&#13;
was the Bank's relationship with the United Nations. The major&#13;
initiatives Boskey and Demuth were associated with included, drafting&#13;
the proposal to set up the McNamara Fellowship Program under the&#13;
auspices of EDI (Economic Development Institute), and working closely&#13;
with the Legal in designing the IDA Articles of Agreement which the&#13;
Bank's Executive Directors were commissioned to do.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Boskey elaborates on the Board meeting informally as the&#13;
Committee of the Whole, where the Directors speak for themselves with&#13;
no vote taken and a Precis circulated as Secretary's memoranda. On the&#13;
other hand, when the Board meets formally, a record of the&#13;
&amp;#12;discussions-a verbatim-is not circulated. However, the minutes&#13;
summarizing the statements related to various Board approvals&#13;
contained in the meetings are circulated to the senior staff.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Boskey discusses the original proposal for Investment Insurance&#13;
which she jointly worked on with Demuth and the study she wrote in&#13;
1962. This, eventually died after ten years of work within the Legal&#13;
Department to reemerge as the Multilateral Investment Guarantee Agency&#13;
(MIGA). She elaborates on MIGA's objective, purpose, rationale, and&#13;
its revival by President Clausen who proposed it in his first Annual&#13;
Meeting speech. Subsequently, Shihata, the Bank's Vice President and&#13;
General Counsel, making it a reality with a new Convention to function&#13;
as an organization separate from the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Boskey elaborates on the procedures involved in handling the&#13;
various proposals and subsequent assignments thereof within the Bank;&#13;
some requiring close coordination with the EDs' offices, others when&#13;
work was dictated by the UN might not require Board involvement. The&#13;
assignments handled directly with the President, some came from the&#13;
governments through the President, and some were dealt with by the&#13;
senior staff directly with the governments such as the negotiations&#13;
for IDA Replenishment which were carried out directly with the&#13;
governments or through the IDA Deputies, whereby those of the Part I&#13;
countries would contribute to the Replenishment. However, the IDA&#13;
Articles of Agreement were considered in the Board and worked on in&#13;
close coordination with the Directors. Loan negotiations, are carried&#13;
out with various government representatives where the Board is not&#13;
involved until the lending stage.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Boskey discusses the notion of IFC (International Finance&#13;
Corporation) emerging in a report prepared outside the Bank and,&#13;
William Diamond writing what might have been the first book, with one&#13;
of the chapters written by Mervyn Weiner. Demuth and Boskey&#13;
subsequently organizing a conference of development bank managers,&#13;
resulting in Boskey producing a second book on development banks based&#13;
&amp;#12;on the precis of the discussions. The financing of development banks&#13;
becoming part of the Bank's activity and a separate department set up&#13;
which then went over to IFC. Boskey elaborates on the concept upon&#13;
which IFC was set up.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Boskey mentions Demuth as the Bank's liaison person with outside&#13;
UN-type organizations, the UN Charter providing that organizations in&#13;
the various economic development fields enter into a relationship&#13;
agreement with it. She also talks about the uniqueness of the Bank's&#13;
agreement and its daily relationship with the UN, the Bank's&#13;
agreements with other international organizations, other agreements&#13;
made with the UN and the evolution of the various cooperative&#13;
programs, especially with the UNDP and her involvement therein.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Boskey talks about the Woods era ('63-'68), the introduction of&#13;
the Young Professional Program, the role of the resident missions,&#13;
Demuth taking the lead in organizing various committees comprised&#13;
mostly of senior staff to discuss and consider various initiatives,&#13;
her contribution to the "Development Services Department Newsletter"--&#13;
already in existence since the 60s--until its demise around '73, the&#13;
Horowitz proposal from UNCTAD and her extensive involvement therein&#13;
together with Demuth and Irving Friedman [economic adviser to Woods],&#13;
and her authoring the principal report and the proposal's final&#13;
demise. She mentions other proposals from UNCTAD asking the Bank to do&#13;
studies such as the one handled by Friedman on Supplementary Financing&#13;
and, the reason why it also died. Finally, her participation at the&#13;
meetings of UN agency heads, where on several occasions she sat in for&#13;
the President, as well as writing and delivering the Bank's speech to&#13;
the Economic and Social Council in Geneva.&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="17968686">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1986/07/17968686/transcript-oral-history-interview-boskey-shirley-e-held-july-14-1986-vol-1-2-summary-oral-history-transcript
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1986/07/17968686/transcript-oral-history-interview-boskey-shirley-e-held-july-14-1986-vol-1-2-summary-oral-history-transcript</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1986/07/17968686/transcript-oral-history-interview-boskey-shirley-e-held-july-14-1986-vol-1-2-summary-oral-history-transcript</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2006-10-25T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2006-10-25T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2013/07/05/000356161_20130705143244/Rendered/INDEX/789450v10TRN0B0ummary0July014001986.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2013/07/05/000356161_20130705143244/Rendered/PDF/789450v10TRN0B0ummary0July014001986.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>1986-07-14T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2013-07-05T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>2</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>2</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Transcript of oral history interview with
            Shirley E. Boskey held on July 14, 1986
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            In July 1986, Shirley E. Boskey was
            interviewed on behalf of the World Bank Group Archives oral
            history program by Professor Robert W. Oliver. During her
            tenure at the Bank from 1954-1983, Mrs. Boskey worked in the
            following areas: in the development services department as a
            policy planning officer and policy planning advisor
            (1954-1975); and in the international relations department
            as director (1975-1983).Her transcript concerns her arrival
            at the World Bank after serving in the U.S. Government as
            Assistant General Counsel of the Office of Territories in
            the Interior Department; her comparison of the presidents of
            the World Bank during her tenure; and her precedence of
            becoming the first woman department director in 1975 to deal
            with the relationship of the World Bank with the United Nations.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Summary
        </docna>
        <display_title>Transcript of oral history
            interview with Shirley E. Boskey held on July 14, 1986 (Vol.
            2) : Summary</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/1986/07/17968686/transcript-oral-history-interview-shirley-e-boskey-held-july-14-1986-vol-2-summary</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Transcript</docty>
        <subtopic>Public Sector Corruption &amp;
            Anticorruption Measures,Hazard Risk Management,Corporate Law,Bankruptcy and Resolution of Financial Distress,Post Conflict Reconstruction</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Conflict and Development,Law and Development,Public Sector Development,Urban Development</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000356161_20130705143244</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>World Bank Group Archives oral history program</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Conflict and Development,Law and Development,Public Sector Development,Urban Development</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Board Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            banks, Board meeting, Charter, Convention,
            Corporation, Economic Development, Finance Corporation,
            General Counsel, IFC, Insurance, International Finance,
            Loan, managers, meetings, Nations, negotiations, UNDP
        </keywd>
        <owner>Knowledge &amp; Information Services (ITSKI)</owner>
        <repnb>78945</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance &amp; Risk Mitigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supplementary</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>