<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>ï»¿. ,'&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                  /                                     -   ;&#13;
                                                                ,/&#13;
       DIVISION OF THE HUMANITIES AND SOCIAL SCIENCES&#13;
       CALIFORNIA INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY&#13;
       PASADENA, CALIFORNIA 91125&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       A CONVERSATION WITH ARON BROCHES&#13;
&#13;
       WASHINGTON, D.C.&#13;
&#13;
       November 7, 1985&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       Â©   Robert W. Oliver&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                                                              2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                             He told Woods, and he acted accordingly, ''If you do that, you won't find&#13;
&#13;
                      A CONVERSATION WITH AIIOH BROCUES                      me snapping at you even though I laid it on the line that I would not&#13;
&#13;
                               WASHINGTON, D.C.                              let money go from the Bank to IDA."         The transfers were authorized in&#13;
&#13;
                               November 7, 198S                              '64 at the Tokyo Annual Meeting.      The history of that is well known,&#13;
&#13;
                               Robert W. Oliver                              but that was an important thing.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                        Woods also emphasized education and agriculture lending,&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     Thank you for granting me this opportunity to ask about George   although even the supposedly conservative Black bad started it. Lending&#13;
&#13;
Woods' accomplishments as Preaident of the World Bank.      You were         for these sectors certainly did not start with McNamara.         He drove&#13;
&#13;
talking before I turned on the tape recorder about Woods opening the         agricultural loans to great heights, but Woods was very active in that&#13;
&#13;
way to more cordial relations with the United Nations.      Would you        field.&#13;
&#13;
continue?                                                                    OLIVER:     I assume that there had been some thinking about both of these&#13;
&#13;
BROCHES:     That was one of the first things that Woods did.   Since the    under Black because there is a lengthy memorandum about education&#13;
&#13;
Bank had always been somewhat distant from, at arm's length with, the        presented to a Senior Staff Meeting quite early in Woods' term.         There&#13;
&#13;
U. H., the French Under Secretary General for Economic and Social            must have been preliminary thinking.&#13;
&#13;
Affairs, Philippe de Seynea, called Wooda "John XXIII" which indicates       BROCHES:     Yea.   In Black's days, there was a Vanderbilt professor who&#13;
&#13;
what they thought of him.                                                    was working out a program on education.         There was also a Black program&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     That was a meritorioua term?                                     for Black Africa.      The foundations were there, but not much was done.&#13;
&#13;
BROCUES:     Of course.   Another thing Woods did (this was in 1964; Woods   It takes time.      Like his predecessors, Woods was somebody who didn't&#13;
&#13;
came in on January 1, 1963), he was instrumental in obtaining authority      plan very precisely.      Hone of us did.     When McNamara came, you had his&#13;
&#13;
for Bank transfers to IDA, which was very important.      Black bad not      five-year plana and so forth.&#13;
&#13;
been in favor of that because when IDA was created fears were expreaaed      OLIVER:    When you say plan, "precisely," you mean â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢&#13;
&#13;
that Bank money would leak, that there would be fuzzy loans -- this,         BROCHES:    When the end of the year came, you knew what you had done.&#13;
&#13;
that and the other thing.      Black guaranteed that there would be no       OLIVER:    And you knew what you might want to do next, but you were not&#13;
&#13;
leaks from the Bank to IDA -- that there would be no commingling of          sure what â&#128;¢â&#128;¢&#13;
&#13;
funds.     He wasn't opposed personally to   a transfer of Bank profits.     BROCHES:     Yes.   You wouldn't be so precise about it.     Another thing&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                 3                                                                                     4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
that Woods did. â&#128;¢         Woods' favorite country was India.         He had been   Then the Australian Director, the Canadian Director. and a couple of&#13;
&#13;
there on missions for the World Bank.      WOods was the first President of        other hardliners said,         Â·~e   will only approve the rescheduling if the&#13;
the World Bank who knew something in advance about the Bank.           He had      Indians say they can't pay."            I had to give a legal opinion, and I&#13;
been head of one of our two principal underwriters:       First Boston.            said, that the Articles clearly authorised the Bank to deal with its&#13;
&#13;
First Boston and Morgan Stanley were our principal underwriters.           Woods   debtors in any manner that would be in the Bank's interests.&#13;
had been on one or two missions to India and so considered himself an              OLIVER:     This was related to the $500 million, as I recall, non-project&#13;
expert.    At a given point (I don't know whether it was '65 or '66),              loan   ~icb    the consortium arranged for India as an inducement to accept&#13;
&#13;
India was in trouble; it vas negotiating with ita creditors, and Woods             the Bell Report recommendation.&#13;
&#13;
did something which was a big aistake.     In order to induce other                BROCHES:      When was the Bell Report?&#13;
&#13;
lenders to reschedule, he offered to reschedule the Bank's own loans in            OLIVER:     It was '66.&#13;
&#13;
a peculiar for..     It was not postponing payments.    They could make            BROCHES:      Yea.      Very likely, very likely.&#13;
&#13;
payments in foreign exchange as they were supposed to, and then we                 OLIVER:     But the contribution made by some of the members of the&#13;
&#13;
would deposit these funds with the Reserve Bank of India.         Strange.         consortium was simply to postpone the principal that was due on past&#13;
&#13;
The point is that the Indians weren't very keen on it.         The Indiana         loans rather than to make new loans.&#13;
&#13;
said, "We pay the World Bank, 11 and this then became an issue of some             BBOCHES:      It probably was at that time that Woods quoted himself as&#13;
                                                                                                    01&#13;
unpleasantness in the Board.     Some Directors said,   Â·~ou   can't               having said,          0.K. Fellows, we're not going to stand aside.     You must&#13;
&#13;
reschedule," and some said, "You can, but only if India swears out a               do it, and we'll make a contribution."            That didn't work out at all--&#13;
&#13;
"Pauper's Oath'."                                                                  economically, perhaps, but not politically.&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:    I didn't understand the words, would you say them again?                OLIVER:     It set a bad precedent.&#13;
&#13;
BROCHES:   To swear out a Pauper's Oath.    Woods used that expression,            BROCHES:     There is something else with which I was connected where&#13;
&#13;
not the Directors.    The opponent's argument was that, under the                  Woods, I thought, acted very well.            I am referring to the International&#13;
&#13;
Articles~    Agreement, the Bank could not reschedule or postpone or               Centre for the Settlement of Investment Disputes.            I started working on&#13;
&#13;
modify the terms of payment in the absence of a request by a member                that in '62.          Black liked it, but he left before discussions really got&#13;
&#13;
baaed on an extreme stringency of foreign exchange.       The Indians, said.       going.     Black told Woods, "George this is a good idea."         In his first&#13;
&#13;
"That is not our problem., and we're not going to make such a request."            we~ks,    Woods said, "I understand that you are working on that.          I like&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                    5                                                                                6&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
the idea, bUt there are so many things to find out in my new job, I'd                 amounts were small, it was a break-through.      Could the Bank do itt      Is&#13;
&#13;
like to put that on the back burner until I have time to study it.                    it proper to transfer part of the profits of the Bank to IDA?&#13;
&#13;
Then I'll talk to you, but I don't want to deal with a matter I don't                            In the Second IDA Replenishment, Woods made the same mistake as&#13;
&#13;
understand."                                                                          all presidents:    his aim waa too high, and then be got into a bind.        I&#13;
&#13;
     Then about June, be said, ''O.K. Counsel, talk, e:u.mine me," and I              think it waa too high.     If you want $500 million, to say $700 million&#13;
had to examine him.      I bad to ask him questions.     I said,    Â·~ou're   doing   ia O.K., but don't say a billion.&#13;
&#13;
pretty well."      Be said, "How we're going to talk to Directors.        We'll       OLIVER:    The Bank did reach a replenishment of a billion by 1970.&#13;
talk first to Directors whose importance is somewhat peripheral.              I       BROCHES:    Of course McNamara did the same thing.     IDA replenishments&#13;
will do the talking.      Unless I say something completely idiotic, you              were always difficult, but that was natural because it is taxpayer's&#13;
stay out of it; but then in diacuaaiona you take over."            Afterwards be      money.&#13;
&#13;
said, "How did I do?"      I said, "fine."   He said, "Yeb, but I didn't              OLIVER:    Was Mr. Woods quite diaappointed that he was not able to get&#13;
know what I was saying."      Second round, "Did I do better now?"        I said      the billion dollars while he was still President?&#13;
exactly the same thing, and he said, "I think I know what I was                       BROCHES:    I guess so.   I'm trying to think.   IDA was organized under&#13;
&#13;
saying.â&#128;¢â&#128;¢    The third time was lunch with the heavies, U. s., U. K. Â£!.              Black and became effective in November of '60.       The first replenishment&#13;
&#13;
~         and he said, "How I feel comfortable."                                      would normally have taken place after 5 years, but we tried it after&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     May I infer from this that Woods, as a person, tried very hard            three years.    That was Woods first year.   Then there was another&#13;
&#13;
to do his homework before he presented aoaething7                                     development which was aort of interesting.&#13;
&#13;
BROCHES:     Oh yea.   I can see it now in retrospect.    The Centre was              OLIVER:    May I ask, before we go on, about the settlement of&#13;
&#13;
something new.      He brought this about, or helped to start to bring it             international disputes.     Has that proved in practice to be an important&#13;
&#13;
about.      It was an achievement of his -- in the same way that Mr.                  opportunity for the Bank?     I have not read in newspapers recently.&#13;
&#13;
Clausen wants to bring about multilateral investment guarantees.              I was   BROCHES:    This is not something that gets into newspapers at all.      The&#13;
&#13;
not consciously trying to build a monument, but I think, looking back                 International Centre for Settlement of Investment disputes, ICSID for&#13;
&#13;
to a precedent, perhaps I did.      (Everybody would like to have                     short, is an institution that has its own international status to which&#13;
&#13;
something, whatever it is, some innovation connected with his term of                 parties can turn if they have a dispute.     I think, until now, there&#13;
&#13;
office.)     For Woods, the IDA transfer was very important.         Although the     have been 19 cases, nearly always fairly important -- otherwise they&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                    7                                                                              8&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
don't come here.     The Centre was not announced aa aometbing epoch-               principal draftsman and negotiator of that treaty.        It took a fair&#13;
&#13;
making, but as a useful neutral forum for third-party settlement of                 amount of my time.     I bad been in the Bank a long time.     I had an&#13;
&#13;
disputes between boat countries and foreign investors.           Woods              excellent second level, so, if it seemed necessary, I could take some&#13;
&#13;
fortunately felt as I did that the time was past when you announced                 time off, so to apeak.        Once the Centre came into being, I was elected&#13;
&#13;
every new program or whatever new initiative as the thing that will                 its Secretary-General.        The S.G. is the person who administers the&#13;
&#13;
save the world. which is silly.        It used to be one of the problema with       Centre and the proceedings that take place under the Convention.           The&#13;
&#13;
Congress.     Each time the administration went to Congress with some               present General Counsel is also the Secretary-General of the Centre,&#13;
&#13;
foreign aid proposal it said, "This is going to do it," -- this, that               and be tells me he finds it difficult to spend enough time on it.&#13;
&#13;
and the other.     It doesn't pay, because there are no simple or single            OLIVER:     So issues are still arising from time to time?&#13;
&#13;
solutions.     I think the Centre bas redounded to the reputation of the            BROCHES:     Oh, there are occasions all the time.    This is not a one-time&#13;
&#13;
Bank.     It has been working usefully.     I'm nov very busy on it, but from       operation at all.     As a matter of fact, you can expect that the number&#13;
&#13;
the other aide. I'm outside.     I~m    President of one Tribunal and Counsel       of cases will increase, because cases are brought on the basis of&#13;
&#13;
in some other cases.                                                                advance undertakings in investment agreements.       You don't have a&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     Do you know off hand of any significant disputes that were              dispute the moment you sign an agreement.&#13;
&#13;
settled while Mr. Woods was President?                                              OLIVER:     Let's hope not.&#13;
&#13;
BROCHES:     Ho, because the Centre    didn~t   come into being until a little      BROCHES:     It's a little bit like the will practice of lawyers.       People&#13;
&#13;
over a year before he left.     I think the first dispute was submitted             make their will.     Eventually they die, and then the lawyer may have&#13;
&#13;
when McNamara was President, but he didn't know anything about it. and.             business.     In the case of the Centre, it might never have had business.&#13;
&#13;
in any event, the President of the Bank         couldn~t   influence, nor could     You may have beard of the bauxite disputes between Jamaica and Kaiser,&#13;
&#13;
the Bank influence, the settlement.        The Convention establishes a             Reynolds and Alcoa.     Those disputes came before the Centre.     They were&#13;
&#13;
framework within which the parties work.          It is administered by ICSID,      settled.     In fact, more than half of all disputes that have been&#13;
&#13;
not by the Bank.     The parties appoint arbitrators and ICSID (and the             submitted to ICSID were settled, which is interesting.&#13;
&#13;
Bank) make facilities available.                                                    OLIVER:     What happened to the other half?&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     Does the General Counsel of the Bank do the administering?              BROCHES:    Well, some cases are still going, and in some there have been&#13;
&#13;
BROCHES:     Well, in my case. I worked on the Convention.         I was also the   awards which have all been complied with.        As it happens, in half of&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                               9                                                                              10&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
the cases where there were final awards, the investors won and in the          lend to Greece for almost twenty years.     I know that Woods was pretty&#13;
&#13;
other half the developing countries won.                                       active in pushing the Greeks finally to settle.    He bad met Andreas&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:    May 1 ask a somewhat related question?     In the middle of the     Papandreou shortly after he had returned to Greece to help his father,&#13;
&#13;
Woods years, I think it was '66.or '67, there was an amendment to an           who was then Prime Minister.    The debt issue was finally settled and we&#13;
&#13;
American foreign aid bill before Congress which was known as the               were going to make our first loan, when the Colonels took over.       Greece&#13;
Hickenlooper Amendment, introduced by Senator Dirksen, which was to            was accident prone.    Papandreaou went in exile in Sweden, wrote a&#13;
prevent foreign aid to governments who bad not settled with foreign            letter to Woods urging him not to proceed with the loan.       Woods wrote&#13;
bond holders.                                                                  back along the following linea:     "I know that you were the one who made&#13;
BROCHES:    The   Hickenlooper amendment was, in fact, introduced by           Greece eligible for the World Bank.     Nothing would have given me more&#13;
Hicken looper.                                                                 pleasure than to sign this first loan with you.     But this is a loan&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:    Well, I think the Bank through Mr. Woods opposed the amendment      which is good regardless of the regime, and, therefore, we have decided&#13;
on the grounds that it would reduce the number of countries which would        to make it."&#13;
in fact try to make a settlement.                                                       We got into another problem.     The U. H. General Assembly for&#13;
&#13;
BROCHES:    Isn;t that funny. I don;t remember.     It aay have been           years bad adopted resolutions calling on the Fund and the Bank not to&#13;
Bickenlooper which excluded foreign assistance to countries which had          deal with South Africa and Portugal.    We acknowledged receipt of the&#13;
&#13;
failed to settle expropriation disputes.    There vas a case in Ceylon.        resolutions and said that we would send them to our members. who, of&#13;
&#13;
They had a dispute with oil companies, not very major, because what            course, had already received them but we took no further action.&#13;
                                                                                                                                          /&#13;
they were expropriating were the gas stations.      We were about to make a             By the middle 60s we bad stopped lending to South Africa and&#13;
&#13;
loan or extend financial assistance to Ceylon, and Woods refused to            Portugal for a variety of reasons-- in the case of Portugal, because it&#13;
&#13;
proceed with either, even though the U.S. Government would have been           was accumulating foreign-exchange reserves against the day when they&#13;
&#13;
quite content if the Bank, which was after all not subject to the              would have to fight a war in Africa.     The result was an economic&#13;
&#13;
Hickenlooper Amendment, had gone ahead.                                        recession.     In South Africa also, we were aware of things not going&#13;
&#13;
      Woods was also tough on defaulting debtors.       He bad been involved   very well.     This was a time when the Bank started to wean away its&#13;
&#13;
with the Council of Foreign Bondholders.     I am now thinking of the          richer members.    We called it "graduating."   The South Africans still&#13;
&#13;
default on the Greek public debt which had caused the Bank to refuse to        wanted money, so we said to the South Africans that if they borrowed in&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                               11                                                                           12&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Germany or the United States in the market. they would get one last           OLIVER:     So in this respect there is no difference between the Bank and&#13;
&#13;
loan of an equivalent amount.                                                 others.&#13;
&#13;
           Then there was a particularly strong recommendation that we        BROCBES:     No, none, none, whatever.   However. in its relationship&#13;
&#13;
should abstain froa lending to Portugal and South Africa.       What          agreement with the UN, the Bank bas a provision which the others don't&#13;
&#13;
happened a couple of months later was that South Africa borrowed in           have, because the others are not operational institutions.         It states&#13;
&#13;
Frankfurt or Rev York, so we were bound to make them a loan.        Then      that by reason of its international responsibilities and the terms of its&#13;
&#13;
Portugal adopted an agricultural reconstruction program that we had           Articles of Agreement. the Bank is, and is required to function as, an&#13;
&#13;
been pushing them to accept, so there also the condition was fulfilled.       independent international organization.     The Bank's Articles provide that&#13;
&#13;
The result was that within months we were aaking loans to Portugal and        the Bank shall not interfere in the political affairs of its members.&#13;
&#13;
South Africa.                                                                 (Keep in mind that the Bank charter was drafted before the U.N. charter&#13;
&#13;
           There was great indignation in the U.N. The Soviet Union           was drafted. and there was no particular link.)&#13;
&#13;
accused the Bank of showing contempt for the United Nations by not even                 It further provides that decisions should be based solely on&#13;
&#13;
attending the meetings of the Trusteeship Council, leaving the seat for       economic considerations.     The meaning of that has often been debated.&#13;
&#13;
the Bank observers empty.     George Woods, probably on the advice of Dick    Do we make a loan to Poland?     (This was in 1947/48.)   If not, why not?&#13;
&#13;
Demuth and in any event in line with his policy of cooperation with the       Is that a political reason?     We said what is prohibited is political&#13;
&#13;
UN, then decided that we should explain our point of view; and I              motivation, not the taking into account of the economic results of&#13;
&#13;
appeared before the U.N. Trusteeship Council    io   ezplain and defend a     political policies. It doesn't need to be foreign policy or human&#13;
&#13;
point of view which wasn't eo easy to defend.     The first issue was, "Is    rights violations, it can be any one of a number of reasons.        So, my&#13;
&#13;
a General Assembly Resolution binding on U. H. aeabers?"      The answer to   brief at the U.N. was that it was not just that we are not obliged to&#13;
&#13;
that is simple:     it isn't binding on the meabers, let alone on             follow these resolution&amp; from the General Assembly, we are not even&#13;
&#13;
institutions.                                                                 permit ted to.&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:    May I ask for a clarification?   Is a U.N. Resolution binding           There was debate.     After that there were exchanges of documents,&#13;
&#13;
on. let's say, UNESCO?     or FAO?                                            and our Board accepted my interpretation.     Dick Demuth drafted a letter&#13;
&#13;
BROCHES:     It isn't binding on its own members. let alone on                to the U.N. for Woods' signature saying they bad presented a very&#13;
&#13;
institutions which are not â&#128;¢â&#128;¢                                                 cogent argument.    I said, "Dick how you can say that -- if we reject&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                               13                                                                               14&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
it!"     He said, '"Well, your interpretation has been adopted, so we don't   occupying powers.      The loans would be self-liquidating.   Then the Poles&#13;
&#13;
haye to say that yours vas good."                                             decided, or were told, not to go into the Marshall group, which meant&#13;
&#13;
         In the end, there was an exchange of correspondence between Woods    that the coal would have to be bartered and there would be no clear way&#13;
&#13;
and    Secretary General U Thant saying in aubatance, .'"Well, the lawyer"a   of repayment.       When the Bank simply said, ''We won't lend to you," the&#13;
&#13;
can't agree, but let"a just say that we want to cooperate."         So the    Poles said it was a political decision.       It was a decision on economic&#13;
&#13;
incident ended in a declaration of cooperation in good apirite, and the       grounds. but the economic situation bad changed because of political&#13;
&#13;
issue was left at that.       However, we never made a loan to South Africa   developments.&#13;
&#13;
again, and we did not make a loan to Portugal until after the                 OLIVER:     I understand.&#13;
&#13;
revolution, so you can see, looking back, that world public opinion           BROCHES:     I think it is the difference between motivation and accepting&#13;
&#13;
does have some effect.                                                        the consequence of certain policies.&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     Was there ever a time when there were differences of opinion      OLIVER:    The Bank was becoming more closely allied, so to speak, with&#13;
&#13;
amongst the Executive Directors_ asking for a legal opinion as to             various U.N. agencies in the early Woods' years.       Did any legal&#13;
&#13;
whether a vote was politically motivated?                                     agreements occur?&#13;
&#13;
BROCHES:     In the case of the dispute with the U.H., I gave a legal         BROCBES:     Yes.    From the first, we had an agreement with the U.N., a&#13;
&#13;
opinion.     I said that we were not bound to accept the recommendations      relationship agreement, signed in '47 which made us a specialized&#13;
&#13;
of the U.H. General Assembly and that political considerations didn't         agency under Article 57 of the U.N. Charter.       That agreement was later&#13;
&#13;
only mean foreign political considerations, but domestic political            extended to cover IDA and IFC.       That was all before Woods.&#13;
&#13;
considerations as well.                                                                 During the Woods years, we started to cooperate with FAO and&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     Presumably much earlier.                                          UNESCO.    We had cooperation agreements which contemplated that these&#13;
&#13;
BROCBES:     â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ in the case of Poland.    I bear McCloy saying, as I've    specialized institutions would identify and analyze projects, and we&#13;
&#13;
just said,    Â·~e   cannot be blind to the economic considerations of         would put them into bankable form.       We paid 75 percent of the coat, and&#13;
&#13;
political developments in the case of Poland."      We were negotiating       I think we've also caught 75 percent of the due.       Some people think&#13;
&#13;
with Poland in 1947, and Poland was then believed about to come into          that is too much, but, in any event, that was a very active period.&#13;
&#13;
the Marshall Plan.      The loan was for the reactivation of the coal         WHO came in later and. I think, ILO also.       Then there was some sort of&#13;
&#13;
mines.     Coal was to go to West Germany to be paid for in dollars by the    informal consultation between UNDP and us about IDA policies.          UNDP&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                               1~                                                                              16&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
became quite large and collected substantial sums of money.         They did    competition there.       On the other hand, there was also cooperation&#13;
&#13;
pre-investment studies at the moment when the Bank becaae somewhat              because the Bank acted as executing agent for UHDP and did it, at least&#13;
&#13;
flush, and there was a change in IDA policies, which meant that the Bank        at that time, against reimbursement of out-of-pocket expenses only.&#13;
&#13;
could also undertake such studies.     You know Dick Demuth?                    There was a substantial financial effort.       Hone of these things existed&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER.:   Yes.                                                                 before Woods.&#13;
&amp;ROCHES: Well, Dick did it.     I mean he was our representative for those      OLIVER:    You were in the process of listing the major achievements of&#13;
&#13;
things.     Dick also became a bit more active in his attendance at             the Woods years, and I interrupted you.&#13;
&#13;
agency meetings and the Adainiatrative Coordination Committee (ACC).            BROCBES:   He started the President's Council.&#13;
&#13;
Be was much more visible and was not afraid to be seen walking out of           OLIVE&amp;:    I was going to ask you about the President's Council:     bow it&#13;
&#13;
the United Nations building!                                                    functioned, and how it happened that particular people were on it.&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     It is my impreaaion that over the years the Bank began to           BROCHES:    Those who were on it rated it from O.K. up to very good.&#13;
&#13;
build up ita own staff to do within ita own bouse a fair amount of what         Those who were not on it thought it was not a bad idea, but they should&#13;
&#13;
it bad been relying on other U.N. agencies to do.                               have been on it.     Late in '64 Woods established the President's Council&#13;
&#13;
BROCHES:    Well, the way in which we got these programs through the            with five people:     Burke Knapp, Lending; Siem Aldewereld, Projects;&#13;
&#13;
Board was to say that it would be a saving of staff, which was not so.          Dick Demuth;    ~self,    Legal;.&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     It might have been so for the time being, but, over two or          OLIVE&amp;:    Geoffrey Wilson?&#13;
&#13;
three years, the Bank staff increased.                                          BROCHES:    Yes, Geoffrey came a little later.     Geoffrey took Finance and&#13;
&#13;
BROCHES:     Which must have given (the agreement with UHIDO is another         Administration.     We were five.    Later we bad Irving Friedman, the&#13;
&#13;
ezaaple) unhappiness, but that was not a subject that I was.                    Economic Adviser.     I think that in the beginning we met every day.     The&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     What about UHDP?                                                    immediate result of the formation of that group was that two very good&#13;
&#13;
BROCHES:     No, I don't think so.   With UNDP there were questions of          department beads left.       They felt that there should have been more than&#13;
&#13;
priority:     would UHDP have the first refusal and the Bank/IDA come in        one lending (we call it "program") person on the Council.       Each thought&#13;
&#13;
only in UNDP couldn't do a project or study either because the                  that he should have been named.       Woods didn't want to choose.   The two&#13;
&#13;
country's allocating limits had been reached or for other reasons?         In   who left were the Canadian, Escott Reid, who had been Ambassador in&#13;
&#13;
some cases, we were accused of acting too quickly, so there was some            Bonn and High Commissioner in Delhi, and the Frenchman, Pierre Moussa,&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                  17                                                                                18&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
who many years later would be much in the news as the President, and               should show that the proposal was adopted by a majority of one.&#13;
&#13;
then ex-President, of the Banque de Paris et des Pays Bas.             They left   OLIVER:     Did the President ever overrule the Staff Loan Committee&#13;
&#13;
after a few .onths but without bitterness.                                         himself, so to apeak?&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     Didn't Reid leave also partly because of the Bell mission              BROCHES:     Burke, until be left (be was always in charge of the Loan&#13;
&#13;
which in some sense was a substitute for his department?                           Committee in various forms), would frequently say,      Â·~ell,   I'll talk to&#13;
&#13;
B&amp;OCBES:     I just don't know.   At the time be was Director of the               Bob," or "I'll talk to George.â&#128;¢â&#128;¢      So it didn't reach that stage.&#13;
&#13;
Western Hemisphere Department.                                                     Presidents often bad strong views.&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     Jerry Alter ea.e later?                                                OLIVER:     1 take it Burke and the President, whoever the President was.&#13;
&#13;
BROCHES:     It is quite possible that Jerry Alter succeeded Escott                worked very closely together so that they would pretty well agree even&#13;
&#13;
Reid.     The President's Council was not a group that decided things, it          before the Staff Loan Committee met.&#13;
&#13;
was sort of a contact group, and for that you could keep the meeting to            BROCHES:     When Black was about ready to leave, he got a little bored&#13;
&#13;
fifteen minutes every aorning.        '"What's new?"   But after that it was       and left matters very much to Burke, who became sort of an acting&#13;
&#13;
not very clear.                                                                    President.     Tbis was not to Woods' liking. Woods then started baiting&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:    What   ~   the decision-making group in the Bank?     Was it the        each member of the President's Council in turn.       For a long time, be&#13;
&#13;
Senior Staff?                                                                      would make all aorta of unpleasant remarks to Burke.       I was temporarily&#13;
&#13;
&amp;ROCHES:     It was Woodsi later it was McNamara.       I don't know where it      in charge of Administration. which was a foolish idea.&#13;
&#13;
is now.                                                                            OLIVER:     Tbia was before Mike Lejeune?&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:    How about Black?    Did Black also make the final decisions             BROCHES:     No, Mike Lejeune was there as Director of Administration.            I&#13;
&#13;
alone?                                                                             was supposed to sit "on top of Administration" in Woods' terms           Mike&#13;
&#13;
BROCHES:    Yes, but much was decided by Burke Knapp as bead of the Staff          and I had no problema.     I bad problems with Woods because he would tell&#13;
&#13;
Loan Committee, which was much larger than loan committees are now.                Mike, "Don't tell this to Ronnie because be would be opposed to it."                  I&#13;
&#13;
The Committee generally dealt with a particular loan proposal, but                 could see why, but Mike told me what he shouldn't tell me.            I spent a&#13;
&#13;
everyone was   welcom~,   including economists.    On one occasion those           lot of time just listening, and then I went to Woods, and said "Look&#13;
&#13;
present were almost unanimously opposed to the proposal. Burke then                George, I didn't want this job. 11    He said ''Yes, you did it as a service&#13;
&#13;
said, "I think we ought to go ahead," and 1 suggested that the minutes             to me ...   I said, "That's right."   That's eXactly the term I used.       He&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                   19                                                                                          20&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
said, "And you didn't know anything about it."           I said, "That's right.       OLIVER:     You mean there are tape recordings kept of the Executive&#13;
&#13;
I was willing to take the responsibility, but just to listen to all                   Director's meetings?&#13;
&#13;
that scuttlebut that you said to so and so is a waste of my time.                He   &amp;ROCHES:     Yea.   I    don~t   know whether they keep the tapes when they are&#13;
said,   \i'bo should do itt"&#13;
        1&#13;
                               I aaid, "I think you sboul.d do it.         You        done with the typing of the verbatim transcript.               Oh yes, there are&#13;
&#13;
think you know personnel and adainiatration and you are interested."                  books of all the meetings.             I think it started almost in the first&#13;
He asked, "Has it been clooe that way anywhere ehe."           1 said, "'Yes, in      year.     Nobody is permitted to cite this record except to recall or&#13;
Europe, at Philips (the Dutch aultinational), the Pre1ident is also his               prove what he himaelf &amp;aid.            One is not permitted to refer to what&#13;
&#13;
own Vice President of Personnel.       Re   likes it."                                someone else said.           But the record is evidence of increasing&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     Wben Woods was nasty to aembera of the Council, was this just             confrontation.&#13;
&#13;
his personality or was be trying to â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢                                             OLIVER:     Ia there any explanation for that?&#13;
&#13;
BROCHES:     With Burke, I think he wanted to establish that be vas                   BROCHES:    Oh, no.      One person who knew Woods before he came to the Bank&#13;
&#13;
the President.                                                                        said, "After a heart attack [Woods bad bad a serious one a few years&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     He vas simply trying to â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢                                           earlier 1 some people have a complete change of character.''                  I once talked&#13;
&#13;
BROCHES:     We were equal membera of the President's Council.          He asked      to someone who knew him as a younger man, and he said,              Â·~oods     was&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                    didn~t&#13;
                                                                                                          11&#13;
ua one Monday -- he aaid, 'Ve ought to have a picture of the                          always that way.         I             know him until he came to the Bank.           Many&#13;
&#13;
President'â&#128;¢ Council." We came and sat there, and I said to Burke,                     people in the Bank had known him in one way or another.                 He was a&#13;
&#13;
"Gee, George isn't here."      He &amp;aid, "Ronnie, as a lawyer you should               difficult . . n.    When be left, relations with the staff were bad, and&#13;
&#13;
have listened to his words.       The President's Council doean't include the         relations with the Board were bad.             It was sad.&#13;
&#13;
President."     So the five of us sat there to be photographed.           He bad a    OLIVER:    Is is sad.        Had be decided by late    ~66   or early   ~67   not to&#13;
&#13;
difficult personality.     Be liked to create -- be would call it,                    seek a second term?&#13;
&#13;
"creative tension," and there was a lot of tension between him and the                BROCHES:    He was too old for a second term, but he had certainly hoped&#13;
&#13;
Directors.     It was so bad his last year that when McNamara came every              to arrange a deal with McNamara that McNamara would resign at the end&#13;
&#13;
Director told him,    '~hatever   you do, don't act like Woods.         Don't have    of Johnson's term (January 1969), which would give Woods another year.&#13;
&#13;
confrontations."     McNamara read three years of verbatim minutes, and               That didn't work out.          President Johnson is supposed to have said that&#13;
&#13;
for awhile McNamara hardly opened his mouth.                                          if McNamara wanted to leave, he should leave as soon as possible.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                               21                                                                                22&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:    Johnson said that to McNamara?                                      bad better come up with large programs.       When it looked as if the&#13;
&#13;
BROCHES:    Yea.   I think that is what happened.    So McNamara    didn~t     Â·targets couldn't be met be would say, "How fellows, this is your&#13;
serve out the tera of the President.     McNamara by then bad grave doubts     program; not .!!Y. program, it is your program."       That didn't sit well.&#13;
&#13;
about the things that Johnson vaa doing and things that he hi.aelf was         It particularly didn't sit well with some of the younger people who&#13;
&#13;
doing.     He came to the Bank on April lat. 1968.    I think it was the day   were at the working level.      They said,   Â·~e   are professionals.   We are&#13;
&#13;
after Johnson announced that he would not run again.                           forced to write up reports that can't properly be done by next June 30&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:    Have we talked about all the positive things of the Woods           lend of fiscal year].&#13;
&#13;
years?                                                                         OLIVER:     Virtually all the top people in the Bank today are people who&#13;
&#13;
BROCHBS:    Yea. There was IDA; a aoaewbat more liberal, if you will.          were appointed by McNamara?      With the new President, â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢&#13;
&#13;
policy on "non-project"' or ''prograa 11 loans and on the financing of         BROCHES:     Yea, I think you are right.     There is a new man here -- a&#13;
&#13;
local ezpenditure1 with foreign exchange.     It was all a bit more open.      Brazilian.&#13;
&#13;
That was all positive.                                                         OLIVER:    Mr. Botafogo.&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:    So there was a sort of natural transition from the end of the       BROCHES:     Of course the whole of the (twelfth] floor is new.         Ernie&#13;
&#13;
Black years to the beginning of the McNamara yeara?                            Stern was brought in by McNamara.&#13;
&#13;
BROCBES:    Yea.                                                               OLIVER:     Is there a parallel with the Woods Bankt       Irving Friedman was,&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:    Onder McNamara. I take it, relations both with the Board and        I think, the only senior person that Woods appointed.&#13;
&#13;
the Staff improved?                                                            BROCHES:     Yes, and McNamara fired him, and Irving went on to do good&#13;
&#13;
BROCHES:    Yea.   Of course, I wasn't there during the last two years.        things with Citibank.      Ernie Stern came in under McNamara.      Hollis&#13;
&#13;
At first we saw the advantages of his systematic approach           his        Cbenery left.     Did Anne Kruger come in under McNamara?&#13;
&#13;
planning of operations.     He said that having a plan meant no more than      OLIVER:    I think.   I'll look that up.&#13;
&#13;
that you have to explain why you are not carrying out the plan. That           BROCHES:     What happened when McNamara came in was that Woods had&#13;
&#13;
sounded very nice, but gradually it became clear that what it really           already fixed him up with two vice presidents.         There was William&#13;
&#13;
meant was that the plan had to be carried out.       McNamara would ask the    Clark.     I think McNamara saw him a few days before be arrived.        There&#13;
&#13;
various regions (in the meantime we had bad this reorganization) to            was Dennis Rickett.     The first hint I had that McNamara might be coming&#13;
&#13;
submit their programs. and the Regional Vice Presidents knew that they         to the Bank was when I read in the society pages of the Washington Post&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                  23                                                                                  24&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
that Mr. and Hra. Shoaib (ex Pakistani Minister of Finance, Vice                      World Bank nevertheless needs the consent of the Government concerned.&#13;
&#13;
President of the Bank] gave a dinner for Secretary and Mrs. McNamara                  The Bank's Articles so provide.    Woods bad very bad relations with&#13;
&#13;
and Mr. and Mrs. Woods, and I said to myself, "There is the handwriting               [Secretary of the Treasury]    Henry Fowler, and it didn't take very long&#13;
&#13;
on the wall."                                                                         before Woods became concerned that the Bank might not be able to borrow&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:    When was that?     Can you recall?                                         the funds it needed to meet ita obligations to ita borrowers.        He and I&#13;
BROCBES:    February or March of '67.                                                 talked about the problem.     Each country has the right to give or&#13;
OLIVER:    '67, that early?     I'â&#128;¢ surprised.                                        vithh~ld   ita consent, but here was the   u.s â&#128;¢â&#128;¢   which at that time was&#13;
&#13;
BROCBES:    In late Noveaber of that year I was in Manila. A local paper              happily voting in favor of a greater loan program saying, "You can't&#13;
&#13;
said that the Board had elected McNamara President. I was surprised.              I   borrow in our market," even though the only way we could pay out on the&#13;
&#13;
phoned Washington. and I was told that the U.S. bad proposed           McNamara       loans we made was by borrowing in large part in the United States&#13;
&#13;
and that the next day by 10:00 o'clock cables were ezpected from all                  market.    This issue was never settled, but after a while it lost ita&#13;
&#13;
the Directors.                                                                        practical importance.&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:    Is there anything I should have asked you that I haven't asked             OLIVER:    Mr. Broches, I appreciate your time and thoughtfulness in&#13;
&#13;
you?                                                                                  coming.&#13;
&#13;
BROCHES:    I don't think so.                                                         BROCBES:    Did you get a much different impression of Woods than you&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:    Any legal implications to the controversy with the Indian                  heard from others?&#13;
&#13;
Government and the publication of the Bell Report on the front pages of               OLIVER:    I get a slightly different impression from everybody.       This is&#13;
&#13;
the papers that would go beyond what we talked about?                                 why it is the totality which I so much need.&#13;
&#13;
BROCHES:    None that I recall. There were some leaks about Bangladesh&#13;
&#13;
that were embarrassing.      Well, the legal issues were that the Bank had&#13;
&#13;
the right to transfer funds to IDA and that we didn't have to comply&#13;
&#13;
with General Assembly resolutions.       We bad one problem that disturbed&#13;
&#13;
Woods very much and that was that the U. S. was becoming difficult in&#13;
&#13;
giving the required consent to borrow.          The World Bank is different&#13;
&#13;
from other borrowers.       Even if a market is open to all comers the&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="17968940">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1985/11/17968940/transcript-oral-history-interview-aron-broches-held-november-07-1985-vol-2-2-main-transcript
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1985/11/17968940/transcript-oral-history-interview-aron-broches-held-november-07-1985-vol-2-2-main-transcript</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1985/11/17968940/transcript-oral-history-interview-aron-broches-held-november-07-1985-vol-2-2-main-transcript</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2008-02-26T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2008-02-26T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2013/07/05/000442464_20130705162431/Rendered/INDEX/789480v20TRN0B0iew0November07001985.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2013/07/05/000442464_20130705162431/Rendered/PDF/789480v20TRN0B0iew0November07001985.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>1985-11-07T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2013-07-05T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>2</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Transcript of oral history interview with
            Aron Broches held on November 7, 1985
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            In November 1985, Aron Broches was
            interviewed on behalf of the World Bank Group Archives oral
            history program by Robert W. Oliver. During his tenure at
            the Bank from 1946 to 1980, Mr. Broches worked in the
            following areas: in the legal department as an attorney
            (1946-1951); as assistant general counsel (1951-1956), as
            associate general counsel (1956-1959), and as general
            counsel (1959-1971) of the World Bank and the International
            Finance Corporation (IFC); as vice president (1972-1979);
            and in the International Centre for Settlement of Investment
            Dispute (ICSID) as secretary general (1967-1980). His
            association with the World Bank dates back to the Bretton
            Woods conference in the summer of 1944. His transcript
            concerns the following: George Woods as president of the
            World Bank; rescheduling the World Bank loans to India and
            the ensuing unpleasantness at the Board; an American foreign
            aid bill known as the Hickenlooper amendment; and his
            involvement with the council of foreign bondholders. Mr.
            Broches also discusses the United Nations (UN) in 1947
            making the World Bank a specialized agency under article 57
            of the UN charter later extended to cover International
            Development Association (IDA) and International Finance
            Corporation (IFC).
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Main transcript
        </docna>
        <display_title>Transcript of oral history
            interview with Aron Broches held on November 7, 1985 : Main transcript</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/1985/11/17968940/transcript-oral-history-interview-aron-broches-held-november-7-1985-main-transcript</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Transcript</docty>
        <subtopic>Public Sector Corruption &amp;
            Anticorruption Measures,Banks &amp; Banking Reform,Corporate Law,Debt Markets,Sustainable Land and Crop Management</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Law and Development,Public Sector Development,Rural Development</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000442464_20130705162431</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>World Bank Group Archives oral history program</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Law and Development,Public Sector Development,Rural Development</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Board Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            agricultural loans, Bank profits, bond, bond
            holders, Bondholders, charter, cooperation agreements,
            creditors, debt, debt issue, debtors, deposit, developing
            countries, expropriation, foreign exchange, foreign
            investors, human rights, human rights violations,
            initiative, lawyer, lawyers, lenders, loan, Minister, public
            debt, reorganization, repayment, Reserve, Reserve Bank,
            Reserve Bank of India, reserves, Settlement, society,
            Treasury, treaty, underwriters, Union
        </keywd>
        <owner>Knowledge &amp; Information Services (ITSKI)</owner>
        <repnb>78948</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crops</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Settlement of Investment Disputes</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Treaties</ml:concept><ml:concept>Treasury</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>