<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>ï»¿                                                                     79013&#13;
DIVISION OF THE HUMANITIES AND SOCIAL SCIENCES&#13;
CALIFORNIA INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY&#13;
PASADENA, CALIFORNIA 91125&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
A CONVERSATION WITH JULIAN GRENFELL&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Washington, D.C.&#13;
&#13;
July 15, 1986&#13;
&#13;
Â©   Robert W. Oliver&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                               ~&lt;;1\lUTf OF&#13;
                                                            ~~~ ~ r.,-~&#13;
                                                        ~                                  ~&#13;
&#13;
                                                      .&#13;
                                                                .&#13;
                                                      :Â§                                   b&#13;
                                                      '-'                        .         "'&#13;
                                                                                           -&lt;&#13;
&#13;
                                                      t.,.1'~ f~~(\ o"'i     \&#13;
                                                             "J~r                    \.~&#13;
                                                                    SlfALL tAP.~&#13;
                                                 CONVERSATIONS ABOUT GEORGE WOODS&#13;
                                                       AND THE WORLD BANK&#13;
&amp;#12;Â·'&#13;
                                                                                                                                          2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                      I was on a visit that he made to East Africa the summer&#13;
&#13;
                         A CONVERSATION WITH JULIAN GRENFELL                 before '66.    We went from Kenya to Uganda.     In those days, Milton&#13;
&#13;
                                                                             Obote was the President of Uganda    ~-   the first time around.   I&#13;
&#13;
                                  WASHINGTON, D.C.                           remember George Woods, Abdullah El Emory, an Egyptian who was then&#13;
&#13;
                                                                             Director of the Africa Department of the Bank, George Wishart, a&#13;
&#13;
                                    July 15, 1986                            Scotsman who was Woods' personal assistant, and 1 had breakfast&#13;
&#13;
                                                                             together on the terrace of the Lake Victoria Hotel before Woods was&#13;
&#13;
                                  Robert W. Oliver                           to go off and have a one-on-one conversation with Obote.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                      As we were having breakfast, he said to El Emory, "Tell me,&#13;
&#13;
                                                                             Abdullah, we haven't lent any money to Uganda for a couple of years&#13;
&#13;
     GRENFELL:     Let's talk about Woods' personality for a little while.   because we have disapproved of the economic policies they were&#13;
&#13;
     He was a supremely self-confident man because he had come up from       pursuing.     We couldn't get any agreement on the terms of this and&#13;
&#13;
     the bottom to the top and had all the prejudices and feelings of        that,     We seem to be agreed that we should start lending again if&#13;
&#13;
     self confidence of somebody who at the top could say, "I made it        you're convinced that there are good things we can lend for."           Then&#13;
&#13;
     here on my own.     I wasn't born to wealth; I wasn't a son of a        he said, "How important is it politically that we resume lending?"&#13;
&#13;
     banker,     anything like that."   He was brusque.   He didn't speak    El Emory said, "It probably means the difference between Obote&#13;
&#13;
     with a very happy turn of phrase.      He could turn people off with    staying in power and Obote going.     If the World Bank does not&#13;
&#13;
     his bluntness.                                                          announce that it's going to resume lending after your visit, this&#13;
&#13;
     OLIVER:     Does that mean any more than that he was not very           is a real blow to a man."     Woods said, "Do we need to keep him in&#13;
&#13;
     diplomatic?                                                             power?     Is there somebody else who could do the job better?"        El&#13;
&#13;
     GRENFELL:     He was not very diplomatic.   He knew his own mind and    Emory said, "No, there is only the army.       If you lose Obote, you&#13;
&#13;
     knew what he wanted to get across.      He didn't believe in mincing    lose most of the good people who are with him at the moment, and&#13;
&#13;
     words.    Maybe he didn't know how to mince words.     I remember one   the army takes over."     Woods said, "Then I guess we'd better make&#13;
&#13;
     occasion which revealed a great deal to me about how he always got      the loan.     If he is the only guy who can really run this country&#13;
&#13;
     down to the core problem.                                               other than the army, I guess we'd better make him some loans."&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                3                                                                           4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     I was sitting there as a very junior staff member eating my                 colonies.     The ruling span of political leaders seemed to be a bit&#13;
&#13;
corn flakes     and wondering,   "My   God, is this the way the Bank             longer than they are nowadays.     There was a familiar cast of&#13;
&#13;
operates?"    But that was very much Woods.       He would always get down       characters.     I think that the Bank in those days felt that it had a&#13;
&#13;
essentially to what was the critical political issue.          He was much       much better grasp of what was going on and what could be done.&#13;
&#13;
talked about as a man. who knew only about investment -- a sense of              Woods needed to do this and that.      That helped him to be smart.&#13;
&#13;
what needed to be done in certain countries to get their economies               But I agree with you. He came to the Bank with a better knowledge&#13;
&#13;
moving, but he was underneath it all a very political man.            He         of development issues in the Third World than McNamara did, more&#13;
&#13;
could see that if we do this, we keep the president of an                        than Clausen did, more than Conable, and certainly more than Gene&#13;
&#13;
independent country in power.          If we decline to do this we're            Black, who had been a bond salesman.     Well, Black had been the&#13;
&#13;
probably condemning him to a revolution.         He was a lot smarter than       American Executive Director on the Board, but in those days it was&#13;
&#13;
people gave him credit for.       I didn't say that he was smart                 basically a question of where we got the money.     He didn't know&#13;
&#13;
necessarily     in the sort of way which the President of the World              very much about the conditions of developing countries.        Woods had&#13;
&#13;
Bank ought to be, but he was politically very astute.                            travelled extensively in the Third World, not only in his capacity&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     One person I talked to said there was no doubt in his mind           as Chairman of First Boston, but the Bank had hired him on a number&#13;
&#13;
that, in terms of I.Q. as a measure of smartness, Woods was                      of occasions to lead World Bank missions to developing countries.&#13;
&#13;
probably the smartest president the Bank ever had.          What is your         OLIVER:     I want to ask in a moment, Why, with this preparation and&#13;
&#13;
view about that?                                                                 his basic brightness, did things not go better?     But before I ask&#13;
&#13;
GRENFELL:     I think that is true.       I have to add that some of the         that, let me ask a pointed question related to your story.        Did&#13;
&#13;
issues were less complicated in those days than they are now.              The   Woods often tend to bypass regular staff procedures for determining&#13;
&#13;
decisions that he had to make about the levels of support that the               which countries got loans and what the loans were going to be for?&#13;
&#13;
Bank would give a particular country were often based on a much                  GRENFELL:     Yes, I think he did on occasion in certain countries.&#13;
&#13;
simplified view of the potential prospects of countries.                         He had his own ideas on what needed to be done.     I think more than&#13;
&#13;
     Everything was very much more stable in those days.            This was     bypassing the staff, he irritated his Board of Directors enormously&#13;
&#13;
the pre-Smithsonian era: there were stable exchange rates, and the               by leaving them with the impression that they were rubber stamping.&#13;
&#13;
colonial powers were still pumping money into their former                       He did not welcome opposing views.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                               5                                                                         6&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     He wasn't going to pay much attention to them.                   that all he thought about was the Bank, that he didn't have any&#13;
&#13;
GRENFELL:     He wasn't going to pay much attention to them.       There     close friends.&#13;
&#13;
were one or two on the Board that he did pay attention to, but by            OLIVER:     Someone said that he was basically a New Yorker.    He had a&#13;
&#13;
in large he reckoned that he and Burke Knapp, who was then the               fair number of close friends in New York, and he always regarded&#13;
&#13;
Senior Vice President of Operations, Chairman of the Loan                    the assignment in Washington as a quite temporary part.&#13;
&#13;
Committee, and Number Two in the Bank Â·Â· between the two of them,            GRENFELL:     Yes, I think he did.   He didn't fight for a second term&#13;
&#13;
they really knew what was needed, and they weren't going to take             in the Bank.     He quite relunctantly stayed on a little longer after&#13;
&#13;
much criticism from the Board.       Relations between the Bank and the      his five year term was up, to accommodate Lyndon Johnson.       Hr.&#13;
&#13;
Board were at their lowest ebb when Woods left and McNamara came             Johnson was not prepared to let McNamara go until the 1969 defense&#13;
&#13;
in.   They'd never been good under Woods.      They had improved under       budget was locked up.&#13;
&#13;
Black.    Black was fairly autocratic, but he had the advantage of                I think there was a transformation of Woods in the second half&#13;
&#13;
personal charm and style.       He could deal with the Board in ways         of his term of office:     he came to an understanding that the&#13;
&#13;
that Woods couldn't.     Black would invite them out to barbeques or         Presidency of the World Bank and the institution of the World Bank&#13;
&#13;
take them off to see a baseball game at the stadium Â·Â· things like           could do a lot more than he had imagined when he first came in.       He&#13;
&#13;
that. They disagreed with him, but they liked him.         Woods was not a   started flexing his muscles, and flexing the institution's muscles&#13;
&#13;
particular likeable person to the Board.       They regarded him as          in the last two years.     He was the one without whom the Pearson&#13;
&#13;
autocratic, grouchy, and determined to have his way.                         Commission would probably never have taken place.      He began to&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     Not, I take it, terribly sociable in the entertainment           realize that his voice counted in the growing and expanding&#13;
&#13;
sense.                                                                       community of people who were really interested in creating an&#13;
&#13;
GRENFELL:     No, he was not.    He lacked social grace.    He was not       international network of development officials and people in&#13;
&#13;
good at small talk really.       In his declining years, he became a man     politics.     He found himself willy nilly as President of the Bank in&#13;
&#13;
of great charm.     When he reeired and I was living in New York as          all of that.     In the last two years, particularly in the last year&#13;
&#13;
the representative to the UN, I used to have lunch with him quite            when he pushed hard for the Pearson Commission and produced the&#13;
&#13;
often.    He was a man full of wisdom and charm.     We talked about         finance for it, he moved out of being an autocratic head of the&#13;
&#13;
theater and music.     I had the impression when he was at the Bank          World Bank to being an international statesman.      It carne very late&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                                                         8&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
in his period in the office.                                               are you going to do about Pakistan?     Those were the major tests of&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     Some have identified these last two years with the period      the Bank, and in relations with India, there is no doubt, none at&#13;
&#13;
of what you might call his greatest "grouchiness."                         all, there is no question that in some respects Woods failed.          He&#13;
&#13;
GRENFELL:     Probably nothing made him more grouchy than his              irritated that government.     He was autocratic with them.       He told&#13;
&#13;
relations with India.     In those days, India was -- I was about to       them this and that, what to do.     Some of the things he told them to&#13;
&#13;
say -- the Jewel in the Crown of the World Bank.      India was the        do turned out to have been not far off the mark, but he was very&#13;
&#13;
biggest country inside of the Bank.      It was the biggest borrowing      tough with them.     He knew that the Bank's reputation was going to&#13;
&#13;
country.     lt was the one with the biggest problems.    It had           rest on how he did in India.     He would be delighted today if he&#13;
&#13;
starving millions.     At that time, the reputation of the Uorld Bank      were alive to see what the results have been, but it cost him a&#13;
&#13;
tended to be measured in terms of what it could do for India.              great deal at that time; and he didn't always make the right&#13;
&#13;
           Africa was just becoming independent. It was considered a       decisions.&#13;
&#13;
challenge for the future, but not for the present.       In Latin          OLIVER:     Can you give an example of a wrong decision?&#13;
&#13;
America the governments were pretty stable,      They were exporting       GRENFELL:     Well, he forced devaluation on India, which was&#13;
&#13;
nicely.     They were doing O.K.   Things were moving along fairly         politically unpopular, and it proved economically bad at the time.&#13;
&#13;
satisfactorily -- high inflation rates, but they weren't really a          OLIVER:     What were the evidences of its being bad?&#13;
&#13;
problem.     The Mediterranean countries were borrowing happily.           GRENFELL:     It didn't increase India's exports, and, at that time,&#13;
&#13;
Yugoslavia, Greece and Turkey had pretty good relations with the           they desperately needed food imports.     They needed a liberalization&#13;
&#13;
Bank.     The East Asian countries were just coming into relations         of their imports too.     But Uoods felt that devaluation was&#13;
&#13;
with the Bank:     Thailand, Malaysia, Burma, Singapore, Philippines,      important for them to do.     He had a real problem with India.      He&#13;
&#13;
Indonesia.      (We neglected Indonesia, or rather Indonesia neglected     once said to me, to mix geographic metaphors, "India is my Cross of&#13;
&#13;
itself, because Sukarno took them out of the Bank.)                        Lorraine,'' and it was.    In the end it turned out all right.      It may&#13;
&#13;
        Today the big test caSe is what the World Bank does about          have turned out all right for reasons that have nothing much to do&#13;
&#13;
Latin America and what it does about Africa.     Those are the             with George Woods, but he certainly didn't ruin the country.&#13;
&#13;
yardsticks on how well the Bank is doing.     In those days, it was        OLIVER:     Wasn't it true that he was backing Bernie Bell, whose&#13;
&#13;
the Indian Consulate.     What are you going to do about India?     What   commission made a recommendation about devaluation and many other&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                 9                                                                           10&#13;
Â·'&#13;
     things, some of which.                                                    So I'm curious how people in the Bank came down, on one side or the&#13;
&#13;
     GRENFELL:    Yes, he was convinced by it.    He could have changed        other on that issue.&#13;
&#13;
     that.     but he was convinced by it.   He had great faith in the         GRENFELL:     My recollection was that there was a lot of resistance&#13;
&#13;
     people he appointed.     The other side to his being autocratic was       from the developing countries.&#13;
&#13;
     that in order to be autocratic he had to have a position to take,         OLIVER:     At the Board level?&#13;
&#13;
     and then he was very autocratic on the implementation of it.         A    GRENFELL:     At the Board level.   Directors felt that if India&#13;
&#13;
     good thing about George Woods was that, before he exercised               doesn't want this devaluation, why are we pushing it?&#13;
&#13;
     autocratic powers, he made sure that he had support, that he was          OLIVER:     Was there much grumbling on the grounds that this should&#13;
&#13;
     taking a position that had support in the Bank.      The problems that    be an affair of the Fund rather than the Bank?&#13;
&#13;
     he had over the decisions that he promulgated and put forward were        GRENFELL:     No, because the Fund agreed with this.   One had the&#13;
&#13;
     not that he was not supported by the Bank staff, for he usually           impression at the time, rightly or wrongly, that the Bank was the&#13;
&#13;
     was, it was that he was not supported by the Board.                       one calling the shots in India.&#13;
&#13;
     OLIVER:     Did the Board raise objections about the devaluation          OLIVER:     In any event, George Woods felt strong personal&#13;
&#13;
     recommendation to India?                                                  responsibility for what happened in India, and the major point is&#13;
&#13;
     GRENFELL:     I don't recall.   I don't recall the details of it.    It   that he was upset that the Indian government continued to resist&#13;
&#13;
     happened just before I arrived at the Bank.                               that recommendation.&#13;
&#13;
     OLIVER:     The reason I press you about the devaluation is because       GRENFELL:     He didn't like it, and it is to his credit   that,&#13;
&#13;
     this has been a controversy going on amongst economists ever since        although he didn't like the reaction he got from India, that didn't&#13;
&#13;
     the "Dollar Shortage" days in England in the late '40s, with some         in any way turn him against India.     In fact, during the Woods&#13;
&#13;
     economists supposing devaluation, while it may take two years or so       years, lending to India escalated -- especially with the new import-&#13;
&#13;
     to work its way through the economy, is the only way really to deal       financing type of lending that we did.     It was the first time we&#13;
&#13;
     with major balance-of-paymebts deficits, with controls on imports         made loans in three figure million dollars.     He never abandoned&#13;
&#13;
     if you want to limit specific imports; and others saying, it is           India and yet he was hurt by the reaction.&#13;
&#13;
     just the wrong thing for the country that has an import shortage          OLIVER:     Was it you last November who told me a story about a&#13;
&#13;
     already -- a capital shortage, and therefore an import shortage.          speech that he made toward the very end of his administration in&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                             11                                                                          12&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
India which was an unfortunate choice of words?                              state.    Then he would be very, very tough indeed.    He would really&#13;
&#13;
GRENFELL:     I don't think it was I, but     remember that speech.     He   tell them what he thought of the way they were managing their&#13;
&#13;
angered them.     He always said what was on his mind, particularly in       economies.     He would always preface it by saying, "Look this is&#13;
&#13;
a one-to-one situation between himself and the country.       When he        between you and me.     It's not going to get out, so I'm really going&#13;
&#13;
spoke to an international forum for international consumption, when          to get tough with you."&#13;
&#13;
he was giving a general speech as at an Annual Meeting, he was very          OLIVER:     How far can speechwriters go in dealing with these kinds&#13;
&#13;
careful.     Yhen he was one-on-one with a country, he could be pretty       of problems?&#13;
&#13;
rough.     He would say it like it is.                                       GRENFELL:     Not very far.   As a speech writer, one should be&#13;
&#13;
         McNamara did the same, but he always did it behind closed           sensitive to what the impact will be on the institution rather -than&#13;
&#13;
doors.     He never made public statements.    The furthest McNamara         on the President.     It's rather like having two mistresses:     you&#13;
&#13;
ever went, further through his term as President, was to mention             have carefully to review your writing and how its going to affect&#13;
&#13;
countries by name at the Annual Meetings.       Saying that one of the       him, what the reaction is going to be; and you have to care for the&#13;
&#13;
problems is that the fruits of growth in developing countries are            institution.     The interests of the two may not always necessarily&#13;
&#13;
not being equitably distributed among the population, he added the           coincide.     Something that might make the President of the Bank look&#13;
&#13;
Words, "such as in Brazil."     I think he put India in as well.             good in a speech may in fact come home to roost for the institution&#13;
&#13;
This was considered almost a heresy for the President of the Bank            later on.     You have to try to find the ways and means of phrasing&#13;
&#13;
to name countries when the Governors of those countries, the                 language so that the President says what he means and means what he&#13;
&#13;
Finance Ministers sitting out in the audience, considered it                 says, but that, at all times, what he says and what he means, the&#13;
&#13;
extremely risky.     I think he did it in Copenhagen in the Annual           institute can live with.      It is a delicate balancing act,&#13;
&#13;
Meeting there.     The protocol before that was that you could say           something you learn over a period of time how to handle.&#13;
&#13;
some countries were doing this, and some countries shouldn't be              OLIVER:     This is sort of a repeat of an earlier question.      Do you&#13;
&#13;
doing that, but you never named names.                                       think George Woods really was disappointed by the end of his term&#13;
&#13;
         McNamara named names and Woods named names, but he did it           in his ability to get things done, so to speak?&#13;
&#13;
when he was in the country, and he wouldn't mind. it if the press            GRENFELL:     I don't think so, no.    worked for him a little bit&#13;
&#13;
reported it.     McNamara did it behind close doors to the heads of          inunediately after he left the Bank.     I wrote a couple of speeches&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                             13                                                                     14&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
for him Â·Â· sort of a courtesy one extends to a retiring president.       institution.     What it needs is a quantitative leap forward in its&#13;
&#13;
I'm writing a couple for Clausen now.     No, he wasn't disappointed.    activities.     Woods had put in place what had not been there when&#13;
&#13;
He didn't want to serve on as President.     I think, with               Black left, which was a broader view of what development was:&#13;
&#13;
considerable justification, he felt that he had positioned the Bank      technical assistance, education, areas that the Bank had not been&#13;
&#13;
for the new era.     He knew about McNamara coming into the Bank as      in before.     He had built up a quite a sizeable economics staff, so&#13;
&#13;
the new President.     Sometime around about July or August of '67,      the Bank was not simply a Bank of technicians, but also one with an&#13;
&#13;
when it became clear.                                                    economic capacity, a research capacity, and a broader understanding&#13;
&#13;
      There was always speculation in the press about McNamara           of development.     He had taken it from being a development bank to a&#13;
&#13;
coming Ln.   Woods was happy about that, and Bob McNamara has            development institution, and McNamara was able to build on that.&#13;
&#13;
confirmed to me     (when I was writing two chapters of William               McNamara said to me that his work would have been ten times&#13;
&#13;
Clark's Autobiography on the World Bank, I checked this with             harder, he would have had to do a lot more reconstruction of the&#13;
&#13;
McNamara) that Woods had been a very good bridge between the Eugene      Bank, if the Bank had continued the way it was and there hadn't&#13;
&#13;
Black Bank and the McNamara Bank.     He had moved the Bank closer to    been this period when Woods came in.     People are saying the same&#13;
&#13;
becoming a development institution.     It was Woods who saw the value   thing about Clausen.     Whatever Conable is expected to do with the&#13;
&#13;
of building a strong economic research staff.     It was Woods who       Bank, he couldn't have done if he followed straight in after&#13;
&#13;
realized that, for political reasons, it was desperately important       McNamara.     Clausen has positioned the Bank to do far more in&#13;
&#13;
that the Bank     cooperate with the UN organizations.   Woods brought   structural adjustment lending, policy based lending, and has&#13;
&#13;
the Bank into a broader sphere of activity.     He was the one who       arranged closer relations with the other sources of finance, the&#13;
&#13;
pushed for loans to education.     He was the one who really talked      commercial banks, etc.&#13;
&#13;
the Bank into social development fields.     He started off on it            I find it interesting that, over the last twentyÂ·two years, you&#13;
&#13;
hesitatantly, but he positioned the Bank so that when McNamara came      have had these periods in which Presidents have had long terms in&#13;
&#13;
in, McNamara was able.                                                   office and have carried the Bank forward and then have reached a&#13;
&#13;
      McNamara viewed the Bank in the following way.     He said,        point where somebody else had to come in and make the changes that&#13;
&#13;
"This is an instrument which can do a hell of a lot more than it is      will prepare the way for the next person to make another big leap&#13;
&#13;
doing, and it won't take much changing the character of the              forward.     I see that as being the function that George Woods&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                              15                                                                        16&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
performed after Gene Black's fourteen year reign to enable McNamara       go and talk about what we are to do; let's have a common basis of&#13;
&#13;
to do what he did, and I regard Clausen as being the man who has          understanding."&#13;
&#13;
made it possible after McNamara's thirteen year reign to do what we       OLIVER:     You certainly don't look forward to a gradual dissolution&#13;
&#13;
have the will to do now.      It looks a little too tidy to be true,      of the Bank on the grounds that private capital is now available in&#13;
&#13;
but there is something in there that. ,                                   sufficient quantity to finance whatever development is needed.&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     Yell, of course Time is a motion picture; it is not a         GRENFELL:     No, I don't.   Private capital is very vulnerable.&#13;
&#13;
series of stills, it is a continuous process.      Let me ask you,        Things get bad enough in a particular developing country, and the&#13;
&#13;
since you are talking about this next era, what do you anticipate         Bank will say we are not going to lend.      The World Bank has to&#13;
&#13;
at this point will be characteristic of the Conable era?                  create conditions which maximize the attraction to the commercial&#13;
&#13;
GRENFELL:       think probably making the Bank a much more flexible       banks of investment in those countries.      Even the World Bank, with&#13;
&#13;
institution.     It will be opened to a lot of ideas about how it can     all its wisdom and expertise, can't convince commercial bankers to&#13;
&#13;
use its financial leverage and its expertise.      I don't think there    invest in a country that they feel is unstable with its debt out of&#13;
&#13;
will be major changes in the constitution of the Bank or anything         hand, etc. etc.     When things go well and commercial banks are&#13;
&#13;
like that.     We are are not really very constricted.    We are          prepared to put a lot of money into these countries, you still need&#13;
&#13;
constricted in one sense, and that is in our one-to-one gearing           an international organization like the World Bank to be able to&#13;
&#13;
ratio.      Providing   we can always increase our capital base,          advise the country that is the recipient of all this largess         to&#13;
&#13;
however, even that doesn't necessarily restrain us.                       say! "Hey, how are they going to use the money?"      At what point do&#13;
&#13;
     Conable is going to make the Bank an instrument that can             you tell, them, "Hey, wait a minute.     You're getting into the same&#13;
&#13;
coordinate the international effort.      He is very anxious to be able   position that you are getting into in the late '70s when you were&#13;
&#13;
to cure what we see as a deficiency in the international effort to        taking an enormous amount of debt and getting into a bad debt&#13;
&#13;
do something about a lack of coordination and common ground to            situation"?&#13;
&#13;
approach these problems.      CoOrdination is not really the right              The amounts that the World Bank lends as a portion of the&#13;
&#13;
word, it is rather a static word.      The French word   "Anim~."         total amount of development capital      is very small.   We get&#13;
&#13;
animate, is probably closer to what I think is going on in                preoccupied and overimpressed by our lending, but, in fact, it's&#13;
&#13;
Conable's mind.     He wants to be the person who says, "O.K., let's      terribly small compared to the total.     What we sometimes&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                           17                                                                         18&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
underestimate is the comfort factor that the other suppliers of           create a new facility, because when we got into the business of&#13;
&#13;
capital get from knowing that the World Bank approves of what the         making large loans to facilitate India's imports we simply called&#13;
&#13;
country is doing and approves of what the commercial banks are            them "industrial import loans.       These permitted them to import&#13;
&#13;
doing.    We have a moral authority there and the deployment of           some of the raw materials and some of the manufactured materials&#13;
&#13;
expertise which counts for a hell of a lot.                               they needed to maintain the industrial sector.       We just made Bank&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     Were you aware in the Woods administration of a proposal      loans; it wasn't necessary to set up a special facility.         The&#13;
&#13;
called the Supplementary Finance Proposal which came out of the           original idea that the Bank should only invest in specific projects&#13;
&#13;
economics staff?                                                          would have made it necessary for us to have a separate facility to&#13;
&#13;
GRENFELL:      Yes. Yes.   If this is the one where we were talking       enable these countries to finance imports.      It was Woods who took&#13;
&#13;
about shortÂ·falls and commodity prices.                                   the decision himself.     Why can't we just make them a loan?     Hake a&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     Well, not only short falls and commodity prices, but short-   list of things they are going to import.      You know where they are&#13;
&#13;
falls in export earnings, which might be due to a decline in              going to applied.     As far as he was concerned, it was a project; it&#13;
&#13;
commodity prices but could be due to a variety of other things            was balance of payments support;      it had the same effect as a&#13;
&#13;
including lending by commercial banks.                                    balanceÂ·ofÂ·payments loan.&#13;
&#13;
GRENFELL:     I remember this.   In the end, this was something the       OLIVER:     It required a bit of a redefinition of "projects."&#13;
&#13;
Fund took over on the grounds that it was considered to be more a         GRENFELL:     Yes, that's right.&#13;
&#13;
short-term than a long-term problem.                                      OLIVER:     The whole industry.&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     Well, there is a Compensatory Finance Facility in the         GRENFELL:     That's right.   Basically, it was the first of the nonÂ·&#13;
&#13;
Fund, but some people in the Bank argued at the time that it was          project loans, though it didn't carry much of a policy implication.&#13;
&#13;
not only a short- term problem, but a long-term problem as well.          OLIVER:     I'm wondering to what extent even this new era that you&#13;
&#13;
If it was the development process itself which was falling short,         are talking about in connection with the Conable administration&#13;
&#13;
then long-term as well as sbort-term funds needed to be available         wasn't perhaps foreshadowed in the Woods days by discussions of&#13;
&#13;
to finance the imports needed for the development program i f             supplementary finance and decisions that loans might be made on a&#13;
&#13;
exports were falling short for short-term or long-term reasons            much broader base than individual projects?&#13;
&#13;
GRENFELL:     Yes, I remember this.   In the end it wasn't necessary to   GRENFELL:       think that started in the Woods era, and the&#13;
&amp;#12;..                                                                 19                                                                      20&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     definition of a project was altered by Burke Knapp, Woods, and             future,   it seems to me, not only of the Bank but of the developing&#13;
&#13;
     others, so that the Bank could respond to what they considered to          world.&#13;
&#13;
     be legitimate needs in India.    That probably made it easier for the      GRENFELL:    I think you have to.   If we base all of our operations&#13;
&#13;
     Bank later on to make central loans.     It's been a steady                on the worse case scenario, everything is going down the drain.&#13;
&#13;
     progression.    I think that one thing that we need to be clear about      We're liable to make our investments in sort of last, short-term&#13;
&#13;
     is that,   for all the talk,   we~   doing more and more in structuralÂ·    attempts at saving the situation.     We take basically the view that&#13;
&#13;
     adjustment and policy-based lending.     That means that we are doing      we don't have to give up on the Third World provided you can get&#13;
&#13;
     less and less project lending.    It's not true in nominal terms,     in   agreement that there are medium to long-term investments that can&#13;
&#13;
     dollar figures.    The amount of lending for specific projects is          be made that will pay off.     You know we're not in the short-term&#13;
&#13;
     going up in nominal terms, but it is not going up in percentages.          salvation business anyway.&#13;
&#13;
          Much more importantly, all the things we are doing in the             OLIVER:     Is there anything else I should ask, or you would care to&#13;
&#13;
     field of structur~l-adjustment and policy-based lending is aimed at        volunteer, about the Woods years?&#13;
&#13;
     strengthening the overall economic position of the country.        If it   GRENFELL:    As I said, I think it was an extremely formative period&#13;
&#13;
     succeeds, the next stage will be an explosion of project lending,          for the Bank.     It put the Bank more on the political map.    Gene&#13;
&#13;
     because the countries will be in a position to turn to the market          Black had started it by using the good offices of the President of&#13;
&#13;
     to borrow for maintenance projects on their roads, for building new        the Bank to intervene and conciliate in certain areas.     But I think&#13;
&#13;
     industrial capacity, or whatever.     I'm very concerned when anybody      the true value of the Woods era was that Woods presided over a&#13;
&#13;
     says the Bank is moving away from project lending     as if we had         bigger explosion in the membership of the Bank than any president&#13;
&#13;
     changed course and from here on in the Bank was going to be in the         has presided over.&#13;
&#13;
     big lanes for less specified purposes.       regard this, and I know       OLIVER:     In percentage terms?&#13;
&#13;
     many of my colleagues do, as being simply a stage we are going             GRENFELL:    Between the day he came in '63 and he left in '68, there&#13;
&#13;
     through in order to position those countries to be able to afford          must have been 20 or 30 African countries that gained independence&#13;
&#13;
     to need and to have a justification for making -- a lot of                 and came into the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
     investments in things that we regard as specific projects.                 OLIVER:     I thought you were talking about the size of the staff.&#13;
&#13;
     OLIVER:    At any rate, you have a very optimistic view of the             You were talking about the membership.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                            21                                                                           22&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
GRENFELL:    Yes, the membership.   The size of the staff grew, but it     and the staff had adjusted itself to the idea that it must have a&#13;
&#13;
wasn't until McNamara got there that it really exploded.         I can't   considerable economic expertise.&#13;
&#13;
remember what the figures were, but McNamara doubled the staff in          OLIVER: Were you with him in Brazil at the '67 annual meeting?&#13;
&#13;
one year and tripled it in three.     Woods presided over an enormous      GRENFELL:     No.    That was a controversial meeting.&#13;
&#13;
increase in the Bank's customers.     He also took the first tentative     OLIVER:     Also a meeting during which an article appeared in      ~&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
steps towards bringing Eastern Europe into the Bank.     He wasn't         York Times critical of Woods and the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
actively seeking them, but the Rumanians were the ones.      I acted on    GRENFELL:     He was a man who was curiously insensitive to what the&#13;
&#13;
his behalf in some negotiations with the Rumanians.     In the early       outside world said about him.          never heard him complain about&#13;
&#13;
days when they were interested in coming in, when it was more              what the press was writing about him.        Of course the press were. not&#13;
&#13;
inconceivable that the hard line Communist countries were coming to        writing that much about Presidents of the Sank as they were shortly&#13;
&#13;
bay, his attitude was, "We're a World Bank, everyone is welcome.           afterwards when they got McNamara.        It's been one of the major&#13;
&#13;
Let them come in.    We probably have some very interesting things to      sports of the US press to keep an eye on the President of the World&#13;
&#13;
tell them, and they may have some things to teach us.â&#128;¢                     Sank, whatever he was doing.        But Woods didn't give a damn.     He was&#13;
&#13;
         He was not at all politically dogmatic.   He generally            a very thick-skinned man.        He didn't give a damn.   He didn't get&#13;
&#13;
believed in the universality of the Bank.     I really think, as I         irritated and go down there and say, â&#128;¢Why the hell did anybody let&#13;
&#13;
said, that he was the right man at the right place in the right            them write that article?"         He just said, I've got a job to do.&#13;
&#13;
time.    He didn't please everybody; he irritated some countries; he       OLIVER:     O.K.&#13;
&#13;
irritated a lot of his staff; he had very poor relations with his          NOTE:     After      had turned off the tape recorder, Sir Julian added a&#13;
&#13;
Board.   That was his style, rather than the substance of what he          few points.        He confirmed the story that George Woods took an&#13;
&#13;
was doing.    The staff were afraid to talk to the Board.    The senior    office in the World Sank for sixty days after McNamara became&#13;
&#13;
management didn't want the staff having any contact with the Board.        President on April 1, 1968, expecting to be called from time to&#13;
&#13;
Woods was constantly at loggerheads with them.     But the net result      time by McNamara for consultation on one thing or another.&#13;
&#13;
of anything he did was that, when McNamara came in on April 1,             McNamara never called.        Woods spent much of his time talking to his&#13;
&#13;
1968, he inherited a Bank which was right for major expansion.             stock broker in New York City, but was otherwise unengaged.           Sir&#13;
&#13;
Woods had already taken the first tentative moves into new areas,          Julian worked with Woods in the preparation of a speech which Woods&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                         23                                                                          24&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
was to deliver at the World Affairs Council in Pittsburgh, but the&#13;
&#13;
period was one of disappointment to Woods.   Sir Julian also made                                          An Addendum&#13;
&#13;
the point that even though Woods might be upset by personal                                              February 10, 1988&#13;
&#13;
criticisms of him by the press, the criticisms never deterred him&#13;
&#13;
from the path he was fQllowing in trying to accomplish one thing or   OLIVER:     This is Robert Oliver about to resume a conversation with&#13;
&#13;
another in the Bank.   In that sense, Sir Julian feels that Woods     Julian Grenfell.&#13;
&#13;
was a thick-skinned person.                                           GRENFELL:     I think there are three points I want to touch on. One&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      was that George Woods understood very early what that debt problem&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      was all about, and I don't think he was given sufficient credit for&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      this.     If you go back to the speech that he made in Stockholm just&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      before he left the Bank in 1968 when he launched the Pearson&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      Commission. .&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      OLIVER:     '67.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      GRENFELL:     Sorry.   It was in the fall of '67.      It was the speech&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      that Barbara Ward drafted for him in which he launched the "Grand&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      Assize" as he called it.      It's very striking how he recognized the&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      growing threat of the external debt problem which in those days was&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      largely associated with public debt.       He probably would never have&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      foreseen the extent to which it would have become a problem of&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      commercial debt, which it is so largely now.        I did talk to him in&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      New York in the mid '70s at the time when the developing countries&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      were borrowing huge sums of money from the commercial banks, .&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      OLIVER:     You mean, after '72?&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      GRENFELL:     Yes. I remember him saying at the time that he felt that&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      this was a very good way of recycling the petro dollars, but that&#13;
&amp;#12;â&#128;¢&#13;
&#13;
                                                               25                                                                          26&#13;
â&#128;¢&#13;
    you had to keep an eye on it because commercial debt could build up      leaving the Bank. This is my last major public pronouncement.           For&#13;
&#13;
    as fast and even more expensively than public debt.     It occurred to   Gods sake, listen.     This is what is going to happen."&#13;
&#13;
    me that he had a very good understanding of what the implications             The enthusiasm for the grand assize, which at that time they&#13;
&#13;
    were of the build up of the debt.     I think the figures around about   thought Oliver Franks was going to head, was very much rooted in&#13;
&#13;
    that time were that the developing countries as a whole were             his, as I say, writing-on-the-wall syndrome.     He thought that&#13;
&#13;
    devoting about 33 percent of all their external resources, funds         things could easily get out of hand.     He understood very clearly&#13;
&#13;
    coming in, on servicing the public debt. He saw the writing on the       what people like Edward Boyle, and Barbara Ward, and Rene Mayer,&#13;
&#13;
    wall.     That was certainly behind his major push to get a huge         and William Clark were saying to him which was that this&#13;
&#13;
    second replenishment of IDA.     It didn't work, of course. He asked     development decade has run out of steam.     The money that is going&#13;
&#13;
    in '66 for a billion dollars, and he got only 400 million, which         in is simply not doing the job.     It's raising GNP, standard of&#13;
&#13;
    was a big disappointment to him.     But the reason why he said we       living, but it's not having much impact on poverty.        I think he&#13;
&#13;
    must do this, why we must to have this quantum leap in resources         understood that quite clearly.&#13;
&#13;
    for IDA, was very largely because he was worried about the debt               That leads me to the second point I wanted to make. (Here I&#13;
&#13;
    structure of the developing countries.     Clearly there were a lot of   admit to a bias, because I spent seven years at the United Nations&#13;
&#13;
    them who needed loans on highly concessionary terms, so in the           as the Bank's representative).     He won a major battle with the&#13;
&#13;
    midst of the debt crisis that we are in now, I look back and think       staff of the Bank in bringing the Bank to closer relation with the&#13;
&#13;
    that he had a lot of foresight.     He could see it coming when a lot    United Nations.    That stands, in my view, as one of his most&#13;
&#13;
    of other people were really not that concerned about it.                 important achievements.     There was a lot of resistance in the Bank&#13;
&#13;
    OLIVER:     The Friedman concept of the IDA replenishment was also 3-4   to our having a closer relationship with the agencies of the UN,&#13;
&#13;
    billion dollars, at least half of which Irving thought should            but he understood that there wasn't much point in the international&#13;
&#13;
    accrue on highly concessionary terms.     He pushed for half of that     community supporting functional agencies, like FAO, like UNESCO,&#13;
&#13;
    which is where the number $f billion comes from.     This was clearly    like the World Health Organization, or UNDP, or a broader spectrum,&#13;
&#13;
    enunciated at least 2 years earlier than the Stockholm speech.           unless those who had the funds available were prepared to work&#13;
&#13;
    GRENFELL:     Yes, it certainly preceeded that at least 2 years          along with them.     Even when I came in the Bank in '65, which was&#13;
&#13;
    earlier. I think the Stockholm speech was saying, "Look I am             after he made his famous UNCTAD speech in New Delhi where he&#13;
&amp;#12;~&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                21                                                                          28&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    pledged the Bank's support, there was still a great deal of                 lot of the work that some of those agencies were doing in the&#13;
&#13;
    resistance to having anything to do with those agencies.                    preinvestment field, they had to rely on whatever meagre resources&#13;
&#13;
            There were those who said there should be a strict separation       there were in the U.N.&#13;
&#13;
    between preinvestment and investment, and the Bank's function was           OLIVER:     So it doesn't get around to an investment survey until the&#13;
&#13;
    to invest using the expertise of its own experts, that the Bank             Bank itself participates?&#13;
&#13;
    could only make wise investments if it had its own capability.              GRENFELL:     Yes, I suppose you could put it that way.   What happened&#13;
&#13;
    Well, that's always been true, but Woods saw that it did not                was that when Woods decided that it was not enough for the Bank&#13;
&#13;
    necessary exclude the possibility, and indeed the desirability, of          simply to focus on infrastructure, which it had been doing&#13;
&#13;
    having a closer relationship with the UN.      Hence, the institution       previously, it would have to get into additional fields:         more in&#13;
&#13;
    of the     cooperative program with the FAO which has worked                agriculture, more in education, more in industrial development,&#13;
&#13;
    remarkably well and which instantly produced a larger flow of               more in program lending, which is basically providing the foreign&#13;
&#13;
    projects which were worth financing.                                        exchange for the import of the essential goods and services.        When&#13;
&#13;
    OLIVER:     Would you distinguish preinvescment from an investment          he reached that decision, he said, "Look, we will have to have a&#13;
&#13;
    survey?                                                                     major expansion in these particular spectors.     Why are we not using&#13;
&#13;
    GRENFELL:     In strictly World Bank terms, -- the staff would have         the expertise of the individual agencies to identify and prepare&#13;
&#13;
    been happy to take on the entire responsibility of preparing the            projects that could be the subject for investment by the World Bank&#13;
&#13;
    ground for their own investments.      They didn't feel they needed         instead of us relying on our relatively small staff to do the same&#13;
&#13;
    anyone else's help.                                                         work?&#13;
&#13;
    OLIVER:     Would pre-investment then be limited to the FAO or some         OLIVER:     Willi Wapenhans reported that as early as 1963 George&#13;
&#13;
    other organization outside of the Bank?                                     Woods looked at a number of agriculture projects and said if you&#13;
&#13;
    GRENFELL:     The FAO and   UNESCO were doing their own pre-investment      can't do better than that we'll get the FAO to participate in&#13;
&#13;
    work,     but it wasn't locked into the Bank's program in any way.          planning the preinvestment of the projects.     I think that is&#13;
&#13;
    The collaboration between the Bank and those agencies was rather            basically what happened.&#13;
&#13;
    tenuous. We knew what they were doing and they knew what we were            GRENFELL:    Well that is basically what happened, and there was a&#13;
&#13;
    doing, but we were tending to plough our own individual furrows.        A   lot of kicking and screaming in the Bank when it happened.        There&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                29                                                                            30&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
was kicking and screaming outside the Bank too.       Sir Robert Jackson         That is sort of a negative attitude that people took, that we are&#13;
&#13;
was an early critic of this Â·- from a different perspective.              His    semi-autonomous according to the wording of it, and as far as we&#13;
&#13;
fear, if I recall it right, was that the Bank was going to become a              are concerned, we can    ~all   it autonomous. Why do we need to&#13;
&#13;
too heavy an influence in the UN agencies.       The tail would be               strengthen that relationship, particularly with UNGTAD which was a&#13;
&#13;
wagging the dog.    ~lle    the Bank was financing 75 percent of the             largely political organization which was dominated by the Third&#13;
&#13;
cost of identification in the preparation of the projects by these               World Countries?&#13;
&#13;
organization, which was not a great sum of money compared to their               OLIVER:     Which UNCTAD speech was this, '65, or '66?&#13;
&#13;
budgets, the Bank would really accumulate a degree of control or                 GRENFELL:     That was in New Delhi, which, I think was the first&#13;
&#13;
authority over the activities of these agencies that would be                    UNCTAD.     Was that '64 or later?   We'll have to check it out and&#13;
&#13;
unhealthy and would cause problems at the political level in the                 see. I think it was in New Delhi when he proposed the broad range&#13;
&#13;
General Assembly and the Economic and Social council.       In the early         with US agencies,     I think that was '64.    I can check it.     The&#13;
&#13;
days, he went along    ~ith   it, but he was very wary of it.        He          succeeding presidents have used and developed the relationships&#13;
&#13;
warned, "Don't let the Bank become the masters of these agencies.                with the agencies quite successfully, but always with sort of an&#13;
&#13;
        nit was never Woods intentions that we should. He said, nLook            attitude of, "Well, I guess we have to do this,R with no great&#13;
&#13;
~here   are guys out there who know what they are talking about in               enthusiasm.     I think the present President is very enthusiastic&#13;
&#13;
these countries.    Why don't we use them?"     Well, if you look at it          about some of the work we are doing with UNICEF.       Certainly&#13;
&#13;
today, the relationship with the agencies is at many different                   McNamara and Clausen regarded the relationship with the UN as&#13;
&#13;
levels and takes on many different shapes and forms. But I do think              something we should pay lip service to at the political level.&#13;
&#13;
that Woods gave it the push that it needed at that time despite the              Yes, we support the UN, and we want to make sure the UN doesn't&#13;
&#13;
fact that he was getting a lot of flack from within the Bank.              His   encroach on any of our business.      Our relationship with the UN&#13;
&#13;
UNGTAD speech, I understand, caused a great deal of dismay in the                agencies should be a relationship based very strictly on the terms&#13;
&#13;
Bank.    What's he doing?     Th&amp; attitude in the Bank at that time was,         and conditions that have been set up and shouldn't go any further&#13;
&#13;
"Look, we signed an agreement with the United Nations which is a                 than that.&#13;
&#13;
very exclusive agreement.       It doesn't link us, it doesn't state how         OLIVER:     Was Barbara Ward the principal writer of the Stockholm&#13;
&#13;
we are linked at the UN, it states why we are linked to the UN"?"                speech.&#13;
&amp;#12;!.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                     31                                                                          32&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     GRENFELL:     Yes.   When they decided that they wanted that group             might encourage him to take on the commission.      He turned it down&#13;
&#13;
     which was basically Edward Boyle, and Rene Hayer, William Clark.               on the grounds that he had too much else on his plate and probably&#13;
&#13;
     Axel Buscher . . . .      Who else? I can't remember.   There was a small      wasn't absolutely sure about what the value of this would be.       That&#13;
&#13;
     group that decided that they would launch some sort of a Grand                 was when he turned to Hike Pearson in Canada. He agreed to take it&#13;
&#13;
     Assize.     They sent William Clark off to Washington to talk to               on.&#13;
&#13;
     George Woods, who had been at the initial meeting in England at                OLIVER:     With, I have to say, indifferent results.&#13;
&#13;
     which they had got the idea going.       They sent him off to see if           GRENFELL:    With indifferent results.     It wasn't a bad survey, but I&#13;
&#13;
     Woods was interested in helping to finance the Assize.          Woods said     think what was wrong was that there was no plan to follow up.       The&#13;
&#13;
     that not only would he finance it, he would be happy to launch it.             Pearson Commission Report hit the public and the governments and&#13;
&#13;
     He had a date with the Swedish bankers for late '67, and this would            the academics. They all read it and said, "Well that's an&#13;
&#13;
     be a good opportunity to launch the whole idea."           But, 'IJood said,   interesting piece of work." Then it sort of faded away in people's&#13;
&#13;
     "You have got to get me somebody who can really put together a                 memories.&#13;
&#13;
     great speech."       Williams suggested Barbara Yard.   Woods was very         OLIVER:     Until the Brandt commission.&#13;
&#13;
     happy with that and so was Barbara Ward.                                       GRENFELL:    Until the Brandt Commission came along which had a&#13;
&#13;
     OLIVER:     \.las this the first time she had been a major speech              rather greater impact because it had a much more clearly defined&#13;
&#13;
     writer?                                                                        program of activities. It did have a bigger impact.&#13;
&#13;
     GRENFELL:     Well, she had written a lot of speeches of her own. 1                  The value of the Pearson report was it drew attention to the&#13;
&#13;
     think she had written for others.       It was certainly the first time        fact that the Development Decade had run into a lot of trouble.&#13;
&#13;
     she had written anything for the President of the Bank.          She did       Various things needed to be done to get it back on course, mainly&#13;
&#13;
     the entire draft.       It was very much her own speech.     Interestingly     sensitizing governments to the importance of not letting the&#13;
&#13;
     enough, in order to induce Oliver Frank's to take on the Assize, as            Development Decade falter any further.      I think it had its value&#13;
&#13;
     it was then called, she put 1n a paragraph comparing what needed to            there.    Some aspects of it were not very pleasing to the Bank,&#13;
&#13;
     be done now with what had been done under the Marshall Plan for                particularly the suggestion that IDA be cut loose from the Bank and&#13;
&#13;
     Europe. Oliver Franks was one of the chief      administ~ators       of the    be set up as an entirely separate organization. That didn't appeal.&#13;
&#13;
     Marshall Plan. This would immediately attract his attention and&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                    33&#13;
â&#128;¢                                                                                                                                           34&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                shouting matches.     McNamara never did.   The only time McNamara&#13;
&#13;
    OLIVER:     Why wasn't he more successful?                                  really got mad at the Board in a very quiet way was one day when an&#13;
&#13;
    GRENFELL:     If one thing marred his presidency, it was his pretty         executive director asked if there could not be a rule that McNamara&#13;
&#13;
    awful relations with the Board.        There are many other aspects that,   would submit the draft of his Annual Meeting speech to the Board to&#13;
&#13;
    I think, were first-class,    ~ut    he treated the Board as though it      take a look at.     McNamara dropped back and said, "I'm perfectly&#13;
&#13;
    was always his quarter in the telephone when he was addressing              prepared to hand over the draft of my Annual Meeting speech if you&#13;
&#13;
    them.     Of course in the old days when there was no IDA, just the         are prepared tomorrow to sit down and decide whom you are going to&#13;
&#13;
    Bank, he could talk to the Board rather differently than he could           have as the next president."     Nothing was ever heard again.      He&#13;
&#13;
    talk to the Board when so much of what was being lent was            ~      used to conceal his frustrations to the Board very well.         He didn't&#13;
&#13;
    money rather than the Bank's money.       Gene Black could be               let them hang out quite the way George Woods did.&#13;
&#13;
    domineering, although he wasn't a domineering man.        He could be       OLIVER:   Well, thank you very much for this edifying addendum.          It&#13;
&#13;
    forceful.     He had the sense, the clout, to be able to tell the           was very useful.&#13;
&#13;
    Board where to get off if he wanted to.        He could say, nLook&#13;
&#13;
    raised this money," But Woods didn't quite adjust to the new&#13;
&#13;
    atmosphere.     With IDA becoming more and more important, he was&#13;
&#13;
    addressing people who were not just helping him spend money, he was&#13;
&#13;
    helping them spend    ~     money.&#13;
&#13;
    OLIVER:     I have, in the last couple of weeks, had a sample of the&#13;
&#13;
    Board's minutes.     I had my attention directed to the possibly more&#13;
&#13;
    acrimonious parts of the minutes, and I must say I have not seen&#13;
&#13;
    with my own eyes the things that were acrimonious.&#13;
&#13;
    GRENFELL:     I think it was his tone more than anything else.       I&#13;
&#13;
    think if you read the written transcripts . .           He used to ramble&#13;
&#13;
    on a bit at times.     He was too opinionated.     He was a man who knew&#13;
&#13;
    what he wanted.     Presidents by and large have not gotten into&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="17973194">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1986/07/17973194/transcript-oral-history-interview-julian-grenfell-held-july-15-1986
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1986/07/17973194/transcript-oral-history-interview-julian-grenfell-held-july-15-1986</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1986/07/17973194/transcript-oral-history-interview-julian-grenfell-held-july-15-1986</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2008-02-26T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2008-02-26T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2013/07/08/000442464_20130708140813/Rendered/INDEX/790130TRN0Gren0erview0July015001986.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2013/07/08/000442464_20130708140813/Rendered/PDF/790130TRN0Gren0erview0July015001986.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>1986-07-15T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2013-07-08T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Transcript of oral history interview with
            Julian Grenfell held on July 15, 1986
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            In July 1986, Julian Grenfell was
            interviewed on behalf of the World Bank Group Archives oral
            history program by Robert W. Oliver. During his tenure at
            the Bank from 1965 to 1995, Mr. Grenfell worked in the
            following areas: in the office of information as speech
            writer (1965-1968); in the information and public affairs
            department, Afro-Asian division, as chief (1968-1969); in
            the information and public affairs department, European
            office, as chief (1969-1970) and as deputy director
            (1973-1975); in the development services department as
            assistant director (1970-1973); in the international
            relations department as special representative to the United
            Nations (1975-1983); in the information and public affairs
            department as speech writer(1983-1987); in the external
            affairs department as senior advisor (1987-1990), as chief
            of the European division (1990-1995), and as senior advisor
            to the office of the president (1995). His transcript
            concerns George Wood, Robert McNamara, devaluation in India,
            and pre-investment and investment surveys.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Transcript of oral history interview with
            Julian Grenfell held on July 15, 1986
        </docna>
        <display_title>Transcript of oral history
            interview with Julian Grenfell held on July 15, 1986</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/1986/07/17973194/transcript-oral-history-interview-julian-grenfell-held-july-15-1986</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Transcript</docty>
        <subtopic>Public Sector Corruption &amp;
            Anticorruption Measures,Banks &amp; Banking Reform,Corporate Law,Sustainable Land and Crop Management,Debt Markets</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Law and Development,Public Sector Development,Rural Development</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000442464_20130708140813</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>World Bank Group Archives oral history program</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Law and Development,Public Sector Development,Rural Development</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Board Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            accounting, arbitration, articles of
            incorporation, banks, bond, bond issues, bonds, Chamber of
            Commerce, Chamber of· Commerce, civil servant, civil
            servants, civil service, company, confidence, contract
            negotiations, corporate practice, Corporation, corporations,
            credibility, currency, developing countries, Economic
            Development, expropriation, foreign currency, foreign
            currency clauses, foreign investors, government guarantee,
            holding, infrastructure financing, initiative, insurance,
            insurance company, International Development, International
            Finance, international lending, international transactions,
            Investment Bank, joint venture, lawyer, lawyers, leadership,
            limited, loan, loan officer, loans to countries, local
            government, Monetary Fund, politicians, portfolio, private
            companies, private investors, private lending, redemption,
            retirement, return, returns, sanctions, Settlement,
            sponsors, Trade Agreement, Treasury, treaties, Treaty, universities
        </keywd>
        <owner>Knowledge &amp; Information Services (ITSKI)</owner>
        <repnb>79013</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Policy Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Policy Formulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Policy Implementation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Productivity-Led Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Banks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Retail Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crops</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>External Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supplementary</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Balance of Payments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inflation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>