<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>﻿                                                                 78967&#13;
                Summary of Oral History Transcript&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                          Collado, Emilio G.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Interview conducted by T. Wilson and R. McKinzie, Harry S. Truman&#13;
Library, on 1971-07-07&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     The first half of the interview addresses Collado's background,&#13;
the various positions held while working for the U.S. Government (US&#13;
Treasury, Federal Reserve Bank, Department of State, and Export-Import&#13;
Bank), and his involvement in the ground work leading to the&#13;
establishment of the IMF and the World Bank prior to his appointment&#13;
in June'46 as first U.S. executive director in the Bank. While in the&#13;
State Department, as Chief of the Financial and Monetary Affairs and&#13;
Development division, he became involved in what eventually became the&#13;
Bretton Woods Conference in the summer of 1944. This, according to&#13;
Collado, was the culmination of a lengthy relationship between Lord&#13;
Keynes [U.K. Treasury] and Harry D. White from the U.S. Treasury as&#13;
well as others from the State Department in preparing plans for new&#13;
international monetary and financial arrangements for the postwar&#13;
world.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Subsequently, and immediately prior to joining the Bank he became&#13;
director of the Office of Financial and Development Policy, dealing on&#13;
the 'monetary' side, and very much second to the Treasury, in the&#13;
eventual development of the International Monetary Fund and, on the&#13;
'development' side with what was to become the World Bank, and the&#13;
Export-Import Bank Collado was also involved in the proposal for the&#13;
development of the Inter-American Bank [1940] which failed&#13;
ratification in the U.S. Senate at the time and was eventually&#13;
established in 1958.&#13;
&amp;#12;     Collado stresses the importance of the U.S. Treasury's senior&#13;
role with regard to international financial affairs. The U.S.&#13;
Government's realization during World War II that it can play a much&#13;
bigger role in aid programs. The establishment [in '43] of the United&#13;
Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration (UNRRA), due in large&#13;
part to the efforts of Dean Acheson [then Assistant Secretary of&#13;
State]. Lend-lease aid ['41-'45, exceeded $50 billion].&#13;
Underestimating the magnitude of postwar economic problems of&#13;
reconstruction and development bringing about the realization of the&#13;
need for a bigger aid program which in turn stimulated the Harvard&#13;
address [June'47] by Marshall [then Secretary of State George C.] thus&#13;
introducing the Marshall Plan in [April]'48. The U.S. Treasury's view&#13;
of postwar economic conditions and its handling of them, as well as&#13;
the State Department's view. The increasing political and economic&#13;
difficulties between the U.S. and the Soviet Union in light of the&#13;
Communist threat and the effects on aid programs. The Russians&#13;
declining to join the Bretton Woods organizations. The diminished&#13;
support for UNRRA, and Collado's involvement on the working level with&#13;
Lord Keynes et al, in the negotiations with the British.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     In mentioning the death of Lord Keynes in 1946 just after the&#13;
Savannah meeting, Collado talks about Keynes the negotiator, and his&#13;
paper published posthumously in the Economic Journal as being one of&#13;
the great pieces of economic literature. And, he briefly talks about&#13;
the CED [Committee for Economic Development, founded in '42].&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Collado talks of his tenure at the World Bank and its top level&#13;
leadership. His resignation as not being personal, but rather due to&#13;
the change in management. The Bretton Woods Agreements Act, the&#13;
ramifications of its application, and the troubles he encountered with&#13;
the foreign executive directors and with then President Eugene Meyer.&#13;
Also, the creation of the National Advisory Council on International&#13;
Monetary and Financial Problems under the Act, chaired by the&#13;
Secretary of the Treasury, and his role within. He expounds on the&#13;
anti-Bank and anti-Fund attitude in the U.S. banking community. Opines&#13;
&amp;#12;on President Truman's selection of Eugene Meyer as first President of&#13;
the Bank, as well as on Meyer himself. Gives a retrospective self-&#13;
assessment of his behavior after Meyer's resignation in December '46&#13;
as due to his youthful 36 years. In conclusion, he talks of a proposal&#13;
in the records to appoint him president of the Bank and, how he did&#13;
not consider himself to be an international figure fit for the post.&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="17970988">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1971/07/17970988/transcript-oral-history-interview-emilio-g-collado-held-july-7-1971
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1971/07/17970988/transcript-oral-history-interview-emilio-g-collado-held-july-7-1971</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1971/07/17970988/transcript-oral-history-interview-emilio-g-collado-held-july-7-1971</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2008-12-02T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2008-12-02T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2013/07/06/000442464_20130706161943/Rendered/INDEX/789670TRN0Coll0Summary0July07001971.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2013/07/06/000442464_20130706161943/Rendered/PDF/789670TRN0Coll0Summary0July07001971.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>1971-07-07T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2013-07-06T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Transcript of oral history interview with
            Emilio G. Collado held on July 7, 1971
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            In July 1971, Emilio G. Collado was
            interviewed on behalf of the World Bank Group Archives oral
            history program by T. Wilson, R. McKinzie for the Harry S.
            Truman Library. Mr. Collado served his tenure at the Bank as
            executive director representing the United States from
            1946-1947. He stresses the senior role of the United States
            treasury with regard to international financial affairs. His
            transcript discusses the establishment in 1943 of the United
            Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration, and the
            creation of the national advisory council on international
            monetary and financial problems. He concludes by giving a
            retrospective self-assessment of his behavior after the
            resignation of president Eugene Meyer in 1946.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Transcript of oral history interview with
            Emilio G. Collado held on July 7, 1971
        </docna>
        <display_title>Transcript of oral history
            interview with Emilio G. Collado held on July 7, 1971</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/1971/07/17970988/transcript-oral-history-interview-emilio-g-collado-held-july-7-1971</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Transcript</docty>
        <subtopic>Public Sector Corruption &amp;
            Anticorruption Measures,Hazard Risk Management,Emerging Markets,Corporate Law,Debt Markets</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Private Sector Development,Finance and Financial Sector Development,Law and Development,Public Sector Development,Urban Development</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000442464_20130706161943</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>World Bank Group Archives oral history program</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Private Sector Development,Finance and Financial Sector Development,Law and Development,Public Sector Development,Urban Development</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Board Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Economic Development, Federal Reserve,
            Federal Reserve Bank, leadership, Monetary Fund,
            negotiations, Treasury, Union, United Nations Relief, War
        </keywd>
        <owner>Knowledge &amp; Information Services (ITSKI)</owner>
        <repnb>78967</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Treasury</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>