<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>ï»¿I'&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                               79008&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     THE WORLD BANK GROUP/HISTORIAN'S OFFICE&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
              ORAL HISTORY PROGRAM&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
               Transcript of interview with&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                K. GEORG GABRIEL&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   December 16, 1993&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
             By: W. Becker &amp; D. Milobsky&#13;
&amp;#12;\.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                        K. Georg Gabriel Interview&#13;
                            December 16, 1993&#13;
&#13;
     Q:   I am Bill Becker from the George washington University&#13;
     and the Business History Group.&#13;
     Q:   And I am David Milobsky from the World Bank Historian's&#13;
     office.&#13;
     Q:   And I am Georg Gabriel.&#13;
     Q:   Dr. Gabriel would you talk a little bit about your&#13;
     educational background.&#13;
     A:   I grew up in Germany, went to high school, or the sort&#13;
     of high school in Germany called the gymnasium.    It&#13;
     emphasized classical education.    I had nine years of Latin&#13;
     and seven years of Greek which has had its uses in many, many&#13;
     different ways subsequently.    I began going to University in&#13;
     Germany in 1948 after World War II.    I was also working while&#13;
     I was studying, which was easier to do in Germany at that&#13;
     time than it has been in some American universities (where&#13;
     full-time attendance is usually required) .&#13;
          I had an opportunity to come to Washington in the German&#13;
     Foreign Service on what initially appeared to be a temporary&#13;
     assignment, but which turned out to be more permanent.&#13;
     Rather than staying here for six months, as originally&#13;
     proposed, I ended up staying in this assignment for several&#13;
     years.    About a year into it, I concluded that it would be&#13;
     advisable to take steps to complete my education, and I&#13;
&amp;#12;, I,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                       Gabriel, Page 2&#13;
&#13;
       decided to go to the Harvard Business School.&#13;
&#13;
            I had thought of joining the World Bank or working in&#13;
&#13;
       the World Bank.   Early on, a colleague in Germany, an&#13;
&#13;
       Englishman, had gone to join the World Bank.    His name was&#13;
&#13;
       Walter Jago.   He may still be around.   He joined the World&#13;
&#13;
       Bank in 1948 or '49, and that prompted me to read up on the&#13;
&#13;
       Institution.   I decided it would be an interesting place to&#13;
&#13;
       work, so I applied for a job there in 1956.     I was 28 and had&#13;
&#13;
       a Master's degree from the Harvard Business School, but I&#13;
&#13;
       never received a response to my application.&#13;
&#13;
            In those days, there was no young professional program.&#13;
&#13;
       The Bank hired only mid-career people.   Although they were&#13;
&#13;
       beginning to employ a few Germans, I think the staff was&#13;
&#13;
       predominantly American, British, canadian, Dutch and French.&#13;
&#13;
       However, as Germany became a more important member in the&#13;
&#13;
       1960s, the Bank made more aggressive efforts to increase the&#13;
&#13;
       number of German staff.&#13;
&#13;
            Not having succeeded in going to the World Bank, I&#13;
&#13;
       picked from a number of other opportunities and joined Price&#13;
&#13;
       Waterhouse in New York with the intention of going to their&#13;
&#13;
       Caracas office where my younger brother was then running a&#13;
&#13;
       small consulting firm.    After three years with Price-&#13;
&#13;
       Waterhouse and in New York and caracas, I left to join my&#13;
&#13;
       brother's consulting firm, because he felt the need for&#13;
&amp;#12;fâ&#128;¢&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                     Gabriel, Page 3&#13;
&#13;
     further education and he, in turn, went to the Harvard&#13;
&#13;
     Business School.    He stayed there for four years and went&#13;
&#13;
     through the MBA and the doctoral program.    He then persuaded&#13;
&#13;
     me that my own education was becoming dated and that I should&#13;
&#13;
     go back and also get a doctorate which I proceeded to do.&#13;
&#13;
          On completing the doctoral program in 1967, I found that&#13;
&#13;
     my economic value in the market place had been cut in half.&#13;
&#13;
     I was thought of as an impractical academician. Â· I had three&#13;
&#13;
     career choices.    I could go into a financial institution,&#13;
&#13;
     such as a commercial bank, a money management firm, or accept&#13;
&#13;
     a job offer from what was then the Standard Oil of New&#13;
&#13;
     Jersey, subsequently Exxon, to join their global strategic&#13;
&#13;
     planning group.    This was an attractive opportunity because&#13;
&#13;
     this was a small group and several of its alumni had become&#13;
&#13;
     board members of the parent company.    I also thought it was&#13;
&#13;
     an interesting jumping off point.    Nevertheless, I applied to&#13;
&#13;
     the World Bank once again.   This time, they thought I had&#13;
&#13;
     sufficiently matured to warrant an interview and I was&#13;
&#13;
     invited to Washington and offered jobs in the IFC and the&#13;
&#13;
     World Bank.   I was too old for the Young Professionals&#13;
&#13;
     program and, given the competition, I probably wouldn't have&#13;
&#13;
     succeeded in getting in even if I had been younger.&#13;
&#13;
          In the end, I decided to come to washington at a salary&#13;
&#13;
     that was less than half of what my compensation would have&#13;
&amp;#12;,,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                     Gabriel, Page 4&#13;
&#13;
     been in the private sector.    I joined the World Bank in&#13;
&#13;
     August 1967.&#13;
&#13;
     Q:   What made you decide to go with the Bank rather than&#13;
&#13;
     Standard Oil or some other options?&#13;
     A:   My father was a professor of theology and clergyman, a&#13;
&#13;
     bishop in the Protestant Reform Church in Germany.    In the&#13;
&#13;
     German middle or professional classes, going into business&#13;
&#13;
     was frowned upon.    There was an opprobrium attached to&#13;
&#13;
     focusing on pursuing a materially rewarding career.    One&#13;
&#13;
     became a civil servant, went into the military, or became a&#13;
&#13;
     clergyman or a teacher at a university.    When I was quite&#13;
&#13;
     young I wanted to become a clergyman in the countryside, a&#13;
&#13;
     pastor with pigs, because I had been very impressed by&#13;
&#13;
     someone who was.    He had the mud of the stable attached to&#13;
&#13;
     his boots when he carne into the church, which for some reason&#13;
&#13;
     struck me as an appealing contrast.&#13;
&#13;
          The World Bank somehow seemed to be an attractive&#13;
&#13;
     institution that combined reasonably tolerable economic&#13;
&#13;
     conditions with high professional goals and standards.       I&#13;
&#13;
     thought it was an institution where--in a manner of speaking-&#13;
&#13;
     -one could do well by doing good.&#13;
&#13;
     Q:   May I ask what happened to your brother who got the DBA?&#13;
&#13;
     A:   He ended up becoming a partner at McKinsey and then dean&#13;
&#13;
     of the School of Management at Boston University under&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                 Gabriel, Page 5&#13;
President John Silber.   He was one of the 11 deans in the&#13;
mid-1970s who had a falling out with the President, but he&#13;
was the only one who actually resigned.    At one point,&#13;
recently, he decided that after 40 years abroad he wished to&#13;
go back to Germany where he joined the faculty of the&#13;
University of Ulm.   Three years into that, he concluded that&#13;
he didn't fit in any more after all.    He built a house in&#13;
western Massachusetts and is now spending his retirement&#13;
working again as a consultant.&#13;
Q:   Your first assignment with the Bank was as a loan&#13;
officer in Latin America?&#13;
A:   Yes.   I became a loan officer responsible for Colombia,&#13;
in part because I was fluent in Spanish.    Colombia was&#13;
becoming a very active borrower from the Bank.     It had been&#13;
one of the first developing country clients of the Bank in&#13;
the early 50s.   It even received one or two IDA credits when&#13;
IDA was started 10 years later.   There had been a hiatus in&#13;
lending to Colombia where a number of operations had been&#13;
under appraisal but hadn't resulted in loans.     I had the good&#13;
fortune of coming in and taking a number of loans to the&#13;
Board.   In fact, at one Board meeting in May or June, 1968, I&#13;
presented four loans to the Board.     In that year (fiscal year&#13;
1968), there were only 37 loans approved, and being&#13;
responsible (or seeming to be responsible) for four of them&#13;
&amp;#12;.,,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                       Gabriel, Page 6&#13;
      gave me some visibility.     I hasten to add that I really&#13;
      reaped the benefits of work done over a number of years by&#13;
      others.     It was a case of being in the right spot at the&#13;
      right time.&#13;
      Q:      But you were a loan officer for a fairly short period of&#13;
      time?&#13;
      A:      I was there until, I believe, August, 1969.    Around May&#13;
      1969, a year after McNamara had become president, he had&#13;
      brought in a new Treasurer, Gene Rotberg.     The outgoing&#13;
      Treasurer was said to have told McNamara that it was not&#13;
      feasible to expand the operations as rapidly as the new&#13;
      President's Council wanted and that precipitous growth would&#13;
      jeopardize the Bank's financial standing.     This, or a&#13;
      combination of other circumstances, led to the appointment of&#13;
      a new Treasurer.     At that time, the Treasurer's Department&#13;
      was, if not the largest, one of the largest departments.        It&#13;
      was decided that the unwieldy group should be divided into a&#13;
      Controller's Department (which didn't exist until then) to&#13;
      take over the mundane tasks of accounting and processing&#13;
      disbursements, and a Treasurer's Department to focus on&#13;
      borrowing and cash management operations.     Thus, the&#13;
      Treasurer's Department would be responsible for raising money&#13;
      and investing it, and the Controller's Department would be&#13;
      responsible for all other financial activities:       disbursing&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                Gabriel, Page 7&#13;
&#13;
loans, keeping the books for the three institutions&#13;
&#13;
(including IFC in those days) and paying payrolls, etc.&#13;
&#13;
Q:    What induced you to move from the loan side to the&#13;
&#13;
financial side?&#13;
&#13;
A:    I was 40 or 41, and eager to assume a more responsible&#13;
&#13;
position.   There was outside pressure to place more Germans&#13;
&#13;
into senior positions.    I learned that they were looking for&#13;
&#13;
a Controller in Germany and in a bit of self-promotion&#13;
&#13;
suggested that the personnel people look also inside, I was&#13;
&#13;
not basically interested in spending my years in the Bank as&#13;
&#13;
a Controller, but regarded the position as a stepping stone&#13;
&#13;
to other more interesting activities.&#13;
&#13;
Q:    So you were Deputy controller for about a year and then&#13;
&#13;
--?&#13;
A:    The Deputy Treasurer at the time the Department was&#13;
&#13;
divided was a man named Francis Poore.    He and I had very&#13;
&#13;
friendly discussions and he said to me, "You know, I am ready&#13;
&#13;
to be either Deputy Controller under you, Georg, or you can&#13;
&#13;
be Deputy Controller under me.    If you become Deputy&#13;
&#13;
Controller under me, you can rest assured that if things work&#13;
&#13;
out you will be Controller in less than two years."      I&#13;
&#13;
thought it was a very generous suggestion on his part to do&#13;
&#13;
it either way.    I was much younger than he.   Since I was&#13;
&#13;
still quite new in the Institution, I felt the more&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                   Gabriel, Page 8&#13;
&#13;
appropriate and more prudent course was to be Deputy&#13;
&#13;
Controller under him.     This was the deal that he and I&#13;
&#13;
concocted which he then sold to the authorities and the&#13;
&#13;
decision-makers.&#13;
&#13;
Q:      But then he left --?&#13;
&#13;
A:      He left somewhat sooner than would have been necessary&#13;
&#13;
for him.     He had a health problem, and I became Controller in&#13;
&#13;
January of 1971.     I had been a deputy for about 18 months.&#13;
&#13;
Q:      In taking the job after having been a deputy, what did&#13;
&#13;
you hope to accomplish?&#13;
&#13;
A:      The controller's Department was a large department.       It&#13;
&#13;
was full of people who had joined the World Bank in the late&#13;
&#13;
1940s.     They were quite set in their ways and put great&#13;
&#13;
emphasis on avoiding mistakes.     I had studied management&#13;
&#13;
methods and systems and was interested in trying out some of&#13;
&#13;
the changes that had been made at other corporations.        In&#13;
&#13;
other words, I felt a need to help this group move into the&#13;
&#13;
modern age.&#13;
&#13;
        Obviously, I couldn't do this by myself.    I took the&#13;
&#13;
trouble of interviewing all 150 (or thereabouts) members of&#13;
&#13;
the Department and tried to form an impression of each one of&#13;
&#13;
them.     I also tried to determine where we had strengths and&#13;
&#13;
weaknesses and then began pushing for changes.       Changes,&#13;
&#13;
however, were not very easy to come by.     I had a difficult&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                  Gabriel, Page 9&#13;
&#13;
cast of characters.    They were older than I.    To them, or at&#13;
&#13;
least some of them, it was offensive to have a young&#13;
&#13;
whippersnapper,    (even though I was 40 plus) become their&#13;
&#13;
boss.    Perhaps the job required more tact and diplomacy than&#13;
&#13;
I was capable of deploying.    There were some difficult&#13;
&#13;
moments.&#13;
&#13;
Q:      Could you elaborate a bit on the new systems that you&#13;
&#13;
introduced?&#13;
&#13;
A:      I was not particularly knowledgeable in computer&#13;
&#13;
systems, but I was convinced that we needed to make more use&#13;
&#13;
of machines to make ourselves more productive.      We began&#13;
&#13;
spending significant amounts of money on data processing and&#13;
&#13;
streamlining operations.&#13;
&#13;
Q:      Did many of the people leave or did the Department grow&#13;
&#13;
in terms of personnel?&#13;
&#13;
A:      I tried to constrain the growth of the Department and in&#13;
&#13;
particular, the growth of the professional staff, because it&#13;
&#13;
seemed clear that we had over-qualified people doing fairly&#13;
&#13;
menial work.     We let the Department grow in numbers, but it&#13;
&#13;
was mostly in the so-called support ranks.       The professional&#13;
&#13;
staff did not increase very significantly while I was there.&#13;
&#13;
Q:      It was unusual for someone to stay in a position like&#13;
&#13;
Controller for the number of years that you stayed there.&#13;
&#13;
You said that when you took this you saw this as a step to&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                Gabriel, Page 10&#13;
&#13;
something else.&#13;
&#13;
A:   Yes.     It wasn't totally unusual in the Bank.   In fact, a&#13;
&#13;
good many people had been in Administration or in Personnel&#13;
&#13;
for a larger number of years than I was in the Controller's&#13;
&#13;
Department.     It was a time of very rapid growth and evolution&#13;
&#13;
in the Bank.    The staff doubled within a few years after&#13;
&#13;
McNamara arrived in April, 1968, and McNamara appeared to&#13;
&#13;
think of the Controller's Department mainly as an entity that&#13;
&#13;
kept him out of petty trouble.     He did not look to the&#13;
&#13;
Controller's Department or to the Controller to help him&#13;
&#13;
manage the institution.     That was done by Programming    ~nd&#13;
&#13;
Budgeting and some other units.     Early in his tenure,&#13;
&#13;
McNamara established an Audit Committee of the Board.        One of&#13;
&#13;
the Controller's important activities was to interact with&#13;
&#13;
that Committee.&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Was there a separation between the operational and the&#13;
&#13;
financial sides of the Bank?&#13;
&#13;
A:   Yes, but the financial side for many years consisted&#13;
&#13;
mainly of the Treasurer's Department.     It included all the&#13;
&#13;
operations which subsequently were entrusted to the&#13;
&#13;
Controller's Department.&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Yes, but was it common for people to shift from&#13;
&#13;
operations to the Controller's office.&#13;
&#13;
A:   There were very few exchanges.     I tried to encourage&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                Gabriel, Page 11&#13;
them.    A few people got into operations from Controller's as&#13;
loan officers simply because of their knowledge of certain&#13;
details in the preparation and processing of loans.     It was&#13;
very hard to persuade people from operations to come&#13;
Controllers.     In order to put some yeast into the cake on the&#13;
Controller's side, we had to hire a number of people from&#13;
outside.&#13;
Q:      Returning then to the question of the Pension Plan, from&#13;
about 1980 it was one of your major responsibilities and&#13;
after about mid-'85 it was your principal responsibility.&#13;
A:      The pension activity was part of the Controller's office&#13;
only to the extent of paying the pensions.     That was done&#13;
through the Payroll Division and in those days (the late 60s)&#13;
we only had about 100 pensioners.     After McNamara, there were&#13;
several important changes made in the Pension Plan. They were&#13;
recommended and engineered by the Personnel people. The&#13;
initial one was in 1969 when they introduced a cost of living&#13;
provision into the Plan.     Initially, that was limited to&#13;
three percent per year.     Each year's adjustment had to be&#13;
approved every year by the Board, and it was funded every&#13;
year out of the administrative budgets.    Two or three years&#13;
later, when inflation kicked up, the three percent limit was&#13;
removed, but it was still subject to annual approval.     A year&#13;
or two after that, a currency option was introduced which&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                Gabriel, Page 12&#13;
&#13;
became desirable and important when exchange rates ceased to&#13;
&#13;
be fixed and started floating.    When McNamara recommended&#13;
&#13;
these changes to the Board, there was criticism, because the&#13;
&#13;
new provisions imposed open-ended obligations on the Pension&#13;
&#13;
Plan and because it was very hard to project how that would&#13;
&#13;
grow in the future.     Not long after that, the organizational&#13;
&#13;
arrangements for the Pension Plan were changed.     The&#13;
&#13;
responsibility for financial staff support was transferred to&#13;
&#13;
the Controllerâ&#128;¢s Department and the committee structure was&#13;
&#13;
changed.     The old structure consisted of a Pension Committee&#13;
&#13;
made up entirely of Executive Directors with the President as&#13;
&#13;
Chairman, an Investment Committee which usually had the head&#13;
&#13;
financial man as Chairman, and an Administration and Benefits&#13;
&#13;
Committee.     The new structure consisted of two committees--&#13;
&#13;
one Finance Committee made up of EDs, staff association&#13;
&#13;
representatives, retirees, and outside exports, and a&#13;
&#13;
Benefits Administration Committee under the chairmanship of&#13;
&#13;
the Personnel Vice President.&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Were outside consultants deeply involved in the&#13;
&#13;
development of this model?&#13;
&#13;
A:   Well, these were internal organizational consultants.&#13;
&#13;
We had McKinsey as organizational consultants, I believe, in&#13;
&#13;
1972, but they had completed their work and this was not part&#13;
&#13;
of the McKinsey reorganization.    This was a way of ensuring&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                Gabriel, Page 13&#13;
&#13;
that future recommendations affecting the Pension Plan&#13;
&#13;
prepared by Personnel wouldÂ·be examined for their financial&#13;
&#13;
consequences by another organizational unit.     At about that&#13;
&#13;
time, I became the Vice Chairman of the Finance Committee.&#13;
&#13;
From then on, I was responsible for the Pension Plan under&#13;
&#13;
the Vice President, Finance (Peter Cargill).&#13;
&#13;
Q:   What kind of investments did the Pension Plan make at&#13;
&#13;
that time?&#13;
&#13;
A:   In those days, during the 1960s, it had the Investment&#13;
&#13;
Committee chaired by Marty Rosen who was the Executive Vice&#13;
&#13;
President of IFC.   It has had only one outside manager,&#13;
&#13;
someone named Woody Redmond who is still around, and you may&#13;
&#13;
wish to interview him also.     He is in his mid-70s and his&#13;
&#13;
family had been friends of Gene Black.      Gene, I think,&#13;
&#13;
engineered this arrangement and, in a somewhat incestuous&#13;
&#13;
relationship, the pension funds manager was also on the&#13;
&#13;
Investment Committee.   However, the arrangement worked and&#13;
&#13;
the results had been good on the whole.&#13;
&#13;
     In 1972, we decided to divide the portfolio in two&#13;
&#13;
parts.   We left half with Redmond and assigned half to T.&#13;
&#13;
Rowe Price, a Baltimore firm.     During the bear market of the&#13;
&#13;
early 1970s, our two managers proceeded to lose prodigious&#13;
&#13;
amounts of money--relatively speaking--and also lost heart.&#13;
&#13;
They were a little like deer transfixed in headlights.       They&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                Gabriel, Page 14&#13;
&#13;
were immobilized and paralyzed.     Meanwhile, there was a&#13;
&#13;
strong inflow of new money from contributions.     We argued, in&#13;
&#13;
late '74, that those cashflows should be invested rather than&#13;
&#13;
held against further market declines.     I recall writing a&#13;
&#13;
memorandum to the Committee and also to the managers urging&#13;
&#13;
that we become more aggressive.     There was a low point in the&#13;
&#13;
market in October 1974 and this is when we stepped in.       The&#13;
&#13;
market rallied shortly thereafter, but reached another low in&#13;
&#13;
December.     It was sort of nerve wracking wondering whether we&#13;
&#13;
were doing the right thing, but, for better or worse, we&#13;
&#13;
charged ahead and it turned out to be a good move.&#13;
&#13;
     We then proceeded to build up a small staff because the&#13;
&#13;
pension assets were growing so rapidly.     We made certain&#13;
&#13;
projections that showed the assets might amount to as much as&#13;
&#13;
$2 billion or $3 billion 20 years in the future.     Actually,&#13;
&#13;
20 years later, they amounted to $5.2 billion which is about&#13;
&#13;
the current size.    We assembled a team under someone named&#13;
&#13;
Bernie Holland.     He hired an economist named Hilda Ochoa.&#13;
&#13;
Hilda was from Venezuela and had also been to Graduate School&#13;
&#13;
at Harvard.     She had unsuccessfully applied to Programming&#13;
&#13;
and Budgeting to work as a financial consultant.     Instead she&#13;
&#13;
ended up working as an investment officer on the pension&#13;
&#13;
assets with Bernie Holland.     She turned out to be very good,&#13;
&#13;
and Bernie's small group proceeded to generate&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                Gabriel, Page 15&#13;
extraordinarily high returns.     This didn't happen overnight,&#13;
but by the early 80s, the Bank's pension portfolio was&#13;
regularly in the top decile and quite often in the top&#13;
percentile of institutional portfolios of similar size.&#13;
     I spent approximately 10 or 15 percent of my time on the&#13;
pension fund, but it was, by far, the most enjoyable part of&#13;
my diverse duties in the World Bank.     The activity was&#13;
completely self-contained.     We had to report to the Finance&#13;
Committee of which I was the Vice Chairman (but under Cargill&#13;
de facto Chairman), and eventually the actual Chairman.        We&#13;
reported to the Board once a year and, since the results were&#13;
good, we were left alone, which was a marvelous position to&#13;
be in at the World Bank.&#13;
Q:   Just as a point of information.     Were you in direct&#13;
control of the fund at this point?     T. Rowe Price was out of&#13;
the picture at this point?&#13;
A:   We dismissed T. Rowe Price shortly after '74 and&#13;
appointed several other managers.     Furthermore, once Gene&#13;
Black had become a less active member of the Investment&#13;
Committee, we felt comfortable removing Woody Redmond also.&#13;
We appointed other managers.     We never managed any of the&#13;
assets directly, but always used outside managers. We felt&#13;
that, by selecting outside managers, we had our choice of a&#13;
wide array of outstanding people.     They served us as sources&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                Gabriel, Page 16&#13;
&#13;
of information and insights, and it was much easier to hire&#13;
&#13;
and dismiss an outside manager than it would have been to do&#13;
&#13;
the same in-house with permanent staff.     It simply was a&#13;
&#13;
better use of everybody's time.&#13;
&#13;
Q:   So the actual investment decisions were made by these&#13;
&#13;
managers?&#13;
&#13;
A:   Yes, but we made the more important asset allocation&#13;
&#13;
decisions while they picked the individual securities to&#13;
&#13;
implement these decisions.     The money management business&#13;
&#13;
evolved very rapidly during the 70s.     There were academic&#13;
&#13;
findings and theories which were put forward that didn't&#13;
&#13;
exist in the 1960s.     Another enjoyable part of the job for me&#13;
&#13;
was that I was forced to stay in touch with these new&#13;
&#13;
developments through my younger associates.     This helped us&#13;
&#13;
remain on the leading edge in this field.&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Lots of it had to do with inflation I presume.&#13;
&#13;
A:   Well, under modern portfolio theory, the asset&#13;
&#13;
allocation decision and broad diversifications were far more&#13;
&#13;
important than the decision to buy a particular security&#13;
&#13;
which would ultimately move more or less in step with the&#13;
&#13;
market.     We protected ourselves against market fluctuations&#13;
&#13;
by diversifying across a whole range of asset classes and&#13;
&#13;
then increasing or decreasing the exposure to particular ones&#13;
&#13;
depending on our assessment of the relative values.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                   Gabriel, Page 17&#13;
&#13;
Q:      If 15 percent of your time was on the pension, what else&#13;
&#13;
were you doing during this period?&#13;
&#13;
A:      Initially, I was in the Controller's Department and&#13;
&#13;
spent endless hours sitting in Board meetings.        I also was on&#13;
&#13;
the Investment Committee of the IFC because I was also&#13;
&#13;
controller of the IFC until '73 or    1   74 when the group that&#13;
&#13;
looked after the IFC's assets became part of the IFC staff.&#13;
&#13;
        There was the President's Council.     There were staff&#13;
&#13;
meetings.     There were fights about classifications, about&#13;
&#13;
budgets with the budgeting people.        Whatever the normal&#13;
&#13;
department head in the Bank spent his time on, or misspent&#13;
&#13;
his time on in some cases.&#13;
&#13;
Q:      Why did the pension fund become independent within the&#13;
&#13;
Bank?&#13;
&#13;
A:      I had a dual title for a number of years.     I became VP,&#13;
&#13;
Finance in the IFC in 1982, but retained the title of VP,&#13;
&#13;
Pension Plan in the Bank.     Before that, I was also VP,&#13;
&#13;
Programming and Budgeting.     so there were two titles.&#13;
&#13;
Furthermore, it was recognized that overseeing the Pension&#13;
&#13;
Plan wasn't really a full-time occupation and if it had been&#13;
&#13;
made a full-time occupation as it subsequently was made, it&#13;
&#13;
created the risk that the incumbent would interfere in the&#13;
&#13;
day-to-day management much more than was good for the Plan.&#13;
&#13;
        In late 1985, the then Executive vice President of IFC&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                Gabriel, Page 18&#13;
&#13;
was not reappointed.     This was a German named Hans Wuttle,&#13;
&#13;
and his replacement was a former British Executive Director,&#13;
&#13;
Bill Ryrie, since elevated to Sir William Ryrie.     Sir William&#13;
&#13;
came in and embarked on a reorganization of IFC which&#13;
&#13;
included a new layer or cast of vice presidents.     I had been&#13;
&#13;
sent by Tom Clausen to IFC to support and buttress Hans&#13;
&#13;
Wuttle and concluded about a year or two into that effort&#13;
&#13;
that for various reasons it was an uphill struggle. I&#13;
&#13;
probably made that known more openly than was appropriate or&#13;
&#13;
diplomatic.     I imagine that I never discussed it in these&#13;
&#13;
terms with Bill Ryrie whom I regarded as a friend.     He may&#13;
&#13;
have been told that I harbored aspirations to move into his&#13;
&#13;
position and that to facilitate his effort to assume the&#13;
&#13;
leadership of IFC it was best if I left IFC.&#13;
&#13;
        In the spring of '86, having left IFC and come back to&#13;
&#13;
the Bank, I was somewhat in limbo. That is, I had the pension&#13;
&#13;
activity, but I really was waiting for a broader assignment.&#13;
&#13;
Then Tom Clausen decided to leave and Barber Conable was&#13;
&#13;
appointed.     I had conversations with Clausen who.said more or&#13;
&#13;
less:     "You have done a marvelous job in the pension area,&#13;
&#13;
but we have very little else for you to do.     Wouldn't you&#13;
&#13;
like to look outside?"     I had thought of doing other things&#13;
&#13;
outside throughout, but since a new president was coming in,&#13;
&#13;
I assumed that he would want to recast things and that there&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                Gabriel, Page 19&#13;
&#13;
might be other opportunities inside the Bank.     When Conable&#13;
&#13;
came in, there wasn't anything immediately available, and I&#13;
&#13;
was then asked whether I would be willing to take over the&#13;
&#13;
Internal Audit Department in an oversight capacity.     Since I&#13;
&#13;
had done that 15 years earlier, I didn't regard that as&#13;
&#13;
progress.     I declined the offer and in October 1986, a few&#13;
&#13;
months after Conable had arrived, I was asked whether I would&#13;
&#13;
be willing to spend all my time on the Pension Plan which by&#13;
&#13;
then had about $2 billion in assets.     I responded that while&#13;
&#13;
this wasn't my first choice, I would be happy to stay on on&#13;
&#13;
this basis for the time being.     I received a letter signed by&#13;
&#13;
Martin Paijmans who was then the Personnel VP and copied to&#13;
&#13;
Conable that said:     "thank you very much for your willingness&#13;
&#13;
to undertake this important assignment."     It said that this&#13;
&#13;
assignment removed all doubts regarding my future career in&#13;
&#13;
the Bank.     I was assured that the organizational arrangements&#13;
&#13;
for the pension activity would not be part of reorganization-&#13;
&#13;
-which was then getting underway.      In the end, however, it&#13;
&#13;
did become part of it.&#13;
&#13;
Q:      So you became head of the pension fund sometime late in&#13;
&#13;
1986.&#13;
&#13;
A:      The full-time head, after having been the part-time head&#13;
&#13;
for many years.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                  Gabriel, Page 20&#13;
&#13;
Q:    And you ran the pension fund in much the same way as it&#13;
&#13;
had been run previously?&#13;
&#13;
A:     I obviously had far more time than I had before.     At&#13;
&#13;
this time, the Pension Plan Administrator, Bernie Holland,&#13;
&#13;
had been taken out of that activity and promoted to Director&#13;
&#13;
of the Investment Department in the Treasurer's Department.&#13;
&#13;
Functionally, this promotion involved a much larger amount of&#13;
&#13;
money, $20 billion or so, which was run in-house in a very&#13;
&#13;
aggressive manner.      However, it was under the close&#13;
&#13;
supervision of the Treasurer and Deputy Treasurer, and in&#13;
that sense, it was not as self-contained as what he had been&#13;
&#13;
doing in running the Pension Plan.        Bernie's place was taken&#13;
&#13;
by Hilda Ochoa, who became the Pension Plan Administrator.&#13;
&#13;
Q:     The Controller's function essentially reintegrated into&#13;
&#13;
the finance then?&#13;
&#13;
A:     It had never been taken out, but it was reorganized as&#13;
&#13;
part of this reshuffle.      Programming and Budgeting had always&#13;
&#13;
been regarded as McNamara's staff department and it&#13;
&#13;
functioned in that capacity.      It was very similar to OMB in&#13;
&#13;
the   u.s.   Government in that regard.   After the 1987&#13;
&#13;
reorganization, the budget function was reduced to a more&#13;
&#13;
mechanical thing and made part of the controller's&#13;
&#13;
Department.      Programming and Budgeting disappeared as a free-&#13;
&#13;
standing entity.      (It may since have been reestablished.)&#13;
&amp;#12;                                               Gabriel, Page 21&#13;
Q:   We would like to talk a little more about the&#13;
reorganization.    Obviously, you were able to experience at&#13;
first-hand.   What, in general, was your view of the&#13;
organization, speaking as someone who had worked very closely&#13;
with the Bank under the old organizational structure?&#13;
A:   Well, the studies leading up to the reorganization were&#13;
run by a small group inside the Bank and under an outside&#13;
management consulting firm.    Burke Knapp's son had once&#13;
worked with this group, a Pittsburgh-based management&#13;
consulting firm.    The impetus for the reorganization was the&#13;
new President who had come in.    He had been told that the&#13;
Bank was a bloated bureaucracyt that it was inefficient; that&#13;
we were spending too much money on administrative expensest&#13;
that we had more vice presidents than we   needed~   and that, in&#13;
general, the organization could be streamlined.      Barber&#13;
Conable had an outstanding reputation as a Congressman, but&#13;
apart from serving as a Colonel in the Marine corps in the&#13;
early 1950s, he had no recent organizational experience and&#13;
none in international organizations.    As a result, he relied&#13;
heavily on the consultants.    They came up with certain&#13;
structural changes:    the appointment of several senior vice&#13;
presidents, two senior vice presidents and several other vice&#13;
presidents.   The theory of it was that the newly appointed&#13;
people would implement the reorganization within their&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                Gabriel, Page 22&#13;
&#13;
bailiwick.     It was intended to be a cascading process.     There&#13;
&#13;
was no Bank wide system put in place, but Ernie Stern, who&#13;
&#13;
became the Senior Vice President of Finance, was supposed to&#13;
&#13;
make certain changes, that he had no part in designing.&#13;
&#13;
Similarly, the newly-appointed Senior VP-Operations was&#13;
&#13;
supposed to do the same in operations and other people below&#13;
&#13;
them were supposed to do similar things elsewhere and down&#13;
&#13;
the line.     I believe there was a fairly mechanical goal to&#13;
&#13;
reduce the number of vice presidents which was an aspect that&#13;
&#13;
was of interest to me as vice president.     Martin Paijmans who&#13;
&#13;
was the head of Personnel was not involved in designing the&#13;
&#13;
reorganization, but he became one of its victims, or&#13;
&#13;
beneficiaries, depending on your viewpoint.&#13;
&#13;
     I recall chairing a meeting of the Finance Committee on&#13;
&#13;
a Thursday, and I received a message that I was to go and see&#13;
&#13;
the President.      I thought he wanted to congratulate me on my&#13;
&#13;
birthday.      In any event, he was tied up that day and we&#13;
&#13;
didn't connect until early the following morning.      Barber was&#13;
&#13;
in his office.     He was very fidgety and quite embarrassed and&#13;
&#13;
said, "Georg, I am under enormous pressure to make certain&#13;
&#13;
changes and I have concluded that you better retire. I had&#13;
&#13;
asked Ernie Stern to tell you this, but he felt that I better&#13;
&#13;
tell you."&#13;
     11&#13;
          I couldn't agree more with Ernie," I replied, "I think&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                    Gabriel, Page 23&#13;
&#13;
it should be very much your task to inform the senior ranks&#13;
&#13;
of the changes."&#13;
&#13;
        I also said two things.      First of all, that I believed&#13;
&#13;
very strongly in the appropriateness of the President, any&#13;
&#13;
president picking his team.         To that extent, all the senior&#13;
&#13;
people, in my mind, were on probation, and if he felt that&#13;
&#13;
they should do something else or leave the organization, then&#13;
&#13;
this was his prerogative.         I had acted on that notion within&#13;
&#13;
my own areas of responsibility.         While I was at IFC, I had&#13;
&#13;
been helpful in terminating someone there and it turned into&#13;
&#13;
a very controversial termination.&#13;
&#13;
        Having taken the decision (that a person was to leave),&#13;
&#13;
the only question then was under what circumstances was that&#13;
&#13;
person to leave?         What would be appropriate terms?    I also&#13;
         11&#13;
said,         Barber, you can rest assured of two things.   One, this&#13;
&#13;
will create a great deal of controversy, because the Pension&#13;
&#13;
Plan is dear to everybody's heart and it is supposedly well&#13;
&#13;
run.     The initial understanding had been that the Pension&#13;
&#13;
group was not to be part of the reorganization or of any&#13;
&#13;
changes."&#13;
&#13;
        The pension fund had acquired an outstanding reputation&#13;
&#13;
not only in the Bank, but outside.         There had been some&#13;
&#13;
changes, mostly the transfer of Bernie Holland into the&#13;
&#13;
Treasurer's Department which had already caused a disruption&#13;
&amp;#12;                                               Gabriel, Page 24&#13;
&#13;
because the group wasn't very large.     In addition, one or two&#13;
&#13;
members of the group were on the verge of leaving the&#13;
&#13;
Institution because they had acquired such a reputation in&#13;
&#13;
the money management business that they were being pursued by&#13;
&#13;
outsiders.    So, I told Barber that this move would be&#13;
&#13;
controversial.    Secondly, I said that he could rely on me not&#13;
&#13;
to stir the fire.     I told him that I would not be part of the&#13;
&#13;
controversy, because I believed it was his right and duty to&#13;
&#13;
pick his team.     If he decided that I was to no longer be part&#13;
&#13;
of it, then there was little I could do about it.     I did not&#13;
&#13;
want to stay longer than I was welcome here.     And I had&#13;
&#13;
debated with myself, and perhaps with others, during the&#13;
&#13;
preceding years, whether it might not be worthwhile to shift&#13;
&#13;
career and do something else.&#13;
&#13;
     In the end, the moveÂ·became quite controversial.&#13;
&#13;
Several members of the Finance Committee resigned, because&#13;
&#13;
they felt that they should have been consulted.     The Staff&#13;
&#13;
Association kicked up a ruckus.    The German government became&#13;
&#13;
involved.    The German Executive Director, who at that&#13;
&#13;
particular juncture was in Germany, called me and asked me if&#13;
&#13;
I would like the German authorities to intervene on my&#13;
&#13;
behalf.     I told him that I appreciated his offer, but since&#13;
&#13;
he did not have to intervene when I was appointed, I did not&#13;
&#13;
think that he needed to intervene when I was terminated.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                               Gabriel, Page 25&#13;
&#13;
     After I departed, Martin Paijmans, who was asked to&#13;
&#13;
leave his position as head of personnel, was appointed&#13;
&#13;
Chairman of the Finance Committee.    He felt somewhat&#13;
&#13;
misplaced I think.    He concluded in short order that in order&#13;
&#13;
to keep the pension group functioning as a team, it would be&#13;
&#13;
desirable to move it outside the Bank (a change would serve&#13;
&#13;
the goal of reducing head count in the Bank) and privatize&#13;
&#13;
the pension fund's investment management activities.     He then&#13;
&#13;
asked me to act as the intermediary in representing the Bank&#13;
&#13;
in negotiating with the group.    I told him that I thought my&#13;
&#13;
serving in this capacity was very inappropriate.    I knew them&#13;
&#13;
very well.    They had asked me a year or two earlier whether I&#13;
&#13;
would be willing to be part of their group (if they ever set&#13;
&#13;
up shop outside the Bank) and I had said "so long as I am&#13;
&#13;
your manager I think that it's not proper that we explore&#13;
&#13;
this possibility.    What we do once all of us are outside the&#13;
&#13;
Institution is another matter entirely."&#13;
&#13;
     In any case, I disqualified myself from that task and it&#13;
&#13;
was then handled by a lawyer.    I believe it was scott White&#13;
&#13;
(or someone before him) who reviewed the terms of such&#13;
&#13;
arrangements used by other entities that had taken this step.&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Did Martin Paijmans become Chairman and Vice President&#13;
&#13;
of Pension?&#13;
&#13;
A:   Yes, but he must have concluded that he was not ideally&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                   Gabriel, Page 26&#13;
&#13;
placed, given his prior limited involvement in the investment&#13;
&#13;
field, to run this activity on a day to day basis.        He may&#13;
&#13;
have concluded that the departure terms established for staff&#13;
&#13;
leaving as part of the reorganization were not all that&#13;
&#13;
unattractive, or that his future in the Institution was not&#13;
&#13;
assured.   There was a lot of behind-the-scenes interplay&#13;
&#13;
which I find difficult to disentangle. Paijmans was taken out&#13;
&#13;
of his job in Personnel and Qureshi refused or was unable to&#13;
&#13;
make room in the operational part of the Bank for Martin&#13;
&#13;
which would have been the logical place for him to go, since&#13;
&#13;
he had spent many years in operations.        This left Ernie Stern&#13;
&#13;
with the task of placing Martin.        Ernie must have been forced&#13;
&#13;
to chose between Martin and myself, and he chose Martin.&#13;
&#13;
They had worked together very closely and they had closer&#13;
&#13;
personal relationships than Ernie and I had.        Ernie and I had&#13;
&#13;
played racquetball together and done other things.        We were&#13;
&#13;
neighbors and we had friendly relations, but more distant&#13;
&#13;
friendly relations.&#13;
&#13;
Q:    Paijmans more or less said thanks, but no thanks.&#13;
&#13;
A:   He said,   11&#13;
                     If I am to preside over a disintegrating&#13;
&#13;
pension staff and this group has established such a marvelous&#13;
&#13;
record, what can we do to keep them together?"&#13;
&#13;
Q:   And he was the one who first suggested setting up a&#13;
&#13;
separate organization?&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                   Gabriel, Page 27&#13;
&#13;
A:   How they came to that conclusion I simply don't know.&#13;
&#13;
As I said, it was controversial and it was a surprise for the&#13;
&#13;
pension group because, initially, only Hilda and one member&#13;
&#13;
of the group were going to leave and set up an independent&#13;
&#13;
money management firm.        They had explored the possibility&#13;
&#13;
with sources of financing and high net worth individuals, and&#13;
&#13;
when it became clear that they might end up with the World&#13;
&#13;
Bank as the first client, they simply took the key members of&#13;
&#13;
the group and left the Bank on October 31, 1987.&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Is there still is a Pension Department in the Bank?&#13;
&#13;
A:   Yes, there is a Pension Department in the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
Q:   What functions does it serve?&#13;
&#13;
A:   Well, initially the Department always had two functions.&#13;
&#13;
One was concerned with the paying of the pensions and telling&#13;
&#13;
people what their pension rights were or working on changes&#13;
&#13;
in the Pension Plan and the other the investment group.           The&#13;
&#13;
investment group was going out the door at that particular&#13;
&#13;
point.     There were support staff who stayed in the Bank and a&#13;
&#13;
new Pension Plan Administrator was appointed effective&#13;
&#13;
December    1&#13;
                87.   Nestor Santiago, who still is the Pension Plan&#13;
&#13;
Administrator, then proceeded to hire a number of people.&#13;
&#13;
How many he has now I do not know.        He does not have as large&#13;
&#13;
or as experienced a professional staff as the group that&#13;
&#13;
left, but this new team has meanwhile acquired skill, and&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                Gabriel, Page 28&#13;
&#13;
experience of its own.&#13;
&#13;
     There was a question whether this would be a temporary&#13;
&#13;
arrangement, or whether this was a permanent solution.     There&#13;
&#13;
was a willingness on the part of Ernie Stern, who then became&#13;
&#13;
the Chairman of the Finance Committee after Paijmans left, to&#13;
&#13;
let it prove itself.     The decision was made not to create&#13;
&#13;
controversy when there was a risk attached to immediately&#13;
&#13;
rebuilding the in-house pension staff.     It might not work as&#13;
&#13;
well as it had worked in the past.&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Let me go back to follow up on one point.     It has to do&#13;
&#13;
with the reorganization.     It seems to me that as a controller&#13;
&#13;
you had a unique perspective on the consultants' criticism&#13;
&#13;
that the Bank was terribly overstaffed and inefficient.        As&#13;
&#13;
someone who had been controller and understood how the Bank&#13;
&#13;
operated, what was your view of these charges.&#13;
&#13;
A:   I felt they had a great deal of justification.     As an&#13;
&#13;
individual, I am inherently impatient and loathe to see 10&#13;
&#13;
people or 15 or 5 sit in a room and spend hours and hours&#13;
&#13;
debating some small change or step of action rather than&#13;
&#13;
getting on with it.    The Bank as an institution was&#13;
&#13;
habitually overinclined to use outside advisors; to use&#13;
&#13;
different advisors to get far more advice than was necessary&#13;
&#13;
to reach a conclusion; and to study things to death.     We were&#13;
&#13;
skilled also in obtaining the advice that we ultimately&#13;
&amp;#12;                                              Gabriel, Page 29&#13;
&#13;
wanted to have and then defending actions vis-a-vis the&#13;
&#13;
Board.&#13;
     I had a strong bias in favor of downsizing.     I thought&#13;
&#13;
we could make do with fewer people and I had discussions with&#13;
&#13;
McNamara when I was the head of P&amp;B on these questions.        I&#13;
&#13;
pointed out to him how perverse the budgeting system had&#13;
&#13;
become.   At one point, we developed standard input data based&#13;
&#13;
on people completing time sheets.    If people worked 11 hours&#13;
and clearly they were doing the work of 1.3 or 1.4 positions,&#13;
&#13;
then that was used in the budgeting process as justification&#13;
&#13;
for asking for additional positions.    I felt that there were&#13;
&#13;
perverse incentives in the system, and I had a great deal of&#13;
&#13;
sympathy for anyone who said we were overstaffed.&#13;
&#13;
     There were inefficiencies created by the pressure to&#13;
&#13;
reach certain targets each year.    We wound up doing 40 or 50&#13;
&#13;
percent of the year's business in May and June of each year.&#13;
&#13;
Our borrowers began to learn how to play that game.     They&#13;
&#13;
stretched out loan negotiations until they had the poor Bank&#13;
&#13;
staff over the barrel and obtained concessions that they&#13;
&#13;
wouldn't have obtained earlier in the fiscal year.     Whether&#13;
&#13;
all this contributed to a deterioration in the execution of&#13;
&#13;
projects I am not in a position to say.    I gather that we&#13;
&#13;
have since found that deterioration had taken place.     But I'm&#13;
&#13;
sure that there are many different factors at work there.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                Gabriel, Page 30&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Did you feel that the 1987 reorganization addressed some&#13;
&#13;
of these issues?&#13;
A:   It was supposed to address them.     I thought it attempted&#13;
&#13;
to address them in incredibly inept ways.     It was a terribly&#13;
&#13;
costly thing.   I believe we gave departing staff members&#13;
&#13;
(including myself) more money than they needed, or perhaps&#13;
&#13;
deserved, but certainly more than was necessary to accomplish&#13;
&#13;
the purpose. It could have been implemented in a much less&#13;
&#13;
disruptive manner.     Saying these things, I do not intend to&#13;
&#13;
criticize Barber conable as President.     I think he was poorly&#13;
&#13;
advised.   Perhaps he responded to pressure from the   u.s.&#13;
Treasury and from his Congressional colleagues.     Perhaps he&#13;
&#13;
thought this was the appropriate way.&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Earlier you mentioned Conable in connection with having&#13;
&#13;
been only a Colonel in the Marine Corps.     I am just trying to&#13;
&#13;
tease out a little bit more of your view of what happened&#13;
&#13;
with the reorganization.    Was it that he wasnâ&#128;¢t experienced&#13;
&#13;
as an administrator, or that he relied too heavily on the&#13;
&#13;
people advising him?&#13;
&#13;
A:   My contacts with him were quite limited.     He was new.&#13;
&#13;
He had senior staff meetings less frequently than Tom Clausen&#13;
&#13;
used to hold them.     Every now and then, Clausen had retreats&#13;
&#13;
of the senior staff that really provided for a very intensive&#13;
&#13;
and intimate exposure of people to each other.     Conable&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                Gabriel, Page 31&#13;
&#13;
instigated the reorganization early on.     He had McNamara on&#13;
&#13;
his steering committee.     In the end, Barber was the President&#13;
&#13;
at the time, so he had to take responsibility for it.       I&#13;
&#13;
think the notion of having people like Stern and Qureshi&#13;
&#13;
trade positions and then telling them the next day to&#13;
&#13;
eliminate "x" vice presidents or "x" department heads, was&#13;
&#13;
quite unfair.   I think the whole structure and system of&#13;
&#13;
Bank-wide equity was violated.     Whether individuals stayed or&#13;
&#13;
left often came down to the luck of the draw.     It was a very&#13;
&#13;
strange process, and I think it damaged the relations between&#13;
&#13;
the institution and staff in a lasting way.     But I don't know&#13;
&#13;
whether that damage has been overcome.     I think it may have&#13;
&#13;
been reinforced by other things.&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Can you tell us a little bit about the performance of&#13;
&#13;
the pension system, so to speak, before and after the&#13;
&#13;
separation from the Bank.     First of all, you are still&#13;
&#13;
involved with this outfit now.&#13;
&#13;
A:   I am, but I am not a principal in the firm.     I am there&#13;
&#13;
half-time.   The other half of my time is devoted to other&#13;
&#13;
things.   I probably spend more than half my time there, but&#13;
&#13;
it is a very convenient arrangement for me.     I have gotten to&#13;
&#13;
know the group much better than I knew them in the World Bank&#13;
&#13;
because I am in Washington, working with them continuously.&#13;
&#13;
They have been successful as a business venture, and they&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                      Gabriel, Page 32&#13;
&#13;
have continued to do well for the Pension Plan.&#13;
&#13;
         Now, when I said that, in the late 70s, the performance&#13;
&#13;
of the plan had always placed it in the top ten percent and,&#13;
&#13;
on a multi-year basis, fairly consistently in the top one&#13;
&#13;
percent, that was a yardstick that existed where you could&#13;
&#13;
obtain data readily.        Since 1987, the World Bank, in&#13;
&#13;
consultation with outside advisors, established a target&#13;
&#13;
portfolio and a target distribution of the assets.            That is,&#13;
11   x 11 percent should be in   u.s.   fixed income; "yn percent&#13;
&#13;
should be in non-dollar fixed income; some other percentage&#13;
&#13;
in     u.s.   equities; and some other percentage in private&#13;
&#13;
equities and partnerships.          This target portfolio or policy&#13;
&#13;
portfolio, reflected a trend in the outside world.            Other&#13;
&#13;
large entities or pools of capital have done that also.               In&#13;
&#13;
some cases, they apply these targets quite rigidly and adjust&#13;
&#13;
the portfolio if prices in one segment rise ahead of prices&#13;
&#13;
in another.        In the World Bank's case, the allowed ranges&#13;
&#13;
revolve around these targets, and the task of Strategic&#13;
&#13;
Investment Partners, this new outside group, is really to&#13;
&#13;
exploit these ranges in an effort to out-perform the returns&#13;
&#13;
obtained on the policy portfolio.&#13;
&#13;
         The performance of the policy portfolio can be&#13;
&#13;
calculated.        It's "x" percent, depending on what the markets&#13;
&#13;
yield in these various asset classes.           The performance of the&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                Gabriel, Page 33&#13;
group, therefore, can no longer be compared to other&#13;
portfolios of similar size unless they have the same target&#13;
portfolio and I can't think of any that have exactly the same&#13;
target portfolio.    The group has outperformed the target&#13;
portfolio quite consistently since the fall of 1987 at the&#13;
rate of between two and four percent per year.     Sometimes a&#13;
little more, sometimes a little less.     So, given this&#13;
purpose, the arrangement works very well and is quite&#13;
successful.&#13;
     In the summer of 1992, the World Bank made a decision to&#13;
repatriate $500 million of the assets which, by then, had&#13;
grown to a little under $4 billion.     It assured the group&#13;
that this was not the first step in a series of&#13;
repatriations, but that because other portfolios had been&#13;
created to fund the health benefits of the retired staff&#13;
population, they had a management responsibility which they&#13;
did not want to farm out.    They wanted to respond to the&#13;
continuing pressure from the Staff Association and from one&#13;
or two Board members to reestablish an in-house capacity to&#13;
do what the outside group had been retained to do and was&#13;
doing so effectively.     Now the in-house group has more than a&#13;
billion dollars under management, of which a portion are&#13;
pension assets.     They sometimes piggyback on steps that the&#13;
outside group is taking.     For example, when we invest in a&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                Gabriel, Page 34&#13;
&#13;
partnership and make a recommendation to the Finance&#13;
&#13;
Committee for the outside portfolio which now amounts to&#13;
&#13;
about $4.7 billion, the in-house portfolio may take another&#13;
&#13;
piece of this investment and thereby create something without&#13;
&#13;
incurring additional expenses.&#13;
&#13;
        In the sense of the group outperforming the target&#13;
&#13;
portfolio, the arrangement has continued to work very well.&#13;
&#13;
Although I did not feel that this was the ideal solution at&#13;
&#13;
the time it was put in, I now believe that the Bank is much&#13;
&#13;
better off to have a group that really derives its whole&#13;
&#13;
livelihood (in a very much less secure way than a Bank staff&#13;
&#13;
member would derive his or her livelihood) from this&#13;
&#13;
activity.    Strategic Investment Partners has a very powerful&#13;
&#13;
incentive to do the best they can to perform these functions&#13;
&#13;
well.    Moreover, the group performs them at a fairly low cost&#13;
&#13;
in terms of the size of the assets.&#13;
&#13;
Q:      It has other clients as well?&#13;
&#13;
A:      It has other clients and it derives a benefit from&#13;
&#13;
having other clients.     First of all, the firm has a much&#13;
&#13;
larger staff than it could have if we had only the world Bank&#13;
&#13;
as a client, and the members of the group are serving on&#13;
&#13;
various boards.     For example, Hilda is on the Board of a&#13;
&#13;
large university endowment.     She is a trustee of a women's&#13;
&#13;
college.    She is on the Investment Committee of the&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                     Gabriel, Page 35&#13;
&#13;
Rockefeller family.        I am on some boards.    We have many more&#13;
&#13;
sources of input and insight than we used to have in the&#13;
&#13;
Bank.&#13;
Q:      What is the proportion of the Bank's assets in that&#13;
&#13;
group?        Is it the bulk of the business?&#13;
&#13;
A:      No.     In revenue terms, it is a minor percentage.      The&#13;
&#13;
group would be successful without the Bank as a client. On&#13;
&#13;
the other hand, there is no question that it wouldn't have&#13;
&#13;
become as successful as quickly, and it would obviously be&#13;
&#13;
regarded as a very serious setback if it lost the Bank as a&#13;
&#13;
client, but it would continue.&#13;
&#13;
Q:      our last set of questions have to do with some&#13;
&#13;
assessments of some of the people.        Mainly we have asked many&#13;
&#13;
of the people we have interviewed about some of the&#13;
&#13;
presidents because that is one of the foci that we have.&#13;
&#13;
You, obviously, worked most closely with McNamara and&#13;
&#13;
Clausen.        I wonder, again because of your interest in&#13;
&#13;
management, which is not something we have always found in&#13;
&#13;
people, how you would assess someone like McNamara and also&#13;
&#13;
Clausen?&#13;
&#13;
A:      It is a very difficult question.        In the case of&#13;
&#13;
McNamara, Programming and Budgeting was his staff department.&#13;
&#13;
The members of the department, and in particular the&#13;
&#13;
director, worked with him closely, but we were also&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                Gabriel, Page 36&#13;
&#13;
neighbors.   We used to walk together to the office on many&#13;
&#13;
days and climb up 12 flights to his office and continue the&#13;
&#13;
conversation.     We have played tennis on weekends since then.&#13;
&#13;
He is a very spry 77 year old and in very good physical&#13;
&#13;
condition.&#13;
&#13;
     Having said that, I speak as someone who can see both&#13;
&#13;
sides of a person or a question.     That can be a strength.    It&#13;
&#13;
can also be a weakness in that it inhibits action.      McNamara,&#13;
&#13;
I think, is a more one-dimensional person in a managerial&#13;
&#13;
sense.   He is a very complex person in a personal sense, but&#13;
&#13;
he was able to articulate certain goals for himself and for&#13;
&#13;
the Institution.     And he also did what was necessary to&#13;
&#13;
achieve them.     On occasion, some of his goals were very&#13;
&#13;
ambitious.   They involved expanding the staff rapidly.&#13;
&#13;
However, when an institution grows faster than at a certain&#13;
&#13;
pace, it creates difficulties.     It creates waste, or it&#13;
&#13;
increases risk of waste.&#13;
&#13;
     I remember one day in the mid-70s when more increases in&#13;
&#13;
staff, budgets and operations were being planned and I said,&#13;
&#13;
"Bob, I feel you have achieved great things.     we   have&#13;
&#13;
expanded very rapidly and we should really have a period of&#13;
&#13;
consolidation."     McNamara put his arm around my shoulder&#13;
&#13;
said, "Georg, I couldn't agree more with you, but I want to&#13;
&#13;
advance while we consolidate."     Not until after I had left&#13;
&amp;#12;                                               Gabriel, Page 37&#13;
&#13;
his office did it occur to me to remind him of certain other&#13;
&#13;
people who had done this in history and had come to grief.&#13;
&#13;
     But the Institution did not come to grief.     We may have&#13;
&#13;
contributed to the debt difficulties of the early 80s in&#13;
&#13;
expanding so rapidly, but these difficulties    might have&#13;
&#13;
occurred in other ways and they were more a reflection of the&#13;
&#13;
excessive recycling of the petro dollars by commercial banks.&#13;
&#13;
I think McNamara gave the Institution a reputation and a&#13;
&#13;
dynamic that was inspiring to most people. It was upsetting&#13;
&#13;
to some people who had been there in the 50s and 60s because&#13;
&#13;
it became a very different institution.&#13;
&#13;
     Tom Clausen spent much of his working life in California&#13;
&#13;
and he had a California style of management which was more&#13;
&#13;
touchy-feely.&#13;
&#13;
Q:   No one has ever accused McNamara of touchy-feely.&#13;
&#13;
A:   No.    Tom was much more comfortable sitting down with a&#13;
&#13;
large group.    McNamara and Clausen both entertained at their&#13;
&#13;
houses.    When Margie McNamara was alive, there was an annual&#13;
&#13;
party at the McNamara's house which was a highlight for many&#13;
&#13;
of us who were there.     Mrs. McNamara was a highly regarded&#13;
&#13;
and much loved person, and as a couple they appeared very&#13;
&#13;
attached to each other.&#13;
&#13;
     Tom also entertained at his house, but under Tom we had&#13;
&#13;
these retreats at the Wyeth Plantation and at other places&#13;
&amp;#12;.â&#128;¢   f   II   Â·-to&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                   Gabriel, Page 38&#13;
&#13;
                     where we sat around for a couple of days and also spent some&#13;
&#13;
                     evenings having drinks together really letting our hair down&#13;
&#13;
                     and getting to know each other quite well.&#13;
&#13;
                     Q:   Both Clausen and McNamara had corporate America&#13;
&#13;
                     backgrounds.&#13;
&#13;
                     A:   Yes, but McNamara was much more a numbers man than Tom&#13;
&#13;
                     Clausen was.   Tom Clausen was more of a banker.   He could&#13;
&#13;
                     apply certain capital adequacy standards, or risk standards&#13;
&#13;
                     that he had established at the Bank of America. Ironically,&#13;
&#13;
                     Clausen departed the Bank of America after a very successful&#13;
&#13;
                     period as president, but left as his legacy the Bank of&#13;
&#13;
                     America with an asset and staff structure which had it poorly&#13;
&#13;
                     positioned to cope with the changing environment of the early&#13;
&#13;
                     1980s.   When he left the World Bank, he was fortunate to go&#13;
&#13;
                     back and, to some extent, reap the benefits of the remedial&#13;
&#13;
                     actions that had been taken by his successor. McNamara became&#13;
&#13;
                     a corporate director for a number of years until he turned 70&#13;
&#13;
                     or 72.&#13;
&#13;
                     Q:   Well, thank you very much.   This has been very useful.&#13;
&#13;
                     A:   Thank you.&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="17972871">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1993/12/17972871/transcript-oral-history-interview-k-georg-gabriel-held-december-16-1993
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1993/12/17972871/transcript-oral-history-interview-k-georg-gabriel-held-december-16-1993</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1993/12/17972871/transcript-oral-history-interview-k-georg-gabriel-held-december-16-1993</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2011-12-29T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2011-12-29T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2013/07/08/000442464_20130708111654/Rendered/INDEX/790080TRN0Gabr0ew0December016001993.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2013/07/08/000442464_20130708111654/Rendered/PDF/790080TRN0Gabr0ew0December016001993.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>1993-12-16T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2013-07-08T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Transcript of oral history interview with
            K. Georg Gabriel held on December 16, 1993
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            In December 1993, K. Georg Gabriel was
            interviewed on behalf of the World Bank Group Archives oral
            history program by W. Becker and D. Milobsky. During his
            tenure at the Bank from 1967 to 1987, Mr. Gabriel worked in
            the following areas: as loan officer for the South America
            department (1967- 1969); as deputy controller (1969-1970)
            and then as controller (1970-1977) in the controller
            department; as director (1977-1980) and then as vice
            president (1980-1982) of programming and budgeting; as vice
            president of the finance committee (1983-1985); and as vice
            president of the pension fund (1980-1987). His transcript
            concerns his tenure at the World Bank. Specifically, he
            discusses how he assembled a team under Mr. Bernie Holland
            to cope up with the growing pension assets and creating
            pension plans for employees.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Transcript of oral history interview with K.
            Georg Gabriel held on December 16, 1993
        </docna>
        <display_title>Transcript of oral history
            interview with K. Georg Gabriel held on December 16, 1993</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/1993/12/17972871/transcript-oral-history-interview-k-georg-gabriel-held-december-16-1993</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Transcript</docty>
        <subtopic>Access to Finance,Banks &amp; Banking Reform,Technology Industry,Emerging Markets,Debt Markets</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Private Sector Development,Industry,Finance and Financial Sector Development</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000442464_20130708111654</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>World Bank Group Archives oral history program</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Private Sector Development,Industry,Finance and Financial Sector Development</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Board Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            accounting, asset classes, Audit Committee,
            beneficiaries, borrower, borrowing, Budgeting, capital
            adequacy, cash management, commercial bank, commercial
            banks, computer systems, consolidation, cost of living,
            credits, currency, data processing, debt, developing
            country, disbursements, diversifications, economic
            conditions, educational background, equities, exchange
            rates, exposure, financial institution, fixed income,
            individual securities, inflation, Internal Audit, investing,
            investment decisions, investment management, loan, loan
            officer, loan officers, money management, net worth,
            Pension, pension assets, pension fund, pension funds,
            pension rights, pension system, pensions, pools of capital,
            portfolio, portfolio theory, portfolios, Programming, rapid
            growth, reorganization, reputation, retirement, returns,
            securities, Treasury, trustee
        </keywd>
        <owner>Knowledge &amp; Information Services (ITSKI)</owner>
        <repnb>79008</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Banks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Retail Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Internal Financial Control (PIFC)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Downsizing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Right-sizing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rightsizing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Size and Structure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pensions &amp; Retirement Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Checks on Executive Power</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen User Satisfaction Survey</ml:concept><ml:concept>Independent Commissions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ombudsmen</ml:concept><ml:concept>Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Parliament</ml:concept><ml:concept>Procurement Complaints Review Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supreme Audit Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Treasury</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Benefits</ml:concept><ml:concept>Internal Audit</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Downsizing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inflation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pensions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Accountability Mechanisms</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>