<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>ï»¿                                   lZ!f (;ccvi--&lt;-&#13;
                                                         79071&#13;
                                  f/r!~;::,.[)/~aÂ· ~:J&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
THE WORLD BANK/IFC ARCHIVES&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  ORAL HISTORY PROGRAM&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   Transcript of interview with&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        DR. JAMES LEE&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          April 4. 1985&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      By: Boe;omir Choke!&#13;
&amp;#12;The World Bank/XFC oral History Proqram&#13;
Memorialist: Dr. James Lee&#13;
Date of Interview: April 4, 1985&#13;
Place of Interview: The World Bank, Washington, D.C.&#13;
Interviewer: Bogomir Choke!&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CHOKEL: Today is April4, 1985. My name is Bogomir Choke!, and I have here Dr. James A. Lee,&#13;
the Bank's Environmental Advisor, and his secretary, Miss Olive Nash. Dr. Lee, I understand that you&#13;
had quite a career as an administrator, teacher, research and even a game warden before you joined&#13;
the Bank. Can you tell us something about yourself prior to your appointment?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
LEE: After service in the Air Force during World War II, I went on to study environmental sciences,&#13;
natural resources management. And you're quite right: when I finished my graduate work, I took a&#13;
position with the state of New Hampshire, which is a northern state as you know, in New England,&#13;
bordering on Canada. I started off as a game warden. I worked on the Canadian border for a period&#13;
of time and would travel throughout the north country, the wilderness country up there, pack on my&#13;
back, or snow shoes, or a canoe or whatever I needed to do my work. Later on, after I finished as a&#13;
game warden, I became chief researcher for that department and then went on to follow a career in&#13;
the field of environmental sciences, conservation/natural resources, in the State of Minnesota. After&#13;
that I decided to go into what I've often referred to as the other side of the man/environment equation&#13;
and so I went into the field of public health, medicine, epidemiology.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
           I came to Washington at about the beginning of the John F. Kennedy Administration and&#13;
worked at the National Institutes of Health, where I did some original work in the area of human&#13;
adaptation to environmental stress, including what in those days we were just beginning to understand&#13;
as pollutants in water, pollutants in the air, toxic materials in general, the problems of urban congestion&#13;
and so on. We went on to establish the National Institute of Environmental Health Sciences, which is&#13;
now down in North Carolina. It was at that time, when I was involved in that work, that the Bank&#13;
expressed interest in my coming to work for it in the environmental area.&#13;
&amp;#12;LEE                                               -2-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CHOKEL: You came to the Bank in 1970. Can you tell us how the Bank's environmental work got&#13;
started? What brought it about and when? I know that in the early years the Bank wasn't too&#13;
concerned about the environment.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
LEE: I think it's safe to say that during the period 1945 to say, 1970, the Bank, not unlike many other&#13;
institutions, did not have a great concern for the environmental impact or environmental consequences&#13;
of the work that it was doing. To the best of my knowledge, and perhaps Miss Nash can comment on&#13;
this, along about late 1968 we began to see, here in North America particularly and in the United&#13;
States most specifically, the beginnings of what we called the "Environmental Movement." There were&#13;
a large number of organizations springing up that were concerned about the actions that were taken by&#13;
large industries, but also by others, which caused air and water pollution, industrial pollution, problems&#13;
of solid waste, and the impact of all this on peoples' health and well-being and social welfare. In 1968&#13;
too, the Ambassador from Sweden to the United Nations issued a call to the General Assembly that, in&#13;
light of these perceived mounting problems, the United Nations should convene a world conference to&#13;
address these problems and issues. The General Assembly responded favorably, and so there were&#13;
some steps taken towards the preparation of such a conference, which took place in 1972.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CHOKEL: Ifl'm correct, [Robert] McNamara quite quickly endorsed the plea for the conference.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
LEE: I don't know that to be sure, Mr. Choke!, but I would assume that he probably did because he&#13;
was a man who himself felt qnite strongly about what was happening to the environment. His family&#13;
and his children particularly were very much concerned, and I think they influenced on his own thinking&#13;
in these matters. The Bank's Board of Directors and the Bank's management ostensibly discussed&#13;
these matters in 1969 and the President, Mr. McNamara, either under his own volition or at the behest&#13;
of the Board, I'm not sure which, asked the United States National Academy of Sciences to put&#13;
together a blue-ribbon panel, to study the Bank's actions and records in that regard and to make&#13;
recommendations as to what steps the Bank might take to put it in a better position to handle these&#13;
dimensions. That Academy of Sciences panel did meet and did prepare recommendations and gave&#13;
them to the President. To the best of my knowledge they were also discussed by the Board and&#13;
received the Board's approval. The upshot of it was a decision in 1969 or 1970, to establish the solo&#13;
post of Environmental Advisor.&#13;
&amp;#12;LEE                                                -3-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
[LEE]&#13;
            The Academy was also asked to recommend a slate of candidates for that post, and&#13;
somewhere on that list of names was my own. I was interviewed and had long days of discussion with&#13;
people like Bernard Chadenet and Siem [Simon] Aldewereld, Dick [Richard H.] Demuth and Mike&#13;
[Michael L.] Hoffman--there was a whole bunch of people. I remember coming down here for three or&#13;
four days in a row and meeting with each one. As a result of all those discussions, the decision was&#13;
made. Mr. McNamara then asked if I would join the Bank in this position, and I did. I joined in&#13;
November of 1970, I think it was. Miss Nash joined me in about what ... ?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NASH: The beginning of 1971 I think, or the end of 1970.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
LEE: Yes, just about the beginning of 1971.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NASH: Bnt I would like to say I don't know too much about what actually were the workings of the&#13;
Bank leading up to the establishment of the post. But I do know that there were many quite famous&#13;
names on that list, one of whom was Barry Commoner. So you know it was a large list.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CHOKEL: That gave you a good start because you had good supporters.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
LEE: Yes. Mr. McNamara called me in the second day after my arrival. You know how his style is,&#13;
very clipped and very positive and almost computer quick in terms of what he wanted. He welcomed&#13;
me and he said that I would have his full support and the full support of the Board in carrying out what&#13;
he felt was going to be a very difficult assigmnent. "In point of fact," he said, "I have a problem for you&#13;
right now." And passed over a document what Miss Nash will remember because it had to do with a&#13;
transmission line that the Bank had approved and was about to build in Tanzania. It seemed that this&#13;
transmission line was routed right through the heart of the Mikumi National Game Park, in sight of&#13;
their newly built lodge. This was of course going to detract from the aesthetic qualities of the park.&#13;
And no less a personage than Prince Bernhard [of The Netherlands], I think, called it to the attention&#13;
of Mr. McNamara and said that this just couldn't be; that he was very upset and the wildlife&#13;
conservation groups were very upset by this. And so McNamara passed me the paper and merely said,&#13;
"I want you to turn this around." And that was my mandate. Then he reached over to the other side&#13;
&amp;#12;LEE&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
[LEE]&#13;
of his desk where he had a pile of letters, Mr. Choke!, that was probably about six or seven inches high.&#13;
These were all letters of criticism and condemnation that had been leveled against the Bank by the&#13;
health community saying that the Bank was not acting in a very responsible way in terms of the impact&#13;
of its projects on the public's health and well-being. They were quite critical of this. And so, with a&#13;
little smile on his face he said, "Oh, I also have these. I want you to read them and turn this around&#13;
too." And that was the end of our discussion.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            Before the day was out, I found myself in a very bloody adversarial relationship with Mike&#13;
[Michael L.] Lejeune--you remember Mike Lejeune? Well, Mike at that time was the responsible&#13;
officer for Tanzania. He had already made up his mind that this transmission line was going to go the&#13;
way that they had selected, planned and worked out, and he wasn't about to make those changes just&#13;
because of some damn animals some place. So we had quite a confrontation on that very first day and&#13;
he was bloodied and I was bloodied.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            The upshot of it was, though, I went to Tanzania shortly thereafter with one of the power&#13;
engineers, Gavin Wyatt, who has since left us. Gavin and I went to Tanzania together. We went out to&#13;
the Mikumi game park and traversed that area. I must say it was the only time in my life where the&#13;
tsetse fly got the better of me. It got so bad that finally in sheer desperation and almost pauic I just&#13;
turned around and hiked on back to the jeep. I got inside, closed the door and killed all the tsetse flies&#13;
that were inside the jeep. We were actually just a mass of bites, we were really bloodied, you know. So&#13;
that was my introduction to the bush country of Africa. But, to summarize, we did fmd a route that was&#13;
much better from the standpoint of its impact on the wildlife and on the game reserve, and when the&#13;
cost-benefit analysis was done, it turned in the end to be a cheaper route--much to everyone's surprise.&#13;
So that was the first two or three days in the Bank's introduction to that subject. Miss Nash maybe has&#13;
some comments?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NASH: Well, I would just like to say that Dr. Lee brought a filing cabinet full of material and that&#13;
became the basis of everything that was in the Bank from then on on environmental matters.&#13;
&amp;#12;LEE                                               -5-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
LEE: Yes, she's quite right, because when I went to the Joint Library to see what its holdings were in&#13;
the area of environment or natural resources or health for that matter, I found nothing. So you're&#13;
quite right when you said the Bank didn't have an interest in the area.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NASH: I can remember when you brought them to be put into a filing system. The last one was&#13;
"zoonosis." I had never heard of "zoonosis."&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
LEE: That's right. It began with "a" with "air pollution" and ended with "z" for "zoonosis". "Zoonosis"&#13;
by the way, are those classes of diseases that are transmittable to man from animals. So there are a&#13;
number ofthem! That was the beginning of our library, I guess, which is now of course expanded.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CHOKEL: In 1972, the Club of Rome published a study, The Limits to Growth. It was the same year&#13;
as the Stockholm Conference was held. What was the effect of the study? I understand it was sort of&#13;
a "doomsday" outlook. There were predictions of famine and over-population in the late 1980s. This is&#13;
exactly what has happened now in Africa. Do you know what impact it had on environmental thinking&#13;
and philosophy?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
LEE: The Club of Rome report, which was carried out under the general direction of Aurelio Pecci,&#13;
who at that time was the chief executive officer for PIAT Company and who founded the Club of&#13;
Rome, and who since passed away not more than a year or two ago. He was a good friend of Mr.&#13;
McNamara's, too. It was under his general direction that they carried out this study, which was the first&#13;
study where they tried to use the computer and to develop a world model.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CHOKEL: MIT [Massachusetts Institute of Technology) did it.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
LEE: Yes, MIT did it. It was Denuis Meadows and Carol Wilson and those types of people that were&#13;
involved in the technical work. You know, that was 1972, thirteen years ago. Actually the work was&#13;
begun in about 1970-1971 so modeling wasn't all that far advanced. They were trying to advance it by&#13;
quantum leaps by doing it on a world scale. So there were many questions asked about whether that&#13;
was a valid way to approach it; whether the model was indeed all that accurate.&#13;
&amp;#12;LEE                                                 -6-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
[LEE]&#13;
            I think the most important things about the report when it came out were the shocking&#13;
revelations that it contained. It was something of a "doomsday'' type of report. I think it served the&#13;
purpose though, at that point in time, of warning political leaders and world leaders that indeed&#13;
something was wrong and that we needed to pay attention to what was happening to the biosphere and&#13;
what was happening to the environment that supports all of us. I think it had a lot to do with giving&#13;
further impetus and further support to the United Nations Conference on the Human Environment,&#13;
which was coming up later that year.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            The Bank's response, incidentally, was very interesting. There was a great deal of&#13;
skepticism voiced within the Bank about the reports accuracy, and a very careful critique of it was made&#13;
under the direction of Mahbub ul Haq. The Bank went into the report in some depth and while it did&#13;
criticize the report in many respects, I think that on balance it agreed with the general thrust, namely&#13;
its predictions of such things as the impact of overpopulation--the possibility that the growing&#13;
populations in Africa would so denude their environment as to bring about the problems of drought&#13;
and famine. And so I think the Bank subscribed to the general thrust of the report, although it found&#13;
"technical faults" with the preparation of it.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CHOKEL: Well, let us go on now to the famous Stockhohn Conference. I know it had quite an&#13;
impact on environmental thinking and philosophy. Could you tell us what role the Bank played in the&#13;
events leading to the conference?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
LEE: It was interesting. Our first word of the conference came in a rather peculiar way. One day a&#13;
gentleman whom I did not know, but who later became very well known to us, walked in. He was a&#13;
close friend of Mr. McNamara's and has since gone on to great fame: Maurice Strong of Canada.&#13;
Maurice came in and visited with Mr. McNamara for a short while and then came down to see me. I&#13;
had only been there a few months. He informed me that he had been selected by the United Nations&#13;
to head the preparations for this big international conference on the human environment that was&#13;
going to be held in Stockholm in June of 1972. It has been called at the behest of the Swedish&#13;
Government and had the support of the United Nations General Assembly. Our fust conversation&#13;
went something like this: he said that the World Bank was the frrst of the development finance&#13;
institutions to take interest in the field and that the Bank had a very rich history in terms of the&#13;
economics of development--that's certainly true. He said that my own position was something of a&#13;
&amp;#12;LEE                                                 -7-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
[LEE]&#13;
pioneering effort, if you will, in development assistance and so therefore he and his staff would be&#13;
calling on the Bank to help them with the preparations for the conference, for defining the issues, for&#13;
defming the problems, for entering into the debate and the dialogue that would precede the&#13;
conference. I remember him saying, I think to Bernard Chadenet or Siem Aldewereld who were at the&#13;
meeting, "This fellow is going to be doing a lot of traveling, if I have my way, because we need the input&#13;
of the Bank,' to which there was agreement. And they were quite right, because I found myself, as&#13;
Miss Nash remembers, virtually commuting to Geneva. I'd be gone virtually every six weeks. I'd be in&#13;
Geneva on a host of committees in whih we were doing the preparatory work.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            Late in 1971, during the midst of these preparations, it appeared that the conference was&#13;
going to founder even before it got started. The problem centered around the fact that the developing&#13;
countries, who after all were our clientele in the World Bank, did not subscribe to the fears and the&#13;
warnings of the developed countries that things weren't right. They said that they perceived it more as&#13;
a subterfuge for diminishing the resources and the economic aid to their countries under the pretext&#13;
that economic development was at the heart of the problem.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CHOKEL: How wrong they were.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
LEE: How wrong they were. But at that time they felt very, very strongly about it and even threatened&#13;
that they would not attend the conference. They threatened to pull out of it and said that this would be&#13;
a conference ouly for the developed countries. This was a serious situation which Maurice Strong knew&#13;
that he had to resolve if he indeed was going to have a conference. So he called upon the Bank and&#13;
said, 'Well, after all, you are the closest to the developing countries. You have been providing them&#13;
with development assistant for about twenty-five years." He said that the Bank was, "well respected"&#13;
and said, 'The developing countries I think will listen to you if you can make a case for us, that is, a&#13;
case for the enviromnent and its importance to the developing countries." The Bank then assigned the&#13;
responsibility for that to two of us. One was Mahbub ul Haq, who was going to look at it from the&#13;
standpoint of the developing countries and economics. I mean, why did it make good sense to be&#13;
concerned about enviromnental matters in development for the Third World? I was going to look at it&#13;
purely from the point of view of identifying the environmental problems, the linkages, the relationship&#13;
to people, and so on. So we were sort of working in tandem.&#13;
&amp;#12;LEE                                                -8-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
[LEE]&#13;
            Early in 1971 was held what has been referred to oftentimes in environmental circles as the&#13;
famous Founex Meeting--F-0-U-N-E-X. It's the name of a village in Switzerland where we all&#13;
assembled. I won't forget it because I'll tell you what happened to me.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            Mahbub and I had each prepared a very lengthy paper. The representatives from the&#13;
developing countries came to Founex and we sat down for what was going to be sort of a head-to-head,&#13;
eye-to-eye, nose-to-nose discussion on these matters. It turned out that I arrived in Geneva on the&#13;
morning of the conference and found myself very, very ill with a very high temperature. I went off to&#13;
seek some help at the World Health Organization--where I couldn't get it. I went to the United&#13;
Nations--where I couldn't get it. And fmally, in desperation I must tell you--because as it turned out I&#13;
had pneumonia--in great desperation I gave my paper to Mahbub and entrusted to him its balanced&#13;
presentation because I couldn't be there myself. I asked TWA if they would put me on the next flight&#13;
back to the United States. I came came back and went into George Washington University Hospital&#13;
for a day or so because I had this pneumonia.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            But the Bank made a major contribution at that Founex Conference through the&#13;
persuasiveness and the arguments put forth by Mahbub ul Haq. Using his paper and mine, he&#13;
persuaded them that indeed there really was good cause, both then and in the future, for them to be&#13;
concerned about these matters. The upshot of it was that they promised that they would come to the&#13;
conference, they would support the conference, and that they would enter into it with good, full faith.&#13;
So we managed to get over that very, very sticky issue and we went on then to finalize preparation for&#13;
the conference.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            One of the next important things, I think, as far as the Bank was concerned, was that they&#13;
had prevailed upon Mr. McNamara to give the keynote address. When Mr. Strong first approached&#13;
him he said no, and then I approached him, and there was quite an argument that went back and forth.&#13;
You know, Mr. McNamara did not like to make very many speeches. He was always very selective&#13;
about those that he made. His argument was, "But I don't know the subject. I don't know the field. I&#13;
just don't feel that I can make a contribution." We argued that he was the President of the World Bank&#13;
and that he was a 9world figure and that people did listen to him and that we could make the case in&#13;
paper form if he would be willing to deliver it. So finally he did.&#13;
&amp;#12;LEE                                               -9-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
[LEE]&#13;
           I recall, Miss Nash remembers, that I prepared the ftrst draft of it and went on up to Mr.&#13;
McNamara who, in his own inimitable style began to tear it to pieces. He literally tore it to bits and&#13;
sent it back down and said, 'Jim, this is the way I want to proceed, in these directions.' Which we did.&#13;
I followed his lead and we prepared a second draft which then went over to his speech writer, John&#13;
Maddux. John, I felt, was one ofthe best speech writers we ever had in the Bank. John took this draft,&#13;
and knowing McNamara as well as he did, he sat down and he converted my language and&#13;
McNamara's ideas and thoughts into what turned out to be, from my point of view, one of the most&#13;
outstanding speeches that Mr. McNamara ever gave as President of the Bank. And certainly it was the&#13;
outstanding address given at the United Nations conference. It did more to convince the developing&#13;
countries right on the spot that they too had a stake in what was happening to the global environment&#13;
and that they did have some problems that needed to be recognized. In his famous line he said, "The&#13;
most serious form of pollution in the world is poverty." And that's been used over and over and over&#13;
again. And the truth of the matter is it was John Maddux who put that together. So the conference&#13;
was successful, Mr. Choke!, it was the beginning of all the environment activity that has happened from&#13;
then on over the past 13, 15 years now. Yes, thirteen years now.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CHOKEL: May I ask you, what were the most enduring results of the conference?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
LEE: Well, I suppose there are many. I think the most enduring result of the conference was the fact&#13;
that it brought to the world's attention the nature and the dimensions of the environmental problems&#13;
and the future trends that we were then only beginning to perceive. So it raised the consciousness, it&#13;
raised the awareness. It sensitized political leaders and others--and the general public for that&#13;
matter--to these issues. It set in motion a number of events that we now see the resnlts of.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
           One, of course, was the establishment of the United Nations Environment Programme,&#13;
which is a central United Nations agency responsible for the global environment. It resulted in many&#13;
countries establishing their own environmental ministries. I remember when we went to Stockholm I&#13;
think there were eleven countries, all developed, that had some form of an environmental organization.&#13;
At that time, here right down the street, for example, the United States was establishing its&#13;
Environmental Protection Agency--EPA--which you know so well today. I used to follow their&#13;
&amp;#12;LEE                                               -10-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
[LEE]&#13;
activities and mine at the same time because we were both doing them. They, on a very large scale, I&#13;
on a small scale obviously. But I think there were only eleven at that time in 1972. Since then that&#13;
figure has grown to something now on the order of about one hundred ten, one hundred eleven. So,&#13;
you know, that reflects a significant increase in countries' awareness, in countries taking responsibility&#13;
for their own environmental matters.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
             And then I do think that the Stockholm Conference had a great deal to do with the events&#13;
that have taken place within the whole development fmance comunity, the whole development&#13;
assistance community. With that motivation and with that impetus and that support we here in the&#13;
World Bank then began to move, I think, quite rapidly in developing a total environmental program&#13;
which had a great deal of spill-over effect. For example, the United States' bilateral aid program&#13;
USAID [United States Agency for International Development] as it's called, took their cue from us and&#13;
began to develop their own program in this dimension. The Norwegians and the Swedes and the&#13;
Canadians and the Australians also began to include environmental dimensions in their aid programs.&#13;
The other multilateral development finance institutions like the Asian Development Bank and the&#13;
African Development Bank and others--even the UNDP [United Nations Development&#13;
Programme]--then began to develop programs into which they could factor the environmental&#13;
dimension.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
             That all culminated, by the way, in 1980 when we took the leadership and drafted what has&#13;
been referred to as the "Declaration on the Environment". This is a forthright declaration to which all&#13;
the twelve major fmancing institutions have subscribed. It requires them to include the environment in&#13;
all their development assistance activities in a very meaningful way, be it project lending or programs&#13;
or technical assistance or training and so on and so forth. That has been followed now by the bilaterals&#13;
doing the same thing. So, I think you can always trace back the threads of how things came about and&#13;
you find that they usually started at the Stockholm Conference. That was sort of the initiation of all&#13;
these activities.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CHOKEL: Now, from its very beginning your environmental program became concerned with health,&#13;
too. I know we have cooperative agreements with WHO [World Health Organization] and so on.&#13;
What was the evolution of that? How did the Bank get into this movement? I'm also talking about&#13;
new-style projects like, oh, poverty, education and so on.&#13;
&amp;#12;LEE                                                -11-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
LEE: New-style projects in 1970 were pretty much limited to two areas, I think. One at that time was&#13;
education, the other was population and nutrition. I remember being in on the discussions when they&#13;
were establishing those as being rather innovative. They were certainly projects where the&#13;
cost-recovery was not in the sector for which they were going to be lending, and this caused the&#13;
economists many problems. But the evolution of health in the Bank, I think, stems more from my own&#13;
interest in it than anything else. You recall that I said earlier to you that on my second day in the Bank,&#13;
Mr. McNamara handed me all these letters from the health community which were very critical and&#13;
said, 'Turn this around." Which meant that we had to address what were the problems, what were the&#13;
criticisms, what did the health community see that could be done that wasn't being done. And then my&#13;
own definition of the environment, which was different from most in those days, included not ouly the&#13;
naturally occurring environment and the urban environment, but it also included public health. It&#13;
included occupational health and safety. I was concerned about the health and welfare of the workers&#13;
in those facilities and plants that we were making loans for. I was concerned about the impact of the&#13;
Bank's projects on the general health of the people who were going to be affected by the projects. So&#13;
that meant that I needed to approach health in a preventative fashion. I saw my role as trying to&#13;
identify those health problems that were going to be associated with any of our development activities.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            One of the very frrst ones that I saw quite obviously was a disease which has now become&#13;
quite famous because nobody can pronounce it. I recall the U.S. Secretary of State Henry Kissinger&#13;
made the word famous because he stumbled over it in trying to talk about that particular disease, in&#13;
terms of aid that was being furnished to Egypt. The word of course, is "schistosomiasis." Not a very&#13;
easy word. Later on both McNamara and our present President both stumbled over the word, too,&#13;
because it's difficult. But the frrst problem I saw was in the hydroelectric projects and irrigation&#13;
projects that we were lending for then. Whenever you manipulate surface waters on the land ifl&#13;
countries where those diseases are present, you're going to exacerbate or increase the incidence of the&#13;
diseases. So I called attention to that on one of the very first projects early in 1971. I think it was the&#13;
Mopti Rice project, wasn't it Miss Nash? The Mopti Rice project in Mali.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NASH: Mali, yes.&#13;
&amp;#12;LEE                                               -12-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
LEE: I remember in those days we sat around a big table--it was called the round table&#13;
discussion--and the project was discussed by people from the programs side and the projects side. It&#13;
was usually chaired by Siem Aldewereld or Bernard Chadenet. This particular project was Mopti Rice.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NASH: You sent a consultant there, didn't you? William Jobin?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
LEE: Yes, we did. That's right, to take a look at the problem. And he came back with his report on it.&#13;
I remember Chadenet turning to me and Jobin and he said, "Dr. Lee, are there any environmental&#13;
problems with this particular project?" I said, "Well, yes, there are." And I mentioned schistosomiasis".&#13;
And he said, "Schistosomiasis? What's that?" So I described it to him, and he listened very carefully. I&#13;
could tell that the other people around the table weren't about to be interested in this at all. Then&#13;
Bernard said, "Do you really think it's a serious problem that we ought to be concerned with?" I said,&#13;
"Yes, I do, or I wouldn't have spoken up." I give him credit. He looked at the rest of the group and he&#13;
said, "Well, if it's an important problem then we must do something about it. We'll include what Dr.&#13;
Lee wants in this." So that was our first health component. This particular disease is transmitted via&#13;
snails, and so we put in a component to control the snails and to treat the people. Anyhow, that was&#13;
our first endeavor along those lines.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            Since then we began to look at all projects for their health implications and that included&#13;
problems like onchocerciasis, you know the river blindness disease in French West Mrica. Problems of&#13;
malaria and a whole host of gastrointestinal disease problems that are associated with water and water&#13;
use, particularly. Trypanosomiasis, which is another disease which is quite fearsome in Mrica. Chagas&#13;
Disease ... all of these. We were careful to identify them and to build in the necessary measures into all&#13;
the projects. There is one very important contribution that the Bank made in that area. This disease I&#13;
just mentioned, schistosomiasis, is a disease that has its origin or endemic home in Egypt. And if one&#13;
looks back at mummies from Egypt as I have--because I'm a member of the Paleopathology&#13;
Association--going back something on the order of 5,000 years, we find the petrified eggs of this&#13;
particular disease still present in the mummified remains. So that we know that this disease was as&#13;
much a problem then, 5,000 years ago, and was distributed up all along the Nile.&#13;
&amp;#12;LEE                                                -13-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
[LEE]&#13;
            In the beginning of the 1970s, the Bank was called in by the Egyptian authorities for, quote,&#13;
'an environmental problem' that had arisen. With the building of the Aswan Dam, water remained on&#13;
the land all year as opposed to the previous system when you got a flood and then after the flood the&#13;
land would dry out again. Previously you'd get one crop of rise. Now, with the Aswan Dam and water&#13;
being on the land all year, you had three and four crops of rice. But at the same time, you extended the&#13;
habitat for the snail. And with more people being in the water for longer periods of time, you quite&#13;
obviously were going to have even more people coming down with the disease. More important, the&#13;
Egyptians themselves began to discover that two problems arose from having water on the land all the&#13;
time. One was the fact that the salts that were in the soil were being brought to the surface--we called&#13;
it 'salinization of the soil'--and the soils were being rendered largely unfit for the growing of crops.&#13;
Secondly, with the water on the land all the time the soil becomes water-logged, it becomes physically&#13;
water-logged, so that you can't get crop growth. So they said, "Look, we need to drain these waters.&#13;
We need to drain these waters off with the Bank's help.' And that meant that the Bank was going to&#13;
embark upon a very lengthy drainage program for Egypt's irrigation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            I remember going there in 1971 with Sir Kenehn Guiness, who was then the irrigation&#13;
advisor. He and I went to Egypt and we talked with the Egyptians about the possibility of also using&#13;
this drainage project as a way of beginning to control schistosomiasis. The Egyptians were of course&#13;
quite enthusiastic about this until they learned what it was going to cost just to control that disease,&#13;
given the extent of it in the Nile Valley. But much to their credit, the Egyptians agreed to it and we&#13;
began to embark upon a program within the drainage project to control that disease. And we&#13;
controlled it two ways: we controlled it by the introduction of chemicals that would kill the snails and&#13;
would not be harmful to people and/or to other fish or other biota. And also we began to treat the&#13;
people that were affected. We began in the ai-Fayyum Governale, I remember that very well, and from&#13;
then on we gradually extended the program. By 1979, 1980, that program had rendered the whole area,&#13;
from Aswan to Cairo, free--I won't say completely free, but certaiuly by any comparison, virtually free&#13;
of that disease. Then we began to move into other areas. These activities have now been going on for&#13;
nearly fifteen years. Just think, it's the longest control project for that disease that has ever taken place&#13;
anyplace in the world!&#13;
&amp;#12;LEE                                               -14-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
[LEE)&#13;
            The Egyptians felt, and I think quite rightly, that they wanted to have an evaluation of it. So&#13;
they called in six or seven or eight people who are experts in the disease from around the world and&#13;
asked them to do an evaluation of this project, for the fifteen years. They did it. It was a very, very&#13;
carefully statistically controlled study, using computers and so on. And I learned from one of my&#13;
colleagues in the Bank the other day that that report, which will be coming out here in just a few&#13;
months, says that the project or the schistosomiasis control component has been an outstanding&#13;
success. That where 90 percent of the people had this disease when we first started, it's down now to&#13;
something approaching, in some places, one or two or three percent and certainly no more than eight&#13;
or nine percent. So for all intents and purposes, we've made a very major contribution to the control of&#13;
that disease in Egypt.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            One fmal note on the health aspects of the Bank's work. In 1975, when we were reporting&#13;
to the Board of Directors on our health programs, they asked the question, "Well, besides providing for&#13;
the prevention of these diseases, is there any way that the Bank can contribute to improving the health&#13;
status of people in our developing countries?" Wbat they were talking about was the provision of&#13;
health care. We said we didn't know but that we would try. So we had a few people added to our staff.&#13;
Miss Nash, do you remember that? And we began to select a number of countries that were both&#13;
geographically and culturally different, to see whether or not we could introduce a "primary health&#13;
care" component to our projects to see if it was effective and if the Bank could make a contribution.&#13;
We carefully selected the countries and we carried out the experiment.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            In 1979, I reported back to the Board and said that we had done this. The results look very&#13;
good. The World Health Organization was quite excited about what we had accomplished. The Board&#13;
of Directors was quite excited about what we had accomplished. The Board of Directors was pleased&#13;
and said to the President and said to management, "Let us move more directly now into the whole field&#13;
of health care." And so at that time then, the management decided to set up a new department which&#13;
is now called the Population, Health and Nutrition Department. Since 1980, it has moved ahead in the&#13;
area providing primary health care to more countries. So from no beginnings in 1970, when there&#13;
wasn't even a piece of paper in the Bank on health, the Bank has evolved fifteen years later into having&#13;
a major health program.&#13;
&amp;#12;LEE                                               -15-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CHOKEL: Do you consider the schistosomiasis project one of the most salient events or highlights in&#13;
the environmental program?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
LEE: Well, yes, I think the evolution of health as an area for concern and for lending and for&#13;
assistance has been a very salient event in the Bank. I haven't any question about that. And I think the&#13;
Bank's record now in the health field, with some exceptions, is quite good. Yes, I would consider that&#13;
as a salient event.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            I think there are a number of salient events that have happened in our program. My&#13;
mandate in the beginning was to be sure that every project was looked at in terms of the impact it&#13;
would have on the environment and on health. In 1975, I'd been reporting to the Board on our&#13;
activities. The Board then asked whether or not it would be possible for the Bank to fmance what they&#13;
referred to as "environmental projects." They said, "Can we not finance projects whose sole objective&#13;
and purpose is to do something on behalf of the environment? To better manage it or to rehabilitate&#13;
it? We don't mean to limit that to the natural environment because there are many problems now&#13;
beginning to occur in the cities in the developing countries." The Bank's management response to that&#13;
was positive and that if developing countries made their wishes known and if these projects could be&#13;
developed in both technically and economically acceptable a ways, the Bank would proceed.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            So we began then in 1975 with that mandate and with those instructions to actually develop&#13;
and propose and promote environmental projects. These included projects on aforestation and&#13;
reforestation and soil conservation and pest control and rehabilitation of the cities, these kind of&#13;
activities. So I think that was another salient event in the Bank's program.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CHOKEL: I recall the newspapers had all written about the case of some tribal people, in the case of&#13;
the development of the Amazon. What did we do about that?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
LEE: Both the problem and the opportunity arose again out of the third leg of what I call our&#13;
"environmental stool." I said in the beginning that the environmental definition included both the&#13;
naturally occuring environment and the urban environment. It included public health and occupational&#13;
health and safety. It also included the third dimension, which was the social dimension. I was&#13;
concerned about the impact of the Bank's projects on people. Mter all, we have projects where people,&#13;
let's say, who are living in an area that's going to be flooded for a hydroelectric power project, are&#13;
going to be removed, are going to be resettled. I found out that they often weren't being resettled in a&#13;
&amp;#12;LEE                                                -16-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
[LEE]&#13;
very humane way. People were sort of looked upon as objects or economic entities. I saw them as&#13;
people and was very much concerned that this had to change, particularly in hydroelectric power&#13;
projects, irrigation projects, rural development projects, where people were going to be moved around,&#13;
resettled; where nomadic people were going to be sedentarized; where transhumant people were going&#13;
to be put in one place; where people were going to be brought together from different tribes that had&#13;
different cultures involving long-standing enmities or different religious backgrounds. We needed to&#13;
look at this. In those early days, Miss Nash, we brought in an anthropologist by the name of Mary&#13;
Elmendorf, didn't we?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NASH: Oh, yes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
LEE: Mary Elmendorf did some pioneer work for us in this, looking at these dimensions and advising&#13;
us. Also, at that time, John King--who has since left us--John and I discussed the need for having a&#13;
full-fledged study of the need for the social sciences in the Bank. John commissioned that study. I&#13;
think that it was Dr. Michael Gwynn, wasn't it, who did the study and who has been with the Bank off&#13;
and on all these years. He conducted a study on the role of the social sciences in the Bank. And of&#13;
course, as you would suspect, he found out that the Bank was very deficient, was very derelict, had not&#13;
paid attention to these dimensions.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CHOKEL: Yes, I saw that report.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
LEE: That report was about 1973, 1974 right around that period of time. Anyhow, stemming from&#13;
that, we saw how the problems began to arise. Our development activities were pushing back into the&#13;
frontiers where tribal people still reside, people in some cases living almost a neolithic existence.&#13;
Places in Africa, in the Amazonian part of Brazil, New Guinea, on some of the outer islands of&#13;
Indonesia. Now we're working also in remote places in China. We began finding that the development&#13;
that we were promoting, that we were financing, had some very, very traumatic effects on these people.&#13;
It introduced new diseases. The acculturation process which goes on when mainstream society comes&#13;
up against these people was very unsavory, was very traumatic. There clearly was a need for the Bank&#13;
to get out in front of this and to adopt a policy and a posture that said that the Bank was concerned&#13;
&amp;#12;LEE                                                -17-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
(LEE)&#13;
about the future of these people and was going to do something about it. There were a number of&#13;
outside groups who were quite vociferous--and quite rightly so--in bringing this to our attention. I&#13;
means groups like Amnesty International in London, the Harvard Group of Cultural Survival in&#13;
Cambridge and others. They were quick to chastise us and rightly so. And so our office, my office,&#13;
moved out in front of this and under the direction of Dr. Robert Goodland we began to fashion, if you&#13;
will, a tribal policy for the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            Well, you can imagine that when you begin to trespass on the sovereign rights of countries&#13;
regarding their people, that becomes politically a very, very delicate affair, to put it mildly. So we had&#13;
to walk a very, very fine line. The end result was, I must say, that we stepped over that line quite far.&#13;
We just said in essence, "Look, the World Bank is being asked to provide financing for development&#13;
projects that are going to impact upon tribal peoples. We're not going to do it unless all the following&#13;
conditions are observed." Our covenants, those measures, those actions that we required were hard for&#13;
some of our member countries to swallow. They found it very, very, very difficult.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CHOKEL: And did they follow them? Do they follow them?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
LEE: Yes, they do follow them but we continue to have problems. Even as of this day we have&#13;
problems on several projects in Brazil where the government and the government organizations that&#13;
are responsible for carrying out the Bank's work have experienced difficulties both within the country,&#13;
with their own administration, as well as with us in the Bank. But in the main, I think our contribution&#13;
has been very meaningful: we took a firm stand, we adopted a policy, and we put out a handbook for&#13;
their use on how to do it and what to avoid and what to be careful of and to be conscious of in the&#13;
acculturation process. This has been picked up by the other development assistance organizations. I'm&#13;
very pleased with what we've accomplished in that area.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CHOKEL: Your comments about guidelines reminds me, I think it was in February that you published&#13;
guidelines for major hazard installation in industrial agricultural projects. Do those guidelines touch&#13;
any Bank project? Industrial agricultural....&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
LEE: Let me just back up just a little, Mr. Choke!. The Bank, as you know, fmances the industrial&#13;
sector and the power sector and it finances facilities that have processes that produce all kinds of&#13;
pollutants which are going into the environment as well as problems for the health and safety of&#13;
&amp;#12;LEE                                                -18-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
[LEE]&#13;
the work force that are working there. So, fairly early on in our career, maybe 1973 or so, we began to&#13;
develop specific guidelines covering a whole range of activities in the industrial sector. And these&#13;
guidelines were furnished to the Bank staff with the idea that if you're going to have a project of a&#13;
certain type, these are the things that you need to be concerned with in terms of environmental&#13;
pollution, industrial pollution, environmental protection and worker health and safety.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NASH: The first "Green Book," wasn't it?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
LEE: Yes, the first so-called "Green Book" had quite a bit of that in it. We were fortunate in the early&#13;
days to get the services of a gentleman who will soon be retiring, Dr. Jean Tixhon, who was a first class&#13;
engineer and who took a great interest in this. He stayed with us for nearly ten years. I think probably&#13;
the fmest set of guidelines in the industrial sector that you'll find any place were produced under his&#13;
general direction. As far as I'm concerned, they surpass anything that you can find either in the private&#13;
sector or the public sector. These guidelines have been continually updated because after all there is&#13;
new research coming along, new development, new technology. So it's necessary for us to keep our&#13;
guidelines updated with new standards, new criteria. I always use the example of asbestos. As you&#13;
know, asbestos is a highly dangerous mineral which, when the particles get in the air, can cause all&#13;
kinds of problems for the respiratory system, including lung cancer, mesothelioma and others. We had&#13;
to change our guidelines on that probably no less than five or six times because the "working standard,"&#13;
as we call it--namely the criteria covering the size of the particle and how many particles per cubic&#13;
meter were allowed at the mine face or in the plant--had to be changed, because new research began to&#13;
show us that the standard we had before was not adequate. So it kept going down, down, down, down.&#13;
Those guidelines were published in French, English and Spanish and they've been sent all over the&#13;
world. No matter where you go in the developing countries, or in the developed for that matter, you&#13;
can find the Environmental Considerations for the Industrial Development Sector.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            Well, as good as that may be, you know late in 1984 we had the infamous "Bhopal Incident,"&#13;
in a plant in India, through a series of events which we won't go into here. It's not important. But&#13;
there was a release of toxic gases and there was a large mortality and a very large morbidity. And I'm&#13;
sure there's going to be a lot of chronic sequelae over the years as a result of it. But, that Bhopal&#13;
incident, more than anything else, I think served to convince both industry, the transnational&#13;
&amp;#12;LEE                                               -19-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
[LEE]&#13;
corporations and ourselves that we needed to look very carefully at the guidelines we had for the&#13;
prevention of these types of accidents. The upshot of it was that we came out, early in 1985, with a new&#13;
set of guidelines which are much more rigorous, much more stringent. And I must say they have been&#13;
well-received by both the industrial community and the developing countries. They were the subject of&#13;
two major seminars here just a few weeks ago which were televised. Our whole thrust here, Mr.&#13;
Choke!, is to take all those steps and measures that are necessary, absolutely necessary, to prevent that&#13;
kind of an incident arising in a Bank-financed project.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            You asked whether these guidelines are associated with any Bank project. I think with the&#13;
good work that was done by Dr. Tixhon and, quite honestly, with a lot of good luck--I cross my&#13;
lingers--we've managed to avoid a serious incident like that in all the industrial projects that we've&#13;
financed over the years. That doesn't mean that it can't happen. But we have managed to avoid that.&#13;
But now, I think, with the new guidelines in place and with the Bank's staff now very alert and very&#13;
concerned that they don't want to be party to anything like that, I think that we're on the road to a very&#13;
good prevention record. And by the way, I think Miss Nash maybe knows more than I do, but certainly&#13;
since we have published these guidelines, we've received a lot of inquiries from all over the world for&#13;
them, to help provide technical assistance.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NASH: Over the years, I think, a lot of the material put out by the office was being best "sellers," with&#13;
quotes on "sellers" because they're always free, you know.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
LEE: Well, Miss Nash mentioned the green handbook. We called it green because the color of the&#13;
cover was green. They were the first set of guidelines that had ever been published anyplace in the&#13;
world on how development assistance should be carried out with respect to the environment and&#13;
health. I forget how many we published in those fust years, but once they had gone out people began&#13;
to see them and recognize them and ask for more and more. Then we decided to come out with a&#13;
revised, updated edition. That came out I think along about 1974 or 1975. I remember the gentleman&#13;
who's in charge of publications--Charlie (Charles] Chih, wasn't it?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NASH: Yes, I think so.&#13;
&amp;#12;LEE                                                   -20-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
LEE: Charlie Chih came to the office one day and said, "You know, we're all out of that handbook,&#13;
and we've got to print more." I was very pleased. He said, "Do you know, this Bank is an economic&#13;
institution, it's a banking institution, it's a financial institution. But the best seller of all its publications&#13;
has been your green handbook on environmental issues!" I don't know how many tens of thousands of&#13;
copies of that handbook were published. You see it's been used all over the world.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CHOKEL: Well, it's nice to hear things like that because it shows that people have confidence in their&#13;
work and in the work of the World Bank. We're doing some things the right way.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            You mentioned before that many environmental institutions have emerged over the past 15&#13;
years, one of the most important being the United Nations Environmental Programme. What's the&#13;
Bank's experience in dealing with those institutions?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
LEE: Going back to about 1970, when we started in the Bank, I daresay there was just a handful of&#13;
institutions either in the public or private sector that were concerned with this matter that we refer to&#13;
as "the environment." There environment." There were just a few organizations I can remember. One&#13;
was called the International Union for the Conservation of Nature, which was headquartered in&#13;
Switzerland. In the United States, there was the Sierra Club, there was the National Wildlife&#13;
Federation, the one who gave the Bank the award, by the way. But there were only a very few and they&#13;
were mostly concerned with some specific issue of the environment. For example, the Audubon&#13;
Society, which has been around for a long time in the world, they were concerned at that time mostly&#13;
about birds, obviously, and the fate of birds and what was happening to bird populations and bird life.&#13;
The National Wildlife Federation was concerned about wildlife, and so on. But they were concerned&#13;
mostly in a national sense, as opposed to being concerned with these things on an international or&#13;
global basis. With the preparations for the Stockholm Conference and afterward, these organizations&#13;
literally began to mushroom. I can remember in those early days, it was absolutely unbelievable. We&#13;
were just besieged by...&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NASH: ...invitations to conferences that were coming in, ten, fllteen a day. It was incredible!.&#13;
&amp;#12;LEE                                                -21-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
LEE: The interest was incredible. And all coming to tbe Bank for information, for assistance.&#13;
Everybody in tbose days wanted to study the Bank. Every graduate student tbat was involved in the&#13;
environment, because it was a new field, wanted to come to the Bank and study the Bank. Professors&#13;
were doing it and it went on. I remember one day about 1973 or so, I came into tbe Bank one morning&#13;
and there were a lot of people around. They were all busy doing things, but I didn't recognize any of&#13;
them. I said to Miss Nash, "Who are these people here?'' She said, "Well, !bat's so-and-so, he's a&#13;
grduate student. That's so-and-so, he's a professor." Come to fmd out there were more people&#13;
studying us than we had on our own staff! I said, "Enough is enough." I remember saying to tbe Vice&#13;
President, "Look, we're just besieged here." But in retrospect it was good because tbey learned about&#13;
us and we learned a lot from them. The organizations emerged and grew up, as I said, like&#13;
mushrooms. Some evolved into very responsible organizations that are ongoing and made a great&#13;
contribution. Others, for one reason or another, you know, have sort of gone out of existence because&#13;
tbeywere concerned, let's say, witb some specific thing. A figure that was mentioned tbe other day--I&#13;
don't know how valid it is--indicated that there are on the average 250 new environmental&#13;
organizations established each year in the developed countries. That means you see a real growtb and&#13;
a real proliferation of these organizations.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            We, over the years, have maintained very good relationships with these organizations.&#13;
We've been open. We've invited them in. We've held seminars for them. We've held exhibits for&#13;
them. We've been free to share our information with them. We have acted, as Miss Nash said, we've&#13;
given speeches and addresses and ran panels virtually all over the world every year. So that we are&#13;
well-known to tbem and tbey are well-known to us. I think in the main we have good, constructive,&#13;
positive relationships witb them.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            Of late however, tbere is a feeling beginning to grow on the part of some of the&#13;
organizations in response to what they see, and I'll come to that in just a minute, what they see as a&#13;
general decline in all tbe environmental indicators all over the world. A whole spate of studies have&#13;
come out in the period from say 1980 to 1985 which show that in all the areas of our concern, when you&#13;
look across tbe world globally, there is still--despite all our efforts--the environmental concerns are real&#13;
and serious and growing. I think we're seeing tbe very tragic evidence of that is now in Africa. So&#13;
tbese organizations are saying to tbe Bank, "Look, you've done fine, but boy you certainly've got a lot&#13;
more to do." So they've been pressuring management. They've been pressuring tbe management from&#13;
the standpoint of putting more human resources and more fmancial resources into the environmental&#13;
&amp;#12;LEE                                                 -22-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
[LEE]&#13;
work of the Bank. They've looked at the Bank and said that the Bank needs desperately to fmance&#13;
more, quote, "environmental-type projects." We need more reforestation, more soil conservation, more&#13;
flood control, more rehabilitation-type projects. Third and last they're saying to the Bank, "Look, in&#13;
many of your member developing countries, the whole natural support system for their economies is&#13;
collapsing, and you desperately need to get in there and to help these countries to identify patterns of&#13;
development that at least offer some promise of being sustainable." If you don't and it isn't done, they&#13;
predict that the next several decades are going to witness the demise of not a few of our developing&#13;
countries because their environmental support system is just collapsing.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            So I would say, Mr. Choke!, that in the main, our relationships with them have been positive&#13;
and constructive and helpful. On both sides I think there's a great deal of respect. You mentioned the&#13;
fact that one of these large organizations did give us an award here several years ago for our work. I&#13;
think that in general the criticism that they level at the Bank is justified to the extent that they perceive&#13;
some real problems down the road and they want the Bank to take some steps now, you know, to head&#13;
them off.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CHOKEL: Well, that brings me now to a very important question, I believe. The Bank has been in&#13;
environmental activities for about the last fifteen years. Now what directions do you see the Bank's&#13;
work going in the next 10 or 15 years?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
LEE: Well, that will be long after both you and I have left this institution. And I hope that in our&#13;
respective fields we will have left something of a legacy. I know you will have in your field in terms of&#13;
the Archives of the Bank. But I think what we're going to see happen in the Bank over the next five&#13;
years and then going on into the decade, I think you're going to see the Bank moving more directly into&#13;
the area of factoring the environmental and natural resource dimensions into country economic&#13;
programming in a very careful and purposeful way. I just mentioned, for example, that a number of&#13;
non-governmental organizations have criticized the Bank by saying that the patterns of development&#13;
being followed by many of our member countries are not in their long-term best interest. That the&#13;
patterns of development are contributing to the demise of their natural support systems and their&#13;
resources and that there is little hope that many of these countries will be able to sustain their&#13;
&amp;#12;LEE                                               -23-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
(LEE]&#13;
economic development in the light of what's happening. I think the Bank here in 1984 and 1985, at the&#13;
time that we're making this tape, is beginning to take those criticisms seriously. The Bank is beginning&#13;
to recognize that it has to adopt a different stance with regard to how it does country economic&#13;
programming and sector work. There are even some questions being asked as to whether or not the&#13;
whole approach that the Bank has historically followed is still contemporarily valid and useful.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            For example, we advocate--I say "we" meaning those of us who speak on behalf of the&#13;
environment and natural resources--we advocate that the Bank and development assistance in general&#13;
take a more holistic look at a country: look at its resource base, look at its environmental systems,&#13;
make a determination as to what kind of development is going to be benign or supportive of these&#13;
essential systems and at the same time provide no less than the basic human needs for the growing&#13;
population. This is not going to prove easy. But on the other hand, following the path we're following&#13;
now is going to lead to a great deal more tragedy.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
           The Bank's approach to countries on a sector by sector basis, where the transportation&#13;
sector does their studies without any recognition of the linkages between transportation and the other&#13;
sectors, namely the urban sector or agricultural sector, where everything is conducted in sort of a&#13;
disparate way and the lending program and the projects are devised in support of sectors without a&#13;
good understanding of these linkages. I think that is going to change. I think what you're going to see&#13;
is that the Bank will help a country develop and devise a development strategy that will take full&#13;
cognizance of its environmental systems and the natural resources, will factor those in a very careful&#13;
way and then will come out with an array, if you will, a spectrum of development projects that will be in&#13;
support of that general overall strategy as opposed to what we do now.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
           And in point of fact, we are taking those very first steps now, Mr. Chokel. My office has&#13;
now entered into arrangements with NASA on one side and a system in Switzerland that you just&#13;
mentioned earlier in your conversation, called GRID. It's the Global Resources and Information Data&#13;
system. These both depend in great measure on the use of remote sensing technologies. By tying in&#13;
with these two systems, we hope to be able to provide first, the database, and second, the analysis that&#13;
is going to be needed by the Bank's regional offices for its country economic programs and to bring&#13;
&amp;#12;LEE                                               -24-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
[LEE]&#13;
about some necessary changes in their sector approaches. We're just in the process of learning&#13;
ourselves how this technology can be employed, how these analytic systems can be used, how we need&#13;
to go about it, because this is the first time this has ever been done. No development assistance&#13;
institution has every used the technology and the computer-based analytic capacities that NASA has&#13;
used for its space exploration and focused that downward, if you will, toward earth saying, "How can we&#13;
use that in support of economic development that's going to be protective of these very important&#13;
resources we have?" We're fortunate now in having made these arrangements, and I think that you'll&#13;
certainly see this emerge and blossom over the next five to ten years.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            I've said before, inside the Bank and outside, that I think this is going to be the vanguard for&#13;
change. You know, change takes place sometimes slowly. But it also starts with some little seed&#13;
somewhere and the idea begins to germinate and spread and people begin to understand it and adapt&#13;
to it. The World Bank is no different from any other bureaucracy. Change comes hard. What we're&#13;
asking for and what we're pointing towards is quite obviously a rather major change in the way the&#13;
Bank does its business. I foresee the Bank doing its business in quite a different way from what you&#13;
and I have been accustomed to since we've been in the Bank. I think that is certainly going to call for&#13;
some structural changes in the organization of the Bank, and it's going to call for a different mix of&#13;
disciplines in the Bank. We're going to be looking at disciplines and fields that the Bank has not been&#13;
accustomed to looking at. This is going to bring about both some problems and some opportunities, to&#13;
be quite honest with you.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CHOKEL: In other words, environmental work in the Bank will have quite an impact on country&#13;
sector programs and other projects.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
LEE: Yes. A lot of my colleagues would disagree with me, but I think what we're aiming for, and what&#13;
my hope would be, is that the word 'environment" will just completely disappear from our lexicon.&#13;
That in the whole concept and process of economic development, which after all is the development of&#13;
resources, the word environment will drop out because it will be subsumed. It will be automatically a&#13;
part of the thinking and the methodology that we and others will use as we go about the job of helping&#13;
these countries with their development activities. So what I'm hoping for is that rather than having&#13;
&amp;#12;LEE                                                -25-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
[LEE]&#13;
"environment" always sitting out as a separate and very visible entity and people referring to something&#13;
as an "environmental problem"--go see the environmental officer"--now it will be broadened. It will be&#13;
folded in, it will be totally integrated with the development process so that your program officers and&#13;
your project officers and others won't be thinking in terms of the environment, .I!l&lt;! g:, or the&#13;
environmental staff; it will be just a normal part of their work because it will be factored in. I think&#13;
that's our challenge and that's our task. That's what I'd like to see happen.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            Now whether that will happen before I leave this institution I don't know. I still think that&#13;
at least for some few years yet we're still going to have to maintain a specific environmental focus&#13;
because we have to remind our colleagues, by our presence, if you will, and by the fact that we're&#13;
working with them, that these are dimensions that they can't afford to overlook. I'm not sure that at&#13;
this point in time either that we would want to completely phase out the environmental focus in the&#13;
Bank. I think that would send the wrong signals to a large number of our constituency on the outside&#13;
and the whole environmental community, that somehow we are beginning to downplay or denigrate the&#13;
activitiy. But I think it will come and I think that over the next decade you'll see the Bank moving in&#13;
that direction. I think that's exciting and I think that's the right way to move. So I like to think that&#13;
maybe we've made some contribution toward that activity.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CHOKEL: Well Dr. Lee, I really thank you for the information that you gave us. Your interview&#13;
focussed on a specific component which we understand is going to be more and more important in the&#13;
future years: environment.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
LEE: Right. I'm surprised though that you as a Yugoslav didn't bring up one of our famous&#13;
environmental projects in Sarajevo, Yugoslavia!&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CHOKEL: Well, I was saving that question for the end. They had the Winter Olympics, which&#13;
apparently was qnite a success. It even turned a little profit of about five million dollars. That's what I&#13;
read in Time magazine. But I know the Bank had a project to clean up the city, because the pollution&#13;
that existed before was just unbearable. Nobody would have any kind of Olympics in a city like that.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
LEE: That's right.&#13;
&amp;#12;LEE                                                 -26-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CHOKEL: Now, did the project relate to the Olympics, or would the Bank have fmanced the project&#13;
regardless of the Olympics?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
LEE: No, it didn't relate to the Olympics at all. Very quickly, the history of the Sarajevo, Yugoslavia,&#13;
project was that in 1972, Mr. McNamara was the guest of President Tito. He traveled in Yugoslavia&#13;
and visited the city of Sarajevo, which is the capital of Bosnia and a city which is, historically and&#13;
culturally, sort of at the crossroads between East and West, if you will. While there, Mr. McNamara&#13;
was approached concerning the serious environmental problems that the city had--I think he&#13;
experienced some himself, if I'm not mistaken--and he told the authorities that he would see what&#13;
could be done. So he came back and called me in and said, "Look, I've been to the city of Sarajevo.'&#13;
He described what he'd seen and said, "I want you to go over and see if there's something we can do. I&#13;
mean technically if there's something we can do."&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            And that started a series of visits by myself and others in the Bank looking at what these&#13;
problems were: the dimensions of them, the severity of them, what might be the correct approaches&#13;
that we could take. We called in a number of consultants from different parts of the world to confer&#13;
with us. The upshot of it was that we did agree with the Yugoslav authorities on a project, and it did&#13;
what you just said. It was aimed at cleaning up what had become a very, very unbearable situation,&#13;
both in terms of their water supply, their water quality, their waste, the absence of a waste treatment&#13;
system--I could tell you all sorts of bad stories about that.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            Of course, the air pollution problem was absolutely horrendous. Sarajevo lies down in a&#13;
deep valley and has a very cold continental climate, which is unlike the coast of Yugoslavia, which has a&#13;
Mediterranean climate. What would happen in that in the winter, which is long and hard in Sarajevo,&#13;
you'd get what we call"temperature inversions,' where there's a warm cap of air atop a cold layer of&#13;
air. That means there's no way for the pollutants to move out of the city. They are trapped there.&#13;
They are trapped under this cap or this lid. That would go on for days or sometimes weeks, and the&#13;
sulphur dioxide concentrations would build up because in those days the homes, the shops, the offices&#13;
and everything all burned this very low-grade, lignite-type coal with a very high sulphur content.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            These sulphur dioxide concentrations would build up to just horrendous levels and in fact&#13;
they would be so bad that two things would happen: first of all they would gather all the school children&#13;
&amp;#12;LEE                                                 -27-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
[LEE]&#13;
together and put them on school busses and bus them up into the mountains above this inversion layer&#13;
to places like J ahorina. There they would stay until the inversion broke and they could come back&#13;
home again! Second, when I first went there, it was in October, which wasn't a real cold month, but I&#13;
remember that they had a bad inversion. I remember going into the hospital there and finding it&#13;
literally jammed to the walls. People on the floor in the hallways! People three to a bed! Can you&#13;
imagine being in a hospital where there are three people in a bed with all kinds of respiratory&#13;
problems, cardiovascular problems and so on. As we found out later when we began to do the&#13;
epidemiological studies, it was a very classic case that as the temperature went down the sulphur&#13;
dioxide went up, and right behind it came all the sickness and all the disease problems.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            But to wrap that up, the Bank did a good job there and the Yugoslavs did an outstanding&#13;
job. Project officers in the Bank confirmed that they've never seen a project that went forward to well,&#13;
so beautifully, so on time as that particular project did. The Yugoslavs put their very best people to&#13;
work on that and did an outstanding job.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CHOKEL: The whole population had a great interest in this project.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
LEE: Absolutely. Absolutely. You know, they voluntarily taxed themselves to support it, giving two&#13;
percent of their gross earnings. In those days, you know, the per capita of income in Bosnia was&#13;
around $900 to $1100 a year. So when you tax yourself two percent of that you're taking a big bite out&#13;
of your income! And they did!&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            But as you said, Mr.   Choke~   when that project was almost completed, they felt confident&#13;
enough--which surprised me--to approach the International Olympic Committee and offer Sarajevo&#13;
and the surrounding mountains as a site for the Winter Olympics. And by golly, they made it! Well,&#13;
you saw the pictures, I'm sure, on television. You could see that the city had become a very livable&#13;
place. It still has some residual problems, but certaiuly it's a place now that they can be proud of.&#13;
They've doine a lot of things in terms of handling the solid waste and re-routng the traffic, this and that.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CHOKEL: Well, finally, is there anything else that we skipped? I believe we didn't cover the whole&#13;
topic. We could talk for days probably, especially if we go into specific projects, but is there anything&#13;
else that you would like to state about your environmental work?&#13;
&amp;#12;LEE                                               -28-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
LEE: Well, I think that in the conduct of this work in the World Bank we've had our up sides and our&#13;
down sides. Miss Nash knows there's been a lot of blood let, both mine and others, because things&#13;
don't happen all that easily, all that simply. Bringing about changes in the Bank of the type that we've&#13;
been talking about for the past hour wasn't all that easy. It was a position and function that for a long&#13;
time .... Not so much now but in the early days, as Miss Nash remembers, there wasn't a day or almost&#13;
an hour that we weren't in some sort of an adversarial position with somebody who didn't want to do&#13;
what we wanted them to do or were doing something we didn't want them to do. Or the outside people&#13;
were telling us we weren't doing enough.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NASH: Or even just the plain lack of understanding of what it was about. I remember seeing perhaps&#13;
one of the ftrst appraisal reports where they were forced to put in something about the environment.&#13;
The project officer had put in that the environment was "very conducive to good negotiation"! So that&#13;
was the level of understanding at that time. Incredible! So you not only had the unwillingness but&#13;
misunderstanding of what it was about.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
LEE: That's right. That's right.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NASH: It's been a tremendous educational process in the Bank over the last 15 years.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
LEE: That's right. So, as I say, it's had its up side and its down side and there was a lot of bloodletting&#13;
and a lot of adversarial position. But I think in the main--I say this quite honestly--that the Bank&#13;
Presidents, Mr. McNamara and Mr. Clausen, have been supportive of what we've tried to do. I think&#13;
the Board of Directors have been supportive. They've encouraged us, they've helped us. And in&#13;
general I think so has Bank management.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NASH: Wasn't that one of the ftrst speeches that Mr. Clausen made?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
LEE: Yes he did. That's right. He made a speech on the question of sustainable development. That's&#13;
right, he did.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CHOKEL: That was the Osborn Lecture.&#13;
&amp;#12;LEE                                               -29-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
LEE: The Osborn Lecture, yes, he made that. That's right.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CHOKEL: I have two of your speeches. I know there are more. The one to the International Wildlife&#13;
Federation that you gave in Milwaukee in 1982 and then the one that I found very interesting:&#13;
"Environmentally Sound Development and Disaster Prevention and Linkage." You gave the speech&#13;
last year in June in Stockholm at the Swedish Red Cross symposium on the prevention of disasters.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
LEE: That's right. There's where the disaster aid agencies, the Red Cross particularly and others,&#13;
carne together for a discussion of the fact that the frequency and severity of natural disasters now is&#13;
such that they just cannot cope--either fmancially or otherwise--with the magnitude of these disasters.&#13;
And furthermore, I think this goes back to what you said in the very beginning of our discussion, they&#13;
have now seen and have begun to realize what we've been talking about for the past 10 or 15 years, that&#13;
many of the so-called "natural disasters" that we attribute to outside forces--God and others--are really&#13;
man-made, and that environmentally unsound economic development is a major causitive factor.&#13;
Again this points a finger at places like the Bauk and others and says, "Look, you've got to pay more&#13;
attention to how your development activities are affecting these vital life-supporting ecological systems&#13;
and natural resources." I tried to make the case, in that paper there. I tried to make that linkage, if&#13;
you will, in a more specific way.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CHOKEL: I found the paper very informative. I found out about many things that I didn't know&#13;
before.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
LEE: Yes. I think that's always the role of papers. I hope!&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CHOKEL: Well, one thing that I have to ask you. You mentioned Mr. McNamara and Mr. Clausen&#13;
being supportive of the concept of environmental work. Which other staff members were the greatest&#13;
and are the greatest supporters of the environmental work?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
LEE: Over the years? Let's see. Miss Nash can think about some, too. I'd say that the people who&#13;
come to my mind certainly would include Robert McNamara, quite obviously. There were certain&#13;
members of the Board I can remember. Robert Wieczorowski who for a number of years was the&#13;
United States Executive Director, was a very strong supporter in the Bank. Morris Miller&#13;
&amp;#12;LEE                                                -30-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
(LEE]&#13;
from Canada, who was the Canadian Executive Director. There were others but these people sort of&#13;
stand out in my mind because they may have stood up at Board meetings and made some comments or&#13;
forced management to consider things in a very forceful way. Certainly within the Bank in the early&#13;
days, people like Bernard Chadenet and Siem Aldewereld, Hal [Richard H.] Demuth, Mike&#13;
(Michael L.] Hoffman, Bill [William] Clark--who for years was involved more in our public affairs&#13;
activities--these stand out as people who believed in and wanted to see it flourish in the Bank. At other&#13;
levels, I was thinking of people like Gautam Kaji and ...&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NASH: (Munir] Benjenk.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
LEE: ...Benjenk. People that were involved with us, for example, in the Sarajevo Project. People who&#13;
really got excited about it and felt that they were involved with something that was very meaningful and&#13;
took a great interest in it and were very supportive, worked very hard. It's hard to pick out a few just&#13;
off the top of my head. I'm sure if I sat here for a while I could think of more people that were helpful.&#13;
I must say, Miss Nash knows, too, it wasn't just the higher levels in the Bank. There were a lot of other&#13;
people, for example, Shirley Boskey. Shirley was a strong supporter of the environment when she was&#13;
in and she helped immeasurably in so many ways. Working with the United Nations, working with the&#13;
specialized agencies, working with the non-governmental organizations. Mahmud Burney came along&#13;
and has been a strong supporter in the same area. Let's face it. There's a whole host of nameless&#13;
secretaries and others at the assistant level and support level who made things happen for us, who got&#13;
papers in where they should go, who arranged for meetings and arranged for interviews and cut comers&#13;
and shaved corners, who liked us, generally, and felt that what we were doing was important and&#13;
wanted to see it grow. By the same token there were probably some that became very discouraged with&#13;
us because, as one Bank staff member said the other day to a person on the outside who was&#13;
interviewing him, 'Yes', he said, 'the environmental staff can be very antagonistic''!&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CHOKEL: Well, I'm qnite sure the Archives will not be antagonistic and will do our best to preserve&#13;
for posterity all the good and bad things that you did.&#13;
&amp;#12;LEE                                              -31-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
LEE: Thank you for giving us the opportunity. I think it's sort of fun to reminisce. You don't have the&#13;
opportunity to do that very often. You're so besieged with the day-to-day activities that you can't think&#13;
back over time. You can't sort of step back and take an overview of it and see it in perspective. I thank&#13;
you for doing this and I think that someday, sometime when somebody's writing up certain parts of the&#13;
Bank's history, this will be a contribution.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CHOKEL: And that's what the Archives are for.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
LEE: Absolutely.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CHOKEL: Thank you, Dr. Lee.&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="17972859">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1985/04/17972859/transcript-oral-history-interview-dr-james-lee-held-april-4-1985
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1985/04/17972859/transcript-oral-history-interview-dr-james-lee-held-april-4-1985</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1985/04/17972859/transcript-oral-history-interview-dr-james-lee-held-april-4-1985</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2006-10-27T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2006-10-27T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2013/07/08/000333037_20130708123630/Rendered/INDEX/790710TRN0Lee00erview0April04001985.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2013/07/08/000333037_20130708123630/Rendered/PDF/790710TRN0Lee00erview0April04001985.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>1985-04-04T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2013-07-08T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Transcript of oral history interview with
            Dr. James Lee held on April 4, 1985
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            In April 4, 1985, Dr. James Lee was
            interviewed on behalf of the World Bank Group Archives oral
            history program by Bogomir Chokel. During his tenure at the
            Bank from 1970 to 1989, he worked in the following areas: in
            the projects department as an environmental advisor
            (1970-1975); in the office of environmental and health
            affairs as director of central projects staff (1975-1979);
            as an environmental advisor to the projects advisory staff
            (1980-1983) and to the project policy department
            (1983-1987); and in the environmental department as a senior
            advisor (1987-1989). His transcript concerns his
            introduction of viewing project the World Bank starting in
            1970 according to education and health.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Transcript of oral history interview with
            Dr. James Lee held on April 4, 1985
        </docna>
        <display_title>Transcript of oral history
            interview with Dr. James Lee held on April 4, 1985</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/1985/04/17972859/transcript-oral-history-interview-dr-james-lee-held-april-4-1985</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Transcript</docty>
        <subtopic>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation,Access to Finance,Technology Industry,Banks &amp; Banking Reform,Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Industry,Health, Nutrition and Population,Environment</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000333037_20130708123630</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>World Bank Group Archives oral history program</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Industry,Health, Nutrition and Population,Environment</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Board Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            air pollution, air pollution problem,
            benefit analysis, cancer, coal, developed countries,
            economic development, economics, economists, Environmental,
            environmental issues, environmental problem, environmental
            problems, Environmental Protection, environmental sciences,
            environmental thinking, fish, health problems, natural
            resources, water pollution
        </keywd>
        <owner>Knowledge &amp; Information Services (ITSKI)</owner>
        <repnb>79071</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crops</ml:concept><ml:concept>Solid Waste Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Solid Waste Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition – Community Based Interventions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition – Raising Awareness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition – Training</ml:concept><ml:concept>Foreign Direct Investments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Linkages</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Protection</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Diseases</ml:concept><ml:concept>Air Pollution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Solid Waste</ml:concept><ml:concept>Congestion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Adaptation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition</ml:concept><ml:concept>FDI Spillovers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Drainage</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>