<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>ï»¿                                79057&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
THE WORLD BANK GROUP ARCHIVES&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    ORAL HISTORY PROGRAM&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Transcript of interview with&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          JOHN A, KING&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          May 18, 1989&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    By:    Charles Ziegler&#13;
&amp;#12;Memorialist's name:      John A. King&#13;
Date of Interview:       May 18, 1989&#13;
Place of Interview:      The World Bank&#13;
Interviewer's name:      Charles Ziegler&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:    Today is May 18, 1989,   My name is Charles Ziegler and I have&#13;
with me here at the headquarters of the World Bank Mr. John A. King.      Mr.&#13;
King joined the staff of the World Bank in 1963 and worked first in the&#13;
Economic Development Institute where he prepared a casebook on project&#13;
appraisal entitled Economic Development Pro1ects and Their Appraisal.      He&#13;
subsequently served in the Development Services Department as a Policy&#13;
Planning Officer and later in the Office of the Director of Projects as&#13;
Training Adviser.     After the 1972 reorganization Mr. King became the&#13;
Assistant to the Vice President, Projects Staff,      In 1978 he joined the&#13;
International Fund for Agricultural Development.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Well, if I can call you John for the purposes of this interview â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:   Yes, call me John for any purpose.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:     Could you relate how it was that you originally came to work for&#13;
the World Bank?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:   I had been working since 1954 at the Harvard Law School as Secretary&#13;
of International Legal Studies.      In the early 1960s I began to hear myself&#13;
repeating myself and I thought that noise indicated that I'd been there&#13;
long enough.    And having long admired the Bank as taking a very practical,&#13;
pragmatic approach to development, I came to see if I could get a job here&#13;
and I succeeded.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:    Your first job was in EDI [Economic Development Institute], as I&#13;
remember?&#13;
&amp;#12;J. A. KING                               -2-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:     Well, really I was always working for Dick [Richard H.] Demuth when&#13;
I started, and he just put me over at the EDI, which was also under his&#13;
direction, as a place to work.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:     While you were attached to EDI, you prepared a casebook entitled&#13;
Economic Development Projects and Their Appraisal, which became something&#13;
of a minor classic of development literature.       What factors led you to&#13;
prepare this book in the first place?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:     Well, Dick Demuth had been concerned for some time about ways in&#13;
which the Bank's experience could be made available to the academic&#13;
community.       He had one try, it didn't work out very well â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:     What was that?    Do you recall?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:     Yes.   He had an economist who was supposed to write a book which&#13;
would incorporate the Bank's use of development economics into a text to be&#13;
used in academia.       It really didn't come out very well.   It wasn't what&#13;
Dick wanted and I don't think other people would have liked it very much,&#13;
either.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:     So it as never published?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:     It was never published.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Dick was a lawyer and he thought maybe a way of getting what he wanted&#13;
would be to have a casebook written, like a law casebook, but based on the&#13;
Bank's project work.       That's what he told me to do, and I tried to do it.&#13;
The concept was not mine at all.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:     It was Demuth's concept?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:     Yes.&#13;
&amp;#12;J. A. KING                               -3-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:     Did you have any particular difficulties in its preparation?         I&#13;
know it took a few years to actually produce the book.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:     Yes.    It took two-and-a-half years.     Part of the time--since I&#13;
didn't know what a project, as defined by the Bank, was--I spent educating&#13;
myself.     Then I read a lot of project appraisal reports and trying to find&#13;
ones which I thought were interesting or had some significant point to&#13;
them.     The obstacles I encountered were mainly that the Projects Department&#13;
really didn't want to have it published.          I think they thought that if what&#13;
they did was written down they would open themselves to all kinds of&#13;
criticism.       So they didn't support the concept of making the Bank's&#13;
experience available to the academic community.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:     You mean criticism in terms of what they had done?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:     Or hadn't done, or the adequacy of what they were doing.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:     In the retrospective sense, rather than criticism of their&#13;
methodologies?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:     Well both, I think.   Both.   Dick believed in openness and he was the&#13;
author of, or at least he directed the writing of, a book which I suppose&#13;
is still in the Bank's library of things they give out. It was written to&#13;
explain to the Congress what the Bank did and how it was done.         He had a&#13;
very, very hard fight to get that published, but he won it.         The book is&#13;
about 150 pages long and it's called The World Bank - Policies and&#13;
Operations.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    The Projects people, I suppose â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢        I love them all dearly, but they&#13;
did not like to be caught out, and I'm afraid they felt that if it was&#13;
written down it would be easier to catch them out.         But after about a year&#13;
of to-ing and fro-ing Mr. Demuth had a meeting with Siem [Simon]&#13;
&amp;#12;J. A. KING                             -4-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
[KING]&#13;
Aldewereld, who was the Director of Projects, and some of his staff, which&#13;
I attended and I explained what I was trying to do.        There was initially a&#13;
lot of objection, but Dick persuaded them that this was something that was&#13;
needed and, more important, that the President was interested in it, and&#13;
then there wasn't any more argument.         Actually I was assigned some&#13;
Projects staff to help me and make sure that I got it right.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    One of the interesting things that came out of having other project&#13;
staff help me was that no one was aware, or appeared to be aware, of the&#13;
different methodologies that were used in different economic sectors for&#13;
economic analysis.     For example, I was working with one person and she&#13;
said, "Well, that's not the way we do it."       And I said, "Maybe not, but&#13;
that is the way they do it in Transportation"--or maybe it was another&#13;
sector.     And she said, "It can't be.â&#128;¢      So we called in the senior&#13;
economist from that sector's division, and he said, "Yes, that's the way we&#13;
do it."     But really, different sectors were very separate and really didn't&#13;
know what other people were doing, to a very large degree, in methods or&#13;
approaches to economic analysis of projects.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:    Did that continue, do you think, after your book appeared, or did&#13;
this lead to a greater convergence of methodology?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:     I think it led to some concern, and perhaps to somewhat more&#13;
thought, but during my time at the Bank, the economic analysis of projects&#13;
was constantly changing and expanding, partly in response to the changes in&#13;
the projects themselves.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:    How was this book initially received, both within the Bank and&#13;
the larger development community?&#13;
&amp;#12;J. A. KING                              -5-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:   You referred to it as a minor classic. It was not received as a&#13;
minor classic.      Within the Bank I don't think it made any impression at&#13;
all, except a few people now had something that they could give to their&#13;
clients in the developing countries if they wanted to give them something&#13;
to tell them a little bit more about how the Bank worked.        In the academic&#13;
community, it was loudly criticized, vehemently criticized by economists&#13;
who didn't think it had any value at all, but other more practical types&#13;
thought it was useful.      And I know that Ed [EdwardS.] Mason and Bob&#13;
[Robert E.) Asher, when they wrote the history of the Bank's first 25&#13;
years, found it very, very useful in explaining exactly what the Bank did&#13;
in its project appraisal at that time.        All those projects, of course, were&#13;
very early and it no longer deals with the Bank's current work.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:   Right.     That's a good use, if nothing else â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:   Yes.   Oh, yes.    Modestia aparte, you will see in the footnotes to&#13;
that history quite a lot of references to the casebook.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:   In your view, how well has the book stood the test of time, which&#13;
is to say, do you believe it is still relevant and useful to the study of&#13;
the process of economic development as it comes to today?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:   It has stood the test of time only in that historical sense that I&#13;
just mentioned.     It's very out of date as to the technology and of course&#13;
it only covers two sectors or three sectors, transportation, electric&#13;
utilities, and a little on industry.      It was proposed at one time that a&#13;
new edition be made.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:   It published in, what, 1965?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:   Yes.&#13;
&amp;#12;J. A. KING                              -6-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
[KING]&#13;
    After the 1972 reorganization it was proposed that a second edition be&#13;
made which would cover the sectors that hadn't been covered in the first&#13;
one, particularly in view of the fact that agriculture, which hadn't been&#13;
referred to at all, was, by then, the biggest single sector of Operations.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:     Education was expanding, too, I believe.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:     Yes, but at nowhere near the rate that agriculture was.      I mean,&#13;
agriculture was just going ape.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:     The green revolution and all that â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:     Yes, yes.   And the concern for the poor.    Because there are a lot of&#13;
poor farmers.     But that idea was turned down.      Though I was Projects'&#13;
representative on the Publications Committee, I'll be goddamned if I can&#13;
remember why.     I think they thought maybe that it was sort of going back&#13;
over old ground, and even if there were going to be new sectors and new&#13;
technology, it had been done.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:     After the casebook was published, what did you do?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:     By that time, the Bank had completed a fair number of sector and&#13;
feasiblity studies, a form of technical assistance aimed at helping member&#13;
countries to identify and prepare suitable projects to be presented to the&#13;
Bank for financing through a project loan.      Most of these studies had been&#13;
financed by the UNDP [United Nations Development Program] which had been&#13;
created precisely for this purpose, but a few had been financed by Bank&#13;
grants.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    In parenthesis, I might mention that this apparent competition between&#13;
the Bank and the UNDP for this kind of work resulted from the high level of&#13;
&amp;#12;J. A. KING                            -7-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
[KING]&#13;
earnings at this time, and managment's feeling that some of these earnings&#13;
should be used for development purposes.      After the creation of IDA,&#13;
however, surplus Bank earnings were contributed to IDA and Bsnk grants for&#13;
sector and feasiblity studies ceased.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    At the beginning, these studies were carried out by firms of consulting&#13;
engineers, sometimes supplemented by economists and later by economic&#13;
consulting firms, or by a consortium of such firms.      Over time, the&#13;
economic consulting firms played a larger and larger role, as the&#13;
importance of economics grew in the Bank's work.      Still later, other&#13;
specialists were needed, such as architects, anthropologists, management&#13;
consultants, financial analysts, and so on.      It must be stressed that these&#13;
firms were hired and supervised by the Bank, not by the potential borrower.&#13;
The Bank was convinced that these studies could be carried out most&#13;
effectively by using firms rather than individual experts.      A firm could&#13;
field an organized team of individuals used to working together, and had&#13;
the capability of providing additional experts, if required by, say,&#13;
illness, or the evolution of the work.      In addition, a firm's home office&#13;
could provide back-up services--secretarial, computing or drafting.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Though other specialised agencies of the UN, such as FAO [Food and&#13;
Agriculture Organization], WHO [World Health Organization], or UNESCO&#13;
[United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization], carried&#13;
out similar sorts of of studies in their fields of specialization, financed&#13;
by UNDP [United Nations Development Program], they tended to use individual&#13;
experts for the work and not firms.     This enabled them to escape the&#13;
constraints of their regular budget for staff and employ individuals,&#13;
ostensibly on a temporary basis, but by shifting them from one UNDP&#13;
financed study to another, make them quasi-permanent staff members, without&#13;
being paid out of the regular staff budget.     But in the Bank's view, this&#13;
practice had its costs in terms of effectively executing the studies, for&#13;
reasons mentioned earlier.&#13;
&amp;#12;J. A. KING                            -8-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
[KING]&#13;
    Dick Demuth believed that the Bank had accumulated a considerable&#13;
amount of experience in carrying out this work and asked me to review it&#13;
and see what were the lessons to be learned.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:     And what did you find?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:     The basic conclusion of my report was that these studies had been&#13;
very useful in identifying and preparing suitable projects for borrowing&#13;
member countries, in improving and strengthening project design and in&#13;
identifying projects where technical difficulties or economic&#13;
considerations made the proposed project unsuitable or uneconomic, and&#13;
thereby stopping it from going forward.     Indeed, without some assistance of&#13;
this sort, most developing member countries would have been unable to&#13;
borrow.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    On the other hand, where the work had included attempts at human or&#13;
institutional development--for example, developing a highway planning&#13;
capability in the Ministry of Works or an organization to maintain the&#13;
roads once they had been built--the studies, with a few exceptions, had&#13;
been much less successful.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    In many cases, individuals trained to strengthen capabilities in public&#13;
sector institutions drifted away into the private sector or even left the&#13;
country, or the government failed to continue support of the capabilities&#13;
created.     I was left with an impression that the consultants were better at&#13;
handling physical problems than human and institutional development.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:     And then what?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:     When my report was discussed in the Loan Committee, the second of my&#13;
conclusions, that about institution building, caused concern, and though&#13;
&amp;#12;J. A. KING                             -9-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
!KING]&#13;
people argued that it was not really true or was overstated, [J,] Burke&#13;
Knapp more or less accepted it and asked what was to be done to improve the&#13;
Bank's performance in this area.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    After discussion, it was agreed that the Bank should make greater&#13;
efforts to help borrowers to train their staff and improve their systems.&#13;
But there were differences as to where responsibility for guiding and&#13;
monitoring these efforts should be located within the Projects complex in&#13;
the Bank.     Some thought it should be in the Education Projects Department,&#13;
but none of the Projects department directors particularly wanted it in his&#13;
department.     Then the position of Training Adviser was created in the&#13;
Office of the Director, Projects and I was appointed to that post with a&#13;
two-man staff.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:     What happened then?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:    Meanwhile, because of changes in the nature of Bank&#13;
lending--declining emphasis on massive, monolithic engineering-oriented&#13;
projects, and increasing emphasis on agriculture and rural development,&#13;
education, health and population and on problems like poverty and&#13;
umemployment--Projects staff became increasingly aware of the importance of&#13;
project-related training and including such training as elements of a loan&#13;
became increasingly the rule.      In agriculture, for example, strengthening&#13;
the institutions responsible for agricultural research and extension was&#13;
critical to the whole effort of agricultural and rural development.     And&#13;
what is extension but a type of training?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    As Training Adviser I had little to do with these developments, other&#13;
than helping to prepare some general policy papers and organizing a couple&#13;
of seminars, but I was consulted from time to time by individual Projects&#13;
staff.     Rather by accident, my staff became specialized in transportation,&#13;
&amp;#12;J. A. KING                            -10-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
[KING]&#13;
In actuality, the bulk of the work was done by officers in the various&#13;
Projects departments, such as Transportation, Agriculture or Public&#13;
Utilities.     For example, financial analysts, led by Jim [James H.] Jennings&#13;
in the Public Utilities Department, did much to strengthen organization,&#13;
systems amd management of the public utility enterprises that operated&#13;
power or water supply and sewereage systems.     The Agricultural Projects&#13;
Department developed, in collaboration with Israeli experts, an innovative&#13;
system of extension, which was introduced into a number of member countries&#13;
as a loan element, or through a loan solely for that purpose.        But, as I&#13;
said earlier, the great increase in project-related training resulted from&#13;
changes in the nature of Bank lending.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Finally, I must add that a Projects staff member, a cynic, once told me&#13;
that this growth was aided by the fact it increased the foreign exchange&#13;
component of the loan; it did not mean that borrowers were particularly&#13;
committed to the concept of training.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:     At this point we come to an issue that's getting more and more&#13;
current, but you were there, present at the creation, so to speak.          And I'm&#13;
speaking about the environmental aspect of the Bank's work.        In 1970 you&#13;
played a significant role in the selection of the first Environmental&#13;
Adviser in the Office of the Director, Projects.     This was the Bank's first&#13;
significant organizational initiative in what has now become a growing area&#13;
of its concern and involvement in the development process.        In your&#13;
experience, what role, if any, had environmental considerations played in&#13;
the preparation and execution of the project prior to this time.       When I&#13;
say prior to this time I mean, say, roughly 1970.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:    A brief answer to that question is that the Projects Department paid&#13;
close attention to environmental matters when they directly affected the&#13;
success of the project.     Say, for example, you're building a&#13;
&amp;#12;J. A. KING                             -11-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
[KING]&#13;
hydroelectric scheme.      The Bank carefully studied the drainage basin of&#13;
that scheme to determine whether the reservoir that was being built would&#13;
silt up at points and so destroy its utility.      I mean, they would be nuts&#13;
if they didn't do that.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    And in agriculture they paid a lot of attention to the environment in&#13;
terms of making sure that the farmers would have a good crop.      But if the&#13;
environmental consequences of a project only affected it in sort of an&#13;
indirect way, then the Bank really didn't worry about it.      There wasn't&#13;
very much knowledge about environment within the Bank except perhaps among&#13;
the water supply people, and that in public health terms.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:     So it was only how the environmental considerations directly&#13;
affected the success of the project that was of concern.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:    Or the rate of return of the project.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:     And there was no real conscious consideration of some of the&#13;
larger â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:    Issues.   Yes.   For example, I never heard anyone in the Bank at that&#13;
time worry about the seismological consequences of building a very, very&#13;
large reservoir.     Yet as I understand it, there are such consequences.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:     But of course in fairness, too, nobody else, or very few people&#13;
generally at this time in the public at large were thinking in these terms.&#13;
This is something that only concerned a few people at this time.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:    That's fair enough, yes.&#13;
&amp;#12;J. A. KING                             -12-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:   Large scale public concern has only recently come forth.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Could you relate how you personally came to have a hand in the process&#13;
of the selection of the Environmental Adviser?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:   Well, I think there were two reasons.    My family had always been&#13;
very interested in environmental matters and I knew the names of some of&#13;
the players.    That was one factor.   But I think far more important is the&#13;
fact that I was Training Adviser, but ironically I was almost never allowed&#13;
to work on training matters because I was sort of--and this I think is&#13;
typical of the way training was regarded in the Bank â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢    It was vaguely&#13;
believed that people who were working on training weren't really busy and&#13;
they had extra time.    And so I was a man in the front office of the&#13;
Projects Department where the decisions were going to be made.      I knew a&#13;
little about it but really I don't want to stress that point.      And it was&#13;
thought that I had extra time.    It wasn't true.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:   What were some of the considerations that led to the Bank&#13;
establishing the position of Environmental Adviser?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:   Well, as far as I know, there wasn't any great spontaneous movement&#13;
within the Bank saying we've got to do something about this.     Mr. McNamara&#13;
was interested and it was all inspired from the top.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:   Basically it was McNamara's idea, as far as you know?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:   Yes.   And I have heard that he was influenced by his daughter,&#13;
Kathleen, who was working at the time for an organization called the&#13;
Conservation Foundation.    But that I don't know.   It's just my guess.     But&#13;
Mr. McNamara was a very thoughtful man and he was thinking about a lot of&#13;
things that were ahead of most other people, I think.    And he took a direct&#13;
interest in the question of how to deal with the problem.     Sometimes he&#13;
called me on the telephone and asked me what was happening, although in&#13;
Army terms I was a long distance down the chain of command from him.&#13;
&amp;#12;J. A. KING                               -13-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:     It seems to me from a look at the record that you sifted through&#13;
quite a number of candidates, too, in the selection process.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:     Well, when I started--when we all started--we didn't know much about&#13;
what was needed.        And the only way I could think of finding out was to ask&#13;
people, some of whom I knew but most of whom I did not know, and just try&#13;
and identify what kind of person might be needed, what should be the&#13;
criteria for the work, and then talk to them and learn more about them.          It&#13;
was lots of fun.        I learned a hell of a lot.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:     In your experience, were there those in the Bank who perhaps felt&#13;
that the position of Environmental Adviser was unnecessary, or perhaps had&#13;
other dissenting views?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:     Uhh.   Yes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:     In a word.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:     In a word.     Projects, I sympathize with the poor Projects staff&#13;
member.     He is being told that not only does he have to make sure that the&#13;
engineering is good, the economics are sound, the management is capable,&#13;
but then they're asking him to do a whole lot of other things that he&#13;
doesn't know anything about, nobody ever taught him about that when he was,&#13;
let's say, working in a big consulting firm.         And I think it was resistance&#13;
of that type.      "Oh, good Lord, another thing we've got to look at?    And we&#13;
don't know how to do it."       I don't think it was any kind of ill will, but&#13;
they just thought, there's so much to do, how can we do it all?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:     And of course today they're really concerned with the&#13;
environment, there's no question.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:     Yes, yes.&#13;
&amp;#12;J. A. KING                             -14-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:     I can sympathize with the view.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:   But nobody ever, ever said to me we shouldn't do that.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:    Right.    It was more just an additional burden and wondering, in&#13;
fact, whether they were equipped to undertake such a task.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:   Yes.     I remember somewhat similar reaction very early on in my&#13;
career at the Bank.      Mr. Demuth wanted to codify the Bank's practice and&#13;
policy with regard to defaults on external debt, expropriations without&#13;
compensation, and disputes with contractors, between governments and&#13;
contractors working on projects.      And I wrote the first policy paper on&#13;
this subject--with Dick's help, thank goodness.      And when I began to&#13;
talking to staff members about this matter, they really didn't want to hear&#13;
about it.      They just kind of said, go away, go away.   But of course I&#13;
couldn't go away and the problem could.n't go away so we eventually did it.&#13;
But when people have a lot to do, I think that's the way they behave.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:    In the early 1970s the governments of some less developed&#13;
countries seemed to be of the view that the environmental considerations&#13;
were, in a sense, toys of the rich and that they could not afford to take&#13;
these considerations too seriously in that they felt they would result in&#13;
serious impediments to economic development.      Did you experience any&#13;
attitude or any manifestation of this attitude during this time, say around&#13;
1970?   I think you had a continuing involvement for a little while.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:   Yes, but very little after, after Jim [James A.) Lee [the Bank's&#13;
first Environmental Adviser) arrived.      As I say, I had a regular job to do.&#13;
But, no, I think that was very true.      I was not in the field but I remember&#13;
talking to a man from Africa who was in the Bank for negotiations, and he&#13;
said something like this:      "I don't know very much about your history, but&#13;
what I do know is that you never bothered about these issues until most of&#13;
the people in your country had something to eat every day.      Until that&#13;
happens in my country, I can hardly support these efforts.â&#128;¢&#13;
&amp;#12;J. A. KING                            -15-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:   Could you relate the process, the actual process you went through&#13;
to help select the Environmental Adviser and describe some of the&#13;
qualifications that were being looked for.     We touched on this a little bit&#13;
earlier in this discussion, but could we now focus on that?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:   Well.   In the search for the individual, criteria began to emerge&#13;
about the sort of person we should be getting.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:   So the criteria evolved in the course of the search?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:   Of the search, yeah.    Dick's original notion was that we should have&#13;
somebody from an academic background.     And it turned out that these guys&#13;
were very hard to get.     They were, I guess, in general short supply at the&#13;
time and a number of them did not wish to leave their academic career; they&#13;
liked that better.     They didn't want to get into the nitty-gritty of&#13;
operational work in the Bank.     So that idea faded away.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Another idea emerged in the course of these studies.        It seemed to me&#13;
that most of the people in the field came into it from one of two&#13;
backgrounds.    First, an interest in and work related to what you might call&#13;
the conservation     aspects of environmental or ecological work.    And the&#13;
others came in via the public health work.     These were always two distinct&#13;
streams of career.     After we found out people in general were very scarce,&#13;
we happened to run across a man who combined both the public health stream&#13;
and the conservation stream.    And that was Jim Lee.   That essentially is&#13;
why he was selected.     He was by no means our first choice.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:   Could I assume from the record that you sifted through a&#13;
seemingly enormous number of candidates, and his name doesn't come up until&#13;
right at the very end?&#13;
&amp;#12;J. A. KING                            -16-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:   That's right, that's the way it happened.    I really haven't thought&#13;
about it for a long time and I really don't know what the answer is.        And I&#13;
don't know anything about the person who succeeded Jim.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:   That was an active time period because shortly thereafter in 1972&#13;
there was reorganization of the Bank, it's first major reorganization in&#13;
twenty years.     What particular role did you yourself play in the&#13;
reorganization process?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:   Well, I was Secretary of the so-called Steering Committee of the&#13;
reorganization.    McKinsey and Company appointed a team of people to work&#13;
with the Bank.    A number of Bank staff were seconded to work with them, and&#13;
the notion was that that this combination would speed up McKinsey getting&#13;
familiar with what the Bank was doing and how it worked.     The Steering&#13;
Committee, which was chaired by Mr. [Mohamed] Shoaib a Vice President,&#13;
never really steered anything.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    I might mention another thing.     As I understand it, Kim [Edward V. K.]&#13;
Jaycox was going to be Secretary of the Steering Committee, but the powers&#13;
that be decided he couldn't be spared from operational work, so good old&#13;
training suffered once more.     They took me.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:   It would have given Jaycox kind of a practice for his later role&#13;
in 1987 reorganization.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:   I suppose so, but he was then still very young.    He had come in as a&#13;
Young Professional and I think he was a division chief but it was a very,&#13;
very small division.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    But as I say, we met regularly with the kind of senior group of&#13;
McKinsey's staff which was supervising the study.    And they put ideas to us&#13;
and we commented on them and criticized them from our perception of what&#13;
&amp;#12;J. A. KING                            -17-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
[KING]&#13;
the Bank was doing and how it was doing it.     And then they went back with&#13;
those comments and retired to some secret cavern and came up with another&#13;
set of ideas.    It was said, or it was thought by some people on the&#13;
Steering Committee, including me, that we weren't really supposed to steer,&#13;
that we understood that.    Mr. McNamara met fairly regularly with the&#13;
Managing Director of McKinsey and that's where the cookie crumbled,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:    That's where the real steering came in?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:    That's where the steering came from.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:    I've heard it said, for what it's worth, that McKinsey&#13;
essentially told McNamara what he wanted to hear, that McNamara had his own&#13;
ideas and he was basically just looking for some means of legitimization&#13;
through McKinsey and Company.     From your perspective â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:    I would agree with that completely.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Except that I would say that McKinsey told Mr. McNamara what he told&#13;
them to tell him.    But their ideas were timely and worthwhile.     Before the&#13;
reorganization, for example, the agricultural projects staff numbered over&#13;
100, maybe 120, I don't remember, but more than 100.      And the agricultural&#13;
lending was still growing at a rate which could enable it to be increased&#13;
four times in the period sort of the five years, 1968-1973.      If something&#13;
hadn't been done, the Agricultural Projects Department under the Office of&#13;
the Director, Projects would have been, I think, almost unmanageable.&#13;
Because shortly after the reorganization there were I think 500&#13;
agricultural projects officers.    So â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:   You briefly referred to this previously, but would you care to&#13;
say just something about the method of operation of the Steering Committee,&#13;
in terms of just how you sat down and discussed these matters?&#13;
&amp;#12;J. A. KING                              -18-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:    We met, I think, weekly.     And, not the Managing Director of&#13;
McKinsey, but the people just below, a number of whom came to work for the&#13;
Bank after the study, Dick [Richard B.] Lynn, [Bruce] Rohrbacher--those are&#13;
the two I can think of particularly--that level of McKinsey would come in&#13;
and talk to us and tell us what they were thinking about.         And we would&#13;
kind of say, well, we didn't think that would work, or, it will be better&#13;
if you did it with some minor modification.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    I honestly don't recall any major differences, except for Dick Demuth,&#13;
who once or twice had a very strong view on what should or should not be&#13;
done.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:     I think you have come close to answering my next question, that&#13;
is to say that the central recommendation made by McKinsey and Company&#13;
consultants was that the Bank be reorganized along regional lines with five&#13;
regional vice presidents reporting to a senior vice president, operations,&#13;
responsible for the Bank's lending and technical assistance to the&#13;
countries in their respective regions.         Did anybody push for an alternative&#13;
model?     I gather not.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:    Not really, I don't think.     It was all kind of trimming and patching&#13;
up around that model.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:     But the central model was pretty much accepted right from the&#13;
beginning.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:    Yes â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢   I really can't say I remember that absolutely clearly.       I&#13;
do remember one time when Dick got quite mad and held the floor for quite a&#13;
long time.    He's a good talker.     But I can't remember what the issue was.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:     But basically the model was accepted and just, as you say,&#13;
trimmed around the edges.     What was the general reaction of the staff to&#13;
this reorganization? Did they feel it was forced upon them, if you will?&#13;
&amp;#12;J. A. KING                          -19-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:   I can say for sure that a great many Projects staff felt that their&#13;
role in the Bank was being cut back.    And there was quite a loss of morale&#13;
within the Projects Department staff, to that.    Furthermore, the process of&#13;
ressigning Projects staff was painful; feelings were hurt and some left.       I&#13;
do not know, but I imagine that the area staff thought that they were going&#13;
to be much higher on the power ladder, but I couldn't actually tell you&#13;
that as a fact.   To the Projects people I said that as long as the Bank&#13;
continues to lend for projects, your position cannot be very much reduced,&#13;
and that is what happened.   In fact, as a consequence of their&#13;
Regionalisation the Projects staff acquired country knowledge and&#13;
expertise, which, before the reorganization had been the specialty of the&#13;
Area staff.   So, to some extent Projects staff was better off, more&#13;
powerful than before.   And I think it's only when structural adjustment&#13;
loans began that the power of the Projects people was kind of reduced.&#13;
Because this wasn't their game.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:   That attitude, then, didn't, or very likely did not persist for a&#13;
long period of time once they actually got going under the new regime?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:   I think so, but attitudes changed   There was definitely a feeling&#13;
that they couldn't do as good a job under the new regime as they could&#13;
under the old one, and the reason was that in these large projects&#13;
departments there was enormous range of skills of people.    Take for example&#13;
in Transportation.   Under the old scheme you had at least one railways&#13;
division, maybe two, and within those railways divisions you had such&#13;
specialists as signal experts, locomotive experts, and a very wide range of&#13;
skills, so you had in your captive staff almost everything you needed.     And&#13;
when Transportation was Regionalized, what happened to those signalers?&#13;
They went to a Region and maybe never ever did any signals work but just&#13;
did general railroad work.   And I think that people felt that quality was&#13;
really going to go down because of this change.   I'm not sure that it&#13;
really did, but that was the feeling.   And it really is wonderful if you&#13;
&amp;#12;J. A. KING                           -20-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
[KING]&#13;
ean walk two steps down the eorridor and get to the guy who knows more&#13;
about railway finanee than almost anybody in the world and get him to help&#13;
you with your problem.    It's a lovely feeling to have that you've got&#13;
someone handy who understands your problem.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:    And then suddenly he's gone to another part of the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:    Yes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:    And you have no direet eall on his expertise.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:    Right.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:    In your view, what lessons eould be learned from the 1972&#13;
reorganization?    By that I mean the whole proeess, not just how the Bank&#13;
was reorganized, but rather in the way the whole study was undertaken.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:    As far as proeess is eoneerned it was very mueh from the top dowm&#13;
and is not the right way to do things.      But â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:    In other words, you feel that perhaps a greater degree of&#13;
partieipation would have been better--! just want to have a better&#13;
term--would improve the proeess?    For instanee, there was some eonsultation&#13;
with the Staff Assoeiation, whieh was in a very embryonie form â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:    Yes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:    It had been in business for less than a year.   I know the Staff&#13;
Assoeiation partieipated to some eonsiderable degree in the 1987&#13;
reorganization.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:    Oh, I assume so, but in 1972 the Assoeiation was very young.&#13;
&amp;#12;J. A. KING                            -21-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:   Perhaps some sort of staff participation might have been called&#13;
for?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:   I think so but perhaps management perceived the Steering Committee&#13;
as serving this purpose.     In fact, it did not do so and in my view, never&#13;
imagined that it was performing this role.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:   Did this lack affect staff in any way?    I think so, but â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:   I can't tell when it began.    But in the old days, in the Projects&#13;
department where Projects staff worked, you would see people working&#13;
regularly until 7:00 or 8:00, sometimes much later.      After the&#13;
reorganization that began to decline until it seemed as if the building was&#13;
empty at 5:30 or 6:00.     And I wonder if that is a silent comment on the&#13;
reorganization and the way it was done.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:   Do you think that the 1972 reorganization can be characterized as&#13;
a, in quotes, success?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:   Yes, as I say, the existing structure was unmanageable practically.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:   So in your view something had to be done.     I mean, there was&#13;
really no question about that.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:   Yes.   I think there's no question about that.   My gosh, if you look&#13;
at the numbers of staff, at the numbers of projects, and the rates of&#13;
increase of both it just couldn't go on that way.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:   Bernard Chadenet and you coauthored an article, which appeared in&#13;
the September 1972 issue of Finance and Development, entitled "WQat is a&#13;
World Bank Project?"     At one point the article states, and I'm going to&#13;
read a fairly lengthy quotation but, it does get to the heart of what I&#13;
&amp;#12;J. A. KING                             -22-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
[ZIEGLER]&#13;
want to discuss at this point, which is the evolution of the concept of the&#13;
Bank project:&#13;
&#13;
            "A Bank project is â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢ designed â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢ to provide the borrower&#13;
            and the member country with a capital investment which&#13;
            will contribute directly to economic development by&#13;
            providing an adequate rate of return but which will also&#13;
            provide such other benefits as the transfer of knowledge&#13;
            and experience through the introduction of new&#13;
            technology, institutional and policy changes, or social&#13;
            and human development through training and&#13;
            demonstration â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢ [T]hese characteristics tend to give&#13;
            Bank projects a special status in the sector of the&#13;
            economy, and they may appear to require for their&#13;
            implementation disproportionate amounts of scarce&#13;
            resources such as managerial or technical staff, skilled&#13;
            manpower or the attention of the government at a high&#13;
            level. As a result, the Bank is sometimes accused of&#13;
            selfishness and of robbing Peter to pay Paul. But we&#13;
            are convinced that, over the longer term, this&#13;
            concentration of effort produces the impact on the&#13;
            sector that brings catalytic or demonstration benefits&#13;
            that outweigh the short-term costs.â&#128;¢&#13;
&#13;
    Retrospectively, from your experience in Bank projects and observing&#13;
them, are you still convinced, as you said in the article, that the&#13;
benefits outweigh the costs?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:   That's a hard one.    It's pretty close, I think, pretty close.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Incidentally, that article, when Bernard gave it to Warren Baum to&#13;
read, Warren said, "Well, you know, that's what we'd like to say we're&#13;
doing but we're really not quite doing it all; it's an idealised view.&#13;
You're a little ahead of the times.â&#128;¢      And so that definition is somewhat&#13;
idealized.     And I doubt very much whether Projects staff ever thought of&#13;
the projects they were working on in those terms exactly.       I think they had&#13;
much simpler and less philosophical ideas of what a project was.&#13;
&amp;#12;J. A. KING                              -23-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
[KING)&#13;
    Could I interrupt for a second?       I wanted to say one more thing about&#13;
the 1972 reorganization.     In my opinion, the 1972 reorganization spent far&#13;
too much of its efforts on what I would call the appraisal report cycle&#13;
rather than on the project cycle as a whole,         And a lot of the agony that&#13;
the Bank has had in recent years about quality control and so on, and too&#13;
much paperwork and not enough delegation and things like that, arises from&#13;
the fact that the consultants really focused much of their time on the&#13;
wrong problem.     They should have looked at the project cycle as a whole and&#13;
not just at that segment which has to do with getting some papers approved&#13;
by the Board.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:    They should have looked at project implementation as a whole.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:    Yes.   And also with the appraisal report cycle I would define as&#13;
from the moment of the departure of the appraisal mission to Board&#13;
approval.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Both supervision and identification/preparation really need much more&#13;
attention than the appraisal report cycle, in my opinion.        And they are&#13;
getting a little bit more now, I think.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:    That's a useful addition.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    We were just discussing--well, you talked about Warren Baum and how he&#13;
said that the article did not really quite match the reality of how&#13;
projects were designed and implemented.         Is that pretty much what you&#13;
wanted to say there, also?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:    Yes, I think that covers that.    Bernard was a person very much of&#13;
the le formation Francais.    He likes putting things in the large dimension&#13;
and that is not quite the way I think.         But it was a great pleasure to work&#13;
with him on it.&#13;
&amp;#12;J. A. KING                             -24-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:      During your career in the Bank, you had occasion to study the&#13;
evolution in Bank projects from the sort of monolithic, engineering-&#13;
oriented projects, which were the norm in the early years of the Bank, to&#13;
the introduction of multi-faceted policy and demonstration projects later&#13;
on, which were essentially referred to in the previous quotations.         Could&#13;
you relate something of the process of discussion or debate, both within&#13;
the Bank and the development community more generally, that accompanied&#13;
this evolution.      And I dare say Mr. McNamara had a bit to do with it, too,&#13;
as he had some, I gather, pretty definite ideas as to what the Bank should&#13;
be doing.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:      Well, essentially I didn't have too much to do with that.     You could&#13;
see it happening.      And you could sense it in the procurement field because&#13;
the industrialised countries had a much smaller share of total procurement&#13;
under the new projects than they did under the old, although the total&#13;
quantity of funds was increasing.      In agriculture, a great deal of the work&#13;
done locally by small contractors and rural development projects are much&#13;
less equipment-oriented than some of the earlier agricultural projects.         So&#13;
that â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:      Basically, what I'm trying to get at is that the Bank was more&#13;
oriented in its earlier years to the infrastructure-type&#13;
projects--transportation, dams, that sort of thing.      And this, as you&#13;
rightly said earlier on, evolved into greater lending in other sectors.&#13;
Agriculture became the predominant sector, what, around 1974, more or less?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:      More or less.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:      And what sort of process led to this evolution?     People like&#13;
McNamara pushing?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:      We've got to give George Woods a little credit, too.&#13;
&amp;#12;J. A. KING                               -25-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:     Very true.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:     George Woods started the cooperative programs in agriculture and&#13;
education.       I don't think the one with WHO came until later, but the model&#13;
was there and, incidentally, Dick played an enormous role in getting those&#13;
programs started.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:     Dick Demuth?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:     Yes.    I suppose, in the early days it was hoped, maybe even&#13;
expected, that if you could build solid infrastructure, good power, good&#13;
roads, good harbors, good railways, that the rest of it would take care of&#13;
itself.     We were not finding that to be true, in fact, and so we began, of&#13;
necessity, to think of things like training or development of local human&#13;
capabilities.       And it just sort of grew.   A wasn't enough, so you'd better&#13;
add a little A-plus.        Then maybe you ought to try B.   In those years you&#13;
have quite a few projects where the Bank was really doing something for the&#13;
first time.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    The guys that were here in the early days didn't know much about â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢&#13;
They certainly didn't know anything about training, but they sure knew how&#13;
to build bridges and roads and railways.        That is what they had been doing.&#13;
And the consultant firms in those days really consisted of nothing but&#13;
engineers.       They were consulting engineers.   They weren't consulting&#13;
economists, they were consulting engineers.        And so like in so many things,&#13;
you did what you knew how to do.        So we started with that and we kind of&#13;
found that that didn't seem to be a complete answer and then kept adding on&#13;
all these trimmings.      And then when you add to that concern for the poor,&#13;
and you add the whole other set of issues--and let me add that designing a&#13;
project where the benefits really will go to the poor is a very, very&#13;
difficult thing to do.       This from my IFAD [International Fund for&#13;
Agricultural Development] experience.&#13;
&amp;#12;J. A. KING                            -26-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
[KING]&#13;
    It's really tough.     !FAD had a provision in its articles that said not&#13;
only did we have to do all the things that the Bank does in terms of&#13;
evaluating a project, but we also had to make sure that the project&#13;
benefits did not go disproportionately to the richer farmers.      That's not&#13;
the exact wording, but that's the idea.      That is a hard one to live up to,&#13;
very hard.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:     To boil it down, then, assuming that the Bank realized that the&#13;
traditional infrastructure projects were not the whole answer to economic&#13;
development and therefore it started activities in other sectors â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:    Yes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:     â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢ as part of the evolutionary process of trying to get&#13;
development going in less developed countries.     Is that a fair summation?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:    That's a fair summation.   And Mr. McNamara certainly played an&#13;
important role.     He became very, very keen on population planning and he&#13;
pushed that one.     On a purely mathematical basis.   It doesn't do any good&#13;
to increase the gross national product if the gross national population is&#13;
growing 10 percent faster.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:     There was another article that you wrote after the 1972&#13;
reorganization, when you became the Assistant to the Vice President,&#13;
Central Projects, who was Warren Baum at that time.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:    Yes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:     The article, in the June 1975 issue of Finance and Development,&#13;
was entitled "Procurement Under World Bank Projects.â&#128;¢     And in this article&#13;
you examine, I think very well, if my comments are worth anything, the&#13;
&amp;#12;J. A. KING                              -27-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
[ZIEGLER]&#13;
history of the procurement process and in addition you respond to various&#13;
criticisms of that process that have been made, such as the complaint that&#13;
various countries have not been getting their, in quotes, fair share of&#13;
procurement contracts.      Is there anything more to be added to what you&#13;
wrote in this article that might further our understanding of the history&#13;
of the procurement process as conducted by the Bank, and its responses to&#13;
the criticisms of that process?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:   Well.    I personally feel the Bank had handled the procurement thing&#13;
really rather well and that the critics, when closely examined, are&#13;
standing on the very weak ground that they're not making as much money as&#13;
they would like.      Procurement, however, is a very important political issue&#13;
and the procurement lobby can hamper IDA replenishment and has indeed done&#13;
that.   I recall reading the report of the Parliamentary subcommittee&#13;
dealing with IDA replenishment.       This was very early in the days of IDA.&#13;
The speaker was quoted as saying â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:    Which country was this?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:   Britain.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER: This was the British Parliament?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:   Yes.    The speaker said, "And remember, gentlemen, that for every&#13;
pound of Britain's contribution to IDA, we have gotten two pounds back in&#13;
procurement."      The reason for that was, of course, India and Pakistan got a&#13;
very large proportion of the IDA moneys and by tradition they did most of&#13;
their shopping in the U.K., if they didn't make it themselves.       But it was&#13;
true in those early days.      So procurement could be a plus but more often&#13;
it's a minus because in general more and more developing countries&#13;
developed the capacity to do some of these things, to provide some of these&#13;
&amp;#12;J. A. KING                              -28-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
[KING]&#13;
things â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢      I mean, when I wrote that article I never would have guessed in&#13;
a million years that Korea would become the major civil works contractor in&#13;
the Bank's docket of such contractors, but things changed, the pie still is&#13;
large but many, many more people are sharing it, it's a touchy and&#13;
difficult subject.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:      But in your view the Bank has handled the procurement process&#13;
quite well over the years?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:    Quite well, in my judgment.     Yes.   But a lot of the countries don't&#13;
like international competitive bidding.         I mean, the supplying countries,&#13;
because â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢      The French don't like it at all and take a very different&#13;
position.       They â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:      They would prefer tied aid of some sort.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:    Yes.     At one point, in connection with the procurement work, I was&#13;
working on the terms of aid provided bilaterally.        And at an international&#13;
meeting I heard the representative of France say, "It doesn't make any&#13;
difference what the terms of aid are as long as our suppliers get enough&#13;
contracts.â&#128;¢       In other words, they would be willing to give more money to&#13;
pay for these higher prices, as long as they got their share of it.         And in&#13;
the former French colonies you will find for example the price of&#13;
telecommunications equipment almost twice that of the market level for that&#13;
kind of equipment.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:      Is there anything else you'd care to add on the procurement&#13;
question?       I think that article did cover it fairly well, in fact very&#13;
well, but I'd like to make sure there's nothing else you'd like to bring up&#13;
on the subject.&#13;
&amp;#12;J. A. KING                            -29-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:    Only perhaps that that's another ease where the Training Adviser&#13;
that was used.     I did not work on training for a couple of years.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:     You began your career in the Bank during the presidency of George&#13;
Woods.     Did you have much contact with him?    Of course the Bank was a lot&#13;
smaller then than it was even when you left.       And would you care to say&#13;
something about your views concerning his presidency?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:    I don't think I had any contact with him on a one-to-one basis.        As&#13;
I said earlier, I think he was more of an innovator than he's given credit&#13;
for being.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:     I've heard this said also.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:    I think that staff in general did not like him very much.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:     Again, I've heard that said also.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:    I can't really figure out why.   But at one time the management was&#13;
making changes in travel policies, mostly economies, by reducing the amount&#13;
of first class travel, and Mr. Woods went down to explain it to staff, who&#13;
weren't getting all the perks that they were used to for travel.       And it&#13;
almost ended in a fist fight.     I don't think that the people that were&#13;
objecting to this were wholly right, either.       But I really can't make&#13;
comments beyond that about Mr. Woods.     I was very much a new boy when he&#13;
was there.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:     He also had the, if you will, misfortune of succeeding an&#13;
extremely popular President, Eugene Black.       Of course, you weren't under&#13;
the Black regime.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:    No, but I know it was different, I know it was different.     And I'm&#13;
sure that has a lot to do with it.&#13;
&amp;#12;J. A. KING                              -30-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:     I gather Black would have been a hard act to follow for anybody.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:     I think so.    I wonder what would have happened if Mr. McNamara had&#13;
followed Mr. Black.       It might have been just as bad.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:     Or worse.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:     Or worse.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:     Well, of course McNamara was not always universally beloved&#13;
either.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:     Oh, I don't think McNamara was universally loved, and his manner was&#13;
sort of distant and cool.      He wasn't easy and warm, but I would have&#13;
thought that most staff had a very high regard for his sense of purpose,&#13;
his concept of what he wanted to do, and his really very great&#13;
intelligence.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:     There was some concern I remember that McNamara would set these&#13;
targets, which is all very well, but you would hear these rumblings--I'm&#13;
sure you heard them, too--that the quality of the projects is&#13;
deteriorating, and the quality doesn't matter as long as you get them&#13;
through the pipeline and get them to the Board and signed and don't worry&#13;
about it.     Is there anything to that?    I've seen items you've written where&#13;
you expressed concern about project quality, not in particular projects but&#13;
simply the need for quality projects.       So maybe this is something you'd be&#13;
sensitive to.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:     Some of Mr. McNamara's mechanics for keeping the pipeline full and&#13;
getting projects in the pipeline approved and lent were exceedingly&#13;
unpopular and were criticized as threatening project quality.      And some of&#13;
these mechanics I think maybe were excessive.       But I have to sympathize&#13;
&amp;#12;J. A. KING                            -31-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
[KING]&#13;
with Mr. McNamara because he did feel obligated to keep the levels of&#13;
lending up and going up.     And to do that you've got to do some of these&#13;
things.     Whether quality was ever jeopardized, I don't know.   The quality&#13;
issue was one of the very, very difficult ones.     Davidson Sommers in the&#13;
course of a discussion of this question--he was on the Steering Committee&#13;
in the 1972 reorganization, and a very, very great man in my&#13;
opinion--wondered whether we were becoming too quality conscious.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
There are several ways in which you can talk about this.     One of the things&#13;
that has always troubled me about quality--and this is perhaps because I'm&#13;
not an economist--was the efforts that went into calculating the rate of&#13;
return on the project.     And, boy, they refined it down to the last decimal&#13;
point.     Really, there are other things that may be more important.     If the&#13;
project is delayed for some inadequacy in the appraisal for, say, eight&#13;
months or longer, your rate of return goes out the window, and you haven't&#13;
got it.     So why spend all this time in these refined calculations?     And why&#13;
not focus on better schemes for project implementation?     But rates of&#13;
return, once you make the assumptions, can be calculated and some people&#13;
like to do it and so it gets done.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:     It's usually a number to hang on to.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:     Yes, yes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Of course my view is very much colored by my experience and training.&#13;
In project work people like to do what they know how to do, and if they're&#13;
asked to do something else they either won't do it at all or spend much&#13;
less time on it than it requires and was intended.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    I can give a little example of this in one case.     The Bank had a&#13;
project in Somalia, a highway project, and the primary purpose of the&#13;
&amp;#12;J. A. KING                               -32-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
[KING]&#13;
project was to develop a new department of highways; there hadn't been one&#13;
before.     And the purpose of the project was to establish and get started a&#13;
highways department.     Incidentally, there were also 60 kilometers of road&#13;
to be built.     And time after time supervision revealed that the road was&#13;
going along okay but very little was happening in the way of creating a&#13;
highway department.     For one thing, no Somali wanted to go to the field;&#13;
they preferred living in the city.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    At any rate, the person responsible for the project finally said we've&#13;
got to do something about this now.        So a project staff officer that was&#13;
sent down to supervise the consultants who were doing the training and&#13;
institution building, to make sure they were doing it right, and so on.           He&#13;
was told to spend virtually all of his time doing nothing but that, but if&#13;
he had an extra half day somewhere, he was to look into a problem of&#13;
alignment of this road that was being built between two cities.        Their&#13;
names I can no longer remember, but they had the great good fortune of&#13;
starting with A and B, so you could say the road from A to B, which always&#13;
appealed to me.     What happens?     The guy goes down there and for the first&#13;
eight days of his mission he works on the alignment of the highway and then&#13;
in the afternoon of the eighth day he's flying back to Washington, he goes&#13;
and kind of looks at what's happening in the training and institution&#13;
building part of the project.       He knew how to align a highway, but he&#13;
didn't know how to do the institution building.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:     Do you have any general or overall observations about McNamara's&#13;
presidency?     Because I know you had said to me you are generally an admirer&#13;
of him.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:     I'm a tremendous admirer.    I think he's a great man.&#13;
&amp;#12;J. A. KING                            -33-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
[KING]&#13;
       Have you ever read The Development Philosophy of Robert S. McNamara by&#13;
Jack [John L.] Maddux?     I thought it was beautiful.    But when McNamara's&#13;
name first was proposed, I thought, my goodness, that's going to be odd.&#13;
It's the first Bank President we've had that doesn't come from Wall Street,&#13;
and raising money is a terribly important part of the Bank's work.       I&#13;
wonder how they're going to do it.     But at least, says I to myself, we'll&#13;
have an executive who's going to be a great manager.       And I couldn't have&#13;
been more wrong, in both respects I think.       Certainly he was very creative&#13;
and imaginative in finding new ways to raise money that nobody had ever&#13;
thought of before.     The postal savings banks in Europe and other entirely&#13;
new sources of funds.     And I don't think he was a terribly good manager.&#13;
I cited the thing of his not going through the chain of command to talk to&#13;
me.     I don't think that's good management.    And he did other things like&#13;
that.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:    He liked to consult individuals, almost a kitchen cabinet, at&#13;
least as I understand it.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:    Yes, maybe.   But he can only be listed as a great President of the&#13;
Bank, for all those new departures that the Bank made under his leadership.&#13;
He's a great man, in my book.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:    Well, we've covered everything that I wanted to cover today, but&#13;
is there anything else that we've not covered in this interview you care to&#13;
add?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:    I've talked about Dick Demuth a lot.    He was a wonderful person to&#13;
work for and he, I think, has not gotten the credit he deserves for his&#13;
leadership role in shaping the Bank in its formative years.        He always had&#13;
a lot of ideas and he was able to persuade Presidents of the Bank to accept&#13;
them.    Just think of the things that he did:     IFC; the Consultative Group&#13;
&amp;#12;J. A. KING                            -34-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
[KING]&#13;
for International Agricultural Research; the cooperative programs; and a&#13;
lot of much, much smaller things.     I just think he's a very wonderful and&#13;
important person.     He really thought of the Bank as a whole and what would&#13;
be best for the Bank as a whole to make it a better development&#13;
institution, and not only in his own department.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER:    Okay.   Thank you very much, John.   I appreciate it.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KING:    Well, I enjoyed it.   Thank you.&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="17973714">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1989/05/17973714/transcript-oral-history-interview-john-king-held-may-18-1989
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1989/05/17973714/transcript-oral-history-interview-john-king-held-may-18-1989</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1989/05/17973714/transcript-oral-history-interview-john-king-held-may-18-1989</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2006-10-27T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2006-10-27T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2013/07/08/000356161_20130708160129/Rendered/INDEX/790570TRN0King0terview0May018001989.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2013/07/08/000356161_20130708160129/Rendered/PDF/790570TRN0King0terview0May018001989.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>1989-05-18T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2013-07-08T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Transcript of oral history interview with
            John A. King held on May 18, 1989
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            In March 1989, John A. King was
            interviewed on behalf of the World Bank Group Archives oral
            history program by Charles Ziegler. During his tenure at the
            Bank from 1963 to 1978, Mr. King worked in the following
            areas: in the development service department as a policy
            planning officer (1963-1970); in the projects department as
            training advisor (1970-1972) and as assistant to the vice
            president (1972-1978). In 1978 he left the World Bank to
            join the International Fund for Agricultural Development.
            His transcript concerns his interest in how environmental
            factors influence economics, the growth of the projects
            department under the presidency of Robert McNamara, and the
            reorganization of the World Bank in 1972 for which he was a
            secretary on the steering committee.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Transcript of oral history interview with
            John A. King held on May 18, 1989
        </docna>
        <display_title>Transcript of oral history
            interview with John A. King held on May 18, 1989</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/1989/05/17973714/transcript-oral-history-interview-john-king-held-may-18-1989</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Transcript</docty>
        <subtopic>Banks &amp; Banking Reform,ICT Policy and Strategies,Housing &amp; Human Habitats,Corporate Law,Sustainable Land and Crop Management</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Rural Development,Law and Development,Information and Communication Technologies,Communities and Human Settlements</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000356161_20130708160129</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>World Bank Group Archives oral history program</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Rural Development,Law and Development,Information and Communication Technologies,Communities and Human Settlements</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Board Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            architects, Bank earnings, chain of command,
            cities, collaboration, Company, competitive bidding,
            contractors, debt, demonstration projects, Economic
            Development, economic sectors, engineers, farmers, foreign
            exchange, individuals, institutional development, programs,
            Public Utilities, reorganization, rural development,
            savings, savings banks, structural adjustment, technical
            assistance, telecommunications, telecommunications
            equipment, water supply
        </keywd>
        <owner>Knowledge &amp; Information Services (ITSKI)</owner>
        <repnb>79057</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT for Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies (ICT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Science and Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banks and Banking Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Railways Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crops</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Research and Extension</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Extension</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture Information Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>External Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banks &amp; Banking Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Engineering</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Growth and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply</ml:concept><ml:concept>Railways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Highways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Innovation Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT and Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Drainage</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>