<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>﻿                                                   79087&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   THE WORLD BANK GROUP ARCHIVES&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         ORAL HISTORY PROGRAM&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          Transcript of interview with&#13;
&#13;
               JlJLES W. MUIS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
              September 14, 2000&#13;
               Washington, D.C.&#13;
&#13;
Interview by: William H. Becker &amp; Marie T. Zenni&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                    1&#13;
&#13;
BECKER: I'm Bill Becker with the Business History Group.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: And I'm Marie Zenni, task manager of the Oral History Program.&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: And I'm Jules Muis, just retired from the Bank as Vice President and Controller, seven&#13;
to eight days now.&#13;
&#13;
BECKER: Well, congratulations.&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: "Retired from the Bank," which doesn't mean "retired".&#13;
&#13;
BECKER: No! We understand that. Well, it's a pleasure to meet you and to conduct this&#13;
interview. Today is Thursday, the fourteenth of September, 2000. Mr. Muis, we'd like to begin&#13;
by asking just a few questions about your background. Where were you born?&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: I was born in Purmerend, which at the time was a little cattle town north of Amsterdam,&#13;
and right in the middle of the war in 1943.&#13;
&#13;
BECKER: And where did you receive your early schooling, in that place?&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: No. We moved immediately after the war to the south of Holland, from the north to the&#13;
south--big difference between the two. The north is Calvinistic with a life philosophy of, "If it&#13;
doesn't hurt, it can't be good!" And the south is Burgundian Catholic, basically saying, "There's&#13;
always Friday for confession." My father was a Calvinist, and my mother was a Catholic.&#13;
&#13;
BECKER: I see! And where did you prefer to live?&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: I felt at ease, probably a little better "dans rna peau" in the south.&#13;
&#13;
BECKER: Where did you receive your formal training?&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: I had my formal training in the south, unless you mean my professional training.&#13;
&#13;
BECKER: Yes, your professional training.&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: Mainly in Amsterdam, not in the university classes as it took about ten to fifteen years in&#13;
the Netherlands to get qualified as a professional accountant. There were two ways, one of&#13;
which is the academic way. I did it the most expedient way. Instead of first getting my doctoral&#13;
in economics and then doing a three to five year post-doctoral study, I hardly went to class. I&#13;
simply went to the university library and for my exams. I did that for about six or seven years&#13;
while at the same time working for Ernst and Young--or Whinney Murray, Ernst and Ernst, as it&#13;
was called in those days. So that meant that I was qualified when I was 27 rather than the&#13;
average 35. And it also meant that I could make some money in the meantime, and so that's&#13;
                                        Jules W. Muis&#13;
                                September 14, 2000 - Final edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                  2&#13;
&#13;
what I did.&#13;
&#13;
BECKER: I see. Were there early experiences that influenced your later career? I mean, were&#13;
there members of your family that had been in the accounting profession?&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: No. I've always been very interested in the business of transparency, and accounting is&#13;
really a much more unique way of looking at the world than people think. You have not only the&#13;
still picture, balance sheet, and "snapshot" of a company every year, every quarter, or at the end&#13;
of each month, but also the "moving picture;" the income statement; it is a very fascinating piece&#13;
of information. If you really look at the life cycle of an organization, accounting is a very, very&#13;
condensed form of real life experience of companies. I've always been fascinated by that, never&#13;
as in looking back as an historian of events, but as an analytical tool.&#13;
&#13;
BECKER: Okay, and so you began with the predecessor of what is today Ernst and Young?&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: No. At first I started as an internal auditor with Phillips, and then I had my military&#13;
draft. I was still in Holland. And after military service I started with Time Life to subsequently&#13;
do exactly the opposite: join the auditor of Time Life which was Whinney Murray, Ernst and&#13;
Ernst. Mostly, accounting careers go the other way around, from an auditor to the client. I went&#13;
from a client to the auditor. I got six to seven years of experience in the Anglo-American&#13;
philosophy of accounting and auditing. And then I joined a European accounting group for&#13;
about six to seven years in the '70s where I got my European grooming. After that I rejoined&#13;
Ernst and Young for a fantastic job which was called "Director Quality Control" for Europe and&#13;
for Africa.&#13;
&#13;
BECKER: What year was that?&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: That was in '79-80 until '82. I subsequently became managing partner of Ernst and&#13;
Whinney in the Netherlands, which was followed by various mergers. In the early '90s I became&#13;
executive partner of Ernst &amp; Young, Europe, for the merged practice of Ernst and Whinney and&#13;
Arthur Young, which had about 25,000 people in Europe. It was a fantastic period where one&#13;
had to bring two cultures together, which was just after the iron curtain had fallen, so under very,&#13;
very spectacular circumstances.&#13;
&#13;
BECKER: What in your career most prepared you for what you came to face at the Bank? In&#13;
other words, what would you consider to have been the most valuable previous experience?&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: I've always worked in a strongly multicultural environment. I've always worked&#13;
professionally in a very diverse environment. I was 50 at the time and felt I'd done everything in&#13;
the public accounting profession that I could possibly do. I had been president of the Dutch&#13;
Institute of CPAs, and within my firm I'd had all the positions that I aspired to. I'd always&#13;
planned to have a different license to life, and I happened to see on television the big&#13;
demonstrations against the Bank in Madrid of "Fifty Years Is Enough!" This happened actually&#13;
                                            Jules W. M uis&#13;
                                September 14, 2000 - Final edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                      3&#13;
&#13;
the year that I turned 50, and I said to my wife, "Maybe there's something to it!" And so I&#13;
resigned from the firm. I had a two-year notice time and worked with major clients, and so I had&#13;
two years to think about it.&#13;
&#13;
And in those two years the opportunity for the World Bank came up. I received a phone call&#13;
from a head hunter who I knew quite well, and he said, "The president of the World Bank invites&#13;
you to become vice president and controller of the World Bank.&#13;
&#13;
And I said, "Oh, that's an easy way of getting a job, but also very fascinating."&#13;
&#13;
And so I came to Washington for my interviews and found that the president of the World Bank&#13;
had invited ten more people to become vice president and controller of the World Bank. It&#13;
turned out to be a real recruitment process at age fifty, which is really quite an experience to go&#13;
through. It's the last thing that you actually prepare yourself for. And so there was a shootout&#13;
between the ten. I interviewed with about ten VPs [vice presidents]. Two of us were short-&#13;
listed, which I heard about ten days later, and so we were called in again to talk to the president&#13;
for his final call. At least I found out who the other short-listed person was--it was a Frenchman-&#13;
-because the recruitment department had by mistake sent his letter and itinerary to my hotel&#13;
room.&#13;
&#13;
I met with Lew [Lewis T.] Preston, and we hit it off very, very well. And so we talked for about&#13;
two and a half hours instead of the originally scheduled half hour. I think it was one of the most&#13;
frank and finest discussions I've ever had with anyone in the Bank. Well, he had been with the&#13;
Bank for two, three years, and I didn't know he was seriously ill. It was very clear to me that he&#13;
had come to a juncture of conclusions on how he wanted to run the Bank. Everything in the&#13;
Bank was done in a "power behind the throne" way. You had the Ernie [Ernest] Stem and&#13;
Moeen Qureshi competing tribes in those days; a very binary construct which, fortunately, I&#13;
never had to take sides on. I understand they were both very strong and very good people,&#13;
basically very, very skilled.&#13;
&#13;
Anyway, Lew had concluded that there were "no controls at the Bank," as he put it; a frankness&#13;
that surprised me. He hadn't hired me yet, and so I had my first disagreement with my future&#13;
boss because I basically told him, "It can't be that there are no controls at the Bank. It is too big&#13;
for that. And yes, you may have had your control problems with the building complex and&#13;
overruns, etcetera, but there has to be a solid start-out base." He still hired me. And that's what&#13;
my opening shot was when I joined the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
I've dealt with very difficult clients in my career in the public accounting sector as well as with&#13;
very difficult staff or managerial situations, and I think those were two very important elements&#13;
that helped me deal with, or prepare myself for, the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
BECKER: And this was '94-'9 5?&#13;
&#13;
                                        Jules W. Muis&#13;
                                September 14, 2000 - Final edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                        4&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: It was the end of '94. I joined the Bank in February '95.&#13;
&#13;
BECKER: And this had to do perhaps with the conclusion and recommendations of the [Willi&#13;
W. A.] Wapenhans Report, the next steps?&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: No, I think that my appointment had to do with the confusion and embarrassment of the&#13;
adverse publicity as a result of the overrun of the budget on the main complex building. That&#13;
was really what triggered it. The Bank actually before that had never thought about a conceptual&#13;
approach to controls; it was very process driven with no philosophy, and it never had a&#13;
professional accountant as a controller for the 50       that it existed. We have never had an en ~&#13;
             rofessional, alt                                                                  ~ ~&#13;
                                                                                                2&#13;
                                                                                                u&#13;
                                                                                                c:l::&#13;
          The Bank has never had a professional controller, like the IMF [International&#13;
Monetary Fund], which still doesn't have one.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: I'm not sure that they want one.&#13;
                                                                                                &lt;&#13;
                                                                                                0&#13;
                                                                                                ~&#13;
                                                                                                ..,         -&#13;
                                                                                                            ~   6&#13;
                                                                                                                ·:fr&#13;
                                                                                                                ~&#13;
                                                                                                                  :::&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: Well, the Bank may not, either. I'm sure there are a lot of people in the Bank who didn't&#13;
want one, either. In the beginning stages I had great difficulties in getting through to the Bank's&#13;
establishment of what a controllership is all about. So that's the long winded answer to your very&#13;
concise question.&#13;
&#13;
BECKER: No, that's a fine answer. Now, Lew Preston in his last months was almost absent&#13;
from the Bank. So you came into the Bank when the person you were working for was very ill&#13;
and very much not on the scene?&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: Right.&#13;
&#13;
BECKER: So when President [James D.] Wolfensohn came in, did he have different&#13;
expectations for you?&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: I think Jim at that time took the assumption of good controls as a working hypothesis.&#13;
That was his premise, which I think was quite understandable. I mean, he wanted first to look at&#13;
the business dynamics of the Bank since he was accustomed from his previous jobs to believe&#13;
that there are proper controls in place, also at the Bank. I had very early on a discussion with&#13;
him and told him that this was not altogether the case so, in other words, that we had a major&#13;
problem. And I had written my kind of "opening balance sheet" within two months after I&#13;
joined. And one of my notes, I think, to Richard Frank is in the book on the Muis Musings.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: Yes, the issues memoranda?&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: Yeah, the issues memoranda. After two months Controllers also wrote the piece on our&#13;
budget systems and budget controls, which is called "Reinvigorating the Planning and Budgeting&#13;
                                        Jules W. Muis&#13;
                               September 14, 2000- Final edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                  5&#13;
&#13;
Process." That's a very interesting document. That's the only document where I feel the Bank has&#13;
not responded to my concerns. When Jim first came in April 1995, he listened to me.&#13;
&#13;
I only worked with Lew Preston for about two to three weeks, no more. I had a second lunch&#13;
with him in March, and I again told him after three weeks, "Lew, your base opening statement&#13;
that there are no controls at the Bank is not right. There are controls at the Bank; they are just&#13;
too formalistic, process driven. We have done away with thinking; everything is in terms of tick&#13;
marks and process, a process construct which makes it look as if things are under proper control,&#13;
but one is simply missing out on a lot of important stuff. You've got some very good people&#13;
there, but it is not designed in a way controls should actually work." I also discovered very, very&#13;
quickly that if I had to convince the other part of the senior management team, like the MDs&#13;
[Managing Directors], and that I would get absolutely nowhere because I think they were either&#13;
not aware or not serious about the type of controls I was talking about.&#13;
&#13;
And so at my first Audit Committee meeting in March, by surprise I put COSO [Committee of&#13;
Sponsoring Organizations of the Treadway Commission] on the table (after a first faint and&#13;
failed attempt by Internal Audit in 1994) and basically told the Audit Committee about COSO. I&#13;
told them that it was a controls philosophy drawing from the lessons of the financial calamities in&#13;
the '80s and '90s and that the good thing about COSO is that it recognized that 50 percent of&#13;
good controls is understanding organizational behavior, which was the element missing in the&#13;
Bank's controls. We had all the debits and credits and tick marks, etcetera, under control. On&#13;
paper these looked very good; the flow charts looked absolutely perfect, but if you don't have a&#13;
thinking organization where people not just say, "We've done everything that we should do in&#13;
terms of tick marks," but they also sit and ask themselves, "Well, but is it right?"&#13;
&#13;
BECKER: Or effective.&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: Or effective. And if people who do that are being labeled trouble makers or wave&#13;
causers--and we don't want waves at the Bank--then you've got the wrong control mentality.&#13;
needed COSO also for a second reason which I did not state at that particular moment, but&#13;
COSO is an empowerment philosophy. It basically gives controllers unfettered access t-o all&#13;
units, which you need to have for a responsible sign off on the financial statements of the Bank.&#13;
Controllers in those days had no substantive access even to Treasury. They had no access to&#13;
Operations. It just was locked into its own box, an aggregation function with a Chief Accountant&#13;
as driver, not a Controller.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: Didn't interface with many other units in the Bank?&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: Right. It was locked into its own box and basically ticked and checked. It was an&#13;
aggregation function of everything else that came out of--for controls purposes--a very&#13;
decentralized Bank, with each unit having their own controller with no reporting lines to a&#13;
central controller, which explains the controls dynamics metaphor used by one of my accounting&#13;
directors: "Twenty dogs wagging one tail or twenty tails wagging one dog?" And I realized that&#13;
                                          Jules W. M uis&#13;
                                September 14, 2000- Final edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                     6&#13;
&#13;
I would never get where I needed to be through normal negotiations because fragmentation was&#13;
so embedded in the culture of the Bank. It was so part and parcel of the power base of the Bank&#13;
that I had to have a concept with which I could actually say, "Listen, guys, this is my signing off,&#13;
the only sign off I have on the financial statements, and I'm taking it seriously. And I will not&#13;
sign off to my President, my auditors, the Board [ofExecutive Directors] or the Audit Committee&#13;
unless I'm satisfied that I understand what's going on underneath."&#13;
&#13;
And so when the Audit Committee--not yet quite understanding what COSO meant other than&#13;
my verbal presentation--signed off on it, I didn't have to negotiate essentials with my senior&#13;
management.&#13;
&#13;
And when Jim Wolfensohn joined he was, of course, very preoccupied with other pressing&#13;
matters. He wasn't even at the Bank at the time we first discussed and agreed on COSO. I did&#13;
mention my COSO push to him in an informal orientation meeting for the new incoming&#13;
president that I had with him in April 1995. I didn't ask his approval. I basically told him that&#13;
it's probably the only major move I've made where I've asked no one's approval but went straight&#13;
to the Audit Committee and made sure that they reasonably understood what it was about. I&#13;
didn't probably explain all the repercussions that it would have, but I knew it was for the good of&#13;
the Bank to have COSO, which at the time was introduced by regulatory imposition to America's&#13;
large banks. So it's not exactly a self-centered or a self-interest inspired move. It was a move&#13;
really in the interest of the Bank, because the Bank did run a tremendousl y high risk in not just&#13;
its weak management controls but also in its financial controls. And if financial controls screw&#13;
up, then the Bank's reputation in the marketplace, as you know, will just go to the dogs. And&#13;
that means higher interest rates and probably a different market rating, and that would be&#13;
absolutely disastrous. I think there were very few people at the Bank at that moment that really&#13;
had the overview and understood the risks the Bank was taking.&#13;
&#13;
BECKER: Wasn't there a procurement scandal in 1995?&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: Well, the standard slogan in the Bank was, and Jim Wolfensohn heard it, and I heard it,&#13;
"We've never had any fraud or corruption at the Bank." Informally, people would say, "Well, we&#13;
had a few cases, but then we, you know, we dealt with that internally." And so in terms offraud&#13;
and corruption--I'm not talking about weak controls that could screw up your numbers; I'm&#13;
talking about fraud and corruption--I needed proof; I needed to prove that this state of denial was&#13;
a case of the Emperor's clothes.&#13;
&#13;
We have a processing unit in accounts receivable, accounts payable, expense reports, etcetera,&#13;
where we very early on introduced, through COSO, the concept of a " thinking organization;"&#13;
i.e., do not just check and go through a check list, but actually think, including validity testing as&#13;
it's called. And this was just done by very informal training, helping each other and saying,&#13;
"Let's after each step stand back and see whether it makes sense." And one unit noted a rather&#13;
unusual movement in the accounts receivable/payables of a budget officer in operations. And so&#13;
we had the great luck of finding a fraud at the launching phase of COSO that went back about&#13;
                                           Jules W. Muis&#13;
                                 September 14, 2000 - Final edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                    7&#13;
&#13;
eight years. It was a couple of months after I came to the Bank and with some luck discovered&#13;
through my accounting unit. (Frauds and corruption mostly are not uncovered by designated&#13;
controllers or auditors; they're mostly discovered by colleagues). This one was uncovered by&#13;
one of my people probing and questioning intelligently. The fraud concerned a budget officer&#13;
who had run off with about $600,000 over eight years. It's nothing dramatic for the Bank's&#13;
financial statements, but it was an enormously powerful signal and wake up call to the&#13;
establishment of the Bank that the existing structure didn't work.&#13;
&#13;
Yet no one felt responsible. I remember the meetings that I had with Gautam Kaji, Caio Koch-&#13;
Weser and Jessica Einhorn. Jim had just put out all these good words about accountability:&#13;
"We're going to hold people accountable "etc        etcetera. So we looked around the table at&#13;
who's       to be held accountable.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                        ~&#13;
                                                                                                        c:::»&#13;
                                                                                                        c-....&#13;
managerial responsibility.                                                                              c-....&#13;
                                                                                                         c:::»&#13;
So I said, "I will take responsibility. I mean, I'm the Controller, and ultimately it is my             ~         c:&#13;
                                                                                                        0...      0&#13;
responsibility."                                                                                        &lt;(       -;::1&#13;
                                                                                                                  fr&#13;
This gave me a very powerful lever to put other changes through, such as getting the controllers                 ~&#13;
of the units to report to me and to get the controllers ofthe units to actively take responsibility&#13;
for their budget officers. As already said, there were no sensible reporting lines in place. We&#13;
had decentralized ourselves out of organic existence such that even within the decentralized units&#13;
there was no feeling of responsibility for one another.&#13;
&#13;
So the question then came up in this meeting--1'11 never forget that everybody was going for the&#13;
exits in terms of accountability--"What do we tell Jim, because Jim wants blood?" And, "Jim&#13;
takes this much too seriously."&#13;
&#13;
Jim called the Board in an informal meeting to tell them--which, I think, given the size of the&#13;
fraud, may have been overdone. But then it was the first acknowledged fraud in the Bank, and it&#13;
did hit the Washington Post, etcetera.&#13;
&#13;
So when we were sitting around Jim's conference table and discussing who should take&#13;
responsibility for it and I said, "Well, I'll do it!" there weren't many protests.&#13;
&#13;
And they said, "Well, that sounds very good. The controller takes responsibility for it."&#13;
&#13;
 I could easily do that, even though it went back eight years, originating long before my time. I&#13;
was the new controller, so I had functional responsibility, a concept no one then knew how to&#13;
handle.&#13;
&#13;
So what I did, basically, was to draft myself the note of admonishment that Jim Wolfensohn had&#13;
                                          Jules W. M uis&#13;
                                September 14, 2000 - Final edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                   8&#13;
&#13;
to send to me and gave it to Jessica, who changed a few words and then gave it to Jim. I think&#13;
Jim never realized that it was drafted by me. I assume he was never told. And so when the&#13;
president's note was out, personal to me, I distributed it-my own concoction--to the whole of&#13;
the Controller's community and basically said, "This is the way accountability works, and this is&#13;
how it should work." That had an enormous effect in terms of rethinking by each individual, be&#13;
it accountant or controller, on what peoples' responsibilities really are because what happened&#13;
this time to "X" next time could happen to "Y," and especially if it happens to the VP &amp;&#13;
Controller (you know how the power base of the Bank is: the VPs are treated like absolute gods),&#13;
then people would realize that the buck stops at the top. That was one of my nicest experiences&#13;
in the Bank. It was absolutely great because the note that Jim sent, of course, I couldn't argue&#13;
with because I was the one who had drafted it and used the occasion to instill a sense of&#13;
accountability in the whole community. The whole process was so absolutely interesting&#13;
because it really sent shock waves through the organization. After that, just to draw it out&#13;
further, we had of course more cases.&#13;
&#13;
You have to see this all in the context of another move. My most cost-benefit effective move in&#13;
the Bank and for controllers was the introduction of a Letter of Representation. Jim and I were&#13;
asked by the auditors to sign off on a couple of control assertions, just after we arrived at the&#13;
Bank. This was my opportunity to tell my colleagues to take their own responsibility at a time&#13;
when there was still a lot of resistance in bringing the controllers of the Bank units under my&#13;
wings with a "dotted line." And so I basically said to my colleagues the VPs, "Guys, I will sign&#13;
off, but, before I sign off, you sign off for your own units; you've got full responsibility; you're&#13;
responsible for your own units' controls in the same way as the auditor is asking for the Bank as&#13;
a whole." We added some venom in the tail, the very last line of that Letter of Representation;&#13;
paraphrasing the very last sentence, "And nothing has come to our attention that one day may&#13;
embarrass the Bank that we have not shared with you." That is a very effective assertion because&#13;
signatories- hence reputations--are on the line. So there was an incredible outburst; people&#13;
going to Jim complaining, etcetera. And Jim, although he never formally told me that he would,&#13;
backed me for all practical purposes.&#13;
&#13;
And so what happened in the years following is what could be predicted: first, that people would&#13;
lie, just as the internal and external auditors told me they would, "Don't do this, because people&#13;
will lie." And people did lie, I'm sure. They'd put their unqualified signature there as good boys&#13;
and that everything was honky dory, not wanting to cause any waves. And I'm sure that they had&#13;
things and concerns on their minds that they should not have signed off on, unqualified. -But&#13;
over time (one, two, three years) we got more and more qualifications. Last year we had, by&#13;
reference to pending investigations, about 40 qualifications, which is superb. Everybody thinks&#13;
you should have a clean Letter of Representation or a clean audit opinion. I'm basically saying&#13;
that I prefer the qualified audit opinions because there's someone who has thought things out, is&#13;
concerned, and shares those concerns with his colleagues. And so the Letter of Representation&#13;
now is doing its work in the organization and is being cascaded down from VPs to directors and&#13;
some even go to the division chief level, and you're on the line.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Jules W. Muis&#13;
                               September 14, 2000- Final edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                   9&#13;
&#13;
And today the Bank has at this moment--I couldn't believe that number; I still think it's&#13;
exaggerated--about 300 cases that are under investigation, which constitute both trust funds,&#13;
lending money, and the Bank's own internal budget. For lending money, one can be a little more&#13;
"cavalier." You have to understand here the control philosophy. The Controller's prime&#13;
responsibility at the Bank is to protect it against "reputational" risks for financial reporting&#13;
purposes in order to make sure that cont~ols for financial reporting purposes, which are big&#13;
numbers, are adequate. I also used to have responsibility when I came into the Bank for the&#13;
budget--we'll come back to that. But I've never signed off over the last five years for adequacy&#13;
of controls for management purposes, which includes efficiency and effectiveness, in practical&#13;
terms.&#13;
&#13;
BECKER: But you've signed off for financial reporting purposes?&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: Yes, I've signed off for financial purposes even though I knew our weaknesses in&#13;
controls for lending purposes where operationally we had dropped the ball. We totally dropped&#13;
the ball in following the money, our lending money. Yet I could sign off because basically my&#13;
interest as a controller for the balance sheet is not whether the money is well spent by our clients,&#13;
but whether we get it back. And basically, for IBRD [International Bank for Reconstruction and&#13;
Development] we do get our money back. We've had a few cases, workout cases, where we got&#13;
it back with some difficulties. But I've always kept an interest in the downstream part of our&#13;
money because I'm responsible for the Loan Department that disburses the money, and in the&#13;
spirit of the same COSO, I don't just want to tum the switch off and on solely based on what&#13;
Operations tell me to do. So I basically told our people, "We have to do the same amount of&#13;
thinking for disbursements." I don't want to be a controller that just mechanically signs off based&#13;
on whatever other people tell me to do, because then I'd rather have the disbursement department&#13;
somewhere else. "Downstream controls" is a whole story by itself.&#13;
&#13;
Administrative budget, treasury, and lending money are the three main component parts of the&#13;
controls construct. Fraud and corruption represent the noise in the system. The Bank now has a&#13;
mountain of problems and cases under investigation. This is in part triggered by a much more&#13;
controls-driven attitude that came with COSO, a new President, and signing off on a Letter of&#13;
Representation. People kind of knew that the first time they got away and with Jules Muis being&#13;
on the receiving end of window-dressing assertions, but everyone realized that ultimately&#13;
everyone's reputation would be on the line unless they acknowledged reality. That came in very&#13;
slow motion, and we're still not there. I still think you've got niches, important niches perhaps,&#13;
where people think, "Well, we've now a new controller for five years, and we'll sit him out, and&#13;
let's see what will happen next." Basically, I think we've had a real change in people realizing&#13;
what damage corruption can do and what damage you cause if you just go for the optical effects&#13;
of controls and not for substance, how you mortgage future generations of the poor if you do not&#13;
make sure someone follows the money.&#13;
&#13;
BECKER: Could we just go back to your early relationship with Jim Wolfensohn? Obviously&#13;
he was preoccupied with other things.&#13;
                                      Jules W. M uis&#13;
                              September 14, 2000 - Final edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                10&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: Yes.&#13;
&#13;
BECKER: When, so to speak, did what you were doing register on his screen?&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: I think the first fraud case registered. The exception that we put on the table registered&#13;
on his screen. The fraud case was one, and then there were more, such that we set up a special&#13;
investigatory unit. I think that he was extremely slow on management reporting and on the&#13;
budget and actually allowed himself to be bulldozed by his MDs, late 1995, into taking the&#13;
budget out of Controllers. And I'll come back to that, because that was for me probably the&#13;
biggest disappointment, that I never had a chance to get our old "PBD," as it was called&#13;
(Planning and Budgeting Department), which is now "CRM" [Corporate Resource&#13;
Management], under quality management. I think there was a coup, more or less at the end of&#13;
my first year, in 1995, when Jim appointed Managing Directors and started reorganizing some of&#13;
the units. And he took the budget away from Controllers and put it under a new VP, close to his&#13;
office, with a broader charter, and honoring half of what I'd asked for, as I had argued right from&#13;
day one that the Bank had no strategic planning at the base of its budget. Planning and&#13;
budgeting are each other's natural extension. It's a matter of inventorying the strategic options&#13;
from the top, then you operationalize it, make the trade-offs, cost it out, get your options lined&#13;
up, and you make your choices. But I think there were too many old guards who didn't want my&#13;
boys and my hand in that process. I'm just speculating. No one ever told me about the rationale&#13;
of the move. Jim never told me. I got the news first through rumors and then through Jessica&#13;
Einhorn. No one ever told me why Budget was taken out of Controllers. I think it had a lot to do&#13;
with the fact that that year I had already started harping very loud about the excesses in our&#13;
benefits system, in particular on salary levels and pensions; not a very popular theme !&#13;
&#13;
I triggered the pension change and also the change in the whole quasi-market-driven benefit&#13;
schemes. Recognizing that eighty percent of the Bank's staff have--it's unmentionable at the&#13;
Bank--a commodity skill function, not a unique, market-premiumed position, from secretaries to&#13;
economists (well, many of the economists), since staff have no professional exposure and very&#13;
long term accountability horizons, to me you're basically in an academic job, except for those&#13;
who are out in the trenches. I think a lot of those are under-paid. You have some very&#13;
courageous people out there, particularly now. I think you've got a new generation of country&#13;
directors who actually are very, very different from the previous ones, who speak their mind and&#13;
follow the courage of their conviction. So I would make an exception for those, but there are&#13;
hundreds, if not thousands, of economists at the Bank who just do routine analytical/research&#13;
jobs, as in academia. They wouldn't get that same money in any academic setting. Or take the&#13;
secretarial functions where a veteran secretary can go home with $55 ,000 net, plus benefits.&#13;
Plus, if he or she stayed long enough with the Bank (e.g., 30-35 years), they will go home with&#13;
close to a net pension--life-long indexed--of about $50,000 plus which cannot be called "market-&#13;
driven." Any one walking around here in Washington knows that you can get secretaries for half&#13;
that salary. And so I started bringing that out and challenging it.&#13;
&#13;
                                       Jules W. M uis&#13;
                               September 14, 2000- Final edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                   11&#13;
&#13;
I think too many people simply didn't want my nose in it. And I forced my hand then on the&#13;
pension part because pensions were and are scandalous for a poverty-fighting institution. I had&#13;
my impact on the benefits part in that we did do a review of the benefits, etcetera. And I&#13;
appreciate the fact that you can't change things from one day to another. Now we have a new&#13;
system and a new consultant working on our salary/benefits comparator scheme, so we're slowly&#13;
"tinkering" it to more realistic proportions. But, you know, this year there is an eight percent .&#13;
average salary increase of what I consider to be--for a public or a private institution-already&#13;
eighty percent of grossly overpaid staff.&#13;
&#13;
Moving forward on pensions, my voice was heard because the extant system was untenable,&#13;
absolutely untenable! The jury is still out on the legacy scheme, but I think no one wants to&#13;
"touch" existing staff and their grandfathered rights. I pushed it to a near breaking point to put it&#13;
on the table and make it discussable.&#13;
&#13;
On the budget system, I would just say that we've missed an excellent opportunity. Yes, we&#13;
added a planning dimension, but my criticism is also one of governance. If you make the Budget&#13;
Department reportable to the Planning Department, it's like making the costing department in a&#13;
car manufacturer reportable to the marketing guys or to the design guys. There's a conflict of&#13;
interest built in because the planning and strategic people have all these good ideas but the&#13;
costing or budget people are there to keep them honest. If you have to keep your own boss&#13;
honest, and you have to do that day after day after day after day, it's not going to work. And so&#13;
from a governance perspective I've always criticized that construct. I think the budget/costing&#13;
part should be under Controllers, keeping us honest in our cost assessments, and the (strategic)&#13;
planning part should actually be very close to the President's office.&#13;
&#13;
BECKER: So after you ended up on Wolfensohn's screen, did he see what you were trying to&#13;
do as part of his larger effort to renew and remake the organization?&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: Yeah, I think so. I did not bother him too often; I tried to keep my own pants up. I think&#13;
he also liked the total directional setting of Controllers, but there are also big egos involved in&#13;
this. Sometimes I had the feeling that there was some competitiveness. And Jim never knew&#13;
quite what to do with me; he never knew how to read me. I don't think he had many vice&#13;
presidents that told him what they thought. I had the freedom to do that because I had a five-year&#13;
term, and you're better protected with a five-year term than with an open ended contract. It's as&#13;
simple as that. And I hadn't joined the Bank to sell my soul. I joined the Bank under very&#13;
difficult circumstances with a very difficult challenge, and so I did not want to give away my&#13;
leverage and my empowerment. Jim is a robust personality, but I think he liked the general&#13;
direction I took. I think he may have seen me--l described it in one of the papers- as being an&#13;
"isolated thunderstorm in his global hurricane," which I still think is probably an apt description.&#13;
There may have been a few times where he made some comments that he was the first, et cetera,&#13;
as on anti-corruption, and that's fine. The truth ofthe matter is that neither he nor I were the first&#13;
tackling corruption. I had commissioned my personal assistant to look into (anti-) corruption&#13;
before he joined in June' 95, without asking anyone's approval, but he was the first in senior&#13;
                                        Jules W. Muis&#13;
                                September 14, 2000 - Final edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                12&#13;
&#13;
management to push the issue externally and courageously. I always felt with Jim a little bit of a&#13;
sense that he wants to be seen for having invented everything new in the Bank. So I just did my&#13;
ground work. And the advantage of my anti-corruption report--or the "C Word," as it was titled-&#13;
-was that it was documented evidence of a broad range of solid opinions within the Bank, that&#13;
there were many more problems out there than we were willing to admit, and that corruption was&#13;
a problem and a non-discussable in the Bank at that time.&#13;
&#13;
BECKER: One of the things that Wolfensolm has been trying to do is to decentralize the Bank's&#13;
operations. How does COSO fit into that?&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: Did you get the ten theses that I sent to Jim Wolfensolm at the very beginning of my&#13;
tenure? Jim asked me at one point in time to give him some food for thought--! think for his&#13;
vacation early in 1995--so I sent him 10 main theses.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: You're talking about "The Ten Commandments of the Controller"?&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: Yeah. There were also ten other issues that I sent him, a one-pager in April or May,&#13;
which he asked for with the ten commandments.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: No. We looked over the ones in The Controller's Handbook with the ten&#13;
commandments, also your strategy plan, in light of the strategic compact.&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: Right. That's later. No, I sent him an issues paper on the ten main topics in one page,&#13;
and one of them was decentralization. I basically said that if you fight a global war on poverty,&#13;
you shouldn't assemble 90 percent of your troops in one square mile in Washington. So I fully&#13;
agree with the decentralization concept. I think there are dangers involved in having resident&#13;
missions where people go too quickly and too easily native and therefore there are control&#13;
concerns, but those control issues are no different from running a public accountant's practice.&#13;
mean, if your partners in Delhi or wherever go native and actually are more truthful towards their&#13;
environment than to the partnership as a whole, then you've got a problem. And so you have to&#13;
manage that problem. And the only way to manage that problem is by knowing exactly what's&#13;
happening there, by having a bit of countervailing power in your system in order to make sure&#13;
that doesn't happen, have adequate quality control, and by choosing the right people. Then at&#13;
least you have people who have something to offer, which is not the 6000 mile away view from&#13;
prosperous Washington, but people who know what it is like living in the trenches. And so I've&#13;
always been in favor of decentralization.&#13;
&#13;
I think he's done it like everything else, as often his decisions, because of the weaknesses of his&#13;
own entourage, were taken without any consultation with Controllers. So we could have done it&#13;
more efficiently; however, as a governance and business process change I fully support it. But it&#13;
was not an orderly process as he unknowingly took risks, I think. He may not even have known&#13;
that Controllers hadn't been involved. But I think the business change was very, very important.&#13;
For Controllers it was rather a minimalist change because I can control the resident missions'&#13;
                                            Jules W. M uis&#13;
                                 September 14, 2000 - Final edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                  13&#13;
&#13;
administrative costs for financial reporting purposes in a global sense without too much&#13;
difficulty. But for PBD/CRM, for management control purposes, it's much more difficult. And&#13;
so we've been busy with pushing the toothpaste back in the tube in terms ofretro fitting these&#13;
business changes such that its design will include control considerations; which was not the case&#13;
when launched.&#13;
&#13;
So I think that's typical Jim. He's an excellent visionary. I think he even oversells the Bank to&#13;
the point that the resultant expectation gap is becoming pretty dangerous because the "troops"&#13;
have difficulties following him. But he is not a good internal manager, and he knows that! And&#13;
he still doesn't understand all my comments on "governance," for instance. That you can find&#13;
back in the COSO Report.&#13;
&#13;
The end product of the COSO process is called the COSO Report. Read the report because you'd&#13;
be very interested to see that there is no other organization that has such frank self-&#13;
criticism/assessment. The COSO Report-a bottom up product reflecting the controls concerns&#13;
of many--says virtually all the right things; inter alia, that the president should have an Executive&#13;
Committee. Jim himself signed off on it! I didn't want to sign the COSO Report by myself as a&#13;
Controller because I thought it should have senior management endorsement. It contains all the&#13;
things that I think still should happen, like the Bank having an Executive Committee so that you&#13;
have collective responsibility at the top, so that not all problems roll immediately into the front&#13;
door of the President's office, that the senior management team has to take responsibility for one&#13;
another, and specifically that Jim can't take fluke initiatives that balloon out of control with no&#13;
one being made responsible. It's all in there, and all the other issues on the Bank's weaknesses on&#13;
enterprise-wide risk management which we have now finally started. These were all flagged&#13;
three or four years ago!! They are now finally being recognized as the root for the resource&#13;
management weaknesses we have, but considered risk taking in a proper governance construct is&#13;
still not being forcefully addressed.&#13;
&#13;
BECKER: Where in the Bank, aside from your office, is there interest in this governance issue?&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: There should be, obviously, in Jim's. And I think there is, at least with three or four&#13;
MDs, serious concern. Actually, for the first time I feel that, for instance, people like Sven&#13;
[Sandstrom] see me as an ally on that issue. I know definitely Shengman [Zhang] does.&#13;
Mamphela [Ramphele] I don't know; she hasjustjoined. Peter Woicke I know too little about;&#13;
would probably agree with that. Jeff [Jeffrey A.) Goldstein I can't read on this particular score,&#13;
but I think in his heart of hearts he agrees. I've seen him change over the last couple of months&#13;
because he is faced with the consequences of a governance construct resembling the Mexican&#13;
army. I think that Jeff was more or less brought in to become kind ofthe "de facto CEO [chief&#13;
executive officer]." I think that he has come to the conclusion that he can't pull that off by&#13;
himself and that a normal governance construct would help. Those are the dynamics from the&#13;
top where I have limited information; where I can only speculate, but from all the signals I get&#13;
back, the majority ofMDs would want a governance construct for an orderly process. And I&#13;
even think that at this moment Jeff Goldstein also thinks that it would be a good move. This is&#13;
                                            Jules W. M uis&#13;
                                  September 14, 2000 - Final edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                    14&#13;
&#13;
now also being supported by Kathy [Katherine] Sierra's report on risk management at the Bank.&#13;
They basically all have come to the conclusion that we can only have proper risk management if&#13;
there's proper ownership at all levels.&#13;
&#13;
BECKER: In implementing COSO, this required an increase in staffing, especially professional&#13;
accountants and all. How easy or difficult was that to affect?&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: Well, it should have been difficult, but it wasn't. And so the part where I haven't really&#13;
screamed that hard--other than flagging it very, very visibly--is that the Bank really reneged on&#13;
its initial agreement with me before I joined, in terms of resources. I've had in my Accounting&#13;
Department a de facto budget cut of about 20 percent over those five years, this all in the wake of&#13;
major control calamities, major skeletons of the past, a new controls philosophy and a&#13;
tremendously changing Bank. I could and would not get angry about it. There was so much fat,&#13;
also in the controls area, that a lot of what my managers have done is basically convert that fat&#13;
back into muscle and brains. To tum a non-thinking organization back into a thinking one&#13;
doesn't require more budget but empowerment, focus, spine and professionalism, which was all&#13;
there to be tapped.&#13;
&#13;
Basically we had excellent people in Controllers. And my role was to empower them and to&#13;
bulldoze the internal barriers which were there and to allow them to tum into full-fledged&#13;
professionals, give them wings, so to speak. And that's really what I did for very little money,&#13;
actually, with a contracting budget, thanks to my excellent managers who were basically in&#13;
control of that process and who followed it through. They never had one extra penny to&#13;
implement COSO, never. I had a front office when I came in of 105 people which were niches&#13;
of dissatisfied people, remnants of old conflicts within the VP. Some of those 105 have been&#13;
laid off; most were part of the restructuring effort, of course. I could say at my farewell&#13;
reception, "I now have four women left, and I didn't even have to change my religion for it!"&#13;
&#13;
So ifthe question is budget and COSO, COSO is an unfunded mandate throughout the Bank, one&#13;
of the many unfunded mandates of the Bank. I think it was doable at the expense of a lot of hard&#13;
work by my managers because the real pain didn't come from the budget; it came in getting the&#13;
mentality changed in an orderly fashion without using too many bazookas. I have had some&#13;
confrontations which would be absolutely unthinkable in any normal organization. And what I&#13;
take with me as professional satisfaction is that I think I've resolved them all--maybe except for&#13;
one--in a quiet fashion that didn't spill over into the rest of the world or didn't unnecessarily spill&#13;
over into the Bank as a whole. It was, of course, always known within the MD group. And, as I&#13;
said, from this moment, as people look back--even the people who thought that I was the worst&#13;
thing that had ever happened to the Bank- they look back with a degree of after-the-fact&#13;
recognition that it has protected us all.&#13;
&#13;
We found calamities in the Treasury Department in 1998 which were absolutely mind boggling,&#13;
such as $500,000,000 plus of accounting errors accumulated over the past 15 years. By fluke&#13;
rather than design, the errors happened to closely offset each other as you had about 350 million&#13;
                                          Jules W. Muis&#13;
                                September 14, 2000 - Final edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                 15&#13;
&#13;
one way and between 250 and 300 million the other way. And we absorb $50,000,000 for&#13;
financial reporting purposes, but for management control purpose it was, of course, horrible!&#13;
Absolutely horrible! Treasury had to do its job with lousy systems--which we identified right&#13;
from day one--as well as too many nonqualified people making erroneous accounting judgments.&#13;
&#13;
That was the problem of the Bank: we had no sense ofwhat a good professional should look like&#13;
or how he/she should be organized/quality managed.&#13;
&#13;
BECKER: In the larger issue that you talked about in some of your speeches and so on, and&#13;
also COSO talks about, efficiency and effectiveness, is this a matter of getting a handle on&#13;
financial control?&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: Yes.&#13;
&#13;
BECKER: What needs to be done to improve, from a controller's point of view, efficiency and&#13;
effectiveness?&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: When you just limit the discussion on the Bank's reputational risk to the context of its&#13;
relevance to the financial statements, I think the main findings were that, yes, there is fraud and&#13;
corruption at the Bank, but it's not material to the financial statements, and that's a very&#13;
important caveat. And yes, we had a major "ball's up," slow motion, starting fifteen years ago in&#13;
accounting for derivatives and everything else, particularly so for financial instruments, but that&#13;
was manageable too. And so the judgment call that I had to make three or four months after I&#13;
joined the Bank, of signing off on the accounts, was that yes, we've got weaknesses but they're&#13;
probably not big enough for financial reporting purposes, a call which proved to be right, but by&#13;
fluke not by design, because had this affair worked the other way around--in other words, if all&#13;
arrows had gone in the same direction--then half a billion dollars is a lot of money, and you'd&#13;
have to tell the world. So basically we were lucky there, and I could have been proven wrong in&#13;
my judgment when signing off. I took that calculated risk because I had no choice and there&#13;
were no indications of errors of this magnitude after 50 years of clean audit opinions, and I was&#13;
just as lucky as the Bank in this respect. Everything else are control issues that do not affect the&#13;
financial statements as such, like efficiency and effectiveness. We can talk about that in terms of&#13;
the administrative budget where my main concern was price efficiency in the first place; i.e.,&#13;
efficiency of our eighty percent cost category in our income statement which is staff benefits and&#13;
where I had two focal points: the benefits system itself on salaries and the added benefits, which&#13;
was more fringe issues, particularly on pensions.&#13;
&#13;
On the pensions there were three issues. I thoroughly disagreed with the actuarial basis on which&#13;
we took the money out of the Bank through premium contributions in favor of the pension fund,&#13;
particularly against the background of a virtually invisible surplus that we build up over many&#13;
years of which everybody would say, "Well, yes, that's because of good investment policies."&#13;
And I kept saying, "No, it's also because we basically hoard the Bank by an actuarial method&#13;
called the 'open group method' which meant that you start setting money aside for future&#13;
                                       Jules W. Muis&#13;
                               September 14, 2000 - Final edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                   16&#13;
&#13;
employees." I've never seen any organization where you would do that. I helped kill that ritual.&#13;
We had to challenge management, the actuaries, and everybody else and said, "Listen, you know&#13;
this is totally irresponsible for an organization like the World Bank, a poverty fighting&#13;
organization. We should go back to normalcy, which is to provide for the real costs, and I don't&#13;
care if you do that moderately prudent for existing employees, but not for future employees."&#13;
&#13;
So we changed that, and with that the level of funding dropped. And we also got a much better&#13;
view of the real surplus in the pension fund, which now is approximately four or five billion&#13;
dollars. Do you need more than four or five billion dollars in surplus? So we forced the Bank to&#13;
listen carefully to U.S. GAAP [Generally Accepted Accounting Principles], which tells you to&#13;
plow that money back into the Bank over time. This is now a substantial accounting credit you&#13;
will find in IDA [International Development Association], IFC [International Finance&#13;
Corporation] and IBRD's financial statements that adds up to between four and five hundred&#13;
million dollars a year. I think by the time I left the Bank we had plowed back, in an accounting&#13;
sense, close to two billion dollars of excess pension money into the Bank Group's income&#13;
statements. The money will follow much slower, because a majority basically felt that this&#13;
"credit" is not useable capital. If we were to use their argument for the rest of the balance sheet,&#13;
the balance sheet would look vastly different. That's why we have accrual accounting. Anyway,&#13;
that was a major issue that caused major grief.&#13;
&#13;
The other was the issue of the pension benefits itself and the way that we gross it up for tax&#13;
purposes. This is an accountability issue. It's still under review by the Audit Committee after&#13;
three years. I have now repeated reference to its lack of resolution for three years in the COSO&#13;
Report. I think it's a major reputational risk for the future of the Bank, still. To the credit of the&#13;
Bank, we've changed the system moving forward two years ago, and the IMF has not. And I&#13;
think they are in much bigger trouble than we are. On this one I really felt pretty bad because&#13;
there's such a disconnect between the way that we calculate the taxes and the real taxes that are&#13;
payable, so you have a windfall in between. And you have to fix that in some way or another.&#13;
And so it has been a very, very hot issue, because we basically converted the system into a veiled&#13;
benefit scheme rather than an open post-retirement benefit scheme. You cash in on it sooner or&#13;
later. It was essentially a non-advertiseable benefit scheme, because you couldn't tell people&#13;
when they come in that, yes, we have a pension scheme that actually will give you a non-&#13;
discussable windfall when you leave. You can't do that. So that's a major contingent&#13;
reputational risk issue that I just want you to remember in so far as it is reflected in the COSO&#13;
Report.&#13;
&#13;
There's still a formal call to be made by the Board on the validity of the old scheme. And that's&#13;
what I've forced out in the open, keeping it above the table by basically saying, "You can't&#13;
grandfather a scheme which is called ' scandalous' by the President and the Board. You can't&#13;
grandfather a scandalous system. You can of course grandfather its outcome, but only for the&#13;
right reasons!" And that means that one of those reasons may be that we can't reverse it because&#13;
it's been in place for so long and staff expect to get it. I think it is, for all practical purposes,&#13;
irreversible, but it doesn't mean that you shouldn't give it a try and certainly have a due process&#13;
                                            Jules W. M uis&#13;
                                September 14, 2000- Final edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                   17&#13;
&#13;
validating or rejecting it. You shouldn't just let it "go" by default. But I seem to be the only one&#13;
holding that view.&#13;
&#13;
BECKER: Are there other efficiency and effectiveness issues that you think still need to be&#13;
addressed?&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: I think that the salary base still is not market-driven. The first phase change in our&#13;
benefits scheme was simply 80 percent cosmetic. Yes, we went to another consultant for a new&#13;
comparator, and we now call it "market-driven." But the only way that the Bank can get to a&#13;
benefit scheme that is efficient is by having a proper functional analysis of what each one of us&#13;
does, such as what a secretary, an accountant, or an economist really does, what their&#13;
occupational exposure is, whether it is a commodity skill position, and is there a market here in&#13;
Washington to fill that post or do we have to go somewhere else. The Bank's main mortgage in&#13;
ever getting real change through is hampered by these golden handcuffs, working with people&#13;
who, because of their G-4 status, have actually very little other options.&#13;
&#13;
Staff really have two barriers that cause them to be afraid of change. The first is that it's not very&#13;
attractive if you've got your kids here, if only for a couple of years, and your job is at stake. I've&#13;
only too slowly started understanding that. Secondly, if in addition to that, you lose a job that&#13;
you couldn't find anywhere else, even here around Washington, in terms of pay and everything&#13;
else, then you've got a double whammy of a problem which makes people reluctant to any kind&#13;
of change. I've been a member of the Staff Association for five years, and I've never--informally&#13;
or formally--said, "If you guys would really let me loose, I would sweep the floor with you. You&#13;
don't realize what a good employer the Bank is." To the point that I, as the ex-Controller, say that&#13;
our benefits still are irresponsible.&#13;
&#13;
So if the Bank were ever to do a proper functional analysis of what each one of us does, then you&#13;
will have a base for assessing realistic salary levels. As long as you don't have the courage to d ~      5&#13;
that, don't talk about "market-driven" salaries. It's as simple as that. Then there's an important  t:C  ~&#13;
other efficiency and effectiveness issue, historically, that you might not have heard of/about. s~ &lt;= \\.)&#13;
                                                                                                  . cno o::&#13;
                                                                                                    ~a;) ~   5&#13;
You should talk to Barbara Opper. There's an important issue that                      and I had a =:~ &lt;C :;::~&#13;
                                                                                                             fr&#13;
regrettable run-in on very early on which was on debt funded liquidities. There's a paper on that.           ~&#13;
I think we changed it in 1997. Basically, the Bank for years invested short and borrowed                    tiJ&#13;
medium term, which means that you have basically a negative spread. And that was an issue that&#13;
lingered on from the late '80s for about six to seven years. For years, there are two competing&#13;
schools ofthought and no winners. Barbara Opper, for instance, used to quote the Chinese&#13;
laundry man, "If you invest short and borrow long, you loose your shirt." The differences&#13;
between those two schools meant-according to some- billions of dollars for the Bank if you've&#13;
got a liquidity portfolio of20-25 billion dollars.&#13;
&#13;
That's an issue that I've forced to some kind of a conclusion by putting it on Jim Wolfensohn' s&#13;
table with a note directly to him and who didn't take long to think it through. I have not often&#13;
                                           Jules W. M uis&#13;
                                 September 14, 2000 - Final edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                  18&#13;
&#13;
used the privilege of having a direct reporting relationship to the President on issues I thought&#13;
important enough and so occasionally jumping over my peers, but on this one I couldn't see eye&#13;
to eye with my direct boss (as I couldn't on pensions either, but where in the end Jessica was of&#13;
great help and basically agreed). But on the issue of debt funded liquidities she simply didn't&#13;
want to have it on Jim's desk, to the point of telling me to rewrite my note to him. So I had to&#13;
tell her that I don't write notes to the president in order for them to be rewritten. The upshot was&#13;
that Jim dealt with it very astutely.&#13;
&#13;
And I think, by just looking at it, the "Opper School" won out, belatedly. You leverage your&#13;
AAA debt rating based on matched asset/liability maturities; that' s how you make a little bit of&#13;
money. But you don't pay negative rates ad infinitum.&#13;
&#13;
Anyway, that was a very costly Bank non-decision that lingered on for years and years, and&#13;
today we are still paying off the "mortgage" that goes with it because you can't de facto liquidate&#13;
that old portfolio from one day to the next without cost. That was a most important,&#13;
unconventional efficiency and financial effectiveness issue that I came across. You could also&#13;
really define it as an efficiency issue that cost the Bank a lot of money, if you believe the&#13;
winning school of thought which claims that it could have been changed much earlier. Barbara&#13;
Opper has been the champion of that.                                          ·&#13;
&#13;
For the rest on "efficiency and effectiveness," the main tickets are the proper use of the Bank's&#13;
"downstream" money, the Bank's main, traditional, core contribution to development. It boils&#13;
down to the 20-30 billion dollars that are pushed out of the Bank through the Loan&#13;
(disbursement) Department. It didn't take me too long, about a year, to figure out how process-&#13;
driven it was. I initially had felt that the Loan Department was the most efficient machinery that&#13;
I had . There were never any mistakes, and everything ticked and everything balanced, until we&#13;
had double payments in Africa and noticed how little thinking there was involved in the process.&#13;
&#13;
BECKER: Is this then the origins of what is the Loan Administration Change Initiative&#13;
(LACI)?&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: Yeah, that's LACI. It's now called FMIS [Financial Information Management System].&#13;
I've never learned that acronym because I felt so comfortable with LACI.&#13;
&#13;
The LACI initiative really had to do with the Bank's integrity in lending, which is probably the&#13;
term that I would prefer to use. There are only two ways for the Bank in looking at its lending&#13;
operations: it's either an investment for, or a mortgage on, future generations. If it doesn't&#13;
disburse it responsibly it mortgages future generations of the poor, and so the Bank has a duty of&#13;
care, reflected in the Articles of Agreement, Article 3, which tells the Bank it is to make sure that&#13;
its money is being used for the purpose intended. We had totally dropped the ball on that one.&#13;
We had done away with all the accountants in this process in the late ' 80s/early ' 90s. The Bank,&#13;
as you know, has been, and probably still is, lending-volume driven in terms of its performance&#13;
indicators. People causing waves or asking questions that might interfere with that process were&#13;
                                           Jules W. M uis&#13;
                                 September 14, 2000 - Final edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                19&#13;
&#13;
not particularly appreciated. And I didn't want to be heading for five years a machinery that was&#13;
just performance measured by the volumes it pushed out without asking too many questions on&#13;
development effectiveness.&#13;
&#13;
And so the first thing I did as a member of senior management was to make corruption&#13;
discussable through the "C Word" report in the summer of 1995. But corruption is not the only&#13;
drawback. You can have a lot of inefficiency in development if you simply don't care or don't&#13;
want to see what's happening. And so we started looking at the potential contribution of&#13;
financial project management as a development booster so that, basically, as a task manager you&#13;
are able not just to look at the histories of a project by looking at your own disbursements, which&#13;
is circular, but by looking first at data that makes sense for disbursements decision-making.&#13;
And, in the meantime, you create some capacity building challenges with clients, too, because&#13;
they too have to go through a process which is relatively new and less antiquated; it reveals&#13;
capacity and skill problems, but you start building capacity, which they need anyway, basically&#13;
for their own development.&#13;
&#13;
so· LACI was born, not without great difficulties. I wrote a letter to Jim Wolfensohn in 1996 on&#13;
where I thought we stood with proper financial project management and the fact that the Bank&#13;
had totally dropped the ball. Gautam Kaji responded to Jim Wolfensohn, basically telling him&#13;
that I was full of non-sense- to put it politely--and so on. This was the acting president telling&#13;
the president. Gautam saw me as this new guy coming in and telling extant management all sorts&#13;
of things they did not want to hear. He and I ultimately developed a pretty good relationship.&#13;
Jim picked up on it, albeit very slowly. I had to do my own pushing and pulling. But in the end&#13;
I also told the Board that the present situation--! used enough euphemisms--is totally&#13;
"untenable"; if anyone ever wanted to challenge the Bank and simply took it, with reference to&#13;
Article 3, to the courts or to the [Administrative] Tribunal, we would not have a leg to stand on.&#13;
We have no leg to stand on, aside from the fact that it is not just an accountability issue but a&#13;
development issue.&#13;
&#13;
So I got the task managers together, a group of three times twenty-five, and did a COSO exercise&#13;
on them as a group, basically asking them questions on whether they could read balance sheets&#13;
and financial statements. And they were very frank in that they simply didn't have the capacity&#13;
and the skills. So everybody was pretty frank about not knowing what was going on underneath&#13;
and about not having the transparency it takes to insure proper project financial management. So&#13;
with the [Strategic] Compact money we hired an adequate number of accountants who actually&#13;
could start doing the work so that we could go through the learning curve, moving forward, and&#13;
at first only for project financial management. I think the fact that we've done this has been the&#13;
saving grace for the Bank when the GAO [U.S. General Accounting Office] came in to access&#13;
Bank controls because at least they saw us do something. We would have looked totally&#13;
ridiculous had we not at least made these preemptive moves in the right direction.&#13;
&#13;
BECKER: Now what year is this? Was it pretty early on?&#13;
&#13;
                                       Jules W. M uis&#13;
                               September 14, 2000- Final edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                 20&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: The first debate started in '96 with the Loan Department taking the initiative. It took&#13;
about a year for me to discover that we had a real problem. It took another year to get the&#13;
problem recognized in the Bank, and it was a very heated debate. And then it took about one or&#13;
two years in getting partial remedial action in place, because we were so short of people who&#13;
actually knew what it was all about.&#13;
&#13;
BECKER: Isn't this a prerequisite for Wolfensohn's concept of the Comprehensive&#13;
Development Framework (CDF)?&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: Right. Totally. Actually everything that was so hotly discussed is by coincidence a&#13;
perfect fit with the CDF, which I think is a supreme concept. And I've joked about it in my&#13;
farewell speech somewhere, basically saying, "Where were we for two generations, all these&#13;
brilliant economists? Why did it take an Australian ex-lawyer only two weeks to figure out how&#13;
it's all put together?" Because the CDF concept is just very, very logical.&#13;
&#13;
And yes, now all these things look like perfect fits, but there was a downside to the way I've&#13;
approached it. Ideally, I should have started with the big picture and then moved to the small&#13;
one. I started with the small picture and moved to the big one. And there was a reason for that.&#13;
By the time we acknowledged the problem, the Asian tigers were roaring like hell and who&#13;
would have been receptive to a Jules Muis coming in having his thirtieth complaint about the&#13;
Bank, saying that "good governance" is an issue and that proper financial reporting at the public&#13;
sector level should be addressed structurally? I wouldn't have had an audience. But I had an&#13;
audience on the micro scale because I could prove that we didn't know what was going on. I&#13;
could prove that by gathering the opinions of task managers through my COSO sessions with&#13;
them--the lack of sign offs--and the audit reports on project financial management. So I started&#13;
with the micro, realizing very well that you may ring fence controls around the project, and the&#13;
only thing you may do in the end is to bring the level of water in the rest of the reservoir up when&#13;
that same reservoir is leaking like hell in non-ring-fenced areas. So I knew that if I were to be&#13;
successful at the micro scale, the macro would have to be addressed at one point in time.&#13;
&#13;
Then, fortunately, the East Asian crisis happened and that brought the Bank back to a macro&#13;
recognition and our economists rediscovering that proper accounting and auditing is an economic&#13;
fundamental. And that brings us back to basically the CDF and everything else, where good&#13;
governance is such a vital prerequisite.&#13;
&#13;
BECKER: We want to tum to some ofthe issues outside ofthe Bank such as the impact of the&#13;
Asian financial crisis, which you've just started talking about. What was the impact of the crisis&#13;
on the Bank, and especially from the controller's point of view?&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: I think the East Asian crisis will one day be described as the biggest blessing in disguise&#13;
for the good governance movement, as well as for accounting and auditing, basically because the&#13;
economists rediscovered--if not discovered- ( the importance of) good governance as well as&#13;
accounting and auditing as an economic fundamental , which they had totally forgotten in the&#13;
                                         Jules W. M uis&#13;
                               September 14, 2000 - Final edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                   21&#13;
&#13;
euphoria of the East Asian boom. For the Bank this is of tremendous importance. Just look at&#13;
the CDF in recognizing the importance of good institutions in accounting and auditing for viable&#13;
economic and market development.&#13;
&#13;
For me, the link became very clear when I looked at, not just project financial management in&#13;
investment lending but also at the structural adjustment lending that we do and which has a&#13;
number of underlying assumptions that are inherently weak. For instance, the assumption of a&#13;
structural adjustment loan is that we have proper public sector financial systems in place, and yet&#13;
we have never delved very deep to test that assumption, maybe because we were afraid of the&#13;
answer.&#13;
&#13;
Actually, in our structural adjustment lending there is no representation at all nor assurance&#13;
where we ask the clients if they know that their own money is being used for purposes intended.&#13;
And so if you co-mingle that money into systems which have no assurance and which&#13;
reputationally and anecdotally are known to be extremely fragile, if existing at all, the Bank&#13;
again may be in a situation where it mortgages rather than invests, mortgages its future&#13;
generations of the poor rather than invests in the present economies. And so there is an organic&#13;
interfacing between the interests of the Bank and those of its "clients" (if we co-define these in&#13;
terms of future generations and not only in terms of current governments that come and go), the&#13;
Bank having the responsibility to make sure that its money is being used for purposes intended,&#13;
an assurance it can only give if the client itself knows that its own money is being used for&#13;
purposes intended. And we're here street length ahead of anyone who has ever done any&#13;
thinking within the Bank of how all that interacts.&#13;
&#13;
And so when the East Asian Crisis took place and our economists were so surprised to see&#13;
finance houses and whole banks implode-hence whole economies--that just had received a&#13;
clean bill of health from their international auditor, I aired a number of concerns to the world,&#13;
including to the Financial Times, which triggered off an avalanche of questions on the&#13;
functioning of the Big Five (Pricewaterhouse Coopers, Ernst &amp; Young, KPMG, Deloitte Touche&#13;
Tohmatsu and Arthur Andersen) as transparency agents in the world, but over and beyond that,&#13;
the functioning of the whole accountancy profession, the importance of transparency, the&#13;
importance of regulation, and the importance of good governance.&#13;
&#13;
[End Tape 1, Side A]&#13;
(Begin Tape 1, Side B)&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: And so we looked at the landscape. Unless you've got good institutions in place-&#13;
public and private--which interface with each other in the context of basic good governance&#13;
principles such as checks and balances, transparency, etcetera, and you split that between the&#13;
private and the public sector, and you look at those as two wings of one plane, basically saying,&#13;
"If we don't have both in order, the plane will nosedive," then one realizes that ifyou don't have&#13;
a public sector that's reliable, transparent and accountable, that you'll never have a private sector&#13;
that is reliable, transparent and accountable. So you discover the interfacing between the two.&#13;
                                             Jules W. M uis&#13;
                                   September 14, 2000 - Final edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                    22&#13;
&#13;
You add to that a little bit of corruption, not as the main theme but as further turbulence to that&#13;
plane, then it's not so difficult to see how all that interfaces with the interest of the Bank because&#13;
the Bank cannot substitute for all the weaknesses that we have on the macro scale. The Bank&#13;
cannot become the mother of all auditors. We have difficulties enough already in dealing with&#13;
our own internal capacity building which is built on the assumption that externally the client has&#13;
its act together. But if we know that things aren't in order with the client, both in the public as&#13;
well as in the private sector, we should have a view and a voice and definitely transparency on&#13;
the inherent risks. And that's basically what Controllers has done.&#13;
&#13;
As a result, most of the issues that we've put on the table were very commonsensical: asking the&#13;
Big Five firms, "Why do you not have minimum standards?" Why hide behind national&#13;
regulators when the world knows many of them are there just to assure collective window&#13;
dressing? And do not just look at the developing countries; look at Japan! There's a moratorium&#13;
on loan loss provisioning. There are also other accounting treatment moratoriums just to keep the&#13;
Emperor optically clothed. Regulators in many of these countries are in charge of collective&#13;
window dressing and act totally counterproductive to what they are initially set up for. If you&#13;
have that kind of situation you basically have no basis for sustainable development, and so the&#13;
Bank should voice its opinion. And that's basically what we've done.&#13;
&#13;
And one thing leads to another. I think the Big Five started out with actually protesting the&#13;
Bank's views, but at this moment they agree that there is a problem. Basically what happened to&#13;
them is in their last merger wave in the '90s-- and I was part of that--they have given away their&#13;
international name. If you go for one firm, under one name, go at least for one quality--&#13;
minimum quality--allowing for some tailoring at the national level. But do not lend your name&#13;
open-endedly to something which you yourself think is substandard. I basically told them,&#13;
"There is no industry in the world--look at Coca-Cola, McDonalds, etcetera--that would allow&#13;
for a local regulator to decide what their minimum standards should be. It's only the accounting-&#13;
-the integrity--industry that apparently allows that." And I basically said, "Draw a line where&#13;
you say, 'Yes, the regulator may allow a set of financial statements that comply with principles&#13;
with which we don't agree.' But then don't lend your good name to financial statements which go&#13;
so 'low' that it just becomes a tremendous reputational risk to you and a real financial risk to&#13;
international investors."&#13;
&#13;
We had some very lively discussions with them. At one point in time they got very, very angry&#13;
with me when they had proposed what they thought was very, very generous, which is to put&#13;
what they call a " legend" in their audit reports. So you have the standard audit report, and then&#13;
there is a footnote to the audit report which basically says that these accounts are prepared in&#13;
accordance with national standards, which may not be the same as the international readers' own&#13;
standards, as a substitute for avoiding going the opposite way (which is not lending their name&#13;
and going for a local name). So I said, "Now you take McDonalds. Suppose that McDonalds&#13;
wants to open a restaurant in North Korea, and they find the best place in town. And you have&#13;
the ceremonial opening, and everything works, and they perfectly serve the five tourists that visit&#13;
in North Korea. One day McDonalds' boss steps in and finds out that these hamburgers look&#13;
                                        Jules W. M uis&#13;
                                September 14, 2000 - Final edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                    -   -   -------~-------------.,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                23&#13;
&#13;
absolutely perfect but they're made out of dog meat. Basically, what you're proposing is that&#13;
they put a little label on the door windows saying, 'Our hamburgers have been prepared in&#13;
accordance with the best of traditions of local country cooking which may not be the same as&#13;
your 'mother would do it.' They are not telling the reader what is in the hamburgers." The&#13;
reason they have difficulties doing that is because they have basically given away their name to&#13;
local national practices. There is an enormous disconnect there. And, again I repeat--Ira&#13;
Millstein has said it also in various articles-the accountancy industry is the only business in&#13;
town that says, "We have no minimum standards. We lend our name and we hide behind a local&#13;
regulator in order to validate what we're doing." Now, that is economic distortion that affects the&#13;
credibility of the whole accounting profession,_even in the eyes ofthe economist, even though&#13;
the economist should have known better.&#13;
&#13;
BECKER: Now, is this why there's been such resistance on the part of these firms to&#13;
international standards?&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: Well, they have now moved to back international standards forcefully and constructively&#13;
through IFAC [International Federation of Accountants] to escape their present situation. But&#13;
watch their internal workings; they've given away their name to national practices as these are&#13;
not profit pools--one firm worldwide organizations. These national practices and their partners&#13;
have no self-propelling interest in becoming serious. They use the counter argument that in&#13;
Japan you can only get ten percent of the audit fees you would get in the United States, which is&#13;
true. But then, if you only do five percent of the work, you still have a very good profit margin.&#13;
So many of these local partners are not interested in real change, and yet the firms have to bring&#13;
these local partners--who use their international name--under control. So there's a lot of&#13;
infighting going on in these firms, particularly provoked by our stressing that they should get&#13;
serious. But they haven't gone all the way yet in terms of living by international accounting and&#13;
auditing standards, which means that the product you get is prepared according to the standards&#13;
of the local countries. So you always have to ask yourself: "What's the regulation of that&#13;
country, because you're not telling me anything. You're not telling me that you live by, at a&#13;
minimum, international accounting standards. You're now giving me a little warning sign that&#13;
says that these accounts have not been prepared in accordance with what I'm accustomed to. But&#13;
you're not saying that you really think that they're lousy." Remember, these may be&#13;
powerhouses but with a lot of conflicting internal financial interests.&#13;
&#13;
What we have achieved is, first of all, that it's on the table, and that we had a magnificent&#13;
endorsement from the Financial Times. Also, the editorials caught the eye ofthe SEC [U.S.&#13;
Securities and Exchange Commission] with which we've established a very good rapport. We&#13;
have also been very instrumental in reorganizing IF AC, which is the worldwide body of&#13;
accountancy organizations or accountancy firms, mainly for auditing standards. We told IF AC&#13;
that it is basically a shoestring organization, a club where 90 percent of the members don't abide&#13;
by its own rules and that they should get more and better enforcement mechanisms. We've made&#13;
major progress by having the international firms agree to set up within IF AC a practice section in&#13;
which the members would abide by the rules ofiFAC. So ifyou're a member firm ofthat&#13;
                                            Jules W. Muis&#13;
                                  September 14, 2000 - Final edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                     24&#13;
&#13;
practice section, you sign off on the fact that you will live by the international rules, which is&#13;
taking IF AC out of its very open ended standard setting mode because it's not so difficult to&#13;
come out with quality standards if you know that by tomorrow you don't have to live by them.&#13;
&#13;
For IASC [International Accounting Standards Committee], it is almost the same story. We were&#13;
a major voice in its recent organizational revamp. We've become over the last three years a major&#13;
opinion maker on the international accounting scene where the voice of the Bank counts. Jim&#13;
Wolfensohn has done sterling work on this by voicing his opinion.&#13;
&#13;
And what we've done in terms of conceptualizing the issue is basically making people&#13;
understand that the macro construct of good accounting and auditing has to be seen as two wings&#13;
of one plane, the public and the private sector, so both have to work properly. In the Bank, many&#13;
people still don't understand that. The Bank should understand that ifyou only deal with the one&#13;
and not the other you're simply flying around in circles and ultimately you will crash.&#13;
&#13;
So the Bank has become a thought leader to some extent in this development, catalyzing changes&#13;
in the institutional workings of the accounting profession. The question is whether it wants to&#13;
hold on to that position.&#13;
&#13;
I have now, just before I left, retrained my guns from the private sector on to the public sector. I&#13;
don't know whether you have read my letter of July 12, 1999, to selected Supreme Audit&#13;
Institutions. If you look at the international financial architecture and all the links in that chain,&#13;
it is basically very simple: the analysis actually says that there are all these links--which include&#13;
the development banks- which are all part of the problem and, at the same time, the only part of&#13;
the solution. So we need one another. One of those links is the Supreme Audit Institutions,&#13;
which have basically almost just as important a role in the financial architecture as the Big Five&#13;
but are very much in the shadow of the Big Five. I sent the letter on July 12th when they came to&#13;
the Bank with a request for funding. We presently fund the Supreme Audit Institutions for&#13;
giving training to Auditor-Generals of selected developing countries. They meet on Fiji Island&#13;
and other exotic places, and I'm sure there's a lot of very good training going on. But then these&#13;
guys have to go back home, and as we basically are saying, "Why should we put money into&#13;
training excellent fighter pilots when we know that when they go back to their home base they&#13;
either don't have any fighter planes or they have no fuel for flying?"&#13;
&#13;
Eighty percent of the Supreme Audit Institutions are dysfunctional organizations, very highly&#13;
politicized. In the developing world, they're greatly over staffed and greatly under-paid and&#13;
under-skilled. And they're under tremendous pressure by their own governments to just sign off&#13;
for the sake of signing off and satisfying the Bank. Fortunately, we now find more and more&#13;
courage and independence in their work. Now, if you don't have an institution in a country that&#13;
can ensure that the government knows that its own budget money is being used for purposes&#13;
intended, who are we as the World Bank to assume that it is the case if you don't have one&#13;
institution, independent, properly skilled, in a country that actually can make that assurance?&#13;
&#13;
                                        Jules W. Muis&#13;
                                September 14, 2000 - Final edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                  25&#13;
&#13;
[Interruption]&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: So, the main theme here is: what we've done with the Big Five we should also do to the&#13;
Supreme Audit Institutions and the GAOs of this world. And I'm basically telling the fNTOSAI&#13;
[International Organization of Supreme Audit Institutions] community that they have no&#13;
compliance teeth; it is a best practice, best effort organization. They have magnificent meetings&#13;
in the world, yet they go home and there is too little enforcement and compliance. And if we as&#13;
the World Bank, in the context of the CDF and in the context of our own accountability, cannot&#13;
rely on the fact that there is at least one institution in a country that is properly skilled and&#13;
independent to give independent opinions on its financial public sector affairs so that the&#13;
government and parliament know that the country's money is being used for purposes intended,&#13;
then we cannot substitute for any such gap. I think the future will tell that that's going to be one&#13;
of the hottest issues to solve because, again, we cannot become the mother of all auditors. The&#13;
Bank would simply over-reach, over-stretch, over-extend, and raise false expectations.&#13;
&#13;
BECKER: And this is obviously the source of a lot of corruption in all places, without this?&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: Yes, yes. Where the auditor general himself can be part of the problem. In South&#13;
America last year, press reports added up to about six Auditor-Generals that are either in jail or&#13;
about to go to jail--half probably for the right reasons and half for the wrong reasons. And so&#13;
there are major problems in that area. We keep pumping money in countries where we do not&#13;
even have client representation letters nor a Minister of Finance who actually tells us that he has&#13;
matters under control. That is a major weakness in our lending agreement structure. And even&#13;
when they assure us that they know that their own money is being used for purposes intended,&#13;
there is still no assurance that our own money is being used for purposes intended unless we&#13;
tighten the rules or be very explicit up front to our Board when discussing the CAS [country&#13;
assistance strategy] and loan agreements and what comfort we actually have.&#13;
&#13;
BECKER: Well, with the decentralized Bank and more people in the field, do you see then that&#13;
this is a function that needs to be part of World Bank operations in the field ?&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: Yeah. And there are tools available. Here we come to the country disclosure statement.&#13;
The Bank has excellent diagnostic tools in terms of assessing the auditing and accounting and&#13;
institutional strengths/weaknesses, but it is really an open-ended prayer because if you really&#13;
want a good country assessment you have to look for the equivalent of a " macro audit&#13;
certificate," of signing off on a country's good governance strength. You can hire 10,000 Arthur&#13;
Anderson soldiers for one country. Look at Russia, for instance, and you wouldn't get that&#13;
assurance if you only do it "outside in." So I'm basically saying since it is so open ended and&#13;
since it is so impossible to come to any form of positive assurance and since any assurance we&#13;
give is immediately high-j acked for self-serving purposes- most users erroneously look at&#13;
negative assurance as positive assurance--and if we say we have seen no problems, the reader&#13;
will interpret it that the Bank doesn't have any problems worth noting and, therefore , there are no&#13;
problems. But the Bank can never come to any positive assurance because the field is too big to&#13;
                                            Jules W. M uis&#13;
                                 September 14, 2000 - Final edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                26&#13;
&#13;
cover "outside in." So I've tried to introduce the Country Disclosure Statement as a very useful&#13;
"inside-out" concept and tool (interestingly, it looks much the same piecemeal as what the SEC&#13;
is discussing with the Big Five for their private sector work).&#13;
&#13;
I'm also saying that the Big Five themselves should put a Disclosure Statement out. They should&#13;
tell the world who they are, what their name stands for, what the financial statements they&#13;
associate their name with stand for, what their internal power structure is, what their decision&#13;
making/governance structure is, just in return for one thing: the privilege of having a public&#13;
function, a monopoly on a public function called "audit." Why shouldn't the supreme agent of&#13;
transparency tell the world who they are, other than through their glossy brochures? And I'm not&#13;
just saying this since I joined the Bank, I've said this when I was executive partner, Europe, with&#13;
Ernst. But there's just too much short-term self-interest for it to fly.&#13;
&#13;
The concept of the Country Disclosure Statement is much the same as the concept of a company&#13;
disclosure statement. You go out to the financial markets, and if you want to tap its money, you&#13;
tell it who you are. You tell it how you're put together, what your risk profile is and how you're&#13;
put together. I'm basically saying we should tell our clients, "If you want to have our&#13;
concessional money, you should tell us who you are. You also should tell us who actuall y&#13;
knows, internally, that your own money is being used for purposes intended and give us&#13;
assurance to that effect. So you give us a Country Disclosure Statement, which has various&#13;
advantages not just to us but also to you because as you write it you will find major holes in your&#13;
bucket, and you'll fix it on your own steam. We, the Bank, will not tell you your imperfections;&#13;
you tell us your imperfections. But we will attach legal jeopardy to any false statements,&#13;
including personal legal jeopardy; otherwise it doesn't work."&#13;
&#13;
So, if a public corporation has to prepare a disclosure statement for the financial markets in&#13;
return for the privilege of giving it money, why shouldn't we, as a concessionallender, not ask&#13;
you who you are, how you're put together, and what assurance you can give us that our lending&#13;
money--and therefore also yours--is being used for purposes intended? It's a very simple&#13;
concept. It will have a major development impact. I'm basically saying it will have the same&#13;
development impact on a macro level as the introduction of COSO had in terms of a micro&#13;
controls impact on the Bank because that's what COSO is based on. It's self- assessment. It is&#13;
bringing things out in the open through people sharing their own problems and concerns. That's&#13;
how the Country Disclosure Statement was born. I'm basically saying that all agents in the&#13;
international financial architecture should do that, including the development agencies.&#13;
&#13;
The Bank is very, very good in this. Three years ago we pioneered what's called the MD&amp;A&#13;
(management discussion and analysis), which you will find in the Bank' s Financial Report where&#13;
we put our heart and mind on the table in terms of our risk profile from a financial perspective.&#13;
Add to that the Bank's financial statements. But we miss one essential piece of information: We&#13;
don't tell the world how and whether we apply Article Three, whether we know that our lending&#13;
money is being used for purposes intended. This goes full circle back to the core question ofthe&#13;
function of the Bank in its lending operations, which is to invest not to mortgage. And the&#13;
                                          Jules W. M uis&#13;
                                September 14, 2000 - Final edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                              -   -   -   -   -   ----- - ~----.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                       27&#13;
&#13;
difference between the one and the other is a very cruel dividing line.&#13;
&#13;
BECKER: How has this proposal gone over in the Bank?&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: I had a lot of support at the third echelon management level. I had a lot of mixed&#13;
reactions at peer level. I think the thrust of it all was summarized by Kathy Sierra (Vice&#13;
President, Operations Core Services)--you should talk to Kathy Sierra on this-"Maybe we don't&#13;
want to know. If we were to know, how could we defend our lending towards our own&#13;
shareholders in a lot of the lending programs that we have?" Kathy is a very straight bullet, and&#13;
we've had an excellent rapport on the LACI where she's been a better change agent than I could&#13;
ever have been, and I think she put her finger on it.&#13;
&#13;
Basically, it boils down to a statement I never will forget of a chairman of the then Big Eight&#13;
firm in the'70s when they had all these audit calamities. He said, "One should never be so open&#13;
minded that one's brains pop out!" And it's almost the same with the Country Disclosure&#13;
Statement. If you really want to know what is underneath and really want to make that public,&#13;
would then our authorizing environment not revolt and basically say, "Should we put money into&#13;
this?"&#13;
&#13;
I think our authorizing environment in terms of the governments would probably be hesitant not&#13;
to keep the carousel going. I think the public at large would lose a lot of its foreign aid appetite.&#13;
I think it may have some very big advantages to the Bank and its clients if we were to push this&#13;
forward because it will be a major learning curve for countries to look at themselves in a realistic&#13;
way and fix their shortcomings on their own accord without necessarily telling us. The other&#13;
advantage is that it's not an "outside in" instrument; it's an "inside out" instrument. The "outside&#13;
in" preferred instrument ofthe Bank, CFAAs [country financial accountability assessment]--&#13;
including all other multilateral banks--keeps a bureaucracy self-propelling. Yet "outside in" you&#13;
only see what you see and what you're being told, and many of our own assessors would not&#13;
know what's going on underneath. If you talk about money being used for purposes intended,&#13;
there's no way that you can actually get there "outside in" other than doing a thorough audit,&#13;
again backed by my 10,000 Arthur Anderson soldiers. And even then you wouldn't know. So I&#13;
thillk the Country Disclosure Statement would be a major cost/benefit alternative instrument for&#13;
change ifwe were to accept it.&#13;
&#13;
It's on the table, and I put it on the table for all the participants in IFAD (International Federation&#13;
of Accountancy Development; set up as a discussion platform of all the links in the international&#13;
financial architecture having to do with accounting and auditing). I couldn't push it too hard,&#13;
because I couldn't put the Bank's cards on the table definitely saying we would do it. But it's on&#13;
the table waiting for when the time is ripe. I'm just waiting for another few major calamities to&#13;
happen and it will be on the table again. We're now doing "outside in" CF As (Country Financial&#13;
Analysis) that are so open ended that they will only tell us whether we and the client are making&#13;
progress. It's a good diagnostic tool; inventorying progress, not performance. It doesn't give you&#13;
any assurance. The only way you can get assurance is from the source, with ownership. So I&#13;
                                              Jules W. M uis&#13;
                                   September 14, 2000 - Final edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                   28&#13;
&#13;
feel very confident that in five to ten years' time that this may be a concept which will be&#13;
mainstreamed and will become a major building block in the CDF because I don't see how we&#13;
can ever get the governance box in the CDF completed without having that country disclosure&#13;
statement. It simply is not possible because we can't do it "outside in."&#13;
&#13;
I see you smiled?&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: Well, how forthcoming will these governments be with the country disclosure&#13;
statements? It seems such a utopian concept. Will it actually happen one day?&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: No, they won't in the first instance. But it will be like the Letter of Representation of the&#13;
Bank on COSO, because there will be a social audit. There will be constituency screening, a&#13;
very powerful truth force . These are public documents, and if you put countries into a situation&#13;
to put their articles of belief vis-a-vis reality on the table, you will make the process self-&#13;
correcting. Democracy, or whatever is left of democracy in many of these countries, and second&#13;
opinions will do the rest of the work.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: In non-democratic governments?&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: Also in non-democratic governments because you have outside opposition. You will&#13;
start a debate. People probably lied the first time that they signed off on the Letter of&#13;
Representation. Or they didn't know. And I think governments will lie-or window dress--the&#13;
first time around. They actually will think, "If the Bank needs this assurance, we'll give them the&#13;
assurance." But you only have to wait and sit them out for one, two or three years. We will have&#13;
ongoing Russian, Ukrainian or African style calamities with money. There's simply no other&#13;
way. We will have new governments coming in that will look at the business of the old&#13;
governments, put the disconnects on the table, and create an historic record. And then the&#13;
question becomes whether or not you're willing to enforce the individual legal jeopardy clauses&#13;
that, I think, should be part of the construct. So it won't be a perfect instrument, but it will be an&#13;
instrument that will have a medium term, slow motion, cleansing effect, and definitely be better&#13;
than nothing- the present state on SALs [structural adjustment loans] or the piecemeal comfort&#13;
emanating from LACI.&#13;
&#13;
BECKER: The Asian crisis was such a "heads up" because people had invested, at the Bank&#13;
and elsewhere, so much in the Asian miracle. Clearly, the Bank has the greater advantage in&#13;
terms of exposure, unlike the people who just didn't know that this was a problem, or as you say&#13;
they were just looking the other way?&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: I think they were just caught up--with the other development banks--in their own&#13;
euphoria, and there was no one who wanted to be a party-pooper, not even the skeptics. I had a&#13;
golden opportunity to do my LACI the other way around; to start macro, from macro to micro&#13;
rather than micro to macro, which is a much more difficult problem. But we had enough&#13;
difficulties, as I said, on the micro scale to actually get consensus that there was a problem and&#13;
                                             Jules W. Muis&#13;
                                September 14, 2000 - Final edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                   29&#13;
&#13;
that the Bank is part of the same kind of social ambience just like any other organization is. You&#13;
should look at the good papers that we wrote in the early '90s about the importance of good&#13;
institutions. But we didn't live by it.&#13;
&#13;
And then there are, of course, a lot of the ulterior motives/drivers of the Bank and their&#13;
shareholders. It's not just development; it's sometimes geo-political, sometimes social, and&#13;
sometimes humanitarian. There are a lot of ulterior drivers that we don't want to recognize that&#13;
make us look in a different direction if it suits us, and all that with the consent of the Board&#13;
because the EDs [Executive Directors] are the proxies of the shareholders.&#13;
&#13;
The way that I see the total sociology of the Bank is basically that we have on the one hand&#13;
shareholders who have quasi-altruistic motives to keep the carousel going. A lot of them see a&#13;
tremendous advantage of pumping money into the developing world because it means tit for tat&#13;
employment creation. Part I countries translate everything into employment. That's why also a&#13;
lot of these governments--particularly the German, Dutch and French- have all for so long been&#13;
so hypocritical about bribery legislation. Finally they have made changes to their own&#13;
legislation. In my country you could for a long time go to the Minister of Finance and say,&#13;
"Listen, I have to bribe the minister of finance of Country X with $2,000,000. Can I get&#13;
assurance that this is tax deductible?" And the Minister of Finance would or would not declare it&#13;
tax deductible. I mean, what sort of an example do you set?&#13;
&#13;
So a lot of it has to do with an unwillingness to face reality. The fact that governments are being&#13;
held accountable for employment by their constituency, competing with one another in getting&#13;
part of the cake of development funds. And a lot of it is recycling of money. It's a very cruel&#13;
game that--and here I'm being a cynic--is not just driven by development idealism. A lot of it is&#13;
driven by the fluke of the moment, geo-political or economic self-interest and the lot. Those are&#13;
the co-drivers.&#13;
&#13;
BECKER: One thing we haven't really touched on is, internally in the Bank, the EDs. What&#13;
kind of support did you get in the Board?&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: I got a lot of optical and a lot of substantive support because, I think, it's a little bit like&#13;
the president. The president doesn't want surprises and doesn't want scandals to happen, and&#13;
therefore you get a lot of support for keeping that from happening. But there is a lot happening&#13;
underneath which is hidden by smoke and mirrors. But if you put solutions on the table, still you&#13;
may get lip service but not necessarily the support. You should follow very closely the&#13;
discussion in the Board now on structural adjustment lending and the fiduciary conditions, and&#13;
you can see people getting cold feet- in particular the Part II countries. It starts with the&#13;
developing world, but I'm sure that some of the developed world are equally vulnerable--I&#13;
declared the Japanese at one point a developing country for accounting and auditing purposes&#13;
and was invited to Tokyo to discuss my views.&#13;
&#13;
In the developed world, good governance is always seen as a virtue. But good governance goes&#13;
                                       Jules W. M uis&#13;
                              September 14, 2000 - Final edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                 30&#13;
&#13;
against the vested interest of 80 percent of the membership of the Bank, and so you'll have a lot&#13;
of natural resistance, not openly but veiled. I mean, it will only become open at the very, very&#13;
end when there are no options left. Therefore, I think the transparency element is so important.&#13;
&#13;
That's why I push, maybe very idealistically, the CDS even though it looks almost like a non-&#13;
starter. But I think if you see what we've done at least in making corruption discussable, making&#13;
transparency discussable should also be a feasible exercise. And if the CDS were to happen, I&#13;
would not mind for about five to ten years keeping the faucet open in terms of Bank lending&#13;
going on in countries where we know we don't have adequate assurance that the money is being&#13;
used for purposes intended; conditional, however, to serious improvement on the government's&#13;
part, because then you are helping.&#13;
&#13;
On the IDA front, I would just like to add one thing in terms of development efficiency. The fact&#13;
is that once you've got the governance--preconditions--in place, you still have no guarantees for&#13;
the money actually being rationally distributed. I think the whole debate that we have now&#13;
between growth and poverty and everything else will key into my only contribution to the Bank's&#13;
strategic future where I've been arguing a lot for differential pricing and, particularly, in IDA&#13;
lending, which is basically 80 percent grants and 20 percent loans.&#13;
&#13;
I'm arguing in favor of loan propositions to the Board that actually are priced at arms-length in&#13;
terms of their risk profile and then "concessional-premiumed" based on a conscious decision of&#13;
what it means to the development of that country or to a project, so that you can see that you&#13;
actually end up with an interest rate of about 25-30 percent which you'll bring down depending&#13;
on how far you want to bring it down based on your development considerations. Take India and&#13;
what the central government does with the money we "lend" India. The central government&#13;
creams off the concessional IDA discount at entry level--80 percent premium-and passes the&#13;
money on to the poor at market price, because our economists have basically argued that if you&#13;
don't do it at market price you distort the markets. I simply think, particularly for countries&#13;
where even the government doesn't know that its own money is being used for purposes&#13;
intended, that this is such an incredible waste of insight in optimally allocating scarce resources.&#13;
In particular, if the same central governments were to build atomic bombs from it with our&#13;
blessing, since we're basically co-financing it with 80 percent out of our own lending money, that&#13;
is also part of the transparency curve that many of the Bank's veterans don't want to see nor&#13;
discuss.&#13;
&#13;
But I've challenged right from the beginning our lending pricing policies, to lend our money to&#13;
the poor at local market rates. I know governments run a currency risk plus other financial risks,&#13;
but to let the government, the central government, run away with the 80% premium without&#13;
questioning their central budget policies and controls is for me a development waste. I would&#13;
want to make the process visible, and it's not unreasonable to question it. But the fact is that too&#13;
often we don't want to see.&#13;
&#13;
BECKER: As you move into your sabbatical and when you think about what you've learned,&#13;
                                        Jules W. Muis&#13;
                                September 14, 2000 - Final edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                 31&#13;
&#13;
what have you learned in trying to redefine the role of the controller in the Bank that you might&#13;
apply to some other institution where you find yourself in a similar position?&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: Also, what has the Bank learned in the process? Would you say that there are lessons&#13;
learned within the institution?&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: I think the Bank has learned to appreciate--and I am not saying this because I had the&#13;
most wonderful farewell evening last week-many things I tried to. I think the Bank also has&#13;
learned to appreciate the fact that if you have a controller who does no more than keep it just&#13;
ahead of the embarrassment curve--because that's the main contribution that I've made--then&#13;
that's a win too. Also, the Bank can tell the world that we have addressed corruption and here&#13;
are the results. We dropped the ball on borrower accountability in the past and have at least&#13;
made a start picking it up again. We're not doing it all ourselves, but we leverage our voice with&#13;
the accounting profession. That is actually in all of our interest. And the Bank can blame itself&#13;
for having for six years or more so many non-discussables on, e.g., our financial policies, but it&#13;
did address many. The Bank can also tell the world that, yes, we had some real professional&#13;
accounting time-bombs in the Treasury Department in terms of not adequately knowing what we&#13;
were doing, but, most of them have been quietly fixed by Treasury itself. And I don't think that I&#13;
have ever looked back or cheered every time we discovered problems. We've done it quietly,&#13;
subtly, and without causing unnecessary waves (not everybody will see it that way). I think that&#13;
the Bank therefore appreciates having a strong controller who can work effectively internally and&#13;
fix what really has to be fixed, even though he or she may be a pain in the neck once in a while,&#13;
and that is a price worth paying.&#13;
&#13;
And I feel very privileged in having Fayezul Choudhury as my successor. I think Fayez is an&#13;
excellent professional, plus the Bank needs at this juncture a different voice, bark, and bite. And&#13;
Fayez will give it to the Bank. I've seen Fayez in action with Jim Wolfensohn, and I think he has&#13;
an independent mind and he's not afraid of speaking it. Jim will probably look at him with the&#13;
same bewilderment once in a while as he looked at me. I think Jim Wolfensohn sincerely&#13;
appreciates some of the things we handled, even though he did not want to address all. For&#13;
instance, on pensions, one can go too far, and his responsibility goes over and beyond mine if the&#13;
right of life of the organization is at stake. There, one can agree to disagree.&#13;
&#13;
So, I think that the Bank has appreciated a robust definition of the function of their controller,&#13;
and I think that the support for COSO is genuine. But, there are still things to be done in terms&#13;
of clearing up all of the non-discussables. When you put your finger on it, they all have to do&#13;
with transparency, the ability for ourselves and the world we serve to look through the&#13;
organization and recognize what we really do to the world by not addressing them.&#13;
&#13;
BECKER: And budgeting is still an issue? As well as strategic planning?&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: Budgeting is still very immature, and real strategic planning is still an issue. In my&#13;
farewell note, I've coined Corporate Day the "sandbox" of an ever expanding management team.&#13;
                                       Jules W. Muis&#13;
                               September 14, 2000- Final edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                     32&#13;
&#13;
Here you see Jim's weaknesses in wanting to be liked. If we were to look at this ever ballooning&#13;
group ofVPs and directors, it's not really a service to the Bank nor to its future. It's the easy way&#13;
out. But at the same time, I think probably no one else would have been in the position to trail&#13;
blaze new thinking into the Bank other than Jim Wolfensohn (including things like information&#13;
systems renewal, even though I think it was implemented in a lousy way). But the very fact&#13;
remains that both in the external outreach as well as internally in the Bank we couldn't have lived&#13;
with the legacy of all the fragmented systems. You'll find reference to this in my very first note&#13;
to Richard Frank.&#13;
&#13;
I think we gave birth to SAP [computer software] by Caesarean, and it is going to be a rather&#13;
long process to heal it because you had to cut so many comers by pushing it so fast. Controllers&#13;
did not want to do it in the big bang fashion Jim wanted. Controllers was the only one that&#13;
actually has constantly flagged SAP implementation as a high risk area. You can find this in our&#13;
COSO Report from two years ago.&#13;
&#13;
That's, I think, the danger that COSO now faces, that in the longer run its predictive ability is&#13;
stronger than its remedial teeth. Then you'll really walk around in circles, and people may ask&#13;
themselves, "Are we just repeating ourselves and saying the same things?" And its effect may&#13;
slip away.&#13;
&#13;
BECKER: What would allow it to be sustainable?&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: First of all, there is still new territory to cover. There's still a very sensitive COSO&#13;
session to be held that I never managed to get organized, which is amongst the senior&#13;
management group itself. That's because people were still licking their wounds and&#13;
remembering the first session in 1995. One ofthe first sessions I did was with senior&#13;
management in 1995 which had such abysmal results of senior Bank people not being aligned in&#13;
terms of objectives, not understanding the Bank's strategic objectives, total discormects between&#13;
groups, etcetera. This was also at the very early stage of Jim Wolfensohn's tenure with all the&#13;
changes that he brought in. It revealed we did not have a senior management but senior&#13;
managers only. And that's not a very good thing.&#13;
&#13;
I figure that we will find four or five years later the same picture. That was my prediction. And&#13;
it is not very attractive to see, especially if you've been President for five years and you still don't&#13;
have a cohesive senior management group. A lot of it has to do with the governance structure,&#13;
and then, of course, Jim's own personality, which is very one-on-one based. He has to put his&#13;
arms around your shoulders. But, I mean, you can't run this Bank the same way that you run&#13;
your own private investment bank. It's not the same, and everyone knows that. He himself has&#13;
actually been quite frank about it.&#13;
&#13;
So what makes COSO sustainable? There's still a very important senior management event to&#13;
take place. I think that we have covered the most crucial areas and people, from a controls&#13;
perspective. But having covered 1500 people out of 10,000 will not do it. There's a hunger&#13;
                                         Jules W. Muis&#13;
                               September 14, 2000 - Final edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                    -   -   -   - -   -~-----------------~&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                 33&#13;
&#13;
underneath in the organization, too. In fact, there are quite a number of people who'd like their&#13;
voice to be heard. Plus I think that the Board will keep it sustainable. Of course, the Board likes&#13;
to promote the frankness that goes with the Report, but a lot of it will depend on whether we can&#13;
maintain the same kind of frankness. Ifwe start word-smithing the Report into cliches, then I&#13;
think that COSO may ultimately peter out. But even then, I would think, in particular given the&#13;
fact that this was an unfunded mandate, it has been a very natural extension of a lot of what Jim&#13;
Wolfensohn wanted in terms of directional change in the Bank. At the same time, it has been a&#13;
natural pain in the neck for Jim when he did not want to hear, because it's been an ongoing echo&#13;
of dissatisfaction or alternative views. Again, the COSO Report predicted the calamities with&#13;
SAP. COSO labeled CRM as being totally under resourced, under skilled, and lacking in vision.&#13;
COSO harped on enterprise-wide risk management that forces one to deal with the paradoxes of&#13;
the Bank. Of course, the Executive Committee still is not there. And so Fayez may come under&#13;
pressure I've hardly ever been under. However, there are a few things such as pensions where&#13;
there had been some manageable pressure to tone it down. But I've always felt good about&#13;
putting my signature on the final text of the COSO Report.&#13;
&#13;
The good news is that there are, in terms of enabling environments, about four things that helped&#13;
me tremendously despite the occasional push-backs from the top or at peer level. The first was&#13;
that I have never felt pressures for income management. Income management means that your&#13;
peers tell you how much income should be and you make sure that it happens. That's the&#13;
challenge of any controller, one that actually lowers their life expectancy by at least half. It's a&#13;
constant conflict situation and sometimes an ethical dilemma. I was never put under such&#13;
pressure, and I am very grateful for that: a tribute to my bosses, in particular Gary Perlin. The&#13;
second was that I was blessed with excellent people in my own team as well as bosses, and I've&#13;
mentioned that before. I've just given them wings and built them some bulldozers. The third is&#13;
very important. I think my agenda, by fluke, was very complementary to what Jim Wolfensohn&#13;
wanted to achieve, except for those rare things where he didn't necessarily agree and didn't act.&#13;
So there've been a lot of things that made my life a lot easier. Fourth, my age bracket and the&#13;
fact that I got this job at a point where in my previous career I'd been through much bigger crises&#13;
with clients on different issues, and so even when I was challenged it was hard to intimidate me&#13;
because I didn't really care. And I thought through most issues very carefully before I brought&#13;
them out into a confrontational situation. Having tried all other things, I thought through all&#13;
possible scenarios. With my experience you can do that.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: How do you see the Controller function evolving in the Bank and, generally, outside of&#13;
the Bank?&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: As Controller, I insisted very early on on a clear governance construct. Actually, in the&#13;
Richard Frank memo I had already argued strongly, more or less, for the job of my future boss,&#13;
which is CFO [chief financial officer]. The way I see the controller function, really, is that there&#13;
will always be a need for some reasonably independent minded professional who will ultimately&#13;
sign off on the financial statements of the Bank. Financial statements are the Bank's external and&#13;
internal representation of how it really is put together in financial terms, and that will always&#13;
                                            Jules W. Muis&#13;
                                September 14, 2000 - Final edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                  34&#13;
&#13;
remain a core function. The degree to which he will put his finger into efficiency and&#13;
effectiveness questions for management purposes is a question of governance. I think the&#13;
Controller will also have an increasingly stronger involvement in the treasury management and&#13;
financial policies of an organization. We came from absolutely nowhere to actually having a&#13;
view, to being asked, and being a respectable and disciplined function within the Bank's&#13;
financial risk management construct as a whole. There's plenty of room left for our good&#13;
professionals in Controllers to contribute to the Bank's overall management.&#13;
&#13;
So on financial project management, the downstream part, I think if Kathy Sierra and her team&#13;
do their work, Controllers should "let go." That's an area where I think that we should now let&#13;
Operations take care of their own responsibilities. But there's still an enormous amount of work&#13;
to be done to keep everybody on their toes and to make sure that the macro picture we talked&#13;
about in terms of good governance is being worked at, including the Country Disclosure&#13;
Statement, the assurance we get from a macro perspective on the fiduciary and development&#13;
conditionalities ofthe Bank vis-a-vis its clients.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: On the controller's function in general, outside the Bank?&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: Outside the Bank, I think that the traditional core part of the controller function will&#13;
become a commodity. I think that the real ongoing difficulty for Controllers will be the income&#13;
management issue. The relationship between reality and real economics is becoming more and&#13;
more challenged. You used to have income management issues in the traditional economy&#13;
which were already very hard to handle because of a historic cost context. Then you look at the&#13;
E-economy at this moment and the fact that you can have a market valuation in the billions of a&#13;
company that has never made any profit. All this has also something to do with accounting and&#13;
accounting discmmects; the room to maneuver either one way or the other becomes even bigger.&#13;
&#13;
So rather than getting a narrowing of the options and possibilities, you will get a broadening of&#13;
the options and possibilities, plus the volatility of income management. And that will put the&#13;
Controllers of the future under even more pressure and will really require more spine than is&#13;
humanly possible because there will be many valid but different ways in which you can look at&#13;
income measurement of a company. And that makes it very difficult. Illegal practices you can&#13;
at least recognize and make a choice. The gray areas don't allow you a clear "No." The nature&#13;
of the micro economics of an organization is becoming such that, if you seem to have a&#13;
promising financial future, the market is going to want your balance sheet to look like absolutes,&#13;
a positive assurance statement. And there's going to be pressure to put that value on the balance&#13;
sheet. And if you put soft, intangible values on the balance sheet, you embark on slippery slopes.&#13;
Look at what happened with Micro Strategy just last year. So I think spit, spine and whatever&#13;
else you have to keep your balance is probably going to be the major attribute of a controller.&#13;
&#13;
Then, of course, his ability to work within the CFO concept in a relatively independent way,&#13;
because the CFO basically combines the bean makers, counters, and the risk takers under one&#13;
heading. And he has to deal with the trade-offs that are to be made at one point in time, while&#13;
                                          Jules W. M uis&#13;
                                 September 14, 2000 - Final edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                   35&#13;
&#13;
allowing his Controller to have an independent opinion on all this and equally call his bluff if he&#13;
has to. The higher you go up in an organization--and I'm not saying anything new--the more&#13;
paradoxes or conflicts of interest become manifest because in the end all key functions meet in&#13;
the president. He is the end bean maker, end bean counter and trader and gambler, all at the&#13;
same time.&#13;
&#13;
So being able to operate in such a new environment is going to be challenging for a Controller,&#13;
including staying ahead of the financial instruments industry game. Controllership was born out&#13;
of the accountancy profession, and I think the accountancy profession has dropped the ball in&#13;
understanding the language of finance, as finance has dropped the ball in keeping a bridge to&#13;
what is called accounting. This is a major macro risk in our world: accountants who don't&#13;
understand the language of finance can't account for its dynamics, and vice versa. And so I think&#13;
a Controller that speaks both languages is a necessity. And we have that at the Bank with Fayez&#13;
and Chuck [Charles A. McDonough) . We have some very good professionals in the Bank who&#13;
can do that.&#13;
&#13;
BECKER: We've talked a good bit about James Wolfensohn. More generally, what qualities&#13;
do you think the next president of the Bank should have? One is, obviously, he should be&#13;
knowledgeable about financial markets and how rapidly they're changing, clearly. This might be&#13;
the technical side of the job. But what else would you say a president would need?&#13;
&#13;
·MUIS: I think the changes that Jim has pushed through, if he can bring them to maturity, from&#13;
transparency, accountability, including technology in developing countries, are very good. A&#13;
number of constituencies recognize very well the new mold and some more business thinking in&#13;
the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
Let me start with the "reorganization" part anew president is faced with. First, he should bring&#13;
more order in our governance construct. Secondly--but that's a value judgment that I have on&#13;
strategy--he should think very carefully and be very, very clear on how he defines "client":&#13;
whether he defines the governments as the client, whether he defines the future government as a&#13;
client, whether he defines the poor as a client, or whether he defines them all as a client and has a&#13;
formula to trade off the difference in interests. Because, for instance, at the Bank--and it's still a&#13;
non-discussable--I think there is a point that if the Bank doesn't know that its money is being&#13;
used .for purpose intended, the poor are .better off with grants than with loans.&#13;
&#13;
The new president also should have a willingness to share on strategy, not just in terms of what&#13;
he thinks is good, but also in getting the buy-in at the very top. I think our strategic musings&#13;
need orderly processes. I've dismissed them as a "sandbox." One Corporate Day and its process&#13;
is simply not enough to get a global buy-in and to do all the trade-offs which are necessary.&#13;
&#13;
I think a new president should also be financial market savvy, at least understand what it means,&#13;
because you've got the bank in the Bank and you've got the development part in the Bank, and&#13;
the bank in the Bank is really the upstream agent that makes the downstream possible, if you&#13;
                                          Jules W. M uis&#13;
                                September 14, 2000 - Final edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                  -   - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - --&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                               36&#13;
&#13;
don't understand that you're handicapped as a leader.&#13;
&#13;
I think a new president should think through very carefully what "tonal setting" he wants in the&#13;
way people deal with each other. We have now, in terms of multilateral organizations, a total of&#13;
about one hundred years of serious experience, whether it is the UN or the EU or whatever else.&#13;
These organizations are being mortgaged by what anthropologists call the "politeness&#13;
conspiracy." People don't tell each other the truth. You have many different tribes, colors, and&#13;
races next to each other who have made almost a habit of avoiding rather than telling each other&#13;
the truth. You look at the IOC (International Olympic Committee) problem; you look at what&#13;
happened at the European Union last year, unthinkable that the Commission would fire itself.&#13;
The same can happen to the Bank or the IMF on different issues. So I think we should think&#13;
through very carefully how we interact with each other.&#13;
&#13;
It is almost the horizontal column of Jim Wolfensohn's CDF: how the future public institutions--&#13;
multilaterals--should be organized in order to avoid endless procrastination in getting rid of&#13;
yesterday and to see whether that can be done the way we've always done it over the last 50 or so&#13;
years, which is by internal reorganization. It is easier to build a new bank next to an old bank&#13;
than to keep building a new bank on top of an old ba:nk. In the end the latter becomes a very&#13;
fragile proposition. And so if you were to have a "thought" leader who could think in terms of&#13;
macro institutional governance and institutional sociology and would actually implement it, it&#13;
would be a real winner.&#13;
&#13;
I can easily see a system where you relinquish the old Bank and build a Bank starting anew with&#13;
a much better governance construct and with a new philosophy also in dealing with&#13;
governments: "If you don't want to be serious in us being serious, don't join us. Don't become a&#13;
shareholder." And to have a second organization that is actually a grant organization--very close&#13;
to what (Allan H .] Meltzer wants--one which goes over the heads of governments. Rather than&#13;
pumping your money into governments where you don't know where the money goes, pump it&#13;
into micro projects to the poor where you at least can create enabling environments and you can&#13;
follow the money almost better than through official channels. I think the most heartbreaking&#13;
part of the Bank is where we finance micro projects and you see how the "non-bankable" poor&#13;
actually are considerably more trustworthy in repaying their loans than the "bankable"&#13;
establishment. In many of our countries the establishments borrow in order to never pay back, to&#13;
be bailed out by either the next government or by nationalization or the mere passage of time.&#13;
&#13;
So, I would also want to have a new thinker who would actually consider a one off zero-base&#13;
budget exercise, as much as we need a new baseline conceptual thinking exercise. We need a&#13;
zero budget exercise because we've lost, I think, all feel for what is really needed in terms of&#13;
resources. For example, we don't know why we need in Bucharest 40 people and in Warsaw&#13;
another 20 or the other way around. If you've lost that sense, the only way then is to go back and&#13;
think through what we would lose if we didn't have it.&#13;
&#13;
BECKER: But this is part of a larger problem, a budget problem.&#13;
                                       Jules W. M uis&#13;
                            September 14, 2000 - Final edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                 37&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: And that paper may still be reinvigorating to the planning and budget process.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: On your assessment of President Wolfensohn, what is the likelihood of him achieving&#13;
his goals, in terms of all that he has set out for himself in the development agenda?&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: I think strategically he's superb but a loner. Also, I think he runs too far ahead of the&#13;
troops, so he's creating an expectation gap which could be very cruel. I think he is really sincere&#13;
and well intentioned. He's just a little na"ive, so driven by his own ideas. And, in the process, I&#13;
think the effect of some of what he does can be very cruel. Take the example of the NRS (Non&#13;
Regular Staff) exercise. You can't just take credit for regularizing half of the NRSs and not talk&#13;
about the other half that have simply been pushed out of the Banlc You can't claim that the&#13;
regular staff salaries are market driven and the NRSs were not, if the reality was that the NRSs&#13;
were market driven-and the Bank's regulars are, overall, overpaid. We have turned market&#13;
driven professionals into new mandarins. And so there is a lot of naivete underneath. I think&#13;
that when his successor comes in, I would predict that there will be a lot of, "Where were you&#13;
guys when this all happened?" Because, you can see that on Corporate Day the VPs are&#13;
considerably more frank when Jim is gone than when he's there. It looks like a whole different&#13;
meeting.&#13;
&#13;
I do think that at this juncture ofthe Bank, in the total scheme ofthings, Jim Wolfensohn has&#13;
been a fantastic blessing, certainly to me. But there is a heavy price to his dominant personality,&#13;
and that heavy price will have to be paid in the future. I would want to have as the next president&#13;
someone who would actually be willing--and that's what Jim is not willing to do--to put the&#13;
future of the Bank on the table. I mean a dramatically changed Bank. We need a president who&#13;
does ask himself the question, "After 55-60 years, since we are in the business to put ourselves&#13;
out of business, how far have we gotten, and if not, why not?" And I would be serious about that,&#13;
which is almost an echo of "Fifty Years is Enough." But I'm not saying that; I'm saying, "We're&#13;
in the business to put ourselves out of business. Have we gotten there yet?"&#13;
&#13;
l would still see for the Bank a very useful and valuable contribution if it were to go for&#13;
differential pricing and if it were to be more "thought" leadership oriented on its non-lending&#13;
roles, be it environmental, health, etcetera. I don't want to say that what I've done in accounting&#13;
is a supreme example, but I had no budget for what we've done with the external world in my&#13;
narrow field. I just put some commonsense ideas on the table, and I've leveraged change in the&#13;
accountancy profession against the background of the quality brand name of the Bank and&#13;
changed, in the meantime, that particular mini world. I think in our work on environment, health&#13;
and education we should have a few good thought leaders who could actually influence the&#13;
world in new thinking and in the implementation field by leveraging rather than implementation.&#13;
I think we should probably be involved only if asked by the client, and even then not too much. I&#13;
think we could shrink this Bank by half if we really wanted to.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: How would you look back on your tenure in the Bank in terms of the contribution you&#13;
                                       Jules W. Muis&#13;
                               September 14, 2000 - Final edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                 38&#13;
&#13;
made, as well as what you have learned, having brought in so much expertise to the Bank?&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: Oh, I learned an enormous amount! I think the nice thing I really learned was my&#13;
redefinition of a bureaucrat, because I always looked at it as somebody who ticked and checked&#13;
and harassed. But, basically, the nature of a bureaucrat is a top notch, very hard working,&#13;
excellent professional who sells his soul one time too many. That means that you can never rely&#13;
on his/her word any more in a meeting. The fact that I discovered this at the Bank doesn't mean&#13;
that you only find them at the Bank and nowhere else. You find them everywhere, in all large&#13;
organizations, public and private. Maybe it's a matter of age, but I came to the conclusion that&#13;
the moment you're not being your own man or woman anymore, that is a bureaucrat, because&#13;
you never know what he or she is thinking, in addition to having given away all his/her good&#13;
talents as a change agent. That's what I learned. I don't know if it is "from" the Bank, but at&#13;
least during the period that I stayed with the Bank. I also learned an enormous amount about&#13;
macro or micro relationships and interfacing.&#13;
&#13;
I learned a lot, even on systems renewal, and the dynamics on governance, macro governance.&#13;
Virtually every project that I undertook I looked as ifl knew what I was doing, but many times I&#13;
was just finding my way as I went along. So I think the Bank has been really the best university&#13;
of my lifetime. And I had the privilege of having basically a tenure status for five years plus.&#13;
And, you know, you learn about your own weaknesses, such that I know that I'm not very good&#13;
in diplomacy. And I do bulldoze once in a while, and in the beginning I did pull a fast one with&#13;
COSO. I mean, I knew that COSO was much more penetrating than people understood it to be&#13;
when I presented it to the Audit Committee. And I had not consulted my colleagues when doing&#13;
that. And so I had my own game plan at entry level. But I think I've played it pretty fair and&#13;
opened doors and windows since. So, I've learned a lot about how to deal with diverse and&#13;
multilateral environments and picked up a few theories of my own on how to go from politeness&#13;
conspiracies to macro accounting. It's been a fantastic time, but I'm also glad I'm gone as I think&#13;
it was really time. I was getting tired of hearing my own voice, which is always a good time to&#13;
go. And so I'll take a six months break, and next spring I'll go for another license on professional&#13;
life. And I would like to think the Bank is a better place in terms of its controls.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: Well, thank you very much for a great contribution to the Bank ' s oral history program .&#13;
&#13;
MUIS: Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: And thank you for participating.&#13;
&#13;
(End Tape 1, Side B)&#13;
(End of interview]&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       Jules W. Muis&#13;
                               September 14, 2000 - Final edited&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="17973579">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2000/09/17973579/transcript-oral-history-interview-jules-w-muis-held-september-14-2000
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2000/09/17973579/transcript-oral-history-interview-jules-w-muis-held-september-14-2000</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2000/09/17973579/transcript-oral-history-interview-jules-w-muis-held-september-14-2000</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2013-04-02T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2013-04-02T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2013/07/08/000333037_20130708155017/Rendered/INDEX/790870TRN0Muis0w0September014002000.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2013/07/08/000333037_20130708155017/Rendered/PDF/790870TRN0Muis0w0September014002000.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2000-09-14T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2013-07-08T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Transcript of oral history interview with
            Jules W. Muis held on September 14, 2000
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            In September 14, 2000, Jules W. Muis was
            interviewed on behalf of the World Bank Group Archives oral
            history program by William H. Becker and Marie T. Zenni.
            During his tenure at the Bank from 1995 to 2000, Mr. Muis
            served as vice president and controller. His transcript
            concerns debates at the World Bank revolving around the role
            of the loan department, the prevalence in income management
            issues, and the merits of accounting professionals.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Transcript of oral history interview with
            Jules W. Muis held on September 14, 2000
        </docna>
        <display_title>Transcript of oral history
            interview with Jules W. Muis held on September 14, 2000</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/2000/09/17973579/transcript-oral-history-interview-jules-w-muis-held-september-14-2000</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Transcript</docty>
        <subtopic>Access to Finance,Public Sector Corruption &amp;
            Anticorruption Measures,Corporate Law,Debt Markets,Banks &amp; Banking Reform</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Law and Development,Public Sector Development</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000333037_20130708155017</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>World Bank Group Archives oral history program</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Law and Development,Public Sector Development</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Board Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            accountability, accountant, accounting,
            Accounting Principles, accounting treatment, accounts
            receivable, accrual, accrual accounting, administrative
            costs, anti-corruption, Audit Committee, auditing, auditor,
            auditors, balance sheet, balance sheets, Bank lending,
            banks, best practice, bribe, bribery, bribery legislation,
            Budgeting, capacity building, CDS, central governments, CEO,
            charter, checks, Chief Accountant, chief executive,
            collective, company, complaint, conflict of interest,
            Corporation, corruption, credibility, credits, currency,
            currency risk, debt, decentralization, deductible,
            Democracy, derivatives, developing countries, developing
            country, development banks, disbursement, disbursements, due
            process, duty of care, employer, employment, empowerment,
            enforcement mechanisms, Exchange Commission, external
            auditors, Financial Analysis, financial crisis, Financial
            Information, financial instruments, financial management,
            financial markets, Financial Report, financial risk,
            financial risks, financial statements, financial systems,
            fraud, Frauds, good governance, governance issue, governance
            principles, holding, income statements, Information
            Management, Initiative, instrument, integrity, interest
            rate, interest rates, Internal Audit, internal barriers,
            international accounting standards, International Bank,
            International Development, International Finance,
            international investors, international standards,
            investigation, investigations, investment policies, jail,
            lawyer, legislation, lending agreement, limited,
            liquidities, liquidity, Loan, loan agreements, local market,
            managers, market development, market price, maturities,
            merger, mergers, Minister, Monetary Fund, monopoly,
            mortgage, mortgages, partnership, pension, pension fund,
            pensions, peoples, portfolio, procurement, profit margin,
            public corporation, retirement, return, risk management,
            risk profile, risk taking, scandal, scandals, Securities,
            shareholders, structural adjustment, tax, transparency,
            Treasury, trust funds, unfunded mandates
        </keywd>
        <owner>Knowledge &amp; Information Services (ITSKI)</owner>
        <repnb>79087</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Alternative Sentencing Options</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community based Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Correctional Services and Facilities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corrections</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime and Society</ml:concept><ml:concept>Defense Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Detention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enforcement Policies and Oversight Mechanism</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigative Task Force Police</ml:concept><ml:concept>Juvenile Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Law Enforcement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Offender Reintegration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Administration and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Problem solving Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Prosecution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Restorative Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Therapeutic Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Assistance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim-Offender Mediation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Strategic Planning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Asset Recovery</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pensions &amp; Retirement Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance for Housing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Mortgages</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corporate Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nationalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Enterprise Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>State Owned Enterprise Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>State-Owned Enterprise Restructuring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deconcentration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delegation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Devolution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sub-National Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subnational Government and Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Anti-Corruption and Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Constitutional Courts</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ombusdam</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Corruption &amp; Anticorruption Measures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Corruption and Anticorruption Measures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Checks on Executive Power</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen User Satisfaction Survey</ml:concept><ml:concept>Independent Commissions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ombudsmen</ml:concept><ml:concept>Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Parliament</ml:concept><ml:concept>Procurement Complaints Review Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supreme Audit Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fuels</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Criminal Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Treasury</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Volatility</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>Strategic Policy Planning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Mountains</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pensions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Housing Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>State Owned Enterprises</ml:concept><ml:concept>Administrative Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Anti-Corruption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Accountability Mechanisms</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>