<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>ï»¿                                                                                           79072&#13;
DIVISION OF THE HUMANITIES AND SOCIAL SCIENCES                                             v2&#13;
&#13;
CALIFORNIA INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY&#13;
PASADENA, CALIFORNIA 91125&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
A CONVERSATION WITH MICHAEL LEJEUNE -- II&#13;
&#13;
Washington, D.C.&#13;
&#13;
November 19, 1985&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Â© Robert W. Oliver&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                        c.;\\1UTE OF I;&#13;
                                                               ~,~                    ~~&#13;
                                                      ,f                                  '1o&#13;
                                                      g                                     co&#13;
                                                      ..,&#13;
                                                      ....&#13;
                                                      ....&#13;
                                                                                             Q.....&#13;
                                                      ~&#13;
                                                       ~&#13;
                                                                                            iii&#13;
                                                                                           ..:&#13;
                                                             ""&#13;
                                                              '~'t-1:              &lt;t-&#13;
                                                                                     .._  &amp;&gt;&#13;
                                                                                 ~&#13;
                                                                    If SHALL lA...&#13;
                                                 CONVERSATIONS ABOUT GEORGE WOODS&#13;
                                                       AND THE WORLD BANK&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                              Department and North Africa from Africa.&#13;
&#13;
                 A CONVERSATION WITH MICHAEL LEJEUNE -- 11                    OLIVER:     Would you say a bit about the events that occurred in the&#13;
&#13;
                             WASHINGTON, D.C.                                 Middle East and North Africa Department when you were its director?&#13;
&#13;
                             November 19, 1985                                LEJEUNE:    Our new venture got off to a poor start, I have got to say,&#13;
&#13;
                              ROBERT W. OLIVER                                because of the June "66 war between Israel and Egypt.       You will&#13;
&#13;
                                                                              remember that within the Middle East there was a sharp reaction&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     I would like to ask   first today, Hr. Lejeune, if you would      against the United States.    The Bank was   view~d   as an institution&#13;
&#13;
say a bit about the way in which the Middle East and North Africa             virtually under the control of the U.S. and hence to be avoided and&#13;
&#13;
Department came to be started and about your role as its first                not trusted.    Conducting relations with Arab countries that had been&#13;
&#13;
director.                                                                     embroiled in the conflict was almost impossible.        We tried, but it was&#13;
&#13;
LEJEUNE:    Well, I had been Director of Administration during the early      not easy.    1 remember well my first visit to Syria.      I got nowhere&#13;
&#13;
years of George Woods' presidency.     We had agreed between us that I        trying to find some common ground for discussions with the Finance&#13;
&#13;
would work in that capacity for about three years.      I had previously      Minister and other ministers responsible for economic development.&#13;
&#13;
been the assistant director in the Far East Department.      Before the       Interestingly enough, however, I was received by the President in a&#13;
&#13;
three years were up, George Woods asked me if I would care to continue        private meeting.     He observed I was an American.     I said that was so,&#13;
&#13;
as Director of Administration.      I said,   ''No."                          but I was from the Bank and was an international civil servant; it was&#13;
&#13;
     The upshot of this was that, when Woods decided to create a new          in this capacity that I was visiting Syria.      He replied:    ''You are the&#13;
&#13;
department for the Middle East and North Africa, he asked me to be            first American I have met since the war with Israel," and seemed to&#13;
&#13;
head of it. I don't remember the precise date off hand, but I think it        look upon me as a curiosity rather than as the emissary of an&#13;
&#13;
was about March of 1967.                                                      institution of which Syria was a member and which was ready to help&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     Had North Africa and the Middle East been in other area           it.   Hardly anything came of this visit.    The hostility was palapable.&#13;
&#13;
departments before?                                                                 While Egypt was the largest of the countries in the area and much&#13;
&#13;
LEJEUNE: 1 think it had been split several ways.       One would have to go   in need of the Bank's help, the Egyptians distrusted the Bank.         A&#13;
&#13;
back to the record -- back to the Annual Reports.      The new department     principal problem was that Egypt had defaulted on its foreign debt,&#13;
&#13;
took the Middle East from the existing Europe and Middle East                 much of which was held by the U.S. govermnent or U.S. financial&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                    2&#13;
&amp;#12;institutions.    The Bank had a firm policy of not lending to a country               President in those days.)&#13;
&#13;
in default unless it was seriously and actively trying to work out a                       Typically, each area department had a director.     The director had&#13;
&#13;
settlement with its creditors.    To clear the way for getting into                   a deputy, called the "Assistant Director, 11 and there was a&#13;
&#13;
business with Egypt, much of my time was spent trying to get the u.s.                 departmental economic advisor (sometimes two).    This group of three&#13;
&#13;
and Egypt to sit down and negotiate.       Given the tensions of the times,           (or four) formed the top management of the department.&#13;
&#13;
it was tough to make any progress.        Many in high places in the U. s.                 Under the Director and Assistant Director, there was a series of&#13;
&#13;
Government felt that Egypt was responsible for encouraging Russia to                  divisions.   Each division was responsible for a group of countries,&#13;
&#13;
extend its influence into the Mediterranean and were, accordingly,                    or, if the country was very large -- India, for instance, only one&#13;
&#13;
unwilling to bend much to improve relations with it.                                  country.   The staff of the division comprised a division chief and a&#13;
&#13;
        The result was that our lending operations were pretty well                   number of loan officers and country economists.    The term '"Loan&#13;
&#13;
confined to the countries of North Africa which had not been closely                  Officer" was, and still is, a misnomer.    He was the person in the Bank&#13;
&#13;
involved in the war: Morocco, Algeria, Tunisia -- and Jordan and                      directly responsible for relations with the client country on a daily&#13;
&#13;
Lebanon, which were amenable to re-establishing relations with the                    basis, and for organizing or coordinating the Bank's work on the&#13;
&#13;
Bank.     It was in these that we began to expand our lending operations.             various aspects of the country program.    Of course most of this work&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     Would you say a word in passing about the work of an                      was done by specialists, some of whom -- particularly project&#13;
&#13;
operational department?                                                               specialists-- were in other departments.     The economic work was done&#13;
&#13;
LEJEUNE:     As I think we may have discussed in our earlier interview,               by the country economists or the economic advisor or economists co-&#13;
&#13;
there was always an operational part of the Bank specifically                         opted from elsewhere in the Bank, such as the Economics Department.&#13;
&#13;
concerned with lending operations.     Originally this was a single                        Broadly speaking, the functions of an area department were to&#13;
&#13;
department, called the Loan Department, headed by the Loan Director,                  manage the Bank's program for a particular country, to be responsible&#13;
&#13;
who was also chairman of the Staff Loan Committee.       There was a                  for assessing the country's development needs, its development plans,&#13;
&#13;
reorganization in the early '50s which resulted in the Loan                           its prospects and its creditworthiness; and to develop a program of&#13;
                                                    11&#13;
Department's being split into three so-called area departments         11&#13;
                                                                            ,   one   lending and technical assistance for that country.     As part of its&#13;
&#13;
each for Asia, Latin America, and Europe, Africa and Australasia.                     responsibility, the area department, assisted by project officers,&#13;
&#13;
These reported to the Vice President.       (There was only one Vice                  lawyers and others, was responsible for negotiating each Bank loan (or&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                      3                                                                                  4&#13;
&amp;#12;IDA credit) with the representatives of the country.     The areaâ&#128;¢            some idea of how meager our prospects were of getting anything done.&#13;
&#13;
department justified each country program and each lending proposal to        I note from the Annual Report that at the close of the 1967 fiscal&#13;
&#13;
the Staff Loan Committee, the President and the Board.                        year, which would be June 30, 1967, we had lent a total of only $82&#13;
&#13;
     As time went on and the operations of the Bank increased, the            million. I was not responsible for much of that year, but,&#13;
&#13;
functions of project identification, preparation, appraisal and               nevertheless, it fell in the first period in which I was concerned&#13;
&#13;
supervision became increasingly important.     Before the reorganization      with this part of the world.    The loans were to Tunisia, Iran and Iraq&#13;
&#13;
in the '50s, these functions (except, to some extent, supervision) had        -- and a very small one to Jordan for agricultural c-redit.     In   !~an   we&#13;
&#13;
been exercised by a unit in the Loan Department, but the                      were lending to the development finance company and in Iraq we were&#13;
&#13;
reorganization reassigned responsibility to a separate Technical              financing roads.    Only in Jordan did we do something a little new, and&#13;
&#13;
Operations or Projects Department which grew to be very large.       In the   even agricultural credit doesn't take us nearly as far as the kind of&#13;
&#13;
next major reorganization in 1972, this project work was regionalized,        agriculture projects which the Bank would be coming to in future&#13;
&#13;
so that each area department       now six in number, each expanded to be     years.&#13;
&#13;
a ''regional vice-presidency"-- was served by its own projects staff.                  The next year, fiscal 1968, shows a considerable step-up in&#13;
&#13;
Actually project and economic sector work is more complex than I have         volume:     more loans and more money-- another $115 million was lent&#13;
&#13;
described.    Two of the best sources of information are a couple of          between the Bank and IDA, but again it was very traditional. In Iran&#13;
&#13;
works by Warren Baum -- a pamphlet on the    ~roject   Cycle" and a book      it was for irrigation and land development.     In Sudan it was for&#13;
&#13;
(written with Stokes Tolbert) which expands on the subject.                   power. In Iran, again, it was for the development finance company.          In&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:    I understand.   I wonder if we could now go back to what the       Israel, a development finance company loan; and in Tunisia, a&#13;
&#13;
Bank was doing in the Middle East when you were in charge.                    development finance company loan.     This not only shows that our tot a 1&#13;
&#13;
LEJEUNE:     We started our business in the spring of 1967 -- at the time     impact was small, but that it was in a pretty narrow range.&#13;
&#13;
when the Middle East had just started to recover from the June '66 war        OLIVER:     Hay one infer from the fact that such a large percentage of&#13;
&#13;
between Israel and Egypt.    This affected the whole of our operations        the loans was to development finance companies that the Bank at that&#13;
&#13;
in the area, most seriously affecting those coUntries which were              time in that area was trying to get private firms of one kind of&#13;
&#13;
immediately concerned or related to this conflict, but not quite so           another started?&#13;
&#13;
much those further away.    The lending programs for the year give you        LEJEUNE;    Oh yes, it is quite clear that in that era, under Bill&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                      5                                                                            6&#13;
&amp;#12;Diamond, the Development Finance Company program in the Bank was very&#13;
                                                                                       The next year was 1969.     By then Bob McNamara had been President&#13;
heavy.     It was a definite effort on everybodY's part to foster the&#13;
                                                                                  for over a year, but his influence was still in an early stage.        Our&#13;
private industrial sector in the developing countries when that seemed&#13;
                                                                                  lending did not improve greatly in terms of volume or character.        In&#13;
possible.     It did seem possible in Iran.     In fact this was not the&#13;
                                                                                  those early days of McNamara's presidency, we had not yet developed&#13;
first loan to Iran, nor the last, for this purpose.        It was possible&#13;
                                                                                  many new ideas and techniques.    That came later.   So I note that we&#13;
in Israel; it was possible in Tunisia.        So I think that is a fair&#13;
                                                                                  were continuing to lend another tranche for the development finance&#13;
judgment.&#13;
                                                                                  company in Iran and that another large loan in Iran was for irrigation&#13;
OLIVER:     Your mentioning Israel leads me to ask how you managed to get&#13;
                                                                                  and land development-- traditional things.       In the agriculture&#13;
loans to Israel approved when, I suppose, the loans to Israel must&#13;
                                                                                  sector, loans were the traditional kind of agriculture loans the Bank&#13;
have been opposed by some of Israel's neighbors.&#13;
                                                                                  had been doing for some time.     In the Sudan, perhaps a slight&#13;
LEJEUNE:    Well, yes, I'm sure they all were. Of course, in the Bank's&#13;
                                                                                  departure:    a small loan for mechanized farming.   In Tunisia, it was&#13;
Board, politics are not allowed to be a consideration, nor are they&#13;
                                                                                  ports, railways, and water supply.    In Morocco, another development&#13;
allowed to be a consideration by the Bank's staff in the course of&#13;
                                                                                  finance company.   Woods had left, and McNamara was beginning to&#13;
their work. The Bank's Articles .Qf Agreement, ita charter, forbid it.&#13;
                                                                                  develop new ideas about things, but none of this was reflected much in&#13;
When for political purposes members of the Board object to something,&#13;
                                                                                  our program in the Middle East that year.&#13;
they find other grounds.    The Arab countries would claim that Israel's&#13;
                                                                                       In that year too, in fiscal 1969, the Europe Department was&#13;
mi 1 itary build-up made it e ssent is lly an uncredi tworthy country.     They&#13;
                                                                                  closed down, and the countries that were handled by it were&#13;
said, the Bank ought not to be lending to Istael; but, of course, the&#13;
                                                                                  transferred to the department of which I was the head.     It became&#13;
Bank made its own appraisals in these matters and concluded that&#13;
                                                                                  ''Europe the Middle East and North Africa," sometimes called ''EMENA".&#13;
Israel    ~creditworthy,    and there was no particular reason to&#13;
                                                                                  Our horizons were considerably broadened, and we got a lot more&#13;
discriminate against Israel from the Banl(s point of view.        The Bank&#13;
                                                                                  business in the so-called European countries in that year than we did&#13;
wasn't allowed to discriminate on political grounds, and the economic&#13;
                                                                                  in the Middle East:    Finland, Turkey, Cyprus, even Ireland and&#13;
grounds were not sufficient to do so.     So even though there were&#13;
                                                                                  Yugoslavia.    That year essentially saw the end of my time in that&#13;
objections in the Board, these loans were approved.        Of course the&#13;
                                                                                  area, because El Emary, who was in charge of Eastern Africa in the&#13;
Arab countries did not have very many votes.&#13;
                                                                                  Bank, stepped aside from that responsibility to become a special&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                      7&#13;
                                                                                                                        8&#13;
&amp;#12;Â·.Â·&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      assistant to the president, and I was asked to take over Eastern              Roger Chauffournier was in charge of Western Africa.     By the time I&#13;
&#13;
      Africa.                                                                       was moved, I fell heir to only El Emary .. s half of the rather large&#13;
&#13;
           I don't know that I can cast much light on the time under George         African sub-Saharan region.&#13;
&#13;
      Woods in the Middle East except to say that he was very interested in         OLIVER:    Are there any stories or lessons, so to speak, about Eastern&#13;
&#13;
      trying to get going in the Middle East and pressed us pretty hard.       As   Africa?    (I realize we are talking about a period after 1968 now.)&#13;
&#13;
      I said earlier, we emphasized our programs in the countries where we          LEJEUNE:    I, of course, had had long experience with Eastern Africa,&#13;
&#13;
      could do business: Morocco, Tunisia, Iran, and, to a minor extent,            because in the early days, when I was just a loan officer and then&#13;
&#13;
      Jordan, Israel, Iraq. Nothing for Egypt: it was not possible given            deputy head of Europe, Africa and Australasia, I had indeed spent a&#13;
&#13;
      that Egypt was in default on its foreign debt.      Nothing to Syria,         lot of time working on countries which fell into the East African&#13;
&#13;
      given the Communist cast of the Syrian government and its reluctance          Gambit: Sudan, Ethiopia, the Congo and particularly Kenya, Uganda,&#13;
&#13;
      to associate itself with anything as westernized as the World BanL            Tanzania, Rhodesia, Northern Rhodesia (which became Zambia) and&#13;
&#13;
      Although we tried to improve the Egyptian situation and the Syrian            Malawi.    These were all countries where I had worked previously, and&#13;
&#13;
      one, I have to confess that during my tenure we didn't get very far.          so, in a way, I picked up a responsibility which I had left behind&#13;
&#13;
      OLIVER:    On the face of it, it seems curious that East Africa would         some four or five years earlier.&#13;
&#13;
      suddenly be added to North Africa the Middle East and Europe.                      Things were changed when I got back. In the earlier times, most&#13;
&#13;
      LEJEUNE:    I misled you: it wasn"t a new department in any way.   It was     of these countries (of course not the Sudan or Ethiopia, but most of&#13;
&#13;
      just that I was transferred from Europe the Middle East and North             them) were dependencies of the United Kingdom or Belgium.      So we were&#13;
&#13;
      Africa to be Director of an entirely different department which was           working both with the metropolitan country and the dependency in all&#13;
&#13;
      concerned with Eastern Africa.                                                that we were doing.   Now there had been a drastic change. By the time&#13;
&#13;
      OLIVER:    I understand.   Eastern Africa became a department all by          I got back to it, all these countries had become independent and were&#13;
&#13;
      itself.                                                                       going through the early stages of self-government.     They were getting&#13;
&#13;
      LEJEUNE:    It was already a department all by itself.   I forget the         along without either the help or the hindrance of the former&#13;
&#13;
      exact timing, but by the time I took over, the Africa Department        (of   metropolitan power.   At the time I took over in Eastern Africa, we&#13;
&#13;
      which Pierre Moussa was the first head and El Emary, the second) had          were already well embarked on   changes in general programs:    much&#13;
&#13;
      been divided into two.     El Emary was in charge of Eastern Africa, and      stronger emphasis on agricultural work; just the beginnings, perhaps,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                            9                                                                          10&#13;
&amp;#12;of things related to rural development-- rural roads, things of that         was true in Western Africa judging from some of the themes, some of&#13;
kind; trying to do something about the live stock operations, live           the ideas, some of the thrusts, which were in Hr. McNamara's Nairobi&#13;
&#13;
stock being so important in many of these countries.     This was an         speech of 1972 when the Bank's new look really came on view.      The&#13;
&#13;
extremely difficult area in which to work, and I regret tc say that          ideas of rural development, doing things for the poorest of the poor,&#13;
&#13;
many of the livestock projects that the Bank got into, not only in my        and all these lines of approach, were developed, not only in the&#13;
time but subsequently, failed to achieve their objectives.      I won't      speech, but in the programming of activities following that speech.&#13;
say they were failures in general because they did accomplish a lot of&#13;
                                                                             Like so many things that happen in governments, in the Bank and&#13;
things, but they did not earn a reasonable economic return.     There are&#13;
                                                                             everywhere else, when they finally come to public view, the public&#13;
probably a lot of reasons.&#13;
                                                                             takes the attitude that this is the first blush, it is the birth of&#13;
     Africa, to begin with, is a very difficult place to do business.&#13;
                                                                             something.    Normally quite a period of gestation has gone by,&#13;
In the rural areas, one is up against all sorts of problemÂ·s:     customs,&#13;
                                                                             including some trial runs and other things before the new set of&#13;
local government, tribal matters, attitudes ingrained over centuries&#13;
                                                                             policies are set out publically.&#13;
which have not caught up with modern developments.     The Bank, while&#13;
                                                                             OLIVER:    I was going to ask a question that dealt with that very&#13;
pretty good at economics and so on, was, I must confess, pretty poor&#13;
                                                                             thing.    If you take a still picture of the Bank in 1950, or even 1952&#13;
on sociological matters. I don't believe we even had a sociologist at&#13;
                                                                             after the reorganization, and a picture of the Bank in 1972, I should&#13;
the Bank in those days, and the truth of it is none of us really&#13;
                                                                             have thought they would appear to be quite different organizations.&#13;
understood how African society worked.    We did not speak the local&#13;
                                                                             Yet, if you follow the motion picture from '52 straight through to&#13;
languages. There were very few who did.     While government bodies, and&#13;
                                                                             "72, the gradual evolution toward what it was 1 ike in '72 must have&#13;
so on, all used English or French, these European languages were not&#13;
                                                                             been apparent.&#13;
spoken in the areas where we were trying to do business with the&#13;
                                                                             LEJEUNE:     I think that is correct.    But one has to look at it quite&#13;
poorest people, the less educated people.    These people communicated&#13;
                                                                             closely from year to year to see what is going on.       I don't know what&#13;
in their tribal languages, or possibly in Swahili or some other lingua&#13;
                                                                             records are most useful in this regard.       I expect the Board minutes&#13;
franca which none of us knew at that time.    I'm not sure that it is&#13;
                                                                             are as useful as anything.     But it is of course true that there was a&#13;
any better in the Bank now.&#13;
                                                                             tremendous evolution and that it was particularly apparent in Africa,&#13;
     We were getting started in that part of Africa.     I think the same&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  11                                                                                 12&#13;
&amp;#12;'&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    because the African countries changed their status during this period;      years as President, I spent three on the administrative side and only&#13;
&#13;
    they changed their objectives, changed their hopes; and all this had a      two on the operational side.    So on the degree to which he was&#13;
&#13;
    great bearing on what we were trying to do.                                 reaching into operations personally, I don't have a very good view,&#13;
&#13;
    OLIVER:    The Bank in turn changed its ideas somewhat on the subject of    except to say that, during the time I was working on the Middle East:&#13;
&#13;
    what kinds of projects might be useful in stimulating the development       yes, he had a lot to say about it.         But that was partly because I was&#13;
&#13;
    of a whole society.                                                         new, and the emphasis on the Middle East was new and it was spurred by&#13;
&#13;
    LEJEUNE:     Yes, I think that is true.   I think the Bank, by the early    external events of great importance.         It was not surprising that the&#13;
&#13;
    1970s, was taking a much broader view of its relationship with its          President of the Bank would think the Middle East was an area to which&#13;
&#13;
    member countries.     It was not only looking at a series of projects, or   he had to pay a lot of    attentio~&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    even a series of economic sectors; it was looking at the whole complex              I do remember one issue, and that was the degree to which&#13;
&#13;
    of a country's economy, its policies, its plans.      There was much more   there should be state control or state interest in essentially&#13;
&#13;
    of a dialogue going on at the highest levels on these matters.      There   commercial enterprises.    It is true that Woods managed to soften the&#13;
&#13;
    were dialogues on individual loan proposals as well, but these all          Banl(s rather rigid policy against lending for governmental industrial&#13;
&#13;
    fitted into a larger scheme of things.      It became even more obvious     or commercial activities which, in much of the West, we customarily&#13;
&#13;
    and more a matter of specific planning under McNamara than had been         think of as being private enterprise as distinct from state&#13;
&#13;
    the case previously.                                                        enterprise.   He softened that; he could do so because he had come out&#13;
&#13;
    OLIVER:    To return for just a moment to some of the things we talked      of Wall Street and no one could accuse him of being unduly soft on&#13;
&#13;
    about in our first interview, I wonder if you would contrast Hr.            this kind of thing.   On the other hand, he was a realist; he could see&#13;
    Woods' manner of operating with, let's say, Hr. Black"'s manner of          what was going on in the underdeveloped world, and that in young&#13;
&#13;
    operating.     It is my impression that Mr. Woods tended to intervene, to   countries with few entrepreneurs, the government often had to lead the&#13;
&#13;
    inject his own personal views rather more into the everyday operations      way.&#13;
&#13;
    of the Bank.     I wonder if that is so, and, if it is, can it be                  There was also a bit of switch-back on this.        I can remember a&#13;
&#13;
    illustrated?                                                                meeting in Woods" office with the Algerian Minister of Finance in&#13;
&#13;
    LEJEUNE:     Well, it is hard for me to comment too much on that because,   which they had an extremely heated argument. The Algerians, being&#13;
&#13;
    as I mentioned in our earlier interview, during George Woods" five          Socialist minded, wanted to get Bank money, especially in connection&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         13                                                                           14&#13;
&amp;#12;with the development of their petroleum resources, for state                   between the Bank and the rising manager administrators        in some of&#13;
&#13;
enterprises of one kind or another.        Woods was saying, '~ot on your      the developing countries.&#13;
&#13;
life; you won't be getting that from the World Bank, 11 reading the man             Under pressure from the Executive Directors, however, it became&#13;
&#13;
a lecture on that subject.    You asked if there was any difference in         more politicized.     The chairmanship of the selection committee was&#13;
&#13;
style.    Well, I cannot imagine Gene Black getting into that kind of a        given to the Secretary of the Bank, Hr. Hendels, who was the senior&#13;
&#13;
personal, heated discussion with a finance minister.       It would have       officer who worked closely with the Executive Directors.       The program&#13;
&#13;
all been a lot smoother.     The outcome might have been the same, but         became a means of arranging for the benefits to be spread evenlY, among&#13;
&#13;
the style would have been entirely different.                                  the various developing countries rather than with a view to selecting&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:    I wonder if there is something that you can add to what has         the people who might be appropriate to the Bank's staff.      The number&#13;
&#13;
already been said on the evolution of three of the new parts of the            of trainees asked to remain on the staff and fell lower and lower,&#13;
&#13;
Bank, namely the Young Professionals, programming and budgeting, and           although the program in fact expanded. Eventually it was brought to a&#13;
&#13;
the operations evaluations work.     I think all of these began during         close as being thought no longer useful.     I think that had happened&#13;
&#13;
the '60s did they not 1                                                        before George Woods came aboard.&#13;
&#13;
LEJEUNE:    Yes. On the Young Professional Program:      early in the Ban~s             After Woods came aboard, the idea of a program specifically&#13;
&#13;
history, at a time when I was still in Personnel -        in fact, I guess I   designed to bring young peopleÂ· into the   B~nk,   not just to be sent back&#13;
&#13;
was head of what was the Personnel Division-- we instituted a                  to their countries after a period of training, was put forward. (I&#13;
&#13;
training program under which we brought young people from abroad for a         think it was Dick Demuth who may have put the refinements on the&#13;
&#13;
year's time in the Bank:     sort of in-service training, no guarantee         plan.)    It was what became known as the ''Young Professionals'&#13;
&#13;
offered of a position in the Bank at the end of the time, but with the         Program." It was instituted during Woods' time.      I became chairman of&#13;
&#13;
possibi 1 ity that some might be offered positions.       Indeed, some were.   the selection committee.    The program has continued ever since,&#13;
&#13;
Some peopleÂ· who went quite a long way in the Bank, although not to the        largely unchanged.    There is, perhaps, a little less emphasis on&#13;
&#13;
top, came out of that original program.        It was small in size, maybe     training than in the early years.    In the first year, when we set this&#13;
&#13;
ten or a dozen people per year, but quite a lot of people attended the         thing up, there was more of a rotational pattern to the assigmaents.&#13;
&#13;
Bank in this way and took back their experience.        Many of them rose to   But almost from the beginning, we expected to take most, if not all,&#13;
&#13;
high positions in their own countries.        It provided a useful nexus       the members of this program onto the pennanent staff of the Bank the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                      15                                                                           16&#13;
&amp;#12;first year.    In fact, I believe now they are appointed to the                 LEJEUNE:     Yes, that was an element.    The most important thing was that&#13;
                                         11&#13;
permanent staff right from the word       go. 11   The first year is just a     we wanted people of high quality.    Every applicant had to meet that&#13;
&#13;
period of orientation, as it were, before they take up their                    criterion.    As an illustration of what we meant by high quality, we&#13;
&#13;
assignments.    It has been an extraordinarily successful program.              meant young peOple who were very bright, very able, and who definitely&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:    The idea was sort of a combination of the earlier program, on        had managerial potential.     The idea was to bring people in at the&#13;
&#13;
the one hand, and a new idea that started either with Hr. Demuth or             bottom of the Bank who would be put into management positions later in&#13;
&#13;
Hr. Woods, or maybe jointly between them?                                       their careers.     We were looking at the development of their careers in&#13;
&#13;
LEJEUNE:   As between Hr. Woods, Hr. Demuth and myself, I don't really          the Bank and looking forward to the day that they might rise to&#13;
&#13;
remember who made the decision to design a program of this kind.            I   positions of that kind.&#13;
&#13;
had always felt strongly that the Bank needed it.         I was concerned            At the same time, the Bank was concerned that the developing&#13;
&#13;
when the one that I had set up in the early days was changed in                 countries were not well represented, that representatives of the more&#13;
&#13;
character and became less useful.    So I was certainly glad that               developed countries -- Americans, British. Dutch and to some degree&#13;
&#13;
something new came along which fitted my own ideas.         It may have come    the French, not so much the Canadians-- were very well represented,&#13;
&#13;
out of (I don't now remember} a recommendation of the Committee on              overly represented, and so this program was part of a more general&#13;
&#13;
Training, which I chaired before I became Director of Administration.           effort to recruit high quality people from the developing countries.&#13;
&#13;
in which we wrote a report on a 11 aspects of training, an effort which         It coincided with an era when there were more such people available.&#13;
&#13;
Woods was very taken with..   I forget whether this idea was developed          It was very hard finding good persons from some of the least developed&#13;
&#13;
in that report or not.    1 do know that the specifics of the program,          countries in the early days of the Bank, but by now, the late ~60l:i,&#13;
&#13;
the shape of the program, was thought out by Demuth's department and            prospects were considerably improved.&#13;
&#13;
was then agreed to by management and the Board.        The management of the    OLIVER:    Would you say a word about the budgeting process?     You did&#13;
&#13;
program was put into the hands of the Personnel Department -- hence my          say something about that before.     Is there anything you care to add?&#13;
&#13;
concern with it at this stage.                                                  It became much more systematic didn't it?&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:    Was there an objective early on in the case of the Young             LEJUENE:     I could expand a little on what I said.   You may remember&#13;
&#13;
Professionals Program not only to recruit bright young people, but              that I said that in the early days of the Bank there really was no&#13;
&#13;
also to obtain a greater geographic distribution in staff of the Bank?          budgeting process in the modern sense.      The person concerned W'ilh thâ&#128;¢Â·&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                    17                                                                               18&#13;
&amp;#12;Bank's budget went around to the various department heads and got          United States Government in determining which parts of the government&#13;
&#13;
their ideas on what they would need the following year, and that was       grow and which parts of the government do not grow, I suspect.&#13;
&#13;
what went into the budget -- mainly in terms of personnel and then, as     LEJEUNE:     Yes, that's true.&#13;
&#13;
extrapolations from that, the other budgetary items.                       OLIVER:     Would you say a word about evaluations of the operations of&#13;
&#13;
     This seemed to me when I became Director of Administration a very     the Bank?     Did that begin in the '60s?&#13;
&#13;
unsophisticated way of proceeding    in what was now becoming a rather     LEJEUNE:    Frankly, I don't quite remember when that began.   We would&#13;
&#13;
large institution.   So I advised Woods that 1 thought we needed to get    have to check some records on that. My impression is that this came&#13;
&#13;
on a much more modern basis of programming and budgeting of some kind.     about in McNamara's time rather than Woods', although the problema to&#13;
&#13;
He agreed with that, and, as a consequence, we set up a Program and        which it would respond were very much in evidence in Woods' time.      You&#13;
&#13;
Budget Department.   It was late in my tenure as Director of               probably have been told this by other people, but the problem at issue&#13;
&#13;
Administration and fairly late, certainly half way through, Woods term     was that the shareholders of the Bank, particularly the United States&#13;
&#13;
as President; indeed, this thing had not really gotten off the ground      but not solely the United States, were determined to have a better&#13;
&#13;
by the time that George Woods left and Bob McNamara came in.               handle on what had been the degree of success of the Bank's operations&#13;
&#13;
     McNamara was a strong advocate of exercising management control       so as to be able to make judgements about how its policies might be&#13;
&#13;
through programming and budgeting, so he greatly strengthened the          changed in the future.    They were also dubious about some of the&#13;
&#13;
capacity of the Program and Budget Department.   He moved the person       things that the Bank had done.    I guess there were doubts for&#13;
&#13;
that Woods had named to the directorship of it out and put in somebody     political reasons in those days. At first the United States felt that&#13;
&#13;
else from within the Bank.   While Woods had recognized that we needed     the interna 1 workings of the Bank should be subject to review by the&#13;
a system much better than we had had in the past, McNamara viewed it       U. S. -- by the Bureau of the Budget or the General Accounting Office.&#13;
&#13;
as a specific way -- in fact the most important way -- of his              OLIVER:    Or by a Congressional Committee?&#13;
&#13;
exercising control over the operations of the Bank.    So he took it to.   LEJEUNE:    Or by a Congressional Committee.   This was, of course,&#13;
&#13;
a much higher level of development and made it, in effect, his             anathema to the Bank as an international organization and to other&#13;
&#13;
personal staff.                                                            international organizations such as the Inter-American Bank.      Nobody&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:   He had perceived in his days as Secretary of Defense that the    was going to permit this if it could be avoided.&#13;
&#13;
Bureau of the Budget was the single most important bureau in the                One way of trying to get the results the United States and,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                    19                                                                         20&#13;
&amp;#12;-&#13;
&#13;
    perhaps, others wanted without giving away the Bank's independence was          own case, and the ca&amp;e of a number of other people, I suppose, there&#13;
&#13;
    to set up within the Bank a semi-autonomous body with the job of                were opportunities, times when one could have left and gone out and&#13;
&#13;
    evaluating past operations and making reports directly to the Board of          done something else and made a lot more money, but it never crossed my&#13;
&#13;
    the Bank.     That is what was done.   I don't know what exactly                mind to leave the Bank, even in times when things were not necessarily&#13;
&#13;
    McNamara's intentions were when this finally got put together, but              going well for me personally.    I cannot imagine an activity which&#13;
&#13;
    certainly, as time went by, this body became virtually independent of           would draw so much on one's abilities and also fit in so well with&#13;
&#13;
    the management of the Bank and became an arm of the Board.         I think      one's personal philosophies and hopes of doing something useful.&#13;
&#13;
    this may of been the original    intentio~    rm   not sure.   At any rate      OLIVER:   Thank you very much.&#13;
&#13;
    it moved more in that direction than some of us assumed to begin with.&#13;
&#13;
    Today it is a body which stands well apart from the operations of the&#13;
&#13;
    Bank, dealing at arm's length with the Bank's operations, evaluating&#13;
&#13;
    them, making reports on individual operations, making reports on kinds&#13;
&#13;
    of operations, looking into whether they meet their objectives or not;&#13;
&#13;
    and all this is done with a good deal of feedback to bring about&#13;
&#13;
    changes in the way we do things, changes in our systems and in our&#13;
&#13;
    processes.&#13;
&#13;
    OLIVER:     Well air, I have run out of questions to ask..     Maybe there&#13;
&#13;
    are some questions which I should have asked.       Are there any closing&#13;
&#13;
    comments on your part from your experience and the wisdom of the&#13;
&#13;
    years?&#13;
&#13;
    LEJEUNE:     I think you have asked the questions that are worthy of&#13;
&#13;
    having answers recorded.    As you probably know, I really spent my&#13;
&#13;
    whole working life in the Bank, and I never ceased to feel that it was&#13;
&#13;
    an extraordinary institution with a tremendous sense of dedication to&#13;
&#13;
    what it was trying to do -- a highly professional organization.         In my&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                           21                                                                          22&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="17973067">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1985/11/17973067/transcript-oral-history-interview-michael-lejeune-held-november-19-1985-vol-2-2-second-interview-session
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1985/11/17973067/transcript-oral-history-interview-michael-lejeune-held-november-19-1985-vol-2-2-second-interview-session</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1985/11/17973067/transcript-oral-history-interview-michael-lejeune-held-november-19-1985-vol-2-2-second-interview-session</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2008-02-26T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2008-02-26T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2013/07/08/000333037_20130708124707/Rendered/INDEX/790720v20TRN0L0020November019001985.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2013/07/08/000333037_20130708124707/Rendered/PDF/790720v20TRN0L0020November019001985.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>1985-11-19T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2013-07-08T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>2</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>2</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Transcript of oral history interview with
            Michael Lejeune held on November 19, 1985
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            In July 1985, Michael Lejeune was
            interviewed on behalf of the World Bank Group Archives oral
            history program by Robert W. Oliver. During his tenure at
            the Bank from 1946 to 1983, Mr. Lejeune worked in the
            following areas: in the department of operations as
            assistant director to Europe (1957-1962) and to the Far East
            (1963-1964); in the administration department as director
            (1964-1969); in the Europe, Middle east and North Africa
            department as director (1969-1970); in the eastern Africa
            region as director of the country programs department
            (1970-1974); and for the Consultative Group for
            International Agricultural Research (CGIAR) (1974-1983). He
            discusses the creation of specific country departments
            during the early years of the World Ban, such as the Africa
            and Middle East departments; the idea that the World Bank
            considered the economics of client countries as more than
            just their creditworthiness; and the formal relationship
            between staff, the board, and the president. His transcript
            mainly observes the World Bank under the presidency of
            George Woods.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Second interview session
        </docna>
        <display_title>Transcript of oral history
            interview with Michael Lejeune held on November 19, 1985
            (Vol. 2) : Second interview session</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/1985/11/17973067/transcript-oral-history-interview-michael-lejeune-held-november-19-1985-vol-2-second-interview-session</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Transcript</docty>
        <subtopic>Access to Finance,Public Sector Corruption &amp;
            Anticorruption Measures,Technology Industry,Corporate Law,Banks &amp; Banking Reform</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Law and Development,Industry,Public Sector Development</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000333037_20130708124707</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>World Bank Group Archives oral history program</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Law and Development,Industry,Public Sector Development</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Board Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Accounting, agricultural credit, Bank loan,
            charter, civil servant, commercial enterprises, creditors,
            creditworthiness, debt, development finance, development
            finance companies, development finance company, economic
            development, entrepreneurs, first loan, foreign debt, land
            development, lawyers, Loan, loan officer, loan officers,
            local government, Minister, ministers, persons, private
            enterprise, professional organization, programming,
            reorganization, shareholders, small loan, society, state
            enterprise, state enterprises, technical assistance, trial,
            water supply
        </keywd>
        <owner>Knowledge &amp; Information Services (ITSKI)</owner>
        <repnb>79072</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Railways Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports</ml:concept><ml:concept>Livestock</ml:concept><ml:concept>Livestock and Animal Husbandry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Growth and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply</ml:concept><ml:concept>Railways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports &amp; Waterways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Animal Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Credit</ml:concept><ml:concept>Local Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Roads</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>