<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>ï»¿                                          79111&#13;
DECLASSIFIED&#13;
    WBG Archives&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 THE WORLD BANK GROUP&#13;
&#13;
     ORAL HISTORY PROGRAM&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      Transcript of interview with&#13;
&#13;
           YVESROV~~I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          March 10 &amp; 25, 2003&#13;
&#13;
           Washington, D.C.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 By: William H. Becker &amp; Marie T. Zenni&#13;
&amp;#12;2&#13;
&amp;#12;Rovani Interview- March 10, 2003&#13;
&#13;
Q:       Good morning, this is March 101h, 2003, and I'm William Becker with the&#13;
         Business History Group and the George Washington University.&#13;
Q:       And I'm Marie Zenni, Task Manager for the Bank's Oral History Program.&#13;
A:       And I am Yves Rovani.&#13;
Q:       Mr. Rovani, it's a pleasure to finally meet you. At this point we feel that we&#13;
         know the people we're interviewing because we've read so much about you. I'd&#13;
         like to begin with some general questions about your background, mainly&#13;
         covering the period before you joined the Bank, and what in your background&#13;
         most influenced your decision to join the Bank in April of 1956?&#13;
A:       Let me first disabuse you of the notion that my joining the IBRD was the result&#13;
         of any premeditation. I was recruited after Siem Aldewereld, IBRD's director of&#13;
         Technical Operations (the predecessor of Projects), visited my employer in Paris,&#13;
         Banque de !'Union Parisienne (BUP). My managers thought that I had the profile&#13;
         that he was looking for and that experience with the IBRD would benefit my&#13;
         career with the BUP. They offered to sponsor me and I seized what I perceived-&#13;
         just ten years after the end of World War Two      as a great learning opportunity;&#13;
         that of working for an international institution with a challenging mandate and in&#13;
         the U.S., the source of        modern business development. I applied, was&#13;
         interviewed, and recruited as a junior financial analyst. BUP's management&#13;
         granted me a reentry guarantee for two years, renewable once for a total of four.&#13;
Q:       Tell us about your employer.&#13;
A:       The Banque de !'Union Parisienne was a banque d'affaires, that is, part&#13;
         investment bank - with a portfolio in mining, industry and regional banks - and&#13;
         part commercial bank, catering only to large accounts and precluded by law from&#13;
         having retail branches.   After spending a year as a trainee, I had been lucky&#13;
         enough to serve as an "attache" in the front offices of each of the three&#13;
         commercial, foreign and finance departments dealing with the issues that were&#13;
         referred to their managers. That gave me great exposure to the Bank's business&#13;
         since only the important or the unusual was transacted in front offices.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                          3&#13;
&amp;#12;Q:   Between the time you joined the Bank in 1956 and the time you served as&#13;
     financial adviser in 1969, to what extent did your early experiences influence and&#13;
     shape your thinking on development issues in general?&#13;
A:   This was, of course, a long time ago. The Bank was much smaller and was&#13;
     involved primarily in infrastructure in fewer countries, including a higher&#13;
     proportion of middle income countries. It was Eugene Black's Bank, the IBRD&#13;
     plus IFC and IDA, but not yet the World Bank. And it was committed to quality&#13;
     without the pressures of time and the constraints of costs that prevailed later. As&#13;
     an example of that culture, Mr. Aldewereld, who headed the department of the&#13;
     Bank concerned with project quality, was quoted in a New York Times interview&#13;
     as saying "l get paid to say no." It made a lot of sense given the high cost of&#13;
     mistaken investments in capital-intensive projects. Imagine a top official using&#13;
     those words in the culture and organization that were introduced by Robert&#13;
     McNamara!&#13;
     In those days, I wasn't thinking about development issues. That carne later, with&#13;
     McNamara. For me, as a project's journeyman, the Bank was the ultimate&#13;
     development model and tool. These were formative years for all ofus, and we all&#13;
     evolved. For example, an irrigation project in the fifties, like Quiroz Piura in&#13;
     Peru, consisted only of a darn and main canals. By the late sixties, that project&#13;
     would have included the reticulation of water, extension services, the credit&#13;
     needed to procure the inputs, the arrangements to market the output, in other&#13;
     words, everything needed to make the settlers productive.&#13;
     Less spectacularly, but with the same ultimate benefit in mind, my concern in&#13;
     electric power was not only to make sure that the project was sound and the&#13;
     utility responsible was financially viable, but also that consumers should not wait&#13;
     unduly for repairs and have to stand in line to pay their bills. This was the period&#13;
     when the Bank's reputation was being built. In the late '60s, the Argentine&#13;
     Minister of Energy told me that he had been informed that the Bank did not want&#13;
     to finance power development in his country any longer. He asked me to have the&#13;
     Bank reconsider because he wanted the quality assurance associated with Bank&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                      4&#13;
&amp;#12;     financing. "Tell them," he said, "that I want the Bank flag on the El Choc6n&#13;
     project." The Bank complied.&#13;
Q:   Could you tell us more about your experiences in these early years?&#13;
A:   When I joined the Bank, I was assigned to public utilities which in those days&#13;
     meant electric power only. I asked to be given other opportunities in due course&#13;
     as power was a nationalized industry in France, whereas I saw my future in&#13;
     private industry. A year later I was offered the chance to join the Transportation&#13;
     Division, which I accepted as an interesting challenge. It was indeed, but when I&#13;
     became eligible for rotation again, I accepted Public Utilities' invitation to return&#13;
     because the power projects pipeline was the strongest, while prospects for&#13;
     railways and port lending seemed limited, and industry projects were longest to&#13;
     mature. The human environment was not a factor as it was equally pleasant and&#13;
     professional in all of the department's divisions. The division chiefs and most of&#13;
     the staff were engineers with at least 15 years of professional experience, many&#13;
     also as executives. We shared the economic analysis, as there were no&#13;
     economists in power, and the few in other sectors were used primarily as&#13;
     advisers. After five years, I went to see Siem Aldewereld, reminded him of the&#13;
     arrangements I had with BUP, saying that they were pressing me to come back&#13;
     and asking for his advice. He said, "You have a great future here and will have&#13;
     frequent and sizeable salary increases." That tipped the balance in favor of&#13;
     staying, not for the money, since I could expect to do better with my previous&#13;
     employer, but for the prospect of a longer-term career in an institution with a&#13;
     great mission and under a management that was generous in delegating&#13;
     responsibility. We were an "army of colonels," as a colleague once put it, and&#13;
     enjoyed considerable decision-making powers, particularly in the field.&#13;
     The bulk of my early work was project supervision which was extraordinarily&#13;
     formative because one could look at what had worked or not and draw lessons&#13;
     for new appraisals. I was involved with all aspects of project execution, including&#13;
     procurement and the monitoring of construction, working closely and often&#13;
     substituting for engineer colleagues when the issues were not excessively&#13;
     technical.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       5&#13;
&amp;#12;     Almost from day one, however, I was pulled out to do appraisals and the&#13;
     proportion of my time spent doing so kept increasing until I ended up supervising&#13;
     only the projects that I had appraised. An amusing episode after my return to&#13;
     Public Utilities will illustrate Bank priorities then and later. I was called in by&#13;
     my chief who said that he had decided_ to give me full responsibility over the&#13;
     supervision portfolio to ensure that proper attention be given to this important&#13;
     matter. The very next day, something had come up: an appraisal was needed&#13;
     urgently. Then there was another and another, and no more was said about my&#13;
     supervision management role.&#13;
Q:   Tell us about financial analysis in those early days?&#13;
A:   When I arrived at the Bank, there were still a number of free-standing, capital-&#13;
     intensive hydroelectric projects for which there had been a pent-up demand for&#13;
     Bank financing as funds and dollars were scarce. Indeed, until the late sixties, no&#13;
     large hydro was built in developing countries without Bank participation. The&#13;
     main appraisal issues were demand and economic justification for which we&#13;
     pioneered the use of de/methodology. The financial issues were to ensure that I)&#13;
     the financing plan would fully cover carefully estimated project costs and&#13;
     contingencies, backed up by government guarantee to cover overruns; and 2)&#13;
     power rates would be so set as to guarantee a return on the investment. Fairly&#13;
     soon, however, we became involved in financing the expansion of utilities. It was&#13;
     then that the reason why I had been recruited became apparent. My predecessors&#13;
     were highly experienced accountants. These skills had been and remained&#13;
     important as we were confronted with poor accounting and auditing practices in&#13;
     most countries. I was bringing the other perspective of corporate finance and&#13;
     banking experience. That was the profile of Dad Wenzell, a retired VP of First&#13;
     Boston and strong private sector advocate, with considerable expertise in the&#13;
     financing of utilities whom Siem Aldewereld had recruited as his front office&#13;
     financial adviser, and also of financial analysts recruited after me, including&#13;
     young investment bankers seconded by Wall Street firms under a program that&#13;
     lasted for five or six years. Dad Wenzel, whom I eventually succeeded, became&#13;
     my mentor and my friend. I remember him with immense gratitude and fondness.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                      6&#13;
&amp;#12;Cash flows, including cash generation from operations, became the crux of the&#13;
financial appraisal. Given the capital intensive and continued expansion&#13;
characteristics of the sector, the rules governing power rates became critical in a&#13;
developing country environment where cheap rates - and no power - had been&#13;
the experience. So we developed tariff covenants which in one form or another&#13;
would ensure that cash generation would cover a high proportion of investment,&#13;
while also providing a good return on the investment. Obviously, it was best if&#13;
the rules were part of the country's own legislation or regulations.&#13;
Working all over the world, we became experts in utility rates legislation,&#13;
franchises, concessions, accounting, etc., bringing about necessary changes&#13;
through advice derived from experience gained from each other, and from other&#13;
developed and developing countries. Much of our work, therefore, was on&#13;
institution-building, including creation of new power companies, restructuring&#13;
power sector entities, and improving management and efficiency of borrowers.&#13;
We often required them to use consultants to help with this work, learning two&#13;
things in this regard: we should devise the basic framework with the borrower;&#13;
and we should closely supervise the work of management consultants and&#13;
auditors as well in order to ensure that borrower~ got value for their money. The&#13;
same approach applied to telecommunications, where institution-building&#13;
became one of the main benefits of Bank involvement, and to water supply, when&#13;
the Bank started lending for these sectors.&#13;
I worked on all of the private companies m our portfolio. They were more&#13;
challenging from a financial standpoint because we had to construct a financial&#13;
plan without the safety net of a provision of funds guaranteed by government. I&#13;
will recount one anecdote on this subject which contains several tidbits about&#13;
management's delegation and flexibility.&#13;
There was a large gap in the financing of Lima Light's Huinco project because of&#13;
several factors. The Swiss shareholders, Walter Boveri's Private Bank, wanted to&#13;
limit the increase in their exposure, which was the reason for our involvement.&#13;
The foreign exchange component of the project was limited because they had&#13;
already arranged to finance part of the generating plant with a credit from&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                 7&#13;
&amp;#12;suppliers affiliated with their group, and because the Bank was not financing&#13;
distribution equipment in those days. Given that financing local costs was out of&#13;
the question, we stretched the loan amount as much as possible by including the&#13;
Â· financing of interest during construction. I asked that the Swiss stretch their own&#13;
contribution in two ways: first, by doubling the share capital increase that they&#13;
had planned by shifting to Lima Light capital increases that they were planning&#13;
for two other Latin American subsidiaries; and second, by committing to&#13;
complete the financing of the first two years with a line of credit. A debentures&#13;
issue to be placed in New York in the third year would complete the financing.&#13;
With all the equity up front, a guaranteed rate of return built into the utility's&#13;
franchise and a record of dividend payments, the success of the debentures' issue&#13;
seemed assured. The General Manager loved the plan and would do his best to&#13;
sell it to Headquarters which we knew would hate it. A long silence followed&#13;
after my engineer colleague and I returned to Washington. Then, I was told that&#13;
the big boss himself would come from Switzerland to give his agreement to the&#13;
Bank's management. He was in for a surprise: Siem Aldewereld thanked him for&#13;
the information and told him that he would pass it on to the staff in charge. He,&#13;
however, was in no position to discuss the project since it had not yet been&#13;
received by the Loan Committee.&#13;
This is not the end of the story. When the time came to issue the debentures, First&#13;
Boston decided not to go forward because of the spell cast by Fidel Castro's&#13;
regime over Latin America's credit worthiness. We went to Lima and found that&#13;
construction would have to stop for lack of funds. Faced with this emergency, we&#13;
decided to ask Management, through the Peru working party, to authorize the&#13;
release of the loan amount allocated to interest during construction, and to use it&#13;
to reimburse the cost of the distribution equipment imported and used during the&#13;
construction period of the Huinco project We checked the distribution program,&#13;
the suitability of the procurement practices followed, and the improved prospects&#13;
for completing the project on schedule with the help of the proposed Â·cash&#13;
injection. We drafted a new project description and list of goods, and helped&#13;
Lima Light prepare an application for reimbursement. Back at headquarters, the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  8&#13;
&amp;#12;     working party endorsed the proposed action, cleared it through the loan&#13;
     committee, and authorized disbursements. The Board was informed ex-post.&#13;
     This is how the policy of financing distribution was introduced.&#13;
     With this anecdote I wanted to show the flexibility and speed with which the&#13;
     Bank could react to the emergency confronting a borrower and the key role&#13;
     played by the working party in the decision process. Chaired by the loan officer&#13;
     for the country, it included representatives from all units involved in decision&#13;
     making - legal, and treasurer as well as projects. It was an extremely valuable&#13;
     institution for newcomers as a way to learn the Bank. It was abolished by&#13;
     McNamara on the grounds that he did not like collective decision making.&#13;
Q:   From the time of the Bank's first major reorganization in 1952 until its second in&#13;
     1972, quality standards in Bank projects were maintained by the Central Projects&#13;
     Department.   As financial adviser in the Projects Department, please discuss&#13;
     what your. main focus was, as well as your views on the Bank's approach to&#13;
     project financing during the early McNamara years in the late 1960s?&#13;
A:   When I joined the front office of Projects late in 1968, it consisted of a deputy&#13;
     and two assistant directors, economic, engineering and procurement advisors,&#13;
     and me. The director, Siem Aldewereld, was delegating the work to this team,&#13;
     spending the bulk of his time on his other functions as VP Finance. One major&#13;
     function of this management team was to control the quality of operations&#13;
     presented by the sector departments before clearing them to be forwarded to the&#13;
     loan committee. As part of the team, I reviewed all of the proposed projects&#13;
     regardless of whether they were revenue-earning. We also reviewed the periodic&#13;
     reports on the state of the portfolio of projects under supervision and the&#13;
     evaluation reports and studies issued by the new Operations Evaluation&#13;
     Department.    We were responsible for project policies and standards and&#13;
     reviewed each sector policy paper that was prepared at Mr. McNamara's request&#13;
     before the '72 reorganization. Every Wednesday, we would meet with the&#13;
     directors of the sector departments to receive and exchange information, a&#13;
     tradition which Warren Baum maintained and perfected over the years as VP&#13;
     Central Projects Staff and a remarkable chairman of this gathering. I am indebted&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     9&#13;
&amp;#12;to him for having helped me to acquire and maintain an extremely valuable&#13;
perspective on the Bank's complex business.&#13;
As financial adviser, I was responsible for preparing policy papers and guidelines&#13;
dealing with project financial issues, accounting standards, audit covenants, etc.&#13;
Much of my time was spent coaching financial analysts and helping improve the&#13;
quality of their work. The standards were uneven. The best were in utilities and&#13;
industry, including development finance companies; the worst were in&#13;
agriculture credit. Eventually, each of the sector departments had its own&#13;
financial adviser and I acquired a deputy, both of which helped to raise quality. I&#13;
also did a number of missions for the sector departments, particularly agriculture&#13;
and power, mostly to deal with project implementation problems or institutional&#13;
issues. These were the most rewarding for me, as I was connected with the&#13;
realities of development.&#13;
Looking back at that period, the most important issues were pricing distortions&#13;
and institutional weaknesses, including poor management and accounting. This&#13;
was also the era when government bureaucracies everywhere were getting&#13;
involved through nationalization, central planning, etc. in business, becoming&#13;
part of the problem rather than the solution.        Before addressing your next&#13;
question, I will tell a little story about my last job as financial adviser of public&#13;
utilities. That job was to appraise the financial condition and prospects of no less&#13;
than the World Bank itself.&#13;
On January 3, 1968, returning from leave, I found a message on my desk, "Siem&#13;
Aldereweld wants to see you." He told me, "Since Mr. Woods appointed me VP&#13;
Finance last year I have solved the organizational problems of that Vice&#13;
Presidency. Now I would like to address the financial issues themselves, and I&#13;
need a financial appraisal of the Bank. To begin with, I want a computer program&#13;
with which we can test different lending program assumptions, starting with zero&#13;
lending. Since you don't know a thing about computers, I have asked an expert,&#13;
Guy Orcutt, to help you with the computer programming. So I did the first&#13;
appraisal of the Bank's finances which turned out to be very sound though arch-&#13;
conservatively managed, matching long-term borrowings with our long-term&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                 10&#13;
&amp;#12;loans, ignoring cash flows from loan repayments, and using short-term&#13;
borrowings only minimally and exclusively from central banks. Mr. Woods&#13;
could therefore be easily satisfied that he was leaving the Bank in good health,&#13;
contrary to what he had been misled to believe.&#13;
Soon after Robert McNamara had been designated to succeed George Woods,&#13;
Siem Aldewereld called me to his office. He said, "Yves, Mr. McNamara has&#13;
asked for a five-year plan. I have appointed John Adler to put together the plan,&#13;
and have reserved the issue of the financing plan and policies for myself, and you&#13;
will do it for me." And so I did, using a primitive computer program which gave&#13;
me headaches because it was generating many mistakes that took detective work&#13;
to identify and correct. For example, the debt service would not look right, and it&#13;
turned out that a box of cards had fallen off a table and the cards had been&#13;
reassembled incorrectly; or the income picture looked too good to be true. We&#13;
had assumed that we would sell loans from our portfolio; the computer program&#13;
had taken those loans out but was not sophisticated enough to take out the&#13;
income from the loans. Other causes for delays were a truck running into a&#13;
telephone pole in Rockville where the data were processed, interrupting&#13;
communications with our contractor. And, he was reluctant to finish the job as he&#13;
was receiving phone threats for staying open while Washington was burning&#13;
following the assassination of Martin Luther King.      Siem Aldewereld was so&#13;
pleased with the financing plan I proposed that he dragged me out of his office to&#13;
tell his two secretaries to "kneel down before this man, he is a genius," with a&#13;
display of antics with which they were quite familiar. The next day he reported&#13;
that McNamara was very pleased and wanted me to present the borrowing&#13;
program country by country for each of the next five years. The subject of Siem&#13;
Aldewereld's enthusiasm and McNamara's endorsement was my proposal to start&#13;
immediately borrowing the higher amounts which we would need in year five of&#13;
the greatly expanded lending program, and to maintain those levels throughout,&#13;
which would result in a high liquidity. My argument was that we should establish&#13;
our credit at these higher levels before we needed the money, and that we should&#13;
have enough liquid funds to carry on should our access to financial markets be&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                II&#13;
&amp;#12;     delayed and/or should one large borrower default. These benefits, I argued,&#13;
     would be well worth the cost of the proposed high liquidity. What I did not&#13;
     anticipate was that these liquid funds would become instead an important source&#13;
     of income for many years, as short-term interest rates were higher than our&#13;
     borrowing costs.&#13;
Q:   Was your promotion in October '72 to the Public Utilities Department related to&#13;
     the 1972 Reorganization?&#13;
A:   Yes. The '72 Reorganization created more departments, and opportunities for&#13;
     promotion, and I was one of the beneficiaries.&#13;
Q:   In the early '70s, during your time in the Public Utilities Department, the Bank's&#13;
     early water supply and waste disposal lending was generally regarded as a&#13;
     contribution to economic infrastructure. This approach changed in I 973, during&#13;
     the McNamara era, with a new wave of ensuring that water was supplied to an&#13;
     entire population while meeting the concerns for health and environmental&#13;
     aspects of development.      Please discuss your role as Director of the Public&#13;
     Utilities Department?&#13;
A:   Let me first set the dates straight. Lending for water supply and sanitation was&#13;
     introduced under George Woods before 1968.           By the time I was appointed&#13;
     Director of Public Utilities in October 1972, the shift in focus to access to service&#13;
     had already become policy. This was clearly reflected in a paper prepared under&#13;
     my predecessor, Mervyn Wiener, as part of a series of sector policy papers issued&#13;
     in '70-'71 at the request of Mr. McNamara. This set the stage for what had to be&#13;
     done by the operational staff of the Water Supply divisions in the Bank's regions,&#13;
     and by the Public Utilities Department of the Central Projects staff as their&#13;
     advisers.&#13;
     My department was responsible for policy, research, operational support, and&#13;
     advice in power, water supply, and telecommunications. The mandate was to&#13;
     strengthen economic analysis, including of pricing, to add a focus on access to&#13;
     service in rural areas, following up on the Nairobi speech, and to contribute to&#13;
     the quality of operational work through policy papers, research, guidelines, how-&#13;
     to paper, etc., and by reviewing and commenting on the operational output of the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                      12&#13;
&amp;#12;regions. 1 disliked the name "Public Utilities" under which we operated, as it&#13;
underlined monopolistic and regulatory features common to the three sectors,&#13;
whereas my goal was to emphasize instead the different contributions they made&#13;
to development and to seek the place that each deserved in country priorities and&#13;
the lending program. I eventually succeeded in getting the department's name&#13;
changed to Energy, Water and Telecommunications before Water and&#13;
Telecommunications were transferred to Transportation in 1979, leaving me in&#13;
charge of the Energy Department which I built up and managed through&#13;
February 1986.&#13;
At the outset, this was a small-scale operation. I was given initially a staff of&#13;
seven, including two and a half to deal with water and sanitation. Small was&#13;
beautiful, however. Harold Shipman, the engineer, was the uncontested sector&#13;
leader; Jeremy Warford, the economic adviser, whom I appointed later as the&#13;
adviser for the three sectors, was a first-rate professional, widely respected&#13;
among engineers, which was no small achievement in sectors where economists&#13;
tended to be regarded as charlatans. Jim Jennings, the department's financial&#13;
adviser, enjoyed the same recognition among his peers for his contributions to&#13;
institution- building in the water supply sector as well as finance. This leadership&#13;
advantage, combined with the professionalism of the water supply staff&#13;
constituted then as now a close knit community which was helpful in achieving&#13;
our common purposes. I added an engineer one or two years later with rural&#13;
water supply experience which was lacking in the Bank's Regions.&#13;
What, then, did we achieve in that period? To start with, a research and policy&#13;
paper commissioned under my predecessor on Village Water Supply, later&#13;
published as a book by Warford and Saunders, which showed the scope for&#13;
providing access to clean water in rural areas. This we followed later, in&#13;
cooperation with others, with research and testing of cheap easy-to-maintain&#13;
pumps that could help bring down costs to acceptable levels. We also produced&#13;
guidelines for sector work and developed marginal cost pricing to the operational&#13;
stage, an important topic since with the growth of cities, water had to be brought&#13;
from further afield at greater cost, requiring that water-intensive industries get&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                 13&#13;
&amp;#12;price signals to locate where water was more abundant and cheaper. This too&#13;
found its way into new lending, for example in Mombasa, where prices had to be&#13;
increased six-fold to reflect rapidly increasing supply costs.&#13;
Given the quality of our small staff, they were often exposed to demands for help&#13;
by regional managers under lending pressure. I had two rules in this regard, one,&#13;
that our staff should contribute original work, as, for example, Warford doing the&#13;
economic analysis of a lake pollution control project in Finland, a first at the&#13;
time; and two, that this work be written up and published in one of the&#13;
department's papers to facilitate replication by operational staff across the Bank.&#13;
As we set up shop, I had designed a few series of papers with which to focus and&#13;
disseminate our output. Besides policy and research, which were governed by&#13;
existing Bank rules, these series consisted of public utility notes, including state&#13;
of the art papers as well as guidelines to operational staff on a broad range of&#13;
topics from how to do sector work to how to estimate tunnel construction costs.&#13;
The latter were to be issued under the department's responsibility after peer&#13;
reviews and quality controls of our own, avoiding the endless and frustrating&#13;
clearances of the Bank's bureaucracy with which I had had all too much&#13;
experience as drafter of operational memoranda in previous incarnations. This&#13;
approach worked very well and helped generate and release a large number of&#13;
useful papers.&#13;
The urban policy proposed by Kim Jaycox in 1974, which found its way into&#13;
McNamara's next annual meeting speech, created an opportunity to boost water&#13;
supply lending. Given the emphasis on supplying the poor, the initial trend was&#13;
to focus on "reticulation" of supplies to the poor as part of urban projects,&#13;
ignoring the much bigger benefit that would result from involving water utilities&#13;
management and resources in providing access to the indigent. I issued a short&#13;
note on this subject making the point that urban water supply was a system&#13;
involving production and transport as well as distribution of water.            Our&#13;
experience showed that in most cities at the time, cross-subsidization from large&#13;
consumers to the poor could be arranged via free standpipes and graduated&#13;
tariffs, charging low rates for the first blocks of consumption meeting basic needs&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                 14&#13;
&amp;#12;     of households. I also asked Harold Shipman to set ambitious goals with the&#13;
     chiefs to expand lending in serving those purposes. They decided that lending&#13;
     .should double over the next five years which they were achieving by the time the&#13;
     central water supply function was transferred out of my department.&#13;
Q:   Although it's been awhile since you had direct responsibility for water and&#13;
     sanitation issues, we assume that you've followed those questions over the years.&#13;
     Today the Bank is recognized as a key player in water supply and sanitation, both&#13;
     in terms of knowledge sharing and financing in IDA countries while at the same&#13;
     time realizing that it cannot achieve improved development outcomes in isolation&#13;
     and needs to look at better donor coordination and partner mobilization. What is&#13;
     your view of the Bank's accomplishments in this area?&#13;
A:   The Bank was already a major player in water supply and sanitation in the '70s&#13;
     and not just in IDA countries. That was pretty obvious, for example, at the World&#13;
     Water Conference in Mar del Plata in 1976, where I represented the Bank. The&#13;
     IDB was also an important regional player. Much more, however, needed to be&#13;
     done by all, and we did have a blueprint for an ambitious program of urban water&#13;
     supply. On sanitation, the Bank's regions did very good and important work in a&#13;
     number of large cities, such as Sao Paolo, Algiers, and later Shanghai. For many&#13;
     smaller cities, however, affordability of waterborne sewage disposal was a&#13;
     problem. By 1979, my water/sanitation team had completed a research project on&#13;
     lower cost alternatives which was tested in Kabul, of all places. I am not aware of&#13;
     what happened in water supply and sanitation after the sector was transferred to&#13;
     the Transportation Department in mid-'79, because I had my hands full with the&#13;
     Energy Program.&#13;
     International cooperation was, of course, a live issue in the seventies also. My&#13;
     problem was how best to use the WHO/Bank Cooperative Program for which I&#13;
     had inherited responsibility, and which had been committed to doing sector work.&#13;
     This was an organizational nightmare since the program was run out of WHO&#13;
     headquarters in Geneva, even though the operational responsibilities belonged in&#13;
     WHO's six sovereign regional offices and the Bank's water supply operations&#13;
     had been regionalized. The Bank's regional staff was unhappy with the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     15&#13;
&amp;#12;     Program's output, complaining that they could make better use of the resources if&#13;
     only they were to be allocated to them. This was out of the question then, as&#13;
     management had intended this and other cooperative programs as a way to&#13;
     catalyze the resources of the partners in support of LDCs.&#13;
     In that spirit, I worked out a plan to transfer the management of the program to&#13;
     the regional offices of WHO, and the Bank's responsibilities for coordination&#13;
     with these offices to our regional divisions. My counterpart agreed to transfer&#13;
     empty slots that I could fill with experienced Bank staff with a mandate to act as&#13;
     catalysts of the health talent in WHO's regional offices. We tried this with&#13;
     P AHO and the South Asia region. I do not know what ensued after me.&#13;
Q:   On the question of water privatization, recent research results on the drinking&#13;
     water crisis show that views are mixed on this issue. Do you have a view on&#13;
     water privatization as a solution?&#13;
A:   No. Even though my own inclination is to favor private sector involvement as a&#13;
     source of effective management and, possibly, capital as well, I do not believe&#13;
     that it is a universal solution. I would consider merits on a case by case basis.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Oil price shocks of '73 and '79 made the world economy volatile and uncertain,&#13;
     and accommodating to higher petroleum prices proved to be a long-term problem&#13;
     in both the developed and developing world.         What policies did the Bank's&#13;
     Department of Energy which you directed between '72 and early '86 develop to&#13;
     help countries cope with adjusting to a world petroleum market of unprecedented&#13;
     high prices?&#13;
A:   That is a long story as we started from scratch and built the policy in steps over&#13;
     many years. When I took over as director of Public Utilities in late '72, the word&#13;
     "energy" was not in the Bank's vocabulary.          Power was, as part of Public&#13;
     Utilities; coal and refineries were, as part of Industry; and pipelines also, as part&#13;
     of Transportation. The policy specifically excluded oil and gas development to&#13;
     be left to the private sector. Our small group had been lifted from operations to&#13;
     be paid to think, a new and thrilling prospect for projects staff whose noses had&#13;
     been kept to the grindstone. After a few weeks, we had received two research&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                      16&#13;
&amp;#12;staff from the Economics vice presidency along with their work program in&#13;
power and telecommunications. As the Telecommunications division proved too&#13;
small to be broken up into the regions, it was recentralized into my department.&#13;
With those additions, we reached the critical mass that enabled me through&#13;
improvements in efficiency to reallocate resources over time to energy policy and&#13;
water supply.&#13;
Let me make two important points. First, within the Bank's operations complex,&#13;
it was impossible to obtain resources for non-operational work, such as energy&#13;
policy. Whatever you started with in 1972 would be your permanent endowment&#13;
Second, management inefficiencies were widespread in operations and, as I also&#13;
discovered, in research. I terminated four or five staff in the first year or two,&#13;
and replaced them with highly experienced people. My deputy, with primary&#13;
responsibility for electric power, was Fred Howell, then one of the two most&#13;
respected power engineers in the Bank. When he transferred to a region a few&#13;
years later, Richard Sheehan, the other most senior power sector staff and a&#13;
friend of both of us, replaced him. As the department was being set up, I was able&#13;
to attract Efrain Friedman, a broad gauged engineer and former official from&#13;
Chile who had joined the Bank when professionals were fleeing the chaos&#13;
created under the Allende regime and who was under-utilized as the power&#13;
engineer assigned to Burundi. I made him my de facto energy adviser, a position&#13;
in which I was able to confirm him later and which grew quickly in importance&#13;
along with the energy policy to which he contributed. As we put together our&#13;
first work program, we decided to take a broad look at the energy picture and&#13;
commissioned a series of state of the art papers on energy sources and issues in&#13;
developing countries.&#13;
When the first oil shock came in the fall of '73 and the price of oil quadrupled,&#13;
McNamara asked Hollis Chenery, his Chief Economist, to review the impact on&#13;
the prospects of developing countries. Within that exercise, I was asked to&#13;
contribute papers on the impact of the higher prices on the main consuming&#13;
sectors and on the energy supply prospects of oil-importing developing countries.&#13;
While we had a head start on all other sources, we knew next to nothing about oil&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                17&#13;
&amp;#12;and gas. Yet, the best alternative to imported oil at the new high prices would be&#13;
domestic oil and gas if they could be found and developed at a lesser cost. Given&#13;
that whatever was in the ground would be four times more valuable, there had to&#13;
be interesting potential in      oil-importing developing countries.        So we&#13;
commissioned a quick review by a geologist from the U.S. Geological Survey.&#13;
The results, based primarily on a comparison of the intensity of drilling across&#13;
regions and countries, looked extremely promising. For example, he described&#13;
Africa, where many poor countries were suffering badly from the higher oil&#13;
prices,                 as            a             "sleeping                giant."&#13;
After the "Prospects Paper," as it was called, had been finalized and put to rest, I&#13;
went to see Ernie Stem, then a director in the economic staff, who had been the&#13;
mastermind behind that paper, to discuss a follow-up strategy to help oil-&#13;
importing developing countries adjust over the longer term by investing in&#13;
energy production from all appropriate sources.       His reply was, "Hold your&#13;
horses; the President's primary concern is to increase financial flows and&#13;
concessional aid to developing countries. He would not want his message to be&#13;
confused by your ideas about energy investments. This is not the time." So that&#13;
was the last of this.&#13;
We remained intrigued, however, by the potential suggested by the geological&#13;
expert's study and decided to learn more about it. We asked the views of the&#13;
French Petroleum Institute (IFP), as the most knowledgeable independent&#13;
organization. Their reply was most encouraging. Much to our surprise, they&#13;
asked if our enquiry was Mr. McNamara's response to a letter that they had sent&#13;
him suggesting that the World Bank consider financing oil and gas development.&#13;
They also said that the Indians had made an important offshore discovery, called&#13;
Bombay High, whieh they thought was typical of what the Bank should finance. I&#13;
had no knowledge of the letter they mentioned, and it was the first that we had&#13;
heard of Bombay High, a name which was to become very familiar less than two&#13;
years later.&#13;
Based on these conversations, in December 1974 we decided to commission the&#13;
IFP to conduct a country-by-country study of the petroleum potential of oil-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                 18&#13;
&amp;#12;importing developing countries, of what, if any, activities were taking place, and&#13;
of the obstacles   legal, technical, and otherwise   to the desirable exploration&#13;
and development by the private sector. As I cleared this possibly sensitive study&#13;
and the nationality of the consultant with Warren Baum, I asked for financial&#13;
help. The study cost $40,000 and I only had $20,000. He said that he did not&#13;
have any budget of his own to help the sector departments reporting to him. So I&#13;
went to Mahbub Ul Haq, the policy director under Hollis Chenery, outlined the&#13;
purpose and asked if he could help. He was enthusiastic about the idea, and&#13;
promised to contribute the $20,000 and more from Chenery's budget should&#13;
there be any overrun. The only thing he would ask was that when this story was&#13;
told, I remember to give him credit for having supported this great idea. I also&#13;
asked his advice on dealing with McNamara. He consulted Hollis Chenery who&#13;
said that I should not ask McNamara's opinion as he might well say no. Instead, I&#13;
should inform him, through Warren Baum, that I had commissioned the study.&#13;
He would not interfere with my decision after the fact. On the other hand, he&#13;
would not forgive me if he learned about this study from outside sources. That&#13;
proved to be good advice as I did not hear from McNamara.&#13;
Then, in the fall of '75, I received a phone call from Ernie Stern who, meanwhile,&#13;
had become Vice-President of the South Asia Region. He said, "Look up the&#13;
India Country Program Paper. There is a paragraph for you that I am asking&#13;
McNamara to focus on and discuss. Make sure that you are prepared to deal with&#13;
the consequences." The paragraph said that the Indian government was asking&#13;
the Bank to consider lending for oil and gas development. So, the President&#13;
would ask the Region to find out what exactly the Indians were looking for and&#13;
would ask someone else to review the Bank's policy. I had to make sure that I&#13;
was that someone. I told the story to Warren Baum who was attending these&#13;
meetings for CPS and asked him to get me the job, which he did.&#13;
By then, we had received the IFP Study, which was most helpful in making a&#13;
case for overturning the Bank's policy of non-involvement in oil and gas. There&#13;
was undeveloped potential in many countries and a clear role for the Bank to&#13;
play in helping attract private oil companies to countries in which they were&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                19&#13;
&amp;#12;inactive, and also to help national oil companies develop their country's potential&#13;
as would be the case in India. The paper recommending the policy change was&#13;
discussed in April '76. Before the meeting, my boss warned me not to get my&#13;
hopes up as the chances of being turned down were very high. And, indeed they,&#13;
were, as the meeting confirmed. If this is so attractive, why not let the private&#13;
sector do their job? What about the Bank's priority to eradicate poverty? Why&#13;
should we build up the Bank's bureaucracy with yet another field of lending?&#13;
Supporters were few, though very important, among whom the Bank's Chief&#13;
Economist who had supported our study, and the head ofthe Africa region which&#13;
had been most affected and would most benefit from the development of&#13;
domestic resources. After hearing from everyone, McNamara said that the Bank&#13;
should help finance any project that had a high return, presented acceptable risks&#13;
and could not be financed from other sources. And that included oil and gas. He&#13;
then turned to me and asked, "Are you happy? Do you want to add anything?" I&#13;
replied that all I needed were the resources to launch a program, to which he said&#13;
that I should ask the budget people. I promptly did and received zero. I was&#13;
angry at first having mistaken McNamara's pronouncement as support when all&#13;
that he had done was to avoid saying no. The issue was dead in the Bank. I had&#13;
not obtained one cent for energy work of any kind since the oil shock two and a&#13;
half years earlier and would not for one more fiscal year, through June 1977.&#13;
Interesting things, however, were happening in the outside world, and three&#13;
external factors eventually forced the attention of the Bank's management. The&#13;
internal paper recommending the new oil policy was leaked - not by me or any&#13;
of my small staff- to country officials involved in a North/South dialogue in&#13;
Paris where talks about a new world economic order were about to end&#13;
inconclusively. That leak revealed wide support, including from the U.S., for an&#13;
active role by the Bank in energy development, including oil. The chairman of&#13;
the Paris meetings, Mr. Yeganeeh, came to see me to encourage me to promote&#13;
the idea. From the State Department the message was, "we will smoke out,"&#13;
because I disclaimed having any policy mandate. The U.S. Federal Energy&#13;
Administration, as it had been called, was favorable. They had even volunteered&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                20&#13;
&amp;#12;to sound out U.S. oil companies on a possible Bank role and had reported that&#13;
there was support from some because of the potential for improving the&#13;
investment climate, and from others negative indifference rather than outright&#13;
opposition. I spent a Sunday in Buenos Aires before the start of the World Water&#13;
Conference with a friend, a former Secretary for Fuels, who, much to my&#13;
surprise, knew all about the proposed policy and was eager to see the Bank&#13;
involved in Argentina to help improve the performance ofYPF, their national oil&#13;
company.&#13;
Another external development was a proposal by Henry Kissinger for a&#13;
multilateral system of guarantees which he thought was needed to foster mineral&#13;
development in developing countries. The proposal made originally to the UN&#13;
had been going nowhere until someone had the bright idea to suggest that it be&#13;
referred to the Bank. I was forewarned by U.S. contacts that this was going to&#13;
happen, and that they wanted the development of oil and gas to be considered as&#13;
part of the review. So when the Kissinger proposal was referred to the Bank, I&#13;
arranged to be invited, along with my Industry Department colleague, to the&#13;
internal discussions about the proposal. We agreed that there was nothing in the&#13;
Kissinger proposal that the Bank could not do, and that a new instrument need&#13;
not be created. We should, instead, propose to our Board a lending program for&#13;
energy and mineral development. I offered to the chairman of our task force who&#13;
was to do the drafting, the paper on oil and gas that had already been reviewed by&#13;
management, plus any help that he might want from us. He had been reluctant to&#13;
include oil and gas in the discussions, arguing that they were not considered&#13;
generally as minerals and may not have been part of the scheme that Kissinger&#13;
had in mind. I thought, however, that I had persuaded him that the U.S., who was&#13;
referring the matter to us, viewed oil and gas as an essential component. What&#13;
was to my surprise then was to learn a few weeks later that the paper which was&#13;
about to be discussed by Management had omitted oil and gas. The management&#13;
meeting saved the day and we were given a few days to add the case for oil and&#13;
gas to the paper which went to the Board as "Minerals and Energy in the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                21&#13;
&amp;#12;Developing Countries." The discussion, on July 8, 1977, centered on energy and&#13;
resulted in a clear policy in support of oil and gas development.&#13;
I had been given two positions for the coming fiscal year, which was clearly&#13;
inadequate to launch the proposed program. Mr. McNamara called me to his&#13;
office after the Board meeting and gave me six more, including one for policy&#13;
and strategy work. As a sad comment on the Bank's budgeting system, this was&#13;
typical of the formative years of the energy programs when only one-third of the&#13;
resources came through the regular budget, and two-thirds through the personal&#13;
intervention of the President or Ernie Stern. That was the start of an oil and gas&#13;
projects division, under Philippe Bourcier, which also included a petroleum&#13;
engineer who transferred with his pipelines work program from                  the&#13;
Transportation department, compliments of its director Chris Willoughby.&#13;
And finally, it was an initiative of the Indian government which started us on the&#13;
path to oil and gas lending. About mid '76, they asked for a mission to advise on&#13;
the development of an offshore discovery of oil and gas, called Bombay High, by&#13;
their national oil company, ONGC. I assigned Philippe Bourcier to lead the&#13;
mission and borrowed a pipeline engineer from Transportation and a chemical&#13;
engineer from Industry to complete the team. I had recruited Philippe from the&#13;
Bank's EMENA Region a couple of years earlier to be our first energy economist&#13;
and lead energy sector missions, which he had done particularly well in Korea.&#13;
Before joining the department, he had worked as a transport economist and led&#13;
appraisals of gas pipeline projects as well as other complex projects such as the&#13;
Suez Canal rehabilitation. Before joining the Bank, he had worked on&#13;
international projects for the consulting arm of Gaz de France. I could not have&#13;
wished for a better combination of oil and gas expertise, leadership talent and&#13;
Bank experience. Upon his return, Bourcier told me that he had laid out the&#13;
terms of reference for three sets of consultants and helped put together lists of&#13;
international consultants capable of helping them for this offshore development.&#13;
They seemed to appreciate the advice, but he believed that we wouldn't hear&#13;
from them for some time, if at all. Only a few weeks later, however, ONGC was&#13;
asking for Bourcier's return to review progress and discuss next steps, which he&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                22&#13;
&amp;#12;was able to do within a few days.       By the Fall, the Bank received a formal&#13;
request from the Indian government to finance the project. The government had&#13;
wanted the Bank's involvement, but ONGC had been reluctant. The quality of&#13;
the professional help that they received convinced them to seek Bank financing,&#13;
and so it was that the prophecy of the French Petroleum Institute came to be&#13;
fulfilled as we presented the Bombay High oil and gas development project to the&#13;
Board at their last meeting of the fiscal year, and one week before they discussed&#13;
and approved the new policy for oil and gas lending in early July. The project&#13;
was appraised in record time because of our prior association with its design, the&#13;
quality of the ONGC staff, and a joint effort with our country program colleagues&#13;
to act promptly on any issue requiring Bank decision to ensure that critical steps&#13;
could be taken by ONGC before the monsoon season. The project was completed&#13;
on time and was hugely successfuL It reduced India's dependence on imported&#13;
oil by 400,000 barrels/day, a substantial figure relative to India's requirements at&#13;
the time. It helped substitute modern technology for the Russian technology used&#13;
previously.   Last but not least, the actual return was very high, exceeding&#13;
expectations, and the payback period was very short.&#13;
This was also the beginning of a long friendship. The Chairman served as a&#13;
mission leader of several of our energy asse.ssments after he retired, and his&#13;
successor and the engineer in charge of the offshore development both joined the&#13;
energy department where they had distinguished careers. I mention this to point&#13;
out that one of the reasons for the quality of our recruitment was that we were&#13;
recruiting from the elite of our borrowers. The Board asked to review the results&#13;
of the policy after one year of experience. So another paper had to be prepared,&#13;
which we called, "An Accelerated Program for Hydrocarbons Exploration and&#13;
Development," and was discussed by the Board in late 1979. Oil and gas lending&#13;
had become very popular with management and Board, which accounts for the&#13;
word "accelerated." The exploration part is another story. Agriculture and&#13;
Energy were now favorite topics of Summit meetings and we would receive&#13;
sherpas' visits to give ideas and/or report progress. So as the Venice meeting was&#13;
being prepared, they were asking why oil development was not progressing faster&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                23&#13;
&amp;#12;in oil importing countries, to which the answer was obvious: oil has to be found&#13;
before it can be developed. The stumbling block was in exploration, more of&#13;
which was needed to generate further discoveries. When McNamara saw the&#13;
Summit communique, he called me to his office and said, "I knew it all along.&#13;
Exploration is the problem. We should set up an exploration fund. You write me&#13;
the justification and I will find the money." I was being hoisted by my own&#13;
petard, as they say. I had never intended the need for exploration to be a&#13;
prescription for Bank involvement. The difficulties of exploration were not my&#13;
concern. We could gear up to do it if we had to. The problem was that once in&#13;
charge of an exploration fund, we would have to act like an oil company to make&#13;
it a success, and no longer act as a development institution. We would shun&#13;
Madagascar, where discovering a few thousand barrel/day of output would make&#13;
a difference for the country's development, and go find oil where it had already&#13;
been found, as, for example, in Angola, where more oil would likely have&#13;
adverse effects.    As I failed to deliver promptly, McNamara entrusted the&#13;
justification to a colleague in his entourage who was able to convince him to&#13;
forget it. We still were required to undertake efforts to help foster exploration if&#13;
necessary by countries and at their risk.&#13;
The Board had asked for a progress report on the implementation of the program&#13;
by October 1980. In the spring of that year, while Ernie Stem was in Indonesia, I&#13;
received a call from McNamara who normally would not deal with me directly.&#13;
He wanted to have the progress report issued and reviewed by the Board before&#13;
the next annual meeting. I said that it could be done. The problem, however, was&#13;
that a second oil shock had occurred recently. A mere progress report would be&#13;
an anti-climax. After the first shock, we had taken the lead in a vacuum. This&#13;
time, I could see all kinds of initiatives taking place, many of which made little&#13;
sense. What was needed if the Bank was to retain its leadership was not a&#13;
progress report on oil but a comprehensive energy policy. He said, "You are so&#13;
right. When can I get it?" I replied that I did not believe it was humanly possible&#13;
without extra resources. So he set the deadline and told me to send him the bill. I&#13;
did and received no reply. I felt that I had committed professional suicide. To top&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                 24&#13;
&amp;#12;it all, Stern was furious that I had taken this initiative. We managed, with some&#13;
help from Baum and Stern, to produce this first comprehensive paper which&#13;
addressed the demand side, including conservation and pricing issues and put the&#13;
various sources of supply, including renewables into perspective. We flagged&#13;
once more the need to step up the domestic use of natural gas in oil exporting as&#13;
well as oil importing countries. There was a strong consensus among&#13;
management and Board to promote energy lending from all sources, including&#13;
power as well as oil and gas to about 25% of Bank lending.&#13;
There was also the episode of the Energy Affiliate, which flared up before dying&#13;
eventually a few months later by the time McNamara resigned. The Energy&#13;
Affiliate was to be set up with funding of around $30 billion, ostensibly to handle&#13;
the energy lending. It was, in fact, nothing but a gimmick to generate the&#13;
additional resources required to fund the needs of China, which had just joined&#13;
the Bank's membership, and of the nascent structural adjustment program, as&#13;
these had not been anticipated in the recent capital increase of the Bank and&#13;
replenishment of IDA.&#13;
The next policy paper, in '83, another comprehensive review, was both better and&#13;
easier to prepare as we had accumulated considerable experience across most&#13;
countries from continued lending for oil and gas, feedback from power lending&#13;
by the regions, and from our energy assessment program initiated three years&#13;
earlier. The mood had changed around the Board, reflecting principally lower oil&#13;
prices and a changed U.S. administration which was now hostile to our program,&#13;
including lending to national oil companies, and demanded that guidelines be&#13;
drawn to rein in our initiatives.&#13;
Allow me to add a few words on our lending program, beginning with petroleum&#13;
exploration. We were not keen to finance exploration at the risk of countries as&#13;
we had been mandated to do. So we did few projects, and those we did undertake&#13;
were carefully evaluated. As we were reviewing our first project in Morocco, I&#13;
set up a committee of our geologists - former senior geologists from oil&#13;
companies, such as Exxon and Shell - to review all of the data and provide an&#13;
independent opinion before we decided to proceed. That ensured that any&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                    25&#13;
&amp;#12;mistake made was made with our eyes open. What enabled us to accelerate&#13;
exploration at no risk to the country was the concept of the exploration&#13;
promotion project which we invented to spare Madagascar from getting involved&#13;
without the necessary skills as they had originally requested. Given the positive&#13;
experience, we replicated the concept on a large scale helping 25 countries within&#13;
a few years. What we financed was the preparation of a package of reprocessed&#13;
and complemented geophysical data, of updated legislation, model contracts and&#13;
incentives, their promotion to the oil industry, and the professional assistance&#13;
needed to help the country negotiate with successful bidders. The loans ranged&#13;
from $5 to $8 million. We also developed with Gulf Oil and Pakistan the so-&#13;
called letter of intent approach under which Gulf felt sufficiently protected by the&#13;
Bank's presence from the political risk they feared to invest about $80 million in&#13;
exploration, which, regrettably, they lost, but Pakistan did not. Most if not all of&#13;
our development projects were successful. Some significant examples:&#13;
1) The rehabilitation of China's super-giant DaChinh oil field, which involved a&#13;
massive transfer of modem technology and restored production from the field's&#13;
production at a time when China was sti11 exporting oil. We were able to send an&#13;
11-person mission, a majority from our own staff with all the top skills required&#13;
for such a complex effort.&#13;
2) A series of oil and gas projects in India, which also helped mobilize private&#13;
financing when access to foreign sources was still limited, and helped expand&#13;
exploration and generate discoveries by foreign as well as domestic companies.&#13;
3) A series of projects in Thailand, starting with a submarine pipeline gathering&#13;
gas from offshore fields, which introduced gas into the Thai economy just as we&#13;
had helped spread electricity use starting with the Yanhee Hydroelectric project&#13;
in the mid' 50s.&#13;
4) Projects done jointly with the private sector, such as the Colombia petroleum&#13;
development with Occidental, etc.&#13;
5) The gas projects in Egypt, which included recovery of flared gas from the Gulf&#13;
of Suez to substitute for fuel in a power station; the gas distribution project in&#13;
Cairo; the Abu Qir offshore gas development supplying Alexandria and the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                26&#13;
&amp;#12;Western Desert exploration project, which helped find oil as well as gas, and&#13;
whose success attracted private oil companies back to that area where they made&#13;
more discoveries.&#13;
Over time, our lending became primarily for gas development, involving chiefly&#13;
domestic infrastructure, and thus inherently less interesting to foreign oil&#13;
companies. We had built up unique skills to deal with the entire chain, from field&#13;
development to the ultimate power, industrial and domestic user, and were&#13;
testing in project components in Bangladesh, Egypt, and Tanzania the use of&#13;
compressed natural gas in automobiles and buses as a clean fuel to substitute for&#13;
gasoline in gas rich countries.&#13;
To conclude, I would like to add a few words on the staffing of the oil and gas&#13;
program. It was a huge and successful effort to which I gave considerable&#13;
attention both in finding and screening staff. The recruitment plans were laid out&#13;
well before positions were obtained so that we wasted no time. For example,&#13;
when the Telecommunication operations and the Water Supply operational&#13;
support were transferred to the Transportation department in mid-1979, our&#13;
professional staff dropped from 28 to 14. By mid-1980, we were back to 28&#13;
having replaced the staff lost to Transportation and the energy staff lost to&#13;
attrition with the geologists, geophysicists, petroleum engineers, financial&#13;
analysts, and economists needed for the accelerated program that we were&#13;
mandated to implement.       Part of our recruitment was internal which helped&#13;
absorb the external recruits into our teams. Surprisingly, and happily, a number&#13;
of the volunteer ex YPs had prior petroleum and/or mining experience and&#13;
enough Bank experience to contribute, in some cases as division chiefs or&#13;
deputies. A shining example of this was Eugene McCarthy who combined a&#13;
mining background with Bank experience as manager of the Young Professional&#13;
Program. He made an outstanding contribution as the manager of our petroleum&#13;
lending in Asia, the Middle East, and Europe. Most of our external recruits were&#13;
executives from our petroleum industry borrowers with prior experience with&#13;
international oil companies and degrees from the best technical schools of the&#13;
West. We recruited senior staff from the international oil companies as they&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  27&#13;
&amp;#12;     retired at age 55. I had an informal arrangement with Shell, who referred top&#13;
     geologists and geophysicists to us, while we seconded several of our economists&#13;
     to Shell over time, some serving as Shell's Chief Economist. I managed the&#13;
     recruitment process to ensure systematic involvement of staff as well as&#13;
     managers in profile definition, identification, follow up, and interviews. I saw&#13;
     every candidate and reviewed every interview note to ensure effectiveness of the&#13;
     process. We made very few mistakes.&#13;
Q:   Please discuss the energy sector assessment program launched jointly with the&#13;
     UNDP, which was followed by the establishment in '83 of the Energy Sector&#13;
     Management Assistance program.       What was your role and contribution, and&#13;
     how do you see the Bank's contribution?&#13;
A:   The quadrupling of oil prices in '73 had introduced chaos in the energy picture of&#13;
     developing countries. Priorities had to be reordered. Policies had to be rethought,&#13;
     including, for instance, those governing pricing or the investment climate as&#13;
     needed to attract foreign capital and skills. I thought from day one that the Bank&#13;
     had an important role to play and that it was my responsibility to build the&#13;
     capacity and the know-how to deliver the advice that was needed. So I started&#13;
     recruiting heavyweights that I could lend to Operations to lead sector missions or&#13;
     to contribute to economic missions. I mentioned the success of Bourcier in Korea&#13;
     before he had to be reassigned to petroleum development. I replaced him. with&#13;
     Fallen-Bailey, who was energy omniscient with experience as a senior oil&#13;
     company geologist, a coal mining engineer, and an international consultant for&#13;
     the UN whom I could lend, for example, to contribute a judgment on the size of&#13;
     the oil reserves of Mexico as part of a country economic report.&#13;
     By the end of 1979, the need for energy sector assistance had become even more&#13;
     obvious, and we had built up, at the rate of one or two exercises a year, the&#13;
     experience necessary to put together an effective action program which I&#13;
     recommended in the policy paper that we issued at the time, though without any&#13;
     tangible result. Ernie Stern agreed to the need but said that the budget resources&#13;
     were lacking. He would, however, support my request to UNDP for a joint&#13;
     program to which they eventually agreed. I had called for a program of Energy&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     28&#13;
&amp;#12;Assessments to avoid confusion with the Bank's conventional sector work. The&#13;
new term concerned Baum and Stern, so over two weekends, I designed the&#13;
guidelines that helped clarify this new concept. The primary purpose was to&#13;
serve the country, which we would involve in the ownership of the exercise&#13;
including the design and production to the extent possible. The secondary&#13;
benefits would accrue to the Bank and others in the international community as a&#13;
means of focusing their respective contributions. For these purposes to be served,&#13;
Energy Assessments should be action documents focused on priority issues and&#13;
the options to deal with them. All reports would be published and made available&#13;
freely to anyone interested in contributing to the country's energy development.&#13;
That, in my mind, was also an incentive for us to be most careful about their&#13;
quality.&#13;
Energy Assessments Missions should not be fishing expeditions as some of the&#13;
traditional sector work I had observed, where staff had to gather everything and&#13;
the kitchen sink to protect themselves against any and all questions. The all&#13;
important preparation phase included reviews of the literature, for which we built&#13;
an energy library, and of the knowledge accumulated in the Bank and in the&#13;
international community. Based on the findings, a preliminary agenda of issues&#13;
was prepared and finalized after discussion with country officials. The country's&#13;
support was discussed, agreement to publish was confirmed, and the timing and&#13;
composition of the mission decided. The mission's report was reviewed in the&#13;
department, the Bank, and eventually the country before being finalized for&#13;
publication. The UNDP made a sizeable cash commitment against which we&#13;
were able to create term positions. I restructured the department to generate four&#13;
initial positions, including the manager, Julian Bahrier, whose performance&#13;
turned out to be brilliant. I lent the services of my personal assistant, Zia Kalim,&#13;
to UNDP to help with their fundraising from bilateral donors as multilateral&#13;
funding became exhausted. That enabled us to also get feedback from donors on&#13;
our performance and to get their input into our priority selections for new work.&#13;
We also held donor meetings jointly with UNDP.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                 29&#13;
&amp;#12;     We had our own mission leaders, supplemented with high caliber consultants&#13;
     from outside or from the regions. We also supplemented our nucleus of&#13;
     Assessments staff with operational staff from our petroleum divisions and from&#13;
     regional power. We were delighted to have country economists involved as they&#13;
     provided a precious link with the Bank's knowledge and country economic work.&#13;
     What mattered to us was to retain control over the process and the quality of the&#13;
     output. I was delighted when the Country director for Nigeria asked to lead the&#13;
     debriefing mission, and when he told me on his return that all key people were&#13;
     attending and that it was the most rewarding policy dialogue he had had in that&#13;
     country. The program called for assessments in 60 countries over five years.&#13;
     After a couple of years, I asked a former director of the Bank to evaluate our&#13;
     initial performance. His report showed that while the assessment program itself&#13;
     was a success, countries were often at a loss on how to arrange follow-up actions.&#13;
     So I did some brainstorming with Julian Bahrier and Masood Ahmed, his deputy,&#13;
     which led us to propose to UNDP an amended program which we called the&#13;
     Energy Sector Management Assistance Program (ESMAP), which they promptly&#13;
     endorsed. The balance of the energy assessments was to be continued under the&#13;
     new name as originally planned. In addition, however, we designed a number of&#13;
     product lines to address the disparate follow-up actions identified by the&#13;
     assessments. ESMAP gave us a flexible tool to help with sector management and&#13;
     do pre-feasibility studies to develop preliminary ideas to the point where they&#13;
     could be picked up by bilateral donors as studies or investments. Issues of rural&#13;
     energy supply, renewable energies, and conservation could be more effectively&#13;
     addressed with this instrument and bilateral funding than via Bank lending. One&#13;
     particularly successful product line in the early years, which Bank power lending&#13;
     was not addressing, consisted in programs to cut power distribution losses&#13;
     involving primarily transfers of know-how, which brought high returns on small&#13;
     investments.&#13;
Q:   How    would   you   assess   your   contribution,   and   the   impact   of your&#13;
     accomplishments as Director of the Energy Department? Is there anything you'd&#13;
     like to add?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     30&#13;
&amp;#12;A:     My contribution was to have seen the opportunity for the Bank to play a leading&#13;
       role in energy development, and to have converted the idea into a policy and&#13;
       programs of operations and sector management assistance responsive to&#13;
       countries' needs despite an environment in the Bank that for several years was&#13;
       indifferent at best. I assembled a highly motivated and skilled staff in the Energy&#13;
       Department Together we left behind a trail of successful oil and gas projects&#13;
       and ESMAP which reflected well on the Bank's image.&#13;
Q:     We assume that you've continued to follow the Bank's promotion of energy&#13;
       development at a distance. Do you have any comments on the Bank's current&#13;
       energy strategy?&#13;
A: ,   On the broad lines of energy strategy and the related environmental issues, the&#13;
       little I know indicates that the Bank's thinking is entirely correct. The problem&#13;
       that I have with the promotion of energy development is that the Bank's&#13;
       management dispersed the Energy Department in 1986-87, thus destroying the&#13;
       formidable development tool constituted by the capacity to integrate energy&#13;
       policy, strategy and operations with each other and with country policies.&#13;
Q:     You sound critical ofthe Bank's reorganizations. Could you elaborate?&#13;
A:     The 1972 reorganization had both positive and negative aspects. Whereas the&#13;
       reorganization of 1987 was all bad, the principal benefit of the 1972&#13;
       reorganization was the rich policy and operational developments which were&#13;
       generated in all sectors by the creation of the Central Project's Staff, as clearly&#13;
       intended by McNamara. On the other hand, the quality control function that had&#13;
       previously been ensured by the Projects front office, did not survive the&#13;
       reorganization. Lending volume targets became the primary incentive under&#13;
       which the regions operated overruling quality concerns. The quality control&#13;
       function that we in CPS could have contributed was powerfully dissuaded. We&#13;
       were instructed to offer quality "enhancement" instead of "control," as the latter&#13;
       was too objectionable. We were asked to make our comments "upstream" before&#13;
       the facts were in; since negative views were unwelcome once an operation was&#13;
       on the launching pad to hit the Board on schedule. And we were told to be&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       31&#13;
&amp;#12;     "selective." So bad things went through across all sectors, including certainly&#13;
     power that could have been avoided.&#13;
     The '87 reorganization decentralized the Bank further into smaller country- or&#13;
     group of countries - operational units with control over all resources, and&#13;
     weakened the central functional units by turning them into pools of experts&#13;
     competing with external consultants for resources from the operational units.&#13;
     Smaller units vested with the responsibility of delivering the ever-expanding&#13;
     panoply of Bank services could no longer afford experts of their own as a result&#13;
     of which much Bank sector experience was lost and could not be renewed. How&#13;
     could you recruit a world caliber expert in dams, irrigation, or geology as we&#13;
     used to do to work on a set of three countries in East Africa? You cannot, and&#13;
     instead you hire generalists and depend on consultants to contribute the cutting&#13;
     edge professional experience on which the Bank's reputation was based. The&#13;
     reorganized Bank relied massively on prematurely retired former staff to fill this&#13;
     need. With time, this resource will disappear to be replaced by whatever the&#13;
     consulting market place has to offer. A major benefit of centrally managed&#13;
     professional groups with a worldwide mandate such as existed before 1972, and&#13;
     in energy and industry thereafter, is that what was learned in one country was&#13;
     passed on to others without delay or geographical limit.&#13;
     What "world" remains in "World" Bank if all that you can bring to a country is&#13;
     what you have learned in the country itself or its immediate neighbors? The&#13;
     World Bank of 1992 bore little resemblance to either the IBRD, which I&#13;
     described at the beginning of this interview, or to the Bank we were dreaming of&#13;
     when conceiving the energy policy and programs.&#13;
Q:   Thank you very much, Mr. Rovani.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     32&#13;
&amp;#12;                    Yves Rovani Interview -March 25, 2003&#13;
&#13;
                   Q:                      Today is Tuesday, March 25th and I'm William Becker.&#13;
                    Q:                     And I'm Marie Zenni.&#13;
                   A:                      And I am Yves Rovani.&#13;
                    Q:                     We would like to begin by asking about your appointment as Director General of&#13;
                                           Operations Evaluations (DGO) in March '86.           In particular, what in your&#13;
                                           experience led to your appointment as Director General?&#13;
                   A:                      I was surprised to be offered that job because in 1984 when I beard that Mervyn&#13;
                                           Weiner was leaving, I told Ernie Stem that I would be interested in the position.&#13;
                                           His answer was, "You are superbly qualified, but you are too late.           Other&#13;
                                           arrangements have been made, which will in effect lock out this position for&#13;
                                           many years."     Under those arrangements, the Director of the Operations&#13;
        RESTRICTED                         Evaluation Department (OED), Shiv Kapur, was promoted to DGO for about 18&#13;
       WBG ARCHIVES&#13;
&#13;
        MAR 1 6 2011                                                       I forgot about the matter. Then in late '85, I told&#13;
                                           Management that I wanted to resign my position as Director of Energy because I&#13;
                                           could no longer work for Jean-Loup Dberse, the Vice President whom they bad&#13;
                                           appointed over me. He was incompetent and destructive.         After two years of&#13;
                                           holding the fort, I was loosing my sanity and wanted out. The answer was not to&#13;
                                           worry and to wait a while longer. And then in February Tom Clausen offered me&#13;
       RESTRICTED&#13;
      WBG ARCHIVES                         the post of DGO.&#13;
&#13;
      MAR 1 6 2011&#13;
                                           As to my qualifications, first, I bad the character, the integrity and the backbone&#13;
Bxception__,;;t_.:- - - -&#13;
{!           v.;t. 1c'1A. /?'vti::f::..(   that are fundamental for this position. Second, I bad the motivation. I was very&#13;
                                           supportive of the goals set by McNamara for the evaluation function. As be was&#13;
                                           leading the Bank into more difficult and risky ventures, be wanted an&#13;
                                           independent evaluation to substitute for the market test to which Bank operations&#13;
                                           were not subjected. And he wanted this same instrument to ensure that the&#13;
                                           lessons from the Bank's experience be systematically learned and reinvested.&#13;
                                           That coincided with my own management style of which self evaluation was an&#13;
                                           important part. ESMAP and Exploration promotion are two programs, for&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                           33&#13;
&amp;#12;     example, that came out of self evaluation. In addition, I had been involved, on&#13;
     the management side, in the early stages of the evaluation system that McNamara&#13;
     had introduced. I participated in the review of QED's Colombia and Power&#13;
     studies as part of the management team of the Projects Department. And as&#13;
     director of Public Utilities, I had been responsible, first for preparing the&#13;
     Management Response to the Power study's recommendations; second, for&#13;
     implementing the recommendations which I had accepted; and third, for&#13;
     preparing the Closing Report accounting for their implementation.&#13;
     I was also familiar, as a former member of the management teams of Projects&#13;
     prior to '72 and of the Central Projects Staff after that date, with all Bank policies&#13;
     and issues related to lending, another essential qualification needed to discharge&#13;
     that function. Finally, I had a wealth of management experience which proved&#13;
     handy in dealing with the circumstances of OED when I took over. Despite these&#13;
     qualifications, my appointment caused an uproar in the Board, as it had not been&#13;
     consulted. Clausen had told me that since the DGO was appointed by the Board,&#13;
     as required by his independent status, he would meet with their Joint Audit&#13;
     Committee to seek their endorsement before submitting my name to the entire&#13;
     Board for approval. He did nothing of the kind and instead circulated my name&#13;
     on a no objection basis, with a week's deadline, as was the custom for the&#13;
     appointment of regular vice-presidents. And then he left, leaving it to Stem to&#13;
     fight it out with the Board. As for me, I left for Florida and came back when I&#13;
     heard that my appointment had been approved. This story shows how much the&#13;
     Bank's Management had come to interfere with the independence of the&#13;
     function. This was also true of the budget of OED and my performance and&#13;
     salary about which the Board had no say.&#13;
Q:   What goals did you set for yourself upon becoming OED's third Director&#13;
     General, at a time when development effectiveness was being increasingly&#13;
     questioned?&#13;
A:   My goals as DGO were the very objectives set for the operation evaluation&#13;
     function by Robert McNamara: to produce credible and relevant independent&#13;
     evaluations of Bank policies and operations; and to encourage self evaluation and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                      34&#13;
&amp;#12;                             to help the Bank learn from its experience. In this connection, I also aimed to&#13;
                             reactivate the system of management responses and closing reports which had&#13;
                             fallen into disuse after McNamara left the Bank. In short, my aim was to assess&#13;
                             and improve the Bank's development effectiveness.&#13;
                             Soon after I arrived on the scene, I arranged a staff retreat in Annapolis to debate&#13;
                             the goals of evaluation. I put on the agenda of the opening session the two topics&#13;
                             most relevant to our work        the environment and development effectiveness.&#13;
                             The Bank's management preempted my goal of using the term for OED's output&#13;
                             by commissioning an annual report on effectiveness. The author assigned would&#13;
                             come to me for ideas for topics and data, and we would oblige. And then we&#13;
                             would hear nothing further. One day, Mr. Conable asked me what I thought of&#13;
                             the report. I said that as far as I was concerned, it wasn't worth the paper it was&#13;
                             written on. He was startled, so I went on to explain that I had not read the report&#13;
                             because it was too confidential for me to get it, which, given the subject, was&#13;
                             simply absurd. As a politician, he was quick to see the point. That was the last I&#13;
                             heard of that report.&#13;
              Q:             You implied that the director of OED had left it in bad shape when you took over&#13;
                             in 1986. Could you elaborate?&#13;
              A:             This is the first time that I have felt free to address this question. It is worth a few&#13;
                             words as it shows how fragile an institution the independent evaluation can be if&#13;
                             it is not supported by the President and protected by the Board. McNamara had&#13;
                             been an active supporter of the independent evaluation system which he had&#13;
                             created. He also treated the Board with respect. Clausen did not like to have to&#13;
                             deal with a sitting board and could not be bothered with the fine points of the&#13;
&#13;
       RESTRICTED            DGO's status.&#13;
      WBG ARCHIVES&#13;
&#13;
       MAR 1 6 29t1&#13;
                1Â· _ .&#13;
  Exception--tJ,_-&#13;
z. _tJjFvaieu.: ,t!!u.t;.Â·&#13;
&#13;
                                                               35&#13;
&amp;#12;     RESTRICTED&#13;
    WBG ARCHIVES&#13;
&#13;
     MAR 1 6 2011&#13;
           ....._Â·&#13;
Exception__.f    Â·----&#13;
                                   Kapur had decided to structure the department into three divisions. Only one,&#13;
{   /(.:t&lt;.t..a -Z &lt;'i.-v -/~u~Â·&#13;
                                   dealing with agriculture and the social sectors, was functioning properly under&#13;
                                   the able leadership of Graham Donaldson. He had come over a year earlier from&#13;
                                   CPS Agriculture with the perfect blend of management, policy and research&#13;
                                   experience, and had begun to attract high quality staff capable of managing&#13;
                                   evaluation studies. The staff of the other two divisions was resisting the new&#13;
                                   structure and the authority of their chief, and of the director for that matter, who&#13;
                                   was absent most of the time. Both chiefs were weak. One of them, a proud and&#13;
                                   able man who was dying from cancer and wanted to carry on until the end, had&#13;
                                   been reassigned to OED from his division chief position in Operations by his&#13;
                                   Transportation colleagues. This illustrates both the absence of a responsible&#13;
                                   director in OED and the perception in Operations of the division chief function in&#13;
                                   OED as a sinecure. The department had no front office. The budget was handled&#13;
                                   by a support staff in one of the divisions. The work program was extremely&#13;
                                   general. There were no cost data. The staff was of uneven quality -some very&#13;
                                   good, a.ttracted by OED's mission or by Graham Donaldson's leadership; some&#13;
                                   very poor, appointed by sector panels which had nowhere else to put them. Many&#13;
                                   were decent projects staff recruited originally to do project audits and lacking the&#13;
                                   experience to conduct evaluation studies. Experience showed that once in OED&#13;
                                   you could not get out. Many believed that the Regions did not want to recruit&#13;
                                   critics of their work.&#13;
                                   Soon after I arrived, I asked Kirmani, a well respected Projects' director who was&#13;
                                   retiring, to come to an OED staff meeting and give us his views on OED. He said&#13;
                                   that he had sampled the opinions of managers and staff and found that staff only&#13;
                                   read OED reports on the operations that they were responsible for; and that only&#13;
                                   a few managers were familiar with a broader cross section of OED's output. The&#13;
                                   view of staff was mildly positive: They did not mind OED as long as it did not&#13;
                                   bother them. A sobering picture.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                    36&#13;
&amp;#12;     I found the culture of OED strange. I was told that Tom Clausen had visited a&#13;
     staff meeting once and asked a seemingly obvious question, "What is your&#13;
     impact?" That was perceived by many as the wrong question to ask. What&#13;
     mattered was that OED existed. As it was independent, it did not have to justify&#13;
     itself. The prevailing attitude among staff was to mark OED's difference by&#13;
     being easily critical and assertive of their independence.&#13;
     The output was uneven, and chronically late. There had been excellent studies&#13;
     such as an impact study of agriculture credit projects in Africa, and the ongoing&#13;
     Pakistan country review, both of which reflected the personal imprint of Shiv&#13;
     Kapur. Yet, I had to throw away a couple of recently completed studies, such as a&#13;
     survey of East Africa Transport, as unsalvageable. They had been carried out by&#13;
     consultants with unclear mandates and without supervision by the staff nominally&#13;
     responsible. The Annual Review, which presents an aggregate view of Bank&#13;
     operations evaluated in the previous year, arrived on my desk in the form of a&#13;
     three volume draft which, I was told, would take months to complete.&#13;
     Considerable data still needed to be gathered and validated. It turned out that the&#13;
     data were not flowing in a useable form as I had surmised. A major reprocessing&#13;
     and validating effort was required which turned the exercise into a nightmare. I&#13;
     was thus confronted by a major data management problem which took several&#13;
     years to resolve.&#13;
     In light of this early experience, I added more specific goals to those I gave you&#13;
     earlier, namely: to retool OED, strengthen management, upgrade staff, introduce&#13;
     planning and programming, ensure timeliness and consistent quality of output&#13;
     and bring about a change in the culture, to aim for impact and, in attitudes, to&#13;
     judge the work of others with more serenity. As staff kept invoking their&#13;
     independence from the rest of the Bank, I coined this motto about independence:&#13;
     "it is about integrity not about isolation."&#13;
Q:   Soon after your appointment the '87 reorganization took place. What impact did&#13;
     that have on your mandate?&#13;
A:   My mandate was not affected. I made it clear to the reorganization team that I&#13;
     had been appointed by the Board under an independent status. They nevertheless&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       37&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                   suggested abolishing the position of director, as had the VP Personnel when I&#13;
                                                   was appointed in 1986; or abolishing the three division chief positions. With&#13;
                                                   respect to the director, the argument was that the position was superfluous and a&#13;
                                                   source of friction with the DGO. I pointed out that the experience was irrelevant.&#13;
       RESTRICTED&#13;
      WBG ARCHIVES&#13;
&#13;
      MAR 1 t: 2011&#13;
â&#128;¢,,.,c;-,ti,,rr __.~.                                                            . My view was that a director was needed to manage&#13;
                  Â·-,-~"" "'"""-".............-&lt;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
'f    l_j~f. ..~:liHt Â·I?~ the high volume of output to high standards of quality, while the DGO was&#13;
                                                   handling policy, external affairs, and relations with Board and Management&#13;
                                                   On my first day as DGO, the director of OED resigned, giving me the golden&#13;
                                                   opportunity to choose my principal partner, and, acting as director for 6 months,&#13;
                                                   to familiarize myself thoroughly with the staff and issues. I turned down the list&#13;
                                                   of three choices for director that was given to me by Management. I chose&#13;
                                                   instead Ram Chopra, a well regarded economist and assistant director in the&#13;
                                                   Economics Vice Presidency in order to give a boost to our policy and adjustment&#13;
                                                   work, and persuaded Management to release him and him to accept. He served&#13;
                                                   well for 3 years before accepting an attractive director position in Operations. I&#13;
                                                   replaced him with Eberhard Kopp, a senior country director with operations&#13;
                                                   policy experience and all of the management know-how needed to tum OED into&#13;
                                                   a first rate department, which he did.&#13;
                                                   Having lost the argument on the director, the reorganization team turned its&#13;
                                                   attention to the division chiefs, arguing duplication with the director and myself.&#13;
                                                   OED staff, supposedly are highly experienced and sophisticated and would need&#13;
                                                   less management. To which I responded that in my experience, the opposite was&#13;
                                                   true. So, I was told, if I did not restructure OED, those of my staff wanting to&#13;
                                                   leave would not have access to the extraordinary severance packages offered in&#13;
                                                   connection with the reorganization. I proposed as a compromise to give up one&#13;
                                                   division chief position, which happened to be vacant due to the death of the&#13;
                                                   incumbent. That was accepted. OED was considered restructured and had access&#13;
                                                   to the related benefits. That made it possible to accelerate the rotation which I&#13;
                                                   had started in the previous year. In a little less than two years, all but one of the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                    38&#13;
&amp;#12;     managers and close to 50% of the staff were replaced. We lost some good people&#13;
     but gained the opportunity to strengthen the quality and match the profile of staff&#13;
     with the changing needs of our program towards more comparative studies,&#13;
     country, adjustment and policy work. We had no problem recruiting. Many&#13;
     perceived the reorganization as a threat to quality work, while they saw in OED&#13;
     under its new management a place where their performance would be valued. We&#13;
     recovered within a year the division chief position that I had traded for&#13;
     restructuring status, simply on the evidence of need. In addition I negotiated an&#13;
     arrangement under which managers could work in OED in a regular staff&#13;
     capacity without losing their grade in a sort of in-house sabbatical program.&#13;
     Strengthening the OED management and staff was one of my most lasting&#13;
     contributions and probably the only good thing to come out of the disastrous '87&#13;
     reorganization. From then on, OED staff had no problem finding operational&#13;
     assignments when they were ready to rotate, and a number left with a promotion.&#13;
     The most spectacular example was that of Marc Baird, promoted from chief of&#13;
     our policy and adjustment division to director and after a short while to vice&#13;
     president in the Economics complex. That reflected not only his excellent work&#13;
     with OED but also the fact that he already ranked among the very best&#13;
     economists in the Bank when we recruited him.&#13;
Q:   Large oil and interest shocks after 1979 found most oil importing countries ill-&#13;
     prepared to deal with adjustment issues forced upon them in the period after&#13;
     1980.   The Bank responded by introducing structural adjustment as a new&#13;
     lending instrument in the early '80s. What did this entail for OED at a time of&#13;
     pressing needs for countries having to adjust to a difficult economic&#13;
     environment?&#13;
A:   By 1986, the adjustment program was in full swing and it was clear that, given&#13;
     the fast disbursing nature of these operations, the number of completed&#13;
     adjustments to be evaluated would rise rapidly, thus the importance of the&#13;
     retooling of OED's management and staff. Evaluation of adjustment was&#13;
     extremely important for two reasons. One was that there was a lot to learn about&#13;
     the content and scope of conditionality, about implementation problems and how&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     39&#13;
&amp;#12;     they could be foreseen. The other was that donors were nervous about this new&#13;
     fast disbursing instrument and were eager to hear from an independent source&#13;
     whether the results matched the great expectations for reform and improved&#13;
     economic performance.&#13;
     A few audits of adjustment operations had been done when I took over as DGO -&#13;
     perhaps seven or eight. And a first review of structural adjustment had been&#13;
     promised to the Board. The draft landed on my desk on the day I arrived. I asked,&#13;
     "When is this due?'' The answer was, "Last November."&#13;
Q:   November '85?&#13;
A:   Yes. The draft was very poor, as was the next. So I brought in a former member&#13;
     of my staff to restructure and strengthen it over the next two months, which he&#13;
     did, ahead of the new deadline. The new draft was provocative but well focused&#13;
     and written. Even though I disagreed with some of the statements, I decided to let&#13;
     it circulate to Bank staff. The paper caused a shock wave all the way to senior&#13;
     management. As the dust settled, however, we received good and constructive&#13;
     comments from staff including leading economists. The final paper was well&#13;
     received by the Board. From then on, evaluation studies and audits of adjustment&#13;
     became an important component of our program.&#13;
Q:   Moving on to project completion reports . (PCRs), now referred to as&#13;
     implementation completion reports (ICRs), they were considered the foundation&#13;
     stone of operations evaluation systems. Please discuss your role in preserving&#13;
     the quality of PCRs and keeping this system of evaluation on track?&#13;
A:   To promote self evaluation is an important part of the DGO's mandate and the&#13;
     PCR is indeed an essential element of that. In addition, for the Bank's evaluation&#13;
     system to be comprehensive and allow a global assessment of the Bank's&#13;
     performance, as had also been intended by McNamara, it is essential that PCRs&#13;
     be prepared for every operation, since audits cover only a selection of projects.&#13;
     By the time I arrived on the scene, however, the system was collapsing. The&#13;
     preparation of PCRs was the last priority of operational staff. To make matters&#13;
     worse, it had been decided that the preparation should be the responsibility of&#13;
     borrowers at least in part. That was nonsense on two counts. One, the Bank had&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     40&#13;
&amp;#12;     an indivisible responsibility to assess its performance and learn from it Two,&#13;
     most borrowers could not care less as they saw this as another bureaucratic&#13;
     demand from the Bank, and most of those who would want to do it did not know&#13;
     how to do so.      At the root of this idea was a gimmick to avoid budgeting&#13;
     adequate resources for that type of work. The '87 reorganization which&#13;
     eliminated or shifted around many of the staff responsible made matters worse.&#13;
     The result was long delays in PCR preparation, an increasing backlog well in&#13;
     excess of a year's output, and poor quality. In many cases, consultants were hired&#13;
     to do the PCRs with little or no self-evaluation benefit.   I easily obtained the&#13;
     agreement of the three Presidents who headed the Bank during my mandate to&#13;
     clear up the problem. Getting action was another matter even though the Board,&#13;
     egged on by my periodic reminders, also added to the pressure. It took practically&#13;
     my entire 6Yz-year mandate to solve the backlog problem. I also had to persuade&#13;
     OED staff to review the quality of each PCR and give feedback to authors or&#13;
     managers, which they viewed as a thankless task. Finally, I announced that we&#13;
     would forward PCRs to the Board as we received them, and would review them&#13;
     afterwards. This way OED was no longer in the critical path and the&#13;
     responsibility of management for timeliness and quality was clear and undivided.&#13;
Q:   Was this in '92?&#13;
A:   It was in 1992 that the backlog was cleared. Before that, however, there had been&#13;
     a gradual progress in quality as well as quantity of output, thanks, in large&#13;
     measure, to the involvement of operations managers in joint PCR task forces&#13;
     with OED as well as the initiatives and professionalism of many Bank staff. That&#13;
     progress enabled me to reduce the proportion of projects that we were auditing&#13;
     and to release resources for the higher value output of evaluation studies. In my&#13;
     last year, we had about trebled our output to 12 studies because of improvements&#13;
     in efficiency, such as the lower audit ratio which I just mentioned, and despite&#13;
     only modest increases in budget We continued to audit all adjustment operations,&#13;
     not only to account for the performance of these newer operations, but also to&#13;
     generate high quality building blocks for comparative evaluation studies of the&#13;
     various types of adjustment operations.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     41&#13;
&amp;#12;Q:   Since '79, OED had been conducting impact evaluations. What is your view on&#13;
     the methodology and design used to evaluate the impact of Bank assistance?&#13;
A:   Let's first understand why impact evaluations are important. One reason is to&#13;
     contribute to the credibility of the Bank's evaluation system, which is based&#13;
     overwhelmingly on project completion reports prepared within a few years of&#13;
     completion    of the    investment,   reflecting   actual   costs   and   timing of&#13;
     implementation, in other words, actual inputs. It is, however, too early at the time&#13;
     these reports are prepared to have a record of output or benefits. As a result, these&#13;
     have to be re-estimated, leaving a big question mark on the actual outcome.&#13;
     Obviously, revisiting projects when the actual benefit stream is assured would&#13;
     help verify the earlier findings.     Another reason is that a large number of&#13;
     operations, including those aimed at alleviating poverty, are focused on people.&#13;
     Finding out whether the intended target group has actually benefited and what&#13;
     valuable lessons have emerged in the operational phase is a good justification for&#13;
     a program of impact evaluations. The main issue for me was not methodology,&#13;
     but rather resources.   The credibility Â·of our evaluations and therefore of the&#13;
     Bank's performance was undermined to the extent that we did not have a&#13;
     systematic program verifYing the outcome of a significant sample of operations.&#13;
Q:   How effective are impact evaluations in influencing Bank policies and programs&#13;
     as well as government policies and their programs?&#13;
A:   Too few have been made to achieve large scale results. But all those done before&#13;
     and during my time have produced valuable results. The outcome of an irrigation&#13;
     project in Morocco, for example, exceeded expectations, as many more people&#13;
     settled in the project area than had been expected. Some workers, it was shown,&#13;
     even came back from factories in France to claim land, settle with their families&#13;
     and benefit from the better working and living conditions. With the help of the&#13;
     OED staff responsible, the study formed the basis of an EDI course taught in&#13;
     Morocco with UNDP financing. That attracted the attention of government which&#13;
     sponsored a seminar on evaluation to which I was invited and which marked the&#13;
     start of evaluation capacity development initiatives.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                      42&#13;
&amp;#12;     A comparative study of cotton development projects in three African countries&#13;
     confirmed that the projects had caused farmers' incomes to rise significantly. An&#13;
     unwanted side effect, however, had been to encourage polygamy, as farmers&#13;
     were "buying" more wives as it is the women in these countries who work the&#13;
     fields.&#13;
     In the Jengka Triangle project in Malaysia, the impact evaluation showed that&#13;
     women did not have access to the extension services provided under the project&#13;
     as the extension workers were male and this was a Muslim country. It was an&#13;
     important finding since, over time, many women had taken over management of&#13;
     the farms.&#13;
Q:   Your successor, Bob Picciotto, who recently retired after serving two terms as&#13;
     Director General of OED, said, "Measuring and evaluating impact rather than&#13;
     input will be a key and difficult challenge facing the Bank group, as well as OED&#13;
     in the years ahead." Do you agree?&#13;
A:   In not very different words, this is exactly what I had been saying all along and&#13;
     said in my parting message to the Board ten years earlier. In a paper entitled,&#13;
     Mandate Mission and Resources, I placed particular emphasis on the need for&#13;
     more impact evaluations, more country reviews and the resources to do them.&#13;
Q:   What impact did an increasingly decentralized Bank have on the dissemination of&#13;
     OED products?&#13;
A:   The decentralization proceeding from the '87 reorganization placed an additional&#13;
     burden on OED for the dissemination of its output. In the previous organization,&#13;
     we could deliver our products on the doorsteps of the central departments of&#13;
     CPS, and expect that they would draw the implications for operational work as&#13;
     part of their responsibilities for providing policy advice, guidelines, and&#13;
     functional support to operational staff in the Bank's regions. As the Bank became&#13;
     decentralized further into many more units, it became necessary for OED to&#13;
     substitute for the CPS sector role and to take its products directly to the users&#13;
     across the Bank. This was more expensive, but it enhanced the impact of our&#13;
     work and gave us invaluable feedback to make subsequent work more relevant,&#13;
     as we gained ideas on topics to study and also on how to present our products for&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                    43&#13;
&amp;#12;impact. In short, we became involved in marketing. For that to succeed, the&#13;
active participation of our staff was essential. That meant that they should have&#13;
leadership qualities as well as professional expertise. That meant also a change of&#13;
culture away from the isolation and the protection of the ivory tower, as&#13;
previously mentioned. My contribution was to understand the new environment,&#13;
to open the windows wide and to encourage the managers and staff of OED in&#13;
this new direction. By the time the decentralization became effective, we had the&#13;
necessary talent to undertake this approach.&#13;
Since we arc on the topic of dissemination, I would add a word about our efforts&#13;
to disseminate our evaluation experience outside the Bank, even though they&#13;
were not related to your question about the Bank's organization. I believe that&#13;
this effort started under my mandate, certainly in any case as a collective effort&#13;
involving staff participation. One intended benefit on my part was a boomerang&#13;
effect on Bank staff. OED evaluation experience relayed from an external source&#13;
would have more impact. We targeted donors as well as developing countries in&#13;
seminars held abroad as well as at headquarters. We invited operational&#13;
managers or staff as a matter of course to give the audience the benefit of their&#13;
perspective as well as the Bank's policy response, where appropriate. Examples&#13;
of seminars for donors included rural development for OECD in Paris, and&#13;
structural adjustment in Paris, Tokyo and Washington. The presentation of our&#13;
reports needed much improvement to encourage reading and achieve effective&#13;
dissemination. That meant crisp writing, particularly for summaries and&#13;
conclusions, and shorter papers with more punch. Better form invariably results&#13;
in better substance. I started this effort right away, reducing the huge Annual&#13;
Review of 1986 from three huge volumes to one and introducing the practice of&#13;
employing professional editors to edit our products. At a later stage, we were&#13;
able to attract Rachel Weaving from Finance and Development to join my office&#13;
with the broader mandate of Information Officer. She oversaw the development&#13;
of our new product line, the OED Precis which, in one to four pages, summed up&#13;
the substance of our evaluations, vastly encouraging their use. I had started a&#13;
program of publishing our more important studies in addition to the Annual&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                44&#13;
&amp;#12;     Review and translating executive summaries into French and Spanish at the&#13;
     request of Executive Directors. Towards the end of my mandate, I decided to&#13;
     stop publishing reports, limiting publication and translation to Precis for reasons&#13;
     of economy.&#13;
Q:   How did the proliferation of technology, such as databases, etc., at the time&#13;
     complement these efforts? How did it help dissemination?&#13;
A:   The issue of technology first came up at our staff retreat in April 1986. The staff&#13;
     wanted personal computers and training in their use. We promptly arranged for&#13;
     every staff member to be so equipped, which proved a great success and a&#13;
     booster of efficiency. We were at that point the Bank's most technologically&#13;
     advanced group and, driven by necessity, remained so for many years thanks to&#13;
     the help of the Information Technology Department. We had one of their staff in&#13;
     residence helping us develop a state of the art data management system. Later on,&#13;
     as technology improved and costs came down, Rachel Weaving and our staff&#13;
     were able to develop with their help a searchable evaluation text base that&#13;
     allowed easy retrieval of QED's entire output by any Executive Director or staff&#13;
     from their personal computers. This was a dream come true.&#13;
Q:   Still on the subject of decentralization of the Bank, from your perspective as&#13;
     DGO at the time, what advantages did you think decentralizing, i.e. bringing the&#13;
     Bank closer to its clients, has on country dialogue, as evidenced from the various&#13;
     evaluations conducted?&#13;
A:   I cannot give you a DGO perspective on your question, particularly one based on&#13;
     the results of evaluations. I can, however, do much better and give you the&#13;
     unique perspective of someone whose entire career in the Bank has been at the&#13;
     center -.in Technical Operations and Projects until 1972, in Central Projects&#13;
     Staff, in Energy and Industry, and as DGO thereafter until retirement in August&#13;
     1992. The quality of the country dialogue is a function of the quality of the&#13;
     people involved - country officials and Bank staff      and of the quality of the&#13;
     country economic and sector work feeding substance to the dialogue. One did not&#13;
     have to break down the critical mass of investment and sector experience of the&#13;
     Bank to achieve closeness and effective dialogue. Doing that may have satisfied&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     45&#13;
&amp;#12;     the ego and need for control of some country managers. It certainly caused&#13;
     severe damage to the Bank's investment expertise.&#13;
Q;   Recruiting better-qualified people for OED was one of the many important&#13;
     initiatives that began under your tenure. Given the strong belief that a mix of&#13;
     internally and externally recruited staff is best for high-quality evaluation, in&#13;
     your view, how does OED ensure both, impartiality and experience, when&#13;
     selecting its staff?&#13;
A:   I did not and do not believe that a mix of internally and externally recruited staff&#13;
     is best for high-quality evaluation. You recruit where the talent is. In my day,&#13;
     there was hardly any worthwhile external evaluation experience that could match&#13;
     the Bank's internal experience. One exception was Pablo Guerrero, who headed&#13;
     the Inter American Development Bank's internal evaluation unit. I recruited him&#13;
     for my own office to help with methodology, international relations and the&#13;
     management of the Evaluation Capacity Development Program. Pablo and the&#13;
     consultants, mostly from the academic community, whom we used for our&#13;
     studies, certainly enriched our work with a different perspective and experience.&#13;
     Impartiality, however, was not singled out as a criterion for their recruitment.&#13;
Q:   How do you ensure a combination of both impartiality and experience for&#13;
     evaluation purposes?&#13;
A:   Professional experience and integrity are good enough as far as I am concerned.&#13;
     The review processes to which evaluation work was subjected at the division,&#13;
     department, and DGO levels ensured conformity with our criteria and standards,&#13;
     including impartiality if that is what you wish to emphasize.&#13;
Q:   Given that organizationally OED reports directly to the Board, how does this&#13;
     affect relations with Management?&#13;
A:   The status of the DGO position is obviously intended to create a distance with&#13;
     management. Not only is the DGO appointed by the Board, reports to it, and can&#13;
     only be fired by it, but also after completing his mandate, the DGO cannot work&#13;
     for the Bank in any other capacity. All of that confers upon the function an&#13;
     external   arms-length   relationship   with management.         That independent&#13;
     evaluation brings to the Board's attention an unadulterated perspective on the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                      46&#13;
&amp;#12;quality of the Bank's operational performance can be perceived as a nuisance by&#13;
management and generate tensions. There were many such instances during my&#13;
tenure. Evaluating adjustment independently in and of itself was a sensitive issue.&#13;
Reporting the decline in Bank performance year after year in the Annual Review&#13;
of completed operations was another; and demonstrating that pressure to lend&#13;
was a factor in that decline yet another.&#13;
That makes the role of the President particularly important. McNamara took an&#13;
active role at least as long as evaluation was reporting to him, which is the period&#13;
I knew best. He was a knowledgeable user and he was also the enforcer of the&#13;
follow-up system of management responses and closing reports. He was in effect&#13;
contributing some of his authority to the evaluation function. The Board, whom&#13;
McNamara treated respectfully but also dominated, was fully involved in the&#13;
process, contributing to transparency.      The role of the three Presidents that&#13;
succeeded him and under whom I served during my tenure was different. They&#13;
did not challenge the independence of the function and affirmed it on occasion.&#13;
They were helpful in words though slower in deeds in the matter of the&#13;
liquidation of the PCRs backlog, probably because I impressed upon them the&#13;
principle that was at stake. But they did not show active support. I failed to&#13;
interest any of them in becoming users. While I eventually succeeded in&#13;
obtaining management responses with the help of Conable and Preston, follow-&#13;
up stopped short of the formal system of closing reports of earlier years. The&#13;
relation, which was friendly in all cases, could be characterized as benign&#13;
neglect: no work program discussion, no budget help. When I was about to&#13;
present my first work program to the Board, Clausen told me "You are not&#13;
supposed to mention your budget to the Board. The budget of 0 ED is part of the&#13;
Bank's budget and should not be discussed separately." Bob Picciotto, who&#13;
before succeeding me was the VP responsible for the budget, even went so far as&#13;
to tell me that I was not to mention the budget of OED in my conversations with&#13;
the chairman of the Joint Audit Committee and other Board members. I ignored&#13;
this, but the Board was powerless, particularly since it was complaining about the&#13;
growth of the Bank's budget.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                 47&#13;
&amp;#12;     Unlike McNamara, the three Presidents who succeeded him failed to dominate&#13;
     the Bank's complexities and fell under the influence of the strong and able&#13;
     managers under them, which was not favorable to OED. The three Presidents&#13;
     regarded the sitting Board of the Bank - a concept foreign to them - as a&#13;
     nuisance, as was evident when my tum came to brief the last two on their arrival.&#13;
     I could see them cringe as I mentioned the role of the Board regarding evaluation&#13;
     and how I was reporting to them. So when Conable once remarked, "the Board&#13;
     likes you," I was not overwhelmed by the compliment. The support of the Board&#13;
     was well-meaning but weak. They were generous and indiscriminating with their&#13;
     compliments. But it was clear that the Joint Audit Committee to which we and&#13;
     the auditors were reporting was more interested in the latter than in the work&#13;
     program, the outline of proposed studies and the actual studies of OED. It was&#13;
     embarrassing to hear committee members admit that they had not read the papers&#13;
     before them, or to demonstrate it by asking question clearly answered in the&#13;
     executive summary. The decision made after my time to devote a separate&#13;
     committee to development effectiveness was therefore an excellent means of&#13;
     strengthening Board oversight and support of OED.&#13;
Q:   Still on the subject of OED's organizational independence, how does this&#13;
     validate accountability in evaluation? Critics have questioned the integrity of&#13;
     OED arguing that it is internal to the Bank and that only an outside audit can&#13;
     ensure objective assessment of Bank-financed operations.                Does OED's&#13;
     independence validate accountability?&#13;
A:   It does and that should be judged by the record. The President, the Board, the&#13;
     developing countries, and interested donors are well served with honest and&#13;
     professional evaluations that are not influenced by operational managers and&#13;
     staff. The record is eloquent. During my tenure, we reported an overall decline in&#13;
     performance and addressed as part of our studies program enough highly&#13;
     sensitive topics such as the environmental disaster of Polonoroeste in Brazil,&#13;
     rural development in Africa, and many others, to demonstrate our independence&#13;
     in the choice of topics as well as in our analyses and   conclusio~s.   And we made&#13;
     efforts to increase transparency with publications and seminars targeting&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     48&#13;
&amp;#12;     developing countries and donors.            Were we independent enough? No.&#13;
     Constitutionally, the budget of OED should be decided by the Board on the merit&#13;
     of a meaningful work program: but not, as it was at the time, by the managers&#13;
     whom evaluation disturbs most before being approved by the Board as part of the&#13;
     Bank's total budget. The need for a program of impact evaluations designed to&#13;
     validate the record and draw rich lessons from the operational phase of Bank&#13;
     financed investments should have been addressed. So should the need for a&#13;
     program of country reviews revisiting the effectiveness of country programming&#13;
     and its results. The Board has failed to exercise its oversight role in ensuring that&#13;
     OED be properly budgeted.&#13;
Q:   Then, how do you respond to those critics who say that OED is, after all, internal&#13;
     to the Bank?&#13;
A:   I would ask, "Who are you and what do you represent?" before bothering to&#13;
     reply. Yes, OED is internal to the Bank, although only in a literal sense since the&#13;
     Board to which it reports represents all of the Bank's member countries. But&#13;
     more importantly, it is independent from the managers and staff whose&#13;
     operations it evaluates, and it is also staffed with top professionals with expertise&#13;
     relevant to the issues at hand. The Bank was first in the international&#13;
     development community to introduce systematic evaluation of its output by a&#13;
     group independent from its operational staff in order to. account for its&#13;
     performance to its shareholders, learn and profit from its experience. Its&#13;
     evaluation system is still the most advanced, transparent and independent.          Is&#13;
     there room for improvement? Of course, internally, to begin with, as I have&#13;
     already   indicated.   Externally,    the   best potential   for   effectiveness   and&#13;
     transparency lies in the development of an evaluation capability in borrowing&#13;
     countries and in the trading of experience among them and with the Bank.&#13;
Q:   Does QED's organizational independence stimulate lesson learning? And, how&#13;
     responsive is the Bank's culture to the lessons of experience, as provided through&#13;
     the evaluation process?&#13;
A:   To encourage self evaluation and learning from experience is a major part of the&#13;
     mandate of independent evaluation. I have mentioned my efforts to ensure that&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                      49&#13;
&amp;#12;     completion reports be prepared for all operations and the efforts of OED staff to&#13;
     review them to enhance quality. I also mentioned our efforts to encourage the&#13;
     use of experience by making it easily accessible (which is why we invented the&#13;
     Precis) and easily retrievable (which is why we put together the electronic&#13;
     evaluation text base). All of those efforts proceeded from the independent&#13;
     character of the function. With respect to responsiveness, you can take the horse&#13;
     to the well but your independence will not make him drink.&#13;
     The Bank is certainly much more alert to the lessons of experience with this&#13;
     system than it would be without it. As to the Bank's culture, it is constantly&#13;
     changing, very much affected by the President's leadership. In my day, as&#13;
     Presidents did not show active support for evaluation, it was at the next levels&#13;
     that the signals were sent. The Executive Vice President of IFC and a former&#13;
     executive director, who did much to improve the monitoring and quality of the&#13;
     portfolio, also increased the resources of evaluation in IFC and showed personal&#13;
     interest on follow up to evaluations. Two regional vice presidents introduced a&#13;
     new section in appraisal reports that stated what experience was relevant to the&#13;
     proposed operation and how it had been addressed. I hoped that the Board's&#13;
     positive comments would help keep up and spread the practice.&#13;
Q:   Does the Bank place enough emphasis within its development assistance&#13;
     programs on strengthening the evaluation capacity in developing countries, and&#13;
     what is the role of OED, or more specifically, the DGO, in making this a&#13;
     priority?&#13;
A:   The Bank was not involved with evaluation capacity development when l&#13;
     became DGO in 1986, and I doubt that it is now. Helping countries acquire their&#13;
     own evaluation capacity was an idea introduced by Mervyn Weiner, and which&#13;
     he was promoting by himself. As I took over, I viewed that as an important part&#13;
     of the DGO job. I realized, however, that once a country was committed, we&#13;
     should be able to nurture and support the initiative. I appointed Pablo Guerrero in&#13;
     my office to be the manager of what we called the "evaluation capacity&#13;
     development program." We would draw expert support from OED's managers&#13;
     and staff as the case warranted, mindful of their other priorities. We might&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     50&#13;
&amp;#12;eventually seek to involve the Bank when we had clearer concepts about needs&#13;
and the Bank's own capacity to help. By the time I left we had not quite reached&#13;
that stage. I saw my role as promoting the idea in connection with travel or&#13;
Annual Meetings of the Bank, finding out whether there was serious interest as&#13;
evidenced, for instance, by the country's willingness to commit resources and&#13;
proceeding from that to the next stages. I explored the question with many&#13;
countries, ending up with about six countries and one regional development bank&#13;
in the active list. Let me illustrate the approach with an example.&#13;
At my first Annual Meeting as DGO, the visiting Colombian minister asked&#13;
whether I would agree to undertake an evaluation of the Bank's role in power&#13;
development in Colombia. I said yes without hesitation because: one, I valued&#13;
having a country as a client of OED; two, I was aware that the Bank and the IDB&#13;
had associated themselves with a massive case of over-investment in power; and&#13;
three, I already had an outstanding team to commit to the effort, Trevor Byer,&#13;
energy policy star and mission leader of energy assessments had just transferred&#13;
from Energy to OED, and Rene Ribi, ex-power division chief had just rejoined&#13;
the Bank to work as regular staff in OED. Ribi had worked as an engineering&#13;
consultant on the design and construction supervision of hydroelectric plants in&#13;
Peru and was familiar with Colombia and the geology of the Andes. Trevor Byer&#13;
had led an Energy Assessment mission in Colombia and was aware of the power&#13;
situation and the need for an independent look. .&#13;
A few years later, the Minister of Finance visited me in my office during the&#13;
Annual Meeting. I asked if he was aware of the results of the evaluation done at&#13;
the request of his predecessor (I was referring to the poor investment choices, the&#13;
bad design and massive cost overruns that had sucked domestic resources and&#13;
external borrowings into excess hydro power at the expense of every priority of&#13;
the country.) He said, "Yes, and it is very critical of the Bank." I nodded. "And&#13;
it is very critical of Colombia." I nodded again, and he was beginning to smile,&#13;
adding, "And it is all true." The purpose of his visit was to invite the authors of&#13;
the study to participate in a follow-up seminar in Colombia to launch discussions&#13;
on a reform of the power sector institutions among all even remotely concerned&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                 51&#13;
&amp;#12;with the subject. When I asked him to invite the Bank's regional staff, he&#13;
answered, "but it is an internal matter." For me, who like most of my colleagues&#13;
of the past had made lifelong friends serving borrowers as a power staff, this was&#13;
a devastating comment on the "closeness to borrowers" and quality of service&#13;
supposedly brought on by decentralizing the Bank. So I asked the Minister, "As&#13;
you observe the power of independent evaluation, why not have your own?" He&#13;
thought it was worth exploring and asked how to go about it. He did not want the&#13;
Bank to know about it for fear that "it would become part of conditionality." I&#13;
suggested that he appoint a senior official close to him to examine the merits of&#13;
the case and report back. We would share our experience and introduce him to&#13;
our network in developed and developing countries. He chose Eduardo Wiesner&#13;
who had just returned to Colombia from serving as Executive Director in the&#13;
Bank. Eduardo Wiesner was fascinated with the assignment. He brought to it a&#13;
keen intellect and drive that led to a rapid and lasting development of evaluation&#13;
in Colombia and a close relation with OED and our network. About a year after&#13;
the decision to go ahead was made, I was invited along with Pablo Guerrero and&#13;
Eleonor Chelimsky of GAO to a seminar in Colombia where the institutional&#13;
follow-up for government and decentralized agencies was discussed, and the first&#13;
three evaluation studies were presented. Meanwhile, and to my amusement, the&#13;
recent revision of the Constitution had made evaluation mandatory which, as I&#13;
had told Wiesner earlier, had been the case in Brazil.&#13;
Two things are worth noting in this case. One, the most effective way to promote&#13;
evaluation is by the example of actual studies and their power for reform rather&#13;
than exhortation or conditionality. And two, the most valuable support comes&#13;
from sharing OED and other countries' experience by way of staff secondments&#13;
and seminars, not external financing.        A final remark, there are cultural&#13;
objections in some countries which may take time to overcome. In one country,&#13;
where initial progress did not seem to lead anywhere, the minister gave me the&#13;
clue over a glass of scotch: "In our country, we do not like criticism. We limit&#13;
evaluation to the middle management level."&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                52&#13;
&amp;#12;Q:   Do you have any thoughts on the Bank's other evaluative mechanisms, such as&#13;
     the Inspection Panel, created in '93, which also reports to the Board?&#13;
A:   The Inspection Panel was created at or after the end of my mandate and I cannot&#13;
     comment on its work. I am, however, familiar with its origin. I had been asked&#13;
     earlier on by several members of the Board to review the ongoing Narmada&#13;
     project in India because of concerns about environmental and particularly&#13;
     resettlement questions. The issue was one of conformity of plans with Bank&#13;
     policy. I had refused on grounds that evaluating and therefore making&#13;
     recommendations about ongoing projects was outside the mandate. Involving&#13;
     OED in operations could make it part of the problem and weaken its evaluation&#13;
     function. An independent committee was appointed to review Narmada, this&#13;
     experience eventually leading to the constitution of the Inspection PaneL My&#13;
     view on this is that if the Bank's Management does not control quality, the Board&#13;
     loses confidence, falls prey to outside critics, and wants external reviews.&#13;
Q:   Moving to inside the Bank, could you discuss the highlights of concrete changes&#13;
     in Bank procedures that were an outcome of the evaluation process during your&#13;
     time as DGO? Are there particular studies that come to mind, that stand out as&#13;
     having had a major impact on Bank policies and procedures?&#13;
A:   As evidence of a Management's response to QED's work, I would first cite the&#13;
     Portfolio Management Review headed by Willi Wappenhans which Ernie Stem&#13;
     commissioned at the end of '91 in reaction to the ever-declining performance of&#13;
     the Bank reported by OED which had reached a new low in the '91 Annual&#13;
     Review. I was one of the advisers and Bob Picciotto, who had already been&#13;
     appointed to succeed me on my retirement, was another. The bulk of the&#13;
     information and analyses on which the Task Force relied came from QED's&#13;
     Annual Reviews and studies, including a recently completed review of Project&#13;
     Supervision&#13;
     Another major input was a review of the quality of economic analysis of projects&#13;
     which I had repeatedly asked Management to commission, finally succeeding&#13;
     two years earlier. I had chaired the first meeting of Bank economists to spell out&#13;
     my concerns and help focus the exercise. I had been struck by their unanimous&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                      53&#13;
&amp;#12;     response that there was nothing wrong with the policies and guidelines; they&#13;
     simply were no longer applied! The study, led by Joanne Salop and assisted by&#13;
     Pablo Guerrero for my office, came out just before the Task Force started work.&#13;
     It raised the issue of "quality at entry" which was stressed by the Wappenhans&#13;
     report and lead to the creation of"QAG".&#13;
     To complement my memory, let me refer you to the Annual Reports, which I&#13;
     sent to the Board during my mandate, in which I reported the answers of Bank&#13;
     managers about the actions they had taken to follow up on OED studies. On&#13;
     policy impact, there was the rural development study which caused this program&#13;
     to be stopped and had a cooling effect on other donors with whom we shared the&#13;
     findings. On procedures, we had the impact on the preparation of Project&#13;
     Completion Reports which I already mentioned via joint task forces with&#13;
     Operations, which clarified the role of borrowers, reestablished the prime&#13;
     responsibility of operational staff for the preparation and of their managers for&#13;
     the quality of the document vis-a-vis the Board, and also helped clarify the&#13;
     criteria for rating project outcomes.&#13;
Q:   What is your opinion of the Bank's other evaluative mechanisms such as the&#13;
     Quality Assurance Group (QAG)- established just after you retired in 1992. For&#13;
     instance, the Quality Assurance Group reports directly to Management where&#13;
     real-time evaluation of Bank operations is provided.       How are these efforts&#13;
     viewed in the context of OED evaluation?         Are there synergies, or, do they&#13;
     represent perhaps an early read on evaluation?&#13;
A:   QAG is better than nothing, i.e. than tbe status quo ante, as a means for&#13;
     contributing to the quality of lending. It is, however, a poor substitute for&#13;
     effective quality control ex ante. It is telling to find that the word control has&#13;
     been banished from references to quality in the Bank's lingo to be replaced by&#13;
     weak terms such as "enhancement" and now "assurance." I would view with&#13;
     extreme suspicion any general statement about Bank performance derived from&#13;
     QAG's work as tainted by conflict of interest. Only independent evaluation can&#13;
     be trusted in this regard.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                      54&#13;
&amp;#12;     You did not ask about the internal audit. You could not take a serious look at the&#13;
     internal audit programs or reports without concluding that it was useless; hence&#13;
     the temptation of their better staff to get into evaluation work without the benefit&#13;
     of independence. Not a threat to OED, of course but yet another case of wasted&#13;
     resources. Calling the internal auditor "Auditor General" belittles the important&#13;
     functions of the Auditors Generals of Member Countries. It came about as the&#13;
     Bank was experiencing serious difficulties filling the job. Instead of looking at&#13;
     the meager job description, which was turning off good candidates the Bank's&#13;
     Personnel management simply boosted the title. QAG, the Inspection Panel, and&#13;
     the Internal Audit should be evaluated by OED to give the Board and&#13;
     Management a better reply than I can.&#13;
Q:   Moving on to global programs.        In August 2002, the Bank Executive Board&#13;
     commissioned an OED evaluation of the Bank's approach to global programs&#13;
     (e.g. GEF, CGIAR), as concerns have grown about inadequate selectivity,&#13;
     increased reputational risks, and Jack of routine reporting on development&#13;
     impact. In your opinion, how adequately developed are joint evaluations in OED&#13;
     of global programs?&#13;
Q:   Some have argued that the Bank should "get back to basics" of the sort&#13;
     envisioned by its founders. In your opinion, how should the Bank address the&#13;
     issue of selectivity in its crowded agenda, in light of greater emphasis on&#13;
     partnerships with borrowers, development actors, and other agencies and&#13;
     organizations?&#13;
A:   I agree with those who advocate going back to basics, judging from the&#13;
     confusing image projected by books, newspapers, and speeches of executives&#13;
     that I have heard from time to time. The only way I know to go back to basics is&#13;
     to reassess country priorities one by one, and the comparative advantage of the&#13;
     Bank and others to meet them.           This is a complex endeavor but worth&#13;
     undertaking.     It is, in a way, what I was trying to achieve with the Energy&#13;
     Assessment Program on the smaller scale of the energy sector. The assessment&#13;
     of country priorities should be done in cooperation with any competent donors&#13;
     and of course the country concerned.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     55&#13;
&amp;#12;Q:   Based on your extensive experience in evaluation, what is the most difficult part&#13;
     of the evaluation process?&#13;
A:   To ensure relevance to current issues working with ex post material that is old&#13;
     and sometimes not old enough. It was frustrating to be asked for the experience&#13;
     with different types of extension services in Africa, a bone of contention between&#13;
     the Bank and some donors, and to have to wait three years to be able to answer&#13;
     because of delays in completing projects and/or obtaining completion reports.&#13;
Q:   What should the Board look for in selecting a DGO for OED? What are the&#13;
     criteria and attributes of a good DGO for OED?&#13;
A:   I would emphasize the following:&#13;
       Q)   Character, including integrity, wisdom, fairness, vision, and backbone,&#13;
            features that are easily overlooked by those making the selection decisions;&#13;
       Q)   Stature and presence;&#13;
       Q)   Familiarity with Bank policies and practices gained in discharging&#13;
            operational responsibilities at staff and management level, essential for&#13;
            credibility and for ensuring relevance of the work program;&#13;
       Q)   A "trail" of high-quality services and investments in member countries; and&#13;
       Q)   Highly developed communication skills.&#13;
     I believe that there should be no more age limit than there is for the President or&#13;
     Executive Directors. After my first five-year mandate, I asked for an extension&#13;
     of only 18 months to my retirement at age 65 because that suited me best&#13;
     professionally    I felt that a cycle of six and a half years accomplished what I&#13;
     wanted     as well as personally. There should be no problem recruiting someone&#13;
     at age 62 or 63 if he or she meets the other criteria. The position of DGO should&#13;
     be upgraded to Senior VP or Managing Director level to reflect the importance of&#13;
     the function, and in keeping with the original status of the function when there&#13;
     was only the SVP and few VPs. Management skills proved enormously helpful&#13;
     in my case, given the situation at hand. These skills are not as important for the&#13;
     DGO in normal circumstances where he or she could depend on a well-managed&#13;
     department. When Bob Picciotto retired, he, Mervyn Weiner, Chris Willoughby,&#13;
     Shiv Kapur in India, and I were all available to advise the Board on the selection&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                      56&#13;
&amp;#12;     of the next DGO. Some of us could have formed a panel to advise on desirable&#13;
     profile and to screen and short-list candidates for selection by the Board or its&#13;
     Committee on development effectiveness.          How could they fail to use this&#13;
     resource?&#13;
Q:   How do you view your accomplishments and contributions as DGO for OED?&#13;
A:   To begin with, I "retooled" QED's management and staff, and set ambitious&#13;
     goals for building up the function and contributing to the Bank's effectiveness.&#13;
     From then on, my accomplishments and contributions cannot be separated from&#13;
     those of the managers and staff associated with me during the period of my&#13;
     mandate. They include:&#13;
      Q) the excellence of the management team and staff, the solution to the earlier&#13;
&#13;
          problems of recruitment and rotation of staff, the fact that, for the first time,&#13;
          some left for promotion;&#13;
      Q) the reporting in Annual Reviews and studies which drew attention to the&#13;
&#13;
          decline in Bank performance, the pressure to lend and deficient economic&#13;
          analysis as significant factors, and caused Management to undertake a&#13;
          Portfolio Management Review and corrective action;&#13;
      Q) the efficient administration, planning, programming, data management, and&#13;
&#13;
          budgeting of the department;&#13;
      Q) the repair and updating of the comprehensive system of PCRs;&#13;
&#13;
      Q) staff participation in the upgrading of PCR preparation and processing, in&#13;
&#13;
          the selection and dissemination of studies, both internally and externally,&#13;
          and in support of evaluation capacity development;&#13;
      Q) improvement of the planning and processing of the Annual Review and its&#13;
&#13;
          evolution into a sum of the year's evaluation output;&#13;
      Q) the increased annual output of evaluation studies, the diversity, relevance,&#13;
&#13;
          and importance of topics addressed, including a growing program of&#13;
          adjustment and country evaluations; the added value to the audit program&#13;
          by clustering audits around themes relevant to current lending;&#13;
      Q) the improved presentation of studies and, with the help of professional&#13;
&#13;
          editing, shorter reports and sharper conclusions;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                      57&#13;
&amp;#12;       a&gt; the publication of evaluation studies and the launching of a series of one-to-&#13;
           four page Precis to make findings more accessible;&#13;
       a&gt; the commissioning of an electronically searchable evaluation text base&#13;
           facilitating the retrieval of all OED output by Executive directors,&#13;
           managers, and staff from their own desks; and&#13;
       a&gt; the interest and commitment of several countries to acquire their own&#13;
           evaluation capacity and the evaluation capacity development program to&#13;
           support it.&#13;
     I believe that I did much to strengthen OED, its independence and its presence. I&#13;
     was not been able, however, to interest any of the three Bank Presidents during&#13;
     my tenure in becoming "clients" and providing active support for follow up as&#13;
     Robert McNamara used to.&#13;
Q:   Speaking of World Bank Presidents, how would you assess the various&#13;
     presidents under whom you served?&#13;
A:   Eugene Black, the founder of the IBRD, IFC and IDA, was a class act. He had&#13;
     the vision to build an institution that was truly international, soundly managed,&#13;
     financially independent and protected from the political interferences .of&#13;
     Treasury, State and foreign governments who were always keen to place their&#13;
     own and exercise influence as is the case in most international institutions. He&#13;
     set high standards and instilled in managers and staff a sense of commitment to&#13;
     quality that lived on with me throughout my career. Like most from that era, I&#13;
     remember him, his trust in staff and care for them with a mixture of respect and&#13;
     affection.&#13;
     George Woods was a more distant figure, even though we had shared the same&#13;
     mentor, Dad Wenzell, who had also come from First Boston about eight years&#13;
     earlier. He was shrewd and rude.&#13;
     Robert McNamara brought to the Bank a considerable intellect and boundless&#13;
     energy. His vision and drive propelled the Bank to the world scene and defined&#13;
     its development mandate. He introduced policy to the agenda of the Board which&#13;
     he treated with outward respect and dominated with his presence. He did what&#13;
     was necessary to attract and motivate excellent staff and deserves credit for&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     58&#13;
&amp;#12;having created jointly with the IMF's Managing Director, the objective&#13;
comparator system which helped protect the compensation of staff from U.S.&#13;
government attacks.      The Bank's evaluation system ranks among his top&#13;
contributions. He believed, and rightly so that if the problem was difficult, the&#13;
Bank should be involved, not the opposite. He caused the Bank and its borrowers&#13;
to take more risks to achieve development objectives. He also created the system&#13;
by which the Bank should be accountable and should learn from its experience ~&#13;
good and bad -to improve its performance. He was also the last President to&#13;
have had a full grasp of the Bank's complexities. Yet, I do not regard him as the&#13;
great manager that he has been painted to be. He was extremely effective at&#13;
controlling everything, particularly with numbers, though as one colleague once&#13;
put it, "what he could not count did not count." Good management, however, is&#13;
not about control but about incentives and signals. The system of incentives&#13;
which he put in place favored lending volumes over quality. Quality controls&#13;
went out of fashion under his regime, dismissed as unnecessary sources of delay.&#13;
The budget system was a mere extrapolation of the past and driven exclusively&#13;
by lending targets at the expense, in my own experience, of new policy initiatives&#13;
and of the preparation and sector work on which to build sound operations.&#13;
Reallocation of resources in the face of changing needs was discouraged by&#13;
organizational and budget structure. Managers could maintain non-performing&#13;
stafi with impunity and the Bank grew fatter. There was a disconnect between&#13;
McNamara's long-term policy vision and his short-term management style. What&#13;
a pity! McNamara, still, was a giant, and the World Bank which he left to his&#13;
successors was an extraordinary institution.      The problems that I mentioned&#13;
could have been fixed by the Presidents who followed him, but they were not.&#13;
Tom Clausen helped improve the Bank's earnings and finances which had&#13;
slipped in the last years of McNamara's regime. As he did not master the Bank's&#13;
complex business and was uncomfortable with top management, he encouraged&#13;
senior managers to retire early and did some organizational restructuring in order&#13;
to recruit externally. I was a victim of this process, in that an Energy and Industry&#13;
Vice Presidency was created, including my department, the head of which was to&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                 59&#13;
&amp;#12;         RESTRICTED&#13;
        WBO ARCHIVES       be recruited externally. My Industry colleague and I, both qualified, were&#13;
        MAR 1 5 2011       excluded from consideration. The Vice President who was recruited externally&#13;
             Â£&#13;
    Exception..;..U_~-     turned out to be a disaster.&#13;
't. Â£:1Q_uta-"ti..V~-. ~&#13;
           Q:              So you favor promotion from within at the senior level?&#13;
           A:              Certainly not. I favor better care and hard work in finding candidates and&#13;
                           choosing the best regardless of source, which is precisely what I was doing at my&#13;
                           less important level. I was in favor of some systematic external recruitment at&#13;
                           lower levels of management to avoid the inbred culture that bothered Clausen.&#13;
                           That would have been easier, too, as salaries were more competitive at lower&#13;
                           levels. The trend was headed in the opposite direction, driven by the need to&#13;
                           promote young professionals whose profile was increasingly similar- economics&#13;
                           PhDs- as more fungible.&#13;
           Q:              What about Messrs. Conable and Preston?&#13;
           A:              Barber Conable, an affable man, was responsible for the 1987 reorganization. I&#13;
                           liked Lou Preston, a patrician with a true Wall Street background. He came in&#13;
                           September 1991, and I left in August '92, so I have no comment on this short&#13;
                           period.&#13;
           Q:              What are the criteria and attributes of a good World Bank President in your&#13;
                           opinion?&#13;
           A:              Stature, vision, leadership, diplomatic skills - Paul Volker, Felix Rohatyn and,&#13;
                           why not, Bill Clinton would have known how to lead the World Bank to greater&#13;
                           achievements.&#13;
           Q:              Thank you for your time, Mr. Rovani, and for your invaluable contribution to the&#13;
                           Bank's Oral History Program.&#13;
           A:              Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                          60&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="17978155">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2003/03/17978155/transcript-oral-history-interview-yves-rovani-held-march-10-25-2003
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2003/03/17978155/transcript-oral-history-interview-yves-rovani-held-march-10-25-2003</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2003/03/17978155/transcript-oral-history-interview-yves-rovani-held-march-10-25-2003</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2012-03-02T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2012-03-02T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2013/07/09/000333037_20130709153209/Rendered/INDEX/791110TRN0Rova0Box0377367B00PUBLIC0.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2013/07/09/000333037_20130709153209/Rendered/PDF/791110TRN0Rova0Box0377367B00PUBLIC0.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2013-07-09T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2003-03-25T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Transcript of oral history interview with
            Yves Rovani  is held on March 10 and 25, 2003
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            On March 10 and 25, 2003, Yves Rovani
            was interviewed on behalf of the World Bank Group Archives
            oral history program by William H. Becker and Marie T.
            Zenni. During his tenure at the Bank from 1969 to 1992, Mr.
            Rovani worked in the following areas: in the projects
            department as financial advisor (1969-1972); as director in
            the departments of public utilities (1972-1976), of energy,
            water, and telecommunications (1977-1979), and of energy
            (1980-1986); and in operations evaluation as director
            general (1986-1992). When he took over as director of public
            utilities, the word energy was not in the vocabulary at the
            World Bank. Power meant public utilities; coal and
            refineries were industry; pipelines were transportation; and
            oil and gas were left to the private sector. Upon the
            quadrupling of oil prices in 1973, affecting developing
            countries, Mr. Rovani prioritized energy policies.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Transcript of oral history interview with
            Yves Rovani  is held on March 10 and 25, 2003
        </docna>
        <display_title>Transcript of oral history
            interview with Yves Rovani  is held on March 10 and 25, 2003</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/2003/03/17978155/transcript-oral-history-interview-yves-rovani-held-march-10-25-2003</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Transcript</docty>
        <subtopic>Access to Finance,Town Water Supply and Sanitation,Corporate Law,Energy Production and Transportation,Banks &amp; Banking Reform</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Energy,Law and Development,Water Supply and Sanitation</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000333037_20130709153209</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>World Bank Group Archives oral history program</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Energy,Law and Development,Water Supply and Sanitation</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Board Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            access to service, accounting, accounting
            standards, actual costs, Affiliate, affordability, approach,
            Audit Committee, auditing, auditors, audits, balance, Bank
            financing, Bank lending, Bank services, basic needs, Board
            meeting, borrower, borrowing, borrowing costs, borrowings,
            business development, Cash flows, central banks, clean
            water, coal, coal mining, collective, commercial bank,
            comprehensive energy policy, corporate finance, credit
            worthiness, cross-subsidization, debt, debt service,
            decentralization, Development Bank, development finance,
            development finance companies, distribution losses, dividend
            payments, domestic companies, domestic oil, drilling,
            drinking water, electric power, electricity, employer,
            Energy Assessments, energy development, energy production,
            energy sources, energy strategy, energy supply,
            environmental issues, families, farmers, finances, financial
            analysis, financial markets, foreign exchange, former
            director, franchise, franchises, fuel, Fuels, gas, gas
            development, gas distribution, gas projects, gasoline,
            generation, government policies, households, Hydrocarbons,
            Information Technology, interest rates, investment bank,
            investment bankers, investment climate, large borrower,
            large cities, learning opportunity, legislation, limited,
            line of credit, loan, loan amount, loan officer, loan
            repayments, managers, mandates, marginal cost, marginal cost
            pricing, modern business, natural gas, Oil, oil companies,
            oil company, oil development, oil field, oil importing
            countries, oil industry, Oil price, oil prices, oil
            reserves, payback period, personal computers, petroleum,
            petroleum industry, pipeline, pipeline projects, pollution,
            pollution control, power distribution, power sector, power
            station, price of oil, private companies, private financing,
            privatization, provision of funds, public utilities, public
            utility, regional banks, renewable energies, reorganization,
            reorganizations, responsibility for water, retirement, rural
            energy, rural water, rural water supply, safety net, sewage,
            sewage disposal, share capital, shareholders, source of
            income, sponsor, structural adjustment, subsidiaries,
            subsidization, supply costs, tariff covenants, transport,
            Union, urban water, urban water supply, Village, waste
            disposal, water supply, water utilities
        </keywd>
        <owner>Knowledge &amp; Information Services (ITSKI)</owner>
        <repnb>79111</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT for Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies (ICT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>PPP</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public-Private Partnerships</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Science and Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public-Private Partnerships (PPP)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation and Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shocks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Denationalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deregulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Destatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Divestiture of Ownership</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Infrastructure (Water and Wastewater)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Water and Small Town Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Impact Evaluations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Randomized Control Trials</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Basic Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>On-site Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Marketing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure and Networks (National; State; Local)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunication and Network Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunications</ml:concept><ml:concept>Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deconcentration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delegation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Devolution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sub-National Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subnational Government and Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Electric Power</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fuels</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Engineering</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Impact Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shocks and Vulnerability</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Privatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Impact Assessment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pipelines</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunications and Broadband Access</ml:concept><ml:concept>Administrative Decentralization</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>