<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>﻿                                    79088&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
THE WORLD BANK GROUP ARCHIVES&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    ORAL HISTORY PROGRAM&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Transcript of interview with&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        MIEKO NISHIMIZU&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       March 11 and 12, 2004&#13;
        Washington, D.C.&#13;
&#13;
    Interview by: Marie T. Zenni&#13;
&amp;#12;                                      Session 1&#13;
                                    March 11, 2004&#13;
                                   Washington, D.C.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: Goodmorning. Today is March 11th, 2004, and I'm Marie Zenni, Task&#13;
Manager for the Bank's Oral History Program.&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: Mieko Nishimizu, former Vice President of the South Asia Region.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: I'm here at World Bank headquarters to interview Ms. Nishimizu, who has&#13;
recently retired from the Bank in November 2003. Perhaps we can begin by discussing&#13;
your educational background to better understand how you became involved in economic&#13;
development prior to joining the Bank?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: Well, I studied economics both at the undergraduate and graduate level to&#13;
the extent that economics is used for a discipline for development; that was my&#13;
background academically. But as an economist, I never studied development. I was not&#13;
interested in development. I had no desire to become involved in development. My field&#13;
was a particular brand of both macro and micro economics called productivity and&#13;
management theory. And so there was that, and I was happily teaching economics at&#13;
Princeton.&#13;
&#13;
My encounter with development issues really didn't happen until I actually came to the&#13;
Bank. When I first came, I came for a very selfish reason. I had a sabbatical. At&#13;
Princeton, they give you a sabbatical once every three years, and by then I was married to&#13;
my husband Peter, who was at the [International Monetary] Fund. And so I was looking&#13;
for someplace to spend my sabbatical year. And Hollis Chenery, who was the Vice&#13;
President and Chief Economist ofthe World Bank, read one of my papers, I think, at the&#13;
recommendation of one of the research staff whom I knew from Princeton, and he invited&#13;
me to give a seminar. And so I came down but was never really interested in the World&#13;
Bank, so I didn't come down for a job. I came down to give a seminar like any other&#13;
academic seminar. It was the first time I gave a seminar in a nonacademic institution.&#13;
And so before I left Princeton, I had this very stuck-up expectation that people here won't&#13;
be good economists, and it won't be a very interesting and challenging seminar. As it&#13;
turned out, it was probably the most challenging seminar I ever gave. It was meant to be&#13;
two hours, and it probably went on for about three, four hours; one afternoon. And, what&#13;
impressed me, first of all, practically all of the Research Department were there, and they&#13;
were outstanding economists asking good theoretical questions. But, what also struck me&#13;
was that everyone was asking questions not to show off, which is what happens in&#13;
academia, but they were asking questions, whether theoretical or empirical, out of an&#13;
obvious desire to learn to apply it for development work because, you know, after all, any&#13;
area, any field of economics is applicable to development. And, there were lots of tough&#13;
policy questions, which, as an academic, beyond certain generalities you don't really&#13;
have a chance to think about them. And it really, really challenged me, and it was fun&#13;
learning and a fantastic seminar. So I was impressed.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                         March 11 and 12,2004- Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                            2&#13;
&#13;
After the seminar--Hollis Chenery was there too--Hollis said, "Well, come to the office&#13;
and have a chat."&#13;
&#13;
And I went to his office to have a chat, and he said, "I hear that you're looking for a place&#13;
for your sabbatical. Do you want to come here?''&#13;
&#13;
And I said, "No. I'm not a development economist, and I have no desire to practice it, and&#13;
I have absolutely no idea what the Bank does anyway. I'm looking for an academic&#13;
appointment."&#13;
&#13;
And he said, "Well, give us a try." And he explained what the Bank does and the role of&#13;
the Research Department. And he said, "Look, you know, nobody else can offer you as&#13;
good a salary as we can, and you don't have to teach spoiled kids. Give us a try."&#13;
&#13;
And so I told him I would think about it. And I thought about it and talked to some of my&#13;
colleagues, and I thought, well, it's something new. I had total freedom to research&#13;
anything I want because he said anything you do will be applicable to development&#13;
economics. So I said, "Okay, I'll give it a try for a year." And that's how I came.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: You came as a consultant between '78 and '79; is that correct?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: No, I wrote some survey papers for some research economists here, and&#13;
so that's what that was about. So that's how the World Bank and I met.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: Do you care to tell us what brought you, a Japanese woman, to the United&#13;
States?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: Yes, but before doing that, why did I stay? Why did I not go back to&#13;
Princeton as was my initial intention? If not Princeton, then somewhere else around&#13;
Washington, because a commuting marriage was tiring. There was one condition that&#13;
Hollis Chenery put on my sabbatical year here, and that was that I join a real live World&#13;
Bank mission to see what the Bank does and to see what a real development country is&#13;
like, and I went to two countries during that year.&#13;
&#13;
The first one was Egypt, and the second one was Yugoslavia, but Egypt changed my life.&#13;
I was a green economist, and so, other than helping out a few operational staff on the&#13;
mission on basically how to think about certain problems, I had very little to do in terms&#13;
of scheduled official appointments. And so I used the time really roaming around the City&#13;
of Cairo. I wanted to learn what it's like and what the poverty is like, basically, in&#13;
developing countries like Egypt. And, mind you, I had never seen poverty, period, up to&#13;
that point. My world was Japan, the United States and Europe, and I had never had a&#13;
chance of thinking even about what it's like to be poor. So every day was a shock to my&#13;
system, but there was a particular day when I befriended someone on the street in the&#13;
slums of Cairo and went into, I think it was some kind ofNGO [non-governmental&#13;
organization] group that was working on health issues in slums, and there was a little girl&#13;
who died in front of my eyes, and the cause of her death was simple diarrhea, with a&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                          March 11 and 12,2004 Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                            3&#13;
&#13;
grieving mother beside her. It was just totally beyond my comprehension that a child can&#13;
die of simple diarrhea.&#13;
&#13;
It was almost a religious experience looking back. I somehow felt, when that happened,&#13;
that here I am a highly trained economist, and I need to think through why things like this&#13;
can happen to another human being like me. And I spent the rest of that stay thinking&#13;
about it, and by the time the plane landed in Washington, I knew my choice. Because the&#13;
choice was either to drastically change my career and fight poverty, and it so happened&#13;
that I understood the World Bank enough by then, that I was at the institution that was the&#13;
best place to use whatever talent I had for that particular work, or go back to academia&#13;
and teach privileged, young students how to think about economics. And, when I&#13;
confronted it, although I wouldn't say it was an easy choice, but the choice was obvious.&#13;
&#13;
And so, I came from that mission and went to Hollis Chenery and said, "Guess what. I&#13;
think I'd like to stay beyond just this year."&#13;
&#13;
And he said, "I knew it." I think he knew Egypt would change my life. So that's a long&#13;
story, but that's what happened.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: Now would you care to tell us about what brought a Japanese woman to the&#13;
United States of America?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: Yes. As long as I can· remember, and my memory goes back to a pretty&#13;
young age, back in Japan, I was conscious of constraints on me because I'm a girl, as&#13;
opposed to my friends.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: As opposed to your male friends.&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: Yes. I was very good at schooL I was always top ofthe class. And one&#13;
thing the Japanese educational system is good at is not to discriminate whether you're a&#13;
girl or boy. And so, if you're a girl, then you compete, and you pursue your studies all the&#13;
way up to wherever, just like a boy, but beyond that, in thinking about one's career or&#13;
what does one do with that education, there are enormous social constraints on women,&#13;
and also the employment laws were quite discriminatory against women. It didn't get&#13;
changed until a few years back. And so, the cultural education and so forth for girls are&#13;
very different from boys and very constrained if you are from a good family. And so my&#13;
memory of growing up in Japan, all the way up to high school, was really in everyday&#13;
situations knowing those constraints and feeling frustrated. It's like, you know that you&#13;
have wings, and you know that you can fly, but you're not allowed to do it. You're just&#13;
kept in a cage. And so, in high school, I applied for a student exchange program with the&#13;
Rotary Club, and that's how I first came to the U.S. The motivation for doing that was&#13;
really to escape, even for one year. I just wanted to see what it's like outside, and you&#13;
know the side benefit would be to perfect my English, which I knew would be good for&#13;
some kind of profession. My parents thought it would be good for my balance sheet on&#13;
the marriage certificate. So that's how I came, and I never went back.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                         March 11 and 12, 2004- Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                   4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 ZENNI: Now, turning to your Bank tenure. You joined the Bank towards the end of the&#13;
 [RobertS.] McNamara era and began work as a research economist in the Development&#13;
 Economics Department, thereafter reorganized as the Development Research&#13;
 Department. What were your main responsibilities?&#13;
&#13;
  NISHIMIZU: My responsibilities were made very clear to me by Hollis Chenery, and&#13;
  my Division Chief then who was Larry Westfall, a very well-known economist: three-&#13;
  quarters research and one-quarter operational support. Research, I mean, your salary is&#13;
  guaranteed, but the research part you have to obtain research funding, get additional&#13;
  resources through Research Committees, very much in that system still remains today .&#13;
. The one-quarter operational support was a serious one; you were expected to spend a&#13;
  quarter of your time providing operational support to somebody outside the Research&#13;
  Department. Everyone in the Research Department back then knew that and knew the&#13;
  reason for it. I don't think that's the case any more, which is one of the sad things, I feel.&#13;
  As for your performance evaluation, the incentive was that you had to hustle. Nobody&#13;
  would help you. It's your academic reputation or economist reputation and your good&#13;
  ideas and your policy sense that would land some request from somebody in the regions&#13;
  to ask you for help. The incentive for that was that it mattered on your performance&#13;
  evaluation every year, and it was serious. And Larry Westfall used to do a very serious,&#13;
  probably a model, performance evaluation.&#13;
&#13;
 The reason why we were serious in pursuing this--because researchers don't necessarily&#13;
 like to take any time away from their own research--was because Hollis Chenery was&#13;
 very clear. The idea was that when a good researcher becomes directly involved in some&#13;
 operational work in the Bank, they will encounter in the real world a policy choice and&#13;
 realize that there are many topics that need to be researched, theoretically or empirically,&#13;
 to address those real-world poverty questions. So, that we were here to engage in long-&#13;
 term research, the benefit of which is a question mark, long-term research is a risky&#13;
 business. So he was very clear thatour ability to spend as much time as three-quarters of&#13;
 our year in basic research of our choice and for the World Bank to take a risk on me is a&#13;
 privilege, and we must make sure that we give something, in the shorter term, to the&#13;
 institution through operational research. In doing so, however, there will be a return:&#13;
 raising the quality of the long-term research by our exposure to real-world poverty. So&#13;
 there is a sort of positive synergy cycle, a complementarity that he was strategically&#13;
 pursuing, and he was a very good manager. He made that a vision, his vision, for the&#13;
 research in the Bank. He used to tell us that if you want to spend 100-percent of your&#13;
 time doing research to go back to the university. There is no room for you here. So that&#13;
 was clear. And so, only those of us who really bought into that vision and that way of&#13;
 working stayed here.&#13;
&#13;
 And Operational support is a lot of fun, if you appreciate it, if you do good work, and all&#13;
 you needed is one good experience. I used to come back from every mission with my two&#13;
 research folders doubling every time, because every time I went out there, I would find&#13;
 that there's some issue that is not researched, that nobody has worked on. So it was a&#13;
 terrific place to be. So that was my role in the context of the mandate of research that was&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                            March 11 and 12, 2004- Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                            5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
unique, and it was made very explicit by a good manager, leader, in the person of Hollis&#13;
Chenery. We really missed him when he left.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: What is your assessment of the Bank's approach towards enhancing&#13;
productivity during that time, for example, in industry, and how has this evolved over the&#13;
years?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: When I arrived, I noticed that the World Bank staff do not think clearly&#13;
about productivity change, when it was obvious to me that an important part of economic&#13;
growth and development is how to think about how to raise productivity of capital and&#13;
workers. So that was surprising then. I'm afraid I would still say the same today, that, on&#13;
average, most economists or most professional staff in the Bank don't tend to think&#13;
clearly in that framework, and even though practically everything that is done in the&#13;
World Bank has an enormous amount to do with helping developing countries raise&#13;
productivity, even that awareness isn't there. There was a time, during the time I was in&#13;
the Research Department, where a number of economists in the region with whom I&#13;
worked took on that way of thinking about their work, but it takes a constant regeneration&#13;
of that. There is not enough attention to that.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: How did this initial period in the Research Development affect your thinking&#13;
on economic development?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: A couple of things. First, it takes more than economics to work on&#13;
development issues. That was very clear to me from the outset. So it takes good&#13;
economic theory and good economic practice, which is not as frequent as I would like to&#13;
see anywhere in the world, including the World Bank. But what I really learned, starting&#13;
on my first operational support assignment, was that one needs to think through politics&#13;
and economics, and one needs to think through a number of micro social issues. And in&#13;
all of that, I became aware very quickly of what is today called a local context, how&#13;
important it is for one to deeply understand the political, cultural, social context of a&#13;
particular community or a particular country. So that's what I learned.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: Please discuss your move in late '83 to the Industry Department, first, as&#13;
industrial economist, then, as senior economist working on Industrial Strategy and Policy,&#13;
and what was your particular focus?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: I think I should discuss why I moved first. When Hollis Chenery retired,&#13;
which was a year after McNamara retired and, with top leadership changes, things&#13;
changed. Anne Krueger came in as the Vice President. I knew her before and respected&#13;
her work--I still do--but as a manager of Research in a place like the World Bank, her&#13;
philosophy was very different. She emphasized too much the short-term returns of&#13;
researchers to the institution, as opposed to long-term academic research, and she failed&#13;
to see the synergy between the two as Hollis did.&#13;
&#13;
And so many people left. Most people left--well, let's say half of them left the Bank,&#13;
including my Division Chief, to go back to academia, and half, like me, went to the new&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                         March 11 and 12,2004- Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                             6&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Industrial Department Policy wing. It was like jumping off a cliff. Even though, by then,&#13;
after three years, I was reasonably familiar with what regions do and what operational&#13;
central Vice Presidents and vice presidencies do, it was still a big change.&#13;
&#13;
But what attracted me to the Policy wing was its mandate; it was established to provide&#13;
policy advice to project staff. And, in order to attract people like me, the management of&#13;
the vice presidency encouraged staff to continue basic research, as long as we can get it&#13;
funded by the Research Committee. So it was a nice halfway house for me, so I thought I&#13;
would give it a try. I seriously thought about leaving the Bank at that point, but there&#13;
were some operational commitments I needed to continue anyway. And so my focus&#13;
when I went was because I identified very strongly with the mandate. It was a brand-new&#13;
face, a newly established Policy wing of the Industrial Department. Back then, most of&#13;
the project staff thought that thinking about policy was a waste oftime.&#13;
&#13;
Just to give you an example, the World Bank (IBRD and IDA) [International Bank for&#13;
Reconstruction and Development and International Development Association] was single&#13;
handedly responsible for something like half or more of the developing world fertilizer&#13;
production capacity, through investment, state-owned fertilizer companies, when&#13;
fertilizer pricing policies were, in most countries, extremely distorted with negative&#13;
impact on farmers and productivity of crops, in addition to their impact on the fiscal&#13;
aspects of these countries, et cetera. And the World Bank had enormous leverage--not&#13;
just in each individual country, but for the whole of the Third World--given its major&#13;
share in investment, to do something about this because fertilizer pricing is something&#13;
that an individual country can't necessarily think of on its own. So it's a number of&#13;
countries together, internationally, that should think about what are the pricing policies,&#13;
and it was an enormous amount of money.&#13;
&#13;
Having missed that opportunity of engagement in dialogue because of the way that&#13;
operational work was being done up to that point, lots of money went missing policy&#13;
leverage opportunity in the interest ofthe people of developing countries. It may be in the&#13;
interests of a few people in developing countries not to have a good pricing policy, but&#13;
for the majority of the very people that we're here to serve, the poor people, the poor&#13;
farmers, in the long term, we missed out on doing something very important. Now, I&#13;
think by then the management at the Bank realized it, and that's the reason why they&#13;
created a Policy wing, and I felt that there's something very important, to help change the&#13;
way operations are done in the World Bank. And so, I thought I would give it a try. It's a&#13;
long story, but ...&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: No, it's very pertinent. Following up on this, how would you assess the Bank's&#13;
industrial policy in the '80s, and how did you contribute to it?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: Sure. There was no clear thinking in any of the regions on how different&#13;
countries' industrial policies ought to be, involving trade and industrial policies (trade&#13;
policy was also a part of the mandate ofthis department); whereas, there was enormous&#13;
interest, I think, from a number of countries to think about, or for the Bank to help them&#13;
think about, their industrial policies and their trade policies. So my assessment ofthe&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                         March 11 and 12,2004 Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                            7&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Bank's industrial development policy in the '80s is that there was no strategic thinking on&#13;
that.&#13;
&#13;
Now, how did I contribute to it? I did a couple of things while I was in the Research&#13;
Department that I'm very proud of. One is China, which had at that time recently joined&#13;
the World Bank, and the division was doing extremely interesting work. The Region on&#13;
China had a strategy of helping Chinese policymakers learn how to think about more than&#13;
economic policies, as opposed to thinking about it within a centrally planned Communist&#13;
regime, and that was China's own strategy, too, to get the Bank to help them think&#13;
through policies differently. One request that came to the division was to help China&#13;
think about its trade and exchange policy regime, both policies that guide capital accounts&#13;
and policies that guide current accounts. They were already thinking about what is now&#13;
called the World Trade Organization, and they knew that their own policies were&#13;
somehow out of line with all sorts of things.&#13;
&#13;
And so, the Region asked me and some of my colleagues from the Industrial Department&#13;
to work on that. And we spent quite a long time in China with a whole bunch of Chinese&#13;
counterparts reviewing the state oftrade and exchange policies together with the&#13;
[International Monetary] Fund people on our mission. We made a number of&#13;
recommendations which I think helped China to begin to change the way that it manages&#13;
its policies, and I can see it over time. It was very satisfying.&#13;
&#13;
The other thing that I'm equally proud of is, I spent a couple of years shuttling back and&#13;
forth between here and Hungary. This was before the fall of the Berlin Wall, so Hungary&#13;
was still under the Communist regime, but unlike other regimes under the USSR&#13;
influence, Hungary has been, for a long time, pursuing market-based socialist economic&#13;
policies. And they invited the World Bank to do a project on industrial restructuring&#13;
because they realized the industries were becoming less and less competitive, and&#13;
something had to be done, but they weren't quite sure what. And that assignment,&#13;
obviously, came to the Industrial Department, and I was invited to sort of the initial&#13;
project discussion meeting as an observer from the Policy wing. When Hungarians would&#13;
make a request, they had pretty much designed the projects, and so we had to review a&#13;
dossier of their project ideas, and it was essentially to make this investment in this steel&#13;
company so that, instead of making steel sheets that are 10-millimeter thick, make them&#13;
2-millimeter thick. It was highly technical engineering. It was all like that.&#13;
&#13;
And my project colleagues--the "hard hats" I used to call them--were debating all of this&#13;
technologically. And so, I jumped in and I think the Director ofthe department was&#13;
chairing the meeting-meetings back then were chaired by Directors. Here I was, a new&#13;
economist from the new Policy wing, and I said nicely, "Excuse me, I really don't think&#13;
that this design that came from Hungary is aligned to the objective that they said they&#13;
wanted to pursue because, the little I know of Hungary on paper, there must be a number&#13;
of policy regimes that need to be addressed." I saw more policy issues than the technical&#13;
design issues. And the "hard hats" around the table sort of, you know, said things to&#13;
ignore me, but one particular "hard hat," and the Director chairing the meeting thought&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                         March 11 and 12, 2004- Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                  8&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
that there was something to what I said. And so they asked me to join the mission of&#13;
"hard hats."&#13;
&#13;
And I went and, you know, I've always spoken my mind, so I spoke my mind to various&#13;
important people in Hungary, asking them to teach me what the policy regimes were like,&#13;
and I knew exactly what questions to ask and where to look. And, I think my questions,&#13;
down to Hungary's own proposal, were actually well-received by a bunch of Hungarians&#13;
in the system who were reformers and wanted to find a way to get away more from the&#13;
Communist Party philosophy, also concerning industrial policies. And so, they requested&#13;
my support, but on economic and sector work, not on projects, to think through changes&#13;
in economic, any economic policy of Hungary that are likely to improve productivity of&#13;
the Hungarian industry. And so I agreed on one condition, that it had to be their work&#13;
and not mine or the World Bank's, obviously, because I sensed the political complexity&#13;
ofthis. And I said, "You guys have to do it, and you're good enough economists," many&#13;
of them better than me. "What I can promise is to bring different perspectives from&#13;
outside, how to think about some of your policies, and also bring some of my contacts&#13;
and sort of first-rate people from academia or from the World Bank as advisers." That's&#13;
how we started.&#13;
&#13;
Laura Tyson, who was teaching at Berkeley at the time, was one of the consultants who&#13;
helped a great deal. She was well-known in comparative economic systems as a&#13;
researcher then, and a few other people like that. It was two years' work, and every other&#13;
month I would go to Hungary, and by the time I finished that work a lot of reforms were&#13;
being implemented because it was their work.&#13;
&#13;
And there were about 120 Hungarian officials from practically all of the ministries&#13;
involved in this engagement. It was an enormous amount of fun. What I ended up doing&#13;
was simply to provide political space because I'm in World Bank and the Communist&#13;
Party can't touch me, although they did follow me around all over the place and&#13;
monitored my telephone calls and faxes, but the Bank has clout and reputation. And&#13;
whether it's in Communist regimes or in any other country, one of our huge value-added&#13;
is that reputation and credibility, and being neutral in this process; ifthe staff uses it that&#13;
way; it opens the political door to people who want to engage in very hard reforms. All&#13;
that these people had to say to the Communist Party was, "Look, this is a World Bank&#13;
engagement."&#13;
&#13;
And it ended up being an outside facilitator over an increasing number of change leaders&#13;
in agencies in Hungary to study, propose, and implement a series of reforms, whether tax&#13;
reforms that affect corporate entities in Hungary or questioning whether the state&#13;
ownership is the right thing, to introducing income tax which they needed and which was&#13;
necessary as a new source of revenue, as Hungary decided, through the course of the&#13;
study, to begin thinking about privatization, later. This is before the Berlin Wall came&#13;
down. And when that strategy became official, they realized that they will no longer be&#13;
able to tax profits of state enterprises in the way that they had been doing, but really they&#13;
need to set up a modem income tax or some other tax revenues. And so it sort of became&#13;
an exercise in essentially revamping the whole tax system: introducing value added tax,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                          March 11 and 12,2004- Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                              9&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
introducing income tax for the first time, and changing labor laws, and changing also to&#13;
policies that regulate infrastructure development, because infrastructure, as you know, is&#13;
important for industrial productivity.&#13;
&#13;
So, when you think about policy issues to raise and create a dynamic industry, it&#13;
essentially brings in practically every economic policy of the land. And we also started to&#13;
touch on the banking reform because interest rate regimes and banking practices matter to&#13;
the productivity of industry. So it was the beginning of a sea change in the Hungarian&#13;
policy regime, and I was in the middle of that change process. It was a fascinating&#13;
experience. So, in the end, part of the work was incorporated into this industrial&#13;
restructuring project, and I think half of the loan was given, provided not as an&#13;
investment, but as a budget support to the Hungarian Government to cover the cost of&#13;
changing these policies.&#13;
&#13;
And we also wrote the report together, which became an issue because it's the&#13;
Hungarians' work. I'm a facilitator. But they wanted this published. And I said, "Well,&#13;
you write it." But the issue was, do we put a gray cover on this one? And in the end, there&#13;
was a sort of small report that came out that was a joint venture between my fingers at the&#13;
keyboard and my 120 Hungarian counterparts. There is a disclaimer on the front page,&#13;
but also it clearly said that this is a joint work with counterparts in Hungary. And I was&#13;
told it was the World Bank's first joint economic and sector work, truly owned by the&#13;
country, where they did it, and I was the icing on the cake.&#13;
&#13;
So I learned an enormous amount. There were good people, not just economists, but&#13;
social scientists, engineers, from all sorts of ministries and companies. So I enjoyed it a&#13;
lot. I learned a lot. I learned a lot about politics.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: How do you see the respective roles of the Bank and IFC [International Finance&#13;
Corporation] in industrial development?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: Yes. The way I think about it is different than the way most people like to&#13;
think about it nowadays; that is, really, the World Bank has no business investing in&#13;
industrial enterprises that really should have gone to IFC. The way I think about it is&#13;
probably a little more like a bank than most people in the Bank. What the World Bank&#13;
takes is a sovereign risk, risk of a country, although we lend other people's money, like&#13;
anybody else, like any other bank. So we take risks, and the risk we take is not on a&#13;
particular project, the risk we take is whether a nation can continue to repay us, and that's&#13;
important for us to continue our business because we have our own debt service to meet&#13;
because we borrow other people's money. And so, we should never take our eyes off that&#13;
banking business that we do. We take risks on Hungary and not on a particular project in&#13;
Hungary.&#13;
&#13;
Now, because we take risks on sovereigns, what we do, operationally, in the real sense,&#13;
what we should be always thinking about is what is good for the people of an economy&#13;
at-large, in the long term; i.e., economic policies and strategies that guide the nation, in a&#13;
major way. And we have a leverage to be able to work on that.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                          March 11 and 12,2004- Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                              10&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The individual investment into a particular enterprise ought to be the expertise of a set-up&#13;
like IFC, and IFC's financial structure is set up to enable that. And I've always felt that&#13;
the two have to work like as a seamless team. And it really should be driven by where the&#13;
best expertise is within the large mandate of each organization.&#13;
&#13;
I studied this on the Hungary work. When a reformer is questioning of their own country&#13;
policy regime this started to naturally touch on capital markets. They didn't have stock&#13;
markets, they didn't have bond markets, and as I said, there are people in the IFC who are&#13;
experts on this and who know not only how to advise on the policy regimes governing&#13;
good set-up of stock markets or bond markets, but also the nitty-gritty of how to do it. So&#13;
I brought in someone from IFC as part of my mission team, and we worked from the&#13;
same World Bank group. It was terrific fun, and I think that work resulted in some IFC&#13;
investments later in Hungary.&#13;
&#13;
It always works that way. If you provide good advice by first-rate people who know how&#13;
to listen, and if the counterparts are driving it--it's their work, it's their country--then you&#13;
don't have to worry about lending. It comes.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: What lessons are drawn from the Bank's early experiences with structural&#13;
adjustment reform in transition countries like Hungary, China?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: I think I touched on this a little bit. But the first thing is the importance of&#13;
politics, the importance of focusing on the political process and actors in the country and&#13;
finding space to do reform. What I mean is that one can think about when countries,&#13;
especially in transition economies, but in general mostly developing countries, engage in&#13;
structural reform, practically everything has to be changed. Economists, including Bank&#13;
economists, often worry about where should one start and how should we sequence&#13;
policy. My three or four years in the Policy wing taught me that it's really not practical to&#13;
think about that on paper, that one has to be pragmatic and start somewhere, however&#13;
small, within the structure of an economy, where there is a political opening, either&#13;
because there is a political leader who wanted to change that particular space like tax&#13;
reform or there is a good political excuse. But find reform policy for which there is a&#13;
political space that you can find and then bring in the Bank's message that will open up&#13;
that space even more. And, given the nature of policies in any country, when you start&#13;
somewhere, you should always be on the lookout for related policies, and then the&#13;
success of a policy change in one comer begins to pull in changes in the other parts, by&#13;
necessity.&#13;
&#13;
A good example was our engagement on industrial policy in Hungary. It ended up doing&#13;
practically everything because you had to do: tax reform, banking reform, capital markets&#13;
development, you name it. We started from where there was a domestic political opening&#13;
because the party was concerned about loss of industrial competitiveness. That was&#13;
important for a socialist way of thinking. So we entered there and carne out with a whole&#13;
economy that was beginning to change. I think it took Hungary 10 years or so to&#13;
complete that work. But had those reformers not done that work then, Hungary today&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                    Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                           March 11 and 12,2004- Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                            11&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
would be very different. It would have taken it longer to join the European Community.&#13;
So that's one thing I learned, the importance of focusing from the start on the political&#13;
landscape and political opportunity, and understanding the political process in a country.&#13;
&#13;
The other thing I learned is the importance of what is now called ownership, which is a&#13;
no-brainer, that the change has to happen in the country, and there's only so much that&#13;
outsiders like us can do. And so, the most important thing is to find those who have the&#13;
courage, the nerve and hopefully positions in power to effect some change as well as&#13;
have the passion to change and the leadership capacity to do so. So judgment on, I call&#13;
them "champions of change" in the country, looking for them, finding them, and making&#13;
judgment about those people is probably as important as the political things.&#13;
&#13;
What I also learned, in the case of my work in Hungary and China, is that when you do&#13;
that, and if you stay with it--and it does take a commitment--but if you stay with that&#13;
work, then one begins to help those leaders in the country change their country's&#13;
governance fundamentally. It's a long-term gain, but the kind of work that we get&#13;
engaged in is of such magnitude in developing countries that if you play the politics right,&#13;
and if you engage with good leaders, then the chance of establishing a different and better&#13;
governance regime in the way that the government manages its affairs, honestly, in those&#13;
countries, begins to get effected.&#13;
&#13;
And so, to summarize, the importance of politics and the importance of focusing on&#13;
ownership, it has to be their work and, as part of it, knowing that in the end good&#13;
governance drives everything and good leaders drive everything. I think worrying about&#13;
sequencing of reforms, worrying about whether you start the banking first or industry&#13;
first or whatever, is a total waste of time, and I think still too many people do that today.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: Many former Bank staff cite the Industry Department that you were a part of&#13;
back in the '80s as an example of a highly motivated and well-run central sector&#13;
department which attracted and trained many future Bank managers like yourself. What&#13;
are your views on what made the Industry Department so unique, and how can some of&#13;
its positive features be incorporated in the Bank today?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: Yeah, it was a fun place. I still miss it today, just as I miss the Research&#13;
Department. It's simple. Good, first-rate leaders of the department and the divisions,&#13;
people who, particularly the Division Chiefs that we had, were people like Kemal Dervis,&#13;
who economists like me and others much more qualified than I am could respect and&#13;
want to work for. So, when you put good leadership at the top of a division, the vision of&#13;
the policy wing, like in the Research Department, was very clear, and we went there&#13;
because we identified with that vision, and the managers who we could respect&#13;
professionally attracted good people.&#13;
&#13;
After all, the quality of the work of any Bank unit is the quality of the people in it. You&#13;
have to have first-rate managers who are also respected in her or his profession to be able&#13;
to attract good people, in addition to a good management environment. The Industrial&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                          March 11 and 12,2004- Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                            12&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Department had that, and the policy wing especially had that, and I think, in that sense,&#13;
it's unique.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: Are there lessons learned from that type of management that can be brought to&#13;
bear in today' s Bank?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: Yes. I mean, it is general management, good management practice to&#13;
have leaders in units of an organization who are good managers and good leaders and&#13;
good professionals that command people's respect. And good leaders mean someone with&#13;
vision who can articulate that vision and really inspire the staff. So that's easy to say but&#13;
a tough thing for them if you don't create a way of appointing managers in the Bank that&#13;
explicitly focus on these qualifications.&#13;
&#13;
There are a number of examples throughout the Bank; places that remind me of the&#13;
Industrial Department, but I'm afraid they tend to be more of a happenstance than by&#13;
design. So it takes time.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: In July 1987, you joined the EMENA Country Department as Lead Economist&#13;
(EMENA, for the sake of users of oral history, stands for Europe, Middle East and North&#13;
Africa.) Please discuss what led to your move to a Country Department, what challenges&#13;
you faced, and the priorities you set for yourself?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: First, what led me finally to a region was during the '87 reorganization.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: Was your move a result of the '87 reorganization?&#13;
&#13;
 NISHIMIZU: Yes. By the time the reorganization was brewing, I had made up my mind&#13;
 that I wanted to go over to a region, and so I applied--it's probably the only time I ever&#13;
·applied for a job in the Bank. I applied and, as soon as Country Departments were set up,&#13;
 I chose EMENA because of my language constraints as I couldn't speak French or&#13;
 Spanish, and I was working on Hungary, and so I thought EMENA would be great.&#13;
&#13;
I went to a Country Director who was just appointed to a new Country Department and&#13;
asked to be considered as his Lead Economist. I didn't make it, and things were done&#13;
very non-transparently, as is well-known, in the '87 reorganization. So, someone not as&#13;
qualified as I thought I was got the job. It didn't phase me much because by then I was&#13;
chosen to be the Division Chief of the division that I was in because Kemal Dervis, I&#13;
think, became a Country Director in EMENA, and the organization scheme changed, but&#13;
the whole division was kept as a division. And in this very opaque way, one day I was&#13;
told, "You are named as the new Division Chief." The staff in the unit begged me to stay&#13;
to be the Division Chief; you know, better the devil you know than the devil you don't&#13;
know. So I said, "Okay, why not?"&#13;
&#13;
I spent a whole month preparing the many things you had to do, and it involved some&#13;
firing of people, which I had to do as designated Division Chief. It was tough. Then, the&#13;
night before the official day, which was July 1, the whole Industrial Department was out&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                         March 11 and 12, 2004- Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                             13&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
on a picnic, I think, and I couldn't go because I still had to sign some papers, having fired&#13;
a few people, just as I was leaving or thinking about leaving, the phone rang, and it was&#13;
my new Director. He called me and said, "Sorry, in the last vice presidential endorsement&#13;
of the Division Chief designate, musical chairs, and you lost." So I was without a job at&#13;
that point.&#13;
&#13;
So I thought, "Okay, I'll go for the package." But it was rather upsetting because things&#13;
were done in such a non-transparent way. So I was getting ready to leave the Bank, trying&#13;
to do some things like deciding if! qualify for Package A or Package B. Either way, it&#13;
was a lot of money back then, and with my husband saying, "Don't worry. I'll support&#13;
you." So it was a sad time.&#13;
&#13;
Then the phone rang again, and someone I have never met, Hans Eberhart Kopp, called.&#13;
He was named a Country Director for EMENA Country Department I, which is Turkey,&#13;
Pakistan, and Afghanistan.&#13;
&#13;
He said, "There was a musical chair of Lead Economists, and I don't have any. Would&#13;
you like to be considered?"&#13;
&#13;
And so I said, "Sure."&#13;
&#13;
So, I was back to where I wanted to be, although not the department that I thought I&#13;
would like to be in, but a Lead Economist in EMENA. And so, I applied. I had never met&#13;
Hans Eberhart Kopp before in my life up to that point. So he interviewed me twice, had&#13;
me interviewed by a number of other people and offered me the job. That's how I ended&#13;
up in the department where ...&#13;
&#13;
I was very nervous because the reason why I wanted to be the Lead Economist in the&#13;
other department was that it included Hungary. And I feared that, at least--since it was&#13;
always my policy, I figured that when I go for a new job I don't want to find myself in a&#13;
situation of having to learn a new job, having to learn about the new people here, new&#13;
people in the country, counterparts, and having to learn about a new country. So I wanted&#13;
some of these parameters known, so that's why I went for the department that had&#13;
Hungary and a few other countries that I knew, where I knew the people here in the Bank&#13;
and in the country.&#13;
&#13;
Now, this was a totally new experience. I knew nothing about any ofthose countries--&#13;
Pakistan, Afghanistan and Turkey. The Director was totally new. There was only one&#13;
manager I knew, I think, in the whole department. So, I tell you, I felt like walking into&#13;
my own death.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: So what priorities, as Lead Economist, did you set for yourself?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: To define clearly what the role is. That's how I am. When I start a job, no&#13;
matter how small or large, the first thing you spend time on is to think about what should&#13;
be the mandate ofthatjob, as opposed to what is the mandate ofthatjob. And so there&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                          March 11 and 12,2004 Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                            14&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
was about half-a-paragraph long explanation of what was expected of the Lead&#13;
Economist that was written up. That was it.&#13;
&#13;
So it was a wonderful opportunity for me to create, and I spent some time over the&#13;
summer thinking about what should be an ideal Lead Economist, and that was not easy to&#13;
do. It was essentially an advisory role, and usually an advisory position is the most&#13;
difficult one to articulate the mandate for. So, what I set out to do is to be adviser for&#13;
strategic thinking; strategy of the country, in terms of development and strategy of the&#13;
whole Bank engagement in the country at a reasonably high level, which is the way I&#13;
knew how to swim. And so, that's how I set out to do that work.&#13;
&#13;
There was one immediate challenge that I faced, which is that all three of those countries&#13;
happen to be Islamic countries, and I was the only female Lead Economist appointed in&#13;
the Bank, and I think I got cheated on the grade because everybody else was 26, and I&#13;
was 25. It's a constant phenomenon in the Bank. But I didn't give a damn. I had an&#13;
interesting job. I decided to spend some time actually practicing, sort of playing out my&#13;
role with people in the department, whenever there were opportunities. Now, I couldn't&#13;
spend all of my existence gazing at my navel as a Lead Economist, and I must say some&#13;
Lead Economists did precisely that, and some of them are still my friends. So it was a&#13;
very tough job to define.&#13;
&#13;
What I did was, whenever there were operational issues or projects of strategic&#13;
importance then I made sure that I added strategic value to it. I reviewed every single&#13;
strategy paper, and I'm sure people back then would remember me as being a little too&#13;
tough, because I was. Most Bank papers that are named strategy, whether it's Country&#13;
Assistance Strategy or something else, are not strategy papers. You look for strategy, and&#13;
it doesn't exist. And so what I tried to do is, through reviewing them, helping people&#13;
revise CASs, helping staff in the department understand what is strategy as opposed to&#13;
writing reams of pages because I thought that's one role that Lead Economists can play.&#13;
Lead Economists should never do a Country Economist's job. There are Country&#13;
Economists to do that. But there are things that you can see, staying above country&#13;
economic work, across countries or at a higher level in the countries that are of a strategic&#13;
nature, and that's a value that I bring into specific concrete work. And that's how I started&#13;
and, if I may boast, and proved that a woman can do the Lead Economist job because&#13;
there was a lot of talk in the corridors.&#13;
&#13;
The other thing that I focused on, in terms of my priorities, was to develop a good&#13;
network of contacts in the country with change leaders, "champions of change," which I&#13;
learned from the Hungary and China work. We couldn't get into Afghanistan already at&#13;
that time, so it was essentially Turkey and Pakistan. So I invested a lot of time the first&#13;
year going on missions and simply meeting people and listening to their dreams and&#13;
bringing the interests of those people to what the staff in the Department and the Bank&#13;
can do for them. This demonstrated that a woman can have access in an Islamic country&#13;
at the highest levels. I got to the highest levels pretty fast. Because what happened was&#13;
that if you engage substantially or substantively with leaders who want to do something&#13;
right, not in their self-interests but in the interests of their country, and you engage with&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                          March 11 and 12,2004- Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                         15&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
them honestly, call black "black," white "white," and they see, through people like me,&#13;
the World Bank as the right ally for their work, then they will quickly ask you to see this&#13;
Minister or that Minister or Prime Minister. So, by the time the year was over, I was able&#13;
to demonstrate that I could indeed open doors, as a woman, in Islamic countries.&#13;
&#13;
And this is something I knew before, but I think as a woman in an Islamic country, just&#13;
because I'm a woman it opened doors provided you conducted yourself correctly in the&#13;
local context of the culture. Why is that? The people you meet are, by and large, men.&#13;
Men tend to be fathers and husbands, and when they see a female professional, it doesn't&#13;
take that long before they ask, "Would you come and meet my daughter and talk about&#13;
your career with her? Would you come and meet my wife? She's an NGO aCtivist" or&#13;
whatever. So, really, the door opens much faster, I think, because of my gender not&#13;
because of what I am.&#13;
&#13;
And, fortunately, at least in Pakistan and Turkey, once you get invited into a family, you&#13;
bond. People define relationships either within the family or the rest of the world. And so,&#13;
once you enter and cross that threshold, a whole different kind of relationship begins.&#13;
And I'm sure it's true in other cultures too. I think it's easier for women to enter in ways&#13;
that are not as threatening, in a totally neutral way without a business interest. But there&#13;
were a lot of unpleasant corridor talks. So that was my big challenge.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: With your promotion to Division Chief soon thereafter, what were the&#13;
challenges you faced as a new manager?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: There was no management training back then. There is some now. So,&#13;
even though when the vacancy arose I did ask for that job, I wanted to do it very badly,&#13;
and actually did. Eberhart Kopp really challenged himself because he wanted me to be&#13;
the Division Chief of the Industry, Trade &amp; Finance Division, but he didn't want to lose&#13;
me as the Lead Economist either. So I ended up doing two jobs for about a year. It was&#13;
the least I could do for him. But I tell you, it was tough. You think you know how to&#13;
manage things, but managing people, I wish there had been some good indoctrination to&#13;
help me out.&#13;
&#13;
So the first challenge was, what do I do? Fortunately, in my case, there was another&#13;
Division Chief in my department who was Japanese, Mr. Yoshi Abe. He is my hero. And&#13;
he's been looking after me ever since I joined the Bank, making sure that I'm being&#13;
treated okay because I was one of the few Japanese women here. And so, he took me&#13;
under his wing and taught me the ABCs of being an Operational Division Chief in the&#13;
region, really the ABCs, every step of the way from project processing, how to do the&#13;
dialogue, to strategy making, to this and that, to politics. So I owe him an enormous&#13;
amount. What I know as a manager, things I didn't know by then I learned from him in&#13;
one year. He was mentoring me, and he made sure he went on a mission with me in the&#13;
first year to show me what he did on missions as Division Chief. I'd be carrying his bags.&#13;
It was really a lot of fun. Oh, he's a fantastic person and a great manager. So that was a&#13;
challenge.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                         March 11 and 12, 2004- Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                                   16&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                         The other challenge was attracting good people because by then I knew that people&#13;
                         matter more than me. So that was a second challenge--stealing good people from other&#13;
                         regions and convincing them to give me a chance.&#13;
&#13;
                         And the third challenge was a substantive one. This is that, given my other experience up&#13;
                         to that point, I knew what I had to focus on strategically in the operational context of&#13;
                         industry, training and financing in those three countries, and that's governance issues,&#13;
                         particularly corruption. Now, those were the days when that was the big "C" word that&#13;
                         you don't talk about. And so the single most substantive challenge that I had to face was&#13;
                         to, through everything we do, focus on governance issues. Fortunately, I was able to&#13;
                         gather some very good staff who were like-minded and passionate to fight corruption&#13;
                         through policy changes. And that's when we started to do some major work on banking&#13;
                         reforms in Pakistan, which ended up taking 10 years to the finish line but they did finish.&#13;
&#13;
                         So there were some scary moments. I think it was within the second year of my time&#13;
                         there, by then we were working with sort of middle managers of the banking system in&#13;
                         Pakistan who are reporting to us all sorts of corruption issues, especially politicians&#13;
                         stealing money from the banking system through fictitious loans, et cetera, and bringing&#13;
                         the country down. It's not just small amounts. It's a huge amount of money. They&#13;
                         eventually ended up as what is called non-performing loans, in the balance sheet of the&#13;
                         system. And by the time we looked into this, it was already sufficiently worrisome that it&#13;
                         might actually crumble the economy one day. But I was fortunate; I had a gutsy director,&#13;
  c:n&#13;
~g;&#13;
!-&lt;-&#13;
        -&#13;
        ("'o...&#13;
        c:::&gt;&#13;
        ("'o...&#13;
                         Eberhart Kopp, and a very gutsy Regional Vice President, Wilfried Thal-witz, both of&#13;
                         whom unquestionably supported my wish to confront the political system with corruption&#13;
u:t:&#13;
;a~&#13;
E-o&lt;&#13;
Cl.lo&#13;
        - .=&#13;
        CD&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        c.o&#13;
        =&gt;&#13;
                         issues in the banking stem. And so, I went to face the Finance Minister at the time and&#13;
                         told him what I knew,                                           unless change didn't&#13;
                         happen, what the consequences                      was something like half-a-billion dollars&#13;
=~&#13;
                   0&#13;
        &lt;(        ·a&#13;
                   0     of proposed lending that the country wanted from us in the financial sector. So, it was lots&#13;
                   u&#13;
                   X&#13;
                  loLl   of effort, scary.&#13;
&#13;
                         ZENNI: Well, looking back at that period in EMENA, what were the highlights of that&#13;
                         country experience?&#13;
&#13;
                         NISHIMIZU: By the time I left, we had a network of changers in the country, both in&#13;
                         Turkey and Pakistan, in the financial sector who wanted to right the governance over the&#13;
                         banking system, who also knew that if they make inroads in there, that they Vvill begin to&#13;
                         change the governance in the whole country, and this entailed a lot of detailed and hard&#13;
                         work by the staff, and a lot of "scary" policy dialogue with some corrupt people by me,&#13;
                         because that was my role as Division Chief. But I think the results, had we not confronted&#13;
                         the issue then and worked with a network of the like-minded in our country who wanted&#13;
                         the same thing, both of these countries would have been in total financial chaos by now.&#13;
&#13;
                         I think Pakistan has done better than Turkey. Turkey had more room to maneuver&#13;
                         because it was a bigger country and economy, but certainly both would have been in&#13;
                         financial collapse by now, that I know. And I don't have to say it. If you talk to any of the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                            Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                                                   March 11 and 12,2004- Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                          17&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
leaders in the banking system in those countries, they will say that because they know&#13;
what I've done. So I'm proud of it.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: Is this a good time to break?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: Okay.&#13;
&#13;
[Interruption]&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: Now let's turn to risk management. In January '92, you were promoted to&#13;
Director in the Risk Management and Financial Policy Department. Please discuss how&#13;
this came about and what were your main responsibilities.&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: Yes. Well, how this came about, ask Johannes Linn. He was made Vice&#13;
President of that by [Lewis T.] Preston, and there was a vice presidency with Financial&#13;
Policy and Risk Management (FRS) on one side governing IBRD finances, and the other&#13;
was FRM governing IDA finances; these were together reporting to the same Vice&#13;
President. So my responsibility, they called my job the "Chief Constable," especially in&#13;
the Treasury Department, in the finance complex side, and in the Treasury and the&#13;
Investment Departments, because--well, the reason why I said ask Johannes, first of all,&#13;
because it was Johannes. I've always wanted to work for people that I respect, and he&#13;
certainly was someone I respected enormously, but also because I knew what the job was.&#13;
&#13;
The job responsibility was making sure that the World Bank doesn't cheat anybody out of&#13;
their money, let us put it that way. The IBRD part of the World Bank, and that meant&#13;
that my mandate in the financial complex was being accountable, at making sure that the&#13;
Investment Department and the Treasury Department do their     ' financial work honestly&#13;
and correctly, on the one hand, and on the other hand, making sure that regions who do&#13;
business in IBRD countries do their work correctly in lending. In a way, it's sort oflike&#13;
being a Central Bank Governor or regulating the banking system, except we don't have&#13;
any regulators outside IBRD, being an international organization. So it takes on some of&#13;
the regulatory role that, in the other situations, would be assumed by the Central Bank or&#13;
Finance Ministry in some countries. And I knew what that work entailed through my&#13;
experience up to that point. And, by that time, my dream job was to be a Governor of the&#13;
Central Bank of Japan, except that I am the wrong gender. They won't take women. So&#13;
this was something that comes closest to doing that job, and I took it very, very seriously.&#13;
On the financial side, whenever there are mistakes made in any of our finance work--and&#13;
finance work is very detailed work--then I come in to help my colleagues understand&#13;
what the problem is and correct it, whether it's overcharging clients--that's happened--or&#13;
doing accounting work, in which case I would have to work with an accountant, Chief&#13;
Accountant.&#13;
&#13;
On the operational side, I was a member of all of the regional Loan Committees which&#13;
were committees chaired by Regional Vice Presidents to decide on CASs, and to decide&#13;
on major lending proposals, which means all structural adjustment loans, anything that&#13;
gets disbursed fast, and some other major initiatives. And there, from outside, to bring in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                         March 11 and 12, 2004- Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                           18&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
the disciplines across the Bank, across IBRD, of the right practices and give advice as&#13;
someone sitting in between the financial banking side of the World Bank and the&#13;
operational side of the World Bank.&#13;
&#13;
So, in a nutshell, these were my main responsibilities, and that entailed also having&#13;
constant dialogue with the Board; i.e., shareholders, representatives of the shareholders;&#13;
our shareholders being sovereign people of different countries, representatives of the&#13;
shareholders, because it's important to have their ownership and technical understanding&#13;
of how things are done for important decisions that they need to make at the Bank. So,&#13;
for example, every year I was responsible for assessing medium- to long-term risk of our&#13;
investments; i.e., in loans to countries, and depending on the risk situation, I have to&#13;
recommend provisioning. And, also every year, I have to recommend to the Board how&#13;
the profits of the World Bank, however small, should be distributed for different&#13;
requirements. Those are major and strategic financial decisions of the Board that the staff&#13;
has to recommend. And my philosophy was that it's important that they understand what&#13;
I do and how I think about things to help make it easy for them to focus on strategic&#13;
issues, depending on the different constituencies. And so, building trust--and I was very&#13;
clear on that one--between the management and staff of IBRD and the Board on those&#13;
issues that I was responsible for. So I was constantly in the Board corridors. So, yes, I&#13;
learned a lot.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: Based on that experience, how well, in your opinion, does the Bank mitigate&#13;
political, operational, and financial risks, and how has this evolved in an increasingly&#13;
globalized environment?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: It's a tough job for the Bank to do this. Honestly, I don't think the Bank&#13;
mitigates the composite of these risks well enough, so I don't think the Bank is as&#13;
efficient a financial institution as the Articles of the World Bank (both IBRD and IDA),&#13;
permit us to be able to. And, I think there are plenty of areas where one needs to look at&#13;
for the relationship between political risks, financial risks and operational risks. One&#13;
doesn't expect one person to be able to do that, but there has to be a system, an explicit&#13;
and well-run system, that brings together risk assessment and management andjudgment&#13;
of different parts of the World Bank to make well-informed and strategic decisions&#13;
proactively and strategically at the top. We don't have such a system yet. I know that we&#13;
started to develop it. We don't have it yet. So, ifwe can perform at a LevellO, or&#13;
performing somewhere inside 10, it's the way to go.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: Turning to the South Asia Country Department, in October '95, you became&#13;
Director of the South Asia Country Department. Please discuss the circumstances leading&#13;
to your move, and how you set out to tackle the overwhelming challenges presented by a&#13;
region that is home to the largest number of the world's poor, 60 percent of whom are&#13;
women.&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: Would you believe that at that time the region, and certainly, well, most&#13;
of the people in South Asia Region, and certainly most ofthe people in the Bank, didn't&#13;
realize that in South Asia resided a majority of the poor of the world. When some of us,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                         March 11 and 12,2004- Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                           19&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
including our Chief Economist then when I got there, Joanne Salop, started to talk about&#13;
that, we used to be shocked that people were shocked to find out that the majority of the&#13;
poor live in South Asia. So that tells you something about the institution back then. We&#13;
didn't have a strategic view of certain aspects of the world. Anyway, circumstances&#13;
leading to how I got there?&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: Yes, what made you decide to take that job?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: I was told to move by then Human Resources Vice President, Shahid&#13;
Husain, who had already discussed it actually with Mr. Preston and Mr. [James D.]&#13;
Wolfensohn in Mr. Preston's hospital room (because he was hospitalized and&#13;
Wolfensohn was already named). So I learned later from Shahid Husain that they talked&#13;
about that in hospital.&#13;
&#13;
Now, one of the things that Shahid started then was to give transparency to management&#13;
appointments and rotations, and that effort continues today. Kathy [Katherine Sierra] has&#13;
done a great job on that. And so I was told to move. And (my mother knows this very&#13;
well) if anybody tells Mieko what to do, her first reaction is, "No thank you." So I said,&#13;
"No, I have another year in FRS."&#13;
&#13;
In fact, this was serious because when I got to FRS, the staff had a list of major financial&#13;
policies that needed to be made, in their view. The first thing I do when I move to a new&#13;
place, I sit with the people there and say, "Tell me. Please teach me." And once I&#13;
understood what their needs were, and some of them were major engagements like&#13;
introducing single currency loans, I committed myself to stay in FRS until that list was&#13;
finished, and that was a serious commitment to them. They had suffered from frequent&#13;
changes in the Directorship. And so, I was there I guess for four years or so, and&#13;
everything was done except one item, and I had another year to go. And so that's why I&#13;
said, "No." I mean, I wanted a Country Directorship, what Shahid asked me probably I&#13;
would have wanted, and I certainly wanted to become a Country Director as my last job&#13;
in the Bank because it's the most challenging, I think. And, you know, my usual rule,&#13;
language, English, since Japan doesn't borrow any more; and the countries I know,&#13;
because that department was half of the region, so it was Pakistan, Bangladesh, Sri&#13;
Lanka, and Afghanistan. So I knew two countries. I knew Pakistan and Afghanistan.&#13;
There were some new countries, but I knew the major player in that. I knew some of the&#13;
people. So that's where I would have gone, but it was a little too early. So I said, "No."&#13;
&#13;
But Shahid Husain, if you knew him, is as stubborn as I am. So we were a very good&#13;
match. So I sat with my staff and asked them to advise me, pointing out that nine out of&#13;
the ten to-do items are finished and there is one more to go. It had something to do with&#13;
how we actually account for things to manage reserves, and it had some political issues.&#13;
So I told them, honestly, that I actually am offered a dream job, but if they tell me that&#13;
they need me for another year to finish this last thing, since I made the promise, I will try&#13;
not to break it, and so I would stay. It's a very small department.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                          March 11 and 12,2004- Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                           20&#13;
&#13;
They thought about it very seriously and came back and said, "Look, you better go. The&#13;
work is half finished anyway," and that they should be able to do it without me.&#13;
&#13;
So I said, "Okay. Then, I'll go." So, with their blessing I left, and that's how it came&#13;
about.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: So how did you set out to tackle the challenges then?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: Well, I guess it's sort of becoming a pattern. I said to Shahid Husain,&#13;
"Look, I need some training. I mean, I don't know how to do a Country Director job. I&#13;
can't just jump in and start," and I was succeeding somebody who was an excellent&#13;
Country Director, Paul Isenman. So they agreed that I would do sort of a half-year&#13;
understudy with Paul Isenman. Paul had been a very good friend anyway, so it helped.&#13;
And so I moved in the middle of August, I think.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: Of '95?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: Yes. And essentially shadowed Paul Isenman, observed what he does,&#13;
how and why he does things, and also went on missions with him and then started on&#13;
October 1st.&#13;
&#13;
So, by the time October 1 came about, I pretty much knew what I wanted to do, and it&#13;
was that the region, not the whole region, but the part that I was responsible for, the&#13;
Country Department, needed a fundamental culture change in the way it worked. It had a&#13;
bunch of very seasoned and excellent people. The people had been in the region for&#13;
many, many, man years, because they liked working in South Asia, and I don't blame&#13;
them. The downside of that is that there was a very strong culture in the Department and&#13;
the Region that was a culture of what's called a supply-driven culture, a culture of, "We&#13;
know what's good for the country. We'll go in and tell them what to do," and being a&#13;
little harsh to make the point. Not everybody was like that, of course. I saw that, and even&#13;
though I was not at all an experienced operational manager, I knew enough about&#13;
operations to recognize that that doesn't work--for me, at least. And so, I think on the day&#13;
I was appointed, I sent an e-mail to staff saying what my vision of the Department is,&#13;
which is having a bunch of people who are professionally first rate with knowledge of&#13;
what the clients are dying to get, money comes last--I remember saying that--and having&#13;
people who know how to listen and engage in the local context and help clients do what&#13;
they want to do, as opposed to making the clients do what we want them to do. And I&#13;
remember telling them that, with all humility, I feel that that means there are some basic&#13;
values we need to share, like integrity, honesty, etcetera, and that I look forward to&#13;
working with them in that way.&#13;
&#13;
And I think the first year I strategically did things that are very obviously aligned to what&#13;
I said. For example, on my first "getting to know you" trip as a Director to each of the&#13;
countries, I learned that they are poor. I knew the government. I'd go straight to the&#13;
village and stay there for a week to understand poverty firsthand, and I always went&#13;
under the care ofNGOs that work with some of those villages. But I did it intentionally,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                          March 11 and 12, 2004- Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                           21&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
by action, to demonstrate to stafithat, for me, it's not good enough that you're a first-rate&#13;
engineer and know how to process things and having visited villages many times over.&#13;
You need to immerse yourself in it and really experience poverty--being hungry and&#13;
working out in the blazing sun--to have it as part of your real life experience. So you&#13;
begin to appreciate what a radically different life that is, and see development from their&#13;
eyes, not from our eyes.&#13;
&#13;
Development is holistic and doesn't come neatly in so many straight lines: education,&#13;
health, road, and irrigation. They are all connected from the villages' point of view. Clean&#13;
water is a health issue for them. And two ministries or two departments in the World&#13;
Bank that do not sort of cross the borders, don't serve holistic needs. So I wanted to&#13;
demonstrate that. I tell you I think it caused some rumblings because I would then report&#13;
back to the staff with my diary, essentially, a sort of a running travelogue of my&#13;
experiences. So that's one thing I did to, if I may use a management word, force them to&#13;
follow me, to radically change their perspective. And, however long they've been in the&#13;
region, they are very good people, and I knew that all I had to do was shock them a little&#13;
bit and change their perspective. And then I knew there were lots of golden eggs and&#13;
golden goose in there. So that was sort of an internal management challenge; changing&#13;
perspectives. Team behavior wasn't there, which meant tough behavior. Even though&#13;
clean water is a health issue, the health people and the water people don't work together,&#13;
stupid things like that. I mean, it still goes on in the bureaucracy, and it's a never-ending&#13;
challenge. It's easy to fix it if you change the budget rules, but it's difficult to convince&#13;
managers in the Bank to take the trouble of really understanding budget as incentives on&#13;
humans.&#13;
&#13;
And, as I sort of went through the first year, which ended up, unfortunately, as my last&#13;
year, because I was allowed essentially to do it for one year, Country Director, de facto,&#13;
through the '96 calendar year, plus two months in '95, I realized the need when I finished&#13;
visiting all of the countries and the country offices of the Bank, and South Asia already&#13;
had a very large share of staff out there in resident missions something like, if you&#13;
accounted for everybody correctly, 40 percent. But back then, those people weren't&#13;
counted. They weren't on the roster. I opened the World Bank phone book and only saw&#13;
60 percent of my staff in there as they didn't add the resident mission staff. Did the HR&#13;
have a complete list of those people? No. We had absolutely no idea of who was working&#13;
for us. You had to actually visit every resident office and count the people or get the&#13;
records. They were really, really invisible. So, whenever people--and we'll have a chance&#13;
to talk about this later--say the South Asia Region is the one that has done&#13;
decentralization the deepest by looking at the number of people out there, I tell them,&#13;
"Wake up. It's not a good indicator. I started high already at 40 percent, and I got to 60&#13;
percent, and you're congratulating me?" Go home, right? What needs to change is not&#13;
just the number of people, but who they are, and how they work, and how we value and&#13;
support their work, which I am somewhat proud of.&#13;
&#13;
So I think by December '95 I started to notice the need to decentralize in a different way,&#13;
not just the people count, but through what these people on the ground do and how the&#13;
headquarters works with them. And so my model was very simple. One, I need to put a&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                          March 11 and 12, 2004- Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                             22&#13;
&#13;
Country Director out there. I need to get rid of my job in Washington. I was a Country&#13;
Director for several countries in Washington. I knew that my responsibility for each&#13;
country had to go out there in the field. So I had made up my mind by the summer&#13;
of '96, which is when I finished my trip to all of the countries and collapsed from&#13;
exhaustion; my resistance gave up, and so I had to be treated. Anyway, I knew I had to&#13;
destroy my job, which I was more than happy to do, decentralize Country Directors in&#13;
residents in the field and then define roles, make sure that the model that I had, which I&#13;
began to implement before I got demoted to being a Regional Vice President, was&#13;
certainly a much bigger field office, with Country Director in residence, if the client&#13;
wants it.&#13;
&#13;
And the value of the staff in the field, by the very fact that they are the nationals, to&#13;
execute my model you have to make sure that your HR strategy is to hire from the local&#13;
market, nationals. In addition to being able to hire good economists--obviously, you can&#13;
always do that--it's an Indian economist who has much better ability to look at the&#13;
economic issues in the context of India, its culture, business, politics, than anybody from&#13;
outside; besides, he or she speaks English plus other dialects oflndia. The role of the&#13;
staff working on India out of Washington would have to bring some distinct value to that&#13;
by having a global perspective or some very rare skilL&#13;
&#13;
What I went after in the model is a marriage between good professionals on both sides of&#13;
the ocean--teamwork-plus, on the country side, people who bring additional knowledge&#13;
that can't be qualified easily. For instance, economics you can learn, but how to be an&#13;
Indian you can't learn as it embodies unqualified knowledge. So, having a team that with&#13;
staff from the outside can bring equally good professional skills, but in addition can bring&#13;
an objective perspective of an outsider which I believe has always value, including&#13;
comparative perspective across countries, and for that model to work, task-by-task, the&#13;
two sides ofthe ocean had to work as a strong team, as one high-performing team. And&#13;
that meant, to implement it, a major change in some ofthe country offices of people, plus&#13;
many other things that had to be done also, which I'm sure we'll have a chance to talk&#13;
about.&#13;
&#13;
But during my year as Country Director, which was really a learning year, and I'm afraid&#13;
I didn't give very much back to the countries; it was a year that helped me develop a&#13;
different way of working that is required, that changes culture, that changes approaches&#13;
to be more effective on the ground. And so, and during the year I started, with the&#13;
Managing Director's permission--Joe [D. Joseph] Wood was my Vice President, and he&#13;
saw it like this immediately and let me experiment, but given the radical nature, we had&#13;
to go to the Managing Director to put a Country Director, as an experiment in Sri Lanka.&#13;
And so, I devolved Sri Lanka with my responsibility to the Country and called him&#13;
Country Manager in Sri Lanka. So the person who was Res Rep then already was given&#13;
the Country Manager responsibility as an experiment to see how it worked. So that's how&#13;
I began.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: In what way did your previous country experience in the EMENA Region help&#13;
you tackle country issues in South Asia?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                         March 11 and 12,2004- Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                          23&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: Well, not just in EMENA, but also even before, work in Hungary and&#13;
China. I think all of the experience up to that point helped me develop an attitude, which&#13;
I think was probably a minority attitude, in line with my conviction that to serve a client&#13;
country, you really need to find a way organizationally to deliver into the local solution&#13;
and make sure that things are driven by the change agency in the country, not by us,&#13;
things like that. And that what's important: knowledge, not money. Because if you have&#13;
good people advising well, in the local context, and adding value through knowledge that&#13;
the policymakers in the country need, there will be more project requests, lending&#13;
requests that would come from those countries, and by the time they come, they are so&#13;
well thought out that processing costs on our side would be very low, and you would go&#13;
from start to finish in three months.&#13;
&#13;
That has always been my conviction, and that's based on my experience in Hungary, in&#13;
particular, and in China and other countries that I've worked on. So it's cumulative. I&#13;
mean, one learns, I hope, over time. So I think everyone I worked with in countries that I&#13;
was assigned to taught me many things that make me have that attitude.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: In February '97, upon your promotion to Regional Vice President for South&#13;
Asia you became responsible for Bank operations covering eight nations with over 1A&#13;
billion people more than one-third of them living on less than one dollar a day. Please&#13;
discuss what priorities you set for yourself and how you went about achieving your goals.&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: I think it's clear by now, given what I said, that I really didn't want the&#13;
job. I took it in the end to set out to create what I thought was a World Bank--at least in&#13;
part of the World Bank--that has the cultural and organizational characteristics in&#13;
everyone that would make us relevant no matter how the country needs change. I wanted&#13;
to create that staying power, not because I think the World Bank should stay on and on&#13;
and on--one day our business should close--but staying on in the sense of a passion to&#13;
serve so that poverty reduction is accelerated.&#13;
&#13;
So I wanted to change the behavior of the South Asia Region to one that serves client&#13;
countries and change leaders by listening and understanding the context and bringing in&#13;
knowledge to help their work. It's a cliche really, to think global and act local, but doing&#13;
it in a very systematic way. And, as a means to that, decentralize heavily, but not in head&#13;
counts but rather in the very real sense of having the best people of the country working&#13;
under a Country Director that has pretty much all of the operational authority and&#13;
responsibility, living in the environment constantly and pulling knowledge and skills&#13;
either from headquarters, anywhere in headquarters, or from the rest of the world--the&#13;
best should win that contract--and working as a strong team all the time.&#13;
&#13;
And I wanted to do it in a way that lasts and continues the role. I knew that Regional Vice&#13;
Presidents were thought to be powerful and that the staff will do what the Regional Vice&#13;
Presidents order them to do--don't ask me why. So I knew that if I wanted to write down&#13;
all of these changes and tell the people what to do, it would happen overnight. But I&#13;
didn't think that would last. What if I get hit by a truck the next day and there is a new&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                          March 11 and 12, 2004- Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                           24&#13;
&#13;
Vice President that has different ways of doing it. I wanted to create something more; a&#13;
chance of growing organically because people are convinced, through their own&#13;
experience, that it's a good way, and most people in the client countries are convinced.&#13;
So because the good things, you know, are not as easy to break as the bad things. So the&#13;
first thing I did when I was appointed was to explain to the staff my vision and the values&#13;
that played to that and I said clearly, "Stay with me if you agree. If you don't, you are&#13;
welcome to leave." I think that was a harsh message and, fortunately, pretty much&#13;
everybody stayed. Then, I said, beyond this, that I really didn't have that much of an idea&#13;
how to go about doing it, but it's about everybody changing in the way we work, and so&#13;
why don't we get together and start to remake and think about how to implement it. If it&#13;
takes organizational change, fine. If it takes something else, fine, but let's do it together.&#13;
&#13;
And so we spent from February to the end of June with staff from different parts of the&#13;
region, including country offices, working on changes in this and that, and began a new&#13;
structure, because the staff said it made sense, on the 1st of July. We got rid of two&#13;
departments and appointed Country Directors in all countries except two that declined&#13;
having Country Directors, which were the two smallest in South Asia--Maldives and&#13;
Bhutan.&#13;
&#13;
I gave countries--i.e., Finance Ministers who are supposed to speak for the government at&#13;
least--a choice: do you want a World Bank Country Office in your country, and do you&#13;
want Country Directors in residence? And everybody, all of the countries--all of the&#13;
Finance Ministers--pretty much in synchrony said, "What took you so long to ask? This is&#13;
how we'd like the World Bank to be," and they were very excited. Bhutan and Maldives&#13;
thought very seriously about it and then decided not to because they are small, and the&#13;
World Bank office presence in their capital they feared would overwhelm them, and they&#13;
were probably right. They already had very large U.N. presence anyway. But what they&#13;
said was, "Look, Information Age, video conference and all of that, let's use aggressively&#13;
technology so that we won't feel ... " They knew, ideally, they would like to have the&#13;
same arrangement, but since they can't have that, they wanted to use the information&#13;
technology differently, too. So that was a very good solution.&#13;
&#13;
Many other changes structurally were made, but we also changed a number of things that&#13;
are supposed to impact on the behavior of the staff, and that was the hardest one. And it&#13;
took a long time to get behaviors to change, especially at the beginning, when Country&#13;
Office staff got to see that they have the power now. They were no longer sort of bag&#13;
carriers and mail carriers, which is what they were. So they gained power, and they were&#13;
starting to say, "Washington, we don't need you. Washington hurts, people are hurt." And&#13;
when, in the old regime, the resident mission staff who could do nothing wrong, all of a&#13;
sudden became a focus of criticism. I mean, it's about power and rebalancing of power.&#13;
So we went through some stormy exchanges. Anyway, so that was my first focus. It was&#13;
very internally focused in the first six months or so.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: In retrospect, and I know you've touched on this, saying that your many&#13;
experiences have brought you to this juncture in your career, but are there still any&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                          March 11 and 12,2004- Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                          25&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
particular experiences back then that you think shaped your role as regional Vice&#13;
President?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: That's a very important question, actually. Every time I was appointed in&#13;
a management job, as I said before, and it was a new job for me, right, and I didn't know&#13;
what to do, and there was no good training, the worst was being appointed as a Vice&#13;
President. You're sort of thrown into it with absolutely no preparation done by the&#13;
institution, and I think we still don't do it today, as if you're supposed to know, and that&#13;
worried me enormously.&#13;
&#13;
Looking back, what helped were several things: one, that I relied on staff or I asked staff&#13;
to help me, and that was a good sort of bonding experience, and staff can teach you a lot.&#13;
If you create an environment for them to feel safe to criticize, you get enormous&#13;
criticisms that are a terrific way to learn. So there was that, and I am forever thankful.&#13;
&#13;
The other was by then I had a mental picture of a composite of managers that I've&#13;
worked for in the past and those I've observed from a distance. So, by the time I hit&#13;
actually the Country Director, and certainly the RVP [regional vice president] job, I had a&#13;
pretty good idea of the kind of manager I like to work for. So a composite of good things&#13;
from everyone, plus the not so good things that I didn't want, especially when I became&#13;
an RVP, I used that image as sort of a check, because I didn't have any particular mentor&#13;
or role model, especially as a woman, and I was the first female Regional Vice President&#13;
in the Bank. It was a little tough. So I had this make-believe, fictitious composite image&#13;
that I always sort of used as a yardstick. So that's second.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                       so&#13;
Lome               was assigned by the ED. There was a management consultant group in&#13;
the Bank, and so he was assigned, and we worked very well together, and I asked him to&#13;
help me out because he consulted for CEOs of a number of large companies before he&#13;
came to the Bank. So he had a perspective of what to do and what to do to be a good&#13;
manager and leader. So it was as if I had an extra pair of eyes looking at what I do and&#13;
how I do things, what I say and how I say things, impact on staff, and helping me to learn&#13;
from that. So that was the third. So those are three main things that helped me learn on&#13;
the job pretty fast, to the extent that I could learn them. But I was still learning by the&#13;
time I left.&#13;
&#13;
One thing where I think the Bank needs to change is in defining the role of different Vice&#13;
Presidents, particularly Regional Vice Presidents. Is it written anywhere? Not really.&#13;
There's implicit tacit understanding of what RVPs do, what different VPs do, but are&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                          March 11 and 12,2004- Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                              26&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 there well-articulated roles and mandates for RVPs? No. So the practice of each RVP in&#13;
 the Bank differs. I'm not saying that's bad, but I think it's about time that one looked at&#13;
 the different practices of all the RPV s in the region today, as well as look back at how&#13;
 other major, notable RPVs practiced their roles, and for the institution to think, because it&#13;
 is RPVs that drive the Bank business in a very important way. And I think it's unusual for&#13;
 such a critical, core management leadership job to go undefined explicitly. So I had&#13;
 nothing to go by. Even the Country Director job had something to go by in terms of&#13;
 written understanding, and even though they were a summary, they were always very&#13;
 useful because I knew what the institutional understanding of a CD job or a sector&#13;
 operational Division Chief job was. For the RVPs, I looked and there was nothing.&#13;
&#13;
 ZENNI: And you weren't about to propose that this be done?&#13;
&#13;
 NISHIMIZU: Well, I first needed to learn. I talked about it a number of times in various&#13;
 fora, so it's no secret that I have this view. But remember, when I took over the South&#13;
 Asia Region, the Bank was in the middle of this change process. And South Asia and&#13;
 East Asia were the last to enter the change process. So my mandate was clear, and since it&#13;
 really didn't matter as much because, since I was going to change it anyway and create&#13;
 something different, my plan was when I felt comfortable, and the other regions' change&#13;
 process also coalesced--because each region was going at a different speed--then that&#13;
 would be the time to compare notes. I think the time to compare notes is pretty much here&#13;
 now. I've said this to Kathy Sierra, Shengman [Zhang], and others, so it's no secret. So&#13;
 I'm sure it will happen one day.&#13;
&#13;
   ZENNI: Now, we tum to the CDF (Comprehensive Development Framework). And by&#13;
   way of background, in June '95, at the time Wolfensohn took over as President of the&#13;
   Bank, the aid community had already begun a candid self-assessment prompted by&#13;
tf growing concerns as to how aid was used and managed. In response, in January '99,&#13;
   Wolfensohn proposed the adoption of the CDF (holistic model of development&#13;
   emphasizing country ownership of the development agenda) as a new way for the Bank&#13;
   to do its business. Noting the institutional pressures to create CDF pilots, how did you&#13;
   approach this in South Asia?&#13;
&#13;
 NISHIMIZU: I said no, in front of everybody. It was at one of the Corporate Days, I&#13;
 think, when Jim presented the CDF. He didn't call it that then, but he presented us with&#13;
 this thinking and said let's do a pilot. All of the other regions, I think, said yes, we want&#13;
 to do pilots, but I said, "No, South Asia will not." And I said the reason is, I agree with&#13;
 everything that's being said--country ownership, looking at development holistically&#13;
 across health, water--and Jim knew this by then--that this is the core of the process of the&#13;
 South Asia Region, which by then I think had been going on for a couple years. And so,&#13;
 in the context of South Asia, just picking one country as a pilot actually divides the&#13;
 region. I feared that it will be a divisive thing. That was one reason.&#13;
&#13;
 And the other was that I feared people's behavior. When a senior management initiative&#13;
 pilot is proposed like that, it creates a possibility that people join in on a pilot not because&#13;
 they really are convinced that that's what they want to do, but because they want to be&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                            March 11 and 12, 2004- Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                            27&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
noticed by senior management. Human beings--maybe half of the human beings--have&#13;
that kind of inclination maybe, and I didn't want that to happen. I wanted genuine&#13;
commitment to the change process for the South Asia Region because it was bad&#13;
behavior, not about how we think about development, as opposed to what we do in&#13;
development, and the attitude of looking for changes as opposed to looking for projects.&#13;
Those are tough things to change. I wanted people in South Asia to become natural in&#13;
doing these things almost instinctively and spending a lot of time with staff helping them&#13;
to do that, and I didn't want to take any risk of a facade, of pretending to come in just&#13;
because it's a good thing for career promotion, to be noticed. So that's why I said no. I&#13;
feared the impact of that pilot on the region at that time.&#13;
&#13;
Instead, I said that if you want to think of the whole region as a pilot, go right ahead.&#13;
We've been doing this anyway. It gives us additional impetus. So Jim started to call us,&#13;
"South Asia mutation," which is cute, as opposed to pilots. So we were the mutation. So&#13;
it's one of the many things that I said no to, but it's for a good reason, and he understood.&#13;
Does that answer your question?&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: Yes. In your opinion, what has been the major constraint to poverty alleviation&#13;
in South Asia?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: Politics and bad governance. In the end, if you want me to go to the very&#13;
source, it's that. It's the politics and bad governance--bad politics, bad governance--&#13;
because from that a huge amount of resources or countries' own resources go into&#13;
admitting somebody, not supporting poverty and reducing development work, and it's not&#13;
any small amount of money. The Bank has studied the magnitude of corruption. South&#13;
Asia studied corruption financially in different countries. It's a huge amount of money for&#13;
any country. So, had South Asian countries, those who have bad governance, had honest&#13;
politicians who had vision and cared about the welfare of the people in the right way and&#13;
stayed in office for sufficient periods of time for stability, etcetera, poverty would have&#13;
been drastically reduced today in South Asia instead of the way things currently are, my&#13;
economist instinct and "back of the envelope," as it were, tell me.&#13;
&#13;
But, much more importantly, when people, especially poor people, and so many poor&#13;
people who have been poor for generations live in a place where they can't trust the&#13;
politicians that they elect, they get harassed almost daily by corrupt bureaucrats who are&#13;
not elected but have job security, from getting a driver's license to getting a little&#13;
community water project going, to you name it, to your village school not having&#13;
teachers because teachers are on a payroll and are pocketing the payroll, they are&#13;
politically appointed, but they are not there to teach. When you live in that kind of&#13;
environment, and you know it's nearly impossible to escape it, and especially if younger&#13;
people get frustrated and have some ways of coalescing to release that frustration and&#13;
anger, that's when something bad happens. That's when revolution, political instability,&#13;
that's when you invite religious extremism. I've seen so much of that on the ground. So,&#13;
much more important, is the reason why I say clearly politics and bad governance,&#13;
because South Asia and other regions have been in this state. So many people have been&#13;
in the state of poverty and desperation for so long that it's more than just a seed for&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                          March 11 and 12, 2004- Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                          28&#13;
&#13;
political instability. It has immediate links to peace and security. So that's why I focus on&#13;
bad politics and bad governance. And there are so many ways through development&#13;
work, not acting in politics in the country because we're not allowed to, but through&#13;
legitimate development work, working with change agents in the country, you can make&#13;
a large impact on the state of governance if you keep at it over time.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: Following up on this, how effective were the CDF principles in this context?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: Mind you, I'm not saying that in South Asia every aspect ofCDF&#13;
worked. I think it's a never-ending process, a learning process. But when you engage&#13;
with courageous leaders of vision, whether at the grassroots levels with NGO leaders or&#13;
at the top of the country or what have you, everywhere in between--the change leaders--&#13;
and work with them, magic happens.&#13;
&#13;
Look, 10 years is nothing in our business. Just think of an example. Ten years ago, as I&#13;
was saying earlier, Pakistan's banking system was riddled with corruption. I'll tell you I&#13;
never thought that Pakistan could get itself out of that. But there were change leaders who&#13;
just kept at it, with us as protection, and they now have a thriving, healthy banking&#13;
system that is adding value to the economy. It's something that I, frankly, didn't think&#13;
could happen in terms of a likelihood, but because through the technical reform efforts of&#13;
the banking system, people who mattered in a country focused on corruption issues. And&#13;
as good things started to happen, it affected others positively. It gave courage to others to&#13;
do similar things in other sectors, not just in banking.&#13;
&#13;
And so, one has to believe in some politicians, however corruptible the powers might be,&#13;
some politicians, realizing that good governance is actually very good politics, because if&#13;
you deliver good governance to people, the next time you get more voters, period. And, if&#13;
you really focus on the majority in the country, the poor, the silent people, and deliver&#13;
good governance to them, which doesn't cost very much, then they'll turn around and&#13;
vote for you the next time. And you have to find ways through development work to get&#13;
that political economy to grow in a democracy and so to facilitate developing countries--&#13;
or any country--to learn good governance through good development work.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: In view of this, how do you see the post-9/11 emphasis on the relationship&#13;
between poverty and peace?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: As I said, I have talked about delinquency and poverty and peace. I did&#13;
exactly what I felt the moment 9/11 happened, I said, "About time." It's a horrible thing&#13;
to say, but I've been making some speeches as Vice President everywhere, and one of the&#13;
themes that I was driving, especially when I had political leaders in the audience, as part&#13;
of the audience, in trying to get them to own up to the fact that addressing policy isn't a&#13;
welfare issue for their country but really about the national security of their country&#13;
whether their country will continue to exist or not. And I've been finding it very difficult&#13;
to get those leaders to see that link. Why? Because they haven't spent enough time at the&#13;
grassroots level; they don't understand poverty themselves.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                          March 11 and 12, 2004- Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                            29&#13;
&#13;
But the link being made now between the security of a nation and development work and&#13;
reducing poverty, nothing else, was part of not just my but the whole Asia Region's&#13;
thought process. And you see it reflected already in Country Assistance Strategies, for&#13;
example, of South Asia as far back as January '98. It was our submission to the Strategic&#13;
Forum, the first Strategic Forum in the Bank, was presented on this. But the message has&#13;
always hit some wall. After September 11th, it became much easier. People understood.&#13;
And so the attitude of our counterparts in the countries working on Poverty Reduction&#13;
Strategies overnight became most serious. They were already serious people, but they&#13;
became most serious.&#13;
&#13;
As unfortunate as that event is, with so many lives lost and all of our lives being affected&#13;
one way or another, it generated a sense of crisis in South Asia proactively--they didn't&#13;
want something like that to happen--that I hope it will pay back positively.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: In the context of poverty alleviation, how important is it to maintain ODA&#13;
[official development assistance] levels in light of current aid fatigue--seeing that Japan is&#13;
a leader in providing ODA?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: With official aid or multilateral aid like ours, it's not about how much at&#13;
all. It's about how every dollar provided leverages the leaders in the country to want to&#13;
do the right thing and do it right and cause reform. What that means is that, whether it's&#13;
the World Bank or ADB [Asian Development Bank] or Japan or U.K. or USAID [U.S.&#13;
Agency for International Development], if we take our eyes off our leverage to help&#13;
cause an internal good policy revolution, then we might as well stop aid because what aid&#13;
does without that is reduce the pain, prolong bad governance, and in the end, end up&#13;
causing all sorts of problems for the country. And who suffers most? It is the poor people.&#13;
&#13;
The World Bank is fortunate because our Articles are terrific, and we have a lot to thank&#13;
our Founding Fathers, including John Maynard Keynes, in protecting our business from&#13;
political interventions because it's up to us to use it. But it really protects us enormously&#13;
to do the right thing.&#13;
&#13;
Multilateral development banks don't have as strong a Constitution as we do on that, so&#13;
they have a higher risk of being politicized. When it comes to official or bilateral aid, it is&#13;
driven obviously by the political aim of a given country which is not always conducive to&#13;
thinking about what's good for the receiving country.&#13;
&#13;
And speaking as a Japanese citizen, there is a lot of Japanese ODA that I feel very&#13;
ashamed of because, in the end, they are harming and not helping the people. I've said&#13;
this publicly in Japan. Those are the instances where the Japanese taxpayers' money is&#13;
essentially wasted in the long term. People in the receiving country, the population, the&#13;
sovereign people, are not necessarily benefiting; it's a lose-lose game. In such situations,&#13;
it's better for Japan to stop ODA to any given country if they can't use it to help affect&#13;
the voice of the invisible people.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                          March 11 and 12, 2004- Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                            30&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
So I have a lot of questions on the efficacy of aid. It's not about the effectiveness of aid.&#13;
Effectiveness of aid is not the issue necessarily of aid agencies. It's really about the&#13;
governance and the quality of the leadership of the country, and how well the agencies&#13;
can align to those people. But efficacy of aid is something else. Efficacy of aid is a&#13;
fundamental question of whether a developing country would be better off without aid or&#13;
not. One needs to be always asking that question as a discipline because it's not charity.&#13;
And I am afraid aid agencies, including the World Bank, don't ask that question often&#13;
enough.&#13;
&#13;
One of my former staff will tell you that I have many broken records, but one of it was&#13;
that I always said to staff, "Say, 'No, I can't lend to you.' Remember how much more&#13;
powerful leverage that is than agreeing to lend." And behaving that way is what I&#13;
support, and the staff understood that, at least, and thank God that they believed me. But&#13;
it's not easy to change to that culture. Even though the World Bank, who I think has gone&#13;
the farthest in the change, thanks to Jim, still has miles to go.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: In your opinion, how well is the Bank addressing the Millennium Development&#13;
Goals ofhalving poverty by 2015 in its sector, country and global programs?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: As well as can be expected under the circumstances, I think. It was&#13;
something that we had to react to. That's how I see it; the principle of ownership is seen&#13;
everywhere. If there isn't ownership in institutions, and institution means people, staff--&#13;
the most important people are staff-it takes time to do a good job, as opposed to making&#13;
it work. I'm afraid there is lots of "making it work" at present in the Bank when it comes&#13;
to the Millennium Development Goals-linked activities. So it takes time.&#13;
&#13;
But what gives me hope is that a number of countries, and certainly all of the South Asian&#13;
countries, took it very seriously. South Asia has always had, in its modem history, a&#13;
system of economic planning, 5-year, 10-year planning. In some countries, it started as&#13;
sort of a socialist plan--India, for example-but over time those countries changed the&#13;
nature of these plans to be much more of a strategic plan; policy plans which are then, in&#13;
tum, linked to how the budgets are made. It frames, at least analytically, annual budgets,&#13;
fiscal budgets, and so it's a powerful instrument. They all have that, and they are much&#13;
better at strategic planning than the World Bank is. And every single one of the South&#13;
Asian countries had this tradition, other than Afghanistan. So, by the time the Poverty&#13;
Reduction Strategy Paper (PRSP) came about as a suggested idea, it was sort of, "before&#13;
breakfast" as we say in South Asia; it had a plan as part of an institutional plan. In South&#13;
Asia, 5-year plans in those countries are done in a more participatory way, with a much&#13;
better articulated vision--it's driven by vision--and certainly aligned to poverty, and since&#13;
September 11th, poverty and security, and every one of them is going through projecting&#13;
themselves on the Millennium Development Goals. Some countries, like Bangladesh, are&#13;
very proud that they are quite likely to achieve some of them, which is giving energy to&#13;
their policy changes.&#13;
&#13;
So, as I see it, there's no way that all of the South Asian countries are going to achieve it,&#13;
but what gets measured, gets managed.' And the people who matter in the country are&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                          March 11 and 12, 2004- Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                             31&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
using it to take their development work forward as a learning process. So achieving the&#13;
Millennium Goals in South Asia has already made a big impact on how governments&#13;
behave, and it will end up impacting on the governance record of the countries simply&#13;
because there is strong ownership and, fortunately, a tradition of planning strategically.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: You've touched on part of the next question about dealing with Country&#13;
Assistance Strategies (CASs), and Poverty Reduction Strategy Papers (PRSPs). How well&#13;
developed are those Bank instruments (CASs, PRSPs, including the HIPC [highly&#13;
indebted poor countries] debt initiative) in improving client engagement and sharpening&#13;
strategic focus, and how effective are they in South Asia; what do results show on the&#13;
ground?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: It's not about the question of instruments, but it's about how, first of all,&#13;
countries and leaders in the countries use those instruments for their objectives, and how&#13;
World Bank staff help that process. The CASs, PRSPs, and the HIPC instruments are&#13;
well-defined on paper. When you read all of the relevant Board papers, people's reaction&#13;
would be that it is a "Christmas tree," and it's actually not very easy to get the sense of&#13;
the coherent instrumentation by any of those. But no matter, what's important is how&#13;
those so-called instruments give rise to opportunities to leaders who want to change&#13;
policies and practices in the country. So that's one way that I see it.&#13;
&#13;
But I can't comment on HIPC because, fortunately, in South Asia, we don't have any&#13;
HIPC cases. South Asian leaders actually reacted very negatively to the HIPC idea&#13;
because, if you look at the finance records, repayment records are impeccable in South&#13;
Asia. It's on time every time, which is very unusual in other regions. This shows a certain&#13;
philosophy of the South Asian culture. You pay back what you borrow. And to ask to be&#13;
forgiven of your debt, because you didn't use it well, is a national shame. And that's&#13;
something that, quoting the former Finance Minister of Bangladesh, when he heard of the&#13;
making of HIPC, he said, "That's what beggars would do. And Bangladesh is poor,&#13;
poorer than some of the HIPC countries, but you will never see us begging." And that&#13;
reflects--it's not just Bangladesh--it sort of reflects a cultural attitude which is very&#13;
strong.&#13;
&#13;
So, on CASs and PRSPs, I think we should do a better job of defining them as critical&#13;
instruments that help staff think strategically. There's too much in there that enables lazy&#13;
results in a sort of series of cut-and-paste things to do as opposed to really thinking hard&#13;
about the vision that the country has and whether we buy into it and the country's own&#13;
strategy to get to that vision and thinking about our own role in buying into that strategy.&#13;
And we don't do that hard enough. I've always said to staff that when I read CASs I read&#13;
them with my military mind on because that's a way in which I can think about strategy&#13;
and tactics of war; objective to win that war, strategy, which means you need to count the&#13;
armies and arms and so forth, and then contemplate the moves to make. So we need to be&#13;
much sharper.&#13;
&#13;
Now, in South Asia, how effectively are they being used? Some of South Asia's past&#13;
CASs have been Christmas trees, too. But I think they've gotten better over time. The one&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                         March 11 and 12, 2004 Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                         32&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
thing that you see in South Asia's CASs and PRSPs is that all ofthem by now drive&#13;
everything by the governance strategy. No matter what sector, for example, or what&#13;
policy that the countries are pursuing or describing in the PRSP or the Bank is describing&#13;
in CASs, it's driven by what we need to do concretely to bring back or create good&#13;
governance for poverty reduction and national security. So, over the years, I've seen&#13;
counterparts in countries use those instruments very well because they're now driving&#13;
everything by governance, and the staff themselves also have gotten better.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: What do implementation results show on the ground?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: South Asia is the fastest growing region in all and has been for a few&#13;
years. And the cause of this growth in each country links back to structural reforms that&#13;
every country in a different way has been implementing. And the driver behind that, the&#13;
motivation behind that of leaders is their conviction by now of good governance being&#13;
good politics. So, it would take too long for me to explain how it happened in each&#13;
country; one measures development by many things. But if economic growth is one&#13;
indicator, and I'm not sure it is, then the results are already showing of the country's&#13;
effort. And the World Bank, with other donors, had a little bit to do ·with it, I think.&#13;
&#13;
So at the aggregate level it's that, and certainly when you see the catalogue of policy&#13;
initiatives and reforms the South Asian countries have implemented over the last five, six&#13;
years, you'll be amazed. It's just incredible. When it accumulates and it hits you, you're&#13;
already where you thought you'd never see the countries to be. So, that doesn't mean that&#13;
the work is finished. There's more to know. But I'm very, very proud of what the South&#13;
Asian countries have done; be it leaders in civil society or in government it doesn't&#13;
matter, they've done a lot.&#13;
&#13;
So at the micro level, you also see--those are sort of community levels--that the growth&#13;
rate, a faster growth has to be reflected in the better standard of living at the village or&#13;
slum level; otherwise rapid growth isn't good for development. This only divides the rich&#13;
and the poor. I think in--not all yet, but in many countries, India, Pakistan, Bangladesh&#13;
certainly, Maldives, Bhutan certainly, question mark in Afghanistan as it is a special case;&#13;
Sri Lanka because o'fthe conflict, question mark; Nepal because of the conflict, question&#13;
mark--but the others, and even within the short period of time I've been visiting these&#13;
countries, I've seen so many villages go from destitution to thriving economies. Some of&#13;
them our financing went in and some of them it didn't. But, what's common amongst all&#13;
of them is empowerment of communities and empowerment of women. In Bangladesh,&#13;
for example, one village in three, four years doubled average household income. You do&#13;
not recognize the place when you go back, and women who, when I first met them hid&#13;
their face (they were ashamed because they are not used to talking to outsiders, even to&#13;
me, a woman), three years after, I went to visit, they were elected local representatives in&#13;
a local assembly and bossing men around. So that's the real magic that can happen.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: Shall we break now and continue tomorrow?&#13;
&#13;
[End of Session 1]&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                         March 11 and 12, 2004- Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                        33&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                      Session 2&#13;
                                    March 12, 2004&#13;
                                   Washington, D.C.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: Good morning. Today is March 12,2004. I'm Marie Zenni, back again at&#13;
World Bank headquarters to resume my interview with Ms. Nishimizu for the Bank's&#13;
Oral History Program. Welcome again, Ms. Nishimizu.                       ·&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: We will begin today's session with the NGOs. The burgeoning number of&#13;
NGOs and their engagement in the development process has resulted today in over one-&#13;
half of Bank projects involving NGOs. How welcome are NGOs in borrowing countries,&#13;
in your opinion?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: Governments welcome them and governments hate them, and here I'm&#13;
talking about bureaucracies as opposed to politicians. Let me put it this way:&#13;
bureaucracies that are not functioning well, including corruption, the worst they are, the&#13;
more they hate NGOs. They compete. And the reason is obvious. NGOs in the&#13;
development business deliver what they promised to the people. And most--I'd say in&#13;
South Asia most of the NGOs actually are doing the work that the government should&#13;
have been able to do, unfortunately, which means that because of the bad governance and&#13;
associated lack of credibility with the people in the government (and here I include both&#13;
civil service and politicians) the NGOs come in to fill the vacuum. And, obviously, they&#13;
compete and take away the opportunity of making money from the bureaucracy and also&#13;
from political leaders. And so in such situations, the governments do not like NGOs.&#13;
&#13;
Having said that, even in countries in South Asia, whose governance is not something to&#13;
be proud of, there are politicians and civil servants who seek to work with NGOs because&#13;
their objectives are different from making money through their job in the wrong way. So&#13;
it's a mixed picture.&#13;
&#13;
And if I may add, it's important for donor agencies to work with NGOs; good ones, that&#13;
is. We have to be very careful about those associations creating a situation where NGOs&#13;
become the government and sustains itself, and bad governance continues on a parallel&#13;
track.&#13;
&#13;
Even before NGO became a household word in the World Bank, the South Asia region&#13;
had, I think, a long history of working with NGOs. And when I became Country Director&#13;
and then Vice President, the only way that I was willing to do that was if we at the same&#13;
time addressed a couple of systemic issues, which is to avoid the risks that I just&#13;
talked about. One was to focus strategically on everything we do in helping the South&#13;
Asian countries tum their governance situation around strategically. And the other is, to&#13;
the extent that NGOs would continue to exist, they need to be correctly protected legally.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                         March 11 and 12, 2004- Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                           34&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
And when I came to the region, most of the countries didn't have any good legal&#13;
framework for NGOs to function and so we helped. I think most, if not all, of South&#13;
Asian countries now do.&#13;
&#13;
The proof of what I said earlier about the inverse correlation between the hospitality of&#13;
NGOs and the government situation in South Asia is they took countries that had&#13;
probably the best governance of any developing countries throughout the world and it&#13;
shows in the IDA ranking. The number one IDA ranking of all the countries is Bhutan,&#13;
which is in South Asia. Number two is Maldives. And those two small countries, when&#13;
you go and see what the governments do at the grass roots level, you see what in other&#13;
countries NGOs do. And so in those two countries there are very few NGOs, if any,&#13;
international or domestic. And the governments are very careful in that they welcome&#13;
NGOs, but they are very careful in making sure that NGOs' mandate are complementary&#13;
to what they do as opposed to competing with what they do. And so it's an interesting&#13;
situation. It's a Catch-22.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: Yes. So, would you say on the whole, based on your experience in South Asia,&#13;
that an alliance between the Bank and NGOs is effective/beneficial?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: If our strategy, operational strategy, includes focusing on the overall&#13;
governance problems, which, I think, is perpetual--it's not something that you can target&#13;
ending in several years; it's a perpetual effort, even in developed countries--and address&#13;
the issue of the right legal framework for development ofNGOs' function, because they&#13;
can't really function very well under corporate laws. In many countries, they still&#13;
function under corporate law.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: How truly representative of the poor and disadvantaged are NGOs?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: It depends. There are NGOs that are not obviously engaged in&#13;
development work. They're more a political animal, advocacy groups, and there's&#13;
nothing wrong with that. The suffrage movement in every country, for example, for&#13;
women was essentially in the end won by NGOs. OfNGOs that do development work at&#13;
the grass roots levels, there are good ones and bad ones. And it depends on, in the end, I&#13;
think, on the quality of the founder-leader and their motivation. Some of them, even&#13;
though they do deliver goods to the people and seem to be doing development work,&#13;
when you look into their motivation, usually there are political motivations behind it.&#13;
&#13;
So, one has to be really careful who one strikes partnerships with. And quite often it's&#13;
nearly impossible to make those judgments as foreigners. It's another reason why&#13;
decentralizing truly the operational work at the core face, employing people of the&#13;
country is really, really important.&#13;
&#13;
A lot of problems that the Bank has experienced in cases that come to the Inspection&#13;
Panel, for example, have some of their roots in our inability to make those judgments,&#13;
whether in the process of project preparation and implementation or in the process of&#13;
dealing with complaints. And, things get very tricky when the situation gets so bad that&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                         March 11 and 12,2004 Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                           35&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
an Inspection Panel case is taken up. By then, usually some Northern NGO, very often&#13;
with some political objectives, usually environmental issues, take up alliance with the&#13;
NGOs in the countries who brought about the inspection case. And the Northern NGOs&#13;
have very, very little capacity in making those judgments, too, because they are not&#13;
decentralized. It's not a pretty scene. It's sad to see good young people, very capable,&#13;
passionate for a right cause being very much misled. So, one does have to be very&#13;
careful.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: Now turning to IDA, South Asia is the largest regional recipient of&#13;
concessionallending from the International Development Association (IDA), following&#13;
Sub-Saharan Africa. In your opinion, are concessional aid flows of both IDA and IBRD&#13;
sufficiently concentrated on the poorest and unquestionably deserving countries?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: South Asia has both IDA and IBRD--IBRD countries being India and&#13;
Pakistan. For IBRD, the judgment on how much to lend per year depends on a country's&#13;
performance, meaning the country's creditworthiness. And this is part of the work I used&#13;
to do in FIS, that you make judgments on how good the credit sovereign risk is, say India.&#13;
And you need to look forward in 20, 30 years and see whether the country's ability to&#13;
service IBRD is deteriorating and make judgments on just how much you want to lend.&#13;
And that's part of the stuff of Country Assistance Strategy. CASs are important&#13;
instruments for risk management for IBRD, meaning how much risk do you want to book&#13;
on the balance sheet, because if you make a bad judgment and lend too much too soon to&#13;
a country that is likely to deteriorate, then when those countries do go kaput and stop&#13;
payments to IBRD, we're in trouble. So it's very much a banking decision, and in my&#13;
experience, I have never had any political experience or political intervention by any&#13;
members of the Board, other than in an extreme situation, and I'll give you a concrete&#13;
example.&#13;
&#13;
When India and Pakistan in sequence tested nuclear bombs ,which happened about a year&#13;
after I took over the RVP job, you might remember that G-7 countries put on an&#13;
international sanction on both countries. And then they turned to IBRD, and IDA,&#13;
actually, because both countries are a blend. They get both. So they turned to the Bank,&#13;
i.e., they turned to me and suggested that we do the same, that we stop lending to those&#13;
two countries, sanction, at least stop making new commitments to them. The World Bank&#13;
Articles that govern both IDA and IBRD are very clear in situations like this. It clarifies&#13;
the role of the Executive Directors in ways that, according to Mr. [Ibrahim F.I.] Shihata,&#13;
no smart lawyer can ever interpret in any other way than how it's written, and that it says&#13;
the role ofEDs is for development purpose only. Ifthey wish to bring the political&#13;
considerations of the constituency they represent, as long as those political considerations&#13;
have economic implications, development implications, they may do so. But ifthat&#13;
means purely political motivation, it cannot convey that to the Bank management; it is&#13;
not part of their job.&#13;
&#13;
Now, I consulted Mr. Shihata before I met with the entire Board over lunch, and Mr.&#13;
Shihata said, "Don't worry, I'll back you up, and tell them they'll get fired if they bring in&#13;
purely political motivation." And, in fact, to help me, he wrote a one-page opinion which&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                          March 11 and 12,2004- Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                               36&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
said that if the Directors can demonstrate the link between their concern on nuclear&#13;
testing and the development of these countries quantitatively, then the management will&#13;
certainly consider it.&#13;
&#13;
And that's what I conveyed to the whole Board over lunch, and I said, "You know, you&#13;
must realize I know what I'm talking about. Quantitatively demonstrate means&#13;
econometrically, and if any of you would like to ask what methodology to employ, please&#13;
don't hesitate to come and see me. As far as my judgment is, it is purely political&#13;
motivation that is beyond your terms of reference. And so what I suggest is that you, G-7,&#13;
sit down with India and Pakistan and deal at that level. Don't bring our work into it."&#13;
&#13;
For a number of years after that, the Board gave us a very hard time every time we took a&#13;
loan to the Board because I told the Board at that meeting that they had approved the&#13;
Country Assistance Strategy that is about poverty reduction, don't start ... that. But they&#13;
did make our life a little miserable, particularly because--this is before September 11th&#13;
and before Pakistan became a baby ofthe G-7--Pakistan's President [Pervez] Musharraf&#13;
had accelerated the structural reform effort enormously. And so as policy vision got&#13;
better quickly, we were supporting it with financial assistance, including sizable&#13;
adjustment loans, and they gave us not a lot but some trouble. But that's okay. They need&#13;
to express their political concerns at the Board. The important thing was that I was 100&#13;
percent protected from having to act political.&#13;
&#13;
So, the Articles that we have are very good, as it is extremely important to keep the&#13;
World Bank a strong financial institution, because political intervention by owners--&#13;
where owners actually include in our case borrowers too which is a no-no for most&#13;
banks--there has to be a very clear separation between the owners and the management.&#13;
And so, I take my hat offto the founding fathers who wrote the Articles. So that's on&#13;
IBRD.&#13;
&#13;
On IDA, once again, on what project to lend, how much to lend beyond this particular&#13;
incident of nuclear tests, I never experienced political intervention at all. In fact, in my&#13;
entire life at the Bank, including as an RVP, the political nature ofiDA comes in when&#13;
IDA replenishment--the pot of money--gets diwied up in terms of allocation, the&#13;
maximum amount that's allocated to different countries. Now, that computation at a&#13;
certain level country by country is done by FRM on a technical basis, taking into&#13;
consideration country performance, population, et cetera. But the issue is to get to that&#13;
point.&#13;
&#13;
Roughly half of IDA has for a number of years been protected for Africa through a quota&#13;
for Africa. That's a political decision ofiDA donors; they're the donors, so they're free&#13;
to bring in their respective political concerns. But the issue of that quota for Africa has&#13;
always troubled me, not because of its implication on South Asia--South Asia gets a huge&#13;
amount less per capita compared to Africa. That fact never troubled me because South&#13;
Asian economies are much bigger and much healthier than African countries. But the&#13;
very fact that when situations arise in South Asia where for a few years additional use of&#13;
allocation of IDA can be useful, we never had that flexibility.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                          March 11 and 12, 2004- Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                           37&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
But as a member of the Bank management thinking about the institution's future and&#13;
thinking about Africa, too, I never thought it was a good thing, simply because if it's a&#13;
little too much money for Africa--and I don't know whether it is or not, okay? But if it is,&#13;
my principle is too much money is never good. In fact, for development purposes, when&#13;
you're working on the program and strategy with change agents in a country to do major&#13;
things that change the course of nation building, you want harsher constraints; those&#13;
people in the country do not want easy money to come in. It's very clear. And they only&#13;
want money to come in if they need it and when they need it politically in their work.&#13;
&#13;
And, I mean, that's the reason why I never complained about South Asia not getting&#13;
enough IDA. And I always said to myself, "It's a blessing in disguise, so don't&#13;
complain." So, Africa is significantly smaller, in terms of population, than South Asia.&#13;
So, if it is the case that they are getting, I mean, they are plenty with money with respect&#13;
to the Bank's operation, then I think there's a strategic issue. I don't think we ever&#13;
thought through this at the corporate level together. And I think one day we need to do&#13;
that. So there's the allocation issue, the big pie issue where political considerations do&#13;
come in. Fortunately, as I said, .South Asia never suffered from any of that.&#13;
&#13;
The other is that at every IDA replenishment donors get together and add a shopping list,&#13;
things they would like IDA to do such as emphasis on gender, emphasis on this, emphasis&#13;
on that, and it changes every three years. Now, on the one hand, you can look at it as&#13;
those donor countries representing their own population's concerns politically, because&#13;
after all it's taxpayers' money. And requiring IDA to do certain things, I think,&#13;
fortunately, the list of things that the donors would like us to focus on have always been&#13;
good things for the country. And if we're doing gender work already, it gives us an&#13;
impetus to do more. If we missed, it gives us a bit of a spank on the back and gets us&#13;
moving. So the sort ofthematic political issues that get into IDA replenishment I always&#13;
thought was a good thing. IDA's role really is to sort of intermediate those political&#13;
themes into development themes that the countries, borrowing countries, have been doing&#13;
in the interest of the people.&#13;
&#13;
But there is one problem, which is the sort of bureaucratic incentives of Bank staff and&#13;
management, lower management. When IDA replenishment results with great emphasis&#13;
on gender, the management, i.e., the Regional Vice Presidents, have to make sure as we&#13;
take on these mandates ofiDA that the entire management team of the region and the&#13;
staff are convinced that it's a good thing, that they understand what gender issues are,&#13;
that they're convinced it's good for development, and they think through how to mobilize&#13;
people in the countries so that the countries can gain ownership. They can't do that unless&#13;
we own it truly ourselves. When a political agenda comes out like that, it's perceived to&#13;
have money attached and the management's work to mobilize it through ownership ofthe&#13;
staffbecomes a little more challenging because of the behavior factor. For example, if I&#13;
put some here that is the rationale for my work, even though I don't understand it really&#13;
but I don't give a damn as it's the flavor of the month or flavor of the year, it stands out&#13;
and I get my project through easy. There's always such behavior that the management&#13;
needs to be aware of and use those behaviors in good ways as opposed to simply doing&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                          March 11 and 12,2004 Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                            38&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
sort of superficial stuff. And it takes time. It takes time for a Vice President to really&#13;
mobilize the entire management team and staff to understand substantively, to think&#13;
carefully about gender and to really in head and heart become convinced. It takes a lot of&#13;
time, and I don't think there is sufficient understanding in the World Bank of how&#13;
difficult that is.&#13;
&#13;
Mr. Wolfensohn understood it. At one point I did share with him what happened on the&#13;
disability issue which was one of the strategic things he introduced into the evaluation.&#13;
&#13;
Whenever a new strategic agenda comes up, what I always did was to sit, spend time with&#13;
my management teams or Country and Sector Directors and really substantively go&#13;
through it: What does this mean? And what does it mean for the countries? And we spent&#13;
a whole day, the whole management team, talking about disability. And it was probably&#13;
one of the most moving meetings I had with my team, to the extent that there were tears a&#13;
couple oftimes during the day. I cry easily and that's well known, but a number of my&#13;
male colleagues were in tears. And we went through capturing disability issues in terms&#13;
of concrete numbers and analytical framework as part of the poverty agenda for South&#13;
Asia, and then went through some of the bottlenecks that people with different disabilities&#13;
have to go through. And what happened was that a couple of managers in my team&#13;
happened to have children with disabilities, and in the morning we sort of analyzed the&#13;
head staff. To convince people, you first have to understand it analytically, and at least&#13;
the head has to be there. So by the time lunchtime came, I think we all saw how precisely&#13;
it fits analytically in our countries' policy strategy and how important it is empirically.&#13;
There were a number of people trapped in poverty because of disabilities. It's huge. Then&#13;
in the afternoon we started unconsciously the process of connecting head to heart because&#13;
until then the conviction hadn't really become natural behavior of your everyday life.&#13;
And unless I do that with every single one on my management team, I can't count on&#13;
them to inspire and mobilize the staff. I can't do it by myself. And that's when the&#13;
managers with kids who have disabilities opened up and talked about their personal&#13;
experience, and that's when there were tears. And so it was a really moving experience.&#13;
&#13;
You do need to go through from time to time something important strategically that will&#13;
change the nature of your business. You have to get the people to buy into it. And if they&#13;
can't buy into it, and assuming that they are the people that you chose and are proud of,&#13;
then it should make you take another look. So that's a really time-consuming process.&#13;
And then also when a good strategic issue is suggested by top management, and if you&#13;
don't go through that process, then there is a risk of the staff and the client country seeing&#13;
the Bank doing something because the boss said so, as opposed to because it's important&#13;
for development. And the moment that question mark arises in the mind of staff and the&#13;
client countries, you lose your credibility. So because it's time-consuming, when IDA&#13;
imposes through replenishment new themes, the regions have to be very careful how to&#13;
go&#13;
about translating that into the real work in a credible way, in a way that counterparts can&#13;
really see and feel that we mean what we say because we believe in it. And that's a big&#13;
risk.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                          March 11 and 12, 2004- Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                              39&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
And so IDA, however good the intention of those things are, the management practice&#13;
has to be good enough to trust that to what was intended for the benefit of the people in&#13;
developing countries. And I think the institution needs to appreciate much more how hard&#13;
that work is. And that's the crux of the credibility issue.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: In terms ofthe of IDA replenishments process, in your opinion, are there&#13;
adequate criteria guiding the decision-making process and shielding the allocation from&#13;
undue political pressure? As we have seen, IDA replenishments are constantly delayed&#13;
and fraught with political pressure.&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: It's a hard negotiation process. And sure, you know, some countries do&#13;
play ball, hardball. But that's the political nature, political reality of any such negotiation.&#13;
That's a question that I can't answer. What I can answer through experience is, when all&#13;
that negotiation is done it is the nature of how do politics affect operational decisions in&#13;
the region. But it's a question that you need to ask FRM. They're the people who are&#13;
responsible.&#13;
&#13;
When I was in Finance with Johannes Linn, the sister Department was FRM. And if I&#13;
recall correctly, one of the things that Johannes and Paula Donovan, who was a director&#13;
of FRM, worked very hard to make the decision process in replenishment negotiations as&#13;
transparent as they can be. So, you know, that's replenishment. Beyond the Africa quota&#13;
in the replenishment process, there is no intervention into how much each country should&#13;
get. There was always an issue of how much should India get because it's big. China was&#13;
also an issue. But that's natural in a big country. Outrageously big countries like India&#13;
and China should get explicit single-country attention just as IBRD does. IBRD financial&#13;
rules set a limit, a maximum limit on the share of one country in our total portfolio. So&#13;
India does face that limit, as China did.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: Moving on to grants. Not so long ago, the Bank agreed to provide up to 22&#13;
percent of IDA money in grants. How does this translate for the South Asia Region? And&#13;
what, in your opinion, might be the ramification of the higher grant percentage for the&#13;
Bank in terms of IDA reflows?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: Yeah, I think sometime yesterday I mentioned South Asia's attitude, the&#13;
South Asia Region's country attitude, meaning the Finance Ministers and cabinet and top&#13;
leadership. They're very careful about grants. And just because things come as grants,&#13;
South Asia Region's leaders don't jump on it; they are very careful. They understand the&#13;
finances very well, and so they understand the sizable grant component of IDA credit&#13;
already. And they also understand the subsidy involved in IBRD, and that having a good&#13;
payment record and sustaining it for a long time is in the country's own interest because&#13;
eventually they want to graduate from the World Bank. So there is no sort of bandwagon,&#13;
thank heavens, but it did open up some good opportunities, like passing through grants to&#13;
some very good NGOs doing work on communicable diseases and things like that. So I&#13;
was happy in the way that every country in South Asia approached this.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                          March 11 and 12, 2004- Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                             40&#13;
&#13;
And one thing that I made sure that staff understand from the very beginning when I&#13;
became VP is that we are not just a development agency, we're also a financial&#13;
institution. And as a banker for development, we do not tell governments which financial&#13;
instruments to use. It has to be the country's choice, and our responsibility is to explain&#13;
what the alternative financial instruments available are, whether it's a grant or IDA credit&#13;
or a different type of IBRD financial instrument. Because, I used to say to staff, if you are&#13;
borrowing money, a mortgage from your bank, you expect your banker to assess your&#13;
creditworthiness. And you expect your banker to receive a report on the structural&#13;
soundness of the house you're buying. But you don't expect your banker to come into&#13;
your house and tell you how to decorate your house. And, if there are choices in the&#13;
instruments, e.g., mortgages (flexible or fixed rates), different maturity, you don't expect&#13;
your banker to tell you which one to use. You expect your banker to explain the&#13;
differences and implications and make sure that you have full information to make the&#13;
choice that suits you. It is the same with our clients. So we should never go beyond&#13;
making sure that the financial alternatives are fully understood by the government. And&#13;
once we make that choice for the government and tell them, "For this HIV/AIDS project&#13;
use this," then you can be sued, just as we can sue a banker if they tell us to choose an&#13;
instrument that may not be suitable to us. So I was very strict about that.&#13;
&#13;
Now in this and other things, too, really what moves the operational work in the Bank&#13;
with clients is the quality of policy dialogue and the quality of all dialogue that we hold&#13;
with different counterparts in the countries, and how much value-added in terms of&#13;
knowledge we can bring to key leaders in the country. That's what moves and opens&#13;
opportunities. And what that means is that essentially it's how good individual staff and&#13;
individual managers are who engage in those conversations with counterparts. It's their&#13;
excellence and their sensitivity and their listening ears and their courage and whatever.&#13;
That's what moves.&#13;
&#13;
Good work gets done in a country. I'm an idealist and theorist, but also I'm a practical&#13;
person. In the end, quality of assistance is driven by the quality of those individual&#13;
people, the people relationships, and the trust in those relationships. And so, as long as&#13;
that's going on in a dynamic way, a little change in financial instruments from time to&#13;
time or a little bit more of grant availability, really doesn't do much.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: What ramification does a higher grant percentage have for the Bank in terms of&#13;
the availability of IDA reflows?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: Yeah, that is a very important issue, and it's because of that, in addition&#13;
to the fact that in the context of South Asia I felt that it makes very little difference in the&#13;
way that the clients work with us, I did not welcome this grant business. I certainly didn't&#13;
welcome it. It slows the time; it pushes out the time when IDA itself as a revolving fund&#13;
becomes sustainable fmancially, self-sustaining.&#13;
&#13;
Reaching that point where IDA no longer needs replenishment from IDA donors remains&#13;
a financial objective ofiDA. And I think it's a very important objective. When Paula&#13;
Donovan and I were in Finance working closely together--because IBRD was then, and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                          March 11 and 12, 2004- Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                          41&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
still is, the largest donor every year to every replenishment to IDA, out ofiBRD's net&#13;
income--at that time we targeted 2004 (or something like that) when IDA could become&#13;
self-sustaining. So it was at that point in time that we were looking forward to a self-&#13;
sustaining IDA and, therefore, to make that happen as quickly as possible, and part of the&#13;
strategy that implements recommendation on net income allocation was to give as much&#13;
out of the residual net income, after you put aside reserves for IBRD. I always argued for&#13;
maximizing IDA contribution out of the residual income, because it's several hundred&#13;
million dollars every year. And a little bit more made a big difference in when it will&#13;
reach a self sustaining point. A lot of parameters changed since then. So I knew that that&#13;
target kept going further and further into the future, and this makes it now even further&#13;
away.&#13;
&#13;
So I think it's a shame. I think as long as that financial objective remains an important&#13;
one--which has to be the Board's and the IDA donors' judgment, I guess--as long as that's&#13;
the case, then we shouldn't be fooling ourselves. And it has an implication on the IBRD&#13;
as well. So I may be not as well informed as the senior management and the Board&#13;
because I wasn't directly involved in those negotiations and discussions. But based on the&#13;
basic numbers, I felt that what the countries are getting was so minuscule in terms of&#13;
grants compared to the potential negative implication on IDA. And so I did worry about&#13;
that.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: Okay. Now we'll tum to decentralizing in the Bank, and you've touched on this&#13;
yesterday. But I'll ask some specific questions. The Bank has decentralized greatly under&#13;
the Strategic Compact implemented in '97 with almost one-third of its total workforce in&#13;
field offices. In your opinion, how well has decentralization worked in bringing the Bank&#13;
closer to its clients, and in promoting greater policy dialogue?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: I think in South Asia it made a big difference. The counterparts in&#13;
countries tell me so, that they really saw a big shift in the way we work with them. So the&#13;
fact that they didn't kick us out, meaning the fact that they didn't ask us to close country&#13;
offices or ask us to kick out the Country Directors, is a good thing. And every time I've&#13;
seen top leadership in all the countries, I never popped the question; I never had to ask&#13;
the question, "How is it going?" They always said this is one of the best things that has&#13;
ever happened. So that's what I expected, and I'm glad it worked.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: Following through with this, please discuss your role in decentralizing the&#13;
South Asia Region, considered today the most decentralized within the Bank with some&#13;
66 percent of its staff located in field offices.&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: My role was that of instigator. In the first six months that I worked with&#13;
the staff to create a new region and begin the culture change process there were--I think it&#13;
was in the first meeting--a few things that I had to say about what they must be as a&#13;
leader, and if they don't agree with it, then I'll find them a different job elsewhere. One&#13;
was decentralization, in the way that I explained yesterday, not just any decentralization.&#13;
I was fortunate that that's how the staff had been thinking for a long time, many of the&#13;
staff. So I put forward, as any leader should if there is something that you're convinced&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                         March 11 and 12,2004- Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                            42&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
you want to do that has to be a parameter, a given, then you have to be explicit. So that&#13;
was one of the few things I was very explicit about and asked for their buy-in. So I was&#13;
an instigator.&#13;
&#13;
But it was also very clear that this would be a hard learning process. It's not something&#13;
that's going to get done in one day. And I made sure that the staff understood, to the best&#13;
of my ability, that they saw it as a process where I said, "You know, you have to expect&#13;
occasionally to make mistakes, but what we ,need to do together is to pick up these&#13;
mistakes and mcike them as part of our learning motivation. As long as we do that, then&#13;
we should be celebrating mistakes as well as successes." And we did make a number of&#13;
mistakes.&#13;
&#13;
I think yesterday I described the model that governed my decentralization idea which is&#13;
the blending of two types of knowledge: one that resides here and one that's in the&#13;
country office, and that then meant a certain HR strategy in country offices. So really the&#13;
share ofthe staff in Washington versus the field is an indication ofprogress in&#13;
decentralization, but one shouldn't just take that as the measure. One needs to really&#13;
understand what is the work done in the field and how the staff is exercising those&#13;
responsibilities and the strength of teamwork between the country office staff and those&#13;
working in Washington.&#13;
&#13;
I need to say that teamwork is really absolutely the critical ingredient for what we used to&#13;
call co-located decentralization, co-locate meaning several country office staff and&#13;
Washington. Each of it is a location, geographical location, with certain mandates&#13;
attached because of the location. And, because of location and recruitment practices, the&#13;
people in each location bring different knowledge. Strategically, what I wanted was really&#13;
good teamwork to happen. That's the only way to sort of weave and blend knowledge,&#13;
different knowledge to work together for the client. So team building was absolutely&#13;
essential, and it was a never-ending challenge for me.&#13;
&#13;
Now, my vision when I started was going as close to 100 percent as possible in terms of&#13;
head counts. When I put to the staff at the beginning that, you know, one parameter is&#13;
decentralization, I gave them some options to think about which included one limiting&#13;
case where there were no regional staff other than just a few core expertise and the sector&#13;
management. Everyone would be located, even in Washington, in network anchors, and&#13;
the operational transaction is to happen between anchor and the country office. So, what I&#13;
put to them as an issue to think about was: Is the staff in the region in Washington needed&#13;
or not? And it was a very interesting debate, and they convinced me--as initially I thought&#13;
that I should really go for 100 percent field--but they convinced me that there is value to&#13;
having a minimum number of expertise who are always working on a particular set of&#13;
countries because even for international staff, country context is important. And, you&#13;
know, looking back on my experience over the years·, they were right and I was wrong,&#13;
and I told them so. But I don't think whatever the percentage in the region now is ..&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: Sixty-six percent.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                         March II and I2, 2004- Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                              43&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: Yes. It is high enough. I think there should be more in the field.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: O.K. In your view, how well do Bank policies and procedures, including&#13;
Human Resources, support these efforts?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: Today it's pretty good. We came a long way, though, from when I first&#13;
started decentralization thinking and working, which was before I took on the RVP job,&#13;
the one year when I was already starting to decentralize the country department. Those&#13;
are things I didn't really know, shame on me.&#13;
&#13;
I only realized some of these constraints by listening to resident mission staff. I went&#13;
around to all ofthe countries to hear some of my staff in a listening session and learned a&#13;
whole bunch of things, like the issue of Bank ID. Today everyone has the same Bank ID,&#13;
no matter where you are located. And so, you know, staff working out of India, when&#13;
they come on mission to Washington, they use their ID in getting into the Bank building.&#13;
Back then that wasn't the case because those people didn't exist on the Bank's roster.&#13;
And so every time they came, they had to get those one-day passes. They said, "Mieko,&#13;
this makes us feel like we're not part of the Bank." Of course, they're part of the Bank. It&#13;
took me a year to fight the bureaucracy to get the staff out in the field this badge. One&#13;
year! Dorothy Berry helped me enormously, and she and I had to fight.&#13;
&#13;
The other was the telephone book. Today, we don't think twice about it--everybody who&#13;
works for the Bank is in that telephone book. It's a very valuable commodity now. Back&#13;
then, no. It had only headquarters staff.&#13;
&#13;
The other thing that I confronted almost immediately was how staff in the field offices&#13;
was classified. I think this must have been the same throughout all the regions. Certainly&#13;
in South Asia they were classified according to UN scale and professional categories. It&#13;
had nothing to do with the Bank. And so, if you're an economist, Bangladeshi economist&#13;
with an Oxford Ph.D. working out of the Dhaka office, I had no way of capturing that&#13;
information in the standardized professional classification that we had in Washington.&#13;
When I was professionally classifying country offices to make sure that they become&#13;
equal pa.r1Ders and expecting staff to work in teams, I couldn't have apples and oranges.&#13;
And so I asked HR--this was in '95/'96--to use South Asia as a pilot, to apply the same&#13;
classification to the field, professional classification and grade classification to field staff,&#13;
and re-grade and reclassify them. What did we call it? Globalizing the Classification;&#13;
there was a cute catch name to the project. Anyway, Dorothy Berry (HRVP) again was&#13;
very supportive and gave me HR's best experts on professional classification and&#13;
grading, and they went to all the resident missions and we put them through the system of&#13;
classification and grading. Global grading, I think it was called. And that pilot was&#13;
successful, and it's now a Bank-wide practice. But it's only a few years ago that it was&#13;
apples and oranges, and going through that process made a big difference on the morale&#13;
of staff out in the field and how staff in Washington perceived them.&#13;
&#13;
And we had some redeeming hiccups through the process. One was that there was a staff&#13;
in the Dakar office who the study recommended to be graded, back then number 24,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                    Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                           March 11 and 12, 2004 Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                           44&#13;
&#13;
senior something, a very good person. And that required clearance of the sector panel,&#13;
network panel, whatever it's called. And I don't name which network it was, but the&#13;
network panel told us that they outright rejected it; they won't even do it simply because&#13;
this is local staff. There must be something wrong with the classification. It took a bit of a&#13;
fight before they very reluctantly held the panel and, thank God, it was cleared. But it's&#13;
essentially quiet discrimination. You know the kind of discrimination ..&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: Subtle.&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: Yes, subtle. You and I know because we've all experienced it. But it was&#13;
horrifying to see that at play so blatantly. There are several other cases like that,&#13;
essentially an attitude that says, "How could the local staff from resident mission be as&#13;
good as me?" But some of the sector boards, when they realized how frustrated those&#13;
people are, then turned around and things are looking better now. But it took several&#13;
years for attitudes to change. There are some sector boards that haven't changed their&#13;
attitude still, and it very much depends on who's on the board and who heads of the&#13;
board. So, I think it's something that we need to continue to be aware of.&#13;
&#13;
Looking at the Bank staff back in the pre-decentralization days, I always felt that the&#13;
Washington staff or mission attitude was very colonial--I used to use that word--using&#13;
their colleagues as servants, as it were. And it definitely had that air of not ever being&#13;
considerate about having to ask those people to stay late or spend weekends working and&#13;
expecting them to drop everything and serve you. Not everybody behaved that way, of&#13;
course, but that was a predominant mind-set, an implicit mind-set. And thank God that's&#13;
all gone, at least. So, cultural change can happen.&#13;
&#13;
Initially, at the beginning, the staff out there didn't exist, as far as the Bank was&#13;
concerned; they were on a different measurement yardstick. Their salaries were also tied&#13;
to UN scales. That's another thing I broke away from. For each country, nowadays a&#13;
competitive market benchmark, just as the Washington staff market is benchmarked. I&#13;
made sure that they became as quickly as possible equal in treatment to us. We won't pay&#13;
them a comparable salary because that would be unfair. Many of them have much better&#13;
living standards in the local currency than we have here. But other than that, I fought&#13;
probably together with my staff every single day, with the commitment of my&#13;
management team especially, and the enormous support of first, Dorothy Berry, and then&#13;
Richard Stern and Kathy Sierra. They've all been very, very supportive of what we&#13;
wanted to do. I wanted the region--because we were ahead of the game compared to other&#13;
regions--to just throw out those problems or policies and help the Bank change them for&#13;
others so as not to suffer. And I'm very grateful for the HR support.&#13;
&#13;
The other thing that we fought for was the benefits, including health insurance, and&#13;
pension reform. And that work now by and large is finished, so by the time I left last&#13;
year, I think, I delivered everything I wanted to deliver on that score. My promise to the&#13;
field staff that I will be the change agent here in the Bank to make sure that the HR policy&#13;
would treat them as equals with the Washington staff, other than the salary. The salary&#13;
cannot be equal in terms of dollars, meaning they can't get paid in dollars, the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                          March 11 and 12, 2004-FinalEdited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                           45&#13;
&#13;
Washington salary. Imagine, even before decentralization, some of the professional staff&#13;
in the field offices were coming to Washington on mission, not as frequently as they do&#13;
now but still they were, and were traveling without health insurance. It was just&#13;
incredible.&#13;
&#13;
And even two years ago, one of the staff made me realize that they were still taking a lot&#13;
of risk because they didn't have credit cards in their own countries and so they carried&#13;
cash. But obviously they can't carry enough cash to meet the emergency situation en&#13;
route that might call for hospitalization or something. I almost had a heart attack when I&#13;
realized the kind of risk that I was forcing, or the Bank was forcing, the staff to take. It&#13;
was a never-ending learning process for me.&#13;
&#13;
What else? I think that's probably about it.&#13;
&#13;
Oh, yeah, last thing, which took the longest time to fight, was membership to the credit&#13;
umon.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: It extended to that as well?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: Yeah, I mean, you would expect the credit union to be open to all staff,&#13;
regardless of location. The past Chairman or President, George West, I think, was&#13;
instrumental in helping us. But before then it was not easy, and all sorts of excuses which&#13;
I as a finance expert knew were just excuses such as, for instance, that the U.S.&#13;
regulations may not permit it. Baloney! Another bias at work! Before those bankers sit&#13;
down and think, okay, it may be a good idea, let's think about it as a banker. It's in the&#13;
interest ofthe association. It took a long time for them to get to that point. So staff was&#13;
coming here, and they didn't have any bank account, obviously. So lots of cash&#13;
transactions, carrying cash around. Another risk! So many things like that had to be&#13;
changed. It was fun.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: The last question on decentralization: How does the Bank ensure that its&#13;
resident staff, both national and intematiopal, is not unduly drawn into local self-interest&#13;
designs?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: I'm glad you asked that question for both national and international staff,&#13;
because risks are there in both ways. The way to do it is to make sure that the staff in the&#13;
organization knows what the vision and values are, and that you expect them to buy into&#13;
it, and those who don't are not welcome. That's another ofMieko's parameters. And I&#13;
think you've seen the stated vision and values of the South Asia Region. It's pretty basic&#13;
stuff. So you have to be pretty devilish to not like it, like honesty and integrity and&#13;
passion. But the key is that the vision and values have to be living in a way that you&#13;
manage your organization and in a way that the staff then conduct themselves. It has to&#13;
be reaL It can't just stay on the piece of paper or on the screen or on a poster as rhetoric.&#13;
&#13;
And that's the most challenging and hard part of being a leader in the region, how to&#13;
translate the vision and values into the very fabric of the everyday work of the staff. Once&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                          March 11 and 12,2004- Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                           46&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
you begin down that road, it's a hard and never-ending road with managers whom you&#13;
recruited based on your vision and values--and I have always recruited them--the final&#13;
decision always had to do with their values. So I had a management team that worked as&#13;
a team, practiced to work as a team, like a baseball team, and I knew that they carried&#13;
their values and vision with them. So I had tremendous allies.&#13;
&#13;
The other part of living operational vision and values is that you deal with it as situations&#13;
arise when the behaviors or conduct of anyone in the region go against the vision and&#13;
values. And there were several occasions like that that I had to sit with the person and&#13;
say, "I observed this; it is against the values." In mild cases, say two people are fighting&#13;
each other in a meeting as opposed to listening to and helping each other, or instances of&#13;
tough behavior, these were mild cases but serious for values, I would call them and say,&#13;
"Explain yourself, don't you think it's against values? If you do it again, you're out of&#13;
here." I mean, some of the managers also got that notice, but it's inhuman to demonstrate&#13;
those values all the time, including myself. We do make mistakes. But when it came to&#13;
all these situations that I observed directly, I made sure that the person knew&#13;
immediately.&#13;
&#13;
And I let go some people, some senior staff, based on their violence against those values.&#13;
And that the top leadership of the region acted that way, that sent a very important signal&#13;
that I don't mean rhetoric, that for me it's a very important part of the way we work. Of&#13;
course more serious cases, like harassment cases, then I deal with it professionally with&#13;
the corporate part that helps us out and makes decisions quickly, which I felt was always&#13;
an important part of it. So, I did the best that I could do, as a human being, to just keep&#13;
walking the talk because that's what matters. If you do that and crea~e an organization&#13;
where you know that everyone at least knows where I stand and then you very quickly&#13;
create a different environment, you raise the bar of behavior and conduct and you create a&#13;
fabric of integrity that the staff themselves value.&#13;
&#13;
So, in the end, you have to start from the basis of trusting your people. Even if you don't&#13;
know them from Adam, you hire them, you trust them. You make sure that they know&#13;
that you start from the trust, and do everything to keep it and build on that trust. If the&#13;
trust is broken, you deal with it then, clearly, and it's a continuous repetition of that. The&#13;
only thing is that there are no rules. I mean, the Bank is very settled in that it has very&#13;
good rules on ethics and codes of conduct, et cetera, one of the best structures in the&#13;
world, but that alone won't get you there, especially when you have an organization that&#13;
is globally located with hundreds of different nationalities working together, with more&#13;
than 100 cultures, probably, and you can't regulate people's behavior by what's on paper.&#13;
You've got to live it.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: ·Would you say this was more difficult to apply on resident staff or to keep&#13;
track of with resident staff or was it the same?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: The same. The same anywhere, in part because I made sure that I spent a&#13;
substantial chunk of a year out in the field because it was very important for me to be&#13;
with my staff everywhere. My husband didn't like it, so he's very happy that I retired, but&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                               , Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                          March 11 and 12, 2004 - Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                              47&#13;
&#13;
he was a very good sport, and he really supported me a great deal. It's difficult to get to&#13;
know another human being, whether it's your husband or your staff out in India or in&#13;
Washington, and you just have to make the effort.&#13;
&#13;
Information technology helps a lot. I think that's one of Jim's tremendous contributions&#13;
that gives enormous leverage to connect. And e-mail actually, for me, was a terrific tooL&#13;
It reduces that scare factor ofstafftalking to a manager, and so I created a separate&#13;
account where only I had access to, that the staff could write to if they had really serious&#13;
concerns. Things like that; ittakes all sorts of effort.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: Is there anything else you'd like to add on decentralization?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: Yes. I think the Bank as a whole--and I don't pretend to know the nature&#13;
of decentralization of other regions. I know what their strategies are because we, the&#13;
RPV s, got together and exchanged lessons and so forth. I think the strategy differs from&#13;
region to region. And so far, the agreement which I bought into has been that different&#13;
regions or geographical regions of the world, as we classify them, have a different need&#13;
in terms of business needs and implication for the way you decentralize.&#13;
&#13;
Looking back, I'm not so sure any more. I think there's room to think through more&#13;
carefully what do we really mean by decentralization. What is our model? What's our&#13;
business objective? What's the resulting HR strategy? I think the time has come to take&#13;
stock. I'm not saying we should straight-jacket different business models, but the staff,&#13;
either from the field office or from Washington or from the South Asia region who&#13;
moved to other regions--and they tend to be good staff who move--always told me of the&#13;
different sort of organizational cultures in other regions, especially when it comes to the&#13;
mind-set of headquarters staff on the country staff. And so, I think it's time to take stock&#13;
and see whether we're missing opportunities or not.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: One of the many issues you have championed, both inside and outside the&#13;
Bank, pertains to gender equity. Quoting from your visit to Japan back in '97, soon after&#13;
assuming your role as RVP for South Asia, you said, "If you educate a boy, you educate a&#13;
human being. If you educate a girl, you educate generations." In your opinion, how&#13;
effective are efforts of the international community in helping mainstream gender equity&#13;
issues in poverty reduction strategies?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: It differs from agency to agency, but overall I'm afraid it still remains&#13;
rhetoric, not because people don't mean it, but because not everybody really understands&#13;
it sufficiently. And that, in part, has to do with the fact that most of the decision-makers&#13;
and staffing of most agencies where the majority of them are usually men, and it takes a&#13;
very special man to try to see the world through a woman's point of view, just as it takes&#13;
a very special women to try to see the world through a man's point of view. So the&#13;
numbers do matter.&#13;
&#13;
And in situations, at least in South Asia--but I'm sure it applies to many other countries&#13;
outside South Asia--that when you go to the grassroots, unless you're a woman, you can't&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                          March 11 and 12, 2004- Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                          48&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
see women or it's more difficult to have interactions or quality interactions with women,&#13;
even if you can see them physically. Of course, in the Islamic countries that practice&#13;
Purdah or in the Islamic communities that practice Purdah, of course you have to be a&#13;
woman in order to sit down with the women, and that's still very much there as practiced&#13;
in South Asia. It's still predominantly in Pakistan and Bangladesh in rural areas, but also,&#13;
believe it or not, in parts of Sri Lanka. So you have to walk the talk by starting the change&#13;
in gender makeup of the organization at home. That's the reason why I was always active&#13;
in gender jnitiatives within the Bank because I felt strategically this is going to make or&#13;
break our organization's contribution to wake up male leaders in developing countries to&#13;
focus on women's issues.&#13;
&#13;
In my own experience, in the international fora, countries that have female leaders--I'm&#13;
talking about donor countries--women ministers, for example, women development&#13;
ministers, and at one point there were several very active, wonderful ones in Europe, they&#13;
were real when they talked about gender. And people from those agencies understood&#13;
what they were talking about and, therefore, were very convincing in international&#13;
meetings, reflecting the quality of their work at the grassroots. So it matters a lot.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: What, in your view, has proved most effective in helping give women a voice&#13;
in a society and in empowering their role in the development process?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: Leadership, not just the leadership in the country understanding and&#13;
valuing women's issues, but also leadership at the local level, especially women leaders,&#13;
leadership and not necessarily political leadership but leadership in community&#13;
movements, and an environment that somehow facilitates those leaders to be able to&#13;
function, and put their money where their mouth is, i.e., micro finance. In fact, micro&#13;
finance has done well in mobilizing women and helping them find strength in unity and&#13;
giving them leadership training which is what that is. It raises very quickly their social&#13;
status and has really changed overnight the situation which I've seen so many times. But&#13;
that can only happen when there are women leaders within the community, women with&#13;
leadership potential, go-getters, people with a little bit more courage, that they get&#13;
encouraged, that they get basic skills, public speaking skills. The stuff that we put our&#13;
own staff through and we call it leadership training, that's what's given through good&#13;
micro-credit work. So, in every community there are women who rise to that challenge&#13;
and start taking leadership. And because they've been repressed for so long, there's so&#13;
much anger inside that those things turn the anger into positive energy and do wonderful&#13;
things.&#13;
&#13;
At the beginning there are some external forces for change--good, trusted, and neutral&#13;
external forces for change. Ideally, it should be the government. In South Asia, in most of&#13;
the cases, they are NGOs. It's the same logic as the World Bank being a trusted, neutral,&#13;
external agent to encourage the change process in a country. The NGOs do the same&#13;
thing at the community level, good NGOs. When those things are combined with the top&#13;
national leadership commitment, head-and-a-half commitment on gender ssues, then&#13;
things move much faster. I'm afraid there were a few--South Asia had female leaders,&#13;
and none of them really connected with the plight of women in their own country. The&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                          March 11 and 12, 2004 - Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                           49&#13;
&#13;
only exception might be the current Prime Minister of Bangladesh. But I was pleasantly&#13;
surprised of a sufficient number of men leaders at the national level that really cared, and&#13;
it took very little time for me to get them to be like-minded, and that's because they've&#13;
got daughters and granddaughters. It's only human.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: To follow up, please discuss your own contribution to women's issues in&#13;
general, including your extended efforts inside the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: Really, not much, other than, essentially, my job was to take up the slack,&#13;
and the rest of the good work was done by everybody else.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: Well, there have been some laudatory remarks about your efforts, especially&#13;
within the Bank, on behalf of women's issues.&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: No, no. I mean, I'm not the only one. There are many. I'm the late-comer.&#13;
There were many trailblazers before me and so forth. And really my job when I was at&#13;
the Staff Association, as the head of the Women's Working Group, what I did was to give&#13;
our work there credibility because back then when people heard women's issues, it was a&#13;
soft, mumbo-jumbo. And so it was Nancy Birdsall and I who put our best hard economist&#13;
hat on, together with management-we invited management to join and analyze the&#13;
econometric model of race discrimination of the Bank over a number of years. And those&#13;
are hard, quantifiable things that you just can't take your eyes off, added to them your&#13;
own story and your fellow women's story of suffering and discrimination which gain&#13;
credibility.&#13;
&#13;
For example, I know now, and I knew then, that I came into the Bank one grade below&#13;
everybody else or one grade below my male equivalent. I knew that because the&#13;
personnel officer who negotiated the salary with me, when I kept insisting that I wanted&#13;
something above what I was making at Princeton--reasonable demand, right?--he, in&#13;
desperation, over the phone said, "Why do you care so much about money? Doesn't your&#13;
husband work?" That was--I mean, many of us still have those unpleasant experiences.&#13;
But I, I alone couldn't prove that I came into the Bank one grade below. Fortunately, my&#13;
manager immediately recognized it and gave me confirmation and promotion at the same&#13;
time, but not everybody is as lucky. And so, we did that work, and we actually asked&#13;
credible and very well-known academics outside the Bank to do the work. We gave them&#13;
the data which gave additional credibility to the stories of discrimination. It's essentially&#13;
those things that I focused on, but my life is much, much easier than everybody else&#13;
before me.&#13;
&#13;
The other thing that I did in South Asia was to increase the number of women, but I said&#13;
to my managers that it is not just because they're women. And I asked them to adopt a&#13;
rule, without which I will not do anything; that the most important part was that they go&#13;
out looking for women candidates when there is an opening. But, one of the few&#13;
instructions that I issued, was that they are welcome to spend as much time and money as&#13;
they need to unearth women candidates for a vacancy, from inside and outside the Bank.&#13;
I said don't just sit back and wait for them to apply because they are few in number. But&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                          March 11 and 12,2004- Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                           50&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
once the application is closed, the selection process must be gender blind, completely&#13;
gender blind, to the extent possible, and we always should take the best, regardless of&#13;
gender. And the other requirement was that the interview panel, the process would&#13;
always have to have a review panel including staff or managers, the gender makeup of&#13;
that panel should be balanced.&#13;
&#13;
And initially, when I told the managers to do that, they said, "Oh, then we'll never get&#13;
women to increase."&#13;
&#13;
I said, "You just wait and see."&#13;
&#13;
And I think it was in the country office in Pakistan where we were doing a complete&#13;
makeover of staffing, the Country Director, Sadek Ahmed, was very cooperative. He saw&#13;
immediately, I think, at that point that all or most ofthe high-level staff in the country&#13;
office were men, and in Pakistan, in this context, that meant we were missing half the&#13;
population in our work at the grassroots. So they had a series of vacancies coming up, six&#13;
or seven, and he and his colleagues applied that rule. I still remember Sadek saying, "You&#13;
were absolutely right. We trusted you. We were not sure whether we believed you were&#13;
right, but you were right," because five out of six were women, the top selection.&#13;
&#13;
The reason is obvious. We don't want to shoot ourselves in the foot. And it's really only&#13;
capable people who can bring a change in culture for women and men. So it's those little&#13;
details that I locked in. I mean, when I became active, I didn't have to fight the basics&#13;
like the right to vote for women. I mean, it's already done.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: Okay. Now, moving on, HIV/AIDS is rapidly reversing the hard-won&#13;
development achievements of the past 50 years, threatening economic, social and as well&#13;
as undermining political stability in some nations. In light of the high prevalence of AIDS&#13;
in the world's most populace nation, such as India, for example, please discuss endeavors&#13;
ofthe South Asia Region, as well as adequacy of the Bank's role in response to the AIDS&#13;
CflSlS.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: The effort in the South Asia Region on HIVI AIDS actually predates me.&#13;
In the South Asia region, I think India was the first country that requested World Bank&#13;
IDA financingfor a project focused on fighting AIDS. And it is one of those bits of&#13;
history that one tends to forget nowadays. It goes back I think roughly 10 years or more; I&#13;
remember it. Let's see, it was a 10-year project, and the second prong started a couple of&#13;
years ago, so it was late '80s, early '90s, I think. Those were the days where AIDS was&#13;
still in U.S. and in Bank corridors. AIDS was associated with homosexuality, and people&#13;
didn't talk about it explicitly, and nobody in the Bank thought of it as a development&#13;
issue, but people in South Asia did. And I don't remember where I was. I certainly was&#13;
not in the region when India's AIDS project was approved by the Board. I remember&#13;
people talking about it and saying, "What does that have to do with development?"&#13;
&#13;
So it's way back, and India has a long way to go, but it fought the counterfactual. Had&#13;
India not done that work, financed by the World Bank and others, to set up a National&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                         March 11 and 12, 2004- Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                             51&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
AIDS Prevention Network, amongst other things, India today would have been in a&#13;
situation similar to parts of Africa. Tliat would have been a time bomb. And my hat is off&#13;
to some people in the Health Ministry in India, and a couple of people in the Bank who&#13;
recognized it as a development issue, as an issue of the national security and&#13;
development, and got the Bank to create a political space, and that's what I was talking&#13;
about yesterday. And the project document and its completion reports are very interesting&#13;
to read because you can really get the feel of what could have happened to India and to&#13;
the world had India not started this so long ago.&#13;
&#13;
That doesn't mean that the work is over. It has to really continue. But that was a legacy of&#13;
my predecessors. In the period that I was there, strategically, it was correct to focus on&#13;
India. That was a fortress that we needed to make sure stayed because of the porosity of&#13;
the borders. If India, with its size, gets to the epidemic stage, then you might as well write&#13;
off all of the region and all of the other countries. As I was engaging in the dialogue in&#13;
the first years, I was investing in helping top leaders to feel comfortable in talking about&#13;
AIDS because that was the value that I could bring to my staffs work. So I was going&#13;
around talking to Prime Ministers, etcetera, about AIDS. And then, gradually, I think we&#13;
now have from every country a request for financing ongoing projects on AIDS. All of&#13;
the countries that share a border with India continue to tell us, in addition to their own&#13;
work, "Please don't give up on India because it's a threat." So it has a long way to go.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: Now, turning to the World Development Report, the WDR as it's called, the&#13;
Bank's think piece for setting the agenda for broad international policy dialogue on&#13;
current critical development issues, first published in 1978. In your opinion, how much&#13;
does the WDR ultimately reflects: a) the participatory process of those affected by the&#13;
development process, e.g., indigenous people, civil society, etcetera; b) input from&#13;
outside parties such as NGOs, development agencies, the private sector, etcetera; and, c)&#13;
the systematic learning of lessons based on distillation ofhands-on experiences in the&#13;
field?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: Since I've never been directly involved in the WDR--it's one of my&#13;
regrets--I don't have a good feel for "a" or "b," other than what I observed with my staff&#13;
from the regional perspective. I think every WDR team puts enormous effort, and it's a&#13;
tough thing to do.&#13;
&#13;
In the South Asia context, they tend to get captured by NGOs that make it a business of&#13;
being somewhat invisible on the WDR stuff. So they're not, by definition, they're not as&#13;
good as regional staff in understanding the political context of how to do good&#13;
participatory stuff in different countries. And, it takes a lot of resources for the regions to&#13;
help them out. It's usually, "We're going there in the next month. Can you help? 11 kind of&#13;
thing. So I'm sure that my staff didn't, and couldn't, do as well as they could otherwise.&#13;
But I don't have a direct experience myself, and I don't like to speak from hearsay.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: Generally, how well does the Bank listen to the people it is trying to help, even&#13;
when challenged by views that are not exactly aligned with its own institutional&#13;
objective?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                          March 11 and 12, 2004- Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                              52&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: I don't think we do as well as we should. I think we've come a long way&#13;
in the past 10 years, but I don't think we do as well as we should.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: As the world's premier development institution, in your opinion how&#13;
committed is the Bank's leadership in seeking out, encouraging and supporting&#13;
champions of change, be it within the institution itself, in client countries, outside parties,&#13;
bilateral and multilateral agencies, etcetera?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: Mr. Wolfensohn does this consciously. He's one of the few managers&#13;
I've seen who really has the knack for it, and it's marvelous to see him do it at the&#13;
grassroots, which has been a tremendous boost for the Bank as an institution. The rest of&#13;
the Bank, with staff and managers, it's still not a conscious effort to do so. It's not an&#13;
explicit effort to do so. Some people, correctly or incorrectly, criticized my line on that&#13;
because I was always explicit. I think some people, well, quite a few people in the Bank,&#13;
felt that I am playing the game of politics in the country as opposed to development&#13;
work. The minute you start to do this, it's a fme line that you have to tread very carefully,&#13;
and it takes skill, art and experience, and I don't claim to have always succeeded. But,&#13;
what's important, I think, is working with champions of change for it to become an&#13;
institutionally accepted wisdom that everybody does explicitly, that they'll be training&#13;
about it. Just as we're going through the transformation of not being able to talk about&#13;
corruption that we and every project staff is fighting, to the days of being able to talk&#13;
about it and making an operational strategy out of it. We do need to make that transition,&#13;
and it will come.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: As key broker in a increasingly interrelated and interconnected world, what is&#13;
your assessment of the Bank as purveyor of global public goods (e.g. GEF [Global&#13;
Environment Fund], the CGIAR, CGAP [Consultative Group to Assist the Poor]) with its&#13;
comparative advantage to "scan globally~~ in identifying good practices, thereby&#13;
facilitating learning between successful and unsuccessful countries engaged in the&#13;
development process?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: Conceptually, it makes sense. That's a corporate strategy that we put&#13;
forward at one of the strategy forums a few years back-we, meaning the senior&#13;
management team. But it's at risk for a number of reasons. I haven't thought about it very&#13;
carefully, but increasingly I noticed, in this Information Age, that our counterparts do&#13;
have much better access to the body of international knowledge that they need directly,&#13;
either through Internet or through their connections.&#13;
&#13;
So, what is our role? It's not just the issue ofthe Development Gateway; it's a much&#13;
more fundamental issue. I don't think we are always careful; I don't think we behave in&#13;
the way Jim wants us to behave all of the time. There are other agencies who have&#13;
comparative advantages or an absolute advantage over us in doing precisely that in&#13;
certain areas, like the WHO [World Health Organization], for example. We don't invest&#13;
enough in striking strategic partnership. It's left a little bit too much to individual efforts,&#13;
efforts by different parts of the Bank, and things like that.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                    Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                           March 11 and 12, 2004- Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                             53&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
So, I believe that the Bank must always be a knowledge Bank and institution and, with&#13;
regards to our financial business, how well we do that knowledge Bank work&#13;
operationally determines the quality and volume of financial business. It's not the other&#13;
way around. To cover more concretely, what should the new World Bank look like, in&#13;
view of all of the new technology, and much easier people-to-people contact of leaders&#13;
across many nations. It's something that we need to think through.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: Based on your experience in South Asia, how well-defined is the Bank's role&#13;
on the issue of governance, and what impact has this had on eradicating corruption and&#13;
encouraging paradigm shifts within country reform strategies, despite political&#13;
complexities?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: The role of the Bank on governance throughout the regions has been that&#13;
of an honest broker: analyzing, wherever there are opportunities, analyzing concrete&#13;
governance issues, including corruption studies, but not just stopping there. Writing a&#13;
report is one thing. But whom are we doing it for? We're doing it for the people of the&#13;
country. And to make sure to disseminate the results in the country, and that means&#13;
working with good journalists on disseminating good stories. So in that sense, the role of&#13;
honest broker, and for the people to understand what the facts are.&#13;
&#13;
I think we did the first corruption report in the Bank on Bangladesh, and this was back in&#13;
'96, when I was Director, and that study is still being used by the country. There's one&#13;
part that talked about estimating the amount of resources lost in corruption every year,&#13;
and the way that it explained it to the people was that if corruption stopped magically in&#13;
Bangladesh, Bangladesh can build one new Jamuna bridge every year. The Jamuna&#13;
Bridge is a huge bridge that spans the Jamuna River that divides the country in two. It&#13;
was the people's dream to build it. And finally with a special Jamuna bridge tax and&#13;
World Bank, ADB, and Japan financing, it was close to a billion dollar project; it was&#13;
built on time and under budget. And when the bridge opened, the Bangladeshi people&#13;
came and kissed the bridge. It was the people's dream. So it has a very important&#13;
message. Everyone in Bangladesh knew the Jamuna bridge, wanted it and knew it was&#13;
very expensive. And you can build a new Jamuna bridge every year. That was a big&#13;
message.&#13;
&#13;
Things like that, bringing the information to people of the facts, that it's not just the daily&#13;
life that they suffer of being harassed by policemen and tax collectors, there are much&#13;
bigger implications that affect their children. And so, in every country we invest a lot of&#13;
time and effort in doing good ESWs [economic and social work], good dissemination&#13;
work, and honest, straight dialogue at all levels. And so, in South Asia, I believe that the&#13;
people of the countries knew where we stood.&#13;
&#13;
Once I went to a poor village about a half-a-day journey north of Dhaka in Bangladesh&#13;
and met with a women's group doing micro credit. And when I was leaving, one of the&#13;
older ladies came up to me and said something which then was translated to me as she&#13;
said, "Thank you for teaching us about governance. Thank you, the World Bank, I think,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                          March 11 and 12,2004- Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                               54&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
for teaching us." So, I mean, on radio, television, newspaper, whatever the mode of&#13;
communication, the knowledge is out there that we stand firm, and that brings us&#13;
credibility as well as like-minded people to want to work with us. And we've never been&#13;
criticized by political parties for doing that. Some of us have had our lives threatened&#13;
because the mafia is involved, but security precautions are there. So that's one important&#13;
thing that we've done and continue to do, and out of that, different kinds of operational&#13;
investment projects or adjustment loans came about.&#13;
&#13;
So that's our role as honest broker with its importance and impact. It hasn't eradicated&#13;
corruption, and it takes a long time. It seems, however, that the Transparency&#13;
International (TI) corruption index in South Asian countries are starting to move upward&#13;
a little bit every time, and the reason behind that are reforms that are going on in the&#13;
country. Paradigm shifts in reform strategies are there in every South Asian country; that&#13;
much the countries have achieved with our meage~ development assistance. But that can&#13;
be broken any time by some awful political leaders winning an election. So it's a&#13;
continuous effort. We have to be always vigilant.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: Moving to talking specifically about leadership, and you've talked about it at&#13;
various levels yesterday and today, but still, in your view, how effectively engaged is the&#13;
Bank in emphasizing and stressing the importance of transforming/results-based&#13;
leadership, both within its business operations, and in its efforts to build client capacity?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: We're starting, but we have a long way to go, I think. This is my view.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: I would like to follow that up with a question on how to best exercise the role&#13;
of leadership and effect paradigm shifts, based on your own experience.&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: Leadership is critical, because without a leader who can inspire people in&#13;
a country, in organizations, you can't change anything. So that's why I emphasize&#13;
operations and always work with champions of change. In my experience, the good&#13;
leaders have certain qualities that are common: a certain passion for their cause and a&#13;
very good mind-set. Some of the qualities are--and those are the hard things to come by--&#13;
humility, that you might be a leader but you're just a human being and at fault like&#13;
anybody else. That basic humility, when a leader has it, everybody notices it. And that&#13;
humility alone then becomes a source of inspiration. It's very rare to see such leaders&#13;
with humility, and I see it as a source of inspiration when you see such leaders.&#13;
&#13;
The other is, I guess, sort of similar to that, and it is tolerance: the ability to tolerate&#13;
different views, to open up, and even invite and exchange different views, and really&#13;
listen to what others have to say, especially those who tell you no, tell you different&#13;
things that are against your beliefs. Tolerance is so important in the credibility of&#13;
leadership, and it's nearly inhuman to have in the kind of people who reach leadership&#13;
positions, either in a village or in the country as a whole or in a corporation where they&#13;
have spent some time going through the power game. And power corrupts, not&#13;
necessarily in the money sense but in the sense of one's natural inclination to be a good&#13;
citizen.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                          March 11 and 12,2004- Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                          55&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
So it's rare to see leaders who have these qualities, but there are. I mean, in South Asia,&#13;
there are quite a few that I have had the privilege of working with. And when there are&#13;
leaders with those qualities, the following sort of becomes almost religious and lots of&#13;
good things can happen. But then the danger is how such leaders find ways to sustain the&#13;
things that they started beyond their own life, professionally or otherwise. And there's a&#13;
trapping of power that makes people just want to keep on going. And so, one of the&#13;
things with leaders who have those qualities that I have gotten to know over the years,&#13;
towards the end of my tenure at the Bank, one of the things I decided to talk to them a lot&#13;
about is my conviction that one of the most important things and probably the toughest&#13;
thing for a leader to do is to know when to leave and leave at the right time having made&#13;
sure, to the extent possible, that what you start to do keeps on growing. It's tough, but&#13;
leadership is critical. It can make a whole word of difference.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: Turning to the Bank's coordination efforts, what is your assessment of the&#13;
Bank's coordination efforts with other international organizations and multilateral and&#13;
bilateral aid agencies in light of increasing emphasis on harmonization of aid efforts&#13;
across international development organizations?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: Initially, that we started and it is long overdue and we need to continue.&#13;
I'm of the view that it will take a long time when it becomes the norm that agencies&#13;
cooperate. Why? Because, in the end, it's about culturally different organizations. So the&#13;
top leadership of all of the institutions involved needs to continue to walk the talk and&#13;
then, in tum, each organization needs to change its own culture. Bridging the different&#13;
institutions together is remarkably easy, in my opinion, when leaders of two institutions&#13;
commit to work together and pay attention to creating a team from both institutions and&#13;
tell them that they've got to work together.&#13;
&#13;
We were able to do that with the Fund, as I am told that it's now a well-known fact in the&#13;
Fund itself that good economists in the Fund like working with South Asia because they&#13;
can be part of the team. And the way we started it, when Pakistan was in a perpetual state&#13;
of financial crisis, was involving the Fund all the time. And I happen to know my&#13;
counterpart in the Fund well, so we sat, and I said, "Look, let's make a deaL We want our&#13;
people to work together on Pakistan. So let us make sure that our respective staff know&#13;
that they form a team, that it's one team." And the slogan was that we expect them to&#13;
work as if there is no 19th Street and that my staff reporting to him is the same thing as&#13;
his staff reporting to me.&#13;
&#13;
It was easy for us to walk the talk because he and I knew each other, we made that&#13;
commitment, and the staff liked working with each other. Good economists like working&#13;
with each other. And good IMF economists really like working with good educationists,&#13;
good health specialists, people who know the sectors. So once you get that chemistry&#13;
going, countries love it. And when countries love it and when it reflects in a cordial&#13;
program and when both the IMF and World Bank Boards start commenting on the good&#13;
relationship, then you have got it made. And I think that tradition will continue as long as&#13;
the commitment is there.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                         March 11 and 12,2004- Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                          56&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: How does that bode for the rest of the Bank and Fund, aside from specifically&#13;
the South Asia Region? Overall, how do you see Bank-Fund collaboration and&#13;
coordination efforts?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: Not good enough. We had our own hiccups in South Asia, too, in&#13;
addition to this commitment. So, if the principal people on both sides don't get along&#13;
with each other, they make trouble, and old habits die hard. So when such behavior&#13;
developed on my side, my counterpart felt free to raise it with me, and I will change the&#13;
staffing. And, ditto, when such behavior developed on their side--and we had some nasty&#13;
instances on the other side--then I was free to raise it. One time the person appointed as&#13;
mission leader at the Fund became a big deal, then this person was changed because of&#13;
that. So it's a continuous effort.&#13;
&#13;
I think that, at the beginning, when you're creating a different culture across not just one&#13;
but two institutions, then both sides, at least at the Vice President level, need to spend&#13;
time communicating to make sure the team understands what the expectations are. The&#13;
higher level management needs to focus even on the details of who's on the team. The&#13;
initial management focus is very important. So it takes time, and overall I don't think it's&#13;
going that well.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: How would you assess the Bank's coordination efforts with the UN as it works&#13;
much closer in its engagement, especially in post-conflict countries?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: There's a lot of competition and experience in Afghanistan and in Sri&#13;
Lanka, a lot of useless competition on both sides. My stance/philosophy has always been-&#13;
-and I was probably correctly criticized about it-"Look, if you're doing good work, then&#13;
the leaders of the countries will recognize it, and they will come to us. If they don't&#13;
recognize it it's because we're doing bad work, then we deserve to lose. If they don't&#13;
recognize it in spite of our good work, then maybe it's not that interesting working for&#13;
those people." So, aside from making sure that the relevant people understood what we&#13;
can and cannot do, I forbade my staff to compete and sell themselves. Either by luck or&#13;
whatever, we always were given the lead responsibility.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: Over the UN?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: Over the UN, yes, on development coordination. And I don't take it as a&#13;
mandate just because we're the World Bank. I believe that the quality of our staff's work&#13;
was recognized, period.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: What about the Bank's coordination efforts with other MDBs, in particular the&#13;
Asian Development Bank, which is a rather large force in South Asia?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: Yes. ADB, in terms of money, is more important to most of our countries&#13;
than the World Bank. The same goes as in the case of the Fund, that with management&#13;
attention magic can happen, and we have a few cases like that in South Asia too. I think a&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                          March 11 and 12, 2004- Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                          57&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
lot of our staff needs to understand what it's like for ADB colleagues to see us through&#13;
their eyes: big bulldozer. And so it takes a long time for us to collaborate in the way that&#13;
I like to see collaboration happen. It takes a special effort to work with ADB well,&#13;
because ADB is more politicized in its mandate than we are or, to put it differently, its&#13;
framework is not as strict as ours. So we need to take care in choosing what topics we&#13;
work with.&#13;
&#13;
One of the things that I started, although I couldn't keep it up as frequently as I wanted&#13;
to, was for the management team of South Asia to spend time with the management team&#13;
of ADB, at least once a year spend a good deal of time, quality time together, and we did&#13;
it twice or three times and with time things improved. People change, you know. I mean,&#13;
it's no problem when it's first-rate people from the World Bank who are working&#13;
together with first-rate people from ADB, then magic happens, but the trick is how to&#13;
create that as a norm, and that's a manager's work.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: How would you assess the Bank's various mechanisms, for example, the OED&#13;
[Operations Evaluation Department], Inspection Panel, QAG [Quality Assurance Group],&#13;
for evaluating and measuring the results of its work, in terms of contribution to quality&#13;
and effectiveness?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: The Inspection Panel, I think, is an unfortunate creature. It destroys the&#13;
governance or it hurts the good governance of the World Bank. Fortunately, I didn't have&#13;
to suffer it on projects that were initiated during the period that I was Vice President, but&#13;
I suffered it on a couple of major issues that came up for the portfolio that I inherited. It&#13;
was pretty nasty stuff. So I did not like it at all. It drives a wedge into what should be a&#13;
trusting relationship between the Board and me, with Mr. Wolfensohn as the Chairman of&#13;
the Board. It brings a wedge between what should be a trusting relationship between the&#13;
World Bank and citizens of the country, and it's almost too political.&#13;
&#13;
OED, I've always made sure that I read QED's work, and it's good to have that&#13;
discipline. OED, in recent years, Bob (Robert Picciotto] and his predecessor, have made&#13;
enormous effort in putting good people in OED. That's made a big difference. So it's&#13;
been very valuable. From time to time, QED's country assessment becomes out of&#13;
context, out of operational context, and they have to find ways to work a little more with&#13;
the regions and trusting us. I think they are justifiably afraid of being captivated by the&#13;
region in their objective OED work, but they need to find ways to do that, especially&#13;
when you have--I think every region has this attitude because we respect OED in that we&#13;
want OED to do good, tough reviews on us, because that's what we want to learn from.&#13;
In return, in South Asia my sector managers and senior staff always used to say that&#13;
we've got to be tougher than OED on our own work, and that was a very good challenge.&#13;
But, you know, I think it's a very important institution that we have.&#13;
&#13;
QAG also, the complementary role, is very important. Over the years, it has become a&#13;
little too costly in the regions, in terms of having to deal with QAG. So it has a resource&#13;
implication, I think. It takes a lot of time and a lot of the Region's own resources to get&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                         March 11 and 12, 2004- Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                          58&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
QAG's work done. We ask for it because results are useful, but we need to make sure that&#13;
it doesn't become too taxing. It's a cost-benefit, right?&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: OK. How well-organized, in your opinion, is the Bank in systemically learning&#13;
the lessons of experience?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: It came a long way, but the part that still has a long way to go is the role&#13;
of the networks. It's still more taxing than generating benefits, I think. It's not a comment&#13;
about all networks, but most networks. Networks are supposed to be for cross-cutting&#13;
lessons which are very important. So, if this doesn't go on working, in spite of all of the&#13;
effort that has been spent--this issue is known--then maybe there is something wrong&#13;
with the way that it is organized. But that's a sore spot: networking is much more taxing.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: Has anybody questioned the way it's organized?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: Oh, yes. It's a constant. There is always fine-tuning that's going on, as it&#13;
should be. We shouldn't let it go, as we notice problems we should change as a learning&#13;
process, and that's been going on with senior management's attention, but I don't like the&#13;
staff suffering in the process. It's a bit much.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: In your view, how should the Bank address the issue of selectivity in its&#13;
crowded agenda, in light of greater emphasis on partnerships with borrowers,&#13;
development actors, and other agencies and organizations?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: Not well at all. In fact, I will say still very badly, not selective enough.&#13;
It's tough to do. But the good news is that the corporate management group is aware of&#13;
this problem and has gone through several iterations of adding things and making sure to&#13;
delete things. But getting rid of things is tough organizationally because the minute you&#13;
create something, the staff working on this--sort of interest groups and managers, me&#13;
included--don't find it possible to fire people, so we have to find better ways of adding&#13;
things, so much so fast, and making sure that we always and consistently jettison stuff.&#13;
But the good news is that the top leadership group is aware of this.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: Now, turning to World Bank Presidents. You have so eloquently talked about&#13;
leadership throughout the interview. Perhaps you could tell us how you would assess the&#13;
various Presidents you served under.&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: On this one, I really don't know because the only President I know is&#13;
Wolfensohn. Look, even for a Country Director or for a deputy Director, and certainly a&#13;
Division Chief, Lead Economist, and staff, Presidents are far away. As I said, I don't like&#13;
to speak out of hearsay. It has to be direct experience. Even Mr. Preston, when I was a&#13;
Director, I mean, I had one meeting with him, in a business sense, and then once a year&#13;
during FRS time, one meeting a year which he chaired. That's it, other than in a Board&#13;
meeting when he is chairing. I never got to know him.&#13;
&#13;
And the ones before him, frankly, I'm not sure ifl can list all ofthe names.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                          March 11 and 12,2004- Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                            59&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: In your opinion, within the context of leadership, what should be the criteria&#13;
and attributes of a good World Bank President?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: In addition to attributes of good leaders that I mentioned already, the&#13;
person has to be a diplomat of substance for development, has to be personable as well as&#13;
possess other characteristics to use in external relations at the heads of state leveL It's&#13;
very important work. That's it.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: Any management skills, financial, development experience?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: When it comes to professional qualifications, you can continue listing,&#13;
and very quickly you make qualifications where there is no living human being that could&#13;
do the job. And so, I go back to my definition of a good leader, the leader who knows&#13;
how to listen with humility, the kind of people who know their own weaknesses, and so&#13;
they create a management team, a trusted management team, with skills that complement&#13;
the President's and really work as a team. So, my sort ofto the limit definition of what's&#13;
an ideal leader would be a good manager, and that goes without saying. So, if the&#13;
President is not a finance person, there are plenty of finance experts who can be the Vice&#13;
President of Treasury, etcetera.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: Turning to some personal reflections. How would you assess your&#13;
accomplishments in the South Asia Region, in terms of your initial objectives and overall&#13;
goals?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: Cultural change I think started and got to the point where I can leave, so I&#13;
should be satisfied with that. That's how I would summarize that.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: How has your experience in South Asia affected your thinking on&#13;
development?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: Beyond what I talked about already, one thing that South Asia taught me&#13;
is that hard policies of development in econol)lics, hard policies of managing economics&#13;
in the country and planning development strategy really need to go beyond tangible&#13;
objectives, like economic growth and the number of kids educated, to what development&#13;
ultimately is about, which is about the contentment and happiness of the people without&#13;
which no sovereign state can exist in the long term if people aren't happy. And the&#13;
importance of making that link, at first implicitly then explicitly, is something that I will&#13;
spend the rest of my life thinking about.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: Looking ahead at South Asia's strategic directions, how do you see that&#13;
region's long-term prospects, especially in light of the geopolitical shifts and the&#13;
emergence of India and China as major powers?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: Asia has always been in my mind, Japan, China, Southeast Asia and&#13;
South Asia, and then you go across the equator at about Maldives, go down, and include&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                          March 11 and 12,2004- Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                            60&#13;
&#13;
Australia and New Zealand, that's my Asia. It has always been that. I've always seen the&#13;
future of the world, the center of the world, in economic and other activities, to be there&#13;
in that sort of cut of the Northern and Southern Hemispheres. It certainly excludes the&#13;
U.S. and Europe. I mean, these are century terms in the future. They will be in decline as&#13;
economies and as cultures. U.S. is still a question mark, Russia a question mark, but the&#13;
future energy will be in that segment of the globe. So I think that rational democracy has&#13;
a big chance in this segment. I think social capital is strong enough in those countries, in&#13;
that segment of the globe, to kick out any crazy religious extremism, I think. Good&#13;
policies are here to stay; at least, efforts to improve policies are here to stay.&#13;
&#13;
The only political risk, of which there are several, is sustainability of the Chinese&#13;
Communist power and how that transits into more democratic political systems, is one&#13;
big risk. If that fails, then China will break up into different countries. So how China&#13;
makes that transition I see as one very important long-term risk.&#13;
&#13;
The other is India's relationship with its neighbors, including China, and there you see&#13;
some short-term thoughts, including the India-Pakistan relationship. The next several&#13;
years will show us whether there is this coalition of political opportunity and some&#13;
genuinely new desire of the majority of citizens which would actually translate into being&#13;
at peace in that region. Those two I see as the big risk.&#13;
&#13;
Beyond that, for all of those countries and the rest of the world, water is a risk. It's the&#13;
shortage of water that comes from wasting, and the management of water. That's a big&#13;
issue. And climate change: we can't escape that. So there will be a few countries and a&#13;
pretty good chunk of economic and other infrastructure in South Asia which might&#13;
actually go under the sea, and countries know that and they have plans, some better than&#13;
others, and that future is closer to us than we like to believe. And so it's a big question&#13;
mark. But other than those risks, I think this is where the future is at.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: What advice would you like to give your successor in South Asia?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: Wish him good luck. Yes, it's probably the best job in the Bank, as far as&#13;
the VPs are concerned. So I'm sure he will have a good time.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: Overall, how would you assess the Bank's efforts at affecting internal&#13;
behavioral change within its organizational culture?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: I don't think we systematically focus on it. Even for someone like Mr.&#13;
Wolfensohn it's been difficult. He's focused on it from day one, I think, so it's hard to&#13;
move a large organization like ours, and systematically we don't do a good job yet.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: How would you assess the Bank's ability in aligning staff skill mix with its&#13;
evolving strategies and priorities? And, in your opinion, is the Bank still able to retain its&#13;
competitive edge in attracting the right caliber staff?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                          March 11 and 12, 2004- Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                        61&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: Assuming that we have a sort of overall strategy, which is a question&#13;
mark, for any network or any particular country, I think I said yesterday we're not good&#13;
at, and we don't know how to spell "strategy," but assuming that, we do a pretty good job&#13;
of aligning the staff skill mix. I think the management of the Bank tend to underestimate&#13;
really the tremendous skill and versatility of Bank staff. Now, over the last 10 years,&#13;
though, I did notice, especially in Washington, within the international recruitment, that&#13;
we were finding it difficult to recruit and retain good people.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: And why is that?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: I think it's got composites of reasons, but the salary is one.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: These days, would you cite personal security as another?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: No, that is the same everywhere, I think. But really our salary, especially&#13;
for higher levels, we overpay at the lower grades, it's very well-known within the market&#13;
that we underpay at the higher levels. I mean, God, I know. There was a huge opportunity&#13;
for me, of course, to be staying at the Bank for a number of years, so I must have been&#13;
enjoying it. It's tough. The Bank used to have seasoned, thoughtful international experts&#13;
in various things that the world would look to for advice. In the Industrial Department, I&#13;
was working with those people, and it was an enormous privilege, and I was trained by a&#13;
number of them as mentors. Those days are gone, and I think it's very unfortunate. We&#13;
went wrong somewhere somehow; we got rid of that talent too quickly. We didn't look&#13;
after that talent. We didn't continue to regenerate those talents, and that's an Achilles&#13;
heel in terms of our human resources. I say that very clearly. We better watch out.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: How would you characterize the periodic organizational changes within the&#13;
Bank (e.g.,'87 and '97 reorganizations), in terms of improving the Bank's efficiency and&#13;
effectiveness, relations with major borrowers, and impact on staff morale?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: The ones that I experienced have been changes that focused on boxes and&#13;
reporting lines to be implemented one day and then it was done with it. That's not real.&#13;
However good those architectural things are, that's not what creates change in an&#13;
organization. It's the constant hard, nitty-gritty stuff of management leadership at every&#13;
level to change the way we work, to utilize the opportunities given by those box changes.&#13;
So I will give a very low grade to those reorganizations that certainly changed the Bank&#13;
but were a blow to staff morale.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: And what about our major borrowers?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: Relationship \\-i.th major borrowers, as long as, at times like this,&#13;
borrowers know that the people that they work with, the Task Managers, Directors or&#13;
whatever, people closest to their work that they enjoy and respect working with, as long&#13;
as those people are around, they won't worry much.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: But in terms of continuity, that at times has suffered.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                         March 11 and 12, 2004- Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                              62&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: Yes, then they worry. I think that needs to be a discipline. It's, in the end,&#13;
about people, good people. So from time to time, if there are crises, then the organization&#13;
needs a shock. But there's a conscious effort on the part of management, the staff, and the&#13;
Board that, in this day and age, change has to be daily, and continuous. The only&#13;
constancy in life is change, period (I'm quoting one of the leaders from South Asia). We&#13;
need to live it.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: What do you see as the next big idea in development thinking?&#13;
&#13;
NISIDMIZU: I don't have that kind of foresight, but I ..&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: What should it be, perhaps?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: What should it be, yes, is what I talked about earlier. I think it's about&#13;
time we take human happiness seriously. Every constitution of every sovereign country&#13;
that I know of, including my own, talks about happiness of the people as their national&#13;
objective. Then you come down to the actual policies that move economies and political&#13;
processes, do they strictly--at least explicitly--align themselves to happiness of their&#13;
citizens in their countries operationally? No. I think the world would be a very different&#13;
place if they did. And the economics need some rethinking.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: What has it meant to you personally serving a unique institution such as the&#13;
World Bank?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: It's been a growing experience, with opportunities that I never would&#13;
have had as an economist to at least want to influence the lives of so many people,&#13;
whatever the results, and the results will speak for themselves. But it's been a privilege.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: Just to conclude, is there anything else you wish to talk about that I might have&#13;
perhaps overlooked?&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: Certainly not. This has been a very comprehensive set of questions.&#13;
Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: Thank you very much for an invaluable contribution to the Bank's Oral History&#13;
Program.&#13;
&#13;
NISHIMIZU: You are welcome. Good luck.&#13;
&#13;
ZENNI: Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
[End of Session 2]&#13;
[End of interview I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   Mieko Nishimizu&#13;
                          March 11 and 12,2004- Final Edited&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="17973554">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2004/03/17973554/transcript-oral-history-interview-mieko-nishimizu-held-march-11-12-2004
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2004/03/17973554/transcript-oral-history-interview-mieko-nishimizu-held-march-11-12-2004</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2004/03/17973554/transcript-oral-history-interview-mieko-nishimizu-held-march-11-12-2004</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2012-08-23T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2012-08-23T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2013/07/08/000333037_20130708155955/Rendered/INDEX/790880TRN0Nish0ew0March011012002004.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2013/07/08/000333037_20130708155955/Rendered/PDF/790880TRN0Nish0ew0March011012002004.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2004-03-12T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2013-07-08T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Transcript of oral history interview with
            Mieko Nishimizu held on March 11 and 12, 2004
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            On March 11 and 12, 2004, Mieko
            Nishimizu was interviewed on behalf of the World Bank Group
            Archives oral history program by Marie T. Zenni. During her
            tenure at the Bank from 1980 to 2003, Mrs. Nishimizu worked
            in the following areas: as an economist in the development
            economics department, industry division (1980-1982) and the
            productivity division (1982-1983); in the industry
            department, strategy and policy division, as an industrial
            economist (1983-1986) and as a senior industrial economist
            (1986-1987); in the Europe, Middle East and North Africa
            (EMENA) region as lead economist of country department 1
            (1987-1988) and as division chief (1988-1991); in the risk
            management and financial policy department as director
            (1992-1995); and in the South Asia region as director
            (1995-1997) and as vice president (1997-2003). She traveled
            on mission to Egypt and Yugoslavia, observing delinquency,
            poverty, and peace. Her transcript concerns her views of the
            World Bank on honest governance by way of analyzing
            corruption studies, disseminating journalism, and investing
            in reporting economic and social work.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Transcript of oral history interview with
            Mieko Nishimizu held on March 11 and 12, 2004
        </docna>
        <display_title>Transcript of oral history
            interview with Mieko Nishimizu held on March 11 and 12, 2004</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/2004/03/17973554/transcript-oral-history-interview-mieko-nishimizu-held-march-11-12-2004</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Transcript</docty>
        <subtopic>Access to Finance,Public Sector Corruption &amp;
            Anticorruption Measures,Debt Markets,Sustainable Land and Crop Management,Banks &amp; Banking Reform</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Public Sector Development,Rural Development</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000333037_20130708155955</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>World Bank Group Archives oral history program</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Public Sector Development,Rural Development</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Board Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            accountant, accounting, ADB, balance sheet,
            Bank of Japan, Bank office, banking practices, banking
            reform, banking system, bond, bond markets, capital
            accounts, capital markets, capital markets development, CD,
            Central Bank, collapse, corrupt, corrupt people, corruption,
            credibility, currency, current accounts, debt, debt service,
            decentralization, democracy, developing countries,
            developing country, development assistance, Development
            Bank, economic development, economic growth, economic
            policies, economic policy, economic systems, educational
            background, employment, farmers, fictitious loans, finances,
            financial institution, financial policies, Financial Policy,
            financial risks, financial structure, gender, good
            governance, governance issues, Human Resources, husband,
            husbands, income tax, industrial enterprises, information
            technology, infrastructure development, initiative,
            instrument, integrity, interest rate, interest rate regimes,
            International Bank, International Development, International
            Finance, investing, job security, laws, leadership, loan,
            loans to countries, local market, mandates, Minister,
            Ministers, Monetary] Fund, Multilateral development banks,
            national security, non-performing loans, operational risks,
            political economy, political leader, political leaders,
            political risks, politicians, privatization, production
            capacity, productivity, reorganization, repayment, repayment
            records, reserves, return, returns, risk management,
            shareholders, sovereign risk, state enterprises, stock
            markets, structural adjustment, tax reform, tax system,
            transition countries, transition economies, transparency,
            Treasury, village, villages, woman
        </keywd>
        <owner>Knowledge &amp; Information Services (ITSKI)</owner>
        <repnb>79088</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Policy Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Policy Formulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Policy Implementation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Productivity-Led Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Structural Measures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Structural Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crops</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>HIPC</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deconcentration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delegation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Devolution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sub-National Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subnational Government and Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Employment Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Labor Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banking Institutional Set-up</ml:concept><ml:concept>Structural Policy and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fertilizers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Heavily Indebted Poor Countries (HIPC)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Administrative Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Labor and Employment Laws and Regulations</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>