<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>ï»¿                               79047&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
THE WORLD BANK/IFC ARCHIVES&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    ORAL HISTORY PROGRAM&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Transcript of interview with&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Oral History Research Office&#13;
&#13;
    Columbia University&#13;
&#13;
      August 12, 1961&#13;
      August 16, 1961&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                           Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Interview with Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
By Prof. Robert Oliver                                    August 12, 1961&#13;
&#13;
Interview # 1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   My name is W.A.B. Iliff.   I am now a Vice President of the Bank,&#13;
&#13;
and have been since 1960.   I joined the Bank as Loan director in&#13;
&#13;
February, 1948, in the very early days of its operations.     Before I&#13;
&#13;
joined the Bank, I had been for some years in the British Treasury, on&#13;
&#13;
the overseas side of the work.    I had been the financial counsellor to&#13;
&#13;
the British embassy in Teheran.     I had then been at Simla in India as&#13;
&#13;
financial advisor to the Governor of Burma.     After that, I became the&#13;
&#13;
British Treasury representative in the Middle East, with headquarters in&#13;
&#13;
Cairo and with responsibility for British financial relations with all&#13;
&#13;
the Arab countries, Iran and Ethiopia.      I came to the Bank straight from&#13;
&#13;
that job.&#13;
&#13;
     I did say that I have been Vice President of the Bank since 1960.&#13;
&#13;
I ought to have said, since 1956.&#13;
&#13;
     As Loan director I was responsible right across the whole board of&#13;
&#13;
the Bank membership for the Bank's lending operations.     In 1951, I&#13;
&#13;
became Assistant to the President with general responsibilities,&#13;
&#13;
assisting the management in all the Bank's operations, and this&#13;
&#13;
continued until Mr. Garner left the Bank to become the President of the&#13;
&#13;
International Finance Corporation, when Mr. Knapp, Mr. Sommers and&#13;
&#13;
myself became the three Vice Presidents.&#13;
&#13;
     When I joined the Bank in February, 1948, the Bank's membership&#13;
&#13;
consisted of 48 member countries.    Today the membership is something&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                    - 1 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                         Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
like 70, and the accretion to the Bank's membership that has happened&#13;
&#13;
over the last 12 years has been mainly from the underdeveloped&#13;
&#13;
countries, and particularly from those countries which have recently&#13;
&#13;
emerged into independence.&#13;
&#13;
     When I started at the Bank, the Bank had already made only its&#13;
&#13;
reconstruction loans in Western Europe.    We had not yet got into the&#13;
&#13;
development field.   And when I arrived in Washington, the first files&#13;
&#13;
that I found on my table related to a loan to Chile.   This loan was&#13;
&#13;
eventually made, and was the first venture of the Bank into the field of&#13;
&#13;
development.&#13;
&#13;
     When I joined the Bank, the loan department was really the engine&#13;
&#13;
room of the Bank.    As well as loan officers, it had economists,&#13;
&#13;
engineers and technicians of various kinds, and no matter from what part&#13;
&#13;
of the world a loan application came, it found its way eventually on to&#13;
&#13;
the desk of the Loan Director.   As our operations in the underdeveloped&#13;
&#13;
countries began to expand, the load of work which the Loan director&#13;
&#13;
found on his table became -- well, really too much for him.   And we&#13;
&#13;
decided, I think it was in 1951, to set up an interdepartmental&#13;
&#13;
committee, of which Mr. Black appointed me as chairman, to examine the&#13;
&#13;
question of the organization of the Bank, and to consider whether any&#13;
&#13;
revamping of our operational setup was required, and if so, along what&#13;
&#13;
lines.&#13;
&#13;
     Well, the committee was established, and we sat for I think several&#13;
&#13;
months.   We took evidence from the heads of all the interested&#13;
&#13;
departments of the Bank, and eventually we came up with a recommendation&#13;
&#13;
that the functions of the loan department should be -- well, I suppose I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   - 2 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                         Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
could say, should be split.   We decided that a territorial organization&#13;
&#13;
was an absolute necessity, the idea there being that it was very&#13;
&#13;
desirable that we should have within the Bank a core of people who were&#13;
&#13;
sufficiently constantly in touch with our various member countries to&#13;
&#13;
acquire some pretty detailed knowledge of conditions there, to make&#13;
&#13;
their contacts with prominent personalities in those countries, and&#13;
&#13;
generally to develop an expertise, on a country basis.&#13;
&#13;
     We also came to the conclusion that it was very highly desirable&#13;
&#13;
that every loan operation should be tested, in the economic sense --&#13;
&#13;
that is to say, that there should be economic specialists specializing&#13;
&#13;
in each of our member countries concerned.   Furthermore, the technical&#13;
&#13;
aspects of these operations had become so important that we decided to&#13;
&#13;
cut away altogether from the loan department the technical examination&#13;
&#13;
of projects which had hitherto been carried out within the loan&#13;
&#13;
department, and this led to our recommendation that a technical&#13;
&#13;
operations department should be established whose job it was, in short,&#13;
&#13;
to review the technical, the economic, the financial and the managerial&#13;
&#13;
aspects of every project that came to the Bank for financing.&#13;
&#13;
     Now, the outcome of all this was a complete change in the&#13;
&#13;
organizational set-up of the Bank.   Instead of the loan department --&#13;
&#13;
well, we replaced the loan department really with four separate&#13;
&#13;
departments, three area departments with territorial responsibilities,&#13;
&#13;
and the technical operations department which covered the technical&#13;
&#13;
aspects of projects right across the whole board, not organized at all&#13;
&#13;
on a territorial basis but organized on a functional basis.   In other&#13;
&#13;
words, we established a public utilities department that examined every&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  - 3 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                        Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
public utility proposal no matter where it came from, whether from&#13;
&#13;
Brazil or from India, an industrial division and an agricultural&#13;
&#13;
division, and I think originally there was also a general division with&#13;
&#13;
the main responsibility for considering the financing of the development&#13;
&#13;
banks.&#13;
&#13;
      Now, the area departments were three at that point in time.    They&#13;
&#13;
were subsequently increased to four, with the addition of new members to&#13;
&#13;
the Bank, when the lead became too great even to be handled by three&#13;
&#13;
departments.   The original three area departments were the Department&#13;
&#13;
for Europe, Africa and Australasia, that was one; the Department for&#13;
&#13;
South Asia and the Middle East, two; and the Department for Latin&#13;
&#13;
America, which was three.   Subsequently the South Asia and Middle East&#13;
&#13;
Department split into two, and at the moment the functions that were&#13;
&#13;
hitherto discharged by that department are now split between an Asia and&#13;
&#13;
Middle East Department, which goes from and including Egypt east to and&#13;
&#13;
including Pakistan.   Everything east of that is now in a new area&#13;
&#13;
department called the Far East Department.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Could I ask a couple of questions about what you've said so far?&#13;
&#13;
When it was being considered that there would be a technical operations&#13;
&#13;
department established, or even before, had it been considered that it&#13;
&#13;
might be an engineering department per se?   Was there ever thought of&#13;
&#13;
having just an engineering department as a separate entity?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   There was quite a bit of discussion on that very point, but the&#13;
&#13;
majority of us, and I think rightly, came to the conclusion that when an&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  - 4 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                         Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
organization like ours is considering the financing of a project, there&#13;
&#13;
are more things that matter than the purely engineering aspects.    One&#13;
&#13;
wants to be satisfied about the economics of the project.   The thing may&#13;
&#13;
be technically perfect, but is it making an adequate contribution to the&#13;
&#13;
economic development of the country?    Is it financially viable?   And of&#13;
&#13;
course on top of that, has it got the necessary managerial techniques to&#13;
&#13;
insure that the project is operated properly?    All these things were&#13;
&#13;
taken into consideration, and for that reason we decided to make the&#13;
&#13;
technical operations something rather more than a purely engineering&#13;
&#13;
department -- although of course, as I say, it has engineers in&#13;
&#13;
considerable strength.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Before the reorganization of '52 had all these four things which are&#13;
&#13;
now being considered by the technical operations department been a part&#13;
&#13;
of the loan department as such?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   That is so, yes.   But the loan department at that time really&#13;
&#13;
had not got a sufficient core of technicians to cover all these aspects&#13;
&#13;
I've been talking about, and if we had grafted them onto the loan&#13;
&#13;
department, in addition to the engineers, and in addition to the area&#13;
&#13;
operators and in addition to the economists, we would have had a very,&#13;
&#13;
very unwieldy unit.   This was one of the motives that led us to the&#13;
&#13;
revision of the organization.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   - 5 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                         Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   I take it that you had economists in the loan department.   What was&#13;
&#13;
the distinction between economists in the loan department and economists&#13;
&#13;
in the economics department?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:    Well, the economists in the loan department were concerned with&#13;
&#13;
the economic analysis of the particular country with which their branch&#13;
&#13;
of the loan department happened to be dealing.   The balance of payments&#13;
&#13;
aspects, for example.   The propriety of the development program that the&#13;
&#13;
country might have been following.   Also the contribution that a&#13;
&#13;
particular project might make to the economy of the country.     The&#13;
&#13;
economics department on the other hand was concerned with, and is today&#13;
&#13;
concerned really with broad across-the-board economic considerations.&#13;
&#13;
For example, one thing that's done by the economics department, a very&#13;
&#13;
valuable part of the work, is what we call commodity studies.    What&#13;
&#13;
about the future of coffee?    What about the future of the shipping&#13;
&#13;
industry?   Coffee, as you can understand of course, is particularly&#13;
&#13;
important as far as the Latin Republics are concerned.   It's their major&#13;
&#13;
expert.    Shipping, for example, is a very important factor in the&#13;
&#13;
economics of a country like Norway or Holland, or even the United&#13;
&#13;
Kingdom.    It's those broader economic considerations which were vested&#13;
&#13;
in the economics department.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Was there ever a time when the economics department was concerned&#13;
&#13;
with the narrower questions dealing with specific countries?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   - 6 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                         Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   In the very early days, 1948, yes, that was so, and as a matter&#13;
&#13;
of fact we had quite a struggle to segregate that particular function&#13;
&#13;
from what was then called the economic department and to integrate it&#13;
&#13;
into the new area departments that we were setting up.   We felt that it&#13;
&#13;
was very desirable that the director of the operating department for the&#13;
&#13;
areas should have under his own control and at his elbow, so to speak,&#13;
&#13;
economists who specialized in the economic problems of the particular&#13;
&#13;
country with which he was dealing.   Now, one objection which was voiced&#13;
&#13;
about the proposed new organization was this:   that you might not get a&#13;
&#13;
uniform economic standard being applied in each of the three area&#13;
&#13;
departments.   You might have one or another going off on a particular&#13;
&#13;
economic approach which differed from what was being followed elsewhere.&#13;
&#13;
Now, that we got over, or at least we proposed to get over it and I&#13;
&#13;
think we did, by establishing what we now call the Staff Economic&#13;
&#13;
Committee.   That's a committee which is presided over by the director of&#13;
&#13;
the economic staff, and its membership consists of the economic advisors&#13;
&#13;
to each of the area departments and certain other prominent economists&#13;
&#13;
engaged, for example, in the technical operations department on economic&#13;
&#13;
work of one kind or another, and in that way, we were able to coordinate&#13;
&#13;
the general economic approach by the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   I'm still just a bit confused about the role of the economist before&#13;
&#13;
the area departments were established.    It seems to me at one time you&#13;
&#13;
said the economists serving country analysis were in the loan&#13;
&#13;
department, and then more recently it seemed to me you said that they&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  - 7 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                         Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
were in the economics department until '52 when the area departments&#13;
&#13;
were established.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Well, I don't think I exaggerate when I say that in the very&#13;
&#13;
early days -- I'm talking now about '48, '49, '50 -- there was a good&#13;
&#13;
deal of confusion on this particular issue, and it was one of the&#13;
&#13;
purposes of the reorganization to remove that confusion, and to fix&#13;
&#13;
squarely within the area departments the responsibility for the economic&#13;
&#13;
analysis of the country with which it was dealing, leaving to the&#13;
&#13;
economic staff as we know it today under the director these broader&#13;
&#13;
questions of economic policy.    Now, I don't know whether in the earlier&#13;
&#13;
interviews the Staff Loan Committee comes up to be talked about at all,&#13;
&#13;
but --&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   -- a little bit.   I'd be happy to have you say more about it, but I&#13;
&#13;
have one more question before you talk about that.    Where were the&#13;
&#13;
credit worthiness studies done before '52?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Well, my recollection is that sometimes they emerged from the&#13;
&#13;
economics department and sometimes they emerged from the loan&#13;
&#13;
department.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   There was a time when both departments were working on this&#13;
&#13;
question?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Yes.   Oh, yes -- which wasn't very satisfactory.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   - 8 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                          Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Well, now perhaps you'd say something about the Staff Loan&#13;
&#13;
Committee.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Well, before I get to the Staff Loan Committee, I think I ought&#13;
&#13;
to say a few words about the working party.     Now, the working party had&#13;
&#13;
been in existence, I should say -- well, it was on a very internal basis&#13;
&#13;
even when I entered the Bank in 1948.     It then became quite an&#13;
&#13;
established feature of our operating techniques.     And in our&#13;
&#13;
reorganization report, we strongly recommended that the working party&#13;
&#13;
should continue.   What it is, of course, is a party under the&#13;
&#13;
chairmanship of the loan officer who is in charge of a particular&#13;
&#13;
operation --&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   -- and who is from the area -- ?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   -- who is from the area department always, and the membership&#13;
&#13;
consists of an economist from the area department to advise on the&#13;
&#13;
economic aspects of the particular operation we're talking of, someone&#13;
&#13;
from the legal department, someone from the treasurer's department, and&#13;
&#13;
always someone from the technical operations department.     Now, the idea&#13;
&#13;
there is to get the views of all the departments that are intimately&#13;
&#13;
concerned with a loan operation properly coordinated and jelled, so that&#13;
&#13;
the Bank can come up with what I might call an integrated across-the-&#13;
&#13;
board policy with regard to that operation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   What was a working party like before '52?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  - 9 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                           Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:    Well, of course, you see, you had no technical operations&#13;
&#13;
department before then, and what really happened, if my recollection&#13;
&#13;
doesn't deceive me, was that the consultation with the other departments&#13;
&#13;
was on a much looser, much more informal basis than it subsequently&#13;
&#13;
became.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   I take that the head of the working party was somebody from the loan&#13;
&#13;
department?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:    Yes, he was.   He was, yes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Were other departments represented?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sir Iliff:      Other departments would have been called in, as they seemed&#13;
&#13;
to be concerned.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   I see.     There was no formal arrangement that there should be one&#13;
&#13;
person from the treasurer's department, say, one from the legal&#13;
&#13;
department?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:    No.   No.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   So to all practical purposes, the working party was constituted&#13;
&#13;
primarily of people from the loan department, with other people being&#13;
&#13;
brought in on an ad hoc basis as necessary.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     - 10 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                         Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   That's right, yes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Can you remember how far back the term â&#128;&#156;working partyâ&#128;? goes?    Were&#13;
&#13;
people talking about working parties when you came?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   No, I don't think they were.   I don't think they were.    No.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Was this a time when Mr. Garner, for example, was personally&#13;
&#13;
concerned with discussions on each loan?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Yes, in the early days Mr. Garner was very much concerned with&#13;
&#13;
the details of each loan, and -- I mean, he then concerned himself with&#13;
&#13;
details very much more than he subsequently did as the organization and&#13;
&#13;
particularly as the operations of the Bank began to develop.   I mean,&#13;
&#13;
when we only had, for example, two or three loans at any one moment on&#13;
&#13;
our plate, it was possible for Mr. Garner to exercise a very, very&#13;
&#13;
detailed supervision over the whole operation.   But when we got to the&#13;
&#13;
stage where we had 20 or 30 or more loans, obviously the task became&#13;
&#13;
much too big for him to cope with it on the basis that he had hitherto&#13;
&#13;
followed.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   When you were director of the loan department, I suppose you must&#13;
&#13;
have been concerned with each loan too?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Yes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  - 11 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                            Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Did you then have somebody under you in the loan department who&#13;
&#13;
would be sort of specifically in charge of bringing together materials&#13;
&#13;
on a particular loan?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Well, at that time I had Mr. Hoar as my assistant director, and&#13;
&#13;
Mr. Hoar and I found it desirable to split the world into two.      He&#13;
&#13;
looked after one half, and I looked after the other half.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Which of you had which half?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   That varied from time to time.      It's better to say probably that&#13;
&#13;
we split the operations in half.    Neither of us looked after a&#13;
&#13;
particular geographical area.   But of course, as Loan director I had the&#13;
&#13;
general responsibility even for those operations for which Mr. Hoar was&#13;
&#13;
originally responsible.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   I take it that you and Mr. Hoar and Mr. Garner must have worked very&#13;
&#13;
closely with each other, on almost all loans.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Oh, yes, yes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Who were some of the other people in your department that were&#13;
&#13;
particularly important?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Well, I had Mr. Hill, who subsequently left the Bank and is now&#13;
&#13;
the Secretary General of the International Chamber of Commerce.      He had&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                    - 12 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                         Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
been at one time a second Assistant Director of the Loan Department, but&#13;
&#13;
within the loan department we altered that and called him Assistant to&#13;
&#13;
the Director.   And he did sort of what one might call advising on the&#13;
&#13;
general policy aspects of loan administration, and --&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   -- he had at one time been for a short time in the economics&#13;
&#13;
department, had he not?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   That is right.   Yes.   Yes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   How did it come about that he got transferred from one department to&#13;
&#13;
the other?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Oh, I don't know.   Don't ask me how any of these transfers ever&#13;
&#13;
came about.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   I was just wondering if this was a time perhaps when some of the&#13;
&#13;
things that had been done by the economics department began to be done&#13;
&#13;
rather more by the loan department.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Well, Mr. Hill was actually in the loan department when I took&#13;
&#13;
over in February, 1948.   Both Mr. Hoar and Mr. Hill were there then, so&#13;
&#13;
the transfer had taken place earlier -- for what reason, I don't know.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Mr. Hoar is not very available to be interviewed this summer, so I&#13;
&#13;
wonder if you could just say a bit about his own background.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                    - 13 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                          Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Well, Mr. Hoar was vintage Bank of England, and he also had been&#13;
&#13;
with the Allied Control Commission in Austria, tidying up the financial&#13;
&#13;
situation there, after or rather during the Austrian occupation, with&#13;
&#13;
the British component, of course, and he came to the Bank I think&#13;
&#13;
sometime either late in '46 or early in '47.    He was here actually when&#13;
&#13;
I got here.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Did you know him before you came?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   No.   No, I'd never met him.   I'd never met him until I met him&#13;
&#13;
at the Union Station here the day I arrived.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Are there other people you can think of who were important in the&#13;
&#13;
loan department?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Well, I had Mr. Burland, who also has since left the Bank and is&#13;
&#13;
now in charge of the industrial financial operations of ICA in Turkey.&#13;
&#13;
I had Mr. Dorsey-Stephens, who has also retired from the Bank's service.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Do you know where he is now?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Yes, he's now living in Mexico, and has become an enthusiastic&#13;
&#13;
collector of Byzantine coins, which is a -- I was almost going to say,&#13;
&#13;
it's a curious occupation for a banker, but I'm not sure that it is --&#13;
&#13;
after all, coins.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                    - 14 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                          Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   He and Mr. [inaudible] should get together.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Yes.   Yes.   And then there was a Mr. Penton from the British&#13;
&#13;
Treasury.   Well, he left us also, about a year after I came here, and I&#13;
&#13;
don't know what he's doing now.     Most of the men who are now in senior&#13;
&#13;
positions in the operating departments were then actually juniors in the&#13;
&#13;
loan department, and of course Mr. Cope, for example, is another one,&#13;
&#13;
and they have now become either directors or assistant directors in the&#13;
&#13;
area departments.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Either Mr. Aldewereld or Mr. Ripman -- or were they in the&#13;
&#13;
treasurer's department?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   They were in the treasurer's department, yes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   How did it come about that one of the major departments that&#13;
&#13;
followed the reorganization of '52 should now be ruled over, so to&#13;
&#13;
speak, by people who had been in the treasurer's department?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Well, both of them -- of course, Mr. Aldewereld had an&#13;
&#13;
investment banking background, and Mr. Ripman had displayed financial&#13;
&#13;
qualities while he was in the treasurer's department that seemed to fit&#13;
&#13;
him for this particular post that he now fills very adequately, I may&#13;
&#13;
say, in the technical operations department.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                    - 15 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                          Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Who are some of the economists other than Mr. Hill who are in the&#13;
&#13;
loan department?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:     --&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Never mind, we can find that.    Perhaps you'd like to say a little&#13;
&#13;
more about the Staff Loan Committee as such?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:    Well, now, that was another point that arose in the course of&#13;
&#13;
the organization.    So long as you had one Loan director who was looking&#13;
&#13;
after operations right across the board, you could expect that there was&#13;
&#13;
a coordinated policy approach to every operation that came up before the&#13;
&#13;
Bank.    I should say, by the way, that the working party's function, of&#13;
&#13;
course, is to work out the details of a project or a Bank operation and&#13;
&#13;
to make recommendations as to the way that that operation ought to be&#13;
&#13;
handled.    But superimposed on that, you need something to make sure that&#13;
&#13;
there's a general policy coordination of the Bank's approach, right&#13;
&#13;
across the whole membership of the Bank, in all the lending operations&#13;
&#13;
that we may be asked to engage in.&#13;
&#13;
        Well, that is the charge of the Staff Loan Committee.   And that, as&#13;
&#13;
someone else has probably said, has always been chaired -- well,&#13;
&#13;
originally I was chairman of the Staff Loan Committee, in 1948.       Then it&#13;
&#13;
was thought desirable to elevate it and make the chairman part of the&#13;
&#13;
management.     Mr. Garner took over, and since then the Staff Loan&#13;
&#13;
Committee has always been chaired by a Vice President of the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     - 16 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                          Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      Now, it consists of the operating heads, the heads of the operating&#13;
&#13;
departments -- that is to say, the heads of the four area departments,&#13;
&#13;
the technical operations department, the legal department, and the&#13;
&#13;
treasurer's department, and the director of the economic staff, and Mr.&#13;
&#13;
Hoffman, who is the director of the Economic Development Institute.     He&#13;
&#13;
is also a member, because we find it very useful to draw on his economic&#13;
&#13;
experience and his economic ideas.&#13;
&#13;
      Now, every operation which goes up to the board of the Bank for&#13;
&#13;
approval, I mean every lending operation, must first pass through the&#13;
&#13;
sieve of the Staff Loan Committee.   The Staff Loan Committee takes care&#13;
&#13;
that the director of one area department doesn't fly off on one&#13;
&#13;
particular line of policy, and the director of another area department&#13;
&#13;
fly off in another.   We hope that the Staff Loan Committee achieves that&#13;
&#13;
result.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   When you were Loan director and presiding at meetings of the Staff&#13;
&#13;
Loan Committee, was it called the Staff Loan Committee?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:    It was called the Staff Loan Committee, yes.   Yes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   In what way does the Staff Loan Committee differ from just the loan&#13;
&#13;
department itself, or from the working parties which might be formed?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:    Well, it was at a higher level.   It was at a higher level.   And&#13;
&#13;
one of the things that we have been trying to do, as a matter of fact,&#13;
&#13;
over the years, and I think we're succeeding, is to insure that the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   - 17 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                         Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
matters that come up before the Staff Loan Committee are really matters&#13;
&#13;
of general policy, and not little detailed aspects of a particular loan&#13;
&#13;
operation.   Because we feel that -- well, that one ought not to&#13;
&#13;
immobilize for several hours I don't know how many hundred thousand&#13;
&#13;
dollars' worth of salary time, to deal with little detailed things that&#13;
&#13;
ought to have been sorted out in the interval.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   What were some of the policy issues that came up in the early days,&#13;
&#13;
'48, '49?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Well, for example, one that occurs to me is the question of the&#13;
&#13;
â&#128;&#156;negative pledgeâ&#128;?.   I mean, what should be the approach of the Bank on&#13;
&#13;
the question of the security that we ought to exact or ask for from a&#13;
&#13;
borrower before we made a loan.   We weren't asking for any preferential&#13;
&#13;
position, that our loan should be the first to be paid, as against all&#13;
&#13;
the other outstanding debt of the country, but equally we were not&#13;
&#13;
saying that we should be put into any junior position.   And that was&#13;
&#13;
eventually -- well, right from the beginning, really, was adopted as a&#13;
&#13;
fixed point of Bank policy.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   I'm surprised that it was still being discussed in '48, '49.   I&#13;
&#13;
thought this had been pretty well decided, even in the case of the first&#13;
&#13;
French loan.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Well, in the case of the first French loan we didn't actually&#13;
&#13;
get a proper negative pledge -- not of the cast-iron type that we have&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  - 18 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                         Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
subsequently succeeded in getting from our borrowers.    But anyway, there&#13;
&#13;
are all sorts of questions that arise in connection with a negative&#13;
&#13;
pledge.   As you know -- well, in substance, it comes to this, that if&#13;
&#13;
the borrower assigns any of his revenues, any of its foreign exchange&#13;
&#13;
revenues, as security for an external debt, or if it, for example, gives&#13;
&#13;
a lien on its gold reserves as security for an external debt, we expect&#13;
&#13;
to be covered by it, unless we agree not to press our claim.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Has the Bank ever agreed not to press it?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:    Yes, there have been one or two cases where we have felt that in&#13;
&#13;
all circumstances, we could do so.    But it's a very difficult field,&#13;
&#13;
this, and there are many legal questions that arise here that require&#13;
&#13;
quite a bit of sorting out.    And I think, to the extent there has been&#13;
&#13;
any different treatment of the negative pledge approach, it can be seen&#13;
&#13;
from the actual texts of our loan agreements.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   There weren't any exceptional cases that stand out in our mind that&#13;
&#13;
you want to comment on because the files would not give the full story?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:    No, I think the files will give the full story of it, in any&#13;
&#13;
case where there was exceptional treatment, I'm sure they will.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   What other sorts of policy issues were being debated in the early&#13;
&#13;
days?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   - 19 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                           Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Well, there was the -- I remember, for example, right away in&#13;
&#13;
the early days, this was I think probably about April or May of 1948, we&#13;
&#13;
had quite a long discussion at the board as to whether or not it was&#13;
&#13;
safe to lend to India 100 million dollars.    Now, we were applying then a&#13;
&#13;
test of credit worthiness that I don't say was unduly conservative, but&#13;
&#13;
there was some misgiving as to whether or not the Bank ought to go into&#13;
&#13;
India on that scale.   Well, look at the position today.    Our total stake&#13;
&#13;
in India today is something like 700 million dollars.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   What was the decision in '48?    Was it decided that 100 million was&#13;
&#13;
in fact too much?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Well, no, but 100 million was about right, put it that way.     The&#13;
&#13;
board was prepared to go to 100 million, but not disposed to go very&#13;
&#13;
much further.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Well, does this imply that the Bank frequently has decided what was&#13;
&#13;
the total amount it might lend to a country and then go about finding&#13;
&#13;
projects which would absorb that amount that had been decided upon?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Well, when we approach our operations in a particular country,&#13;
&#13;
we do first of all try to get what one might call a benchmark, I&#13;
&#13;
suppose, in our minds, about how much the Bank would appropriately put&#13;
&#13;
into a country, taking into consideration the whole economic and&#13;
&#13;
financial situation as we find it in that country at that time.     Now,&#13;
&#13;
there are all sorts of criteria of course that can be applied so far as&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     - 20 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                            Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
credit worthiness is concerned, but I don't think, nor I'm sure do any&#13;
&#13;
of the other senior officers of the Bank think that you can reach an&#13;
&#13;
absolutely rigid formula -- for example, that x percent relationship&#13;
&#13;
between external debt service and foreign exchange earnings, that that&#13;
&#13;
should be an absolutely rigorous criterion, or the relationship between&#13;
&#13;
debt service and budget revenues.    There are very many other&#13;
&#13;
considerations that come into it.    For example, what has been the past&#13;
&#13;
debt record of that country?   One is naturally less reluctant to go into&#13;
&#13;
a country on a particular scale if the past record of that country in&#13;
&#13;
paying its foreign obligations, as in the case of Finland, for example,&#13;
&#13;
has been good, one is less reluctant to go into that situation than into&#13;
&#13;
another situation where the past debt record has shown defaults.      The&#13;
&#13;
existence of a capacity to pay debt but the absence of willingness to&#13;
&#13;
pay it.   So it's very, very difficult, as I say, to establish any rigid&#13;
&#13;
criterion of credit worthiness, but one can so to speak -- well, put it&#13;
&#13;
this way, have a smell of a situation.       And, of course, banking is not&#13;
&#13;
by any means an exact science.   I mean, there are psychological aspects&#13;
&#13;
to it as well as the purely technical and financial.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   I should think the political maturity of a given government would be&#13;
&#13;
a thoroughly important factor.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:    That's another, certainly, not only the political maturity but&#13;
&#13;
also the administrative competence of a country.      I mean, can they&#13;
&#13;
administer?   Can they absorb foreign aid?     Have they got the&#13;
&#13;
administrative, the managerial, the technical setup to do the best with&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                    - 21 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                          Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
whatever money you're putting in?     Now, one country may be able to&#13;
&#13;
absorb 100 million, another country may not be able to absorb 5 or 10.&#13;
&#13;
All these considerations must enter into it.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   When you say here absorb, are you identifying the absorptive&#13;
&#13;
capacity with credit worthiness, or are these two distinct concepts?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Well, I think absorptive capacity has got a good deal to do with&#13;
&#13;
credit worthiness.     I mean, we have got some member countries (don't ask&#13;
&#13;
me to name them) whose foreign exchange earnings, if you apply the test&#13;
&#13;
of the ratio of debt service to foreign exchange, have got the capacity&#13;
&#13;
to absorb a good deal of debt, but where we are not satisfied that they&#13;
&#13;
have got the managerial competence, shall we say, to put that money to&#13;
&#13;
work.    And that's one factor.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   I suppose many Latin American countries would fall into that&#13;
&#13;
category?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Some of them.   Some of them.&#13;
&#13;
Q:   But the Bank in its early days, '49, '50, might be willing to make a&#13;
&#13;
loan of 250 million dollars to Australia, for example, and feel that&#13;
&#13;
Australia was a more credit-worthy country, largely because of its&#13;
&#13;
political machinery, than a country like Chile which perhaps could only&#13;
&#13;
be credit worthy to the extent of 25 or 30 million, something like that?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   That is so.   That is so.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     - 22 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                            Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   And all these questions would be discussed, I take it, at the Staff&#13;
&#13;
Loan Committee and other places in the Bank in these early days.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:    Oh, yes.   Yes.   Yes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Could you say just a bit more about India?     What has happened to&#13;
&#13;
India to cause the Bank to regard it as much more credit worthy now than&#13;
&#13;
in '49?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:    Well, of course, for one thing India had only just emerged into&#13;
&#13;
independence, and the political outlook, for one thing, couldn't really&#13;
&#13;
be very accurately forecast.       Secondly, one didn't quite know what sort&#13;
&#13;
of trade pattern might be developed in the new India.      The partition of&#13;
&#13;
the continent of course was another factor.      What subsequently became&#13;
&#13;
East Pakistan, for example, was the big jute producer of the old&#13;
&#13;
undivided India.     Those resources of course were lost to the new India&#13;
&#13;
at the time of partition.&#13;
&#13;
      Well, as time went on and political stability emerged, and when it&#13;
&#13;
became evident that probably among all our underdeveloped member&#13;
&#13;
countries the standard of administration in India was -- well, I don't&#13;
&#13;
think it's an exaggeration to say, very much higher than one would find&#13;
&#13;
in any of the other underdeveloped countries -- these were all factors.&#13;
&#13;
I mean, you have good financial management in India, and really have&#13;
&#13;
had, right from the time of independence.      Now, that's a factor that&#13;
&#13;
obviously made for some slackening up in the Bank's attitude.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                      - 23 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                            Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       Of course, apart from that, you've got in India now nearly 400&#13;
&#13;
million people, which is -- well, I suppose about a third of the total&#13;
&#13;
population of the free underdeveloped world, and India therefore looked&#13;
&#13;
like being the kind of place that the Bank was really set up to operate&#13;
&#13;
in.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:    I don't suppose that more population would be enough to cause the&#13;
&#13;
Bank to be excited about making loans to Communist China, even if China&#13;
&#13;
were a member of the Bank?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Well, no, I don't think so.      No, I don't think so.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:    In the early days, '48, '49, again about India, was the Bank&#13;
&#13;
concerned about India's credit worthiness in part because of its&#13;
&#13;
avowedly Socialistic leanings?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Well --&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:    Or openly antagonistic attitude toward private enterprise as such?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:    Well, you can say the â&#128;&#156;Bank.â&#128;?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:    Or people in the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff: There were some people in the Bank, shall I put it that way.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   - 24 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                          Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   I heard that Mr. Garner, for example, was concerned about this.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:    Mr. Garner was very concerned about it, yes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   I even heard that the Bank's attitude toward India changed somewhat&#13;
&#13;
after Mr. Garner went to IFC.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:    Well, the Bank's attitude toward India had already begun to&#13;
&#13;
change, I mean, before Mr. Garner left the Bank, although it's quite&#13;
&#13;
true that I think we have done considerably more lending in India, over&#13;
&#13;
the last four years, than we did in the earlier period.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Has the credit worthiness of India improved to some extent because&#13;
&#13;
of the very large amount of aid that the US government gives?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:    Undoubtedly that has had its effect.   It's certainly had its&#13;
&#13;
effect.   But of course, India today has got to the stage where she has&#13;
&#13;
got so much hard debt on her shoulders that I think we're very near the&#13;
&#13;
limit of what the Bank can lend her.   So long as these other aid-giving&#13;
&#13;
countries keep piling hard loans on hard loans, and adding to India's&#13;
&#13;
foreign debt burden.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Would you say something in general about the Bank's developing&#13;
&#13;
attitude towards stimulating private enterprise in its member countries?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   - 25 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                          Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:    Well, we have, as you know, loaned quite substantial sums to&#13;
&#13;
private industries in various member countries.     We never fail to try&#13;
&#13;
and influence our member countries to realize the importance of getting&#13;
&#13;
foreign private capital in, as a contribution towards the development&#13;
&#13;
effort.   And, of course, as I'm sure you've heard already, we have been&#13;
&#13;
very active in attempting to establish these development banks -- that's&#13;
&#13;
domestic development banks within certain of our member countries which&#13;
&#13;
on the whole have been very successful in the promotion of domestic&#13;
&#13;
private industry.   Of course, we do have -- for example, if you take&#13;
&#13;
Yugoslavia, a member of the Bank which of course is a Socialist, well, a&#13;
&#13;
Communist country, really -- I mean, there's nothing very much that the&#13;
&#13;
Bank can do against a background of that sort of economic ideology to&#13;
&#13;
promote private enterprise, because private industry, to all intents and&#13;
&#13;
purposes, doesn't exist.    But in India, in Pakistan, in Turkey, for&#13;
&#13;
example, where these development banks that we have organized and&#13;
&#13;
promoted have been quite a catalyst in stimulating the growth of private&#13;
&#13;
industry.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   How about the Bank's feeling that it does not want to make loans to&#13;
&#13;
government-owned industry if that industry is in a field where private&#13;
&#13;
enterprise could operate?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:    I think it even goes further than that.   I think the Bank policy&#13;
&#13;
is that we don't in any circumstances loan to government-owned&#13;
&#13;
industries, or even to government-owned development banks, even though&#13;
&#13;
they are promoting private industry.   But up till now Mr. Black has been&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   - 26 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                        Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
quite adamant on that point.   But I don't know that we may not find&#13;
&#13;
ourselves in a bit of a dilemma about this, in some of these little&#13;
&#13;
emerging republics in Africa, for example, where there's really no&#13;
&#13;
private capital which can be mobilized, and where it seems to me anyway,&#13;
&#13;
personally, that the only possibility really of promoting domestic&#13;
&#13;
private enterprise is through a development bank for which the&#13;
&#13;
government puts up some capital.   But the vital thing here of course is&#13;
&#13;
management.   I mean, I think it's one thing to have government ownership&#13;
&#13;
or part ownership in an enterprise of that kind, and quite another thing&#13;
&#13;
to have it government controlled and government managed and subject to&#13;
&#13;
political decisions on the operations in which it engages.   So as I say,&#13;
&#13;
there's a bit of a dilemma I think that's going to confront us in these&#13;
&#13;
countries.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Had this policy we're talking about been pretty firmly established&#13;
&#13;
even at the time you arrived at the Bank in '48?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Well, the development bank concept -- that arose after I had&#13;
&#13;
been at the Bank.   But certainly the practice of not lending to&#13;
&#13;
government-owned industries had already been quite firmly established.&#13;
&#13;
And has been adhered to.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Do you feel that this was pretty much a management decision in the&#13;
&#13;
early beginning of the Bank, or was it thoroughly discussed in the&#13;
&#13;
staff?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   - 27 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                           Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Well, it was a management decision.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   I wonder if I might ask what you did as Assistant to the President,&#13;
&#13;
an office which I take it no longer exists?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Well, it was felt about that time that with the increasing&#13;
&#13;
workload on the management of the Bank, some addition to the management&#13;
&#13;
was desirable, and at that time, Mr. Black was very reluctant to add a&#13;
&#13;
second Vice President to the hierarchy.      I don't think Mr. Garner would&#13;
&#13;
have liked the idea either.    So it was decided to put me in there in&#13;
&#13;
this -- I don't know what I ought to call it, a sort of tweeny position&#13;
&#13;
-- as Assistant to the President.    And I was in that capacity, of&#13;
&#13;
course, consulted on all major management policy decisions.     When both&#13;
&#13;
Mr. Black and Mr. Garner were absent from Washington, I presided at the&#13;
&#13;
board meetings, and I was also the chief executive officer of the Bank&#13;
&#13;
in their absence.   But I can't say that I could put into any sort of&#13;
&#13;
specific department a kind of catalogue of my duties.     It was perfectly&#13;
&#13;
general.   Mr. Black would send for me on Monday and say, â&#128;&#156;Look, I think&#13;
&#13;
you should take a look at this and let me know what you think of it.â&#128;?&#13;
&#13;
On Tuesday, it would be something else, and so on.     Then, when we&#13;
&#13;
embarked on this mediation function, that was thrown at me, I don't&#13;
&#13;
know, perhaps I could say a word about that?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Yes, I hope you will.   Just one other question first.   When Mr.&#13;
&#13;
Garner was in town, did he continue to preside over the Staff Loan&#13;
&#13;
Committee?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                    - 28 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                         Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   He did, yes, and in his absence I presided.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Maybe you'd just say a word about the three Vice Presidents in '55.&#13;
&#13;
Any particular reason for three, as such?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Well, by that time, of course, our operations had really&#13;
&#13;
expanded very substantially, and looking into the crystal ball of the&#13;
&#13;
future, it was very obvious that they were going to expand still more.&#13;
&#13;
Mr. Black of course has got very heavy demands on his time, I mean Bank&#13;
&#13;
demands on his time, apart altogether from sitting here in Washington.&#13;
&#13;
He has got to travel a lot.   Good will visits, for example, are very&#13;
&#13;
important to some of our member countries and have got to be handled at&#13;
&#13;
the top level.   And it was decided with all these considerations in mind&#13;
&#13;
-- the increasing workload of the Bank and the demands made on Mr. Black&#13;
&#13;
for visits here and there all around the world -- that we needed some&#13;
&#13;
strengthening of the management.   So it was decided then that we should&#13;
&#13;
have the three Vice Presidents.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Was there a division of responsibility among the three?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   That was never very clearly delineated, as a matter of fact,&#13;
&#13;
because it was just about that time that I, for example, got switched&#13;
&#13;
off into these mediation functions.   However, it was clear that Mr.&#13;
&#13;
Knapp would be the Vice President responsible for the operation of the&#13;
&#13;
lending activities of the Bank.    Mr. Sommers, of course, as well as&#13;
&#13;
being Vice President, continued as general counsel, although not as head&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   - 29 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                              Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
of the legal department.      Well, I think general counsel is just about&#13;
&#13;
the best description of him, because I don't think there's anybody in&#13;
&#13;
the Bank or anybody who has been in the Bank in whose opinion I placed a&#13;
&#13;
higher value than on Mr. Sommers'.      I mean, one consulted him really on&#13;
&#13;
every aspect of the Bank's work.      I can tell you, I was very sorry when&#13;
&#13;
he left.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   I think everybody that I talk to says much the same thing.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Oh, yes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   But I take it he traveled less than you in particular and also less&#13;
&#13;
than Mr. Knapp?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:     Yes.&#13;
&#13;
Q:   So he was more management staff liaison person, and Mr. Knapp was in&#13;
&#13;
charge of staff loan work, and you were mediation, to a large extent.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Yes.     â&#128;&#156;The Wandering Minstrel.â&#128;?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   I wonder if we mightn't begin the story of your work in the&#13;
&#13;
mediation field?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Well, let me start with Suez.        The background of this, I think,&#13;
&#13;
was rather a pathetic story.      It begins of course with High Aswan.    You&#13;
&#13;
will remember that President Nasser made up his mind, as he himself put&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     - 30 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                          Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
it, that he was going to construct the modern Pyramids of Egypt.    Now,&#13;
&#13;
the High Aswan Dam is going to be the monument of the Nasser&#13;
&#13;
administration for posterity.    Well, arrangements were made to finance&#13;
&#13;
this project, and the financing was to be done on a joint basis by the&#13;
&#13;
government of the United States, the government of the United Kingdom,&#13;
&#13;
and the Bank.     And we were a long way towards setting up the project and&#13;
&#13;
the financing had all been worked out.&#13;
&#13;
      Then, as you may remember, certain political circumstances&#13;
&#13;
intervened.   The Egyptian government, quite unbeknownst to either the&#13;
&#13;
government of the United States or the government of the United Kingdom,&#13;
&#13;
entered into this big arms deal with Czechoslovakia, which looked like&#13;
&#13;
mortgaging Egyptian foreign exchange earnings from her expert, anyway      -&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q: -- which would substantially reduce its credit worthiness.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Right.   And the United States government then decided not to&#13;
&#13;
proceed with their part of the financing of the High Aswan project.      The&#13;
&#13;
British government felt that the United States government having pulled&#13;
&#13;
out, they couldn't go ahead.    Then of course the Bank, properly so in&#13;
&#13;
the situation, saw that the whole rug, so to speak, had been pulled out&#13;
&#13;
from underneath our feet, because our financing was completely dependent&#13;
&#13;
upon this financing by the two governments.    So we had to pull out also.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   I take it the Bank had previously decided that Egypt was not&#13;
&#13;
sufficiently credit-worthy that the Bank would care to finance the thing&#13;
&#13;
all by itself.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                    - 31 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                          Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:    That is true, because the money involved here was a very, very&#13;
&#13;
substantial amount.&#13;
&#13;
        Well, anyway, the financing of the High Aswan Dam by the West,&#13;
&#13;
including the Bank, fell down.    The next thing that happened was, the&#13;
&#13;
Egyptian government nationalized the Suez Canal, as their riposte to&#13;
&#13;
this -- what they regarded as the unfriendly attitude of all the Western&#13;
&#13;
governments.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Might I just ask if the US government consulted the management of&#13;
&#13;
the Bank at the time that it decided that it would pull out of the&#13;
&#13;
financing the Aswan?    Or was this pretty much a unilateral decision by&#13;
&#13;
Mr. Dulles?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:    Well, I remember that one evening at about 5 o'clock -- on this&#13;
&#13;
particular day both Mr. Black and Mr. Garner were absent from the Bank -&#13;
&#13;
- I had a call from someone in the United States State Department to say&#13;
&#13;
that at that particular moment, the Egyptian ambassador was in&#13;
&#13;
conference with Mr. Dulles, who was then Secretary of State, and Mr.&#13;
&#13;
Dulles was informing the ambassador of the intention of the United&#13;
&#13;
States government not to proceed with their financing of the High Aswan&#13;
&#13;
Damn.    My friend in the State Department read to me over the telephone&#13;
&#13;
the text of a communiquÃ© that the US government proposed to issue.&#13;
&#13;
        That was the first I had heard of the intentions of the United&#13;
&#13;
States government to pull out.    Now, I don't know whether or not Mr.&#13;
&#13;
Black may have known something of this, nor do I know whether or not the&#13;
&#13;
British government may have been consulted beforehand.    But while one&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   - 32 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                          Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
knew, of course, that both the United States government and the&#13;
&#13;
government of the United Kingdom were very concerned about this arms&#13;
&#13;
deal that Nasser had entered into, and one also knew that an â&#128;&#156;agonizing&#13;
&#13;
reappraisalâ&#128;? of Western Europe towards Egypt was under consideration,&#13;
&#13;
one did not know, at least I did not know, what form that reappraisal&#13;
&#13;
might take.   And this thing came to me as -- well, quite a surprise.&#13;
&#13;
     Well, then, as I said earlier, Nasser's riposte to this was the&#13;
&#13;
nationalization of the Canal.   And then you remember that for months&#13;
&#13;
there were conferences going on in London about how this situation&#13;
&#13;
should be dealt with, setting up the Suez Canal Users' Association to&#13;
&#13;
administer the Canal, and various other approaches, all designed to&#13;
&#13;
insure the use of the Canal for international shipping.    All of these&#13;
&#13;
came to nothing.   The Egyptians persisted in their attitude that the&#13;
&#13;
Canal had now become Egyptian and was to be operated only by Egyptians,&#13;
&#13;
and that the revenues of the Canal were to accrue only to Egypt.    And as&#13;
&#13;
part of the nationalization decree, the Egyptians had declared that they&#13;
&#13;
were prepared to pay compensation to the former company, or rather to&#13;
&#13;
the stockholders of the Suez Canal Company, on the basis related to the&#13;
&#13;
price of the shares on the Paris Bourse on the day before&#13;
&#13;
nationalization.&#13;
&#13;
     Well, of course, an offer of that kind could be criticized on this&#13;
&#13;
basis, that in view of all the uncertainty and anxiety about the&#13;
&#13;
Egyptian situation, that had been in existence over the previous months,&#13;
&#13;
the stock of the Suez Co. had fallen, fallen, fallen to an artificially&#13;
&#13;
low figure, and there was this criticism, that compensation on that&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  - 33 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                            Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
basis could hardly be regarded as an adequate offer, for the reasons&#13;
&#13;
that I mentioned.&#13;
&#13;
      Well, now, the Egyptians -- they wanted -- well, better put it this&#13;
&#13;
way first.   The Suez Canal Company had under consideration an expansion&#13;
&#13;
program which they were proposing to carry out, but then nationalization&#13;
&#13;
came and they were out of the picture.       They would presumably have&#13;
&#13;
financed this expansion.     The Canal Company would have financed this&#13;
&#13;
expansion themselves, but the Egyptian government wished to proceed with&#13;
&#13;
this expansion.   They hadn't got the money, and there was some talk&#13;
&#13;
about the Bank financing the expansion.&#13;
&#13;
      We took the position that we were not prepared to lend any money at&#13;
&#13;
any time to Egypt until the compensation issue with the Suez Canal Co.&#13;
&#13;
had been sorted out, on a basis which the company was prepared to&#13;
&#13;
accept.&#13;
&#13;
      Well, months and months of diplomatic activity went on.      We were&#13;
&#13;
not in it, but the United Nations of course was.      Mr. Hammarskjold&#13;
&#13;
played a very important part here.     And eventually, the situation arose&#13;
&#13;
that both the Egyptian government and the Suez Canal Co. put in a&#13;
&#13;
request through Mr. Hammarskjold that the Bank should attempt to mediate&#13;
&#13;
this compensation issue.     And thereupon we took a dive into the Suez&#13;
&#13;
Canal.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Did the Bank actually seek this role of mediator, or was it strictly&#13;
&#13;
a request from Mr. Hammarskjold?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:    It was -- yes.   Yes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                    - 34 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                         Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Tape 2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      Well, as I said, thereupon we dived into the Suez Canal.    Mr. Black&#13;
&#13;
asked me to take this thing on, and I think I ought to say this, that&#13;
&#13;
some doubts were expressed from various quarters of the Bank as to&#13;
&#13;
whether, in view of the very strained relationship that existed at the&#13;
&#13;
time between the British government and the Egyptian government, whether&#13;
&#13;
it was appropriate that a UK national should be designated to handle&#13;
&#13;
this rather delicate piece of business, especially as I had been for&#13;
&#13;
four years the financial counsellor on the staff of our embassy in&#13;
&#13;
Cairo, and of course was known to all the Egyptian personalities.&#13;
&#13;
      Well, I must admit that I went to Cairo myself, for my first visit&#13;
&#13;
in connection with this Suez business, with some trepidation, but the&#13;
&#13;
Egyptians really put out the red carpet, and I was treated with complete&#13;
&#13;
courtesy and cooperation and understanding right through.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Had Mr. Black had some dealings with Mr. Nasser before that time?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:     Oh, yes.   Oh, yes, yes, even before the nationalization of the&#13;
&#13;
Canal.   Well, throughout the High Aswan financial discussions, of&#13;
&#13;
course, Mr. Black had been in quite intimate touch with Nasser.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   So I take it that was a personal relationship that was quite good,&#13;
&#13;
even before you went over?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Indeed, yes.   Oh, yes.   Yes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                    - 35 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                         Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       Well, associated with me on this particular enterprise was Mr.&#13;
&#13;
George Woods, who is the chairman of the First Boston Corporation, and I&#13;
&#13;
must say that I was delighted when Mr. Black suggested to me that it&#13;
&#13;
might be a good idea if he joined me, because -- well, a good many of&#13;
&#13;
the technical issues here were technical issues of corporate finance,&#13;
&#13;
and of course nobody in the United States or anywhere else knows more&#13;
&#13;
about corporate finance than Mr. George Woods does, and apart from that,&#13;
&#13;
he's a man of a very keen diplomatic sense.   He and I worked together on&#13;
&#13;
this thing throughout most of the negotiation, and I must say that I&#13;
&#13;
believe he would say the same, that we made a very happy team.&#13;
&#13;
       I remember the first operation in which we engaged here was to go&#13;
&#13;
to Paris and talk to the directorate of the Suez Canal Co., and I had&#13;
&#13;
thought that it would eventually or at some appropriate moment be&#13;
&#13;
absolutely essential to get the two sides together around a table.      I&#13;
&#13;
was told by Monsieur Jacques George-Picot -- the director general of the&#13;
&#13;
Suez Canal Co. -- that I had my head in the clouds, and that there never&#13;
&#13;
was the slightest possibility that the Egyptians would ever sit down&#13;
&#13;
with any representatives of the company around the table.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Did the company expect that there would just be no compensation at&#13;
&#13;
all?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Well, I think that was the fear at the back of their minds, that&#13;
&#13;
there would be no compensation.&#13;
&#13;
       Now, one interesting thing about this operation was this, that the&#13;
&#13;
Egyptians, having nationalized the Canal, took the position that the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  - 36 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                        Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
former company was out of existence, and that they were not prepared to&#13;
&#13;
sit down with any body of people who called themselves the&#13;
&#13;
representatives of the Suez Canal Co.   So eventually, however -- and&#13;
&#13;
there had been some consultations on this issue between Mr. Hammarskjold&#13;
&#13;
and ourselves -- eventually, we got the Egyptians to agree that they&#13;
&#13;
would be prepared to talk with â&#128;&#156;representatives of the shareholders.â&#128;?&#13;
&#13;
But they were not prepared to recognize the existence of the Suez Canal&#13;
&#13;
Company.   And the representatives of the shareholders who were nominated&#13;
&#13;
for this purpose were Mr. Charles Spofford, who's a very eminent New&#13;
&#13;
York lawyer -- he's a partner in Davis, Polk and Co. -- and had been for&#13;
&#13;
quite a time legal advisor to the Suez Canal Co, Mr. John Foster, a&#13;
&#13;
British international lawyer of reputation, a member of Parliament, and&#13;
&#13;
the third was a French lawyer, Mr. Jerome Sauerwein, and they were&#13;
&#13;
solemnly designated as â&#128;&#156;representatives of the shareholders.â&#128;?&#13;
&#13;
     Now, the first issue that I ran up against with the Egyptians was&#13;
&#13;
whether or not Mr. George Picot, the director general of the company,&#13;
&#13;
should be permitted to be a member of the â&#128;&#156;shareholdersâ&#128;&#153; delegation,â&#128;?&#13;
&#13;
and the Egyptians were pretty tough about this for some time, but&#13;
&#13;
eventually they conceded the point, and Mr. George Picot was added to&#13;
&#13;
the party.&#13;
&#13;
     Well, having been told back in Paris that there was no possibility&#13;
&#13;
that the Egyptians would ever sit down round the table, even with this&#13;
&#13;
group, we went to Cairo, and as I say, they put out the red carpet and&#13;
&#13;
received me and Mr. Woods with extreme courtesy and cooperation, and we&#13;
&#13;
sounded out the Egyptians as to what their attitude was with regard to&#13;
&#13;
compensation.   They stuck to their point that under the nationalization&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  - 37 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                        Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
decree, they would compensate the company only on the basis of the&#13;
&#13;
shares -- at the price they were on the Paris Bourse the day before&#13;
&#13;
nationalization -- and they were taking over all the assets and&#13;
&#13;
liabilities of the company, both in Egypt and elsewhere.&#13;
&#13;
     Now, the important part of the assets of the company was&#13;
&#13;
investments by the company and bank balances owned by the company with&#13;
&#13;
various banks and other financial institutions around the world, and the&#13;
&#13;
Egyptian government had applied for writs of attachment in the United&#13;
&#13;
Kingdom, in the United States, in Switzerland, wherever they could&#13;
&#13;
discover that these balances were being held.   Now, they were not&#13;
&#13;
successful in getting the writs of attachment, but naturally the banks&#13;
&#13;
and the other financial institutions that were holding these assets were&#13;
&#13;
very reluctant, in view of the possibility that there might be legal&#13;
&#13;
proceedings with regard to them, they were very reluctant to release&#13;
&#13;
them to the company even.   So the result was that these things were&#13;
&#13;
frozen all around the world.&#13;
&#13;
     The properties in Egypt were not really so important in the&#13;
&#13;
financial sense.   The Canal itself was due to revert to the Egyptian&#13;
&#13;
government without compensation at the end of the concessionary period,&#13;
&#13;
which I think was 1968, and apart from that, the assets in Egypt&#13;
&#13;
consisted mainly of -- I think there was 10 million Egyptian pounds in&#13;
&#13;
cash balances, and of course there were certain items of equipment of&#13;
&#13;
one kind or another and real estate, but the big financial issue here&#13;
&#13;
related to the assets held outside Egypt.&#13;
&#13;
     Well, as I say, we had this conversation, our first conversation&#13;
&#13;
with the Egyptians, to find out what their position was.   They stated&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  - 38 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                          Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
their position.     Then we went back to Paris and had a meeting with the&#13;
&#13;
company there.    The company's approach to the question of compensation&#13;
&#13;
was that not only should they be compensated for all the assets which&#13;
&#13;
the Egyptians were taking over within Egypt, but that there should also&#13;
&#13;
be an element in the compensation settlement which could be roughly&#13;
&#13;
described like this: the present value, capital value, of the loss of&#13;
&#13;
profits which the company would suffer, because the concession so to&#13;
&#13;
speak would be terminated, I think about 13 years before it was actually&#13;
&#13;
due to run out.&#13;
&#13;
      Well, now, when the company and we proceeded to calculate what the&#13;
&#13;
amount of the compensation, calculated on the company's approach, would&#13;
&#13;
be, it amounted to -- I think, if my memory serves me right, something&#13;
&#13;
like 230 million pounds, and the Egyptian offer I think was 11 million&#13;
&#13;
pounds, so that's the sort of bracket that we were confronted with.&#13;
&#13;
      Well, we --&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   -- what was the relation between either of these figures and the&#13;
&#13;
values of the shares on the Paris Bourse the day before nationalization?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   I think -- well, the value of the shares on the Paris Bourse was&#13;
&#13;
much nearer the Egyptian offer, of course, than to the company's&#13;
&#13;
proposal.   I've forgotten actually what the value of the shares on the&#13;
&#13;
Bourse was at that particular time.&#13;
&#13;
      Well, anyway, we started off with talks with the Egyptians on the&#13;
&#13;
one hand, and the representatives of the shareholders on the other, the&#13;
&#13;
Egyptians in Cairo and the representatives of the shareholders in Paris.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                    - 39 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                            Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Eventually we decided that the only thing to do was to try to get these&#13;
&#13;
people together around a table.    And I proposed a meeting of the two&#13;
&#13;
sides to be held in Rome.    And they both accepted.    We got them together&#13;
&#13;
there.    We had the Egyptian representatives on this side and we had the&#13;
&#13;
representatives of the company on that side, Mr. Woods and myself&#13;
&#13;
sitting at the top of the table in between them.       And till I held my&#13;
&#13;
first meeting with the Indians and the Pakistanis in connection with the&#13;
&#13;
Indus negotiation, I don't think I have ever sat in a more tense&#13;
&#13;
atmosphere in my life.&#13;
&#13;
        Well, we asked the Egyptians to open their case, which they did,&#13;
&#13;
and they had brought with them as part of their delegation a very, very&#13;
&#13;
competent Egyptian lawyer and he developed the legal case of the&#13;
&#13;
Egyptians for the nationalization.    Then we asked the other side for&#13;
&#13;
their comments.    They presented their legal case, and attempted to show&#13;
&#13;
that the Egyptians had got absolutely no right under international law&#13;
&#13;
or anything else to carry out this nationalization.&#13;
&#13;
        So I took the floor and I said, â&#128;&#156;Now, look, gentlemen, this is all&#13;
&#13;
very interesting.â&#128;?    (It took three days while these submissions were&#13;
&#13;
being made from the two sides!)    At the end of it I said, â&#128;&#156;Well,&#13;
&#13;
gentlemen, this is all very interesting, but I think the real issue&#13;
&#13;
before us is this, if I may bring it down to rather mundane terms.&#13;
&#13;
Whatever the legal issues may be that are involved here, this is a&#13;
&#13;
question of compensation that we're discussing, and I think what we&#13;
&#13;
ought to get down to is this:    (a) How much are you Egyptians prepared&#13;
&#13;
to offer? and (b) What are you people on the other side prepared to&#13;
&#13;
take?    Irrespective of what legal issues may be involved.â&#128;?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   - 40 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                        Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Well, we then got down to pencil sharpening and calculations of one&#13;
&#13;
kind or another.   Mr. Woods and I went back and forth from Rome to&#13;
&#13;
Cairo, Cairo to Paris, Paris to Rome, and we finally got to a point&#13;
&#13;
where we had narrowed the gap very, very considerably, and we had got&#13;
&#13;
this position established, that Egypt would keep everything of the&#13;
&#13;
company's former properties in Egypt, including the cash balance; the&#13;
&#13;
company would retain all its assets outside Egypt, and in addition the&#13;
&#13;
Egyptians undertook to put up a certain amount, a flat sum, by way of&#13;
&#13;
compensation, over and above these two elements I'm talking about.&#13;
&#13;
     Well, we knew that the company was prepared to abate very, very&#13;
&#13;
substantially the original demands that they had put in.   We also knew&#13;
&#13;
that this ante of the Egyptians was not their last word.   By this time&#13;
&#13;
we had a fairly narrow bracket, and at that point, Mr. Black had been, I&#13;
&#13;
think, in Rhodesia, and he was coming back to London and to Washington.&#13;
&#13;
We got him to come through Cairo, and we had an interview with President&#13;
&#13;
Nasser, and at that interview Nasser agreed to up the Egyptian ante to&#13;
&#13;
the figure that was subsequently embodied in the compensation agreement.&#13;
&#13;
That was accepted by the company, and then all that remained really was&#13;
&#13;
to draw up the actual text of the international agreement.&#13;
&#13;
     Well, that took a lot of very hard and very detailed work, and in&#13;
&#13;
this I had great assistance from Mr. Elsworth Clark, who's now one of&#13;
&#13;
the assistant general counsels at the Bank.   And we eventually got the&#13;
&#13;
treaty signed in Geneva on the 13th of July, 1957, I think it was.    My&#13;
&#13;
memory's gone very bad.&#13;
&#13;
     I remember, on one of the last meetings that Mr. Woods and I had&#13;
&#13;
with the Egyptian delegation in Cairo, a very amusing incident happened,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  - 41 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                           Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
but if any future historian of the Bank would want to give the light of&#13;
&#13;
day to this particular incident, I hope that he'll first of all get the&#13;
&#13;
permission of Mr. George Woods.&#13;
&#13;
      The Egyptians had been very difficult on this particular morning,&#13;
&#13;
and they had been chiseling a lot at certain proposals that we had put&#13;
&#13;
up to them as, in our view, an appropriate approach to this problem.&#13;
&#13;
Mr. Woods had listened to them very patiently for about three quarters&#13;
&#13;
of an hour, and he suddenly got up from the table where he and I were&#13;
&#13;
sitting, and he walked over into a far corner of the room, and he put&#13;
&#13;
his hand underneath the lapel of his coat and he scratched his shoulder,&#13;
&#13;
in a very characteristic gesture of his which always indicates that some&#13;
&#13;
devastating remark is about to come out.     He came back to the table and&#13;
&#13;
he sat down, and he looked at the Egyptians on the other side of the&#13;
&#13;
table and he said, â&#128;&#156;Look here, gentlemen, don't you realize that you&#13;
&#13;
have made the greatest steal in history since the Dutch bought Manhattan&#13;
&#13;
from the Indians for 20 bottles of gin?      Stop your chiseling!â&#128;?   And the&#13;
&#13;
Egyptians did stop their chiseling.    That was one of the breaks that we&#13;
&#13;
had in this particular situation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   I understand that even after this agreement had been signed, there&#13;
&#13;
still came up some question of compensation for real estate that had not&#13;
&#13;
been known about, and Mr. Black had to go back yet again to see Mr.&#13;
&#13;
Nasser about this.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Well, that was not in relation to any of the Canal properties.&#13;
&#13;
That question arose out of the general financial settlement between the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                    - 42 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                          Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
government of the United Kingdom on the one hand and the Egyptian&#13;
&#13;
government on the other.   And this dealt with properties of British&#13;
&#13;
nationals that also had been nationalized by the Egyptians as part of&#13;
&#13;
their general nationalization program.     And there had been direct&#13;
&#13;
conversations going on between the United Kingdom and Egypt about this&#13;
&#13;
for months, and very little progress was made.    In fact, I might say no&#13;
&#13;
progress at all, and it looked as though the whole thing was going to&#13;
&#13;
break down, and Mr. Black was then asked to come in in his personal&#13;
&#13;
capacity and see what he could do to get this straightened out.     He did,&#13;
&#13;
and finally a financial agreement between the government of the United&#13;
&#13;
Kingdom and the Egyptian government was signed, providing for&#13;
&#13;
compensation for these British properties.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   That was completely apart?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Completely apart from the Suez thing -- although of course the&#13;
&#13;
British government was a 44-percent stockholder in the Suez Canal&#13;
&#13;
Company.   But in the Suez compensation negotiations, they didn't&#13;
&#13;
intervene at all.   They left their interests to be handled by the&#13;
&#13;
â&#128;&#156;shareholders' delegation.â&#128;?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   I was going to ask also whether or not the Egyptians raised the&#13;
&#13;
question of compensation on account of the British and French invasion,&#13;
&#13;
whether this was related in any way?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  - 43 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                           Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   That was produced by the Egyptians, not in relation to the Canal&#13;
&#13;
issues at all, but in relation to the governmental financial settlement&#13;
&#13;
between the Egyptians and the United Kingdom.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Over property?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Yes.   They put in a compensatory claim for the damage that had&#13;
&#13;
been done -- at Port Said, for example.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Did you personally or representatives of your Bank have anything to&#13;
&#13;
do with that particular negotiation?&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   No, Mr. Black himself handled that negotiation, assisted, by the&#13;
&#13;
way, by Mr. Sommers.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Did the Egyptians or anybody else for that matter raise the question&#13;
&#13;
of arbitration, or submitting the question to a Court of International&#13;
&#13;
Justice, or anything like this?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   No.    No.   I don't think this was an issue that could have got to&#13;
&#13;
a court.   I think the International Court of Justice is always reluctant&#13;
&#13;
to pronounce on disputes between a government on the one hand and&#13;
&#13;
private interests on the other.     That's a point, though, that the Bank&#13;
&#13;
has really been quite concerned about the question of the lack of&#13;
&#13;
machinery for resolving disputes between governments and private&#13;
&#13;
interests, and we have been called in on several -- for example, Suez&#13;
&#13;
for one.   Just at the moment we have another one on our plate, where the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     - 44 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                          Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Colombian government has officially approached us, and has asked us to&#13;
&#13;
mediate a dispute that they have with a Canadian company, Parsons and&#13;
&#13;
Whittemore Inc., who supplied some machinery to the Colombian government&#13;
&#13;
during the days of the dictatorship.   The Colombian government gave them&#13;
&#13;
notes evidencing liability to pay for this machinery.   These notes were&#13;
&#13;
discounted by the company with the Bank of America, and the present&#13;
&#13;
Colombian government dispute the terms of the contract.    So we have now&#13;
&#13;
three parties in this thing, the Colombian government, the Canadian&#13;
&#13;
company, and the Bank of America, all of whom are interested, and all&#13;
&#13;
three of them have come to us and asked us to extend our good offices to&#13;
&#13;
see if we can mediate a mutually satisfactory solution.&#13;
&#13;
      Now, we get into this thing I think as much for this reason as any&#13;
&#13;
other, that there isn't any appropriate machinery today, either in the&#13;
&#13;
field of conciliation or in the field of arbitration, that can settle&#13;
&#13;
these disputes.   As a matter of fact, it's a subject that we have under&#13;
&#13;
critical examination in the Bank at the moment, to see whether or not we&#13;
&#13;
can come up with some proposal, not necessarily that the Bank should do&#13;
&#13;
it, because it's really outside of our regular routine.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Is there any machinery for settling disagreements between the Bank&#13;
&#13;
and one of its borrowing countries, concerning the interpretation of the&#13;
&#13;
loan agreement, let's say?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Well, there are arbitration provisions actually in the loan&#13;
&#13;
agreement.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  - 45 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                         Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Who would arbitrate, is it specified?   Or just specified that the&#13;
&#13;
matter would be settled by arbitration?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   You know, I'm ashamed to say I don't know who would arbitrate,&#13;
&#13;
but there is a provision for arbitration.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Is there anything more you'd care to say about Suez or Egypt in&#13;
&#13;
general?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   No, except that in view of my former interest in Egypt and&#13;
&#13;
former association with Egypt, I was very glad that I was able to play&#13;
&#13;
some part anyway in getting this very troublesome issue settled.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   What has been the Bank's attitude since then toward the high dam?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Well, as you know, after the West pulled out, the Egyptians went&#13;
&#13;
to the Soviets, and the Soviets have now undertaken -- the Russians have&#13;
&#13;
now undertaken to finance and construct the project, and it's going&#13;
&#13;
ahead.&#13;
&#13;
Q:   If the Egyptians should need some additional financing somewhere&#13;
&#13;
along the way, do you think the Bank would be reluctant to help on&#13;
&#13;
account of the fact that the Soviets are involved?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Well, I think, the Soviets having started, I think we'd let them&#13;
&#13;
finish it.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  - 46 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                         Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   How about the Indus matter?   Would you say a bit about it?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   - 47 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                           Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Interview with Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
By Prof. Robert Oliver                                    August 16, 1961&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Interview # 2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Continuing on the subject of the Bank's excursions into efforts&#13;
&#13;
at mediation, of course, probably the largest and certainly the most&#13;
&#13;
onerous job that we've had to do in that field, during the time I've&#13;
&#13;
been with the Bank anyway, has been on mediation in the Indus waters&#13;
&#13;
dispute between India and Pakistan.   Now, one might well ask how the&#13;
&#13;
Bank got into that particular subject.      Well, of course, we had been&#13;
&#13;
right from the start of our operations interested in the development of&#13;
&#13;
both India and Pakistan, who together, population-wise anyway, probably&#13;
&#13;
comprise about half the total population of the underdeveloped world,&#13;
&#13;
and if development was to go ahead, it was very necessary that we should&#13;
&#13;
find a situation where there were not matters such as serious disputes&#13;
&#13;
with economic consequences between the two countries.     This Indus&#13;
&#13;
dispute, so far anyway as Pakistan was concerned, was quite a serious&#13;
&#13;
menace, for this reason, that the whole of west Pakistan depends for its&#13;
&#13;
agricultural development on the supply of water from the six rivers of&#13;
&#13;
the Indus system.   Now, all of these rivers rise in Indian territory, or&#13;
&#13;
if they don't rise in Indian territory they all flow through Indian&#13;
&#13;
territory before they reach Pakistan.    After independence and after the&#13;
&#13;
boundary between the two new dominions, as they then were, was drawn,&#13;
&#13;
the boundary was drawn right across the river system, and Pakistan&#13;
&#13;
became the downstream riparian on every one of them.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   - 48 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                        Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Now, that gave India the physical power to divert the water of&#13;
&#13;
these rivers and prevent the historic flow of water coming down to&#13;
&#13;
Pakistan.   I don't mean to suggest that there was any deliberate policy&#13;
&#13;
on India's part to do so, but nevertheless she had the physical power to&#13;
&#13;
do it if she chose.&#13;
&#13;
     Well, in fact, very shortly after partition, there was some&#13;
&#13;
interference by the Indian engineers on the Indian side of the border&#13;
&#13;
with some of the canals that took off from in India and carried water&#13;
&#13;
down into Pakistan.   This created very serious concern in the minds of&#13;
&#13;
the Pakistan government, and a very tense situation indeed arose.    If&#13;
&#13;
Pakistan was deprived of her canal water from the Indus system, the&#13;
&#13;
whole of west Pakistan would really become a desert.&#13;
&#13;
     As I say, a very tense situation arose, and at times there was even&#13;
&#13;
a danger of a shooting war along the frontiers.   Now, I think it was&#13;
&#13;
during the winter of 1950-51 that Mr. David Lilienthal, a former&#13;
&#13;
chairman of the Tennessee Valley Authority, paid a visit to the Indian&#13;
&#13;
subcontinent, and he spent some time in the Punjab, which is the part of&#13;
&#13;
the Indian subcontinent which is irrigated by this Indus system of&#13;
&#13;
rivers.   He was there at a moment when the water situation was really&#13;
&#13;
quite tense, and when he returned to the United States he wrote a very&#13;
&#13;
well-informed article which was published in Colliers Magazine, and the&#13;
&#13;
line that he took was something like this: that it was really quite&#13;
&#13;
stupid that these two countries should quarrel about how the waters of&#13;
&#13;
the Indus were to be apportioned between them, and they ought to forget&#13;
&#13;
about political considerations, and engineers from both sides ought to&#13;
&#13;
sit down round the table and work out a comprehensive development plan&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  - 49 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                         Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
to not merely distribute the waters of the Indus system between the two&#13;
&#13;
countries, but also to develop them beyond the extent to which the&#13;
&#13;
irrigation system had been developed already.    Now, that, Mr. Lilienthal&#13;
&#13;
realized, would require the construction of quite a large and expensive&#13;
&#13;
system of works, and he suggested that it would be an ideal operation&#13;
&#13;
for the World Bank to go into the financing of these works.&#13;
&#13;
     Well, this particular article caught Mr. Black's eye, and Mr. Black&#13;
&#13;
felt that here was a situation in which perhaps the Bank could make some&#13;
&#13;
contribution, and accordingly he wrote a letter to Mr. Nehru, the Prime&#13;
&#13;
Minister of India, and to the then Prime Minister of Pakistan, offering&#13;
&#13;
the Bank's good offices to work out a comprehensive plan of irrigation&#13;
&#13;
development roughly along the lines that Mr. Lilienthal had indicated.&#13;
&#13;
     Well, both Prime Ministers accepted the Bank's offer, and thereupon&#13;
&#13;
a working group was set up, a working group of engineers, engineers from&#13;
&#13;
Pakistan, engineers from India, and a team of engineers from the Bank&#13;
&#13;
headed by General Wheeler, who has been associated with the Bank for&#13;
&#13;
many years as engineering advisor and consultant.&#13;
&#13;
     The team of engineers worked hard for two years, and they did a lot&#13;
&#13;
of valuable work in collecting necessary hydrological and engineering&#13;
&#13;
data about the basin, but it became apparent that the real issue here&#13;
&#13;
was, how were the waters to be divided?    How many million acre feet, to&#13;
&#13;
use the technical term, were to go to India, and how many million acre&#13;
&#13;
feet were to go to Pakistan?   And it became obvious that if we didn't&#13;
&#13;
get some agreement on that particular point, it was quite hopeless to&#13;
&#13;
try to work out any comprehensive engineering plan.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  - 50 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                        Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     So General Wheeler, with the approval of the management of the&#13;
&#13;
Bank, finally put forward a Bank proposal for the division of the&#13;
&#13;
waters, and his proposal was this -- that the waters of the three&#13;
&#13;
eastern rivers, which up till then had irrigated not only parts of India&#13;
&#13;
but also parts of Pakistan, that these three eastern rivers should go to&#13;
&#13;
India; that the three western rivers should go to Pakistan; that a&#13;
&#13;
system of works should be constructed which would carry water from the&#13;
&#13;
western rivers down into the area of Pakistan, which had hitherto been&#13;
&#13;
irrigated by the eastern rivers, and that that system of works should be&#13;
&#13;
paid for by India.   It was realized that this system of works would take&#13;
&#13;
some years to complete, and therefore that there should be a transition&#13;
&#13;
period during which India's inroads on the eastern rivers should be&#13;
&#13;
regulated to take account of the speed with which Pakistan could replace&#13;
&#13;
from the western rivers the water that she had hitherto got from the&#13;
&#13;
eastern rivers.&#13;
&#13;
     Well, this proposal was accepted by India, with certain minor&#13;
&#13;
reservations.   Pakistan was very reluctant to accept it because the Bank&#13;
&#13;
proposal did not indicate that there would be any provision for&#13;
&#13;
reservoir storage on the Pakistan side, and Pakistan felt that it was&#13;
&#13;
absolutely essential that she should have this reservoir storage to take&#13;
&#13;
care of her irrigation needs during the critical periods of the year&#13;
&#13;
when the river flow is low.&#13;
&#13;
     However, we did persuade both sides to get together again, and to&#13;
&#13;
discuss the possibilities of working out some settlement, taking the&#13;
&#13;
Bank proposal for the division of the waters as a jumping off point.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  - 51 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                        Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      Well, it was about that time that I came into the operation, almost&#13;
&#13;
on a full-time basis, and one worked for almost four and a half years&#13;
&#13;
through all sorts of vicissitudes, with all sorts of frustrations.     At&#13;
&#13;
times the whole operation very nearly blew up, but eventually, by July&#13;
&#13;
of 1959, we had reached a point where the issues that were involved had&#13;
&#13;
sharpened up, and Mr. Black and myself paid a special visit to India to&#13;
&#13;
talk with Mr. Nehru, and then subsequently to Pakistan to talk with&#13;
&#13;
President Ayub, and we then got agreement at that level to the general&#13;
&#13;
principles on which a treaty could be based.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   During these four and a half years when you were working on it by&#13;
&#13;
yourself, were you holding almost daily talks with people?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Practically daily talks throughout that period, interspersed&#13;
&#13;
with very frequent visits to India and to Pakistan.   Of course, I had&#13;
&#13;
associated with me General Wheeler as my chief technical advisor, and I&#13;
&#13;
also had associated with me a firm of New York consultants, Tibbets,&#13;
&#13;
Abbot, McCarthy and Stratton, who did the very necessary and very&#13;
&#13;
complicated hydrological studies that were required in order to know&#13;
&#13;
really just where we were going.   Every proposal that was made, for&#13;
&#13;
example, had to be tested with regard to its effect on water uses.     And&#13;
&#13;
you have no idea of the arguments that developed.   I mean, although&#13;
&#13;
there's something like 150 million acre feet, more than that, but 180&#13;
&#13;
million acre feet of water in that system, we spent days debating on a&#13;
&#13;
matter of five or ten cusecs which is probably not much more than would&#13;
&#13;
fill a good bath.   But I mean, water is as precious as that.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   - 52 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                            Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:    Did you have your family with you?     Were you living all the time in&#13;
&#13;
--?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:    No.   Well, on one occasion, when I spent about two months in the&#13;
&#13;
subcontinent, my wife came with me on that particular trip.      But&#13;
&#13;
otherwise I went back and forth leaving my family here.&#13;
&#13;
       However, on this question of the preciousness of water, I remember&#13;
&#13;
an incident that happened in the course of one of my trips to the&#13;
&#13;
subcontinent.    This was down in Sindh, which is the southern province of&#13;
&#13;
West Pakistan, and one evening at a dinner party I was talking to the&#13;
&#13;
police superintendent of the area in which we happened to be at the&#13;
&#13;
time, I hadn't got anything about water or the Indus in my mind, and I&#13;
&#13;
said to the superintendent, â&#128;&#156;By the way, Superintendent, what's the main&#13;
&#13;
cause of crime in your area?â&#128;?&#13;
&#13;
       And he said to me, â&#128;&#156;Sir, there are two.     Water and women, in that&#13;
&#13;
order.â&#128;?   Which gives one an idea of the importance; you see, they&#13;
&#13;
attached to this particular commodity.&#13;
&#13;
       But as I say, after this trip that Mr. Black and myself undertook,&#13;
&#13;
we did get agreement to the general terms on which a treaty could be&#13;
&#13;
based.    But the terms of the settlement involved the construction of a&#13;
&#13;
very elaborate system of works, something like, I think it's about 300&#13;
&#13;
or 350 miles of canals to carry water from the western rivers down into&#13;
&#13;
the eastern rivers, the construction of two very large reservoirs, one&#13;
&#13;
on the Jhelum River in Pakistan and one on the Indus, also in Pakistan,&#13;
&#13;
and a third reservoir on the Beas River in India.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                    - 53 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                          Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Well, the total cost of this system of works was estimated as&#13;
&#13;
something over one million dollars, and it was quite clear that&#13;
&#13;
financing of that magnitude was quite beyond the unaided efforts of the&#13;
&#13;
two countries that were concerned.    So the next problem was, and this&#13;
&#13;
went on simultaneously with our treaty negotiations, to try and raise&#13;
&#13;
from those countries which were interested in India and Pakistan&#13;
&#13;
development, and also in the maintenance of reasonably good relations&#13;
&#13;
between the countries -- we had these negotiations, to attempt to raise&#13;
&#13;
the necessary funds to construct this system of works.    Well, that took&#13;
&#13;
quite a bit of doing.   However, we eventually succeeded, and&#13;
&#13;
contributions were offered and committed by Australia, Canada, Germany,&#13;
&#13;
New Zealand, the United Kingdom and the United States and the World Bank&#13;
&#13;
of course undertook also to put in a substantial amount of money.&#13;
&#13;
     Now, so far as the works in Pakistan are concerned, they are all&#13;
&#13;
being financed out of what is called the Indus Basin Development Fund,&#13;
&#13;
and these contributions that have been offered by the various&#13;
&#13;
contributing governments find their way into that fund.    The Bank&#13;
&#13;
administers it, and we disburse from the fund the expenditures on the&#13;
&#13;
construction of the works as they are carried out.   Now, the reservoir&#13;
&#13;
that is being constructed in India, that is not being financed out of&#13;
&#13;
the Indus Basin Development Fund.    It will be financed directly so far&#13;
&#13;
as the foreign exchange costs are concerned, by the Bank and the United&#13;
&#13;
States government, on the basis of a loan, and the local expenditure&#13;
&#13;
will be by the government of India.    Now, the establishment of this&#13;
&#13;
Indus Basin Development Fund, that was insured by an international&#13;
&#13;
financial agreement which was signed actually at the same time as the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                    - 54 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                           Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
treaty.   So as I say, these two negotiations were going on&#13;
&#13;
simultaneously.   We, the Bank, trying to get the Indians and the Paks&#13;
&#13;
together on the basis of a treaty, and simultaneously we, the Bank,&#13;
&#13;
trying to organize this consortium, perhaps I'd better call it, of&#13;
&#13;
countries that were prepared to put finance into the settlement&#13;
&#13;
arrangements.&#13;
&#13;
     Well, we -- even after we had agreed with India and Pakistan as to&#13;
&#13;
the general basis of the treaty, we had about another 15 months actually&#13;
&#13;
working out the detailed text of the agreement, and that was finally&#13;
&#13;
achieved by the end of August of 1960.      The treaty was a very imposing-&#13;
&#13;
looking document.   It's extremely complicated.     I remember, just before&#13;
&#13;
the treaty signature, I was having a conversation with Mr. Nehru, the&#13;
&#13;
Prime Minister of India, who told me that the night before he had been&#13;
&#13;
reading over the treaty and he said there was one particular section&#13;
&#13;
which he just couldn't understand.    He said to me, â&#128;&#156;I wonder if you&#13;
&#13;
could explain this to me?â&#128;?&#13;
&#13;
     I said, â&#128;&#156;Well, Prime Minister, this rather reminds me of a story&#13;
&#13;
that's told of the poet, Robert Browning.      He was at a dinner party one&#13;
&#13;
night and found himself sitting beside a very attractive young woman who&#13;
&#13;
was a great admirer of his works, and this young woman said to him, â&#128;&#152;By&#13;
&#13;
the way, Mr. Browning, I wonder if you'd mind explaining to me the&#13;
&#13;
meaning of a particular passage in your poem, Sordello?â&#128;&#153;     It's a very&#13;
&#13;
obscure poem anyway.   And Browning's reply to her was, â&#128;&#152;My dear, when&#13;
&#13;
Sordello was written, only God and Robert Browning knew what it meant,&#13;
&#13;
and now only God knows.â&#128;&#153;â&#128;?    I said to Mr. Nehru, â&#128;&#156;I'm afraid I find&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   - 55 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                          Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
myself almost in the same situation with regard to this passage in the&#13;
&#13;
treaty.â&#128;?&#13;
&#13;
      It's a very complicated subject, as you can readily understand.&#13;
&#13;
      Well, we eventually got to the stage of signature, and the treaty&#13;
&#13;
signing ceremony was held in Karachi on I think the 13th of September,&#13;
&#13;
1960, when Mr. Nehru signed for India, President Ayub signed for&#13;
&#13;
Pakistan, and I signed for the Bank, because there are certain aspects&#13;
&#13;
of the treaty settlement with which the Bank was concerned.    The Indus&#13;
&#13;
Basin Development Fund Agreement was signed of course by representatives&#13;
&#13;
of the various contributing governments.     And that we hope has put the&#13;
&#13;
Indus water dispute to bed -- in fact, more than put it to bed, because&#13;
&#13;
that rather suggests it may waken again tomorrow morning.    I hope it's&#13;
&#13;
buried it.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   I still have some difficulty in understanding what on earth you all&#13;
&#13;
talked about for the 4 1/2 years?    Was the whole thing made much more&#13;
&#13;
difficult because of personal animosities between the Pakistanis and the&#13;
&#13;
Indians?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   No, I wouldn't say that that had really anything to do with it.&#13;
&#13;
Of course, each side was -- well, I said earlier that in that particular&#13;
&#13;
area, water is a very, very precious commodity, and India was not&#13;
&#13;
prepared without a fight to give up even one single cusec; Pakistan&#13;
&#13;
found herself in the same position.    There were all sorts of questions&#13;
&#13;
that arose here.   For example, was India to be allowed to construct&#13;
&#13;
storage on the western rivers?   Now, the construction of storage on the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                    - 56 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                          Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
western rivers can be a positive benefit to Pakistan, from the&#13;
&#13;
irrigation point of view, because that means that in India where the&#13;
&#13;
best of the storage sites are, water could be stored in the flood season&#13;
&#13;
and released during the dry season and let down to Pakistan, which we of&#13;
&#13;
course would be of enormous value to Pakistan from the irrigation point&#13;
&#13;
of view.   But Pakistan said, â&#128;&#156;Well, now, look, we appreciate this, but&#13;
&#13;
we would find it impossible to agree to the construction of any works&#13;
&#13;
upstream from us on these three rivers that you're allotting to us, if&#13;
&#13;
those works would give India the power to turn off a tap and stop supply&#13;
&#13;
of water coming down to us.â&#128;?&#13;
&#13;
     Now, that was the kind of situation that cropped up.    The same&#13;
&#13;
thing arose in relation to hydroelectric developments.    There's a very,&#13;
&#13;
very substantial hydroelectric potential in these western rivers.&#13;
&#13;
Power, of course, is a very much-needed commodity in both India and&#13;
&#13;
Pakistan, but there again Pakistan is quite unwilling to allow any hydro&#13;
&#13;
installation where it might be used to hurt her, if relations between&#13;
&#13;
the two countries deteriorated for some reason quite unconnected with&#13;
&#13;
water.&#13;
&#13;
     So now that meant that it sometimes took literally months in order&#13;
&#13;
to work out designs, engineering designs, either for reservoir storage&#13;
&#13;
or for hydro works which India might or would be permitted to construct&#13;
&#13;
under the treaty.   That was very time consuming.   Then, I mentioned&#13;
&#13;
earlier that when the Bank put in those proposals for the waters, India&#13;
&#13;
had accepted it with minor reservations.   Well, now, this minor&#13;
&#13;
reservation was for the development of additional uses, irrigation uses,&#13;
&#13;
in Kashmir.   So here we were in the Kashmir situation.   Now, the three&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  - 57 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                          Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
western rivers which were being allotted to Pakistan all flow through&#13;
&#13;
Kashmir, and the Indian position was that we can't pin down Kashmir to&#13;
&#13;
just the irrigation uses that she has had, we would like to develop some&#13;
&#13;
additional uses.    Now, Pakistan was in something of a political&#13;
&#13;
difficulty here.    On the one hand, she wanted to get as much -- well,&#13;
&#13;
all of the western river waters really for herself -- but if she had to&#13;
&#13;
take a position denying additional irrigation uses to Kashmir, she would&#13;
&#13;
have been very vulnerable vis-Ã -vis the Kashmiris.    So the Pakistan&#13;
&#13;
proposal was:    â&#128;&#156;Well, all right, if you Indians want to develop these&#13;
&#13;
additional uses in Kashmir, where you've no right to be anyway because&#13;
&#13;
you never ought to be there, you can do it out of the western rivers.&#13;
&#13;
But you must compensate us by a corresponding split of the eastern&#13;
&#13;
rivers.â&#128;?   Well, there was no future at all in that, and again here there&#13;
&#13;
was literally months of controversy went on, but we finally did arrive&#13;
&#13;
at a formula under which India was entitled to develop on an average&#13;
&#13;
basis so many additional acres of irrigation in the Indian-occupied part&#13;
&#13;
of Kashmir.&#13;
&#13;
     Now, that led us into the question, Pakistan said, â&#128;&#156;Well, how do we&#13;
&#13;
know that India won't develop more than this?     We must have a system of&#13;
&#13;
inspection.â&#128;?    India said, â&#128;&#156;Certainly not.   We've put our name to a&#13;
&#13;
treaty, you've got to accept that we are going to carry out that treaty,&#13;
&#13;
and we're not going to have any action of the government of India&#13;
&#13;
policed by Pakistan.â&#128;?&#13;
&#13;
     Well, we got that one compromised eventually, on this sort of&#13;
&#13;
basis, that the treaty provides for the appointment of a permanent Indus&#13;
&#13;
Commission, to consist of a representative appointed by the government&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   - 58 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                        Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
of India, one appointed by the government of Pakistan, and those two&#13;
&#13;
commissioners have got complete freedom to inspect works on any of the&#13;
&#13;
rivers in the system.   Now, Pakistan didn't regard that as entirely&#13;
&#13;
satisfactory, but in our view it was a very, very important step&#13;
&#13;
forward, and we strongly recommended to Pakistan that they ought not to&#13;
&#13;
break on this issue and ask for any more.&#13;
&#13;
      Well, I don't think it's worth my going into the various other&#13;
&#13;
detailed points that arose from time to time.   They're all really rather&#13;
&#13;
complicated engineering and hydrological points.   But I mean, one got&#13;
&#13;
into questions for example of how much rainfall was there in this little&#13;
&#13;
particular area of about seven square miles, and can't you, with all&#13;
&#13;
that rainfall coming down there, do you need any irrigation water at&#13;
&#13;
all? and so on.   Days were consumed in studying these rainfall&#13;
&#13;
statistics, and also statistics of transpiration, as they call it.     Oh,&#13;
&#13;
it was all a highly technical process.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   How about power development in connection with this project?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Well, in the settlement plan, there's provision in the Mangla&#13;
&#13;
Dam for I think it was 250 kilowatts of power, that's on the Pakistan&#13;
&#13;
side, and 200 kilowatts in the Beas Dam on the Indian side.   So apart&#13;
&#13;
from the irrigation benefits that flow from the thing -- and there's a&#13;
&#13;
certain element of flood control in that too.   I mean, if you trap these&#13;
&#13;
waters during the flood season, you do minimize to some extent anyway&#13;
&#13;
the serious risk of floods that there always is in that particular area.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  - 59 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                            Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   But there wasn't any problem of dividing power, resulting from the&#13;
&#13;
project?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   No.   The power that will be produced in India will be consumed&#13;
&#13;
in India.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Any point costs of the operation or difficulty in deciding who would&#13;
&#13;
pay what?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Well, India will pay.   The figure has just slipped my mind for&#13;
&#13;
the moment.    I think it's 175 million dollars toward the cost of the&#13;
&#13;
construction of these works in Pakistan, and that amount will be paid&#13;
&#13;
into the Indus Basin Development Fund.       Yes, it's 175 million dollars.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   There must have been some difficulty I should think in reaching that&#13;
&#13;
figure, if it was going to be on the Pakistan side.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   That was a separate negotiation in itself, as between the Bank&#13;
&#13;
and India.     Pakistan of course didn't care whether India was putting up&#13;
&#13;
anything or not so long as the system of works was being constructed at&#13;
&#13;
no cost to herself.    But when I say she didn't mind if India was putting&#13;
&#13;
up nothing, she was less concerned with what India was going to put up&#13;
&#13;
than whether or not she (Pakistan) was going to get the whole system of&#13;
&#13;
works.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                    - 60 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                          Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Would you care to say a bit about how the Bank arranged for the&#13;
&#13;
consortium to finance all this?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Well, when we realized what the cost of this system of works was&#13;
&#13;
going to be, we informally got in touch with the various governments&#13;
&#13;
that we thought might be likely to ship in some financial assistance,&#13;
&#13;
and when we got an indication that in principle they were prepared to do&#13;
&#13;
so, then we called a meeting, I mean, put the thing on a much less&#13;
&#13;
informal basis.   We called together what I might call really an&#13;
&#13;
intergovernmental working party of representatives of these various&#13;
&#13;
countries here in Washington, and we worked with them.    Now, don't ask&#13;
&#13;
me how we split the cost, as between countries A, B, C, and D.     That was&#13;
&#13;
very much plucking the figure out of the air.     We said to ourselves,&#13;
&#13;
â&#128;&#156;Well, we think country A can afford so much.     On the basis of that&#13;
&#13;
country B ought to put out so much,â&#128;? and so on.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   These were put up as straight grants, were they not?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Everything that comes from the governments, except the&#13;
&#13;
government of the United States, is in a straight grant form.     The&#13;
&#13;
government of the United States is putting up 175 million dollars in&#13;
&#13;
grants, and the rest she's putting up in the form of loans which are&#13;
&#13;
payable in local currency.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   About the same thing as another grant, then.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  - 61 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                         Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Yes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   How did the Bank decide what proportion of the total it was prepared&#13;
&#13;
to finance on a straight loan basis?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Well, I think there again, we pulled a figure largely out of the&#13;
&#13;
air, but of course we were having some regard to Pakistan's capacity to&#13;
&#13;
repay hard foreign debt, and we were very anxious to keep the Bank's&#13;
&#13;
contribution down, not so much because we didn't want to invest Bank&#13;
&#13;
funds, but because we didn't want to impose an excessive hard currency&#13;
&#13;
repayment on Pakistan.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   I take it Pakistan is very near the limit of its credit worthiness.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   She's about there now.   So is India, as a matter of fact, for&#13;
&#13;
that matter, with these additional credits that have been extended under&#13;
&#13;
these recent consortia arrangements.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Well, are there any matters other than the Indus that you would like&#13;
&#13;
to report for history?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Well, I have no doubt that Mr. Black mentioned his own personal&#13;
&#13;
intervention in the Anglo-Egyptian financial dispute.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Very sketchily -- if there is something you can add about this, I&#13;
&#13;
think it would be worthwhile.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   - 62 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                          Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Well, I thought I'd mentioned this before.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   No, we didn't talk about the land settlements so much.   We talked&#13;
&#13;
about the Suez settlement.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Well, after the Suez settlement, of course, there was still&#13;
&#13;
outstanding the financial differences between Egypt and the United&#13;
&#13;
Kingdom, arising on the one hand out of the Egyptian nationalization of&#13;
&#13;
British properties in Egypt, and on the other hand, Egypt's claims&#13;
&#13;
against the United Kingdom, arising out of the Suez incident.    There had&#13;
&#13;
been direct negotiations between the -- although they were not in&#13;
&#13;
diplomatic relationship, there were ad hoc direct negotiations conducted&#13;
&#13;
between the two governments over quite some months, that really didn't&#13;
&#13;
get very far, and eventually they called Mr. Black in, in his personal&#13;
&#13;
capacity, to sort the thing out, and after conversations, both with the&#13;
&#13;
Egyptian government and with the government of the United Kingdom, Black&#13;
&#13;
made a proposal, and they accepted it.     The settlement was drawn up on&#13;
&#13;
that basis.&#13;
&#13;
      Well, then the other intervention in which Mr. Black was concerned&#13;
&#13;
was the -- I don't know whether he mentioned this one or not -- was the&#13;
&#13;
settlement of a very longstanding dispute between the city of Tokyo and&#13;
&#13;
some French bond holders.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   I've heard it mentioned by that title but nobody's said very much&#13;
&#13;
about it.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  - 63 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                         Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Well, this was quite a complicated issue.   I wasn't very closely&#13;
&#13;
in touch with this particular operation myself.   I'm afraid I don't know&#13;
&#13;
the details of it, but they did call in Mr. Black to suggest an&#13;
&#13;
arrangement that in his view was equitable so far as both sides are&#13;
&#13;
concerned, and he did so.   And as I think I mentioned already, within&#13;
&#13;
the last few days we have been asked by the Colombian government to&#13;
&#13;
settle a dispute that has arisen there.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:    Now, this business of distinguishing between Mr. Black in his own&#13;
&#13;
personal capacity and the World Bank as an official mediator intrigues&#13;
&#13;
me.   How is it decided when one is to be done, or the other is to be&#13;
&#13;
done?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Well, I think we approach that very empirically.   I think Mr.&#13;
&#13;
Black really makes up his mind as to whether it's appropriate that he&#13;
&#13;
should do this in his personal capacity.    Of course, he's really doing&#13;
&#13;
it as President of the World Bank, but institutionally the Bank is not&#13;
&#13;
involved, if you go in on that sort of fiction.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:    Could it be said that the Bank only becomes involved as a mediator&#13;
&#13;
if financing of something is important to the mediation?    As it was in&#13;
&#13;
Indus, for example?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Well, yes, although I think the same situation arose really in&#13;
&#13;
relation to the Anglo-Egyptian financial arrangement, because you see&#13;
&#13;
until Egypt and the United Kingdom had settled their financial&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   - 64 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                          Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
differences, we weren't prepared to lend any money.    There was a&#13;
&#13;
situation where Egypt had nationalized and hadn't paid any compensation,&#13;
&#13;
at least compensation on a scale acceptable to the other side.    And yet&#13;
&#13;
that was a case where Mr. Black's personal intervention was sought.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Were you involved in any way in the mediation attempts in Iran, the&#13;
&#13;
Iranian oil dispute?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:    No.   No, that was unsuccessful --&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   -- that was the earliest one, though?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:    That was the earliest one, yes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   And this was a case where the Bank didn't have any financing to be&#13;
&#13;
undertaken as a consequence of settlement, even if there had been one?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:    No, but I suppose you can say this, that unless that was settled&#13;
&#13;
we were not prepared to lend any money, so that -- I mean, Bank&#13;
&#13;
financing would have to follow and not precede a settlement.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   I wonder if I might ask one last very broad question which I like to&#13;
&#13;
ask almost everybody.     It kind of gives them a chance to appraise the&#13;
&#13;
whole sweep of history of the Bank.     What are the similarities and&#13;
&#13;
contrasts between Mr. McCloy's term of office and Mr. Black's term of&#13;
&#13;
office?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                    - 65 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                          Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Well, of course, Mr. McCloy took over the affairs of the Bank at&#13;
&#13;
a very early stage of our growth.    He took it over when I think it's&#13;
&#13;
fair to say that the political situation around the world was still in a&#13;
&#13;
pretty unsettled state, where it was very difficult to say what sort of&#13;
&#13;
financial and economic pattern was going to emerge not only in some of&#13;
&#13;
these new countries, like India and Pakistan, but even in how the war&#13;
&#13;
was going to affect some of the older countries.   Also, there was the&#13;
&#13;
question of how far the Bank was going to be able to go in raising&#13;
&#13;
money, because at that time our capital -- I think it was only the&#13;
&#13;
United States and Canada, during Mr. McCloy's regime, that had released&#13;
&#13;
what we call the 18 percent capital subscription for use by the Bank in&#13;
&#13;
its operations.    There may have been some small releases by some of the&#13;
&#13;
other countries.   So that if we were going to loan on any substantial&#13;
&#13;
scale, the only source of funds that we could have had was the capital&#13;
&#13;
markets, and at that time substantially the only capital market that was&#13;
&#13;
open to us was the capital market of the United States.    So Mr. McCloy&#13;
&#13;
found himself faced really with a situation where the first thing to be&#13;
&#13;
done was perhaps not so much to develop the lending operations of the&#13;
&#13;
Bank as to develop the Bank's capacity to borrow funds.    And of course,&#13;
&#13;
in that he had tremendous assistance from Mr. Black.   Black was at that&#13;
&#13;
time as you know the United States Executive Director, and this was his&#13;
&#13;
principal chore.   I mean, he devoted most of his time to introducing&#13;
&#13;
Bank securities into the financial markets of the United States, and I&#13;
&#13;
think that's a tremendous job that he did for the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
     Well, then, of course, after Mr. Black took over as President the&#13;
&#13;
situation did alter, in the sense that the sort of political and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                    - 66 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                          Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
economic and financial patterns in the Bank member countries had begun&#13;
&#13;
to emerge.   We were in a position to make better assessments of the&#13;
&#13;
situation; simultaneously we were able to borrow money.    We were in a&#13;
&#13;
situation where we were reasonably confident that we could borrow money&#13;
&#13;
if we wished to do it.&#13;
&#13;
     Another point I ought to mention is that during Mr. McCloy's time,&#13;
&#13;
which was very soon after the war, member countries really had not begun&#13;
&#13;
to work out their development programs along any sane lines.    Most of&#13;
&#13;
them had no notion whatever about how to prepare even a simple project&#13;
&#13;
for financial and economic and technical analysis.   So there was an&#13;
&#13;
education job to be done among our member countries.   And all that began&#13;
&#13;
to take time -- took time, rather -- but as that began to take shape,&#13;
&#13;
the opportunities for Bank lending, the opportunities for Bank&#13;
&#13;
borrowing, all developed and made it much easier for us to cooperate on&#13;
&#13;
a more substantial scale than we had done during the earlier years of&#13;
&#13;
the Bank's existence.&#13;
&#13;
     Of course, Mr. McCloy, during his time when we took his plunge of&#13;
&#13;
going into Western Europe, as you know, to the tune of half a billion&#13;
&#13;
dollars -- this was just before the Marshall Plan -- but I mean, once&#13;
&#13;
the Marshall Plan came into existence, the opportunities for Bank --&#13;
&#13;
well, there wasn't really any necessity for Bank lending in Europe.     And&#13;
&#13;
it had already become evident that the financial requirements of Western&#13;
&#13;
Europe for reconstruction were on a scale far beyond what the Bank would&#13;
&#13;
have found it possible to meet.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  - 67 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                         Sir William Iliff&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      So I wouldn't -- I don't think any inferences really ought to be&#13;
&#13;
drawn from the fact that during Mr. McCloy's regime, Bank lending was at&#13;
&#13;
a much lower tempo than it subsequently reached.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Was there any difference between the two administrations in their&#13;
&#13;
relations to staff, or just the way they ran the Bank itself?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Iliff:   Well, of course, we were a very much smaller organization during&#13;
&#13;
Mr. McCloy's time, and Mr. McCloy found it possible, and Mr. Garner also&#13;
&#13;
found it possible to devote much more time to the details of a&#13;
&#13;
particular operation than Mr. Black would find it possible to do.     So&#13;
&#13;
Mr. Black has been disposed to -- well, I think he's a believer in this,&#13;
&#13;
that if you keep a dog, don't do your own barking, so to speak -- I&#13;
&#13;
mean, he has picked his team very carefully, and he has confidence in&#13;
&#13;
them, and he's prepared to let them get on with the job.   But at the&#13;
&#13;
same time, in matters of really important Bank policy, of keeping his&#13;
&#13;
fingers on the pulse.   But he's less disposed to concern himself with&#13;
&#13;
the intimate details about a lending operation.    And of course it was&#13;
&#13;
probably -- it was certainly much more necessary in the earlier days of&#13;
&#13;
the Bank, that even the details of an operation should be kept under&#13;
&#13;
pretty careful review by the management.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   This is the end of the second tape of Sir William Iliff.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  - 68 -&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="17973518">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1961/08/17973518/transcript-oral-history-interview-sir-william-iliff-held-august-12-16-1961
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1961/08/17973518/transcript-oral-history-interview-sir-william-iliff-held-august-12-16-1961</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1961/08/17973518/transcript-oral-history-interview-sir-william-iliff-held-august-12-16-1961</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2009-03-09T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2009-03-09T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2013/07/08/000356161_20130708153748/Rendered/INDEX/790470TRN0Ilif0gust0120and016001961.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2013/07/08/000356161_20130708153748/Rendered/PDF/790470TRN0Ilif0gust0120and016001961.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>1961-08-16T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2013-07-08T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Transcript of oral history interview with
            Sir William Iliff held on August 12, and 16, 1961
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            In August 1961, Sir William Iliff was
            interviewed on behalf of the World Bank Group Archives oral
            history program by Robert Oliver. During his tenure at the
            Bank from 1948 to 1962, Sir Iliff worked in the following
            areas: in the loan department as director (1948-1951); as
            assistant to the president (1951-1956); and as vice
            president to the World Bank and the Internal Development
            Association (1956-1962). When he joined the World Bank in
            1948, its membership consisted of only 48 member countries.
            His transcript concerns the origins of the loan department,
            a loan to Chile, and how the loan department was really the
            engine room of the World Bank.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Transcript of oral history interview with
            Sir William Iliff held on August 12, and 16, 1961
        </docna>
        <display_title>Transcript of oral history
            interview with Sir William Iliff held on August 12, and 16, 1961</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/1961/08/17973518/transcript-oral-history-interview-sir-william-iliff-held-august-12-16-1961</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Transcript</docty>
        <subtopic>Access to Finance,Public Sector Corruption &amp;
            Anticorruption Measures,Corporate Law,Debt Markets,Banks &amp; Banking Reform</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Law and Development,Public Sector Development</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000356161_20130708153748</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>World Bank Group Archives oral history program</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Law and Development,Public Sector Development</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Board Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            arbitration, assets, balance of payments,
            Bank borrowing, Bank financing, Bank lending, Bank of
            England, Bank policy, board meetings, bond, bond holders,
            borrower, borrowing, Bourse, capital market, capital
            markets, cash balance, cash balances, Chamber of Commerce,
            chief executive, company, confidence, corporate finance,
            Corporation, credit worthiness, credits, crime, debt burden,
            debt service, defaults, development bank, development banks,
            earnings, economic development, economic policy, equipment,
            expenditure, expenditures, external debt, financial
            assistance, financial institutions, financial management,
            financial markets, financial patterns, foreign debt, foreign
            exchange, government ownership, hard loans, holding,
            International Court, International Finance, international
            law, investment banking, Justice, lawyer, liability, lien,
            Loan, loan agreement, loan agreements, loan application,
            loan officer, loan officers, local currency, maturity,
            Minister, Ministers, outstanding debt, police, political
            stability, preferential, present value, private capital,
            private enterprise, public utilities, real estate,
            reorganization, repayment, reserves, securities, settlement,
            shareholders, source of funds, stockholder, stockholders,
            Treasury, treaty, Union, woman
        </keywd>
        <owner>Knowledge &amp; Information Services (ITSKI)</owner>
        <repnb>79047</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Science and Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Policy Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Policy Formulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Policy Implementation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Productivity-Led Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Flood Control</ml:concept><ml:concept>Flood Control and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Flood Mitigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Flood Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Flood Protection and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Flood Rehabilitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Floods and Droughts</ml:concept><ml:concept>Policy Coordination</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corporate Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nationalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Enterprise Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>State Owned Enterprise Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>State-Owned Enterprise Restructuring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deconcentration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delegation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Devolution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sub-National Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subnational Government and Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>External Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Use</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Engineering</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Treaties</ml:concept><ml:concept>Treasury</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Examinations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Flood Protection</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>Arbitration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Center of Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Balance of Payments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>State Owned Enterprises</ml:concept><ml:concept>Administrative Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Mediation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>