<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>ï»¿                                                                         79129&#13;
                                                                         v4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
THE WORLD BANK GROUP HISTORIAN'S OFFICE .&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            ORAL HISTORY PROGRAM&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
             Transcript of interview with&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                 ERNEST STERN&#13;
&#13;
      December 16 &amp; 29, 1994, January 5, 1995                    ;....&#13;
                                "1"   â&#128;¢         .;"&#13;
                                 ;-&lt;.;Â·"Â· " .   Â·'Â· â&#128;¢â&#128;¢&#13;
                                                         '   t&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 By: Jochen Kraske Louis Galambos &amp; David Milobsky&#13;
&amp;#12;                      Interview with Ernest Stern&#13;
                             The World Bank&#13;
                            January 20, 1995&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   You were just telling us that in reflecting on what we&#13;
&#13;
talked   about   in   the   previous     session,   you   thought     of    the&#13;
&#13;
circumstances which had brought you to look into the Indian&#13;
&#13;
procurement issue. Would you like to tell us a little bit about&#13;
&#13;
what you thought?&#13;
&#13;
A:   Upon reflection,       the answer to your question about the&#13;
&#13;
Indian   procurement     problem    is    that   there    was   no   obvious&#13;
&#13;
connection between that problem and my job. I knew some of the&#13;
&#13;
Indian officials in the Ministry of Finance well, having served&#13;
&#13;
in India before I came to the Bank;          I knew the Bank; and here&#13;
&#13;
was a problem which seemed to be a perennial irritant in Bank-&#13;
&#13;
Indian relations and impeded important Bank assistance. The&#13;
&#13;
Qnly reason for my involvement that I can identify is that I&#13;
&#13;
don't believe I       ever had been much concerned about formal&#13;
&#13;
assignments. So I believe that without any particular mandate&#13;
&#13;
or anybody asking me to do it, I became interested in the issue&#13;
&#13;
and tried to solve it. In that case, successfully.&#13;
&#13;
     That approach is also the reason I showed you this box, a&#13;
&#13;
commemorative gift from the Secretary of Agriculture of what&#13;
&#13;
was then West Pakistan.       And what he was thanking me for also&#13;
&#13;
was an intervention outside my regular responsibilities as the&#13;
&#13;
Deputy Director of the USAID Mission. In those days, IRRI-8, a&#13;
&#13;
high-yielding    rice    variety,   was     being   introduced       in    East&#13;
&amp;#12;                                     Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 2&#13;
Pakistan,     (now Bangladesh),      because of the availability of&#13;
&#13;
irrigated land and an ample water supply. Toward the end of the&#13;
&#13;
planting season, in East Pakistan, 80 tons of the new seed was&#13;
&#13;
left over.       In West Pakistan,    they had been growing Basmati&#13;
&#13;
rice, a high quality rice principally produced for export. The&#13;
&#13;
Secretary of Agriculture in the Provincial Government of West&#13;
&#13;
Pakistan was an entrepreneurial man who wanted to try the highÂ·-&#13;
&#13;
yielding IRRI-8 that he had heard about. But the seed was in&#13;
&#13;
the East, and he was in the West, and shipment by sea around&#13;
&#13;
India    would     take weeks    and would   not   arrive   in   time   for&#13;
&#13;
planting.     He came to see me and told me about this dilemma. I&#13;
&#13;
found a way to use some of AID's rupee accounts, which enabled&#13;
&#13;
the Ministry to charter an airplane, and transport the seed to&#13;
&#13;
West Pakistan in time to introduce it during the sowing season.&#13;
&#13;
That was the beginning of a major development in non-Basmati&#13;
&#13;
rice production in West         Pakistan, which today is an important&#13;
&#13;
crop.&#13;
&#13;
        I mention this only to illustrate that my intervention in&#13;
&#13;
the India procurement issue was not so unusual. Well before I&#13;
                                                                               ...&#13;
                                                                              .,&#13;
&#13;
came    to   the   Bank,   my   style was   not   to be   constrained by&#13;
&#13;
bureaucratic compartments when it came to solving a problem. I&#13;
&#13;
was not an agricultural specialist and I was not in charge of&#13;
&#13;
seed production but I recognized that there was a problem and&#13;
&#13;
used the resources available to me to deal with it.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                           Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 3&#13;
Q:     You facilitated a solution.&#13;
&#13;
A:     I was a facilitator. Right.&#13;
&#13;
Q:     Any other reflections that you had?&#13;
&#13;
A:     As I       tried to construct my farewell                speech,    I   thought&#13;
&#13;
about the question you raised, which I had at first rejected&#13;
&#13;
out of     hand,         about   how my personal background might have&#13;
&#13;
affected my career decisions. Why did I go into development,&#13;
&#13;
and stay so long?           On further reflection, I now think there may&#13;
&#13;
well   have       been      a    link    with   my    wartime      and    immigration&#13;
&#13;
experiences.         I    have    always    felt     much    compassion        for   the&#13;
&#13;
underdog, a great interest in trying to help eliminate inhumane&#13;
&#13;
conditions, great poverty, health problems, etc.&#13;
&#13;
       I favor practical, concrete steps to dealing with issues;&#13;
&#13;
being skeptical about the latest theories                       to solve today' s&#13;
&#13;
problem.      I am averse to over-intellectualizing and excessive&#13;
&#13;
zeal, particularly in the social sciences where it is easy to&#13;
&#13;
lose one's reality anchor.                And above all, I have grave doubts&#13;
&#13;
about our ability to predict what will happen with sufficient&#13;
&#13;
precision to be operationally meaningful and hence am not fond&#13;
&#13;
of grand visions.&#13;
&#13;
       We had much discussion recently in the Bank about our 50th&#13;
&#13;
anniversary. Having completed 50 years, everybody wanted to&#13;
&#13;
know what the Bank would do in the next 50 years,- which I&#13;
&#13;
consider      a    totally       inane    question.      I   was    quoted by The&#13;
&amp;#12;                                         Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 4&#13;
&#13;
Economist, as responding to the question of what came after the&#13;
&#13;
50th,       by saying "the 51st". The Economist thought this was&#13;
&#13;
terrible and demonstrated a deplorable lack of vision.                        People&#13;
&#13;
around the Bank thought it was amusing and clever, I know.                       But&#13;
&#13;
I did not mean this to be a flippant remark. I meant.to convey&#13;
&#13;
that        there   are    very   few   things   in    the    world    which    are&#13;
&#13;
permanent, except flux, and that anybody who thinks he can sit&#13;
&#13;
down and sketch out what the world is going to look like 50&#13;
&#13;
years        from   now,    which   obviously     is    the    first     step     in&#13;
&#13;
determining what           the World Bank will be doing               then,    as a&#13;
&#13;
serious basis for action, is either ignorant or delusional.&#13;
&#13;
        Obviously one wants to know broadly where one is going. I&#13;
&#13;
think we in the Bank know broadly where we are going.                           The&#13;
&#13;
question then becomes: How can the Bank be helpful in solving&#13;
&#13;
today' s      problems,     this year's problems,        encountered by the&#13;
&#13;
policy makers of our member countries? So, yes, after the 50th&#13;
&#13;
comes the 51st.&#13;
&#13;
        Q:      Looking over the past, do you think that the world's&#13;
&#13;
problems were, to a considerable degree, economic in origin.&#13;
&#13;
There was a strong feeling based on reflections on the inter-&#13;
&#13;
war period, the first and second wars, that if economic changes&#13;
&#13;
had been made they might have prevented what were terrible&#13;
&#13;
political consequences?&#13;
&#13;
A:      I    don't believe that theory very much.              I   think mankind&#13;
&amp;#12;                                             Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 5&#13;
goes to war because by and large we are only partially and&#13;
temporarily civilized.               I am aware of the theory that if war&#13;
&#13;
reparations had not deprived Germany of resources, and if the&#13;
&#13;
protectionism          of    the     inter-war          period    had     not     stifled&#13;
&#13;
international          trade,       there    would        not    have    been     massive&#13;
&#13;
unemployment and inflation in Germany, and we would not have&#13;
&#13;
seen the rise of Nazism.&#13;
&#13;
        Of course economic factors can contribute to developments&#13;
&#13;
of this kind but generally I think they are used to rationalize&#13;
&#13;
decisions          taken    on    quite     different      grounds.       And,     in   all&#13;
&#13;
probability, those factors added to the impetus of political&#13;
developments during the Weimar Republic. But, after all, it was&#13;
&#13;
not the first time that Germany had gone to war with France (or&#13;
&#13;
vice versa), nor was it the first time a political leader had&#13;
&#13;
sought        geographic         expansion    by        aggression      with     national&#13;
&#13;
support. If we look at the wars in the developing world since&#13;
then,     I    do    not    think    economic       conditions          have     been   the&#13;
&#13;
principal cause. None of which is to gainsay the proposition&#13;
that people and societies which are relatively better off may&#13;
&#13;
have less reason, and may show less tendency,                            to go to war.&#13;
&#13;
However, it does not stop them from going to war, as we can see&#13;
&#13;
in   Yugoslavia,           which    was     one    of    the    better     off     of   the&#13;
&#13;
developing countries, or in Ireland.&#13;
        So,    I    don't    think poverty or economic                  factors     are   a&#13;
&amp;#12;                                        Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 6&#13;
&#13;
primary cause of wars.         They can be contributing factors. Nor&#13;
&#13;
does   being wealthy prevent            people       from going    to war,      but&#13;
&#13;
perhaps it reduces the probability of armed conflict.&#13;
&#13;
Q:     We are going to leap to the reorganization of the Bank in&#13;
&#13;
1987. We would like you to talk about that a little bit, and&#13;
&#13;
perhaps     compare   it   with       the   reorganization        of   1972,    and&#13;
&#13;
consider these two reorganizations in that kind of framework.&#13;
&#13;
A:     As you must     know,      I   wasn't     a   great   fan of     the    1987&#13;
&#13;
reorganization.&#13;
&#13;
Q:     We are aware of that.&#13;
&#13;
A:     Mr. Conable once was heard to say, not in my hearing, so&#13;
&#13;
this is hearsay, that       ~e    had to reorganize the World Bank to&#13;
&#13;
get rid of Ernie Stern. A srange compliment. Even though that&#13;
&#13;
may not have been true, it certainly seemed part of the flavor&#13;
&#13;
of the exercise.&#13;
&#13;
       The 1987 reorganization and its implementation was not&#13;
&#13;
thought through.       We had a President who had never managed&#13;
&#13;
anything,    let alone something as big as the Bank. He had no&#13;
&#13;
particular interest in managing the Bank nor in learning how to&#13;
&#13;
manage it. He came to the Bank and heard about the difficulties&#13;
&#13;
his predecessor had had recently with the Board on the budget.&#13;
&#13;
He also saw the organizational structure we had in place and,&#13;
&#13;
I suppose, my influence in the Bank. Relying on his Republican&#13;
&#13;
mandate,    he may have felt committed to limit my influence,&#13;
&amp;#12;                                            Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 7&#13;
&#13;
although I am neither a Republican nor a Democrat. There was a&#13;
&#13;
lot    of   talk   about     furthering         the    country          focus    of     Bank&#13;
&#13;
operations-- a slogan that no one in the Bank much disagreed&#13;
&#13;
with; indeed there were a lot of people who thought we already&#13;
&#13;
had a country focus. In any event, Mr. Conable decided it had&#13;
&#13;
to be sharpened.&#13;
&#13;
       Aside     from   that,          he   seemed     to       have    no    particular&#13;
&#13;
substantive objective in mind, except change for the sake of&#13;
&#13;
change. He hired a consultant firm which most people had never&#13;
&#13;
heard of, and he did not give his consultants much guidance.&#13;
&#13;
He set up staff task forces, explicitly excluding the Bank's&#13;
&#13;
senior managers.        One can certainly hold the view that managers&#13;
&#13;
are bound to be hidebound.                    On the other hand,                they have&#13;
&#13;
experience which might at least bear on continuity and the&#13;
&#13;
proposals for structural changes. The reorganization was a kind&#13;
&#13;
of a revolution from the bottom up, and the outcome was more or&#13;
&#13;
less   predictable.          It    culminated         in    a    final       stage    where&#13;
&#13;
everybody in the Bank lost their jobs and became subject to&#13;
&#13;
reappointment. A traumatic way of eliminating less than 10% of&#13;
&#13;
the work       force.   Lots      of    changes      took place.             People were&#13;
&#13;
assigned to jobs for which they had no known experience.                              Files&#13;
&#13;
disappeared,       offices      were        disorganized,         the    Bank     was    in&#13;
&#13;
turmoil.    And the termination packages were generous so the&#13;
&#13;
exercise was financially expensive too.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                        Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 8&#13;
&#13;
Q:     Were there no controls over the process?&#13;
&#13;
A:     No.     Personnel systems were dismantled, reporting systems&#13;
&#13;
disappeared, and it was, I think this is a fair description,&#13;
&#13;
pretty chaotic.&#13;
&#13;
Q:     What replaced the reporting systems?&#13;
&#13;
A:     Not much.      I guess it was not something Mr. Conable was&#13;
&#13;
interested in.&#13;
&#13;
Q:     As a quintessential operating man, you must have been just&#13;
&#13;
dismayed by what was being done to Operations.&#13;
&#13;
A:     I was.     And I certainly wasn't alone, although there also&#13;
&#13;
were a lot of people who thought the concept was right,                   that&#13;
&#13;
this       was what we needed     to do,      and   that   it would not be&#13;
&#13;
disruptive. But, aside from the country focus, which I thought&#13;
&#13;
was there in the first place, although maybe not as clear as it&#13;
&#13;
might have been,          the reorganization on balance caused much&#13;
&#13;
damage. A good part of the monitoring and control systems were&#13;
&#13;
dismantled;      initially, we had a rocky time with our lending&#13;
&#13;
operations;      business practices and personnel systems became&#13;
&#13;
less       transparent.   There   was    an   explosion    of   front   office&#13;
&#13;
staffs.       We lost control of our grading structure (grade creep&#13;
&#13;
set in) further adding to costs and staffing inefficiency.&#13;
&#13;
       I retired to Finance.&#13;
&#13;
Q:     I    know that.      But you are       still watching all of       this&#13;
&#13;
happen. So the reorganization began to impact very quickly on&#13;
&amp;#12;                                 Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 9&#13;
lending policy?&#13;
&#13;
A:   I    was no longer involved in lending policies.            At the&#13;
&#13;
outset the President and others tried to insist that I,              as&#13;
&#13;
Senior Vice President for Finance, should remain as a member of&#13;
&#13;
the "Statutory Loan Committee", the Committee which certifies&#13;
&#13;
that each loan is consistent with the Bank's Articles.              The&#13;
&#13;
Senior VP Finance had not been a member before. This was an&#13;
&#13;
effort to keep me associated with the lending operations for&#13;
&#13;
symbolic purposes-in name only. I asked that this be changed&#13;
&#13;
and ultimately    I   refused   to   sign because   I   had no    other&#13;
&#13;
association with the loan process. And I was not about to sign&#13;
&#13;
off on matters of which I had no substantive knowledge.&#13;
&#13;
     In other words, I was no longer involved in the details of&#13;
&#13;
Operations, and I cannot tell you what did or did not happen to&#13;
&#13;
the quality issues,     except as     seen from a distance.       There&#13;
&#13;
certaiÂ·nly were a lot more people doing what fewer people had&#13;
&#13;
done before,    without any evidence that the result was any&#13;
&#13;
better.&#13;
     So when we came to the reorganization of 1991, when Mr.&#13;
&#13;
Preston arrived, a large part of that reorganization consisted&#13;
&#13;
of cleaning out front offices of Senior Vice Presidents because&#13;
&#13;
they had grown so very large.&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Now,    this reorganization started in October of 1986 and&#13;
&#13;
extended into the summer of '87. Throughout this period, you&#13;
&amp;#12;                                     Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 10&#13;
were in charge of Operations, as you had been before and in&#13;
&#13;
constant contact with Conable, what interaction did you have&#13;
with Conable in this period?&#13;
&#13;
A:      On the reorganization? No interaction at all.                Conable&#13;
&#13;
excluded the senior staff from any discussion of where he was&#13;
&#13;
headed or why he was headed that way, or anything else.                   There&#13;
&#13;
was no consultation.&#13;
&#13;
        The decisions were taken by Conable, with Bill Stanton and&#13;
&#13;
a couple of other people in the President's office. He relied&#13;
&#13;
on the recommendations of a number of task forces which were&#13;
&#13;
pulled together by Kim Jaycox who was the head of the overall&#13;
&#13;
task force. However,       the results were never discussed in the&#13;
&#13;
President's Council or with the Senior Vice Presidents as a&#13;
&#13;
group.&#13;
Q:      So you learned about the results of this reorganization&#13;
&#13;
only when the decisions had been more or less taken?&#13;
&#13;
A:      Yes. Well,    towards the end of the process some people,&#13;
&#13;
working in the task forces, would come around and talk about&#13;
&#13;
their     concerns.    That    was    before      they    had   arrived     at&#13;
&#13;
conclusions.     Towards      the    end    of   the     process,   the    new&#13;
&#13;
organizational matrix emerged.             But   even then there was no&#13;
&#13;
discussion with the President that I ever was part of, nor I&#13;
&#13;
think were any other members of the President's Council. Nor&#13;
&#13;
did Mr.Conable ever deign to discuss my reassignment with me&#13;
&amp;#12;                                   Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 11&#13;
&#13;
personally -that was done through an emissary.&#13;
&#13;
Q:    If you look at the '72 reorganization as McNamara changed&#13;
&#13;
the Bank, the people who came up in that process were people&#13;
&#13;
dedicated to McNamara's objectives for the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
A:    That   reorganization   was     pefore    my   time;   actually   it&#13;
&#13;
happened just as I came but I knew too little of the Bank to&#13;
&#13;
have any perspective on it. But yes, I think McNamara sought&#13;
&#13;
out kindred souls.&#13;
&#13;
Q:    So what happened in '87?      Who came up?     Who benefited from&#13;
&#13;
the reorganization in terms of power in the Bank?&#13;
&#13;
A:    Well, as you know, Kim Jaycox headed the staff effort. But&#13;
&#13;
he was meticulous about not benefitting personally. Afterwards,&#13;
&#13;
he went back to being Vice President of Africa--albeit of a&#13;
&#13;
combined Region. At the next level down, there were a number of&#13;
&#13;
people who had worked on the          task forces who ended up as&#13;
&#13;
department directors. But I honestly cannot tell you how those&#13;
&#13;
decisions were made.      I went on vacation while the personnel&#13;
&#13;
decisions were being made since no input from me was wanted.&#13;
&#13;
I was in France.       I did rescue a few people from Operations&#13;
&#13;
into Finance by telephone, but I really did not have any part&#13;
&#13;
in   the   personnel   decisions    affecting    other   units.    Those&#13;
&#13;
decisions were made mostly on the basis of personal relations;&#13;
&#13;
professional qualifications had little to do with them. Ann&#13;
&#13;
Hamilton, for example, who was an outstanding division chief in&#13;
&amp;#12;                                      Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 12&#13;
the India Department, ended up as the Department Director in&#13;
&#13;
charge of Education and Human Resources Development; although&#13;
she had no background in these subjects and had never expressed&#13;
&#13;
an interest in this type of assignment. There were lots of&#13;
&#13;
those seemingly arbitrary personnel decisions.&#13;
&#13;
Q:    Again    comparing       this        reorganization        with       the   '72&#13;
&#13;
reorganization,      it    struck     me    that   the     '72   reorganization&#13;
&#13;
addressed certain obvious problems in the Bank while the '87&#13;
&#13;
reoganization seemed imposed from the outside and motivated by&#13;
&#13;
exogenous considerations.             Can you say anything about what&#13;
&#13;
might have pushed Conable to undertake this reorganization?&#13;
&#13;
Conable by his own confession did not know anything about&#13;
&#13;
management,    about      the Bank,    about development,              and yet he&#13;
&#13;
embarked on this very ambitious and intrusive exercise. The&#13;
&#13;
budget crisis experienced by Clausen was a reason for change&#13;
&#13;
referred to by Conable himself, but there must have been people&#13;
&#13;
in the U.S. Treasury or somewhere who told Conable, "This is&#13;
&#13;
what is now needed, and you've got to do it."                    This must have&#13;
&#13;
been part of his mandate, in a sense.&#13;
&#13;
A:    That has      always    been    the    speculation,        but    I   have Â·no&#13;
&#13;
information which would confirm this.&#13;
&#13;
Q:    So there wasn't any Republican Administration-led effort&#13;
&#13;
to   change   the   Bank     in ways       suitable   to   an Administration&#13;
&#13;
skeptical about       the Bank,       the nature of         the Bank and          its&#13;
&amp;#12;                                     Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 13&#13;
&#13;
function? Then what you are describing is a much more haphazard&#13;
&#13;
process.&#13;
&#13;
A:      Yes. I think the process was essentially haphazard--in the&#13;
&#13;
sense that it did not seem to be guided by any substantive&#13;
&#13;
objective of Conable's.         Anyhow, even if the speculation about&#13;
&#13;
a Republican Administration wanting to bring the Bank under&#13;
&#13;
better     control   were     right,        the   changes      would      not     have&#13;
&#13;
accomplished     much   along       these     lines.     The    number     of   U.S.&#13;
&#13;
citizens did not change as a result of the reorganization and,&#13;
&#13;
in any event, there has never been a link between nationality&#13;
&#13;
of   staff members      and   the    decisions      made       by   the   Bank.     If&#13;
&#13;
anything, the most important operational position went from an&#13;
&#13;
American to Mr. Qureshi, a Pakistani.&#13;
&#13;
        It would have been more likely that there was U.S. concern&#13;
&#13;
about the size of the organization--along the lines of "this is&#13;
&#13;
a big organization, it is out of control, and its budget has to&#13;
&#13;
be brought down." But those concerns were long-standing ones.&#13;
&#13;
Indeed,    today we are engaged in a budget reduction exercise&#13;
&#13;
because the Bank is regarded as bloated and it is of course&#13;
&#13;
larger today than it was then.&#13;
&#13;
        There were also continuous battles about salaries                         and&#13;
&#13;
staff    benefits.   And,     certainly that           was   picked up by          the&#13;
&#13;
Administration.&#13;
&#13;
        There may well have been concerns about how well the Bank&#13;
&amp;#12;                                    Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 14&#13;
&#13;
matched the interests of the Administration and Conab1e would&#13;
&#13;
have been briefed about these concerns.                  But the people who&#13;
briefed him presumably did not know much more about the Bank&#13;
&#13;
than Conable himself.        So if they expected personnel changes to&#13;
&#13;
make   a   difference   in    the   way   the    Bank     reacted   to   those&#13;
&#13;
concerns, they were kidding themselves.                That's not the way it&#13;
&#13;
could have worked or did work.&#13;
&#13;
Q:     It is disturbing to think of a restructuring that does not&#13;
&#13;
achieve your objectives.&#13;
&#13;
A:     Yes, .it is disturbing because, looking back, even now, you&#13;
&#13;
ask yourself what did this reorganization Â·achieve? It was a&#13;
&#13;
tremendous upheaval and many people were traumatized and staff&#13;
&#13;
morale was at a low.&#13;
&#13;
       Not to mention the cost of the exercise.                  Many of the&#13;
&#13;
changes which were made did not survive for long. The regions&#13;
&#13;
soon discovered that the new organizational structures were too&#13;
&#13;
fragmented.     Very quickly an effort started to reconsolidate&#13;
&#13;
the. sector operating divisions.          The early concept that you&#13;
&#13;
have one department per country never made any sense and even&#13;
&#13;
the compromise that was worked out failed. There has been a&#13;
&#13;
steady     agglomeration     of   countries     into    larger   departments&#13;
&#13;
again; today's country departments are very different from the&#13;
&#13;
original (1987) lineup.&#13;
&#13;
       There was supposed to be greater delegation of authority.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                        Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 15&#13;
&#13;
But it didn't mean anything until Preston removed the Senior&#13;
&#13;
Vice    Presidents,     because with a          Senior Vice President           for&#13;
&#13;
Operations in overall charge,               the organization remained as&#13;
&#13;
hierarchical     as    ever.     (The    same   was    true,    of    course,    in&#13;
&#13;
Finance, Economics and Administration).&#13;
&#13;
        So it is hard to see what the reorganization accomplished.&#13;
&#13;
It had a tremendous cost in terms of morale, it was expensive,&#13;
&#13;
it created long lasting problems of quality control and in&#13;
&#13;
personnel.     It     also    set    back   development        of    information,&#13;
&#13;
accounting and control systems. The Bank has still not totally&#13;
&#13;
recovered.&#13;
&#13;
        There were of course other factors which intervened and it&#13;
&#13;
would    be   wrong    to    blame   all    current    problems      on   the   '87&#13;
&#13;
reorganization.&#13;
&#13;
        But the lack of proper oversight and control was a problem&#13;
&#13;
resulting from the reorganization and continued to be a problem&#13;
&#13;
through the end of Conable's period.                  It's probably right to&#13;
&#13;
say that we would not have gotten into the mess related to the&#13;
&#13;
construction of the new headquarters building if the system of&#13;
&#13;
safeguards and controls had not been dismantled.&#13;
&#13;
Q:      Are there specific problems in the operational area that&#13;
&#13;
you would blame on this lack of control, projects that were&#13;
&#13;
picked up that were obviously not up to the standards of the&#13;
&#13;
Bank?&#13;
&amp;#12;                                     Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 16&#13;
&#13;
A:   I was not close enough to pick out any problems, except&#13;
&#13;
for the Argentine case, which we talked about last time.                 That&#13;
&#13;
was a relevant though perhaps an isolated example.&#13;
&#13;
Q:   You were shifting to the Finance complex as a result of&#13;
&#13;
the reorganization. A totally new field for you.&#13;
&#13;
A:   It was very educational.            I learned a lot.&#13;
&#13;
     Finance was not an area I knew much about. However, I was&#13;
&#13;
blessed by having people around who were very capable and&#13;
&#13;
knowledgeable,     such as Mr. Wood on the financial policy side.&#13;
&#13;
The Treasurer, Mr. Rotberg, had resigned at the time of the '87&#13;
&#13;
reorganization because he did not wish to remain subordinate to&#13;
&#13;
any Senior Vice President.          Although it scared me at the time,&#13;
&#13;
it turned out to be helpful. Gone was a superb treasurer. He&#13;
&#13;
was a very powerful personality.            However, he had been at the&#13;
&#13;
Bank a long time and he was looking for new activities since&#13;
&#13;
the regular Treasury operations posed few new challenges or&#13;
&#13;
interesting tasks. Fortunately, we found somebody who became a&#13;
&#13;
very good member of the team, Don Roth. He and I worked well&#13;
&#13;
together   and   we    complemented      each   other   well.   He was    an&#13;
&#13;
experienced banker but new at the Bank while I was old at the&#13;
&#13;
Bank but new to        the    subject.    As people who brought      fresh&#13;
&#13;
perspectives to the task, we were able to clear up a number of&#13;
&#13;
problems. When you look at things which are new to you and&#13;
&#13;
people   explain      how    they   do   things,   anomalies    appear   and&#13;
&amp;#12;                               Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 17&#13;
&#13;
questions arise. To those who have .lived with the process for&#13;
&#13;
a long time rules have become habits and the assumptions are&#13;
&#13;
accepted. We faced some problems in our Investment Department&#13;
&#13;
because people were leaving. This was a good time to go to Wall&#13;
&#13;
Street.-&#13;
&#13;
     [END OF TAPE 1, SIDE 1]&#13;
&#13;
     Shortly after Don Roth arrived, a group of senior people&#13;
&#13;
left the Investment Department.       This provided an opportunity&#13;
&#13;
to look at our investment guidelines and to change the culture&#13;
&#13;
of the Department. We found, to our amazement, that there were&#13;
&#13;
no guidelines for what the traders were or were not allowed to&#13;
&#13;
do, and that we.did not have a very systematic appproach to&#13;
&#13;
managing risk.&#13;
&#13;
Q:   This is a subject of very general interest in the United&#13;
&#13;
States today.&#13;
&#13;
A:   In the Bank,   don't   forget,    we   are supposed to   run a&#13;
&#13;
"plain vanilla" financial operation.        We are not supposed to&#13;
&#13;
have speculators in our Investment Department; we do not take&#13;
&#13;
positions on currencies. We maintain a large liquidity as a&#13;
&#13;
matter of policy in order to ensure the availability of cash&#13;
&#13;
for loan disbursements and bond repayments in case we run into&#13;
&#13;
market access problems. So we invest very conservatively-- only&#13;
&#13;
in high-rated government or governmental agency securities.&#13;
&#13;
Most Wall Street traders would consider our investment approach&#13;
&amp;#12;                                         Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 18&#13;
&#13;
uninteresting.         And on the borrowing side, we are AAA rated,&#13;
&#13;
and we do not use complex instruments.&#13;
&#13;
      Given the Bank's conservative objectives, the evolution of&#13;
&#13;
financial markets and the rapid technological changes in the&#13;
&#13;
investment houses with which we traded, it                      was clear that our&#13;
      ...&#13;
systems were out of date and that we had no adequate investment&#13;
&#13;
framework with clearly assigned limits and responsibilities. We&#13;
&#13;
formulated detailed investment guidelines and for the first&#13;
&#13;
time presented them to the Board for discussion. They defined&#13;
&#13;
the    instruments,            the     objectives         and       the     fiduciary&#13;
&#13;
responsibilities. They specified what the Department Director&#13;
&#13;
could approve, what the Treasurer could authorize, and what the&#13;
&#13;
Senior VP had to authorize.&#13;
&#13;
      The capital market department also changed. The head of&#13;
&#13;
the   department,       Heinz        Vergin,   moved      as    a    result     of    the&#13;
&#13;
reorganization,        and I    appointed Jessica Einhorn, one of our&#13;
&#13;
first women department directors.&#13;
&#13;
      We changed our borrowing strategy and instruments.                              We&#13;
&#13;
developed global bonds,              which became a benchmark for large&#13;
&#13;
borrowers        and   thus     reduced        the    number        of    our   issues&#13;
&#13;
dramatically. We developed a number of other new instruments.&#13;
&#13;
We began to make changes in our borrowings in the Japanese&#13;
&#13;
market;     we    reduced      our    reliance       on   special        Central     Bank&#13;
&#13;
financing, and gradually closed it out.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                           Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 19&#13;
     We     simplified     the       procedures       to     obtain      consent       from&#13;
governments to enter capital markets.                      As you know, when we&#13;
borrow we have to get the consent of governments, both covering&#13;
&#13;
the currency of the issue and the market in which we borrow.&#13;
&#13;
     We    streamlined      our      Board presentations.                    It was    the&#13;
&#13;
practice to have every borrowing authorized by the Board. Of&#13;
&#13;
course, when you were pricing a bond issue it was not always&#13;
&#13;
possible    to    wait    for    a    scheduled Board meeting.                  So,    not&#13;
&#13;
infrequently, special Board meetings had to be called. Since&#13;
&#13;
the pricing was not within the control of the Board anyway, we&#13;
&#13;
changed     the   practice,          shifting        instead       to    a    quarterly&#13;
&#13;
authorization      to borrow within             specific       cost      ranges..     Each&#13;
&#13;
quarter we then reported on the transactions which had been&#13;
&#13;
executed in the preceeding quarter.&#13;
&#13;
     But the most important change we introduced was the reform&#13;
of our currency management.                This is a technically complicated&#13;
&#13;
subject and may not be of broad interest. But the impact on the&#13;
&#13;
financial     position     Â·of       our    borrowers        was     large     and     the&#13;
&#13;
transparency of the system was much improved. We used to be&#13;
&#13;
able to decide on the currency of disbursement.                                When the&#13;
borrower gets a loan, it is denominated in dollar equivalents,&#13;
&#13;
but the Bank was free to choose the currencies in which actual&#13;
&#13;
disbursements      were    made.       And     the    Bank     had      the    right    to&#13;
&#13;
determine the repayment of currencies within the amortization&#13;
&amp;#12;                                    Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 20&#13;
&#13;
schedule at our discretion. So the borrower never knew which&#13;
&#13;
currency he would have to pay in, in the next billing period&#13;
&#13;
and his currency risk was essentially indeterminable.&#13;
&#13;
     Moreover, we borrowed dollars which we kept in our liquid&#13;
&#13;
assets and which during the '70s and '80s yielded high returns.&#13;
&#13;
We disbursed "hard currencies," e. g. Yen, DM, Swiss Franc,&#13;
&#13;
which we could borrow at relatively low interest rates. The&#13;
&#13;
rate on our loans was set not by the cost of funds used for&#13;
&#13;
loan disbursements but on the cost of funds of all borrowings,&#13;
&#13;
including   funds      kept   in   liquidity.    As   the   low   interest&#13;
&#13;
currencies appreciated against the dollar our borrowers bore&#13;
&#13;
the full cost of the exchange rate changes since, by and large,&#13;
&#13;
the declining dollar was only a small portion of their loans.&#13;
&#13;
The Bank's net income, however, benefitted from the high dollar&#13;
&#13;
interest rates.&#13;
&#13;
     In other words, there were two problems. First, we did not&#13;
&#13;
transmit the currency basket we were borrowing equally to every&#13;
&#13;
borrower.   So   the    effective    cost   of   borrowing    could   vary&#13;
&#13;
substantially     depending on the currencies actually disbursed&#13;
&#13;
on a specific loan. Second, we made the borrowers carry the&#13;
&#13;
cost of the borrowing which went into liquidity and used to&#13;
&#13;
generate investment income. But our borrowers did not benefit&#13;
&#13;
from the Bank's investment income except very indirectly and&#13;
&#13;
tangentially as higher net income added to our reserves and our&#13;
&amp;#12;                                 Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 21&#13;
&#13;
creditworthiness.&#13;
&#13;
        The big change in currency management was to deal with&#13;
&#13;
those issues.      First, we fixed the currency composition of the&#13;
&#13;
disbursement pool for a five year period, and all borrowers&#13;
&#13;
would receive disbursement in the same fixed ratio of dollars,&#13;
&#13;
Yen and the DM group, (Deutschmarks, Swiss Francs and the Dutch&#13;
&#13;
guilders).    Every borrower would know his          foreign   exchange&#13;
&#13;
liabilities with reasonable precision and could hedge their&#13;
&#13;
liabilities. Second, we separated the borrowing for liquidity&#13;
&#13;
purposes_from the borrowing needed to disburse against loans.&#13;
&#13;
This meant that our decisions on which currencies to keep for&#13;
&#13;
cash flow or investment reasons, would not affect the lending&#13;
&#13;
rate.    The stabilized disbursement pool, with an interest rate&#13;
&#13;
reflecting the actual cost of funds actually received by all&#13;
&#13;
borrowers, made our borrowing members much happier; They no&#13;
&#13;
longer     faced   large   potential   fluctuation    in   their   debt&#13;
&#13;
repayment obligations.&#13;
&#13;
        It also was a much more equitable system.&#13;
&#13;
        This change took a lot of work because of the complexity&#13;
&#13;
of the Bank's financial structure. Some of this complexity is&#13;
&#13;
inherent in the Bank's Articles of Agreement but others were&#13;
&#13;
self-induced. For instance, I discovered that we were keeping&#13;
&#13;
reserves in currencies in which they had been earned on the&#13;
&#13;
assumption that this was required by the Articles.             In fact,&#13;
&amp;#12;                                  Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 22&#13;
&#13;
this was not true; it was just that it had become a habit. By&#13;
&#13;
converting our reserves into the same basket of currencies as&#13;
&#13;
our   disbursements      we   simplified         liquidity    management&#13;
&#13;
considerably.&#13;
&#13;
      Now the world has changed again and we have moved into a&#13;
&#13;
pilot operation for lending in single currencies.               The most&#13;
&#13;
sophisticated borrowers today are capable of managing currency&#13;
&#13;
risk in a way that was not true a decade ago. And they had&#13;
&#13;
rather do this themselves than have the Bank give them a pre-&#13;
&#13;
determined,    albeit balanced,      currency basket. We will,       I   am&#13;
&#13;
sure, in the years ahead move to a much larger single currency&#13;
&#13;
lending program.&#13;
&#13;
Q:    Are the Bank's borrowers more sophisticated because of&#13;
&#13;
things the Bank has done?&#13;
&#13;
A:    No,    I don't suppose so.      This is more the result of a&#13;
&#13;
general evolution. The Bank contributed to the opening of the&#13;
&#13;
markets,     including   financial    markets,     and   in   some   cases&#13;
&#13;
provided some training.       But these borrowers are the Latin&#13;
&#13;
American, and East Asian countries who have grown a lot and can&#13;
&#13;
access capital markets. As they accessed the capital markets&#13;
&#13;
they became more sophisticated in the management of the risks.&#13;
&#13;
Q:    So they have developed new technical capabilities?&#13;
&#13;
A:    Yes.    Absolutely.&#13;
&#13;
Q:    How much of these changes you introduced, especially the&#13;
&amp;#12;                                 Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 23&#13;
&#13;
change of the currency pooling system, were driven by active&#13;
&#13;
complaints and agitation by the borrowers?            And how much was&#13;
&#13;
motivated by your own sense of fairness and your efforts to do&#13;
&#13;
a better job?&#13;
&#13;
A:   I think there was a bit of both. There had been a lot of&#13;
&#13;
complaints from borrowers when the dollar turned and they were&#13;
&#13;
stuck with the substantial currency risk and the increased&#13;
&#13;
effective debt burden. Until we changed the currency pool, we&#13;
&#13;
would admit the increased debt burden due to exchange rate&#13;
&#13;
changes but     (a) would point out that the dollar rates moved&#13;
&#13;
cyclically and would even out over time and (b) to the extent&#13;
&#13;
the Bank had a higher net income we could charge lower interest&#13;
&#13;
rates or build up the reserves of the Bank and therefore its&#13;
&#13;
strength,   from which the borrowers would benefit ultimately.&#13;
&#13;
Conceptually,    of   course,   that   was   right,   but   it   was   too&#13;
&#13;
abstract and I believe a bit disingenious. It was not true for&#13;
&#13;
particular borrowers which were not governments.             Individual&#13;
&#13;
corporations or agencies might not have outstanding loans from&#13;
&#13;
the Bank for a whole exchange rate cycle. More, an operating&#13;
&#13;
agency, bank or corporation might have a cash flow problem due&#13;
&#13;
to a large yen exposure. So the argument that ultimately all&#13;
&#13;
borrowers would benefit did not turn out to be very persuasive.&#13;
&#13;
     But there was also concern about fairness. For instance,&#13;
&#13;
Jessica Einhorn was very concerned about the equity of the&#13;
&amp;#12;                               Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 24&#13;
&#13;
system and believed that as a cooperative we ought not to have&#13;
&#13;
such a mismatch between what we give the borrowers and what we&#13;
&#13;
ask back from them.      A view I   shared fully. .So I think both&#13;
&#13;
elements were at work.&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Were there any people in the Board who were very active?&#13;
&#13;
A:   Well, sometimes the subject came up. But, you know, in our&#13;
&#13;
Board not very many people worry about finance. There never&#13;
&#13;
were many people who understood the financial structure of the&#13;
&#13;
Bank. Occasionally somebody passed through a complaint from a&#13;
&#13;
country, but there was not a lot of Board pressure.&#13;
&#13;
     There were some people who participated quite actively in&#13;
&#13;
the reform, such as Murray Sherwin, the Executive Director from&#13;
&#13;
New Zealand. As a Central Banker, he understood the subject and&#13;
&#13;
was interested. But by and large, the Board was supportive of&#13;
&#13;
what we did but was not deeply involved. It remains true today&#13;
&#13;
that the finance side of the Bank does not get much attention&#13;
&#13;
in the Board.&#13;
&#13;
     Aside from the changes in currency management, investment&#13;
&#13;
procedures and borrowing procedured, among other things we did&#13;
&#13;
in Finance, we restructured the Controller's operations which&#13;
&#13;
we found in a mess.&#13;
&#13;
Q:   What was the nature of the mess?&#13;
&#13;
A:   Well, it had always been a backwater, and had not received&#13;
&#13;
much managerial attention. I found some operations still being&#13;
&amp;#12;                                       Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 25&#13;
&#13;
done with punch cards. This was 1988. Internal controls were&#13;
&#13;
weak;    reporting was not timely;             vouchers were in unsecured&#13;
&#13;
places;     there was        no monthly      financial       report.   It was   an&#13;
&#13;
astonishing situation for an institution like the World Bank,&#13;
&#13;
requiring a cleanup.&#13;
&#13;
        We did not start out very successfully. The person I had&#13;
&#13;
picked during the reorganization, by phone from France had been&#13;
&#13;
the Auditor General, Suny Carlsson. He turned out not to be a&#13;
&#13;
very good manager. It did not work out and about a year later&#13;
&#13;
he agreed         to   resign.    We got Steve Eccles,          who was Deputy&#13;
&#13;
Treasurer, to move over. He has been superb. Now I think it is&#13;
&#13;
quite a professional, modern controller operation.&#13;
&#13;
        Another        function   of   the   Finance    Complex was      Pension&#13;
&#13;
Administration. There was a big battle just at the time of the&#13;
&#13;
reorganization as the staff of the Pension Division decided to&#13;
&#13;
leave    the Bank to         form a    private   corporation to do         asset&#13;
&#13;
management. It turned out the Bank should have known about it&#13;
&#13;
because there had been a letter to the Department Director six&#13;
&#13;
or   nine    months       earlier,     announcing      the    Division   Chief's&#13;
&#13;
intention. But Finance was not the best managed outfit at the&#13;
&#13;
time and nobody seemed to have paid any attention to                        that&#13;
&#13;
letter.     So,    in November 1987,         the Bank's pension staff got&#13;
&#13;
ready to go outside to set up its own firm, as planned.&#13;
&#13;
Q:      But was that firm going to manage the Bank's pension fund?&#13;
&amp;#12;                                    Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 26&#13;
A:     No; that had not been the intention. They had new clients&#13;
&#13;
lined up.       And they were going to start their own boutique, a&#13;
&#13;
money management venture.&#13;
&#13;
Q:      This was not part of the reorganization.&#13;
&#13;
A:     Oh, no.     It had nothing to do with the reorganization.&#13;
&#13;
Q:     --because the reorganization also brought some critical&#13;
&#13;
personnel changes.       Georg Gabriel, for example, left.&#13;
&#13;
A:     But Gabriel was not managing the pension fund.           No.   This,&#13;
&#13;
this was unconnected, it just converged in time.            The pension&#13;
&#13;
staff had given notice and nobody had done anything about it,&#13;
&#13;
and so, I've forgotten when it was, October or November, they&#13;
&#13;
had clients lined up, one or two, I guess, and they decided to&#13;
&#13;
go.    And of course it didn't come at a great time.&#13;
&#13;
Q:     Right.&#13;
&#13;
A:     Because here we were laying off people and the place was&#13;
&#13;
in    turmoil.    Managing    the   pension   fund   required   technical&#13;
&#13;
skills,   and where were we going to get replacements?                  So,&#13;
&#13;
together with Martijn Paijmans,          who was Vice President for&#13;
&#13;
Personnel at the time, we worked out a contract to let the new&#13;
&#13;
firm - Strategic Investment Partners- manage our pension funds.&#13;
&#13;
But that was our idea for lack of practical alternatives.&#13;
&#13;
Q:     Really?&#13;
A:     Yes, really. Well, one can always posit a conspiracy or&#13;
&#13;
plot. It's possible.         But I don't think so.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                     Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 27&#13;
&#13;
Q:      If I were going out, that's what I would have plotted.&#13;
&#13;
A:      Perhaps. Except, they had given notice at a time when they&#13;
&#13;
could     not    have   predicted      the     scope    or     timing    of    the&#13;
&#13;
reorganization. And at that time it was only the Division Chief&#13;
&#13;
and 1-2 staff who were going to leave. But I can only tell you&#13;
&#13;
what I know. It is conceivable of course that the other staff&#13;
&#13;
members       decided   to   join    the    move   as    the    reorganization&#13;
&#13;
unfolded. In any event, I did not think we had much choice; we&#13;
&#13;
had a responsibility for about $2.5 billion.                   We negotiated a&#13;
&#13;
contract with them where they continued to do on the outside&#13;
&#13;
what they had been doing on the inside.                   Nonetheless,        this&#13;
&#13;
unleashed a tremendous furor in the Bank.                Well, you know, the&#13;
&#13;
Bank is a little antediluvian.               People thought all of their&#13;
&#13;
money was going to get lost.               There were a lot of people who&#13;
&#13;
visualized the staff of the Pension Department moving into&#13;
&#13;
their new offices with bags of our pension fund money.                        The&#13;
&#13;
fact that these people were only making investment allocations&#13;
&#13;
didn't sink in too fast.&#13;
&#13;
        Nor   did   the point,      that    these were       exactly    the   same&#13;
&#13;
individuals Bank staff had trusted before, penetrate. There was&#13;
&#13;
also an uproar in the Board. And tnere was a furious debate for&#13;
&#13;
a long time in the Pension Finance Committee, -- which is made&#13;
&#13;
up of representatives of the management, the Board, the Staff&#13;
&#13;
Association and retirees.           I inherited the Chairmanship of this&#13;
&amp;#12;                                 Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 28&#13;
&#13;
committee and it was not a very pleasant introduction. It took&#13;
&#13;
a year, a year and a half, to quiet it all down.             But, in fact,&#13;
&#13;
it all worked fine.       In    the   last   fiscal   year    (1994),   the&#13;
&#13;
pension fund h,ad a 25 percent increase in assets. So they have&#13;
&#13;
not done badly by us.&#13;
&#13;
     We    restructured   the    remaining     part   of     the   Pension&#13;
&#13;
Department to perform an oversight function. We also cleaned up&#13;
&#13;
some other items.    We began to accrue retired staff medical&#13;
&#13;
benefits, which previously had been handled on a "pay as you&#13;
&#13;
go" basis. These funds were managed internally by the Pension&#13;
&#13;
Department. So that was the great saga of the pension debate.&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Did the pension fund managers raise the yield by doing&#13;
&#13;
better, by doing new things, or by taking slightly more risk?&#13;
&#13;
A:   No.   They did not take greater risks. We did substantially&#13;
&#13;
restructure the benchmarks, putting more weight on equities and&#13;
&#13;
non-US markets generally. But I don't know that they increased&#13;
&#13;
the yield substantially over a long period of time.            Markets in&#13;
&#13;
FY â&#128;¢ 94 were good.&#13;
&#13;
Q:   That's still aÂ·lot.&#13;
&#13;
A:   Yes, but everybody did well in that year.             But they have&#13;
&#13;
been in the upper four deciles of pension fund managers.                The&#13;
&#13;
larger the pension fund becomes the harder it is obviously to&#13;
&#13;
beat the market.&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Right.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                      Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 29&#13;
&#13;
A:    But they had a very good go at it and their outstanding&#13;
&#13;
reputation is deserved. They had diversified early into non-&#13;
&#13;
U.S. markets--one of the first pension funds to so diversify--&#13;
&#13;
and caught the Japanese upswing.            But of course,          eventually&#13;
&#13;
others followed suit. Eventually, the difference between a good&#13;
&#13;
outfit and the market is not a huge number of basis points,&#13;
&#13;
particularly      if   the    asset    manager   is    expected      to   be    a&#13;
&#13;
reasonably cautious and diversified investor.&#13;
&#13;
Q:    Right.    Now, if it was said, whether true or not, that the&#13;
&#13;
'87 reorganization was to get Ernie Stern, and you have moved&#13;
&#13;
into Finance, you are right where the action is at this point.&#13;
&#13;
You   are   not    looking     like    a   person     who's   had    a    whole&#13;
&#13;
reorganization dumped on him.&#13;
&#13;
A:    Well. Don't take this out of context. Finance is not the&#13;
&#13;
center of the Bank. I was merely describing what I was doing&#13;
&#13;
where I was.      I may have accomplished a few things. But it was&#13;
&#13;
not the period which I enjoyed most in my life. It was fun to&#13;
&#13;
learn something about finance and, yes indeed, there were lots&#13;
&#13;
of things which were not what they ought to have been, so we&#13;
&#13;
got busy.      But this was not a voluntary career. shift.&#13;
&#13;
Q:    What about your relationship with Conable while you were&#13;
&#13;
doing these things?          How did that go?&#13;
&#13;
A:    Well. I was dealing with subjects which did not interest&#13;
&#13;
him much.      The Budget was not part of Finance at the time.                 He&#13;
&amp;#12;                                     Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 30&#13;
&#13;
carefully kept that to himself for obvious reasons, because the&#13;
&#13;
budget influences many things.            Our relations were cordial; I&#13;
&#13;
can't say they were intimate.            If we wanted to do things which&#13;
&#13;
did not create any conflicts, like systems improvements, it was&#13;
&#13;
fine. But if there were changes which were controversial, he&#13;
&#13;
could not be counted on.&#13;
&#13;
        One of the things we did in Finance, was to go over our&#13;
&#13;
chart of accounts and our systems architecture. Out of that&#13;
&#13;
came, what we have today, a new basic accounting system.                 From&#13;
&#13;
the beginning it had            two components,    the basic      accounting&#13;
&#13;
system and the cost accounting system.            And this, indeed, had&#13;
&#13;
been recommended by the Reorganization Task Force. They were&#13;
&#13;
supposed to be two parts of the same system, giving us for the&#13;
&#13;
first     time    cost   data   on   individual   activities.      The   cost&#13;
&#13;
accounting part was           supposed   to be handled by       the Budget&#13;
&#13;
Office.     But in the four remaining years of Conable's tenure,&#13;
&#13;
the Budget Office,         under Mr.     Picciotto,   made virtually no&#13;
&#13;
progress on this. And even though the Budget Office reported to&#13;
&#13;
Mr.   Conable, he never instructed them to get moving. So we&#13;
&#13;
entered the Preston era with a one-wing airplane.                 We had got&#13;
&#13;
the   basic      accounting     system up   and   running   but    the   cost&#13;
&#13;
accounting system did not exist.&#13;
&#13;
        Even in the workings of the basic accounting system, there&#13;
&#13;
were parts of the Bank such as Administration and Personnel,&#13;
&amp;#12;                                    Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 31&#13;
under Mr. Wapenhans, which never was prepared to change its&#13;
&#13;
procedures and work definitions during the Conab1e period to&#13;
&#13;
conform to the new system. As a result, we had to build the&#13;
&#13;
system around them because Mr. Conable would not support us&#13;
&#13;
(me) saying "Hey, fellows, here is a system; it will be Bank-&#13;
&#13;
wide; you have got to join it." It was a period of staying&#13;
&#13;
within my own bailiwick and trying to do the best I could and&#13;
&#13;
have as much fun as possible.&#13;
&#13;
Q:     But Conable was not leaning on you?&#13;
&#13;
A:     No.    Why should he?&#13;
&#13;
Q:     Well, I can think of a corporate setting, where you would&#13;
&#13;
not have been allowed to do these things, as freely.&#13;
&#13;
A:     No.     I   suppose   that   is   true,   but I     suppose    I    had a&#13;
&#13;
reputation and that helped.          Many Board members had opposed my&#13;
&#13;
removal from Operations, strongly. I guess he did not want to&#13;
&#13;
be seen as forcing me out. And, as far as he was concerned, I&#13;
&#13;
was not in a significant position.&#13;
&#13;
Q:     Why not?&#13;
&#13;
A:     Well, because he did not like confrontations, so why get&#13;
&#13;
into   one.    Having me     around      was   seen   as   a   sign   of    good&#13;
&#13;
housekeeping in some way, and having me in a place where I was&#13;
&#13;
not part of the mainstream of activities did not cost much.&#13;
&#13;
And, he didn't come from the corporate world, either. He came&#13;
&#13;
from a world where, unless you are running an election, you do&#13;
&amp;#12;                                     Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 32&#13;
not really slay your opponent, you give him a nice sinecure and&#13;
&#13;
keep him quiet. So I think that was the model that was in his&#13;
&#13;
mind.&#13;
&#13;
Q:      But, even though you were in charge of your own bailiwick,&#13;
&#13;
you were still very much part of the Bank, and participated in&#13;
&#13;
all the major decisions that were taken at that time.&#13;
&#13;
A:      Of course; but participation was more formal than real.&#13;
&#13;
Q:      I   suppose that did not work very well in the Conable&#13;
&#13;
years?&#13;
&#13;
A:      There was no collegial body where operational or country&#13;
&#13;
issues      were   decided.   The    way   Conable    ran    the    President's&#13;
&#13;
Council it was not very much part of a decision-making system.&#13;
&#13;
He   took    many    decisions   without     consultation,         outside     the&#13;
&#13;
Council.      A lot of minutes were taken, but that's not where&#13;
&#13;
things got decided. It certainly was not a very consultative&#13;
&#13;
process.&#13;
&#13;
Q:      Did he deal with people one-on-one and make decisions on&#13;
&#13;
that basis?        Was that the way it was done?&#13;
&#13;
A:      Yes, that was very common. In the President's Council, I&#13;
&#13;
think he knew the answers to most of the topics on the agenda&#13;
&#13;
before the meeting started.&#13;
&#13;
        The people who were his assistants,--like Marianne Haug,&#13;
&#13;
A.   Khanna    and    later   Sven    Sandstrom      spent   a     lot   of   time&#13;
&#13;
clarifying the issues, preparing for the meetings, and drafting&#13;
&amp;#12;                                      Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 33&#13;
the    conclusions.       So   Conable    went     into    these   meetings,&#13;
&#13;
particularly during Marianne Haug's tenure, with a piece of&#13;
&#13;
paper which defined the questions,               which he then read out&#13;
&#13;
verbatim.      It would be hard to say that he dealt with the&#13;
&#13;
substance beyond that on most issues or that he intervened in&#13;
&#13;
the disscussion. Similarly,           the conclusion was prepared with&#13;
&#13;
sometimes only a tenuous connection to the discussions; results&#13;
&#13;
often were quite unpredictable. So his staff spent a lot of&#13;
&#13;
time consulting on the text for the agenda and, subsequently,&#13;
&#13;
on the text of the decision. If there was a serious division of&#13;
&#13;
opinion the conclusion might be held up for a few days for&#13;
&#13;
further consultation by his staff.&#13;
&#13;
       But many issues were not really things that interested him&#13;
&#13;
and    he   did   not   contribute     much   to   their    implementation.&#13;
&#13;
However, he was very interested in the outside world.                    He did&#13;
&#13;
contribute a great deal to better Congressional relations. He&#13;
&#13;
was very good with governmental representatives. He put a lot&#13;
&#13;
of emphasis on poverty issues in which he really believed; and&#13;
&#13;
he extended the dialogue with the environmental organizations&#13;
&#13;
and other NGO' s.       But the management issues of the organizationÂ·&#13;
&#13;
were    just   not   things    that    interested him;      nor    did    broad&#13;
&#13;
economic policy issues or structural adjustment problems. But,&#13;
&#13;
I   do not think it would be fair to blame him for that;                    the&#13;
&#13;
people who chose him presumably knew of his                  interests      and&#13;
&amp;#12;                                       Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 34&#13;
experience.&#13;
&#13;
Q:     What about   the    tension between you and Moeen in this&#13;
&#13;
period. Was that a problem?&#13;
&#13;
A:     So it was said.&#13;
&#13;
Q:     So it was said.     But to what extent was that a reflection&#13;
&#13;
of Conable's lack of leadership?               And to what extent was it&#13;
&#13;
also the cause of the fact that he was left to find his own&#13;
&#13;
way?&#13;
&#13;
A:     I don't know.      My view of that relationship is obviously&#13;
&#13;
biased.    Of course, I was not happy being removed as the Senior&#13;
&#13;
Vice President for Operations, but on the other hand I never&#13;
&#13;
thought Moeen was responsible for that. So I did not start off&#13;
&#13;
with a bias against Moeen.             I remember early on I once went to&#13;
&#13;
visit him and said, I would be happy to help in any way I could&#13;
&#13;
in   the   transition.    But he did not             seem interested in any&#13;
&#13;
collegial cooperation.       I    think, he felt more tension than I&#13;
&#13;
thought was there.        He always seemed worried about receiving&#13;
&#13;
total approbation and seemed to think that I was running a&#13;
&#13;
resistance movement.       But     I    was   not.    I   tried to bend over&#13;
&#13;
backwards to stay out of operational issues or to comment on&#13;
&#13;
them to anyone. He resented it when people said, "well, that's&#13;
&#13;
how we did it before. "          Maybe that rubbed him the wrong way.&#13;
&#13;
He tends to be very touchy about status issues.&#13;
&#13;
       And there were periods of              tension in part because he&#13;
&amp;#12;                                  Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 35&#13;
&#13;
tended to be very protective of his prerogatives. For instance,&#13;
&#13;
we used to have extended discussions at President's Council&#13;
&#13;
meetings on the budget. With an operations budget of say, $400&#13;
&#13;
million--&#13;
&#13;
        [END OF TAPE 1, SIDE 2]&#13;
&#13;
A:      --Moeen might feel he needed another million i.e.       less&#13;
&#13;
than 1/4%. Yet an interminable debate would ensue as to why he&#13;
&#13;
couldn't possibly do without it.         That isn't my style and it&#13;
&#13;
was very frustrating. My own approach to budgetary decisions&#13;
&#13;
had always been, you tell me how much I've got for Operations,&#13;
&#13;
I will allocate it. Nobody can honestly tell me that $1 million&#13;
&#13;
more or less out of so large a budget makes a difference one&#13;
&#13;
way or the other.        So I would not be patient with that sort of&#13;
&#13;
thing.&#13;
&#13;
        And then I suppose, from time to time, when we had policy&#13;
&#13;
changes up for discussion on the lending side, on which we did&#13;
&#13;
not see eye to eye. But I never thought I was saying anything&#13;
&#13;
on those matters that I would not have said to anybody else. I&#13;
&#13;
thought I was participating in a substantive debate.           But I&#13;
&#13;
know    it   often got    taken more   personally certainly   than   I&#13;
&#13;
intended.&#13;
&#13;
Q:      Were you then involved with the IDA replenishments at this&#13;
&#13;
time?&#13;
&#13;
A:      I did them. My first IDA negotiation was IDA-9. IDA 7 and&#13;
&amp;#12;                                           Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 36&#13;
&#13;
8 had been difficult. IDA-7 was a disaster, a sharp drop in&#13;
&#13;
funding;    IDA-8 represented a partial recovery.                       We tried to&#13;
&#13;
build on that in IDA-9, with moderate success.&#13;
&#13;
      The IDA negotiations were a new experience for me. It was&#13;
&#13;
very interesting to build relationships with the major donors--&#13;
&#13;
both with their IDA deputies and the senior officials--in the&#13;
&#13;
capitals.       It    involved a         lot    of    consultation and a     lot of&#13;
&#13;
analytical work.&#13;
&#13;
      Actually        I    had been       involved a         bit   earlier with IDA&#13;
&#13;
related issues. After the poor results of the IDA-7 discussions&#13;
&#13;
it became apparent tha a number of donors could have made&#13;
&#13;
larger contributions than they had. But since the US insisted&#13;
&#13;
on keeping its share at 25% while at the same time limiting the&#13;
&#13;
dollar value of its contribution, the total value of the IDA&#13;
&#13;
replenishment was less               than a         substantial number of donors&#13;
&#13;
could have supported. The funds included in their budget plans&#13;
&#13;
were left uncommitted.&#13;
&#13;
      Although I was the Senior Vice President for Operations at&#13;
&#13;
the time, I proposed to explore whether some of the funds could&#13;
&#13;
not be mobilized for a special purpose, without the US. It was,&#13;
&#13;
admittedly, not a normal part of my responsibilities and was&#13;
&#13;
not   especially           appreciated         by    those   responsible   for   fund&#13;
&#13;
raising.    I    convened a donors meeting in Paris and we were&#13;
&#13;
successful       in       creating   a    Special       Facility    for Africa   and&#13;
&amp;#12;                                             Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 37&#13;
ultimately         mobilized      a     little        over     $1.5    billion.       The   US&#13;
&#13;
Administration initially refused to contribute to the Special&#13;
&#13;
Facility but ultimately the Congress, at the initiative of the&#13;
&#13;
Black Caucus, authorized a contribution of $136 million. This&#13;
&#13;
Special Facility evolved into the Special Program for Africa,&#13;
&#13;
which has become a major coordinating function for the Bank;&#13;
&#13;
the additional funding of the Special Facility was folded back&#13;
&#13;
into IDA in the IDA-8 discussions. In fact,                             the increase in&#13;
&#13;
IDA-8 over IDA-7 was just about equal to the amount of the&#13;
&#13;
Special Facility.&#13;
       I    think the most notable thing about IDA-9 was that we&#13;
&#13;
were able to maintain the IDA-8 level in real terms. And we&#13;
&#13;
were       able    to   improve       some   of       the    aspects    of    the   overall&#13;
&#13;
framework previously agreed, such as changing the agreed share&#13;
&#13;
for Africa from a               fixed number to a              range,   which improved&#13;
&#13;
operational          flexibility.        And      we    were     able    to    reduce       the&#13;
&#13;
unfunded gap a bit.&#13;
       The relationship we built up with the donors served us&#13;
&#13;
well       in     IDA-10.   We    reached         a    replenishment          which    again&#13;
&#13;
maintained the value of IDA in real terms despite the very&#13;
&#13;
difficult budgetary situation faced by a number of the donors.&#13;
We were able to achieve this because we held out, ultimately&#13;
&#13;
successfully,           for a    substantial US contribution -- a large&#13;
&#13;
increase over their previous commitment. And that, ultimately&#13;
&amp;#12;                                            Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 38&#13;
helped the Japanese to continue their strong support for IDA.&#13;
&#13;
Mr.   Preston was instrumental in getting the US decision on&#13;
&#13;
their     contribution,            which    came      at    the    end     of        the    Bush&#13;
&#13;
Administration.&#13;
&#13;
        We also had to do some creative financing in IDA-10 to get&#13;
&#13;
so    large     a    replenishment          in    a   period       when    a    number        of&#13;
&#13;
contributors were forced, due to general budgetary austerity,&#13;
&#13;
to reduce their share in IDA. The British cut their share, as&#13;
&#13;
did the Canadians. The Finnish budget was slashed dramatically&#13;
&#13;
while     the       IDA     negotiations         were      still    in    process.           The&#13;
delegation          still    committed       their      previous      share      but        that&#13;
&#13;
commitment          could    not    be     sustained       afterwards          and    Finland&#13;
&#13;
reduced its contribution later on. The Australians were very&#13;
&#13;
negative and obstreperous and rejected all appeals to join in&#13;
&#13;
a collaborative effort despite the importance they allegedly&#13;
&#13;
attached to increased IDA availability for Asia. They did not&#13;
&#13;
even maintain their contribution in nominal terms. And Saudi&#13;
&#13;
Arabia, which had contributed well beyond the standard criteria&#13;
&#13;
during the period of the high oil prices, continued the process&#13;
&#13;
of reducing its share to more normal levels.&#13;
&#13;
        Despite these important setbacks we were able to hold a&#13;
&#13;
core group of             donors    together,         based on      the    increased US&#13;
&#13;
contribution          and     the    consequent         Japanese         support,          which&#13;
&#13;
cons is ted     of    the    Nordics,       Dutch,      Frerich     and Germans.             The&#13;
&amp;#12;                                       Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 39&#13;
Italians,       despite   their   own    budgetary chaos           at   the    time,&#13;
&#13;
maintained their share. To augment these efforts we also had to&#13;
&#13;
accelerate the donor payment schedule, which increased present&#13;
&#13;
value     of    contributions,    and    had    to    agree   to    a   permanent&#13;
&#13;
reduction in IDA's liquidity to reach closure.                  But we ended up&#13;
&#13;
with a very, very respectable IDA.               It stretched, to be sure,&#13;
&#13;
the political willingness of countries to contribute.                         We can&#13;
&#13;
see that in the delays in the Italian contributions; and in the&#13;
&#13;
uncertainties       created by the         election results         in the U.S.&#13;
&#13;
Congress.       Implementation    of    the    IDA-10   commitments           is   not&#13;
&#13;
certain.&#13;
&#13;
Q:      IDA-9 was in the Conable period.&#13;
&#13;
A:      Yes.&#13;
&#13;
Q:      Did he contribute actively to this replenishment?&#13;
&#13;
A:      He contributed tremendously on               the U.S.      Congressional&#13;
&#13;
side.    Absolutely.      And to return to one of your earlier themes&#13;
&#13;
during    this     period of     preparation     for    IDA-9,      there was        a&#13;
&#13;
convergence of interests between Moeen and myself and Conable.&#13;
&#13;
We discussed the preparatory papers and then of course during&#13;
&#13;
the   negotiations,       we   consulted closely.        There was        always,&#13;
&#13;
particularly on the U.S.           side,      a strong drive for imposing&#13;
&#13;
policy conditions. That certainly was true during IDA-9 and&#13;
&#13;
IDA-10.        And negotiating what you had to give and what you did&#13;
&#13;
not have to give was a subject for discussion, not only with&#13;
&amp;#12;                                  Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 40&#13;
&#13;
Moeen, but also with the General Counsel, who was interested,&#13;
&#13;
and with other Senior Vice Presidents because, obviously, these&#13;
&#13;
conditions affected a       range of Operational policies               the&#13;
&#13;
environment, targeted poverty interventions, collaboration with&#13;
&#13;
the IMF on country strategies,          and so forth. These were the&#13;
&#13;
things the U.S. was pushing very hard.            And so, yes, Conable&#13;
&#13;
was involved in those issues, although I cannot say he gave a&#13;
&#13;
lot of guidance as to how to handle them. Moeen was very proper&#13;
&#13;
in those discussions by saying,          "here are my views,        and why&#13;
&#13;
can't you do it this way. But you are the negotiator and I&#13;
&#13;
can't judge." So there was a lot of interaction but there was&#13;
&#13;
no friction.   Toward the end of the process Conable was helpful&#13;
&#13;
in getting the final US commitment and even more influential in&#13;
&#13;
getting Congressional approval.&#13;
&#13;
Q:   If you compare the IDA-9 experience with the IDA-8 and&#13;
&#13;
particularly IDA-7     in   the   Clausen period,      was   that    now a&#13;
&#13;
tribute   to   the   different    set    of   people   who   handled    the&#13;
&#13;
negotiations here in the Bank?          Or was that just the result of&#13;
&#13;
a different climate, a different environment?&#13;
&#13;
A:   Well, I think all these factors affected the outcome. In&#13;
&#13;
IDA-7 US support for the international institution was weak.&#13;
&#13;
But also, the appointment of Mr. DeLattre as chief negotiator&#13;
&#13;
was a mistake. Up to that point, the IDA negotiations had been&#13;
&#13;
conducted (as far as I know) by a senior Bank officer. But Mr.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                   Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 41&#13;
&#13;
Qureshi     decided     to   recruit    someone    from     the    outside,&#13;
&#13;
specifically for this task. It did not work well. Mr. DeLattre,&#13;
&#13;
a French Finance official, had no particular committment to the&#13;
&#13;
Bank nor a strong interes.t in a large IDA. He was a good friend&#13;
&#13;
of Beryl Sprinkel, the Undersecretary of the Teasury, who was&#13;
&#13;
no fan of the Bank. DeLattre,           as a result,      accepted the US&#13;
&#13;
position uncritically and the US reduction elicited similar&#13;
&#13;
actions by others. As a result the IDA-7 Replenishment was very&#13;
&#13;
disappointing. There was a partial recovery in IDA-8, which Mr.&#13;
&#13;
Qureshi negotiated. By the time of IDA-9 there were different&#13;
&#13;
people involved at the Bank and in the US. And the climate had&#13;
&#13;
improved.    Certainly the U.S. Administration was not exactly&#13;
&#13;
very forthcoming, but then they had not been for some time. I&#13;
&#13;
never found it too hard to work with David Mulford.&#13;
&#13;
Q:    I guess he had mellowed also by then. That would not be&#13;
&#13;
the word you would have used?&#13;
&#13;
A:    Well, David was a man of very firm views and, I don't know&#13;
&#13;
how much he had mellowed. But he was always a very straight-&#13;
&#13;
shooter, and open to discussion.             But you know, the U.S. had&#13;
&#13;
serious     budget    problems   and   the   constraints    they   faced&#13;
&#13;
political, legislative, financial - were real enough. But the&#13;
&#13;
US,   as the single largest contributor, defined the range of&#13;
&#13;
possibe conclusions. No other donor was prepared to compensate&#13;
&#13;
for a   further decline in the US share. And the problem was&#13;
&amp;#12;                                        Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 42&#13;
&#13;
compounded    by     the    fact   that    the    US     had    by Â· far   the   most&#13;
&#13;
extensive policy demands.           So they generally managed to set&#13;
&#13;
everybody's teeth on edge early in all the discussions.                       But it&#13;
&#13;
was also a period when people recognized that IDA had not grown&#13;
&#13;
in Â·real terms, for some time.&#13;
&#13;
     It was also a period when the Japanese had a fair amount&#13;
&#13;
of aid resources available and,             in IDA-9,          the Europeans were&#13;
&#13;
reasonably flush and the French were strong supporters                            for&#13;
&#13;
increased financing for Africa. So there were some things to&#13;
&#13;
work with.&#13;
&#13;
     But in IDA-9 there were big battles about environmental&#13;
&#13;
issues, country strategies and performance measures. Charles&#13;
&#13;
Dallara,    the Assistant Secretary of the Treasury was the US&#13;
&#13;
representative and he was very demanding. As a result, when the&#13;
&#13;
agreement    was     submitted     to     the    Board    of     Directors,      very&#13;
&#13;
divisive debates ensued about the role of the IDA Deputies and&#13;
&#13;
the binding nature of the Report of the IDA Deputies, which was&#13;
&#13;
the culminating document of the replenishment negotiations. The&#13;
&#13;
report was the basis for the donor contributions and, as such,&#13;
&#13;
reflected what the donors expected. The Board, of course, is&#13;
&#13;
constituted differently and it is the policy making body of IDA&#13;
&#13;
(and the Bank). It had great difficulty in accepting the policy&#13;
&#13;
changes     donors    had    demanded      in    the     context      of   the    IDA&#13;
&#13;
negotiations. Indeed, the system is anomalous in this regard.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 43&#13;
&#13;
     This was not only a problem with the        u.s.,   mind you.     The&#13;
&#13;
Canadians through their Executive Director, Mr.            Potter,     had&#13;
&#13;
strong   views   about   aspects   of    Bank   policy   and   generally&#13;
&#13;
supported the US views. These, and other donors, used the IDA&#13;
&#13;
negotiations     to   change Bank policies      or procedures.       While&#13;
&#13;
legally what is agreed for IDA does not necessarily apply to&#13;
&#13;
the Bank,   the practical reality is         that if you adopt some&#13;
&#13;
particular policy or procedure for IDA it can't be very long&#13;
&#13;
before they will apply to Bank operations as well. You cannot&#13;
&#13;
operate two separate systems for long, particularly since some&#13;
&#13;
countries borrow from both the Bank and IDA and, indeed, some&#13;
&#13;
projects have both Bank and IDA financing.&#13;
&#13;
Q:   In dealing with Congress, to what extent did you work .with&#13;
&#13;
staff rather than principals?           Most organizations that deal&#13;
&#13;
with Congress say that since the 1970s the action has all been&#13;
&#13;
with the staff, particularly on technical details.&#13;
&#13;
A:   That's probably true but I have little experience with the&#13;
&#13;
Congress. One of the luxuries I have allowed myself in my life&#13;
&#13;
at the Bank is not to deal with the U.S. Congress. We have&#13;
&#13;
people in the External Affairs Department who maintain contact&#13;
&#13;
with the staff Congressional Committee.         At the principal level&#13;
&#13;
the p.resident deals with Congressmen and Senators. We had a&#13;
&#13;
former Congressman under Clausen and Conable who assisted the&#13;
&#13;
President and Mr. Preston recruited Mr. McHugh, also a former&#13;
&amp;#12;                                             Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 44&#13;
Congressman when Mr.             Stanton retired. Mr.           Conable obviously&#13;
&#13;
knew a lot of Congressmen personally and, during his tenure,&#13;
&#13;
interaction with Congress was more active.                          It was not so&#13;
active during the Clausen period.&#13;
&#13;
Q:      I suppose that was something that Clausen really did not&#13;
&#13;
know how to do? But what I am after here is, whether there was&#13;
&#13;
at the level of staff the permanent relationship with Congress&#13;
&#13;
that was a factor in the IDA replenishments or did it exist at&#13;
&#13;
a     higher level?&#13;
&#13;
A.:     No.    In negotiating the IDA replenishments you really are&#13;
&#13;
concerned with what              the Administration is prepared to do;&#13;
&#13;
prepared        to      submit     to        the    Congress.    Obviously,    the&#13;
&#13;
Administration has an eye on Congress,                     and on the political&#13;
&#13;
feasibility of both the commitment level and the policy issues&#13;
&#13;
to     be     agreed.     But,     as    you       know,   almost   anything   any&#13;
&#13;
Administration           submits        is     subject     to   change   in    the&#13;
&#13;
authorization and the appropriation process.&#13;
&#13;
Q:      Right.&#13;
&#13;
A:      So in the IDA negotiations you are focused on what the&#13;
&#13;
Executive is prepared to put in the budget and their assessment&#13;
&#13;
that the final agreement is salable. Of course the Treasury&#13;
&#13;
consults with the appropriate Congressional leadership, but the&#13;
&#13;
Bank Management does not get involved in that.                        That is an&#13;
&#13;
internal US problem.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                          Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 45&#13;
&#13;
      Our staff is active throughout the year with issues in the&#13;
&#13;
Congress - from specific complaints to draft legislation but&#13;
&#13;
not   the   US    commitment         to   the    IDA    replenishment    which    is&#13;
&#13;
determined by the Executive. They, of course, also track the&#13;
&#13;
authorization          and    appropriation          process    and   involve    the&#13;
&#13;
President or other senior managers to try and help resolve any&#13;
&#13;
problems.&#13;
&#13;
Q:    I was thinking conditionality attached to the IDA bills&#13;
&#13;
would be one of the areas of concern to the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
A:    True:      but     we    are    now       talking    of   the   process    of&#13;
&#13;
Congressional       approval         of   a     UScommitment made by the&#13;
                                                       â&#128;¢&#13;
Executive.       When a draft bill            is prepared in Committee our&#13;
&#13;
people usually are informed. If there is something inconsistent&#13;
&#13;
with our Articles of Agreement, or if there is a particularly&#13;
&#13;
troublesome provision, we try to work with the Committee staff&#13;
&#13;
and the Treasury officials. Ultimately, of course, Treasury, on&#13;
&#13;
behalf of the Administration, is responsible for representing&#13;
&#13;
the Executive on legislation and has to see what accomodations&#13;
&#13;
can be worked out.            Conversely,        Congress cannot affect Bank&#13;
&#13;
policies or procedures directly. They can do one of two things.&#13;
&#13;
They can      instruct the US, through its Executive Director, to&#13;
&#13;
oppose certain policies or to vote against projects which do&#13;
&#13;
not meet their criteria. But while the US is the largest single&#13;
&#13;
shareholder it still has only 17%                    of the vote. So a "no" vote&#13;
&amp;#12;                                       Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 46&#13;
&#13;
by the US does not by itself determine the outcome of an issue&#13;
&#13;
before the Board. The second thing the Congress can do is to&#13;
&#13;
withhold all or part of the funds for IDA. That has taken the&#13;
&#13;
form   of   deducting   from      the    appropriated     IDA   fund   amounts&#13;
&#13;
approved for operations which the US does not approve of. But&#13;
&#13;
that technically does not reduce the formal US commitment to&#13;
&#13;
the other donors. It builds up arrears which have to be settled&#13;
&#13;
before a new IDA replenishment would be agreed on by the other&#13;
&#13;
contributors.&#13;
&#13;
Q:     Now I want to ask about the GEF and your role in that.&#13;
&#13;
A:     Well, the GEF came up in the IDA-9 negotiations.                 It was&#13;
&#13;
a French idea, although the Germans had a similar proposal. I&#13;
&#13;
believe the French were attracted by the earlier example of the&#13;
&#13;
Special Facility for Africa as a model. And they,                  and other&#13;
&#13;
OECD    countries,    wanted      to    preempt     the   creation     of   new&#13;
&#13;
international funds or organizations . The Convention on Ozone&#13;
&#13;
Depletion and its Montreal Protocol, were under discussion and&#13;
&#13;
the.    environment     was       becoming        increasingly       important&#13;
&#13;
politically. Some major donors were concerned that each subject&#13;
&#13;
would have not only its own technical organization but also a&#13;
&#13;
separate fundraising effort. However, the proposal came at an&#13;
&#13;
inopportune time. It was made at the Annual Meeting when the&#13;
&#13;
IDA negotiations      had   not    yet been completed.          There was     a&#13;
&#13;
susbtantial risk that the environment fund proposal, if pursued&#13;
&amp;#12;                                         Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 47&#13;
&#13;
at that time would have been at the expense of IDA. After&#13;
&#13;
considerable discussion with the proponents, we were able to&#13;
&#13;
agree that the Bank would take the initiative to convene a&#13;
&#13;
meeting the following January, after we had completed the IDA&#13;
&#13;
negotiations in December as expected.&#13;
&#13;
       Actually there is a very good manuscript on the history of&#13;
&#13;
the GEF which someone in the Bank has prepared. If you have not&#13;
&#13;
read it you should.&#13;
&#13;
Q:     I have.&#13;
&#13;
A:     It is very accurate and I can add little to it. We had&#13;
&#13;
preliminary discussions with the French to define the draft&#13;
&#13;
proposal - in terms of objectives and priority areas - so that&#13;
&#13;
it could be presented to a meeting of potentially interested&#13;
&#13;
donors.    And     although originally         only   a     few   countries   had&#13;
&#13;
indicated    any     interest       in   the   proposal,     when   we   finally&#13;
&#13;
convened     the    meeting,    virtually       all   the     significant     IDA&#13;
&#13;
contributors insisted on attending. For some it simply was to&#13;
&#13;
ensure that they had a say in the evolution of the idea even if&#13;
&#13;
they   did   not    intend     to    contribute.      The    negotiations     and&#13;
&#13;
consultations were complex because we had to deal with many&#13;
&#13;
people who were not our traditional contacts. Staffs of the&#13;
&#13;
Environmental Ministries or Agencies generally did not trust&#13;
&#13;
the Bank as an actor in the environmental area. And indeed some&#13;
&#13;
of the national delegations were divided; they were led by the&#13;
&amp;#12;                                      Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 48&#13;
&#13;
Finance Ministries which their own environmental staff did not&#13;
&#13;
always trust .&#13;
&#13;
       .And we had to resolve many issues. Since the GEF was the&#13;
&#13;
first of its kind there were constitutional,                    institutional,&#13;
&#13;
funding and technical issues to resolve as well as issues of&#13;
&#13;
collaboration with UN agencies and with the Montreal Protocol&#13;
&#13;
which was under negotiation simultaneously.&#13;
&#13;
        And a good deal of effort was spent on trying to define&#13;
&#13;
what it was we would be trying to "pilotâ&#128;¢. This was easier to&#13;
&#13;
define in such areas as power generation --i.e. where we would&#13;
&#13;
be     trying    to    demonstrate    that    cleaner     technologies         were&#13;
&#13;
consistent with profitable operations                    than in such other&#13;
&#13;
areas as water pollution and biodiversity.&#13;
&#13;
        But ultimately,      we   raised about      $1 billion,         including&#13;
&#13;
cofinanced contributions, for a trust fund which was structured&#13;
&#13;
to operate simply. And while at the outset there was strong&#13;
&#13;
emphasis on the pilot nature of the GEF, by the time of the Rio&#13;
&#13;
conference every one          thought    the GEF,    with its ability to&#13;
&#13;
accept trust funds for a variety of purposes, was a Godsend. It&#13;
&#13;
validated the original French intention of creating an umbrella&#13;
&#13;
fund     for    international     environmental      agreements          and    the&#13;
&#13;
associated funding requirements.              Of course,       as    the GEF was&#13;
&#13;
expanded        it    was   considered    necessary       to        redesign    the&#13;
&#13;
institutional         architecture.      It   now   is    a     quite     complex&#13;
&amp;#12;                                        Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 49&#13;
structure.&#13;
&#13;
Q:    This idea of doing this in partnership with UNDP and UNEF,&#13;
&#13;
was that something the French had also brought up at the start?&#13;
&#13;
A:    Well,        that   I   don't    honestly   remember      in detail.      The&#13;
&#13;
Nordics and others were very emphatic on this.                     I'm not sure&#13;
&#13;
whether      the    French had        this   originally    in mind.        It was&#13;
&#13;
motivated by the distrust               of   the Bank as       an environmental&#13;
&#13;
player.&#13;
&#13;
      The negotiations involved a muchÂ· broader participation&#13;
&#13;
than an IDA replenishment and many of the people particularly&#13;
&#13;
those from environmental agencies insisted,                    on a     tripartite&#13;
&#13;
arrangement.         And the head of UNEP was very concerned that we&#13;
&#13;
were about to swallow his turf and he too favored the idea of&#13;
&#13;
a joint administration. Of course, it made sense from a global&#13;
&#13;
perspective that if you are going to set up a funding mechanism&#13;
&#13;
you ought not to have separate funding mechanisms for all these&#13;
&#13;
international conventions which were being negotiated by UNEP)&#13;
&#13;
      The UNDP, similarly, was concerned since some of the GEF&#13;
&#13;
funding was to go for technical assistance and the development&#13;
&#13;
of   local     institutions             both   topics     in   which     they   had&#13;
&#13;
experience         and considered       their prerogative.         So    they   too&#13;
&#13;
favored a joint administration.&#13;
&#13;
      So,    it was a new experience for us because we had to&#13;
&#13;
negotiate in four different directions simultaneously.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                        Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 50&#13;
&#13;
        The UNDP generally was very helpful.                  UNEP, on the other&#13;
&#13;
hand,    was quite distrustful of us,                and we spent many hours&#13;
&#13;
haggling about words,             But in the end I think we came out with&#13;
&#13;
a reasonable package, in which each agency could contribute to&#13;
&#13;
the development of the program and execute activities in areas&#13;
&#13;
of its special expertise.&#13;
&#13;
Q:      Is   it    your   sense    that      the   environmental    movement   is&#13;
&#13;
antithetical to the Bank's basic strategy in a very fundamental&#13;
&#13;
way.    Do you see that as a fundamental challenge to the Bank's&#13;
&#13;
mission?&#13;
&#13;
A:      There are lots of components to the movement -- so the&#13;
&#13;
answer to the question is "no" as far as the whole movement is&#13;
&#13;
concerned. But the Bank is not an environmental organization.&#13;
&#13;
It has multiple objectives.               In my view balances have to be&#13;
&#13;
struck between different objectives. The problem is that for&#13;
&#13;
some environmental organizations, the environmental issues is&#13;
&#13;
seen as superior to all other considerations. I do not believe&#13;
&#13;
that to be realistic or sustainable.&#13;
&#13;
        There are some environmental groups that fully recognize&#13;
&#13;
that the environment is an important issue in development but&#13;
&#13;
not the only one. But there are others, who are more extreme&#13;
&#13;
and with them it is hard to have a collaborative relationship&#13;
&#13;
because they do not believe in trade-offs.&#13;
&#13;
Q:      So   you    saw   the     GEF   as    a    way   of   facilitating   some&#13;
&amp;#12;                                    Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 51&#13;
cooperation?&#13;
&#13;
A:      I doubt that we would have sought to create a supplemental&#13;
&#13;
fund if the French had not made their proposal. The objective&#13;
&#13;
of the GEF was not to improve relations with the environmental&#13;
&#13;
organizations. Actually some of the environmentalists were very&#13;
&#13;
much opposed to the GEf because they didn't think the Bank&#13;
&#13;
could or would do it properly. They felt it did not belong in&#13;
&#13;
the Bank.       They were not enthusiastic.        Some openly lobbied&#13;
&#13;
against it.      So as a tool to get them on board, the GEF would&#13;
&#13;
not have been effective; it certainly wasn't the way it worked&#13;
&#13;
for quite a long time.&#13;
&#13;
Q:      Since we are on the environmental issue, when did that&#13;
&#13;
really come on your scope as something that was going to be a&#13;
&#13;
major issue?      Can you remember when that would have been?&#13;
&#13;
A:      Well, it's difficult to be precise.       Maybe in the mid-80s.&#13;
&#13;
As you know,       the Bank started early with an environmental&#13;
&#13;
department but I don't think there was a clear view in those&#13;
&#13;
days,    of the complexity or scope of the issues.            The initial&#13;
&#13;
functions reflected McNamara's early reaction to the issue. He&#13;
&#13;
wanted     to   make   sure   the   Bank's   projects   did   not   do   any&#13;
&#13;
environmental damage.&#13;
&#13;
        And that was seen as a sensible and responsible behavior&#13;
&#13;
for the Bank for a considerable time. But gradually, thinking&#13;
&#13;
on the subject evolved, outside the Bank and internally. The&#13;
&amp;#12;                                      Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 52&#13;
&#13;
scope     of   the    environmental      issues    became   clearer     and   the&#13;
&#13;
complexity of         environmental      impacts      even at     the project&#13;
&#13;
level. We moved from thinking about environmental problems in&#13;
&#13;
terms of industrialized country issues -- cutting down forests&#13;
&#13;
or the direct effect of plant waste disposal on air and water -&#13;
&#13;
- to consider protection of indigenous people, the resettlement&#13;
&#13;
of people dislocated by projects, and what came to be called&#13;
&#13;
the "brown" problems -         the environmental issues in everyday&#13;
&#13;
life among the poor.&#13;
&#13;
Q:      Snail garters.&#13;
&#13;
A:     At the same time, the environmental movement grew, and its&#13;
&#13;
emphasis on global aspects of the environmental issues, drew&#13;
&#13;
attention to the developing countries. And this turned out to&#13;
&#13;
be a fertile field - because the problems were real but also&#13;
&#13;
because the political link to bilateral and multilateral aid&#13;
&#13;
flows was discovered. It seemed easier to lobby parliaments on&#13;
&#13;
environmental requirements overseas than at home. Compounding&#13;
&#13;
this    interest      was   that   the    implementation     of   the    Bank's&#13;
&#13;
policies left much to be desired. A Bank-financed highway in&#13;
&#13;
Brazil,    into      the Amazon,   and later the Narmada Project in&#13;
&#13;
India, became big controversies. And there were others . To be&#13;
&#13;
sure some of our policies, turned out to be very difficult to&#13;
&#13;
implement, although they were highly lauded when issued. For&#13;
&#13;
instance, the operational directives on indigenous people and&#13;
&amp;#12;                                       Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 53&#13;
resettlement were written during my tenure as Chairman of the&#13;
&#13;
Loan Committee --in about '85, '86. Michael Chernea and others,&#13;
&#13;
played     an   important    role.     The   Operational Directives were&#13;
&#13;
statements of superb intentions, and with these policies the&#13;
&#13;
Bank led the international agencies at the time. The attitude&#13;
&#13;
was, "Okay, if these are the implications of a project that is&#13;
&#13;
sound, let's be sure we do it right."&#13;
&#13;
       Today, having learned of what it takes to make those words&#13;
&#13;
reality,    we would write           those     O.Ds.   more       carefully.      They&#13;
&#13;
promise a       lot of things which are very hard to deliver in&#13;
&#13;
countries       with   little      available    land       and    few    alternative&#13;
&#13;
employment opportunities.&#13;
&#13;
       Because of the growing interests of                       the environmental&#13;
movement        in     developing      countries,           our      failures       of&#13;
&#13;
implementation         and   the     forging     of    a     link       between   aid&#13;
&#13;
appropriations and the environmental groups the Bank came under&#13;
&#13;
very   heavy     criticism.     I    remember     that      early       in Conable's&#13;
&#13;
tenure, he invited a group of critics, including a Congressman&#13;
&#13;
(whose name I have forgotten) to try to reach a better mutual&#13;
&#13;
understanding. But this did not work well. The division between&#13;
&#13;
those who thought that environment issues were paramount, and&#13;
&#13;
the Bank which,         by definition,         did not believe that,              grew&#13;
&#13;
increasingly pronounced. We devoted one of our WDRs,                          to the&#13;
subject, focussing on the human environmental problems--lots of&#13;
&amp;#12;                                       Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 54&#13;
&#13;
poor people without water, without sewage, having to scrounge&#13;
&#13;
for firewood, having to walk miles simply to obtain water or&#13;
&#13;
fuel -- in order to provide some perspective on environmental&#13;
&#13;
priorities in developing countries. We were trying to put those&#13;
&#13;
issues on the environmental agenda where they were not and&#13;
&#13;
still are not today.&#13;
&#13;
Q:   To what     extent    do    you,     personally,       see   tension   here&#13;
&#13;
between the developed and developing countries,                    in that the&#13;
&#13;
developing countries are still more dedicated to the concept of&#13;
&#13;
development, the basic mission of the Bank, while to a great&#13;
&#13;
extent the environmental movement is coming out of developed&#13;
&#13;
countries?&#13;
&#13;
A:   It   varies.    First,      the    environmental       movement   in    the&#13;
&#13;
developing countries has grown rapidly. But it is true that at&#13;
&#13;
the political/policy/parliamentary level it does not yet have&#13;
&#13;
the same influence it has in some OECD countries. Second,                      I&#13;
&#13;
think there are a number of industrialized countries which no&#13;
&#13;
longer    accept     the        primacy        of     environmental     issues&#13;
&#13;
unconditionally. To some extent, environmentalists overdid it&#13;
&#13;
     [END OF TAPE 2, SIDE 1]&#13;
&#13;
intellectually;      at       the       same        time,    non-governmental&#13;
&#13;
organizations with other concerns - particularly those focused&#13;
&#13;
on poverty issues - became more insistent and influential. And&#13;
&#13;
third,    many     developing       country         governments     introduced&#13;
&amp;#12;                                              Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 55&#13;
&#13;
environmental standards and regulations. That forced both them&#13;
&#13;
and environmental groups to look at relative priorities in very&#13;
&#13;
practical situations and in political frameworks. On balance,&#13;
&#13;
this      did    not   mean       a    choice       between    development          and   the&#13;
&#13;
environment,           but    a        more     nuanced       approach         emphasizing&#13;
&#13;
development which is environmentally sustainable. That is very&#13;
&#13;
much      the    Bank's      view      and    one    on    which     there     is    growing&#13;
&#13;
consensus.&#13;
&#13;
       However, there are some organizations which simply oppose&#13;
&#13;
development, growth and change. With these I think there is a&#13;
&#13;
conflict which is not going to go away.&#13;
&#13;
       My       line   of    response         to    those     who    are      unreasonably&#13;
&#13;
demanding, or who think the Bank ought to stay out if it cannot&#13;
&#13;
dictate the rules,            always has been that "the Bank may have&#13;
&#13;
deficiencies and we may not always do it right, but any project&#13;
&#13;
will be done environmentally better with us than without us."&#13;
&#13;
I   was     pleased       when        the    Indians      asked     us   to    cancel     the&#13;
&#13;
outstanding balances on the Narmada project because the outside&#13;
&#13;
world was being totally unrealistic in its demands.                                 We still&#13;
&#13;
get streams of Internet messages, whenever an Indian policeman&#13;
&#13;
beats up someone on the Narmada project site or when the water&#13;
&#13;
in the reservoir rises beyond agreed levels, but the response&#13;
&#13;
now has to be "Fellows, you wanted us out, and now we are out."&#13;
&#13;
I have no doubt, whatsoever,                   that the treatment of the local&#13;
&amp;#12;                                   Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 56&#13;
&#13;
people and the development of the water resources of the region&#13;
&#13;
will be less satisfactory without Bank participation. The same&#13;
&#13;
thing may happen now with the Arun dam in Nepal.&#13;
&#13;
     The cost that these people generate is tremendous and in&#13;
&#13;
my view the Bank cannot afford them. Member governments provide&#13;
&#13;
inadequate   support   to    the , Bank       on   these   topics.    If    the&#13;
&#13;
political cost gets     too high,        we   just have to leave these&#13;
&#13;
projects      but    that   will    be   a    great   loss   for     the   poor&#13;
&#13;
countries. In middle income countries, increasingly, there is&#13;
&#13;
private financing available for infrastructure but in Nepal if&#13;
&#13;
we do not help, the dam will not be built.&#13;
&#13;
Q:    On another issue, you told us when we came in today that&#13;
&#13;
you experienced a conversion, an epiphany? Would you like to&#13;
&#13;
tell us about this?&#13;
&#13;
A:   I don't think I had an epiphany.&#13;
&#13;
Q:   A conversion?&#13;
&#13;
A:   Well, not even a conversion.             As I told you earlier I am&#13;
&#13;
a fan of the underdog and this farewell present is a way a&#13;
&#13;
group of women recognized my efforts on behalf of more equal&#13;
&#13;
treatment.&#13;
&#13;
Q:   We are talking about the role of women not only in the&#13;
&#13;
Bank but in general.&#13;
&#13;
A:   I believe in equity and I therefore have never accepted&#13;
&#13;
the concept of unequal pay for women, unequal promotion rates&#13;
&amp;#12;                                 Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 57&#13;
&#13;
or the absence of women in senior management ranks - in the&#13;
&#13;
Bank or as a general proposition. Any justification based on an&#13;
&#13;
inadequate supply of trained women became irrelevant years ago.&#13;
&#13;
     I   have supported an active program to promote women.           I&#13;
&#13;
always, with one exception, had women as my assistants when I&#13;
&#13;
was Senior Vice President. Two are Department Directors now -&#13;
&#13;
good role models.      I always have believed that women have a&#13;
&#13;
very different style of managing, of discussing issues and of&#13;
&#13;
approaching problems. They make an important contribution which&#13;
&#13;
you don't have in an all-male environment.&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Could you      just specify what    that   difference   in style&#13;
&#13;
consists of?&#13;
&#13;
A:   It is hard to spell out: and of course those are general&#13;
&#13;
propositions, not applicable to every individual man or woman.&#13;
&#13;
On the whole, women tend to be more civilized in debate, less&#13;
&#13;
status conscious, less confrontational and they bring different&#13;
&#13;
perspectives   to    issues.   They   seek   resolution   rather   than&#13;
&#13;
victory. Even decisive women are more patient than men,            and&#13;
&#13;
generally more tolerant of diversity. I always started from the&#13;
&#13;
proposition, which was not a conversion here in the Bank, that&#13;
&#13;
it made no sense not to have a reasonably equal proportion of&#13;
&#13;
women in the work place.       Women represent half the population&#13;
&#13;
and in the OECD countries, today, they are as well educated as&#13;
&#13;
the men.   Intellectual quality is equally distributed across&#13;
&amp;#12;                                 Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 58&#13;
&#13;
genders. So, not having drawn on half the population deprives&#13;
&#13;
any organization of badly needed skills. The small proportion&#13;
&#13;
of women, or women managers, in the Bank or elsewhere, is the&#13;
&#13;
result of bias. And I dislike biased behavior strongly.&#13;
&#13;
Q:    We are talking about the '80s here.&#13;
&#13;
A:    Right.    But I am sure I believed that before the            '80s.&#13;
&#13;
And I always got along very well, for those reasons I guess,&#13;
&#13;
with professional women, well before I got to the Bank.              So I&#13;
&#13;
was   always   available   to   help   recruit   in   a   more   balanced&#13;
&#13;
fashion, and to help ensure women get promoted equitably.              So&#13;
&#13;
this was not a recent conversion.       I think it was always there.&#13;
&#13;
Q:    But it was in the '80s that you began to think more about&#13;
&#13;
actually doing something specific about it?&#13;
&#13;
A:    Well, I got to be more senior. I was able to do something&#13;
&#13;
more about it. I remember the battle we had in the Bank about&#13;
&#13;
a day-care facility--&#13;
&#13;
Q:    What year was that roughly?&#13;
&#13;
A:    I don't remember exactly-- It was during Clausen's time.&#13;
&#13;
The arguments against were the same kind of themes I heard when&#13;
&#13;
I was a member of the Cosmos Club and the membership didn't&#13;
&#13;
allow women in.&#13;
&#13;
Q:    It was a big issue.&#13;
&#13;
A:    There were lots of meetings; it was an annual item.               I&#13;
&#13;
finally resigned from the Cosmos Club.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                     Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 59&#13;
&#13;
Q:      You resigned from the place because they wouldn't admit&#13;
&#13;
women?&#13;
&#13;
A:      That is right. But that was before I was at the Bank.             But&#13;
&#13;
the     debates   at   the    Bank   had   the    same   kind   of   nonsense&#13;
&#13;
arguments. Not implausible proposi tons - but exaggerating every&#13;
&#13;
possible problem so as to avoid change. The Cosmos Club, by its&#13;
&#13;
charter, was to admit people on professional achievement. How&#13;
&#13;
you can have      that and not allow women in,           I   just could not&#13;
&#13;
understand.&#13;
&#13;
        In the Bank, we also were supposed to be a meritocracy. If&#13;
&#13;
so, there can be no excuse for not being more evenly balanced.&#13;
&#13;
It is that simple. And that is what the "Stern" " Report on the&#13;
&#13;
Role of Women in the Bank" essentially said in 1991.&#13;
&#13;
        But back to the daycare center. Debates about liability;&#13;
&#13;
about misuse of facilities; about not being able to accomodate&#13;
&#13;
everybody,    etc.     So I    worked on that and then Mr.           Clausen&#13;
&#13;
finally went along. He didn't like confrontations and agreeing&#13;
&#13;
with me may have been the lesser of various evils at the end.&#13;
&#13;
But in all of its years of operation I have never heard that&#13;
&#13;
the daycare center ran into any of these problems. It works&#13;
&#13;
fine.&#13;
&#13;
Q:      your mentioning Clausen brings me back up to a question to&#13;
&#13;
ask you.      If it were said that a reorganization would take&#13;
&#13;
place in order to get Ernie Stern,               that suggests to me that&#13;
&amp;#12;                                    Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 60&#13;
&#13;
your role prior to that time was a little more important than&#13;
&#13;
you have indicated in our previous discussions. There certainly&#13;
&#13;
were    people who    said   that    Clausen   did not   pay   a   lot   of&#13;
&#13;
attention to Operations and that you were running the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
A:     It's a non sequitur.     Even if it were true that he did not&#13;
&#13;
pay much attention to Operations, the only conclusion you could&#13;
&#13;
draw from that is that I ran Operations            not that I ran the&#13;
&#13;
Bank. I was the head of Operations, so, I ran Operations. In&#13;
&#13;
fact, major issues, policies or resource allocation issues were&#13;
&#13;
decided by Mr.       Clausen.   He delegated detail and management&#13;
&#13;
responsibility -- not strategy.&#13;
&#13;
Q:     But if a friend of mine says, "Well, Ernie Stern ran the&#13;
&#13;
Bank," what would I say to him?&#13;
&#13;
A:     You'd say people exaggerate.        Operations, of course, was&#13;
&#13;
a large part of the Bank. And it has lots of externalities. It&#13;
&#13;
deals with issues involving most of the shareholders and the&#13;
&#13;
borrowers. So it is certainly an important part of the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
       Beyond that, of course, Mr. Clausen was a newcomer. One of&#13;
&#13;
the problems the Bank has been facing after McNamara is that it&#13;
&#13;
has had a series of one-term Presidents, and running the Bank&#13;
&#13;
is very hard for one-term Presidents. This is a big place, in&#13;
&#13;
a    very complicated business,        and if you come    in from        the&#13;
&#13;
outside, it takes a while to get to know what it's all about.&#13;
&#13;
It's a very demanding job, with lots of responsibilities; a lot&#13;
&amp;#12;                                  Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 61&#13;
&#13;
of travel to see projects and to visit shareholders.&#13;
&#13;
     So when Mr.       Clausen came,       he   found an operationally&#13;
&#13;
functioning senior management and he was a great believer in&#13;
&#13;
delegation. So he let people run their territory. That may have&#13;
&#13;
contributed to the perception you cite.&#13;
&#13;
     And, it is also true that I've always thought of myself as&#13;
&#13;
a corporate officer. I was not just responsible for Operations&#13;
&#13;
but had -   and thought I was supposed to have -views on the&#13;
&#13;
Bank's institutional interest in other areas.             I still believe&#13;
&#13;
that to be correct. And if I have views, I have a tendency to&#13;
&#13;
express them. But that does not, and did not, mean that I ran&#13;
&#13;
Administration, or Finance, or Economics.&#13;
&#13;
     I should add that at that time we had a very able person,&#13;
&#13;
now a   good    friend of mine,        Martijn Paimans,    who was Vice&#13;
&#13;
President      for   Personnel   and    Administration.    He   was   very&#13;
&#13;
interested in improving our approaches to personnel management,&#13;
&#13;
and to learn from practices in the private sector. Since he&#13;
&#13;
could not get the attention of the whole Bank, and since I was&#13;
&#13;
interested, we innovated in Operations.&#13;
&#13;
     Mr. Kaji, who is now a Managing Director, reminded me the&#13;
&#13;
other day that when he was Director of Administration and&#13;
&#13;
Personnel, and Mr. Paijmans was the Vice President, he got me&#13;
&#13;
to sign a letter to all the Vice Presidents saying, "You should&#13;
&#13;
be aware that you are serving at the pleasure of the President,.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                     Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 62&#13;
&#13;
and    you    can    only   continue      to   serve   while   you    have     the&#13;
&#13;
confidence of the President."             That was seen as ground-breaking&#13;
&#13;
from   the bureaucracy's point             of view.     We were       trying      to&#13;
&#13;
establish accountability for senior managers who had a great&#13;
&#13;
deal of responsibility.&#13;
&#13;
       With Mr. Paijmans we did many things.             We tried to ensure&#13;
&#13;
that   staff    returning     from overseas        assignments       got placed&#13;
&#13;
expeditiously; set up rotational panels which I guess I have&#13;
&#13;
already described to you to assure systematic reassignments; we&#13;
&#13;
introduced collegiate evaluations of managers; we developed a&#13;
&#13;
common view in Operations on who was promotable; we initiated&#13;
&#13;
staff â&#128;¢retreatsâ&#128;¢ etc.&#13;
&#13;
       All of these activities were limited to Operations. We&#13;
&#13;
worked with the people in Personnel because I thought they had&#13;
&#13;
good ideas,         and because I    considered staff development and&#13;
&#13;
communication important. But that, I guess, may have added to&#13;
&#13;
the view "I ran the Bank" because Operations was such a large&#13;
&#13;
chunk of the Bank in terms of staff.             These activities, perhaps&#13;
&#13;
excepting "retreats", did not extend to the other units, such&#13;
&#13;
as Administration, Finance, or Economics Department.&#13;
&#13;
       So I    can see where        the    idea comes    from but      it    is    a&#13;
&#13;
ridiculous overstatement.&#13;
Q:     Now,    on those innovations that you introduced,                 if Mr.&#13;
&#13;
Clausen had wanted to, he could have extended those to other&#13;
&amp;#12;                               Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 63&#13;
parts of the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
A:   Certainly.&#13;
&#13;
Q:   And why wouldn't he?&#13;
&#13;
A:   I don't know.    I never asked him.&#13;
&#13;
Q:   You must have had some perception.       Do you mean he simply&#13;
&#13;
didn't see that as part of his role to pick that up and say,&#13;
&#13;
"Well, this is working here really well in Operations.       Let's&#13;
&#13;
do it in the rest of the Bank as well"?&#13;
&#13;
A:   I have no idea. We certainly reported to him that this was&#13;
&#13;
being done. Maybe he felt that managers in the other units, if&#13;
&#13;
they saw it worked, would want to join. That this was their&#13;
&#13;
responsibility.    But they didn't.&#13;
&#13;
Q:   All right.    Okay.   You know what MEGO is.    My eyes glaze&#13;
&#13;
over. Sometimes when you report to somebody, . they get MEGO when&#13;
&#13;
they are not really interested in what you are saying.&#13;
&#13;
A:   Mr.   Clausen was in fact quite interested in management&#13;
&#13;
issues.    He introduced the staff attitude survey, and Paijmans&#13;
&#13;
worked with him on   a Bank-wide   career development system. A lot&#13;
&#13;
was done on personnel administration during Clausen's time.&#13;
&#13;
There was rotation among the Vice Presidents and a system to&#13;
&#13;
plan management succession.        Mr. Clausen was quite interested&#13;
&#13;
in these issues.&#13;
&#13;
     Why what we were doing at the Operations level did not&#13;
&#13;
spread, I don't know.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                            Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 64&#13;
&#13;
Q:      We have used our time up, but                I   wondered if you just had&#13;
&#13;
any final        reflections      on       the    Presidents under whom you've&#13;
&#13;
served? Some general perceptions of                       these people and their&#13;
&#13;
contribution.&#13;
&#13;
A:      Well,     I    told you       at    the   beginning    that   I   find    that&#13;
&#13;
difficult.            Comparisons like that are hard.              People live in&#13;
&#13;
different times.           And one does not want to be glib about it.&#13;
&#13;
We    have    talked about        Mr.      McNamara.      He was   an exceptional&#13;
&#13;
person--      intellectually very stimulating,                 very challenging,&#13;
&#13;
very driving. That made working for him fun -- certainly for&#13;
&#13;
me.&#13;
&#13;
        Mr. Clausen, who succeeded him,                   had a terrible problem&#13;
&#13;
from the start - he wasn't McNamara. He was succeeding somebody&#13;
&#13;
who many people in the Bank thought was God, or at least his&#13;
&#13;
immediate disciple, and who had been there for 13 years. The&#13;
&#13;
World Bank as it then existed was Bob McNamara's creation. I&#13;
&#13;
don't think anybody could have dealt with that handicap very&#13;
&#13;
well.&#13;
&#13;
        Mr. Clausen had a great deal of experience in finance, and&#13;
&#13;
as a senior manager.              He came from the Bank of America,                the&#13;
&#13;
second largest Bank in the US. He had a good deal of experience&#13;
&#13;
in Latin America and Asia, particularly Japan and China. But he&#13;
&#13;
did     not     have     the   high     level     political    connections       which&#13;
&#13;
McNamara had developed as Secretary of Defense. I think Mr.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                   Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 65&#13;
Clausen, like the rest of us, did not fully realize just how&#13;
much the management structure of the Bank had been designed&#13;
&#13;
around the way Mr. McNamara operated and that the systems for&#13;
&#13;
the management of the Bank by somebody less all-encompassing&#13;
&#13;
weren't really in place.         Or that the vision of the Bank, or&#13;
&#13;
the development agenda, derived so heavily from McNamara.                 In&#13;
&#13;
general,    I   think,    Clausen found he was inheriting something&#13;
&#13;
which wasn't quite the way he thought it was.                 He was a very&#13;
&#13;
good man;       very concerned about poverty and the low income&#13;
&#13;
countries; he was a good manager, who delegated responsibility.&#13;
&#13;
But he did not come to the Bank with a personal development&#13;
&#13;
agenda.    He believed that that would take more knowledge of&#13;
&#13;
development      than he had.    He     expected to   find     that in the&#13;
institution.        And    similarly,    he   expected   to    find   senior&#13;
&#13;
managers who, within a corporate framework,              could be relied&#13;
&#13;
upon to manage effectively. But neither was part of his legacy.&#13;
&#13;
Q:   He did have aspirations to do another term, I suppose?&#13;
&#13;
A:   I think that's probably right; but I am not sure. He was&#13;
&#13;
a little weary of criticism and lack of support from the U.S.&#13;
&#13;
Administration--&#13;
     So I'm not sure how that ultimately would have come out.&#13;
&#13;
But the u.s. decided they wanted somebody else so he had no&#13;
&#13;
choice.     And that of course did hurt him.             But whether he&#13;
&#13;
wouldn't have done the same thing if he'd had a free choice,&#13;
&amp;#12;                                 Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 66&#13;
&#13;
I'm not really sure.&#13;
&#13;
        We have talked about Mr. Conable.       He was misplaced at the&#13;
&#13;
Bank. Mr. Preston, the current President, I think is a great&#13;
&#13;
asset to the Bank.      He is a man who understands management and&#13;
&#13;
the importance of it.       He has been a great supporter of trying&#13;
&#13;
to   improve our operations;      to   repair. things,      if you   like,&#13;
&#13;
damaged or neglected in the Conable era. His emphasis is on&#13;
&#13;
streamlining     the   organization    and    making   it   more   client-&#13;
&#13;
oriented in a real, practical sense.           He believes the Bank is&#13;
&#13;
seriously undermanaged -- a view I share. It's always been the&#13;
&#13;
case.    Unlike McNamara,    he doesn't come to the task with a&#13;
&#13;
development     agenda.     He   is    less    interventionist;       less&#13;
&#13;
prescriptive. He is a great believer in delegated authority,&#13;
&#13;
taking the approach that "We've got to get our senior managers&#13;
&#13;
to use the power they've got in an accountable fashion."                Of&#13;
&#13;
course, the existing policy framework is pretty comprehensive&#13;
&#13;
and well articulated by now --          that was not the case when&#13;
&#13;
McNamara started. Mr. Preston is a firm believer in performance&#13;
&#13;
-- whether by staff or borrowers. So, all told, I think he is&#13;
&#13;
very much on the right track. My great regret is that he, like&#13;
&#13;
his two predecessors,       is likely to be a one-term President,&#13;
&#13;
given his age. Yet, for an institution like this, maybe for any&#13;
&#13;
institution, for a President from the outside to understand the&#13;
&#13;
mandate and the institutional framework and to bring about&#13;
&amp;#12;                                       Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 67&#13;
&#13;
change takes more time than that.&#13;
&#13;
      He and I get along very well and we talk a lot about these&#13;
&#13;
things.       And I think the changes he has helped put in place are&#13;
&#13;
beginning to create a different structure and culture. We now&#13;
&#13;
have the beginning of a cost accounting system; we have more&#13;
&#13;
accountability; we have a budget system which makes sense.                 We&#13;
&#13;
are increasing cost effectiveness.             We are trying to streamline&#13;
&#13;
processes.       And we keep emphasizing that client relationships&#13;
&#13;
are important in a sense that the Bank has not been accustomed&#13;
&#13;
to.   Of course the Bank staff always was concerned about its&#13;
&#13;
clients, because that is what development is about, but it's&#13;
&#13;
also true that we defined our concerns sometimes more than a&#13;
&#13;
little bit,       from the vantage point of what we thought                the&#13;
&#13;
client wanted and needed.&#13;
&#13;
      Of course that will always be true, because if the clients&#13;
&#13;
know exactly what they wanted and needed,                 they wouldn't be&#13;
&#13;
underdeveloped, right?          Well, that is a little flippant. Today&#13;
&#13;
there are many countries capable of defining their objectives&#13;
&#13;
realistically       and   the   help    they   need.    But   in many   other&#13;
&#13;
countries, particularly in Africa, that is not yet the case and&#13;
&#13;
they tend to be too susceptible to outside advice. So there is&#13;
&#13;
always    a    tension at   the bottom of        this    argument.   But   the&#13;
&#13;
attitudes in the Bank were a little off center on this and Mr.&#13;
&#13;
Preston's point, that we have to listen more to the client even&#13;
&amp;#12;                                 Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 68&#13;
&#13;
though   they may   not   be   technically   fully    competent,   is   a&#13;
&#13;
salutary change, very relevant to the changes in the world.&#13;
&#13;
     So, Mr. Preston has got another year and a half to go. I&#13;
&#13;
believe he has put the Bank on the right track and I have been&#13;
&#13;
privileged to help him do that.       I hope the Bank is going to&#13;
&#13;
stay on this track and that the U.S. and the other shareholders&#13;
&#13;
find a successor which will continue on this path.&#13;
&#13;
Q:   But clearly relationships with Mr. Preston didn't shape&#13;
&#13;
your decision to move to another sector.&#13;
&#13;
A:   Not at all. I think I helped to persuade Lew to accept the&#13;
&#13;
offer that had been made to him, because I'd known him from&#13;
&#13;
before. I have apologized to him for leaving him here while I'm&#13;
&#13;
going to his old home base (J.P. Morgan).&#13;
&#13;
     Our relationship has been very good and very productive.&#13;
&#13;
Certainly our relationship has nothing whatsoever to do with my&#13;
&#13;
decision to call it a day.&#13;
&#13;
Q:   But after a lifetime in the public sector why would you&#13;
&#13;
now move to the private sector?&#13;
&#13;
A:   Come and listen to my farewell speech.          Oh, I do not think&#13;
&#13;
there's much mystery to it. Together with my time in AID,               I&#13;
&#13;
have been in public service for 36 years. I have been in the&#13;
&#13;
Bank for almost 25 years. That's a long time. And of course, no&#13;
&#13;
matter how exciting the development challenges, the umpteenth&#13;
&#13;
Board meeting, the umpteenth argument about the budget, or the&#13;
&amp;#12;                                     Stern (January 20, 1995), Page 69&#13;
&#13;
umpteenth    debate   about     this    or   that    does   get   a     little&#13;
&#13;
wearisome. I have always told staff in the Bank that the Bank&#13;
&#13;
is not the only place in the world.          They should go and sample&#13;
&#13;
the outside.    What I'm doing is a little late in my career, I&#13;
&#13;
recognize, but I just thought it was time for a change. But if&#13;
&#13;
I was going to do something else I really have to do it now&#13;
&#13;
because, Mr. Preston has got a year and a half to go and he&#13;
&#13;
ought to have time to build a new new management team. I should&#13;
&#13;
not walk out together with him because that would be unfair to&#13;
&#13;
his successor. And even if the successor would not want me to&#13;
&#13;
stay, I'd be super-annuated by then and would find it hard to&#13;
&#13;
find   an   interesting   job   in     the private    sector.     The   exact&#13;
&#13;
timing, now or March or April, that wasn't so important, that&#13;
&#13;
was determined by the outside, the availability of offers.                But&#13;
&#13;
I thought I should leave a decent period before the end of Mr.&#13;
&#13;
Preston's tenure.     So I think that's all that's involved.             And,&#13;
&#13;
after all, changing gears after 36 years is not doing it too&#13;
&#13;
frequently, is it?&#13;
&#13;
       I will be dealing with emerging markets in J. P. Morgan,&#13;
&#13;
much the same clientele, but from a different perspective.&#13;
&#13;
Q:     Well, thank you very much.&#13;
&#13;
       [END OF RECORDING, TAPE 2, SIDE 2]&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="17985829">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1995/01/17985829/transcript-oral-history-interview-ernest-stern-held-december-16-29-1994-january-5-1995-vol-4-4-fourth-interview-session
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1995/01/17985829/transcript-oral-history-interview-ernest-stern-held-december-16-29-1994-january-5-1995-vol-4-4-fourth-interview-session</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1995/01/17985829/transcript-oral-history-interview-ernest-stern-held-december-16-29-1994-january-5-1995-vol-4-4-fourth-interview-session</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2008-03-27T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2008-03-27T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2013/07/10/000333037_20130710143902/Rendered/INDEX/791290v40TRN0S0Box0377367B00PUBLIC0.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2013/07/10/000333037_20130710143902/Rendered/PDF/791290v40TRN0S0Box0377367B00PUBLIC0.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2013-07-10T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1995-01-20T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>4</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>4</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Transcript of oral history interview with
            Ernest Stern held on December 16 and 29, 1994, and January
            5, 1995
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            On December 16 and 29, 1994, and January
            5, 1995, Ernest Stern was interviewed on behalf of the World
            Bank Group Archives oral history program by Jochen Kraske,
            Louis Galambos, and David Milobsky. During his tenure at the
            World Bank from 1968 to 1995, Mr. Stern worked in the
            following areas: for the Pearson commission as deputy to the
            executive secretary and staff director (1968-1972); in the
            office of the vice president as senior advisor for
            development policy (1972-1974) and as director (1974-1975);
            as vice president in the South Asia regional office
            (1975-1978) and in operations (1978-1980); as senior vice
            president in operations (1980-1987) and in finance
            (1987-1991); as a member of the policy committee (1987-1991)
            and as managing director (1991-1995). He helped supervise
            the preparation of the landmark first World Development
            Report in 1977. He discusses at length the United States
            International Cooperation Administration (ICA) and its
            subsequent change to the Agency for International
            Development (AID). His transcript also concerns the budget
            office, the staff association, and congressional approval.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Fourth interview session
        </docna>
        <display_title>Transcript of oral history
            interview with Ernest Stern held on December 16 and 29,
            1994, and January 5, 1995 (Vol. 4) : Fourth interview session</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/1995/01/17985829/transcript-oral-history-interview-ernest-stern-held-december-16-29-1994-january-5-1995-vol-4-fourth-interview-session</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Transcript</docty>
        <subtopic>Access to Finance,Banks &amp; Banking Reform,Financial Intermediation,Debt Markets,Bankruptcy and Resolution of Financial Distress</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000333037_20130710143902</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>World Bank Group Archives oral history program</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Board Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            access to credit, accountability, adjustment
            loans, advanced economies, agricultural products,
            agricultural sector, auditing, balance of payment, balance
            of payments, balance sheets, bank lending, Bank policies,
            banking system, bankrupt, borrower, borrowing, borrowing
            requirement, budgeting, business plan, capital flows,
            capital requirements, cash flow, central banks, civil
            service, commercial bank, commercial bank lending,
            commercial banking, commercial banks, commodity price,
            Commodity prices, counterpart funds, creditor,
            creditworthiness, cross default, currency, current account,
            current account deficit, debt, debt crisis, debt problem,
            debt reductions, Debt service, decentralization, developing
            countries, developing country, disbursement, disbursements,
            economic systems, Economics, employment, employment
            opportunities, entrepreneurial activity, equity issue,
            expatriate, expatriates, Expenditures, exporters, external
            borrowing, external capital, external financing, face value,
            farmers, Finance Ministries, financial flows, financial
            markets, financial planning, fiscal policy, fixed interest,
            foreign investment, fuel taxes, General Counsel, governance
            issues, holding, income distribution, income groups,
            inflation, inflationary policies, informal arrangements,
            institutional infrastructure, interest rate, interest rate
            risk, interest rates, legislation, lender, lender of last
            resort, lending instrument, leverage, liquidity, liquidity
            problem, living standard, loan, loan agreements, loan
            policy, loan program, macroeconomic adjustments, mandate,
            market prices, maturity, monetary policy, monetary value,
            negotiations, nutrition, order of priority, political risks,
            portfolio, portfolio supervision, portfolios, private banks,
            private capital, private investment, procurement,
            productivity, project financing, public services, purchasing
            power, real interest, real interest rates, regional banks,
            remedy, reorganization, repayment, repayment record,
            resource allocation, resource mobilization, return, returns,
            shareholders, social safety nets, social services, sovereign
            debt, sovereign risk, sovereign risk lending, structural
            adjustment, structural problem, structural problems,
            systemic risk, technical assistance, trade liberalization,
            trade regime, Treasury, woman
        </keywd>
        <owner>Knowledge &amp; Information Services (ITSKI)</owner>
        <repnb>79129</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fragility, Conflict and Violence</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Technological Change</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Capacities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Staffing Needs Assessments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crops</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets and Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pensions &amp; Retirement Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deconcentration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delegation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Devolution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sub-National Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subnational Government and Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Market Access</ml:concept><ml:concept>Checks on Executive Power</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen User Satisfaction Survey</ml:concept><ml:concept>Independent Commissions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ombudsmen</ml:concept><ml:concept>Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Parliament</ml:concept><ml:concept>Procurement Complaints Review Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supreme Audit Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Armed Conflict</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Treasury</ml:concept><ml:concept>Technology Transfer and Diffusion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>Reparations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pensions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Administrative Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Accountability Mechanisms</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>