<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>24278&#13;
April 2002&#13;
z&#13;
= ~A Water Scorecard&#13;
I-I&#13;
Ni!coltl 7;'1Zba11 nt7f1 Bill  Setting Performance Targets for Water Utilities&#13;
Using data from 246 water utilities in SI developed and developing&#13;
Vlc/I 7j7fy7 s 11countries, this Note highlights the wide variation in performance on key&#13;
am%tatl11t piofvessoi of&#13;
ecoylo011lls a ,f Dickm%I{J  indicators: unaccounted-for water, labor costs, the working ratio, service&#13;
O   CRlege 1Z e)t7^1vf1lll coverage, water prices and connection costs, and continuityr of service. On&#13;
ralpi,, a,,,,1 saii,atiZoi  the basis of the performance of the top 25 percent of developing country&#13;
r   speccrliv/ls/ thl//e lVoild1  utilities, the Note proposes "best practice" targets for developing countries.&#13;
e:  Batik1 HP eZ1 Wtltrh&#13;
B,,7ik'% rffmste II 11a )te?&#13;
=                      ~~~~~~~~~~~Thlcpe-foli-iiaiiceofwatei-titilitiescaiI beassessed  aCCOLIllt for- 70 per-ceiit of asset xaltie buIt ar-e&#13;
Umlsaiito         ililit    IIg fotul br-oad  Illsue-,sL S  cfficciincv of  mivest-  oftien neglectcli in  favor of  miot-e visible assets.&#13;
O m~~~~~~~~~~ieiit, eflicileiicy of operations anclI mainaten1ance,  Dn -ect m-eastii-es of asset maintenlance are&#13;
z   Prepaiteotiofl olhlls fVole&#13;
fiiiaiicial SLItainabil. ility, aii(i r esponsiveness to ctis-&#13;
TovfitiN llded/ b)t SI&amp;   E?ig               I11,XCX.., &#13;
z         '       {    ~~~~~~~torners Tlus N\olC Luses Clat.t fiom11 theC World  l 1 -1 &#13;
_1:d 117 1 ileyr I)ep7fin1lewl  of&#13;
Illr l1'orlfl en/7* ~~~~Baink's   Bend 1imar king   WaLer-  ancl SainitaLiol1  *  Developed country utdilites  * Developing country utilites&#13;
o                      ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~UtiliLles database anicl fi-omi tiie ,Msiaii Develop-  _Unaccounted-for water&#13;
,                       me~~~~~~~~~~~~iclit B3aiik to rev ew Llhe perflormliance of a saiili-  supplied (percent)  Utilities&#13;
,_                     ~~~~~~~~~~~~ple Of Lt-liLies The samiple inCILKICeSLtilltiC% II all  0  5  10  15  20  25  30  35&#13;
&lt;                       r ~~~~~~~~~~~~Iegiolis anll( III COtuliLies at all iincoiile icvels; half  0_&#13;
~~~~~~~~~~~~~~(123) are in 44 developinigcoLiiti-ies. The utilitieKs     105&#13;
IL                     r~~~~~~~~~iatige ti-oiii smiall (sei-vinig a popullationl of less  15 o w~&#13;
O                      ~~~~~~~~~~thiail 125,000) to miecitiiii (IY25,000-500,000) aind  20 5 _mow&#13;
-                       l~~~~~~~~~~~~arge (miore Llhaii 500,000), %zridi at least 30 uitili-  25 ii_s&#13;
0~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~3&#13;
Y                      ~~~~~~~~~~~ties fi-omi devieloping COLIII tries ancl 30 fi-om- clevel-  35 1~&#13;
z                               oped COLI1tLt es iln eachi category.             4°5 &#13;
W                                                                                 50c&#13;
ffi                    ~~~~~~~~~~~~Efficiency of investment               650_&#13;
Thian and  U      lilvestting Pnerassnts shOLCOCCL o    r Ivwaie te  65 UL&#13;
Uabsolutnda necessafry-and to  utSltI esffiCled     oe, 70n&#13;
3Cp   f pfesso of      lonig-l ll opes,atios of existhig assets,  tiaily widao- 80  &#13;
Lefai 1      1                    indce Icaos Clical MailcLcouteace is paLter,Lla orlv&#13;
tollege on lcnlana     coverage,waterprices and con          tio  c   os, Andcalc on nuiy Worl  vi nk (001) and ciosh and&#13;
t- )ecialiot at th _'I'ailil  uiplties, the Noc pipe nctvorgks, vliicif trypically oitgUtp 1199 fp&#13;
Bank He leadi the~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
A WATER     SCORECARD      SETTING PERFORMANCE TARGETS FOR WATER UTI LITIES&#13;
ing coIIntry utilities report more than 20 statf&#13;
per I,000 connectiois. The mean value for&#13;
9   Developed country utilities * Developing country utilities  developed countiy utilities is 2.1 staff&#13;
2s      0      10     20Utilities                     These hligh ratios in1 developing countries&#13;
0      10     20     30     40     50     may mean that single water coninections are serv-&#13;
04r                                         ing multiple hotiseholds Or they may reflect&#13;
05                                          loose employment practices, often a restult of&#13;
0 6                                         political interference in the water- company's&#13;
2                                      0 8                                         operation. (Recent water sector reforimis, sucIh as&#13;
09   _                                       those in Buenos Aires and Manila, shiow that util-&#13;
I 0                                         ities can sListaiin services wvith significantly feweI-&#13;
12m                                         employees.) The staff ratios achievecl by the top&#13;
13 .                                        25 percent of developing country utilities In the&#13;
_14in1&#13;
I 5_'                                       sample steggest that a target of 5 or fewer stafl' per&#13;
1 6                                         1,000 connectionis is achiev'able.&#13;
1 7 1                                         A second indicator- of operational efficiency&#13;
1 9                                         is staff per 1,000 people served, whicih elimi-&#13;
20                   _nates the distortion caused when single water-&#13;
More                                         connections serve mtiltiple houselholds This&#13;
Note iee the text ior a deinioon of workingr ntio  measure tOO suggests excess labor in developmg&#13;
Sourte Authorsi  alculationso bated on data Irom Word  Bank (12001) and Mcitosh and&#13;
Okiguer (1997)                                cotontry utiolities. So dloes a thil-d measuore com-&#13;
normally unavailable, so sterrogates are needed    bining wages and staffing to give personinel costs&#13;
A  crtide  measure   of asset maintenance    Is    as a share of total operating costs. 29 percent in&#13;
unaccotiuitecl-for water-the differenice betwvei   developed countries and 39 percent in devel-&#13;
water supploecl and water sold as a percenitage of  oping COUlntrieCS&#13;
water stipplied (figture 1) This meastore capttires&#13;
not only physical losses but also comimler-cial    Financial sustainability&#13;
losses, due to inefficient billing or illegal con-  Failure to cover costs leads to tinderinvestmeint&#13;
nections. Thus highi levels of uiaccotinted-fo-    in assets, weakened operations, ancl declininig&#13;
water- idicate poor system   managemilenit ancd&#13;
pooI- ctommer-cial pracLices as well as imadeqtiate&#13;
pipelinc mainteniance.                              9        Developed eountry utilities * Developing country utilities&#13;
Based on the performanice of the top 25 per-     J    Accounts receivable in&#13;
months of sales   Utilities&#13;
cent of developing country titilities, a target for       0   5  10 15 20 25 30 35 40      45  50&#13;
utnaccotieitecl-for water of less thani 23 percenit is   0&#13;
recommended. (The mean for developed coun-              I-_&#13;
trees is 16 percent..) Achieving this tar-get requlir-es  2&#13;
recducing both physical and commer-cial losses           4&#13;
-5-&#13;
Efficiency of operations and maintenance                 6 -&#13;
Operationial efficiency is defined as the lowest-        7 -&#13;
cost use of inputs-labor, energy, water, and             9&#13;
materials-in the claily operation of' a utility.         10&#13;
The   most eflficient combination    of inputs          11 &#13;
12&#13;
clepends in part on local Input prices and past         13 m&#13;
capital investment decisions                             14&#13;
To meastire operational efficiency, analysts          15&#13;
use ratios of inputs to outputs One such ratio is       16&#13;
stall per 1,000 connections. A high ratio may          Source Authors oalcatiDons, based on data from Word Bank (2001) and McIntosh and&#13;
indicate inefficienit tuse of staff Many develop-      Yitguer (1991)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Responsiveness to customers&#13;
Customer focus is assessed on the basis of cover-&#13;
A                                                  age, affordability, and quality of service&#13;
Connection fee as&#13;
4   a share of per capita&#13;
GDP (percent)       Utilities                  Coverage&#13;
0      5       10     is     20     25      In most urban settings a pipe network is thie&#13;
10                                           cheapest and most effective means of supplying&#13;
15                                           water-wvhether through individual hotise COI1-&#13;
20                                           nections or shared yard connectionis The share&#13;
50                                           of households covered by pipe networks differs&#13;
35                                           significanitly between developed and cleveloping&#13;
40&#13;
45°                                          country tutilities. In developed cotenti-ies cover-&#13;
50                                           age rates exceed 99 percent, and all btit two util-&#13;
55                                           ities have 100 percent coverage In developing&#13;
60&#13;
More *                                         countries coverage rates range from 100 percenit&#13;
to a lowv of 18 percent For sewerage, the worst&#13;
Source Author  calculanons based orn data from Word Bank (21001) and McIntosh and&#13;
ltEguea (1997)                                  coverage rates are even lower. The proposed tar-&#13;
get is I 00 percent coverage with alpp5roltnale levels&#13;
service qutality. Definitions of cost recovery vary,  of service for each hotisehold The top qtuartile of&#13;
with ntLcic debate on issues relatinig to capital    developing cotintry utilities in the sample have&#13;
asset valLies and rates of return on investmeit,     achieved this tat-get.&#13;
A simple measuLre of cost recovery is the&#13;
working ratio-the ratio of total anntial opera-      Affordability&#13;
tional expenses, excluding depreciation and          Two indicator-s of access to new coninections are&#13;
debt service, to total anniual pretax collections    important the cost of a new coninectioni and the&#13;
fiom billing and subsicies A working ratio of        waiting time for a connection No data are avail-&#13;
more thani I means that a utility fails to recover   able on waiting times, but figtires for connec-&#13;
even its operating costs fromil annual revenue,      tion fees, rotigily normalized against anntial&#13;
while a ratio of less than 1 means that it covers    per capita GDP, show     that for some of the&#13;
all operating costs, plis some or all of its capital&#13;
costs The proposed target working ratio for               .&#13;
developing countiiity titilities is 0 68, the pet-          * Developed country utilities * Developing country utilities&#13;
tormilaniic  arclievecl by the top qual-tile of utill-    Annual cet of 20 liters&#13;
ties in developing countries as wvell as the mean         a day as a share of per&#13;
for those in developed countries (figfure 2).             capita GDP (percent)  Utilities&#13;
0     10   20    30    40    50    60&#13;
Finaicial stistainability also requires timely           0 00&#13;
collection of payments. A common measure of                 002&#13;
efficiency In this area is the collection period-           0 04&#13;
accoulIts receivable as a share of annual rev-              0.00&#13;
enties, expressed in months of sales (figul-e 3).           0 10&#13;
The recommended collection period is 3                   012 -&#13;
monthis or less. At first glance that target looks          0 14&#13;
ambitious the top quartile of developing coun-              0 16&#13;
tty titilities In the salmple achieves a perforimianice     0 20&#13;
of 9 7 montils. Btit closer inspection of the               022&#13;
results for the top qiar-tile reveals a clear division      0 26&#13;
into cltusters, with one grotip achieving a collec-         0 29.&#13;
tion periocd of 4 months or less, and another a              3or n0o30&#13;
collectioni period of more than 8 months. The            Source Aunhon'caions. based an data fom World Bark (20u) and McIntosh and&#13;
dleveloped country average is 1.8 months.                lgtauez (1997)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
A WATER     SCORECARD      SETTING PERFORMANCE TARGETS FOR WATER UTI LITIES&#13;
show the burden on consumers in developing&#13;
coiinti-ies anicl Lnclerline the need to cut costs&#13;
I?.    * Developed (ountry utilities * Developing country utilities&#13;
6    Hours of service                              Quality&#13;
a day             UtilitiesQu                    lt&#13;
0      30     60     90     120    150     The quality of service has several dimenesions-     viewpoint&#13;
2                                           water availability, water qctallty, water pressure,       X&#13;
46                                          and customer relations. But the only one for&#13;
8X                                          which the sample provides sufficienit data is&#13;
I                                            water aaiabity, as captred by the contiity         is an open forum to&#13;
12 n                                                                                            encourage dissemination of&#13;
141                                          of service (10oUrIs of service a day). Based on the  public policy innovations for&#13;
16 a                                         perform-lanice of the top quartile of developing   private sector-led and&#13;
18                                           country utilities, the recommended target is 24    market-based solutions for&#13;
22                                           hour-s a day (figure 6).                           development. The views&#13;
24&#13;
published are those of the&#13;
SDurce Authors' salculaons,i bused on data Irom Wodd Bank 12001) and Mdntosh and   Conclusion     authors and  should  not be&#13;
tOi5unz (1997)&#13;
The indicator-s and proposed targets captLre a     attributed to the World&#13;
broad range of perform-lance measuLes for ttil]l-  Bank or any other affiliated&#13;
developing counti-y utilities the fees are clearly  ties. They are not comprehensive More wvork is     organizations. Nor do any of&#13;
tinaffor-dable (figture 4) In some cases they      needed to provide a Inore complete assessment       the conclusions represent&#13;
exceecl 60 percent of per capita GDP               of utility performance, expanding the measures      official policy of the World&#13;
The connection fee is often what prevents       to governance and accountability, to capital effi-  Bank or of its Executive&#13;
people from obtaining piped water supplies-        ciency, and to better measures of responsiveness    Directors or the countries&#13;
once connected, consumer-s can usually pay         to the needs ofthe poor Still, the key point is that  they represent.&#13;
their usage fees The data in figure 4 suggest a    the target indicators covered here are benng&#13;
rule of thumb for conniection fees most titilities  achieved by 25 percent of developing countr-ies   To order additional copies&#13;
in developing countr-ies should charge connlec-    in the data set These targets canl be achieved by   contact Suzanne Smith,&#13;
tion fees equivalent to nlo more than 20 percent   the rest by strengtheniniig the focus on ctistomers,  managing editor,&#13;
of per capita GDP.                                 Improving governance, providung incentives for      Room 19-017,&#13;
Water prices depend in part on local condi-     Litllty managers to lift performance-somethinig     The World Bank,&#13;
tionls. BeCCatse family income, houselld coIn-     they often lack-and finally, if necessary, raising  Wastreet, NW,&#13;
sumptioni, and constiiners per connection vary     tarifls&#13;
considerably amonig countrites, most sUmmary                                                           Telephone&#13;
tariff meastires (such as average cost per cubic                                                      001 202 458 7281&#13;
meter) are more useful for comparing titilities                                                        Fax&#13;
wilthli  countries than for comparing themii       References                                          001 2025223181&#13;
across COu1ntries A roughl mcasurc for compar-        Mclntosh, Alrthiur C, and Cesar E Yfiig_ci, eds 1997  Email&#13;
ison across couLntries, however, is the afford-    Serond Wilate.i Utilities Data Book Manila Asian Developimient  ssmith7@worldbank org&#13;
ability of the minimum water requirement set by    Bank&#13;
the World Health Organiizationi-the annual            World Bank 2001 BeinchmarkanigWVatci aldSanulitioin&#13;
cost of 20 liter-s a day as a share of per capita  Utiliticsdatuibase [tttp //\wwx+s worldbtrrikoig/hiinl/fpd/  Printed on recycled paper&#13;
GDP.                                               water-/topics/benclh_nlenevor-k hi tml]&#13;
Calculations based on the average tariff for&#13;
each utility in the sample slhow that in devel-     Viaola 'J7uinan, I&#143;coloonocs D)eprlnurnt, Drokinvon College&#13;
oped countries customers of the highest quar-      (1ynanin@dhrkinsown edit), and Bdil Kingdom, Water and&#13;
tile of utllities (those charginig the highest     Samntation Unit, 1W1zo1ld Bank (uoingdomtinoonl-bank orgJ&#13;
prices) pay the eqLiivalent of 0.036-0.120 per-&#13;
cent of per capita GDP for 20 liters of water a&#13;
day (figure 5). In developing countries cus-&#13;
tomers of the highest quartile pay more thani 0 2&#13;
percent of annual per capita GDP These results&#13;
This Note is available online:&#13;
www.worldbank.orglhtmllfpd/notesI&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1799495">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2002/04/1799495/water-scorecard-setting-performance-targets-water-utilities
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <virt_coll>Knowledge Notes</virt_coll>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2002/04/1799495/water-scorecard-setting-performance-targets-water-utilities</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2002/04/1799495/water-scorecard-setting-performance-targets-water-utilities</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2002/06/24/000094946_02060704033047/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2002/06/24/000094946_02060704033047/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2002-04-30T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2002-07-02T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            A water scorecard - setting performance
            targets for water utilities
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            This note highlights the wide variation
            in performance on key indicators: unaccounted-for water,
            labor costs, the working ratio, service coverage, water
            prices and connection costs, and continuity of service. As
            governments struggle with rising health care costs,
            public-private partnerships in constructing and managing
            public hospitals can provide innovative ways to control
            costs and improve service. Experience shows that such
            partnerships offer significant benefits as long as
            policymakers structure the transactions carefully and create
            sound regulatory arrangements to ensure universal access,
            quality care, and improvements in efficiency.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            A water scorecard - setting performance
            targets for water utilities
        </docna>
        <display_title>A water scorecard - setting
            performance targets for water utilities</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2002/04/1799495/water-scorecard-setting-performance-targets-water-utilities</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Viewpoint</docty>
        <subtopic>Town Water Supply and Sanitation,Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Water Supply and Sanitation Governance
            and Institutions,Water Conservation,Water and Industry</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Environment,Water Supply and Sanitation,Water Resources</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Tyman, Nicola</author>
            <author>Kingdom, Bill</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000094946_02060704033047</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Other Water Supply &amp; Sanitation</subsc>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>Public policy for the private sector ; Note
            no. 242</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Environment,Water Supply and Sanitation,Water Resources</historic_topic>
        <sectr>Water, sanitation and flood protection</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Water utilities; Performance indicators;
            Unaccounted for water; Labor costs; Service coverage; Water prices
            Bend,broad range,Connection fee,cost
            recovery,customer relations,debt,developed
            countries,employment,Hours of
            service,households,income,Input prices,investment
            decisions,labor costs,operational efficiency,pipe
            network,piped water,quality of service,service
            Quality,wages,water availability,water pressure,water
            prices,water sector,water supplies,water utilities
        </keywd>
        <owner>Private Sctr Devel &amp; Infrastr VP (PSI)</owner>
        <repnb>24278</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wastewater Collection and Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Basic Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>On-site Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Marketing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Economics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Pricing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wage Setting</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages, Compensation and Benefits</ml:concept><ml:concept>Town Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sewerage</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Allocation and Water Economics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>