<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>﻿                                  79103&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
THE WORLD BANK/IFC ARCHIVES&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  ORAL HISTORY PROGRAM&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   Transcript of interview with&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   SIR DENIS H. F. RICKETT&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Date: August 20. 1986&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      By: Charles Ziegler&#13;
&amp;#12;The world Bank/IFC oral History Proqram&#13;
Memorialist's name: Sir Denis H.F. Rickett&#13;
Date of Interview: August 20, 1986&#13;
Place of Interview: Salisbury, England&#13;
Interviewer's name: Charles Ziegler&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER: Today is August 20, 1986. My name is Charles Ziegler of the World Bank's&#13;
Oral History Program, and I'm here at the home of Sir Denis Rickett in Salisbury, England, to discuss&#13;
with him his career at the World Bank.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Sir Denis, I am wondering if you could begin by just reviewing, very briefly for the record, the&#13;
course of your career at the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
RICKETT: Yes, my first contact with the Bank was in the summer of 1954. I was then Economic&#13;
Minister at the British Embassy in Washington where I had been since August 1951. From 1951 to&#13;
1954 the Executive Directors of the Bank and Fund were separate from the Embassy. But in the&#13;
summer of 1954, when Sir Edmund Hall-Patch retired--he being at that time the British Executive&#13;
Director of the Bank and the Fund--I recommended that he should not be replaced in that capacity but&#13;
that the position of the Executive Director of the Bank and Fund should be amalgamated with the&#13;
position of Economic Minister. Obviously, with that additional burden of work, the Economic Minister&#13;
would not be able to handle everything at the Bank and Fund that affected us himself, but would have&#13;
to rely to a considerable extent on his Alternate Directors both of the Bank and the Fund. This&#13;
recommendation was accepted, and I think that a similar system has also been adopted by one or two&#13;
other governments. When I completed my three year term as Economic Minister in Washington in&#13;
October of that year, I was succeeded by Lord Harcourt, and he was Executive Director of the Bank&#13;
and the Fund as well as Economic Minister. So, for a short period of three or four months, I was an&#13;
Executive Director in the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    I don't remember much about the detailed decisions that came before the Board. The main&#13;
episode, which I do remember, was a series of discussions, including even an unprecedented meeting&#13;
after dinner on the question of whether Czechoslovakia should remain a member of the Bank.&#13;
&amp;#12;RICKETT                                            -2-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
[RICKETT)&#13;
The Fund had determined that Czechoslovakia should be expelled from the Fund because they refused&#13;
to give any statistics on their balance of payments, which they said were a military secret. As far as the&#13;
Bank was concerned, I don't remember that they had defaulted on their obligations. Maybe they had&#13;
refused to accept some additional subscription or something of that kind. At any rate, after some&#13;
prolonged discussion, they were asked to leave and we therefore, no longer had an Iron Curtain&#13;
country as a member. Before Czechoslovakia left, Poland had been a member but had also withdrawn&#13;
from the Bank and the Fund.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    After I went back to London to work in the Overseas Finance Division of the Treasury, I had no&#13;
direct contact with the Bank--though naturally I was interested in Bank and Fund affairs--until1958,&#13;
when Sir Leslie Rowan retired and I succeeded him as head of the Division. I then became the U.K.&#13;
Alternate Governor in the Bank. Then fmally, when I retired from the the British Treasury in 1968,&#13;
Mr. Woods asked me to join the Bank staff as a fourth Vice President. They ouly had four then. He&#13;
told me that he wanted me to concentrate on the relations between the Bank and what we called the&#13;
Part One countries who contributed the funds of IDA [International Development Association) and to&#13;
pay frequent visits to the Ministers and top officials in the various capitals in order to make sure that&#13;
they were given all the information and explanation of the Bank policies that they wanted. This was&#13;
what I tried to do. Mr. Woods had retired by the time I reached the Bank. In fact, Mr. McNamara and&#13;
I took up our appointments on the same day, April!, 1968.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    When I arrived only two days later, a large part of Washington was in flames after the&#13;
assassination of Dr. Martin Luther King, and I remember staying in the house of a friend in&#13;
Georgetown with the National Guard camping in the garden and with a curfew of 4:30 p.m. in force&#13;
each day. That episode fortunately passed away, though I believe that there are still parts of 14th&#13;
Street which have not been rebuilt.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    The work of liaison with the Part One countries very soon became mainly concerned with the&#13;
successive Replenishments of IDA--the International Development Association. The first thing I had&#13;
to do was to go around and solicit advance contributions for the Second Replenishment, because owing&#13;
to delay in the United States deposit of their notification, which resulted from difficulties with the&#13;
&amp;#12;RICKETT                                           -3-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
[RICKETT)&#13;
Congress, the agreement had not come in to force, and in the meantime it was important that IDA&#13;
should not run out of commitment authority. So I went to a numher of European capitals, starting with&#13;
London, to press for these advance contributions. And in the end I think we got a very satisfactory list&#13;
of contributors which enabled us to keep up the process of granting IDA credits.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    I did also carry out one or two special missions on hehalf of other members of the President's&#13;
Council. For example, Siem Aldewereld was Vice President of Finance, and he asked me to help in&#13;
lobbying the central bank Governors, whom I had come in contact with in my Treasury days, to make&#13;
the largest possible contributions to our successive issues of two-year World Bank bonds and to&#13;
persuade them to treat these as a first class reserve asset. But maiuly my work at that stage was on the&#13;
IDA Replenishments, and after we had obtained the advance contributions on the Second&#13;
Replenishment we hegan to prepare for the Third Replenishment.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    I won't try to enter into the details of the negotiations, which were complicated and difficult. The&#13;
main problem was to fmd a combination of the total of the Replenishment with a system of burden&#13;
sharing which would produce the best results for the Bank. If there were countries which didn't wish to&#13;
have a high total for the Replenishment, one could consider reducing their percentage contribution. In&#13;
the case of the Third Replenishment, in contrast to what happened subsequently, we got the strongest&#13;
possible support from the United States administration. Mr. John Petty, Assistant Secretary of the&#13;
U.S. Treasury, was their representative in the negotiations, and he, I think, led the way in proposing a&#13;
figure of $1 billion a year for the three-year Replenishment, which would have been more than double&#13;
the Second Replenishment total of $400 million a year.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    The difficulty in the Third Replenishment, therefore, was not in any sense due to lack of&#13;
cooperation from the United States, but from the French and the Germans. The French took the view&#13;
that since they were one of the few countries which had achieved the UN target of 0.75 percent of GNP&#13;
in official development assistance and since they had a large bilateral assistance program, it was not&#13;
reasonable to ask them to accept a substantial increase in their contribution to IDA. The German&#13;
Government, for different reasons, were also against an appreciable increase in the IDA&#13;
Replenishment and, therefore, a somewhat unholy alliance hetween Monsieur Giscard d'Estaing&#13;
&amp;#12;RICKETI                                            -4-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
(RICKETI)&#13;
and Professor Schiller, the German Finance Minister, made itself apparent, and they tried to limit the&#13;
amount of the replenishment to $600 million a year.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    We managed to outflank Dr. Schiller by making a concession to the French on the size of their&#13;
percentage contribution, which we agreed to reduce--I think it was by one-and-a-half percentage&#13;
points. I haven't got that figure exactly in mind. At any rate, it reduced their percentage to six percent,&#13;
and six percent of $1 billion was much more manageable for them than would have been seven-and-a-&#13;
half percent. They were quite happy to accept that solution, and in the end, because of continuing&#13;
difficulty with the Germans, we compromised on the figure of $800 million, somewhat to the&#13;
disappointment of eight or uine other governments who had all accepted the annual total $1 billion.&#13;
However, we felt that $800 million in the circumstances was not unsatisfactory.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    There then followed the usual difficulty in getting the ratification of the agreement. One had every&#13;
sympathy with the U.S. administration, because they had to deal with Mr. (Otto) Passman, who was&#13;
Chairman of the House Appropriations Subcommittee, and was a violent opponent of foreign aid and&#13;
made everything as difficult as could be. I think I remember rightly in saying that in the case of the&#13;
Third Replenishment also we had to ask for advance contributions to keep IDA supplied with&#13;
commitment authority before the agreement entered into force. So much for the Third&#13;
Replenishment. As I say, the interval between the Third and the Fourth Replenishments was to some&#13;
extent taken up with the soliciting of advance contributions.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    I did at that time have an additional assignment. Mr. McNamara decided to commission a staff&#13;
study of the problem of indebtedness, and with the able assistance of John Adler and with a consultant&#13;
whom we recruited from Stockhohn, we produced a study which no doubt today would look much too&#13;
optimistic because we hadn't had the the two shocks from the oil price increase followed by another&#13;
shock of an oil price decrease.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    The broad conclusion was that there were three long-term debtors who would always require&#13;
substantial amounts of concessional aid--the Indians, the Egyptians and the lndonesians. At the other&#13;
extreme there were those small landlocked, very low income countries in Africa which were so poor&#13;
&amp;#12;RICKETI                                           -5-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
(RICKETT]&#13;
that they could never be creditworthy. They had no debt problem, because they had no debt. No one&#13;
would lend to them and, therefore, as far as capital flow from abroad went it had to be entirely in terms&#13;
of concessional aid, whether bilateral or multilateral. The third class that we distinguished was that of&#13;
countries who were well up in the middle income group at that time--Argentina, Brazil, Mexico, some&#13;
others--whose main problem was that they had borrowed a large amount of money at very short term,&#13;
and they had no prospect then of meeting their immediate obligations over the coming year. It seemed&#13;
clear that the remedy for them would have to be rescheduling agreements which would spread the&#13;
debts out over a longer period ahead.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    I think the debt study fmally went to the Executive Board in the summer of 1970. I'm not quite&#13;
sure of this date. We tried to get agreement on an early warning system. We tried to get agreement&#13;
with the Bank and the Fund together to prepare assessments of creditworthiness for different&#13;
countries. This was violently opposed by the Executive Directors for Mexico and for Brazil on the&#13;
ground that it wouldn't help, it would hinder. It would precipitate a loss of confidence in countries&#13;
whic~   were nearing the borders of creditworthiness. So that recommendation fell by the wayside.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    After that we began to make preparations for the negotiations for the Fourth Replenishment. We&#13;
were having great difficulty in getting adequate advance contributions to bridge the gap resulting from&#13;
a delay in the coming into force of the Third Replenishment because of the very critical attitude which&#13;
the U.S. Administration was taking. They wanted--under pressure from the Congress, to a large&#13;
extent--to stretch out the Third Replenishment and see it committed over four years instead of three&#13;
years, but eventually we found a modus vivendi. We arrived at a formula which enabled discussions to&#13;
start and we started in January, I think, 1972 with a meeting in Paris at which there was quite an&#13;
encouraging response from an appreciable majority of the countries concerned in a favor of an armual&#13;
total of $1500 million. That was before the Smithsonian Agreement. Ftfteen hundred million old&#13;
dollars was the equivalent of 1650 million new dollars after the Smithsonian Agreement.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    The United States representative, Mr. (John M.) Hennessey, the then Assistant Secretary of the&#13;
Treasury, who had taken over from Mr. Petty, was very sympathetic, but he was under strict orders&#13;
from the Secretary, Mr. (John) Connolly, and under strong pressure too from contacts with the&#13;
Congress, not to commit the United States to anything at that stage.&#13;
&amp;#12;RICKETI'                                             -6-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
(RICKETI']&#13;
     Following our practice of trying to build up a consensus of the more helpful countries and&#13;
generously inclined countries, we asked to have to have a series of meetings at which we could&#13;
gradually organize a majority in favor of a reasonable total. We tried to fix a meeting in London in&#13;
March. The United States representative said he thought it quite useless to do that. The United States&#13;
would not be able to make any statement about its position. We said, well, never mind. It is useful to&#13;
us to know the position of the other countries, and we had the meeting in March. It was to be followed&#13;
by a further meeting in the summer in Tokyo.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    The United States was not only refusing to commit itself, but it was also pressing very strongly for&#13;
a substantial reduction in the American percentage contribution, which had been 40 percent in the&#13;
Second Replenishment. This they wanted to see reduced to 35 percent. We said that this was totally&#13;
on-negotiable with the other contributors. They also wanted to reduce the figure of 1500 million old&#13;
dollars to 1200 million. All of which would mean a very large cumulative loss over the years, because if&#13;
you make a reduction, you never get it back. This would mean a very large loss of commitment&#13;
authority for IDA, and, since IDA never financed one hundred percent of any project, an even larger&#13;
loss of project finance. I think we calculated that by 1980 the loss would amount to $7 or $8 billion&#13;
dollars, and there was no logical reason to stop at 1980. And all this to save a comparably trifling sum&#13;
for the United States.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    We urged upon them that since there was always a considerable lag between commitments and&#13;
disbursements, the fact that we were asking them to get the Congress to agree to a Replenishment at a&#13;
level of around--I think we said we would be prepared to let the level drop from 1500 million old&#13;
dollars to 1500 million new dollars. The fact that under their procedure they required not only&#13;
authorizing legislation but appropriations for at least the first of the three years didn't really reflect&#13;
what the impact on their economy would be. Whatever commitment authority they granted to us&#13;
wouldn't be fully used for anything up to ten years afterwards.&#13;
&amp;#12;RICKETI                                           -7-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
(RICKETI]&#13;
    On the question of the percentage contribution, even if they were prepared to accept something a&#13;
good deal higher than 25 percent--! think we calculated 32 percent would be tolerable in terms of both&#13;
the total for the Replenishment and a reasonable sharing of the burden as between the countries&#13;
concerned--we would need to make up this fall in the U.S. contribution by getting increased&#13;
contributions from some other members. It so happened, very fortunately, that the Japanese&#13;
government had become increasingly of the view that they needed to increase their proportion of&#13;
multilateral assistance, that they needed to increase their aid program and to do a higher proportion of&#13;
it through multilateral channels. We were given to understand through private inquiries that it was not&#13;
impossible that the Japanese would increase their percentage from 6 percent to 12 percent, and we put&#13;
a lot of pressure on the Germans to go higher too. I think there were three other governments who we&#13;
thought might reasonably accept a small increase. So that by that means we might be able to balance&#13;
the books.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    But the great difficulty was to get the United States Administration to take any decision because&#13;
they were well aware of the difficulties they would face with Congress. They also adopted a position&#13;
which they had never taken in the Third Replenishment, that there must be some quid pro quo for the&#13;
U.S. contribution. They wanted a smaller proportion of IDA lending to go to India. They wanted to&#13;
introduce for the first time IDA lending in Indochina. I think it emerged in the end that Congress was&#13;
mainly interested in aid for South Viet Nam. They weren't at that stage interested in aid for North&#13;
VietNam. The U.S. Treasury added various other reqnisites, such as a system of efficiency post-audit,&#13;
a system of examination of projects to see whether they had achieved the projected internal rates of&#13;
return. There may have been others. I don't remember what they were, but they all added to the&#13;
difficulty of negotiation because the other countries--or some of them, at any rate--didn't see why the&#13;
United States should achieve such a large reduction in its percentage and at the same time should&#13;
impose these various conditions.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    So the negotiations hung fire, and instead of being completed by July of 1973 they were still facing&#13;
an impasse at the time of the annual meeting in Nairobi in September. I think the meeting was for&#13;
&amp;#12;RICKETI                                             -8-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
(RICKETI]&#13;
some reason somewhat later than usual that year. Mr. McNamara had a series of meetings with Mr.&#13;
(George) Shultz, who was then the Secretary of the Treasury, and with Mr. [Paul) Volcker, the&#13;
Undersecretary. In the end, after some very difficult discussions, we did get agreement on a&#13;
Replenishment figure of 1500 million new dollars, with the United States accepting a share of I think 32&#13;
percent of Part One country contributions.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    I'm perhaps dwelling unduly on the details of the negotiation. I think the general point worth&#13;
making is that the great contrast between the Third Replenishment and the Fourth Replenishment was&#13;
symptomatic of a change which was going to persist: that we no longer had the wholehearted support of&#13;
the U.S. Treasury, still less of the Congress, and everything had to be fought for at great length. And&#13;
although the Fourth Replenishment was the last one with which I personally was concerned--but I have&#13;
read from time to time what was going on since then--that is an attitude on the part of the United&#13;
States which persisted for a long time. There were new factors which to some extent alleviated the&#13;
position because of the very large surpluses in the Middle Eastern countries, such as Kuwait and Saudi&#13;
Arabia and others, and so new donors were brought in, which helped to make the level of the&#13;
replenishment less disastrously low than it might otherwise have been.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    In 1974 when there came the ftrst dramatic increase in the oil price, Mr. McNamara was very&#13;
much of the opinion that the World Bank and the International Monetary Fund must play a full part in&#13;
trying to overcome the difficulties which this created. Obviously it created fust class problems for the&#13;
non-oil-producing developing countries. They would be forced to borrow money to pay for their&#13;
imports of oil--to the extent that their creditworthiness allowed--or otherwise accept a serious&#13;
slowdown in their development programs. Unfortunately, Mr. (William) Simon, who was then&#13;
Secretary of the U.S. Treasury, took the view that there was no need for any intervention by the&#13;
international organizations; that the recycling, as it was called, of the petrodollars would all be&#13;
successfully carried out through private banking channels. He didn't seem to attach much weight to the&#13;
notion that if United States banks were going to accept relatively short term deposits from, say,&#13;
&amp;#12;RICKETI                                              -9-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
[RICKETI]&#13;
Saudi Arabia and were then going to lend the money on much longer term to countries of doubtful&#13;
creditworthiness, this would have great dangers for the stability of the banking system, and not least,&#13;
the United States banking system. We've all seen what has happened since then. The one encouraging&#13;
thing that I have heard about from my newspaper reading in my retirement is the so-called Baker Plan,&#13;
which in one of its elements, envisages a very substantial increase in the role of the international&#13;
organizations.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     There were however some new developments. I can't recall the exact details, but the Fund did set&#13;
up something called the 'Oil Facility.' They created additional medium term lending for countries with&#13;
particular balance of payments difficulties as a result of the rise in the oil price. But I think it's fair to&#13;
say that what has been done didn't really meet the demands of the situation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     On the one hand, Saudi Arabia was a country which experienced a vast increase in its income,&#13;
where as its absorptive capacity for development expenditure was limited and, therefore, they built up&#13;
very large surpluses. On the other hand, in Latin America you had economies which had been growing&#13;
very rapidly indeed and which were prepared to borrow large amounts of money. They incurred&#13;
greatly increased development commitments based on optimistic expectations about their oil revenues.&#13;
So in a sense an even greater problem has been created by the recent fall in the oil price, which has&#13;
accentuated the need for a solution, no doubt on a case by case basis, not on some kind of automatic&#13;
formula, but on one which requires the cooperation of the central banks in all the major countries, and&#13;
of the commercial banks to the extent that they are willing to roll over their indebtedness or to&#13;
substitute, shall we say, for outright default, a process under which they provide the money to maintain&#13;
the repayments to them. Finally, the international institutions must also be involved.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER: Sir Denis, you were talking about the IDA Replenishments and the debt study. Could you&#13;
just say a little about the people with whom you worked most closely in the Bank on these topics and&#13;
anything that you might remember about them?&#13;
&amp;#12;RICKEIT                                           -10-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
RICKEIT: Yes, I've already mentioned the name of John Adler, who largely bore the brunt of the&#13;
debt study and was of the greatest help to me in the two IDA Replenishments. He had a very&#13;
ingenious mind. He got on well with his opposite numbers in the various departments, particularly in&#13;
Washington, both in the White House and in the Council of Economic Advisors, and not exclusively in&#13;
the Treasury. I can't speak too highly of the work that he did, and I obviously was sorry when he died&#13;
of a heart attack rather before his time.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Lester Nurick was number two to Ronnie (Aron] Brocbes, and he was of immense help, because&#13;
there were very difficult technical problems about voting rights and about the question whether&#13;
contributions might to some extent be replaced by subscriptions and what effect that would have. He&#13;
and Mr. Adler between them were absolutely invaluable.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    We also had great help from the Economics Department before the negotiations for the Third&#13;
Replenishment started. We had four or five people from Irving Friedman's domain, who worked on a&#13;
series of briefing papers, and at the time of the Fourth Replenishment, also Hollis Chenery made a&#13;
valuable contribution. That is in the World Bank.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    There were a number of close friends of mine representing the other countries. The&#13;
representative of France was Monsieur Jacques de Larosi~re, and certainly one acquired the greatest&#13;
possible respect for his abilities, both for his analytical mind and as a rather tough negotiator. But&#13;
there were others who were perhaps more favorably disposed to what we were trying to do in London,&#13;
and certainly in The Hague. And in Bonn there was Herr Moltrecbt, who was then the German&#13;
Deputy. He came from the Ministry of Economic Cooperation. He was extremely helpful.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER: If we could step back in time a little farther, you were Executive Director for a short time&#13;
in 1954. Even though the assignment was brief, what impression did you gain of Mr. Black's&#13;
relationship with the Board?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
RICKEIT: I think I find it hard to distinguish between my first hand experience at that time and what&#13;
I knew of on other occasions. I think Mr. Black was a person who was a supreme diplomat, and he had&#13;
a great gift of friendship. He didn't want to get involved in a great mass of detail. He reserved&#13;
&amp;#12;RICKEIT                                            -11-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
(RICKEIT)&#13;
himself for the really important things. He was particularly effective in dealing with the heads of&#13;
government or the key ministers.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    This doesn't relate to my period as an Executive Director, but when I was back in the Treasury, I&#13;
became involved in some very difficult negotiations between the United Kingdom and the Egyptian&#13;
Government in resolving the financial consequences of the Suez episode. When Nasser nationalized&#13;
the Suez Canal, we retaliated. We ought to put something about the use of sanctions in everybody's&#13;
briefing book, I think. We tried to apply the sanction of blocking the Egyptian Number 1 Account at&#13;
the Bank of England, which was their main reserve account. Nasser retaliated by sequestrating all&#13;
British property in Egypt. He also pushed ahead with something more than sequestration, which could&#13;
be regarded as a temporary measure. He pushed ahead with the so-called Egyptianization of British&#13;
enterprises in Egypt, so that after the Suez the fighting had come to an end, it was quite a difficult&#13;
problem to unwind this process of sanctions and counter-sanctions.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Mr. Black let it be known that if we would welcome his help as a mediator, he'd be willing to&#13;
undertake that. Eventually he and I went to Cairo and he helped us by the time-honored process of&#13;
splitting the differences to get a settlement. He went to see Nasser more than once, which I am sure&#13;
contributed to the settlement. And, as I say, I think that he always had great gift of making friends and&#13;
handfing people. I'm sure that applied to the Executive Director at that time, though I can't single out&#13;
episodes or persons.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER: I believe George Woods had something to do with negotiations over Suez. He was&#13;
Chairman of First Boston Corporation at that time. He did various jobs for Mr. Black on occasion.&#13;
Suez was one. Did you have any contact with him over Suez?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
RICKEIT: The answer is no. I think the reason is because he didn't play a role in the negotiations&#13;
between the British Government and the Egyptian Government, but he did play a role, if I am right, in&#13;
the negotiations between the Shell Oil Company and the Egyptian government. It may even have been&#13;
the Suez Canal Company. He had help from Sir William Iliff.&#13;
&amp;#12;RICKETT                                           -12-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER: Sir Denis, you were involved for a time with the beginnings of the negotiations for entry of&#13;
the People's Republic of China into the World Bank- Would you care to discuss some of your&#13;
experiences in this regard, if you please?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
RICKETT: Yes. This was not the first time that the Chinese Government had demanded to replace&#13;
Taiwan as a member of the Bank and the Fund. But this demand was made with still greater urgency&#13;
and publicity in Nairobi in 1973. Mr. McNamara and I think Mr. Witteveen, the Managing Director of&#13;
the IMF, both received telegrams from the Chinese government, and it had to be decided what replies&#13;
should be made. It was a problem which I should have thought would naturally have fallen in the&#13;
province of the General Counsel, but for personal reasons he didn't want to take it on at that stage. I&#13;
think he had other engagements in view, and Mr. McNamara asked me to do it.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    I worked with a small group in the World Bank on the problem, which was quite a complicated&#13;
one because frrst of all it involved the question of the outstanding indebtedness of Taiwan to the World&#13;
Bank and whether that would be met if they were expelled from the Bank, or whether mainland China&#13;
would agree to a sort of "two China" solution, would agree to come in if Taiwan were not expelled.&#13;
Then on the other side of the coin so to speak, there was the question whether the Chinese would be&#13;
willing to meet their obligations to the Bank, to meet their future obligations and to in a sense meet an&#13;
obligation dating back to a period before they joined. In other words, what subscription would they&#13;
agree to make to the Bank, what subscription and contributions would they agree to make to IDA.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     This proved quite a diflieult and complicated problem, but we worked out a solution the details of&#13;
which I won't try to reproduce now. Eventually [Frank] Southard, who was the Deputy Managing&#13;
Director of the Fund, and I were sent to New York to interview either the Chinese Ambassador to the&#13;
United Nations or the Chinese representative on the Economic and Social Council, I'm not quite sure&#13;
which. We had a rather stormy interview, most of which was taken up by a sort of tirade from the&#13;
Chinese representative who accused us of cooperating with a criminal or usurper government. It ended&#13;
up oddly enough on quite a friendly note with the Chinese representative saying what great respect he&#13;
had for President Nixon, what great respect he had for Prime Minister Heath. In any case he would&#13;
&amp;#12;RICKETI                                           -13-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
[RICKETI)&#13;
refer to matter the his government, and that, so far as I remember, was the last contact I had with this&#13;
issue. Months went by and the Chinese government didn't send any reply at all. I think that was still&#13;
the position when I left the Bank in October 1974. But there has since been a solution.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER: WeU, it's all been very interesting, Sir Denis. I think we can close the interview at this&#13;
point.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
RICKETI: I quite agree. I think we've covered enough ground.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ZIEGLER: Thank you very much.&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="17997517">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1986/08/17997517/transcript-oral-history-interview-sir-denis-h-f-rickett-held-august-20-1986
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1986/08/17997517/transcript-oral-history-interview-sir-denis-h-f-rickett-held-august-20-1986</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1986/08/17997517/transcript-oral-history-interview-sir-denis-h-f-rickett-held-august-20-1986</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2006-10-27T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2006-10-27T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2013/07/12/000356161_20130712145652/Rendered/INDEX/791030TRN0Rick0Box0377367B00PUBLIC0.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2013/07/12/000356161_20130712145652/Rendered/PDF/791030TRN0Rick0Box0377367B00PUBLIC0.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2013-07-12T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1986-08-20T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Transcript of oral history interview with
            Sir Denis H. F. Rickett held on August 20, 1986
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            In August 1986, Sir Denis H. F. Rickett
            was interviewed on behalf of the World Bank Group Archives
            oral history program by Charles Ziegler. During his tenure
            at the Bank from 1968 to 1974, Sir Rickett worked in the
            following areas: as an alternate governor for the World Bank
            in the United Kingdom (1958-1968); as vice president for the
            World bank and the International Development Association
            (IDA) (1968-1974); and as a member of the president&#146;s
            council (1968-1974). Before his tenure, he had served an
            economic minister at the British Embassy in Washington since
            August 1951. When he retired from the British government in
            1968, president George Woods asked him to join the World
            Bank staff as the fourth Vice President. His transcript
            concerns IDA lending projects and policies, as well as the
            relationship of the World Bank with the United States.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Transcript of oral history interview with
            Sir Denis H. F. Rickett held on August 20, 1986
        </docna>
        <display_title>Transcript of oral history
            interview with Sir Denis H. F. Rickett held on August 20, 1986</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/1986/08/17997517/transcript-oral-history-interview-sir-denis-h-f-rickett-held-august-20-1986</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Transcript</docty>
        <subtopic>Access to Finance,Public Sector Corruption &amp;
            Anticorruption Measures,Corporate Law,Debt Markets,Banks &amp; Banking Reform</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Law and Development,Public Sector Development</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000356161_20130712145652</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>World Bank Group Archives oral history program</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Law and Development,Public Sector Development</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Board Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            balance of payments, Bank bonds, Bank of
            England, Bank policies, banking system, banks, capital flow,
            capitals, central bank, central banks, commercial banks,
            Company, confidence, Corporation, credits, creditworthiness,
            criminal, debt, debtors, debts, deposit, deposits,
            developing countries, development assistance, disbursements,
            Economic Cooperation, expenditure, income group,
            indebtedness, internal rates of return, International
            Development, legislation, limited, lobbying, loss of
            confidence, Minister, Ministers, Monetary Fund, oil price,
            persons, private banking, rates of return, remedy,
            repayments, reserve, reserve account, retirement, sanction,
            sanctions, settlement, term deposits, Treasury
        </keywd>
        <owner>Knowledge &amp; Information Services (ITSKI)</owner>
        <repnb>79103</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sustainable Climate Business</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sustainable Energy Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Climate Change</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation and Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shocks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Banks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Retail Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets and Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Treasury</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banking Institutional Set-up</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shocks and Vulnerability</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Examinations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Balance of Payments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Early Warning Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>