<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>﻿                                                                                       79141&#13;
DIVISION OF THE HUMANITIES AND SOCIAL SCIENCES&#13;
CALIFORNIA INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY&#13;
PASADENA, CALIFORNIA 91125&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
A CONVERSATION WITH LADISLAUS VON HOFFMANN.&#13;
&#13;
WASHINGTON, D.C.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
February 11, 1988&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
IC Robert   w.   Oliver&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                               ~c,"\\lUTE OF/;&#13;
                                                          ,..'!-"                l'('+.&#13;
                                                    ~                                  'fa&#13;
                                                  t2                                     '0&#13;
                                                 ~&#13;
                                                 ....                                     Q.&#13;
                                                  .:. -                                       tti&#13;
                                                  ~&#13;
                                                    ......,&#13;
                                                        1'1/&#13;
                                                                                          ~&#13;
                                                                                       ~.:-&#13;
                                                                                   ...._o-&#13;
                                                               '~'lf SHALL !AI';..\.&#13;
                                                 Conversations about George Woods&#13;
                                                        and the World Bank&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                                                   2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                            with Jack Evans, who at that time was Bob Garner's right hand man at&#13;
&#13;
                 A CONVERSATION WITH LADISLAUS VON HOFFMANN                 IFC.   They felt that I would fit their bill.    I then went around in&#13;
&#13;
                               WASHINGTON, D.C.                             Germany seeking advice on whether this was a good idea or not.          What&#13;
&#13;
                              February 11, 1988                             really finally persuaded me to do it was that Herman Abs, who at the&#13;
&#13;
                               Robert Y. Oliver                             time was the chairman of the Deutschebank, advised me to do it.          It&#13;
&#13;
                                                                            was a respectable institution and a good experience which wouldn't do&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:      Mr. Von Hoffmann, it is a great pleasure to meet you today     me any harm.    Robert Garner invited me to come to Washington in the&#13;
&#13;
to learn more about the IFC.     1 wonder if you would begin by saying a    fall of '59, and it was then agreed that after whatever time it would&#13;
&#13;
word about your background:    how you came to the IFC and what you did     take for me to extricate myself from my previous job, I would then&#13;
&#13;
before?                                                                     come on board in Washington in 1960.     That is the background.&#13;
&#13;
von HOFFMANN:       1 came co IFG in July, 1960.   In the previous five     OLIVER:   How many people were here and what was the order of magnitude&#13;
&#13;
or six years, I had been working for a German chemical company.      The    of the lending at the time?&#13;
&#13;
last three years, from '56 to '59, I spent in the Middle East building      von HOFFMANN:      It was a very small organization.       There were only 15-&#13;
&#13;
up their export organization and running one or two operations there.       20 people.     IFC worked like a Swiss watchmaker spending a tremendous&#13;
&#13;
I didn't know anything about IFC in those years.     In 1959 I ran into a   amount of time on extremely complicated operations.          I don't remember&#13;
&#13;
friend who had spent several years with IFC and who was going back to       now but I think the commitment level was less than $10 million. Garner&#13;
&#13;
Germany.     I was somewhat on a crossroad professionally -- either to      was the President and then, of course, there was Broad Haskell.          I&#13;
&#13;
stay with the company with which I had been associated for the              think his title was Director of Investments or something like that.&#13;
&#13;
previous years or do something else.     My friend suggested that I might   Jack Evans was really the operator.     There were six or seven key&#13;
&#13;
take a look at IFC, which was looking for somebody from Germany and         people maybe a little bit more.     It was a very small operation.&#13;
&#13;
which, at that time, was a very small operation.     It saw itself          OLIVER:   Was Marty Rosen a part of the operation?         Or was he still a&#13;
&#13;
essentially as an outfit to do industrial financing.                        part of the Bank?&#13;
&#13;
     My first reaction was that I didn't know anything about                von HOFFMANN:     Marty hadn't appeared on the scene.&#13;
&#13;
financing.     I was much more on the industrial management side, but I     OLIVER:   Might I ask for purposes of the record if you would say a&#13;
&#13;
decided that this was something worth looking at.     I met in Germany      word about your academic background?     Were you an economist?&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                       3                                                                          4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
von HOFFMANN:        I was an economist in the European sense which meant      unknown entity.   Marty also saw this as an investment banking&#13;
&#13;
that you had to do both business school and economics.        I got a          operation.   He put a great deal of emphasis on operating an&#13;
&#13;
masters in Freiburg, Germany, in 1949.                                         institution in such a way that would bring money into the projects&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:    Thank you.                                                          which we were financing.   It was really Marty who developed the&#13;
&#13;
von HOFFMANN:     I'd like to emphasize that I am not an economist in the      concept of syndicated financing -- joint operations with other&#13;
&#13;
American sense.    American economists usually don't know what business        institutions in that field.&#13;
&#13;
is like.                                                                            One of the very important achievements in Marty's period was that&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:    It is a business school equivalent.                                 we established a working relationship with Arab institutions who were&#13;
&#13;
von HOFFMANN:        It was really both.    I was very lucky because I went    beginning to explore the field of investing in underdeveloped&#13;
&#13;
to the University in the days when there were not that many people in          countries.   We had a very close working relationship with the Kuwaiti&#13;
&#13;
the University.    You could work with pretty good fellows directly in         Investment Company and others which at that time were beginning.&#13;
&#13;
small seminars of six to ten people.       You got the direct impact of a      Marty was very good at that.    He cultivated these relationships.    He&#13;
&#13;
good teacher.                                                                  also developed the concept of the syndicated participations in loans&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:    You did your work on the White plan?                                which we made.&#13;
&#13;
von HOFFMANN:       That was the thesis which I had to write for                    The other important development of that period was that George&#13;
&#13;
graduation, but I don't remember what was in it.                               Woods saw to it that the charter of the Bank and of IFC was amended so&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:    Well, I interrupted you.                                            that IFC could borrow money from the Bank.    In the Garner period, IFC&#13;
&#13;
von HOFFMANN:       Yes, so I became in IFC an investment officer.         I   had no access to the Bank's lending power.&#13;
&#13;
did project work, I don't remember now what it was.        Garner's concept    OLIVER:   Was the amount of borrowing a substantial fraction of the&#13;
&#13;
of IFC was a really small, profit oriented, investment-bank type of            original capital of the Bank?&#13;
&#13;
operation.    Frankly IFC wasn't going anywhere with that.      It was a       von HOFFMANN:      No, as measured by the scale of the Bank, these were&#13;
&#13;
good school, good people, very high standards of work, but as an               relatively small amounts, maybe a couple of hundred million dollars,&#13;
&#13;
institution it wasn't really getting very far.       It was very small.        but for IFC it was tremendously important.    The issue really was&#13;
&#13;
     When Garner left, Harty Rosen appeared on the scene.       From the       Should IFC move in the direction of going into the capital market&#13;
&#13;
point of view of the working population of the institution, he was an          itself, or should it borrow from the Bank?    The decision was made, I&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                    5                                                                             6&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
think rightly, that it would be a mistake to go directly to the            OLIVER:   I take it less than 25 percent?&#13;
&#13;
market.   We didn't have a record, and it was better and cheaper to        von HOFFMANN:     Yes, by and large, that was the guideline.     We really&#13;
&#13;
borrow money from the Bank.   The terms of this borrowing were quite       scratched our heads for quite a while if we went beyond 20 percent.&#13;
&#13;
favorable. These were twenty or twenty-five year loans and we were         OLIVER:   How much later did the policy come up of actually voting the&#13;
&#13;
lending out the money for ten, so we built ourselves a cash flow for       stock?&#13;
&#13;
future years.   In the long run then, it really helped IFC to go into      von HOFFMANN:    I don't know about that.   That never happened during my&#13;
&#13;
the capital markets on its own, which happened many years later.           period.   That happened after I left.    Anyway coming back to the&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:   How many years later?   Yas this in the McNamara period?         chronology, somewhere around the early '60s, I became the Deputy&#13;
&#13;
von HOFFMANN:      Well, the first non IBRD borrowing for IFC, I           Director to the Asia and Africa Department.       El Emary was the Director&#13;
&#13;
negotiated with the Saudi's in 1976, at the end of 1976.                   of the Department.&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:   Ue'll come to that presently.                                    OLIVER:   That was before he became associated with the Bank?&#13;
&#13;
von HOFFMANN:    That was the first one, but that really wasn't a          von HOFFMANN:        That was before he became associated with the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
capital market operation in that it was a friendly government.       I     He then left to become the Director of the Africa Department of the&#13;
&#13;
think it was maybe another three or four years later when they started     Bank, and I became the Director of that department at IFC.       That was&#13;
&#13;
to borrow generally.   In my time the concept was to bring other           my job until '69.     I think Marty left at the end of '69, and that was&#13;
&#13;
sources of capital to participate in loans which IFC made.    This         again a turning point.     I felt that perhaps I had spent enough time in&#13;
&#13;
policy and the possibility to borrow money from the Bank enabled IFC       IFC and I should really do something else.       But then when Gaud came&#13;
&#13;
to go into much larger operations.    This was really the turn; this was   in, James Raj, who had been vice president of IFC under Marty, decided&#13;
&#13;
the first really fundamental change in the policy of the institution.      to go back to India, and he recommended to Gaud and to McNamara that I&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:   Uas there also a prohibition against voting the stock of the     succeed him.    When Gaud proposed that to me, it seemed to me that that&#13;
&#13;
equity part of the operation at the time?                                  was another step on the ladder which one shouldn't forego too lightly,&#13;
&#13;
von HOFFMANN:      There was no statuatory prohibition, but there was a    particularly because it was obvious that Gaud, for reasons of age,&#13;
&#13;
policy statement that we would not vote our stock except in an             sooner or later would leave, and then there would be an opportunity to&#13;
&#13;
emergency.   Since we usually took relatively small percentages of the     run the institution.     So I decided to stay.    I was the day-to-day&#13;
&#13;
stock during my time, the issue was never raised.                          operating man in IFC. When Gaud left somewhere in the mid-70s, '74 or&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                        7                                                                               8&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
something like that, 1 succeeded him.       One of my concerns at that time       was the way it was done.    When the Board walked into the Board room,&#13;
&#13;
was that it would not make much sense for me to stay as vice president            they didn't know why that meeting was called.      I think it was the only&#13;
&#13;
if I didn't have a chance to succeed Gaud.       Since the job of the             personnel matter in the Bank that didn't leak.      Well, anyway that is&#13;
&#13;
executive vice president had always been held by Americans, I was                 the chronology.&#13;
&#13;
concerned that there might be some kind of political constraint.           So I   OLIVER:    Well, now, I think we should go back.    May we talk first&#13;
&#13;
asked the question.    I said to Gaud that I wanted to be reassured that          about the increase in capital under your vice presidency and then&#13;
&#13;
there was no nationality obstacle to succeeding him.         McNamara then        about some of the other things you accomplished when you were at the&#13;
&#13;
told me that there was no such reason at all.         Of course there would       top?&#13;
&#13;
be no assurance that 1 would succeed Gaud.       That would simply be a           von HOFFMANN:     When I became the Executive Vice President, IFC was&#13;
&#13;
question of performance.       That was all right with me.    That was fair       still operating with the capital which it had received 20 years&#13;
&#13;
enough.                                                                           before,      It was clear that every other institution in this business&#13;
&#13;
       1 succeeded Gaud.     Then, at the end of '76, I was approached by         was growing.    We needed additional money.   It was also clear that this&#13;
&#13;
people in private business, whom I have known for a long time and who             was the first thing to attend to if I was planning this institution&#13;
&#13;
were trying to revamp their management, eo join them.         I decided that      for some length of time.     So I asked McNamara whether he had any&#13;
&#13;
really the time had come eo do something else.         I was 49 by then, and      objection if I tried for a capital increase.       He gave me the green&#13;
&#13;
it was clear chat if I didn't move I would be stuck in the institution            light.     So 1 went to talk to the major shareholders, the United States&#13;
&#13;
for the rest of my life.        I decided to leave.                               first.     It turned out that the US, in its own planning for&#13;
&#13;
       I went to see McNamara and said, "I want to leave."      McNamara          international institutions, had been thinking about IFC.        They wanted&#13;
&#13;
said "Don't do that.       You are doing very well, etc. etc. Think about         to show support for private business in the developing countries.         So&#13;
&#13;
it."    I had suggested to him my successor, Moen Qureshi, who had                the US was very supportive.&#13;
&#13;
worked with me for several years.       He was my chief economist.    I                  I talked to the others, to the major Part II countries, the&#13;
&#13;
remember that it was a Thursday.       So McNamara said, "Well, think about       Europeans and the Japanese, and generally there was understanding and&#13;
&#13;
it.     I called him on Friday morning and I said, ''I have thought about         support.    We then set out to do all the things that you need to do in&#13;
&#13;
it, and I want to leave" So he called a Board meeting on Friday                   these things like producing five-year plans and so forth and so on.&#13;
&#13;
afternoon to tell them and to tell them also about a successor.           This    By the time I left in the end of '76, we had this pretty much in the&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                      9                                                                               10&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
bag, except we had some countries that were dragging their feet and              about development finance?     I understand that Development Sanks have&#13;
&#13;
creating difficulties.    It was the eternal issue of whether or not             been part of IFC and maybe also a part of the World Bank.     They have&#13;
&#13;
public resources should be used to support private business, and on              gone back and forth so to speak.&#13;
&#13;
that, of course, the views of the various governments, depending on              von HOFFMANN:     The Development Banks were the constant institutional&#13;
&#13;
their political outlook, was different.                                          battleground between IFC and the Bank.     We, of course, felt that we&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:    In that time, I take it, the British were dragging their feet         had the turf of private business, and, since these institutions were&#13;
&#13;
a bit.    They had a labor government.                                           mostly operating in the private sector, we should be running the show.&#13;
&#13;
von HOFFMANN:     Yes, the British were dragging their feet a bit.        In     Obviously the people on the Bank side had a different view.        This was&#13;
&#13;
France, it was my judgement that it was bureaucratic difficulties, but           going back and forth for a variety of reasons.     There were good&#13;
&#13;
we had reasonably good support on the whole.       It was really Moen            arguments on both sides as to why this should be done one way or&#13;
&#13;
Qureshi who, after he took over, ironed out the last wrinkles.          He got   another.&#13;
&#13;
the thing finally signed and sealed.      The Arabs were quite supportive.               I think that as far as the private sector development is&#13;
&#13;
To be more specific, the Saudi's were quite supportive.       The Kuwaitis       concerned, perhaps the single most important thing the Bank Group has&#13;
&#13;
were a bit more ambivalent.                                                      done, leaving aside the institutional differences, was the setting up&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:    Just as an aside, may I ask how long Moen Qureshi served?             of this network of industrial banks.     Bill Diamond and his people&#13;
&#13;
von HOFFMANN:       He may have spent another two years, and then                established a remarkable professional discipline in these&#13;
&#13;
McNamara moved him into the Bank finance job.      Wuttke was his                institutions, and I think these institutions have bred a generation of&#13;
&#13;
successor, and he was succeeded by Bill Reilly.      You asked me earlier        people in these countries who really contributed to the private&#13;
&#13;
what do I feel I have done in IFC.       I think that the initiative and         sector.&#13;
&#13;
the politicking of getting this capital increase together -- from the                    Of course, there are always problems.   In the last five or ten&#13;
&#13;
point of view of the long-range existence of the institution, that was           years, I understand that some of these institutions have come to&#13;
&#13;
relatively important.                                                            grief, but that is to be expected.     There were some thirty or forty of&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:    Would you care now to go back again to the Garner and Woods           them.     But in terms of professional competence, many of them have&#13;
&#13;
era in the Bank and say a bit about some of the individual projects              really contributed to their own country, and they would not have come&#13;
&#13;
that you helped to finance?    Would you say something along the line            into existence in this form if the Bank Group had not been involved.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                     11                                                                            12&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      I think George Woods was very supportive of this idea.     He in     the mid 60s, I spent an enormous amount of time in India, and we did a&#13;
&#13;
effect set up one of the first one in the Phillipines.     The Bank        number of, by and large, good projects.      That was a remarkable&#13;
&#13;
became a major, major source of loan financing through these               experience to enter a country of that size and establish personal&#13;
&#13;
institutions.   It would be worthwhile to look at the history of that      relationships and create a customer base, if I may put it that way.&#13;
&#13;
more closely.   I think that some work has been done.                      That was one thing which I was involved in.&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:   I think the work that Woods did was before he became             OLIVER:   Might I interrupt again to ask for some specifics.       Were you&#13;
&#13;
President.                                                                 involved in steel?&#13;
&#13;
von HOFFMANN:      That's right.                                           von HOFFMANN:     We financed an alloy steel plant.     The MUSCO steel&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:   Yould you say something about that?                              company was a joint venture between UGINE, the French steel alloy&#13;
&#13;
von HOFFMANN:      I don't know much about it.     All 1 know is that he   people, and the Mahindras, a major industrial group.         That's one&#13;
&#13;
had been involved in setting up the Phillipine Development Bank before     project we put together which is still around; very successful, it was&#13;
&#13;
he came to the Bank,   I have very little knowledge of high policy         a major affair.&#13;
&#13;
issues in the 60s because I was just a working stiff on projects, so I     OLIVER:   This was not part of the TATA?&#13;
&#13;
don't know what went on on whatever floor it was at that time, 12 or       von HOFFMANN:        No, we never got into business with the TATAs.       I&#13;
&#13;
13.                                                                        think the TATAs felt that we would be asking too many questions.&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:   Well, maybe you would be good enough to mention some of the      Also, the steel sector, the big heavy steel sector, was financed by&#13;
&#13;
projects that you worked on.   Were you in the field of a great deal       the Bank with government guarantees.     The Bank financed TATA and the&#13;
&#13;
for example?                                                               Mukarjees, the coal people.&#13;
&#13;
von HOFFMANN:      I've done several things.     One, the relationship     OLIVER:      Did you do any work in fertilizers?&#13;
&#13;
between IFC and India in Garner's day was practically non existent.        von HOFFMANN:        That was later.   The big surge in the fertilizer&#13;
&#13;
When Rosen came in, he decided that this just couldn't be like that.       industry came later, I would imagine, perhaps, in the early 70s or&#13;
&#13;
He and I went to India, and L.K. Tha, who was at that time the             later 60s.    This was in Pakistan and in India.      We were heavily&#13;
&#13;
Secretary of Finance, was really interested.      The Indians were         involved in that as far as the private sector was concerned.        Of&#13;
&#13;
ambivalent on the role of IFC, but somehow we managed to establish         course the Bank got involved in the government sector.        At that time&#13;
&#13;
basic guidelines which would permit us to do some transactions.       In   the Pakistanis had decided that they would have this industry&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                     13                                                                         14&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
developed in the private sector.     We financed the Davood fertilizer      OLIVER:   Gene Black was opposed to most public, that is to say&#13;
&#13;
plant in Pakistan.    In India, there were big policy battles going on      government, loans for industry, and yet it was difficult to justify&#13;
&#13;
whether the private sector should be allowed in.     Finally the Birlas     public loans for private enterprise.     It seems to me to be a kind of&#13;
&#13;
managed to get a license, so we were involved in that.                      "Catch 22."&#13;
&#13;
     That was a very interesting experience.     The fundamental issue      von HOFFMANN:    Well, I would rephrase your statement.   I think the&#13;
&#13;
was that you were putting up a tremendous amount of capacity in a           objection was not to government loans, it was to the ownership of&#13;
&#13;
central point, and you had no market records.     There wasn't any          industry by government.    That was the problem.   In India, the Bank did&#13;
&#13;
fertilizer being used.     You had to make a judgement linked to the        not lend money to the government steel industry, but they lent money&#13;
&#13;
distribution system and to the kind of seeds which they would use.          to the private steel industry.    That indeed was the policy of the Bank&#13;
&#13;
One of the reasons the nitrogen fertilizer consumption took off that        at that time.&#13;
&#13;
enormously on the subcontinent was the introduction of Mexican wheat        OLIVER:   But only under the circumstance that strictly commercial&#13;
&#13;
which requires a great deal of nitrogen.      So we financed a fertilizer   bank loans were not available.&#13;
&#13;
plant in Goa with US Steel and the Birlas.      It was very interesting.    von HOFFMANN:        Well, that was always the theory, at least in the&#13;
&#13;
     Another area which was very interesting and where I think we           case of IFC.    One of the problems which we had to struggle with was&#13;
&#13;
helped things happen which otherwise wouldn't have happened was after       that the mandate of IFC included a provision that we should not&#13;
&#13;
Suharto came into Indonesia.     Their economic policy group decided that   compete with private capital.     So one of the check points in any&#13;
&#13;
they wanted to promote private investment, foreign investment in            transaction was, "Is this something where we are really substituting&#13;
&#13;
particular.     We did the first major private financing in Indonesia for   for private capital or is it something which wouldn't be financed&#13;
&#13;
a cement plant.     Of course the Bank, thanks to Bernie Bell's excellent   otherwise?"     Fairly Byzantine discussions took place on this subject&#13;
&#13;
work there, had an enormously successful relationship with Indonesia        from time to time.     Of course it is never black and white, but a&#13;
&#13;
at that time.     That was most helpful.   We were heavily involved in      tremendous amount of time was spent on arguing about these things.&#13;
&#13;
Indonesia at the very beginning of this new economic policy approach.       OLIVER:   A specific case of the "Catch 22" was involved in the&#13;
&#13;
That was very interesting because you really had to work yourself           Algerian oil industry where it was supposed funds could be obtained&#13;
&#13;
through the administrative procedures, the political procedures, in         privately for the development of the oil resources, but that was not&#13;
&#13;
trying to make things happen which otherwise would not have happened.       allowed because the government controlled the oil industry.     No loans&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                        15                                                                             16&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
could be made on either hand.                                                      course, there are highly political areas which, thank God, I have&#13;
&#13;
von   HOFFMANN:      I think that was a Bank problem.        I don't know much     never been involved with -- like financing the oil industry.       If you&#13;
&#13;
about that.                                                                        are an institution like the Bank, you don't like to get in a fight&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:      I wonder if you would say a word in general about all of              between the oil companies and the local governments.     These are very&#13;
&#13;
this?                                                                              delicate issues, but I never had anything to do with them.&#13;
&#13;
von HOFFMANN:        As time went by and as everybody learned, the                 OLIVER:      I take it that the tourism industry was fairly important at&#13;
&#13;
difference between the various types of ownership of industry became               one time.&#13;
&#13;
less and less relevant.     For example, IFC persuaded itself that the             von HOFFMANN:        The tourism industry was an opportunity which&#13;
&#13;
Yugoslav form of cooperative ownership of industry was really the                  developed for many countries as air travel became cheaper and&#13;
&#13;
equivalent of private ownership. A lot of people wouldn't agree with               infrastructure was created.     The general level of living in Europe was&#13;
&#13;
that.     I don't remember if it was in George Woods' period or whether            increasing.     People had the money to go on vacation wherever they&#13;
&#13;
it was later, but the Bank decided to finance public, that is                      wanted:     Tunisia, or Spain, or whatever. The countries on the&#13;
&#13;
government-owned, industries.     I don't think this was a religious               Mediterranean saw an opportunity.     There was a very substantial effort&#13;
&#13;
issue; I think this is simply a question of effective management.              I   there.    We in IFC were also involved in this, particularly in Tunisia&#13;
&#13;
think that over the last ten or twenty years, a lot has been learned               where we financed a couple of projects.&#13;
&#13;
about separating management from government ownership in well-run                       In East Africa, we financed the first major new hotel (in&#13;
&#13;
countries.     I think humanity has found out that private industry isn't          Nairobi) with Intercontinental.     This was simply a cyclical matter.&#13;
&#13;
that faultless either in making wrong judgements.                                  Whether it was supposed to be private or government really didn't make&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:      What was a substantial issue in Black's day was a bit less            that much difference.     I don't think one can say that one is&#13;
&#13;
of an issue in Woods' day, and, I take it, by McNamara's day had                   absolutely better than the other.      I think there are very poor&#13;
&#13;
essentially become a moot point.     The issue was whether or not                  examples of both. The opportunity for mischief in a government-run,&#13;
&#13;
industry was well run as distinct from public versus private                       poorly administered tourism program are just enormous.     But if anybody&#13;
&#13;
ownership.                                                                         looks at the history of zoning in Washington, there are also&#13;
&#13;
von HOFFMANN:     Yes, I think the ownership question was less important.          opportunities for mischief there.&#13;
&#13;
What was more important was the general policy framework.           Then, of       OLIVER:      I wonder if there is some way you can illustrate the&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                     17                                                                                    18&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
difference between an IFC project and a Bank project.        I realize that          the policy framework in which enterprises operate.         There are&#13;
&#13;
equity investment is involved in the one and not in the other.           I           countries in which business in theory is private, but it is hemmed in&#13;
&#13;
wonder if you can illustrate the difference between the kind of                      by government regulations.     India is the perfect example:      everything&#13;
&#13;
project which is amenable to treatment by one as opposed to the other                in India, in those days at least, was subject to licenses, and&#13;
&#13;
as a classic case?                                                                   permits, and this and that and the other.&#13;
&#13;
von HOFFMANN:        It is not that easy to find a simple example.           First   OLIVER:     Was the incidence of failure in the case of IFC projects at&#13;
&#13;
of all the Bank has no risk; there is the guarantee of government, so                all high?&#13;
&#13;
no matter what happened to the enterprise which they financed, they                  von HOFFMANN:        Not during my time.   I dori' t remember now the&#13;
&#13;
would get their money back.     Secondly, they were involved in much                 numbers, but you see we were inclined to spend a great deal of time in&#13;
&#13;
larger projects.     (I am talking about direct projects;     I am not               correcting situations which had gone sour.      We didn't have too many&#13;
&#13;
talking about secondary projects done by the development banks                       outright failures.     Now I understand (you would have to ask somebody&#13;
&#13;
locally.)   We in IFC were involved in much smaller and also, by                     else about this in the later years) in the late 70s, they had some&#13;
&#13;
definition, riskier operations.                                                      problems.    This has something to do with a very substantial expansion&#13;
&#13;
     The key issue on any IFC project was that one had to make a                     of the lending volume.     What was identified disrespectfully as the&#13;
&#13;
judgement on the capabilities of the sponsoring group, both the local                numbers game··the Bank group got itself into the position that they&#13;
&#13;
sponsoring group and the motivation of the foreign·sponsoring group.                 had some targets to meet.     That's really fatal.   You tend to make more&#13;
&#13;
In some instances, it was a credible affair.     It fitted into some kind            mistakes if you cannot cut off something that you are not satisfied&#13;
&#13;
of strategy which the foreign investor had.     In some instances, these             with.     But that wasn't too bad in my time.&#13;
&#13;
were just dressed·up equipment sales affairs, and one had to be very                 OLIVER:      I understand that Burke Knapp has been invited back to the&#13;
&#13;
careful about picking that.     I think that we in IFC were very much                Bank as a consultant to look into the whole issue of the relationship&#13;
&#13;
concerned with the risk of the individual venture.        The Bank was more          between IFC and the Bank.     I take it that it is thought to be fuzzy at&#13;
&#13;
likely to be involved in fundamental industries, like steel where your               the margin at least.&#13;
&#13;
market protection is really GNP related.     Maybe that has given a Bank             von HOFFMANN:        I don't know anything about that.&#13;
&#13;
a different outlook, but I don't really know.     1 don't think that one             OLIVER:      I appreciate the fact that you don't know anything about it.&#13;
&#13;
can specify some kind of identifiable difference.     It also depends on             I guess I am just asking you for your reaction to the difference at&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                     19                                                                             20&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
the margin between IFC and the Bank.     I take it, for example, that one       the business community.    The staff had a different background than&#13;
&#13;
thing that can be said is that you are more careful with the                    most of the Bank staff.    On the other hand, we were dealing with much&#13;
&#13;
appointments you are making at the Board of Director level when you             less weighty policy issues.    Maybe the one exception was the&#13;
&#13;
get involved in an IFC loan.                                                    development of the capital-markets department, which was initiated by&#13;
&#13;
von HOFFMANN:       Well, in my days we didn't have directors in the            Gaud and which did a great deal of work in the development of&#13;
&#13;
industrial companies.     There were directors in development banks.        I   financial intermediary institutions.     There you were moving into&#13;
&#13;
don't think that it made any difference whether we had a director in a          policy matters much more than on the question of financing a paper&#13;
&#13;
company board or not.     We had enough muscle to find out what was going       mill in a particular place or not.&#13;
&#13;
on even if we were not on the board.     In fact, we talked about this               By the way, that is something we did not mention before but&#13;
&#13;
many times, and we always decided that we were much better off if we            which, in looking at the history of IFC in addition to the Development&#13;
&#13;
were not on the board.                                                          Banks which was largely a Bank affair, the development of capital-&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:      I don't quite understand that.                                     market institutions was an important innovation in the IFC field.&#13;
&#13;
von HOFFMANN:        Because we had both equity and loan positions, and         Whether it was good, bad, or indifferent, I don't really know because&#13;
&#13;
as a lender, we had a pretty strong hand with these companies.        We        in my time it was very much beginning.    We really didn't have any&#13;
&#13;
also tried to establish a personal relationship with the sponsors.              experience on how useful it was.&#13;
&#13;
That was very important.     Whether you have one director out of ten or             The relationship of the Bank and IFC?     I always felt that if one&#13;
&#13;
not, it doesn't make any difference.     I cannot recall a single case          could draw a clean line and really concentrate the private sector work&#13;
&#13;
where a company would have refused to give me information by saying,            in IFC and then staff IFC accordingly, one could probably be more&#13;
&#13;
"You are not on the board so we won't tell you."     They certainly             effective, particularly as the Bank grew and became such an enormously&#13;
&#13;
wouldn't have gotten away with it.                                              large institution.     They were really not that close to the life of&#13;
&#13;
     The difference between IFC and the Bank?     Well, first of all, as        private business, but I have to admit that I have also suffered from&#13;
&#13;
you well know, every institution develops its own methodology.        IFC       institutional ambitions which may have colored my view on that.       What&#13;
&#13;
has prided itself on being the more business oriented, which I think            else to say on that?&#13;
&#13;
we were because we were much smaller.     It was a very hands-on                OLIVER:   Is there some question that I have overlooked, some&#13;
&#13;
operation.      We attached a great deal of importance to understanding         important issues that I have not referred to at all in passing?&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                         21                                                                          22&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
von HOFFMANN:        I think the one area that is perhaps worth mentioning        successful, but it took much longer than anybody thought.     My feeling&#13;
&#13;
is the effort to introduce institutions of capital-exporting countries            was that it would take ten years to turn around a new venture.     That's&#13;
&#13;
to participate in investments.        This is now running under the flag of       probably a fair judgement.&#13;
&#13;
co-financing and similar things.        It was really Marty Rosen who laid             Of course the other question which every now and then people ask&#13;
&#13;
the groundwork for this, and very skillfully, with a great deal of                is How profitable were the investments?   Like any business of this&#13;
&#13;
effort.     I    think it is fair to say that IFC was the first institution       type, probably twenty percent of the investments accounted for eighty&#13;
&#13;
which brought long-term capital alongside into these industrial                   percent of the rewards.   Among the other 80 percent of the&#13;
&#13;
ventures.        There was an institutional reason for this.     We didn't have   investments, there were the usual assortment of dogs which didn't get&#13;
&#13;
the money.        If we wanted to do larger operations, we had to bring           anywhere.   On the whole IFC return on capital was very modest&#13;
&#13;
other people along.                                                               partly, because it was a very expensive operation and, partly contrary&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:         So co-financing didn't begin in the Clausen era?                  to what a lot of people thought, we were not maximizing profits.      If&#13;
&#13;
von HOFFMANN:        When I left we had something like a billion dollars in       we had done that, we would have been running against the principle of&#13;
&#13;
participations, maybe a little bit less; it can be looked up in the               not substituting for private capital.&#13;
&#13;
Annual Report.        We did a tremendous amount of work in the proper legal      OLIVER:     Well, sir I appreciate very much your time and consideration&#13;
&#13;
documentation, the designing of the contracts in such a way that it               today and the opportunity to visit your lovely home.&#13;
&#13;
would satisfy the participating institutions.         That was a real&#13;
&#13;
innovation.&#13;
&#13;
     I think the other question I would ask if I were in your place is&#13;
&#13;
how successful IFC was in revolving its portfolio?            The original idea&#13;
&#13;
was, as I understand it, you would make equity investments and when&#13;
&#13;
they matured you would sell them, replenish the funds, and go on from&#13;
&#13;
there.     This turned out to be a much more lengthy process than anybody&#13;
&#13;
had envisaged, partly because of the narrowness of the          ~apital&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
markets.        There was nobody to sell to.   In the major countries, which&#13;
&#13;
had some capital markets, like Brazil, we had been reasonably&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="17997887">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1988/02/17997887/transcript-oral-history-interview-ladislaus-von-hoffmann-held-june-28-1990
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1988/02/17997887/transcript-oral-history-interview-ladislaus-von-hoffmann-held-june-28-1990</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1988/02/17997887/transcript-oral-history-interview-ladislaus-von-hoffmann-held-june-28-1990</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2008-02-27T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2008-02-27T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2013/07/12/000333037_20130712160402/Rendered/INDEX/791410TRN0Von00Box0377367B00PUBLIC0.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2013/07/12/000333037_20130712160402/Rendered/PDF/791410TRN0Von00Box0377367B00PUBLIC0.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2013-07-12T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1988-02-11T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Transcript of oral history interview with
            Ladislaus von Hoffmann held on June 28, 1990
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            On February 11, 1988, Ladislaus Von
            Hoffmann was interviewed on behalf of the World Bank Group
            Archives oral history program by Robert W. Oliver. During
            his tenure at the Bank from 1960 to 1977, Mr. Von Hoffman
            worked in the following areas: for the International Finance
            Corporation (IFC) department of investments for Africa,
            Asia, and the Middle East as an assistant director
            (1963-1965) and as a director (1965-1970); and for the IFC
            as vice president (1970-1974) and as executive vice
            president (1974-1977). This interview was conducted for the
            George Woods biography. His transcript concerns work in the
            Middle East building up export organization; work on private
            investment under Suharto in Indonesia; and the design of
            innovative investment contracts in industry.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Transcript of oral history interview with
            Ladislaus von Hoffmann held on June 28, 1990
        </docna>
        <display_title>Transcript of oral history
            interview with Ladislaus von Hoffmann held on June 28, 1990</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/1988/02/17997887/transcript-oral-history-interview-ladislaus-von-hoffmann-held-june-28-1990</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Transcript</docty>
        <subtopic>Access to Finance,Public Sector Corruption &amp;
            Anticorruption Measures,Corporate Law,Debt Markets,Banks &amp; Banking Reform</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Law and Development,Public Sector Development</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000333037_20130712160402</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>World Bank Group Archives oral history program</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Law and Development,Public Sector Development</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Board Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Board meeting, borrowing, business
            community, capital market, capital markets, cash flow,
            charter, commercial bank, commercial bank loans, company,
            customer base, developing countries, Development Bank,
            Development Banks, development finance, economic policy,
            equipment, equity investment, equity investments, financial
            intermediary, foreign investment, foreign investor,
            government guarantees, government ownership, government
            regulations, industrial banks, industrial companies,
            initiative, institutional differences, investing, investment
            banking, joint venture, lender, loan, loan financing, local
            governments, long-term capital, major shareholders, oil
            resources, portfolio, private capital, private enterprise,
            private financing, private investment, private ownership,
            return, shareholders, sponsors, transaction
        </keywd>
        <owner>Knowledge &amp; Information Services (ITSKI)</owner>
        <repnb>79141</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Industry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Policy Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Policy Formulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Policy Implementation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Productivity-Led Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets and Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Industrial Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Graduation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Policy Framework</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fertilizers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Local Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Intermediaries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>