<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>X0                                                                                              24276&#13;
April 2002&#13;
Vouchers for Health&#13;
Peter Sandiford, Anna   Using Voucher Schemes for Output-Based Aid&#13;
Gorter, and Micol&#13;
Salvetto                This Note examines an innovative, donor-supported               voucher scheme&#13;
to treat and prevent sexually transmitted            diseases in Nicaragua.&#13;
Petei Sandiford ii 7wit/i&#13;
the Instit,te for Health  Voucher schemes enable donors to purchase outputs rather than&#13;
Sector in iL hLon Anna  inputs while also offering beneficiaries a choice of provider, a feature&#13;
Gorter is withl tile Londlon&#13;
School of Hygiene and   that sets them     apart from     other output-based       approaches, such as&#13;
7TopicalMedicine Anid   supply-side subsidies to providers operating under performance-based&#13;
Plicol Salvetto is withi&#13;
Iinstituito Cettoarneiic(nno  contracts. Choice creates incentives to lower prices or raise quality&#13;
de la Saluid in Managua  (or both).&#13;
A   donor-supported  voucher   scheme   in      In developed countries a range of special pro-&#13;
Nicaragua provides treatment and prevention   grams have been set up to address the health&#13;
services for sexually transmitted infections  needs of high-risk groups In developing coun-&#13;
(STIs) to high-risk populations such as com-  tries governments have been less successful in&#13;
mercial sex workers and their partners and  reaching these groups and meeting their special&#13;
clients. Beyond detecting and treating STIs,  needs. They often resort to counterproductive&#13;
these health services can also raise awareness of  coercive measures, such as having the police&#13;
a.                              nrisks and promote safer behavior, leading to  oblige sex workers to attend government-run&#13;
widespread benefits. Because STIs increase the  STI clinics. But sex workers shy away from dedi-&#13;
transmiiission of HIV by a factor of three to five or  cated STI clinics because the clinics are stigma-&#13;
more, the population groups that are extremely  uzing, tend to treat their patients discourteously,&#13;
vulnerable to STIs and HIV infection facilitate  and are perceived as having scant respect for&#13;
the entry and spread of AIDS in the general pop-  patient confidentiality. Sex workers tend to visit&#13;
m                                tuilation. Thus small interventions targeted to  general outpatient clinics instead, choosing not&#13;
such high-risk groups can have a large impact on  to reveal their occupational risks. Consequently,&#13;
the spread of STIs and HIV. But these groups-  they rarely receive adeqtiate diagnosis or treat-&#13;
O)  -sex workers, regular clients and partners of sex                          ment for their sexual health problems.&#13;
workers, adolescent glue-sniffers, migrant labor-  In the absence of special client-friendly pro-&#13;
7                  1         ers, long-distance tranisport workers-tend to be  grams, the use of sexual health services among&#13;
difficult to reach and are often mobile.     these vulnerable groups is low and usually inef-&#13;
4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
VOUCHERS FOR HEALTH       USING VOUCHER SCHEMES FOR OUTPUT-BASED AID&#13;
fective. What these grouips need is subsidized  vouchers non transferable, for two reasons. First,&#13;
access to convenient, courteous, confidential  preventing the vouchers from being used by&#13;
services of high quality that identify their sexual  someone other than the original recipient is&#13;
health needs in a nonstigmatizing manner and  costly. And second, the secondary recipienit of&#13;
provide appropriate counseling, diagnostic   the voucher might be at higher risk of having an&#13;
information, and treatment.                  STI than the primary one, so the transfer could&#13;
serve the program's objectives. Providers are&#13;
How the scheme works                         unlikely to exchange vouchers for cash, because&#13;
2                           The Central Amencan Health Institute (Instituto  that would simply reduce their income and in&#13;
Centroamericano de la Salud, or ICAS)l has   any case each redeemed voucher must be&#13;
attempted to provride such services in Nicaragua  accompanied by a blood test and other samples.&#13;
through a voucher scheme since 1995 At six-     The government has no direct involvement&#13;
month intervals ("rounds") the scheme distrib-  in the scheme. ICAS acts as the voucher agency,&#13;
utes 2,000 vouchers to the vuilnerable groups (in  contracting and monitoring clinical and labo-&#13;
later rounds, including clients and partners of  ratory services, training clinic staff (doctors,&#13;
sex workers), some directly and some (at no cost)  nurses, and receptionists) in handling sex work-&#13;
through community-based organizations in close  ers in a nondiscriminatoiy manner, defining&#13;
contactwiththegroups(figutire1) Thevoucliers,  the service package covered by the voucher,&#13;
which remain valid for two and a half months,  analyzing data, and monitoring technical qual-&#13;
entitle the bearer to a predefined package of  ity and patient satisfaction, both generally and&#13;
"best practice" sexual health services free of  for each clinic In addition, its fieldworkers&#13;
charge at any one of about 10 contracted clinics.  maintain a map of the 50-60 prostittition sites&#13;
Clinic staff need not ask patients embarrassing  in and around the capital city ofManagua where&#13;
questions about their membership in the tar-  the vouchers are distributed.&#13;
geted grotip, since this is declared uith the pres-  Clinics compete for contracts on the basis of&#13;
entation of a voucher.                       price, quality, and location. For the initial round&#13;
To preventcounterfeiting, vouchers are indi-  ofcontracting clinics were individually invited to&#13;
vidually numbered, stamped with the ICAS seal,  participate (since a newspaper advertisement&#13;
and laminated. Their expiration date is printed  generated little interest). Those responding&#13;
on them. No meastires are taken to make the  were assessed against predefined criteria. With&#13;
1                                     7  Voucher agency&#13;
Vocher&#13;
a payment J    |            Cashoa           \          Cimmunty-based&#13;
organizations&#13;
Voucher  men ~  ~   ~   ~~~ouhe&#13;
Donor and&#13;
government                                            Sex workers&#13;
ClinVcsu&#13;
Source Diagram adapted from Harper and others (2000)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
each clinic that met the criteria ICAS negotiated  zations (NGOs). Since rounld four, however,&#13;
a price for the servce package, whilch consists of  only private and NCO clinics have participated&#13;
a medical consultation, follow-up visit, counsel-  The program dropped the public sector clinics&#13;
ing, and the taking of test samples (treatment is  because they attracted few voucher redeemers&#13;
dispensed separately).                       and had long waiting times and unfriendly&#13;
For new clinics ICAS uses the range of prices  "gatekeepers." The private for-profit clinics sur-&#13;
paid under existing contracts as a benchmark,  vive on their fees, but most of the NGOs also&#13;
but it also considers their strategic importance  receive subsidies and can therefore charge&#13;
to the program. ICAS gives particular weight to  lower prices. The public clinics charged nomi-&#13;
clinics' location and the perceived quality of  nal user fees.&#13;
their service, both important determinants of   Since 1995, in 12 rounds, the scheme has dis-&#13;
use by sex workers. The contracts between ICAS  tributed more than 15,000 vouchers, provided&#13;
and the provider-s require staff to follow a speci-  more than 6,000 consultationis, and treated&#13;
fied treatmen1t protocol and to participate in  countless cases of STIs. Of a dynamic popula-&#13;
training sessions ICAS regularly invites new cdn-  tion of about 1,150 female sex workers active at&#13;
ics to join the scheme, but to keep the adminis-  any one time, more than 40 percent have&#13;
trative burden manageable it contracts no more  redeemed their voucher. More than 2,500 sex&#13;
than about 10 providers for each round. Clinics  workers have participated, with the highest rates&#13;
are paid according to the nuimber of voLtchers  of redemption among the poorest women and&#13;
they return (along with data collection sheets).  among the groups with the higlhest initial rates&#13;
ICAS revqews the performance of participat-  of STIs&#13;
ing clinics in each round and does not renew    The program reduced the prevalence of gon-&#13;
the contracts of those judged to have been   orr-lea in the female sex worker population by&#13;
unsatisfactory To monitor- quality, it conducts  an average 5.25 percent a year, and the inci-&#13;
semistructured interviewvs with 10 percent of the  dence in repeat users by 11 5 percent a year. It&#13;
patients redeeming vouchers at each clinic, ana-  reduced the prevalence of syphilis by an average&#13;
lyzes medical record-keepinig, and looks at  10.25 percent a year The poorest sex workers&#13;
other indicators of quality, such as the number  had the higlhest initial prevalenice rates for gon-&#13;
of vouchers redeemed and the share of women  orrhea and syphilis; these rates fell by an aver-&#13;
attending their follow-up consultation. (The  age 9.4 percent and 8.6 percent a year.&#13;
interniews, conducted by a small, multidiscipli-  Although prevalence at follow-up constiltations&#13;
nary team, also explore ideas for increasing the  was not zero, these women remained free of&#13;
redemption of vouchers ) The voucher agency  STIs longer, which considerably reduces the&#13;
gives clinics feedback based on the results of the  risk of being infected with HIV or infecting their&#13;
quality monitoring.                          clients. HIV prevalence in sex workers in&#13;
ICAS contracts a single laboratory to per-  Managua was 0.8 percent in 1991,1.3 percent in&#13;
form diagnostic tests, to simplify the logistics  1997, and 2.0 percent in 1999, a rate of increase&#13;
and allow some economies of scale. The labora-  well below that observed in the sex worker pop-&#13;
tory provides swabs and transport media, col-  ulations of other major cities.&#13;
lects samples daily, reports results, and       Today the voucher scheme IS sustained at a&#13;
distributes treatment. A second laboratory pro-  cost of US$60,000 a year, reflecting the relatively&#13;
vides quality control. Drugs, condoms, medical  low cost of patient visits. While a baseline stud)'&#13;
supplies, and health education material are cen-  estimated the cost of an outpatienit constiltation&#13;
trally procured by competitive tender.       in public facilities to be US$7.65, the average&#13;
price the voucher scheme paid to clinics for a&#13;
Results                                      consultation and follow-up visit wvas initially only&#13;
By 2001 the program had contracted 20 service  US$6.70. And despite increasing slightly at first,&#13;
providers at one time or another. These have  the average price was only US$5.15 in the 12th&#13;
been a mix of public and private providers,  round. This cost redtiction was due mostly to the&#13;
including nonprofit, nongovernmental organi-  gradual devaluation of the currency, but also in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
VOUCHERS      FOR   HEALTH    USING VOUCHER SCHEMES FOR OUTPUT-BASED AID&#13;
part to competitive pressures and effective nego-  ent. But this approach would be vulnerable to col-&#13;
tiation. In fact, contracted prices may be quite   lusion between clinics and probably would not&#13;
close to the clinics' marginal costs Reducing      achieve the broad geographic coverage necessary&#13;
costs further through cost recovery fi-om the sex  to ensure high redemption rates. Moreover, the&#13;
workers is unrealistic and would exclude the       current process allows the program to take advan-&#13;
poorest, who also have the greatest health nieeds.  tage of the subsidies received by some of the NGO         p&#13;
As it is, the costs to sex workers in transport and  clinics by contracting the NGOs at a lower pnce&#13;
lost income are significant, and for some a rea-   than the private providers and thereby "leveling   is an open forum to&#13;
son not to use their voucher.                      the playing field" to some degree.                  encourage dissemination of&#13;
The direct cash benefits to the clinics partici-   Some of the potential problems of voucher              g disseination of&#13;
public policy innovations for&#13;
pating In the scheme are not large. The largest    schemes have not arisen. One is counterfeiting.     private sector-led and&#13;
provider has received only about US$1 0,000 iii    In theory a counterfeiter could reproduce the       market-based solutions for&#13;
six years. But the program offers clinics steady,  vouchers, selling  them   to  users or sermce       development. The views&#13;
reliable income Moreover, some clinic directors    providers But because of the measures taken to     published are those of the&#13;
report that the presence of voucher-bearing        reduce this risk, a counterfeiter would need       authors and should not be&#13;
clients has helped to fill the clinics and attract  some sophistication in producing vouchers as       attributed to the World&#13;
paying clients. And participation has improved     well as confidence that the vouchers could be       Bank or any other affiliated&#13;
the technical quality of services, since the clinics  sold (or, if sold to a provider, redeemed by the  organizations. Nor do any of&#13;
usually apply the lessons learned in the training  voucher agency). A related risk is black market     the conclusions represent&#13;
to their services for all clients. Participation also  sales ofvouchers. The market would probably be  official policy of the World&#13;
confers a certain status on the clinics, improving  significant only if the vouchers covered a broad   Bank or of its Executive&#13;
their prospects when competing for other con-      range of senices of value to a large part of the    Directors or the countries&#13;
tracts, such as with the nationial social insurance  population or interventions that are particularly  they represent.&#13;
program. For these reasons providers were pre-     costly. Moreover, black market sales are not nec-&#13;
pared from the outset to offer services at prices  essarily a bad thing in this case. The secondary    To order additional copies&#13;
well below their standard rates                    recipients of vouchers would probably be mem-       contact Suzanne Smith,&#13;
bers of the target population or at least poorer   managing editor,&#13;
Conclusion                                         or at higher risk than the general population.      Room 19-017,&#13;
The World Bank,&#13;
The voucher scheme has provided access to-&#13;
1 81I8 H Street. NW,&#13;
and increased the use of-high-quality, tailored&#13;
sexual health services in a nonistigmatizing man-                                                     Washington, DC 20433&#13;
ner for commercial sex workers and their regu-     Note&#13;
lar sexual contacts. It has used scarce publlc        1 ICAS is an indepenidenit, nonilofit, nonlgovern-  001 202 458 7281&#13;
resources cost-effectively to provide services to a  mncital organization with no political or religious affilia-  Fax&#13;
group whose members have major health needs        tioIn whose sole aim is to nrnprovc the healthi of Central  001 202 522 3181&#13;
and are generally unable to pay for care. And it   Americans Its healthi programs are fundic( primilai-ly by  Emal&#13;
has reduLced the risk of STIs, incltuding HIV,     donor agenicies                                    ssmith7@worldbank org&#13;
among the general population Few input-based&#13;
programs of HIV/AIDS prevention can lay            Reference&#13;
claim to such stuccess.                               I-larper, Malcolm,Joige Ar-ioyo, Tusliar Bhattacharya,  Printed on recycled paper&#13;
But the voucher scheme also has some limita-    and Tom Bulmain 2000 Pubhc Senvce5 thiough Puvate&#13;
tions and risks. The scheme's admilistrative costs  Enterpnse Milrcw-Pnvalisation fo? Impioved Dehveiy London&#13;
account for a large share of total spending,       Initermediate Technology Development Giotip&#13;
although this share might decline if the pro-&#13;
gram's geographic coverage expancled. In addi-&#13;
tion, the scheme's price formation, through&#13;
individual negotiations with each clinic, might&#13;
raise questions abotit transparency. Fixing the&#13;
number of clinics to be contracted and selecting&#13;
just the lowest bidders might be more transpar-&#13;
This Note is available online:&#13;
www.worldbank.org/viewpoint/&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1799493">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2002/04/1799493/vouchers-health-using-voucher-schemes-output-based-aid
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <virt_coll>Knowledge Notes</virt_coll>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2002/04/1799493/vouchers-health-using-voucher-schemes-output-based-aid</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2002/04/1799493/vouchers-health-using-voucher-schemes-output-based-aid</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2002/06/24/000094946_02060704032945/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2002/06/24/000094946_02060704032945/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2002-04-30T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2002-07-02T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Vouchers for health - using voucher schemes
            for output-based aid
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            This Note examines an innovative,
            donor-supported voucher scheme to treat and prevent sexually
            transmitted diseases in Nicaragua. Voucher schemes enable
            donors to purchase outputs rather than inputs while also
            offering beneficiaries a choice of provider, a feature that
            sets them apart from other output-based approaches, such as
            supply-side subsidies to providers operating under
            performance-based contracts. Choice creates incentives to
            lower prices or raise quality (or both).
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Vouchers for health - using voucher schemes
            for output-based aid
        </docna>
        <display_title>Vouchers for health - using
            voucher schemes for output-based aid</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2002/04/1799493/vouchers-health-using-voucher-schemes-output-based-aid</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Viewpoint</docty>
        <subtopic>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation,Adolescent Health,Housing &amp; Human Habitats,Health Systems Development &amp; Reform,Health Economics &amp; Finance</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Health, Nutrition and Population,Communities and Human Settlements</teratopic>
        <count>Nicaragua</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Sandiford, Peter</author>
            <author>Gorter, Anna</author>
            <author>Salvetto, Micol</author>
        </authors>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>America!$!80450</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Central America!$!80455</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000094946_02060704032945</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Specific Diseases, including Malaria, TB, Others</subsc>
        <admreg>Latin America &amp; Caribbean,Latin America &amp; Caribbean</admreg>
        <colti>Public policy for the private sector ; Note
            no. 243</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Health, Nutrition and Population,Communities and Human Settlements</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Health, Nutrition &amp; Population</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Health care delivery; Voucher programs;
            Donor participation; Disease prevention &amp; control;
            Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome; Outputs; Subsidies;
            Performance indicators
            adolescent,cities,commercial sex,commercial
            sex workers,condoms,counseling,diagnostic
            tests,doctors,Drugs,economies of scale,female sex
            workers,health education,health needs,health
            services,high-risk,high-risk populations,HIV
            infection,Hygiene,income,infections,marginal
            costs,media,medical consultation,nurses,outpatient
            clinics,patient confidentiality,patient satisfaction,patient
            visits,patients,population groups,prevalence of
            syphilis,private providers,private sector,public
            sector,public sector clinics,quality control,risk
            groups,sex,sex work,sex worker,sex workers,sexual
            health,sexual health problems,sexual health
            services,sexually transmitted diseases,sexually transmitted
            infections,social insurance,STIs,voucher scheme,voucher
            schemes,vulnerable groups
        </keywd>
        <owner>Private Sctr Devel &amp; Infrastr VP (PSI)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>America</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Central America</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>24276</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Arts and Culture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>AIDS HIV</ml:concept><ml:concept>HIV AIDS</ml:concept><ml:concept>HIV/AIDS</ml:concept><ml:concept>Behavior Change Communication</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Compulsory Pension and Unemployment Insurance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Non-Compulsory Pensions and Insurance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Insurance (pension,unemployment benefits)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Very Vulnerable Groups (disability, orphans, children and youth)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Media</ml:concept><ml:concept>Diseases</ml:concept><ml:concept>HIV and AIDS</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Insurance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Vulnerable Groups</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Americas</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Caribbean</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Nicaragua</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>