<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>ï»¿THE WORLD BANK/IFC ARCHIVES&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    ORAL HISTORY PROGRAM&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Transcript of interview with&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Oral History Research Office&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Columbia University&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       August 2, 1961&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                       Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Interview with Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
By Prof. Robert Oliver                                  August 2, 1961&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Tape #1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Would you state your name and tell a little about the conditions&#13;
&#13;
that brought you to the Bank?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sommers:   Yes.   My name is Davidson Sommers, and I came to the Bank&#13;
&#13;
after the war.    I had been in the service and then I'd been assistant&#13;
&#13;
to the Secretary of War in the Pentagon, where I had worked in the&#13;
&#13;
office of John McCloy, who was Assistant Secretary of War, and it&#13;
&#13;
happened that his partner, Chester McClain, was the first general&#13;
&#13;
counsel of the World Bank.   I was also a good friend of Dick Demuth,&#13;
&#13;
who was in those days assistant to the President, and I had retired&#13;
&#13;
from the War Department and was living up in Connecticut, trying to&#13;
&#13;
decide which direction to move, and McClain came along and offered me&#13;
&#13;
a job in the World Bank.   I'd never heard of the World Bank, and I&#13;
&#13;
rushed out and bought a 25-cent paperback by Alvin Hanson on&#13;
&#13;
Instruments of Postwar Recovery, read that through, and then went&#13;
&#13;
down and said I'd take the job.&#13;
&#13;
           That's how I got there.   I started in as a lawyer in the&#13;
&#13;
law department, and after a couple of years--I started in in&#13;
&#13;
November, 1946--and after a year or two I was made assistant general&#13;
&#13;
counsel, and in   1949 I think it was, when McCloy left to become High&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  - 1 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                        Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Commissioner to Germany, he took McClain, my boss, with him as his&#13;
&#13;
counsel to Germany, and Black came in as President, and McCloy was&#13;
&#13;
feeling a little bit shamefaced, guilty about taking Black's lawyer&#13;
&#13;
away from him, because McClain was a very, very influential man in&#13;
&#13;
the early days of the Bank, and offered to send McClain back to help&#13;
&#13;
Black through his first annual meeting.    And I think that rather&#13;
&#13;
rubbed Black the wrong way and he said, "Thank you, we'll get along&#13;
&#13;
very well without him."    I think he was rather annoyed with McClain's&#13;
&#13;
being taken away.    I was made general counsel then and I stayed as&#13;
&#13;
general counsel until I guess it was 1955, when I became vice&#13;
&#13;
president.&#13;
&#13;
             So I was there from a few months after the Bank opened its&#13;
&#13;
doors until January, 1960.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   I have heard that the US government attempted to have somebody&#13;
&#13;
made general counsel, provided a suggestion--&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sommers:   --in the earliest days?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   In '49--&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sommers:   I don't know about that.   It doesn't surprise me either&#13;
&#13;
that this was proposed, or that it wasn't taken up.    I think there'd&#13;
&#13;
been a proposal by the United States government in 1946 or '47 that&#13;
&#13;
one of the men that had been in the Treasury and had been much&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  - 2 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                       Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
concerned with the affairs of the organization of the Bank, Luxford,&#13;
&#13;
would be given the general counselship.   Actually Mr. Meyer, who was&#13;
&#13;
the first President, didn't want a Treasury man as counsel.     He had&#13;
&#13;
the idea that he wanted somebody who would be more his man, and he&#13;
&#13;
brought in McClain.    Luxford did stay on as assistant general&#13;
&#13;
counsel, and even after I became general counsel had that job, but&#13;
&#13;
then he left to go into private practice.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Can you say anything in general about relationships to the United&#13;
&#13;
States government, in managing the Bank in the early days?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sommers:   Yes.   Are your questions being put onto this?   They are.&#13;
&#13;
Yes, the US was suspected by the British and the Europeans of wanting&#13;
&#13;
to keep the Bank and the Fund under its thumb, and that's really the&#13;
&#13;
essential basis of the whole fight between the Europeans and the&#13;
&#13;
Americans that took place at Savannah, that I mentioned in my speech,&#13;
&#13;
which went on in the Fund for many years after it had no longer been&#13;
&#13;
an issue in the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
           I can't say that I saw too many signs of this after the&#13;
&#13;
first United States Director left.   He certainly expected to run the&#13;
&#13;
Bank, but whether that was a personal idea or an idea of the&#13;
&#13;
government, I don't know.    I'm sure the official position of the US&#13;
&#13;
government was always quite proper, and always recognized the&#13;
&#13;
independent position of the Bank, but there's a lot of room within&#13;
&#13;
that official position for degrees of choice.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  - 3 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                        Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
           After Mr. Meyer quit, and after the interregnum and after&#13;
&#13;
McCloy came in, I think the United States government was pretty well&#13;
&#13;
resigned, in fact, more than resigned, was determined to keep hands&#13;
&#13;
off the Bank as a method of saving it or preserving it.    The battle&#13;
&#13;
went on in the Fund.   I must say, I think the US government was&#13;
&#13;
pretty scrupulous in avoiding pressure on us.   Now and then&#13;
&#13;
individual ambassadors would try to put pressure on us.    I remember&#13;
&#13;
on one occasion, when we were sending a telegram from Washington to&#13;
&#13;
one of our men in the field and we made use of American cable&#13;
&#13;
communications because we had no really good code of our own,&#13;
&#13;
somebody in the State Department who had read the message (because&#13;
&#13;
everything gets distributed all around) had nerve enough to call up&#13;
&#13;
Black and say he didn't agree with the policy Black was following, in&#13;
&#13;
the message sent from Black to one of his own subordinates.    But&#13;
&#13;
these were all sort of individual pieces of foolishness, and I don't&#13;
&#13;
recollect any really concerted drive to take over the Bank or to&#13;
&#13;
pressure the Bank, except in a few cases like the Aswan Dam and&#13;
&#13;
Brazil, where they made it clear what they would like us to do--to&#13;
&#13;
follow one line or another on a particular project, but even there&#13;
&#13;
they recognized that the Bank was an independent thing and that all&#13;
&#13;
they could do was suggest.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Would you say a bit more about Aswan and Brazil?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                 - 4 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                        Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sommers:   Aswan Dam?   Gosh, I could take the whole two hours on the&#13;
&#13;
Aswan Dam.    I think the thing that I remember best was in the days&#13;
&#13;
when, after several years in which we had been working along on the&#13;
&#13;
Aswan Project without any particular interest on the part of the&#13;
&#13;
Americans and the British, and after we finally decided it was a&#13;
&#13;
project that made sense, provided it was surrounded with enough&#13;
&#13;
conditions, the Russians made an offer to finance it, or were alleged&#13;
&#13;
to make an offer to finance it, and then the British and the&#13;
&#13;
Americans practically trampled us to death in their hurry to get into&#13;
&#13;
the act and we were being pushed very vigorously to not be so tough&#13;
&#13;
on such pieces of red tape and technicality as asking agreement from&#13;
&#13;
the Sudan before the dam flooded a town of 65,000 Sudanese and so&#13;
&#13;
forth.   This was regarded as pretty--by the British and Americans, as&#13;
&#13;
being pretty finicky on our part, that we should ask for Sudanese&#13;
&#13;
consent.&#13;
&#13;
             And I remember attending a meeting at the State Department&#13;
&#13;
at which Black and the British--I don't remember whether Eden was&#13;
&#13;
there or Roger Maken--and I can't remember, I guess it must have been&#13;
&#13;
Hoover was there for the State Department.    I remember--&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Herbert Hoover, Jr.?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sommers:   Yes.   I remember Black's standing up pretty firmly and&#13;
&#13;
saying that we intended to go along with the project, but that he&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  - 5 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                       Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
wasn't going to be pushed into relaxing any of the conditions he&#13;
&#13;
intended to impose.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   How about Brazil?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sommers:   Well, Brazil is not an incident.   Brazil is a whole&#13;
&#13;
history.   I think it would take too long to get into it.   Brazil was&#13;
&#13;
a series of recurrent crises in which the United States government&#13;
&#13;
ventured forth on rescue missions.   That's the most rescued maiden in&#13;
&#13;
history, and the dragon is still in hot pursuit.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Did the US government want the Bank to be more lenient in its&#13;
&#13;
policy towards Brazil?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sommers:   I would have thought so, on several occasions, yes, and on&#13;
&#13;
several occasions we were not as lenient as they would have liked.&#13;
&#13;
But of course there's nothing peculiar about the United States'&#13;
&#13;
position in that.   We had all kinds of cases in which the British&#13;
&#13;
might be interested in a particular loan, or the French--the&#13;
&#13;
underdeveloped countries were mostly not interested--they had no&#13;
&#13;
interest to spare for loans to other countries.    They were devoting&#13;
&#13;
it all to loans to themselves.   So we very seldom got into a case&#13;
&#13;
where India was pounding the table about, "You have to make a loan to&#13;
&#13;
Ceylon."   That wasn't very usual.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                 - 6 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                       Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   How were these negotiations between the US government and the&#13;
&#13;
management of the Bank to proceed?    Were they outside of the&#13;
&#13;
executive director meetings?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sommers:   Oh, yes.   In fact, all negotiations in the Bank, or as far&#13;
&#13;
as I know in practically any company or organization, if they're&#13;
&#13;
really negotiations and hard points that are proceeding with a&#13;
&#13;
prospect of working something out, that doesn't go on in the&#13;
&#13;
meetings, any more than it does here.&#13;
&#13;
           In the early days--there's a whole story which you should&#13;
&#13;
go into, of coordination between the Americans and the Bank.     It's&#13;
&#13;
always been a cardinal principle of everybody that activities of the&#13;
&#13;
Bank on the one hand, and the Export-Import Bank and the ECA and the&#13;
&#13;
Development Loan Fund on the other hand should be coordinated, and&#13;
&#13;
the United States government had its piece of machinery, the National&#13;
&#13;
Advisory Council, as it used to be called, which was supposed to&#13;
&#13;
effect this coordination.&#13;
&#13;
           In the early days under McCloy and Black, we had regular&#13;
&#13;
meetings with the Export-Import Bank management, in which we would&#13;
&#13;
exchange lists of things we had in mind doing, and projects.     We&#13;
&#13;
always felt we didn't get told anything by the Export-Import Bank&#13;
&#13;
until after it had happened.   The relationships were very bad indeed.&#13;
&#13;
There was a great deal of jealousy.   There was a great deal of&#13;
&#13;
competition, and as between Black and the then heads of the Export-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  - 7 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                        Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Import Bank there was not very much love lost.   So this was a real&#13;
&#13;
failure at coordination.&#13;
&#13;
           The Development Loan Fund worked very much better, because&#13;
&#13;
by the time it got going--and the ICA or the ECA or the MSA or&#13;
&#13;
whatever it was called from time to time--here the coordination went&#13;
&#13;
on at the working level pretty much, and there wasn't any attempt at&#13;
&#13;
regular meetings between the tops.   It went pretty well.&#13;
&#13;
           We had a similar long history of cool, cold and hot with&#13;
&#13;
the United Nations.   I think we were regarded by the United Nations&#13;
&#13;
originally as being pretty difficult and independent.    You know, we&#13;
&#13;
insisted on this unique kind of treaty with the United Nations that's&#13;
&#13;
different from all the other specialized agencies, because the Bank&#13;
&#13;
and the Fund who were together in this have a different status from&#13;
&#13;
the other specialized agencies.   They're not under the United&#13;
&#13;
Nations.   Their budgets are not coordinated by the United Nations.&#13;
&#13;
So we had a different kind of a treaty.   This created a rather cool&#13;
&#13;
relationship in the beginning, because we were trying to prevent the&#13;
&#13;
United Nations from making recommendations to us for particular&#13;
&#13;
projects for financing.&#13;
&#13;
           Over the years, the thing got a lot closer, and finally the&#13;
&#13;
relationship between Black and Hammarskjold as a result have--as a&#13;
&#13;
result of Suez and the Indus and Congo and a lot of things, where we&#13;
&#13;
were of real service to the United Nations and where we worked&#13;
&#13;
together with Hammarskjold, got considerably warmer.    Nevertheless&#13;
&#13;
there was always a good deal of well, sort of jealousy on behalf of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  - 8 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                        Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
the United Nations, in that it was natural for them to think that it&#13;
&#13;
was too bad that all this money was wasted on us when they had the&#13;
&#13;
really intelligent ideas as to how to use it.    That's the natural&#13;
&#13;
feeling of anybody who's got a lot of ideas and hasn't any funds&#13;
&#13;
available to carry them out with.&#13;
&#13;
            Within the United Nations staff as well as the membership,&#13;
&#13;
there's been a real movement that the United Nations ought to get&#13;
&#13;
into the capital financing business.     Technical assistance was a&#13;
&#13;
first step, and the Hoffman Special Fund is a second step, a&#13;
&#13;
compromise, something short of capital financing.    But the other --&#13;
&#13;
the pure SUNFED idea, if you remember that proposal, is not dead.&#13;
&#13;
That will revive again from time to time.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   To go back to the Aswan Dam question for a moment, when the US&#13;
&#13;
government decided it would not help finance the Aswan Dam, did it&#13;
&#13;
suggest to the Bank that it ought to pull out also?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sommers:   It didn't have to suggest to the Bank, because the whole&#13;
&#13;
basis of our considering the Aswan Dam from long before the British&#13;
&#13;
and Americans had come into it was that we would only consider it,&#13;
&#13;
and that the Egyptians should only consider it, on the basis of&#13;
&#13;
something like 50 percent loan, 50 percent grants.    Their economy&#13;
&#13;
couldn't handle it if they had to repay it all.    In fact, one of&#13;
&#13;
these famous conditions was based on the concept that if they&#13;
&#13;
undertook the Aswan Dam, they were going to have to tighten their&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                 - 9 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                       Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
belt in a whole lot of other fields, as far as development was&#13;
&#13;
concerned, during the period when Aswan represented all outgo and no&#13;
&#13;
return.    Once it started earning a return, then it would be all&#13;
&#13;
right, but it was such a slow project that you practically had,&#13;
&#13;
putting it in financial terms, ten years of interest to capitalize.&#13;
&#13;
They had just about that much potentiality.   So we had always said,&#13;
&#13;
any loan by us is conditional on in effect having it matched by grant&#13;
&#13;
contributions.   So when the British and the US withdrew, our loan&#13;
&#13;
wasn't even a starter any longer.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   How about the Indus Project?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sommers:   I was in that from the earliest stage.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Could you tell us a little about that?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sommers:   Well, the start of the Indus Project in the Bank I think&#13;
&#13;
was legitimately the Lilienthal article in Colliers which suggested&#13;
&#13;
that the Bank might be called in to solve this problem because it was&#13;
&#13;
essentially a functional and engineering problem--(which wasn't true&#13;
&#13;
at all) and because it didn't involve the passions that were involved&#13;
&#13;
in the Kashmir problem, which was incapable of resolution.&#13;
&#13;
            Well, like many of the things of Lilienthal's, this was a&#13;
&#13;
fairly intelligent insight, as events proved, except--well, I think&#13;
&#13;
Black was taking to it because of his feeling that engineers speak a&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                 - 10 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                       Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
sort of international language and communicate across political&#13;
&#13;
difficulties that stop the politicians.    And he also thought that&#13;
&#13;
this was primarily an engineering problem.   But that was not the&#13;
&#13;
case.   It was a lot of other things besides that.   In any event, he&#13;
&#13;
asked either Iliff or me, as I remember it, to draft a letter to both&#13;
&#13;
prime ministers suggesting that we would go ahead, and we did draft&#13;
&#13;
such a letter.   I remember showing it to B.K. Nehru in advance.    He&#13;
&#13;
said, "Well, it's a nice letter, the Prime Minister is expert at&#13;
&#13;
answering such letters and you'll get a very polite answer which&#13;
&#13;
won't say no but will mean no."&#13;
&#13;
           But in fact, the letter got a fairly warm response.     It&#13;
&#13;
didn't get a negative response from either side, although the&#13;
&#13;
Pakistanis were somewhat warmer than the Indians, and afforded us a&#13;
&#13;
basis for following it up with a second letter, when we could see a&#13;
&#13;
little bit more what was bothering the two sides--and before we knew&#13;
&#13;
it, we were in business for eight or nine years.&#13;
&#13;
           That's one of the most interesting things I've ever had&#13;
&#13;
anything to do with.   It went in three stages or four stages, the&#13;
&#13;
preliminary negotiations, to get the mediation going, in which I&#13;
&#13;
think I took a fairly active role; then the whole stage of the&#13;
&#13;
engineer's negotiations, in which Wheeler was the leading Bank man,&#13;
&#13;
and it was almost purely on an engineering basis.    Then I was brought&#13;
&#13;
in again to write up the proposal that the Bank made, and after that&#13;
&#13;
proposal was made, the engineers sort of dropped into a secondary&#13;
&#13;
role, and it became a--more of a negotiating matter when Black and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  - 11 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                         Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Garner and I and Wheeler were all in the act, trying frantically to&#13;
&#13;
keep the thing from flying apart.&#13;
&#13;
              Finally we found a formula on which both sides were willing&#13;
&#13;
to go ahead and renew these discussions.     And I remember Iliff and I&#13;
&#13;
going in to see Black and saying together, "This is no longer a thing&#13;
&#13;
that should be treated as a pure engineering matter.     You have to&#13;
&#13;
have somebody higher up in the Bank's management and also with a&#13;
&#13;
little more political savvy in charge of it."     We jointly suggested&#13;
&#13;
that one or the other of us be put in charge of it.     Iliff was put in&#13;
&#13;
charge of it at the time.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Iliff?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sommers:   Iliff, yes, and I think he stayed in it for three or four&#13;
&#13;
years after that, maybe more, until its successful conclusion.       It&#13;
&#13;
was a wonderful achievement on his part.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Was this the first occasion in the history of the Bank when the&#13;
&#13;
Bank became a mediator?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sommers:   Oh, no.    It wasn't even the first occasion on which the&#13;
&#13;
Bank became a successful mediator.     We had done several things.     The&#13;
&#13;
one that sticks in my mind of course is the unsuccessful attempt to&#13;
&#13;
mediate the Abadan Oil Refinery nationalization, where we did a lot&#13;
&#13;
of work and we made a proposal that essentially formed the framework&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   - 12 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                       Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
on which a solution was later found by the US government.    We made a&#13;
&#13;
proposal that in effect the Bank would take over the refinery, as a&#13;
&#13;
trustee--not using that name--but that we would provide an&#13;
&#13;
international facade, under which the operations could be resumed,&#13;
&#13;
bringing in a management not exclusively British but headed by a non-&#13;
&#13;
Britisher and with an international flavor, which would run the&#13;
&#13;
refinery and the oil operations, under our auspices.   We didn't&#13;
&#13;
pretend that we, the Bank, would actually direct the refinery, but we&#13;
&#13;
would select the people to do it, and there would be some current&#13;
&#13;
payments made to Iran, and the whole question of ultimate title, as I&#13;
&#13;
remember it, would be held in abeyance.    So this was an interim&#13;
&#13;
receivership kind of operation.&#13;
&#13;
          And part of this format later was adopted.    Unfortunately,&#13;
&#13;
although both the British and the Iranians agreed to all this in&#13;
&#13;
principle, it was just impossible for Mossadegh to actually agree to&#13;
&#13;
anything, because any agreement was a retreat from his pretensions,&#13;
&#13;
and he just wasn't strong enough or else he wasn't the kind of person&#13;
&#13;
who makes those concessions.&#13;
&#13;
          So that was not a success, although I must say it held the&#13;
&#13;
situation in a state of healthy suspension for some time, and I think&#13;
&#13;
made a contribution.   Then we had a few smaller cases of mediation.&#13;
&#13;
We had a claim between an American contracting company and a&#13;
&#13;
Guatemalan borrower of ours, in which there was a dispute as to the&#13;
&#13;
amount of the contract.   It wasn't really a mediation but it was a--&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  - 13 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                      Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
we finally said that we would designate an arbitrator for them and we&#13;
&#13;
did.&#13;
&#13;
           Then we had a whole lot of things that weren't formal&#13;
&#13;
mediations, but where we would intervene, let's say, in such matters&#13;
&#13;
as the proper rate structure for one of the borrowers in Mexico.     I&#13;
&#13;
think we had a case in Colombia where there were some charges that&#13;
&#13;
the Colombian government was unfairly treating a private utility, not&#13;
&#13;
our project, and we said, "Look, before--" I don't believe it was the&#13;
&#13;
Colombian government, I believe it was a municipality.   I believe&#13;
&#13;
that we said that before we would go ahead, we wanted to see what&#13;
&#13;
they could do about that.&#13;
&#13;
           And really the way we got into this most directly, I&#13;
&#13;
suppose, was in the area of the policy of not lending to countries&#13;
&#13;
that were in default on their outstanding public debt, because that&#13;
&#13;
immediately got us into conversations as to how that might be&#13;
&#13;
settled.&#13;
&#13;
           But certainly the Indus was the first--except Iran--the&#13;
&#13;
Indus was the second world-shaking scale mediation that the Bank went&#13;
&#13;
into.   It was the most complicated, in the sense that what we did in&#13;
&#13;
regard to compensation for Suez and the British UK financial&#13;
&#13;
agreement was essentially looking at each side's position and putting&#13;
&#13;
your finger down on a figure in between, fairly arbitrary, that's&#13;
&#13;
what mediators normally do.   The Indus thing was different in that it&#13;
&#13;
was of such enormous technical complexity that you couldn't do that&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                - 14 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                       Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
without--until you'd mastered the whole subject, and it was a dispute&#13;
&#13;
that had been going on for 30 years.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   I'm curious as to how the Bank got involved in mediating.   Did it&#13;
&#13;
take the initiative?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sommers:   Sometimes it took the initiative.   It took the initiative&#13;
&#13;
in Indus, at Lilienthal's suggestion.    It took the initiative in the&#13;
&#13;
case of Iran, and I don't know whether that was suggested by&#13;
&#13;
outsiders or not.   Sometimes just friends might come along and say,&#13;
&#13;
"Nobody can do anything about this but you, why don't you get into&#13;
&#13;
this?"   I don't remember the origins of the Egyptian Suez&#13;
&#13;
compensation agreement.   My guess is that we got into it at the&#13;
&#13;
initiative of the Suez Canal Company, to whom it was suggested,&#13;
&#13;
probably by some American lawyer, if they had American lawyers, or&#13;
&#13;
somebody like that who was desperately looking around for ideas, who&#13;
&#13;
suggested, "Why don't you go see the Bank?"&#13;
&#13;
           Now, we protected ourselves in this field by the rule that&#13;
&#13;
we never went into this kind of thing except at the invitation of&#13;
&#13;
both sides, both governments, even if one side was a private party.&#13;
&#13;
And that we never would go into anything that was political, rather&#13;
&#13;
than economic or financial.   Of course, it's sometimes fairly hard to&#13;
&#13;
keep a straight face when you say that the Egyptian-British troubles&#13;
&#13;
were financial rather than political.    But that isn't the point.   The&#13;
&#13;
point was that the meat of the controversy that was to be settled was&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                - 15 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                       Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
money.   And as long as it could be settled on the basis of either&#13;
&#13;
money or technical engineering considerations, then we would deal&#13;
&#13;
with it.   If it got into elaborate political settlements, we couldn't&#13;
&#13;
handle it, although in the Indus, of course, you couldn't stay out of&#13;
&#13;
the Kashmir problem, because it involved building works in the&#13;
&#13;
disputed areas of Kashmir, and they would have to invent the most&#13;
&#13;
elaborate disclaimer provision ever devised by the mortal man, that&#13;
&#13;
nothing anybody did or failed to do should be a recognition or an&#13;
&#13;
acknowledgment of anybody else's position, and nobody could invoke&#13;
&#13;
this treaty in any other dispute.    Quite a thing.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Were there any suggestions of mediations during Mr. McCloy's term&#13;
&#13;
as President?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sommers:   I don't remember whether the Abadan incident started before&#13;
&#13;
McCloy left or not.   That was primarily a Garner matter anyway.    It&#13;
&#13;
wasn't either Black or McCloy.    Garner was the one who worked that up&#13;
&#13;
and did most of the work of it.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   I take it that Mr. Black rather enjoys the role of mediator.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sommers:   Yes.   I think he enjoys it, and I think he feels that it's&#13;
&#13;
a very important part of what the Bank has done--important in the&#13;
&#13;
sense that nobody else has been able to do this, except perhaps the&#13;
&#13;
UN in the purely political field.    But there are none of the other&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  - 16 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                        Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
financial bodies that have had a role of this kind, successful or&#13;
&#13;
unsuccessful, and of course the Bank had a pretty unhappy picture of&#13;
&#13;
lots of attempts and no successes, until Suez.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   "Lots of attempts"--this sounds as if there must have been more&#13;
&#13;
than the two you mention.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sommers:   Well, it depends upon what you include in this area.    There&#13;
&#13;
were only three of this magnitude--Iran--four really.    Iran, two&#13;
&#13;
connected with the Suez Canal, and the Indus.    But there are all&#13;
&#13;
kinds of little ones coming up all the time; sometimes your role as a&#13;
&#13;
mediator is formal, sometimes it's just incidental to some work on a&#13;
&#13;
project.&#13;
&#13;
           For example, I think--I've lost my familiarity with all&#13;
&#13;
this, but there's something like only one river between the Nile and&#13;
&#13;
the Ganges of any size that isn't an international river.    So any&#13;
&#13;
river loan, any loan you make for power or hydroelectric power or&#13;
&#13;
irrigation anywhere in that area is likely to involve international&#13;
&#13;
issues, and there is no law on the subject and there are no&#13;
&#13;
agreements on the subject.    In Europe this has all been covered by&#13;
&#13;
agreements for generations.   And these people don't know how to&#13;
&#13;
negotiate these things, so it's quite likely that any loan in that&#13;
&#13;
area will involve a mediation.   We did not mediate in a formal sense&#13;
&#13;
between the Egyptians and the Sudanese in regard to the Nile, but we&#13;
&#13;
did say to the Egyptians at the time of the Aswan Dam, "No loan until&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                 - 17 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                        Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
you come to an agreement with the Sudanese," and Black was being&#13;
&#13;
gotten out of bed at Cairo at 3 o'clock in the morning by people from&#13;
&#13;
the Sudan pushing this view on him.    Of course, later on when the&#13;
&#13;
Sudanese came to us for a loan on a Sudanese Dam and we said "No loan&#13;
&#13;
until you come to an agreement with the Egyptians," they thought this&#13;
&#13;
was very highhanded.    But the result was, we talked a great deal to&#13;
&#13;
both sides.    We gave some idea of what we thought was feasible.   We&#13;
&#13;
made it clear we thought there was plenty of water for both, and the&#13;
&#13;
result was, they came to an agreement to which we were not a formal&#13;
&#13;
party, although we offered ourselves, and I think the British&#13;
&#13;
suggested that we get into the act.&#13;
&#13;
             Well, now, I don't know whether that's a mediation or not.&#13;
&#13;
That's another important one.    But this doesn't appear in the books&#13;
&#13;
as a mediation.    And there are lots of little ones.   There's&#13;
&#13;
compensation for the American and Foreign Power properties in&#13;
&#13;
Argentina.    There's a mediation between French bondholders and the&#13;
&#13;
city of Tokyo on a bond issue.    There are lots of these things on a&#13;
&#13;
smaller level.    But there was a time when we had quite a few attempts&#13;
&#13;
and hadn't had one success.    And then they started falling in fairly&#13;
&#13;
quickly.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Might it be said that these mediation attempts began in a sense&#13;
&#13;
as early as the Chilean negotiations when the Bank insisted that the&#13;
&#13;
Chileans had to make an agreement on the defaulted debt?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  - 18 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                        Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sommers:   Yes.   Yes, and they all had some relation to lending.&#13;
&#13;
There's a common thread.    The Egyptians wanted us to do the Aswan&#13;
&#13;
Dam, and that led to our position in the Egyptian negotiations&#13;
&#13;
because I think Black had the confidence of Nasser, in spite of the&#13;
&#13;
Aswan business.    In the Indus, what seemed to give us an interest in&#13;
&#13;
it was that we had been asked by both sides to finance projects on&#13;
&#13;
the Indus system, and had refused because of the unresolved question&#13;
&#13;
of the water.     We've done that in various parts of the world.    And so&#13;
&#13;
you're right, that there is a relation to lending.    If you write a&#13;
&#13;
letter asking to be invited in as mediator, to put it crudely, you&#13;
&#13;
generally find the letter winds up with some such phrase as appeared&#13;
&#13;
in our letter to Nehru and--I don't remember who the Pakistani Prime&#13;
&#13;
Minister was, Mohammed Ali Khan, I think--saying "If you would like&#13;
&#13;
to proceed, the Bank will assign people and will be prepared to&#13;
&#13;
consider sympathetically any financing proposals that result from the&#13;
&#13;
agreement."   There's always an overtone of financial help in the&#13;
&#13;
background.   Otherwise it doesn't have the necessary sex appeal.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   To come back to relations between the Bank and the US government,&#13;
&#13;
I wonder if you could say something about the Polish loan&#13;
&#13;
negotiations?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sommers:   No.    I don't know where I was at that time, except that I&#13;
&#13;
wasn't--I was pretty new and I wasn't in on that one at all.       All I&#13;
&#13;
could say was about fourth hand and you could probably get better&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  - 19 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                       Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
sources.   You ought to go and see Jack McCloy.   I'm sorry you can't&#13;
&#13;
see my old boss, Chester McClain, who was really a tower of strength.&#13;
&#13;
All I know is that the Bank felt it ought to do something about East-&#13;
&#13;
West Europe, and started with an ultra-cautious move, an offer&#13;
&#13;
suggested I believe from the EEC or ECE, the East-West European&#13;
&#13;
Organization.   Are you an economics professor?   Ok, you know all this&#13;
&#13;
stuff more than I do.   I think somebody on Myrdal's staff had the&#13;
&#13;
idea that it was very important that something be done to counteract&#13;
&#13;
the disintegration tendencies of the European Economic situation, and&#13;
&#13;
he thought up a rather ingenious scheme which was almost too&#13;
&#13;
ingenious, as it proved--that you could make a loan to the timber&#13;
&#13;
producers, and since there was such a shortage of timber in Western&#13;
&#13;
Europe that it would be practically a self-liquidating short-term&#13;
&#13;
loan.    And the Bank offered to make loans of small amounts, 10&#13;
&#13;
million dollars or something like that, to Poland, Czechoslovakia,&#13;
&#13;
Finland and Yugoslavia.&#13;
&#13;
            It did make such offers, which were accepted by Yugoslavia&#13;
&#13;
and Finland.    The arrangements were so complicated it took months and&#13;
&#13;
months to work out this three-cornered deal.   And it came to be sort&#13;
&#13;
of a farce, because the money kept coming in too fast.    The loans&#13;
&#13;
were paid off so soon that they really didn't make much economic&#13;
&#13;
sense.   But the Czechs and the Poles turned those loans down, and the&#13;
&#13;
Yugoslavs and Finns took theirs.   The Yugoslav loan was the first&#13;
&#13;
loan fully repaid to the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                 - 20 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                      Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
           Now, as a second step from that, somebody was working on a&#13;
&#13;
large Polish loan which would not have this elaborate sort of&#13;
&#13;
collateral security in terms of payments from somebody else.    I don't&#13;
&#13;
remember the relationship between this and the London government, and&#13;
&#13;
the revival of a supposedly consolidated Polish government and free&#13;
&#13;
elections and all that business, but I've always been told that the&#13;
&#13;
Bank was willing to go in for a loan and that the United States&#13;
&#13;
government finally said they would not vote for it, and the Bank&#13;
&#13;
finally told the Poles if the US government wouldn't vote for it,it&#13;
&#13;
couldn't get through, and therefore it would not be put up.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   I've heard that at about this same time, the British indicated&#13;
&#13;
reluctance to vote in favor of a proposed loan to Belgium.    Do you&#13;
&#13;
recall anything about that?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sommers:   Oh, well, the British have indicated reluctance to vote for&#13;
&#13;
proposed loans to the Belgians for years and years, but that's an&#13;
&#13;
entirely different thing.   All of the Europeans felt kind of peeved&#13;
&#13;
about the Belgians, because in the first place they felt the Belgians&#13;
&#13;
had got out of the war relatively cheaply, and there was a lot of&#13;
&#13;
feeling in the US Marshall Plan people that the Belgians were getting&#13;
&#13;
away too easy, and for that reason they made the Belgians grant&#13;
&#13;
conditional aid, as a counterpart of the Marshall Plan, you remember.&#13;
&#13;
And there was a lot of feeling that Governor Frere's monetary policy&#13;
&#13;
was much too conservative, and that therefore the Belgians were&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                - 21 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                       Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
asking for help which they didn't need; that if they had a less rigid&#13;
&#13;
policy of carrying high reserves, and in gold, they would have&#13;
&#13;
loosened up their own economy a good deal more.   The Belgians had a&#13;
&#13;
policy of deliberate deflation.    It was an attitude of:   Well, if&#13;
&#13;
they won't help themselves, why should we help them?&#13;
&#13;
          I doubt that this ever got to the point where the British&#13;
&#13;
would have voted against the Belgians, if it came to a showdown.       But&#13;
&#13;
there was always a great deal of difference of opinion in the Bank&#13;
&#13;
and outside, as to whether, once the Marshall Plan had taken over,&#13;
&#13;
the Bank should make loans for what were essentially internal&#13;
&#13;
metropolitan Belgian projects.    We did several of them--the canal&#13;
&#13;
loan, pure window dressing for a balance of payments loan to Belgium,&#13;
&#13;
not for balance of payments purposes but for internal purposes, to&#13;
&#13;
enable Frere to maintain a conservative fiscal and monetary policy.&#13;
&#13;
Frere was refusing to lend money to the government from the Central&#13;
&#13;
Bank, and the World Bank enabled him to get by with it by putting in&#13;
&#13;
resources from the outside.&#13;
&#13;
          I don't think this was a silly loan for Belgium.     It's&#13;
&#13;
really a question of priority in the use of the Bank's resources.      If&#13;
&#13;
there were plenty of money to go around, I don't see why that isn't&#13;
&#13;
perfectly sensible.   But it was in the context of people thinking&#13;
&#13;
that Belgium was not doing its part in various other organizations&#13;
&#13;
that this friction arose.   It has nothing to do with the first issue,&#13;
&#13;
the Polish issue.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  - 22 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                        Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   What I'm concerned about is any pressure that might be brought by&#13;
&#13;
a member government to keep the Bank from making loans.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sommers:    Well, pressure is one thing.   After all, you've got to&#13;
&#13;
distinguish in the Bank between affirmative pressure and negative&#13;
&#13;
pressure.   It's always been recognized--after all, the Bank has a&#13;
&#13;
board of directors that is supposed to exercise a lot more authority&#13;
&#13;
than it sometimes did.   And there never has been any question but the&#13;
&#13;
fact that the United States government alone could prevent the Bank&#13;
&#13;
from doing anything that it decided to, and that any group of&#13;
&#13;
countries, the underdeveloped countries as a whole could, if they&#13;
&#13;
banded together, probably block the Bank from doing it.    It's much&#13;
&#13;
easier to say "don't do something" than to make the Bank do&#13;
&#13;
something, affirmatively.&#13;
&#13;
            There was the Polish case, and there have been several&#13;
&#13;
occasions on which waves of opinion among groups of countries in the&#13;
&#13;
Bank have persuaded the management to put a different emphasis on its&#13;
&#13;
line.   But these were not for extraneous political considerations,&#13;
&#13;
these were for perfectly respectable considerations of policy&#13;
&#13;
relevant to the Bank's operations, such as, "do we have international&#13;
&#13;
competition on procurement under Bank loans?"    This was actually a&#13;
&#13;
management proposal in the first place, but the eagerness with which&#13;
&#13;
it was accepted by the advanced countries sort of kept the Bank's&#13;
&#13;
nose to the grindstone, once it adopted this policy.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                 - 23 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                         Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
             There have been several other things.   On the question of&#13;
&#13;
taking security--there was a general wave of opinion among the&#13;
&#13;
governments, as to what was proper and what was not, that had its&#13;
&#13;
influence on the Bank's management.    There's nothing improper about&#13;
&#13;
that.   I don't know of any successful effort to pressure the Bank&#13;
&#13;
into doing something that it did not want to do, and I don't know&#13;
&#13;
even of the very many serious unsuccessful efforts.     Of course, there&#13;
&#13;
are always Senators and Congressmen writing you, but I don't know&#13;
&#13;
many cases in which any government, the United States or other,&#13;
&#13;
really made a determined drive to push the Bank into doing something&#13;
&#13;
that was completely apart from its regular line of operations.&#13;
&#13;
             We made a silly loan in Brazil for suburban railway cars,&#13;
&#13;
in Rio de Janeiro.    I guess this was a little urging by the US&#13;
&#13;
government that we ought to do something, and I don't think any of us&#13;
&#13;
were too happy with that loan.    But I think we made the mistake&#13;
&#13;
ourselves.    We thought we ought to do something in Brazil.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Now, I take it that Mr. Black has become very adept at personal&#13;
&#13;
diplomacy, in managing relations between the Bank and its member&#13;
&#13;
governments in such a way so that controversial issues never get to&#13;
&#13;
the floor of the meeting of the Board.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sommers:   Well, that's true.   They try to deal with them outside of&#13;
&#13;
the meetings, but sometimes they do get to meetings, and--but it's&#13;
&#13;
pretty hard, with a board of 18, to get a solution in a round table&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  - 24 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                         Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
conference, and it's also embarrassing when you have weighted voting,&#13;
&#13;
in the sense that you don't want three or four countries to vote down&#13;
&#13;
a whole lot of countries.   So it's generally much more palatable to&#13;
&#13;
get some kind of a compromise or deal worked out.   I don't think&#13;
&#13;
that's any different from any other organization.   I don't think very&#13;
&#13;
much is decided in the Security Council in debates either.     I think&#13;
&#13;
that what distinguishes the Bank from the Security Council is not the&#13;
&#13;
mechanism by which agreements are reached, but the relative frequency&#13;
&#13;
of reaching agreement, instead of reaching an impasse.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   I wonder if there are any general contrasts that could be drawn&#13;
&#13;
between Mr. McCloy's term in office and Mr. Black's?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sommers:   Yes.   Well, the major contrast of course is that McCloy was&#13;
&#13;
during the formative period, came in when the Bank was at its&#13;
&#13;
absolutely lowest ebb.   It was almost on the rocks.   It had no&#13;
&#13;
reputation.   It was regarded by the British as almost a dead issue.&#13;
&#13;
They were much more concerned about the Fund.   It had no credit.    It&#13;
&#13;
had no money available to it.   It was an empty shell.    And McCloy,&#13;
&#13;
mostly I think through Black and Garner, put flesh and bones on this&#13;
&#13;
paper structure.   But still, by the time McCloy left in 1949, the&#13;
&#13;
Bank was not a howling success.    I think it had a lending rate&#13;
&#13;
averaging something like 200 million dollars a year.     The Marshall&#13;
&#13;
Plan had vastly overshadowed it.    It had hardly got into the&#13;
&#13;
development field on a major scale, and--but the foundation had been&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  - 25 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                      Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
laid and I think Black had been primarily responsible for building&#13;
&#13;
contacts with the market in the United States.   Garner was primarily&#13;
&#13;
responsible for the organization, the essential attitude of the Bank,&#13;
&#13;
the somewhat tough attitude which was pretty useful in those days,&#13;
&#13;
and the counterpart of it--because Bob Garner was responsible for&#13;
&#13;
both the good and the bad parts--a certain atmosphere of smugness,&#13;
&#13;
"we know more about it than anyone else."   That atmosphere is not too&#13;
&#13;
pleasant even now when it's probably true that they do know more&#13;
&#13;
about it than most other people, but in the days when they obviously&#13;
&#13;
didn't know anything, it was a little bit unpleasant to take.&#13;
&#13;
          But it in its turn was responsible for making people think&#13;
&#13;
they were better than they were, and they finally got to be better&#13;
&#13;
than they had been.&#13;
&#13;
          McCloy provided in this picture, I think, essentially a&#13;
&#13;
very magnetic personality in whom everyone had confidence.   He was&#13;
&#13;
very well liked by the Europeans.   He devoted a great deal of his&#13;
&#13;
time to this fight that I reported in my speech, about the board,&#13;
&#13;
which he didn't win.   But I never thought that he as a person was the&#13;
&#13;
main builder of the early days of the Bank.   I think it was Black and&#13;
&#13;
Garner.&#13;
&#13;
          Now, Black came in, with an equally good personality, with&#13;
&#13;
a very much better--much more extensive experience as what he calls a&#13;
&#13;
"deal man," a man who knows how to make financial deals, and on the&#13;
&#13;
whole I would say a less timid approach to taking risks.   And two&#13;
&#13;
things set Black off, and made him a success--first, as I reported in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                - 26 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                        Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
that speech of mine, at his first annual meeting he inherited the&#13;
&#13;
whole uproar created by McCloy's attempt to reform the board of&#13;
&#13;
directors along the British line.    Black took that over, when the&#13;
&#13;
United States government, which had pledged to help McCloy, turned&#13;
&#13;
tail and ran when they saw the opposition.&#13;
&#13;
             Black was left with this whole mess in his lap at his&#13;
&#13;
opening annual meeting, and--I'll take some credit for this, because&#13;
&#13;
I was just general counsel for the first time, and I said to him,&#13;
&#13;
"Don't let the governors go through with what they've decided to do.&#13;
&#13;
They have postponed the issue for a year.     Don't let it come before&#13;
&#13;
the governors again.    Get the credit for solving this issue with the&#13;
&#13;
directors.    Come up with some compromise.   You can't win on the&#13;
&#13;
McCloy line."&#13;
&#13;
             So he did, and he's awfully good at it--he's a wonderful&#13;
&#13;
tactician, and he immediately went into the directors' meeting and&#13;
&#13;
said, "Look, this is a question of relationship between me and you.&#13;
&#13;
This isn't something on which we have to go to our stockholders to&#13;
&#13;
get it solved.    Let's make a joint recommendation to them, they'll&#13;
&#13;
adopt it."&#13;
&#13;
             And he did this in a few months after he came in.    I can't&#13;
&#13;
even remember what the compromise was.     It isn't so terribly&#13;
&#13;
important.    Anyway, they made a report, and this was adopted by the&#13;
&#13;
governors and was kept off the agenda for the next annual meeting.&#13;
&#13;
This was a little triumph for Black when he came in.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  - 27 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                        Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
             Also, about the same time, he completely began to reverse&#13;
&#13;
the previous attitude of McCloy and Garner, which probably had been&#13;
&#13;
necessary, but had been vastly overdone, of not telling the board&#13;
&#13;
anything, of presenting them with faits accomplis.    Black, as part of&#13;
&#13;
this same compromise, proposed a much more liberal treatment to the&#13;
&#13;
board, in terms of giving them information and giving them advance&#13;
&#13;
notice, and that improved the atmosphere a great deal.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Tape #2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sommers: So I think that one of Black's key acts was this better&#13;
&#13;
relationship with the board of directors and the governors.    From the&#13;
&#13;
moment he came on, the whole tone was different.     The second thing&#13;
&#13;
was that he took a more active role, or had a more active influence,&#13;
&#13;
I think, on our lending policy, than had been true of McCloy, partly&#13;
&#13;
because McCloy was so much more interested in political things than&#13;
&#13;
financial.    He was essentially a Secretary of State man.   I never got&#13;
&#13;
the impression that he either had much interest or much real&#13;
&#13;
expertise in financial matters.    He was not a financial lawyer,&#13;
&#13;
although he was always called a Wall Street lawyer.    His experience&#13;
&#13;
had been in litigation, and in one big case, the Black Tom case; he&#13;
&#13;
was not a well-rounded financial lawyer.&#13;
&#13;
             Well, in my mind--I suppose you always tend to consider the&#13;
&#13;
important things in the history of the Bank are things you yourself&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  - 28 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                       Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
were connected with, I'm trying to discount that--but to my mind, the&#13;
&#13;
most important thing that Black did in getting the Bank started on a&#13;
&#13;
more expansive vein was the first Australian loan.   I don't know when&#13;
&#13;
that happened, but it came pretty close after he took over.&#13;
&#13;
            Now, the history of this had been that we'd had an&#13;
&#13;
Australian director on the board who was a bitter hater of Garner and&#13;
&#13;
the Bank, and reacted violently against this relationship between the&#13;
&#13;
management and the board.   And there were a lot of these people.    The&#13;
&#13;
Bank was an engine of bad propaganda for itself.   All over the world&#13;
&#13;
the directors were sending out things saying how unpleasant it was.&#13;
&#13;
            So this was a leftover inherited by Black of that old&#13;
&#13;
atmosphere.   The Australians of course had far better credit than&#13;
&#13;
almost all the other countries who were members of the Bank.     They&#13;
&#13;
had carried their full debt through the '30s when I think the foreign&#13;
&#13;
debt burden was something like 40 percent of its export revenues at&#13;
&#13;
one point, and in Bank's rule of thumb, 10 percent debt service in&#13;
&#13;
relation to exports is pretty high.&#13;
&#13;
            It had bonds outstanding in the market, and it had to have&#13;
&#13;
a big refunding progress in the market, and needed to borrow&#13;
&#13;
something besides, because it was a developing economy.   And this&#13;
&#13;
director had told the Australians to stay away from the Bank.    But in&#13;
&#13;
the early days, the Bank had, as part of the rivalry with the Export-&#13;
&#13;
Import Bank, persuaded the US government that countries should be&#13;
&#13;
sent to the Bank first, unless there were special American interests&#13;
&#13;
involved.   There were a whole lot of exceptions, but that the Bank&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                 - 29 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                         Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
was the lender of first resort for development purposes.      I think&#13;
&#13;
this was even before George Humphrey.&#13;
&#13;
            In any event, the Australians went to the American&#13;
&#13;
government and said they'd like to borrow from the Export-Import&#13;
&#13;
Bank, and the Americans said, "Well, you have to go to the World Bank&#13;
&#13;
first."    So the Australians came to us, hoping and expecting to be&#13;
&#13;
turned down, and making some impossible conditions--no project loans,&#13;
&#13;
a balance of payments loan, you don't have time for any investigation&#13;
&#13;
of projects, as a matter of fact we've only got three weeks and then&#13;
&#13;
we're going home.&#13;
&#13;
            Black was going away.    He saw them, and he was going away.&#13;
&#13;
We didn't have a well-organized loan department or areas in those&#13;
&#13;
days.   Anyway, I know I was called into Black's office and he said,&#13;
&#13;
"Now, the Australians are coming in and they're trying to get us to&#13;
&#13;
turn them down.   And I want you to go in and chair this meeting with&#13;
&#13;
them at which you hear their demands, and you do what you want but I&#13;
&#13;
would like to make this loan, I don't want them to go back to the&#13;
&#13;
Export-Import Bank."&#13;
&#13;
            So we came in, and they had in charge a very unpleasant&#13;
&#13;
fellow--actually, he's a nice man, but he was acting unpleasant under&#13;
&#13;
orders.    I can't remember his name but he later became a good friend&#13;
&#13;
of mine.    And an Australian acting unpleasant can be pretty&#13;
&#13;
unpleasant.    They sat down at the table, and they just made all these&#13;
&#13;
demands on us, and we said at the end, "Well, we don't see anything&#13;
&#13;
impossible in all these things.      Of course, it's not up to us, it's&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                    - 30 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                         Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
primarily up to you.    If you can supply us with reliable information&#13;
&#13;
in time to meet your schedule, we don't see why we can't get the loan&#13;
&#13;
through."&#13;
&#13;
             They were really shocked.   I can't remember all the&#13;
&#13;
details, but the loan went through in something like three weeks.        I&#13;
&#13;
think actually they finally delayed it, because after they decided&#13;
&#13;
that they'd been misled by their director, they changed completely,&#13;
&#13;
and we made them a loan, and from that time on the Australians were&#13;
&#13;
staunch supporters of the Bank, although they used this precedent to&#13;
&#13;
make us continue to make loans to them for a long time that we&#13;
&#13;
wouldn't make to anybody else.&#13;
&#13;
             But this also made sense.   There were reasons for it.   But&#13;
&#13;
the whole attitude, I think, of Europe towards the Bank changed,&#13;
&#13;
because this was the first time somebody was borrowing from the Bank&#13;
&#13;
who wasn't a pauper.    You see, Australia was borrowing in the&#13;
&#13;
markets, in London and the United States.     Up to this time the&#13;
&#13;
attitude was, "well, you go to the Bank when you're either a banana&#13;
&#13;
republic or else you're just so desperate you have to do anything,&#13;
&#13;
but it's not a place where countries with respectable credit standing&#13;
&#13;
go for their normal financing requirements."&#13;
&#13;
             Well, this changed this attitude.   This also changed the&#13;
&#13;
whole attitude about "you take so long and you make so many&#13;
&#13;
requests."    I think it was a very important move on Black's part.&#13;
&#13;
These two things together, in my opinion, much more so than what is&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  - 31 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                        Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
generally attributed to him, the ability to handle the market and&#13;
&#13;
borrow money, set him off with flying colors.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Was there any concern in the staff of the Bank that the&#13;
&#13;
Australian loan was not a project loan?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sommers:   Well, sure.   The point is, in an organization like the Bank&#13;
&#13;
you have to have much more inflexibility of policy than anybody would&#13;
&#13;
like, because the first thing--governments, or government officials,&#13;
&#13;
worry about is being criticized by their bosses for getting a worse&#13;
&#13;
deal than somebody else got, particularly when they're all&#13;
&#13;
sovereigns.     We never had this difficulty with private borrowers.&#13;
&#13;
They would say "Well, if we get what we want, we don't care whether&#13;
&#13;
you ask us for more security or more restrictive covenants than&#13;
&#13;
you're getting from so and so."     But governments compare these things&#13;
&#13;
with a fine-tooth comb, and if you're from Pakistan the first thing&#13;
&#13;
you look at is whether the Indians got something better than you did.&#13;
&#13;
And for that reason, making loans of the Australian type was&#13;
&#13;
embarrassing, when you came to countries like Guatemala.    The&#13;
&#13;
Australians have a sensible management of their economy.    There are&#13;
&#13;
two things put together which cause trouble in this respect, three&#13;
&#13;
things.    First, the project versus the general purpose loan.    All&#13;
&#13;
these terms are highly ambiguous.    We never made a general purpose&#13;
&#13;
loan in the sense that this phrase is used in the UN, which means&#13;
&#13;
that you don't know what it's for and what the economic justification&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  - 32 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                        Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
of it is.    But there are cases, as in Australia, where the foreign&#13;
&#13;
exchange component of any one project might be so small that you&#13;
&#13;
don't really meet the country's lending needs by the specific project&#13;
&#13;
method, if you combine with that the requirement that you only lend&#13;
&#13;
to meet the foreign exchange component.&#13;
&#13;
             So there was always the question as to whether we should&#13;
&#13;
divert from our standard lending attitude, in the direction of&#13;
&#13;
departing from the specific project approach, or in the direction of&#13;
&#13;
financing local expenditures.    Either one of these would probably do&#13;
&#13;
the trick.    Black and Garner originally were very, very rigid on both&#13;
&#13;
of these, particularly Garner.    Garner felt that, as a result of his&#13;
&#13;
experience I think in the '20s, that there was something almost&#13;
&#13;
immoral about borrowing foreign exchange for a domestic purpose.     I&#13;
&#13;
think the general view in the staff was that we were too rigid on&#13;
&#13;
both these points, and there was a difference of opinion as to&#13;
&#13;
whether you should sway in one direction or the other.&#13;
&#13;
             Black finally came down pretty strongly in the direction of&#13;
&#13;
financing local expenditures rather than in getting away from the&#13;
&#13;
specific project approach.    On the other hand, if he'd had no&#13;
&#13;
customers except India, Belgium, Australia, and countries which&#13;
&#13;
really managed their finances fairly intelligently, I think we all&#13;
&#13;
would have felt there was much more latitude for going in the other&#13;
&#13;
direction.&#13;
&#13;
             You had to find a line which you could be reasonably&#13;
&#13;
flexible with, without making too much trouble for yourself.      And in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  - 33 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                      Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
the case of the Indians, for example, we solved this--I remember&#13;
&#13;
saying to P.K. Nehru, "Why do you fight these theological battles&#13;
&#13;
with us?   We have now found you a project which satisfies our concept&#13;
&#13;
of a project, namely the development of the Indian railways, which&#13;
&#13;
can absorb twice as much as the entire Bank lending program for a&#13;
&#13;
definite period of time, and it performs all the purposes of a&#13;
&#13;
specific project loan and a foreign exchange loan, and yet from your&#13;
&#13;
purposes is just as flexible as a balance of payments loan."&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   What did he reply?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sommers:   Well, he said, "This is all right for the Bank, but then&#13;
&#13;
we've got the Development Loan Fund and the Export-Import Bank and&#13;
&#13;
they're also following these same lines, and unless we can get either&#13;
&#13;
a general purpose loan," which he wanted, "or at least local&#13;
&#13;
expenditure financing, we're going to have to pick so many projects,&#13;
&#13;
and the financing institutions are going to want to scrutinize each&#13;
&#13;
one of those many projects, and it will just take too damn long to&#13;
&#13;
get the total that we need."&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   I wonder if you'd say a bit about the Bank's attitude toward&#13;
&#13;
relaxing the credit worthiness approach to lending and particularly&#13;
&#13;
the development of IDA as a new organization?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                - 34 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                         Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sommers:   Well, there are three kinds of credit worthiness that the&#13;
&#13;
Bank has been urged--I mean, three kinds of relaxation that the Bank&#13;
&#13;
has been urged to undertake.   The first two have nothing to do with&#13;
&#13;
IDA, as it finally turned out.   One is the general purpose loan&#13;
&#13;
versus the specific project.   The underdeveloped countries are always&#13;
&#13;
saying, "There should be loans for general development purposes."&#13;
&#13;
This really doesn't mean anything except that there should be no&#13;
&#13;
control, no mutual understanding over the purposes of the loans.       All&#13;
&#13;
these terms are used as camouflage.&#13;
&#13;
           Second is the local expenditure issue.     There's a good&#13;
&#13;
argument for it, but the real reason for so much agitation is that if&#13;
&#13;
you advance money against local expenditures, this becomes free&#13;
&#13;
foreign exchange in the hands of the government, so it's not subject&#13;
&#13;
to control.&#13;
&#13;
           There was nothing in the Bank restrictions that made it&#13;
&#13;
necessary to create another institution to get around those two&#13;
&#13;
issues.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Just a question about the local currency--&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sommers:   --not local currency, local expenditure.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Would you feel that--&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                 - 35 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                        Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sommers:   --providing foreign exchange to finance local expenditures.&#13;
&#13;
That meant that the borrower takes the dollars to the central bank&#13;
&#13;
and gets pesos and the central bank has free dollars.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   As in the case of the loan to south Italy?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sommers:   As in the case of the loan to south Italy.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Would the Bank feel that this sort of loan is more sensible â&#128;&#147; the&#13;
&#13;
Bank at least has some control over some project, rather than a&#13;
&#13;
general purpose loan?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sommers:   I would say, that if we were only dealing with Italy or&#13;
&#13;
Australia or Belgium, the only purpose of that technique is really&#13;
&#13;
public relations, to associate yourself with some big venture, --they&#13;
&#13;
have something to take a picture of.     Probably that's a little too&#13;
&#13;
cynical.   The pressure from the Bank might, in the case of Italy,&#13;
&#13;
mean (and did) that they would devote more of their resources to this&#13;
&#13;
program than they would if the Bank loan were a general purpose loan.&#13;
&#13;
You may have more control over it, but what you're controlling there&#13;
&#13;
is the allocation of domestic resources, not the allocation of&#13;
&#13;
imports.   It is a question of whether you want to be in the position&#13;
&#13;
of taking that responsibility or not.&#13;
&#13;
           Now, in Australia, there wasn't any single big thing that&#13;
&#13;
the Australians had to do.   In Italy there was something very big&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                - 36 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                        Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
that they had to do, and I think the Bank was right in doing it this&#13;
&#13;
way.   In Western Germany, for example, if we'd made a loan to them,&#13;
&#13;
there isn't any outstanding thing that we'd want to concentrate their&#13;
&#13;
resources on.     I frankly can't see anything but a public relations&#13;
&#13;
difference between a Monetary Fund type of operation, and the kind of&#13;
&#13;
thing we did in Italy--except that when you come to the next country,&#13;
&#13;
that you want to make a project loan to, it's much easier to make a&#13;
&#13;
project loan to them if you've made Italian-type loan to Italy.     So&#13;
&#13;
public relations and this appearance of uniformity of policy are the&#13;
&#13;
two reasons.&#13;
&#13;
           Now I'm way off my track.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   In any event, whether the loan is really going to result in&#13;
&#13;
productive development of the country receiving the loan, I take it&#13;
&#13;
you feel is a function more of the maturity of the borrowing&#13;
&#13;
government than it is of whether or not it's a local expenditure loan&#13;
&#13;
or a general balance of payments loan?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sommers:   Yes.   I don't think that you can determine the value of a&#13;
&#13;
project in any case in isolation.    The Bank has been accused of&#13;
&#13;
meaning, by the specific project approach, that we judge it by&#13;
&#13;
commercial standards, which is a lot of hooey--the Bank's loans have&#13;
&#13;
not been judged by commercial lending standards at all.    It has made&#13;
&#13;
use of techniques that are common in the financial market, but in&#13;
&#13;
credit and in terms it's a very different kind of process, and in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  - 37 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                        Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
motivation it's an entirely different process.     The accusation has&#13;
&#13;
been made that the specific project approach means that you look for&#13;
&#13;
the safest project in the whole country and you don't care what&#13;
&#13;
happens anywhere else.    This has never been the Bank's attitude&#13;
&#13;
towards the lending process.   We've never felt that a project could&#13;
&#13;
be viewed in isolation.   It has to be viewed as part of the whole&#13;
&#13;
plan of the country, --if it's got any plans.     Some countries don't&#13;
&#13;
have any plans, and then you have the question, are you going to&#13;
&#13;
refuse to lend to them until they've got a five-year program?    Or are&#13;
&#13;
you going to try to help things along that look as though they're&#13;
&#13;
worth doing in the meantime?    The Bank has taken the second attitude.&#13;
&#13;
But they've always tried to see this in the general context, and if&#13;
&#13;
you see it in the general context, then the particular format of the&#13;
&#13;
loan does not have complete importance, at least from an economic&#13;
&#13;
standpoint.   It's not all logic and economics.    There is a lot of&#13;
&#13;
public relations and a lot of other tactical considerations involved&#13;
&#13;
in it.   But I would say that if you're regarding the development&#13;
&#13;
effects of this loan, the general purpose loan in Germany or Belgium&#13;
&#13;
is practically as good as the project loan, unless there's something&#13;
&#13;
like the Italian case which is of predominant importance.     But when&#13;
&#13;
you come even to such a well-managed country relatively as India,&#13;
&#13;
then I think there's an entirely different element that enters into&#13;
&#13;
it, and there the project method gives you an opportunity to set a&#13;
&#13;
standard of project evaluation and analysis.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                 - 38 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                          Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
             I do think that, even though from an overall economic&#13;
&#13;
standpoint, the specific project approach isn't too vital, it has a&#13;
&#13;
tremendous demonstrative effect particularly in the more backward&#13;
&#13;
countries, of introducing standards of appraisal, evaluation, and&#13;
&#13;
performance that are not known there.      And that's even been true in&#13;
&#13;
countries which know or claim to know a good deal more, like India.&#13;
&#13;
I think the Bank has had quite an effect in that respect. I'd like to&#13;
&#13;
make a digression here, to go back to something that you asked me&#13;
&#13;
about before, which is the difference between the McCloy and the&#13;
&#13;
Black era.&#13;
&#13;
             I think a very important difference, which really wasn't&#13;
&#13;
the result of Black being different from McCloy, but was just an&#13;
&#13;
evolution, was the shift in emphasis in project evaluation from the&#13;
&#13;
pure economic and pure engineering point of view to more of a&#13;
&#13;
business or financial point of view.       Originally we put more&#13;
&#13;
resources into the economics and the engineering aspects, the&#13;
&#13;
physical engineering aspects, and much less to studies of market&#13;
&#13;
potentialities, of rates of return, rates to be charged to the&#13;
&#13;
customer, of cash flow, of sensible balance sheet, capital structure.&#13;
&#13;
This developed later on.    These also contribute to the demonstrative&#13;
&#13;
effect, because in many of these countries it is this essential&#13;
&#13;
element that is lacking rather than the physical engineering design&#13;
&#13;
and the broader assessment of economic priorities.      Those skills are&#13;
&#13;
available to them, but this financial analysis--which really began in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  - 39 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                        Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
a major way when Aldewereld took charge of project evaluation is very&#13;
&#13;
important.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   You put emphasis upon management techniques?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sommers:   Financial techniques, I would say.   These are the points of&#13;
&#13;
views and techniques which are very familiar in all private lending&#13;
&#13;
operations, and this is what I meant earlier when I said the Bank&#13;
&#13;
makes use of techniques of private lending, although they might not&#13;
&#13;
necessarily require the same relationship between earnings and&#13;
&#13;
coverage of service requirement on the loan that would be required on&#13;
&#13;
a utility loan in this country.    They might or might not, depending&#13;
&#13;
on other features.&#13;
&#13;
             Now, these things, in addition to a demonstrative effect,&#13;
&#13;
probably have some relationship to credit worthiness, in the sense&#13;
&#13;
that when you're dealing not with the government itself but with some&#13;
&#13;
autonomous body, whether public or private, this gets over the first&#13;
&#13;
obstacle to getting repaid--that is, having the local currency left.&#13;
&#13;
You still of course are faced with the transfer problem, which in 95&#13;
&#13;
percent of the Bank's cases has no relationship to the particular&#13;
&#13;
enterprise being financed, but depends on the whole balance of&#13;
&#13;
payments situation of the country.    Nevertheless there have been&#13;
&#13;
cases in the past, (probably they are less likely to arise in the&#13;
&#13;
future) in which private debts have been honored from good companies&#13;
&#13;
even though the government itself has defaulted on its obligations.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  - 40 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                        Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
For example, the Brazilian Traction Co, I believe, honored its&#13;
&#13;
foreign creditors, paid its foreign debts, even though it had to go&#13;
&#13;
to the government and get foreign exchange to do so at a time when&#13;
&#13;
Brazilian governmental debts were in default.&#13;
&#13;
          So financial evaluation has some relationship to credit&#13;
&#13;
worthiness.&#13;
&#13;
          Now, coming back to the various points to which criticism&#13;
&#13;
and relaxation have been directed--the first point was, general&#13;
&#13;
purpose loans against specific projects.   I've covered that, and that&#13;
&#13;
is closely related to financing local expenditures.&#13;
&#13;
          The second one I think is in what the Bank called "lending&#13;
&#13;
standards"--the care by which these projects are gone into from a&#13;
&#13;
financial and economic and a technical point of view.    There has been&#13;
&#13;
some attack on that, but I don't think it really comes from&#13;
&#13;
responsible quarters.   Nobody claims that the Bank shouldn't make the&#13;
&#13;
studies and the evaluation.   What has been attacked is the conditions&#13;
&#13;
that the Bank interposes on some elements that are considered to be&#13;
&#13;
matters of local political concern.   In the field of utility&#13;
&#13;
financing, for example, the Bank has insisted on adequate rates being&#13;
&#13;
charged, to provide coverage of the cost of service.    It has not&#13;
&#13;
followed a black and white line but has pushed in the direction of&#13;
&#13;
discouraging governments from subsidizing railroads, power and things&#13;
&#13;
of that kind.   The Bank has been more successful in the area of power&#13;
&#13;
than in the area of railroads because obviously power is something&#13;
&#13;
that is in much greater demand, and there's more elasticity in what&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                - 41 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                      Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
the traffic will bear.   The Bank's position essentially has been that&#13;
&#13;
since, except maybe in the one bulb user category, the cost of&#13;
&#13;
electricity is a very minor part of the cost of producing in general&#13;
&#13;
(with the exception also of chemical industries and a few others&#13;
&#13;
which are not very frequent in the underdeveloped countries).&#13;
&#13;
Therefore the customer can well afford to pay the cost of providing&#13;
&#13;
electricity, and in a capital-short country it's silly to subsidize&#13;
&#13;
industries which can be self-supporting when there are such colossal&#13;
&#13;
demands for government assistance in the area of hospitals,&#13;
&#13;
education, transportation and so forth, where the government's going&#13;
&#13;
to have to put in resources anyway.&#13;
&#13;
          A good deal of this philosophy has penetrated around the&#13;
&#13;
world, not only in the underdeveloped countries.   I think it's had&#13;
&#13;
its impact in England.   I know it had a tremendous impact in India,&#13;
&#13;
in Austria, and in places of that kind.   I think this makes pretty&#13;
&#13;
good sense.   Nevertheless, it's unpopular, particularly in Latin&#13;
&#13;
America, because the lesson of the New Deal was mis-imported,&#13;
&#13;
imported in a distorted fashion.   The New Deal emphasis on low rates,&#13;
&#13;
promotional rates, was at a time of overcapacity, at a time of large&#13;
&#13;
amounts of available resources in the bond market, and at a time of&#13;
&#13;
very little demand, and in a mature economy which already had a&#13;
&#13;
system built up.   To import that concept into an economy where there&#13;
&#13;
is no capital available for low return investment, where there's no&#13;
&#13;
bond market available, where the demands for capital on all hands are&#13;
&#13;
colossal, and where there are endless unfilled demands for&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                - 42 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                       Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
electricity, has been a great distortion and has cost those countries&#13;
&#13;
a lot of misdirection of public money.&#13;
&#13;
           That's the second field.   Related to that is the Bank's&#13;
&#13;
emphasis on not financing industrial, as distinct from public works&#13;
&#13;
or public utilities, ventures, for which private management and&#13;
&#13;
capital is available.   This derives from a provision of the charter&#13;
&#13;
which says the Bank can't make a loan if private capital is ready to&#13;
&#13;
undertake it.   The Bank has extended the application of that&#13;
&#13;
provision so as to say to Pakistan, "We're not going to finance a&#13;
&#13;
pulp mill project on a government-owned basis if you can attract&#13;
&#13;
private investors to go into it."&#13;
&#13;
           There's a great deal of argument, both within and without&#13;
&#13;
the Bank, as to whether the Bank hasn't pushed this far too far.      My&#13;
&#13;
own view is that there's something to the Bank's position, but it was&#13;
&#13;
pushed too rigidly and too far.&#13;
&#13;
           Now, I wouldn't say there was any necessary reason to&#13;
&#13;
create an IDA in order to cope with these problems and get more&#13;
&#13;
flexibility.    All you needed to do is to decide on a different&#13;
&#13;
policy.   And in general, I don't think that there will be any&#13;
&#13;
difference in policy, as between IDA and the Bank.    In other words,&#13;
&#13;
IDA is not supposed to be a lending agency for lower priority&#13;
&#13;
projects, for less carefully planned or executed projects, or&#13;
&#13;
generally for sloppier lending techniques.   It's designed to meet one&#13;
&#13;
particular problem, which is credit worthiness, and not in the&#13;
&#13;
project sense but in the balance of payments sense.   This has been a&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  - 43 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                      Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
longstanding position of the Bank, that there is a limit to the&#13;
&#13;
amount of high-quality external debt repayable in foreign exchange at&#13;
&#13;
levels of interest comparable to what prevails in the outside world&#13;
&#13;
and at fixed maturities, that the very backward countries can absorb,&#13;
&#13;
and that reasonable development in those countries (of which India&#13;
&#13;
and Pakistan of course are the outstanding examples) will need more&#13;
&#13;
external capital than can be supplied on that hard loan basis.&#13;
&#13;
          For a long time, the Bank and everybody else flirted with&#13;
&#13;
various alternatives to IDA.   Black's view was grants.   Then people&#13;
&#13;
played with loans repayable in local currency, up until the time that&#13;
&#13;
Public Law 480 came into effect, when excess or large amounts of&#13;
&#13;
local currency counterparts got to such magnitudes that it made the&#13;
&#13;
whole thing rather meaningless.&#13;
&#13;
          But, in any event, the feeling that there was a need for an&#13;
&#13;
institution which could provide loans that had a less severe and a&#13;
&#13;
more flexible impact on the balance of payments, long term, was the&#13;
&#13;
origin of IDA.   In the minds of some of our governments, including&#13;
&#13;
the United States, it was also colored by a desire to beat the SUNFED&#13;
&#13;
advocates to the gun, and to get this kind of an agency out of the&#13;
&#13;
United Nations' auspices and into an organization which had a&#13;
&#13;
tradition of perhaps less political logrolling and a more&#13;
&#13;
businesslike approach.&#13;
&#13;
          The actual way in which IDA received its initial impetus&#13;
&#13;
was as usual in these political things, pretty haphazard.   Senator&#13;
&#13;
Monroney, who had a mixture of motives, was promoting something--he&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  - 44 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                        Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
didn't know what it was, except that it had a title, the&#13;
&#13;
International Development Association.    I should say that the idea&#13;
&#13;
for some kind of a grant or soft loan agency under international&#13;
&#13;
auspices went way back to the Rockefeller--Nelson Rockefeller&#13;
&#13;
Advisory Committee Report.   I think Rockefeller originally got the&#13;
&#13;
idea from McCloy, who got it from Dick Demuth, who had been thinking&#13;
&#13;
along these lines.   In those days it was thought of more along the&#13;
&#13;
lines of a Ford or a Rockefeller Foundation approach, a grant agency.&#13;
&#13;
Anyway, Monroney had three motivations.   In the first place, he was&#13;
&#13;
terribly worried about these vast quantities of local currency piling&#13;
&#13;
up.   He couldn't see why they weren't useful.    The distinction&#13;
&#13;
between foreign exchange and local currency as being one in which, on&#13;
&#13;
the one hand, you actually brought resources into the country, on the&#13;
&#13;
other you just decided how local resources were going to be&#13;
&#13;
allocated, never really penetrated his    mind.   He just thought it was&#13;
&#13;
terrible that the funds were piling up and couldn't be used.    In the&#13;
&#13;
second place, he had visited Southeast Asia and was very discouraged&#13;
&#13;
about some of the US aid programs, I think in Thailand, and liked&#13;
&#13;
what the Bank was doing.   And in the third place, all of Congress was&#13;
&#13;
then and continues to be awfully tired of voting on foreign aid every&#13;
&#13;
year.   Monroney had the idea that maybe we could take one big swallow&#13;
&#13;
and do something like allocating all Marshall Plan repayments to an&#13;
&#13;
international agency and get foreign aid out of the way so we&#13;
&#13;
wouldn't have to vote appropriations year after year.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                - 45 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                        Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
           Anyway, he was vehement in urging this viewpoint on&#13;
&#13;
Anderson and the Treasury.   On the other hand, the Treasury was being&#13;
&#13;
pushed by some people in the US government to look more kindly on&#13;
&#13;
SUNFED which had a great deal of support in the United Nations.    I&#13;
&#13;
remember that Anderson finally called up Black and said, "Monroney&#13;
&#13;
says he's going to spring this idea publicly unless I can come up&#13;
&#13;
with something that I can suggest to him."&#13;
&#13;
           I went over to Anderson's office in the Treasury with Black&#13;
&#13;
and Demuth.   We said, "Well, we'll get up an outline of something,"&#13;
&#13;
and I think in about 24 hours we produced the first draft outline of&#13;
&#13;
a proposal for IDA, which didn't differ essentially from what finally&#13;
&#13;
came out, except that there was more emphasis on loans repayable in&#13;
&#13;
local currency.   (This was what Anderson thought Monroney was&#13;
&#13;
interested in.    But Monroney really was interested only in using the&#13;
&#13;
frozen local currency resources and having them paid back in local&#13;
&#13;
currency, while Anderson was talking about foreign exchange loans&#13;
&#13;
repayable in local currency.)&#13;
&#13;
           There was a great deal of skepticism on the part of the&#13;
&#13;
United States administration that the European countries could really&#13;
&#13;
match the American contribution, in meaningful money, in money which&#13;
&#13;
wasn't frozen in some way.   Black insisted that he could get at least&#13;
&#13;
one good dollar from Europe and Japan for every dollar the Americans&#13;
&#13;
put up.   Actually it came out much better than that.   This was an&#13;
&#13;
early example of what continued for several years to be the fact,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                 - 46 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                         Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
that the US government never believed that the Europeans really could&#13;
&#13;
be pushed up into putting more money into foreign aid.&#13;
&#13;
             Well, Anderson took this outline and gave it to Monroney,&#13;
&#13;
and Monroney brought it out as his idea.     At the next annual meeting&#13;
&#13;
of the Bank, Anderson sprung it as a US proposal, and it was voted&#13;
&#13;
that it should be studied, not by an international conference but by&#13;
&#13;
the executive directors of the Bank acting as an international&#13;
&#13;
conference.    We carried on negotiations for several months and drew&#13;
&#13;
up a charter.&#13;
&#13;
             The main battles in developing the IDA charter were along&#13;
&#13;
two lines.    First, between the underdeveloped countries and the&#13;
&#13;
developed countries--the underdeveloped countries wanted it much&#13;
&#13;
larger and looser.    They didn't ever use the word "looser," but they&#13;
&#13;
kept talking about "social projects."      The Latin Americans wanted IDA&#13;
&#13;
to do health and education, housing, things of this kind.     There was&#13;
&#13;
a more general feeling that IDA should continue to put emphasis on&#13;
&#13;
the kinds of projects financed by the Bank, but perhaps be a little&#13;
&#13;
bit less rigid than the Bank is, in terms of productivity, concepts&#13;
&#13;
of what kind of a project is productive and what is not.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Doesn't the question of credit worthiness arise here?    A country&#13;
&#13;
might be at the limit of its foreign borrowing, foreign exchange, but&#13;
&#13;
still be within limits of usefully using additional domestic&#13;
&#13;
resources.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  - 47 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                          Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sommers:   Well, that was not an area of dispute.   That was generally&#13;
&#13;
agreed, that IDA should be a complementary agency.   I might say that&#13;
&#13;
the reason it was set up as a separate entity was merely so as not to&#13;
&#13;
get IDA operations entangled in the Bank's credit, as far as&#13;
&#13;
marketability goes.   It was agreed that for all practical purposes it&#13;
&#13;
should not be a separate institution, but just a different kind of&#13;
&#13;
money.&#13;
&#13;
            Everybody agreed that IDA was to be used for countries&#13;
&#13;
whose credit was limited, and there was discussion of possible&#13;
&#13;
questions about applying the principle.    It doesn't mean that you&#13;
&#13;
have to fill a country up to the full with hard loans before you can&#13;
&#13;
do any soft loans.    Credit worthiness is not such a clear concept as&#13;
&#13;
that.    It was agreed that in a country like India you would continue&#13;
&#13;
to make hard and soft loans in combination.   In some countries--&#13;
&#13;
Jordan, let's say--you might not want to make any hard loans, you&#13;
&#13;
might make all loans from IDA.   Mexico, I think Mexico itself agreed&#13;
&#13;
that it was not an IDA candidate.    But then you get into borderline&#13;
&#13;
cases like Argentina, which ought to be able to finance itself&#13;
&#13;
entirely on good loans, hard loans, but what do you do when it's just&#13;
&#13;
recovering from the Peron period?    Might not IDA be the first venture&#13;
&#13;
on the part of the Bank into the Argentine situation, before the Bank&#13;
&#13;
might be ready to hazard its own credit?&#13;
&#13;
            That's the kind of discussion that went on.    I don't think&#13;
&#13;
there was any major difference on that.    The difference came in the&#13;
&#13;
softness of the project standards.   By and large the American,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                 - 48 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                      Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
European and Bank staff approach was adhered to.   A second difference&#13;
&#13;
concerned the technique of lending, whether IDA should do grants,&#13;
&#13;
loans repayable in foreign exchange, or loans repayable in local&#13;
&#13;
currency.   The United States wouldn't go along with grants, although&#13;
&#13;
there was a great deal of sympathy for them, and the question of the&#13;
&#13;
character and terms of a loan was left open in the charter, so as to&#13;
&#13;
postpone the decision.   But the Bank staff had pretty much a definite&#13;
&#13;
idea as to what it was going to ask for, and what it was going to ask&#13;
&#13;
for turned out to be the kind of lending format that has been&#13;
&#13;
announced--very long-term loans, no interest at all except a half a&#13;
&#13;
percent which is designed as a sort of service charge, no repayments&#13;
&#13;
during the first ten years, but all payments to be in the currency&#13;
&#13;
lent in foreign exchange.   The theory was that even in the case of a&#13;
&#13;
country whose credit worthiness is very hazardous, it's one thing to&#13;
&#13;
bear a debt burden of 12 percent per year in terms of amortization&#13;
&#13;
and interest, and another to have a free period of ten years and then&#13;
&#13;
to pay off at the rate of 2 percent a year, taking into account the&#13;
&#13;
fact that all currencies decline in value and that all economies&#13;
&#13;
grow.   This was thought to be the best possible middle line between&#13;
&#13;
the grant, which is rather invidious, and the loan repayable in local&#13;
&#13;
currency which is just kidding yourself.   There was thought to be no&#13;
&#13;
reason at all why countries couldn't repay on this kind of a&#13;
&#13;
schedule, particularly with the understanding that since the money&#13;
&#13;
wasn't borrowed and there was no rigid requirement for repayment to&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                - 49 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                        Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
private creditors, in case of need, even these payments could be&#13;
&#13;
postponed and made flexible.&#13;
&#13;
           I think IDA really made a great contribution in bringing&#13;
&#13;
out this formula.   The United States government was converted to this&#13;
&#13;
from its own lending formulas.   Unfortunately, IDA delayed so long in&#13;
&#13;
announcing it, that it lost some of the credit for it.    It leaked out&#13;
&#13;
first.   But all of the countries that had been in favor of loans&#13;
&#13;
repayable in local currencies, the underdeveloped countries, I think&#13;
&#13;
liked this formula much better, and I find it very sensible.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Yes, I can't imagine myself what the United States government is&#13;
&#13;
going to do with all of its local currency.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sommers:   Well, they appointed three â&#128;&#156;wise menâ&#128;? to look for&#13;
&#13;
suggestions for using it, and then interviewed me.    I suggested that&#13;
&#13;
instead of getting this currency deposited in bank accounts, they&#13;
&#13;
should ask for payment in bank notes, which they could then burn,&#13;
&#13;
thereby creating energy without inflation.    They said they weren't&#13;
&#13;
prepared to adopt this plan but that it was the most constructive&#13;
&#13;
suggestion they'd received so far.&#13;
&#13;
           You said you wanted anecdotes.    I've got one anecdote about&#13;
&#13;
the IDA negotiations.   I can't remember the people involved, but the&#13;
&#13;
Malayan director in the course of the debate as to the size of IDA--&#13;
&#13;
he was plumping for a much bigger IDA--referred to a remark made by&#13;
&#13;
the governor for Vietnam to the effect that the IDA should be three&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                 - 50 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                        Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
times as big as proposed, or something like that, and he asked his&#13;
&#13;
colleagues at the table whether they remembered the remark.    One of&#13;
&#13;
the other directors said, "I remember it very well, and my sentiment&#13;
&#13;
about it is one of regret that the remark wasn't made by the governor&#13;
&#13;
for the United States instead of the governor for Vietnam."&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Well, it is a very small capitalization.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sommers:   It's not so terribly small.   It's only small if you regard&#13;
&#13;
it as something finished, but everybody went into IDA on the idea&#13;
&#13;
that this should be replenished.   There was a good deal of debate as&#13;
&#13;
to what the replenishment period should be.     I and my colleagues in&#13;
&#13;
the Bank staff said we would much rather have a low lending rate for&#13;
&#13;
a few years, namely 200 million dollars a year, which is about what&#13;
&#13;
this will furnish, with a five-year replenishment period, than be in&#13;
&#13;
the position of going back every two years or one year for more&#13;
&#13;
appropriations, because we would gradually become more and more under&#13;
&#13;
the thumb of parliaments and the US Congress if we did that.    Now,&#13;
&#13;
after all, they've only done 100 million dollars the first year, so&#13;
&#13;
that they'll have a little leeway to build up.    This capitalization&#13;
&#13;
isn't very big, but I think it is not so far out of line with what&#13;
&#13;
IDA is going to be able to use in the first three years.    At the end&#13;
&#13;
of three years they'll have to start their replenishment process&#13;
&#13;
anyway, and if they've done a good job presumably they'll get more&#13;
&#13;
money.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                - 51 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                       Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   I wonder if you could say a few things about the concept of&#13;
&#13;
absorptive capacity and credit worthiness?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sommers:    Well, I think absorptive capacity is a highly debatable&#13;
&#13;
subject on which I don't know very much and I don't know whether&#13;
&#13;
anybody else does.   Certainly absorptive capacity is greater than&#13;
&#13;
credit worthiness, and it certainly is far less than need.   Now, in&#13;
&#13;
between the two, I don't know.   The absorptive capacity in India,&#13;
&#13;
which has already reached a fairly high level of economic activity&#13;
&#13;
and particularly a high level of sophistication of institutions, is,&#13;
&#13;
I would say, pretty great.   The absorptive capacity of Panama is very&#13;
&#13;
low, if you're talking about absorptive capacity for high-priority&#13;
&#13;
projects.   Brazil, Argentina, there it really isn't a question of&#13;
&#13;
absorptive capacity, it's a question of whether other governmental&#13;
&#13;
policies aren't so bad that no matter how much you absorb, all the&#13;
&#13;
economic benefit is being drained off in other directions.   I don't&#13;
&#13;
know whether absorptive capacity with ruinous inflation that distorts&#13;
&#13;
the whole economy is absorptive capacity, or whether both these are&#13;
&#13;
part of the same equation.   I think absorptive capacity for the&#13;
&#13;
underdeveloped countries as a whole is probably almost meaningless.&#13;
&#13;
In fact, I think the term "underdeveloped countries" is almost&#13;
&#13;
meaningless.   I think all the economists and the underdeveloped&#13;
&#13;
countries and the Bank and everybody else is falling into, or pushing&#13;
&#13;
themselves into, an intellectual trap by creating this&#13;
&#13;
classification, which seems to put Argentina and Jordan in the same&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                 - 52 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                       Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
class.    Actually, Argentina is much nearer to Italy than it is to&#13;
&#13;
Jordan.    Leonard Rist made a good comment when he visited Argentina&#13;
&#13;
for the first time after Peron.    He said, "I was very much surprised.&#13;
&#13;
I thought I was going to an underdeveloped country and I found&#13;
&#13;
instead something very familiar to me, a bankrupt European country."&#13;
&#13;
            So I think you can only estimate absorptive capacity on a&#13;
&#13;
country-by-country basis, and then add them up.   My guess is that the&#13;
&#13;
studies of absorptive capacity have been done on all kinds of&#13;
&#13;
macroeconomic calculations which are valuable but highly imprecise.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   In other words, if you ask people talking about the absorptive&#13;
&#13;
capacity of a country, if you ask for what specific projects it might&#13;
&#13;
be used, they'd have a terrible time?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sommers:   Yes, they start with what is the desirable rate of economic&#13;
&#13;
growth?    Well, you can put so much error into that value judgment to&#13;
&#13;
begin with that the error may be greater than all the precision of&#13;
&#13;
all the other calculations that follow.    But even if the growth rate&#13;
&#13;
is right, it is right on a planning basis, and I just don't believe&#13;
&#13;
they're able to assay the abilities in execution.   The Indians, I&#13;
&#13;
would say, were better in planning than in execution, but even in the&#13;
&#13;
planning area they made some colossal miscalculations.   They just&#13;
&#13;
didn't have the--well, for example, now the UN census is showing that&#13;
&#13;
their whole census figures are wrong by 12 to 15 million people.&#13;
&#13;
That just throws a gimmick into the whole planning mechanism which&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  - 53 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                        Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
makes it completely distorted.    They werenâ&#128;&#153;t able to get cost&#13;
&#13;
estimates the way you could do in the United States--from the&#13;
&#13;
executory agencies.    They weren't able to figure out how long it&#13;
&#13;
would take and which things had to be in which order or sequence.     It&#13;
&#13;
was too unreliable.    So there's a big lag which these calculators try&#13;
&#13;
to allow for, but I don't know how they do it, frankly.&#13;
&#13;
             I've heard it said, "I'm not sure it's true--that the&#13;
&#13;
planners in India calculated that with an increased standard of&#13;
&#13;
living, the masses would change their dietary habits, and there would&#13;
&#13;
be a great need for the next higher level of diet, more proteins and&#13;
&#13;
so forth; but in experience it turned out that the great impact was&#13;
&#13;
for more of the same kind, more rice and more grain, rather than a&#13;
&#13;
shift to higher levels of diet.    Such a complicated business.   I&#13;
&#13;
don't know how you can make it very precise.    Nevertheless, I don't&#13;
&#13;
know that it really makes an awful lot of difference, because I think&#13;
&#13;
every conceivable calculation of absorptive capacity on a global&#13;
&#13;
basis will show more absorptive capacity than there is capital&#13;
&#13;
available.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   That of course is the thing that puzzles me a little bit, these&#13;
&#13;
various computations of capacity are fairly high, and yet many people&#13;
&#13;
in the Bank say that there's never been a shortage of Bank funds to&#13;
&#13;
stop the Bank from making more loans, but lack of credit-worthy&#13;
&#13;
countries and leak of sound projects.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  - 54 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                       Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sommers:   Well, the Bank has never turned down a loan for lack of&#13;
&#13;
funds available to the Bank.   But 700 million dollars a year is not a&#13;
&#13;
whole lot.   I don't think this is a very meaningful statement.   It's&#13;
&#13;
a good statement to make and I think it's true, but there's an awful&#13;
&#13;
lot that goes on in the world that the Bank has nothing to do with.&#13;
&#13;
Take the whole area of education, for example.   I haven't any doubt&#13;
&#13;
that there is a colossal absorptive capacity, although there are&#13;
&#13;
limiting factors perhaps in the rate.    I don't think you can get into&#13;
&#13;
high gear in absorptive capacity the first year that capital is&#13;
&#13;
available, because teachers aren't available and people aren't&#13;
&#13;
available.   But I still think that if there were no limit on the&#13;
&#13;
amount of capital available, that absorptive capacity would be pretty&#13;
&#13;
large, because if you have enough money, people become available.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   You mean by absorptive capacity here now the ability of a country&#13;
&#13;
to use the funds for some productive purpose.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sommers:   For some sensible purpose, not necessarily productive in&#13;
&#13;
the narrow sense--education, health, all these things, social things&#13;
&#13;
as well as economically productive, directly economically productive.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Well, it's sometimes argued that you increase the productive&#13;
&#13;
ability of a country if you increase the education of its citizens.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                - 55 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                       Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sommers:   Oh, sure, there's no question about that, but very often in&#13;
&#13;
these circles "productive" means something that directly increases&#13;
&#13;
the production of goods-- the production of goods and services.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Tape #3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sommers:   In the early days of the Bank, I think the lawyers played&#13;
&#13;
an unusually predominant role.   This is partly because of the fact&#13;
&#13;
that the Bank's general counsel was a very strong figure who had the&#13;
&#13;
confidence of Meyer,   McCloy, Black and Garner, and was a very&#13;
&#13;
experienced financial figure; second, because the recruitment of&#13;
&#13;
lawyers went rather ahead of the recruitment in some of the other&#13;
&#13;
areas, and I think that the legal staff was stronger relatively than&#13;
&#13;
some of the other departments; next, because the early work of the&#13;
&#13;
Bank involved legal techniques, getting our framework of legislation,&#13;
&#13;
getting our basic loan contract forms, our basic bond issues format,&#13;
&#13;
and so forth.   But the lawyers certainly had a role extending way&#13;
&#13;
beyond that.    And I might give as an illustration of the position of&#13;
&#13;
the lawyers at that time the Brazilian Traction loan which was the&#13;
&#13;
first really complex development loan that the Bank negotiated,&#13;
&#13;
although it took a long time getting on the books.   This was in&#13;
&#13;
substance, though not in form, negotiated largely by the lawyers.&#13;
&#13;
And I think that illustrates the fact that American lawyers are&#13;
&#13;
rather used to being injected into formless, chaotic organizations,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                 - 56 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                       Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
and found it a little easier to make their way than some of the&#13;
&#13;
people who had been used to more regular kinds of procedure.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   I've heard that in the case of the French loan, the very first&#13;
&#13;
loan the Bank made, there was some concern, mainly on the part of the&#13;
&#13;
French, in the language used because it was drawn up by attorneys who&#13;
&#13;
were accustomed to draw up--&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sommers:   --yes, well, the Bank's original loan agreements were&#13;
&#13;
pretty formidable in language.   But, I think the French are&#13;
&#13;
intelligent enough to really have their eye on the substance and not&#13;
&#13;
on the form, and there were some substantive things that they didn't&#13;
&#13;
like.   The form was a little obnoxious to them.   After I became&#13;
&#13;
general counsel, we got rid of most of that heat by taking all of the&#13;
&#13;
mechanical and standard and boilerplate language, particularly the&#13;
&#13;
part of it that had caused most trouble, and adopting it as a loan&#13;
&#13;
regulation which could be incorporated by reference into loan&#13;
&#13;
documents, and although it was subject to change, in any negotiation,&#13;
&#13;
and wasn't binding or mandatory, we found that as soon as this was&#13;
&#13;
adopted as a sort of a standard thing, people hardly ever paid any&#13;
&#13;
attention to it.   The loan agreements became documents of seven or&#13;
&#13;
eight pages instead of documents of about 50 pages, and it reduced&#13;
&#13;
the area of fighting about language very, very much.&#13;
&#13;
           I may also say that a lot of these asperities of language&#13;
&#13;
were softened in the process.    We also had them translated into&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                 - 57 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                        Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Spanish and French, so that it became easier to deal with.     Also as&#13;
&#13;
we got more and more loans, people were less worried about making a&#13;
&#13;
better deal or making a worse deal than anybody else and having their&#13;
&#13;
parliaments compare different provisions.    The whole issue faded into&#13;
&#13;
insignificance.    There were a few substantive provisions that the&#13;
&#13;
Bank insisted on from the beginning, like the right to be consulted&#13;
&#13;
on external debt, which was later found to be unworkable and thrown&#13;
&#13;
out.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Could you say something about the work of the Bank lawyers in&#13;
&#13;
preparing the market of the United States for sale of bonds?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sommers:   Yes.   This was divided into two areas.   In the first place,&#13;
&#13;
preparing the market was done by Black and Dunston and the marketing&#13;
&#13;
people--that is, going around and seeing all the dealers and the&#13;
&#13;
financial people, and preaching the quality of the security behind&#13;
&#13;
the Bank's bonds.    We--the lawyers got into this in a small way, by&#13;
&#13;
preparing statements showing the rather novel and peculiar corporate&#13;
&#13;
structure and its relationship to the security available to the&#13;
&#13;
creditors, and also by clearing up ambiguities that needed to be&#13;
&#13;
cleared up.   But essentially the law department's role was in the&#13;
&#13;
field of getting legislation, which was needed to enable the bonds to&#13;
&#13;
be sold.   This consisted in part of a state-by-state drive to get&#13;
&#13;
legislation or administrative regulation which authorized insurance&#13;
&#13;
companies, savings banks, trustees and institutional investors&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                 - 58 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                       Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
generally to invest in the securities.    There was hardly a state in&#13;
&#13;
which any of these institutions could buy them, by law, when we&#13;
&#13;
started business.   In many states each of these separate kinds of&#13;
&#13;
institutions had a separate law and had to have a separate hearing&#13;
&#13;
before a separate Senate and House committee.    In Ohio we had to have&#13;
&#13;
one for life insurance companies, one for casualty companies, one for&#13;
&#13;
savings banks, one for trustees--and several for state funds, five or&#13;
&#13;
six different kinds of legislative enactments.   That was a big job,&#13;
&#13;
full of a lot of big and little fights.&#13;
&#13;
           Then there was the whole federal area.   We'd early got a&#13;
&#13;
ruling from the Controller of the Currency that national banks could&#13;
&#13;
invest in the bonds, but we wanted to get two other freedoms.   We&#13;
&#13;
wanted to get exempt from the Federal Securities Act, and we wanted&#13;
&#13;
to do that because the sanctions of the Securities Act really made no&#13;
&#13;
sense.   The sanctions of the Securities Act are liability on behalf&#13;
&#13;
of directors and officers and underwriters.   Our directors were&#13;
&#13;
exempt by international agreement from these liabilities, as were our&#13;
&#13;
officers, and the underwriters didn't have the same control over the&#13;
&#13;
issue that they do in a normal private issue, so it was unfair to put&#13;
&#13;
the whole burden on them.   You have the anomaly that the Bank can't&#13;
&#13;
issue securities in the United States without the approval of the&#13;
&#13;
United States government, and so we had to put on the first page of&#13;
&#13;
the prospectus, when we were under the SEC, as required by the SEC&#13;
&#13;
laws, "It is a criminal offense to represent that the Securities and&#13;
&#13;
Exchange Commission has approved the issuance of these securities,"&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                - 59 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                       Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
and on the first page we had to put "The issuance of these securities&#13;
&#13;
has been approved by the United States government."   The whole thing&#13;
&#13;
just didn't fit.&#13;
&#13;
          But the history had been that at the time of the Bretton&#13;
&#13;
Woods agreements' ratification, there'd been a question in the United&#13;
&#13;
States government whether to try for exemption from the SEC laws.      I&#13;
&#13;
understand the decision was not to try for it but hope to have them&#13;
&#13;
exempted later on.   But, on one occasion, in answer to a statement by&#13;
&#13;
Barkeley that the United States government's liability was limited to&#13;
&#13;
the United States subscription, Senator Taft got up and said, "How&#13;
&#13;
can that be?   Securities will be issued in this country under&#13;
&#13;
auspices under which it will be impossible for the United States to&#13;
&#13;
deny full responsibility for every penny that's issued."    Barkeley&#13;
&#13;
then said that he didn't understand that at all.   These securities&#13;
&#13;
would be "approved" by the Securities and Exchange Commission in the&#13;
&#13;
same way that they approve all other securities (which of course they&#13;
&#13;
don't do); therefore the United States would have no more&#13;
&#13;
responsibility for these than they would for any other security,&#13;
&#13;
except to the extent of its stock subscription.&#13;
&#13;
          Well, this was a silly exchange, but the fact that Barkeley&#13;
&#13;
in answer to Taft had said these bonds would go through the SEC&#13;
&#13;
process even though he'd said it incorrectly, was the basis on which&#13;
&#13;
the SEC said, "It's perfectly clear that these bonds are not entitled&#13;
&#13;
to exemption from the securities laws."    So our first issue was&#13;
&#13;
subject to the securities laws.    We later tried to get an exemption.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  - 60 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                         Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The bill was referred to the Committee which usually deals with SEC&#13;
&#13;
matters, which wasn't very sympathetic, so it got thrown out one&#13;
&#13;
year.   The next year Luxford, who was the assistant general counsel&#13;
&#13;
and a very capable legislative representative, had the whole bill&#13;
&#13;
recast in the form of an amendment to the Bretton Woods Agreements&#13;
&#13;
Act rather than an amendment to the Securities Act, with the idea&#13;
&#13;
that it would be steered to the Banking and Finance Committee which&#13;
&#13;
was sympathetic to the Bank, rather than the Interstate Commerce&#13;
&#13;
Commission which had turned us down before.   We coupled this with an&#13;
&#13;
exemption to the Banking Law which would permit commercial banks to&#13;
&#13;
deal in International Bank bonds, to underwrite them.     This time it&#13;
&#13;
went through pretty easily.   I remember one incident.&#13;
&#13;
            The only way we could get the bill through finally in the&#13;
&#13;
Senate was by unanimous consent, because we got caught in a&#13;
&#13;
legislative jam at the end of the year.   There'd been a favorable&#13;
&#13;
report by the committee; and if we could get unanimous it would go&#13;
&#13;
through; otherwise it would be taken up in order and it would die on&#13;
&#13;
the vine.&#13;
&#13;
            At the last minute the sponsor of the bill, and I can't&#13;
&#13;
remember who it was, got up and asked for unanimous consent to this&#13;
&#13;
bill, the purpose of which was to exempt the Bank's securities from&#13;
&#13;
the jurisdiction of the Securities and Exchange Commission, but which&#13;
&#13;
did have the provision that the Bank must make reports to the SEC.&#13;
&#13;
Senator Langer got up and said, "Before deciding whether to comment&#13;
&#13;
or object, I would like to ask, what is the purpose of the bill?"&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                 - 61 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                       Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
And the sponsor said, "The purpose of this bill is to subject the&#13;
&#13;
International Bank's bonds more effectively to the jurisdiction of&#13;
&#13;
the Securities and Exchange Commission."    Senator Langer said, "No&#13;
&#13;
objection," and the bill went through.    That's a sample of the&#13;
&#13;
haphazard way in which the legislative process takes place.&#13;
&#13;
            This story you asked me about is another small example of&#13;
&#13;
that.    For years we tried to get legislation in Congress authorizing&#13;
&#13;
District of Columbia insurance companies, of which there are only one&#13;
&#13;
or two and small ones, to be authorized to invest in Bank bonds.     We&#13;
&#13;
didn't care much about this as an extension of our market, but it&#13;
&#13;
looked anomalous that when we were trying to go around to get similar&#13;
&#13;
legislation in all the states, we couldn't even get it in our back&#13;
&#13;
yard from the United States government, which was our creator.     But&#13;
&#13;
the District committee of the House and Senate, if you've ever been&#13;
&#13;
there, spends all its time deciding what size rockfish can be taken&#13;
&#13;
and what to do about the starlings and major issues of this kind, and&#13;
&#13;
year after year we would never get to first base.    Nobody was against&#13;
&#13;
our bill but nobody was in favor of it.    Nobody was interested in it.&#13;
&#13;
One year we'd get through the House and die in the Senate, and so&#13;
&#13;
forth.   Of course, all these District bills can be passed only by&#13;
&#13;
unanimous consent.&#13;
&#13;
            So we started out another year, and I asked one of the&#13;
&#13;
young lawyers, Dick Bateson, to prepare for the introduction of the&#13;
&#13;
bill in the usual way, by drafting a letter for the Secretary of the&#13;
&#13;
Treasury to send to the chairman of the committee.    He drafted a&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                 - 62 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                         Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
letter in routine form reporting what had happened the last year, and&#13;
&#13;
he said, "The bill passed the House without amendment but failed of&#13;
&#13;
enactment in the Senate."   We sent this over to the Treasury and the&#13;
&#13;
Secretary signed it and sent it in.&#13;
&#13;
           The clerk of the House committee called me up and said,&#13;
&#13;
"There's a misstatement in this letter of the Secretary's.      The bill&#13;
&#13;
was amended in the House, though not in any material way."&#13;
&#13;
           I said, "That's funny, we looked it up in the Congressional&#13;
&#13;
Record.   It says there it was passed without amendment."&#13;
&#13;
           He said, "I know it says that.     That's wrong.   The only&#13;
&#13;
person who knows it was amended is me and I have it in my records."&#13;
&#13;
           So I reported this to the Treasury, and the general&#13;
&#13;
counsel's office of the Treasury got awfully excited and said,&#13;
&#13;
"You've made the Secretary of the Treasury make a misstatement in a&#13;
&#13;
letter to Congress.   This is very serious.    You will have to appear&#13;
&#13;
and make a statement explaining this and assuming responsibility for&#13;
&#13;
it."&#13;
&#13;
           So I went to the District Committee and they were dozing&#13;
&#13;
along talking about starlings and rockfish, and I started out by&#13;
&#13;
saying, "I want to begin by apologizing for causing the Secretary of&#13;
&#13;
the Treasury to make a misstatement in his submission to Congress."&#13;
&#13;
I explained this.   Well, for the first time in five years the members&#13;
&#13;
of the committee got interested, and they cross-examined me about all&#13;
&#13;
this to make sure there wasn't any funny business.     By that time they&#13;
&#13;
began to get interested in the merits of the bill, and somebody said,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                - 63 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                       Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
"Well, these sound like pretty good bonds.   Why shouldn't they be&#13;
&#13;
legal investments?"&#13;
&#13;
           And by the time this was over, the committee really got&#13;
&#13;
behind it and for the first time we went sailing through, all because&#13;
&#13;
we started off with making the Secretary of the Treasury make a&#13;
&#13;
misstatement.   I told the young lawyers not to profit by this&#13;
&#13;
experience.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   How important do you feel the type of loans the Bank has made&#13;
&#13;
have been in the ability of the Bank to sell bonds?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sommers:   Well, that's a very complicated question.   I think that&#13;
&#13;
unless we had made--we had adopted a lending posture and lending&#13;
&#13;
techniques which sounded sensible to the market in this country and&#13;
&#13;
in Europe, it would have been very hard to get off the ground.     At&#13;
&#13;
the present stage--and of course, the fact that there have been no&#13;
&#13;
defaults and all that has been a terrific selling point.   At the&#13;
&#13;
present time, the Bank's--the confidence of the market in the Bank's&#13;
&#13;
operations is pretty firmly established, and I think it's been five&#13;
&#13;
or more, eight years since the Bank has been in any way under&#13;
&#13;
pressure from the market to avoid going into things that it hadn't&#13;
&#13;
gone into before.&#13;
&#13;
           If we had made a big loan to some country which had just&#13;
&#13;
expropriated an oil business, there would have been an awful furor.&#13;
&#13;
Whether it would have actually limited our ability to sell bonds, I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                - 64 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                       Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
don't know.   It certainly would have in the early days.   But I don't&#13;
&#13;
think they scrutinize the day-to-day lending operations the way they&#13;
&#13;
used to.   Of course, the Bank has sold a billion dollars' worth of&#13;
&#13;
its loans to banks, without guarantee, and although these&#13;
&#13;
participations are not made wholly on a lender's motivations--there's&#13;
&#13;
a good deal of new business getting on the part of the banks&#13;
&#13;
involved--nevertheless I don't think the Bank could go haywire in&#13;
&#13;
lending without having that dry up, and if that dried up, there would&#13;
&#13;
be questions asked about how the Bank was operating.   But the&#13;
&#13;
questions of policy on which I've said there have been some&#13;
&#13;
differences of opinion, questions of degree as to how far you would&#13;
&#13;
go with general purpose loans or local expenditure lending, whether&#13;
&#13;
the Bank decided to go in for loans for water distribution, which&#13;
&#13;
it's never done, municipal water supplies or telephones which it&#13;
&#13;
doesn't often do, I don't think these things would have the slightest&#13;
&#13;
affect on its credit.   In fact, most of those are loans for which&#13;
&#13;
domestic lending agencies lend normally.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   I understand there was a time when some investment bankers' act&#13;
&#13;
focused on the International Bank?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sommers:   Well, that was in the days when we were under the&#13;
&#13;
jurisdiction of the SEC, and the investment bankers thought they were&#13;
&#13;
going to have the liability of underwriters.    We got a ruling from&#13;
&#13;
the SEC that they didn't have that liability.   It wasn't that the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                - 65 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                       Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
investment bankers wanted to look at the books, it was that the&#13;
&#13;
investment bankers raised the question as to whether they should not&#13;
&#13;
follow their normal practice of having their own lawyer give them a&#13;
&#13;
legal opinion that the organization of the bank was legal and that&#13;
&#13;
the members had all subscribed and that the United States was liable&#13;
&#13;
for its subscription.   I don't think anybody took it very seriously.&#13;
&#13;
We said, "no lawyers," to begin with--in those days we had a vast&#13;
&#13;
crowd of underwriters and we didn't want to get into too much&#13;
&#13;
complication--but after we hit on our pattern of borrowing, of having&#13;
&#13;
an underwriting syndicate headed by First Boston and Morgan Stanley,&#13;
&#13;
they were represented by lawyers and we've worked out a pattern by&#13;
&#13;
which those lawyers rely on an opinion of the Bank lawyers as to the&#13;
&#13;
legality of the Bank's existence and the membership and so forth.&#13;
&#13;
There never was any question of looking at the books in an auditor's&#13;
&#13;
sense.   After all, we have Price Waterhouse and we always work on&#13;
&#13;
audited figures.   It was really a question of the legal structure of&#13;
&#13;
the Bank, and it was pretty silly, because we didn't want to get&#13;
&#13;
into, in the early days, the question of how the United States had&#13;
&#13;
accepted some of the required documents saying that all steps had&#13;
&#13;
been completed under a country's domestic laws--a lot of it was&#13;
&#13;
pretty sloppy.   But it was sloppy by Wall St. corporate standards.&#13;
&#13;
It was normal by international diplomatic standards.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                - 66 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                       Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Some people I've talked to have said that the Bank's ability to&#13;
&#13;
sell bonds depended solely on the guarantee of the US government,&#13;
&#13;
that it could sell bonds given that guarantee regardless of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sommers:   --well, I think originally this was a necessary but not a&#13;
&#13;
sufficient condition.   I think the bare guarantee of the US&#13;
&#13;
government would provide an adequate security for anybody who was&#13;
&#13;
otherwise inclined to invest.   But these bonds didn't offer so much&#13;
&#13;
better yield than other bonds that were available, and of course,&#13;
&#13;
nowadays, they offer very poor yield compared to what the Equitable,&#13;
&#13;
for example, expects to get.    I'm sure that there had to be some&#13;
&#13;
affirmative motivation, and the affirmative motivation was that this&#13;
&#13;
was going to be a good thing and run sensibly, and that the financial&#13;
&#13;
community had an interest in this kind of organization going on.      I&#13;
&#13;
don't believe that the US guarantee alone would have been sufficient.&#13;
&#13;
Nowadays, of course, it's very easy--you just say, "Well, the Bank&#13;
&#13;
has two billion dollars' worth of bonds outstanding, and there's a&#13;
&#13;
direct call on the US Treasury for over five billion."   In the old&#13;
&#13;
days people used to think: well, what's going to happen when you make&#13;
&#13;
loans?   (Everybody thought you were just going to dish out the&#13;
&#13;
money.) And what's going to happen when you go beyond the US&#13;
&#13;
guarantee?   Well, now it's been proved that it took 15 years to get&#13;
&#13;
to the limit of the US guarantee, and when the Bank got to that point&#13;
&#13;
all the guarantees were increased.    So I think people treat it as&#13;
&#13;
substantially a US guaranteed obligation, but in the meantime, of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                 - 67 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                      Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
course, all the guarantees of all the other countries have become so&#13;
&#13;
much better than they were in those days that the whole credit&#13;
&#13;
structure of the Bank has enormously improved, as is evidenced by the&#13;
&#13;
rating of its bonds improving to Triple A.&#13;
&#13;
           But I doubt very much if, let's say, UNRRA, with the same&#13;
&#13;
US guarantee, would have had an easy time establishing itself in the&#13;
&#13;
bond market.   I don't know.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Given the fact that the US government guarantees, I take it you&#13;
&#13;
don't feel that it takes much to sell these bonds?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sommers:   Well, if the Bank had agreed in advance that it would limit&#13;
&#13;
its bond issuing amount to the level of the US guarantee, it would&#13;
&#13;
have had a Triple A rating right from the beginning, or might have,&#13;
&#13;
and probably could have saved fractional interest rates.   But in&#13;
&#13;
those days the Bank's interest rates anyway were 3 percent, (what it&#13;
&#13;
paid, it loaned at 4 1/4) and I don't think its interest rates have&#13;
&#13;
been unreasonable.   And I don't think really the policy aspects of&#13;
&#13;
interest rates are settled entirely by what the Bank has to pay.     I&#13;
&#13;
think the policy aspects of interest rates are more influenced by the&#13;
&#13;
question, how great a subsidization should be given to the&#13;
&#13;
underdeveloped countries, many of whom couldn't borrow at all without&#13;
&#13;
this capital structure, but should they be enabled to borrow on a--at&#13;
&#13;
a rate which is lower than the Bank's best European members would&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                - 68 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                      Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
have to pay if they borrowed much smaller amounts directly in the&#13;
&#13;
capital markets of the world?&#13;
&#13;
           Generally, apart from all other considerations, there's&#13;
&#13;
been a sort of an unconscious feeling that if Belgium and Holland and&#13;
&#13;
Norway would have to pay 5 1/4 percent or 5 1/2 percent to borrow in&#13;
&#13;
the American market, there is no reason why Jordan should borrow from&#13;
&#13;
the Bank at less, and particularly so since this would defeat the&#13;
&#13;
Bank's efforts to force countries like Norway and Belgium to meet&#13;
&#13;
their demands in the markets rather than coming to the Bank.   I think&#13;
&#13;
this is a more important consideration than some of these other&#13;
&#13;
things.&#13;
&#13;
           On the other hand, the pressure for lower interest rates&#13;
&#13;
should be, will not be but should be reduced, because you accomplish&#13;
&#13;
the same result now by a judicious mixture of Bank loans and IDA&#13;
&#13;
loans, and you can arrive at practically any service level you want&#13;
&#13;
by dishing them out in the proper proportions.   So that ought to give&#13;
&#13;
the Bank all the flexibility it wants to meet the problem.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Would you say just a bit about the development of Bank policy&#13;
&#13;
with respect to selling some of its borrowers' obligations to the&#13;
&#13;
private market?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sommers:   Well, this has always been an objective of the Bank.   At&#13;
&#13;
Bretton Woods, as you know, the idea was that the Bank was going to&#13;
&#13;
act primarily as a guaranteeing agency.   Well, that didn't prove&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                - 69 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                       Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
feasible for a lot of reasons.   In the first place, guarantees are&#13;
&#13;
not very acceptable in the American market.   There are a lot of legal&#13;
&#13;
quirks in guarantees.   In the second place, what would have happened&#13;
&#13;
would have been what happened in the case of housing bonds.    Those&#13;
&#13;
essentially have the same investment quality because they're all&#13;
&#13;
backed by the US government.   Nevertheless they sell at different&#13;
&#13;
yield bases because of the so-called names.   A good city sells at one&#13;
&#13;
yield and a bad city at another.   Similarly, a Holland loan with the&#13;
&#13;
Bank's guarantee would have sold at one rate, and a Nicaraguan loan&#13;
&#13;
at another.   In fact, you might have been giving the market more&#13;
&#13;
power to dictate the allocation of your resources than you would have&#13;
&#13;
liked, because the market might have said, "No Nicaraguas at all,&#13;
&#13;
nothing but Holland no matter what the rate."   It might have said,&#13;
&#13;
"We've got a lot of people who don't like Nicaragua or Egypt, for&#13;
&#13;
example."&#13;
&#13;
            So there were a lot of reasons for not going the guarantee&#13;
&#13;
route.   Nevertheless, the concept of the Bank as being a sort of a&#13;
&#13;
bridge, to use McCloy's figure of speech, between the public&#13;
&#13;
institutions and the private market, that we should try to bring the&#13;
&#13;
private investment community into our operations, was very important.&#13;
&#13;
It's had a tremendous effect on the good will of the investment&#13;
&#13;
community towards the Bank.    It's always been regarded as a friendly&#13;
&#13;
institution, and the fears that the Bank would try to take over the&#13;
&#13;
international business--such as it was, there was practically none of&#13;
&#13;
it--have been allayed, because any time anybody has accused us of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                 - 70 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                       Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
doing something that they might have done, we've just said, "Our&#13;
&#13;
whole portfolio is for sale, you can take it all over."   This has&#13;
&#13;
been a wonderful line.&#13;
&#13;
          So even in the early days of the Bank lending operations,&#13;
&#13;
we sold out of our portfolio.    But in those days we could do it only&#13;
&#13;
with a full guarantee.    This was silly, because in effect it meant we&#13;
&#13;
were paying more for money than we did when we issued direct.     These&#13;
&#13;
were non-marketable type securities, and we had to pay a higher&#13;
&#13;
effective interest rate on them.   Nevertheless, it was done for&#13;
&#13;
public relations purposes, and gradually we've moved away from the&#13;
&#13;
guarantee technique into direct sales.    At first this was only the&#13;
&#13;
short maturities to central banks.   There was a good deal of buying&#13;
&#13;
back loans in the country in which they were made.   It was a nice&#13;
&#13;
way--if a central bank had a little excess money, it could cut down&#13;
&#13;
on the interest rate their country was paying by retiring obligations&#13;
&#13;
a few years in advance.    And it meant that the Bank's borrowing&#13;
&#13;
requirements were somewhat lowered at a time when the buildup was&#13;
&#13;
very fast, and where it didn't want to be forced into the market over&#13;
&#13;
and over and over again.   The chief weakness in the whole bank's&#13;
&#13;
borrowing operation has been the necessity for coming back several&#13;
&#13;
times a year.   Investors didn't have the feeling, "gee, we'd better&#13;
&#13;
get in on this issue while we can," because up until later years when&#13;
&#13;
the Bank did not borrow so much in the United States: "Well, what's&#13;
&#13;
the hurry, there'll be another issue along in three months."    And the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                 - 71 -&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                        Davidson Sommers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
problem of keeping the market guessing and hungry was a very--a&#13;
&#13;
problem of very great tactical skills, which Black is a master at.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   The only other question I can think of I'd like to ask--how long&#13;
&#13;
have we?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sommers:   About two minutes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   The reasons for the three vice presidents?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sommers:   Oh, that was just the usual bureaucratic reason of not&#13;
&#13;
being willing or able to choose any one.    You'd better ask Mr. Black&#13;
&#13;
about that.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Q:   Well, thank you very much.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sommers:   Thank you.   I enjoyed it.   An interesting institution.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  - 72 -&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="18004818">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2009/05/18004818/transcript-oral-history-interview-davidson-sommers-held-august-2-1961
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2009/05/18004818/transcript-oral-history-interview-davidson-sommers-held-august-2-1961</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2009/05/18004818/transcript-oral-history-interview-davidson-sommers-held-august-2-1961</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>1961-08-02T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>1961-08-02T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2013/07/15/000356161_20130715165739/Rendered/INDEX/791230TRN0Somm0Box0377367B00PUBLIC0.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2013/07/15/000356161_20130715165739/Rendered/PDF/791230TRN0Somm0Box0377367B00PUBLIC0.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2013-07-15T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2009-05-08T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Transcript of oral history interview with
            Davidson Sommers held on August 2, 1961
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            In August 1961, Davidson Sommers was
            interviewed on behalf of the World Bank Group Archives oral
            history program by Prof. Robert Oliver. During his tenure at
            the Bank from 1946 to 1959, Mr. Sommers worked in the
            following areas: in the law department as a lawyer and also
            as assistant general counsel starting in 1946; as general
            counsel (1949-1959); and as vice president for the
            International Bank for Reconstruction and Development (IBRD
            and the International Finance Corporation (IFC) (1956-1959).
            He contrasts the presidencies of John McCloy and Eugene
            Black and speaks to the management of the World Bank. His
            transcript concerns investment banking, First Boston and
            Morgan Stanley, and projects in India, Pakistan, Brazil, and Vietnam.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Transcript of oral history interview with
            Davidson Sommers held on August 2, 1961
        </docna>
        <display_title>Transcript of oral history
            interview with Davidson Sommers held on August 2, 1961</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/2009/05/18004818/transcript-oral-history-interview-davidson-sommers-held-august-2-1961</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Transcript</docty>
        <subtopic>Access to Finance,Public Sector Corruption &amp;
            Anticorruption Measures,Bankruptcy and Resolution of Financial Distress,Debt Markets,Banks &amp; Banking Reform</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Public Sector Development,Finance and Financial Sector Development</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000356161_20130715165739</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>World Bank Group Archives oral history program</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Public Sector Development,Finance and Financial Sector Development</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Board Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            absorptive capacity, amount of capital,
            auditor, balance of payments, balance sheet, banana
            republic, bank accounts, Bank bonds, Bank lending, Bank
            loan, Bank loans, Bank management, Banking Law, bankrupt,
            bond, bond issue, bond issues, bond market, bondholders,
            bonds, borrower, borrowing, capital structure,
            capitalization, cash flow, Central Bank, claim, collateral,
            commercial banks, commercial lending, concessions,
            confidence, cost estimates, credit standing, credit
            structure, credit worthiness, creditors, criminal, debt,
            debt burden, debt service, debts, defaults, domestic laws,
            earnings, economic activity, Economic situation, Exchange
            Commission, expenditure, expenditures, external capital,
            external debt, finances, financial analysis, financial
            market, financing requirements, first loan, foreign
            creditors, foreign debt, foreign debts, foreign exchange,
            general counsel, government officials, hard loan, hard
            loans, housing, inflation, initiative, institutional
            investors, insurance, insurance companies, International
            Bank, International Development, investigation, investment
            bankers, issuance, judge, judgment, jurisdiction, lack of
            credit, laws, lawyer, lawyers, legislation, lender, lending
            agencies, lending agency, lending policy, lending
            techniques, liability, life insurance, life insurance
            companies, loan, loan agreements, loan contract, Loan Fund,
            local currencies, local currency, long-term loans,
            maturities, maturity, Minister, ministers, Monetary Fund,
            monetary policy, national banks, negotiation, negotiations,
            new business, offense, outstanding public debt, politicians,
            private borrowers, private capital, private creditors,
            private debts, private investors, private lending, private
            party, procurement, productivity, public debt, public money,
            rates of return, receivership, red tape, repayment,
            repayments, reserves, sanctions, savings, savings banks,
            securities, securities laws, settlements, soft loan, soft
            loans, Special Fund, Technical assistance, terms of
            amortization, title, Treasury, treaty, trustee, trustees,
            unanimous consent, underwriters
        </keywd>
        <owner>Knowledge &amp; Information Services (ITSKI)</owner>
        <repnb>79123</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>PPP</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public-Private Partnerships</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Science and Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public-Private Partnerships (PPP)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Alternative Sentencing Options</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community based Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Correctional Services and Facilities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corrections</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime and Society</ml:concept><ml:concept>Defense Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Detention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enforcement Policies and Oversight Mechanism</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigative Task Force Police</ml:concept><ml:concept>Juvenile Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Law Enforcement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Offender Reintegration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Administration and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Problem solving Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Prosecution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Restorative Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Therapeutic Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Assistance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim-Offender Mediation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Banks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Retail Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Railways Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets and Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monetary and Exchange Rate Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corporate Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nationalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Enterprise Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>State Owned Enterprise Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>State-Owned Enterprise Restructuring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Securities Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Engineering</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Criminal Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Treaties</ml:concept><ml:concept>Treasury</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banking Institutional Set-up</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Railways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Refineries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Municipality</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Balance of Payments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monetary Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>State Owned Enterprises</ml:concept><ml:concept>Mediation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets Law and Regulation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>