<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>ï»¿                                                         .~/j;ff//                c&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                  79126&#13;
DIVISION OF THE HUMANITIES AND SOCIAL SCIENCES&#13;
CALIFORNIA INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY&#13;
                                                                                      :o~&#13;
                                                                                         t c"&#13;
                                                                                         .&#13;
                                                                                         l             P,"'? ...,&#13;
                                                                                                       .,. , j . .&#13;
                                                                                                                     '-?   \&#13;
                                                                                                                               \&#13;
                                                                                                                               .'&#13;
                                                                                                                               .&#13;
                                                                                                       .&#13;
                                                                                         \&#13;
PASADENA, CALIFORNIA 91125                                                                   \&lt;\;,Â·Â·. )./                      !&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
A CONVERSATION WITH CONGRESSMAN WILLIAM STANTON&#13;
&#13;
WASHINGTON, D.C.&#13;
&#13;
July 16, 1986&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Â© Robert W. Oliver&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                        '"c,,11UTÂ£ 0!&gt;&#13;
                                                                   ~...                       "~"r.:&#13;
                                                              ~&#13;
                                                              ~&#13;
                                                                                                  ~0&#13;
&#13;
                                                              ..&#13;
                                                              ~&#13;
                                                              â&#128;¢&#13;
                                                              ~&#13;
                                                                                                       'g&#13;
                                                                                                        -&lt;  .&#13;
                                                                                                           It:&#13;
                                                                ~                                      ~&#13;
                                                                     &lt;:-,.+                    ...,&lt;f&gt;&#13;
                                                                                         .,_\.&#13;
                                                                              Slf.-LL lA..&#13;
&#13;
                                                  CONVERSATIONS ABOUT GEORGE WOODS AND&#13;
                                                            THE WORLD BANK&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                                                                            2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
             A Conversation with Congressman William Stanton                     Committee, a real power.       1964 was a disastrous year for the Republican&#13;
&#13;
                              Washington. D. C.                                  Party.     We loat 30 - 40 aeata, and   elected only three new Republicans&#13;
&#13;
                                July 16. 1985                                    between the Allegheny's and the Rocky Mountains. 1 was fortunate enough&#13;
&#13;
                              Robert W. Oliver                                   to be one of them.      In 1964, two Ohio members lost:    Bob Taft lost in a&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                 bid to move on to the United States Senate and left the Banking&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:    I might begin the conversation by asking if you would tell a          Committee, and a man naaed Oliver Bolton left to run aa       11&#13;
                                                                                                                                                    Congreaaman at&#13;
&#13;
bit about your background, your years in Consreaa, and how you happen            Large" and regretfully lost. Be waa also on the Banking Committee; eo&#13;
&#13;
to be in the   E~ternal   Relations Division of the Bank; and then you           there was a vacancy in the State of Ohio, and when I got to Congress I&#13;
&#13;
might talk a bit about the IDA Replenishment issues before the American          was told that I waa very fortunate, that I would serve on the Banking&#13;
&#13;
Congress over the years.                                                         Committee.     While â&#128;¢Y father had been a buaineaa aan, a banker, I never&#13;
&#13;
STANTON:    Well, I vas very privileged to represent the 11th                    myself vaa active in the industry.&#13;
&#13;
Congressional District of Ohio in the Congress of the United States,             OLIVER:     So you came to Congress and bad the opportunity of serving on&#13;
&#13;
first being elected in 1964 and serving 9 nine consecutive terms, or 18          the Banking Committee.      What sort of issues in general came before the&#13;
&#13;
years.     The 11th district comprises the outskirts of Cleveland, Akron         Banking Comaittee?      When did you begin to be aware of the Banking&#13;
&#13;
and Youngstown, in Northeast Ohio.         It is a great ezporting area of the   Committee'a interest in legialation dealing with the World Bank?&#13;
&#13;
United States and the fastest growing area in Ohio for the last several          STANTON:     Well, you know in retrospect, the amount of time and energy&#13;
&#13;
decades.     During that eighteen years in Congress, I spent the entire          that one spent aa a comaittee member on all international matters was&#13;
&#13;
time on the House Banking and Finance Committee, the entire time on the          dwarfed by the domestic banking industry.      The first that I got&#13;
&#13;
Sub-Committee on International Finance, and 10 of those 18 years as the          involved in culminated in the One-Bank Holding- Company legislation of&#13;
ranking Republican and Minority Leader on the Banking Committee.                 1969 which laid the groundwork for the formation of your holding&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     Could I just interrupt to ask if your     e~perience   before you    companies and the commercial banking structure that       e~ists     today -- the&#13;
&#13;
were elected to Congress had been in banking or fields related to this?          major changes in what we call the 4C8 Statues of the Federal Reserve&#13;
&#13;
STANTON:     No. In those days, your election to a specific committee was        which constitutes what are and what are not banks: What is the proper&#13;
&#13;
determined by the leader in your state in Congress. We happened to have          roles of banks in functionally related businesses?&#13;
&#13;
a man by the name of Clarence     Bro~n.    Sr, who was head of the Rules             It    wasn~t   long, though, before you became cognizant that under our&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                     3                                                                               4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
responsibility came all of the authorization for the international           that time.     It bad to be talked into it.&#13;
&#13;
lending institutions.    When I came on the Committee, there were one        OLIVER:    So it ia your feeling that the idea for IDA really originated&#13;
&#13;
large one and one regional bank, and early in ay first year in Congress      in Congress rather more than in the Bank itself?&#13;
&#13;
we saw the formation of the second regional bank.     It was true then and   STANTON:     That ia absolutely a true ltatement.    But, and history will&#13;
it is today that the World Bank in ita separate facilities -- the IDA,       abow, the recorda will ahov, the Bank only accepted, aa 1 understand&#13;
&#13;
the IBRD, and the International Finance Corporation -- doainated the         it, reluctantly.      To see it in a relatively abort term of five to seven&#13;
&#13;
action on the Committee as well as it did in the lending world.      The     years, an institution started by encouragement of Congress, and then&#13;
&#13;
Inter-American Development Bank, of course, was new at that particular       not to support it financially, sometimes reluctantly. certainly not&#13;
&#13;
time, had much motivation and interest by congressmen, and was               entbuaiaatically, one baa to wonder why.&#13;
&#13;
extremely popular.    My first year in Congress saw the formation and the    OLIVER:    The name Mike Monroney ia sometimes mentioned as one of those&#13;
&#13;
founding of the Asian Development Bank and then, of course, in later         who was a strong early supporter of a soft-loan approach.        He was still&#13;
years, before I left the Committee, the establishment of and then            in Congress when you were?&#13;
&#13;
finally our membership in, the African Development Bank.                     STANTON:     Yea.   Be was at that time.   Of course be was no longer&#13;
&#13;
     I think that, looking back, we were in an era of complete change        associated with the legislation as far as I can remember, at least in&#13;
&#13;
as far as our relationship with the international lending institutions       the Bouse aide, at that time.      The recorda in the '60s, and the&#13;
&#13;
were concerned.      In 1965, for example, it had only been five short       teatimony will show he j i j play a very big part in the formation of the&#13;
&#13;
years since the Republican Administration of Eisenhower, with strong         legislation -- along with the Eisenhower Administration.&#13;
&#13;
bi-partisan support in the United States Senate, literally forced upon            As 1 look back on it, there were a couple of reasons why Congress'&#13;
&#13;
the Bank, as I understood it in those days, the existence of the soft-       attitude toward IDA changed.      The annual authorization and&#13;
loan window of the International Development Association.     It bad its     appropriation for the IBRD, which was considered a hard loan business,&#13;
strongest support from western states who, I think, perceived of it          an excellently run institution, was never challenged in Congress.           We&#13;
truthfully as a method in which we could secure financing for the            accepted what was proposed by the Treasury Department. We on the&#13;
&#13;
excess grain and agriculture products that they found themselves with.       Committee accepted whatever general capital increase it asked for, and&#13;
&#13;
For ont&gt; reason or another, motivated for economic or humanitarian           much the same attitude was handled by the Appropriations Committee.&#13;
&#13;
re.arwna, it waa luluâ&#128;¢warm. to say the least, on the part of the Bank at          The criticism rested strictly with the IDA -- soft loans.          I think&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                         5                                                                                 6&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
as you examine the recorda, this came about for several different                 golf courae.&#13;
&#13;
reasons.    Humber one, I tbink 1 you would soon discover that the                OLIVER:     Could you aay a little bit more about that?     What was the&#13;
&#13;
majority (literally almost 60 percent, I think) of the funds went to              criticiam7     That there was a golf courae at all? or.&#13;
&#13;
India; and this was in good times and bad, under one ruler or another;            STANTON:     The criticiam grew in an animosity towards international&#13;
&#13;
the Indian Government was either pro-Aaerican or not pro American.           It   public servants.        The fact is that members of the institutions could&#13;
&#13;
was a source of pain for many congressmen to support the IDA when the             not play golf.     They could not become aembera because the memberships&#13;
&#13;
majority of money went to India, and you read in the papers that they             in local clubs -- they weren't discriminated against, there just&#13;
&#13;
were anti-west, and so forth.       That was true in that particular era,         weren~t    any vacancies.     They waited too long to become members, or it&#13;
&#13;
not necessarily noncooperation with the Weat, but certainly not a                 waa too expensive.        It did not sit well with member&amp; in Congress who&#13;
&#13;
close ally.                                                                       did not play golf, or, if they did play golf, they bad no problem&#13;
     Secondly and equally important was the general feeling that the              playing golf locally.        The majority did not because they went home.&#13;
Bank was    ~   -- when I say the Bank, IBRD -- a give-away program, was          But thie was something that â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢          Once again the idea of going out&#13;
not foreign aid.     IDA was, and the 50-year grants became a source of           and building a country club with tazpayers funds was something that was&#13;
contention.     The economic condition of the United States. â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢       Why        driven home, and it was very damaging to the image.&#13;
you~re   building railroads and dams, communication systems, with our             OLIVER:     About what year vaa it that that became a particular issue?&#13;
taxpayers money when we    don~t   even allow it in our own country?    A         STANTON:     Don't bold me to this, but it was in the late '60s that this&#13;
&#13;
backlash appeared, and these two reasons, 1 think. combined to make it            started, became an issue.&#13;
&#13;
most difficult.     Then there is a question if IDA ezpanded too fast.        A   OLIVER:     Ia it atilt an issue to this day, do you think?&#13;
&#13;
60 percent jump was a little bit more than Congress was used to at that            STANTON:     No, no.     Over the years this issue has lost interest.&#13;
&#13;
particular time.                                                                  IDA never was particularly popular at all with the Republican members&#13;
&#13;
     There were a lot of aide interests in the period of the late '60s.           of the House. I was always a strong supporter, a believer in the idea&#13;
Led by Congressman H.R. Gross of Iowa, we found one year that the IDA             of multilateral lending.       We had some great battles in the late sixties&#13;
authorization was in trouble because of the Bretton Woods Golf Course.            over the value of multilateral or bilateral support.        In general some&#13;
&#13;
One year I remember debating that on the House Floor.       It waa eztremely      of the best debates that I can remember were over this one subject.&#13;
&#13;
damaging.     It had come up in previous years when the IHF had built the         Not specifically the World Bank, but the principle.        I thought we had&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                    7&#13;
                                                                                                                                                8&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
solved that question forever in that it was determined by a majority&#13;
                                                                             abort supply. Congress would send a strong signal. and the Bank&#13;
that the beat bang for the buck of the taxpayers money was multilateral&#13;
                                                                             cooperated over the years.    Of course the amount of aid to India has&#13;
institutions for a variety of reatona, not the leaat of which was a&#13;
                                                                             declined in percentage to the other donors to 1985 where you have not&#13;
recognition that you can't try to buy friendship as you do with&#13;
                                                                             only China but India both combining at 40 percent maximum of the total&#13;
bilateral aid.   And two. the expertise that you receive froa people in&#13;
                                                                             disbursement of IDA funda.&#13;
the projects, which both the Inter-American Developeent Bank and the&#13;
                                                                             OLIVER:    Well, do you think the American Congress would have become&#13;
World Bank were performing around the world was far greater in&#13;
                                                                             in~olved   in second guessing the Bank ao to apeak if there had never&#13;
acceptance and in quality than the projects you aupport if you do it&#13;
                                                                             been an IDA in the first place?&#13;
bilaterally.&#13;
                                                                             STANTON:    I've always been proud that Congress had pushed the idea of&#13;
OLIVER:    Could we then come back to your earlier comment about the&#13;
                                                                             IDA, and I think it wal important in history that you recognized that&#13;
concern for the large amount of IDA assistance that was going to India.&#13;
                                                                             this vas the first time the international comaunity as a whole made&#13;
Clearly the political allegiance internationally of India was a matter&#13;
                                                                             concessionary lending a goal, worldwide.    They made poverty officially&#13;
of some consequence, and yet, if one accepts the principle of&#13;
                                                                             a recognized social problem of developed countries, and 1 think, for&#13;
multilateral lending, then presumably the international organization in&#13;
                                                                             this principal alone, we should always be very proud that we initiated&#13;
charge of the multilateral lending baa got to be free to choose for&#13;
                                                                             it.     I think that it's regrettable that, for one reason or another, we&#13;
itself how the multilateral lending shall go?&#13;
                                                                             never quite sold the American public on what we do, and what we did.&#13;
STANTON:   There is no question of that, and there was not in any time&#13;
                                                                             That was one of the things in my determining what I was going to do&#13;
in history to my knowledge when any member of Congress attempted to&#13;
                                                                             after Congress:    to come here.&#13;
establish by law a percentage per country of allocations.    They cannot,&#13;
                                                                             OLIVER:    Perhaps, since I aaked that question at the outset, maybe you&#13;
of course, and they have not attempted over the years to dictate to the&#13;
                                                                             would tell a little bit about bow you decided you would come to the&#13;
Bank, which is against the charter.    What they can do is direct the&#13;
                                                                             Bank.&#13;
U.S. Executive Director of the World Bank to do this or that.     We later&#13;
                                                                             STANTON:    Well, I'll be glad to.   I found myself voluntarily retiring.&#13;
got into, as the years weat on, regrettably, a lot of those things.&#13;
                                                                             As I approached 60 years of age and 18 years in congress, I became&#13;
The biggest thing that I ever remember was palm oil became a big issue,&#13;
                                                                             very tired of being a lifetime in the minority.     If I could have become&#13;
and citrus fruit, and sugar and different commodities that were in&#13;
                                                                             Chairman of the Banking Committee in the next four or six years ahead,&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                       9                                                                                10&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
I would never have left. I did not have that confidence that                    on our coamitteea â&#128;¢pent very little time on international affairs.           The&#13;
&#13;
Republicans would become that strong.     After awhile. it became true          situation did not basically change over the years.      The priorities of&#13;
&#13;
that you could almost stop anything in the committees. but you couldn;t         the Congress even today, while we here at the World Bank think the&#13;
&#13;
pass a darn thing on your own without majority support.        So in turning    World rises and sets on one particular loan or another,      it~a   not a top&#13;
&#13;
to somewhere else, I looked at my experience on the committee               I   priority to Congress.       Their own domestic programs and policies are&#13;
&#13;
had some offers â&#128;¢ from l!A.ll   ~    and New York â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢       And yet I had a     number one.    They have the over-riding subject of war and peace.&#13;
&#13;
love of this institution and recognized that aaybe 1 could be of a              Domestic programs and the budget consume the majority of time and&#13;
&#13;
little help.     I suffered financially in coming here from what I could        interest for members of Congress.       And ao that even today we are still&#13;
&#13;
have gotten from the big city international centers. 1 wanted to coae           a low priorities     it~   for the Congress.&#13;
&#13;
here and I;ve never been sorry. I have been very happy the last two and         OLIVER:    It baa been suggested from time to time that it has never been&#13;
&#13;
one-half years.                                                                 clear whether it is the job of the Bank, the people in the Bank, to&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     One of the things you do is to maintain liaison with Congrees7      somehow deal directly with Congress in an attempt to get their message&#13;
&#13;
STANTON: By all means. One of ay prime reaponsibilitiea is to make sure         across. or whether. on the other hand. the Bank should rely on the&#13;
&#13;
that the individual membera of committees involved with our                     United States Treasury Departaent to intercede, so to apeak, with the&#13;
&#13;
legislation. and all others, are aware of what the iaauee are.         How we   Congress and present the case for the Bank.      Does that seem to you to&#13;
&#13;
look at it.    We do oooperate totally with the Executive Director of the       have been a dilemma?&#13;
&#13;
United States and try to help him in any way that we can. public                STANTON:   Yea.     You had different eras involved.   In the late '60s and 0&#13;
&#13;
relationa wise.    We;re all after the same goal.     It vas just an            of courae, in the early ;70a. we experienced an extremely rapid growth&#13;
&#13;
advantage having served there and knowing the ball players to be able           of the Bank.      You did not find any cloaer ties with Congress then as&#13;
&#13;
to relate to them our particular problem.                                       you did when the Bank was smaller.       In fact. you grew apart even&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     In the ;60s in particular did you have the feeling that the         further.&#13;
&#13;
Bank was getting its message across to Congress adequately?                     OLIVER:    Why was that?&#13;
&#13;
STANTON:     No. There is no question that they were not.     There is no       STANTON:    I think this was once again the recognition of the leadership&#13;
&#13;
question that they genuinely felt in those days that there was no need          of the Bank.      The fact is that whatever the amount that was determined&#13;
&#13;
to.   Th~   Bank wss a much smaller institution.    Congress, as I say, even    by the administration as the U. s. contribution to IDA or IBRD, this&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                          11                                                                12&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
was a responsibility    of the   a~inistration   to see that Congress was       OLIVER:    So as to reduce the annual ..aunt?&#13;
&#13;
informed.     It is certainly true that the success of an operation in          STANTON:   Well, it did reduce the annual a-aunt.     What basically it did&#13;
&#13;
this regard depended upon the dedication of the administration.           You   was to throw back IDA Seven one additional year.      We lost a year, which&#13;
&#13;
see people that did it very well under the Democratic administration            the rest of the donora help to make up for, but only to a degree.&#13;
&#13;
and those who did not do it well under the Republican administration.           OLIVER:    What is your own prediction today?&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     Was it such a partisan issue that the Democratic                    STANTON:    Well, my own prediction today is that we will enter into&#13;
&#13;
administrations worked harder at â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ ?                                        early 1986 seeking an Eighth Replenishment.       I think that we will&#13;
&#13;
STANTON:     It became very definitely in the late '70s and the                 reverse the tide of the Seventh Replenishment, which was in reality a&#13;
&#13;
early '80s, Bob.     If it wasn't for the Democratic majority in                46 percent cut in real ter.a coapared to the $1.08 billion that the&#13;
&#13;
the Rouse of Representatives, I doubt, .yaelÂ£, today, we would                  u.s. authorized for IDA Siz in 1977, compared to $750 million in 1984.&#13;
&#13;
see the IDA aa it is now exists.     Once again the Republicans                 I think that prospects are good for at least the same amount in IDA&#13;
&#13;
got it into their minds that it was a give-away program.          Going         Eight and perhaps a little bit   ~re.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
into more recent days, the rapid expansion of the Bank in the                   OLIVER:    People you personally talk to on the Hill are more sympathetic&#13;
&#13;
Sixth Replenishment probably was the low point. It vas too big                  that they were 7 years ago?&#13;
&#13;
of a jump.     It would never pass the Bouse of Representativeâ&#128;¢.                STANTON:    Well, it's a combination of things.     It ia the recognition of&#13;
&#13;
It was thrown into what we call the continuing resolution.                      the fact that the institution baa dramatically changed.      A decade ago,&#13;
We're nov just coming out of it, and I think IDA Seven suffered                 better than 60 percent of the IDA authorization vent to India.       At that&#13;
&#13;
for it.                                                                         aame period of time, the contribution to sub-Saharan Africa, for&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     What vas the year of the Sixth Replenishment?                       example, was under 15 percent. In IDA Seven, that commitment vas&#13;
&#13;
STANTON:     It vas supposed to be passed in 1980.    It was first              spelled out by the Directors of the Bank to be in the minimum of 35&#13;
&#13;
proposed by the Carter Administration in '76, and it was never                  percent, and I would think, no question in my mind, in IDA Eight you&#13;
&#13;
passed, even authorized, until the first year of the Reagan                     will see that it is somewhere between 40 and 50 percent, and there are&#13;
&#13;
 administration, in '61.    Then they, unilaterally in that year,               many more advocates for concessionary lending to sub-Saharan Africa&#13;
&#13;
 changed it from a three-year    authori~ation   to a four-year                 than there were to India.&#13;
&#13;
 aull,or izal ion.                                                              OLIVER:    Is this primarily because of the poverty in Africa, or because&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                               13                                                                                14&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
of the international alliances?                                                    countries. Governments and their tax payers are interested in this&#13;
&#13;
STANTON:    It is a combination of both.   We're dealing with some real            institution, and they are glad to know.        It is not a lobbying process.&#13;
&#13;
poverty in truly non-creditworthy countries.       Secondly, there is more         It is an educational process.        MOat country legislators do not vote&#13;
&#13;
compassion today for Africa. It's the real poorest of the poor. Poverty            directly on our budget.        The United States and   Switzerland are two&#13;
&#13;
is very evident and existing.      Then. to exacerbate the issue. the              that do.     In molt cases, the average parliamentarian, especially in&#13;
&#13;
drought question of the last year and a half came about and there vas a            Europe, is not that faailiar with the work of the Bank.        We're&#13;
&#13;
media concentration on the starving and dying in Africa. about 6 months            atteapting to overcome that.&#13;
&#13;
after the completion of IDA Seven.      I have no doubt in     ~    â&#128;¢ind the IDA   oLIVER:    Do you personally, on occasion, meet with people in Parliament&#13;
&#13;
Replenishment would have been hisher if it had coincided with the                  in European countries?&#13;
&#13;
disclosure of the damage caused by the drought.                                    STAHTOH:     Oh yea.     I've taken advantage of the fact that for many years&#13;
OLIVER:    Could you say just a bit more about the earlier         att~pts   of    I vas on what they call an exchange of legislators' program in the&#13;
&#13;
the Bank in the '60s and the '70s to get ita       ~saage   across about IDA.      Common Market countries, and, through tboae years we bad a home and&#13;
&#13;
Did the Bank have anybody like yourself in those days whose prt.ary                home sessions of four and five day duration in which they would come&#13;
&#13;
concern it was to be in touch with people     LD   Congress?                       here in the apring and we would go there in the fall, or vice versa,&#13;
&#13;
STANTON:    Not to my knowledge.    The Bank bad one employee and be~&amp;             and we would go to different cities like Munich, Dublin, Paris. etc.&#13;
&#13;
still here, but his job was one of monitoring different committees and             OLIVER:    It sounds like a marvelous job.&#13;
&#13;
reporting back to the Bank. He had the reputation of being well liked,             STANTON:     It was an excellent exchange prograa.     All of these&#13;
&#13;
but he in no way bad any particular influence on legislation.                      countries~   :epreaentativea whom we met with came from the European&#13;
&#13;
        I think that there again the institution looks upon itself, and            Community.     This was before they were elected members of the&#13;
&#13;
rightly ao, aa an international institution.        We never appear before         Community.    After they became elected, it was still. as far as they&#13;
&#13;
committees of Congresa 1 but, in recent years, we certainly have gone to           were concerned. one of the moat prestigious committees that they&#13;
&#13;
the point of informal consultation.      We make apecific attempts not only        could serve on.        Over here 1 it is   an~~   thing, but over there it&#13;
in the U. S. but with legislatures around the world to apprise them of             is a recognized committee.        So now what we have done&#13;
the goals and the hopes of the Bank, and we find a good reception to               in recent years is getting those who attend meetings involved in&#13;
that.     We concentrate on Great Britain, Germany, Italy and other                knowing what the World Bank does.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                           15                                                                           16&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:    It baa been said that when Hr. Eugene Black was President of      and is a good friend of present majority leader, Senator Bob Dole.             He&#13;
&#13;
the World Bank, it did no harm to the Bank that he was a very close          baa been to the office for courtesy visits durin&amp; the years that I have&#13;
&#13;
friend of Richard Russell, in particular. from Georgia 1 but other           been here with George Buab 1 Bovard Baker, Speaker O'Neill; and it bas&#13;
&#13;
Congressmen and Senators from Georgia aa well.     Tbe question is:   Does   helped.&#13;
&#13;
the personality of the Preaident of the Bank enter into the relations        OLIVER:     Do you happen to remember what sort of relations there were&#13;
between the Bank and Congress?                                               between George Woods when he was President of the Bank and people in&#13;
&#13;
STANTON:    There ia no question of that.   And no reflection on any of      Congress?&#13;
&#13;
the individuals involved.    But looking back, looking at several years      STANTON: This was before my tiae but I never heard anything but good&#13;
&#13;
of involvement, Eugene Black had the beat built-in reservoir of good         about him.     He had a lot of strons ties in the U. S. Government.&#13;
will. He, of course, was a living legend in his time,and his close           OLIVER:     Speaking of George Woods, and Eugene Black also?&#13;
relationship with very powerful members of the Congreaa is recognized.       STANTON: Both of them had good personal relationships with Congress.&#13;
McNamara bad many friends within the Johnson Administration, but had a       It wasn't so important then. The aoney wasn't an issue.        We should&#13;
different type of personality.     He waa advised on some occasions not to   throw one other item in that has caused criticism for the Bank and has&#13;
&#13;
come to the Hill?    He was a man who knew where he wanted to go and what    affected legislation.     We alluded to the Palm Oil and citrus problema.&#13;
&#13;
he had to do to get there. He was more pragmatic.     Mr. Clausen is well    World economic conditions brousbt home to America competition from&#13;
&#13;
liked, well known, and baa made himself available to individual membere      abroad.     As the IFC grew in importance to Third World Countries, we&#13;
&#13;
of Congress. Tbia is necessary, in order to keep a good relationship         8upported for domestic reasons a product that later turned into&#13;
&#13;
with our Number One stockholder.                                             exports.     They competed with American production here at home.       That&#13;
OLIVER:    Could you amplify just a little bit just what you meant when      lost us many friends.&#13;
&#13;
you said Mr. McNamara vas advised not to come to the Hill?                   OLIVER:     Baa there been a tendency in Congress to write into the&#13;
&#13;
STANTON:    Yes.   There was a period of time in which Bob McNamara was      legislation a tied-loan procedure? Was a suggestion that American&#13;
&#13;
advised not to come up on the Hill under the theory that this was an         exports have to be related to the dollars made available?&#13;
&#13;
international institution.     To this day. the International Monetary       STANTON:     They unearthed many, many versions of that fact.     The&#13;
&#13;
Fund fo1lowa this theory.     This is not true with Hr. Clausen.   When he   authorization here in 1985 for the Bank in the United States Senate&#13;
is invited to a meeting with metnbers he goes.    He baa met informally,     went flying through the Senate Finance Committee and was reported out&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                              17                                                                                    18&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
to the full Senate floor, but word got to Senator Lugar that Senator              Republican on the House Foreign Affairs Committee. a man named Bill&#13;
&#13;
Dominici was interested in his own state's Â·copper, and there were                Brumfield -- holding up that great tradition.           Many say it goes back to&#13;
&#13;
amendments that the Treasury felt they couldn't live with.         That vas       Vandenberg~&amp;       day, and this has been a conâ&#128;¢istent policy.         I remember&#13;
&#13;
the prime reason that that legislation was not brought to the floor.              well in 1980,       ~at,   in World Bank legislâ&#128;¢tion, of the then 16, 17&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:   This is legislation to expand the capital of the Bank or to             members of Congress for the Stlte of Michigan, al.l but one voted&#13;
&#13;
replenish IDA?                                                                    solidly for the institution, and that one happened to be later our&#13;
&#13;
STANTON: This was the legislation that would involve an increase of               Director of the Budget, Mr. Stockman.           Mr. Stockman was mostly opposed&#13;
&#13;
capitalization for the IFC, not the general Bank capitalization itself.           to international institutions.&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:   Did you yourself run into any problema with your constituents           OLIVER:     If I want to meet soaebody who works in the Committee and&#13;
&#13;
in Ohio because of your strong support of the Bank and IDA?                       Congress to ask more questions of the sort that you and I have been&#13;
&#13;
STANTON: Not that I can remember.     You always found a certain element          talking about, whom should I go tot&#13;
&#13;
of what I would call the right wing -- where the Republican Party would           STANTON:     There is one man above all others, and that is a man called&#13;
&#13;
criticize strong international support.        My constituents never did.     I   Dr. Paul Nelson. Paul bas been director since 1965 of the Banking and&#13;
&#13;
come from one of the top ten export-minded districts in the United                Currency Committee.         I'm sure he would be very happy to talk to you,&#13;
&#13;
States.   We bad in our area, the rubber capital of the world:                    and I'll be glad to set it up.&#13;
&#13;
Goodyear, Goodrich, Firestone; Akron and suburbs.        We had the great         OLIVER:     Are there any questions that I should have asked you and that&#13;
&#13;
chemical shores of southern Lake Erie; in those days, Union Carbide,              I haven't asked you?&#13;
&#13;
Diamond Shamrock. etc.   In addition.   it~s    a large plastic center:           STANTON:     No.     I think perhaps,   it~a   worthwhile, that you read some&#13;
&#13;
products. are sold internationally.                                               Committee Prints 1 have of the transcripts of our Banking Committee and&#13;
&#13;
     A certain element of the Republican party has always strongly                ita involvement with international legislation.           I have some years&#13;
&#13;
supported the World Bank and international institutions. Surprisingly             right here but I       don~t   have all of them.&#13;
&#13;
(this came as a surprise to me), the Number One state in the Union for            OLIVER:     Thia is what, Hearjnga â&#128;¢â&#128;¢&#13;
&#13;
support of international lending institutions is the state of Michigan.           STANTON:     This is all the Hearigu, JU .t.hl Cogpittee .2.f. Banking ..f..!l!l&#13;
&#13;
This was true of Jerry Ford. when he vas Congressmen, Minority Leader             Currency.     I have many years up there (on the bookshelf].            But I   don~t&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
and President of the United States.     It is true today of the ranking           have '66, ;67.        There is a book here of 1960 which is the best one to&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                           19&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
show who wanted the World Bank and wby, the original message of the&#13;
&#13;
Eisenhower administration to the Congreas.     1 had Mr. Clauaen read that&#13;
&#13;
when I first came.     He took it home and read all the marked sections,&#13;
&#13;
so he became familiar with the background.     Aa 1 eay, I will be glad to&#13;
&#13;
set up a meeting with Dr. Nelson.     How long will you be here?&#13;
&#13;
OLIVER:     For another 10 days, and I may very well be back in the fall&#13;
&#13;
sometime.    Well, let me thank you very much officially on the tape for&#13;
&#13;
your kindness and your very good information.     I;ve appreciated your&#13;
&#13;
interview very much.&#13;
&#13;
STANTON:    Well, you're very welcome.&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="18010531">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1986/07/18010531/transcript-oral-history-interview-william-stanton-held-july-16-1986
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1986/07/18010531/transcript-oral-history-interview-william-stanton-held-july-16-1986</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1986/07/18010531/transcript-oral-history-interview-william-stanton-held-july-16-1986</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2008-02-27T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2008-02-27T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2013/07/16/000356161_20130716162310/Rendered/INDEX/791260TRN0Stan0Box0377367B00PUBLIC0.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2013/07/16/000356161_20130716162310/Rendered/PDF/791260TRN0Stan0Box0377367B00PUBLIC0.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2013-07-16T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1986-07-16T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Transcript of oral history interview with
            William Stanton held on July 16, 1986
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            In July 1986, William Stanton was
            interviewed on behalf of the World Bank Group Archives oral
            history program by Robert W. Oliver. During his tenure at
            the Bank from 1983 to 1991, Mr. Stanton worked in the
            following areas: in the office of external affair as senior
            advisor to the vice president (1983-1986) and as acting vice
            president (1987); and in the office of the president as a
            counselor (1986-1991). Beginning in 1964, he spent 18 years
            as representative of the eleventh Congressional District of
            Ohio in the Congress of the United States. His transcript
            concerns the House Banking and Finance Committee and its
            relation to the World Bank Group.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Transcript of oral history interview with
            William Stanton held on July 16, 1986
        </docna>
        <display_title>Transcript of oral history
            interview with William Stanton held on July 16, 1986</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/1986/07/18010531/transcript-oral-history-interview-william-stanton-held-july-16-1986</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Transcript</docty>
        <subtopic>Access to Finance,Banks &amp; Banking Reform,Corporate Law,Debt Markets,Sustainable Land and Crop Management</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Law and Development,Rural Development</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000356161_20130716162310</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>World Bank Group Archives oral history program</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Law and Development,Rural Development</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Board Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Bank capitalization, Bank Holding, banking
            industry, banking structure, banks, bid, capitalization,
            charter, commercial banking, Company, concessionary lending,
            Corporation, Currency, Development Bank, disbursement,
            domestic banking, economic conditions, employee, Federal
            Reserve, hard loan, holding companies, individuals,
            International Development, International Finance,
            international lending, legislation, lending institutions,
            loan, Market countries, soft loans, stockholder, tax,
            Treasury, Union
        </keywd>
        <owner>Knowledge &amp; Information Services (ITSKI)</owner>
        <repnb>79126</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Arts and Culture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation and Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Banks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Retail Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crops</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Checks on Executive Power</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen User Satisfaction Survey</ml:concept><ml:concept>Independent Commissions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ombudsmen</ml:concept><ml:concept>Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Parliament</ml:concept><ml:concept>Procurement Complaints Review Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supreme Audit Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Affairs</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Media</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Treasury</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Mountains</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Accountability Mechanisms</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>