<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>ï»¿                                                                                                       79704&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                         HARRAL Â· WINNER&#13;
                                     Â·                   Â· Â· KLEIN&#13;
                                         Â· THOMPSON Â· SHARP&#13;
                                       MEMORANDUM&#13;
&#13;
                          To: Afghanistan Resource Corridor Team, World Bank&#13;
&#13;
                          From: Jonathan Klein &amp; John Winner&#13;
&#13;
                          Date: June 30, 2012&#13;
&#13;
                          Subject: Success Factors: Rail â&#128;&#147; Truck Terminals In Afghanistan&#13;
&#13;
CLELL G. HARRAL&#13;
4629 Crestline Road       I. Purpose &amp; Organization of Memorandum&#13;
Fort Worth, Texas 76107&#13;
Phone + 1.817.731.9224&#13;
Harral@HWTSKl.com         The purpose of this memorandum is to set out the key success requirements for new terminals&#13;
                          that connect with higher-capacity cargo railways. The terminals discussed are for dry general&#13;
JOHN H. WINNER&#13;
8606 Timber Hill          cargo and for containers that transfer between cargo wagons and highway trucks. The transfer&#13;
Potomac, Maryland         may move between either mode. The railways in mind are those of the Commonwealth of&#13;
                          Independent States in Central Asia, and, in particular, logistics in Afghanistan.1&#13;
20854&#13;
Phone + 1.301.983.9098&#13;
Mob + 1.301.633.8091&#13;
Winner@HWTSK.com&#13;
                          The memorandum is organized as follows: Firstly, different types of terminals are discussed.&#13;
W. H. THOMPSON            This discussion defines what kinds of terminal we are interested, and what kinds we are not.&#13;
Suite 504                 Second, once we have defined just what kinds of terminal we are interested in, we then describe&#13;
                          that kind of terminalâ&#128;&#153;s critical investment construction elements. These elements include both&#13;
1780 Avenue Del Mundo&#13;
Coronado&#13;
California 92118          the â&#128;&#156;hardâ&#128;? and the â&#128;&#156;softâ&#128;? costs of bringing that terminal on-line. Third, once we know the&#13;
Phone + 1.619.437.1167&#13;
Fax + 1.619.437.1167&#13;
                          construction elements, we identify which of these elements are the key investment cost drivers.&#13;
Thompson@HWTSK.co&#13;
m&#13;
                          Fourth, the memorandum takes a detour to describe three key operating cost drivers for successful&#13;
R ICHARD G. SHARP         terminals of almost any kind. We describe these three key operating costs drivers because the&#13;
626 Shelton Street        three are not intuitively visible during the design or construction phases of creating terminal&#13;
Charlotte&#13;
North Carolina 28270&#13;
                          assets. Therefore, these three necessary precedents to design are often neglected. This neglect,&#13;
Phone + 1.704.362.1415    or oversight, is likely when transportation modes are regulated or when public financial&#13;
Mob + 1.703.303.1610&#13;
                          participation is part of the undertaking.&#13;
Sharp@HWTSK.com&#13;
&#13;
JONATHAN H. KLEIN         The fifth step explores the proper role between public and private financing for terminals&#13;
Suite 807&#13;
241 South Sixth Street&#13;
                          contemplated in this memorandum. This financing topic could be an entire concept note in&#13;
Philadelphia              itself; however, we treat it only in the depth required to structure a successful enterprise.&#13;
Pennsylvania 19106&#13;
Phone + 1.215.413.0760&#13;
Mob + 1.215.917.2552      The sixth and final section develops a list of common success and failure factors. This list is to&#13;
Klein@HWTSK.com           assist financiers, designers, and public concessioning agencies in structuring and monitoring new&#13;
JEREM Y DREW&#13;
                          terminal enterprises.&#13;
63 Aberdeen Road&#13;
London N5 2XB&#13;
United Kingdom&#13;
                          The organization of this memorandum corresponds to the specific questions raised by the&#13;
Phone +44.20.7354.3451    Bankâ&#128;&#153;s e-mail of June 19 2012, and following e-mails. The success and failure factors raised&#13;
Mob +44.780.3724.5712     below are sometimes discussed several times to match the structure of the e-mail.&#13;
&#13;
                          1&#13;
                              The analysis in this memorandum is necessarily constrained by its required short length. Because of&#13;
&amp;#12;MEMORANDUM&#13;
Subject: Success Factors:   Rail â&#128;&#147; Truck Terminals In Afghanistan&#13;
Date: June 30, 2012&#13;
Page 2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
II. Types of Rail Terminals&#13;
&#13;
For purposes of this memorandum, it is useful to divide rail terminals into five broad groups. It&#13;
is possible to categorize terminals in other ways; however, for our purposes of defining what we&#13;
are discussing and what we are not discussing, we feel these five groups are the most useful.&#13;
&#13;
    1.   Tank Farms&#13;
    2.   Fuel Distribution&#13;
    3.   Warehouse &amp; General Freight&#13;
    4.   Container, Highway Trailer, Dry Ports&#13;
    5.   Other: Grain, Bulk Transfer, Truck with Driver, etc.&#13;
&#13;
The Bank indicates that the Bank is, at the moment, most interested in the third and fourth&#13;
categories, that of general freight and general containers. General freight includes complete&#13;
motor vehicles, such as trucks, backhoes, automobiles, and military equipment, lashed to flat&#13;
wagons.&#13;
&#13;
Background: Understanding Rail Terminals&#13;
&#13;
A very short description of what is meant by a â&#128;&#156;rail terminalâ&#128;? is useful at this point, along with a&#13;
description of the five categories. The descriptions aid in understanding the specific&#13;
recommendations about what causes success at what kind of terminal, and what causes failure.&#13;
&#13;
By rail terminal, we mean â&#128;&#147; only for the purposes of the memorandum - a place where one or&#13;
many siding or spur tracks branch off a railway to a place where considerable specialized&#13;
infrastructure is built to permit transfer of cargo between highway trucks and railway cargo&#13;
wagons. We do not mean classification yards, marshaling yards, passenger terminals and&#13;
stations, or small cargo houses built into passenger stations. We do not mean sidings that permit&#13;
manufacturing, mining, milling, or refining plants to load directly from their processes or their&#13;
inventory holding points into rail cargo wagons. Instead, we mean a place where a variety of&#13;
highway trucks, often operated by a variety of owners, transfer their cargo into or out of rail&#13;
wagons. Like the highway trucks, these railway wagons may be owned or leased by a variety of&#13;
firms or agencies, and the wagons may be of quite a variety of designs. Very often, the wagons&#13;
and trucks originate from or are destined to a variety of places.&#13;
&#13;
The terminals typically have the following elements:&#13;
&#13;
a. A connection to one or more railways.&#13;
b. A connection to the general highway network.&#13;
c. Various loading or unloading assets, such as ramps, platforms, forklifts, cranes,&#13;
   pumps, pipes, and driveways.&#13;
d. Intermediate storage to hold inventory, such as warehouses, open storage yards,&#13;
   paved parking lots, and tanks.&#13;
               Continued â&#128;¦&#13;
&amp;#12;MEMORANDUM&#13;
Subject: Success Factors:       Rail â&#128;&#147; Truck Terminals In Afghanistan&#13;
Date: June 30, 2012&#13;
Page 3&#13;
&#13;
e. Security, such as lighting, fences, armed guards, fire protection, and drainage.&#13;
f. Procedures â&#128;&#147; preferably automated â&#128;&#147; to keep track of where everything is.&#13;
g. Established tariffs or, alternatively, efficient brokerages, to minimize usersâ&#128;&#153;&#13;
   transactions costs.&#13;
h. Ancillary services, such as Customs, scales for weighing, and for maintenance of&#13;
   equipment.&#13;
&#13;
Other ancillary services are typically provided by establishments outside of the formal&#13;
boundaries of the terminal. These services include truck fuel &amp; repair businesses, banking,&#13;
insurance agents, restaurants, and sleeping quarters. Another service, often invisible to investors,&#13;
is speedy courts to fairly adjudicate disputes and property crimes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      1. Tank	&#13; Â Farms	&#13; Â &#13;
&#13;
A â&#128;&#156;tank farmâ&#128;? has many large tanks that collect&#13;
or distribute various petroleum and natural gas&#13;
products. The combined storage capacity is&#13;
usually well in excess of 10 million liters.&#13;
Each tank may be dedicated to a particular&#13;
product, such as diesel fuel, various grades of&#13;
gasoline, kerosene/aircraft fuel, and heating oil.&#13;
The product arrives by rail, is stored in a tank,&#13;
and is then distributed by large trucks or rail&#13;
wagons. Alternatively, trucks and small&#13;
pipelines may bring petroleum or natural gas to&#13;
the terminalâ&#128;&#153;s tanks, where it is aggregated, and&#13;
then it loaded into rail wagons for movement&#13;
to a refinery.2 Afghanistan has such terminals at the Port of Hairatan. Railway tank farms often&#13;
use barges and pipelines as well as trucks.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      2. Fuel	&#13; Â Distribution	&#13; Â &#13;
&#13;
Fuel distribution terminals typically retail or wholesale fuels to end users or smaller retailers,&#13;
often in small amounts. The fuels may be of a wide variety. The fuel may include LPG or LNG&#13;
gas, coal of many sizes and grades, heating oil, gasoline and diesel fuel, and even charcoal. The&#13;
terminalâ&#128;&#153;s operator â&#128;&#147; or â&#128;&#156;dealerâ&#128;? â&#128;&#147; buys the fuels on its own account, stores it, and then hopes&#13;
to resell it to urban or regional users at a profit. Fuel distribution terminals are usually smaller&#13;
than tank farms. These terminals are indispensible for local and regional economic growth&#13;
because the dealers provide efficient transport of fuel for smaller users, down to the household&#13;
level of the ubiquitous 12.5-kilo or even 5-kilo canister of cooking gas. Small industries, from&#13;
local blacksmiths to farmers to manufacturers, have ready access to coal and distillate fuels&#13;
provided by these terminals. The lowered cost of cooking fuels does a great deal to prevent&#13;
deforestation and improve the condition of women.3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
2&#13;
    See, for example: http://www.aslrra.org/images/news_file/iowa_northern_transportation_partnership.pdf&#13;
3&#13;
    For example, see http://www.iocl.com/Products/Indanegas.aspx&#13;
&amp;#12;MEMORANDUM&#13;
Subject: Success Factors:      Rail â&#128;&#147; Truck Terminals In Afghanistan&#13;
Date: June 30, 2012&#13;
Page 4&#13;
&#13;
Some â&#128;&#156;dealersâ&#128;? have become quite large enterprises, with wide distribution. Examples include&#13;
Indane in India and Amerigas or Blue Rhino in the United States.&#13;
&#13;
    3. Warehouse	&#13; Â &amp;	&#13; Â General	&#13; Â Freight	&#13; Â Rail	&#13; Â Terminals	&#13; Â &#13;
&#13;
Warehouse and general freight terminals are large-scale analogues of fuel terminals, with the&#13;
important difference that the terminal operator does not purchase the material to be distributed&#13;
for its own account. The other difference is that the merchandise is usually packaged. The&#13;
package may be a drum, a box, a pallet, a bag, or a complete farm tractor on four wheels.&#13;
&#13;
                                              Intermediate storage is provided by large warehouses or&#13;
                                              in well-drained, paved lots. Warehouses may include&#13;
                                              refrigeration or freezers. Warehouses become quite large,&#13;
                                              often up to of 100,000 square meters of floor space.4&#13;
                                              Material handling is usually mechanized, using forklifts&#13;
                                              and cranes. But some handling may be manual where&#13;
                                              labor is expensive and goods arrive loose instead of&#13;
                                              palletized.&#13;
&#13;
Cranes may be provided to unload pipe and other steel products, metal coils, or heavy&#13;
machinery. Ramps may be provided to unload highway, military, farm, and construction&#13;
machines. Terminals permit more than transloading from rail and trucks of packaged&#13;
merchandise stored in warehouses. Logistics firms use these terminals to extend the distribution&#13;
reach of their customers.&#13;
&#13;
Many warehousing operations become extensions of customerâ&#128;&#153;s operations, as part of their&#13;
supply chain management. Often goods arriving in batches from different suppliers are stored&#13;
in the warehouse, and then mixtures of these batches are loaded out for distribution to&#13;
customers. Warehouse logistics companies are hired to reassemble orders and shipments from a&#13;
variety of other shipments that may arrive from many locations. This is more than just&#13;
transloading or storing bulk material. Some firms offer final manufacturing and assembly&#13;
services inside the warehouse.&#13;
&#13;
This final manufacturing greatly aids local economic development because it adds semi-skilled&#13;
manufacturing to the economic activity of the region. On the other hand, mere order-assembly&#13;
may replace local wholesalers and local handicraft industries, such as the ironworkers and&#13;
millworkers in Northern Afghanistan. But the lowered cost of raw material that a general&#13;
warehouse provides, generally aids local manufacturing.&#13;
&#13;
By now, it should be obvious that effective warehousing and general freight operations requires a commercially&#13;
nimble, flexible, globalized management. The management must have a strong sales and IT component with&#13;
global and national sales agents.&#13;
&#13;
Are sea containers part of general warehouse and distribution terminals? The useful answer is&#13;
â&#128;&#156;noâ&#128;?. A sea container may arrive and depart at a warehouse, but the container arrives upon a&#13;
highway truck chassis, even if only after a short drive. The container is, practically speaking,&#13;
undistinguishable from an ordinary highway truck.&#13;
&#13;
4&#13;
 North American experience is that 1 million square feet under one roof, or 100,000 square meters, is the&#13;
practical limit for even the most sophisticated management.&#13;
&amp;#12;MEMORANDUM&#13;
Subject: Success Factors:       Rail â&#128;&#147; Truck Terminals In Afghanistan&#13;
Date: June 30, 2012&#13;
Page 5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
A sea container terminal may be right next-door to the general warehouse terminal. But their&#13;
operators and owners needed not be the same, while some common assets may be shared, e.g.&#13;
connection roads, offices, security, scales, perhaps software. This noted, it might be very useful to&#13;
combine a container terminal with a general freight and warehouse terminal for smaller operations.&#13;
&#13;
    4. Container,	&#13; Â Highway	&#13; Â Trailer,	&#13; Â Dry	&#13; Â Ports	&#13; Â &#13;
&#13;
Container, highway trailer, and dry ports specialize in taking sea containers and highway trailers&#13;
on and off railway flatcars using specialized cranes or loaders. The containers or trailers are de-&#13;
facto boxes or pallets, only of a truckload size and weight. Indeed, they are often called â&#128;&#156;boxesâ&#128;?.&#13;
The containers or trailers are stored out-of-doors in large lots, until owners of the merchandise&#13;
claim their boxes. Often, shippers will deliver their boxes to await shipment on an outbound&#13;
train (or ship or barge). Or, the empty boxes may be stacked to await a customer. The boxes&#13;
are typically owned by steamship or logistics companies. Highway trailers are owned by logistics&#13;
companies or motor freight companies.&#13;
&#13;
Physical assets include long railway tracks to assemble cost-efficient trains to be loaded with&#13;
many boxes, often from fifty to two hundred containers on one train. Other assets include&#13;
expensive loading cranes and huge forklifts, paving, land, security to prevent theft because the&#13;
containers often are packed with imported consumer goods, and â&#128;&#156;paperworkâ&#128;? that is&#13;
characterized by an absence of actual paper, bureaucratic approvals, and customs processing.&#13;
Containers are preferred where speed of movement over long-distances is paramount; therefore,&#13;
interminable delays while paperwork is processed defeats the purpose of the terminal.&#13;
&#13;
A container terminal may include a small, conventional warehouse to permit local enterprises or&#13;
local agricultural cooperatives to â&#128;&#156;stuffâ&#128;? or â&#128;&#156;unstuffâ&#128;? a container prior to the containerâ&#128;&#153;s delivery&#13;
to a wagon or to a highway chassis.&#13;
&#13;
    5. Other:	&#13; Â Grain,	&#13; Â Refrigerated,	&#13; Â Other	&#13; Â Terminals.	&#13; Â &#13;
&#13;
There are many other kinds of terminals. These are specialized,&#13;
and require large volumes to be efficient. These terminals include&#13;
grain terminals that gather or distribute soybeans, wheat, flour, and&#13;
corn. In some cases, agricultural produce is gathered by truck into&#13;
a specialized terminal, often for processing as well as shipment.&#13;
These agricultural terminals are often cooperatives of users,&#13;
farmers, or buyers. The cooperatives may own or operate the&#13;
terminals.&#13;
&#13;
In North America, railroads operate specialized terminals to unload&#13;
privately-owned or leased rail wagons of bulk material â&#128;&#147; plastic&#13;
pellets, sugar, flour, chemicals, fuels, cement â&#128;&#147; directly into waiting&#13;
trucks. Some firms even â&#128;&#156;dealâ&#128;? by distributing such products from&#13;
rail cars right into waiting customersâ&#128;&#153; trucks, using the specialized&#13;
wagons as a temporary â&#128;&#156;tank farmâ&#128;?, or as a warehouse silo to retail their products.&#13;
&amp;#12;MEMORANDUM&#13;
Subject: Success Factors:         Rail â&#128;&#147; Truck Terminals In Afghanistan&#13;
Date: June 30, 2012&#13;
Page 6&#13;
&#13;
The list of different terminals could be extended;5 however, for the purposes of economic&#13;
resource growth corridors, the above discussion should suffice.6&#13;
&#13;
Critical investment elements are assets necessary for successful operation, but whose prices must&#13;
be managed. At the outset, we note that terminals located at distant ends of machinery&#13;
maintenance supply chains, should acquire machinery assets based upon reliability rather than&#13;
based upon initial price. This is fundamental for container terminals where shippers rely on fast,&#13;
reliable service rather than ragged, undependable, but low-price service.&#13;
&#13;
Critical investment elements that are common both to warehouse and general freight terminals&#13;
and to container terminals are now discussed. Then, investment elements important to each&#13;
terminal type are described. Finally, investment elements that are not critical to control in&#13;
magnitude, but which are necessary, are noted.&#13;
&#13;
a. Start-up and Working Capital, Sales program:&#13;
   Salaries and travel expenses, such as training the local operations and maintenance&#13;
   staff, developing sales and clients, a vigorous advertising campaign, and deploying&#13;
   information technologies are all necessary investments for a terminal that will&#13;
   promote economic development. The paramount asset to invest in is the ability to sell the&#13;
   services offered by the terminal.&#13;
&#13;
       Training includes training in loss and damage prevention, including small scale and&#13;
       large scale theft losses.&#13;
&#13;
b. Land, if purchased or leased:&#13;
   Land is not only required for the warehouse building, but also for railway tracks,&#13;
   roads, parking lots, and storage lots. Land ought to be acquired for future expansion&#13;
   during the initial construction. Land prices can vary markedly. In general, the&#13;
   cheaper the land, the further this land is from the end consumer of cargo&#13;
   transportation, and, therefore, the less likely the end a consumer will move its goods&#13;
   through a terminal.&#13;
&#13;
c.     Site preparation:&#13;
       Site preparation can be considerable, depending on the site. If removal and&#13;
       replacing of soil and rock to the depth of only 0.5 meter is required, and then the&#13;
       surface is paved, the cost in the United States is perhaps US$700,000 to $800,000&#13;
       per hectare. Where substantial excavation or compacted fill is required, the cost can&#13;
       exceeded $1 million per hectare. To this must be added the cost of drainage for&#13;
       sudden, heavy storms: Mazar-i-Sharifâ&#128;&#153;s airport in April 2009 experienced 25 cm of&#13;
       rain.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
5&#13;
     http://www.transnetportterminals.net/PortTerminals.asp?Terminal=16&#13;
6&#13;
  Europe has attempted to develop terminals where highway truck drivers load their trucks and trailers onto flatcars,&#13;
and then accompany the trucks and trailers overnight. The European use of straight-body trucks towing trailers makes&#13;
the use of highway trailer-only terminals â&#128;&#147; such as North American TOFC â&#128;&#147; often infeasible. North America has vast&#13;
terminals that have the sole purpose of moving thousands of smaller motor vehicles by specialized, efficient wagons.&#13;
Factories or ocean ports load the cars onto the wagons, which are then moved considerable distances to these&#13;
specialized distribution terminals. The terminals load specialized highway trailers to take new cars and new trucks to&#13;
local new car dealerships.&#13;
&amp;#12;MEMORANDUM&#13;
Subject: Success Factors:       Rail â&#128;&#147; Truck Terminals In Afghanistan&#13;
Date: June 30, 2012&#13;
Page 7&#13;
&#13;
d. Railway Infrastructure:&#13;
   Connections to the railway may require traffic control signals or a second track, as&#13;
   well as the expensive switches and the actual tracks within the terminal. A fast,&#13;
   heavy-duty #11 switch connecting to the main line costs over $150,000 in the&#13;
   United States. If a traffic control signaling junction is required, the cost may be on&#13;
   the order of US$1 million. It is unlikely that the trains operating on lines in&#13;
   Afghanistan would require complex traffic control. The terminal itself may require a&#13;
   few switches and considerable track.&#13;
&#13;
e.     Highway and Road Infrastructure:&#13;
       Highway and road infrastructure includes both the large number of hectares of&#13;
       paved area within the terminal and the wide highways needed to provide highway&#13;
       access to the terminal. Failure to provide swift highway access results in congestion,&#13;
       driving up the real price of shipping via the terminal. Paved areas within the&#13;
       terminal must sustain very heavy loads, not only of trucks, but also of loaded cranes.&#13;
&#13;
f.     The warehouse building:&#13;
       A one-hectare starter warehouse with loading docks would cost approximately&#13;
       US$6.5 million in non-urban areas of North America, including design and&#13;
       construction services.7&#13;
&#13;
g. Machinery, Equipment &amp; Spare Parts.&#13;
   Forklifts, trucks, cranes, perhaps pumps and hoses, truckload scales, high-capacity&#13;
   pallet racks, and a copious supply of spare parts are required for smooth operation.&#13;
   A small container terminal requires a side loading, mobile container packer that will&#13;
   cost between $380,000 and $420,000, new with parts &amp; a training program. To this&#13;
   must be added shipping, local assembly, &amp; insurance. The ability to unload and load&#13;
   pipe and other steel mill products, lumber, concrete culverts, and large crates&#13;
   requires a rough-terrain forklift that, with parts and training, will cost upwards of&#13;
   $190,000, plus shipping, local assembly, and insurance. This forklift would have a&#13;
   capacity to lift 15 metric tonnes.&#13;
&#13;
       In addition to this major machinery, warehouses require forklifts and pallet jacks.&#13;
       Container yards require container chassis in some number, along with several&#13;
       tractors to move the container chassis both in the yard and to deliver containers to&#13;
       local businesses.&#13;
&#13;
       Any terminal that involves trucking in Afghanistan requires a small asphalt roller,&#13;
       pick-up trucks and a stake body truck, and even a small backhoe to maintain the&#13;
       other assets.&#13;
&#13;
       While the cost of each machine or vehicle is not large, in the aggregate, several&#13;
       million dollars may be required to efficiently equip a terminal, train the employees&#13;
       safely, and supply parts to maintain the assets.&#13;
&#13;
       Very bad weather is too-often not taken in account when purchasing machinery and&#13;
       equipment. Weather abnormalities include sub-zero temperature, over-heating of&#13;
&#13;
7&#13;
     Construction costs are approximately $60 per square foot.&#13;
&amp;#12;MEMORANDUM&#13;
Subject: Success Factors:    Rail â&#128;&#147; Truck Terminals In Afghanistan&#13;
Date: June 30, 2012&#13;
Page 8&#13;
&#13;
     equipment in the summer, snow-plowing and snow piling, and especially frequent dust&#13;
     storms.&#13;
&#13;
Land â&#128;&#156;zonedâ&#128;?, or carefully set aside, for support services, such as truck fuel and repair stations,&#13;
restaurants, hotels and guest houses, mosque, and so forth are not an investment element. This&#13;
land will be developed privately. But for a terminal to be successful, land must be identified by&#13;
the local authorities, then set aside to provide these ancillary services in a scheme that reduces local&#13;
road congestion.&#13;
&#13;
Other assets are critical to success. But these assets are not costly to acquire, and may be used&#13;
jointly between general cargo and containers. These assets include:&#13;
&#13;
h. Software and telecom, especially:&#13;
   Â§ï&#130;§ reliable connections for e-commerce;&#13;
   Â§ï&#130;§ packaged software to locate shipments, expedite customs and duties&#13;
   Â§ï&#130;§ reliable specialized software to connect to logistics firms and to connect to&#13;
       railwaysâ&#128;&#153; shipment tracking databases;&#13;
&#13;
i.   Security lighting; guard stations; fencing and crash barriers; cameras; fire protection;&#13;
     emergency generators;&#13;
&#13;
j.   Utilities and offices, other general construction.&#13;
&#13;
         Unseen Asset: The Container Railroad Investment Asset&#13;
&#13;
One major asset required for a successful container, highway trailer, or dry port, is not visible at&#13;
the terminal. This asset is a railway infrastructure capable of moving containers, etc. more&#13;
efficiently over long distances than highway trucks can move them. The railway must have the&#13;
large axle and loading gauges that permit the use of efficient net-to-tare wagons, the deployment&#13;
of powerful locomotives, and operations at speeds typically of 80 km/hour or better. Finally,&#13;
container trains must have sufficient size to avoid the delays of intermediate switching in&#13;
marshaling yards; trains must operate terminal-to-terminal. No matter how efficient the assets of&#13;
a dry port or container terminal is, the operating practices and infrastructure of the railway&#13;
connecting the terminals will govern the success or failure of the terminal.&#13;
&#13;
IV. Key Investment Cost Drivers&#13;
&#13;
Key investment drivers are defined to be parameters that accelerate or delay completion of a rail&#13;
to truck terminal. These parameters are often determined by the government or non-&#13;
government funding agency. The parameters affect the basic cost of capital; the amount of&#13;
capital it will take to build the terminal; the risk premium the capital will demand for uncertainty&#13;
about commercial success; the risk premium the capital will demand for security issues; and,&#13;
mostly importantly, the amount of time that construction work-in-progress must be financed&#13;
while regulatory, zoning, social approval, licensing, security, and other government decisions are&#13;
being made.&#13;
&#13;
Government may choose to see its role as an inhibitor or as a facilitator. The more&#13;
governmental and non-governmental units act to reduce uncertainty in the very uncertain&#13;
environment of Afghanistan, the lower the investment costs will be, and the greater the success&#13;
&amp;#12;MEMORANDUM&#13;
Subject: Success Factors:   Rail â&#128;&#147; Truck Terminals In Afghanistan&#13;
Date: June 30, 2012&#13;
Page 9&#13;
&#13;
of the investment will be. Success includes both the return on capital and the quality of the lives&#13;
of the people.&#13;
&#13;
The first driver is sheer size and complexity of the terminal. If a government requires&#13;
overbuilding â&#128;&#147; huge size, huge complexity â&#128;&#147; the basic cost of construction will rise accordingly.&#13;
For example, the operator or owner may be required to build a cold storage warehouse, which is&#13;
both expensive to build and difficult to obtain cheap operational electricity for. Local demand&#13;
should drive the size and nature of facilities rather than long-range national ambitions.&#13;
&#13;
Procurement processes drive investment cost. Cumbersome, lengthy procurement processes&#13;
instead of a private Design-Build-Operate-Maintain process often drive up investment costs.&#13;
The more complex the process, the more uncertainty is introduced about the eventual length of&#13;
the process. It is clearly ironic that the use of generalized performance specifications instead of&#13;
product â&#128;&#156;hardwareâ&#128;? specifications may increase costs significantly in circumstances such as&#13;
Afghanistan.6 The generalized specifications create uncertainty about what is or is not&#13;
acceptable. Generalized specifications encourage many low-bid proposals. Many of the low-bid&#13;
proposals barely meet the required performance, or may prove, and quickly prove, unable meet&#13;
the durability and reliability required by the actual operations. The government may respond by&#13;
using consulting engineers who â&#128;&#156;gold plateâ&#128;? performance specifications far beyond what a&#13;
private sector firm would ever build. The consulting engineers may also write the use of cost-&#13;
efficient, late-model used machinery out of the specification.&#13;
&#13;
Approval processes drive investment costs. Involving many stakeholders in the process of&#13;
granting permits, it may be argued as a heuristic, increases both the variability in final approval&#13;
time and the total approval time. The increase in time may be in direct proportion to the&#13;
increase in stakeholder numbers. Uncertainty increases the cost of capital â&#128;&#147; and not all capital is&#13;
supplied by the builder of the terminal â&#128;&#147; and approval time increases the amount of time&#13;
construction must be financed. Thus, stakeholder involvement should be complete before&#13;
selling the terminal concession or taking bids for construction work.&#13;
&#13;
Security and insurance are cost drivers. Our experience is that insurance requirements â&#128;&#147; liability&#13;
insurance, performance bonds, casualty insurance, irrevocable Letters of Credit for advanced&#13;
funds â&#128;&#147; often reduce costs by eliminating unqualified or marginal contractors for environments&#13;
where risks are well-understood and small. In well-understood, less-risky environments, the&#13;
more that qualified bidders sense that unqualified bidders are eliminated, then the more&#13;
aggressive these qualified bidders will become in their pricing. However, the risks entailed by the&#13;
security situation in Afghanistan may make the cost of insurance prohibitive, and such insurance&#13;
requirements may be very counter-productive.&#13;
&#13;
Finally, social programs may drive costs upwards, often to prohibitive levels. Examples of these&#13;
programs include:&#13;
&#13;
a. requiring the use of local human resources where these resources do not exist â&#128;&#147; as&#13;
   opposed to training local residents;&#13;
b. requiring lengthy analysis of environmental impacts and the impacts on&#13;
   disadvantaged groups, such as women, when the prima-facie evidence is that the&#13;
   impact will be minimal or beneficial;&#13;
c. reducing carbon emissions by requiring the use of state-of-the-art technologies in&#13;
   operating environments that have grave difficulty in maintaining even the most basic&#13;
   of technologies;&#13;
&amp;#12;MEMORANDUM&#13;
Subject: Success Factors:       Rail â&#128;&#147; Truck Terminals In Afghanistan&#13;
Date: June 30, 2012&#13;
Page 10&#13;
&#13;
d. giving precedent to local zoning and land use policies that are more restrictive than&#13;
   national regulations; and&#13;
e. requiring extensive, exhaustive efforts to explore for, then preserve, cultural assets of&#13;
   significance using state-of-the-art techniques;&#13;
&#13;
We understand that procurement processes and that social programs may be of paramount&#13;
importance. All these efforts may be eminently desirable. However, the efforts come at a cost,&#13;
and the cost may reach prohibitive levels.&#13;
&#13;
A final investment cost driver is corruption. Corruptionâ&#128;&#153;s costs have been explored many times&#13;
before. This memorandum need not dwell upon its well-understood pernicious effects.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
V. Key Operating Cost Drivers&#13;
&#13;
Key operating cost drivers is defined to be parameters that increase the costs of operating a rail&#13;
to truck terminal. The increase in costs either generates the need for a subsidy or requires higher&#13;
tariffs. Afghanistanâ&#128;&#153;s government can ill-afford the financial drain of a subsidy. High tariffs&#13;
dissuade corridor growth. Therefore, minimizing these key cost drivers is a success or failure&#13;
factor.&#13;
&#13;
These operating cost drivers are often determined by the government and, sometimes, by the&#13;
funders. Government may choose to see its role as an inhibitor or as a facilitator by how it&#13;
treats these operating cost drivers. Three of these drivers are discussed here. The three drivers&#13;
are tariff arrangements; railway operating plan; and terminal layout and industrial engineering.&#13;
Funders may greatly influence the latter two drivers.&#13;
&#13;
a. Railway Tariffs: The First Node on the Critical Path&#13;
   The rate that the railways charge for moving wagons of general cargo and containers to and&#13;
   from the terminal is the first cost element of any terminal. The rate also applies to the&#13;
   movement of empty wagons, and to the hourly/daily rental of wagons and containers while&#13;
   on the terminalâ&#128;&#153;s land.8&#13;
&#13;
      There may be several railways involved in tariffs as it is quite likely that all the wagons&#13;
      arriving at a terminal â&#128;&#147; except for coal and other fuels â&#128;&#147; will originate or terminate in another&#13;
      nation. While the total tariff to move goods over two railways may be adequate, the division&#13;
      of this rate may not be adequate for one of the partners. This causes the financially-&#13;
      aggrieved partner to balk at providing quality services.&#13;
&#13;
      Demand for a given quality of service depends on price. It is imperative that pricing for all parts&#13;
      of railway transportation â&#128;&#147; wagon hire, transportation charges, and division of tariffs â&#128;&#147; be contractually&#13;
      agreed to before anyone makes any designs.9 How big a terminal is justified depends on demand,&#13;
      and demand depends upon pricing. Otherwise, a connecting railway may charge prohibitive&#13;
      rates after the sunk-cost of the terminal is made.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
8&#13;
    The usual term for this rental is â&#128;&#156;demurrageâ&#128;?.&#13;
9&#13;
 CIS railways generally have published tariffs approved by an independent regulatory body; they also&#13;
have pre-arranged, negotiated (and regulated) agreements between nationsâ&#128;&#153; railways that dictate tariffs.&#13;
&amp;#12;MEMORANDUM&#13;
Subject: Success Factors:   Rail â&#128;&#147; Truck Terminals In Afghanistan&#13;
Date: June 30, 2012&#13;
Page 11&#13;
&#13;
     â&#128;¢   Large, global logistics firms may have the ability to negotiate firm, favorable&#13;
         rates based upon the volume of business the firm can offer not only to&#13;
         Afghanistan, but to other destinations.&#13;
     â&#128;¢   A military entity may find itself with enough marketplace leverage to influence&#13;
         pricing.&#13;
     â&#128;¢   Building a northern Afghani rail network that connects to two or more nationsâ&#128;&#153;&#13;
         railways yields some negotiating leverage.&#13;
&#13;
b. Railway Operating Plan As Part of Due Diligence Analysis&#13;
   Railways' operating plans is another node on the initial critical path to build a terminal. Too&#13;
   often, yards, stations, and terminals are designed and built by one party without having a&#13;
   definite idea how the yard, station or terminal will integrate into the general railway&#13;
   operation. The result is higher-than-necessary operating costs because of train delays,&#13;
   backhauls, and unnecessary switching. Too often, civil engineers design and build a rail&#13;
   facility, then abandon it to an operator to figure out how to make it work. Alternatively,&#13;
   railway operating managers, conservative by necessity, will typically design what they&#13;
   understand well, even if it is overbuilt and obsolete. Developing a rationalized operating&#13;
   plan mitigates these untoward tendencies&#13;
&#13;
     The operating plan, as part of due diligence efforts, should include when and how often the&#13;
     connecting railway(s) will visit the terminal. For general cargo, the key marshaling yards,&#13;
     frequency of trains â&#128;&#147; three times a week, daily, twice daily, etc. â&#128;&#147; and maximum number of&#13;
     wagons that can be delivered by one train needs to be known to create an efficient,&#13;
     minimum investment that is effective.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
VI. Role of Government&#13;
&#13;
The role of government is to provide what governments provide best, which are:&#13;
&#13;
Â§ï&#130;§   public goods in insecure times, especially security and roads;&#13;
Â§ï&#130;§   predictability about laws and regulations;&#13;
Â§ï&#130;§   and eliminating uncertainty about what is acceptable to the public, its governmental&#13;
     units, and what is not acceptable.&#13;
&#13;
We specifically recommend that governments focus on the issues given below. These issues,&#13;
taken one at a time, form a virtual template for what might be part of a contract or Agreement&#13;
between a private entity contemplating constructing and operating a terminal and a national&#13;
government. These issues may find use in evaluating the suitability of a loan to an entity seeking&#13;
to create a terminal.&#13;
&#13;
a. Providing Quality Land&#13;
   The land may be provided under long-term leases or reversionary leases. The land must&#13;
   have good title to it, with no legacy disputes as to ownership or tribal encumbrances.&#13;
   The land must be chosen because of its proximity to users rather than reasons of&#13;
   nepotism.&#13;
&#13;
b. Congestion Reduction &amp; Highway Connection:&#13;
   This has two aspects:&#13;
   (1) Zoning or effective land use controls to permit ancillary developments around&#13;
&amp;#12;MEMORANDUM&#13;
Subject: Success Factors:   Rail â&#128;&#147; Truck Terminals In Afghanistan&#13;
Date: June 30, 2012&#13;
Page 12&#13;
&#13;
         the terminal; and&#13;
     (2) Good road access to alleviate congestion.&#13;
&#13;
c.   Reliable utilities:&#13;
     These include electric power, water, and waste water treatment. It may be necessary for&#13;
     the terminal to provide some of these itself. Also critical are reliable telecommunications&#13;
     that are secure from eves dropping or interruption.&#13;
&#13;
d. Security:&#13;
   This is security outside the gates of the terminal. It also includes in assisting with&#13;
   security inside the terminal.&#13;
&#13;
e.   Local Cooperation:&#13;
     The government provides access to and acceptance by helping operators and investors&#13;
     understand local power structures and accommodating informal local interests.&#13;
&#13;
f.   Permits and Approvals:&#13;
     The government provides short-and-sure permitting and licensing for construction and&#13;
     for associated work permits and visas. These are expected of a government that is&#13;
     seeking operators and investors, or even just firms willing to ship goods to Afghanistan&#13;
     or purchase from Afghan people. The government provides a complete, exhaustive list&#13;
     of such permits and licenses, with the requisite details, agreeing that anything not on this&#13;
     list, will not become the responsibility of the constructors, owners, lenders, or operators,&#13;
     and will not cause delays.&#13;
&#13;
g.   Rail Connection:&#13;
     The government facilitates quick construction of rail access line, terminal tracks inside&#13;
     the fence, and storage tracks if the railway is owned or operated by the government. If a&#13;
     third party owns or operates the railway, the government expedites construction and&#13;
     licenses.&#13;
&#13;
h. Adjudication:&#13;
   The government provides reliable, predictable courts that settle disputes fairly and on&#13;
   commonly accepted commercial terms. The government treats theft as a major crime,&#13;
   and provides local police assistance in apprehending suspects and recovering stolen&#13;
   goods. The government not only accepts responsibility for adequate adjudication, but&#13;
   also can point to specific law enforcement and court precedents at the time a terminal is&#13;
   planned. The adjudication is consistent with general terms of carriage used by other&#13;
   nations.&#13;
&amp;#12;MEMORANDUM&#13;
Subject: Success Factors:      Rail â&#128;&#147; Truck Terminals In Afghanistan&#13;
Date: June 30, 2012&#13;
Page 13&#13;
&#13;
VII. Public and Private Sector Financing&#13;
&#13;
There is a natural question of public financing for what is often a private enterprise. Afghanistan&#13;
is a nation in transition; therefore, public finance may play a more significant role than in mature&#13;
market economies. Public financing is also desirable to induce the public sector to cooperate in&#13;
making a terminal a success by giving the government a stake in the successful outcome.&#13;
&#13;
Our financing recommendations, in light of the Resource Growth Corridor initiative, are&#13;
&#13;
a. Highways, Roads and Utilities:&#13;
   At the present, these should be public because of security problems and common, joint use&#13;
   of infrastructure.&#13;
&#13;
b. Rail Infrastructure:&#13;
   If government now owns rail infrastructure, new railway construction should be publicly&#13;
   funded. The funding should be by the railway unit itself so that the railway has a financial&#13;
   stake in the successful outcome of the enterprise. This may extend to leasing container&#13;
   wagons.&#13;
&#13;
c.    Warehouses and Container Yards:&#13;
      These may be public if they are basic and general purpose, e.g. â&#128;&#156;dryâ&#128;? facilities, and can be&#13;
      readily leased to many parties. However, private capital tends to build a more efficient&#13;
      successful warehouse that is sized to the likely market.&#13;
&#13;
d. Security:&#13;
   Basic security during construction should be public, and publicly paid for. The government,&#13;
   both national and local, should have a financial stake in a successful outcome. The expense&#13;
   of providing security appears to a natural public contribution to construction. It does not&#13;
   present the threats to national sovereignty that private â&#128;&#147; or even specially hired public10 â&#128;&#147;&#13;
   military forces present. Security within the terminal gates should be private once operations&#13;
   commence, but outside the terminal, security remains publicly provided.&#13;
&#13;
e.    Land:&#13;
      Public land may be leased at attractive terms to the terminal enterprise as a method of&#13;
      reducing the cost of capital. However, it is not recommended that public land be given or&#13;
      leased at nominal rates. If the terminal obtains land for virtually free, there are two&#13;
      untoward results.&#13;
       i.   The terminal now enjoys an unnatural advantage over its competitors,&#13;
            including competing modes; and&#13;
      ii.   The governments have less of a stake in the financial success of the enterprise.&#13;
            An enterprise that already provides a legal, steady cash income to government&#13;
            may discourage government from taking irrational steps to harm the&#13;
            enterprise.&#13;
&#13;
The rest should be private for reasons that are implicit in the preceding sections. Experienced&#13;
private logistics firms are more likely to have access to marketing and sales, successful software,&#13;
existing shippers, and other soft assets. Private entities usually know what designs are successful,&#13;
how to staff these terminals, and do not over-build. They can purchase reliable, used equipment&#13;
&#13;
10&#13;
     These for-hire public armies often become â&#128;&#156;warlordâ&#128;? armies as time passes.&#13;
&amp;#12;MEMORANDUM&#13;
Subject: Success Factors:    Rail â&#128;&#147; Truck Terminals In Afghanistan&#13;
Date: June 30, 2012&#13;
Page 14&#13;
&#13;
because of their flexible procurement processes. Above all, these logistics firms are likely to be&#13;
order-seekers rather than order-takers; that is, the private firms are most likely to aggressively&#13;
seek out customers and economic growth around Afghanistan and around the regional Asian&#13;
economies, if not around the globe.&#13;
&#13;
VIII. Typical Success and Failure Factors&#13;
&#13;
The preceding sections of this memorandum have touched upon many factors that encourage or&#13;
inhibit successful terminals in the environment of a developing economy with weak public&#13;
infrastructure, limited commercial experience, and grave security problems.&#13;
&#13;
This section, the final section, creates a catalogue of these and other aspects of terminals,&#13;
whether container, dry cargo warehouse, or others, that cause a terminal to fail in the objectives&#13;
of profitability and of inducing local economic growth along a resource corridor. This section&#13;
will be straightforward and frank in its discussion. It is not a list of everything that can go&#13;
wrong; instead, this section focuses on commonly made mistakes.&#13;
	&#13; Â &#13;
Too Grand An Initial Design&#13;
National administrations and their donors/lenders often construct far too grand an initial&#13;
investment. The resulting fixed costs and maintenance requirements overwhelm budgets and&#13;
generate crippling debt service requirements. Success is building small and then operating&#13;
multiple shifts rather than constructing monuments to national ambition or funder pride.&#13;
&#13;
Build small does not mean building light-duty. As to specific examples: It means that a container&#13;
terminal should have tracks to handle fifty wagons with 25 tonne axle gauge rather than tracks to&#13;
handle one hundred wagons with 22.5 tonne axle gauge. It means designing for fifty 53â&#128;&#153;&#13;
modern containers per day rather than three hundred increasingly obsolete 40â&#128;&#153; containers per&#13;
day.&#13;
&#13;
Favoritism in Granting Concession or Building Rights:&#13;
Political savvy is not a substitute for commercial savvy where highway competition exists. The&#13;
choice of land, operators, contractors, IT, and equipment requires economic objectivity if the&#13;
terminal is to be competitive. Economic irrationality and corruption are contagious in a project;&#13;
it is unrealistic to expect to compartmentalization of corruption or nepotism.&#13;
&#13;
Economic Discrimination to Protect Cartels:&#13;
Economic discrimination is another aspect of favoritism. In this instance, selected facilities and&#13;
services are prohibited from competing to protect other interests, such as existing terminals or a&#13;
trucking cartel. Economic irrationality and corruption are contagious in a project; it is unrealistic&#13;
to expect to compartmentalization of irrationality.&#13;
&amp;#12;MEMORANDUM&#13;
Subject: Success Factors:       Rail â&#128;&#147; Truck Terminals In Afghanistan&#13;
Date: June 30, 2012&#13;
Page 15&#13;
&#13;
                                               Investing in Large Immobile Assets:&#13;
                                          Container and yard cranes are an example of investing in&#13;
                                          immobilized and often obsolete assets. These assets are&#13;
                                          more difficult to redeploy and hence finance, become&#13;
                                          obsolete quickly, and may have higher initial purchase&#13;
                                          costs. Below is a photograph of two forms of container&#13;
                                          and yard gantry cranes. The yellow-painted model side&#13;
                                          loader container straddle crane is highly mobile, has&#13;
                                          available late-model â&#128;&#156;usedâ&#128;? versions for sale, and can be&#13;
                                          driven anywhere in the terminal yard. The gantry cranes,&#13;
                                          on the&#13;
                                          other&#13;
hand, are the standard Soviet models used&#13;
throughout the Soviet economy, tied to its fixed&#13;
tramway at Hairatan. The photograph at&#13;
Hairatan includes three cranes: Two â&#128;&#156;dinosaurâ&#128;?&#13;
fixed gantry cranes, and a third construction&#13;
crane brought in for its flexibility and versatility.&#13;
The three Soviet models are visually impressive,&#13;
but one mobile side loader crane does the work&#13;
faster.&#13;
&#13;
Location:&#13;
Sites must be chosen that are close to the end-user, otherwise the local trucking costs, sometime&#13;
called â&#128;&#156;drayageâ&#128;?, can be so high as to throw the entire idea of rail to truck terminals into&#13;
economic question.11&#13;
&#13;
Proper location may require relocation of existing businesses and residences. Relocation costs&#13;
money and is socially disruptive. This is just an unavoidable fact. However, the alternative of&#13;
putting the right thing in the wrong place can be a fatal mistake. Transport is about location,&#13;
about moving goods from one location to another, desired location. A railroad terminal in an&#13;
undesired location defeats the entire purpose of the effort.&#13;
	&#13; Â 	&#13; Â &#13;
Congestion: General&#13;
It is well understood that congestion at ports often determines the success or failure of a port, or&#13;
a terminal. The below is a discussion of many congestion-causing delays&#13;
&#13;
Â§ï&#130;§   No Streamlining of Paperwork by the Government:&#13;
     Streamlining paperwork is crucial for success. Simplification and streamlining paperwork to&#13;
     expedite movement is a critical success requirement. No shipment should await external&#13;
     document processing or even electronic approvals before transloading, once an inbound&#13;
     shipment has been cleared for movement from the originating consignor.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
11&#13;
    An example of this is the Hairatan to Mazar-i-Sharif new rail line. The real market is southbound Solang Pass&#13;
traffic. To serve this market, the rail line ought to have gone eastward at Naibabad, substituting another 75 km of&#13;
rail travel for 75 km of truck travel. Instead, the line was routed towards westward towards Mazar, requiring trucks to&#13;
24 km backhaul from Mazar-i-Sharif eastward to Naibabad, thence to resume the trucks journey towards Solang.&#13;
The resulting complex geometry, net, substitutes 75 km of rail travel for only 50 km of truck travel.&#13;
&amp;#12;MEMORANDUM&#13;
Subject: Success Factors:    Rail â&#128;&#147; Truck Terminals In Afghanistan&#13;
Date: June 30, 2012&#13;
Page 16&#13;
&#13;
     A terminal will fail if paperwork is not highly streamlined. Delays are fatal. Terminal capacity&#13;
     will be lost while shipments are cleared. A terminal is a distribution point in a supply chain.&#13;
     A terminal is not a holding entrepot while nations squabble over redundant paperwork and,&#13;
     most regrettably, bribes.&#13;
&#13;
Â§ï&#130;§   Inadequate Local Roads &amp; Highway Investment by the Government:&#13;
     This has been discussed above, and is related to location, zoning, and the provision of land&#13;
     for ancillary services and businesses.&#13;
&#13;
Â§ï&#130;§   Development Agencyâ&#128;&#153;s Civil Engineers vs. Logistics Companyâ&#128;&#153;s Industrial Engineers&#13;
     This success factor is a simplified restatement of what was discussed in above sections. A&#13;
     success terminal has its process flows designed by an experienced logistics firm rather than&#13;
     by civil engineering firms working for donors or for inexperienced governmental agencies.&#13;
&#13;
Commercial Enterprise vs. Government Agency&#13;
Successful terminals are designed, built, and operated by largely private logistics firms and&#13;
railways. There is no direct subsidy except by the adequate provision of public services of&#13;
highways, utilities, courts, and security.&#13;
&#13;
Financing of the logistics company may be through entities such as the International Finance&#13;
Corporation or the EBRD, or partially though the capital grants. But the operator must have a&#13;
strong incentive to see that its own capital is deployed successfully. Finally, the national or local&#13;
governments might have a minority stake in the income stream or concession payments that is a&#13;
percent of net profits so that governments have an incentive to make the project succeed rather&#13;
than hinder it through bureaucratic requirements.&#13;
&#13;
Inadequate Start-Up Capital:&#13;
Funding for a new terminal may often be only for hard construction costs and the costs of&#13;
construction management; that is, the cost of hard assets that can be claimed by a lender or&#13;
grantor in the event of a default.&#13;
&#13;
A successful start-up should include funds for the acquisition of initial equipment, for extensive&#13;
training, for energetic sales efforts and publicity, for copious inventories of spare parts and&#13;
supplies, and to pay for the initial operating losses until volume builds up.&#13;
&#13;
Poor Rail Service:&#13;
Rail service may be infrequent and late for reasons that can be foreseen and mitigated prior&#13;
to commencing construction of a terminal, but often are not. These reasons include:&#13;
&#13;
Â§ï&#130;§   the lack of a good operating plan that has been agreed to by the connecting railways;&#13;
Â§ï&#130;§   a lack of wagons and especially of locomotives, both of which can be leased by the&#13;
     terminal and then the leases serviced by reductions in tariffs charged by the&#13;
     railway(s); and&#13;
Â§ï&#130;§   exploitive tariffs that seek to extract â&#128;&#156;rentsâ&#128;? from the terminal assets, or the lack of&#13;
     any agreed-upon tariffs at all.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 *****&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="18028840">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2012/06/18028840/memorandum-afghanistan-resource-corridor-program
        </url>
        <availablein>Pashto,Dari,English</availablein>
        <fullavailablein>
            <available_in lang="Pashto" entityid="000356161_20130827120651" node_id="18028840"/>
            <available_in lang="Dari" entityid="000356161_20130827120113" node_id="18028840"/>
        </fullavailablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2012/06/18028840/memorandum-afghanistan-resource-corridor-program</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2012/06/18028840/memorandum-afghanistan-resource-corridor-program</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2013-07-23T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2013-07-23T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2013/07/23/000333037_20130723143919/Rendered/INDEX/797040BRI0P1280Box0377384B00PUBLIC0.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2013/07/23/000333037_20130723143919/Rendered/PDF/797040BRI0P1280Box0377384B00PUBLIC0.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2012-06-30T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2013-07-23T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Memorandum for the Afghanistan Resource
            Corridor Program
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The purpose of this memorandum is to set
            out the key success requirements for new terminals that
            connect with higher-capacity cargo railways. The terminals
            discussed are for dry general cargo and for containers that
            transfer between cargo wagons and highway trucks. The
            transfer may move between either mode. The railways in mind
            are those of the Commonwealth of Independent States in
            Central Asia, and, in particular, logistics in Afghanistan.
            The memorandum is organized as follows: firstly, different
            types of terminals are discussed. This discussion defines
            what kinds of terminal we are interested, and what kinds we
            are not. Second, once we have defined just what kinds of
            terminal we are interested in, we then describe that kind of
            terminal's critical investment construction elements.
            These elements include both the 'hard' and the
            'soft' costs of bringing that terminal on-line.
            Third, once author know the construction elements, we
            identify which of these elements are the key investment cost
            drivers. Fourth, the memorandum takes a detour to describe
            three key operating cost drivers for successful terminals of
            almost any kind. This paper describes these three key
            operating costs drivers because the three are not
            intuitively visible during the design or construction phases
            of creating terminal assets. Therefore, these three
            necessary precedents to design are often neglected. This
            neglect, or oversight, is likely when transportation modes
            are regulated or when public financial participation is part
            of the undertaking. The fifth step explores the proper role
            between public and private financing for terminals
            contemplated in this memorandum. This financing topic could
            be an entire concept note in itself; however, the author
            treat it only in the depth required to structure a
            successful enterprise. The sixth and final section develops
            a list of common success and failure factors. This list is
            to assist financiers, designers, and public concession
            agencies in structuring and monitoring new terminal enterprises.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Memorandum for the Afghanistan Resource
            Corridor Program
        </docna>
        <display_title>Memorandum for the Afghanistan
            Resource Corridor Program</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2012/06/18028840/memorandum-afghanistan-resource-corridor-program</listing_relative_url>
        <projn>AF-Afghanistan Resource Corridor Program -- P128211</projn>
        <docty>Working Paper (Numbered Series)</docty>
        <subtopic>Transport Economics Policy &amp; Planning,Common Carriers Industry,Roads &amp; Highways,Transport and Trade Logistics,Railways Transport</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Industry,Transport</teratopic>
        <count>Afghanistan</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Asia!$!80451</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>South Asia!$!80470</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000333037_20130723143919</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <theme>Export development and competitiveness,Social Inclusion,Regional integration,Infrastructure services for private sector development</theme>
        <subsc>General energy sector,Other Mining and Extractive Industries,General transportation sector,General industry and trade sector</subsc>
        <admreg>South Asia,South Asia</admreg>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Industry,Transport</historic_topic>
        <prdln>Technical Assistance (Non-lending)</prdln>
        <sectr>Energy and mining,Transportation,Industry and trade</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            airport, asphalt, automobiles, barges,
            boxes, car, carbon emissions, carriage, cement, chassis,
            civil engineering, cold storage, concrete, congestion,
            Congestion Reduction, construction, container chassis,
            container terminals, Container yards, containers, Corridor,
            cranes, crash barriers, culverts, Customs, demurrage,
            diesel, diesel fuel, docks, drainage, drayage, drivers,
            driving, dry cargo, dust, efficient transport, environmental
            impacts, excavation, fixed costs, flatcars, floor space,
            Freight, freight operations, Freight Rail, freight
            terminals, Fuel, Fuel Distribution, fuels, gasoline,
            generators, handling, highway, highway access, Highway
            Investment, highway network, highways, income, inventory,
            journey, land use, land use policies, leases, leasing,
            Letters of Credit, liability, loaders, loading, loading
            gauges, local authorities, Local Roads, locomotives,
            manufacturing, motor vehicles, pallet racks, pallets,
            parking, passenger, passenger stations, paving, pipes,
            police, Ports, Rail, rail access, rail cargo, rail cars,
            Rail Connection, Rail Infrastructure, rail line, rail
            network, Rail Service, Rail Terminals, rail travel,
            Railroad, railroad terminal, railroads, railway, railway
            construction, Railway Infrastructure, railway operation,
            Railway Tariffs, railway tracks, railways, rain, return on
            capital, Road, road congestion, Road Infrastructure, roads,
            shipments, shippers, shipping, snow, specialized
            infrastructure, speed, speeds, steel, storage capacity,
            storms, straddle crane, structures, supply chain management,
            supply chains, temperature, terrain, Timber, track, tracks,
            tractors, traffic, traffic control, trailers, trains,
            tramway, transportation, truck drivers, trucking, trucks,
            vehicle, wagons, warehouses, warehousing, wheels
        </keywd>
        <owner>Finance &amp; PSD Unit (SASFP)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>South Asia</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <trustfund>TF011285-PHRD STAFF GRANT SUPPORT FOR
            SHIORI ONISHI,TF011852-Afghanistan Resource Corridor,TF014144-PHRD Staff Grant Support for
            Shiori Onishi</trustfund>
        <majtheme>Trade and integration,Financial and private sector development,Social dev/gender/inclusion</majtheme>
        <repnb>79704</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT for Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies (ICT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>PPP</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public-Private Partnerships</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public-Private Partnerships (PPP)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supply Chain Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport Economics Policy &amp; Planning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Railways Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance &amp; Risk Mitigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Servers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Switches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Logistics and Trade Facilitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Facilitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Logistics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Checks on Executive Power</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen User Satisfaction Survey</ml:concept><ml:concept>Independent Commissions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ombudsmen</ml:concept><ml:concept>Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Parliament</ml:concept><ml:concept>Procurement Complaints Review Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supreme Audit Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fuels</ml:concept><ml:concept>Oceans</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Boundaries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pharmaceutical Supply Chain</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport Economics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Railways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports &amp; Waterways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Airports</ml:concept><ml:concept>Highways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Congestion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pipelines</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Network Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Facilitation and Logistics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Accountability Mechanisms</ml:concept><ml:concept>Drainage</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Afghanistan</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Southern Asia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>