<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>﻿OFFICIAL     I&#13;
DOCUMENTS&#13;
Amy Baker                                                            August 21, 2013&#13;
Senior Director, Ethiopia Program&#13;
Southern and Eastern Africa&#13;
Geographic Programs Branch&#13;
Department of Foreign Affairs, Trade and Development&#13;
Canadian Embassy&#13;
P.O. Box 1130&#13;
Addis Ababa, Ethiopia&#13;
Administration Arrangement between the Government of Canada&#13;
as represented by the Minister for International Development, acting through the Department of&#13;
Foreign Affairs, Trade and Development (DFA TD) and the International Development&#13;
Association concerning the Multi Donor Trust Fund for the Women Entrepreneurship&#13;
Development Project (TFNo. 072072)&#13;
1.    The International Development Association (the "Bank") acknowledges that the&#13;
Government of Canada as represented by the Minister for International Development, acting&#13;
through the Department of Foreign Affairs, Trade and Development ("DFATD" or the "Donor"),&#13;
the Donor agrees to provide to the Bank the sum of ten million Canadian Dollars (CAD$&#13;
10,000,000) (the "Contribution") for the Multi Donor Trust Fund established for the co-financing of&#13;
the Women Entrepreneurship Development Project in Ethiopia (the "Trust Fund") (TF No. 072072)&#13;
in accordance with the terms of this Administration Arrangement. Other donors are also expected&#13;
to contribute to the Trust Fund on the terms and conditions specified in the Annexes to this&#13;
Administration Arrangement. All references to "Agreement" made in Annexes and related&#13;
documents will have the same meaning as the term "Administration Arrangement" used herein.&#13;
2.    The Contribution will be used to finance the activities set forth in the "Multi Donor Trust&#13;
Fund Women Entrepreneurship Development Project Trust Fund Description" attached hereto as&#13;
Annex 1, and will be administered by the Bank on behalf of the Donor in accordance with the terms&#13;
of this Administration Arrangement, including the "Standard Provisions" attached hereto as Annex&#13;
2.&#13;
3.    Upon signature of this Administration Arrangement by the Bank and the Donor, the Donor&#13;
authorizes the Bank to transfer a sum of three million five hundred thousand Canadian Dollars&#13;
(CAD$3,500,000) from the Donor's Balance Account at the Bank - TF029048, to the Trust Fund&#13;
established for co-financing of the Women Entrepreneurship Development Project (TF072072).&#13;
4.    The Donor will deposit the remaining Contribution in accordance with the following&#13;
schedule and in the currency specified in Section 1 above ("Contribution Currency") into such bank&#13;
account designated by the Bank (each amount deposited hereinafter referred to as an "Installment")&#13;
upon submission of a payment request:&#13;
(A)   Promptly following signature of the Administration Arrangement , by March 31,&#13;
2014,&#13;
1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿for the Donor's fiscal year 2013-2014, CAD $2,000,000&#13;
(B)   By March 31, 2015, CAD $2,000,000 for the Donor's fiscal year 2014-2015&#13;
(C)   By March 31, 2016, CAD $2,000,000 for the Donor's fiscal year 2015-2016&#13;
(D)   By March 31, 2017, CAD $500,000 for the Donor's fiscal year 2016-2017&#13;
5.    When making any deposit, the Donor will instruct its bank to include in its deposit details&#13;
information (remittance advice) field of its SWIFT deposit message, information indicating: the&#13;
amount deposited, that the deposit is made by the Donor for the Multi Donor Trust Fund Women&#13;
Entrepreneurship Development Project Trust Fund (TF No. 072072), and the date of the deposit (the&#13;
"Deposit Instructions"). In addition, the Donor will provide a copy of the Deposit Instructions to&#13;
the Bank's Accounting Trust Funds Division by e-mail sent to tfremitadvice@worldbank.org or by&#13;
fax sent to +1 (202) 614-1315.&#13;
6.    Except with respect to the Deposit Instructions, any notice, request or other communication&#13;
to be given or made under this Administration Arrangement will be in writing and delivered by&#13;
mail, fax or e-mail to the undersigned at the respective address specified below or at such other&#13;
address as such undersigned notifies in writing to the other undersigned from time to time:&#13;
For the Bank (the "Bank Contact"):&#13;
Ms. Yasmin Tayyab&#13;
Senior Social Development Specialist&#13;
AFTCS&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Tel: 001-202-4582894&#13;
E-mail: ytayyab@worldbank.org&#13;
For the Donor (the "Donor Contact"):&#13;
Ms. Amy Baker&#13;
Senior Director, Ethiopia Program&#13;
Southern and Eastern Africa&#13;
Geographic Programs Branch&#13;
Department of Foreign Affairs, Trade and Development&#13;
Canadian Embassy&#13;
P.O. Box 1130&#13;
Addis Ababa, Ethiopia&#13;
7.    In the event any amounts are to be returned to the Donor under this Administration&#13;
Arrangement, the Bank will transfer such amounts to the Donor's applicable donor balance account&#13;
with the Bank.&#13;
8.    No member of the Canadian House of Commons will be admitted to any share or part of this&#13;
Arrangement or to any benefit to arise therefrom.&#13;
9.    No current or former public office holder or public servant of the Government of Canada&#13;
who is not in compliance with the Conflict of Interest and Post-Employment Code for Public Office&#13;
2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿Holders or the Values and Ethics Code for the Public Service will derive a direct benefit from this&#13;
Arrangement.&#13;
10.   Any transfer into the Trust Fund to be made under this Administration Arrangement is&#13;
subject to there being an appropriation by the Parliament of Canada for the fiscal year in which such&#13;
transfer is to be made. If the Department of Foreign Affairs, Trade and Development appropriation&#13;
is changed by the Parliament of Canada, the Department of Foreign Affairs, Trade and&#13;
Development may reduce the Grant or terminate this Administration Arrangement.&#13;
11.   No offer, gift or payment, consideration or benefit of any kind, which constitutes an illegal&#13;
or corrupt practice, has been or will be made to anyone, either directly or indirectly, as an&#13;
inducement or reward for the award or execution of this Arrangement. Any such practice will be&#13;
grounds for terminating this Arrangement or taking any other corrective action as required.&#13;
12.   All annexes hereto constitute an integral part of this Administration Arrangement, whose&#13;
terms taken together will constitute the entire agreement and understanding between the Donor and&#13;
the Bank. Unless otherwise specified in an annex hereto, this Administration Arrangement may be&#13;
amended only by written amendment between the Bank and the Donor; provided, however, that any&#13;
annexes to this Administration Arrangement may be amended only by written amendment of all&#13;
donors contributing to the Trust Fund.&#13;
13.   It is understood that this Administration Arrangement, including any annexes, is not an&#13;
international treaty.&#13;
14.   Each of the undersigned represents, by confirming its acceptance below, that it is authorized&#13;
to enter into this Administration Arrangement and act in accordance with its provisions. The&#13;
undersigned are requested to sign and date this Administration Arrangement, and upon possession&#13;
by the Bank of this fully signed Administration Arrangement, this Administration Arrangement will&#13;
become effective as of the date of the last signature.&#13;
INTERNATIONA DEVELOPMENT ASSOCIATION&#13;
By:5                                        L&#13;
Bame:            &amp;4"                    VI&#13;
Date:   As&#13;
GOVERNMENT OF CANADA&#13;
(Represented by the Minister for International Development, acting through the Department of&#13;
Foreign Affairs, Trade and Development)&#13;
By:&#13;
Name:         e&#13;
Title:         ;(&#13;
Date:&#13;
3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿ANNEX 1&#13;
Multi Donor Trust Fund - Women Entrepreneurship Development Project&#13;
(TF No. 072072)&#13;
Trust Fund Description&#13;
This Annex shall be applicable to and form an integral part of all Administration Arrangements for&#13;
the Trust Fund (collectively, the "Administration Arrangements" and each an "Administration&#13;
Arrangement") between the Bank and any entities that provide any funds to the Trust Fund&#13;
(collectively, the "Donors").&#13;
1. Objectives&#13;
The Trust Fund will support the Women Entrepreneurship Development Project (the "Project")&#13;
whose objective is to increase the earnings and employment of micro and small enterprises (MSEs)&#13;
owned or partly owned by female entrepreneurs in targeted cities of Ethiopia.&#13;
2. Definitions and Activities&#13;
2.1   Definitions:&#13;
Unless the context requires otherwise, the capitalized terms used in this Administration&#13;
Arrangement have the meanings ascribed to them in this arrangement, Financing Agreement (as&#13;
hereinafter defined), and the following additional terms have the following meanings:&#13;
(a)   "Beneficiary" means an individual or group which is a recipient of a loan from a PFI&#13;
under the credit facility established pursuant to Part 1(a) of the Project, in accordance&#13;
with the eligibility criteria for Beneficiaries adopted for the purposes of the guidelines&#13;
applicable to such credit facility and included in the PIM.&#13;
(b)   "City MSE Development Offices" means the city administrative offices responsible for&#13;
providing technical guidance for micro and small enterprises within the respective cities&#13;
targeted under the Project.&#13;
(c)   "DBE" means the Development Bank of Ethiopia, as re-established and operating&#13;
pursuant to the Development of Bank of Ethiopia Re-Establishment Amendment&#13;
Regulation No. 116/2005 of Council of Ministers of the Recipient.&#13;
(d)   "FeMSEDA" means the Federal Micro and Small Enterprise Development Agency of&#13;
the Recipient.&#13;
(e)   "Financing Agreement" means the financing agreement, dated June 12, 2012, signed&#13;
between Federal Democratic Republic of Ethiopia and the International Development&#13;
Association for the Women Entrepreneurship Development Project (Credit No. 5112-&#13;
ET).&#13;
4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿(f)   "National Project Management Team" or "NPMT" means the team established referred&#13;
to in paragraph 2 of Section L.A of Schedule 2 to the Financing Agreement.&#13;
(g)   "One Stop Shops" means the entry point for micro and small enterprises to seek related&#13;
services.&#13;
(h)    "PFI" or "Participating Financial Institution" means a microfinance institution&#13;
registered and operating in accordance with the applicable laws and regulations of&#13;
Ethiopia and selected in conformity with the eligibility criteria set forth in the WCEF&#13;
Operations Manual.&#13;
(i)   "PIM" or "Project Implementation Manual" means the Project implementation manual&#13;
referred to in Section I.B of Schedule 2 to the Financing Agreement, as such manual&#13;
may be amended from time to time, and such term includes any schedules to the manual.&#13;
(j)   "PMT" means the Project Management Team at DBE, established pursuant to the&#13;
provisions of paragraph 2 of Section L.A of Schedule 2 to the Financing Agreement.&#13;
(k)   "ReMSEDAs" means Regional Micro and Small Enterprise Development Agencies of&#13;
the National/Regional States within the Federal Democratic Republic of Ethiopia.&#13;
(1)   "TVET Colleges" means technical and vocational education and training colleges.&#13;
(m)   "WECF Operations Manual" or "Operations Manual" means the Women&#13;
Entrepreneurship Credit Facility Operations Manual referred to in paragraph B. 1 of&#13;
Section I of Schedule 2 to the Financing Agreement.&#13;
2.2   Activities&#13;
The activities (which may be described as "components" of activities) to be financed by the&#13;
Trust Fund are:&#13;
(i)  Bank-executed activities:&#13;
Carry out impact evaluation of the Women Entrepreneurship Development Project to&#13;
investigate effectiveness of the Project.&#13;
(ii) Recipient-executed activities:&#13;
Part 1: Access to Microfinance&#13;
(a)     Establishment and operation of a credit facility providing access to finance&#13;
for working capital and investment for qualifying growth-oriented micro and small&#13;
enterprises owned (or partly owned) by female entrepreneurs.&#13;
(b)     Provision of technical assistance to support: (i) capacity building in&#13;
participating financial institutions; and (ii) an institutional development plan for DBE,&#13;
including capacity building of the PMT.&#13;
5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿Part 2: Entrepreneurial Skills, Technology, and Cluster Development&#13;
Design and implementation of a capacity building technical assistance program to&#13;
strengthen the capacity of the implementing agencies connected with the Project, that&#13;
provide direct services to the Beneficiaries, including, in particular, NPMT,&#13;
ReMSEDA, One Stop Shops and TVET Colleges, and the supporting/coordinating&#13;
institutions such as the City MSE Development Offices.&#13;
Part 3: Project Management, Advocacy and Outreach, Monitoring and Evaluation,&#13;
and Impact Evaluation&#13;
(a) Establishment of the NPMT within FeMSEDA.&#13;
(b) Advocacy and Outreach. Provision of technical assistance (consisting of&#13;
consultants' services and Training) to build awareness and expand the outreach&#13;
and understanding and acceptance of the Project among targeted Beneficiaries and&#13;
other stakeholders. Carrying out of a program of public information disclosure&#13;
about the Project, including, inter alia, organizing meetings and strengthening&#13;
access to sources of information through public media such as newspapers, mobile&#13;
phones, radio and television. Dissemination of results, lessons learned and good&#13;
practices.&#13;
(c) Monitoring and Evaluation. Development of a monitoring and evaluation system&#13;
to collect data from all the implementing agencies to identify gaps in Project&#13;
implementation, corrective actions and improved planning by FeMSEDA.&#13;
3. Eligible Expenditures&#13;
3.1    For Bank-executed activities, the Trust Fund funds may be used to finance:&#13;
(i)   associated overheads&#13;
(ii)  consultant fees (individuals and firms)&#13;
(iii)  contractual services&#13;
(iv)  equipment and office premises least cost&#13;
(v)   extend term consultants (no in-directs)&#13;
(vi)  extended term consultants&#13;
(vii)  field assigned benefits&#13;
(viii) media, workshop, conference and meeting cost&#13;
(ix)  staff costs (with in-directs)&#13;
(x)   staff costs (no in-directs)&#13;
(xi)  temporary support staff costs&#13;
(xii)  temporary staff costs (no in-directs)&#13;
(xiii) travel expenses.&#13;
6&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿3.2.  For Recipient-executed activities, the Trust Fund funds may be used to finance:&#13;
(i)   civil works&#13;
(ii)  consulting&#13;
(iii)  goods&#13;
(iv)  operating costs&#13;
(v)   training, and&#13;
(vi)  Others&#13;
4. Taxes&#13;
4.1 The foregoing activities and categories of expenditures may include the financing of taxes in&#13;
accordance with the Bank's applicable policies and procedures.&#13;
7&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿ANNEX 2&#13;
Standard Provisions&#13;
This Annex shall be applicable to and form an integral part of all Administration Arrangements&#13;
between the Bank and the respective Donors.&#13;
1.    Administration of the Contributions&#13;
1.1   The Bank shall be responsible only for performing those functions specifically set forth in&#13;
this Administration Arrangement and shall not be subject to any other duties or responsibilities to&#13;
the Donors, including, without limitation, any duties or obligations that might otherwise apply to a&#13;
fiduciary or trustee under general principles of trust or fiduciary law. Nothing in this&#13;
Administration Arrangement shall be considered a waiver of any privileges or immunities of the&#13;
Bank under its Articles of Agreement or any applicable law, all of which are expressly reserved.&#13;
1.2   Each Donor's Contribution (collectively, the "Contributions") shall be administered in&#13;
accordance with the Bank's applicable policies and procedures, as the same may be amended from&#13;
time to time, including its procurement, financial management, disbursement and safeguard&#13;
policies, its framework to prevent and combat fraud and corruption and its screening procedures to&#13;
prevent the use of Bank resources to finance terrorist activity, in line with the Bank's obligations to&#13;
give effect to the relevant decisions of the Security Council taken under Chapter VII of the of&#13;
Charter of the United Nations. The Donors acknowledge that this provision does not create any&#13;
obligations of the Bank under the anti-terrorist financing and asset control laws, regulations, rules&#13;
and executive orders of an individual member country that may apply to a Donor.&#13;
2.    Management of the Contributions&#13;
2.1   The funds deposited in the Trust Fund shall be accounted for as a single trust fund and shall&#13;
be kept separate and apart from the funds of the Bank. The funds deposited in the Trust Fund may&#13;
be commingled with other trust fund assets maintained by the Bank. The Bank, in its capacity as&#13;
trustee, has legal title to the funds deposited in the Trust Fund.&#13;
2.2   The currency in which the funds in the Trust Fund shall be held is United States Dollars&#13;
(the "Holding Currency").&#13;
2.3    Donors agree to deposit their Contributions in the Contribution Currency stated in their&#13;
respective Administration Arrangements. In the case of deposits received in a Contribution&#13;
Currency other than the Holding Currency, promptly upon the receipt of such amounts and the&#13;
accompanying Deposit Instructions, the Bank shall convert such amounts into the Holding Currency&#13;
at the exchange rate obtained by the Bank on the date of the conversion. Where deposits prove to&#13;
be insufficient to complete activities as a result of exchange rate fluctuations, neither the Bank nor&#13;
the Donor shall bear any responsibility for providing any additional financing.&#13;
2.4   The funds deposited in the Trust Fund may be freely exchanged by the Bank into other&#13;
currencies as may facilitate their disbursement at the exchange rate obtained by the Bank on the&#13;
date of the conversion.&#13;
8&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿2.5   The Bank shall invest and reinvest the funds deposited in the Trust Fund pending their&#13;
disbursement in accordance with the Bank's applicable policies and procedures for the investment&#13;
of trust funds administered by the Bank. The Bank shall credit all income from such investment to&#13;
the Trust Fund to be used for the same purposes as the Contributions.&#13;
3.    Trust Fund Fees and Costs&#13;
3.1   The Bank shall deduct and retain for its own account, as a deduction from each Installment,&#13;
an amount equal to two percent (2%) per Installment as an administrative fee for the Trust Fund.&#13;
3.2   In addition, costs incurred by the Bank for other expenses, such as for Trust Fund&#13;
administration, that are: (i) not covered by the percentage deduction specified above as an&#13;
administrative fee; and (ii) not included under Annex 1 of the Administration Arrangements in&#13;
accordance with the Bank's applicable policies and procedures shall be charged to the Trust Fund&#13;
on an actual basis up to a maximum of four point seventy-seven percent (4.77%) of the total&#13;
Contributions under all Administration Arrangements.&#13;
3.3.  Each Donor acknowledges and agrees that the percentage deductions for fees in this Trust&#13;
Fund Fees and Costs section are estimated on the basis of anticipated Contributions. If actual&#13;
Contributions significantly differ from what was originally anticipated at the time of signature of&#13;
the first Administration Arrangement, or if other circumstances affecting Trust Fund fees or costs&#13;
change, the Bank reserves the right to request a change to the terms of this Trust Fund Fees and&#13;
Costs section, which would be effectuated by amendments made to the Administration&#13;
Arrangements of all Donors and which would thereafter be applicable to all new Contributions that&#13;
are provided either as amendments to supplement existing Administration Arrangements or from&#13;
new Donors under new Administration Arrangements.&#13;
4.    Accounting and Financial Reporting&#13;
4.1   The Bank shall maintain separate records and ledger accounts in respect of the funds&#13;
deposited in the Trust Fund and disbursements made therefrom.&#13;
4.2   The Bank shall furnish to the Donors current financial information relating to receipts,&#13;
disbursements and fund balance in the Holding Currency with respect to the Contributions via the&#13;
World Bank's Trust Funds Donor Center secure website. Within six (6) months after all&#13;
commitments and liabilities under the Trust Fund have been satisfied and the Trust Fund has been&#13;
closed, the final financial information relating to receipts, disbursements and fund balance in the&#13;
Holding Currency with respect to the Contributions shall be made available to the Donors via the&#13;
World Bank's Trust Funds Donor Center secure website.&#13;
4.3   The Bank shall provide to the Donors via the World Bank's Trust Fund Donor Center secure&#13;
website, within six (6) months following the end of each Bank fiscal year, an annual single audit&#13;
report, comprising (i) a management assertion together with an attestation from the Bank's external&#13;
auditors concerning the adequacy of internal control over cash-based financial reporting for all&#13;
cash-based trust funds as a whole; and (ii) a combined financial statement for all cash-based trust&#13;
9&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿funds together with the Bank's external auditor's opinion thereon. The cost of the single audit shall&#13;
be borne by the Bank.&#13;
4.4   If a Donor wishes to request, on an exceptional basis, a financial statement audit by the&#13;
Bank's external auditors of the Trust Fund, the Donor and the Bank shall first consult as to whether&#13;
such an external audit is necessary. The Bank and the Donor shall agree on the appropriate scope&#13;
and terms of reference of such audit. Following agreement on the scope and terms of reference, the&#13;
Bank shall arrange for such external audit. The costs of any such audit, including the internal costs&#13;
of the Bank with respect to such audit, shall be borne by the requesting Donor.&#13;
4.5   The Bank shall make available to the Donors copies of all financial statements and auditors'&#13;
reports received by the Bank from Recipients pursuant to any Grant Agreements (as defined below)&#13;
in accordance with the Bank's Access to Information Policy.&#13;
5.    Progress Reporting&#13;
5.1   The Bank shall provide the Donors with semi-annual reports on the progress of activities&#13;
financed by the Contributions. Within six (6) months of the End Disbursement Date (as defined&#13;
below), the Bank shall furnish to the Donors a final report on the activities financed by the Trust&#13;
Fund.&#13;
5.2    Any Donor may review or evaluate activities financed by the Trust Fund at any time up to&#13;
six (6) months following the End Disbursement Date. The Donor and the Bank shall agree on the&#13;
scope and conduct of such review or evaluation, and the Bank shall provide all relevant information&#13;
within the limits of the Bank's applicable policies and procedures. All associated costs, including&#13;
any costs incurred by the Bank, shall be borne by the Donor. It is understood that any such review&#13;
or evaluation will not constitute a financial, compliance or other audit of the Trust Fund.&#13;
6.    Disbursement; Cancellation; Refund&#13;
6.1   It is expected that the funds deposited in the Trust Fund will be fully disbursed by the Bank&#13;
by&#13;
June 30, 2018 (the "End Disbursement Date"). The Bank shall only disburse funds deposited in the&#13;
Trust Fund for the purposes of this Administration Arrangement (other than returns to Donors) after&#13;
such date to the extent such date is changed in accordance with amendments made to the&#13;
Administration Arrangements of all the Donors. Following the End Disbursement Date, the Bank&#13;
shall return any remaining balance of the Trust Fund to each Donor in the Holding Currency in the&#13;
manner specified in its respective Administration Arrangement on a pro rata basis with regard to the&#13;
total funds deposited in the Trust Fund by such Donor relative to the total funds deposited in the&#13;
Trust Fund by all Donors, all calculated as Holding Currency amounts.&#13;
6.2    Any Donor may cancel all or part of such Donor's pro rata share, and the Bank may cancel&#13;
all or any Donors' pro rata shares, upon three (3) months' prior written notice, of any Contributions&#13;
(paid and not yet paid) that are not committed pursuant to any agreements entered into between the&#13;
Bank and any consultants and/or other third parties for the purposes of this Administration&#13;
Arrangement, including any Grant Agreements, prior to the receipt of such notice. In the event of a&#13;
cancellation, the Bank shall return to the relevant Donor or Donors in the Holding Currency in the&#13;
10&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿manner specified by each such Donor in its respective Administration Arrangement the pro rata&#13;
share(s) of any such uncommitted balance of the Trust Fund, in accordance with any additional&#13;
terms that may be agreed between the Bank and each such Donor.&#13;
7.    Disclosure: Dispute Resolution&#13;
7.1   The Bank shall disclose the Administration Arrangements and related information on this&#13;
Trust Fund in accordance with the Bank's Policy on Access to Information. By entering into&#13;
Administration Arrangements, the Donors consent to such disclosure of their respective&#13;
Administration Arrangements and such related information.&#13;
7.2   The Donors and the Bank shall use their best efforts to amicably settle any dispute,&#13;
controversy, or claim arising out of or relating to the Administration Arrangements.&#13;
8.    Grants to Recipients&#13;
8.1   The Bank shall, as administrator of the Trust Fund on behalf of the Donors, enter into one or&#13;
more grant agreements (the "Grant Agreements") with recipients (the "Recipients") consistent with&#13;
the purposes of this Administration Arrangement and on the terms and conditions set forth in the&#13;
Grant Agreements. Grant Agreements may be entered into up to the maximum amount of the&#13;
Contributions that all Donors have agreed to make available under the Administration&#13;
Arrangements between the Bank and the Donors.&#13;
8.2   The Bank shall be responsible for the supervision of the activities financed under any Grant&#13;
Agreements. Subject to the consent of any relevant Recipients, representatives of the Donors may&#13;
be invited by the Bank to participate in Bank supervision missions related to the Trust Fund.&#13;
8.3   The Bank shall promptly inform the Donors of any significant modification to the terms of&#13;
any Grant Agreements and of any contractual remedies that are exercised by the Bank under any&#13;
Grant Agreements. To the extent practicable, the Bank shall afford the Donors the opportunity to&#13;
exchange views before effecting any such modification or exercising any such remedy.&#13;
11&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="18201605">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2013/08/18201605/official-documents--administration-arrangement-canada-tf072072
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2013/08/18201605/official-documents--administration-arrangement-canada-tf072072</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2013/08/18201605/official-documents--administration-arrangement-canada-tf072072</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2013-09-05T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2013-09-05T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <docm_id>090224b081e8cf1a</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b081e8cf1a</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/AFR/2013/09/05/090224b081e8cf1a/1_0/Rendered/INDEX/Official0Docum00Canada0for0TF072072.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/AFR/2013/09/05/090224b081e8cf1a/1_0/Rendered/PDF/Official0Docum00Canada0for0TF072072.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2013-09-05T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2013-08-21T16:06:47Z</docdt>
        <docna>
            Official Documents- Administration
            Arrangement with Canada for TF072072
        </docna>
        <display_title>Official Documents-
            Administration Arrangement with Canada for TF072072</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/2013/08/18201605/official-documents--administration-arrangement-canada-tf072072</listing_relative_url>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <docty>Trust Fund Administrative Agreement</docty>
        <count>Ethiopia</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Pavluk,Jonathan David</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>HQBOCS</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <trustfund>TF072072-Women Entrepreneurship Development</trustfund>
        <lang>English</lang>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Arts and Culture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutritional supplements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Vitamins</ml:concept><ml:concept>Impact Evaluations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Randomized Control Trials</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>Freedom of Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>Bank Supervision</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Continuous Vocational Training (CVT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Lifelong Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Strengthening Technical Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Strengthening Vocational Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Technical Vocational Education and Training Policies and Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Technical and Vocational Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Vocational Education and Training</ml:concept><ml:concept>Vocational Training</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Remittances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Migration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Checks on Executive Power</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen User Satisfaction Survey</ml:concept><ml:concept>Independent Commissions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ombudsmen</ml:concept><ml:concept>Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Parliament</ml:concept><ml:concept>Procurement Complaints Review Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supreme Audit Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enforcement of Judgements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Informal Dispute Resolution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Media</ml:concept><ml:concept>Treaties</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Impact Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supplements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Impact Assessment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>Right to Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>External Audit</ml:concept><ml:concept>Bank Regulation and Supervision</ml:concept><ml:concept>Microfinance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Movement of Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Accountability Mechanisms</ml:concept><ml:concept>Dispute Resolution</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Africa</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Ethiopia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>