<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>﻿OFFICIAL j6&#13;
DCUMVIENTS /&#13;
The World Bank                             1818 H Street N.O.      (202) 473-1000&#13;
INTERNATIONAL BANK FOR RECONSTRUCTION AND DEVEM "UTW&amp;Whintn, 20433  Cable Address: INTBAFRAD&#13;
INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPMENT ASSOCIATION      U.S.A.                  Cable Address: INDEVAS&#13;
September 25, 2013&#13;
Mr. Federico Ramos de Armas&#13;
Secretary of State for Environment&#13;
Ministry of Agriculture, Food and Environment&#13;
Plaza de San Juan de la Cruz s/n&#13;
Madrid 28071 SPAIN&#13;
Mr. Fernando Jim6nez Latorre&#13;
Secretary of State for Economic and Business Affairs&#13;
Ministry of Economy and Competitiveness&#13;
Paseo De La Castellana, 162&#13;
Madrid 28071 SPAIN&#13;
Trust Fund Administration Agreement between the Kingdom of Spain,&#13;
represented by the Ministry of Agriculture, Food and Environment and the&#13;
Ministry of Economy and Competitiveness, and the International Bank for&#13;
Reconstruction and Development concerning the Partnership for Market&#13;
Readiness Multi-Donor Trust Fund (TFO71670)&#13;
Dear Mr. Ramos de Armas and Mr. Jim6nez Latorre:&#13;
1.    We are pleased to acknowledge on behalf of the International Bank for Reconstruction&#13;
and Development ("IBRD" or the "Bank") that the Kingdom of Spain, represented by the&#13;
Ministry of Agriculture, Food and Environment and the Ministry of Economy and&#13;
Competitiveness (the "Contributor"), shall make available as a grant the sum of EURO&#13;
4,000,000 (four million Euros) from the Ministry of Agriculture, Food and Environment (the&#13;
"Contribution") for the Partnership for Market Readiness Multi-Donor Trust Fund (the "Trust&#13;
Fund") in accordance with the terms of this Agreement. Other contributors are also expected to&#13;
contribute to the Trust Fund on the terms and conditions specified in the Annexes to this&#13;
Agreement.&#13;
2.    The Contribution shall be used to finance the activities and the categories of expenditure&#13;
in accordance with the terms set forth in the "Description of Activities, Expenditures and&#13;
Governance Arrangements for the Partnership for Market Readiness Multi-Donor Trust Fund"&#13;
attached hereto as Annex 1, and shall be administered by the Bank on behalf of the Contributor&#13;
in accordance with the terms of this Agreement including the "Standard Provisions Applicable to&#13;
the Partnership for Market Readiness Multi-Donor Trust Fund" attached hereto as Annex 2.&#13;
3.    The Contributor hereby authorizes the Bank to transfer the Contribution funds from the&#13;
Spanish Carbon Fund Main Fund Tranche II (TF070998) to the Trust Fund (TFO71670),&#13;
promptly following countersignature of this Agreement by the Contributor.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-2-&#13;
4.    The Bank will convert the Contribution funds into the holding currency of the Trust&#13;
Fund, namely United States Dollars, promptly upon receipt of the Contribution funds at the&#13;
exchange rate obtained by the Bank on the date of the conversion. Where the Contribution&#13;
proves to be insufficient to complete the activities as a result of an exchange rate fluctuation,&#13;
neither the Bank nor the Contributor will bear any responsibility for providing any additional&#13;
financing.&#13;
5.    Any notice, request or other communication to be given or made under this Agreement&#13;
shall be in writing and delivered by mail, facsimile or e-mail to the respective party's address&#13;
specified below or at such other address as such party notifies in writing to the other party from&#13;
time to time:&#13;
For the Bank:&#13;
International Bank for Reconstruction and Development&#13;
Task Team Leader for Partnership for Market Readiness&#13;
Carbon Finance Unit, Climate Policy and Finance Department (CPFCF)&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
1818 H Street, NW&#13;
Washington, DC 20433&#13;
U.S.A.&#13;
Tel:  +1 202 458 5831&#13;
Fax: +1 202 522 7432&#13;
E-mail: xwang5@worldbank.org&#13;
For the Contributor:&#13;
Mr. Federico Ramos de Armas&#13;
Secretary of State for Environment&#13;
Ministry of Agriculture, Food and Environment&#13;
Plaza de San Juan de la Cruz s/n&#13;
Madrid 28071&#13;
SPAIN&#13;
Tel: +34 91 436 1547&#13;
Fax: +34 91 436 1501&#13;
E-mail: buzon-dioecc(kmagrama.es&#13;
Mr. Fernando Jim6nez Latorre&#13;
Secretary of State for Economic and Business Affairs&#13;
Ministry of Economy and Competitiveness&#13;
Paseo De La Castellana, 162&#13;
Madrid 28071&#13;
SPAIN&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-3-&#13;
Tel: +34915835893&#13;
Fax: +34915837319&#13;
E-mail: seeae@mineco.es&#13;
6.    Annexes 1 and 2 to this Agreement constitute an integral part of this Agreement. This&#13;
Agreement may be amended only in writing between the Bank and the Contributor; provided,&#13;
however, that Annexes 1 and 2 may be amended only with the agreement of the Bank and all&#13;
contributors contributing to the Trust Fund.&#13;
7.    Please confirm your agreement with the foregoing, on behalf of the Contributor, by&#13;
signing, dating, and returning to us the enclosed copy of this Agreement. Upon receipt by the&#13;
Bank of the copy of this Agreement countersigned by you, this Agreement will become effective&#13;
as of the date of the countersignature.&#13;
Sincerely,&#13;
INTERNATIONAL BANK FOR RECONSTRUCTION AND DEVELOPMENT&#13;
Ms. Karin Kemper&#13;
Director&#13;
Climate Policy and Finance Department&#13;
CONFIRMED AND AGREED:&#13;
MINISTRY OF AGRICULTURE, FOOD AND ENVIRONMENT&#13;
By:                                                Date:  /     l/t 21PI)&#13;
Mr. Federi&amp;c. amos de Armas&#13;
Secretary of State for Environment&#13;
MINISTRY OF ECONOMY AND COMPETITIVENESS&#13;
2 5 OCT 2013&#13;
By:                                               Date:&#13;
Mr. Fernando Jim6nez Latorre&#13;
Secretary of State for Economic and Business Affairs&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-4-&#13;
ANNEX 1&#13;
Description of Activities, Expenditures and Governance Arrangements for the Partnership&#13;
for Market Readiness Multi-Donor Trust Fund&#13;
This Annex shall be applicable to and form an integral part of all&#13;
agreements/arrangements entered into between the Bank and contributing countries and/or&#13;
entities (collectively, the "Contributors") that provide contributions (the aggregate of all&#13;
contributions from the Contributors, the "Contributions") to be administered by the Bank for the&#13;
Partnership for Market Readiness Multi-Donor Trust Fund (the "Trust Fund").&#13;
1.    Description of Activities and Governance Arrangements&#13;
1.1   The objectives, operating principles, activities and governance arrangements of the Trust&#13;
Fund are described in the PMR Governance Framework, which was adopted at the organizational&#13;
meeting of the Trust Fund on April 11, 2011, as such framework may be amended from time to&#13;
time in accordance with its terms (the "PMR Governance Framework"). The PMR Governance&#13;
Framework, as originally adopted, is provided as Attachment 1 to this Annex 1. It is attached&#13;
here for informational purposes only, as any amendments to the PMR Governance Framework,&#13;
made in accordance with its terms, shall become applicable to this Agreement as such&#13;
amendments take effect without further need to amend this Agreement; provided that, in the&#13;
event of any conflict with other parts of this Agreement, the terms of this Agreement shall&#13;
prevail.&#13;
1.2   The activities financed by the Trust Fund may be: (a) implemented by the Bank ("Bank-&#13;
Executed Activities"); (b) implemented by the eligible recipients that enter into grant agreements&#13;
with the Bank as the principal delivery partner under the Trust Fund ("Recipient-Executed&#13;
Activities"), which are under the Bank's monitoring and supervision; and (c) on a case-by-case&#13;
basis, handled by other multilateral development banks or UN agencies that serve as additional&#13;
delivery partners under the Trust Fund (the "Additional Delivery Partners"), as described in the&#13;
PMR Governance Framework ("Additional Delivery Partner-Executed Activities").&#13;
1.3   Under the Bank-Executed Activities, the Bank shall provide assistance to facilitate the&#13;
work of the Trust Fund and to support the implementing countries in undertaking the activities&#13;
under the Trust Fund, which may include, but not limited to, providing technical assistance to the&#13;
countries for the preparation of market readiness proposals and for grant implementation; hiring&#13;
of experts; providing advisory services; carrying out grant preparation and supervision work; and&#13;
carrying out trainings, meetings, workshops and feasibility studies.&#13;
1.4   Under the Recipient-Executed Activities, grants shall be provided by the Bank, as the&#13;
principal delivery partner under the Trust Fund, to the implementing countries to carry out the&#13;
agreed activities under the Trust Fund.&#13;
1.5   Under the Additional Delivery Partner-Executed Activities, the Bank shall, subject to the&#13;
availability of applicable resources in the Trust Fund and the terms of the administration&#13;
agreements/arrangements between the Bank and the Contributors, make commitments and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-5-&#13;
transfers of the Trust Fund resources to the Additional Delivery Partners, in accordance with the&#13;
decisions of the Partnership Assembly and/or Partnership Committee (as described in the PMR&#13;
Governance Framework) and provisions of the transfer agreement to be agreed between the Bank&#13;
and the respective Additional Delivery Partners. Each Additional Delivery Partner shall be&#13;
responsible for the use of funds transferred to it under the Trust Fund and the activities carried&#13;
out therewith in accordance with its own fiduciary, safeguard and operational policies and&#13;
procedures. Each Additional Delivery Partner shall report, and be directly accountable, to the&#13;
Partnership Assembly and/or the Partnership Committee, as applicable.&#13;
2.    Categories of Expenditures&#13;
2.1    For Bank-Executed Activities, the Contributions may be used to finance (a) consultant&#13;
fees, (b) media and workshop costs, (c) travel expenses, (d) associated overheads, (e) staff costs,&#13;
(f) contractual services, (g) equipment costs lease, (h) extended term consultants, (i) field&#13;
assignment benefits, (j) temporary support staff costs and (k) staff costs: no indir.&#13;
2.2    For Recipient-Executed Activities, the Contributions may be used to finance (a) goods,&#13;
(b) consulting services, (c) operating costs, (d) trainings and (e) other expenditures allowable under&#13;
the Bank's policies and procedures for Recipient-Executed Activities.&#13;
2.3    For Additional Delivery Partner-Executed Activities, categories of expenditures&#13;
applicable to Contribution funds transferred to an Additional Delivery Partner shall follow such&#13;
Additional Delivery Partner's own applicable policies and procedures. Following disbursement&#13;
by the Bank of funds from the Trust Fund to an Additional Delivery Partner, the Bank shall have&#13;
no further responsibility for the Additional Delivery Partner's use of the funds and activities&#13;
carried out therewith.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-6-&#13;
Attachment 1&#13;
PMR Governance Framework&#13;
Adopted on April 11, 2011&#13;
(provided for informational purposes only)&#13;
PARTNERSHIP FOR MARKET READINESS (PMR)&#13;
PMR Governance Framework&#13;
1.    Objectives of the PMR&#13;
1.1   The PMR aims to provide a platform for technical discussions and the exchange of&#13;
information on market instruments for mitigation, and to help interested countries build&#13;
capacity for scaling up their mitigation efforts through market instruments, and to pilot&#13;
instruments appropriate to their domestic context.&#13;
1.2   The PMR intends to achieve the following objectives:&#13;
(a)   to provide grant financing to countries for building market readiness components;&#13;
(b)   to pilot, test and sequence new concepts for market instruments, both for domestic&#13;
and new international mechanisms, and to identify potential synergies between national&#13;
market based instruments at an early stage;&#13;
(c)   to create a platform  to enable policy makers of government agencies,&#13;
practitioners, and public and private entities to share experiences and information&#13;
regarding elements of market readiness, to learn from one another, promote south-south&#13;
cooperation, and explore and innovate together on new instruments and approaches;&#13;
(d)   to create and disseminate a body of knowledge on market instruments that could&#13;
be tapped for country-specific requirements; and&#13;
(e)   to share lessons learned, including with the UNFCCC.&#13;
2.    Operating Principles&#13;
2.1   Building on the objectives, the PMR will operate in accordance with the following&#13;
principles:&#13;
For the purpose of the PMR, market instruments refer to domestic instruments (e.g., emissions trading scheme)&#13;
and, without prejudging the outcomes under the United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change&#13;
(UNFCCC) negotiations, scaled-up market mechanisms.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-7-&#13;
(a)   to be country-led and to build on nationally defined and prioritized mitigation&#13;
policies, according to each implementing country's national circumstances;&#13;
(b)   to coordinate with other readiness efforts to avoid duplication and ensure effective&#13;
use of resources;&#13;
(c)   to cooperate with other actors and processes that are undertaking similar&#13;
initiatives, such as UN agencies and other multilateral development banks; and&#13;
(d)   to promote learning-by-doing through early and integrated efforts.&#13;
3. Activities for Support&#13;
3.1   The activities to be supported by the PMR will be developed on a country-specific basis&#13;
and will build on the country's existing initiatives to meet nationally defined priorities.&#13;
As countries' technical and institutional capacities differ, the PMR resources may be used&#13;
to undertake the activities that serve the objectives of the PMR set out in Section I&#13;
(Objectives of the PMR) above, which may include some or all of the following activities:&#13;
(a)   Assessment - Carrying out a feasibility and capacity assessment for utilizing&#13;
market mechanisms within a portfolio of policy instruments in the context of the&#13;
country's mitigation strategies, including analysis and appraisal of national, sub-national&#13;
and sectoral approaches.&#13;
(b)   Data - Building or enhancing capacity of data collection systems and institutional&#13;
capacity for data reporting and management and for setting up activity reference level.&#13;
(c)   Measurement, Reporting and Veriying (MR V) - Designing or enhancing existing&#13;
MRV frameworks to ensure transparency, quality, credibility and consistency with&#13;
international good practice.&#13;
(d)   Institutional capacity - Carrying out capacity building activities that aim to&#13;
engage with key stakeholders early in the planning process and help the responsible&#13;
government agencies organize cross-agency dialogues and broader consultations.&#13;
(e)   Policy and legal frameworks - Facilitating the design of policy and legal&#13;
frameworks for implementation of market instruments.&#13;
(f)   Piloting and testing - Learning-by-doing is one of the most efficient means to&#13;
gain experience, improve capacity and develop effective instruments. If a country so&#13;
wishes, a pilot program could be set up to test a market instrument selected by the&#13;
country.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-8-&#13;
4. Participation and Governance Structure&#13;
4.1   The participation and governance structure of the PMR include a Partnership Assembly, a&#13;
Partnership Committee (if established by the Partnership Assembly), Observers, Experts,&#13;
a Secretariat, a Trustee and Delivery Partners.&#13;
Partnership Assembly&#13;
4.2   The Partnership Assembly will consist of the following participants:&#13;
(a)   all donors that have contributed financially to the PMR and that have entered into&#13;
an administration agreement with the International Bank for Reconstruction and&#13;
Development (the Bank) (the Contributing Participants); and&#13;
(b)   all countries that have submitted an expression of interest to participate in the&#13;
PMR and whose participation have been confirmed at the organizational meeting or any&#13;
meeting of the Partnership Assembly (the Implementing Country Participants) (the&#13;
Contributing Participants and the Implementing Country Participants will be collectively&#13;
referred to as the PMR Participants).&#13;
4.3   The Partnership Assembly will have the following roles and responsibilities:&#13;
(a)   provide strategic guidance for the operation of the PMR;&#13;
(b)   confirm the participation of countries that have submitted an expression of&#13;
interest to participate in the PMR as described in Section 4.2(b) above;&#13;
(c)   in the absence of the establishment of a Partnership Committee described in&#13;
Sections 4.6 and 4.7 below, approve the allocation of PMR resources to the Implementing&#13;
Country Participants;&#13;
(d)   approve the budget for the operation of the PMR;&#13;
(e)   monitor the operation of the PMR;&#13;
(f)   decide on other matters related to the operation of the PMR;&#13;
(g)   provide guidance to the Partnership Committee, if established; and&#13;
(h)   exercise such other functions as the Partnership Assembly may deem appropriate&#13;
to fulfill the purposes of the PMR.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-9-&#13;
4.4    The Partnership Assembly will meet twice a year or at any other frequency as may be&#13;
decided by the Partnership Assembly on the basis of recommendation by the Secretariat.&#13;
4.5   (a)    Decisions of the Partnership Assembly will be made by PMR Participants on a&#13;
consensus basis, and any PMR Participant who holds a different view may request to&#13;
record its view as a note to the decisions. If all efforts to reach a consensus have been&#13;
exhausted and no decision has been reached, decision will be taken by two-thirds (2/3)&#13;
majority of the Contributing Participants and two-thirds (2/3) majority of the&#13;
Implementing Country Participants, present and voting at the meeting of the Partnership&#13;
Assembly, on the basis of one (1) vote per PMR Participant.&#13;
(b)   Unless the Partnership Assembly decides otherwise, the Bank will chair the&#13;
meetings of the Partnership Assembly at the initial stage of the operation of the PMR,&#13;
which may cover the first two (2) meetings, and subsequent meetings will be co-chaired&#13;
by a representative elected from the Contributing Participants and another representative&#13;
elected from the Implementing Country Participants.&#13;
(c)   Further details on the conduct of the meetings of the Partnership Assembly will be&#13;
set forth in the Rules of Procedure, to be adopted at the organizational meeting or any&#13;
subsequent meeting of the Partnership Assembly.&#13;
Partnership Committee&#13;
4.6   Once there are ten (10) Contributing Participants and ten (10) Implementing Country&#13;
Participants in the Partnership Assembly, the Partnership Assembly may consider&#13;
establishing a Partnership Committee to perform the functions identified in Section 4.3(c)&#13;
above and other functions as may be designated by the Partnership Assembly.&#13;
4.7   (a)    The Partnership Committee will consist of an equal number of representatives&#13;
from the Contributing Participants and the Implementing Country Participants. The&#13;
Partnership Assembly will decide on the size of the Partnership Committee. In order to be&#13;
elected as a member of the Partnership Committee representing the Contributing&#13;
Participants, the Contributing Participant will be required to make a financial contribution&#13;
to the PMR in no less than the minimum amount of five million United States dollars&#13;
(US$ 5,000,000) or equivalent.&#13;
(b)   Decisions of the Partnership Committee will be made by its members on a&#13;
consensus basis, and any member of the Partnership Committee who holds a different&#13;
view may request to record its view as a note to the decisions. If all efforts to reach a&#13;
consensus have been exhausted and no decision has been reached, decision will be taken&#13;
by two-thirds (2/3) majority of the members of the Partnership Committee representing&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿- 10-&#13;
the Contributing Participants and two-thirds (2/3) majority of the members of the&#13;
Partnership Committee representing the Implementing Country Participants, present and&#13;
voting at the meeting of the Partnership Committee, on the basis of one (1) vote per&#13;
member.&#13;
(c)   Further details on the conduct of the meetings of the Partnership Committee will&#13;
be set forth in the Rules of Procedure, to be adopted at the organizational meeting or any&#13;
subsequent meeting of the Partnership Assembly.&#13;
Observers&#13;
4.8   The countries, organizations and entities relevant to the activities of the PMR and the&#13;
Delivery Partners described in Sections 4.13 to 4.15 below may be invited to attend the&#13;
meetings of the PMR as observers (the Observers), and may participate in the meetings&#13;
without the right to vote. Further details on the Observers' participation in the meetings&#13;
of the PMR will be set forth in the Rules of Procedure, to be adopted at the organizational&#13;
meeting or any subsequent meeting of the Partnership Assembly and, where necessary, in&#13;
the decisions of the Partnership Assembly.&#13;
Experts&#13;
4.9   Experts, including those drawn from a roster of experts established by the Secretariat (the&#13;
Experts), will facilitate the work of the PMR, including attending the meetings of the&#13;
PMR to provide expert advice, and may provide technical assistance to the Implementing&#13;
Country Participants for readiness preparation and implementation. Where necessary, the&#13;
modality of the expert support to the work of the PMR may be further developed by the&#13;
Secretariat for consideration by the Partnership Assembly.&#13;
Secretariat&#13;
4.10  The Bank will serve as the secretariat of the PMR (the Secretariat) to provide secretariat&#13;
services and technical support for day-to-day operations of the PMR.&#13;
4.11  The Secretariat will have the following roles and responsibilities:&#13;
(a)   to propose a provisional agenda for the meetings of the PMR;&#13;
(b)   to provide secretariat services to meetings of the PMR;&#13;
(c)   to develop guidelines for allocation of funding for consideration by the&#13;
Partnership Assembly;&#13;
(d)   to review funding proposals for completeness and quality;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿- 11 -&#13;
(e)   to propose a budget for approval by the Partnership Assembly;&#13;
(f)   to prepare updates or consolidated progress reports on the individual activities of&#13;
the PMR and on the PMR as a whole, for the meetings of the Partnership Assembly;&#13;
(g)   to maintain a website with details and relevant documentation about the PMR;&#13;
(h)   to disseminate knowledge gained under the PMR; and&#13;
(i)   to perform other functions necessary for facilitating the operation of the PMR.&#13;
Trustee of PMR trust fund&#13;
4.12  The Bank will serve as the trustee of the trust fund for the PMR (the Trustee). The Bank&#13;
as Trustee will establish a trust fund to receive contributions from donors to the PMR,&#13;
and will hold in trust, as a legal owner and administer the funds, assets and receipts that&#13;
constitute the trust fund, pursuant to the terms of the administration agreements entered&#13;
into with the donors with respect to their contributions to the PMR.&#13;
Delivery Partners&#13;
4.13  The delivery partners of the PMR (the Delivery Partners) will be responsible for (a)&#13;
collaborating with the agreed Implementing Country Participants to assist them in&#13;
carrying out the activities of the PMR, including providing technical assistance for&#13;
preparing market readiness proposals and grant implementation; (b) supervising grant&#13;
implementation in such Implementing Country Participants; and (c) providing technical&#13;
support as needed for activities financed by the PMR. Each Delivery Partner will be&#13;
responsible for the use of funds transferred to it under the PMR and the activities carried&#13;
out therewith in accordance with its own fiduciary, safeguard and operational policies&#13;
and procedures. Each Delivery Partner will report, and be directly accountable, to the&#13;
Partnership Assembly and/or the Partnership Committee, as applicable.&#13;
4.14  The Bank will serve as the principal Delivery Partner. Where the Bank agrees to serve as&#13;
the Delivery Partner for an Implementing Country Participant, the Bank may, at its&#13;
discretion, enter into grant agreement(s) with such Implementing Country Participant to&#13;
implement the agreed activities.&#13;
4.15  At the request of the Implementing Country Participant, the Partnership Assembly may&#13;
decide, with agreement of the Bank as the Trustee, on a case-by-case basis for one or&#13;
more multilateral development banks and UN agencies other than the Bank to serve as&#13;
additional Delivery Partners. In the event an additional Delivery Partner has been agreed&#13;
upon, the Bank as the Trustee will enter into a transfer agreement with such additional&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿- 12 -&#13;
Delivery Partner to set forth the terms and conditions of the arrangement and the transfer&#13;
of PMR funds, based on the decision of the Partnership Assembly and/or the Partnership&#13;
Committee, as applicable. Following disbursement by the Trustee of the funds from the&#13;
PMR trust fund to an additional Delivery Partner, the additional Delivery Partner will be&#13;
responsible for the use of the funds transferred to it and the activities carried out&#13;
therewith as described in Section 4.13 above, and the Trustee will have no further&#13;
responsibility for the additional Delivery Partner's use of the funds and activities carried&#13;
out therewith.&#13;
5. Amendment to the PMR Governance Framework&#13;
5.1   The provisions of this PMR Governance Framework may be amended with the prior&#13;
consent of all PMR Participants; provided that, any amendments that would affect the&#13;
rights or obligations of the Bank or the additional Delivery Partners will only be effective&#13;
upon the agreement of the Bank or the additional Delivery Partners, respectively.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿- 13-&#13;
ANNEX 2&#13;
Standard Provisions Applicable to the Partnership for Market Readiness Multi-Donor&#13;
Trust Fund&#13;
The following provisions (hereinafter referred to as the "Standard Provisions") shall be&#13;
applicable to and form an integral part of all agreements/arrangements entered into between the&#13;
International Bank for Reconstruction and Development (the "Bank") and contributing countries&#13;
and/or entities (collectively, the "Contributors") that provide contributions (the aggregate of all&#13;
contributions from the Contributors, the "Contributions") to be administered by the Bank for the&#13;
Partnership for Market Readiness Multi-Donor Trust Fund (the "Trust Fund").&#13;
1.    Administration of the Contributions by the Bank and the Additional Delivery Partners&#13;
1.1   The Bank shall be responsible only for performing those functions specifically set forth&#13;
in this Agreement and shall not be subject to any other duties or responsibilities to the&#13;
Contributors, including, without limitation, any duties or obligations that might otherwise apply&#13;
to a fiduciary or trustee under general principles of trust or fiduciary law. Nothing in this&#13;
Agreement shall be considered a waiver of any privileges or immunities of the IBRD under its&#13;
Articles of Agreement or any applicable law, all of which are expressly reserved.&#13;
1.2   The Bank shall, in accordance with the terms of this Agreement and its applicable&#13;
policies and procedures, serve as the trustee of the Trust Fund (the "Trustee"), the secretariat of&#13;
the Trust Fund (the "Secretariat") and the principal delivery partner under the Trust Fund (the&#13;
"Principal Delivery Partner"), pursuant to the provisions of the PMR Governance Framework.&#13;
For the purpose of these Standard Provisions, the "PMR Governance Framework" shall mean the&#13;
PMR Governance Framework, adopted at the organizational meeting of the Trust Fund on April&#13;
11, 2011, as such framework may be amended from time to time in accordance with its terms.&#13;
1.3   At the request of the implementing country, the Partnership Assembly (as described in&#13;
the PMR Governance Framework) may decide, with agreement of the Bank as Trustee, on a&#13;
case-by-case basis for one or more multilateral development banks and UN agencies, other than&#13;
the Bank, to serve as additional delivery partners under the Trust Fund (the "Additional Delivery&#13;
Partners"), pursuant to the provisions of the PMR Governance Framework.&#13;
1.4   The Bank as Principal Delivery Partner and each of the Additional Delivery Partners&#13;
shall respectively be responsible for the use of funds transferred to it under the Trust Fund and&#13;
the activities carried out therewith in accordance with its own fiduciary, safeguard and&#13;
operational policies and procedures. Each of them shall report, and be directly accountable, to&#13;
the Partnership Assembly and/or the Partnership Committee (as described in the PMR&#13;
Governance Framework), as applicable.&#13;
1.5   In the event an Additional Delivery Partner has been agreed upon, the Bank as Trustee&#13;
shall enter into a transfer agreement with such Additional Delivery Partner (the "Transfer&#13;
Agreement") to set forth the terms and conditions of the arrangement and the transfer of the&#13;
Trust Fund funds, based on the decision of the Partnership Assembly and/or the Partnership&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿- 14-&#13;
Committee, as applicable. Following disbursement by the Bank as Trustee of the funds from the&#13;
Trust Fund to an Additional Delivery Partner, the Additional Delivery Partner shall be&#13;
responsible for the use of the funds transferred to it and the activities carried out therewith as&#13;
specified in Section 1.4, and the Bank shall have no further responsibility for the Additional&#13;
Delivery Partner's use of the funds and activities carried out therewith.&#13;
1.6   Except for those Contributions transferred by the Bank to the Additional Delivery&#13;
Partners which shall be administered in accordance with the respective Additional Delivery&#13;
Partner's own policies and procedures, the Contributions shall be administered in accordance&#13;
with the Bank's applicable policies and procedures, as the same may be amended from time to&#13;
time, including its framework to prevent and combat fraud and corruption and its screening&#13;
procedures to prevent the use of Bank resources to finance terrorist activity, in line with the&#13;
Bank's obligations to give effect to the relevant decisions of the Security Council, taken under&#13;
Chapter VII of the of Charter of the United Nations. The Contributor acknowledges that this&#13;
provision does not create any obligations of the Bank under the anti-terrorist financing and asset&#13;
control laws, regulations, rules and executive orders of an individual member country that may&#13;
apply to the Contributor, nor shall it be deemed a waiver, express or implied, of any of the&#13;
privileges and immunities of the Bank.&#13;
2.    Commingling, Exchange and Investment of the Contributions&#13;
2.1    The Contributions shall be accounted for as a single trust fund and shall be kept separate&#13;
and apart from the funds of the Bank. The Contributions may be commingled with other trust&#13;
fund assets maintained by the Bank.&#13;
2.2    The Contributions may be freely exchanged by the Bank into other currencies as may&#13;
facilitate their disbursement.&#13;
2.3    The Bank shall invest and reinvest the Contributions pending their disbursement in&#13;
accordance with the Bank's policies and procedures for the investment of trust funds&#13;
administered by the Bank. The Bank shall credit all income from such investment to the Trust&#13;
Fund to be used for the same purposes as the Contributions.&#13;
3.    Administrative Cost and Fee Recovery&#13;
3.1   In order to assist in the defrayment of the costs of administration and other expenses&#13;
incurred by the Bank under this Agreement, the Bank may deduct and retain for its own account&#13;
an amount equal to one percent (1%) of each Contribution. In addition, costs for program&#13;
management and Trust Fund administration expenses will be charged to the Trust Fund on an&#13;
actual basis. If the contributions increase beyond what was originally expected at the time of&#13;
counter-signature of the first administration agreement/arrangement, and the administrative costs&#13;
increase as a result, the Contributors acknowledge that an additional administrative fee may be&#13;
applied to such new contributions.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿- 15-&#13;
4.    Grants to Recipients&#13;
4.1    The Bank, as Principal Delivery Partner on behalf of the Contributors, if so decides, may&#13;
enter into grant agreements (the "Grant Agreements") with eligible recipients (the "Recipients")&#13;
consistent with the purposes of this Agreement and on the terms and conditions set forth in the&#13;
Grant Agreements. Grant Agreements may be entered into up to the maximum amount of the&#13;
Contributions allocated by the Partnership Assembly or Partnership Committee, as applicable,&#13;
for the Bank to enter into the Grant Agreements. Upon request by a Contributor, the Bank shall&#13;
furnish a copy of the Grant Agreements to the Contributors.&#13;
4.2    The Bank shall be responsible for the supervision of the activities financed under the&#13;
Grant Agreements. Subject to the consent of the relevant Recipients, representatives of the&#13;
Contributors may be invited by the Bank to participate in Bank supervision missions related to&#13;
the Trust Fund.&#13;
4.3    The Bank shall promptly inform the Contributors of any significant modification to the&#13;
terms of any Grant Agreements and of any contractual remedies that are exercised by the Bank&#13;
under any Grant Agreements. To the extent practicable, the Bank shall afford the Contributors&#13;
the opportunity to exchange views before effecting any such modification or exercising any such&#13;
remedy.&#13;
5.    Procurement&#13;
5.1   For Recipient-Executed Activities (as defined in Annex 1 to this Agreement), the Grant&#13;
Agreements shall provide that the Contributions shall be used by the Recipients to finance&#13;
expenditures for goods and services, as the case may be, in accordance with the Bank's&#13;
Guidelines on "Procurement under IBRD Loans and IDA Credits" and the Bank's Guidelines on&#13;
the "Selection and Employment of Consultants by World Bank Borrowers," as in effect at the&#13;
date of entry into the respective Grant Agreements.&#13;
5.2.  For Bank-Executed Activities (as defined in Annex 1 to this Agreement), the&#13;
employment and supervision of any consultants and the procurement of any goods financed by&#13;
the Contributions shall be the responsibility of the Bank and shall be carried out in accordance&#13;
with its applicable policies and procedures.&#13;
6.    Accounting and Financial Reporting&#13;
6.1    The Bank shall maintain separate records and ledger accounts in respect of the&#13;
Contributions deposited in the Trust Fund account and disbursements made therefrom.&#13;
6.2   The Bank shall furnish to the Contributors current financial information relating to&#13;
receipts, disbursements and fund balance in United States Dollars of the Trust Fund with respect&#13;
to the Contributions via the World Bank's Trust Funds Donor Center secure website. Within six&#13;
(6) months after all commitments and liabilities under the Trust Fund have been satisfied and the&#13;
Trust Fund has been closed, the final financial information relating to receipts, disbursements&#13;
and fund balance in United States Dollars of the Trust Fund with respect to the Contributions&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿- 16-&#13;
will be made available to the Contributors via the World Bank's Trust Funds Donor Center&#13;
secure website.&#13;
6.3   The Bank shall provide to the Contributors, within six (6) months following the end of&#13;
each Bank fiscal year, an annual single audit report, comprising (1) a management assertion&#13;
together with an attestation from the Bank's external auditors concerning the adequacy of&#13;
internal control over cash-based financial reporting for all cash-based trust funds as a whole; and&#13;
(2) a combined financial statement for all cash-based trust funds together with the Bank's&#13;
external auditor's opinion thereon. The cost of the single audit shall be borne by the Bank.&#13;
6.4   If a Contributor wishes to request, on an exceptional basis, a financial statement audit by&#13;
the Bank's external auditors of the Trust Fund, the Contributor and the Bank shall first consult as&#13;
to whether such an external audit is necessary. The Bank and the Contributor shall agree on the&#13;
appropriate scope and terms of reference of such audit. Following agreement on the scope and&#13;
terms of reference, the Bank shall arrange for such external audit. The costs of any such audit,&#13;
including the internal costs of the Bank with respect to such audit, shall be paid by the requesting&#13;
Contributor.&#13;
6.5   Upon a Contributor's request, the Bank shall provide such Contributor with copies of&#13;
financial statements and auditors' reports received by the Bank from the Recipients pursuant to&#13;
the Grant Agreements and from the Additional Delivery Partners pursuant to the Transfer&#13;
Agreements.&#13;
7.    Progress Reporting&#13;
7.1   The Bank as Principal Delivery Partner shall provide the Bank as Secretariat with an&#13;
annual report on the progress of the Bank-Executed Activities and Recipient-Executed Activities&#13;
it carried out or supervised under the Trust Fund. Within six (6) months of the final&#13;
disbursement date specified in Section 8.2, the Bank as Principal Delivery Partner shall furnish&#13;
to the Bank as Secretariat a final report on the Bank-Executed Activities and Recipient-Executed&#13;
Activities it carried out or supervised under the Trust Fund.&#13;
7.2   The Additional Delivery Partners shall provide the Bank as Secretariat with reports on&#13;
the progress of the Additional Delivery Partner-Executed Activities (as defined in Annex I to&#13;
this Agreement) pursuant to the terms of the Transfer Agreements.&#13;
7.3    The Bank as Secretariat shall provide the Contributors with updates or consolidated&#13;
progress reports on the individual activities of the Trust Fund and on the Trust Fund as a whole&#13;
at the meetings of the Partnership Assembly.&#13;
7.4    Any Contributor may review or evaluate Bank-Executed Activities and Recipient-&#13;
Executed Activities financed by the Trust Fund. The Contributor and the Bank shall agree on the&#13;
scope and conduct of such review or evaluation, and the Bank shall provide all relevant&#13;
information within the limits of its policies and procedures. All associated costs shall be borne&#13;
by the Contributor. It is understood that any such review or evaluation will not constitute a&#13;
financial, compliance or other audit of the Trust Fund.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿- 17-&#13;
8.    Disbursement; Cancellation, Refund&#13;
8.1     The Contributions may be used to retroactively finance payments for eligible&#13;
expenditures under the Bank-Executed Activities and Recipient-Executed Activities, which were&#13;
incurred on or after September 1, 2010, in accordance with the Bank's policies and procedures.&#13;
8.2   It is expected that the Contributions will be fully disbursed by the Bank by June 30, 2021.&#13;
The Bank shall only disburse Contributions for the purposes of this Agreement after such date&#13;
with the written approval of the Contributors.&#13;
8.3   Any Contributor or the Bank may, upon three (3) months' prior written notice, cancel all&#13;
or part of the Contributor's pro rata share, of any remaining balance of the Contributions that is&#13;
not committed pursuant to any agreements entered into between the Bank and any consultants,&#13;
Additional Delivery Partners and/or other third parties for the purposes of this Agreement prior&#13;
to the receipt of such notice, including the Grant Agreements and the Transfer Agreements.&#13;
8.4   Following the final disbursement date specified in Section 8.2, the Bank shall return any&#13;
remaining balance of the Contributions then held by the Bank to the Contributors on a pro rata&#13;
basis based on the Contributors' paid Contributions. In the event of a cancellation the Bank shall&#13;
promptly return to the relevant Contributor or Contributors the Contributor's pro rata share of&#13;
uncommitted Contributions then held by the Bank in accordance with Section 8.3.&#13;
9.    Disclosure&#13;
The Bank will disclose this Agreement and related information on this Trust Fund in&#13;
accordance with the World Bank Policy on Access to Information. By entering into this&#13;
Agreement, Contributors consent to disclosure of this Agreement and related information on this&#13;
Trust Fund.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="18493886">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2013/09/18493886/official-documents--administration-agreement-kingdom-spain-fo-contribution-tf071670
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2013/09/18493886/official-documents--administration-agreement-kingdom-spain-fo-contribution-tf071670</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2013/09/18493886/official-documents--administration-agreement-kingdom-spain-fo-contribution-tf071670</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2013-11-08T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2013-11-08T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <docm_id>090224b082052be4</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b082052be4</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/SDN/2013/11/08/090224b082052be4/1_0/Rendered/INDEX/Official0Docum0ribution0to0TF071670.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/SDN/2013/11/08/090224b082052be4/1_0/Rendered/PDF/Official0Docum0ribution0to0TF071670.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2013-09-25T16:29:19Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2013-11-08T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docna>
            Official Documents- Administration Agreement
            with the Kingdom of Spain fo Contribution to TF071670
        </docna>
        <display_title>Official Documents-
            Administration Agreement with the Kingdom of Spain fo
            Contribution to TF071670</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/2013/09/18493886/official-documents--administration-agreement-kingdom-spain-fo-contribution-tf071670</listing_relative_url>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <docty>Trust Fund Administrative Agreement</docty>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Pohlmann,Markus</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>HQBOCS</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <owner>Carbon Finance (CPFCF)</owner>
        <trustfund>TF071670-Partnership for Market
            Readiness Multi-Donor Trust Fund</trustfund>
        <lang>English</lang>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Arts and Culture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Organisational Structures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Organizational Assessments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>Freedom of Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>Bank Supervision</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Leasing law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Contract Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Arrangements in Public Procurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Capacity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legal Regulatory Framework</ml:concept><ml:concept>State-Society Relations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Media</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Privileges and Immunities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance Structures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Right to Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>External Audit</ml:concept><ml:concept>Bank Regulation and Supervision</ml:concept><ml:concept>Leasing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>