<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>                                                      83903&#13;
                                                        Working Paper 5&#13;
 NAD   Nias&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MDF-JRF Working Paper Series:&#13;
Lessons Learned from Post-Disaster Reconstruction in Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The Multi Donor Fund for Aceh and Nias:&#13;
A Framework for Reconstruction through&#13;
Effective Partnerships&#13;
&amp;#12;A young girl amid the rubble of her&#13;
destroyed school.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
             Photo: Rekompak Team&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                  Working Paper 5&#13;
NAD   Nias&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
             MDF-JRF Working Paper Series:&#13;
             Lessons Learned from Post-Disaster&#13;
             Reconstruction in Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
             The Multi Donor Fund for Aceh and&#13;
             Nias: A Framework for Reconstruction&#13;
             through Effective Partnerships&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
             Published by:&#13;
             MDF-JRF Secretariat&#13;
             The World Bank Office&#13;
             Indonesia Stock Exchange Building&#13;
             Tower I, 9th Floor&#13;
             Jl. Jendral Sudirman Kav. 52-53&#13;
             Jakarta 12910, Indonesia&#13;
             Tel	 : (+6221) 5299-3000&#13;
             Fax	 : (+6221) 5299-3111&#13;
&amp;#12;ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS&#13;
&#13;
The MDF-JRF Working Paper Series: Lessons Learned from Post-Disaster Reconstruction in&#13;
Indonesia was prepared by the Secretariat of the Multi Donor Fund for Aceh and Nias (MDF) and the&#13;
Java Reconstruction Fund (JRF). The World Bank serves as trustee of both funds. The series, consisting&#13;
of five working papers, was produced under the guidance of Shamima Khan, MDF and JRF&#13;
Manager. Anita Kendrick, Monitoring and Evaluation Officer of the MDF and JRF, developed the&#13;
concepts and managed the production of the Working Paper Series and the Knowledge Notes&#13;
based on each paper.&#13;
&#13;
This paper, Working Paper 5 in the series, is entitled The Multi Donor Fund for Aceh and Nias:&#13;
A Framework for Reconstruction through Effective Partnership. The paper is based on concept&#13;
and text written by Shamima Khan, with extensive research and content from Lina Lo, MDF-JRF&#13;
Quality Assurance Officer. Shaun Parker, Operations Officer, and Anita Kendrick also contributed&#13;
to the text and quality review. Overall editorial oversight and guidance to the production&#13;
and content was provided by Anita Kendrick. Josef Leitmann, Program Manager for the Haiti&#13;
Reconstruction Fund and Jonathan Caldicott, Senior Financial Officer, provided extensive and&#13;
useful comments on the text as peer reviewers. Devi Asmarani provided editorial support and&#13;
managed the production process.&#13;
&#13;
Safriza Sofyan, Deputy Manager of the MDF, and Olga Lambey provided significant inputs to the&#13;
working paper on content, design, layout, and production as well as logistical support for the&#13;
review team Ola Santo and her team from Studio Rancang Imaji prepared the design and layout&#13;
of the Working Paper Series and accompanying Knowledge Notes.&#13;
&#13;
The MDF Secretariat would like to thank the many partners and stakeholders who cooperated&#13;
with the review team during the fieldwork and research period. These included representatives&#13;
of the Government of Indonesia, including line ministries, as well as local governments of Aceh,&#13;
North Sumatra, and Nias, and donors, partner and implementing agencies, and beneficiary&#13;
communities in Aceh and Nias.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Published by:&#13;
MDF-JRF Secretariat&#13;
The World Bank Office&#13;
Indonesia Stock Exchange Building&#13;
Tower I, 9th Floor&#13;
Jl. Jendral Sudirman Kav. 52-53&#13;
Jakarta 12910, Indonesia                                                     www.worldbank.org&#13;
Tel	 : (+6221) 5299-3000                                                www.multidonorfund.org&#13;
Fax	 : (+6221) 5299-3111                                          www.javareconstructionfund.org&#13;
&amp;#12;THE MDF-JRF WORKING PAPER SERIES&#13;
&#13;
The Multi Donor Fund for Aceh and Nias (MDF) and the Java Reconstruction Fund (JRF) are widely&#13;
recognized as having played a significant role in the remarkable recovery of Aceh, Nias and Java,&#13;
following some of the worst disasters in Indonesia over the last decade.&#13;
&#13;
The MDF and the JRF, which is patterned after it, are each considered a highly successful model&#13;
for post-disaster reconstruction. Key factors in this success have been the leadership provided by&#13;
the Government of Indonesia and the strong partnership of multiple stakeholders in support of&#13;
the governmentâ&#128;&#153;s reconstruction agenda. The two programs have produced impressive results,&#13;
both in terms of physical reconstruction, and in the less tangible but equally important benefits&#13;
such as community empowerment, strengthened governance, and communities that are more&#13;
resilient to future disasters. The experiences of the MDF and JRF have generated many useful&#13;
lessons and created effective models and approaches that can be adapted and replicated in other&#13;
reconstruction contexts.&#13;
&#13;
The Secretariat of the MDF and JRF, as part of its culminating activities, has prepared a series&#13;
of working papers to document these achievements and lessons learned. The MDF-JRF Working&#13;
Paper Series: Lessons Learned from Post-Disaster Reconstruction in Indonesia consists of&#13;
five working papers covering five key areas. These are: (1) Community driven approaches for&#13;
post-disaster recovery; (2) Capacity building in a post-disaster context; (3) Reconstruction of&#13;
infrastructure; (4) Promoting gender equality and womenâ&#128;&#153;s empowerment through post-disaster&#13;
reconstruction; and (5) Multi-donor trust funds as a framework for effective partnerships for&#13;
reconstruction. Each Working Paper describes the strategy and approaches adopted by the MDF&#13;
and/or JRF across its projects, notes the achievements, and draws lessons that will be useful in&#13;
other post-disaster settings. In addition to the full working papers, a series of Knowledge Notes has&#13;
also been prepared, providing a short summary of the key lessons and conclusions from each of&#13;
the longer working papers.&#13;
&#13;
This paper, Working Paper 5 in the series, is entitled The Multi Donor Fund for Aceh and Nias: A&#13;
Framework for Reconstruction through Effective Partnerships. It presents experiences from the&#13;
implementation of the MDF, and documents key lessons on its strategic framework and design&#13;
which contributed to the MDFâ&#128;&#153;s success in supporting the Government of Indonesiaâ&#128;&#153;s reconstruction&#13;
agenda. The model was applied equally well for the Java Reconstruction Fund, demonstrating its&#13;
replicability and adaptability. This paper offers the key lessons learned from these two programs&#13;
to help inform the design and implementation of post-crisis reconstruction programs elsewhere.&#13;
&#13;
Collectively, the lessons and experiences from the MDF and JRF form a legacy of the remarkable&#13;
achievements of these two programs and the effective partnerships on which they were based.&#13;
We hope that the lessons captured in these papers will contribute to future reconstruction and&#13;
preparedness efforts in Indonesia and other disaster-prone countries around the world.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Shamima Khan&#13;
Manager&#13;
The Multi Donor Fund for Aceh and Nias&#13;
The Java Reconstruction Fund&#13;
December 2012&#13;
&amp;#12;TABLE OF CONTENTS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS	4&#13;
THE MDF-JRF WORKING PAPER SERIES	                   5&#13;
THE DISASTERS â&#128;&#147; A MAP OF INDONESIA	                 8&#13;
A SERIES OF DISASTERS IN INDONESIA	                 10&#13;
ABOUT THE MULTI DONOR FUND FOR ACEH AND NIAS (MDF)	 15&#13;
ABOUT THE JAVA RECONSTRUCTION FUND (JRF)	           20&#13;
&#13;
EXECUTIVE SUMMARY	                                                         22&#13;
&#13;
INTRODUCTION	30&#13;
&#13;
CHAPTER 1 â&#128;&#147; BACKGROUND AND CONTEXT	                                        32		&#13;
	 1.1 Setting the Stage for the MDF: The International Aid Architecture	   33		&#13;
	 1.2 Motivations and Interests of MDF Stakeholders 	                      35		&#13;
	&#13;
&amp;#12;CHAPTER 2 â&#128;&#147; THE STRATEGIC FRAMEWORK FOR THE MDF	             40		&#13;
	 2.1 Strong Partnerships for Results	                       41&#13;
	 2.2 Effective Implementation Strategies	                   46&#13;
	 2.3 Cross-Cutting Considerations	                          50&#13;
	 2.4 Strong Accountability Framework	                       52&#13;
	 2.5 The MDF Experience on Aid Effectiveness	               56&#13;
&#13;
CHAPTER 3 â&#128;&#147; LESSONS LEARNED FROM THE MDF	                   60&#13;
	 3.1 An Organization Structure Based on Partnerships	      61		&#13;
	 3.2 Phased Implementation of Recovery and Reconstruction	 62		&#13;
	 3.3 An Early Start on Qualitative Elements	               62&#13;
		&#13;
CONCLUSION	64&#13;
ANNEXES	68&#13;
ACRONYMS AND ABBREVIATIONS	                                 86&#13;
&amp;#12;THE DISASTERS â&#128;&#147; A MAP OF INDONESIA&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         December 2004:                          March 2005:&#13;
         Earthquake &amp; Tsunami                    Earthquake&#13;
         â&#128;¢ 220,000 people perished &amp; missing     â&#128;¢ 1,000 people perished&#13;
         â&#128;¢ 585,000 people displaced              â&#128;¢ 50,000 people displaced&#13;
         â&#128;¢ Estimated damages: US$4.5 billion     â&#128;¢ Estimated damages: US$390 million&#13;
         ACEH AND NIAS ISLANDS                   NIAS ISLANDS AND ACEH&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       JAKARTA&#13;
July 2006:&#13;
Tsunami&#13;
â&#128;¢ 1,000 people perished&#13;
â&#128;¢ 50,000 people displaced&#13;
â&#128;¢ Estimated damages: US$110 million&#13;
WEST JAVA&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
May 2006:&#13;
                                               October - November 2010:&#13;
Earthquake&#13;
                                               Volcanic Eruptions&#13;
â&#128;¢ 5,700 people perished&#13;
                                               â&#128;¢ 300 people perished&#13;
â&#128;¢ 40,000 people injured&#13;
                                               â&#128;¢ 350,000 people displaced&#13;
â&#128;¢ Estimated damages: US$3.1 billion&#13;
                                               â&#128;¢ Estimated damages: US$360 million&#13;
YOGYAKARTA AND CENTRAL JAVA&#13;
                                               MOUNT MERAPI&#13;
&amp;#12;&amp;#12;10&#13;
&#13;
                                     A SERIES OF DISASTERS IN INDONESIA&#13;
A Series of Disasters in Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     Indonesia is one of the most disaster prone countries in the world. It is vulnerable to earthquakes,&#13;
                                     tsunamis, landslides, floods, volcanic eruptions, and wildfires. Between 2004 and 2010 Indonesia&#13;
                                     experienced a series of devastating natural disasters which attracted an outpouring of support&#13;
                                     from around the world.&#13;
&#13;
                                     December 2004â&#128;&#148;Earthquake and Tsunami in Aceh&#13;
&#13;
                                     The earthquake and tsunami that struck Indonesia and several other countries in the Indian Ocean&#13;
                                     region on December 26, 2004 was one of the worst natural disasters in recorded human history.&#13;
                                     The massive earthquake measuring 9.1 on the Richter scale was centered in the Indian Ocean&#13;
                                     about 150 kilometers off the coast of the province of Aceh on the northernmost tip of the island&#13;
                                     of Sumatra. Huge tidal waves fanned across the Indian Ocean, causing death and destruction&#13;
                                     across Southern Asia including Thailand, Bangladesh, Sri Lanka, India, and as far away as East&#13;
                                     Africa. No country suffered more than Indonesia. Waves towering ten meters high came&#13;
                                     crashing into the shoreline in Aceh. The scale of physical devastation and human suffering was&#13;
                                     enormous. In Aceh alone, 221,000 people were killed or missing, and over a half million were left&#13;
                                     homeless. As many as 750,000 people lost their livelihoods. At all levels, infrastructure was&#13;
                                     paralyzed or completely destroyed.&#13;
&#13;
                                     In minutes, human settlements along the coastline of Aceh and parts of North Sumatra were&#13;
                                     demolished. People, houses, boats, cars, and buildings were engulfed as the tsunami swallowed&#13;
                                     everything in its way. Villages were reduced to rubble where minutes before thriving communities&#13;
                                     had flourished. Many roads, bridges, communications systems, schools, hospitals and clinics&#13;
                                     collapsed or were severely damaged. Fishermen, farmers and others lost their livelihoods and&#13;
                                     many businesses were destroyed or could no longer operate.&#13;
&#13;
                                     The subsequent assessment of the impact of both disasters, conducted by the Government along&#13;
                                     with the World Bank and other partners, assessed the damage and needs to be US$4.9 billion.1 This&#13;
                                     figure was later revised to $6.2 billion.&#13;
&#13;
                                     The massive destruction in Aceh seriously affected provincial and local governments already&#13;
                                     weakened by years of conflict. The tsunami destroyed 21 percent of public buildings and 19 percent&#13;
                                     of the equipment in these buildings. Approximately nine percent of civil servants perished and at&#13;
                                     least 21 percent of surviving civil servants were severely affected, impacting their ability to function&#13;
                                     as a local government. Twenty-seven percent of public records were destroyed. The replacement&#13;
                                     value of these losses was estimated to be over $81 million.&#13;
&#13;
                                     Prior to the tsunami, governance in Aceh already faced numerous challenges, including lack of&#13;
                                     institutional capacity and inefficient delivery of public services such as health and education,&#13;
                                     especially in the rural areas. The tsunami exacerbated these challenges to say the least, and the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     	&#13;
                                     1&#13;
                                         All $ amounts in this report refer to US dollars.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                                     11&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                          A Framework for Reconstruction through Effective Partnerships&#13;
                                                                                                          The Multi Donor Fund for Aceh and Nias:&#13;
Many people were saved from the tsunami by taking refuge in Acehâ&#128;&#153;s Grand Mosque. They       Photo:&#13;
could only watch helplessly as the torrent raged through the streets, carrying debris and   Antara News&#13;
victims along with it.                                                                      Agency&#13;
&#13;
provincial and local governments were not in a position to manage the immense and extensive&#13;
recovery effort that would be required. The national government stepped in urgently to take the&#13;
lead in the reconstruction process.&#13;
&#13;
March 2005â&#128;&#148;Earthquake in North Sumatra and Aceh&#13;
&#13;
Just three months later on March 28, 2005, another massive earthquake measuring 8.7 on the&#13;
Richter scale struck Aceh and the neighboring province of North Sumatra. This quake devastated&#13;
the Nias islands in the province of North Sumatra, located in the Indian Ocean 130 kilometers off&#13;
the western coast of Sumatra just south of Aceh. The island of Simeulue, part of the province of&#13;
Aceh off the western coast of the mainland, was also hard hit. This second disaster resulted in the&#13;
death of nearly 1,000 people and the displacement of nearly 50,000 survivors. The earthquake&#13;
wreaked more havoc on an already ravaged area. The physical damage was severe. Approximately&#13;
30 percent of buildings were destroyed. The destruction rendered transportation and other critical&#13;
infrastructure inoperative, including the major ports linking the remote island populations with the&#13;
mainland. Nias and Simeulue stood among the poorest areas of Indonesia prior to the disasters and&#13;
were only further isolated by the destruction of the earthquake.&#13;
&#13;
These two disasters devastated two areas of Indonesia that were already grappling with multiple&#13;
challenges. The province of Aceh was in the grip of an internal conflict between the Acehnese&#13;
&amp;#12;12&#13;
A Series of Disasters in Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     Many roads, bridges, communication systems, school and other infrastructure collapsed or sustained   Photo:&#13;
                                     such serious damage that they could no longer be used as the result of the disasters. Much of the    IREP-IRFF&#13;
                                     coastline of Aceh was swallowed by the sea and most ports were annihilated.                          Team&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     separatist rebel movement and the Indonesian military. This conflict, stretching over thirty years,&#13;
                                     had paralyzed development and economic growth, and had seriously weakened both public and&#13;
                                     private sector capacities. At the time of the December 2004 tsunami, poverty in Aceh was 28.4&#13;
                                     percent, substantially higher than the national average of 16.7 percent.2 The districts of Nias&#13;
                                     and South Nias on Nias Island ranked among the poorest districts in Indonesia. Poverty, largely&#13;
                                     attributable to the isolation of the island, was approximately 31 percent at the time of the March&#13;
                                     2005 earthquake.3 These dual challenges of poverty and isolation created an extremely difficult&#13;
                                     operating environment for reconstruction in Nias.&#13;
                                     	&#13;
                                     The local governments, already weakened by the conflict in Aceh and isolation in Nias, were&#13;
                                     initially overwhelmed by the disasters. Recognizing this, and recognizing the magnitude of the&#13;
                                     reconstruction task at hand, the central government created the Agency for the Reconstruction&#13;
                                     and Rehabilitation of Aceh and Nias (Badan Rekonstruksi dan Rehabilitasi Aceh dan Nias, widely&#13;
                                     known as the BRR) to manage reconstruction. This special agency was based in Aceh and led by a&#13;
                                     minister-level appointee who reported directly to the President.&#13;
                                     	&#13;
&#13;
                                     	&#13;
                                     2&#13;
                                         World Bank 2008&#13;
                                     	&#13;
                                     3&#13;
                                         Indonesia Central Statistics Agency National Social Economics Survey 2005-2007&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                                 13&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                      A Framework for Reconstruction through Effective Partnerships&#13;
                                                                                                      The Multi Donor Fund for Aceh and Nias:&#13;
May 2006â&#128;&#148;Earthquake in Java&#13;
&#13;
Disaster again struck Indonesia on May 27, 2006, when an earthquake measuring 5.9 on the Richter&#13;
scale hit the island of Java, resulting in extensive damage in the province of Central Java and the&#13;
Special Region of Yogyakarta. The earthquake hit one of the most densely populated areas in Asia,&#13;
claiming more than 5,700 lives and destroying over 280,000 homes. Damage to private houses made&#13;
up more than 60 percent of the total destruction, which also affected small and medium enterprises,&#13;
a large number of them home-based industries. While infrastructure suffered comparatively less&#13;
damage, hundreds of thousands of homes and smaller structures were destroyed.&#13;
&#13;
Many houses in the area had been built without proper reinforcement and with low quality&#13;
building materials, resulting in more deaths and damage than would normally be expected from&#13;
an earthquake of this magnitude. Approximately 40,000 people were injured in the earthquake.&#13;
Thousands of people were trapped and buried beneath their toppled houses and buildings.&#13;
&#13;
A joint team led by the National Development Planning Agency (Bappenas), with local governments&#13;
and the international community, prepared the preliminary Damage and Loss Assessment in order&#13;
to determine the overall needs for the rehabilitation and reconstruction phase. Total damage and&#13;
losses from the earthquake were estimated at around $3.1 billion.&#13;
&#13;
The economic impact of the earthquake was particularly heavy because of the concentration of&#13;
home-based industries in the areas destroyed by the earthquake. More than 650,000 workers&#13;
were employed in economic activities directly affected by the earthquake with close to 90 percent&#13;
of damage and losses concentrated in small and medium enterprises. Many of the home-based&#13;
industries in the areaâ&#128;&#153;s important handicraft sector were severely affected. Rebuilding homes&#13;
would also support recovery of home-based businesses and livelihoods.&#13;
&#13;
July 2006â&#128;&#148;West Java Tsunami&#13;
&#13;
Just two months later, on July 17, 2006, a second major submarine earthquake struck off the&#13;
southern coast of Java. The earthquake, measuring a magnitude of 7.7 on the Richter scale,&#13;
triggered a tsunami that caused widespread damage. The tsunami hit the south coast of West&#13;
Java, taking more than 650 lives and displacing over 28,000 people. Almost 1,000 people died&#13;
or remained missing and more than 50,000 people were displaced. Damage and losses reached&#13;
an estimated $112 million. Ciamis district, West Java, was the worst affected. Along the coast of&#13;
Ciamis alone, close to 6,000 families were displaced. The tsunami caused economic destruction in&#13;
the fishing villages and tourist resorts along the south coast of West Java, where large numbers of&#13;
fishing boats were lost and the small fishing ports destroyed.&#13;
&#13;
October and November 2010â&#128;&#148;Mount Merapi Volcanic Eruptions&#13;
&#13;
On October 26, 2010, disaster hit Java once again when Mount Merapi, a volcano located on the&#13;
border between Yogyakarta and Central Java, erupted. This was followed by seven additional major&#13;
eruptions, with the last one occurring on November 11, 2010. For two long weeks, the eruptions&#13;
&amp;#12;14&#13;
A Series of Disasters in Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     spewed hot gas into nearby villages and hot lava accompanied by hot gas flowed into several&#13;
                                     rivers. The clouds of hot ash and poisonous gas combined with heat clouds at temperatures of 600&#13;
                                     to 800 degrees Celsius incinerated everything they reached, including livestock, crops and trees&#13;
                                     that were essential to the livelihoods of evacuees. Ash rain, which blanketed everything in fine&#13;
                                     volcanic dust, was found in cities across Java. All villages within 20 kilometers of the crater were&#13;
                                     evacuated. Along with massive damage to local infrastructure, approximately 2,900 houses were&#13;
                                     destroyed and 350,000 people were displaced and accommodated in evacuation camps. Due to&#13;
                                     timely evacuation, casualties were limited but still almost 300 people perished and more than 500&#13;
                                     were injured. The eruptions impacted areas in the province of Central Java and the Yogyakarta&#13;
                                     Special Region, including some communities that had been affected by the 2006 earthquake and&#13;
                                     were still in the process of rebuilding.&#13;
&#13;
                                     These eruptions resulted in widespread damage to housing and local infrastructure, as well as&#13;
                                     loss of livelihoods. During the eruptions, volcanic debris mixed with rain flowed down the slopes&#13;
                                     of Mount Merapi as massive mud flows. In Java this is known as â&#128;&#156;lahar dinginâ&#128;&#157; or cold lava and&#13;
                                     is made up of ash and sand from the eruption which when combined with rain turns into thick,&#13;
                                     slushy rivers of mud that gather up everything in the way. Cold lava surged down the mountain&#13;
                                     burying entire villages, farms and fields. Huge boulders, trees, houses, livestock, motor bikes, and&#13;
                                     cars were carried away by the mud. Several villages located in the danger zone near the volcano&#13;
                                     were relocated to safer areas.&#13;
&#13;
                                     Facing the Future&#13;
&#13;
                                     The numerous disasters since 2004 are a stark reminder that Indonesia is highly prone to natural&#13;
                                     hazards. Improvements in early warning systems are expected to save lives, as will ensuring that&#13;
                                     homes and other structures are built to seismic resistant standards. Many of the homes destroyed&#13;
                                     during the earthquakes were found to have used poor quality materials and building techniques,&#13;
                                     both of which contributed greatly to the number of lives lost and the high level of damage. Through&#13;
                                     the recovery and reconstruction efforts following these disasters, Indonesia has learned many&#13;
                                     lessons. It has created institutions and put systems in place for disaster risk reduction. As a result&#13;
                                     of the recovery and reconstruction process communities across Aceh, Nias, and Java are more&#13;
                                     resilient to face future disasters.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                                15&#13;
&#13;
ABOUT THE MULTI DONOR FUND FOR ACEH AND NIAS (MDF)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                     A Framework for Reconstruction through Effective Partnerships&#13;
                                                                                                     The Multi Donor Fund for Aceh and Nias:&#13;
The Multi Donor Fund for Aceh and Nias (MDF) was established in April 2005, in response to&#13;
the Government of Indonesiaâ&#128;&#153;s request to coordinate donor support for the reconstruction and&#13;
rehabilitation of affected areas following the December 2004 earthquake and tsunami, and the&#13;
subsequent March 2005 earthquake.&#13;
&#13;
The MDF pools $655 million in contributions from 15 donors. These funds amount to nearly ten&#13;
percent of the overall reconstruction funds. At the request of the Government of Indonesia, the&#13;
World Bank serves as Trustee of the MDF. Grant funds are provided to projects which are&#13;
implemented by government and non-government agencies and communities, with partner&#13;
agencies providing oversight. Partner agencies include the United Nations Development Programme&#13;
(UNDP), the World Food Programme (WFP), the International Labour Organization (ILO) and the&#13;
World Bank.&#13;
&#13;
Under the MDF portfolio, 23 projects were financed in six outcome areas: (1) Recovery of&#13;
Communities; (2) Reconstruction and Rehabilitation of Large Infrastructure and Transport; (3)&#13;
Strengthening Governance and Capacity Building; (4) Sustaining the Environment; (5) Enhancing&#13;
the Recovery Process; and (6) Economic Development and Livelihoods. These projects reflected the&#13;
priorities of the Indonesian government throughout the reconstruction process.&#13;
&#13;
The MDF was coordinated by the Government of Indonesia, initially through the Agency for&#13;
the Rehabilitation and Reconstruction of Aceh and Nias (BRR), which was set up to manage the&#13;
reconstruction and recovery effort. After the BRR closed in April 2009, the National Development&#13;
Planning Agency, Bappenas, took on this critical role. The MDF is governed by a Steering Committee&#13;
with representatives from the government, donors, the trustee, and civil society. The Steering&#13;
Committee is supported in its work by a secretariat.&#13;
&#13;
                                         MDF Contributions&#13;
&#13;
                            MDF Donors                  Contributions (US$ million)&#13;
               European Union                                     271.31&#13;
               Government of the Netherlands                      146.20&#13;
               Government of the United Kingdom                   68.50&#13;
               World Bank                                         25.00&#13;
               Government of Sweden                               20.72&#13;
               Government of Canada                               20.22&#13;
               Government of Norway                               19.57&#13;
               Government of Denmark                              18.03&#13;
               Government of Germany                              13.93&#13;
               Government of Belgium                              11.05&#13;
               Government of Finland                              10.13&#13;
               Asian Development Bank                             10.00&#13;
               Government of the United States                    10.00&#13;
               Government of New Zealand                           8.80&#13;
               Government of Ireland                               1.20&#13;
                Total Contributions:                              654.67&#13;
&amp;#12;16&#13;
About the Multi Donor Fund for Aceh and Nias (MDF)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                     The MDF provides a successful model for post-disaster reconstruction based on partnerships&#13;
                                                     between government, donors, communities and other stakeholders. The partnerships created&#13;
                                                     by the MDF have played a key role in the strong performance of the program and robust results&#13;
                                                     achieved. Pooling resources through the MDF has resulted in the harmonization of donor efforts&#13;
                                                     and provided an important platform for policy dialogue for many stakeholders. The MDF has&#13;
                                                     filled gaps in the reconstruction in line with government priorities and has brought together key&#13;
                                                     government players, donors, and members of civil society and communities. The MDFâ&#128;&#153;s strong&#13;
                                                     support for coordination of the overall reconstruction effort has resulted in huge multiplier effects&#13;
                                                     so that the MDFâ&#128;&#153;s impact has been able to exceed the value of its contributions.&#13;
&#13;
                                                     The MDF Portfolio&#13;
&#13;
                                                     The MDFâ&#128;&#153;s portfolio was designed to meet the changing needs of Aceh and Nias as they progressed&#13;
                                                     from recovery to rebuilding infrastructure to laying the foundations of economic development.&#13;
                                                     Consisting of 23 projects in six outcome areas, the projects were implemented by government&#13;
                                                     and non-government partners, including national and provincial governments, agencies of the&#13;
                                                     United Nations, international development institutions, and non-governmental organizations.&#13;
                                                     Environmental sustainability, gender, capacity building and disaster risk reduction were important&#13;
                                                     cross-cutting elements of the MDF program throughout its life cycle.&#13;
&#13;
                                                     1. Recovery of Communities (5 projects totaling $202 million)&#13;
                                                     The first group of MDF projects supported recovery of communities, with a focus on housing&#13;
                                                     and local infrastructure. Using a community-driven approach and implemented by government,&#13;
                                                     these programs enabled disaster survivors to re-establish their communities and begin rebuilding&#13;
                                                     their lives.&#13;
&#13;
                                                     â&#128;¢	 The Community-Based Settlement Rehabilitation and Reconstruction Project, better&#13;
                                                        known as Rekompak, used a community driven approach to rebuild homes and local&#13;
                                                        infrastructure in Aceh and Nias. Implemented by the Ministry of Public Works (MPW) and&#13;
                                                        managed by the World Bank, Rekompak rebuilt nearly 15,000 houses and restored basic&#13;
                                                        infrastructure to 180 villages.&#13;
&#13;
                                                     â&#128;¢	 The Community Recovery through the Kecamatan Development Project (KDP) was part of a&#13;
                                                        national program and partly funded by the MDF. Through KDP, the MDF assisted communities&#13;
                                                        in Aceh and Nias to plan and manage the reconstruction of rural infrastructure, schools,&#13;
                                                        clinics, and other public buildings. It also provided business training and loans. The project was&#13;
                                                        implemented by the Ministry of Home Affairs (MoHA) and managed by the World Bank.&#13;
&#13;
                                                     â&#128;¢	 The Community Recovery through the Urban Poverty Program (UPP) provided support for&#13;
                                                        reconstruction to urban communities to rehabilitate and develop community infrastructure&#13;
                                                        in municipalities in Aceh. UPP repaired urban infrastructure, rebuilt schools and other public&#13;
                                                        buildings, and provided scholarships. The project was implemented by the MPW and managed&#13;
                                                        by the World Bank.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                                  17&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                       A Framework for Reconstruction through Effective Partnerships&#13;
                                                                                                       The Multi Donor Fund for Aceh and Nias:&#13;
â&#128;¢	 The Kecamatan-Based Reconstruction and Rehabilitation Planning in Nias Project (KRRP) was&#13;
   a community-based recovery and planning project for reconstruction in Nias. Implemented by&#13;
   the MoHA and managed by the World Bank, it rebuilt houses, schools, public buildings, and&#13;
   village infrastructure.&#13;
&#13;
â&#128;¢	 The Reconstruction of Aceh Land Administration System (RALAS) restored land property rights&#13;
   and a computerized land records management system. Over 220,000 land title certificates were&#13;
   issued, nearly one-third to women. The project was implemented by the National Land Agency&#13;
   (BPN) and managed by the World Bank.&#13;
&#13;
2. Recovery of Large Infrastructure and Transport (7 projects totaling $217 million)&#13;
The MDF, working in partnership with the Government of Indonesia, contributed significantly&#13;
to the reconstruction of large infrastructure in Aceh and Nias. These projects restored&#13;
transportation links and critical infrastructure, thereby improving peopleâ&#128;&#153;s lives and providing new&#13;
economic opportunities.&#13;
&#13;
â&#128;¢	 The Banda Aceh Flood Mitigation Project (BAFMP), implemented by Muslim Aid and managed&#13;
   by the World Bank, repaired pumping stations, flood valves, and drainage systems damaged by&#13;
   the tsunami to protect the central business area of Banda Aceh from storm and tidal flooding.&#13;
&#13;
â&#128;¢	 The Infrastructure Reconstruction Enabling Program (IREP) and its companion project, the&#13;
   Infrastructure Reconstruction Financing Facility (IRFF), planned, designed, and built strategic&#13;
   infrastructure such as roads, water systems and bridges in Aceh and Nias. Co-financed by BRR,&#13;
   the projects were implemented by the MPW and managed by the World Bank.&#13;
&#13;
â&#128;¢	 The Lamno-Calang Road Maintenance Project (LCRMP) maintained a key road from Lamno to&#13;
   Calang to ensure overland access to tsunami-affected communities on Acehâ&#128;&#153;s west coast. The&#13;
   project was implemented by the UNDP.&#13;
&#13;
â&#128;¢	 The Sea Delivery and Logistics Progamme (SDLP) met the urgent recovery transportation&#13;
   needs for construction materials in Aceh and Nias. Implemented by the WFP, it also provided&#13;
   training for better management of ports and disaster-risk reduction.&#13;
&#13;
â&#128;¢	 The Tsunami Recovery Port Redevelopment Programme (TRPRP) rehabilitated damaged ports&#13;
   in Aceh and Nias so that equipment and materials could be supplied to isolated communities.&#13;
   The project, implemented by the UNDP, also provided designs and technical support for&#13;
   reconstructing major sea ports.&#13;
&#13;
â&#128;¢	 The Rural Access and Capacity Building Project (RACBP) helped residents of participating&#13;
   districts in Nias effectively use improved rural transport infrastructure and services to take&#13;
   advantage of economic opportunities and social services. Implemented by the ILO, it also&#13;
   included a cultural heritage component.&#13;
&amp;#12;18&#13;
About the Multi Donor Fund for Aceh and Nias (MDF)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                     3. Economic Development and Livelihoods (2 projects totaling $58 million)&#13;
                                                     Restoring livelihoods is an important part of disaster recovery. These projects strengthened&#13;
                                                     important sectors that provide employment and income to Aceh and Nias, paving the way for long-&#13;
                                                     term economic growth.&#13;
&#13;
                                                     â&#128;¢	 The Aceh Economic Development Financing Facility (EDFF) promoted post-tsunami&#13;
                                                        economic recovery. Managed by the World Bank, the EDFF was implemented by the&#13;
                                                        Ministry for Development of Disadvantaged Areas (KPDT) and the Government of Aceh. The&#13;
                                                        project provided sub-grants to support growth in key sectors including coffee, cocoa, rice,&#13;
                                                        meat and fisheries.&#13;
&#13;
                                                     â&#128;¢	 The Nias Islands Livelihoods and Economic Development Program (LEDP) provided training&#13;
                                                        to improve technical and business skills for livelihoods and overall economic development.&#13;
                                                        Implemented by KPDT and managed by the World Bank, the project also developed skills within&#13;
                                                        local government for implementing livelihoods programs in Nias.&#13;
&#13;
                                                     4. Strengthening Governance and Capacity Building (3 projects totaling $40 million)&#13;
                                                     The MDF encouraged good governance and strengthened the capacity of local communities and&#13;
                                                     district governments. It encouraged the development of civil society organizations involved in the&#13;
                                                     reconstruction process.&#13;
&#13;
                                                     â&#128;¢	 The Capacity Building for Local Resource-based Rural Roads (CBLR3) strengthened the&#13;
                                                        capacity of district government and small-scale contractors to undertake local road works. The&#13;
                                                        project was implemented by the ILO.&#13;
&#13;
                                                     â&#128;¢	 The Support for Poor and Disadvantaged Areas Project in Aceh and Nias (SPADA) project,&#13;
                                                        implemented by KPDT and managed by the World Bank, strengthened local participation in&#13;
                                                        development planning, promoted private investment and job creation, and improved health,&#13;
                                                        education and dispute resolution services. The project complemented a national program&#13;
                                                        funded by a World Bank loan.&#13;
&#13;
                                                     â&#128;¢	 Support to Strengthen the Capacity and Role of Civil Society Organizations (CSO),&#13;
                                                        implemented by the UNDP, built the capacity of local civil society organizations in Aceh and&#13;
                                                        Nias to enhance grass-roots participation in the reconstruction process.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                                  19&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                       A Framework for Reconstruction through Effective Partnerships&#13;
                                                                                                       The Multi Donor Fund for Aceh and Nias:&#13;
5. Enhancing the Recovery Process (4 projects totaling $56 million)&#13;
In order to strengthen government capacity to manage the recovery effort, the MDF provided&#13;
technical assistance and operational support to BRR and other government agencies.&#13;
&#13;
â&#128;¢	 The Aceh Government Transformation Programme (AGTP) provided strategic support to the&#13;
   government of Aceh to provide the capacity and institutional strength to take over projects,&#13;
   resources, and assume oversight of reconstruction and recovery programs after the closure&#13;
   of BRR in April, 2009. The project was implemented by the MoHA and Provincial Government&#13;
   of Aceh and managed by the UNDP.&#13;
&#13;
â&#128;¢	 Making Aceh Safer through Disaster Risk Reduction in Development (DRR-A) established&#13;
   disaster risk reduction in Acehâ&#128;&#153;s local government agencies, its public and private partners, and&#13;
   local communities. The project was implemented by the MoHA and Provincial Government&#13;
   of Aceh, and managed by the UNDP.&#13;
&#13;
â&#128;¢	 The Nias Island Transformation Programme (NITP), managed by the UNDP and implemented&#13;
   by the MoHA and local governments in Nias, enhanced district capacity to successfully complete&#13;
   the recovery process and reduce risks from future natural disasters.&#13;
&#13;
â&#128;¢	 Technical Assistance to the BRR and Bappenas (TS-R2C3), managed by the UNDP, the project&#13;
   supported BRR in managing the overall recovery process. After BRR closed in April 2009,&#13;
   the project worked with Bappenas and was referred to as Rehabilitation and Reconstruction&#13;
   Completion and Continued Coordination (TS-R2C3).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
6. Sustaining the Environment (2 projects totaling $57 million)&#13;
Throughout the recovery process, the MDF committed to protecting the environment. The MDF&#13;
played an important part in post-disaster cleanup and long-term waste management. It also&#13;
worked to protect the ecosystems of Aceh and Nias.&#13;
&#13;
â&#128;¢	 The Tsunami Recovery Waste Management Programme (TRWMP) helped local government&#13;
   clear, recycle and dispose of tsunami waste, rehabilitate waste management infrastructure,&#13;
   and implement sustainable solid waste management systems. It also promoted livelihoods&#13;
   related to waste management. The project was implemented by the UNDP.&#13;
&#13;
â&#128;¢	 The Aceh Forest &amp; Environment Project (AFEP) worked closely with communities, civil society&#13;
   and government to protect the Leuser and Ulu Masen forests from illegal logging and promoted&#13;
   sustainable forest management. Managed by the World Bank, the project was implemented&#13;
   by Fauna &amp; Flora International (FFI) and Leuser International Foundation (LIF).&#13;
&amp;#12;20&#13;
&#13;
                                           ABOUT THE JAVA RECONSTRUCTION FUND (JRF)&#13;
About the Java Reconstruction Fund (JRF)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                           Following a request from the Government of Indonesia, the Java Reconstruction Fund (JRF) was&#13;
                                           established to respond to the May 27, 2006 earthquake that struck near Yogyakarta, and the&#13;
                                           tsunami that hit the southern coast of West Java Province in July 2006. The JRF was later extended&#13;
                                           to respond to volcanic eruptions of Mount Merapi in October and November of 2010. The JRF&#13;
                                           program closed on December 31, 2012.&#13;
&#13;
                                           The JRF is based on the successful model of the Multi Donor Fund for Aceh and Nias. Seven&#13;
                                           donors supported the JRF with contributions totaling $94.1 million. The donors are: the European&#13;
                                           Union, the Governments of the Netherlands, United Kingdom, the Asian Development Bank,&#13;
                                           Canada, Finland and Denmark. The World Bank serves as Trustee of the JRF. Following the&#13;
                                           governmentâ&#128;&#153;s priorities, the JRF supports the recovery of communities and livelihoods, and&#13;
                                           increases disaster preparedness.&#13;
&#13;
                                           The JRF was coordinated by the Government of Indonesia, initially through the Governmentâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
                                           National Coordinating Team (NCT) and the National Technical Team (TTN). After the mandate of&#13;
                                           the NCT and the TTN ended in 2008, the JRF worked with the National Development Planning&#13;
                                           Agency (Bappenas) and the Provincial Planning Agencies (Bappeda) for the overall coordination of&#13;
                                           the reconstruction.&#13;
&#13;
                                           Using a governance structure similar to the MDF, the JRF was governed by a Steering Committee&#13;
                                           with representatives from the Government of Indonesia and donors. Bappenas co-chaired the&#13;
                                           Steering Committee, along with the European Union as the largest donor, and the World Bank&#13;
                                           as Trustee. The Steering Committee is supported by a secretariat. Through shared staffing and&#13;
                                           expertise with the MDF for Aceh and Nias, the secretariat achieved efficiencies of scale, resulting in&#13;
                                           reduced program administration costs.&#13;
&#13;
                                           The JRF portfolio consisted of five projects which drew from the MDFâ&#128;&#153;s experience and used a&#13;
                                           phased approach to address: (1) Transitional Housing; (2) Restoring Housing and Community&#13;
                                           Infrastructure; and (3) Restoring Livelihoods. The World Bank had a supervisory and oversight role&#13;
                                           on all JRF projects as the partner agency.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                    JRF Contributions&#13;
&#13;
                                                                       JRF Donors                    Contributions (US$ million)&#13;
                                                          European Union                                        51.17&#13;
                                                          Government of the Netherlands                         12.00&#13;
                                                          Government of the United Kingdom                      10.77&#13;
                                                          Asian Development Bank                                10.00&#13;
                                                          Government of Canada                                  6.53&#13;
                                                          Government of Finland                                 1.99&#13;
                                                          Government of Denmark	                                1.60&#13;
                                                           Total Contributions:                                 94.06&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                                    21&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                         A Framework for Reconstruction through Effective Partnerships&#13;
                                                                                                         The Multi Donor Fund for Aceh and Nias:&#13;
The JRF Portfolio&#13;
&#13;
The JRF portfolio followed a phased approach to reconstruction, adopting lessons learned from&#13;
the MDF. Early support focused on meeting housing and community recovery needs and&#13;
subsequent support focused on addressing economic recovery. The JRF prioritized disaster risk&#13;
reduction in all its programs. Five projects were supported:&#13;
&#13;
â&#128;¢	 Transitional Housing Projects (2 projects totaling $2.3 million). The JRF financed two transitional&#13;
housing projects, implemented by the International Organisation for Migration (IOM) and&#13;
Cooperative Housing Foundation (CHF) International and managed by the World Bank. The projects&#13;
provided nearly 5,000 transitional shelters.&#13;
&#13;
â&#128;¢	 The Community-based Settlement Rehabilitation and Reconstruction Project (1 project&#13;
totaling $75.1 million), better known as Rekompak, made up most of the JRF funding allocation.&#13;
Following the model established in Aceh, it used a community driven approach to rebuild homes&#13;
and local infrastructure in earthquake affected areas of Yogyakarta Special District, and Central&#13;
Java, and later, parts of West Java affected by a subsequent earthquake and tsunami. After&#13;
the 2010 eruptions of Mount Merapi, the project was expanded further. Implemented by the&#13;
Ministry of Public Works (MPW) and managed by the World Bank, the project rebuilt over 15,000&#13;
houses and completed over 4,000 local infrastructure projects.&#13;
&#13;
â&#128;¢	 Livelihood Recovery Projects (2 projects totaling $17.1 million):&#13;
   -	The Livelihood Recovery in Yogyakarta Special District and Central Java project&#13;
   contributed to the Government of Indonesiaâ&#128;&#153;s initiatives to assist micro, small and medium&#13;
   enterprises (MSMEs) affected by the earthquake to revitalize their businesses and re integrate&#13;
   affected low-income communities into economic life. The project provided access to finance,&#13;
   developed loan work-out strategies for defaulting borrowers, restored capacity and improved&#13;
   competitiveness of medium-sized companies in Yogyakarta and Central Java. The project&#13;
   was implemented by the Deutsche Gesellschaft fÃ¼r Internationale Zusammenarbeit (GIZ) and&#13;
   managed by the World Bank.&#13;
&#13;
  -	 The Access to Finance and Capacity Building for Earthquake Affected Micro             and Small&#13;
  Enterprises project, implemented by the IOM and managed by the World Bank,               supported&#13;
  the recovery of micro and small enterprises in Yogyakarta and Central Java               to enable&#13;
  them to reach their pre-earthquake capacity. It provided asset replacement,              marketing&#13;
  support, and techical assistance. The project worked with over 4,000 micro               and small&#13;
  enterprises (MSEs), over 40 percent run or owned by women.&#13;
&amp;#12;22&#13;
&#13;
                    EXECUTIVE SUMMARY&#13;
Executive Summary&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       The MDF Mission Statement:&#13;
&#13;
                                       â&#128;&#156;The Multi-Donor Fund for Aceh and Nias is a partnership of the international&#13;
                                       community, Indonesian government and civil society to support the recovery&#13;
                                       following the earthquakes and tsunami. It contributes to the recovery process&#13;
                                       by providing grants for quality investments that are based on good practice,&#13;
                                       stakeholder participation, and coordination with others. In doing so, the&#13;
                                       Multi-Donor Fund seeks to reduce poverty, (re)build capacity, support good&#13;
                                       governance and enhance sustainable development.â&#128;&#157; 1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  The Multi Donor Fund for Aceh and Nias (MDF), established to support the post-tsunami&#13;
                                  reconstruction of Aceh and Nias, is widely considered to be one of the most successful&#13;
                                  programs of its kind. The fundamental and core factors for this success have been the&#13;
                                  leadership of the Government of Indonesia (GoI) and the partnership of stakeholders&#13;
                                  to support the governmentâ&#128;&#153;s agenda. Many other factors and perspectives come into&#13;
                                  play, all of which reinforce and enhance the effectiveness of partnerships in delivering&#13;
                                  a remarkable result.&#13;
&#13;
                                  The MDF was established with the Paris Declaration as its backdrop. While&#13;
                                  operationalizing the aid effectiveness principles of Parisâ&#128;&#148;ownership, alignment,&#13;
                                  harmonization, results and accountabilityâ&#128;&#148;was not a primary objective, the MDF&#13;
                                  program implementation exemplifies the Paris declaration in action.&#13;
&#13;
                                  In the course of seven years of operation, the MDF has brought together partners&#13;
                                  spanning all levels of government (central, provincial, local), donors, partner and&#13;
                                  implementing agencies, non-government actors, and communities. Together, these&#13;
                                  partners have helped to move Aceh and Nias forward from conflict and fragility&#13;
                                  through post-disaster reconstruction to a platform for effective development.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    1	&#13;
                         MDF Recovery Assistance Policy (RAP), 2005.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                                            23&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                 A Framework for Reconstruction through Effective Partnerships&#13;
                                                                                                                 The Multi Donor Fund for Aceh and Nias:&#13;
      The MDF adopted a phased approach to address the needs of disaster survivors and for         Photo:&#13;
      a more effective implementation. In the first phase, it financed reconstruction of housing   MDF&#13;
      and local infrastructure with involvement of local communities.                              Secretariat&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Context and Challenges of Reconstruction&#13;
      Aceh and Nias presented multilayered challenges. The magnitude of the disaster was&#13;
      unprecedented in terms of human losses and physical damage. Both Aceh and Nias&#13;
      faced serious governance challenges, and had weak and fragmented local capacities.&#13;
      In Aceh, the natural disaster took place in a province that had been battered by a&#13;
      bloody civil war for the past 30 years. In Nias, difficulties of a fragile environment&#13;
      were compounded by years of isolation and neglect. Local administrations lacked skills&#13;
      to handle the massive reconstruction. The partnership of national and international&#13;
      stakeholders needed a financing mechanism able to deal with delivering reconstruction&#13;
      in this complex context, and the MDF was established to meet this need.&#13;
&#13;
      In coming together to support reconstruction, the motivations of the many&#13;
      stakeholders were varied, but complementary. For the government, providing&#13;
      leadership was essential. To this end, the government wanted to use its own systems&#13;
&amp;#12;24&#13;
Executive Summary&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                          The second phase of the MDF built complex infrastructure such as the water treatment   Photo:&#13;
                          plant for Sabang under the IRFF project.                                               Irwansyah&#13;
                                                                                                                 Putra&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                          and have a clear say in the choice of investments and instruments to respond to local&#13;
                          needs. Donors wanted to be partners in decision making, and needed accountability&#13;
                          for funds, visibility of their contributions, and effective results. Other development&#13;
                          partners, including international agencies and civil society, sought to contribute based&#13;
                          on their comparative advantages to establish good operations and strong partnerships&#13;
                          to support affected peoples. For the World Bank as Trustee, ensuring effective results&#13;
                          and accountability of funds were of paramount importance. And the most important&#13;
                          players in this arena, the communities themselves, needed to feel that peace and&#13;
                          reconstruction dividends were forthcoming, and that they were part of the process to&#13;
                          define local priorities. While they had no control over the disasters of the past, they&#13;
                          needed to have some control over rebuilding their own future.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    A Strategic Framework for Reconstruction&#13;
                          The framework for the MDF was based on three interrelated strategies of strong&#13;
                          partnerships, effective implementation and focus on cross-cutting, qualitative aspects.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                            25&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                 A Framework for Reconstruction through Effective Partnerships&#13;
                                                                                                 The Multi Donor Fund for Aceh and Nias:&#13;
       These strategies can elevate programs from being good to being extraordinary in&#13;
       fulfilling the hopes of affected people.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Strong Partnerships for Results&#13;
       The most critical driver of the MDF success has been GoI leadership of recovery in&#13;
       Aceh and Nias. The Government of Indonesia took the lead to conduct and complete&#13;
       the Damage and Loss Assessment (DALA) within the first month of the tsunami. The&#13;
       Master Plan for Rehabilitation and Reconstruction was developed to prioritize results-&#13;
       oriented operational programs.&#13;
&#13;
       A special agency with ministerial level authority was established, the Agency&#13;
       for Rehabilitation and Reconstruction of Aceh and Nias (BRR), to coordinate the&#13;
       reconstruction efforts and implement the Master Plan. In another, somewhat smaller&#13;
       disaster, the 2006 Java earthquake, Indonesia has relied on regular government&#13;
       systems to effectively manage and coordinate large-scale reconstruction efforts. These&#13;
       experiences show that the type of organizational structure should be designed to fit&#13;
       the nature and scope of a disaster, as long as the commitment and strength of the&#13;
       governmentâ&#128;&#153;s leadership role that is essential to the success of the reconstruction&#13;
       effort is maintained.&#13;
&#13;
       Support from development partners was aligned to the GoIâ&#128;&#153;s agenda. With the&#13;
       governmentâ&#128;&#153;s leadership of the reconstruction agenda, other partners were able to&#13;
       align their support under one framework. The MDF was established to support the&#13;
       GoIâ&#128;&#153;s Master Plan and operate in alignment with its institutions and procedures. Over&#13;
       70 percent of the MDF funds were channeled through the national budget, utilizing&#13;
       the countryâ&#128;&#153;s public financial management system.&#13;
&#13;
       The MDF signified different things to different donors. For the larger donors, the&#13;
       MDF provided an opportunity for influencing policy and operations at many levels&#13;
       of the reconstruction effort. To relatively smaller donors, it was the best way to help&#13;
       without requiring major operations. For many others, it was the best tool to support&#13;
       a multilateral approach, as well as a vehicle for minimizing transaction costs and&#13;
       maximizing the impact of aid money, with assurance of high fiduciary management&#13;
       standards. The MDF provided a single platform for 15 donors to plan, fund, disburse,&#13;
       monitor, evaluate and report on MDFâ&#128;&#153;s activities.&#13;
&#13;
       The mix of partner agencies and implementing agencies under the MDF minimized&#13;
       fragmentation and provided the opportunity to use individual organizationsâ&#128;&#153;&#13;
&amp;#12;26&#13;
Executive Summary&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                          comparative advantages. Major multilateral organizations such as the United Nations&#13;
                          Development Programme (UNDP), the International Labour Organization (ILO),&#13;
                          the World Food Programme (WFP) and the World Bank served as partner agencies.&#13;
                          Implementing agencies included government line ministries and international&#13;
                          NGOs. The partner agencies carried out the appraisal, supervision, monitoring&#13;
                          and evaluation of MDF funded projects, and administered grants from the MDF to&#13;
                          finance them, applying their own fiduciary framework and governance arrangements.&#13;
                          The implementing agencies brought different strengths in terms of capacity and&#13;
                          procedures. This arrangement led to a multi-pronged response to the governmentâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
                          recovery agenda, allowing greater speed and coverage than would otherwise have&#13;
                          been possible.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    An Inclusive and Effective Governance Structure&#13;
                          The success of the MDF was also due to an inclusive governance structure, with a&#13;
                          Steering Committee comprised of representatives from BRR, the National Development&#13;
                          Planning Agency (Bappenas), Ministry of Finance, and Governments of Aceh and North&#13;
                          Sumatra, the 15 donors to the MDF, as well as representatives of Acehâ&#128;&#153;s civil society,&#13;
                          and observers such as the UN and the international NGO community. Voting members&#13;
                          of the Steering Committee decided on policy and funds allocation, and a Technical&#13;
                          Review Group supported its functions.&#13;
&#13;
                          The MDF also pioneered a multi co-chair arrangement represented by GoI, the&#13;
                          Government of Aceh, European Union representing the donors, and the Bank as the&#13;
                          Trustee. This arrangement supported efficient decision making, consensual working&#13;
                          of the Steering Committee and effective implementation of the MDF. The Steering&#13;
                          Committee meetings became a significant forum for discussion of a wide range of&#13;
                          policy and operational issues for Aceh and Nias.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    Effective Implementation Strategies&#13;
                          The most useful strategy was that of phased implementation, which helped to manage&#13;
                          expectations throughout reconstruction. In any post-crisis situation, there is a tension in&#13;
                          balancing speed of implementation, quality and ownership of reconstruction, and long&#13;
                          term sustainability. These competing goals do not move in tandem, and the inevitable&#13;
                          trade-off was reduced by implementing in three phases. The first phase focused on&#13;
                          immediate recovery of housing, small infrastructure, logistics and transportation links.&#13;
                          The second phase took on major reconstruction of infrastructure and environment,&#13;
                          such as roads, bridges, and ports. The final phase shifted to laying the foundation for&#13;
                          economic development through livelihoods and targeted capacity building.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                                     27&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                          A Framework for Reconstruction through Effective Partnerships&#13;
                                                                                                          The Multi Donor Fund for Aceh and Nias:&#13;
As part of its final phase that focused on laying the foundation for sustainable economic   Photo:&#13;
growth, the MDF supported improved coffee farming, processing and marketing in Aceh,        MDF&#13;
and supported a coffee development research center at a local university in Takengon.       Secretariat&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The principal driver for immediate recovery was speed; the need for quality was&#13;
paramount for the reconstruction; and sustainability was the driver for transition to&#13;
the long-term. The first phase focused on supporting implementation of urgent needs,&#13;
while involving communities so that they were part of the process of reconstruction. This&#13;
resulted in raising beneficiary satisfaction, enhancing social cohesion and contributing&#13;
to the healing process of individuals and communities. In the reconstruction phase,&#13;
focus was on implementation of projects and investments where quality and ownership&#13;
are critical, when procurement and safeguards processes can be complex and outcomes&#13;
will take time. This includes, particularly, investment in large infrastructure. For the&#13;
final phase of transition to economic development, the driver was sustainability. This&#13;
phase supported the transition to long term growth coupled with capacity building, so&#13;
that the impact of reconstruction and the sustainability of donor investments continue&#13;
well beyond the reconstruction program.&#13;
&#13;
Several specific project design elements and operational principles helped the MDF&#13;
to deliver quickly and within the timelines available for reconstruction. With an open&#13;
menu approach, the MDF served as a flexible gap filling instrument, and provided&#13;
support in areas not addressed by other donors or partners. Project selection was also&#13;
geared towards speed by scaling up existing programs/projects wherever possible.&#13;
&amp;#12;28&#13;
Executive Summary&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                          The MDFâ&#128;&#153;s experience shows that it may be more effective to choose projects with&#13;
                          short duration implementation, given the limited time horizon for most reconstruction&#13;
                          programs. A key design lesson learned from the MDFâ&#128;&#153;s success is to have a clear exit&#13;
                          strategy built into project design. The government and the World Bank also utilized&#13;
                          internal approval processes that were streamlined and emergency focused, resulting in&#13;
                          faster implementation. Streamlining government decision making and budget issuance&#13;
                          were significant sources of efficiency. And strong supervision and implementation&#13;
                          support by the partner agencies led to high quality and sustainable investments.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    Some Cross-Cutting Considerations&#13;
                          The scope of the MDFâ&#128;&#153;s support was embodied in its Recovery Assistance Policy&#13;
                          (RAP). The RAP specified that the MDF would provide support for investments based&#13;
                          on good practice, stakeholder participation and coordination with others. The RAP&#13;
                          stipulated that attention should be given to cross-cutting issues such as gender equity,&#13;
                          environmental sustainability, and building capacity for good governance in order to&#13;
                          enhance the quality of the recovery process.&#13;
&#13;
                          For the MDF, relevant cross-cutting elements were capacity development, gender,&#13;
                          environmental and social safeguards, and disaster risk reduction. All projects were&#13;
                          also designed to be conflict sensitive. These elements need to span across all aspects&#13;
                          of the program. Challenges and solutions should be anticipated as early as possible in&#13;
                          order to fully and credibly address them. The solutions need to apply to all projects&#13;
                          across the program; the MDF addressed these through technical and institutional&#13;
                          interventions, and specific and generic approaches.&#13;
&#13;
                          And finally, cross-cutting solutions need to apply at all levels of government or players.&#13;
                          In practical terms, these need to be reflected in the Joint Assessment/ DALA. Even&#13;
                          if a â&#128;&#156;quick and dirtyâ&#128;&#157; analysis is done, it is important to include these cross-cutting&#13;
                          elements in the initial needs assessment to provide a baseline and understanding of&#13;
                          challenges, so that an appropriate strategy and interventions can be designed.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    A Strong Accountability Framework&#13;
                          While quick delivery may seem paramount in a post-conflict or post-disaster situation,&#13;
                          a strong and robust accountability framework is the foundation for good stewardship&#13;
                          of reconstruction programs.&#13;
                          â&#128;¢	 Monitoring and evaluation is important to measure and document results and&#13;
                             lessons learned, and to ensure value for money. The challenge is to develop a&#13;
                             Results Framework that captures program level results from cascading projects that&#13;
                             are often undefined.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                         29&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                              A Framework for Reconstruction through Effective Partnerships&#13;
                                                                                              The Multi Donor Fund for Aceh and Nias:&#13;
      â&#128;¢	 Regular reporting on program outcomes is key to establishing trust and confidence,&#13;
         and to inform citizens both in donor countries as well as in recipient countries&#13;
         regarding the good use of funds.&#13;
      â&#128;¢	 Strategic communications are extremely important for transparency and for&#13;
         managing expectations of all stakeholders. Appropriate communications promotes&#13;
         inclusiveness and allows stakeholdersâ&#128;&#153; engagement on critical issues.&#13;
      â&#128;¢	 Good funds management is a non-negotiable factor for success in any reconstruction&#13;
         program or MDF. This includes sound fiduciary management, as well as transparent&#13;
         and efficient use of funds.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
A Replicable Model for Reconstruction&#13;
      The overall reconstruction of Aceh and Nias, in which the MDF played a strategic&#13;
      and significant role, is widely acknowledged as a successful model for post-&#13;
      disaster reconstruction. The MDF streamlined the governmentâ&#128;&#153;s recovery efforts by&#13;
      coordinating donor resources and providing a single voice and partner for supporting&#13;
      its reconstruction agenda. The strong relationships between government and partners&#13;
      have been a critical element of the MDFâ&#128;&#153;s success.&#13;
&#13;
      The MDF provides a model that can be replicated or adapted in other post-conflict&#13;
      or post-disaster reconstruction scenarios. This has already been proved through the&#13;
      Java Reconstruction Fund (JRF), set up in 2006 to respond to another set of disasters&#13;
      in Indonesia. Based on the MDF experience, the GoI requested the World Bank and&#13;
      donors to establish the JRF, adapting the MDF model to local needs. The experience&#13;
      has successfully demonstrated the flexibility of the model in responding to multiple&#13;
      disasters of earthquakes, tsunamis, landslides, and the volcanic eruptions of Mount&#13;
      Merapi in 2010.&#13;
&#13;
      The MDF model and strategic framework is robust enough to be adjusted for situations&#13;
      where not all factors for success are fully met. The need for government leadership&#13;
      and stakeholder partnership around a local agenda is critically important, and these&#13;
      partnerships can be fostered if they are weak. A phased approach to reconstruction&#13;
      coupled with strategic selection of projects is a smart way to deliver peace and&#13;
      reconstruction dividends. And enhancing capacity and inclusion of communities and&#13;
      government agencies will ensure that a legacy of resilience and preparedness, born&#13;
      from conflict and disaster, will endure into the future.&#13;
&amp;#12;INTRODUCTION&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                                                                            31&#13;
                     Never before had the world come together in such a show of solidarity as it did after&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                 A Framework for Reconstruction through Effective Partnerships&#13;
                                                                                                                                                 The Multi Donor Fund for Aceh and Nias:&#13;
                     the devastating 2004 Asian Tsunami that was triggered by the Great Sumatra-Andaman&#13;
                     Earthquake. The earthquake and tsunami resulted in over 221,000 people killed or&#13;
                     missing in Aceh alone, with additional casualties in a dozen other littoral states of the&#13;
                     Indian Ocean. Shortly thereafter, in March 2005, Indonesia once again received global&#13;
                     attention when another massive earthquake measuring 8.7 on the Richter scale struck&#13;
                     the islands of Nias causing widespread damages.&#13;
&#13;
                     In response to the disasters, the Government of Indonesia set up the Rehabilitation&#13;
                     and Reconstruction Agency for Aceh and Nias (BRR),1 a specialized agency with&#13;
                     ministerial level leadership, to coordinate the overall reconstruction effort. Kuntoro&#13;
                     Mangkusubroto was assigned as the head of the BRR, which was endowed with special&#13;
                     authorities to respond rapidly beyond usual government procedures for disbursing&#13;
                     funds and implementing reconstruction activities.&#13;
&#13;
                     In May 2009, Kuntoro told an audience gathered in Jakarta for the closure of the&#13;
                     BRR that the reconstruction of the areas in Indonesia affected by the tsunami was an&#13;
                     unprecedented success and an ideal case study for future post disaster operations.&#13;
                     Kuntoroâ&#128;&#153;s audience consisted of high-level representatives from donor countries and&#13;
                     international organizations. Several of the attendees stated that the international&#13;
                     response to the tsunami and earthquake had changed the way the global community&#13;
                     would handle future disasters.&#13;
&#13;
                     One such response of the global community was the establishment of the Multi Donor&#13;
                     Fund for Aceh and Nias (MDF). The MDF was a financing mechanism that has been&#13;
                     used by the international community in many other situations for global and regional&#13;
                     partnerships â&#128;&#147; a multi donor trust fund (MDTF) that pools together contributions from&#13;
                     various donors, disburses them to a number of recipients under an administrator&#13;
                     or trustee, and utilizes the funds towards an agreed objective or purpose. The MDF&#13;
                     for Aceh and Nias supported the Indonesian governmentâ&#128;&#153;s agenda for post-disaster&#13;
                     reconstruction and was an integral part of the success of the overall reconstruction.&#13;
&#13;
                     This working paper is structured as follows: Chapter 1 provides some history and&#13;
                     a background of the MDF. Chapter 2 outlines the strategic framework of the MDF,&#13;
                     including the fundamental success that rendered this particular MDF effective. Chapter&#13;
                     4 outlines the key lessons learned from the positive and negative experiences of the&#13;
                     MDF, which could be used by policy makers and practitioners in other contexts in&#13;
                     the future.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       1&#13;
        	   BRR or Badan Rekonstruksi dan Rehabilitasi (Agency for Rehabilitation and Reconstruction of Aceh and Nias) was set up by a&#13;
            presidential decree in May 2005 to provide leadership and direction to all of the rebuilding efforts by national and international&#13;
            assistance agencies, and to develop and implement the reconstruction master plan.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
President Susilo Bambang Yudhoyono (center) flanked by World Bank Regional Vice President Pamela Cox and&#13;
Minister of National Development Planning Armida Alisjahbana is photographed here with representatives&#13;
of donors during MDFâ&#128;&#153;s international conference on disaster reconstruction and preparedness in Jakarta in&#13;
November 2012. Close coordination between MDF, the GoI and the international partners was key to the&#13;
MDFâ&#128;&#153;s success.&#13;
&#13;
Photo: MDF Secretariat&#13;
&amp;#12;Chapter 1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BACKGROUND AND CONTEXT&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                                                                              33&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                   A Framework for Reconstruction through Effective Partnerships&#13;
                                                                                                                                                   The Multi Donor Fund for Aceh and Nias:&#13;
       1.1	 Setting the Stage for the MDF:&#13;
            The International Aid Architecture&#13;
                     The MDF for Aceh and Nias was established against the backdrop of the Paris&#13;
                     Declaration and operated in an evolving landscape of development aid. At the&#13;
                     time of its establishment, global aid architecture was undergoing major changes: (i)&#13;
                     objectives expanded to address globalization, climate change, and persistent political&#13;
                     instabilities or conflicts as well as financial crises and natural disasters; (ii) increased&#13;
                     public scrutiny of aid in the aftermath of the Cold War; and (iii) new donors, including&#13;
                     both state and non-state ones, flourished.1 In response, to ensure aid effectiveness&#13;
                     in the new development landscape, over 100 development actors came together and&#13;
                     signed the Paris Declaration on Aid Effectiveness in March 2005. The Paris Declaration&#13;
                     set in motion a new paradigm in development assistance, first affirmed in the Accra&#13;
                     Agenda for Action in 2008 and re-affirmed in the Busan Partnership for Effective&#13;
                     Development Cooperation in 2011. The Accra Agenda and the Busan Partnership were&#13;
                     triggered by two trends. The first is the growing role of middle-income countries as&#13;
                     recipients as well as providers of development cooperation. The second is the increased&#13;
                     attention to principles of effective aid as a response to the criticism of decades of&#13;
                     under-performing aid delivery resulting in largely unmet goals in sustainable economic&#13;
                     growth and poverty reduction.2&#13;
&#13;
                     Before the tsunami struck, the multi donor trust fund (MDTF) model was already&#13;
                     considered to be an effective tool. The MDTF model has proven particularly suited for&#13;
                     post-crisis situations such as wars or natural disasters, for a collective donor emergency&#13;
                     response to support government-led disaster response efforts. MDTFs are designed to&#13;
                     enable funding to flow quickly and coherently and are often a forum where some of&#13;
                     the most difficult issues of coordination are dealt with. Since the late 1980s, donors&#13;
                     had come to recognize post-crisis MDTFs as good instruments to limit operational&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       1	&#13;
            This paper excerpts several passages from the work of an MDF consultant, Fabio Scarpello, especially those on the structure of multi&#13;
            donor trust funds in general and the structure of the MDF in particular.&#13;
       2	&#13;
            OECD. 2009. â&#128;&#156;Triangular Co-operation and Aid Effectiveness: Can Triangular Co-operation Make Aid More Effective?â&#128;&#157; Mexico City:&#13;
            OECD&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Reconstruction of the port in Gunung Sitoli, Nias. The MDF&#13;
contributed to the restoration of transportation networks in Aceh&#13;
and Nias by supporting the reconstruction of ports, roads and&#13;
bridges. Ports were reconstructed as part of the IRFF project.&#13;
&#13;
Photo: MDF Secretariat&#13;
&amp;#12;34&#13;
Chapter 1 - Background and Context&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     costs and enhance the impact of aid with assurance of high fiduciary management&#13;
                                     standards. The World Bankâ&#128;&#153;s involvement in post-crisis situations dated back to post&#13;
                                     World War II and led to a deepening of relations with donors that favor a multilateral&#13;
                                     approach to aid and development.&#13;
&#13;
                                     In this national and international context, a financing mechanism was needed&#13;
                                     to support the effective flow of external funds in line with GoI priorities. It&#13;
                                     quickly became clear that the partnership of national and international stakeholders&#13;
                                     needed a coordinated response for effective reconstruction of Aceh and Nias.&#13;
                                     Established in May 2005, the MDF pulled together 15 bilateral and multilateral donors,&#13;
                                     including the World Bank which also acted as the trustee. It operated under three&#13;
                                     complementary and strategic pillars which resulted in a framework for effective post-&#13;
                                     crisis reconstruction model that can be adapted and replicated in other post-crisis&#13;
                                     settings. The three pillars are to: (i) foster partnerships for reconstruction; (ii) adopt&#13;
                                     effective implementation strategies; and (iii) mainstream cross-cutting issues. These&#13;
                                     strategic pillars were also fundamentally based on the need to maintain a strong and&#13;
                                     transparent accountability framework.&#13;
&#13;
                                     The challenges facing the reconstruction of Aceh and Nias after the disasters&#13;
                                     were immense. Aceh and Nias, though quite different in many ways, presented&#13;
                                     multilayered challenges that have few precedents. The first layer was represented by&#13;
                                     the magnitude of the disaster. The tsunami left a trail of destruction that is difficult&#13;
                                     to comprehend. In Aceh, the entire west coast and most of the east coast was&#13;
                                     demolished. More than 221,000 Acehnese lost their lives or were missing, over half a&#13;
                                     million people were left homeless, and nearly every survivor had losses to grieve over.&#13;
                                     The tragedy left profound psychological scars, and the already struggling economy&#13;
                                     was deeply affected. Secondly, the natural disaster took place in a province that had&#13;
                                     been battered by a bloody civil war for the past 30 years. The tsunami brought to the&#13;
                                     fore the imperative for a peace agreement, which was signed eight months after the&#13;
                                     tsunami/earthquake disaster. The province was flooded with weapons, former rebels&#13;
                                     had to be reintegrated, violence persisted, and political tension never fully dissipated.&#13;
                                     The war had also paralyzed the local administrations, rendering them largely unable&#13;
                                     to handle the massive reconstruction. In Nias, difficulties of a fragile environment&#13;
                                     were compounded by years of isolation and neglect. Local administrations lacked&#13;
                                     skills to handle the massive reconstruction. In both Aceh and Nias, the lack of skills&#13;
                                     soon emerged as a real issue.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                              35&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                   A Framework for Reconstruction through Effective Partnerships&#13;
                                                                                                   The Multi Donor Fund for Aceh and Nias:&#13;
      The MDF model proved to be robust and replicable as even more disasters affected&#13;
      other areas of Indonesia. In May 2006, a massive earthquake hit the island of Java with&#13;
      significant damages to the Special Region of Yogyakarta. A repeat disaster followedâ&#128;&#148;&#13;
      in July 2006 a tsunami was triggered by another earthquake off the west coast of Java,&#13;
      causing widespread damages in West Java and Central Java. Given the success and the&#13;
      advantages of the MDF model for coordinating donor support, the GoI requested the&#13;
      establishment of the Java Reconstruction Fund (JRF), which was set up in May 2006 to&#13;
      support the reconstruction of Yogyakarta, West and Central Java. Although the scale of&#13;
      the disaster was much smaller and the recovery activities were more narrowly focused,&#13;
      the MDF model still proved adaptable to the scale and nature of the disaster and the&#13;
      reconstruction efforts. At a later stage, the JRF provided a ready response mechanism&#13;
      when the earthquake affected areas were massively affected by the volcanic eruptions&#13;
      of Mount Merapi in 2010.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
1.2	 Motivations and Interests of MDF Stakeholders&#13;
&#13;
      In coming together to support reconstruction, the motivations of the many stakeholders&#13;
      of the MDF and the overall reconstruction process were varied, but complementary.&#13;
&#13;
      Government of Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
      For the GoI, establishing clear leadership of reconstruction and a coordinated&#13;
      engagement with donors was a key advantage of the MDF construct. The GoI&#13;
      led the overall reconstruction, allocating funds from various sources to address&#13;
      reconstruction needs. Government leadership was an essential keystone of the entire&#13;
      process, and allowed the government to have a clear say in the choice of investments&#13;
      and instruments to be used for the response. Within one month after the disasters, a&#13;
      Damage and Loss Assessment (DALA) was carried out by the national government with&#13;
      support from the World Bank and the United Nations. Based on the DALA, the Master&#13;
      Plan for Rehabilitation and Reconstruction for Aceh and Nias was prepared to outline&#13;
      results-oriented operational programs with a specified timeframe and associated&#13;
      budgets. The MDF supported the overall reconstruction in line with the priorities&#13;
      identified in the Master Plan through grant funding in designated sectors aimed at&#13;
      filling gaps in the reconstruction efforts. Similarly the JRF supported the GoI-identified&#13;
      key sectors of housing and economic development. The MDF model provided the GoI&#13;
&amp;#12;36&#13;
Chapter 1 - Background and Context&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                   with a flexible financing mechanism to address needs that were not met through other&#13;
                                                   funding channels. It also reduced transaction costs for the government by providing&#13;
                                                   one set of policies, procedures and practices for all the participating donors, and this&#13;
                                                   was an important consideration for the government in seeking the creation of an&#13;
                                                   MDTF. Most importantly, funds from multiple donors could coherently be channeled&#13;
                                                   through the governmentâ&#128;&#153;s own systems, with government agencies largely responsible&#13;
                                                   for project implementation.&#13;
&#13;
                                                   Local governments were interested in having local priorities clearly identified and&#13;
                                                   implemented during reconstruction. Particularly in the post-conflict context of&#13;
                                                   Aceh, the local governmentâ&#128;&#153;s priorities were critically important to ensure smooth&#13;
                                                   implementation and ultimate sustainability of investments. For local governments,&#13;
                                                   this was an important opportunity to engage with the national government as equal&#13;
                                                   partners in reconstruction and to ensure that both post-conflict and post-disaster&#13;
                                                   needs were substantially met.&#13;
&#13;
                                                   Donors&#13;
&#13;
                                                   The MDF and JRF provided different advantages for different donors. A recent World&#13;
                                                   Bank evaluation of its trust fund portfolio3 notes that donors mainly use trust funds&#13;
                                                   to fill gaps in the multilateral aid system to respond to emergencies, and financing&#13;
                                                   development in non-sovereign entities and global public goods. In addition, donors&#13;
                                                   tend to use trust funds to (i) target priority issues or countries; (ii) scale up bilateral&#13;
                                                   programs; (iii) influence issues already on the development agenda; and (iv) attract&#13;
                                                   or mobilize additional funding for priority issues beyond bilateral arrangements. The&#13;
                                                   donors who eventually joined the MDF program, and those who later joined the JRF,&#13;
                                                   included the proponents of multilateralism and several smaller donors, in part due&#13;
                                                   to their commitment to the international dialogue on aid effectiveness in recent&#13;
                                                   years. While operationalizing the aid effectiveness principles as espoused in Paris&#13;
                                                   was never explicitly stated, the MDF program exemplifies a textbook study of the&#13;
                                                   Paris Declaration in action. It has over its eight-year life span, followed the aid&#13;
                                                   effectiveness journey from Paris to Accra to Busan, from effective aid to cooperation&#13;
                                                   of effective development.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     3	&#13;
                                          World Bank. 2011. â&#128;&#156;An Evaluation of the World Bankâ&#128;&#153;s Trust Fund Portfolio: Trust Fund Support for Development.â&#128;&#157;&#13;
                                     	    Jakarta: World Bank.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                              37&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                   A Framework for Reconstruction through Effective Partnerships&#13;
                                                                                                   The Multi Donor Fund for Aceh and Nias:&#13;
Construction site of the Blang Bintang Regional Landfill, implemented by the UNDP.   Photo: MDF&#13;
                                                                                     Secretariat&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Donors wanted to be partners in decision making, and they needed visibility of their&#13;
contributions, effective results and accountability for funds. For the MDF and JRF, all&#13;
donors had a seat at the table of the Steering Committee, irrespective of the size of&#13;
their contribution. For the larger donors, the MDF and JRF provided an opportunity for&#13;
influencing policy and operations at many levels of the reconstruction effort. The seat&#13;
at the table was particularly beneficial to donors who may have provided smaller overall&#13;
contributions (even though the contribution rate per capita of the donor country could&#13;
have been amongst the highest), due to the high visibility of the reconstruction of Aceh&#13;
and Nias. For these relatively smaller donors, the MDF provided a way to help without&#13;
requiring major operational structures of their own. Other donors found the MDF and&#13;
JRF to be highly effective tools for supporting a multilateral approach, as well as a&#13;
rational vehicle for minimizing total transaction costs and maximizing the impact of&#13;
&amp;#12;38&#13;
Chapter 1 - Background and Context&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     the aid money, with assurance of high fiduciary management standards. The onus was&#13;
                                     on each donor to become involved in the governance and decision making processes&#13;
                                     of the MDF, and most of the donors did so. Pooling of donor funds also leveraged each&#13;
                                     donorâ&#128;&#153;s contributions, allowing them to influence investments and results that were&#13;
                                     much greater in totality than their own funding. The trust funds provided benefits&#13;
                                     from the technical expertise, country experience, supervision capacity and ability to&#13;
                                     monitor and report on results of the different Partner Agencies.&#13;
&#13;
                                     A common concern for some donors in a pooled fund is the visibility of their&#13;
                                     contributions which is deemed important for local constituencies at home. Donors&#13;
                                     often feel that while the use of trust funds fosters collaboration and reduces aid&#13;
                                     fragmentation through pooled resources, visibility and due credits could be less&#13;
                                     prominent in these structures. The ability to demonstrate results that can be attributed&#13;
                                     to tax payer contributions is important; however, such one-to-one correspondence&#13;
                                     is not meaningful in a multi-donor setting. Both the MDF and JRF were particularly&#13;
                                     responsive to donorsâ&#128;&#153; concern by providing regular and detailed reports to donors&#13;
                                     on the results achieved through their contributions, and both programs implemented&#13;
                                     communication strategies that incorporated donor visibility efforts. At the end of the&#13;
                                     day, donor visibility was largely achieved through the high level partnerships that the&#13;
                                     two programs established, and attribution could be made to the overall results of a&#13;
                                     large pool of funds.&#13;
&#13;
                                     Other Development Partners&#13;
&#13;
                                     Strong partnership and collaboration played important roles in contributing to the&#13;
                                     GoI reconstruction efforts. The MDF, in particular, included a number of Partner&#13;
                                     Agenciesâ&#128;&#148;the World Bank, the International Labour Organization (ILO), the World&#13;
                                     Food Programme (WFP) and the United Nations Development Programme (UNDP)â&#128;&#148;&#13;
                                     who were responsible for the appraisal, supervision, monitoring and evaluation&#13;
                                     of MDF funded projects, as well as the administration of grant funds allocated to&#13;
                                     finance the projects. Partner agencies were selected for projects based on the&#13;
                                     comparative advantages that the agencies offered to deliver the multidisciplinary&#13;
                                     post-disaster assistance in response to the governmentâ&#128;&#153;s recovery agenda. Projects&#13;
                                     were implemented and funds administered in accordance with the Partner agencyâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
                                     own fiduciary framework and governance arrangements, policies and procedures,&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                     39&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                          A Framework for Reconstruction through Effective Partnerships&#13;
                                                                                          The Multi Donor Fund for Aceh and Nias:&#13;
including audits and procurement procedures. For all these development partners,&#13;
the MDF allowed an opportunity to support and help in the reconstruction efforts&#13;
in line with their own skills and expertise, and to collaborate with each other in the&#13;
process. Development partners, including international agencies and civil society,&#13;
sought to contribute based on their comparative advantages to establish good&#13;
operations and strong partnerships to support affected peoples. For the World Bank&#13;
as Trustee, ensuring effective results and accountability of funds were of paramount&#13;
importance. In addition, the MDF and JRF also enabled the Bank to engage and&#13;
provide critical assistance in a situation where its other traditional instruments may&#13;
not have been well suited.&#13;
&#13;
Beneficiary communities&#13;
&#13;
Beneficiary communities needed to be included and involved in the reconstruction&#13;
process. Communities wanted to be directly involved in the reconstruction process to&#13;
define local priorities and to be informed of the peace and reconstruction dividends.&#13;
Community involvement in the MDF and JRF programs increased their ownership over&#13;
the process and the results. While they had no control over the disasters, they needed,&#13;
and were afforded, some control over rebuilding their future.&#13;
&amp;#12;Chapter 2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
THE STRATEGIC FRAMEWORK&#13;
FOR THE MDF&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                                            41&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                 A Framework for Reconstruction through Effective Partnerships&#13;
                                                                                                                 The Multi Donor Fund for Aceh and Nias:&#13;
                    The success of the MDF and the JRF can be attributed to a strategic framework based&#13;
                    on strong partnerships, effective implementation and attention to cross-cutting,&#13;
                    qualitative aspects. These strategies can elevate programs from being good to being&#13;
                    extraordinary in fulfilling the needs of affected people. These factors for success are&#13;
                    the key lessons learned from these two programs which are offered to help to inform&#13;
                    post-crisis reconstruction programs elsewhere.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       2.1	 Strong Partnerships for Results&#13;
&#13;
                    Both the MDF and the JRF have been characterized by strong government leadership&#13;
                    of a wide and inclusive partnership of many stakeholders. The GoIâ&#128;&#148;at national,&#13;
                    provincial and local levelsâ&#128;&#148;provided leadership by defining its reconstruction strategy&#13;
                    and agenda. Donors have pooled their resources to support this agenda. Partner&#13;
                    Agencies provided oversight of project implementation, applying their own systems&#13;
                    for appraisal, supervision, monitoring and reporting, and financial management&#13;
                    to ensure quality of operations. Implementing agencies, including national and&#13;
                    international implementers, government and non-government, delivered on a massive&#13;
                    reconstruction effort following the agenda laid out by the government. The World&#13;
                    Bank as Trustee of the funds ensured strong financial management with accountability&#13;
                    and transparency. And critically important has been the role of communities in&#13;
                    participating in and taking charge of local level reconstruction. Significant results were&#13;
                    achieved by the MDF through this inclusive approach, and some key achievements are&#13;
                    described in Annex 1.&#13;
&#13;
                    Government Leadership and Policy Setting&#13;
&#13;
                    At the outset, the GoI prepared several key planning documents which underpinned&#13;
                    the definition and scope of the reconstruction program for Aceh and Nias.&#13;
&#13;
                    The Damage and Loss Assessment represented the foundation of the government-&#13;
                    led post-tsunami rebuilding. Within one month after the disasters, a Damage and&#13;
                    Loss Assessment (DALA) was carried out by the GoI with support from the World Bank&#13;
                    and the United Nations. The DALA captured important and timely information on the&#13;
                    magnitude of the disaster, which was key to mobilize international assistance.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Multi-donor trust funds are financing mechanisms that pool&#13;
contributions from many donors to support an agreed program&#13;
of activities. They have proven to be effective instruments for&#13;
cooperation in post-disaster situations.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Photo: MDF Secretariat&#13;
&amp;#12;42&#13;
Chapter 2 - The Strategic Framework for The MDF&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  Based on the DALA, the Master Plan for Rehabilitation and Reconstruction for Aceh&#13;
                                                  and Nias was prepared. The Master Plan outlined a set of results oriented operational&#13;
                                                  programs with a specified time frame and associated budgets. The Master Plan also&#13;
                                                  called for a â&#128;&#156;Build Back Betterâ&#128;&#157; principle in the reconstruction that underpinned the&#13;
                                                  entire philosophy of the effort. The Master Plan classified the recovery into three&#13;
                                                  phases: the relief/emergency phase, the rehabilitation phase and the reconstruction&#13;
                                                  phase. It was estimated that the Master Plan would take up to five years to implement.&#13;
                                                  Further development would then be included in more sustainable programs of the&#13;
                                                  provincial medium-term development plan. The main difference between the DALA&#13;
                                                  and the Master Plan was in the allocation of funds: the Master Plan set aside much&#13;
                                                  less to compensate for private lossesâ&#128;&#148;businesses, vehicles, buildings, etc.â&#128;&#148;and much&#13;
                                                  more to rebuild public assets and infrastructure, including education centers, health&#13;
                                                  facilities, and roads. The difference reflected the governmentâ&#128;&#153;s desire to use the&#13;
                                                  disaster as an opportunity to rebuild better, rather than just to rebuild.&#13;
&#13;
                                                  At the inception of the MDF, a Recovery Assistance Policy (RAP) was developed to&#13;
                                                  provide guidance to the stakeholders of the MDF. The RAP reflected the current state&#13;
                                                  of knowledge about the rehabilitation and reconstruction program, the comparative&#13;
                                                  advantages of the MDTFANS and the policy environment for development in Aceh&#13;
                                                  and Nias. The mission statement of the MDF notes that the MDF is a partnership of&#13;
                                                  the international community, Indonesian government and civil society to support&#13;
                                                  the recovery following the earthquakes and tsunami. It contributes to the recovery&#13;
                                                  process by providing grants for quality investments that are based on good practice,&#13;
                                                  stakeholder participation, and coordination with others. In doing so the MDF seeks to&#13;
                                                  reduce poverty, (re)build capacity, support good governance and enhance sustainable&#13;
                                                  development. At program closing in December 2012, there were 23 projects in the&#13;
                                                  MDF portfolio valued at US $655 million covering six expected outcome areas. These&#13;
                                                  outcomes included: (i) Communities recovered; (ii) Large infrastructure and transport&#13;
                                                  rehabilitated and reconstructed; (iii) Governance strengthened and capacity rebuilt;&#13;
                                                  (iv) Environment sustained; (v) Recovery process enhanced; and (vi) Economic&#13;
                                                  development and livelihoods restarted.&#13;
&#13;
                                                  The GoI established different institutional arrangements for different disasters,&#13;
                                                  depending on the nature and scope of the disaster. In the case of Aceh where the&#13;
                                                  magnitude of the disaster was unprecedented, a special agency with ministerial&#13;
                                                  level authorityâ&#128;&#148;the BRRâ&#128;&#148;was established to coordinate the reconstruction efforts&#13;
                                                  and implement the Master Plan. In another, somewhat smaller disaster, the 2006&#13;
                                                  Java earthquake, GoI established a coordination team, the National Coordinating&#13;
                                                  Team (NCT) and the National Technical Team (TTN) with staff drawn from regular line&#13;
                                                  agencies to effectively manage and coordinate large-scale reconstruction efforts. After&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                       43&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                            A Framework for Reconstruction through Effective Partnerships&#13;
                                                                                            The Multi Donor Fund for Aceh and Nias:&#13;
the mandate of the NCT and the TTN ended in 2008, the JRF worked with Bappenas&#13;
and the Provincial Planning Agencies (Bappeda) for the overall coordination of&#13;
the reconstruction.&#13;
&#13;
In more localized disasters, the GoI has relied on regular government systems to&#13;
address recovery and reconstruction. These experiences show that the type of&#13;
organizational structure should be designed to fit the nature and scope of a disaster, as&#13;
long as the commitment and strength of the governmentâ&#128;&#153;s leadership roleâ&#128;&#148;essential&#13;
to the success of the reconstruction effortâ&#128;&#148;is maintained. The ability and authority&#13;
of the government agency to coordinate and implement reconstruction in a speedy&#13;
manner, and to allocate and disburse funds quickly, are critical to the process. For&#13;
the MDF and the JRF, a strong counterpart in government was essential for decision&#13;
making on funds use.&#13;
&#13;
In leading the reconstruction, the GoI effectively coordinated the support from&#13;
different partners to maximize impact and reduce duplication. In Aceh and Nias,&#13;
the outpouring of international support was huge, and the number of agencies&#13;
implementing reconstruction projects was similarly enormous. Once the strategy&#13;
and institutional structure for disaster response had been established, the BRR was&#13;
responsible for coordinating the support from different agencies, according to the&#13;
Master Plan. This also allowed BRR to use the MDF as a gap-filling partner, focusing&#13;
on investments and support in areas where other reconstruction players were absent&#13;
or unwilling. As such, the impact of the MDF was much greater than the size of the&#13;
funding it represented, which was only 10 percent of overall reconstruction assistance,&#13;
by addressing critical gaps and bringing to completion the GoIâ&#128;&#153;s agenda.&#13;
&#13;
Support from Development Partners&#13;
&#13;
With the governmentâ&#128;&#153;s leadership of the reconstruction agenda, other partners&#13;
were able to align their support under one framework. The MDF was established&#13;
to support the GoIâ&#128;&#153;s Master Plan and operate in alignment with its institutions and&#13;
procedures. Over 70 percent of the MDF funds were channeled through the national&#13;
budget, utilizing the countryâ&#128;&#153;s public financial management system.&#13;
&#13;
The mix of partner agencies and implementing agencies minimized fragmentation&#13;
and provided the opportunity to use individual organizationsâ&#128;&#153; comparative&#13;
advantages. Major multilateral organizations such as UNDP, ILO, WFP and the World&#13;
Bank served as partner agencies. Implementing agencies included government line&#13;
ministries and international NGOs. The partner agencies carried out the appraisal,&#13;
supervision, monitoring and evaluation of MDF funded projects, and administered&#13;
&amp;#12;44&#13;
Chapter 2 - The Strategic Framework for The MDF&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  The MDF approach gave voice to both men and women in deciding how to rebuild their       Photo:&#13;
                                                  villages. The community-driven and local resource based approaches to post-disaster      MDF&#13;
                                                  reconstruction and recovery in MDF projects demonstrated that communities and            Secretariat&#13;
                                                  government could work together in partnership to achieve results that are transparent,&#13;
                                                  cost-effective, and of high quality.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  grants from the MDF to finance them, applying their own fiduciary framework and&#13;
                                                  governance arrangements. The implementing agencies brought different strengths in&#13;
                                                  terms of implementation capacity and procedures. This arrangement led to a multi-&#13;
                                                  pronged response to the governmentâ&#128;&#153;s recovery agenda, allowing greater speed and&#13;
                                                  coverage, with quality oversight, than would otherwise have been possible.&#13;
&#13;
                                                  Various fund channeling mechanisms to enhance the use of government systems&#13;
                                                  were employed by the different partner agencies. As new government policies and&#13;
                                                  regulations came on line during the course of the program, innovative procedures&#13;
                                                  were devised to channel funds to subnational governments and beneficiaries. Where&#13;
                                                  appropriate, funds for projects with World Bank as the partner agency were channeled&#13;
                                                  through the governmentâ&#128;&#153;s budget system. By 2009, most off-budget projects slowly&#13;
                                                  transitioned to on-budget implementation modality in response to the GoIâ&#128;&#153;s changing&#13;
                                                  requirements related to foreign assistance. The result was an increasing sense of&#13;
                                                  government ownership and hands-on participation of the MDF program from both&#13;
                                                  the national and subnational agencies. Other partner agencies were able to provide&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                                 45&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                      A Framework for Reconstruction through Effective Partnerships&#13;
                                                                                                      The Multi Donor Fund for Aceh and Nias:&#13;
flexibility in channeling funds both on and off-budget, and having a mix of channels&#13;
was also an advantage in the reconstruction. The multiple partners and different&#13;
modes of fund channeling allowed the MDF to employ a range of approaches and&#13;
strike a balance between speed and quality during implementation.&#13;
&#13;
An Inclusive and Effective Governance Structure&#13;
&#13;
The success of the MDF was also due to an inclusive governance structure&#13;
with delegated authority to make decisions. This structure included a Steering&#13;
Committee comprised of representatives from BRR, Bappenas, Ministry of Finance,&#13;
and Governments of Aceh and North Sumatra, the 15 donors to the MDF, as well&#13;
as representatives of Acehâ&#128;&#153;s civil society, and observers such as the UN and the&#13;
international NGO community. The purpose of the MDFâ&#128;&#153;s deliberative body was&#13;
threefold: (i) to mobilize resources in order to fill strategic gaps in the recovery; (ii)&#13;
to enhance coordination between major development partners in support of the&#13;
GoIâ&#128;&#153;s recovery program; and (iii) to serve as a forum for policy dialogue between the&#13;
GoI and the international community. Over time, the Steering Committee meetings&#13;
became a significant forum for discussion of a wide range of policy and operational&#13;
issues for Aceh and Nias. A Technical Review Group supported the functions of the&#13;
Steering Committee.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Figure 1: MDF Governance Structure&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        Trustee&#13;
                                      (World Bank)&#13;
&#13;
                                                                     15 Donor&#13;
                                                                  Representatives&#13;
                 INGOs             Steering Committee&#13;
                                                                                     Voting Members&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
               1 Observer               Co-chairs:&#13;
   Observers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                 Bappenas; Govt of Aceh;           6 Government&#13;
                                         EU; WB                   Representatives&#13;
                  UN&#13;
                                     Policy, Strategy,&#13;
               1 Observer&#13;
                                     Funds Allocation&#13;
                                                                   2 Civil Society&#13;
                                                                  Representatives&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        Secretariat&#13;
                                   Supports the SC and&#13;
                                   runs daily operations&#13;
                                        of the MDF&#13;
&amp;#12;46&#13;
Chapter 2 - The Strategic Framework for The MDF&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                         A clearly defined, streamlined decision making process meant that informed&#13;
                                                         decisions could be made in a timely way. Voting members of the Steering Committee&#13;
                                                         decided on policy and funds allocation. The Technical Review Group met to discuss and&#13;
                                                         recommend decisions on project and program issues to the Steering Committee. The&#13;
                                                         MDF also pioneered a shared co-chair arrangement consisting of the GoI (represented&#13;
                                                         initially by the head of the BRR and later by the Minister for National Development&#13;
                                                         Planning), the Government of Aceh, the European Union as the largest donor, and&#13;
                                                         the World Bank as the Trustee. This co-chair arrangement supported efficient decision&#13;
                                                         making, consensual working of the Steering Committee and effective implementation&#13;
                                                         of the MDF. However, the system did not always work efficiently, and deliberations&#13;
                                                         at the TRG level often led to delays in decision making. The advantage of having&#13;
                                                         consensus at the Steering Committee level was sometimes associated with delays in&#13;
                                                         decision making, and a tight decision making body with a broad consultative body&#13;
                                                         could be a better governance construct in future situations. See Annex 3 for the roles&#13;
                                                         and responsibilities of the MDFâ&#128;&#153;s governing body.&#13;
&#13;
                                                         Involvement of Local Communities&#13;
&#13;
                                                         The MDFâ&#128;&#153;s inclusive and pluralistic approach extended from national government&#13;
                                                         and international donors to local communities and subnational governments. After&#13;
                                                         years of conflict in Aceh and isolation and neglect in Nias, the community-driven and&#13;
                                                         local resource based approaches to post-disaster reconstruction and recovery in MDF&#13;
                                                         projects demonstrated that communities and government could work together in&#13;
                                                         partnership to achieve results that are transparent, cost-effective, and of high quality.&#13;
                                                         A number of the MDF projects adopted community-based approaches specifically and&#13;
                                                         most of the projects in the portfolio took into consideration the socio-political-economic&#13;
                                                         conditions in Aceh and Nias post-crisis in close consultation with the communities and&#13;
                                                         local governments. Communities were very much part of the reconstruction decision-&#13;
                                                         making process and citizens were able to reap the reconstruction dividends.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  2.2	 Effective Implementation Strategies&#13;
&#13;
                                                         Sequencing Implementation to Manage Expectations&#13;
&#13;
                                                         The most useful strategy was that of phasing and sequencing the implementation of&#13;
                                                         MDF projects to address needs as they evolved. This helped to manage expectations&#13;
                                                         throughout reconstruction. In any post-crisis situation, there is a tension between&#13;
                                                         balancing speed of implementation, quality and ownership of reconstruction, and long&#13;
                                                         term sustainability. These competing goals do not move in tandem. In the case of the&#13;
                                                         MDF, the inevitable trade-off was reduced by implementing in three phases and the&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                       47&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                            A Framework for Reconstruction through Effective Partnerships&#13;
                                                                                            The Multi Donor Fund for Aceh and Nias:&#13;
approach was in line with the GoIâ&#128;&#153;s Master Plan. The first phase focused on immediate&#13;
recovery of housing, small infrastructure, logistics and transportation links. The second&#13;
phase took on major reconstruction of infrastructure, such as roads, bridges, and ports,&#13;
and protection of the environment. The final phase shifted to laying the foundation for&#13;
economic development through support for livelihoods and targeted capacity building.&#13;
A further tension was inevitable between the desire of MDF partners to get results&#13;
quickly on the ground and the longer-term objective of building local capacity to take&#13;
over and complete the recovery process. Given the weakness of local government,&#13;
these two objectives were not always compatible and it took time to develop a strong&#13;
focus on local ownership and institutional development.&#13;
&#13;
The principal driver for immediate recovery was speed to support implementation of&#13;
urgent needs, while involving communities so that they were part of the process of&#13;
reconstruction. The initial projects financed by the MDF focused on community driven&#13;
reconstruction of housing and local infrastructure, logistics and re-establishment&#13;
of critical transport links, and removal of tsunami debris. The community driven&#13;
processes enhanced social cohesion and contributed to the healing process of&#13;
individuals and communities, and the benefits of reconstruction on the local economy&#13;
and empowerment were felt immediately. The transport and logistics allowed critical&#13;
recovery support to reach dispersed communities, and provided a wide range of&#13;
humanitarian and reconstruction agencies to reach their beneficiaries. This was&#13;
particularly important given the post-conflict context in Aceh, and the MDFâ&#128;&#153;s support&#13;
had multiplier effects across the overall reconstruction effort at this stage.&#13;
&#13;
The need for speed was a very strong characteristic of the MDF in the first phase&#13;
of implementation. Given the urgency to allocate funds and implement projects,&#13;
performance standards were specifically built into the MDFâ&#128;&#153;s Operations Manual to&#13;
ensure that activities would move according to a continued sense of urgency. The&#13;
Secretariat kept track of how long the grant approval and implementation process&#13;
took for each project, so that all parties were informed of pace and adjustments could&#13;
be made as needed.&#13;
&#13;
The driver for the second phase of reconstruction under the MDF was the need for&#13;
quality and ownership of complex projects and initiatives. In the reconstruction&#13;
phase, focus was on implementation of projects and investments where quality and&#13;
ownership are critical, when procurement and safeguards processes can be complex and&#13;
outcomes will take time. This included, particularly, investment in large infrastructure&#13;
with projects such as roads, bridges, ports, etc. The focus also shifted to include&#13;
measures to protect the environment, as well as initiatives to enhance the capacity&#13;
of national, provincial and local governments to implement reconstruction. Many&#13;
&amp;#12;48&#13;
Chapter 2 - The Strategic Framework for The MDF&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  Workers put the final touches on a bridge in Nias built through a project implemented   Photo:&#13;
                                                  by one of MDFâ&#128;&#153;s partner agency, the ILO. ILO introduced the local resource-             MDF&#13;
                                                  based approach which employed local labor and used environmentally friendly             Secretariat&#13;
                                                  construction methods.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  reconstruction actors were impatient with the time it took to startup and implement&#13;
                                                  the large-scale infrastructure investment projects. For complex investments, GoI and&#13;
                                                  partner agency procedures for on-budget implementation and decision making took&#13;
                                                  up much time and effort, and the MDF was criticized by stakeholders for having lost&#13;
                                                  the urgency and impetus of the initial phase. In hindsight, however, it is clear that&#13;
                                                  the benefits of careful quality assurance, targeted design and ownership by local&#13;
                                                  authorities can only be achieved at the cost of a slower pace of reconstruction, and is&#13;
                                                  well worth the trade-off in terms of sustainability of investments.&#13;
&#13;
                                                  For the final phase of transition to economic development, the driver was&#13;
                                                  sustainability. This phase of the MDF supported the transition to long term growth&#13;
                                                  coupled with targeted capacity building to ensure the impact of reconstruction and the&#13;
                                                  sustainability of donor investments would continue well beyond the reconstruction&#13;
                                                  program. As noted by the GoI, disasters result in interruption to development, often&#13;
                                                  bringing a reversal of initial development conditions. During this phase the MDF&#13;
                                                  focused on strengthening key economic sectors in Aceh and Nias, including rice,&#13;
                                                  fisheries, livestock and important export crops such as coffee, cacao, and rubber.&#13;
                                                  This focus on longer term growth, particularly in the post-conflict context of Aceh&#13;
                                                  and relative neglect in Nias, was critical to ensure that reconstruction would not&#13;
                                                  create further divisions and could be maintained by local authorities and&#13;
                                                  communities in the future. Targeted capacity building for local government to assume&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                         49&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                              A Framework for Reconstruction through Effective Partnerships&#13;
                                                                                              The Multi Donor Fund for Aceh and Nias:&#13;
the transition from reconstruction to development was also a major focus of this&#13;
phase, further consolidating the efforts to maximize the long-term impact of MDF&#13;
investments.&#13;
&#13;
Project Design and Selection&#13;
&#13;
Several specific project design elements helped the MDF to deliver quickly and&#13;
within the timelines available for reconstruction. The need for speed, quality and&#13;
sustainability that were managed by phasing the MDFâ&#128;&#153;s interventions was also&#13;
supported by specific strategies at entry and at closure. Scaling up existing projects,&#13;
defining realistic timelines and exit strategies and rapid response polices all contributed&#13;
to effective reconstruction. However, where these strategies were not applied or were&#13;
insufficient, the pace of reconstruction sometimes left partners frustrated and reduced&#13;
the overall effectiveness and quality of the engagement.&#13;
&#13;
Scaling up of Existing Projects: Project selection was geared towards speed at the&#13;
beginning of the program. By scaling up existing programs/projects in terms of scope&#13;
and reach, the MDF was able to utilize existing mechanisms in the field to speed up&#13;
the start of implementation. Two of the first projects financed by the MDF leveraged&#13;
the project mechanisms of existing World Bank-financed Kecamatan Development&#13;
Project (KDP) and Urban Poverty Project (UPP) by scaling them up for post-disaster&#13;
Aceh and Nias. The Tsunami Recovery Waste Management Programme (TRWMP) was&#13;
a continuation of a UNDP initiative to manage tsunami-related waste and to create&#13;
cash for work opportunities immediately after the tsunami. This scaling up allowed&#13;
immediate response to the crisis needs of affected communities, while new projects&#13;
were being developed.&#13;
&#13;
Duration of Projects: The MDFâ&#128;&#153;s experience shows that it may be more effective&#13;
to choose projects with implementation periods that fit within the lifetime of a&#13;
reconstruction program, given that the time horizon for most reconstruction programs&#13;
is short and limited. Two projects implemented for one year or less, the Lamno-Calang&#13;
Road Maintenance Project (LCRMP) and the Tsunami Recovery Port Redevelopment&#13;
Programme (TRPRP) came on line within the first 18 months of establishing the&#13;
MDF, each to tackle a single issue. The 12-month LCRMP was designed to ensure&#13;
uninterrupted overland access to tsunami-affected communities on the west coast&#13;
of Aceh and the nine-month TRPRP was to quickly restore critical ports for delivery&#13;
of equipment and materials for the rebuilding of communities. LCRMP and TRPRP&#13;
were the shortest running projects in the entire MDF portfolio and both achieved their&#13;
objectives on time and within the budget.&#13;
&#13;
Exit Strategies: A key design lesson learned from the MDF is to have a clear exit strategy&#13;
built into project design at the outset. This is often overlooked in reconstruction&#13;
projects, including most of the MDFâ&#128;&#153;s initial projects. With the exception of some&#13;
&amp;#12;50&#13;
Chapter 2 - The Strategic Framework for The MDF&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                         of the community recovery projects which were spun off from the governmentâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
                                                         national community-driven development programs and were later merged back into&#13;
                                                         these programs post MDF, most of the MDFâ&#128;&#153;s early projects were designed to address&#13;
                                                         particular immediate needs, with little thought given to exit strategies at the time they&#13;
                                                         were designed. As these projects progressed and the situation normalized, project&#13;
                                                         teams began to recognize the need to better prepare for smooth project closure and&#13;
                                                         exit strategies to sustain project benefits post MDF. Several of the projects were able&#13;
                                                         to make use of an extension phase to implement exit strategies and enhance the&#13;
                                                         sustainability of project outcomes.&#13;
&#13;
                                                         Streamlined Procedures: Both the Indonesian government and the World Bank&#13;
                                                         utilized internal approval processes that were streamlined and emergency focused,&#13;
                                                         resulting in more efficient decision making and funds flow. Built into the streamlined&#13;
                                                         processes were strong supervision and implementation support by the partner agencies&#13;
                                                         that led to high quality and sustainable investments. The governmentâ&#128;&#153;s streamlined&#13;
                                                         approach was through the establishment of a specialized ad hoc agency, the BRR,&#13;
                                                         which reported directly to the President. The World Bank quickly introduced a new&#13;
                                                         Bank-wide rapid response framework known as OP/BP 8.00 to provide operational&#13;
                                                         flexibility and to establish the corporate oversight arrangements and mechanisms to&#13;
                                                         ensure an appropriate level of institutional response to emergency situations.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  2.3	 Cross-Cutting Considerations&#13;
                                                         Several critical elements to enhance the quality of the MDFâ&#128;&#153;s support were embodied&#13;
                                                         in its Recovery Assistance Policy (RAP). The RAP specified that the MDF would provide&#13;
                                                         support for investments based on good practice, stakeholder participation, and&#13;
                                                         coordination with others. Interestingly for a recovery agenda in the aftermath of a&#13;
                                                         devastating disaster, the RAP also had the foresight to stipulate that attention should&#13;
                                                         be given to cross-cutting issues such as gender equity, environmental sustainability,&#13;
                                                         and building capacity for good governance in order to enhance the quality of the&#13;
                                                         recovery process.&#13;
&#13;
                                                         For the MDF, relevant cross-cutting elements were capacity development, gender,&#13;
                                                         environmental and social safeguards, and disaster risk reduction. All projects were&#13;
                                                         also designed to be conflict sensitive. Where appropriate, projects considered these&#13;
                                                         cross-cutting elements at the design phases, and as the program developed, more&#13;
                                                         emphasis was placed on the inclusion of these elements in the projects. This deepened&#13;
                                                         the quality of the results achieved across the portfolio, and enhanced the robustness&#13;
                                                         and sustainability of the achievements. Very often, in post-conflict or post-disaster&#13;
                                                         situations, stakeholders are reluctant to invest in these cross-cutting elements;&#13;
                                                         however, it is precisely crisis situations which provide an opportunity to do things right&#13;
                                                         and for significant pay-offs in terms of the impact on reconstruction.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                       51&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                            A Framework for Reconstruction through Effective Partnerships&#13;
                                                                                            The Multi Donor Fund for Aceh and Nias:&#13;
The MDF played a significant role in strengthening capacity, injecting explicit capacity&#13;
building elements in most of its projects. The intensity of the capacity building efforts&#13;
increased over the life of MDF projects. The capacity building strategies ranged from&#13;
empowering communities to participate in the rebuilding of housing and community&#13;
infrastructure to strengthening skills and systems for local governments to manage&#13;
reconstruction assets, to organizational development for local government to better&#13;
address public sector management reform.&#13;
&#13;
The experience of promoting womenâ&#128;&#153;s equality and empowerment was uneven in&#13;
the MDF and JRF programs, all providing lessons for the future. A range of good&#13;
practice examples for gender mainstreaming abound throughout the MDF and JRF&#13;
projects. At the same time, processes and mechanisms for actively involving women in&#13;
decision-making and implementation could have been better institutionalized. As good&#13;
practice lessons from these experiences show, when women are active participants in&#13;
reconstruction with a voice to shape the design and management of reconstruction,&#13;
there are better quality outcomes for everyone.&#13;
&#13;
Managing the environment and disaster risk reduction were cross cutting themes&#13;
pursued both in specific projects as well as throughout the portfolio. The MDF was&#13;
the only major program in the overall reconstruction that provided direct support to&#13;
mitigate the adverse impact of reconstruction on the environment. An additional focus&#13;
on disaster risk reduction (DRR) was embedded in the projects as well, to support&#13;
resilience of the communities and local governments to future disasters. Both these&#13;
aspects support sustainability and mitigate adverse impacts in an already fragile&#13;
context, both during disaster response and in preparedness of future disasters. This&#13;
focus on incorporating DRR and resilience was further developed under the JRF in the&#13;
reconstruction of housing and settlements and has developed into a model of good&#13;
practice for post-disaster housing reconstruction.&#13;
&#13;
Challenges and solutions related to the inclusion of cross-cutting issues should&#13;
be anticipated as early as possible in order to fully and credibly address them. In&#13;
practical terms, these need to be reflected early on in the Joint Damage and Loss&#13;
Assessment and other needs assessments. Even if a â&#128;&#156;quick and dirtyâ&#128;&#157; analysis is done,&#13;
it is important to include these cross-cutting issues in the initial needs assessment to&#13;
provide a baseline and understanding of challenges, so that an appropriate strategy&#13;
and interventions can be designed. The solutions need to apply to all projects across the&#13;
program; the MDF addressed these through technical and institutional interventions,&#13;
and specific and generic approaches. Additionally, cross-cutting solutions need to&#13;
apply at all levels of government and/or players. Reconstruction processes in the wake&#13;
of a disaster are a window of opportunity to address quality issues. Disasters create&#13;
legitimate reasons to do things differently: to introduce new polices, programs and&#13;
legislation and support progress on dimensions that greatly enhance the impact of&#13;
reconstruction and long term recovery.&#13;
&amp;#12;52&#13;
Chapter 2 - The Strategic Framework for The MDF&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  2.4	 A Strong Accountability Framework&#13;
                                                                The MDF employed different levels of accountability which together enabled a robust&#13;
                                                                system. At the highest level, accountability in funds use and allocation was ensured&#13;
                                                                by the governance structure of the MDF, which had different levels with different and&#13;
                                                                complementary roles and responsibilities. Funds allocation was supported by a robust&#13;
                                                                system of monitoring and evaluation, and reporting and communications for timely&#13;
                                                                and regular information flow to all relevant players. Finally, financial management of&#13;
                                                                MDF funds to ensure appropriate use and accountability was essential to maintain&#13;
                                                                credibility with all stakeholders.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                Governance Structure for Decision Making&#13;
&#13;
                                                                The MDF had a two-tier decision-making and governance structure with the&#13;
                                                                Steering Committee the highest authority. The MDF Steering Committee included&#13;
                                                                seven1 government representatives from BRR, Bappenas, Ministry of Finance,&#13;
                                                                and Governments of Aceh and North Sumatra, the 15 donors to the MDF, as well&#13;
                                                                as representatives of Acehâ&#128;&#153;s civil society, the international NGO community, and&#13;
                                                                several key noncontributing countries. Voting rights were reserved for government&#13;
                                                                representatives as well as donors that contributed at least US$10 million. Two voting&#13;
                                                                seats were also allocated to members of Acehâ&#128;&#153;s civil society. The Steering Committee&#13;
                                                                did more than making decisions related to the MDF. In the early days it served as an all-&#13;
                                                                encompassing forum for dialogue on policy and reconstruction issues. The extension&#13;
                                                                of observer status to representatives from an international NGO consortium and the&#13;
                                                                UN and noncontributing countries including Australia and Japan facilitated this role.&#13;
                                                                Early meetings were often standing room only. From the beginning donors agreed to&#13;
                                                                proceed by consensus and throughout the MDFâ&#128;&#153;s lifetime the voting procedure was&#13;
                                                                never exercised.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                A Technical Review Group (TRG) acted as an intermediary layer to prepare the&#13;
                                                                groundwork before a project or a policy was submitted to the Steering Committee&#13;
                                                                for endorsement. While the Steering Committee was comprised of the highest level&#13;
                                                                of representations such as ministers and ambassadors, the TRG gathered mid-level&#13;
                                                                representatives of the same organizations and agencies. The TRG presented a less formal&#13;
                                                                setting for more in-depth technical discussions that resulted in a recommendation to&#13;
                                                                the Steering Committee for its final endorsement.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  1	&#13;
                                                       This was reduced to six when BRR closed in April 2009.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                            53&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                 A Framework for Reconstruction through Effective Partnerships&#13;
                                                                                                 The Multi Donor Fund for Aceh and Nias:&#13;
Kuntoro Mangkusubroto, Director of the Agency for the Rehabilitation and           Photo:&#13;
Reconstruction of Aceh and Nias (BRR) speaks at a steering committee meeting.      MDF&#13;
Comprehensive monitoring and evaluation was done at different levels for the MDF   Secretariat&#13;
by different entities.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The World Bank as the Trustee established a Secretariat for the day-to-day operations&#13;
of the MDF. The Secretariat, led by a World Bank designated Program Manager, was&#13;
accountable to the Steering Committee on all operational matters and to the Trustee&#13;
on all administrative matters and was based at the World Bank Office in Jakarta as well&#13;
as in Banda Aceh. The Secretariat supported the Steering Committee on coordination,&#13;
communication, financial oversight, and monitoring and evaluation and reporting.&#13;
The MDF operated in accordance with fundamental principles of good governance:&#13;
working in close partnership among key agencies; separating responsibilities for&#13;
allocation, fiduciary and administrative functions; and demonstrating full transparency&#13;
and openness in its processes.&#13;
&#13;
Monitoring and Evaluation, Reporting,&#13;
and Strategic Communications&#13;
&#13;
The MDF fully and consciously embraced transparency and established a strong set&#13;
of measures to this end. At the governance level, many different stakeholder groups&#13;
were invited and participated as observers even when they were not directly involved&#13;
in the MDF itself. The Secretariat scrupulously circulated and disclosed the agendas&#13;
and minutes of meetings to ensure wide information sharing of decisions. The MDF&#13;
&amp;#12;54&#13;
Chapter 2 - The Strategic Framework for The MDF&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  Middle school students practice delivering first aid to commemorate Disaster Risk   Photo:&#13;
                                                  Reduction (DRR) Day. The Ministry of Home Affairs and the Government of Aceh        UNDP&#13;
                                                  implemented DRR programs and made it part of the school curriculum.                 Collection&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  website provided comprehensive information on the program and projects. Reports&#13;
                                                  covering implementation and financial progress were provided to government and&#13;
                                                  donors on six-monthly basis, and the general public was informed of MDF activities&#13;
                                                  through detailed annual reports. These and other measures helped to ensure that&#13;
                                                  program activities and funds use was transparently conveyed to a wide range of&#13;
                                                  stakeholders in Acehâ&#128;&#153;s reconstruction.&#13;
&#13;
                                                  Comprehensive monitoring and evaluation was done at different levels for the MDF&#13;
                                                  by different entities. In addition to the MDF Secretariat providing overall program&#13;
                                                  monitoring, evaluation and reporting, development partners and other stakeholders&#13;
                                                  also took a keen interest in recording progress and results. Bappenas, the GoI custodian&#13;
                                                  of the MDF after BRRâ&#128;&#153;s closure in April 2009, established a monitoring and evaluation&#13;
                                                  system that called for monitoring meetings of all MDF projects on a quarterly basis.&#13;
                                                  Monitoring and oversight were key responsibilities of the Partner Agencies, who&#13;
                                                  also reported on project progress and results to the MDF on a quarterly or semi-&#13;
                                                  annual basis, in line with each Partner Agencyâ&#128;&#153;s own internal policy requirements.&#13;
                                                  The European Union periodically conducted results based on monitoring missions&#13;
                                                  in conjunction with the projects. Communities also participated in monitoring&#13;
                                                  activities, which helped increase the ownership that beneficiary communities felt over&#13;
                                                  assets created.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                        55&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                             A Framework for Reconstruction through Effective Partnerships&#13;
                                                                                             The Multi Donor Fund for Aceh and Nias:&#13;
Monitoring and evaluation is highly important to measure and document results&#13;
and lessons learned, and to ensure value for money. There were 23 projects in&#13;
the MDF portfolio, each with its own monitoring and evaluation system and results&#13;
framework. The MDF Secretariat successfully addressed the challenge of developing&#13;
a Results Framework that captures program level results from cascading projects. The&#13;
MDF reported on the project and portfolio performance on a semi-annual basis to&#13;
the donors and annually to the general public. The MDF found regular reporting on&#13;
program outcomes to be crucial to establishing trust and confidence, and to inform&#13;
citizens both in donor countries as well as in recipient countries regarding the good&#13;
use of funds. Results and findings of the MDF projects were publicly released in an&#13;
annual report and shared widely. The MDF also promoted joint field missions which&#13;
included donors and arranged portfolio-wide evaluations. An integral component&#13;
of accountability is close and constant project supervision, to identify and address&#13;
implementation issues and make mid-stream adjustments. All partner agencies played&#13;
this role carefully to ensure that project funds were well utilized for intended purposes,&#13;
and followed agreed policies and procedures. See Annex 2 for a description of the&#13;
Results Framework and key indicators for the MDF.&#13;
&#13;
Strategic communications enhanced transparency of the projects implemented and&#13;
was a key factor in the MDFâ&#128;&#153;s success. Different community forums were employed&#13;
to socialize project activities and procedures, and monitoring by communities played&#13;
an important part in promoting transparency. Helplines and project complaints-&#13;
handling systems were implemented across projects, and both project and program&#13;
level websites were established to provide online reporting of project activities. The&#13;
MDF Secretariat maintained regular communications and engagements with the&#13;
Steering Committee, partner agencies, line ministries and local governments which&#13;
allowed for inclusive and consultative resolution of problems and issues as they arose.&#13;
Timely, high quality strategic communications with a wide reach was important for&#13;
managing expectations of all stakeholders, promoting transparency and inclusiveness&#13;
and allowing stakeholdersâ&#128;&#153; engagement on critical issues.&#13;
&#13;
Fiduciary Management&#13;
&#13;
Good funds management is a non-negotiable factor for success in any reconstruction&#13;
program or MDF. This includes sound fiduciary management, as well as transparent&#13;
and efficient use of funds. The World Bankâ&#128;&#153;s trusteeship functions are governed by the&#13;
documents used to establish the trust fund, relevant internal rules and regulations,&#13;
together with agreements between the Bank and individual donors and Partner&#13;
Agencies, and the MDF Operations Manual.&#13;
&#13;
Partner Agencies administered projects in line with their internal policies and&#13;
procedures. Steering Committee endorsements of projects indicated that the&#13;
&amp;#12;56&#13;
Chapter 2 - The Strategic Framework for The MDF&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                        The lessons of the MDF will help to enhance resilience and preparedness of       Photo:&#13;
                                                        communities and local governments into the future. Above, MDF Co-Chairs during   MDF&#13;
                                                        a press conference in Jakarta in November 2012.                                  Secretariat&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                        Partner Agencyâ&#128;&#153;s own fiduciary framework and governance arrangements, policies&#13;
                                                        and procedures, including audits, safeguards, and procurement procedures, were&#13;
                                                        acceptable to the World Bank as Trustee and the Steering Committee. As a result&#13;
                                                        of ongoing harmonization among some multi-lateral agencies, there was extensive&#13;
                                                        commonality among the fiduciary frameworks, governance arrangements, policies&#13;
                                                        and procedures of each agency.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  2.5	 The MDF Experience on Aid Effectiveness&#13;
                                                        The MDF program successfully operationalized the aid effectiveness principles&#13;
                                                        as espoused in the 2005 Paris Declaration on Aid Effectivenessâ&#128;&#148;ownership,&#13;
                                                        harmonization, alignment, results, and mutual accountabilityâ&#128;&#148;and was able to evolve&#13;
                                                        from effective aid to effective partnership for development as the program matured&#13;
                                                        over its more than seven years life.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                      57&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                           A Framework for Reconstruction through Effective Partnerships&#13;
                                                                                           The Multi Donor Fund for Aceh and Nias:&#13;
Ownership&#13;
&#13;
The GoI defined the overall plans for reconstruction and led the reconstruction&#13;
efforts. At the initial stages of the reconstruction, the BRR identified sector-specific&#13;
strategies for housing infrastructure, local government assistance etc. that provided&#13;
the basis for the MDFâ&#128;&#153;s support. The alignment with BRR policies and programs&#13;
ensured that the MDFâ&#128;&#153;s interventions were fully owned by the government. The&#13;
GoI also had authored the Master Plan for reconstruction, and the Master Plan&#13;
provided guidance to reconstruction partners. This resulted in strong ownership of&#13;
the entire reconstruction and recovery agenda at national government level. The&#13;
MDF provided a platform for donors to follow the country leadership and to assist in&#13;
strengthening its capacity through various projects. Projects under the MDF were&#13;
designed through close consultation with the government and aligned with the&#13;
governmentâ&#128;&#153;s Master Plan.&#13;
&#13;
Alignment&#13;
&#13;
Projects funded by the MDF were in line with the GoI strategy and agenda for&#13;
reconstruction. GoI identified potential projects which were presented to the MDF&#13;
Steering Committee. The MDF portfolio followed the governmentâ&#128;&#153;s 3-phased approach&#13;
to the reconstruction. Immediate recovery was addressed through the CDD projects,&#13;
while longer term reconstruction activities came on board later. These included large&#13;
infrastructure projects such as the Infrastructure Reconstruction Financing Facility&#13;
(IRFF) and the Infrastructure Reconstruction Enabling Program (IREP). The third&#13;
phase focused on sustaining economic growth through capacity building (such as the&#13;
Capacity Building for Local Resource-based Rural Roads or CBLR3, Aceh Government&#13;
Transformation Programme or AGTP, Nias Islands Transition Programme or NITP, etc.)&#13;
and livelihoods development (the Economic Development Financing Facility or EDFF&#13;
and the Nias Livelihoods and Economic Development Project or LEDP).2&#13;
&#13;
Where appropriate, project funds were channeled directly through the governmentâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
budget system. MDF funds were totally untied. More than 70 percent of the MDF&#13;
projects/programs were on-budget and on-treasury which meant that MDF funds were&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
2	&#13;
     See â&#128;&#156;About the MDFâ&#128;&#157; for a full description of the 23 projects supported by the MDF.&#13;
&amp;#12;58&#13;
Chapter 1 - Background and Context&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     channeled through the GoIâ&#128;&#153;s national budget, utilizing the countryâ&#128;&#153;s public financial&#13;
                                     management system. A new fund channeling mechanism amongst different levels of&#13;
                                     government was jointly developed and introduced by some of the MDF projects to&#13;
                                     enable project implementation by institutions other than those at the national level.&#13;
                                     Both AGTP and NITP started out as off-budget projects and later developed fund&#13;
                                     channeling procedures to align with the newly enacted government regulations that&#13;
                                     all foreign funded projects should be on-budget.&#13;
&#13;
                                     Harmonization&#13;
&#13;
                                     The MDF brought together representatives from all the stakeholders in the&#13;
                                     reconstruction process. Fifteen donors came together to form the MDF program.&#13;
                                     This had greatly reduced fragmentation and the duplication of efforts. The MDF&#13;
                                     leveraged the comparative advantage of a mix of partner and implementing agencies&#13;
                                     in delivering the reconstruction and recovery program. Under the MDF program,&#13;
                                     technical assistance was provided for the subnational governments to establish their&#13;
                                     respective Regional Disaster Alleviation Agencies (Badan Penanggulangan Bencana&#13;
                                     Daerah or BPBD) to address future disasters.&#13;
&#13;
                                     Managing for Results&#13;
&#13;
                                     The MDF aggregated expected results from all its projects under six outcome&#13;
                                     areas. While the framework was in essence retrofitted as new projects were added,&#13;
                                     it provided a harmonized monitoring and reporting framework for all stakeholders to&#13;
                                     manage the overall program results for effective decision making, and avoided the&#13;
                                     imposition of additional layers and systems on top of the individual projects which&#13;
                                     were already facing a difficult post-disaster implementation context.&#13;
&#13;
                                     Mutual Accountability&#13;
&#13;
                                     A robust, multi-tiered accountability framework ensured inclusiveness of all related&#13;
                                     stakeholders. All levels of stakeholders, from the beneficiaries to the national&#13;
                                     government and development partners provided input into monitoring projects,&#13;
                                     creating a shared accountability for the reconstruction. The MDF governance structure,&#13;
                                     with regular meetings through the TRG and Steering Committee levels, meant that a&#13;
                                     joint decision-making process was implemented, and that the government and the&#13;
                                     donors were kept abreast of the progress on the MDF program.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                            59&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                 A Framework for Reconstruction through Effective Partnerships&#13;
                                                                                                 The Multi Donor Fund for Aceh and Nias:&#13;
Replicable and Adaptable Models&#13;
&#13;
The MDF provides a model that can be replicated or adapted in other post-conflict or&#13;
post-disaster reconstruction scenarios. This has already been proved through the Java&#13;
Reconstruction Fund (JRF), set up in 2006 to respond to another set of disasters in Indonesia.&#13;
&#13;
In May 2006, the special region of Yogyakarta and parts of Central Java were hit by an&#13;
earthquake. The GoI requested the World Bank and donors to mobilize support through&#13;
a multi-donor trust fund similar to the MDF. Once again donors rallied to respond, and&#13;
in October 2006 the Java Reconstruction Fund was established with contributions from&#13;
seven donors totaling approximately $94 million. As with the MDF, the World Bank served&#13;
as Trustee of the fund at the request of the government. The model was used effectively&#13;
to coordinate donors around the governmentâ&#128;&#153;s agenda, proving to be easily adaptable to&#13;
multiple disasters and institutional structures of the GoI.&#13;
&#13;
One of the most powerful examples of replicability and transfer is the adoption of the&#13;
CDD approach for housing reconstruction from Aceh to Yogyakarta. The Rekompak project&#13;
was initially developed under the MDF for community driven housing and settlements&#13;
reconstruction. When the JRF was established, the local government requested the&#13;
same approach to be applied. More than $75 million, or 80 percent of JRF funds, were&#13;
allocated to Rekompak to build earthquake resistant houses and community infrastructure.&#13;
Local government, partners and volunteers were quickly mobilized to begin building&#13;
permanent housing in disaster affected areas in Java. Disaster risk reduction was included&#13;
in all activities to ensure homes were earthquake-resistant and communities were better&#13;
prepared to face possible future disasters. The JRF built more than 15,000 earthquake&#13;
resistant houses in Java.&#13;
&#13;
In addition to the houses and activities supported with JRF grant funds through the&#13;
Rekompak project, the Government of Indonesia also applied the Rekompak approach more&#13;
broadly for its overall housing reconstruction program in Java, using the Governmentâ&#128;&#153;s own&#13;
funds. Through this approach nearly 200,000 houses were rebuilt in Java in less than two&#13;
years, one of the largest and fastest housing reconstruction experiences globally. The JRF&#13;
experience has also successfully demonstrated the flexibility of the MDF model, and the&#13;
Rekompak community-based reconstruction approach, in responding to multiple disasters&#13;
of earthquakes, tsunamis, landslides, and the volcanic eruptions of Mount Merapi in 2010.&#13;
&amp;#12;Chapter 3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
LESSONS LEARNED FROM THE MDF&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                                        61&#13;
                    The overall reconstruction of Aceh and Nias, in which the MDF played a strategic&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                             A Framework for Reconstruction through Effective Partnerships&#13;
                                                                                                             The Multi Donor Fund for Aceh and Nias:&#13;
                    and significant role, is widely acknowledged as a successful model for post-disaster&#13;
                    reconstruction. The MDF represents a strategic framework (see Figure 2) that can&#13;
                    be replicated or adapted in other post-conflict or post-disaster reconstruction&#13;
                    scenarios. The MDF streamlined the governmentâ&#128;&#153;s recovery efforts by coordinating&#13;
                    donor resources and harmonizing efforts through a single window for supporting its&#13;
                    reconstruction agenda. In fact, the MDF operationalized the 2005 Paris Declaration&#13;
                    on Aid Effectiveness, and by so doing, it established strong relationships amongst&#13;
                    different levels of government, donors, and other development partners. The program&#13;
                    mirrored the governmentâ&#128;&#153;s Master Plan for Rehabilitation and Reconstruction by&#13;
                    delivering a phased approach to post-disaster aid to balance speed, quality, and&#13;
                    sustainability. Looking back, the MDF could have established baselines on some cross-&#13;
                    cutting qualitative dimensions such as gender and capacity needs at the onset. Moving&#13;
                    forward, future post-disaster and post-conflict reconstruction programs could use&#13;
                    these lessons from the MDF experience, both positive and negative, to better design&#13;
                    their interventions in other contexts and situations.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       3.1	 An Organization Structure Based on Partnerships&#13;
                    The MDF success has shown that a key element in a strong organization for post-&#13;
                    disaster reconstruction is partnerships. Such partnerships necessitate Government&#13;
                    leadership in the overall reconstruction strategy. Donors, development partners, and&#13;
                    other stakeholders can then support the strategy, especially in framing it and further&#13;
                    articulating the agenda.&#13;
&#13;
                    Partnerships promote inclusiveness. An inclusive governance structure that is&#13;
                    reflective of and sensitive to interests of all partners builds trust and ownership.&#13;
                    Timely, open, and strategic communications with stakeholders form the backbone of&#13;
                    broad consultative processes to effectively inform the decision making body.&#13;
&#13;
                    Another form of partnership is the use of a mix of partner and implementing&#13;
                    agencies to leverage the comparative advantage of each. The use of each partnerâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
                    comparative advantages promotes participation of a wide range of stakeholders. This&#13;
                    approach at once maximizes and harmonizes reconstruction efforts.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MDF Steering Committee members and project and partner agency staff&#13;
share a traditional Acehnese meal with community leaders at Gampong&#13;
Baro village, the first pilot site of Rekompak, the MDFâ&#128;&#153;s community-based&#13;
housing project in Aceh.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Photo: MDF Secretariat&#13;
&amp;#12;62&#13;
&#13;
                                           3.2	 A Phased Implementation of Recovery and Reconstruction&#13;
Chapter 3 - Lessons Learned from The MDF&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  A phased implementation means that the approach evolves over time in response&#13;
                                                  to externalities. It is not possible to address all aspects of a reconstruction effort all&#13;
                                                  at once, especially immediately after a man-made conflict or natural disaster. The&#13;
                                                  immediate recovery phase is driven by speed to quickly restore housing, logistics,&#13;
                                                  and transport links. Temporary housing is quickly erected and access to areas&#13;
                                                  affected is established. During the second or reconstruction phase, there is need&#13;
                                                  for quality and to ensure ownership. As programs transition out of reconstruction&#13;
                                                  into economic development, sustainability becomes the driver in project design. It is&#13;
                                                  therefore important to specify the outcomes at each phase to manage expectations.&#13;
                                                  Often, this strategy is not apparent at the start; however, MDF has shown that the&#13;
                                                  phased implementation contributed to its success in balancing speed, quality,&#13;
                                                  and sustainability.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                    Figure 2: A Strategic Framework for Reconstruction&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                      Organizational Structure&#13;
                                                                                       Make partnerships the basis of&#13;
                                                                                        the organizational structure&#13;
&#13;
                                                                  Economic Development&#13;
                                                                  â&#128;¢	 Livelihoods                                                             Gender and Safeguards&#13;
                                                                                                             Capacity Development&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                  â&#128;¢	 Capacity Building&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                     Disaster/Conflict&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                      Risk Reduction&#13;
                                                                  Reconstruction&#13;
                                                                  â&#128;¢	 Infrastructure&#13;
                                                                  â&#128;¢	 Environment&#13;
                                                                  Immediate Recovery&#13;
                                                                  â&#128;¢	 Housing&#13;
                                                                  â&#128;¢	 Logistics&#13;
                                                                    Base phasing on speed, quality                                  Establish baseline and&#13;
                                                                          and sustainability                                         strategy at the start&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  By leveraging existing programs/projects at the immediate recovery phase, the MDF&#13;
                                                  was able to bring projects on line relatively quickly. It is shown that streamlined&#13;
                                                  and emergency focused internal processes are crucial in post-disaster/post-conflict&#13;
                                                  situations. Streamlined processes are then complemented by robust mechanisms for&#13;
                                                  monitoring, evaluation and supervision.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                           3.3	 An Early Start on Qualitative Elements&#13;
&#13;
                                                  A key lesson from the MDF experience is that it is important to identify cross-cutting&#13;
                                                  elements for reconstruction, and establish baseline and strategy for these at the&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                            63&#13;
start. These cross-cutting elementsâ&#128;&#148;capacity development, gender and safeguards&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                 A Framework for Reconstruction through Effective Partnerships&#13;
                                                                                                 The Multi Donor Fund for Aceh and Nias:&#13;
conditions, and disaster/conflict risk reduction in the case of MDFâ&#128;&#148;are usually&#13;
not part of the initial condition assessment through the routine Damage and Loss&#13;
Assessment (DALA). These cross-cutting issues should be included in all DALA work&#13;
to provide a basis for project design, even if the initial assessment is a quick one. The&#13;
MDF experience indicates that cross-cutting elements should span the entire life of a&#13;
reconstruction program, starting from the beginning and applying to all projects, at all&#13;
levels of government, with the involvement of all reconstruction stakeholders.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   Summary of Lessons Learned from the MDF for Aceh and Nias&#13;
&#13;
   1. Start with a strong organizational structure based on PARTNERSHIPS:&#13;
      â&#128;¢	 Establish strong partnership with Government leading the agenda, supported&#13;
         by others&#13;
      â&#128;¢	 Support the Governmentâ&#128;&#153;s reconstruction strategy, including providing help in&#13;
         framing/defining the strategy as needed&#13;
      â&#128;¢	 Build an inclusive governance structure reflective of and sensitive to interests&#13;
         of all partners&#13;
      â&#128;¢	 Have a tight decision-making body, with broad consultative processes&#13;
      â&#128;¢	 Use comparative advantages of each partner and at each level, promote&#13;
         participation of a wide range of stakeholders&#13;
      â&#128;¢	 Timely, open and strategic communications with stakeholders is KEY to a&#13;
         successful program&#13;
&#13;
   2. Implement reconstruction in PHASES to manage expectations of peace or&#13;
      reconstruction dividends:&#13;
      â&#128;¢	 Phase implementation to be appropriate to evolving context: immediate recovery&#13;
         should focus on need for SPEED, reconstruction on need for QUALITY and&#13;
         OWNERSHIP, and the transition to development on SUSTAINABILITY. It is important&#13;
         to specify the outcomes at each phase to manage expectations&#13;
      â&#128;¢	 Design projects for speed and closure by building on existing programs/projects,&#13;
         choosing projects with short duration&#13;
      â&#128;¢	 Minimize substantial design needs, and design exit strategies&#13;
      â&#128;¢	 Apply streamlined and emergency focused internal approval processes&#13;
      â&#128;¢	 Use robust mechanisms for monitoring, evaluation and supervision with good&#13;
         baselines early&#13;
&#13;
   3. Identify CROSS-CUTTING ELEMENTS and establish baseline and strategy for&#13;
      these at the start:&#13;
      â&#128;¢	 Cross-cutting elements need to span program: include them from the start, apply&#13;
         to all projects and apply to all levels of government or reconstruction stakeholders&#13;
      â&#128;¢	 Reflect cross-cutting concerns and assess initial conditions in the Joint Assessment/&#13;
         Damage and Loss Assessment&#13;
&amp;#12;CONCLUSION&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                                          65&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                               A Framework for Reconstruction through Effective Partnerships&#13;
                                                                                                               The Multi Donor Fund for Aceh and Nias:&#13;
                    The MDF delivered results to the intended beneficiaries and generated lessons learned.&#13;
                    These lessons have been documented in a body of knowledge and shared with a wide&#13;
                    range of policy makers and practitioners both nationally and internationally. During its&#13;
                    final year the MDF served as a valuable source of knowledge and information for those&#13;
                    implementing post-disaster reconstruction and recovery in other settings (see Box).&#13;
                    This body of knowledge leaves a legacy of the MDF beyond its mandate.&#13;
&#13;
                    The MDF model and strategic framework is robust enough to be adjusted for situations&#13;
                    where not all factors for success are fully met. The need for government leadership&#13;
                    and stakeholder partnerships around a local agenda is critically important, and these&#13;
                    partnerships can be fostered if they are weak. A phased approach to reconstruction&#13;
                    coupled with strategic selection of projects is a smart way to deliver peace and&#13;
                    reconstruction dividends. And enhancing capacity and inclusion of communities and&#13;
                    government agencies will ensure that a legacy of resilience and preparedness, born&#13;
                    from conflict and disaster, will endure into the future.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Projects like this paved road supported by the ILO and built by&#13;
community members in an isolated village in Gido Nias connect&#13;
remote areas of Aceh and Nias to larger population centers,&#13;
creating greater economic opportunities. Strategic selection of&#13;
projects coupled with a phased approach brings more effective&#13;
results to MDFâ&#128;&#153;s works in Aceh.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Photo: MDF Secretariat&#13;
&amp;#12;Conclusion   66&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                        67&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                             A Framework for Reconstruction through Effective Partnerships&#13;
                                                                                             The Multi Donor Fund for Aceh and Nias:&#13;
Sharing the Experiences of the MDF&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The MDF Secretariat produced a series of publications to document and share lessons&#13;
from Indonesiaâ&#128;&#153;s experience in implementing two post-disaster reconstruction programs,&#13;
the MDF and the JRF. These products are meant to be shared with policy makers and&#13;
practitioners in Indonesia and globally. The products include:&#13;
&#13;
â&#128;¢	 A book and video documentary on the Rekompak housing reconstruction project,&#13;
   documenting the approach and experience of the community-led housing and settlement&#13;
   reconstruction model in Aceh and Java.&#13;
&#13;
â&#128;¢	 A series of five working papers and knowledge notes discussing lessons learned from key&#13;
   areas of the MDFâ&#128;&#153;s work, including:&#13;
 		 o	 The community-driven approach to reconstruction&#13;
 		 o	 Reconstruction of large infrastructure&#13;
 		 o	 Capacity building in a post-disaster context&#13;
 		 o	 Mainstreaming gender in post-disaster programs&#13;
 		 o	 The MDFâ&#128;&#153;s framework for effective reconstruction.&#13;
&#13;
â&#128;¢	 A photo book, The Power of Partnerships, documenting the MDFâ&#128;&#153;s work in Aceh and Nias.&#13;
&#13;
These products are available in both English and Bahasa Indonesia. They are being widely&#13;
shared with the MDFâ&#128;&#153;s partners and will continue to be available after the program closes&#13;
through the MDFâ&#128;&#153;s website (www.multidonorfund.org) and the World Bankâ&#128;&#153;s website (www.&#13;
worldbank.org).&#13;
&amp;#12;ANNEXES&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                                       69&#13;
&#13;
       Annex 1 â&#128;&#147; MDF Key Achievements&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                            A Framework for Reconstruction through Effective Partnerships&#13;
                                                                                                            The Multi Donor Fund for Aceh and Nias:&#13;
       Overview&#13;
&#13;
       MDF Funds supported 23 projects in six outcome areas: community recovery, reconstruction&#13;
       of large infrastructure and transport, strengthening governance, sustaining the environment,&#13;
       enhancing the overall recovery process, and economic development and livelihoods.&#13;
&#13;
       Impressive results have been achieved across the portfolio. MDF projects built thousands of homes,&#13;
       repaired and expanded infrastructure, and put in place a foundation for economic growth. The&#13;
       projects improved local governance, brought women into decision-making process, and protected&#13;
       the environment. The MDF pioneered new approaches to disaster response by building effective&#13;
       partnership and tapping into the strengths of communities. The quality of MDFâ&#128;&#153;s outputs has&#13;
       generally been high and prospects for sustainability are good. Beneficiary satisfaction with the&#13;
       outputs and outcomes has been high.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       MDF Funds allocation by outcome area&#13;
&#13;
                                                     Enhancing&#13;
                                                    the Recovery&#13;
                                                     Process 8%&#13;
&#13;
                                Economic&#13;
                            Development and&#13;
                             Livelihoods 9%&#13;
                                                                                      Community&#13;
                                                                                     Recovery 32%&#13;
&#13;
                      Sustaining the&#13;
                     Environment 9%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    Governance and&#13;
                  Capacity Building 7%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                            Large Infrastructure&#13;
                                                                             &amp; Transport 35%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Local children at the Oyo bridge that connects the villages of&#13;
Lahagu and Taraha in Nias Selatan. The bridge now provides&#13;
year-round accessibilty to schools, health services and markets.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Photo: ILO Team&#13;
&amp;#12;70&#13;
Annexes&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          MDF key results/ achievements by outcome area&#13;
&#13;
          1. Community recovery (5 projects totaling US$202 million)&#13;
              â&#128;¢	 19,500 houses reconstructed and rehabilitated&#13;
              â&#128;¢	 3,000 km village roads&#13;
              â&#128;¢	 1,600 km irrigation and drainage channels&#13;
              â&#128;¢	 8,200 wells and water supply points&#13;
              â&#128;¢	 676 schools&#13;
              â&#128;¢	 511 local government offices or village halls&#13;
              â&#128;¢	 223,000 land certificates&#13;
&#13;
          2. Large infrastructure and transportation (7 projects totaling US$217 million)&#13;
              â&#128;¢	 572 km national &amp; provincial roads&#13;
              â&#128;¢	 227 km district roads&#13;
              â&#128;¢	 5 strategic ports&#13;
              â&#128;¢	 11 water resources/coastal protection systems&#13;
              â&#128;¢	 98,000 metric ton reconstruction materials transported&#13;
&#13;
          3. Strengthening governance and capacity building (3 projects totaling US$40 million)&#13;
              â&#128;¢	 142 grants to CSOs&#13;
              â&#128;¢	 3 MIS systems for reconstruction&#13;
              â&#128;¢	 4,100 government officers trained&#13;
              â&#128;¢	 13,000 teachers trained&#13;
              â&#128;¢	 202 CSOs trained&#13;
              â&#128;¢	 400 km local roads&#13;
&#13;
          4. Sustaining the environment (2 projects totaling US$57 million)&#13;
              â&#128;¢	 1 provincial/7 district spatial plans&#13;
              â&#128;¢	 47 agro-forestry nurseries established&#13;
              â&#128;¢	 Community based forest monitoring&#13;
              â&#128;¢	 233 SMEs created in waste management sector&#13;
              â&#128;¢	 3 district landfills constructed&#13;
              â&#128;¢	 1 state of the art regional landfill completed&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                      71&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                           A Framework for Reconstruction through Effective Partnerships&#13;
                                                                                           The Multi Donor Fund for Aceh and Nias:&#13;
5. Enhancing the recovery process (4 projects totaling US$ 56million)&#13;
    â&#128;¢	 Enhanced capacity of BRR and Bappenas for coordination of recovery process&#13;
    â&#128;¢	 DRR mainstreamed into regular development&#13;
    â&#128;¢	 Provincial/local disaster management agencies and local institutions strengthened&#13;
    â&#128;¢	 Public awareness and capacity building in DRR increased&#13;
    â&#128;¢	 Supported asset transfer process&#13;
&#13;
6. Economic development and livelihoods (2 projects totaling US$ 58 million)&#13;
    â&#128;¢	 34,000 farmers/fishermen supported&#13;
    â&#128;¢	 13,800 primary produces linked to markets&#13;
    â&#128;¢	 800 producer groups supported and 68 new cooperatives formed&#13;
    â&#128;¢	 5 district-level commodity-based forums for public-private dialogue established&#13;
&amp;#12;72&#13;
Annexes&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          Aceh and Nias â&#128;&#147; Before and After&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          The tsunami and earthquake changed the coastline in many places, such as this shoreline, 64&#13;
          kilometres south of Banda Aceh along the west coast, pictured before (left) and after (right) the&#13;
          disasters. The tsunami destroyed several villages, killing over 1,000 people in this one area.&#13;
&#13;
          Photos: UNDP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          The national highway connecting Calang with Meulaboh on Acehâ&#128;&#153;s west coast (right) was the&#13;
          last major infrastructure project completed under the MDF. The road included the Kuala Bubon&#13;
          bridge shown in the background, which replaced makeshift ferries (left) as the only option for&#13;
          locals to cross the river.&#13;
&#13;
          Photos: Mosista Pambudi and MDF Secretariat&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                             73&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                  A Framework for Reconstruction through Effective Partnerships&#13;
                                                                                                  The Multi Donor Fund for Aceh and Nias:&#13;
Mesjid Raya is an iconic symbol of not only Banda Aceh, but the province as a whole. During the&#13;
tsunami, the Grand Mosque served as a refuge for many residents fleeing the rushing waters.&#13;
The adjacent park, Taman Sari is shown in the foreground covered with debris (left) and after&#13;
rehabilitation (right).&#13;
&#13;
Photos: UNDP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The village of Lambung, in Banda Aceh, was completely devastated by the tsunami (left). Three&#13;
years later, survivors had rebuilt their homes and related infrastructure with the help of the&#13;
Rekompak project.&#13;
&#13;
Photos: Rekompak team&#13;
&amp;#12;74&#13;
Annexes&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          The MDFâ&#128;&#153;s TRWMPâ&#128;&#153;s project cleared over 1.3 million cubic meters of tsunami debris. The photos&#13;
          above show the Governorâ&#128;&#153;s Office in Banda Aceh immediately after the tsunami (left) and after&#13;
          debris clearing and reconstruction (right).&#13;
&#13;
          Photos: UNDP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          Mesjid Al Makmur in Banda Aceh was badly damaged in the quake (left). The TRWMP demolished the&#13;
          damaged structure and today, a new mosque takes its place (right).&#13;
&#13;
          Photos: UNDP&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                             75&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                  A Framework for Reconstruction through Effective Partnerships&#13;
                                                                                                  The Multi Donor Fund for Aceh and Nias:&#13;
A district road in Aceh Besar District before (left) and after (right) reconstruction. The IRFF&#13;
project funded the reconstruction of large infrastructure including roads, ports and coastal&#13;
protection barriers.&#13;
&#13;
Photos: Kris Hedi&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
River crossings in Nias were often precarious (left) and these conditions were exacerbated by&#13;
the earthquake in Nias. Under the RACBP almost 2,000 meters of bridges were constructed,&#13;
providing safe river crossings for many rural inhabitants.&#13;
&#13;
Photos: RACBP Project&#13;
&amp;#12;76&#13;
Annexes&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          Annex 2 â&#128;&#147; Ensuring Quality: the MDF Results Framework&#13;
          The MDF Goals and Expected Results&#13;
&#13;
          The overall goal of the MDF was to efficiently and effectively contribute to the reconstruction of&#13;
          a better Aceh and Nias following the earthquakes and tsunami. In this context, a â&#128;&#156;betterâ&#128;&#157; Aceh&#13;
          and Nias meant not only improving infra-structure in accordance with the Governmentâ&#128;&#153;s Master&#13;
          Plan, but also adhering to social concerns such as reducing poverty, improving livelihoods, and&#13;
          increasing equity.&#13;
&#13;
          The Recovery Assistance Policy of the MDF (RAP) stated that this overall goal was to be&#13;
          accomplished by:&#13;
             â&#128;¢	 Pooling donor resources to support a mutually agreed portfolio of projects and programs;&#13;
             â&#128;¢	 Working through and within the Governmentâ&#128;&#153;s Master Plan for recovery;&#13;
             â&#128;¢	 Promoting bottom-up and demand-driven development of initiatives that are eligible&#13;
                for financing;&#13;
             â&#128;¢	 Partnering with government and non-government agencies;&#13;
             â&#128;¢	 Serving as a forum for donor coordination;&#13;
             â&#128;¢	 Supporting a policy dialogue between the international community, civil society and the&#13;
                government on progress in the recovery process;&#13;
             â&#128;¢	 Having funds flow through the government budget wherever effective, and outside of the&#13;
                budget if the Steering Committee deems this more effective;&#13;
             â&#128;¢	 Pursuing gender-sensitive activities;&#13;
             â&#128;¢	 Seeking opportunities to support the peace process (conflict sensitivity); and&#13;
             â&#128;¢	 Avoiding worsening regional disparities.&#13;
&#13;
          In attaining the goal of the MDF as set out in the RAP, the expected results for Aceh and Nias&#13;
          were characterized as being: (i) communities/community infrastructure regenerated; (ii) larger&#13;
          infrastructure repaired; (iii) livelihoods restarted and poverty reduced; (iv) governance rebuilt; and&#13;
          (v) environment sustained.&#13;
&#13;
          The MDF placed great importance on ensuring the quality of the implementation of the portfolio&#13;
          across all projects. This was achieved through a multi-pronged approach, encompassing the&#13;
          formulation and use of the MDF Results Framework, the use of a Management information System&#13;
          (MIS) tracking the implementation status of all projects and participating in and facilitating various&#13;
          visits and missions to the field that promote and ensure a first-hand experience of the conditions&#13;
          and workings of the projects in the MDF portfolio.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                                  77&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                       A Framework for Reconstruction through Effective Partnerships&#13;
                                                                                                       The Multi Donor Fund for Aceh and Nias:&#13;
The MDF Results Framework&#13;
&#13;
In order for the MDF to determine whether its goal and expected results were met, a comprehensive&#13;
Logical Results Framework was developed. Determining appropriate macro-indicators, baseline&#13;
values, and deliverable outputs and outcomes in order to ensure the efficient and effective tracking&#13;
of results created a challenge due to the complex and diverse nature of projects that made up the&#13;
MDF portfolio. The complexity of formulating a suitable Logical Results Framework to encompass&#13;
the expected results in this diverse portfolio was compounded by the use of both on-budget and&#13;
off-budget funding mechanisms in the portfolio, as well as the role of different Partner Agencies&#13;
in project supervision and monitoring. These Partner Agencies, as set out in the overarching&#13;
agreements between the MDF and the Partner Agencies, were not required to report to the MDF&#13;
in a customized manner, but rather complied with their own internal reporting requirements.&#13;
This posed a significant challenge to the preparation of the framework for tracking results, and&#13;
complicated monitoring and reporting.&#13;
&#13;
However, this Framework managed to encompass clear qualitative and quantitative indicators to&#13;
measure the expected results and also used a standardized format for easy stakeholder review,&#13;
reference, monitoring and evaluation. It put the policy into a broader context that:&#13;
   â&#128;¢	 Focused on verifiable results (immediate deliverables, and longer term effects and impacts).&#13;
   â&#128;¢	 Highlighted assumptions and risks.&#13;
   â&#128;¢	 In view of the need to periodically modify the policy, permitted a rapid review and&#13;
      examination of it.&#13;
&#13;
The recovery of communities and regenerating of community infrastructure was tracked&#13;
through various results focusing on the restoration of land ownership, housing and community&#13;
infrastructure that contribute to improved living conditions. These included the number of&#13;
land titles registered and distributed, including to women, the number of households resettled&#13;
in reconstructed or rehabilitated homes, and the number and kind of key village infrastructure&#13;
completed. Qualitative results such as the satisfaction level of the beneficiaries relating to the&#13;
planning processes and the end products (e.g. houses), and the average participation rates for&#13;
women in community planning and representation rates of women in project-related elected&#13;
bodies were also measured.&#13;
&#13;
In the monitoring of the recovery of large infrastructure, the quality of the rehabilitation,&#13;
reconstruction and maintenance of key primary and secondary infrastructure were measured&#13;
through both qualitative and quantitative indicators. The completion of designs and infrastructure&#13;
components were measured in relation to the priorities of the GoI planning documents, and the&#13;
number and volume of investments approved in a participatory process with local government and/&#13;
or community representation. Completion against quality specifications of technical designs and&#13;
maintenance requirements was also measured, as well as the amount of reconstruction materials&#13;
transported. The satisfaction rate of users was also a key indicator for measuring success.&#13;
&amp;#12;78&#13;
Annexes&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          In measuring the improved quality of governance and public services, the percentages of sub-&#13;
          projects (in value and in number) that were managed by local governments, as well as proportion&#13;
          of projects administered by the local governments that apply appropriate practices during&#13;
          project design and implementation were considered. Measures to capture the numbers of local&#13;
          government officers and CSO members and village teachers trained (male/female) were used,&#13;
          and indicators for health centers completed, primary schools rehabilitated and local government&#13;
          facilities restored were tracked. The number and value of grants disbursed compared to targets&#13;
          (to district governments, NGOs/CBOs) was measured. Qualitative results indicators included the&#13;
          satisfaction level of beneficiaries with education and health services provided.&#13;
&#13;
          The monitoring of the sustainability of the environment in the reconstruction process was&#13;
          measured against the implementation of environmental safeguards by the projects, as well as&#13;
          the increased access to effective waste management systems by communities and the clearance&#13;
          of tsunami waste. Measures included the number of households that were able to take up their&#13;
          economic activities on agricultural land cleared from tsunami waste, and the hectares of agricultural,&#13;
          public and privately owned land that were cleared from tsunami waste. Local level agreements&#13;
          and legislation regarding forest management and conservation was measured, as well as spatial&#13;
          planning with environmental and conservation inputs; forest cover and replanting, and training&#13;
          of community monitors and forest guards was monitored. Use of interim landfills and completion&#13;
          of new landfills was also monitored.&#13;
&#13;
          In tracking the effectiveness and efficiency of the recovery process, the Results Framework&#13;
          measured the enhanced capacities of the BRR in strategic planning, policy development,&#13;
          implementation and quality monitoring. The number of complaints received through MDF-&#13;
          supported transparency systems (number and percentage of alleged cases of corruption) and&#13;
          percentage of complaints/ corruption cases resolved was tracked, as well as the use by NGOs of&#13;
          the NGO-administered pre-qualification database. The allocation and supervision of projects and&#13;
          volume of grants given was also an important indicator for this cluster.&#13;
&#13;
          The recovery of livelihoods and economic development was measured through business&#13;
          constraints that were successfully alleviated and the improved ability of local government to&#13;
          identify, develop and support livelihood opportunities. The number and value of sub-projects&#13;
          selected and managed and the number of local government staff trained in key project&#13;
          management and technical skills was measures, as well as employment generated in key&#13;
          production sectors. The number of recipients of micro-credits (individuals/groups/womenâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
          groups) and scholarships, and the volume of micro-credits provided along with the percentage&#13;
          of non-performing loans were key indicators. Recipients and value of small grants for recovery of&#13;
          livelihood activities, including to women were tracked. In the area of employment generation, the&#13;
          number, type, and dimensions of pilot activities to create sustainable employment and number&#13;
          of persons employed on average were measured for impact.&#13;
&#13;
          The logical framework was periodically revisited and updated to assure correspondence with the&#13;
          MDFâ&#128;&#153;s dynamic portfolio. Projects in the MDF portfolio all had individual results frameworks or&#13;
          equivalent tracking systems based on the partner agency models and requirements. This framework&#13;
          was a requirement for approval of funding.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                                          79&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                               A Framework for Reconstruction through Effective Partnerships&#13;
                                                                                                               The Multi Donor Fund for Aceh and Nias:&#13;
Rice famers harvesting in Jeuram, Nagan Raya District. The Canadian Co-operative Association         Photo:&#13;
worked with local co-ops to improve the technical and business skills of local farmers, with grant   Mosista&#13;
funds from the EDFF project.                                                                         Pambudi&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Challenges and Complementary Approaches&#13;
&#13;
The MDF placed great emphasis on ensuring the quality of its reconstruction activities. Managing&#13;
a large trust fund requires greater effort in ensuring quality of individual projects. A single project&#13;
trust-fund would only require a results framework that focuses on one specific area. In the case of&#13;
the MDF determining appropriate macro indicators, baseline values and deliverable outputs and&#13;
outcomes for tracking of results was challenging due to the complex and diverse nature of projects&#13;
that made up the MDF portfolio.&#13;
&#13;
To enhance monitoring, other approaches were also adopted such as project reports, supervision&#13;
missions, donor-funded missions, independent reviews (social, environment and portfolio level),&#13;
and managing feedback from beneficiaries, etc. As part of the monitoring activities of the MDF&#13;
to ensure quality in the portfolio, the MDF Secretariat provided regular reports to the Steering&#13;
Committee and the public on the status and progress of the projects and portfolio. These&#13;
evaluations, reviews, site visits and supervision missions all contributed to the capture of results&#13;
and adjustments to the projects to ensure high quality delivery of the portfolio.&#13;
&amp;#12;80&#13;
Annexes&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          Annex 3 â&#128;&#147; Governance and Structure of the MDF: Roles and&#13;
          Responsibilities&#13;
          The Multi Donor Fund was established to operate in accordance with fundamental principles of&#13;
          good governance as follows:&#13;
&#13;
             â&#128;¢	 In close partnership among key agencies;&#13;
             â&#128;¢	 The separation of responsibilities for allocation, fiduciary and administrative functions of&#13;
                the MDF; and&#13;
             â&#128;¢	 Full transparency and openness in MDF processes.&#13;
&#13;
          Based on these principles, the MDF was set up with the following governance and structure1:&#13;
&#13;
          The Steering Committee&#13;
&#13;
          The MDF was governed by a Steering Committee, which was supported by the Secretariat&#13;
          established by the Bank. Each Steering Committee member played a role similar to, but somewhat&#13;
          more limited than, a corporate board member. A Steering Committee Member evaluates project&#13;
          proposals and endorses them to a Partner Agency which is then responsible for appraising,&#13;
          approving and supervising the projectâ&#128;&#153;s design, objectives and implementation.&#13;
&#13;
          Steering Committee members include representatives of the National Government (initially BRR&#13;
          and later Bappenas), the Provincial Governments of Aceh and North Sumatra, each contributor&#13;
          (with more than $10 million equivalent in contribution), and civil society. The United Nations&#13;
          Resident Coordinator and a representative of international NGOs were non-voting members.&#13;
          Other donors involved in Aceh reconstruction were also represented on the Steering Committee&#13;
          as observers.&#13;
&#13;
          The Steering Committee members were responsible for: (i) setting overall priorities and providing&#13;
          strategic guidance to the MDF; (ii) reviewing progress of the MDF operations and ensuring proper&#13;
          reporting to all Contributors; (iii) ensuring coherence and collaboration between the MDF and&#13;
          the Governmentâ&#128;&#153;s priority program; and (iv) endorsing the project and program activities to be&#13;
          supported under the MDF, along with the corresponding proposals for grants to finance such&#13;
          project and program activities. The Steering Committee, through its endorsement and review&#13;
          function, exercised oversight of the grants that it endorsed.&#13;
&#13;
          The Government (national and provincial), the Bank as Trustee, and the European Commission, as&#13;
          the largest donor, were the co-chairs of the Steering Committee. The co-chairs had complementary&#13;
          but different responsibilities, based on their comparative advantages. All were responsible for&#13;
          helping to ensure the efficient and consensual working of the Steering Committee and effective&#13;
          implementation of the MDF.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                                    81&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                         A Framework for Reconstruction through Effective Partnerships&#13;
                                                                                                         The Multi Donor Fund for Aceh and Nias:&#13;
The Government of Indonesia as co-chairs, had responsibility for: (i) ensuring that the Governmentâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
voiceâ&#128;&#148;central, provincial and localâ&#128;&#148;is reflected coherently; (ii) ensuring that project concepts&#13;
were consistent with the Governmentâ&#128;&#153;s Reconstruction Program, with adequate support from&#13;
relevant agencies; and (ii) resolving disagreements among government agencies on implementation&#13;
responsibilities and issues on funds flows.&#13;
&#13;
The Provincial Government as co-chair had the additional responsibility for: (i) ensuring that&#13;
programs are followed up effectively by the relevant agencies; (ii) oversight of all implementing&#13;
units to ensure sustained projects implementation; and (iii) coordinating closely to synchronize&#13;
the sustainability of reconstruction with central and local governments along with other&#13;
related stakeholders.&#13;
&#13;
As tasked by the donor members of the Steering Committee, the largest single contributor as co-&#13;
chair was responsible for: (i) engaging with other members of the Steering Committee, especially&#13;
other contributors, to ensure that a consensual and constructive spirit is maintained; (ii) liaising&#13;
with large bilateral and multi-lateral donors to help ensure that their programs are complementary&#13;
to those of the MDF; and (iii) coordinating the Steering Committeeâ&#128;&#153;s policy dialogue with the&#13;
Government on special issues and concerns on behalf of the contributors.&#13;
&#13;
The Bank as co-chair was responsible for (i) ensuring effective relations and communications&#13;
with the Government; (ii) ensuring that concerns of contributors and observers to the Steering&#13;
Committee are reflected coherently in Steering Committee meetings; (iii) preparing agendas in&#13;
consultation with the Secretariat; (iv) oversight of the Secretariat, with the purpose of ensuring&#13;
a strong pipeline of well-prepared proposals, well-recorded meetings, agendas and minutes, and&#13;
adherence to operational guidelines; and (v) identifying and inviting key external participants to&#13;
take part in meetings.&#13;
&#13;
The Trustee&#13;
The World Bank was approved to serve as Trustee of the MDF, with responsibility to manage,&#13;
invest and administer the MDF funds. In the World Bank context, trust funds are financial and&#13;
administrative arrangements between the World Bank and donors under which donors entrust&#13;
funds to the World Bank to finance specific or programmatic development-related activities.&#13;
&#13;
The key responsibilities of the World Bank as Trustee were to (i) establish and manage the Secretariat&#13;
(see later) to manage the day-to-day operations of the MDF; and (ii) establish and maintain&#13;
separate records and ledger accounts to identify the contributions to MDF, the commitments to&#13;
be financed out of MDF and the receipts and disbursements of MDF resources for project and&#13;
program activities. The Trustee is also responsible for receiving, holding, investing and disbursing&#13;
funds to Partner Agencies (see later) and grant recipients. The Bank as Trustee was also responsible&#13;
for executing legal agreements, and for financial reporting and audits.&#13;
&amp;#12;82&#13;
Annexes&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          The Technical Review Group&#13;
&#13;
          The Steering Committee was assisted in their oversight function by the Technical Review Group&#13;
          (TRG), which carried out any duty delegated to it by the Steering Committee. The TRG was&#13;
          composed of officially nominated representatives of the members and official observers of the&#13;
          Steering Committee. Its functions included review of proposals, the Quarterly Financial Reports&#13;
          and the semi-annual MDF portfolio reports prepared by the Secretariat, ethe progress reports&#13;
          submitted by the individual projects, as well other related documentation such as project inception&#13;
          reports, project mid-term evaluations and project completion reports. The TRG provided guidance&#13;
          on Monitoring and Evaluation related matters to the Secretariat, and with its assistance highlighted&#13;
          issues in project and program performance to the Steering Committee.&#13;
&#13;
          The Secretariat&#13;
&#13;
          The Steering Committee was supported by a Secretariat which coordinated the day to day operations&#13;
          of the MDF. The World Bank, as Trustee, managed the Secretariat. The key responsibilities of the&#13;
          Secretariat were to: (i) prior to each meeting of the Steering Committee, prepare reports and make&#13;
          recommendations, as appropriate, for endorsement by Steering Committee; (ii) prepare a semi-&#13;
          annual consolidated report on activities funded by the MDF; (iii) review all reports submitted on&#13;
          the activities of the MDF prior to their submission to the Steering Committee; (iv) answer all queries&#13;
          related to the MDF; (v) handle logistical arrangements for meetings of the Steering Committee and&#13;
          the TRG, and prepare minutes of the meetings; (vi) disseminate information to Contributors; (vii)&#13;
          ensuring timely reporting of all MDF operations by the designated partner agencies to the Steering&#13;
          Committee and the public; and (viii) monitoring and evaluation of the MDF program according to a&#13;
          logical framework and reporting against that logframe.&#13;
&#13;
          Partner Agencies&#13;
&#13;
          The World Bank, the United Nations Development Programme (UNDP), the World Food Program&#13;
          (WFP) and the International Labour Organization (ILO) were endorsed by the GOI and the Steering&#13;
          Committee as partner agencies to be responsible for the appraisal, supervision, and monitoring and&#13;
          evaluation of MDF projects, and for the administration of grants from the MDF. In each case, the&#13;
          partner agencyâ&#128;&#153;s own fiduciary framework and governance arrangements, policies and procedures,&#13;
          including audits, safeguards, and procurement procedures, were applicable.&#13;
&#13;
          The partner agency generally enters into a grant agreement with a recipient to implement the&#13;
          project under the supervision of the partner agency. Grant recipients could be the government&#13;
          or non-governmental organizations. Each grant was approved and administered in accordance&#13;
          with the applicable guidelines of the partner agency, with due regard to appropriate standards of&#13;
          transparency, accountability and good governance, and the need to combat corruption and illegal&#13;
          practices in the management of grant funds.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                                83&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                     A Framework for Reconstruction through Effective Partnerships&#13;
                                                                                                     The Multi Donor Fund for Aceh and Nias:&#13;
The World Bank as Trustee acted as a Fiscal Agent when another entity was designated as the&#13;
partner agency for a project endorsed by the Steering Committee, and the Bank had a limited&#13;
role. The Fiscal Agent is responsible for entering into a fiscal agency agreement with the partner&#13;
agency, transferring MDF funds in the amount endorsed by the Steering Committee to the&#13;
partner agency, and ensuring reporting by the partner agency to the Steering Committee. The&#13;
Partner Agency was itself responsible for the appraisal, implementation supervision, monitoring&#13;
and evaluation of the project according to its own rules and regulations.&#13;
&#13;
Implementing Agencies&#13;
&#13;
Projects and programs for which funding is channeled through the governmentâ&#128;&#153;s budget were&#13;
implemented by a Government Line Agency or its designated Implementing Agency such as an&#13;
NGO, and where requested by the GoI, by a UN agency. This was referred to as â&#128;&#156;on-budgetâ&#128;&#157;&#13;
modality. Projects and programs for which funding is not channeled through Governmentâ&#128;&#153;s budget&#13;
were implemented by entities other than Government line agencies such as Partner Agencies&#13;
(UNDP and WFP), UN agencies and NGOs. This was referred to as â&#128;&#156;off-budgetâ&#128;&#157; modality. In&#13;
general, the MDF operated on a policy of financing projects under APBN (State Budget of Revenues&#13;
and Expenditures), and the majority of MDF funds was channeled through the governmentâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
budget channel.&#13;
&amp;#12;   Annex 4 â&#128;&#147; MDF Timeline&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  2004&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  2005                                                                                                    2007&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  2005                                                                   2008&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
2004                    2005                                                                   2006                            2007&#13;
&#13;
  December:               January:                            July:                              February:                        February:&#13;
â&#128;¢	 Massive              â&#128;¢	 Government of Indonesia          â&#128;¢	 TA to BRR and Bappenas          â&#128;¢	 SDLP project starts.          â&#128;¢	 SPADA project starts.&#13;
   earthquake off          requests establishment of a         project starts.                 â&#128;¢	 8th MDF Steering Committee    â&#128;¢	 12th MDF Steering&#13;
   the coast of            multidonor trust fund.           â&#128;¢	 4th MDF Steering Committee         meeting.                         Committee meeting.&#13;
   Aceh triggers                                               meeting.&#13;
   Asian tsunami.         March:                                                                 March:                           March:&#13;
   President            â&#128;¢	 Earthquake in Nias islands and     August:                          â&#128;¢	 CBLR3 project starts.         â&#128;¢	 IRFF project starts.&#13;
   Susilo Bambang          parts of Aceh causing further    â&#128;¢	 KDP and UPP projects start.     â&#128;¢	 9th MDF Steering Committee&#13;
   Yudhoyono               widespread damage.               â&#128;¢	 5th MDF Steering Committee         meeting.                        July:&#13;
   declares a                                                  meeting.                                                         â&#128;¢	 13th MDF Steering&#13;
   national disaster.     April:                            â&#128;¢	 Peace agreement ends Aceh         April:                            Committee meeting.&#13;
                        â&#128;¢	 MDF established.                    conflict.                       â&#128;¢	 IREP project starts.&#13;
                        â&#128;¢	 BRR established.                                                                                       September:&#13;
                                                              October:                           June:                          â&#128;¢	 14th MDF Steering&#13;
                          May:                              â&#128;¢	 Rekompak project starts.        â&#128;¢	 10th MDF Steering                Committee meeting.&#13;
                        â&#128;¢	 1st MDF Steering Committee       â&#128;¢	 6th MDF Steering Committee         Committee meeting.&#13;
                           meeting.                            meeting.                                                           December:&#13;
                                                                                                 September:                     â&#128;¢	 LCRMP and TRPRP projects&#13;
                          June:                               December:                        â&#128;¢	 AFEP and BAFMP projects          close.&#13;
                        â&#128;¢	 RALAS project starts.            â&#128;¢	 TRPRP and CSO projects start.      start.                        â&#128;¢	 15th MDF Steering&#13;
                        â&#128;¢	 2nd MDF Steering Committee       â&#128;¢	 7th MDF Steering Committee      â&#128;¢	 11th MDF Steering                Committee meeting.&#13;
                           meeting.                            meeting.                           Committee meeting.            â&#128;¢	 16th MDF Steering&#13;
                        â&#128;¢	 3rd MDF Steering Committee                                                                              Committee meeting.&#13;
                           meeting.                                                              October:&#13;
                                                                                               â&#128;¢	 LCRMP project starts.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                 November:&#13;
                                                                                               â&#128;¢	 KRRP project starts.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                                              2011&#13;
                                                           2009&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                           2010                                                               2012&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
2008                       2009                       2010                   2011                       2012&#13;
&#13;
  July:                      March:                     April:                 March:                     May:&#13;
â&#128;¢	 AGTP project starts.    â&#128;¢	 EDFF project starts.    â&#128;¢	 Rekompak            â&#128;¢	 22nd MDF Steering       â&#128;¢	 DRR-A project closes.&#13;
â&#128;¢	 MDF closing date                                      project closes.        Committee meeting.&#13;
   extended to December      April:                                                                       June:&#13;
   2012.                   â&#128;¢	 NITP project starts.      May:                   June:                    â&#128;¢	 23rd MDF Steering&#13;
                           â&#128;¢	 19th MDF Steering       â&#128;¢	 CSO project         â&#128;¢	 KRRP project closes.       Committee meeting.&#13;
  September:                  Committee meeting.         closes.                                        â&#128;¢	 AGTP, NITP, and SDLP&#13;
â&#128;¢	 17th MDF Steering       â&#128;¢	 BRR closes.                                      December:	                  projects close.&#13;
   Committee meeting.                                   September:	          â&#128;¢	 IREP, IRFF, and SPADA&#13;
                             June:	                   â&#128;¢	 21st MDF Steering      close.                    November:	&#13;
  November:                â&#128;¢	 RALAS project closes.      Committee                                      â&#128;¢	 International conference&#13;
â&#128;¢	 DRR-A project starts.                                 meeting.                                          marks closing of the MDF&#13;
                             October:	                                                                     and JRF.&#13;
  December:                â&#128;¢	 RACBP project starts.     October:	                                       â&#128;¢	 EDFF and CBLR3 projects&#13;
â&#128;¢	 18th MDF Steering                                  â&#128;¢	 LEDP project                                      close.&#13;
   Committee meeting.        November:	                  starts.&#13;
                           â&#128;¢	 20th MDF Steering                                                           December:	&#13;
                              Committee meeting.                                                        â&#128;¢	 IRFF-AF, TRWMP, RACBP,&#13;
                                                                                                           TA to BRR and Bappenas,&#13;
                             December:	                                                                    AFEP, and LEDP projects&#13;
                           â&#128;¢	 BAFMP, KDP, and UPP                                                          close.&#13;
                              projects close.                                                           â&#128;¢	 MDF program closes on&#13;
                                                                                                           December 31.&#13;
&amp;#12;86&#13;
&#13;
                           ACRONYMS &amp; ABBREVIATIONS&#13;
Acronyms &amp; Abbreviations&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                           ADB             Asian Development Bank&#13;
                           AFEP            Aceh Forest and Environment Project&#13;
                           AGTP            Aceh Government Transformation Programme&#13;
                           ANUE            Australian National University Enterprise Pty. Limited&#13;
                           AusAID          Australian Agency for International Development&#13;
                           BAMFP           Banda Aceh Flood Mitigation Project&#13;
                           Bappeda         Badan Perencanaan Pembangunan Daerah&#13;
                                           (Regional Development Planning Agency)&#13;
                           Bappenas        Badan Perencanaan Pembangunan Nasional&#13;
                                           (National Development Planning Agency)&#13;
                           BPBA            Badan Penanggulangan Bencana Aceh (Aceh Disaster Alleviation Agency)&#13;
                           BPBD            Badan Penanggulangan Bencana Daerah (Regional Disaster Alleviation Agency)&#13;
                           BRR             Badan Rekonstruksi dan Rehabilitasi NAD-Nias (Agency for the Aceh-Nias&#13;
                                           Reconstruction and Rehabilitation Board)&#13;
                           CB              Capacity Building&#13;
                           CBLR3           Capacity Building for Local Resource-based Rural Roads Project&#13;
                           CBO             Community Based Organization&#13;
                           CD              Capacity Development&#13;
                           CIDA            Canadian International Development Agency&#13;
                           CSO (project)   Support to Strengthen the Capacity and Role of Civil Society Organizations in&#13;
                                           the Recovery of Communities in Aceh and Nias&#13;
                           CSO             Civil Society Organisation&#13;
                           DIPA            Daftar Isian Pelaksanaan Anggaran (State Budget Execution Document)&#13;
                           DRR             Disaster Risk Reduction&#13;
                           DRR-A           Making Aceh Safer through Disaster Risk Reduction in Development Project&#13;
                           EDFF            Economic Development Financing Facility&#13;
                           GIZ             Deutsche Gesellschaft fÃ¼r Internationale Zuzammenarbeit GmbH&#13;
                                           (German International Assistance Agency, formerly GTZ)&#13;
                           GoA             Government of Aceh&#13;
                           GoI             Government of Indonesia&#13;
                           GTZ             Deutsche Gesellschaft fÃ¼r Technische Zuzammenarbeit GmbH&#13;
                                           (German Technical Assistance Agency)&#13;
                           IREP            Infrastructure Reconstruction Enabling Program&#13;
                           IRFF            Infrastructure Reconstruction Financing Facility&#13;
                           ILO             International Labour Organization&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                      87&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                           A Framework for Reconstruction through Effective Partnerships&#13;
                                                                                           The Multi Donor Fund for Aceh and Nias:&#13;
KDP           Kecamatan Development Project&#13;
KRRP          Nias Kecamatan-based Reconstruction and Rehabilitation Planning Project&#13;
LEDP          Nias Livelihoods and Economic Development Program&#13;
MDF           Multi Donor Fund for Aceh and Nias&#13;
MoA           Memorandum of Agreement&#13;
MoF           Ministry of Finance&#13;
MoHA          Ministry of Home Affairs&#13;
MoU           Memorandum of Understanding&#13;
MTR           Mid Term Review&#13;
M&amp;E           Monitoring and Evaluation&#13;
NAD           Nanggroe Aceh Darussalam&#13;
NGO           Non-Governmental Organization&#13;
NITP          Nias Islands Transition Programme&#13;
PAD           Project Appraisal Document&#13;
PK2-APBA      Pengendalian dan Percepatan Kegiatan Anggaran Pendapatan&#13;
              dan Belanja Aceh&#13;
PMU           Project Management Unit&#13;
ProDoc        Project Document&#13;
RACBP         Nias Rural Access and Capacity Building Project&#13;
Rekompak      Rehabilitasi dan Rekonstruksi Masyarakat dan Permukiman Berbasis Komunitas&#13;
RPJMD         Rencana Pembangunan Jangka Menengah Daerah&#13;
              (Regional Medium Term Development Plan)&#13;
SDLP          Sea Delivery and Logistics Programme&#13;
SPADA         Support for Poor and Disadvantaged Areas Project&#13;
TA            Technical Assistance&#13;
TA-BRR/R2C3   Technical Assistance for BRR and Bappenas/&#13;
              Rehabilitation and Reconstruction Completion and Continued Coordination&#13;
TDMRC         Tsunami and Disaster Mitigation Research Centre&#13;
TOR           Terms of Reference&#13;
TRPRP         Tsunami Recovery Ports Redevelopment Program&#13;
TRWMP         Tsunami Recovery Waste Management Programme&#13;
UNDP          United Nations Development Programme&#13;
UPP           Urban Poverty Program UPP&#13;
USAID         United States Agency for International Development&#13;
WFP           World Food Programme&#13;
&amp;#12;                                    NAD   Nias&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Published by:&#13;
MDF-JRF Secretariat&#13;
The World Bank Office&#13;
Indonesia Stock Exchange Building&#13;
Tower I, 9th Floor                                              December 2012&#13;
Jl. Jendral Sudirman Kav. 52-53&#13;
Jakarta 12910, Indonesia                                    www.worldbank.org&#13;
Tel	 : (+6221) 5299-3000                               www.multidonorfund.org&#13;
Fax	 : (+6221) 5299-3111                         www.javareconstructionfund.org&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="18775381">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2012/12/18775381/multi-donor-fund-mdf-aceh-nias-framework-reconstruction-through-effective-partnerships
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2012/12/18775381/multi-donor-fund-mdf-aceh-nias-framework-reconstruction-through-effective-partnerships</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2012/12/18775381/multi-donor-fund-mdf-aceh-nias-framework-reconstruction-through-effective-partnerships</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2014-01-09T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2014-01-09T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2014/01/09/000461832_20140109190939/Rendered/INDEX/839030NWP0Box382108B00PULBIC00no5.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2014/01/09/000461832_20140109190939/Rendered/PDF/839030NWP0Box382108B00PULBIC00no5.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2014-01-09T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2012-12-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            The Multi Donor Fund (MDF) for Aceh and
            Nias : a framework for reconstruction through effective partnerships
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The Multi Donor Fund for Aceh and Nias
            (MDF) and the Java Reconstruction Fund (JRF) have played
            significant roles in the remarkable recovery of Aceh, Nias
            and Java, following some of the worst disasters in Indonesia
            in recent years. The MDF and the JRF, which is patterned
            after it, are each considered a highly successful model for
            post-disaster reconstruction. This paper presents
            experiences from the implementation of the MDF, and
            documents key lessons on its strategic framework and design
            which contributed to the MDF's success in supporting
            the government of Indonesia's reconstruction agenda.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            The Multi Donor Fund (MDF) for Aceh and Nias
            : a framework for reconstruction through effective partnerships
        </docna>
        <display_title>The Multi Donor Fund (MDF) for
            Aceh and Nias : a framework for reconstruction through
            effective partnerships</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2012/12/18775381/multi-donor-fund-mdf-aceh-nias-framework-reconstruction-through-effective-partnerships</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Working Paper (Numbered Series)</docty>
        <subtopic>Post Conflict Reconstruction,Hazard Risk Management,Natural Disasters,Disaster Management,Public Sector Economics</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Environment,Public Sector Development,Urban Development,Conflict and Development</teratopic>
        <count>Indonesia</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Asia!$!80451</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Southeast Asia!$!80471</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000461832_20140109190939</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>East Asia and Pacific,East Asia and Pacific</admreg>
        <colti>MDF-JRF working paper series ; no. 5</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Environment,Public Sector Development,Urban Development,Conflict and Development</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            casualties, civil society, civil war,
            climate change, conflict, conflicts, counterpart, crises,
            damages, deaths, Declaration, devastation, development aid,
            development assistance, Development Project, Disaster,
            disaster assistance, disaster preparedness, disaster prone
            countries, Disaster Reconstruction, disaster recovery,
            disaster response, disaster risk, disaster risk reduction,
            disaster situation, disaster situations, disaster survivors,
            disaster-prone countries, disasters, dispute resolution,
            documents, donor countries, donor country, early warning,
            early warning systems, Earthquake, earthquakes, Economic
            Development, economic growth, economic recovery,
            emergencies, emergency response, emergency situations,
            eruption, evacuation, evacuees, farmers, financial
            management, Flood, flooded, flooding, floods, foundations,
            housing, international agencies, international assistance,
            international community, international context,
            international development, international donors, lahar,
            landslides, local governments, MDF, meeting, meetings,
            modality, multilateral aid, multilateralism, municipalities,
            national budget, Nations, natural disaster, natural
            disasters, natural hazards, needs assessment, Observer,
            observers, peace, physical damage, polices, ports,
            post-tsunami reconstruction, private sector, project design,
            project implementation, Project selection, property rights,
            provincial governments, public, public goods, Public Works,
            rebel, rebels, recipient countries, Reconstruction,
            reconstruction activities, Rehabilitation, Road, roads,
            storm, streets, subnational governments, survivor,
            survivors, tax, tidal waves, transparency, Tsunami, Tsunami
            Recovery, tsunamis, UNDP, urban infrastructure, Urban
            Poverty, victims, violence, Volcanic Eruptions, volcano,
            wars, weapons
        </keywd>
        <owner>World Bank Office: Jakarta (EACIF)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Southeast Asia</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>83903</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fragility, Conflict and Violence</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports</ml:concept><ml:concept>Livestock</ml:concept><ml:concept>Livestock and Animal Husbandry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Organisational Structures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Organizational Assessments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Post Conflict Reconstruction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Postconflict Reconstruction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Disaster Resilience</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Checks on Executive Power</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen User Satisfaction Survey</ml:concept><ml:concept>Independent Commissions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ombudsmen</ml:concept><ml:concept>Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Parliament</ml:concept><ml:concept>Procurement Complaints Review Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supreme Audit Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civil Society</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Disasters</ml:concept><ml:concept>Oceans</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports &amp; Waterways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Animal Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forests</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Sustainability</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance Structures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Local Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Post-Conflict Reconstruction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Disaster Risk Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Accountability Mechanisms</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Eastern Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Indonesia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>