<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>﻿OFFICIAL I IT~'&#13;
DOCUMENTS&#13;
December 12, 2013&#13;
Administration Arrangement between the Government of the United&#13;
Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland, represented by the&#13;
Department for International Development and the International Bank for&#13;
Reconstruction and Development and the International Development&#13;
Association Concerning Revitalizing Education Development in Sierra-Leone&#13;
Multi-Donor Trust Fund (REDiSL MDTF) (No. TF072152)&#13;
DFID Component Code: 240278-101&#13;
1.    The International Bank for Reconstruction and Development and the International Development&#13;
Association (collectively, the "World Bank") acknowledge that the Government of the United Kingdom of&#13;
Great Britain and Northern Ireland, represented by the Department for International Development (the&#13;
"Donor". and together with the World Bank, the "Parties" and each a "Party") decided to provide the sum of&#13;
four million four hundred thousand Pounds Sterling (f4,400,000.00) (the "Contribution") for the Revitalizing&#13;
Education Development in Sierra-Leone Multi-Donor Trust Fund, No. 072152 (the "Trust Fund") in&#13;
accordance with the terms of this Administration Arrangement. Other donors are also expected to contribute&#13;
to the Trust Fund on the provisions specified in the Annexes to this Administration Arrangement.&#13;
2.    The Contribution will be used to finance the activities set forth in the Revitalizing Education&#13;
Development in Sierra-Leone Multi-Donor Trust Fund (REDiSL MDTF) Trust Fund Description" attached&#13;
hereto as Annex 1, and will be administered by the Bank on behalf of the Donor in accordance with the terms&#13;
of this Administration Arrangement, including the "Standard Provisions" attached hereto as Annex 2 and&#13;
"Governance" attached hereto as Annex 3.&#13;
3.     The Donor will deposit the Contribution in accordance with the following schedule and in the&#13;
currency specified in Section I above ("Contribution Currency") into such bank account designated by the&#13;
Bank (each amount deposited hereinafter referred to as an "Installment") upon submission of a payment&#13;
request by the Bank:&#13;
(a)    Promptly following countersignature    f 2,000,000.00&#13;
(b)    By 30"' November 2014                  f 1,400,000.00&#13;
(c)    By 30"' November 2015                  f 1,000.000.00&#13;
4.     When making any deposit, the Donor will instruct its bank to include in its deposit details&#13;
information (remittance advice) field of its SWIFT deposit message, information indicating: the amount&#13;
deposited, that the deposit is made by the Donor for TF072152the Revitalizing Education Development in&#13;
Sierra-Leone Multi-Donor Trust Fund), and the date of the deposit (the "Deposit Instructions"). In addition,&#13;
the Donor will provide a copy of the Deposit Instructions to the Bank's Accounting Trust Funds Division by&#13;
e-mail sent to tfremitadvice@tworldbank.org or by fax sent to + 1 (202) 614-1315.&#13;
-1-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿5.     Except with respect to the Deposit Instructions, any notice, request or other communication to be&#13;
given or made under this Administration Arrangement will be in writing and delivered by mail, fax or e-mail&#13;
to the respective Party's address specified below or at such other address as such Party notifies in writing to&#13;
the other Party from time to time:&#13;
For the Bank (the "Bank Contact"):&#13;
Kaliope Azzi-Huck&#13;
Sr. Operations Officer /Task Team Leader&#13;
West and Central Africa Education Unit (AFTEW)&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
1818 H Street, NW&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433&#13;
Tel: +1 202 473 4686&#13;
E-mail: kazzi-huck(aworldbank.org&#13;
For the Donor (the "Donor Contact"):&#13;
Edward Davis&#13;
Education Adviser&#13;
DFID Sierra Leone &amp; Liberia&#13;
5 Off Spur Road, Freetown, Sierra Leone&#13;
Tel: +232 (0)76 801498&#13;
E-mail: e-davis@dfid.gov.uk&#13;
6.     In the event any amounts are to be returned to the Donor under this Administration Arrangement, the&#13;
Bank will transfer such amounts to the Donor, unless otherwise agreed with the Bank,&#13;
7.     In providing funds under this Arrangement, the Donor does not intend to accept any responsibility or&#13;
liability towards any third parties for any claims, debts, demands, damage or loss as a result of the&#13;
implementation of the activities under the Trust Fund.&#13;
8.     All annexes hereto constitute an integral part of this Administration Arrangement, whose terms taken&#13;
together will constitute the entire arrangement and understanding between the Donor and the Bank. Unless&#13;
otherwise specified in an annex hereto, this Administration Arrangement may be amended only by written&#13;
amendment between the Bank and the Donor; provided, however, that any annexes to this Administration&#13;
Arrangement may be amended only by written amendment of all donors contributing to the Trust Fund.&#13;
9.     Each of the undersigned represents, by confirming its acceptance below, that it is authorized to enter&#13;
into this Administration Arrangement and act in accordance with its provisions. The Bank and the Donor are&#13;
each requested to sign and date this Administration Arrangement, and upon possession by the Bank of this&#13;
fully signed Administration Arrangement, this Administration Arrangement will become carried out as of the&#13;
date of the last signature. It is understood that this Administration Arrangement, including any annexes, is&#13;
not an international treaty. It is an administrative arrangement between the Trustee and the Donor.&#13;
-2-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿INTERNATIONAL BANK FOR RECONSTRUCTION AND DEVELOPMENT&#13;
INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPMENT ASSOCIATION&#13;
By    :_      _    _    _&#13;
Name: Sergiy V. Kulyk&#13;
Title: Acting Country Director&#13;
Ghana, Liberia, and Sierra Leone&#13;
Date: December 12, 2013&#13;
UNITED KINGDOM OF GREAT BRITAIN AND NORTHERN IRELAND REPRESENTED BY&#13;
DEPARTMENT FOR INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPMENT&#13;
By:&#13;
Name: Phil Evans&#13;
Title:  Head of Office&#13;
DFID Sierra Leone and Liberia&#13;
Date: December 13, 2013&#13;
-3-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿ANNEX 1&#13;
Revitalizing Education Development in Sierra-Leone (REDiSL) MDTF&#13;
Trust Fund Description&#13;
This Annex will be applicable to and form an integral part of all administration arrangements for the Trust&#13;
Fund (collectively, the "Administration Arrangements" and each an "Administration Arrangement") between&#13;
the Bank and any entities that provide any funds to the Trust Fund (collectively, the "Donors").&#13;
1. Obiectives&#13;
The objective of the Sierra Leone Multi-Donor Trust Fund is to improve the learning environment and&#13;
establish systems for monitoring of education interventions and outcomes.&#13;
2. Activities&#13;
The activities (which may be described as "components?' of activities) to be financed by the Trust Fund are:&#13;
2.1    Bank-executed activities, for which the Bank has implementation responsibility:&#13;
Provision of technical assistance to the Government of Sierra Leone to help in implementing,&#13;
monitoring and reporting on the Education Sector Strategy.&#13;
2.2    Recipient-executed activities, for which one or more Recipients (as defined in Annex 2) have&#13;
implementation responsibility:&#13;
This Trust Fund will focus on: (i) implementing and monitoring specific elements of the education sector&#13;
strategy; (ii) coordinating donor activities in education; and (iii) addressing capacity gaps at the Ministry and&#13;
local levels.&#13;
(i) Implementing and Monitoring Sjcific Elements of the Education Sector Strategy: The trust&#13;
fund will co-finance specific areas of Education Sector Plan (ESP), which have been identified as bottlenecks&#13;
for the implementation of the plan. In this context, it will put in place the systems and processes to ensure an&#13;
effective monitoring and evaluation of the ESP and educational services in general.&#13;
(ii) Coordinating Donor Activities in Education: The trust fund will provide support to the change&#13;
process currently being developed in the Ministry of Education, Science and Technology (MEST) aimed&#13;
at creating structures to give for better coordination of efforts in the sector.&#13;
(iii) Addressing Capacity Gaps at the Ministry and Local Levels: In line with recommendations of&#13;
the Capacity Development Strategy (CDS), this TF will support capacity development for MEST at both the&#13;
central and district level.&#13;
3. Eligible Expenditures&#13;
3.1    For Bank-executed activities, the Trust Fund funds may be used to finance:&#13;
-4-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿(a) Associated Overheads; (b) Consultant Fees Individuals and Firms; (c) Contractual Services; (d);&#13;
Equipment and Office Premises Lease Cost; (e) Extended Term Consultants-No Indirects; (0&#13;
Extended Term Consultants; (g) Field Assignment Benefits; (h) Media, Workshop, Conference and&#13;
Meeting; (i) Staff Costs - with Indirect Costs; (j) Staff Costs - No Indirect Costs; (k) Temporary&#13;
Support Staff Costs; (1) Temporary staff costs - No Indirects; and (m) Travel Expenses.&#13;
3.2    For Recipient-executed activities, the Trust Fund funds may be used to finance eligible expenditures&#13;
in accordance with the Bank's applicable policies and procedures.&#13;
(a) Civil Works; (b) Consulting; (c) Goods; (d) Operating Costs; and (e) Training&#13;
4. Taxes&#13;
4.1    The foregoing activities and categories of expenditures may include the financing of taxes in&#13;
accordance with the Bank's applicable policies and procedures.&#13;
5. Proeram Criteria&#13;
5.1    Activities are to be financed in accordance with the following program criteria:&#13;
- Relevance to the Trustfund objective&#13;
-  Likelihood that activities will support the recipient executed activities in the three main areas: (i)&#13;
implementing and monitoring specific elements of the education sector strategy; (ii) coordinating&#13;
donor activities in education; and (iii) addressing capacity gaps at the Ministry and local lcvels.&#13;
6. Retroactive Financing&#13;
6.1    The Trust Fund funds may be used to retroactively finance payments for eligible expenditures made&#13;
as of December 13, 2013 in accordance with the Bank's applicable policies and procedures.&#13;
-5-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿ANNEX 2&#13;
Revitalizing Education Development in Sierra-Leone (REDiSL) MDTF&#13;
Standard Provisions&#13;
This Annex will be applicable to and form an integral part of all Administration Arrangements between the&#13;
Bank and the respective Donors.&#13;
1.     Administration of the Contributions&#13;
1.1   The Bank will be responsible only for performing those functions specifically set fordi in this&#13;
Administration Arrangement and will not be subject to any other duties or responsibilities to the Donors,&#13;
including, without limitation, any duties or commitments that might otherwise apply to a fiduciary or trustee&#13;
under general principles of trust or fiduciary law. Nothing in this Administration Arrangement will be&#13;
considered a waiver of any privileges or immunities of the Bank under its Articles of Agreement or any&#13;
applicable law, all of which are expressly reserved.&#13;
1.2    Each Donor's Contribution (collectively, the "Contributions") will be administered in accordance&#13;
with the Bank's applicable policies and procedures, as the same may be amended from time to time,&#13;
including its procurement, financial management, disbursement and safeguard policies, its framework to&#13;
prevent and combat fraud and corruption and its screening procedures to prevent the use of Bank resources to&#13;
finance terrorist activity, in line with the Bank's commitments to give effect to the relevant decisions of the&#13;
Security Council taken under Chapter VII of the of Charter of the United Nations. The Donors acknowledge&#13;
that this provision does not create any commitments of die Bank under the anti-terrorist financing and asset&#13;
control laws, regulations, rules and executive orders of an individual member country that may apply to a&#13;
Donor.&#13;
2.     Managiement of the Contributions&#13;
2.1    The funds deposited in the Trust Fund will be accounted for as a single trust fund and will be kept&#13;
separate and apart from the funds of the Bank. The funds deposited in the Trust Fund may be commingled&#13;
with other trust fund assets maintained by the Bank. The Bank, in its capacity as trustee, has legal title to the&#13;
funds deposited in the Trust Fund.&#13;
2.2    The currency in which the funds in the Trust Fund will be held is United States Dollars (the&#13;
"Holding Currency").&#13;
2.3    Donors accept to deposit their Contributions in the Contribution Currency stated in their respective&#13;
Administration Arrangements. In the case of deposits received in a Contribution Currency other than the&#13;
Holding Currency, promptly upon the receipt of such amounts and the accompanying Deposit Instructions,&#13;
the Bank will convert such amounts into the Holding Currency at the exchange rate obtained by the Bank on&#13;
the date of the conversion. Where deposits prove to be insufficient to complete activities as a result of&#13;
exchange rate fluctuations, neither the Bank nor the Donor will bear any responsibility for providing any&#13;
additional financing.&#13;
2.4    The funds deposited in the Trust Fund may be freely exchanged by the Bank into other currencies as&#13;
may facilitate their disbursement at the exchange rate obtained by the Bank on the date of the conversion.&#13;
-6-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿2.5    The Bank will invest and reinvest the funds deposited in the Trust Fund pending their disbursement&#13;
in accordance with the Bank's applicable policies and procedures for the investment of trust funds&#13;
administered by the Bank. The Bank wilt credit all income from such investment to the Trust Fund to be used&#13;
for the same purposes as the Contributions.&#13;
3.     Trust Fund Fees and Costs&#13;
3.1    The Bank will deduct and retain for its own account, as a deduction from each Installment, an&#13;
amount equal to two percent (2%) per Installment as an administrative fee for the Trust Fund.&#13;
3.2   In addition, costs incurred by the Bank for other expenses, such as for program management and&#13;
Trust Fund administration, that are (i) not covered by the percentage deduction specified above as an&#13;
administrative fee and (ii) not included tinder Annex I of the Administration Arrangements in accordance&#13;
with the Bank's applicable policies and procedures will be charged to the Trust Fund on an actual basis up to&#13;
a maximum of three point thirty two percent (3.32%) of the total Contributions under all Administration&#13;
Arrangements.&#13;
3.3    Each Donor acknowledges and accepts that the percentage deductions for fees in this Trust Fund&#13;
Fees and Costs section are estimated on the basis of anticipated Contributions. If actual Contributions&#13;
significantly differ from what was originally anticipated at the time of signature of the first Administration&#13;
Arrangement, or if other circumstances affecting Trust Fund fees or costs change, the Bank reserves the right&#13;
to request a change to the terms of this Trust Fund Fees and Costs section, which would be effectuated by&#13;
amendments made to the Administration Arrangements of all Donors and which would thereafter be&#13;
applicable to all new Contributions that are provided either as amendments to supplement existing&#13;
Administration Arrangements or from new Donors tinder new Administration Arrangements.&#13;
4.     Accounting and Financial Reporting&#13;
4.1    The Bank will maintain separate records and ledger accounts in respect of the funds deposited in the&#13;
Trust Fund and disbursements made therefrom.&#13;
4.2    The Bank will furnish to the Donors current financial information relating to receipts, disbursements&#13;
and fund balance in the Holding Currency with respect to the Contributions via the World Bank's Trust&#13;
Funds Donor Center secure website. Within six (6) months after all commitments and liabilities under the&#13;
Trust Fund have been satisfied and the Trust Fund has been closed, the final financial information relating to&#13;
receipts, disbursements and fund balance in the Holding Currency with respect to the Contributions will be&#13;
made available to the Donors via the World Bank's Trust Funds Donor Center secure website.&#13;
4.3    The Bank will provide to the Donors via the World Bank's Trust Fund Donor Center secure website,&#13;
within six (6) months following the end of each Bank fiscal year, an annual single audit report, comprising&#13;
(i) a management assertion together with an attestation from the Bank's external auditors concerning the&#13;
adequacy of internal control over cash-based financial reporting for all cash-based trust funds as a whole; and&#13;
(ii) a combined financial statement for all cash-based trust funds together with the Bank's external auditor's&#13;
opinion thereon. The cost of the single audit will be borne by the Bank.&#13;
4.4   If a Donor wishes to request, on an exceptional basis, a financial statement audit by the Bank's&#13;
external auditors of the Trust Fund, the Donor and the Bank will first consult as to whether such an external&#13;
audit is necessary. The Bank and the Donor will decide on the appropriate scope and terms of reference of&#13;
such audit. Following agreement on the scope and terms of reference, the Bank will arrange for such&#13;
-7-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿external audit. The costs of any such audit, including the internal costs of the Bank with respect to such&#13;
audit, will be borne by the requesting Donor.&#13;
4.5    The Bank will make available to the Donors copies of all financial statements and auditors' reports&#13;
received by the Bank from Recipients pursuan't to any Grant Agreements (as defined below) in accordance&#13;
with the Bank's Access to Information Policy.&#13;
5.     Progress Reporting&#13;
5.1    The Bank will provide the Donors with annual reports on the progress of activities financed by the&#13;
Contributions. Within six (6) months of the End Disbursement Date (as defined below), the Bank will&#13;
furnish to the Donors a final report on the activities financed by the Trust Fund.&#13;
5.2    Any Donor may review or evaluate activities financed by the Trust Fund at any time up to six (6)&#13;
months following the End Disbursement Date. The Donor and the Bank will decide on the scope and conduct&#13;
of such review or evaluation, and the Bank will provide all relevant information within the limits of the&#13;
Bank's applicable policies and procedures. All associated costs, including any costs incurred by the Bank,&#13;
will be borne by the Donor. It is understood that any such review or evaluation will not constitute a&#13;
financial, compliance or other audit of the Trust Fund.&#13;
6.     Disbursement; Cancellation: Refund&#13;
6.1   It is expected that the funds deposited in the Trust Fund will be fully disbursed by the Bank by&#13;
September 30, 2017 (the "End Disbursement Date"). The Bank will only disburse funds deposited in the&#13;
Trust Fund For the purposes of this Administration Arrangement (other than returns to Donors) after such&#13;
date to the extent such date is changed in accordance with amendments made to the Administration&#13;
Arrangements of all the Donors. Following the End Disbursement Date, the Bank will return any remaining&#13;
balance of the Trust Fund to each Donor in the Holding Currency in the manner specified in its respective&#13;
Administration Arrangement on a pro rata basis with regard to the total funds deposited in the Trust Fund by&#13;
such Donor relative to the total funds deposited in the Trust Fund by all Donors, all calculated as Holding&#13;
Currency amounts.&#13;
6.2    Any Donor may cancel all or part of such Donor's pro rata share, and the Bank may cancel all or any&#13;
Donors" pro rata shares, upon three (3) months' prior written notice, of any Contributions (paid and not yet&#13;
paid) that are not committed pursuant to any agreements entered into between the Bank and any consultants&#13;
and/or other third parties for the purposes of this Administration Arrangement, including any Grant&#13;
Agreements, prior to the receipt of such notice. In the event of a cancellation, the Bank will return to the&#13;
Donor its pro-rata share in the Holding Currency as specified in the Administration Arrangement; unless&#13;
otherwise agreed between the Bank and the Donor.&#13;
7.     Disclosure; Dispute Resolution&#13;
7.1    The Bank will disclose the Administration Arrangements and related information on this Trust Fund&#13;
in accordance with the Bank's Policy on Access to Information. By entering into Administration&#13;
Arrangements, the Donors consent to such disclosure of their respective Administration Arrangements and&#13;
such related information.&#13;
7.2    The Donors and the Bank will use their best efforts to amicably settle any dispute, controversy, or&#13;
claim arising out of or relating to the Administration Arrangements.&#13;
-8-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿8.     Grants to Recipients&#13;
8.1    The Bank will, as administrator of the Trust Fund on behalf of the Donors, enter into one or more&#13;
grant agreements (the "Grant Agreements") with recipients (the "Recipients") consistent with the purposes of&#13;
this Administration Arrangement and on the provisions set forth in the Grant Agreements. Grant&#13;
Agreements may be entered into up to the maximum amount of the Contributions that all Donors have agreed&#13;
to make available under the Administration Arrangements between the Bank and the Donors.&#13;
8.2    The Bank will be responsible for the supervision of the activities financed under any Grant&#13;
Agreements. Subject to the consent of any relevant Recipients, representatives of the Donors may be invited&#13;
by the Bank to participate in Bank supervision missions related to the Trust Fund.&#13;
8.3    The Bank will promptly inform the Donors of any significant modification to the terms of any Grant&#13;
Agreements and of any contractual remedies that are exercised by the Bank under any Grant Agreements.&#13;
To the extent practicable, the Bank will afford the Donors the opportunity to exchange views before effecting&#13;
any such modification or exercising any such remedy.&#13;
-9-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿ANNEX 3&#13;
Revitalizing Education Development in Sierra-Leone (REDiSL) MDTF&#13;
Governance&#13;
This Annex will be applicable to and form an integral part of all Administration Arrangements between the&#13;
Bank and the respective Donors.&#13;
The trust fund will rely on a two-tier governance structure to ensure objectivity, selectiveness, and relevance&#13;
in the activities to be funded. As such, a technical secretariat will be designated to manage the TF and its&#13;
activities per Bank guidelines and in compliance with donor agreements. In addition, a Steering Committee&#13;
will be established with the mandate of approving proposals, ensuring their consistency with the REDiSL&#13;
MDTF framework.&#13;
-10-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="18804900">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2013/12/18804900/official-documents--administration-arrangement-between-ibrd-ida-dfid-contribution-tf072152
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2013/12/18804900/official-documents--administration-arrangement-between-ibrd-ida-dfid-contribution-tf072152</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2013/12/18804900/official-documents--administration-arrangement-between-ibrd-ida-dfid-contribution-tf072152</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2014-01-15T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2014-01-15T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <docm_id>090224b0821e1cf5</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b0821e1cf5</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/AFR/2014/01/15/090224b0821e1cf5/1_0/Rendered/INDEX/Official0Docum0ribution0to0TF072152.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/AFR/2014/01/15/090224b0821e1cf5/1_0/Rendered/PDF/Official0Docum0ribution0to0TF072152.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2013-12-12T16:37:16Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2014-01-15T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docna>
            Official Documents- Administration
            Arrangement between IBRD, IDA and DFID for Contribution to TF072152
        </docna>
        <display_title>Official Documents-
            Administration Arrangement between IBRD, IDA and DFID for
            Contribution to TF072152</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/2013/12/18804900/official-documents--administration-arrangement-between-ibrd-ida-dfid-contribution-tf072152</listing_relative_url>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <docty>Trust Fund Administrative Agreement</docty>
        <count>Sierra Leone</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Farid,Mazhar</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>HQBOCS</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <trustfund>TF072152-Revitalizing Education
            Development in Sierra Leone Multi-Donor Trust Fu</trustfund>
        <lang>English</lang>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Arts and Culture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutritional supplements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Vitamins</ml:concept><ml:concept>Organisational Structures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Organizational Assessments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>Freedom of Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>Bank Supervision</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Leasing law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Remittances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Migration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enforcement of Judgements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Informal Dispute Resolution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Media</ml:concept><ml:concept>Treaties</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supplements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance Structures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Right to Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>External Audit</ml:concept><ml:concept>Bank Regulation and Supervision</ml:concept><ml:concept>Leasing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Movement of Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Dispute Resolution</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Africa</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Sierra Leone</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>