<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>﻿OFFICIAL          TFouib6&#13;
DOCUMENTS&#13;
Administration Arrangement between the United Kingdom of Great Britain and&#13;
Northern Ireland, acting through the Department for International Development&#13;
and the International Bank for Reconstruction and Development and the&#13;
International Development Association concerning the Umbrella Facility for&#13;
Impact Evaluation to Impact Development Multi-Donor Trust Fund&#13;
(TF No. 072161)&#13;
1.    The International Bank for Reconstruction and Development and the International&#13;
Development Association (collectively, the "Bank") acknowledge that the United Kingdom of&#13;
Great Britain and Northern Ireland, acting through the Department for International&#13;
Development (the "Donor", and together with the Bank, the "Parties" and each a "Party")&#13;
agrees to provide the sum of nineteen million and eight hundred- thousand Pounds Sterling&#13;
(E19,800,000) (the "Contribution") for the Umbrella. Facility for Impact Evaluation to Impact&#13;
Development Multi-Donor Trust Fund (TF No. 072161) (the "Trust Fund") in accordance with&#13;
the terms of this Administration Arrangement. Other donors are also expected to contribute to&#13;
the Trust Fund on the terms and conditions specified in the Annexes to this Administration&#13;
Arrangement.&#13;
2.    The Contribution will be used to finance the activities set forth in the "Umbrella Facility&#13;
for Impact Evaluation to Impact Development Multi-Donor Trust Fund Description" attached&#13;
hereto as Annex 1, and will be administered by the Bank on behalf of the Donor in accordance&#13;
with the terms of this Administration Arrangement, including the "Standard Provisions"&#13;
attached hereto as Annex 2 and "Other Terms" attached hereto as Annex 3.&#13;
3.    The Donor will deposit the Contribution in accordance with'the following schedule and&#13;
in the currency specified in Section 1 above ("Contribution Currency") into such bank account&#13;
designated by the Bank (each amount deposited hereinafter referred to as an "Installment")&#13;
upon submission of a payment request by the Bank:&#13;
(A)   Promptly following countersignature, four million seven hundred and forty&#13;
four thousand Pounds Sterling (f4,744,000).&#13;
(B)   By September 30, 2014, two million eight hundred and forty-one thousand&#13;
Pounds Sterling (f 2,841,000).&#13;
(C)   By March 30, 2015, two million eight hundred and forty-one thousand&#13;
Pounds Sterling (E 2,841,000).&#13;
(D)   By September 30, 2015, three million one hundred and ninety four&#13;
thousand Pounds Sterling (f 3,194,000).&#13;
(E)   By March 30, 2016, three million one hundred and ninety four thousand&#13;
Pounds Sterling (f 3,194,000).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-2-&#13;
(F)   By September 30, 2016, eight hundred and ninety seven thousand Pounds&#13;
Sterling (E 897,000).&#13;
(G)   By March 30, 2017, eight hundred and ninety seven thousand Pounds&#13;
Sterling (f 897,000).&#13;
(H)   By September 30, 2017, five hundred and ninety six thousand Pounds&#13;
Sterling (f 596,000).&#13;
(1)   By March 30, 2018, five hundred and ninety six thousand Pounds Sterling&#13;
(E 596,000).&#13;
4.    When making any deposit, the Donor will instruct its bank to include in its deposit&#13;
details information (remittance advice) field of its SWIFT deposit message, information&#13;
indicating: the amount deposited, that the deposit is made by the Donor for TF No. 072161&#13;
(Umbrella Facility for Impact Evaluation to Impact Development Multi-Donor Trust Fund),&#13;
and the date of the deposit (the "Deposit Instructions"). In addition, the Donor will provide a&#13;
copy of the Deposit Instructions to the Bank's Accounting Trust Funds Division by e-mail sent&#13;
to tfremitadvice@worldbank.org or by fax sent to +1 (202) 614-1315.&#13;
5.    Except with respect to the Deposit Instructions, any notice, request or other&#13;
communication to be given or made under this Administration Arrangement will be in writing&#13;
and delivered by mail, fax or e-mail to the respective Party's address specified below or at such&#13;
other address as such Party notifies in writing to the other Party from time to time:&#13;
For the Bank (the "Bank Contact"):&#13;
Arianna Legovini&#13;
Adviser&#13;
Development Impact Evaluation (DECIE)&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
1818 H Street NW, Washington, DC 20433 USA&#13;
Tel: (202) 458-8828&#13;
Fax: (202) 522-1158&#13;
E-mail, alegovini@worldbank.org&#13;
For the Donor (the "Donor Contact"):&#13;
Simon Calvert&#13;
Acting Head of the Evaluation Support Group&#13;
Evaluation Department, Department for International Development&#13;
Abercrombie House, East Kilbride, Glasgow, UK&#13;
Tel: +44 (0) 1355 84 3384&#13;
E-mail: S-Calvert@dfid.gov.uk&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-3-&#13;
6.    In the event any amounts are to be returned to the Donor.under this Administration&#13;
Arrangement, the Bank will transfer such amounts to the Donor, unless otherwise agreed with&#13;
the Bank.&#13;
7.    In providing funds under this Arrangement, the Donor does not intend to accept any&#13;
responsibility or liability towards any third parties for any claims, debts, demands, damage or&#13;
loss as a result of the implementation of the activities under the Trust Fund.&#13;
8.    All references made in the Annexes to "Agreement" and "shall" will have the same&#13;
meaning as the terms "Arrangement" and "will" herein.&#13;
9.    All annexes hereto constitute an integral part of this Administration Arrangement,&#13;
whose terms taken together shall constitute the entire agreement and urderstanding between the&#13;
Donor and the Bank. Unless otherwise specified in an annex hereto, this Administration&#13;
Arrangement may be amended only by written amendment between the Bank and the Donor;&#13;
provided, however, that any annexes to this Administration Arrangement may be amended only&#13;
by written amendment of all donors contributing to the Trust Fund.&#13;
10.   It is understood that this Administration Arrangement, including any annexes, is. not an&#13;
international treaty. It is an administrative arrangement between the Bank and the Donor.&#13;
11.   Each of the undersigned represents, by confirming its acceptance below, that it is&#13;
authorized to enter into this Administration Arrangement and act in accordance with its&#13;
provisions. The Bank and the Donor are each requested to sign and date this Administration&#13;
Arrangement, and upon possession by the Bank of this fully signed Administration&#13;
Arrangement, this Administration Arrangement will become effective as of the date of the last&#13;
signature.&#13;
INTERNATIONAL BANK FOR RECONSTRUCTION AND DEVELOPMENT&#13;
INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPMENT ASSOCIATION&#13;
By:                                               Date:&#13;
Kaushik Basu&#13;
Senior Vice President and Chief Economist&#13;
UNITED KINGDOM OF GREAT BRITAIN AND NORTHERN IRELAND, ACTING&#13;
THROUGH THE DEPARTMENT FOR INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPMENT&#13;
By:                          .                    Date:&#13;
Penelope Hawkins&#13;
Chief Professional Officer and Head of Evaluation'&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-4-&#13;
ANNEX 1&#13;
Umbrella Facility for Impact Evaluation to Impact Development Multi-Donor Trust Fund&#13;
Description&#13;
This Annex shall be applicable to and form an integral part of all administration agreements for&#13;
the Trust Fund (collectively, the "Administration Agreements" and each an "Administration&#13;
Agreement") between the Bank and any entities that provide any funds to the Trust Fund&#13;
(collectively, the "Donors").&#13;
1.    Objectives&#13;
The objectives of the Trust Fund are to:' (i) increase the use of impact evaluations by&#13;
governments and other stakeholders for knowledge generation and evidence-based policy&#13;
formulation; (ii) build capacity for governments and other stakeholders to develop and&#13;
implement impact evaluations; and (iii) share findings and lessons learned to improve&#13;
development results.&#13;
2.    Activities&#13;
The activities to be financed by the Trust Fund are:&#13;
(a)   Impact Evaluation Products&#13;
Develop new impact evaluation products and support the implementation of&#13;
existing impact evaluations that contribute to improve the design and implementation of&#13;
development policies through knowledge generation across themes such as agriculture&#13;
and rural development, financial sector development, private sector development, labor&#13;
markets,' infrastructure, governance, climate change, gender, and fragile and conflict&#13;
situations.&#13;
(b)   Capacity Building&#13;
Provide technical assistance to governments and other stakeholders to develop&#13;
and implement impact evaluations as tools for evidence generation and improvement of&#13;
policies and programs. Specific activities may include, but are not limited to, carrying&#13;
out training events, clinics and workshops; organizing and consolidating impact&#13;
evaluations across themes; and developing analytical frameworks, measurement&#13;
instruments and other tools.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-5-&#13;
(c)   Dissemination and Knowledge Sharing&#13;
Disseminate the knowledge and lessons learned from impact evaluations to&#13;
enable countries and other stakeholders to improve development results. Specific&#13;
activities may include, but are not limited to, organizing seminars and conferences,&#13;
preparing technical papers, policy briefs and reports, and web materials.&#13;
(d)   Program management and Administration&#13;
Carry out activities related to the administration and management of the Trust&#13;
Fund. Specific activities may include, but are not limited to, managing the work&#13;
program, and monitoring and reporting on progress and results.&#13;
3.    Elieile Expenditures&#13;
The Trust Fund funds may be used to finance: (a) Associated Overheads; (b) Consultant Fees&#13;
Individuals and Firms; (c) Contractual Services; (d) Equipment and Office Premises Lease&#13;
Cost; (e) Equipment purchased; (f) Extended Term Consultants; (g) Media, Workshop,&#13;
Conference and Meeting; (h) Staff Costs - with Indirect Costs; (i) Temporary Support Staff&#13;
Costs; and (j) Travel Expenses.&#13;
4.    Taxes&#13;
The foregoing activities and categories of expenditures may include the financing of taxes in&#13;
accordance with the Bank's applicable policies and procedures.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-6-&#13;
ANNEX 2&#13;
Standard Provisions&#13;
This Annex shall be applicable to and form an integral part of all Administration Agreements&#13;
between the Bank and the respective Donors.&#13;
1.    Administration of the Contributions&#13;
1.1   The Bank shall be responsible only for performing those functions specifically set forth&#13;
in this Administration Agreement and shall not be subject to any other duties or responsibilities&#13;
to the Donors, including, without limitation, any duties or obligations that might otherwise&#13;
apply to a fiduciary or trustee under general principles of trust or fiduciary law. Nothing in this&#13;
Administration Agreement shall be considered a waiver of any privileges or immunities of the&#13;
Bank under its Articles of Agreement or any applicable law, all of which are expressly&#13;
reserved.&#13;
1.2   Each Donor's Contribution (collectively, the "Contributions") shall be administered in&#13;
accordance with the Bank's applicable policies and procedures, as the same may be amended&#13;
from time to time, including its procurement, financial management, disbursement and&#13;
safeguard policies, its framework to prevent and combat fraud and corruption and its screening&#13;
procedures to prevent the use of Bank resources to finance terrorist activity, in line with the&#13;
Bank's obligations to give effect to the relevant decisions of the Security Council taken under&#13;
Chapter VII of the of Charter of the United Nations. The Donors acknowledge that this&#13;
provision does not create any obligations of the Bank under the anti-terrorist financing and&#13;
asset control laws, regulations, rules and executive orders of an individual member country that&#13;
may apply to a Donor.&#13;
2.    Managiement of the Contributions&#13;
2.1   The funds deposited in the Trust Fund shall be accounted for as a single trust fund and&#13;
shall be kept separate and apart from the funds of the Bank. The funds deposited in the Trust&#13;
Fund may be commingled with other trust fund assets maintained by the Bank. The Bank, in&#13;
its capacity as trustee, has legal title to the funds deposited in the Trust Fund.&#13;
2.2    The currency in which the funds in the Trust Fund shall be held is United States Dollars&#13;
(the "Holding Currency").&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-7-&#13;
2.3   Donors agree to deposit their Contributions in the Contribution Currency stated in their&#13;
respective Administration Agreements. In the case of deposits received in a Contribution&#13;
Currency other than the Holding Currency, promptly upon the receipt of such amounts and the&#13;
accompanying Deposit Instructions, the Bank shall convert such amounts into the Holding&#13;
Currency at the exchange rate obtained by the Bank on the date of the conversion. Where&#13;
deposits prove to be insufficient to complete activities as a result of exchange rate fluctuations,&#13;
neither the Bank nor the Donor shall bear any responsibility for, providing any additional&#13;
financing.&#13;
2.4   The funds deposited in the Trust Fund may be freely exchanged by the Bank into other&#13;
currencies as may facilitate their disbursement at the exchange rate obtained by the Bank on the&#13;
date of the conversion.&#13;
2.5    The Bank shall invest and reinvest the funds deposited in the Trust Fund pending their&#13;
disbursement in accordance with the Bank's applicable policies and procedures for the&#13;
investment of trust funds administered by the Bank. The Bank shall credit all income from&#13;
such investment to the Trust Fund to be used for the same purposes as the Contributions.&#13;
3.    Trust Fund Fees and Costs&#13;
3.1   The Bank shall deduct and retain for its own account, as a one-time deduction from the&#13;
funds in the Trust Fund, an amount equal to and not greater than thirty-five thousand United&#13;
States Dollars (US$35,000) as a set-up fee for the Trust Fund upon receipt of funds in the Trust&#13;
Fund.&#13;
3.2   The Bank shall additionally deduct and retain for its own account, as a deduction from&#13;
each Installment, an amount equal to five percent (5%) per Installment as an administrative fee&#13;
for the Trust Fund.&#13;
3.3   Each Donor acknowledges and agrees that the percentage deductions for fees in this&#13;
Trust Fund Fees and Costs section are estimated on the basis of anticipated Contributions. If&#13;
actual Contributions significantly differ from what was originally anticipated at the time of&#13;
signature of the first Administration Agreement, or if other circumstances affecting Trust Fund&#13;
fees or costs change, the Bank reserves the right to request a change to the terms of this Trust&#13;
Fund Fees and Costs section, which would be effectuated by amendments made to the&#13;
Administration Agreements of all Donors and which would thereafter be applicable to all new&#13;
Contributions that are provided either as amendments to supplement existing Administration&#13;
Agreements or from new Donors under new Administration Agreements.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-8-&#13;
4.    Accounting and Financial Reporting&#13;
4.1   The Bank shall maintain separate records and ledger accounts in respect of the funds&#13;
deposited in the Trust Fund and disbursements made therefrom.&#13;
4.2   The Bank shall furnish to the Donors current financial information relating to receipts,&#13;
disbursements and fund balance in the Holding Currency with respect to the Contributions via&#13;
the World Bank's Trust Funds Donor Center secure website. Within six (6) months after all&#13;
commitments and liabilities under the Trust Fund have been satisfied and the Trust Fund has&#13;
been closed, the final financial information relating to receipts, disbursements and fund balance&#13;
in the Holding Currency with respect to the Contributions shall be made available to the&#13;
Donors via the World Bank's Trust Finds Donor Center secure website.&#13;
4.3   The Bank shall provide to the Donors via the World Bank's Trust Fund Donor Center&#13;
secure website, within six (6) months following the end of each Bank fiscal year, an annual&#13;
single audit report, comprising (i) a management assertion together with an attestation from the&#13;
Bank's external auditors concerning the adequacy of internal control over cash-based financial&#13;
reporting for all cash-based trust funds as a whole; and (ii) a combined financial statement for&#13;
all cash-based trust funds together with the Bank's external auditor's opinion thereon. The cost&#13;
of the single audit shall be borne by the Bank.&#13;
4.4   If a Donor wishes to request, on an exceptional basis, a financial statement audit by the&#13;
Bank's external auditors of the Trust Fund, the Donor and the Bank shall first consult as to&#13;
whether such an external audit is necessary. The Bank and the Donor shall agree on the&#13;
appropriate scope and terms of reference of such audit. Following agreement on the scope and&#13;
terms of reference, the Bank shall arrange for such external audit. The costs of any such audit,&#13;
including the internal costs of the Bank with respect to such audit, shall be borne by the&#13;
requesting Donor.&#13;
5.    Progress Reporting&#13;
5.1   The Bank shall provide the Donors with annual reports on the progress of activities&#13;
financed by the Contributions. Within six (6) months of the End Disbursement Date (as&#13;
defined below), the Bank shall furnish to the Donors a final report on the activities financed by&#13;
the Trust Fund.&#13;
5.2   Any Donor may review or evaluate activities financed by the Trust Fund at any time up&#13;
to six (6) months following the End Disburiement Date. The Donor and the Bank shall agree&#13;
on the scope and conduct of such review or evaluation, and the Bank shall provide all relevant&#13;
information within the limits of the Bank's applicable policies and procedures. All associated&#13;
costs, including any costs incurred by the Bank, shall be borne by the Donor. It is understood&#13;
that any such review or evaluation will not constitute a financial, compliance or other audit of&#13;
the Trust Fund.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-9-&#13;
6.    Disbursement: Cancellation; Refund&#13;
6.1   It is expected that the funds deposited in the Trust Fund will be fully disbursed by the&#13;
Bank by April 30, 2019 (the "End Disbursement Date"). The Bank shall only disburse funds&#13;
deposited in the Trust Fund for the purposes of this Administration Agreement (other than&#13;
returns to Donors) after such date to the extent such date is changed in accordance with&#13;
amendments made to the Administration Agreements of all the Donors. Following the End&#13;
Disbursement Date, the Bank shall return any remainifg balance of the Trust Fund to each&#13;
Donor in the Holding Currency in the manner specified in its respective Administration&#13;
Agreement on a pro rata basis with regard to the total funds deposited in the Trust Fund by such&#13;
Donor relative to the total funds deposited in the Trust Fund by all Donors, all calculated as&#13;
Holding Currency amounts.&#13;
6.2   Any Donor may cancel all or part of such Donor's pro rata share, and the Bank may&#13;
cancel all or any Donors' pro rata shares, upon three (3) months' prior written notice, of any&#13;
Contributions (paid and not yet paid) that are not committed pursuant to any agreements&#13;
entered into between the Bank and any consultants and/or other third parties for the purposes of&#13;
this Administration Agreement, including any Grant Agreements, prior to the receipt of such&#13;
notice. In the event of a cancellation, the Bank shall return to the Donor its pro-rata share in&#13;
the Holding Currency as specified in the Administration Agreement; unless otherwise agreed&#13;
between the Bank and the Donor.&#13;
7.    Disclosure, Dispute Resolution&#13;
7.1   The Bank shall disclose the Administration Agreements and related information on this&#13;
Trust Fund in accordance with the Bank's Policy on Access to Information. By entering into&#13;
Administration Agreements, the Donors consent to such disclosure of their respective&#13;
Administration Agreements and such related information.&#13;
7.2   The Donors and the Bank shall use their best efforts to amicably settle any dispute,&#13;
controversy, or claim arising out of or relating to the Administration Agreements.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-10-&#13;
ANNEX3&#13;
Other Terms&#13;
The following governance terms shall apply to the Umbrella Facility for Impact Evaluation to&#13;
Impact Development Multi-Donor Trust Fund:&#13;
I.    The Donors agree that the Bank has responsibility for Trust Fund operations under the&#13;
terms of this Administration Agreement, including with respect to the allocation of funds and&#13;
the implementation of Bank-executed activities. For clarity, decisions on work programs and&#13;
allocation of funds will be made by the Bank.&#13;
2.    The Bank agrees to convene annual meetings to which all Donors are invited ("Annual&#13;
Consultations"). The purpose of the Annual Consultations is for the Bank and the Donors to&#13;
discuss:&#13;
(a)   Results (as defined below) presented by the Bank;&#13;
(b)   future program plans presented by the Bank;&#13;
(c)   broad strategic guidance reflective of (a) and (b).&#13;
3.    "Results" will be reported by the Bank and reviewed at the Annual Consultations on the&#13;
basis of the results framework for the Impact Evaluation to Impact Development Multi-Donor&#13;
Trust Fund, as may be modified over time.&#13;
4.    Progress reporting will occur on a unified, common basis for all Donors.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="18917174">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2014/01/18917174/official-documents--administration-agreement-dfid-contribution-tf072161
        </url>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2014/01/18917174/official-documents--administration-agreement-dfid-contribution-tf072161</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2014/01/18917174/official-documents--administration-agreement-dfid-contribution-tf072161</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2014-02-07T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2014-02-07T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <docm_id>090224b08226592f</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b08226592f</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/CTR/2014/02/07/090224b08226592f/1_0/Rendered/INDEX/Official0Docum0ribution0to0TF072161.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/CTR/2014/02/07/090224b08226592f/1_0/Rendered/PDF/Official0Docum0ribution0to0TF072161.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2014-01-21T11:36:52Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2014-02-07T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docna>
            Official Documents- Administration Agreement
            with DFID for Contribution to TF072161
        </docna>
        <display_title>Official Documents-
            Administration Agreement with DFID for Contribution to TF072161</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/2014/01/18917174/official-documents--administration-agreement-dfid-contribution-tf072161</listing_relative_url>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <docty>Trust Fund Administrative Agreement</docty>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Pardo De La Pena,Maria Lourdes</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>HQBOCS</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <trustfund>TF072161-Impact Evaluation to Impact
            Development (i2i) Umbrella Facility</trustfund>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Arts and Culture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutritional supplements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Vitamins</ml:concept><ml:concept>Impact Evaluations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Randomized Control Trials</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>Freedom of Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>Leasing law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Evidence-Based Policy, Impact Analysis and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Remittances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Migration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enforcement of Judgements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Informal Dispute Resolution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Growth and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Media</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Treaties</ml:concept><ml:concept>Impact Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supplements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Impact Assessment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Right to Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>External Audit</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Leasing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Evidence-Based Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Movement of Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Dispute Resolution</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>