<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>﻿OFFICiAL&#13;
DOCU MENTS&#13;
The World Bank                                       1818 H Street N.W.        (202) 473-1000&#13;
INTERNATIONAL BANK FOR RECONSTRUCTION AND DEVELOPMENT  Washington, D.C. 20433  Cable Address: INTBAFRAD&#13;
INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPMENT ASSOCIATION                U.S.A.                    Cable Address: INDEVAS&#13;
___________________2014&#13;
Mr. Joachim Prey&#13;
Director General Sectoral Department&#13;
Deutsche Gesellschaft fir Internationale Zusammenarbeit (GIZ) GmbH&#13;
Dag-Hammarskj6ld-Weg 1-5&#13;
D-65760 Eschborn&#13;
Trust Fund Administration Arrangement between the Deutsche Gesellschaft fir Internationale&#13;
Zusammenarbeit (GIZ) GmbH commissioned by the German Federal Ministry of Economic&#13;
Cooperation and Development (BMZ) and the International Bank for Reconstruction and&#13;
Development (IBRD) and the International Development Association (IDA) concerning the&#13;
Multi Donor Trust Fund for the Africa Climate Change Program&#13;
(Trust Fund No. TFO 71857) (GIZ Contract Number: 81152527)&#13;
Dear Mr. Prey:&#13;
1.      We are pleased to acknowledge on behalf of the International Bank for Reconstruction&#13;
and Development ("IBRD") and the International Development Association ("IDA")&#13;
(collectively, the "World Bank" or the "Bank") that the Deutsche Gesellschaft ftir Internationale&#13;
Zusammenarbeit GmbH (the "GIZ"), commissioned by the German Federal Ministry of&#13;
Economic Cooperation and Development ("BMZ"), shall make available as a grant to the World&#13;
Bank (already agreed by GIZ under their Contract Number 81152527), the sum of Euro four&#13;
million seven hundred twenty five thousand (EUR 4,725,000) (equivalent of six million one&#13;
hundred ninety one thousand six hundred forty United States Dollars (USD 6,191,640)) to finance&#13;
the activities related to the Multi-donor Trust Fund for the Africa Climate Change Program (the&#13;
"Trust Fund"), in accordance with the terms of this Administration Arrangement. No further&#13;
payments will be made by GIZ. Other donors are also expected to contribute to the Trust Fund on&#13;
the terms and conditions specified in the Annexes to this Administration Arrangement&#13;
("Arrangement"). All references in Annexes and related documents to "Administration&#13;
Agreement" will have the same meanings as the terms "Administration Arrangement" or&#13;
"Arrangement" used herein.&#13;
2.     The Contribution will be used to finance the activities and the categories of expenditure&#13;
set forth in the "Description of Activities and Expenditures under the Multi-donor Trust Fund for  ...&#13;
the Africa Climate Change Program" attached hereto as Annex 1, and will be administered by the&#13;
Bank on behalf of GIZ in accordance with the provisions of this Arrangement including the&#13;
"Standard Provisions Applicable to the Multi-donor Trust Fund for the Africa Climate Change&#13;
Program" (the "Standard Provisions") attached hereto as Annex 2.&#13;
*    *0&#13;
*    *0&#13;
3.     GIZ hereby authorizes the Bank to transfer an amount of six million one hundred ninety&#13;
one thousand six hundred forty dollars (US$ 6,191,640) from the trust fund for the Strategic  *&#13;
Climate Fund (MTO 069012) as the GIZ's Contribution to the Multi-donor Trust Fund for the&#13;
Africa Climate Change Program (TF071857), promptly following countersignature of this&#13;
Arrangement by the GILZ.                                                                 * **&#13;
****&#13;
**&#13;
*0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-2-&#13;
4.     It is expected that the Trust Fund will be completed by October 31, 2015, or by such later&#13;
date as the Bank and all Trust Fund donors may agree upon in writing.&#13;
5.     Following the final disbursement date specified in paragraph 7.1 of Annex 2 (Standard&#13;
Provisions) to this Agreement, the Bank will return any remaining balance of the Contributions to&#13;
GIZ Balance Account ("TF059086") ("GIZ Balance Account") on a pro rata basis based on the&#13;
donors' paid Contributions. In the event of a cancellation the Bank will promptly return to the&#13;
GIZ Balance Account the donor's pro rata share of uncommitted Contributions in accordance&#13;
with paragraph 7.2 of Annex 2 to this Agreement.&#13;
6.     Any notice, request or other communication to be given or made under this Arrangement&#13;
will be in writing and delivered by mail, facsimile-or e-mail to the respective party's address&#13;
specified below or at such other address as such party notifies in writing to the other party from&#13;
time to time:&#13;
For the Bank:&#13;
Mr. Nagaraja Rao Harshadeep&#13;
Senior Environmental Specialist&#13;
(AFTEN)&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
1818 H Street, NW&#13;
Washington, DC 20433&#13;
U.S.A.&#13;
Tel: +1 202-473-9173&#13;
Fax: +1 202-6141598&#13;
E-mail:harsh@worldbank.org&#13;
For GIZ:&#13;
Mr. Joachim Prey&#13;
Director General Sectoral Department&#13;
Deutsche Gesellschaft ffir Internationale Zusammenarbeit (GIZ) GmbH&#13;
Dag-Hammarskj6ld-Weg 1-5&#13;
D-65760 Eschborn&#13;
7.     All annexes hereto constitute an integral part of this Arrangement. This Arrangement&#13;
may be amended only in writing between the Bank and GIZ; provided, however, that such&#13;
annexes may be amended only with the arrangement of all donors contributing to the Trust Fund.&#13;
*   *&#13;
*0 *&#13;
0 0&#13;
* 0&#13;
0  *&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-3-&#13;
8.     Please confirm your arrangement with the foregoing, on behalf of GIZ, by signing,&#13;
dating, and returning to us the enclosed copy of this Arrangement. Upon receipt by the Bank of&#13;
the copy of this Arrangement countersigned by you, this Arrangement will become effective as of&#13;
the date of the countersignature.&#13;
Sincerely,&#13;
INTERNATIONAL BANK FOR RECONSTRUCTION AND DEVELOPMENT&#13;
INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPMENT ASSOCIATION&#13;
Jamal Saghir&#13;
Director, Sustainable Development&#13;
Africa Region&#13;
Confirmed:&#13;
GIZ&#13;
(commissioned by the German Federal Ministry of Economic Cooperation and&#13;
Development (BMZ))&#13;
By:&#13;
Na   :                                           Name:     oa&#13;
Title: / 4    4                                 Title:   1 k, K&#13;
Date:                     A,                     Date:         0 2  ? 4 1(&#13;
*s*&#13;
*    *&#13;
** *&#13;
* *&#13;
*   *&#13;
***&#13;
*0&#13;
@000&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿ANNEX 1&#13;
Description of Activities and Expenditures&#13;
Multi-donor Trust Fund for the Africa Climate Change Program&#13;
This Annex will be applicable to and form an integral part of all arrangements entered into&#13;
between the Bank and entities (collectively, the "Donors") that provide contributions (the&#13;
aggregate of all contributions from the Donors, the "Contributions") to be administered by the&#13;
Bank for the Trust Fund.&#13;
A. DESCRIPTION OF ACTIVITIES&#13;
Objectives:&#13;
1.     The objective of the Trust Fund is to: (i) strengthen development planning processes in&#13;
African countries to integrate climate change risks; and (ii) develop innovative financing&#13;
packages for implementation of priority measures.&#13;
Bank Executed Activities&#13;
2.     The Trust Fund will support the following activities:&#13;
(a)    Preparation of technical and synthesis papers such as national and/or regional&#13;
vulnerability profiles; financial and socio-economic assessments;&#13;
(b)    Inventorying and assessment of existing financing mechanisms and/or&#13;
developing and supervising the implementation of new climate financing mechanisms at national&#13;
level;&#13;
(c)    Assisting government partners to identify appropriate country specific adaptation&#13;
and mitigation measures;&#13;
(d)    Development of regional and country specific climate change simulation models;&#13;
(e)    Assessing  existing  institutional and  legal frameworks  and  making&#13;
recommendations to strengthen them in view of promoting climate resilient management; and&#13;
(f)    Mobilizing specialized technical assistance, capacity building and training&#13;
events, and support for stakeholder consultations and information workshops.&#13;
B. CATEGORIES OF EXPENDITURE&#13;
The Contributions may be used to finance Consultant Fees, Extended Term Consultants,  ,**&#13;
Travel Expenses, Media and Workshop Costs, Contractual Services, Associated Overheads,&#13;
Temporary Support Staff Costs, Field assignment benefits and Staff Costs (with no in-direct cost)  **  :&#13;
**&#13;
The foregoing categories of expenditures may include the financing of taxes.&#13;
*    *0&#13;
*.   *&#13;
*   *S&#13;
**   *&#13;
*   *S&#13;
*SS&#13;
**.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-2-&#13;
ANNEX 2&#13;
Standard Provisions&#13;
Applicable to the Multi-donor Trust Fund for the Africa Climate Chan2e Program&#13;
This Annex will be applicable to and form an integral part of all arrangements entered&#13;
into between the Bank and the Donors that provide Contributions to be administered by the Bank&#13;
for the Trust Fund.&#13;
1.    Administration of the Contributions&#13;
1.1.  The Bank will be responsible only for performing those functions specifically set forth in&#13;
this Arrangement and will not be subject to any other duties or responsibilities to the Donors,&#13;
including, without limitation, any duties or obligations that might otherwise apply to a fiduciary&#13;
or trustee under general principles of trust or fiduciary law. Nothing in this Arrangement will be&#13;
considered a waiver of any privileges or immunities of the IBRD and IDA under their Articles of&#13;
Agreement or any applicable law, all of which are expressly reserved.&#13;
1.2.  The Contribution will be administered in accordance with the Bank's applicable policies&#13;
and procedures, as the same may be amended from time to time, including its framework to&#13;
prevent and combat fraud and corruption and its screening procedures to prevent the use of Bank&#13;
resources to finance terrorist activity, in line with the Bank's obligations to give effect to the&#13;
relevant decisions of the Security Council, taken under Chapter VII of the of Charter of the&#13;
United Nations. The Donor acknowledges that this provision does not create any obligations of&#13;
the Bank under the anti-terrorist financing and asset control laws, regulations, rules and executive&#13;
orders of an individual member country that may apply to the Donor, nor will it be deemed a&#13;
waiver, express or implied, of any of the privileges and immunities of the Bank.&#13;
2.     Commingling, Exchange and Investment of the Contributions&#13;
2.1.   The Contributions will be accounted for as a single trust fund and will be kept separate&#13;
and apart from the funds of the Bank. The Contributions may be commingled with other trust&#13;
fund assets maintained by the Bank.&#13;
2.2.   The Contributions may be freely exchanged by the Bank into other currencies as may&#13;
facilitate their disbursement.&#13;
2.3.   The Bank will invest and reinvest the Contributions pending their disbursement in&#13;
accordance with the Bank's policies and procedures for the investment of trust funds&#13;
administered by the Bank. The Bank will credit all income from such investment to the Trust&#13;
Fund to be used for the same purposes as the Contributions.&#13;
3.     Administrative Cost Recovery ...*&#13;
3.1.   In order to assist in the defrayment of the costs associated with the establishment of the&#13;
Trust Fund, the Bank may, following deposit of the first Contribution from any Donor to the&#13;
Trust Fund, deduct and retain for its own account from that Contribution an amount equal to and&#13;
not greater than thirty-five thousand United States Dollars (US$35,000).&#13;
3.2.   In order to assist in the defrayment of the costs of administration and other expenses&#13;
incurred by the Bank under this Arrangement, the Bank may deduct and retain for its own&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-3-&#13;
account an amount equal to five percent (5%) of each Contribution. If the contributions increase&#13;
beyond what was originally expected at the time of counter-signature of the first administration&#13;
arrangement, and the administrative costs increase as a result, the Donors acknowledge that an&#13;
additional administrative fee may be applied to such new contributions.&#13;
4.     Procurement&#13;
4.2.   The employment and supervision of any consultants and the procurement of any goods&#13;
financed by the Contributions will be the responsibility of the Bank and will be carried out in&#13;
accordance with its applicable policies and procedures.&#13;
5.    Accounting and Financial Reporting&#13;
5.1.   The Bank will maintain separate records and ledger accounts in respect of the&#13;
Contributions deposited in the Trust Fund account and disbursements made therefrom.&#13;
5.2.   The Bank will furnish to the Donors current financial information relating to receipts,&#13;
disbursements and fund balance in United States Dollars of the Trust Fund with respect to the&#13;
Contributions via the World Bank's Trust Funds Donor Center secure website. Within six (6)&#13;
months after all commitments and liabilities under the Trust Fund have been satisfied and the&#13;
Trust Fund has been closed, the final financial information relating to receipts, disbursements and&#13;
fund balance in United States Dollars of the Trust Fund with respect to the Contributions will be&#13;
made available to the Donors via the World Bank's Trust Funds Donor Center secure website.&#13;
5.3.   The Bank will provide to the Donors, within six (6) months following the end of each&#13;
Bank fiscal year, an annual single audit report, comprising (1) a management assertion together&#13;
with an attestation from the Bank's external auditors concerning the adequacy of internal control&#13;
over cash-based financial reporting for all cash-based trust funds as a whole; and (2) a combined&#13;
financial statement for all cash-based trust funds together with the Bank's external auditor's&#13;
opinion thereon. The cost of the single audit will be borne by the Bank.&#13;
5.4.   If a Donor wishes to request, on an exceptional basis, a financial statement audit by the&#13;
Bank's external auditors of the Trust Fund, the Donor and the Bank will first consult as to&#13;
whether such an external audit is necessary. The Bank and the Donor will decide on the&#13;
appropriate scope and provisions of reference of such audit. Following arrangement on the scope&#13;
and terms of reference, the Bank will arrange for such external audit. The costs of any such audit,&#13;
including the internal costs of the Bank with respect to such audit, will be paid by the requesting&#13;
Donor.&#13;
6.     Progress Reporting&#13;
6.1.   The Bank will provide the Donors with an annual report on the progress of activities  .*.&#13;
financed by the Contributions. Within six (6) months of the final disbursement date specified in  **&#13;
paragraph 7.1, the Bank will furnish to the Donors a final report on the activities financed by the  **:&#13;
Trust Fund.&#13;
6.2    Any Donor may review or evaluate activities financed by the Trust Fund. The Donor and&#13;
the Bank will decide on the scope and conduct of such review or evaluation, and the Bank will  .&#13;
provide all relevant information within the limits of its policies and procedures. All associated  :&#13;
costs will be borne by the Donor. It is understood that any such review or evaluation will not&#13;
constitute a financial, compliance or other audit of the Trust Fund.                   .&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-4-&#13;
7.     Disbursement Cancellation Refund&#13;
7.1   It is expected that the Contributions will be fully disbursed by the Bank by&#13;
October 31, 2015. The Bank will only disburse Contributions for the purposes of this&#13;
Arrangement after such date with the written approval of the Donors.&#13;
7.2    Any Donor or the Bank may, upon three (3) months' prior written notice, cancel all or&#13;
part of the Donor's pro rata share, of any remaining balance of the Contributions that is not&#13;
committed pursuant to any arrangements entered into between the Bank and any consultants&#13;
and/or other third participants for the purposes of this Arrangement prior to the receipt of such&#13;
notice.&#13;
7.3.   Following the final disbursement date specified in paragraph 7.1, the Bank will return&#13;
any remaining balance of the Contributions to the Donors or to the relevant Donor Balance&#13;
Account on a pro rata basis based on the Donors' paid Contributions. In the event of a&#13;
cancellation the Bank will promptly return to the Germany's Balance Account the Donor's pro&#13;
rata share of uncommitted Contributions in accordance with paragraph 7.2.&#13;
8.     Disclosure&#13;
The Bank will disclose this Arrangement and related information on this Trust Fund in&#13;
accordance with the World Bank Policy on Access to Information. By entering into this&#13;
Arrangement, Donors consent to disclosure of this Arrangement and related information on this&#13;
Trust Fund.&#13;
*&#13;
** *&#13;
*  *0&#13;
* 0&#13;
**S&#13;
**   *&#13;
**   *&#13;
* 0&#13;
*  *0&#13;
*00&#13;
***&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="18984368">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2014/01/18984368/official-documents--administration-arrangement-giz-tf071857-ref-contract-81152527
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2014/01/18984368/official-documents--administration-arrangement-giz-tf071857-ref-contract-81152527</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2014/01/18984368/official-documents--administration-arrangement-giz-tf071857-ref-contract-81152527</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2014-02-14T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2014-02-14T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <docm_id>090224b08228eb42</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b08228eb42</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/AFR/2014/02/14/090224b08228eb42/1_0/Rendered/INDEX/Official0Docum0f00Contract081152527.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/AFR/2014/02/14/090224b08228eb42/1_0/Rendered/PDF/Official0Docum0f00Contract081152527.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2014-02-14T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2014-01-28T16:22:33Z</docdt>
        <docna>
            Official Documents- Administration
            Arrangement with the GIZ for TF071857 Ref. Contract 81152527
        </docna>
        <display_title>Official Documents-
            Administration Arrangement with the GIZ for TF071857 Ref.
            Contract 81152527</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/2014/01/18984368/official-documents--administration-arrangement-giz-tf071857-ref-contract-81152527</listing_relative_url>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <docty>Trust Fund Administrative Agreement</docty>
        <count>Africa</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Nadeem,Mohammad</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>HQBOCS</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <owner>Env., NRM, WRM &amp; DRM Prac 1 (AFTN1)</owner>
        <trustfund>TF071857-Multi-donor Trust Fund for the
            Africa Climate Change Program</trustfund>
        <lang>English</lang>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sustainable Climate Business</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sustainable Energy Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Arts and Culture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Climate Change</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Climate Change Adaptation Financing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Climate Change Mitigation Financing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Climate Investment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>Freedom of Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Media</ml:concept><ml:concept>Privileges and Immunities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Climate Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Adaptation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Right to Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>External Audit</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>