<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>WATER AND SANITATION PROGRAM: FIELD NOTE                                    October 2013&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                85200&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Results, Impacts, and Learning&#13;
from Improving Sanitation at Scale&#13;
in East Java, Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   The Water and Sanitation Program is a multi-donor&#13;
                   partnership administered by the World Bank to&#13;
                   support poor people in obtaining affordable, safe, and&#13;
                   sustainable access to water and sanitation services.&#13;
&amp;#12;Acknowledgments&#13;
This Field Note was prepared by Rebekah Pinto, with valuable inputs provided by&#13;
Deviariandy Setiawan, Ari Kamasan and Claire Chase. The author also gratefully&#13;
acknowledges review comments provided by Almud Weitz, WSP Principal&#13;
Regional Team Leader, and Eduardo Perez, WSP Senior Sanitation Specialist.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Water and Sanitation Program (WSP) reports are published to communicate the&#13;
results of WSPâ&#128;&#153;s work to the development community. Some sources cited may be&#13;
informal documents that are not readily available.&#13;
&#13;
The ï¬&#129;ndings, interpretations, and conclusions expressed herein are entirely those&#13;
of the author and should not be attributed to the World Bank or its afï¬&#129;liated&#13;
organizations, or to members of the Board of Executive Directors of the World Bank&#13;
or the governments they represent. The World Bank does not guarantee the accuracy&#13;
of the data included in this work. The boundaries, colors, denominations, and other&#13;
information shown on any map in this work do not imply any judgment on the part of&#13;
the World Bank Group concerning the legal status of any territory or the endorsement&#13;
or acceptance of such boundaries.&#13;
&#13;
The material in this publication is copyrighted. Requests for permission to&#13;
reproduce portions of it should be sent to wsp@worldbank.org. WSP encourages&#13;
the dissemination of its work and will normally grant permission promptly. For more&#13;
information, please visit www.wsp.org.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Â© 2013 International Bank for Reconstruction and Development/The World Bank&#13;
&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
1818 H Street NW&#13;
Washington DC 20433&#13;
Telephone: 202-473-1000&#13;
Internet: www.worldbank.org&#13;
&amp;#12;              Contents&#13;
              Overview .................................................................................................................................................. 1&#13;
&#13;
              Background .............................................................................................................................................. 2&#13;
&#13;
              Departing from Business As Usual: â&#128;&#156;Lightâ&#128;&#156; Technical Assistance for Sanitation Service at Scale ............... 4&#13;
&#13;
              Objectives and Targets .............................................................................................................................. 4&#13;
&#13;
              Results and Learning ................................................................................................................................ 7&#13;
&#13;
              Measuring Results and Impact ................................................................................................................. 14&#13;
&#13;
              Program Effects on Child Health Outcomes .............................................................................................. 14&#13;
&#13;
              Lessons Learned from Scaling Up Rural Sanitation in Indonesia .............................................................. 15&#13;
&#13;
              References .............................................................................................................................................. 17&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
www.wsp.org&#13;
&amp;#12;D   www.wsp.org&#13;
&amp;#12;Results, Impacts, and Learning&#13;
from Improving Sanitation at Scale&#13;
in East Java, Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                  However, in 2005 the Government of Indonesia embarked&#13;
                                                                                  on a new approach to improving rural sanitation known as&#13;
                                                                                  Community-Led Total Sanitation (or CLTS) piloted origi-&#13;
                                                                                  nally in Bangladesh. Instead of focusing on toilet construc-&#13;
                                                                                  tion, the CLTS approach recognized that sustainable de-&#13;
                                                                                  mand for improved sanitation came only when households&#13;
                                                                                  and communities were part of the process of identifying&#13;
                                                                                  and addressing the problem. In order to demonstrate the&#13;
                                                                                  success of this new approach, a small pilot began in 2005&#13;
                                                                                  as part of two larger scale water and sanitation programs&#13;
                                                                                  funded by the World Bank and Asian Development Bank.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                  The success of this small pilot led to its initial expansion to&#13;
                                                                                  additional villages and eventually in 2007 to the creation of&#13;
                                                                                  the Scaling Up Rural Sanitation Program (initially known&#13;
OVERVIEW                                                                          as the Total Sanitation and Sanitation Marketing Project or&#13;
Inadequate access to sanitation remains a persistent issue, af-                   TSSM). TSSM, which was a demonstration of a community-&#13;
fecting the lives of millions of children and families especially                 led approach at scale2, started in the East Java province of In-&#13;
in poor and rural communities throughout the world. In                            donesia as a result of collaboration between the Government&#13;
Indonesia, efforts to expand coverage have barely affected the                    of Indonesia, Bill &amp; Melinda Gates Foundation and the Wa-&#13;
lives of poorest populations where rampant diarrheal disease                      ter and Sanitation Program (WSP) of the World Bank.&#13;
continues to affect the health and well-being of the next gen-&#13;
eration of children. These efforts were further complicated                       The TSSM approach combines three innovative approach-&#13;
by policies that provided sanitation hardware subsidies lim-                      es: (i) CLTS to generate demand; (ii) sanitation marketing&#13;
ited to populations identified under specific programs, rather                    to reinforce demand generation and increase supply of sani-&#13;
than strategies aimed at promoting large-scale sustained be-                      tation goods and services; and (iii) strategies to strengthen&#13;
havior change such as awareness building and hygiene educa-                       the countryâ&#128;&#153;s enabling environment so that improvements&#13;
tion. As a result, Indonesia has the second highest number                        could grow and ultimately be sustained. By December&#13;
of open defecators worldwide at 59 million, according to the                      2011, 2,200 communities in 29 districts have been official-&#13;
2013 update published by the WHO/UNICEF Joint Moni-                               ly declared and verified as Open Defecation Free (ODF),&#13;
toring Programme (JMP)1, and lags substantially behind its                        and over 1.4 million people have gained access to improved&#13;
peers in the region in terms of access to sanitation.                             sanitation as a result of exposure to the program.3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
1&#13;
  Progress on Drinking Water and Sanitation: 2013 Update. Joint Monitoring Programme, WHO/UNICEF.&#13;
2&#13;
  East Java has a total population of 37 million (70 percent rural).&#13;
3&#13;
  WSP Project Monitoring Data. 2011. These figures have continued to grow beyond the December 2011 closing date of TSSM but December 2011 is used for&#13;
consistency throughout the document.&#13;
&#13;
www.wsp.org&#13;
                                                                                                                                                        1&#13;
&amp;#12;    FIELD NOTE: Results, Impacts, and Learning from Improving Sanitation at Scale in East Java, Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                         TSSM signified a strategic policy shift for sanitation on the&#13;
                                                                                         part of the Government of Indonesia. What began as an&#13;
                                                                                         at-scale, provincial program has become the backbone of&#13;
                                                                                         Indonesiaâ&#128;&#153;s national rural sanitation program today. A new&#13;
                                                                                         National Strategy for Community-Based Total Sanitation&#13;
                                                                                         (Sanitasi Total Berbasis Masyarakat, or STBM) was adopted&#13;
                                                                                         in 2008 and builds further upon TSSMâ&#128;&#153;s three-pronged ap-&#13;
                                                                                         proach for improving the health of poor households and&#13;
                                                                                         communities. Under the umbrella of STBM, and building&#13;
                                                                                         on lessons learned in East Java, 32 out of 33 provinces in&#13;
                                                                                         Indonesia5 are now beginning to assume full responsibility&#13;
                                                                                         for financing and implementation of the new strategy, pro-&#13;
                                                                                         gressively internalizing the new approaches and applying&#13;
                                                                                         these to their entire province, with technical assistance pro-&#13;
                                                                                         vided by WSP to the STBM secretariat and 5 provinces as&#13;
                                                                                         well as through the World Bank-funded Third Water Sup-&#13;
                                                                                         ply and Sanitation for Low Income Communities (Pamsi-&#13;
                                                                                         mas) project.6&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                         This Field Note presents the achievements, learning and&#13;
                                                                                         reflections that resulted from implementing a large-scale&#13;
                                                                                         sanitation program in East Java, Indonesia and provides&#13;
                                                                                         recommendations for future initiatives aimed at increasing&#13;
                                                                                         access to improved sanitation globally.&#13;
&#13;
    As part of efforts to gather evidence on the health and wel-                         BACKGROUND&#13;
    fare impacts of this approach, TSSM utilized a rigorous im-                          Over the past decade the Indonesian economy has experi-&#13;
    pact evaluation to measure the effects of the intervention                           enced positive economic growth, witnessed impressive reduc-&#13;
    on individual and collective sanitation behaviors, as well as                        tions in poverty, and has made continued progress toward&#13;
    the programâ&#128;&#153;s impact on the health and welfare of children                           many of its Millennium Development Goal targets for 2015.&#13;
    under the age of five. Of 160 randomly selected commu-                               However, these improvements partially mask the persistent&#13;
    nities including 2,100 households, treatment communi-                                problem of inadequate access to sanitation still facing mil-&#13;
    ties witnessed a 29 percent increase in toilet construction                          lions of Indonesians, especially those that are from poor, rural&#13;
    (albeit not among the poorest quintile of the households                             households. Indonesia is currently not on track to meet the&#13;
    surveyed) and a 30 percent decrease in diarrhea prevalence                           2015 sanitation Millennium Development Goal: of Indone-&#13;
    reported by care-givers of children under the age of five.4                          siaâ&#128;&#153;s 240 million residents, just over half (56 percent) belong&#13;
    This randomized controlled trial evaluation also found that                          to households with access to any kind of sanitation. In rural&#13;
    the program had impacts on other child health indicators                             areas the problem is magnifiedâ&#128;&#148;just 39 percent of individu-&#13;
    ranging from reducing parasitic diseases to improvements                             als have access to sanitation and another 40 percent of rural&#13;
    in height and weight among households with no sanitation                             residents still regularly engage in the practice of open defeca-&#13;
    at baseline.                                                                         tion, using fields, beaches and most often rivers.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    4&#13;
       Cameron, Shah and Olivia. Impact Evaluation of a Large-Scale Rural Sanitation Project in Indonesia. World Bank Impact Evaluation Series No. 83. February 2013.&#13;
    5&#13;
       The exception is DKI Jakarta which is classified as 100 percent urban.&#13;
    6&#13;
       Additional funding for Pamsimas to be implemented over the period 2013-2016 has been approved in May 2013 and will cover 32 provinces. As agreed with the&#13;
    Government, the STBM implementation approach has been revised towards a district-wide approach that allows STBM implementation not only in selected Pamsimas&#13;
    sites but across all villages in a district.&#13;
&#13;
2                                                                                                                                                       www.wsp.org&#13;
&amp;#12;FIELD NOTE: Results, Impacts, and Learning from Improving Sanitation at Scale in East Java, Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                     Motivated by mounting challenges in the rural sanitation&#13;
                                                                                     sector, the Government of Indonesia launched STBM in&#13;
                                                                                     2008 in an effort to improve sector effectiveness and reach&#13;
                                                                                     the sanitation MDG. The new STBM strategy focuses on&#13;
                                                                                     sustaining behavior change for sanitation and hygiene, cre-&#13;
                                                                                     ating demand at scale through community participation&#13;
                                                                                     and empowerment and improving market supply as a re-&#13;
                                                                                     sponse to generated demand. To complement these efforts&#13;
                                                                                     the Ministry of Health and the East Java Provincial Gov-&#13;
                                                                                     ernment, with support from WSP, implemented the TSSM&#13;
                                                                                     project from 2007-20109 as an at-scale demonstration of&#13;
                                                                                     implementing STBM at the local level.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                     When implementation started in East Java, a host of chal-&#13;
                                                                                     lenges had to be overcome to ensure effectiveness:&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                     â&#128;¢ Clarity on Roles &amp; Responsibilities: Indonesia is&#13;
Inadequate sanitation disproportionately affects poor com-                             highly decentralized and although policies are designed&#13;
munities, as well as contributes to diarrheal disease, one of                          at the national level, local district governments are fully&#13;
the leading causes of death in children under five. Wide-                              responsible for planning, funding and implementing&#13;
spread open defecation leads to feces being tracked through                            their development agendas, including those related to&#13;
villages and into peopleâ&#128;&#153;s houses, where it is ingested. Re-                           rural sanitation. Decentralization has also meant that a&#13;
peated bouts of diarrhea as a result of poor sanitation and                            widening pool of stakeholders and administrative bod-&#13;
hygiene practices have been linked to long-term growth de-                             ies are charged with improvements to rural sanitation.&#13;
ficiencies (stunting) in children under two, which in turn                             At the beginning of TSSM, confusion and fragmenta-&#13;
leads to impaired long-term cognitive development and                                  tion over responsibilities and procedures often delayed&#13;
schooling attainment, as well as adult morbidity and lower                             implementation of a sustained sanitation program.&#13;
incomes. Currently 36 percent of Indonesian children un-                             â&#128;¢ Lack of Demand &amp; Awareness: Among participating&#13;
der 5 are moderately or severely stunted, making it among                              districts an important gap existed between knowledge&#13;
the 14 countries along with India and Nigeria that share                               about transmission of diseases from open defecation when&#13;
the greatest percentage of the global burden of stunted chil-                          feces did not visibly contaminate the immediate environ-&#13;
dren.                                                                                  ment. Despite relatively high levels of knowledge among&#13;
                                                                                       the population about sanitation, few seemed to under-&#13;
Poor sanitation also places a high economic burden on                                  stand the health hazards of openly defecating in rivers or&#13;
countries, particularly in Indonesia. According to a WSP                               far from where people lived. Information and education&#13;
study, the economic costs of poor sanitation are estimated                             campaigns focusing primarily on top-down messages&#13;
to be as high as Rp56 trillion (US$6.3 billion), equivalent                            around health hazards did not seem to reach the broad&#13;
to 2.3 percent of the countryâ&#128;&#153;s GDP in 2006.7 This same                                population in order to instigate lasting behavior change.&#13;
study estimated that poor sanitation and hygiene prac-                               â&#128;¢ Hardware vs. Behavior Change Approach: Prior to&#13;
tices also contributed to 120 million disease incidents and                            TSSM, the government maintained a subsidy-based&#13;
50,000 premature deaths annually.8                                                     approach to providing sanitation hardware to house-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
7&#13;
   Napitupulu and Hutton, 2008.&#13;
8&#13;
   ibid, 2008.&#13;
9&#13;
   The project was subsequently extended to December 2011.&#13;
10&#13;
   Mukherjee et. al. 2012.&#13;
www.wsp.org&#13;
                                                                                                                                                     3&#13;
&amp;#12;    FIELD NOTE: Results, Impacts, and Learning from Improving Sanitation at Scale in East Java, Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      holds under various programs. This did not foster last-                            and fiscal allocations at the central and local levels support&#13;
      ing change â&#128;&#147; Indonesiaâ&#128;&#153;s rural sanitation coverage rates                           the scaling up and sustainability of interventions.&#13;
      barely changed over the past decades - because it ig-&#13;
      nored why communities continued to defecate in the                                 The success of the demand generation approach lies in&#13;
      open. It also under-utilized the power of collective ac-                           combining distinct elements aimed at getting communities&#13;
      tion and responsibility for improving sanitation facilities                        to both stop open defecation, as well as build and utilize&#13;
      for all community members. Expectations that subsidies                             improved latrines, community-led total sanitation (CLTS)&#13;
      would eventually become available for all hampered col-                            and behavior change communications (BCC). CLTS uses&#13;
      lective action and created social divisions.10 For the new                         community-based sanitation â&#128;&#152;triggeringâ&#128;&#153; events, awareness&#13;
      approach to be successful, districts had to be convinced                           building and careful verification to successfully catalyze&#13;
      one-by-one that having two competing approaches                                    community commitment and demand for becoming 100&#13;
      would not work and that a broad-based policy shift in                              percent Open-Defecation Free (ODF).&#13;
      line with STBM was required.&#13;
    â&#128;¢ Limited Availability of Low-Cost Latrine Options:                                  This is complemented by formative research-based BCC&#13;
      The challenge of increasing demand for improved sanita-                            strategies and a market research-based supply improve-&#13;
      tion options was compounded by the fact that local mar-                            ment program. The objective of the supply improvement&#13;
      kets did not offer latrines catering to those with lower                           program is to build on CLTS efforts by increasing individ-&#13;
      purchasing power. Many households used personal sav-                               ual consumer demand for and market supply of improved&#13;
      ings to fund what was perceived as highly-priced latrine                           sanitation solutions that are both affordable and preferred&#13;
      construction. Local masons had limited experience on                               by consumers of all classes and income levels. Over time,&#13;
      how to package together a variety of low-cost latrine so-                          growth of improved supply is sustained through continued,&#13;
      lutions for households that would enable consumers to                              quality entrepreneur training, monitoring and regulation of&#13;
      invest in affordable and upgradable sanitation solutions.                          the market. This is complemented with targeted advocacy&#13;
      Such supply needed to be built up quickly if the newly                             to local governments and capacity building for local gov-&#13;
      created demand was to lead to substantial latrine uptake.                          ernment agencies.&#13;
&#13;
    DEPARTING FROM BUSINESS AS USUAL:                                                    OBJECTIVES &amp; TARGETS&#13;
    â&#128;&#156;LIGHTâ&#128;&#157; TECHNICAL ASSISTANCE FOR                                                     The projectâ&#128;&#153;s overall goal in East Java was to design and&#13;
    SANITATION SERVICES AT SCALE                                                         implement an innovative, sustainable program to reduce&#13;
    The TSSM approach departs from typical modes of deliver-                             open defecation and increase access to hygienic sanitation&#13;
    ing sanitation services by recognizing that sanitation is a                          in all 29 rural districts throughout East Java. The hypoth-&#13;
    multi-sectoral issue that has long-term impacts on health,                           esis behind the approach (or â&#128;&#152;theory of actionâ&#128;&#153;) was that&#13;
    education and the economy and next, that improvements                                â&#128;&#152;lightâ&#128;&#153;, time-bound11 technical assistance could be extended&#13;
    in sanitation infrastructure alone will not solve the myriad                         across the whole province provided that local governments&#13;
    of sanitation problems. Demand for new and improved la-                              would be in the driver seat and implement â&#128;&#147; and largely&#13;
    trines, as well as improvements in hygiene behaviors, come                           fund â&#128;&#147; interventions through existing government systems,&#13;
    only when there is a change in community-level percep-                               while households would be able to fund their own toilet&#13;
    tions about the impacts of the lack of sanitation.                                   investments provided the market catered to their demand&#13;
                                                                                         for affordable and desirable products.&#13;
    TSSM utilizes a theory of change developed globally by&#13;
    WSP that connects strengthened sanitation supply with de-                            The following section summarizes the results against these&#13;
    mand creation and behavior change, rooted in an enabling                             objectives, as well as lessons learned over the course of the&#13;
    environment whereby policy, institutional arrangements                               TSSM project in East Java.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    11&#13;
         Each district received technical assistance for a period of only 8-9 months.&#13;
&#13;
4                                                                                                                                           www.wsp.org&#13;
&amp;#12;FIELD NOTE: Results, Impacts, and Learning from Improving Sanitation at Scale in East Java, Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 TABLE 1. RESULTS SUMMARY AND KEY ACHIEVEMENT&#13;
                             Objectives and Targets                                       2007 Baseline             2009 Target             2011 Achievement&#13;
&#13;
 Objective 1: Increase Collective Demand and Behavior Change Among Communities and Households through CLTS and BCC Campaign&#13;
&#13;
 Number of communities â&#128;&#156;triggeredâ&#128;&#157;                                                                0                     2,700                   6,250 (231%)&#13;
&#13;
 Number of communities declared and veriï¬&#129;ed open defecation free                                  0                      870                    2,200 (252%)&#13;
 Population gaining access to improved sanitation fully ï¬&#129;nanced by&#13;
 households                                                                                       0                  1.4 million                  1.4 million&#13;
&#13;
 Objective 2: Strengthening the Supply of Affordable Latrines and Services for Households12&#13;
 Business model of one-stop-shop sanitation developed and promoted to                                                                    60 entrepreneurs from 28&#13;
                                                                                                 n/a                     n/a&#13;
 local entrepreneurs                                                                                                                         districts trained&#13;
 Objective 3: Strengthening the Enabling Environment&#13;
&#13;
 Policy, Strategy and Direction&#13;
 Strategic Planning&#13;
 STBM Approval                                                                                   No                     Yes                           Yes&#13;
 District Strategies Implemented                                                                  0                   14 (48%)                    28 (96%)13&#13;
 Political Support&#13;
 National Sanitation Budget Allocation                                                    US$1.3 million          US$2.2 million              US$800 million14&#13;
 Policy Alignment: Total Sanitation&#13;
 UNICEF Indonesia                                                                                No                      Yes                         Yes&#13;
 Plan Indonesia                                                                                  No                      Yes                         Yes&#13;
 Ministry of Public Works                                                                        No                      Yes                        Partial&#13;
 Program Methodology&#13;
 Total Sanitation at Scale&#13;
 Number and percentage of districts using total sanitation approach                      54 districts (15%)     150 districts (43%)          252 districts (72%)&#13;
 UNICEF Indonesia                                                                                No                    Yes                          Yes&#13;
 Plan Indonesia                                                                                  No                    Yes                          Yes&#13;
 Sanitation Marketing at Scale&#13;
 Number and percentage of districts using sanitation marketing approach                           0                       -                     28 districts15&#13;
 UNICEF Indonesia                                                                                No                      Yes                         Yes&#13;
 Plan Indonesia                                                                                  No                      Yes                         Yes&#13;
 Implementation Capacity&#13;
 Knowledge Management&#13;
 Exposure visits (people per year)                                                                0                      200                         16016&#13;
 Best practice seminars                                                                           0                       4                            4&#13;
 WSP ï¬&#129;eld notes                                                                                   0                       1                           117&#13;
 Active Sanitarians&#13;
 East Java: ï¬&#129;lled positions                                                               620/826 (75%)           750/833 (90%)                632/833 (76%)&#13;
 East Java: active entrepreneurs                                                                0                      29                           618&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
12&#13;
   Project activities related to supply strengthening were introduced following a consumer market survey showing limited knowledge and accessibility presented&#13;
challenges to adoption of improved household sanitation options. For this reason 2009 targets were not originally included in the programâ&#128;&#153;s design.&#13;
13&#13;
   Thirteen districts have completed their strategic sanitation plans for 4-5 years with official endorsement by the Head of District or the head of the local health&#13;
department, and 15 districts have incorporated the rural sanitation strategic plans into existing multi-year district strategic plans for water and sanitation (Renstra&#13;
AMPL) or Health (Renstra Kesehatan).&#13;
14&#13;
   The majority of this amount has been earmarked for urban sanitation infrastructure.&#13;
15&#13;
   One district in East Java has not adopted the main elements of the TSSM methodology.&#13;
16&#13;
   Fourteen internal district-to-district and nine international/external (from Cambodia, Laos, East Timor, the Philippines, Vietnam, India, Pakistan, WSLIC-2, and the&#13;
Asian Development Bank-supported Community Water Services and Health Project) exposure visits over the last two years.&#13;
17&#13;
   WSP 2009.&#13;
18&#13;
   These data were obtained from an assessment that took place in July 2010. At the completion of the project in December 2011, the number of active sanitation&#13;
entrepreneurs in East Java reached 30.&#13;
www.wsp.org&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                          5&#13;
&amp;#12;    FIELD NOTE: Results, Impacts, and Learning from Improving Sanitation at Scale in East Java, Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     TABLE 1. RESULTS SUMMARY AND KEY ACHIEVEMENT (CONTâ&#128;&#153;D)&#13;
&#13;
                                 Objectives and Targets                                      2007 Baseline            2009 Target              2011 Achievement&#13;
&#13;
     Availability of Goods and Services&#13;
     Technology Options&#13;
     Promoted by local producers                                                                     5                      10                           6&#13;
     Found in poor households                                                                        2                       4                           3&#13;
     Rural Service Providers&#13;
     Number of trained masons                                                                        0                    +25%                         +3%&#13;
     Number of sanitation businesses                                                                 0                    +44%                          6&#13;
     User Satisfaction&#13;
     Owners of improved latrines                                                                Unknown                    75%                        85%19&#13;
     Owners of unimproved latrines                                                              Unknown                      -                         57%&#13;
     Users of shared latrines                                                                   Unknown                      -                         34%&#13;
     Financing&#13;
     Sanitation Finance&#13;
     Annual sanitation budget                                                                 US$169,000              US$750,000                  US$372,00020&#13;
     (East Java)&#13;
     Sanitation Incentives&#13;
     National sanitation award                                                                      No                    Yes                         No&#13;
     East Java sanitation award                                                                     No                    Yes                         Yes&#13;
     East Java ODF incentive                                                                         0                 US$67,000                   US$22,000&#13;
     Cost-Effective Implementation&#13;
     Effectiveness (East Java)&#13;
     Nr. triggered communities                                                                       0                    2,700                   6,250 (231%)&#13;
     Veriï¬&#129;ed ODF communities                                                                         0                     870                    2,200 (252%)&#13;
     ODF success rate                                                                                -                      -                         35%&#13;
     Cost-Effectiveness&#13;
     Program cost per ODF community                                                             US$6,400                US$4,000                    US$1,060&#13;
     Program cost per latrine in use                                                             US$9                    US$5                       US$4.26&#13;
     Leverage ratio (household: program)                                                          2:1                     4:1                         5.3:1&#13;
     Monitoring &amp; Evaluation&#13;
     Monitoring systems&#13;
     National outcome monitoring                                                                   No                      Yes                       Yes21&#13;
     Finance for national monitoring                                                              US$0                      -                     US$110,00022&#13;
     Harmonization with JMP indicators                                                             No                      Yes                        No&#13;
     Sanitation evaluations&#13;
     WSP-ï¬&#129;nanced (East Java)                                                                         0                       2                           2&#13;
     Government-ï¬&#129;nanced (national)                                                                   0                       2                           0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    19&#13;
       User satisfaction data from Nielsen (2008) that demonstrated satisfaction is far higher among owners of improved latrines, and thus satisfaction should increase as&#13;
    improved sanitation coverage rises.&#13;
    20&#13;
       Total budget allocations by the provincial government and 29 district governments peaked at US$603,000 in 2009, then declined to US$372,000 in the 2010 election&#13;
    year.&#13;
    21&#13;
       The national sms and web-based monitoring ssystem was launched in October 2011, during national coordination meeting for STBM (Rakornas).&#13;
    22&#13;
       Puskesmas budget for all sanitation software activities (100 puskesmas in 2010; 8,000 puskesmas in 2011 is equal to US$8.9 million in budget allocations).&#13;
&#13;
6                                                                                                                                                            www.wsp.org&#13;
&amp;#12;FIELD NOTE: Results, Impacts, and Learning from Improving Sanitation at Scale in East Java, Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                     expressing their desire to participate, with priority given to&#13;
                                                                                     those willing to co-finance implementation; (ii) no subsi-&#13;
                                                                                     dies would be provided for household toilet construction in&#13;
                                                                                     accordance with STBM; (iii) no monetary incentives would&#13;
                                                                                     be given to communities verified as ODF.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                     At the sub-village level, triggering events typically begin&#13;
                                                                                     with a â&#128;&#152;walk of shameâ&#128;&#153; where villages are asked to provide a&#13;
                                                                                     tour of where defecation occurs. Following this, facilitators&#13;
                                                                                     help individuals analyze how fecal contamination spreads&#13;
                                                                                     from exposed excreta to their living environments, food and&#13;
                                                                                     drinking water supply. Finally, a social mapping exercise&#13;
                                                                                     leads community members through the process of identify-&#13;
                                                                                     ing where they live, where they defecate and the routes they&#13;
                                                                                     take there and back. The realization of how closely these&#13;
RESULTS AND LEARNING                                                                 activities take place, often leads to collective action to be&#13;
Objective 1: Increasing Collective Demand and Be-                                    free from the hazard by becoming ODF. In order to achieve&#13;
havior Change Among Communities and Households                                       this following triggering, communities must come together&#13;
Through CLTS and BCC Campaign                                                        and forge their own action plan, with only limited support&#13;
                                                                                     from project staff. Communities that are verified ODF by&#13;
One of the key challenges to expanding sanitation interven-                          government agencies receive recognition from local and&#13;
tions in Indonesia is motivating households to recognize                             provincial government leadership. Sub-villages who have&#13;
and appreciate the importance of defecating in hygienic la-                          received CLTS are also vital in triggering other sub-villages&#13;
trines for their families and their community. In East Java                          to become ODF.23&#13;
96 percent of households that do not have access to sani-&#13;
tation report defecating in rivers. Open defecation, espe-                           In East Java the CLTS approach resulted in tangible im-&#13;
cially in rivers, is still culturally acceptable and frequently                      provements to household-level sanitation behavior change.&#13;
considered more convenient than using sanitation facilities.                         The fraction of households reporting that at least one mem-&#13;
To combat this perception the CLTS approach aims to â&#128;&#152;trig-                           ber engages in open defecation is systematically lower in&#13;
gerâ&#128;&#153; the desire for a community environment that is ODF.                             communities that participated in the project (â&#128;&#152;treatmentâ&#128;&#153;&#13;
At the district level, the TSSM intervention began with a                            communities). Households reporting that a member con-&#13;
series of roadshows aimed at generating stakeholder buy-                             tinues to practice open defecation is 4.4 percentage points&#13;
in through presentations that demonstrated the economic                              lower in treatment villages. Among communities on rivers,&#13;
and social impacts of poor sanitation. These roadshows also                          open defecation by any household member is 6 percent-&#13;
provided a forum for establishing the programâ&#128;&#153;s â&#128;&#152;rules of                            age points lower in treatment communities than in control&#13;
engagementâ&#128;&#153;, namely that (i) formal letters of interest had                          communities participating in the TSSM impact evalua-&#13;
to be received from district, subdistrict and village leaders                        tion.24&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
23&#13;
     Typically 5-10 subvillages comprise a single village.&#13;
24&#13;
     Draft. TSSM Impact Evaluation. 2012.&#13;
&#13;
www.wsp.org&#13;
                                                                                                                                                      7&#13;
&amp;#12;    FIELD NOTE: Results, Impacts, and Learning from Improving Sanitation at Scale in East Java, Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                          sustained. One pathway that has proved successful for&#13;
                                                                                          ensuring sustained repeat behavior change messaging to&#13;
                                                                                          communities is working in collaboration with health pro-&#13;
                                                                                          motion units (Promkes) at the Ministry of Health. Work-&#13;
                                                                                          ing through Promkes provided an institutional â&#128;&#156;homeâ&#128;&#157; for&#13;
                                                                                          promoting messages around rural sanitation, with forma-&#13;
                                                                                          tive research aiding in the development of tools that dis-&#13;
                                                                                          trict governments can use to develop their own sanitation&#13;
                                                                                          improvement campaigns.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                          Objective 2: Strengthening the Supply of Affordable La-&#13;
                                                                                          trines and Services for Households&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                          While CLTS has proved effective for triggering a commu-&#13;
                                                                                          nity desire and effort to be free from open defecation, it&#13;
    Lessons Learned                                                                       alone is not sufficient for driving the adoption of improved&#13;
    TSSM monitoring data show rapid progress in more than                                 latrines. For a community to be able to sustain ODF status,&#13;
    5,000 triggered communities in East Java, with demand ac-                             increased household demand must be met with a range of&#13;
    celerating from district governments.25 About 83 percent of                           options that would allow individuals to progressively up-&#13;
    these communities were â&#128;&#152;triggeredâ&#128;&#153; with local government                              grade facilities over a sustained period of time. Supply-side&#13;
    funding, indicating a high â&#128;&#147; and growing â&#128;&#147; degree of local                            challenges centered around how to popularize what con-&#13;
    government ownership of the approach. One of the keys                                 stitutes an ideal safe, healthy, hygienic sanitation facility&#13;
    to success was an approach that required early buy-in from                            among consumers and suppliers, as well as how to motivate&#13;
    districts, subdistrict and village leadership, as well as their                       the market (including manufacturers, suppliers, vendors&#13;
    explicit interest and commitment to engaging with proj-                               and masons) to deliver a range of sanitation options priced&#13;
    ect facilitators. Over time TSSM shifted to explore alter-                            for different segments of consumers.&#13;
    native strategies for sustaining buy-in from districts such&#13;
    as competitions between areas, award ceremonies, and re-                              In order to meet these challenges WSP developed a stra-&#13;
    purposing project outcomes to lobby for additional budget                             tegic sanitation behavior change framework to help guide&#13;
    allocation.                                                                           the analysis of determinants of sanitation behavior change&#13;
                                                                                          based on extensive market research collected in East Java.&#13;
    However, triggering alone was not enough to guarantee                                 Formative research using SaniFOAM (Sanitation Frame-&#13;
    successful progression to ODF, which was achieved by                                  work of Opportunity, Ability and Motivation) revealed a&#13;
    over 2,200 communities by December 2011. Repeat mes-                                  number of clear factors constraining adoption of latrines:&#13;
    saging and targeted monitoring and follow-up through&#13;
    household visits were key to ensuring consistent support                              â&#128;¢ Flush latrines were perceived as prohibitively expensive&#13;
    to households. Repeat messaging, which mainly occurred                                  by households&#13;
    through existing congregational and communal gather-                                  â&#128;¢ Disease was seen as a result of poverty and/or destiny&#13;
    ings, was especially important for reinforcing the themes                               and not related to sanitation behaviors&#13;
    of the original triggering event. For communities that take                           â&#128;¢ Sanitation was perceived as a waste of clean water espe-&#13;
    several months to become ODF, periodic re-checks may                                    cially in water scarce areas, whereas open defecation is&#13;
    be a valuable tool for ensuring that ODF status has been                                clean, convenient and free&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    25&#13;
         Inception Report for the Five Year At-Scale Sanitation and Hygiene Implementation Program in Indonesia. WSP, World Bank Group. 2011.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
8                                                                                                                                               www.wsp.org&#13;
&amp;#12;FIELD NOTE: Results, Impacts, and Learning from Improving Sanitation at Scale in East Java, Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
â&#128;¢ Although sanitation materials and services appeared                                market research to understand consumer preferences and&#13;
  plentiful, suppliers presented relatively expensive op-                            the supply capacity of local markets, followed by devel-&#13;
  tions when asked about the cost of a hygienic latrine                              oping pro-poor marketing strategies in response, should&#13;
  facility                                                                           have preceded implementation of CLTS and BCC inter-&#13;
â&#128;¢ The supply market chain for sanitation was fragmented                              ventions to generate demand while helping local capacity&#13;
  and lacked clear standards to identify safe, hygienic la-                          to grow.&#13;
  trines, thus perpetuating the assumption among consum-&#13;
  ers that safe latrines were unaffordable                                           In addition to implementation delays, this component&#13;
                                                                                     required a substantial revision in its approach based on&#13;
It was from this new framework for action that the following                         emerging lessons from the first half of the year. Training&#13;
features were added to TSSM in an effort to enhance supply                           of masons proved to be ineffective as participants, who&#13;
and bolster community demand for low-cost latrine options:                           were chosen by the district to ensure district ownership&#13;
                                                                                     in this component, were not appropriate candidates for&#13;
       a) Promotion of definitions of â&#128;&#152;improvedâ&#128;&#153; and â&#128;&#152;unim-                          training and in some cases had limited interaction with&#13;
          provedâ&#128;&#153; sanitation as part of all program implemen-                        communities that needed upgraded facilities the most.&#13;
          tation tools and resources in a way that makes it easy                     Initially, this resulted in an imbalance between communi-&#13;
          to understand the difference between the two at the                        ties in which demand was ignited through CLTS and local&#13;
          community level                                                            marketsâ&#128;&#153; ability to provide a range of low-cost options for&#13;
       b) Creation of an Informed Choice Catalogue (ICC)                             consumers. Adjustments to the approach included intro-&#13;
          of safe sanitation options that: (i) illustrates all pos-                  ducing increasingly rigorous selection criteria for training&#13;
          sible combinations from lowest to highest cost; and                        recipients; shifting the pool of trainees from masons â&#128;&#152;one&#13;
          (ii) promotes the idea that safe, hygienic latrines are                    level upâ&#128;&#153; to sanitation entrepreneurs; and ensuring that&#13;
          affordable and good for all                                                there was a better match between those trained and the&#13;
       c) Development of mason training/accreditation pro-                           communities being targeted as part of TSSM. The result&#13;
          gram designed to equip every district with masons                          was a marked increase in the number of toilets sold and&#13;
          capable of facilitating informed consumer choice-                          built in treatment communities since TSSMâ&#128;&#153;s inception,&#13;
          making from the ICC, as well as promote and deliver                        almost 30 percent higher in treatment versus control com-&#13;
          safe improved sanitation options (â&#128;&#156;WC-ku Sehatâ&#128;&#157;)                           munities (representing a 31 percent increase in the rate of&#13;
       d) Promotion of â&#128;&#156;WC-ku Sehatâ&#128;&#157; thumbs-up sign brand-                           toilet construction over baseline).26&#13;
          ing for facilities that meet â&#128;&#152;improved sanitationâ&#128;&#153; criteria&#13;
       e) Launch of a vendor orientation program to promote&#13;
          â&#128;&#156;WC-ku Sehatâ&#128;&#157; option and link consumers with&#13;
          trained masons&#13;
&#13;
Lessons Learned&#13;
Strengthening the supply of affordable latrine proved to&#13;
be substantially more difficult than increasing demand.&#13;
Progress in improving local supply capacity was initially&#13;
delayed due to difficulties in identifying and recruiting&#13;
a marketing expert for TSSM, a position henceforth not&#13;
seen in the sanitation sector. The sanitation-marketing&#13;
component thus started with an 18-month delay. Ideally,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
26&#13;
     Ibid. Draft. TSSM Impact Evaluation. 2012.&#13;
&#13;
www.wsp.org&#13;
                                                                                                                                                    9&#13;
&amp;#12; FIELD NOTE: Results, Impacts, and Learning from Improving Sanitation at Scale in East Java, Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 But traditional individual training models alone are not                             entrepreneurs, was a valuable tool for encouraging house-&#13;
 enough to motivate sanitation market transformation. Part-                           holds to upgrade existing latrines and building awareness&#13;
 nerships with community organizations proved effective, as                           about low-cost options for progressive upgrades of latrine&#13;
 was done with â&#128;&#152;one-stop-shopâ&#128;&#153; sanitation centers in East                             facilities. Actors at the provincial and district level that&#13;
 Java. These centers provide conventional mason services                              were exposed to the catalogue found it a useful tool, al-&#13;
 with information centers, promotional creativity, technical                          though many at the village level, for which cost is perceived&#13;
 support provision, as well as sanitation construction materi-                        as the main impediment to latrine adoption, reported less&#13;
 als. Currently there are approximately 85 one-stop centers                           exposure to the ICC. Evidence from the TSSM Impact&#13;
 in operation in East Java that have sold over 15,000 sani-                           Evaluation demonstrates the need for continued awareness&#13;
 tation packages, generating more than US$1.3 million in                              building about low-cost latrine options, especially at the&#13;
 revenue.27                                                                           household level. On average households surveyed estimated&#13;
                                                                                      that it would cost approximately Rp1.2 million to build a&#13;
 Delays in project implementation of this objective also had                          latrine (US$135), roughly equal to the average householdâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
 an effect on the distribution of the informed choice cata-                           per capita, per month income. In reality, TSSM estimates&#13;
 logue (ICC) to various stakeholders. This catalogue, which                           the actual cost to install a latrine with a slab to be in the&#13;
 was used widely in training of sanitarians, masons and                               range of US$50 to US$90.28&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       BOX 1. LEARNING FROM SUCCESS: LATRINE SAVINGS CLUBS IN JOMBANG DISTRICT&#13;
       The sanitation business in Jombang district is growing thanks to the efforts of a local sanitarian named Subianadi.&#13;
       As part of his job responsibilities Subianadi is responsible for environmental programming in each of the areas&#13;
       sub-villages, including the construction of healthy latrines. To accelerate community demand for construction of&#13;
       healthy latrines, Subianadi initially proposed the idea of a latrine savings club or arisan where club members could&#13;
       pay Rp1,000 (approximately US$0.09) a day towards a new latrine, an idea that was readily accepted by villagers&#13;
       who felt it was easy to set aside Rp1,000 a day without too much trouble. Volunteers were set to collect contribu-&#13;
       tions from club members every day and the idea was ofï¬&#129;cially endorsed by the subdistrict leader.&#13;
       Using this savings club scheme, Subianadi and his team have been able to help construct 23 household latrines&#13;
       per month, per village, with outstanding orders for 111 latrines. Under this scheme, each member of the savings&#13;
       club eventually receives a savings pot of Rp600,000 (approximately US$54), which can be used towards the con-&#13;
       struction of a new latrine. The modelsâ&#128;&#153; success has meant that word has continued to spreadâ&#128;&#148;with the club now&#13;
       being developed in several subdistricts beyond Subiandiâ&#128;&#153;s subdistrict of Sumobito.&#13;
       Subiandi said when the idea of the savings club scheme was introduced, villagers initially doubted that Rp600,000&#13;
       was sufï¬&#129;cient funding to build a healthy latrine. He often uses BCC materials to address these concerns, and&#13;
       demonstrates that there are a range of healthy latrines at various prices. The savings club scheme also does away&#13;
       with the need for hardware subsidies and loans from ï¬&#129;nancial institutions because the turnover of funds is rapid&#13;
       enough for Subianadi to purchase materials and pay the masons.&#13;
       Subianadi also believes that sanitarians are instrumental to the successful construction of healthy latrines as they&#13;
       are considered credible experts in the eyes of the community. However, more needs to be done to socialize the&#13;
       importance of this work among sanitarians who still feel that it is occasionally â&#128;&#156;unfamiliar and bothersomeâ&#128;&#157; work&#13;
       that places additional burdens such as travel on their everyday work.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 27&#13;
      WSP Project Monitoring Data. August 2012.&#13;
 28&#13;
      Water and Sanitation Program, 2012.&#13;
&#13;
10                                                                                                                                      www.wsp.org&#13;
&amp;#12;FIELD NOTE: Results, Impacts, and Learning from Improving Sanitation at Scale in East Java, Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                     Each of these community-led innovations provides indica-&#13;
                                                                                     tions that support the idea that poor households are will-&#13;
                                                                                     ing to invest in the mid-priced pour-flush latrine options&#13;
                                                                                     if some form of credit to enable payment by installments is&#13;
                                                                                     made available to them.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                     In the future, support to Indonesiaâ&#128;&#153;s sanitation entrepre-&#13;
                                                                                     neurs is poised to expand. Entrepreneurs have come togeth-&#13;
                                                                                     er to form the Asosiasi Pengelola and Pemberdayaan Sanitasi&#13;
                                                                                     Indonesia (APPSANI, or Indonesia Sanitation Developer&#13;
                                                                                     and Empowerment Association) in early 2012. Through&#13;
                                                                                     APPSANI entrepreneurs will be able to collectively advo-&#13;
                                                                                     cate for standardization of pricing, standards, recruitment&#13;
                                                                                     of new entrepreneurs and a training curriculum. These ef-&#13;
However, cost alone does not paint the full picture of why                           forts are also being reinforced by the Ministry of Health,&#13;
poor households decided not to adopt improved latrines.                              which has begun to require local governments interested in&#13;
Households that cited â&#128;&#152;lack of moneyâ&#128;&#153; as a reason for not                            expanding STBM to provide cofinancing for local sanita-&#13;
owning a latrine also reported owning assets such as tele-                           tion entrepreneur training.&#13;
visions, motorbikes, bicycles, livestock, cell phones, paddy&#13;
fields and permanent housing with brickwork, masonry and                             Objective 3: Strengthening the Enabling Environment&#13;
tiled roofs.29 The issue is not only of cost, but also of house-&#13;
hold prioritization and awareness about the continued dan-                           In order to seriously address the sanitation crisis in Indo-&#13;
gers of open defecation. The one advantage of assets, such                           nesia, national and local governments need to take a strong&#13;
as a television or motorbike, is that they can be bought on                          lead in ensuring accountability and sustainability of sani-&#13;
credit and paid off over several months. Affordable financ-                          tation interventions in the short, medium and long-term&#13;
ing options such as installment credit or deferred payments                          in order to ensure that project outcomes, no matter how&#13;
would provide affordable pathways for poor households                                successful, survive once external funding ceases. For this&#13;
looking to upgrade latrines, especially when coupled with                            reason, an enabling environment is central to the scaling up&#13;
targeted promotion about the range of products available                             and sustainability of project outcomes. For the purposes of&#13;
on the market.                                                                       TSSM an enabling environment was defined as one where&#13;
                                                                                     the policy, institutional and financial environment pro-&#13;
In East Java the cost barrier was also addressed through a                           motes mutually self-sustaining growth of, demand for&#13;
number of innovative financing mechanisms that empow-                                and supply of improved sanitation. Success in achieving&#13;
ered villages to leverage group resources to help poor house-                        this objective is focused on eight dimensions:&#13;
holds gain access to latrines. In some cases, entrepreneurs&#13;
engaged with local microfinance institutions to provide                                   ï&#131;¼   Policy, Strategy and Direction&#13;
households with available credit. Another mechanism was                                   ï&#131;¼   Institutional Arrangements&#13;
the use of group savings (arisans) commonly used in Java                                  ï&#131;¼   Program Methodology&#13;
to enable poor households to raise funds for large expenses,                              ï&#131;¼   Implementation Capacity&#13;
such as sanitation revolving funds. In some cases, arisan                                 ï&#131;¼   Availability of Products and Tools&#13;
groups even entered into agreements with local sanitation                                 ï&#131;¼   Financing&#13;
material retailers to get supplies on credit, build facilities                            ï&#131;¼   Cost-Effective Implementation&#13;
and pay back the total amount in six monthly installments.                                ï&#131;¼   Monitoring &amp; Evaluation&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
29&#13;
     Ibid, Mukherjee et. al. 2012.&#13;
&#13;
www.wsp.org&#13;
                                                                                                                                               11&#13;
&amp;#12; FIELD NOTE: Results, Impacts, and Learning from Improving Sanitation at Scale in East Java, Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     BOX 2. STRENGTHENING THE ENABLING ENVIRONMENT&#13;
     As part of WSPâ&#128;&#153;s commitment to supporting sustainable change at scale in Indonesia, the program has continued&#13;
     to provide high quality technical support well beyond the life of the project. Since 2010, Ministry of Healthâ&#128;&#153;s STBM&#13;
     Secretariat, with support from WSP, has continued to scale up its efforts to strengthen the enabling environment&#13;
     through sanitation policy development, adoption of behavior change and sanitation marketing strategies, creation&#13;
     of improved systems for monitoring and evaluation and greater sub-national investment in rural sanitation im-&#13;
     provements. WSP also provides capacity building support to the Department for Human Resource Development&#13;
     within Ministry of Health, where together they are making strides in improving:&#13;
     â&#128;¢ Standardization and accreditation of sanitation entrepreneurs&#13;
     â&#128;¢ Provision of performance-based provider incentives for civil servants&#13;
     â&#128;¢ Collaboration with provincial training institutes (Health Polytechnics) to integrate STBM training material into for-&#13;
       mal curriculum&#13;
     WSP is also co-managing the health component of the Pamsimas project in 32 provinces through provision of&#13;
     technical, monitoring and training assistance at provincial, regional and national levels.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Lessons Learned&#13;
 Policy, Strategy and Direction support for STBM (using                               As part of creating sustainable Institutional Arrangements,&#13;
 the TSSM approach) is continuing to grow in Indonesia                                the TSSM approach has been successful in developing own-&#13;
 and is already significant among key ministries such as the                          ership and encouraging greater allocation of local govern-&#13;
 Ministry of Health and the Ministry of Planning (BAPPE-                              ment funds towards rural sanitation. For every Rp1 million&#13;
 NAS). For the Ministry of Health, STBM is an essential                               the project was successful in leveraging an additional Rp2-37&#13;
 part of the 2009-2014 Strategic Plan, targeting implemen-                            million, depending on the district, between January 2008&#13;
 tation in 20,000 villages and as a program priority for su-                          and December 2010. Decentralization of decision-making&#13;
 pervision under the National Medium-Term Development                                 has also been critical for assuring local governmentsâ&#128;&#153; involve-&#13;
 Plan by the Presidential Unit for Development, Monitoring                            ment in taking responsibility for decisions around whether to&#13;
 and Control, all of which are aimed at making Indonesia                              adopt particular approaches, utilize project tools or partici-&#13;
 ODF by 2014. Through the project, WSP also provided                                  pate in capacity building activities.&#13;
 intensive technical assistance to districts about how to pre-&#13;
 pare detailed district sanitation plans for scale-up to ensure                       Increases in the Availability of Products, Tools and Ser-&#13;
 sustained funding for rural sanitation. These plans pro-                             vices have led to improved latrine designs and technology&#13;
 vide a roadmap for how sanitarians, village midwives and                             options that have now expanded beyond East Java into four&#13;
 health cadres can work collaboratively in order to imple-                            additional provinces, both through TSSM training courses&#13;
 ment STBM strategies in their community. This effort has                             and knowledge sharing at stakeholder events. One of the&#13;
 born ample fruit as several districts have already completed                         most popular models of provision remains the one-stop&#13;
 their strategic plans and/or incorporated these plans into                           shop where customers can organize latrine construction in&#13;
 their existing multi-year district strategic plans for water                         one easy visit, allowing them to choose from a range of low-&#13;
 and sanitation. NGOs have also signaled their support of                             cost latrine options that can be delivered and installed in a&#13;
 CLTS, with variations having been adopted by UNICEF                                  timely manner. One-stop shops, run by sanitation entre-&#13;
 and Plan Indonesia as central components of their sanita-                            preneurs, have now expanded to four new provinces where&#13;
 tion programs.                                                                       local governments are increasingly providing resources to&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
12                                                                                                                                       www.wsp.org&#13;
&amp;#12;FIELD NOTE: Results, Impacts, and Learning from Improving Sanitation at Scale in East Java, Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
support the training and coordination needed to match                                in improved sanitation. Under this project, total govern-&#13;
increased community demand for improved latrines with                                ment costs were US$2.73 per beneficiary. The study found&#13;
entrepreneurs ready to serve them.                                                   that households with no exposure to the program invested&#13;
                                                                                     approximately US$5.82 while households that did partici-&#13;
District governments have also begun to select communica-                            pate spent an additional US$2.94 on improving sanitation&#13;
tion materials from a menu of design templates and repli-                            over and above control households, representing a 47 per-&#13;
cate them over local media channels using their own funds.                           cent increase in spending. Thus, every US$1 spent by the&#13;
Progress in getting districts to fully utilize these resources                       government returned increased household investment of&#13;
is beginning to climb, although future research into les-                            US$1.08. Increases were also reported for poor households&#13;
sons learned about why some district governments decide                              who were also willing to make substantial investments in&#13;
to use or not use BCC materials could potentially provide                            improved sanitation, spending US$1.55 per capita more&#13;
pathways for improving and sustaining utilization. Going                             than their counterparts who were in control communities.30&#13;
forward, opportunities also exist to expand distribution and                         Moreover, the treatment induced greater investments from&#13;
awareness building around the ICC, as well as create formal                          the private sector on the supply side, and from the com-&#13;
systems at all levels of government (district, province and                          munity in terms of volunteer time, totaling an additional&#13;
national) to collect and share innovative designs and techni-                        US$2.86 per beneficiary. Once this is accounted for, ev-&#13;
cal options.                                                                         ery US$1 spent by the government leveraged an additional&#13;
                                                                                     US$2.13 in total new investments from households, com-&#13;
One result of the TSSM project in East Java has been a                               munities and the private sector. This demonstrates that rela-&#13;
growing awareness of the importance of Cost-effective Imple-                         tively small amounts of government spending can trigger&#13;
mentation rather than simple measurement of latrine and                              significant non-government investments, emphasizing the&#13;
latrine subsidies. A recent costing study on the TSSM pro-                           importance of collecting information on these investments&#13;
gram in East Java demonstrates the potential of the TSSM                             when estimating cost-effectiveness of implementation.&#13;
program to leverage noteworthy investments by households&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
30&#13;
     Chase, Briceno, Naafs, 2013.&#13;
&#13;
www.wsp.org&#13;
                                                                                                                                                13&#13;
&amp;#12; FIELD NOTE: Results, Impacts, and Learning from Improving Sanitation at Scale in East Java, Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                           â&#128;¢ Documentation and dissemination of lessons,&#13;
                                                                                             which provided stakeholders at the central and local&#13;
                                                                                             level with publications, study tours and opportuni-&#13;
                                                                                             ties to engage in learning events in order to review&#13;
                                                                                             progress and capture lessons learned before further&#13;
                                                                                             expansion of activities.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                      One of the biggest challenges faced over the course of the&#13;
                                                                                      TSSM project was availability of reliable, timely data on rural&#13;
                                                                                      sanitation access and hygiene behaviors. Currently in Indo-&#13;
                                                                                      nesia there exists no functional monitoring system for rural&#13;
                                                                                      sanitation, other than the annual Susenas socio-economic&#13;
                                                                                      household survey, which provides only representative data on&#13;
 MEASURING RESULTS &amp; IMPACTS                                                          use of household sanitation facilities. Likewise, at the local&#13;
 Monitoring and evaluation of progress towards each of the                            level, there is no reliable monitoring of sanitation outcomes&#13;
 projectâ&#128;&#153;s objectives and targets was considered a major com-                         such as latrine usage, hand washing with soap, safe disposal&#13;
 ponent of the program from its earliest stages. Multiple col-                        of infant excreta or open defecation rates. Thus, TSSM fo-&#13;
 lection pathways, as well as continuous monitoring of data                           cused heavily on improving the quality and reliability of rural&#13;
 accuracy and efficiency, allowed WSP to measure success                              sanitation data by developing a community-based monitor-&#13;
 frequently, as well as highlight areas where course correc-                          ing system that feeds access and behavior data regularly into&#13;
 tions were necessary during implementation. The monitor-                             local, provincial and ultimately national databases. Currently,&#13;
 ing and evaluation component of TSSM included the fol-                               an improved version of the system, developed as part of the&#13;
 lowing elements:                                                                     original program design, is being managed by the STBM&#13;
                                                                                      Secretariat in order to provide resources for local-level facili-&#13;
        â&#128;¢ Project implementation monitoring and improve-                              ties to collect and analyze project-monitoring data. This new&#13;
          ment regularly monitored progress of individual,                            web and SMS-based system will eventually provide an inter-&#13;
          planned activities. This process was an ongoing dy-                         active platform for program trouble-shooting and up-to-date&#13;
          namic process that allowed the project to use data                          information for policy decision-making.&#13;
          and information in real time to make adjustments as&#13;
          needed to project implementation.                                           PROGRAM EFFECTS ON CHILD HEALTH&#13;
        â&#128;¢ Monitoring and evaluation of expected outcomes                              OUTCOMES&#13;
          and results that monitored increases in access to                           Of the four most important causes of under-5 mortality&#13;
          hygienic sanitation, number of open-defecation free                         in Indonesia two - diarrhea and typhoid - are preventable&#13;
          communities and hygiene behavior changes.                                   fecal-borne illnesses directly linked to inadequate water&#13;
        â&#128;¢ Impact Evaluation that measured the project inter-                          supply, sanitation and hygiene issues.31 In Indonesia alone,&#13;
          ventionâ&#128;&#153;s health, behavioral, welfare and economic                          about 11 percent of children suffer from diarrhea in any&#13;
          impacts.                                                                    2-week period and it has been estimated that an excess of&#13;
        â&#128;¢ Enabling Environment Assessment that examined                               33,000 children die each year in Indonesia from diarrhea&#13;
          national and local government policies for accelerat-                       and 11,000 from typhoid.32 Children under five in Indone-&#13;
          ing rates of increased access to sanitation, especially                     sia continue to bear the brunt of inadequate rural sanitation&#13;
          among the poorest communities.                                              through increased instances of morbidity through early life.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 31&#13;
      MOH, 2002.&#13;
 32&#13;
      Curtis, 2004.&#13;
&#13;
14                                                                                                                                         www.wsp.org&#13;
&amp;#12;FIELD NOTE: Results, Impacts, and Learning from Improving Sanitation at Scale in East Java, Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Diarrheal diseases are one of the most significant causes of                                 way, the project was successful in generating local govern-&#13;
malnutrition and nutrient malabsorption, which can lead                                      mentâ&#128;&#153;s early interest and creating a strong foundation for&#13;
to impaired physical growth (stunting), reduced resistance                                   sustained partnership over the course of the projectâ&#128;&#153;s imple-&#13;
to infection, long-term gastrointestinal disorders and even                                  mentation. The project also managed to adjust implemen-&#13;
long-term cognitive deficiencies.33                                                          tation approaches based on a continuing flow of lessons&#13;
                                                                                             coming in through a variety of formal and informal reviews&#13;
Among TSSMâ&#128;&#153;s achievements was a notable reduction in                                         and reflections that helped define which of the approaches&#13;
diarrhea prevalence (7-day and 2-day recall) among com-                                      was working well (for example, pairing government coun-&#13;
munities receiving the intervention. Specifically, being                                     terparts with CLTS specialists to learn from them during&#13;
in treatment communities was associated with diarrhea                                        triggering and verification) and which needed adjustment&#13;
prevalence being lowered by approximately 1.3 percent-                                       (such as revising supply side strengthening from a focus on&#13;
age points from a 4.6 percent base. These decreases were                                     masons to entrepreneurs).&#13;
driven largely by non-poor households that did not have&#13;
adequate sanitation facilities at the beginning of the proj-                                 Enhancing local government capacities to fully imple-&#13;
ect. Among the other effects on child health, instance of                                    ment STBM requires continued, long-term commitment.&#13;
parasitic infection in treatment communities was lower, as                                   Despite growing steadily over the past few years, local gov-&#13;
was the instance of refusal to eat and instance of blood or                                  ernments are still working under their capacity to imple-&#13;
mucous in stool.34                                                                           ment and sustain resourcing for large-scale rural sanitation&#13;
                                                                                             programs. This includes greater supervision of CLTS facili-&#13;
LESSONS LEARNED FROM SCALING UP                                                              tators, greater support for sanitarians and engagement of&#13;
RURAL SANITATION IN INDONESIA                                                                private sector suppliers. Going forward, it will be necessary&#13;
Four years of TSSM implementation have not only provided                                     to continue to develop the capacity of local governments to&#13;
a wealth of lessons but also a pathway forward for scaling up                                adopt total sanitation and sanitation marketing strategies&#13;
rural sanitation throughout Indonesia. With an established                                   including strategic plans, standardized tools, training mate-&#13;
legal framework, widespread political support and demon-                                     rials and budget allocations. Institutionalizing knowledge&#13;
strated effects at a large scale, the STBM framework has the                                 sharing, especially through peer-to-peer exchanges, has&#13;
potential to substantially increase the number of rural Indo-                                been especially helpful in improving capacity and sustain-&#13;
nesians with access to and use of an improved toilet.                                        ing local governmentsâ&#128;&#153; engagement in building the sector.&#13;
&#13;
A project approach that adjusts for country context was                                      Quality formative research is central to effective pro-&#13;
key for ensuring client ownership. The decentralized na-                                     gram design. Over the course of the project, carefully&#13;
ture of Indonesiaâ&#128;&#153;s regulatory environment made work-                                        planned, early formative research was critical in both&#13;
ing closely with district leadership an essential element in                                 understanding the underlying factors motivating indi-&#13;
ensuring project ownership and sustainability. Early road                                    vidual sanitation behavior change and potential gaps in&#13;
shows provided an opportunity to socialize a wide array of                                   the sanitation supply chain. Through this research district&#13;
stakeholders from health, education, finance and develop-                                    governments have been able to more effectively use local&#13;
ment to the importance of scaling-up rural sanitation in-                                    media to deliver targeted messages to the community as a&#13;
terventions through a behavior change-focused approach.                                      pathway for increasing demand for improved sanitation&#13;
Following socialization, districts were required to submit                                   solutions. In turn, suppliers have been able to offer a bet-&#13;
letters of intent guaranteeing their commitment to staffing                                  ter array of product options that are tailored to meet con-&#13;
and providing future resourcing for rural sanitation. In this                                sumer preferences.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
33&#13;
     Murray, Lopez (1997); Guerrant et al (1999); Baqui et al (1993); Schneider et al (1978); Humphrey (2009).&#13;
34&#13;
     Instance of parasitic infection intensity for Ascaris and Trichuris, estimated as egg worms per milligram, was not statistically significant over the whole sample.&#13;
&#13;
www.wsp.org&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                           15&#13;
&amp;#12; FIELD NOTE: Results, Impacts, and Learning from Improving Sanitation at Scale in East Java, Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Champions from a variety of stakeholders can facilitate                              lies. Results from the programâ&#128;&#153;s impact evaluation indicate&#13;
 greater program reach and sustainability. Identifying and                            that non-poor households were more likely to build a toilet&#13;
 acknowledging champions can be the catalyst to accelerate                            as a result of exposure to the program rather than poorer&#13;
 governmentâ&#128;&#153;s buy-in to the program. In Indonesia, an early                           households. According to government data, a number of&#13;
 understanding of various actorsâ&#128;&#153; motives prior to imple-                             treatment and control villages have become open defe-&#13;
 mentation allowed WSP flexibility in being able to package                           cation-free after the endline survey was finalized, which&#13;
 the projectâ&#128;&#153;s potential benefits from a variety of stakehold-                        would suggest that all households including the poorest&#13;
 erâ&#128;&#153;s perspectives. The process of identifying or monitoring                          have by now been able to build some kind of toilet for&#13;
 individual(s) or institution as champions should be embed-                           the community to be verified as open defecation-free.&#13;
 ded into the project intervention design from the earliest                           However, further in-depth research is necessary to confirm&#13;
 stages of planning. It is important to ensure that emerging                          these results and more importantly, to fully understand&#13;
 champions â&#128;&#148; be they government employees, volunteers,                                willingness to pay, availability of affordable products, and&#13;
 engaged mothers, etc. â&#128;&#148; are embedded in the program to                               financing strategies and options (e.g., provision of cred-&#13;
 ensure maximum program reach.                                                        it for households and/or entrepreneurs, collective saving&#13;
                                                                                      schemes for households, or â&#128;&#152;smartâ&#128;&#153; subsidies well targeted&#13;
 For the poorest, cost is still the biggest challenge to adopt-                       at these families) to speed up equitable access to improved&#13;
 ing improved sanitation. The cost of toilet construction                             sanitation and to ensure that the poorest households are&#13;
 still presents a challenge in particular to the poorest fami-                        not left behind.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
16                                                                                                                                     www.wsp.org&#13;
&amp;#12;FIELD NOTE: Results, Impacts, and Learning from Improving Sanitation at Scale in East Java, Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
REFERENCES&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Amin, S., Rangarajan, A., Borkum, E. Improving Sanita-                               Inception Report for The Five Year At-Scale Sanitation and&#13;
tion at Scale: Lessons from TSSM Implementation in East                              Hygiene Implementation Program in Indonesia. Water and&#13;
Java, Indonesia. Mathematica Policy Research, Inc. May                               Sanitation Program, The World Bank Group. 2011.&#13;
10, 2011.&#13;
                                                                                     Ministry of Health. Indonesia Health Profile. Ministry of&#13;
Baqui, A. et al. Methodological Issues in Diarrheal Diseases                         Health, Indonesia. 2002.&#13;
Epidemiology: Definition of Diarrheal Episodes. International&#13;
Journal of Epidemiology. 20(4): 1057-1063.                                           Mukherjee, N. et al. Achieving and Sustaining Open Defeca-&#13;
                                                                                     tion Free Communities: Learning from East Java. Water and&#13;
Cameron, L., Manisha, S. Scaling Up Rural Sanitation:                                Sanitation Program, The World Bank Group. March 2012.&#13;
Findings from the Impact Evaluation Baseline Survey in In-&#13;
donesia. Water and Sanitation Program, The World Bank                                Mukherjee, N. Factors Associated with Achieving and Sus-&#13;
Group. November 2010.                                                                taining Open Defecation Free Communities: Learning from&#13;
                                                                                     East Java. Water and Sanitation Program: Research Brief.&#13;
Cameron, L. et al. Impact Evaluation of a Large-Scale Rural                          The World Bank Group. September 2011.&#13;
Sanitation Project in Indonesia. Impact Evaluation Series No.&#13;
83the TSSM Project in East Java, Indonesia. Water and Sani-                          Mukherjee, N. et al. Managing the Flow of Monitoring In-&#13;
tation Program, The World Bank Group. 2012.                                          formation to Improve Rural Sanitation in East Java. Water&#13;
                                                                                     and Sanitation Program, The World Bank Group. February&#13;
Chase, C., Briceno, B., Naafs, A. Itâ&#128;&#153;s Going to Cost You: Cost-                      2011.&#13;
ing the Total Sanitation &amp; Sanitation Marketing Program in&#13;
East Java, Indonesia. Water and Sanitation Program, The                              Mukherjee, N. Total Sanitation and Sanitation Market-&#13;
World Bank Group. 2013.                                                              ing Project: Indonesia Country Update June 2009 Learning&#13;
                                                                                     at Scale. Water and Sanitation Program, The World Bank&#13;
Curtis, V. Hand-washing, Hygiene, and Health: Proposals for                          Group. August 2009.&#13;
Strengthening WSLIC-2â&#128;&#153;s Health Component and National&#13;
Hand-wash Campaign. Hygiene Centre, London School of                                 Murray, C. and Lopez, A. Global Mortality, Disability and&#13;
Hygiene and Tropical Medicine. London. 2004                                          the Contribution of Risk Factors: Global Burden of Disease&#13;
                                                                                     Study. Lancet 349(9063): 1436-1442.&#13;
Frias, J. Opportunities to Improve Sanitation: Situation As-&#13;
sessment of Sanitation in Rural East Java, Indonesia. Water                          Napitupulu and Hutton. Economic Impacts of Sanitation&#13;
and Sanitation Program, The World Bank Group. 2007.                                  in Indonesia. Water and Sanitation Program, World Bank&#13;
                                                                                     Group. August, 2008&#13;
Guerrant, D., Moore, S., Lima, A., et al. Association of&#13;
Early Childhood Diarrhea and Cryptosporidiosis with Im-                              Nielsen Indonesia. Total Sanitation and Sanitation Market-&#13;
paired Physical Fitness and Cognitive Function in Four-Seven                         ing Report. Prepared for The World Bank Water and Sanita-&#13;
Years Later in a Poor Urban Communities in Northeast Bra-                            tion Program. March 2009.&#13;
zil. American Journal of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene.&#13;
61(5): 707-713.                                                                      Perez, Eduardo, Amelink, C., Briceno, B. et al. Progress Re-&#13;
                                                                                     port July 1, 2009-June 30, 2010. Global Scaling Up Sanita-&#13;
Humphrey, J. Child undernutrition, tropical enteropathy, toi-                        tion Project, Water and Sanitation Project, The World Bank&#13;
lets, and handwashing. Lancet 2009: 374: 1032-35.                                    Group. 2011.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
www.wsp.org&#13;
                                                                                                                                               17&#13;
&amp;#12; FIELD NOTE: Results, Impacts, and Learning from Improving Sanitation at Scale in East Java, Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Perez, E. et al. What Does It Take to Scale Up Rural Sani-&#13;
 tation? Water and Sanitation Program, The World Bank&#13;
 Group. July 2012.&#13;
&#13;
 Robinson, A. Enabling Environment Assessment for Scaling&#13;
 Up Sanitation Programs: East Java, Indonesia. Global Scaling&#13;
 Up Sanitation Project, Water and Sanitation Project, The&#13;
 World Bank Group. January 2008.&#13;
&#13;
 Schneider, R.E. Shiffman, M. and Faigenblum, J. Potential&#13;
 Effects of Water on Gastrointestinal Infections Prevalent in De-&#13;
 veloping Countries. American Journal of Clinical Nutrition.&#13;
 31(11): 2089-2099.&#13;
&#13;
 U-Primo Rodriguez, Guy Hutton, Nelissa Jamora, Dieldre&#13;
 Harder, Jeremy Ockelford and EdKarl Galing. Economic as-&#13;
 sessment of sanitation interventions in the Philippines. World&#13;
 Bank, Water and Sanitation Program. 2011.&#13;
&#13;
 Water and Sanitation Program. Economic Impacts of Sanita-&#13;
 tion in Indonesia: A five-country study conducted in Cambo-&#13;
 dia, Indonesia, Lao PDR, the Philippines, and Vietnam under&#13;
 the Economics of Sanitation Initiative (ESI). Water and Sani-&#13;
 tation Program East Asia and the Pacific. The World Bank.&#13;
 2008.&#13;
&#13;
 Water and Sanitation Program. Learning at Scale: Total San-&#13;
 itation and Sanitation Marketing Project, Indonesia Country&#13;
 Update June. The World Bank. 2009.&#13;
&#13;
 Water and Sanitation Program. Achieving and Sustaining&#13;
 Open Defecation Free Communities: Learning from East Java.&#13;
 Water and Sanitation Program. The World Bank. 2012.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
18                                                                                                       www.wsp.org&#13;
&amp;#12;&amp;#12;THE WORLD BANK&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="19123423">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2013/10/19123423/results-impacts-learning-improving-sanitation-scale-east-java-indonesia
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2013/10/19123423/results-impacts-learning-improving-sanitation-scale-east-java-indonesia</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2013/10/19123423/results-impacts-learning-improving-sanitation-scale-east-java-indonesia</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2014-02-25T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2014-02-25T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2014/02/25/000333037_20140225143456/Rendered/INDEX/852000WSP0Box30valuation0Field0Note.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2014/02/25/000333037_20140225143456/Rendered/PDF/852000WSP0Box30valuation0Field0Note.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2014-02-25T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2013-10-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Results, impacts, and learning from
            improving sanitation at scale in East Java, Indonesia
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Inadequate access to sanitation remains
            a persistent issue, affecting the lives of millions of
            children and families especially in poor and rural
            communities throughout the world. In Indonesia, efforts to
            expand coverage have barely affected the lives of poorest
            populations where rampant diarrheal disease continues to
            affect the health and well-being of the next generation of
            children. These efforts were further complicated by policies
            that provided sanitation hardware subsidies limited to
            populations identified under specific programs, rather than
            strategies aimed at promoting large-scale sustained behavior
            change such as awareness building and hygiene education. As
            a result, Indonesia has the second highest number of open
            defecators worldwide at 59 million, according to the 2013
            update published by the WHO/UNICEF Joint Monitoring Program
            (JMP), and lags substantially behind its peers in the region
            in terms of access to sanitation. This field note presents
            the achievements, learning and reflections that resulted
            from implementing a large-scale sanitation program in East
            Java, Indonesia and provides recommendations for future
            initiatives aimed at increasing access to improved
            sanitation globally.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Results, impacts, and learning from
            improving sanitation at scale in East Java, Indonesia
        </docna>
        <display_title>Results, impacts, and learning
            from improving sanitation at scale in East Java, Indonesia</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2013/10/19123423/results-impacts-learning-improving-sanitation-scale-east-java-indonesia</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>UNDP-Water &amp; Sanitation Program</docty>
        <subtopic>Hygiene Promotion and Social Marketing,Wastewater Treatment,Urban Water Supply and Sanitation,Population Policies,Health and Sanitation</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Water Supply and Sanitation,Health, Nutrition and Population</teratopic>
        <count>Indonesia</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Pinto, Rebekah</author>
        </authors>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Asia!$!80451</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Southeast Asia!$!80471</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000333037_20140225143456</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>East Asia and Pacific,East Asia and Pacific</admreg>
        <colti>Water and sanitation program field note ; WSP</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Water Supply and Sanitation,Health, Nutrition and Population</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            access to latrines, access to sanitation,
            access to water, adequate sanitation facilities, adult
            morbidity, behavior change, capacity building, Child Health,
            clean water, Community Water, Developing Countries,
            diarrhea, diarrheal disease, Diarrheal diseases, Disability,
            dissemination, Drinking Water, drinking water supply, Early
            Childhood, economic growth, equitable access, feces, flush
            latrine, Flush latrines, generation of children, government
            agencies, government policies, hand washing, handwashing,
            health promotion, household latrines, household level,
            household sanitation, Human Resource Development, hygiene,
            hygiene behavior, hygiene behaviors, hygiene education,
            hygiene issues, hygiene practices, illnesses, Inadequate
            sanitation, inadequate water, inadequate water supply,
            infant, infant excreta, information centers, Informed
            Choice, International Journal of Epidemiology, lack of
            sanitation, Latrine, latrine construction, leading causes,
            leading causes of death, legal status, levels of knowledge,
            local capacity, local governments, Low Income Communities,
            midwives, Millennium Development Goal, Ministry of Health,
            mortality, national level, national levels, National
            Strategy, Nutrition, parasitic diseases, policy development,
            Policy Research, Political Support, Progress, Public Works,
            purchasing power, regulatory environment, Risk Factors,
            rivers, rural areas, rural communities, rural residents,
            Rural Sanitation, rural sanitation coverage, safe disposal,
            safe sanitation, SANITATION, sanitation access, sanitation
            data, sanitation facilities, sanitation facility, sanitation
            improvement, sanitation improvements, sanitation
            infrastructure, sanitation interventions, sanitation market,
            sanitation options, sanitation policy, sanitation problems,
            SANITATION PROGRAM, sanitation programs, sanitation sector,
            Sanitation Service, sanitation services, sanitation
            solutions, School of Hygiene, Service Providers, soap,
            sustainable access, Technical Assistance, television,
            toilet, toilets, Total Sanitation, typhoid, Urban
            Communities, urban sanitation, Users, waste, Water Supply
        </keywd>
        <owner>Water- Water and Sanit Prgrm (GWASP)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Southeast Asia</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>85200</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Impact Evaluations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Randomized Control Trials</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Basic Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>On-site Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Marketing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>PIM Diagnostic Tool</ml:concept><ml:concept>Project Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Child Survival and Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Early Child and Children's Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deconcentration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delegation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Devolution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sub-National Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subnational Government and Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Hygiene Promotion and Social Marketing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Boundaries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Impact Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Diseases</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water, Sanitation and Hygiene</ml:concept><ml:concept>Impact Assessment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Project Cycle Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Local Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Child Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Administrative Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Eastern Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Indonesia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>