<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>                                   69923&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
An AMCOW Country Status Overview&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Water&#13;
Supply and&#13;
Sanitation in&#13;
South Africa&#13;
Turning Finance into&#13;
Services for 2015&#13;
and Beyond&#13;
&amp;#12;The first round of Country Status Overviews (CSO1) published in 2006 benchmarked the preparedness of sectors of&#13;
16 countries in Africa to meet the WSS MDGs based on their medium-term spending plans and a set of â&#128;&#152;success&#13;
factorsâ&#128;&#153; selected from regional experience. Combined with a process of national stakeholder consultation, this prompted&#13;
countries to ask whether they had those â&#128;&#152;success factorsâ&#128;&#153; in place and, if not, whether they should put them in place.&#13;
&#13;
The second round of Country Status Overviews (CSO2) has built on both the method and the process developed in&#13;
CSO1. The â&#128;&#152;success factorsâ&#128;&#153; have been supplemented with additional factors drawn from country and regional analysis&#13;
to develop the CSO2 scorecard. Together these reflect the essential steps, functions and results in translating finance&#13;
into services through government systemsâ&#128;&#148;in line with Paris Principles for aid effectiveness. The data and summary&#13;
assessments have been drawn from local data sources and compared with internationally reported data, and, wherever&#13;
possible, the assessments have been subject to broad-based consultations with lead government agencies and country&#13;
sector stakeholders, including donor institutions.&#13;
&#13;
This second set of 32 Country Status Overviews (CSO2) on water supply and sanitation was commissioned by the African&#13;
Ministersâ&#128;&#153; Council on Water (AMCOW). Development of the CSO2 was led by the World Bank administered Water and&#13;
Sanitation Program (WSP) in collaboration with the African Development Bank (AfDB), the United Nations Childrenâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
Fund (UNICEF), the World Bank and the World Health Organization (WHO).&#13;
&#13;
This report was produced in collaboration with the Government of South Africa and other stakeholders during 2009/10.&#13;
Some sources cited may be informal documents that are not readily available.&#13;
&#13;
The findings, interpretations, and conclusions expressed in this volume do not necessarily reflect the views of the&#13;
collaborating institutions, their Executive Directors, or the governments they represent. The collaborating institutions&#13;
do not guarantee the accuracy of the data included in this work. The boundaries, colors, denominations, and other&#13;
information shown on any map in this work do not imply any judgment on the part of the collaborating institutions&#13;
concerning the legal status of any territory or the endorsement or acceptance of such boundaries.&#13;
&#13;
The material in this publication is copyrighted. Requests for permission to reproduce portions of it should be sent to&#13;
wsp@worldbank.org The collaborating institutions encourage the dissemination of this work and will normally grant&#13;
permission promptly. For more information, please visit www.amcow.net or www.wsp.org&#13;
&#13;
Photograph credits: Cover photograph by The Department of Water Affairs (South Africa)&#13;
Photograph on inside back cover by Lani van Vuuren-WRC&#13;
&#13;
Â© 2011 Water and Sanitation Program&#13;
&amp;#12;                   Water Supply and Sanitation in South Africa: Turning Finance into Services for 2015 and Beyond&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
An AMCOW Country Status Overview&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                           Water&#13;
                           Supply and&#13;
                           Sanitation in&#13;
                           South Africa&#13;
                           Turning Finance into&#13;
                           Services for 2015&#13;
                           and Beyond&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                               1&#13;
&amp;#12;An AMCOW Country Status Overview&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Strategic Overview&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Reform overview. South Africa underwent a major                  Learning and Improving&#13;
transition to a full democracy in 1994. The new government&#13;
embarked on an ambitious program to eradicate backlogs in        Notwithstanding these impressive achievements, South&#13;
water supply and sanitation, underpinned by development          Africa has demonstrated a willingness to seek ongoing&#13;
of sound sector policy and legislation. Initially, this          improvements and to meet new challenges.&#13;
program was driven by the central government. In 2003&#13;
responsibilities for service provision were devolved to local    There remain three areas of service backlogs that are â&#128;&#156;hard&#13;
government in line with the constitutional allocation of         to reachâ&#128;&#157;: sanitation in informal settlements; water supply&#13;
functions. Although much has been achieved, significant          in deep rural areas; and rural sanitation. There is evidence&#13;
challenges remain. There is a need to build and sustain          that the pace of delivery in these three areas has slowed.1&#13;
capacity at the local government level to continue to invest     Participatory approaches for the development of rural water&#13;
in, operate, and maintain services; to innovate and create       supply and sanitation projects, piloted and implemented&#13;
more effective delivery pathways to reach the â&#128;&#156;hard to           in the early 1990s by nongovernmental organizations&#13;
reachâ&#128;&#157;; and, to improve the sustainability of services already   (NGOs), were largely overtaken by a government-led drive&#13;
delivered.                                                       to supply new infrastructure from about 1995 onwards.&#13;
                                                                 Responsibility for investment and operation was later&#13;
Progress. South Africa has met the Millennium                    decentralized to local government in 2003. It is possible&#13;
Development Goal targets for water supply and sanitation,        that a supply-driven and infrastructure-focused approach is&#13;
according to its own service level definitions (which            less suited to addressing the remaining challenges and that&#13;
are higher than those used internationally by the Joint          delivery pathways that are more demand driven and involve&#13;
Monitoring Programme). South Africa has its own ambitious        communities more closely may be needed.&#13;
service coverage targets of 100 percent coverage for both&#13;
water supply and sanitation by 2014. These targets are           Although progress with investing in new infrastructure to&#13;
unlikely to be met for reasons elaborated below.                 reduce service backlogs has been impressive, this is not&#13;
                                                                 the whole story. Where infrastructure exists, not all poor&#13;
Financial resources. South Africa has mobilized extensive        households experience the benefits of this infrastructure as&#13;
resources to meet its service delivery targets. These are        a result of a large number of poorly functioning systems&#13;
primarily through government capital grants, to provide          in rural areas2 and, in some cases, having access restricted&#13;
new infrastructure, and operating grants, to support the         in urban areas as a result of affordability or technical&#13;
ongoing provision of services to poor households and the         problems.3&#13;
governmentâ&#128;&#153;s Free Basic Water policy. Government grant&#13;
allocations to water supply and sanitation have increased        There are also concerns related to the sustainability of the&#13;
significantly in real terms over the period. The use of grants   infrastructure (both the new infrastructure that has been&#13;
from donors and external loans is insignificant in the           built as well as the aging infrastructure which has been&#13;
context of the overall scale of government investment and        neglected in favor of extending services). The evidence for&#13;
local mobilization of resources. Anticipated investments are     this comes from multiple sources: a significant proportion of&#13;
significant but are not sufficient to achieve universal access   rural water supply schemes are not functional; maintenance&#13;
within the planned timeframe. This is partly due to the high     budgets are inadequate;4 many ventilated improved pit&#13;
cost of providing bulk water services (through regional          (VIP) latrines are full and are not being emptied;5 many&#13;
schemes) to the remaining remote rural households and            wastewater treatment works are operating over capacity&#13;
the high cost of urban sanitation (provision of waterborne       and/or performing poorly;6 there are drinking water&#13;
systems is the accepted standard in cities and towns). The       quality risks in small towns and rural areas;7 the full costs&#13;
existing cost model does not cater adequately for the            of providing services are often not fully accounted for;&#13;
regional bulk infrastructure required for rural water supply     and insufficient resources are available to the sector from&#13;
schemes in areas where groundwater resources are deemed          user fees and government grants to maintain and sustain&#13;
to be inadequate or unreliable.                                  services over time.&#13;
&#13;
2&#13;
&amp;#12;                                              Water Supply and Sanitation in South Africa: Turning Finance into Services for 2015 and Beyond&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
There is a shortage of the necessary skills and experience          The performance of water boards acting in support of local&#13;
at the artisan, technical, engineering, and management              government has been mixed, and water boards themselves&#13;
levels to operate, maintain, and manage water services              have been subject to governance instability with rapid&#13;
appropriately in many municipalities.8 The replacement              turnover at the board and senior management levels.10&#13;
of the old apprenticeship training for artisans with a new&#13;
approach has not been a success and there has been a                In order to address these challenges, the South African&#13;
serious loss of good artisan skills in the sector. There has        government, through collaboration between the&#13;
been a serious reduction in the number of engineers active          Department of Cooperative Governance and Traditional&#13;
in municipalities to manage large infrastructure investment         Affairs, the Department of Water Affairs and other&#13;
programs and many managers lack the necessary skills and            government departments, is implementing an intensive&#13;
experience.                                                         turnaround strategy for local government.11&#13;
&#13;
There are also governance failures within local government,         This second Country Status Overview (CSO2) was&#13;
the tier of government responsible for water services               commissioned by AMCOW and has been produced in&#13;
provision to households in terms of the constitution.               collaboration with the Government of South Africa and&#13;
This has led to inappropriate appointments of staff and             other stakeholders. Agreed priority actions to tackle these&#13;
interference in the day-to-day operations of the service, to        challenges, and ensure finance is effectively turned into&#13;
the detriment of the overall functioning and sustainability.9       services, have been identified here.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Agreed priority actions to tackle these challenges, and ensure finance is effectively&#13;
turned into services, are:&#13;
&#13;
   Institutional framework&#13;
   â&#128;¢	   Clarify the respective roles and responsibilities of the Departments of Cooperative Governance and Traditional Affairs&#13;
        and the Department of Water Affairs with respect to an effective turnaround in the performance of water services in&#13;
        municipalities, and clarify the respective roles of the departments of Human Settlements and Water with respect to&#13;
        sanitation.&#13;
   â&#128;¢	   Strengthen accountability by allocating responsibility for water services from district municipalities to local&#13;
        municipalities where local municipalities are performing this function.&#13;
   â&#128;¢	   Initiate an open debate on the respective merits of decentralized delivery of services versus regionalized delivery&#13;
        taking into account local circumstances.&#13;
   â&#128;¢	   Strengthen mechanisms to enforce compliance with legislated standards.&#13;
   â&#128;¢	   Introduce minimum competency requirements for municipal water management.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   Financing&#13;
   â&#128;¢	 Initiate a study to understand the reasons for high capital costs and to make recommendations for improving value&#13;
      for money in water and sanitation investment.&#13;
   â&#128;¢	 Increase support to NGOs active in the sector.&#13;
   â&#128;¢	 Actively increase the use of loan finance in the sector.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   Monitoring and evaluation&#13;
   â&#128;¢	   Develop a clearer understanding of recent trends in access to services.&#13;
   â&#128;¢	   Simplify and rationalize local government reporting requirements for water supply and sanitation.&#13;
   â&#128;¢	   Improve understanding of service outcomes, particularly health-related outcomes in relation to water and sanitation&#13;
        investments.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                          3&#13;
&amp;#12;An AMCOW Country Status Overview&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Rural water supply&#13;
    â&#128;¢	   Undertake more regular surveys on the functionality and performance of rural water supply schemes.&#13;
    â&#128;¢	   Develop a better understanding of the factors constraining the sustainability of rural water supplies and how these&#13;
         can be addressed.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Urban water supply&#13;
    â&#128;¢	   Improve the quality of urban water management with a view to sound asset management, best practice network&#13;
         management, and appropriate pricing to ensure adequate maintenance, timely replacement of infrastructure,&#13;
         reduced nonrevenue water (water losses and unaccounted-for water), and wise and effective use of public resources.&#13;
         Implement a sound management development program for water managers.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Rural sanitation and hygiene&#13;
    â&#128;¢	   Pilot a more demand-orientated approach to the provision of rural sanitation.&#13;
    â&#128;¢	   Investigate the extent and seriousness of VIP latrine emptying challenges and the implications of these for policy,&#13;
         technology choice, and future investment programs.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Urban sanitation and hygiene&#13;
    â&#128;¢	 Develop a priority national initiative on sanitation in informal settlements, particularly in large cities, pilot new&#13;
       approaches and seek to take these to scale.&#13;
    â&#128;¢	 Explore new service delivery models for high density settlements where insecurity of tenure makes planning and&#13;
       implementing standard waterborne sanitation solutions difficult.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
4&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                           Water Supply and Sanitation in South Africa: Turning Finance into Services for 2015 and Beyond&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Contents&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
	                                ........................................................................................................................... 6&#13;
       Acronyms and Abbreviations.&#13;
&#13;
1.	                .................................................................................................................................................... 7&#13;
       Introduction.&#13;
&#13;
2.	                                                ............................................................................................... 8&#13;
       Sector Overview: Coverage and Finance Trends.&#13;
&#13;
3.	                                                  ......................................................................................... 11&#13;
       Reform Context: Introducing the CSO2 Scorecard.&#13;
&#13;
4.	    Institutional Framework................................................................................................................................. 14&#13;
&#13;
5.	                                    .................................................................................................................. 16&#13;
       Financing and its Implementation.&#13;
&#13;
6.	    Sector Monitoring and Evaluation.................................................................................................................. 18&#13;
&#13;
7.	    Subsector: Rural Water Supply....................................................................................................................... 20&#13;
&#13;
8.	    Subsector: Urban Water Supply..................................................................................................................... 22&#13;
&#13;
9.	    Subsector: Rural Sanitation and Hygiene........................................................................................................ 24&#13;
&#13;
10.	   Subsector: Urban Sanitation and Hygiene...................................................................................................... 26&#13;
&#13;
	      Notes and References.................................................................................................................................... 28&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                        5&#13;
&amp;#12;An AMCOW Country Status Overview&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Acronyms and Abbreviations&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
AfDB	        African Development Bank                     NGO	      Nongovernmental organization&#13;
AMCOW	       African Ministersâ&#128;&#153; Council on Water          O&amp;M	      Operations and maintenance&#13;
CAPEX	       Capital expenditure                          OPEX	     Operations expenditure&#13;
COGTA	       (Department of) Cooperative Governance and   RSH	      Rural sanitation and hygiene&#13;
             Traditional Affairs                          RWS	      Rural water supply&#13;
CSO2	        Country Status Overviews (second round)      SALGA	    South African Local Government Association&#13;
DWA	         Department of Water Affairs                  SWAp	     Sector-Wide Approach&#13;
GDP	         Gross domestic product                       UNICEF	   United Nations Childrenâ&#128;&#153;s Fund&#13;
GNI	         Gross national income                        USH	      Urban sanitation and hygiene&#13;
HH	          Household                                    UWS	      Urban water supply&#13;
JMP	         Joint Monitoring Programme (UNICEF/ WHO)     	&#13;
kl	          kilo liter                                   VIP	      Ventilated improved pit (latrine)&#13;
l/c/d	       liters per capita per day                    WASH	     Water, sanitation and hygiene&#13;
M&amp;E	         Monitoring and evaluation                    WHO	      World Health Organization&#13;
m	           meter                                        	&#13;
MDG	         Millennium Development Goal                  WSP	      Water and Sanitation Program&#13;
MIC	         Middle income country&#13;
&#13;
Exchange rate: US$1 = 7.34 South African Rand.12&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
6&#13;
&amp;#12;                                             Water Supply and Sanitation in South Africa: Turning Finance into Services for 2015 and Beyond&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
1.	 Introduction&#13;
&#13;
The African Ministersâ&#128;&#153; Council on Water (AMCOW) commissioned the production of a second round of Country Status&#13;
Overviews (CSOs) to better understand what underpins progress in water supply and sanitation and what its member&#13;
governments can do to accelerate that progress across countries in Sub-Saharan Africa (SSA).13 AMCOW delegated this&#13;
task to the World Bankâ&#128;&#153;s Water and Sanitation Program and the African Development Bank which are implementing&#13;
it in close partnership with UNICEF and WHO in over 30 countries across SSA. This CSO2 report has been produced in&#13;
collaboration with the Government of South Africa and other stakeholders during 2009/10.&#13;
&#13;
The analysis aims to help countries assess their own service delivery pathways for turning finance into water supply and&#13;
sanitation services in each of four subsectors: rural and urban water supply, and rural and urban sanitation and hygiene.&#13;
The CSO2 analysis has three main components: a review of past coverage; a costing model to assess the adequacy of&#13;
future investments; and a scorecard which allows diagnosis of particular bottlenecks along the service delivery pathway.&#13;
The CSO2â&#128;&#153;s contribution is to answer not only whether past trends and future finance are sufficient to meet sector&#13;
targets, but what specific issues need to be addressed to ensure finance is effectively turned into accelerated coverage in&#13;
water supply and sanitation. In this spirit, specific priority actions have been identified through consultation. A synthesis&#13;
report, available separately, presents best practice and shared learning to help realize these priority actions.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                         7&#13;
&amp;#12;An AMCOW Country Status Overview&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
2.	 Sector Overview:&#13;
    Coverage and Finance Trends&#13;
&#13;
Coverage: Assessing Past Progress                                                met the MDG targets. The key reason for the difference is&#13;
                                                                                 that the South African data uses different definitions for&#13;
The CSO2 compares countriesâ&#128;&#153; own estimates of coverage                           an acceptable service compared to the JMP data. For the&#13;
with data from the UNICEF/WHO Joint Monitoring                                   South African government, an acceptable basic level of&#13;
Programme (JMP).14 The impact of these different coverage                        service is a piped water supply within 200 m of a dwelling&#13;
estimates on investment requirements is also assessed.                           and a basic sanitation facility is regarded as a VIP latrine&#13;
                                                                                 (or equivalent). These definitions are for a higher level of&#13;
According to South African data and definitions, access                          service compared to the JMP definitions which refer to&#13;
to water infrastructure in South Africa improved from 58                         only improved water sources and improved sanitation&#13;
percent in 1994 to 91 percent in 2009. Access to sanitation                      (including ordinary pit latrines).&#13;
infrastructure, starting from a lower base, improved from&#13;
34 percent to 76 percent in the same period (Figure                              Investment Requirements: Testing the&#13;
1).* Accordingly, South Africa has met the Millennium                            Sufficiency of Finance&#13;
Development Goal (MDG) targets for water supply and&#13;
sanitation.                                                                      Methodology. South Africa has set itself ambitious&#13;
                                                                                 coverage targets, aiming for universal coverage for both&#13;
This report accepts that South Africa has met the MDG                            water supply and sanitation by 2014. The required capital&#13;
target with respect to water supply even though the                              investments (including major rehabilitation) have been&#13;
JMP data differs from the South African data. In terms                           calculated using a target of 2015 (rather than 2014)&#13;
of the JMP data, South Africa started from a higher                              to align with the approach used in other countries and&#13;
coverage base in 1990 and has made slower progress. The                          for ease of comparison between countries. The CSO2&#13;
conclusion from this data set is that South Africa has not                       costing model has been used, incorporating local unit cost&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 1&#13;
Progress in water supply and sanitation coverage&#13;
&#13;
Water supply                                                                     Sanitation&#13;
&#13;
           100%                                                                             100%&#13;
           80%                                                                              80%&#13;
Coverage&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                 Coverage&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
           60%                                                                              60%&#13;
           40%                                                                              40%&#13;
           20%                                                                              20%&#13;
            0%                                                                               0%&#13;
              1985	 1990	 1995	 2000	 2005	 2010	 2015	 2020                                   1985	 1990	 1995	 2000	 2005	 2010	 2015	 2020&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                  Government estimates         Government target                                   Government estimates          Government target&#13;
                  JMP estimates                MDG target                                          JMP estimates                 MDG target&#13;
&#13;
Sources: JMP 2010 Report and Department of Water Affairs (DWA).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
* Official update 2010 report: 59 percent in 1994 to 93 percent in 2010 for water and 48 percent in 1994 to 79 percent in 2010 for sanitation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
8&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                Water Supply and Sanitation in South Africa: Turning Finance into Services for 2015 and Beyond&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
estimates (based on a recent cost survey of engineering               investments are likely to be underestimated and hence that&#13;
consultancies) and a technology mix assumed to remain                 anticipated investments are inadequate. The South African&#13;
constant over the period. There is a concern that the                 government estimates that the required investment to&#13;
CSO2 model does not adequately account for the water                  meet the total backlog (including the upgrading of water&#13;
resource development costs (dams and regional scheme                  services in informal settlements in association with the&#13;
components) for rural water supply investments, leading               housing program) by 2014 is R82 billion (US$10.2 billion),&#13;
to an underestimation of investment requirements for                  including an investment in bulk regional infrastructure of&#13;
rural water supply. This issue is not as pronounced for               R36 billion (US$4.5 billion).15&#13;
urban water supply because coverage is already very&#13;
high. However, the country requires major investments                 Sanitation CAPEX. In the case of sanitation, the&#13;
in new large urban water augmentation schemes over                    anticipated CAPEX is US$546 million per year, compared&#13;
the next 20 years. These investments have not been                    to a calculated required investment of US$1,218 million&#13;
taken into account in the model. Lastly, in the case of               per year, revealing a gap of US$672 per year. The&#13;
sanitation, it is government policy to provide only flush             South African government estimates that the required&#13;
toilets in urban areas. At the same time there is a need to           investment to meet the total backlog (including the&#13;
rehabilitate, upgrade, and expand wastewater treatment                upgrading of sanitation in informal settlements in&#13;
works. This results in high investment requirements for               association with the housing program) by 2014 is&#13;
urban sanitation. Anticipated investments were obtained               R67 billion (US$8.5 billion).16&#13;
from government medium-term (three-year) budgets&#13;
extrapolated into the future (Figure 2).                              It should be noted that the calculated investment&#13;
                                                                      requirements are to provide universal access by 2015 (and&#13;
Water CAPEX. Anticipated capital investment (CAPEX)                   not the MDG targets which have already been met). These&#13;
for water supply is just under US$1 billion per year,                 targets are ambitious.&#13;
compared to a calculated required investment of US$857&#13;
million per year (CSO2 estimate). Although this indicates             For these investments to be sustainable, the resources&#13;
that the anticipated investment is sufficient, the required           necessary to operate and maintain assets need to&#13;
investment calculation does not adequately cater for                  be mobilized on an ongoing basis. In South Africa,&#13;
the future higher costs of rural water supply schemes.                municipalities are responsible for operating and&#13;
Consequently, it may be concluded that the required                   maintaining assets (in most cases). Municipalities are&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 2&#13;
Required vs. anticipated (public) and assumed (household) expenditure&#13;
&#13;
Water supply                                                          Sanitation&#13;
&#13;
               Required CAPEX                                                          Required CAPEX&#13;
                                                        Required                                                                Required&#13;
                                                         OPEX                                                                    OPEX&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
0	                  500	               1000	             1500         0	             500	           1000	            1500	           2000&#13;
                             US$ million/year                                                        US$ million/year&#13;
&#13;
     Public CAPEX (anticipated)                                            Public CAPEX/software (anticipated)&#13;
     Household CAPEX (assumed)                                             Household CAPEX (assumed)&#13;
                                                                           CAPEX deficit&#13;
&#13;
Source: CSO2 costing.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                            9&#13;
&amp;#12;An AMCOW Country Status Overview&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table 1&#13;
Coverage and investment figures&#13;
&#13;
	 Coverage	 Target	 Population	    CAPEX	      Anticipated	                                                 Assumed	 Total&#13;
			                  requiring	 requirements	 public CAPEX	                                                    HH	   deficit&#13;
			                    access			                                                                             CAPEX&#13;
	                           1990	 2009	 2015				                 Total	 Public	 Domestic	 External	 Total&#13;
 	                            %	        %	      %	     â&#128;&#152;000/year					US$ million/year&#13;
&#13;
 Rural water supply	        40%	        82%	   100%	      433	    314	 314	       397	        27	    424	        0	       -&#13;
 Urban water supply	        75%	        96%	   100%	      617	    542	 488	       509	         8	    517	       57	       -&#13;
 Water supply total	        58%	        91%	   100%	    1,050	    857	 802	       906	        35	    942	       57	       -&#13;
 Rural sanitation	          13%	        61%	   100%	    1,114	    405	 405	       162	         8	    170	        0	     235&#13;
 Urban sanitation	          53%	        85%	   100%	    1,179	    813	 732	       336	         3	    339	       38	     437&#13;
 Sanitation total	          34%	        76%	   100%	    2,292	   1218	 1137	      497	        11	    508	       38	     672&#13;
&#13;
Sources: For coverage, JMP and DWA.17&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
required to set aside money for the depreciation of the              Table 2&#13;
assets, and to budget appropriately for the operation and            Annual O&amp;M&#13;
maintenance (O&amp;M) of the assets.&#13;
                                                                        Subsector	                          O&amp;M&#13;
                                                                        	                              US$ million/year&#13;
The total annual operating and maintenance costs are&#13;
                                                                        Rural water supply	                   149&#13;
estimated to be US$530 million per year for water supply&#13;
                                                                        Urban water supply	                   381&#13;
and US$493 million per year for sanitation (Table 2). The&#13;
                                                                        Water supply total	                   530&#13;
South African government supports municipalities to&#13;
                                                                        Rural sanitation	                      93&#13;
provide services to poor households through the equitable&#13;
                                                                        Urban sanitation	                     400&#13;
share grant (an operating grant). The total grant amounted&#13;
                                                                        Sanitation total	                     493&#13;
to around US$3.2 billion in 2009. Reliable estimates on&#13;
                                                                     Source: CSO2 costing.&#13;
the share of this allocated to water supply and sanitation&#13;
by municipalities are not available. As coverage and levels&#13;
of service increase, the level of government support                 The investment requirements for sanitation could be&#13;
necessary to maintain viable municipal services will also            lowered if different assumptions were made with respect&#13;
increase. This will place additional demand on the central           to service levels.&#13;
government budget.&#13;
                                                                     These considerations are only part of the picture.&#13;
South Africa has a free basic water policy. The sound                Bottlenecks can in fact occur throughout the service&#13;
intention of this policy is to supply all poor households with       delivery pathwayâ&#128;&#148;all the institutions, processes, and actors&#13;
a basic water supply (25 l/c/d) at no cost to the household.         that translate sector funding into sustainable services.&#13;
Unfortunately, the unintended consequence of this policy             Where the pathway is well developed, sector funding&#13;
is a frequent expectation on the part of households to               should turn into services at the estimated unit costs.&#13;
receive free water. Consequently, municipalities receive             Where it is not, the above investment requirements may&#13;
almost no revenue from households living in rural areas,             be gross underestimates. The rest of this report evaluates&#13;
even where the level of service provided may be a yard               the service delivery pathway in its entirety, locating the&#13;
connection. This situation creates a very high dependence            bottlenecks and presenting the agreed priority actions to&#13;
on government grants to sustain the service.                         help address them.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
10&#13;
&amp;#12;                                             Water Supply and Sanitation in South Africa: Turning Finance into Services for 2015 and Beyond&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
3.	 Reform Context:&#13;
	 Introducing the CSO2 Scorecard&#13;
&#13;
Prior to 1994, municipalities were responsible for providing       involvement in project design and implementation, to that&#13;
water supply and sanitation (sewerage) services in cities and      of sector leader, supporter, and regulator.&#13;
towns. The traditional rural areas were the responsibility of&#13;
satellite â&#128;&#152;homelandâ&#128;&#153; governments set up by the apartheid           This recent history puts the service delivery pathway in&#13;
state. In 1994, the new democratic government assumed              context, which can then be explored in detail using the&#13;
responsibility for water supply and sanitation nationally          CSO2 scorecard, an assessment tool providing a snapshot&#13;
and embarked on an ambitious program of delivering basic           of reform progress along the service delivery pathway. The&#13;
services, primarily in rural areas. A national Community           CSO2 scorecard assesses the building blocks of service&#13;
Water Supply and Sanitation Program was established                delivery in turn: three building blocks which relate to&#13;
with dedicated funding from the national government.               enabling services, three which relate to developing new&#13;
The programâ&#128;&#148;built on the experience of the NGO, Mvula              services, and three which relate to sustaining services.&#13;
Trust, established a few years previouslyâ&#128;&#148;had strong               Each building block is assessed against specific indicators&#13;
elements of community consultation and participation,              and scored from 1 to 3 accordingly.19&#13;
required community contributions, used local labor to&#13;
build schemes, and involved communities in the O&amp;M of              A major driver for sector reform has been the national&#13;
schemes.18                                                         political priority to rapidly provide basic services to&#13;
                                                                   households previously disadvantaged under the apartheid&#13;
Political and social pressures to accelerate delivery              government. A second driver of reform has been the&#13;
increased over time. In response to these pressures, the           Constitutional imperative to devolve the responsibility of&#13;
private sector was used in regional large-scale build-             water services to local government. A third driver of reform&#13;
operate-train-transfer contracts. The pace of delivery was         has been the reform of inter-governmental funding,&#13;
substantially increased, but at a high cost per household          moving from dedicated and project-based funding to an&#13;
served. In 2000, a free basic water policy was introduced as       approach of â&#128;&#156;budget supportâ&#128;&#157; between national and local&#13;
part of a broader commitment by government to provide              government, within a stable and predictable medium-term&#13;
free basic services. In 2003, rural water services assets          (three-year) budgeting framework.&#13;
were transferred to local government. This was in line&#13;
with the constitutional allocation of powers and functions         The enabling environment for facilitating service&#13;
between national and local government, following the               delivery in South Africa is well developed. The policies&#13;
principle of subsidiarity contained within the Constitution.       and legislation were developed early in the reform&#13;
Meanwhile, local government had undergone its own                  process (with sanitation policy lagging a little behind),&#13;
restructuring, with the boundaries of local government             and provided a sound basis on which to proceed. For&#13;
reconfigured to span both urban and rural areas. In parallel       example, the Community Water Supply and Sanitation&#13;
to this, governmentâ&#128;&#153;s funding policies were reformed. The          program was accompanied by a White Paper, one of&#13;
dedicated water supply and sanitation funding (previously          the first policy papers of the new government. Sector&#13;
allocated to the national department responsible for water)        legislation was promulgated within four years of the new&#13;
was aggregated with other grants into a two-channel                government coming into power. These policies enabled&#13;
municipal grant system: a conditional capital grant and an         a consistent Sector-Wide Approach (SWAp) to be&#13;
unconditional operating grant. The capital grant, called the       developed and implemented. Budget reform facilitated&#13;
Municipal Infrastructure Grant, was intended to support            delivery too. Initially, dedicated program budgets were&#13;
investment in municipal infrastructure serving poor people.        created at the national level. Later, this evolved to budget&#13;
The role of national government thus changed from direct           support to municipalities, when they became responsible&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                        11&#13;
&amp;#12;An AMCOW Country Status Overview&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
for providing and sustaining services. The parallel reform      Figure 3&#13;
of local government budgeting also supported the                Average scorecard results for enabling,&#13;
process. The Masibambane (â&#128;&#156;let us work togetherâ&#128;&#157;)               sustaining, and developing service delivery, and&#13;
program promoted a SWAp with donor support.20 For               peer-group comparison&#13;
these reasons, South Africa compares well against its&#13;
                                                                                            Enabling&#13;
peer group of middle-income countries (MICs),21 with a&#13;
higher average score for enabling building blocks (see&#13;
Figure 3).&#13;
&#13;
South Africa has also performed well with respect to&#13;
the â&#128;&#152;developingâ&#128;&#153; building blocks. The stable budgeting&#13;
framework has enabled good spending performance and&#13;
reporting on outcomes against budget. Criteria for the&#13;
allocation of grant budgets from national government to&#13;
local government are clearly defined and allocations are&#13;
equitable. Local governments must involve communities&#13;
                                                                        Sustaining                      Developing&#13;
in their planning and budgeting processes in terms of&#13;
legislative requirements. The Fiscal and Finance Commission        South Africa average scores&#13;
regularly reviews the fairness of budget allocations and           Averages, MICs&#13;
outcomes. Service output performance is generally&#13;
                                                                Source: CSO2 scorecard.&#13;
good. Subsidies are largely spent as intended, drinking&#13;
water quality is monitored, and hygiene promotion and&#13;
monitoring tools have been developed.                           Sections 4 to 6 highlight progress and challenges across&#13;
                                                                three thematic areasâ&#128;&#148;the institutional framework, finance,&#13;
The main challenges for South Africa lie in the area of         and monitoring and evaluation (M&amp;E)â&#128;&#148;benchmarking&#13;
sustaining services. Maintenance expenditure is not             South Africa against its peer countries based on a&#13;
adequate and there are insufficient resources from tariffs      grouping by gross national income. The related indicators&#13;
and subsidies to properly sustain the service. There are also   are extracted from the scorecard and presented in charts&#13;
critical skills shortages, particularly at the technical and    at the beginning of each section. The scorecards for&#13;
management levels. Nevertheless, South Africa performed         each subsector are presented in their entirety in sections&#13;
well relative to its peers in this area too.                    7 to 10.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
12&#13;
&amp;#12;                                            Water Supply and Sanitation in South Africa: Turning Finance into Services for 2015 and Beyond&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table 3&#13;
Key dates in the reform of the sector in South Africa&#13;
&#13;
Year	              Event&#13;
1994	              First democratic elections and new emphasis on meeting the basic needs of all citizens. Community&#13;
                   Water Supply and Sanitation White Paper adopted and investment program launched&#13;
1996	              Constitution finalized and adopted, allocating the functions of water supply and sanitation services&#13;
                   provision to local government&#13;
1997	              Water Services Act promulgated, defining the role of DWA as regulator, the role of water boards&#13;
                   as bulk providers and the role of municipalities as responsible for provision&#13;
1998	              National Water Act promulgated, redefining water rights in South Africa (away from riparian and&#13;
                   first-use system) and establishing a new framework to manage and regulate water resources&#13;
2000, 2001	        Democratic local government established, local government legislation introduced, new&#13;
                   decentralized financial framework introduction. Basic Household Sanitation Policy adopted, with&#13;
                   a focus on grant-funded basic sanitation provision in rural areas&#13;
2002	              Free Basic Water Policy introduced with intention to provide all poor households with a free basic&#13;
                   supply of water (25 l/c/d or 6 kl per connection per month)&#13;
2003	              The Strategic Framework for Water Services approved. Updated water policy document. More&#13;
                   emphasis is placed on performance, sustainability, and moving to higher levels of service&#13;
2000 to 2010	      DWA shifts its role from implementer and operator of schemes to supporter of local government.&#13;
                   A Joint National Support Strategy adopted (2007)&#13;
2009	              The sanitation function is moved from DWA to the National Department of Sustainable Human&#13;
                   Settlements (housing)&#13;
2010	              DWA changes emphasis from support to regulation. The National Water Services Regulation&#13;
                   Strategy is adopted, emphasizing drinking water quality and wastewater quality monitoring&#13;
                   through Blue and Green Drop programs. Sanitation allocated to national Department of Human&#13;
                   Settlements&#13;
2010	              Turnaround strategy for local government approved by Cabinet and the implementation of&#13;
                   the strategy rolled out by Department of Cooperative Governance and Traditional Affairs, in&#13;
                   collaboration with DWA and other government departments&#13;
2010	              National Planning Commission established in the Office of the President. Water identified as an&#13;
                   important focus area for the Commission&#13;
&#13;
Source: Various.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                       13&#13;
&amp;#12;An AMCOW Country Status Overview&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
4.	 Institutional Framework&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Priority actions for institutional framework&#13;
  â&#128;¢	    Clarify the respective roles and responsibilities of the Departments of Cooperative Governance and&#13;
        Traditional Affairs and the Department of Water Affairs with respect to an effective turnaround in the&#13;
        performance of water services in municipalities.&#13;
  â&#128;¢	    Clarify the respective roles of the departments of Human Settlements and Water with respect to&#13;
        sanitation.&#13;
  â&#128;¢	    Reduce/diffuse accountability by allocating responsibility for water services from district municipalities to&#13;
        local municipalities where local municipalities are performing this function.&#13;
  â&#128;¢	    Initiate an open debate on the respective merits of decentralized delivery of services versus regionalized&#13;
        delivery taking into account local circumstances.&#13;
  â&#128;¢	    Investigate factors underlying recent trends in service delivery.&#13;
  â&#128;¢	    Strengthen mechanisms to enforce compliance with legislated standards.&#13;
  â&#128;¢	    Introduce minimum competency requirements for water management.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
South Africa has established clear sector goals and targets,   Cooperative Governance and Traditional Affairs (COGTA)&#13;
has a sound policy and legislative framework for the sector,   has oversight of local government while the Department&#13;
and has clearly defined the roles and responsibilities of      of Water Affairs (DWA) supports and regulates local&#13;
institutions active in the sector. The Department of           government with respect to water services (in collaboration&#13;
                                                               with COGTA and the provincial governments).&#13;
&#13;
Figure 4&#13;
                                                               For these reasons, scores for related scorecard indicators&#13;
Scorecard indicator scores relating to institutional&#13;
                                                               compare well relative to other middle income countries&#13;
framework compared to peer group (see&#13;
                                                               participating in the CSO2 (Figure 4). Nevertheless, there are&#13;
endnotes)22&#13;
                                                               some gaps and challenges. The responsibility for sanitation&#13;
                                                               has recently been reallocated to the Department of Human&#13;
                          RWS&#13;
                                                               Settlements and the relative roles of this department and&#13;
                                                               the DWA must still be worked out. National government&#13;
                                                               sets national targets but responsibility rests with local&#13;
                                                               government to deliver. National government provides&#13;
                                                               general budget support to local government (capital and&#13;
     USH                               UWS                     operating grants) but does not control how this money is&#13;
                                                               locally allocated and spent. There is a lack of clarity with&#13;
                                                               respect to the responsibility for hygiene promotion and&#13;
                                                               how this relates to new sanitation investments. These and&#13;
                                                               other institutional challenges are elaborated below.&#13;
                          RSH&#13;
&#13;
     South Africa average scores                               Respective roles of Departments of Water and&#13;
     Averages, MICs&#13;
                                                               Human Settlements. The Water Services Act addresses&#13;
                                                               both water supply and sanitation and gives the DWA a&#13;
Source: CSO2 scorecard.                                        very clear regulatory role with respect to both water supply&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
14&#13;
&amp;#12;                                              Water Supply and Sanitation in South Africa: Turning Finance into Services for 2015 and Beyond&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
and sanitation services. The implications of allocating the         Urban bias and preference for service&#13;
responsibility for sanitation to the Department of Human            upgrades. The decentralization of service delivery to&#13;
Settlements need to be addressed within this context.               local government, together with the design of the local&#13;
                                                                    government system, has arguably led to a tendency&#13;
Targets and decentralization. There is an inherent                  towards urban bias as well as a preference for investment&#13;
tension between the setting of national targets                     in service upgrades rather than provision of services&#13;
and achievement of these targets in the context of                  to marginalized rural communities. Whereas national&#13;
decentralized service delivery. National government can             government prioritized investments to communities&#13;
increase budget support to local government but does                without services, and provided a basic level of service,&#13;
not control local service delivery choices. These are subject       the outcomes-based survey evidence suggests that&#13;
to local democratic processes within a national legislative         spending has shifted to providing higher levels of service&#13;
framework. For example, the equitable share to local                possibly at the expense of providing basic services to the&#13;
government is an unconditional operating grant.                     unserved.23&#13;
&#13;
Accountability between         tiers   of   local                   Community-based operations. Although South&#13;
government. A distinctive feature of South African                  Africa has good experience with community-based&#13;
local government is its two-tier structure, with wall-              operation of rural water supply systems, there appears&#13;
to-wall local government at both the local and district             to have been a tendency for municipalities to take over&#13;
level. The responsibility for water provision is allocated          these operations itself. Ironically, the decentralization&#13;
to either the district or local municipality. However, it is        of service delivery to municipalities seems to have been&#13;
common practice for a district municipality (that has been          accompanied by a â&#128;&#152;centralization tendencyâ&#128;&#153; among the&#13;
allocated the responsibility for water services) to ask a local     municipalities themselves.&#13;
municipality within its area to undertake water services&#13;
provision on its behalf. Problems have been experienced             Role of the private sector. South African water&#13;
with this arrangement, which are typically related to clarity       policy and legislation contain a policy bias towards public&#13;
of roles and responsibilities, allocations of budgets, and          management of water services. Nevertheless, South&#13;
addressing instances of poor performance.                           Africa has had both varied and good experiences with&#13;
                                                                    the participation of the private sector. The build-operate-&#13;
Local government capacity. Many municipalities                      train-transfer contracts to deliver rural water supply&#13;
struggle to attract and retain the necessary managerial             infrastructure at scale were arguably a success if measured&#13;
and technical skills and experience to manage water                 against the primary goals of scale and speed. The five-&#13;
services operations adequately.                                     year management contract for Johannesburg Water is&#13;
                                                                    widely regarded as a success. Perspectives differ on the&#13;
The role of water boards. Prior to 1994, water                      merits and benefits of the small number of concession&#13;
boards sold bulk treated water to municipalities and                and lease contracts. These are generally not favored by&#13;
mines. After 1994 the role of water boards was expanded.            municipalities. Nevertheless, the private sector still plays&#13;
From 1994 to 2003 some water boards operated rural                  an active role in supporting municipalities. This role goes&#13;
water supply schemes on behalf of the DWA. These assets             beyond its extensive role in design and construction, and&#13;
were then transferred to local government. Water boards             includes management and operational support.&#13;
can still play a support role to municipalities, and can be&#13;
contracted by municipalities to manage and/or operate               Pricing. National government sets norms and standards&#13;
municipal water systems on behalf of municipalities. There          for the pricing of water, but local government is free&#13;
is a national debate under way on the future role of water          to determine its own price levels within this guiding&#13;
boards. Should water boards be mandated to manage                   framework.&#13;
bulk and/or retail water services in terms of a regionalized&#13;
provision model (such as that in existence in Brazil)? What         Enforcement. The relative emphasis between national&#13;
are the Constitutional implications of this choice? Bearing         government support to local government and the&#13;
in mind that the full decentralization of service delivery          enforcement of regulated standards needs to be clarified.&#13;
responsibilities to local government is very recent (2003),         Mechanisms to effectively enforce compliance need to be&#13;
is it too soon to be reconsidering this choice?                     strengthened.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                         15&#13;
&amp;#12;An AMCOW Country Status Overview&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
5.	 Financing and its Implementation&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Priority actions for financing and its implementation&#13;
  â&#128;¢	    Initiate a study to understand the reasons for high capital costs and to make recommendations for&#13;
        improving value for money in water supply and sanitation investment.&#13;
  â&#128;¢	    Increase support to NGOs active in the sector.&#13;
  â&#128;¢	    Actively increase the use of loan finance in the sector.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Substantial reform of South Africaâ&#128;&#153;s public financial          Key reforms have helped establish this sound financial&#13;
management policies and processes stands out as a major        framework: of budgeting, financial management, and&#13;
achievement and a key enabler of effective spending on         government grants. South Africa adopted a medium-term&#13;
water supply and sanitation investments. South Africa          income and expenditure budgeting framework soon after&#13;
adopted a sectorwide approach early on, set targets            1994 at the national level and then extended this to the&#13;
to achieve universal coverage, mobilized its resources,        local government level later on. This created a stable and&#13;
developed the necessary plans and translated these             predictable basis for planning investments.&#13;
into budgets, monitored spending against budgets and&#13;
achieved a high level of spending. Consequently, South         The budget reform was accompanied by a more extensive&#13;
Africa has performed well relative to its peers (Figure 5).    reform of the financial management, accounting and&#13;
                                                               reporting systems, including the development of new&#13;
                                                               legislation.25 This created the necessary basis for sound&#13;
Figure 5&#13;
                                                               accounting standards, common reporting, and clearly&#13;
Scorecard indicator scores relating to financing&#13;
                                                               regulated procurement processes. These reforms have&#13;
and its implementation, compared to peer&#13;
                                                               played a very significant enabling role for government in&#13;
group24&#13;
                                                               general, and have also benefited the water sector.&#13;
&#13;
                          RWS                                  Grant reform also began soon after 1994, with a&#13;
                                                               dedicated grant to support the Community Water Supply&#13;
                                                               and Sanitation program. This grant was managed by&#13;
                                                               the national DWA which procured directly on a project-&#13;
                                                               by-project basis. This proved to be cumbersome and&#13;
       USH                              UWS&#13;
                                                               the process of procurement was accelerated through&#13;
                                                               contracting intermediary â&#128;&#152;implementing agentsâ&#128;&#153;. These&#13;
                                                               agents in turn procured on a project-by-project basis.&#13;
                                                               The practice evolved to larger build-operate-train-transfer&#13;
                                                               contracts with the private sector. To coincide with the&#13;
                          RSH&#13;
                                                               reform of local government, the numerous sector-&#13;
     South Africa average scores                               based government grants were consolidated into a two-&#13;
     Averages, MICs                                            channel grant system comprising a capital grant and an&#13;
Source: CSO2 scorecard.                                        unconditional operating grant. These grants are, in effect,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
16&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                   Water Supply and Sanitation in South Africa: Turning Finance into Services for 2015 and Beyond&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
budget support grants to local government. The grants                    Crowding out private finance. It is possible that&#13;
are stable, predictable, and allocated equitably between                 the very significant increases in government grants have&#13;
municipalities.26                                                        crowded out the use of loan finance in some municipalities.&#13;
                                                                         The extensive availability of grants may also have lowered&#13;
Notwithstanding these significant achievements, there                    household willingness to invest in water supply and&#13;
still is room for improvement in some areas. These are                   sanitation improvements.&#13;
elaborated below.&#13;
                                                                         Value for money. South Africaâ&#128;&#153;s average per capita&#13;
Support to NGOs. Over 95 percent of sector funding                       investment requirement is expensive compared to the&#13;
has been direct government funding and loan financing.                   region (Figure 6). Although this is partly the result&#13;
There is very limited donor support (Figure 6). The majority             of higher service levels, this also points to possible&#13;
of the donor support has been through a sectorwide                       inefficiencies within a sector context of investment driven&#13;
program called Masibambane.27 An unintended                              by government grants and a lack of strong competitiveness&#13;
consequence of this is that NGOs, historically strong and                in the procurement environment. The South African&#13;
a source of innovation in the sector, have struggled. The                governmentâ&#128;&#153;s estimates of the annual capital investment&#13;
major water NGO, Mvula Trust, for example, must rely on                  requirements are considerably higher than those estimated&#13;
contracts from government to survive.                                    in this report.28&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 6&#13;
Overall annual and per capita investment requirements and contribution from different sources&#13;
&#13;
Rural water supply:                   Urban water supply:            Rural sanitation:                     Urban sanitation:&#13;
Total: $314,000,000                   Total: $542,000,000            Total: $405,000,000                   Total: $813,000,000&#13;
Per capita: $278                      Per capita: $385               Per capita: $213                      Per capita: $420&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Domestic anticipated investment          Assumed household investment&#13;
    External anticipated investment          Gap&#13;
&#13;
Source: CSO2 costing.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                              17&#13;
&amp;#12;An AMCOW Country Status Overview&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
6.	 Sector Monitoring and Evaluation&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Priority actions for sector monitoring and evaluation&#13;
  â&#128;¢	    Develop a clearer understanding of recent trends in access to services.&#13;
  â&#128;¢	    Simplify and rationalize local government reporting requirements for water supply and sanitation.&#13;
  â&#128;¢	    Revise water supply and sanitation access targets.&#13;
  â&#128;¢	    Improve understanding of service outcomes, particularly health-related outcomes in relation to water&#13;
        supply and sanitation investments.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
South Africa has a relatively well-developed monitoring           conducted and these include questions on access to water&#13;
and evaluation (M&amp;E) framework with strong scores on              supply and sanitation, and service quality. Nevertheless,&#13;
related scorecard indicators, relative to its peers (Figure 7).   some areas of monitoring and evaluation can be improved.&#13;
Sector targets are set, reviewed regularly and progress is        Some challenges are elaborated below.&#13;
measured against them. Overall spending on water supply&#13;
and sanitation is identifiable and donor funding is included      Understanding urban and rural performance.&#13;
in government budgets. The equity of subsidy allocations          The design of the local government system (including&#13;
is periodically reviewed. Sector outputs such as drinking         the boundaries, financial system, reporting system and&#13;
water quality and wastewater discharge compliance                 so on) does not lend itself to a clear differentiation and&#13;
are monitored. Regular national household surveys are             understanding of urban and rural subsector performance.&#13;
                                                                  For the purposes of this report, municipalities that serve&#13;
                                                                  metropolitan areas, cities, and large towns are assumed&#13;
Figure 7&#13;
                                                                  to be urban, and municipalities that serve small towns and&#13;
Scorecard indicator scores relating to sector M&amp;E,&#13;
                                                                  the traditional rural areas are assumed to be rural.30&#13;
compared to peer group29&#13;
&#13;
                                                                  Reconciliation of JMP and country baseline&#13;
                           RWS                                    data. There is a large difference between the JMP and&#13;
                                                                  country data for the baseline, though the data is more&#13;
                                                                  closely aligned for 2009.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                  Understanding recent trends in access to&#13;
        USH                               UWS                     services. Different sources of data show different trends&#13;
                                                                  in access to services. The recent general household surveys,&#13;
                                                                  for example, show declining performance in household&#13;
                                                                  access to basic water supply and sanitation services.&#13;
&#13;
                            RSH                                   Understanding financial performance. In the&#13;
     South Africa average scores                                  absence of better financial ring-fencing of the water&#13;
     Averages, MICs                                               services function within municipalities, it is difficult to&#13;
                                                                  properly understand the financial performance of water&#13;
Source: CSO2 scorecard.&#13;
                                                                  services.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
18&#13;
&amp;#12;                                            Water Supply and Sanitation in South Africa: Turning Finance into Services for 2015 and Beyond&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Revising sector targets. The current sector targets (to           Reporting on spending efficiency. There is a need&#13;
achieve universal access by 2014) are unrealistic and need        for a greater emphasis on value for money when reporting&#13;
to be revised.                                                    on grant spending.&#13;
&#13;
Municipal reporting. Municipal reporting on water                 Understanding citizen perspectives. Much of the&#13;
services compliance and performance is poor. Current              reporting on sector performance is â&#128;&#152;technocraticâ&#128;&#153;. These&#13;
reporting requirements are too onerous. Too much detail is        statistics tend to hide poor personsâ&#128;&#153; everyday experiences&#13;
required and reporting requirements to different national         of services. There is a need to deepen understanding of,&#13;
departments are overlapping and duplicated. There is a            and to improve reporting on, citizen perspectives on service&#13;
need for the rationalization and simplification of reporting      access and quality. The â&#128;&#152;citizen voiceâ&#128;&#153; initiative is a good&#13;
requirements.                                                     starting point from which to develop this area further.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                       19&#13;
&amp;#12;An AMCOW Country Status Overview&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
7.	 Subsector: Rural Water Supply&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       Priority actions for rural water supply&#13;
       â&#128;¢	    Improve national-level knowledge of the status of rural water supply schemes, including more regular&#13;
             surveys on their functionality and performance.&#13;
       â&#128;¢	    Develop a better understanding of the factors constraining the sustainability of rural water supplies and&#13;
             how these can be addressed.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
South Africaâ&#128;&#153;s own country data show good progress in             the anticipated CAPEX of over US$400 million per&#13;
access to a piped water supply within 200 meters, starting        year. However, it is likely that the required CAPEX is&#13;
from a low base. The JMP data also shows progress, but            underestimated because the underlying unit costs do not&#13;
from a much higher base and consequently at a slower              take into account the cost of water resource development&#13;
pace. The differences arise from a difference in service          and the high costs of regional schemes. There is very little,&#13;
level definitions.                                                if any, cost-recovery from users, hence the anticipated&#13;
                                                                  capital investment grants will also need to meet the&#13;
For practical reasons, the universal coverage target for          burden of O&amp;M costs. Additional OPEX (and hence grant)&#13;
2014 is unlikely to be met, notwithstanding the trend             requirements are estimated at US$149 million per year.&#13;
shown. The pace of delivery in rural areas has also slowed&#13;
(notwithstanding the simplified linear depiction in Figure        Figure 10 shows the scorecard results for the rural water&#13;
8). There are concerns related to the functionality and           supply service delivery pathway. The scorecard uses a simple&#13;
sustainability of rural water supply schemes.                     color code to indicate: building blocks that are largely&#13;
                                                                  in place, acting as a driver on service delivery (score &gt;2,&#13;
CAPEX requirements are estimated to be about US$314               green); building blocks that are a drag on service delivery&#13;
million per year. These requirements are less than                and require attention (score 1â&#128;&#147;2, yellow); and building&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 8                                                          Figure 9&#13;
Rural water supply coverage                                       Rural water supply investment requirements&#13;
&#13;
           100%&#13;
            80%&#13;
Coverage&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            60%                                                                      Required CAPEX&#13;
                                                                                                                      Required&#13;
            40%                                                                                                        OPEX&#13;
            20%&#13;
            0%&#13;
              1985	 1990	 1995	 2000	 2005	 2010	 2015	 2020     0	          100	         200	        300	   400	      500&#13;
                                                                                          US$ million/year&#13;
                  Government estimates       Government target        Public CAPEX (anticipated)&#13;
                  JMP improved               JMP, piped&#13;
                                                                  Source: CSO2 costing.&#13;
Sources: JMP 2010 Report/DWA.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
20&#13;
&amp;#12;                                             Water Supply and Sanitation in South Africa: Turning Finance into Services for 2015 and Beyond&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 10&#13;
Rural water supply scorecard&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
               Enabling                            Developing                                     Sustaining&#13;
   Policy        Planning   Budget      Expenditure      Equity        Output         Maintenance Expansion          Use&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      3               3         2            3              3              3                 1            2                3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Source: CSO2 scorecard.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
blocks that are inadequate, constituting a barrier to service      Figure 11&#13;
delivery and a priority for reform (score &lt;1, red). As can         Average RWS scorecard scores for enabling,&#13;
be seen, South Africaâ&#128;&#153;s service delivery pathway registers         sustaining, and developing service delivery, and&#13;
high scoresâ&#128;&#148;an impression confirmed by comparing the               peer-group comparison&#13;
average results to its peer group (Figure 11). There are,&#13;
                                                                                         Enabling&#13;
nonetheless, areas for attention around budgeting, and&#13;
improving the sustainability of rural systems:&#13;
&#13;
Enabling environment. The enabling environment for&#13;
rural water supply is generally sound with good policy and&#13;
planning.&#13;
&#13;
Rural water budgets not separately identifiable.&#13;
The local government financial reporting systems do not                                                 Developing&#13;
                                                                         Sustaining&#13;
facilitate the separate identification of spending on rural&#13;
water systems; instead reporting is for water expenditure&#13;
as a whole, which may include both urban and rural                    South Africa average scores&#13;
&#13;
settlements within a municipality.                                    Averages, MICs&#13;
&#13;
                                                                   Source: CSO2 scorecard.&#13;
Uneven knowledge of rural water infrastructure.&#13;
The state of knowledge of the condition and functioning&#13;
of rural water supply assets varies by municipality and, at a      Sustainability of rural water supply systems. The&#13;
national level, is inadequate. Regular national or regional        funding of the O&amp;M costs for rural water supply systems&#13;
surveys are not undertaken.                                        are almost entirely reliant on national government grants.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                        21&#13;
&amp;#12;An AMCOW Country Status Overview&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
8.	 Subsector: Urban Water Supply&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       Priority actions for urban water supply&#13;
       â&#128;¢	    Improve the quality of urban water management with a view to sound asset management, best practice&#13;
             network management, and appropriate pricing to ensure adequate maintenance, timely replacement&#13;
             of infrastructure, reduced water losses and unaccounted-for water, and wise and effective use of public&#13;
             resources. Implement a sound management development program for water managers.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Urban water coverage is 96 percent according to South           investment requirements. This estimate does not take into&#13;
 African Government data, and 99 percent according to            account major bulk water augmentation schemes whose&#13;
 JMP data. The difference is most likely due to the definition   costs are recovered through the water tariff. South Africa&#13;
 of urban areas used in this report.31                           will need to, and plans to, invest significantly in water&#13;
                                                                 resource development costs for its major urban areas.&#13;
 Although this level of coverage is excellent, and includes&#13;
 many households living in informal settlements, some            South Africa performs well in the urban water supply&#13;
 households experience restricted access that may be less        subsector in all of the elements measured in the scorecard&#13;
 than 50 liters per person per day. These problems typically     (Figure 14), and is ahead of its peer group (Figure 15).&#13;
 arise due to technological and management problems              The budgeting system is sound but the local government&#13;
 rather than as a result of policy.                              framework does not facilitate separate identification&#13;
                                                                 of urban (versus rural) expenditure. There are also still&#13;
 The anticipated public CAPEX of over $500 million per           areas of concern related to unaccounted-for water,&#13;
 annum, supplemented by an additional 10 percent user            maintenance expenditure, network asset management,&#13;
 contribution, is sufficient to meet the CSO2â&#128;&#153;s estimate of      and pricing.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Figure 12                                                       Figure 13&#13;
 Urban water supply coverage                                     Urban water supply investment requirements&#13;
&#13;
           100%&#13;
           80%&#13;
Coverage&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
           60%                                                            Required CAPEX&#13;
                                                                                                                   Required&#13;
           40%                                                                                                      OPEX&#13;
           20%&#13;
            0%&#13;
              1985	 1990	 1995	 2000	 2005	 2010	 2015	 2020     0		                          500		                1000&#13;
                                                                                         US$ million/year&#13;
                  Government estimates       Government target      Public CAPEX (anticipated)&#13;
                  JMP improved               JMP, piped             Household CAPEX (assumed)&#13;
&#13;
 Sources: JMP 2010 Report/DWA.                                   Source: CSO2 costing.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
22&#13;
&amp;#12;                                              Water Supply and Sanitation in South Africa: Turning Finance into Services for 2015 and Beyond&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 14&#13;
Urban water supply scorecard&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
               Enabling                             Developing                                      Sustaining&#13;
   Policy        Planning    Budget      Expenditure      Equity        Output       Maintenance Expansion              Use&#13;
&#13;
      3              3          2             3               3             3                 2.5           3              3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Source: CSO2 scorecard.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Reducing unaccounted-for water. South Africa is a                   Figure 15&#13;
water scarce country and needs to use its water resources           Average UWS scorecard scores for enabling,&#13;
wisely. Water losses and unaccounted-for water are                  sustaining, and developing service delivery, and&#13;
excessive compared to best practice.                                peer-group comparison&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                          Enabling&#13;
Maintenance and network asset management.&#13;
When municipal financial budgets are under pressure it&#13;
is often the maintenance budget that is sacrificed. There&#13;
is evidence that there is inadequate spending on the&#13;
maintenance and rehabilitation of water assets in South&#13;
Africaâ&#128;&#153;s urban areas leading to a deterioration of the&#13;
assets over time. This results in higher water losses and&#13;
will require costly investments in the future.                      Sustaining                                  Developing&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Pricing. South Africa has a free basic water policy with&#13;
                                                                       South Africa average scores&#13;
the intention of making available at least 25 l/c/d (and&#13;
                                                                       Averages, MICs&#13;
preferably 50 l/c/d) of water available to poor households,&#13;
at no cost to the household. National government                    Source: CSO2 scorecard.&#13;
&#13;
provides an operating grant to municipalities that can be&#13;
used to support the implementation of this policy at the            cases water is underpriced and hence the water service is&#13;
local level. Beyond this, water should be priced at its full        underresourced, contributing to the lack of maintenance&#13;
cost to ensure financial viability and sustainability. In many      and rehabilitation identified above.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                         23&#13;
&amp;#12; An AMCOW Country Status Overview&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 9.	 Subsector: Rural Sanitation and Hygiene&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       Priority actions for rural sanitation and hygiene&#13;
       â&#128;¢	    Pilot a more demand-orientated approach to the provision of rural sanitation.&#13;
       â&#128;¢	    Investigate the extent and seriousness of VIP latrine emptying challenges and the implications of these for&#13;
             policy, technology choice, and future investment programs.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Impressive progress has been made from a low base,                the infrastructure and operating cost of rural household&#13;
 according to South African government data. The JMP               sanitation facilities. In terms of policy, investment in&#13;
 data uses a less stringent definition of an acceptable            sanitation facilities must be accompanied by hygiene&#13;
 sanitation facility (pit latrine rather than a VIP latrine or     education, which will carry additional costs.32&#13;
 equivalent) and hence has a higher base value, depicting&#13;
 a slower trend.                                                   According to the CSO2 scorecard, South Africa compares&#13;
                                                                   well relative to its peers in putting in place an effective&#13;
 South Africa has met the rural share of the MDG target in         service delivery pathway for rural sanitation (Figure 19),&#13;
 terms of its own definitions, but is unlikely to meet its own     registering high scores in most building blocks (Figure 18).&#13;
 ambitious universal access target for 2014 for reasons that       Nevertheless, there are challenges.&#13;
 include practicality (the pace and scale required is much&#13;
 higher than past performance achieved) and availability           Rural sanitation budget. The rural sanitation&#13;
 of funds.                                                         budget is insufficient to meet the targets set. The local&#13;
                                                                   government structure does not facilitate dedicated focus&#13;
 The anticipated CAPEX investment (for hardware) of                on, or reporting of, rural sanitation spending.&#13;
 around US$170 million per year is less than half the CSO2&#13;
 estimate of required CAPEX, of around US$400 million              Infrastructure-led approach. The South African&#13;
 per year. Additional OPEX will increase the pressure on           government has invested significantly in the provision of&#13;
 government grants. Government fully subsidizes both               infrastructure (toilet facilities), with benefits in terms of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Figure 16                                                         Figure 17&#13;
 Rural sanitation coverage                                         Rural sanitation investment requirements&#13;
&#13;
           100%&#13;
           80%&#13;
Coverage&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
           60%                                                                     Required CAPEX&#13;
                                                                                                                       Required&#13;
           40%                                                                                                          OPEX&#13;
&#13;
           20%&#13;
            0%&#13;
              1985	 1990	 1995	 2000	 2005	 2010	 2015	 2020       0	       100	        200	     300	        400	   500	    600&#13;
                                                                                            US$ million/year&#13;
              Government estimates        Government target&#13;
              JMP improved                JMP, improved + shared        Public CAPEX (anticipated)&#13;
                                                                        CAPEX deficit&#13;
 Sources: JMP 2010 Report/DWA.&#13;
                                                                   Source: CSO2 costing.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 24&#13;
&amp;#12;                                              Water Supply and Sanitation in South Africa: Turning Finance into Services for 2015 and Beyond&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 18&#13;
Rural sanitation and hygiene scorecard&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
               Enabling                             Developing                                     Sustaining&#13;
   Policy        Planning        Budget   Expenditure Equity           Output         Markets         Up-take         Use&#13;
&#13;
     3               3               2        3               3             2              2.5             1.5              3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Source: CSO2 scorecard.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 19                                                           Monitoring quality of uptake. Monitoring the&#13;
Average RSH scorecard scores for enabling,                          quality of uptake (in terms of health outcomes achieved)&#13;
sustaining, and developing service delivery, and                    needs to be improved through, for example, more regular&#13;
peer-group comparison                                               and widespread use of household surveys.&#13;
                          Enabling&#13;
                                                                    Promoting sanitation and health. Tools for&#13;
                                                                    promoting sanitation and hygiene have been developed&#13;
                                                                    but have not been implemented at scale.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                    Local employment generation. A large-scale rural&#13;
                                                                    infrastructure program has the potential to generate local&#13;
                                                                    employment opportunities. Arguably more can be done to&#13;
  Sustaining                               Developing               promote local economic benefits associated with the rural&#13;
                                                                    sanitation program.&#13;
   South Africa average scores&#13;
   Averages, MICs                                                   Lifespan of rural VIP toilets. Many VIP latrine toilets&#13;
Source: CSO2 scorecard.                                             have filled up much more quickly than anticipated. The&#13;
                                                                    cost of emptying VIP latrine toilets is prohibitively high&#13;
speed and scale. However, it is not clear to what extent            in rural areas due to the high transport costs, and the&#13;
these investments can be associated with improvements               frequent emptying of these toilets presents a significant&#13;
in health outcomes. The current approach may need to                financial burden on households and/or municipalities.&#13;
be complemented with a more demand-led approach in                  The responsibility for toilet emptying is also not clearly&#13;
those rural areas still without adequate sanitation.                defined.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                         25&#13;
&amp;#12; An AMCOW Country Status Overview&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 10.	Subsector: Urban Sanitation and Hygiene&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
           Priority actions for urban sanitation and hygiene&#13;
           â&#128;¢	    Develop a priority national initiative on sanitation in informal settlements, particularly in large cities, pilot&#13;
                 new approaches and seek to take these to scale.&#13;
           â&#128;¢	    Explore new service delivery models for high density settlements where insecurity of tenure makes planning&#13;
                 and implementing standard waterborne sanitation solutions difficult.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 South Africa has made good progress in access to basic                  Anticipated public CAPEX for urban sanitation&#13;
 sanitation in urban areas in terms of its own country                   infrastructure of around US$340 million per year, with an&#13;
 definitions and according to its data has surpassed the                 additional 10 percent assumed user contribution, is less&#13;
 urban share of the MDG target. The JMP data shows                       than half the US$800 million per year estimated by the&#13;
 slower progress, but from a much higher base, due to                    CSO2 to be required to meet the subsector target. OPEX&#13;
 differences in definitions used (the JMP definition regards             requirements of about $400 million per year will require&#13;
 a pit latrine as improved sanitation.) South Africa has an              additional government grant funding due to the South&#13;
 ambitious universal access target for urban areas by 2014.              African governmentâ&#128;&#153;s policy of supporting the operating&#13;
 This target is unlikely to be met. The main reason has to               cost of providing basic services to poor households, and&#13;
 do with the difficulty of providing adequate sanitation                 are thus likely to present a further strain on anticipated&#13;
 facilities in urban informal settlements (where much of                 public spending.&#13;
 the remaining backlog lies) and in keeping pace with the&#13;
 growth of these settlements. Insufficient public funding is             As for rural sanitation, the CSO2 scorecard indicates a&#13;
 also a factor (see Figure 21).                                          strong performance throughout the urban sanitation&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Figure 20                                                               Figure 21&#13;
 Urban sanitation coverage                                               Urban sanitation investment requirements&#13;
&#13;
           100%&#13;
            80%&#13;
Coverage&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            60%                                                                   Required CAPEX&#13;
                                                                                                                        Required&#13;
            40%                                                                                                          OPEX&#13;
&#13;
            20%&#13;
                0%&#13;
                  1985	 1990	 1995	 2000	 2005	 2010	 2015	 2020        0	                   500	               1000	          1500&#13;
                                                                                                 US$ million/year&#13;
                  Government estimates        Government target&#13;
                                                                             Public CAPEX (anticipated)&#13;
                  JMP improved                JMP, improved + shared&#13;
                                                                             Household CAPEX (assumed)&#13;
 Sources: JMP 2010 Report/DWA.                                               CAPEX deficit&#13;
                                                                        Source: CSO2 costing.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 26&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                 Water Supply and Sanitation in South Africa: Turning Finance into Services for 2015 and Beyond&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 22&#13;
Urban sanitation and hygiene scorecard&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                 Enabling                               Developing                                    Sustaining&#13;
    Policy        Planning       Budget       Expenditure    Equity         Output       Markets         Up-take           Use&#13;
&#13;
       3               3           2               3              3            2                3             1.5              3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Source: CSO2 scorecard.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 23                                                              urban informal settlements is a complex challengeâ&#128;&#148;this&#13;
Average USH scorecard scores for enabling,                             is, arguably, the single greatest challenge facing the water&#13;
sustaining and developing service delivery, and                        supply and sanitation sector in South Africa. The latest&#13;
peer-group comparison                                                  data show that between 1 and 2 million households live&#13;
                                                                       in informal settlements in South Africa. High settlement&#13;
                      Enabling                                         densities, insecurity of tenure, and complex community&#13;
                                                                       dynamics make planning and implementing standard&#13;
                                                                       infrastructure solutions difficult, if not impossible. A&#13;
                                                                       willingness to explore new delivery models, together with&#13;
                                                                       careful planning, reflective learning and engagement with&#13;
                                                                       local communities, are required.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                       Cost-effectiveness.      Investment requirements for&#13;
 Sustaining&#13;
                                          Developing                   sanitation are higher than those for water supply. It is&#13;
                                                                       particularly important that these investments represent&#13;
                                                                       good value for money.&#13;
   South Africa average scores&#13;
   Averages, MICs                                                      Flush sanitation and water scarcity. Within a&#13;
                                                                       context of water scarcity, and increasing pressures on&#13;
Sources: CSO2 scorecard.&#13;
                                                                       water resources, the appropriateness of the conventional&#13;
                                                                       practice of waterborne sanitation will need to be re-&#13;
                                                                       examined when making future investment choices,&#13;
service delivery pathway (Figure 22), and South Africa                 particularly in the dryer and more water-scarce parts of&#13;
again outperforms its peers by some margin (Figure 23).                South Africa.&#13;
Nevertheless, important challenges remain.&#13;
                                                                       Quality of outcomes. There is a need for greater&#13;
Sanitation in informal settlements. Providing                          understanding of the impact of urban sanitation on health&#13;
adequate sanitation to South Africaâ&#128;&#153;s large and growing                outcomes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                            27&#13;
&amp;#12;An AMCOW Country Status Overview&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Notes and References&#13;
&#13;
1&#13;
    	 The last two General Household Surveys and the                  	 Global Economic Monitor, World Bank.&#13;
                                                                     12&#13;
&#13;
      Community Survey of 2007 show a stable or declining&#13;
      access to basic services.                                       	 The first round of CSOs was carried out in 2006 covering 16&#13;
                                                                     13&#13;
&#13;
                                                                        countries and is summarized in the report, â&#128;&#152;Getting Africa&#13;
2&#13;
    	 For example, a survey of rural water schemes in KwaZulu-          on-track to Meet the MDGs on Water and Sanitationâ&#128;&#153;.&#13;
      Natal in 2003 revealed that only 74 percent of schemes&#13;
      were functional and that more than half of the functioning      	 JMP estimates are based on a linear regression of nationally&#13;
                                                                     14&#13;
&#13;
      schemes were not meeting the basic minimum standard.              representative household surveys.&#13;
      Hemson, D. 2003. The sustainability of community water&#13;
      projects in KwaZulu-Natal.                                      	 It is difficult to reconcile the CSO2 water estimates&#13;
                                                                     15&#13;
&#13;
                                                                        with DWA estimates due to different assumptions&#13;
3&#13;
    	 Some cities, for example, have implemented flow-                  and methodologies used. DWA unit cost estimates&#13;
      restriction devices or prepayment meters. While their             are approximately 50 percent higher than the CSO2&#13;
      intention is to support the provision of a free basic amount      estimates.&#13;
      of water each month, the practical implementation has&#13;
      been problematic, with households denied access due to          	 It is difficult to reconcile the CSO2 sanitation estimates&#13;
                                                                     16&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      faulty or leaking meters.                                         with DWA estimates due to different assumptions and&#13;
                                                                        methodologies used.&#13;
4&#13;
    	 See, for example, South African Institute of Civil&#13;
      Engineering. 2006. The SAICE Infrastructure Report Card         	 Due to rounding, component figures may not sum to&#13;
                                                                     17&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      for South Africa: 2006.                                           totals.&#13;
&#13;
5&#13;
    	 A study to evaluate the sustainability of all sanitation        	 The 1994 Community Water Supply and Sanitation Policy&#13;
                                                                     18&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      facilities built in 2004â&#128;&#147;09 has been commissioned by the          White Paper required that users pay for the operation&#13;
      Department for Human Settlements.                                 and maintenance costs. Department of Water Affairs and&#13;
                                                                        Forestry. 1994. Water Supply and Sanitation Policy White&#13;
6&#13;
    	 Department of Water Affairs (DWA). 2009. Green                    Paper: Water, An Indivisible Asset.&#13;
      Drop Report 2009: South African Wastewater Quality&#13;
      Management Performance.                                         	 The CSO2 scorecard methodology and conceptual&#13;
                                                                     19&#13;
&#13;
                                                                        framework are discussed in detail in the synthesis report.&#13;
7&#13;
    	 DWA. 2010. Blue Drop Report 2010: South African&#13;
      Drinking Water Quality Management Performance.                  	 The Masibambane program is a â&#128;&#156;partnership between&#13;
                                                                     20&#13;
&#13;
                                                                        the department of local government (now CoGTA), the&#13;
8&#13;
    	 Lawless, A. 2005. Numbers &amp; Needs: Addressing                     South African Local Government Association (SALGA),&#13;
      Imbalances in the Civil Engineering Profession.                   the European Union and its member states; the Swiss&#13;
                                                                        Government and Ireland Aid. The Masibambane Sector&#13;
9&#13;
    	 The Local Government Turnaround Strategy described the            Wide Support Approach works from the premise of&#13;
      governance problem as follows: â&#128;&#156;Political parties that are        coordinated strategies and joint implementation involving&#13;
      undermining the integrity and functioning of municipal            all players in the water sector: national and provincial&#13;
      councils through intra- and inter-party conflicts and             government, municipalities, civil society, donors, water&#13;
      inappropriate interference in councils and administration.â&#128;&#157;       utilities and the private sector.â&#128;&#157; www.dwa.gov.za/&#13;
      Department of Cooperative Governance and Traditional              masibambane/About.aspx&#13;
      Affairs (CoGTA). 2009. Local Government Turnaround&#13;
      Strategy.                                                       	 World Bank Atlas method.&#13;
                                                                     21&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
10&#13;
     	 A report on governance issues with respect to water            	 Scorecard indicators relating to the institutional framework&#13;
                                                                     22&#13;
&#13;
       boards has been commissioned by the DWA.                         section are as follows: All subsectors: targets in national&#13;
                                                                        development plans/PRSP; subsector policy agreed and&#13;
11&#13;
     	 Cabinet approved the comprehensive Local Government              approved (gazetted as part of national policy or as&#13;
       Turnaround Strategy on December 2, 2009.                         standalone policy); RWS/UWS: institutional roles defined;&#13;
                                                                        RSH/USH: institutional lead appointed.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
28&#13;
&amp;#12;                                              Water Supply and Sanitation in South Africa: Turning Finance into Services for 2015 and Beyond&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 	 The Community Survey of 2007 and the recent General&#13;
23&#13;
                                                                         covers domestic/donor finance; RWS, RSH, and USH:&#13;
   Household Surveys show a shift in the distribution of                 domestic/donor expenditure reported; UWS: audited&#13;
   service levels between communal supplies and yard                     accounts and balance sheets from utilities; RWS, RSH,&#13;
   connections and a slowing in the reduction of the service             and USH: periodic analysis of equity criteria by CSOs&#13;
   backlog (households without a piped supply with 200                   and government; UWS: pro-poor plans developed&#13;
   meters).                                                              and implemented by utilities; RWS/UWS: nationally&#13;
                                                                         consolidated reporting of output; RSH/USH: monitoring&#13;
 	 Scorecard indicators relating to section on financing&#13;
24&#13;
                                                                         of quantity and quality of uptake relative to promotion&#13;
   and its implementation are as follows: All subsectors:                and subsidy efforts; all subsectors: Questions and choice&#13;
   programmatic Sector-Wide Approach; investment program                 options in household surveys consistent with MDG&#13;
   based on MDG needs assessment; sufficient finance to                  definitions.&#13;
   meet MDG (and subsidy policy in the case of sanitation);&#13;
   percent of official donor commitments utilized; percent of       30&#13;
                                                                      	 This definition of urban and rural is not strictly correct.&#13;
   domestic commitments utilized.                                       For example, some metropolitan municipalities (most&#13;
                                                                        notably eThekwini) also contain rural areas within their&#13;
 	 The Public Financial Management Act 1 of 1999 and the&#13;
25&#13;
                                                                        boundaries, and small towns in South Africa are effectively&#13;
   Municipal Financial Management Act 56 of 2003.                       urban. However, given the current reporting systems,&#13;
                                                                        this is the only practical way to distinguish between the&#13;
 	 There are some technical issues related to the formula&#13;
26&#13;
                                                                        urban and rural subsectors for the purposes of this report.&#13;
   design which are currently being addressed.&#13;
                                                                        Municipalities and the national household surveys do not&#13;
 	 See note 20.&#13;
27                                                                      report on urban and rural areas separately.&#13;
&#13;
 	 See notes 15 and 16.&#13;
28&#13;
                                                                    31&#13;
                                                                      	 See note 29.&#13;
&#13;
29&#13;
     	 Scorecard indicators relating to the M&amp;E section are&#13;
                                                                    32&#13;
                                                                      	 The CSO2 investment requirement estimates do not&#13;
       as follows: All subsectors: annual review setting new            include the cost of hygiene promotion and other software&#13;
       undertakings; subsector spend identifiable in budget             activities, relative to the targets, due to the difficulty of&#13;
       (UWS: inc. recurrent subsidies); budget comprehensively          estimating such costs on a per capita basis.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                         29&#13;
&amp;#12;Notes&#13;
&amp;#12;Notes&#13;
&amp;#12;Notes&#13;
&amp;#12;&amp;#12;For enquiries, contact:&#13;
Water and Sanitation Programâ&#128;&#147;Africa Region&#13;
The World Bank, Upper Hill Road&#13;
P.O. Box 30577, 00100, Nairobi, Kenya&#13;
Tel: +(254) 20 322 6300&#13;
E-mail: wspaf@worldbank.org&#13;
Web site: www.wsp.org&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="19123212">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2011/01/19123212/water-supply-sanitation-south-africa-turning-finance-services-2015-beyond
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2011/01/19123212/water-supply-sanitation-south-africa-turning-finance-services-2015-beyond</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2011/01/19123212/water-supply-sanitation-south-africa-turning-finance-services-2015-beyond</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2014-02-25T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2014-02-25T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2014/02/25/000442464_20140225131423/Rendered/INDEX/6992300REPLACE0LIC00CSO0SouthAfrica.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2014/02/25/000442464_20140225131423/Rendered/PDF/6992300REPLACE0LIC00CSO0SouthAfrica.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2014-02-25T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2011-01-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Revised white cover</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309942</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Water supply and sanitation in South Africa
            : turning finance into services for 2015 and beyond
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The African Ministers' Council on
            Water (AMCOW) commissioned the production of a second round
            of Country Status Overviews (CSOs) to better understands
            what underpins progress in water supply and sanitation and
            what its member governments can do to accelerate that
            progress across countries in Sub-Saharan Africa (SSA). AMCOW
            delegated this task to the World Bank's Water and
            Sanitation Program and the African Development Bank which
            are implementing it in close partnership with UNICEF and
            World Health Organization (WHO) in over 30 countries across
            SSA. This CSO2 report has been produced in collaboration
            with the Government of South Africa and other stakeholders
            during 2009/10. The analysis aims to help countries assess
            their own service delivery pathways for turning finance into
            water supply and sanitation services in each of four
            subsectors rural and urban water supply, and rural and urban
            sanitation and hygiene. The CSO2 analysis has three main
            components: a review of past coverage; a costing model to
            assess the adequacy of future investments; and a scorecard
            which allows diagnosis of particular bottlenecks along the
            service delivery pathway. The CSO2's contribution is to
            answer not only whether past trends and future finance are
            sufficient to meet sector targets, but what specific issues
            need to be addressed to ensure finance is effectively turned
            into accelerated coverage in water supply and sanitation. In
            this spirit, specific priority actions have been identified
            through consultation. A synthesis report, available
            separately, presents best practice and shared learning to
            help realize these priority actions.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Water supply and sanitation in South Africa
            : turning finance into services for 2015 and beyond
        </docna>
        <display_title>Water supply and sanitation in
            South Africa : turning finance into services for 2015 and beyond</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2011/01/19123212/water-supply-sanitation-south-africa-turning-finance-services-2015-beyond</listing_relative_url>
        <projn>3A-Country Status Overviews On Water Supply
            And Sanitation 2010 -- P117854</projn>
        <docty>UNDP-Water &amp; Sanitation Program</docty>
        <subtopic>Town Water Supply and Sanitation,Water and Industry,Urban Water Supply and Sanitation,Water Supply and Sanitation Governance
            and Institutions,Water Conservation</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Water Supply and Sanitation,Water Resources</teratopic>
        <count>Africa</count>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000442464_20140225131423</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <theme>Water resource management</theme>
        <subsc>General water, sanitation and flood
            protection sector</subsc>
        <admreg>Africa,Africa</admreg>
        <colti>An AMCOW country status overview</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Water Supply and Sanitation,Water Resources</historic_topic>
        <prdln>Economic and Sector Work</prdln>
        <sectr>Water, sanitation and flood protection</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Access to sanitation, access to services,
            access to water, access to water supply, adequate
            sanitation, areas of service, asset management,
            augmentation, basic sanitation, basic water supply, bulk
            water, central government, channel, civil society, Community
            Water, Community Water Supply, connection, connections,
            construction, cost of water, democratic processes, drinking
            water, drinking water quality, financial viability, flush
            toilets, Forestry, free water, government grant funding,
            groundwater, groundwater resources, Household Sanitation,
            households, hygiene, hygiene education, hygiene promotion,
            investment program, investment requirements, kilo liter,
            large cities, large towns, liters per capita per day, local
            communities, local government framework, local service
            delivery, maintenance costs, management of water,
            metropolitan areas, municipal councils, Municipal
            Infrastructure, municipal services, municipal water,
            municipal water systems, municipalities, National Water,
            Participatory approaches, piped water, pit latrine, pit
            latrines, programs, providing water supply, provincial
            government, provincial governments, provision of services,
            public management, rehabilitation of water, responsibility
            for water, responsibility for water supply, riparian, rural
            communities, rural sanitation, rural water, rural water
            schemes, rural water supply, sanitation budget, sanitation
            coverage, sanitation facilities, sanitation facility,
            sanitation infrastructure, sanitation investment, sanitation
            investments, sanitation policy, Sanitation Program,
            sanitation sector, sanitation services, sanitation
            solutions, senior management, service delivery, service
            provision, service quality, sewerage, small towns, supply of
            water, sustainable services, toilet, toilet facilities,
            toilets, urban areas, urban sanitation, Urban water, Urban
            water supply, Urban water supply coverage, users,
            wastewater, wastewater discharge, wastewater treatment,
            Water Affairs, water boards, water budgets, water coverage,
            water infrastructure, water losses, water managers, Water
            policy, water projects, water quality, Water Quality
            Management, water resource, water resources, water rights,
            water scarcity, water schemes, water sector, water service,
            water services, water sources, Water Supply, water supply
            assets, water supply service, water supply systems, water
            systems, water tariff, water utilities
        </keywd>
        <owner>Water - Water &amp; Sant. Prgrm-AFR (GWASA)</owner>
        <majtheme>Environment and natural resource management</majtheme>
        <repnb>69923</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Science and Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation and Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Infrastructure (Water and Wastewater)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Water and Small Town Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Basic Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>On-site Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Marketing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Basic Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deconcentration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delegation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Devolution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sub-National Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subnational Government and Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Town Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Engineering</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Boundaries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water, Sanitation and Hygiene</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Onsite Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Local Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Municipality</ml:concept><ml:concept>Administrative Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Asset Management</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>