<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>                                   70061&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
An AMCOW Country Status Overview&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Water&#13;
Supply and&#13;
Sanitation in&#13;
Nigeria&#13;
Turning Finance into&#13;
Services for 2015&#13;
and Beyond&#13;
&amp;#12;The first round of Country Status Overviews (CSO1) published in 2006 benchmarked the preparedness of sectors of&#13;
16 countries in Africa to meet the WSS MDGs based on their medium-term spending plans and a set of â&#128;&#152;success&#13;
factorsâ&#128;&#153; selected from regional experience. Combined with a process of national stakeholder consultation, this prompted&#13;
countries to ask whether they had those â&#128;&#152;success factorsâ&#128;&#153; in place and, if not, whether they should put them in place.&#13;
&#13;
The second round of Country Status Overviews (CSO2) has built on both the method and the process developed in&#13;
CSO1. The â&#128;&#152;success factorsâ&#128;&#153; have been supplemented with additional factors drawn from country and regional analysis&#13;
to develop the CSO2 scorecard. Together these reflect the essential steps, functions and results in translating finance&#13;
into services through government systemsâ&#128;&#148;in line with Paris Principles for aid effectiveness. The data and summary&#13;
assessments have been drawn from local data sources and compared with internationally reported data, and, wherever&#13;
possible, the assessments have been subject to broad-based consultations with lead government agencies and country&#13;
sector stakeholders, including donor institutions.&#13;
&#13;
This second set of 32 Country Status Overviews (CSO2) on water supply and sanitation was commissioned by the African&#13;
Ministersâ&#128;&#153; Council on Water (AMCOW). Development of the CSO2 was led by the World Bank administered Water and&#13;
Sanitation Program (WSP) in collaboration with the African Development Bank (AfDB), the United Nations Childrenâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
Fund (UNICEF), the World Bank and the World Health Organization (WHO).&#13;
&#13;
This report was produced in collaboration with the Government of Nigeria and other stakeholders during 2009/10. Some&#13;
sources cited may be informal documents that are not readily available.&#13;
&#13;
The findings, interpretations, and conclusions expressed in this volume do not necessarily reflect the views of the&#13;
collaborating institutions, their Executive Directors, or the governments they represent. The collaborating institutions&#13;
do not guarantee the accuracy of the data included in this work. The boundaries, colors, denominations, and other&#13;
information shown on any map in this work do not imply any judgment on the part of the collaborating institutions&#13;
concerning the legal status of any territory or the endorsement or acceptance of such boundaries.&#13;
&#13;
The material in this publication is copyrighted. Requests for permission to reproduce portions of it should be sent to&#13;
wsp@worldbank.org. The collaborating institutions encourage the dissemination of this work and will normally grant&#13;
permission promptly. For more information, please visit www.amcow.net or www.wsp.org.&#13;
&#13;
Photograph credits: Getty Images&#13;
&#13;
Â© 2011 Water and Sanitation Program&#13;
&amp;#12;                     Water Supply and Sanitation in Nigeria: Turning Finance into Services for 2015 and Beyond&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
An AMCOW Country Status Overview&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                        Water&#13;
                        Supply and&#13;
                        Sanitation in&#13;
                        Nigeria&#13;
                        Turning Finance into&#13;
                        Services for 2015&#13;
                        and Beyond&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                            1&#13;
&amp;#12;An AMCOW Country Status Overview&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Strategic Overview&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The Federal Republic of Nigeria is made up of 36 states          national access indicating that Nigeria is unlikely to achieve&#13;
and a Federal Capital Territory, and 774 local government        the Millennium Development Goal (MDG) targets unless&#13;
areas. At the federal level, substantial progress has            it takes drastic steps to improve current performance. In&#13;
been made to define institutional roles and develop              large part the ingredients for a reformed sector have been&#13;
supporting policies for water supply and sanitation              agreed upon at the federal level, but require rolling out&#13;
service delivery.                                                in all states. These include sector policies and strategies&#13;
                                                                 and a review of legislation to conform with intentions&#13;
The key challenge for Nigeria is to promulgate this policy       regarding the roles of government and the private sector,&#13;
guidance at the state level as water supply and sanitation       and separation of policy formulation and regulation from&#13;
(WSS) is mostly the state governmentsâ&#128;&#153; responsibility.           service delivery.&#13;
States have a high degree of autonomyâ&#128;&#148;compared&#13;
to other countries in Africa with a federal structureâ&#128;&#148;           Estimates of the investment in WSS required to meet 2015&#13;
and their adoption of national WSS policy guidance is            sector MDG targets range from US$2.5 billion (MDG Office)&#13;
uneven. While some states have created strong enabling           to US$4 billion annually (US$1.7 billion for water supply&#13;
environments (some more advanced than that at federal            and US$2.3 billion for sanitationâ&#128;&#148;CSO2 costing). Current&#13;
level), other states are yet to start the reform process. This   spending, whilst being difficult to discern, is around a third&#13;
uneven commitment to WSS and shaping its enabling                of the CSO2 costing estimate. This calls for increases in&#13;
environment is also reflected in vast disparities in rates of    sector spending, which can only be meaningfully realized&#13;
access to WSS services across states: from 81 percent in         once investment plans are prepared at different tiers of&#13;
Lagos state to 13 percent in Sokoto state for water supply,      government. The implementation of the innovative Water&#13;
and from 97 percent in Kano to 12 percent in Bayelsa for         Investments Mobilization and Application Guidelines will&#13;
sanitation.1 Whilst there are differences among sources of       present great opportunities for this.&#13;
data on access to WSS, and an array of sector targets,&#13;
both the Water Supply and Sanitation Baseline Study              This second AMCOW Country Status Overview (CSO2)&#13;
(WSSBS) of 2007 and the UNICEF/WHO Joint Monitoring              has been produced in collaboration with the Government&#13;
Programme (JMP) 2010 report provide estimates of                 of Nigeria and other stakeholders.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
2&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                  Water Supply and Sanitation in Nigeria: Turning Finance into Services for 2015 and Beyond&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Agreed priority actions to tackle these challenges, and ensure finance is effectively&#13;
turned into services, are:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Sectorwide&#13;
  â&#128;¢	   Support the completion of the preparation of statesâ&#128;&#153; water policies.&#13;
  â&#128;¢	   Increase level of funding for water and sanitation.&#13;
  â&#128;¢	   Implement the Water Investments Mobilization and Application Guidelines (WIMAG) to facilitate state-level policy&#13;
       and plan development as well as leverage matching finance for WSS.&#13;
  â&#128;¢	   Clearly identify an institutional home for sanitation.&#13;
  â&#128;¢	   Promote private sector participation in the provision of goods and services.&#13;
  â&#128;¢	   Undertake phased establishment of regulatory commissions in all states (as proposed by the National Water Policy).&#13;
  â&#128;¢	   Agree achievable national and state WSS targets (with MDG requirements as a minimum).&#13;
  â&#128;¢	   Prepare Strategic Investment Plans to meet state targets.&#13;
  â&#128;¢	   Clearly indicate budget lines for sanitation for greater visibility and improve financial reporting to be able to track&#13;
       sector investments.&#13;
  â&#128;¢	   Implement the framework for monitoring and evaluation which remains on the drawing board.&#13;
  â&#128;¢	   Institutionalize an Annual Sector Review dedicated to drinking water and sanitation.&#13;
  â&#128;¢	   Prepare annual consolidated reports on sector output.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Rural water supply&#13;
  â&#128;¢	 Rural Water and Sanitation Agencies should be established in states where this has not been done and their roles&#13;
     substantially limited to facilitation and capacity building of local government areas.&#13;
  â&#128;¢	 Increase the pace of implementation of the framework for rural water and sanitation delivery, emphasizing community&#13;
     ownership and management.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Urban water supply&#13;
  â&#128;¢	 Review edicts of water agencies to make them consistent with the National Water Policy.&#13;
  â&#128;¢	 Wean urban water utilities off state subsidies for operation and maintenance (O&amp;M) and increase the pace of utility&#13;
     commercialization.&#13;
  â&#128;¢	 Undertake regular review of tariffs to permit recovery of O&amp;M costs at a minimum.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Rural sanitation and hygiene&#13;
  â&#128;¢	   State governments to prioritize sanitationâ&#128;&#148;putting in place policies, plans, and budgets for sanitation.&#13;
  â&#128;¢	   Scale up implementation of community-led total sanitation and regularly review its contribution to improving access.&#13;
  â&#128;¢	   Improve awareness through advocacy to mobilize public and private stakeholders on good sanitation and hygiene&#13;
       practices.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Urban sanitation and hygiene&#13;
  â&#128;¢	   Identify clear leader for sanitation service delivery in urban areas.&#13;
  â&#128;¢	   Develop and implement appropriate sanitation approaches in peri-urban and low income communities.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                         3&#13;
&amp;#12;An AMCOW Country Status Overview&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
4&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                 Water Supply and Sanitation in Nigeria: Turning Finance into Services for 2015 and Beyond&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Contents&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
	                                ........................................................................................................................... 6&#13;
       Acronyms and Abbreviations.&#13;
&#13;
1.	                .................................................................................................................................................... 7&#13;
       Introduction.&#13;
&#13;
2.	                                                ............................................................................................... 8&#13;
       Sector Overview: Coverage and Finance Trends.&#13;
&#13;
3.	                                                  ......................................................................................... 12&#13;
       Reform Context: Introducing the CSO2 Scorecard.&#13;
&#13;
4.	    Institutional Framework................................................................................................................................. 15&#13;
&#13;
5.	    Financing....................................................................................................................................................... 17&#13;
&#13;
6.	    Sector Monitoring and Evaluation.................................................................................................................. 20&#13;
&#13;
7.	    Subsector: Rural Water Supply....................................................................................................................... 23&#13;
&#13;
8.	                                 ..................................................................................................................... 25&#13;
       Subsector: Urban Water Supply.&#13;
&#13;
9.	    Subsector: Rural Sanitation and Hygiene........................................................................................................ 27&#13;
&#13;
10.	                                          ...................................................................................................... 29&#13;
       Subsector: Urban Sanitation and Hygiene.&#13;
&#13;
	      Notes and References.................................................................................................................................... 31&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                         5&#13;
&amp;#12;An AMCOW Country Status Overview&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Acronyms and Abbreviations&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
AfDB	        African Development Bank                  PER	     Public Expenditure Reviews&#13;
AMCOW	       African Ministersâ&#128;&#153; Council on Water       PSP	     Private sector participation&#13;
CAPEX	       Capital expenditure                       PWI	     Presidential Water Initiative&#13;
CLTS	        Community-Led Total Sanitation            RBDA	    River Basin Development Authorities/Boards&#13;
CSO2	        Country Status Overviews (second round)   RSH	     Rural sanitation and hygiene&#13;
EU	          European Union                            RWS	     Rural water supply&#13;
FMoWR	       Federal Ministry of Water Resources       RWSSA	   Rural Water Supply and Sanitation Agency&#13;
GDP	         Gross domestic product                    SMoWR	   State Ministries responsible for water&#13;
GNI	         Gross national income                              resources&#13;
HH	          Household                                 SON	     Standards Organization of Nigeria&#13;
JMP	         Joint Monitoring Programme (UNICEF/WHO)   SSA	     Sub-Saharan Africa&#13;
LGAs	        Local Government Areas                    SWA	     State Water Agency (or Board)&#13;
M&amp;E	         Monitoring and evaluation                 SWAp	    Sector-Wide Approach&#13;
MDG	         Millennium Development Goal               UNICEF	  United Nations Childrenâ&#128;&#153;s Fund&#13;
MIC	         Middle-income country                     USH	     Urban sanitation and hygiene&#13;
MTEF	        Medium-Term Expenditure Framework         UWS	     Urban water supply&#13;
NCWR	        National Council on Water Resources       WASH	    Water, sanitation and hygiene&#13;
NEEDS	       National Economic Empowerment and         WES	     Water and Environmental Sanitation&#13;
             Development                                        Departments&#13;
NGO	         Nongovernmental organization              WESCOMS	 Water and Environmental Sanitation&#13;
NW&amp;SP	       National Water and Sanitation Policy               Committees&#13;
NWP	         Draft National Water Policy               WHO	     World Health Organization&#13;
NWRI	        National Water Resources Institute        WIMAG	   Water Investment Mobilization and&#13;
NWRMS	       National Water Resources Management                Application Guidelines&#13;
             Strategy                                  WSP	     Water and Sanitation Program&#13;
NWRS	        National Water Resources Strategy         WSS	     Water supply and sanitation&#13;
NW-SP	       National Water Sanitation Policy          WSSBS	   Water Supply and Sanitation Baseline Survey&#13;
O&amp;M	         Operations and maintenance                WSSSRP	  Water Supply and Sanitation Sector Reform&#13;
OPEX	        Operating expenditure                              Programme&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Exchange rate: US$1 = 130 Naira.2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
6&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                 Water Supply and Sanitation in Nigeria: Turning Finance into Services for 2015 and Beyond&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
1.	 Introduction&#13;
&#13;
The African Ministers Council on Water (AMCOW) commissioned the production of a second round of Country Status&#13;
Overviews (CSOs) to better understand what underpins progress in water supply and sanitation and what its member&#13;
governments can do to accelerate that progress across countries in Sub-Saharan Africa (SSA).3 The African Ministersâ&#128;&#153;&#13;
Council on Water (AMCOW) delegated this task to the World Bankâ&#128;&#153;s Water and Sanitation Program and the African&#13;
Development Bank who are implementing it in close partnership with UNICEF and WHO in over 30 countries across SSA.&#13;
This CSO2 report has been produced in collaboration with the Government of Nigeria and other stakeholders during&#13;
2009/10.&#13;
&#13;
The analysis aims to help countries assess their own service delivery pathways for turning finance into water supply and&#13;
sanitation services in each of four subsectors: rural and urban water supply, and rural and urban sanitation and hygiene.&#13;
The CSO2 analysis has three main components: a review of past coverage; a costing model to assess the adequacy of&#13;
future investments; and a scorecard which allows diagnosis of particular bottlenecks along the service delivery pathway.&#13;
The CSO2â&#128;&#153;s contribution is to answer not only whether past trends and future finance are sufficient to meet sector&#13;
targets, but what specific issues need to be addressed to ensure finance is effectively turned into accelerated coverage in&#13;
water supply and sanitation. In this spirit, specific priority actions have been identified through consultation. A synthesis&#13;
report, available separately, presents best practice and shared learning to help realize these priority actions.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                        7&#13;
&amp;#12;An AMCOW Country Status Overview&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
2.	 Sector Overview:&#13;
    Coverage and Finance Trends&#13;
&#13;
Coverage: Assessing Past Progress                               The 2008 access data implies that as many as 63 million&#13;
                                                                Nigerians have no access to improved water supply. In&#13;
Data from the Water Supply and Sanitation Baseline              respect of sanitation, the JMP reports that 37 percent of&#13;
Survey (WSSBS), gathered in 2007, reported a national           the total population had access to improved sanitation&#13;
access figure of 54.3 percent for water supply and 65.6         facilities in 1990. In addition, a further 26 percent used&#13;
percent for improved sanitation. That survey also found         shared facilities, which are not considered improved. By&#13;
that 18.8 percent of the population resorts to open             2008, 32 percent of the total population had access to&#13;
defecation (22 percent of the rural and 5.7 percent of the      improved sanitation, indicating a fall in the percentage of&#13;
urban population).                                              people served, even though the absolute number of people&#13;
                                                                with access increased by 11.5 million. Of those without&#13;
The CSO2 also compares countriesâ&#128;&#153; own estimates                 access to improved sanitation, 26 percent use facilities&#13;
of coverage with data from the UNICEF/WHO Joint                 which are shared, 20 percent use unimproved facilities&#13;
Monitoring Programme (JMP).4 The impact of these                and 22 percent (33.3 million) practice open defecation.&#13;
different coverage estimates on investment requirements&#13;
is also assessed. According to the JMP, access to improved      Data differences between the two sources are not very&#13;
water supply in Nigeria nationally was 47 percent in 1990,      significant for water supply (54 percent vs. 58 percent).&#13;
with 79 percent (27 million) of the urban population of 34      The difference is much greater in the case of sanitation&#13;
million having access, compared to 30 percent (19 million)      where the WSSBS access figure of 65.6 percent contrasts&#13;
of the 63 million people living in rural areas. By 2008 the     with the 32 percent estimated by the JMP. This is principally&#13;
percentage of the population with access had increased          because the definitions differ: the WSSBS figure includes&#13;
to 58 percent (86 million), spread across 75 percent of the     shared facilities, which are not considered improved by&#13;
urban population and 42 percent of the rural population.        JMP definition.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 1&#13;
Progress in water supply and sanitation coverage&#13;
&#13;
Water supply                                                    Sanitation&#13;
&#13;
           100%                                                            100%&#13;
           80%                                                             80%&#13;
Coverage&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                Coverage&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
           60%                                                             60%&#13;
           40%                                                             40%&#13;
           20%                                                             20%&#13;
            0%                                                              0%&#13;
              1985	 1990	 1995	 2000	 2005	 2010	 2015	 2020                  1985	 1990	 1995	 2000	 2005	 2010	 2015	 2020&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                  WSSBS 2007 estimate       Government target                     WSSBS 2007 estimate      Government target&#13;
                  JMP estimates             MDG target                            JMP estimates            MDG target&#13;
&#13;
Sources: WSSBS 2007, MDG Office (2007), and JMP 2010 report.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
8&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                           Water Supply and Sanitation in Nigeria: Turning Finance into Services for 2015 and Beyond&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The overall national access figures, however, mask                          Investment Requirements: Testing the&#13;
wide disparities in access among Nigeriaâ&#128;&#153;s 36 states. For                   Sufficiency of Finance&#13;
example, the WSSBS data indicate that whereas water&#13;
supply access in Lagos state was 81 percent in 2007, that                   Two estimates of investment required to meet the&#13;
for Sokoto state was 13 percent. Similar disparities exist                  MDG targets are compared in this report. The Nigeria&#13;
in the case of sanitation, ranging from Kanoâ&#128;&#153;s 97 percent                   MDG Office estimates that US$2.5 billion is required&#13;
access to Bayelsaâ&#128;&#153;s 12 percent.                                             annually to meet the water supply and sanitation&#13;
                                                                            targets between 2007 and 2015â&#128;&#148;an average US$15&#13;
Two sets of targets for 2015 are depicted in Figure 1:                      per capita. The investment cost is almost equally split&#13;
the MDG targets as derived from the 2010 JMP report,                        between water supply and sanitation.5 The report&#13;
as well as government targets issued by the Millennium                      conceded some of the challenges in estimating the&#13;
Development Goal (MDG) Office. Based on the JMP trend                       investment requirements, such as (a) the nonavailability&#13;
line Nigeria could miss the water supply MDG target of 74                   of comprehensive data; and (b) the difficulty in&#13;
percent by about 12 percentage points, and the 82 percent                   quantifying or assigning percentages with regard to&#13;
MDG target by a greater margin. The JMP trend line for                      infrastructural decay.&#13;
sanitation is negative, with the result that the MDG target&#13;
of 69 percent could be missed by a very wide margin if                      The CSO2 costing model was used to provide alternative&#13;
progress is not accelerated, while the MDG Office target of                 estimates of required investment, utilizing input data&#13;
88 percent is again an even more distant prospect. Figure                   including coverage from the JMP 2010 report, along&#13;
1 also shows the government estimates from the WSSBS                        with population and the mix, unit costs, and lifespan of&#13;
2007, starkly illustrating the higher sanitation coverage                   technologies derived from the MDG Office. According&#13;
if shared facilities are included. If one considers that the                to the CSO2 model annual financing required to&#13;
2000 National Water and Sanitation Policy (NW&amp;SP) had                       achieve the MDG targets for Nigeria is estimated at&#13;
in fact aimed for universal access by 2011, it is clear that                US$1.7 billion for water supply and US$2.3 billion for&#13;
Nigeria is way off both the MDG targets as well as the                      sanitation. The financing requirements can be further&#13;
more ambitious targets set previously in the policy and                     disaggregated into rural water supply (RWS) (US$604&#13;
other initiatives. It should be appreciated, however, that                  million per year), urban water supply (UWS) (US$1.1&#13;
given their stronger performance, some states are more                      billion per year), rural sanitation (US$1.1 billion per&#13;
likely to achieve their (localized) MDG targets, whilst many                year) and urban sanitation ($1.2 billion per year) (see&#13;
others will not be able to so.	                                             Figure 2 and Table 1).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 2&#13;
Required vs. anticipated (public) and assumed (household) expenditure&#13;
&#13;
Water supply                                                                Sanitation&#13;
&#13;
               Required CAPEX                                                                Required CAPEX&#13;
                                                       Required                                                                      Required&#13;
                                                        OPEX                                                                          OPEX&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
0	          500	        1000	        1500	         2000	       2500         0	        500	       1000	    1500	      2000	      2500	      3000&#13;
                                US$ million/year                                                          US$ million/year&#13;
&#13;
     Public CAPEX (anticipated)                                                  Public CAPEX (anticipated)&#13;
     CAPEX deficit                                                               Household CAPEX (assumed)&#13;
                                                                                 CAPEX deficit&#13;
Source: CSO2 costing.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                  9&#13;
&amp;#12;An AMCOW Country Status Overview&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table 1&#13;
Coverage and investment figures7&#13;
&#13;
	 Coverage	 Target8	Population	    CAPEX	      Anticipated	                                                             Assumed	 Total&#13;
			                  requiring	 requirements	 public CAPEX	                                                                HH	   deficit&#13;
			                    access			                                                                                         CAPEX&#13;
	                            1990	 2008	 2015				                         Total	 Public	 Domestic	 External	 Total&#13;
 	                             %	       %	       %	      â&#128;&#152;000/year					US$ million/year&#13;
&#13;
 Rural water supply	         30%	     42%	      69%	       4,569	        604	 604	            350	         84	   434	       0	     170&#13;
 Urban water supply	         79%	     75%	      95%	       4,927	       1113	 1113	           350	         94	   444	       0	     669&#13;
 Water supply total	         47%	     58%	      82%	       9,507	       1716	 1716	           700	        178	   878	       0	     839&#13;
 Rural sanitation	           36%	     28%	      87%	       8,434	       1051	    0	             0	         14	    14	    1051	       -&#13;
 Urban sanitation	           39%	     36%	      89%	       8,059	       1225	 612	              0	         15	    15	      15	    1195&#13;
 Sanitation total	           37%	     32%	      88%	      16,655	       2276	 612	              0	         29	    29	    1066	    1181&#13;
&#13;
Source: For coverage, JMP 2010 report; for targets, MDG Office 2007; for investment data, CSO2 costing.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                Table 2&#13;
The CSO2 costing model also compares required                                   Annual O&amp;M requirements&#13;
investment with anticipated investment from government,&#13;
                                                                                    Subsector	                         O&amp;M&#13;
donorsâ&#128;&#148;including        nongovernmental       organizations&#13;
                                                                                    	                             US$ million/year&#13;
(NGOs)â&#128;&#148;and users, to derive the expected annual finance&#13;
                                                                                    Rural water supply	                   92&#13;
gap. It has been difficult to establish the extent of the&#13;
                                                                                    Urban water supply	                  233&#13;
financing gap given the weak reporting of sector spending&#13;
                                                                                    Water supply total	                  325&#13;
at various levels of government. An analysis of the sector&#13;
                                                                                    Rural sanitation	                     94&#13;
investments in selected states indicates an average annual&#13;
                                                                                    Urban sanitation	                    154&#13;
state level spend of some US$15 millionâ&#128;&#148;from which an&#13;
                                                                                    Sanitation total	                    249&#13;
annual national spending of around US$550 million can&#13;
                                                                                Source: CSO2 estimates.&#13;
be inferred. A higher figure of US$700 million per year has&#13;
been applied in the costing. A little over US$200 million&#13;
per year is expected from donors and NGOs, mainly for                           invested in public subventions will leverage a dollar from&#13;
the water supply subsector.                                                     households in return. However, anticipated public finance&#13;
                                                                                for urban sanitation is marginal, restricting the leveraging&#13;
The costing model also incorporates assumed user                                of user contributions in turn (these issues are explained&#13;
contributions to sanitation capital investments (hardware).                     further in Sections 9 and 10).&#13;
In the case of rural sanitation, the adoption of Community-&#13;
Led Total Sanitation (CLTS) implies that the full hardware                      Total anticipated investment is therefore less than what&#13;
costs of sanitation must be met by users. However, CLTS                         is required under the more modest estimates from the&#13;
also requires government to catalyze the adoption of                            MDG Office. Relative to the CSO2 costing estimates,&#13;
latrines by communities through promotion, marketing,                           anticipated investment is even more starkly insufficient&#13;
and other â&#128;&#152;softwareâ&#128;&#153; activities. There is little evidence of                    (Figure 2).&#13;
capacity or funding for this in Nigeria, which would mean&#13;
the substantial assumed household spending on capital                           There are a number of reasons why the above depiction&#13;
(CAPEX) depicted in Figure 2 is unlikely to materialize.6                       of required investments may be underestimated. The&#13;
In the case of urban sanitation, the model assumes users                        first is the need to cover operating expenditure (OPEX)&#13;
will contribute 50 percent of the costs, on average, across                     requirements, estimated at US$325 million for water&#13;
technologies. For this subsector the model assumes that                         supply and US$249 million for sanitation (Table 2).&#13;
public finance will have a leveraging effect: each dollar                       As in many countries, in Nigeria there is an implicit&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
10&#13;
&amp;#12;                                              Water Supply and Sanitation in Nigeria: Turning Finance into Services for 2015 and Beyond&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
assumption that operation and maintenance (O&amp;M)                bulk water to utilities, though these have not received&#13;
costs will be recovered from users, though in practice         adequate O&amp;M expenditure.9 Out of 31 billion cubic&#13;
this is not always achieved. Nigerian utilities are            meters in about 200 multipurpose dams, only 18 percent&#13;
confronted by particularly poor power supplies. This           is effectively utilized.10 Therefore investment requirements&#13;
has necessitated high expenditure for the acquisition          for new dams are unlikely to be a major issue but&#13;
of generators and the associated running costs. With           rehabilitation may be required.&#13;
a tendency for states to subsidize utilities (including&#13;
meeting salaries of utility staff), operational costs          These considerations are only part of the picture.&#13;
will further reduce the amount available for capital           Bottlenecks can, in fact, occur throughout the service&#13;
expenditures, or else systems will be run down as a            delivery pathwayâ&#128;&#148;all the institutions, processes, and actors&#13;
result of a lack of maintenance. In the RWS subsector,         that translate sector funding into sustainable services.&#13;
many of the states (if not all) do not implement a policy      Where the pathway is well developed sector funding&#13;
of cost recovery, and water is free in many areas, when        should turn into services at the estimated unit costs.&#13;
it is provided at all.                                         Where it is not, the above investment requirements may&#13;
                                                               be gross underestimates. The rest of this report evaluates&#13;
On the other hand a very strong water resource                 the service delivery pathway in its entirety, locating the&#13;
infrastructure base (in terms of dams operated by River        bottlenecks and presenting the agreed priority actions to&#13;
Basin Authorities) has been created in Nigeria to provide      help address them.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                    11&#13;
&amp;#12;An AMCOW Country Status Overview&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
3.	 Reform Context:&#13;
	 Introducing the CSO2 Scorecard&#13;
&#13;
Nigeria has demonstrated a clear commitment to ensuring        autonomy of water supply agencies; and (i) technical and&#13;
water security over the years through the establishment        financial capacity building to efficiently manage the water&#13;
of relevant institutions and investments in water-related      delivery system.13 As a more sanitation-focused document,&#13;
infrastructure. Substantial investments have been made in      the NW-SP also aims to address such issues as health and&#13;
dams for irrigation and to supply bulk water for drinking      hygiene education, relevant operational research, efficient&#13;
water supply. However, most interventions had been             and affordable sanitation systems, roles of government&#13;
centrally driven and local participation and ownership of      and all other stakeholders including funding arrangement&#13;
the processes that ensure sustainability (in conformity with   and relevant legislation.&#13;
the principles of integrated water resources management)&#13;
were missing. Poor management of upstream infrastructure       A number of key reforms are awaited, including the passage&#13;
(such as dams and bulk water pipelines) invariably affects     of the Draft National Water Resources Bill, April 2007 by&#13;
operations within utilities. In addition, poor maintenance     the federal legislature. The Bill contains provisions for the&#13;
left much of the bulk infrastructure operating well            equitable, beneficial, efficient, and sustainable use and&#13;
below capacity. The National Water Resources Strategy          management of the nationâ&#128;&#153;s surface water and groundwater&#13;
document noted that â&#128;&#156;there has been no water resource          resources and will establish a new institutional framework&#13;
management in Nigeria to this point, only a top down,          for Nigeriaâ&#128;&#153;s water resources. It is largely informed by the&#13;
supply-driven, development of water resources. This has        NWP. The Water Investment Mobilization and Application&#13;
led to investments which have not been effectively utilized,   Guidelines (WIMAG) are awaiting adoption and roll-out.&#13;
representing a major waste of government funding which         WIMAG provides guidelines on best practice investment&#13;
continues until todayâ&#128;&#157;.11 The result has been a vicious        in water supply services, including clear and enforceable&#13;
cycle of unreliable projects that provide services that do     standards of service performance, operation, and&#13;
not meet consumer needs and for which the consumers            management at the state level. States are required to sign&#13;
are unwilling to pay.12                                        up to WIMAG through a Memorandum of Understanding&#13;
                                                               with the federal government to enable them to enjoy&#13;
In respect of drinking water supply and sanitation (WSS),      complementary funding of WSS in the states.&#13;
various policy reform measures have been taken over&#13;
the years to define federal, state, and local level actions    A significant policy move is that of redefining the role of&#13;
for service delivery and to meet the targets to which the      government as a regulator, facilitator, and co-coordinator,&#13;
country has committed. The reform strategy for WSS has         rather than an implementer. A regulatory body will be&#13;
been encapsulated in Nigeriaâ&#128;&#153;s 2004 National Economic          created to provide for the monitoring and setting of&#13;
Empowerment and Development Strategy (NEEDS) and               standards for water service tariffs.14 A number of guidelines&#13;
other policy documents, including the 2004 Final Draft         for the subsectors to support implementation at state level&#13;
National Water Policy (NWP), the 2004 National Water           and for water quality monitoring have been developed by&#13;
Sanitation Policy (NW-SP) and the 2006 National Water          the Federal Ministry of Water Resources (FMoWR).&#13;
Resources Management Strategy (NWRMS). These attempt&#13;
to address the main sector challenges identified, including:   In addition, the model Water Supply Services Regulatory&#13;
(a) clear and coherent regulation; (b) clear definitions       Law (WSSRL) aims to promote sound water laws and policies&#13;
of functions and relationships of sector institutions; (c)     (consistent with the NWP) through the establishment&#13;
coordination; (d) dwindling funds; (e) reliable and adequate   of a clear legal basis for powers of a regulator and the&#13;
data for planning; (f) decentralizationâ&#128;&#148;for efficiency,        separation of functions between the government (policy&#13;
performance, and sustainability; (g) accountability; (h)       and planning), the regulator and the water services&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
12&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                  Water Supply and Sanitation in Nigeria: Turning Finance into Services for 2015 and Beyond&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
providers (including state water agencies), among others.          Figure 3&#13;
The model is intended to serve as a basis for water reform         Average scorecard results for enabling,&#13;
legislation to be considered by the participating statesâ&#128;&#153;          developing, and sustaining service delivery, and&#13;
Houses of Assembly, in conjunction with the relevant               peer-group comparison&#13;
stakeholders.&#13;
                                                                                                 Enabling&#13;
&#13;
This recent history puts the service delivery pathway in&#13;
context, which can then be explored in detail using the&#13;
CSO2 scorecard, an assessment tool providing a snapshot&#13;
of reform progress along the service delivery pathway. The&#13;
CSO2 scorecard assesses the building blocks of service&#13;
delivery in turn: three building blocks which relate to&#13;
enabling services; three which relate to developing new&#13;
services; and three which relate to sustaining services. Each&#13;
building block is assessed against specific indicators and&#13;
scored from 1 to 3 accordingly.15 The scorecard has been&#13;
                                                                            Sustaining                               Developing&#13;
prepared for the federal level and does not fully capture&#13;
the diversity of service delivery pathway development at              Nigeria average scores&#13;
the state level. Therefore the results should be interpreted          Averages, MICs&#13;
with some caution. As appropriate, observations have&#13;
                                                                   Source: CSO2 scorecard.&#13;
been made based on knowledge of the sector at state&#13;
levels.                                                            see more resources released by the federal government to&#13;
                                                                   the states for investments; and the substantial disconnect&#13;
An examination of the â&#128;&#152;enablingâ&#128;&#153;, â&#128;&#152;developingâ&#128;&#153;, and                between what is required, what is allocated for investments,&#13;
â&#128;&#152;sustainingâ&#128;&#153; building blocks indicates that overall Nigeria        and what is effectively utilized at state and local levels.&#13;
falls slightly behind its peer group, of middle-income             Legally there is no opportunity for federal authorities to&#13;
countries (MICs) participating in the CSO2, in all three areas     reprimand states or utilities for nonperformance, and the&#13;
(Figure 3). In terms of the enabling building blocks in the        WIMAG has been intended to play a â&#128;&#152;carrot and stickâ&#128;&#153; role&#13;
service delivery pathway, the evidence points to substantial       by encouraging states to match federal funding, while&#13;
efforts at reforms since the early 1990s. However, progress        demanding reforms and best practice in return. Evidence&#13;
appears to have stalled as policy documents await                  suggests low levels of utilization of funds allocated to&#13;
approval, bills await enactment, and strategies remain             the sector, even though there is better performance with&#13;
in draft.16 This has also affected progress of reforms at          respect to donor-led projects. There is annual reporting of&#13;
the state level, as states look to the federal government          expenditure by the better-performing utilities such as Lagos&#13;
for guidance and support. States are required to develop           State Water Corporation and Cross River Water Board, but&#13;
their State Water and Sanitation Policies informed by the          the same cannot be said of all the water utilities.&#13;
National Water Policy; only a few of them, however, have&#13;
taken this up. Institutionally, the policy has identified the      Poor reportingâ&#128;&#148;of system performance, functionality&#13;
needed structures at federal, state, and local government          and availability, outputs, and related expendituresâ&#128;&#148;&#13;
levels, with considerable clarity for water supply, while for      exacerbates the challenges, particularly given Nigeriaâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
sanitation leadership is still unclear. Economic regulationâ&#128;&#148;       federal structure. In general states do not have a&#13;
particularly to ensure efficient and accountable operation         consolidated reporting of sector output and this is mirrored&#13;
of utilitiesâ&#128;&#148;is planned, but still remains on paper, and           at the national level as little or no data are submitted by&#13;
tariff reviews are seldom. Only Lagos state has established        the states for consolidation.&#13;
a regulator.&#13;
                                                                   The downstream end of the service delivery pathway relates&#13;
The key challenges regarding developing services relate            to sustaining services. The biggest barrier to sustainability&#13;
to the stalled implementation of WIMAG, which could                is the lack of cost recovery in both urban and rural water&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                        13&#13;
&amp;#12;An AMCOW Country Status Overview&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
service delivery. Many utilities have very high nonrevenue      Sections 4 to 6 highlight progress and challenges across&#13;
water and the absence of adequate regulation and                three thematic areasâ&#128;&#148;the institutional framework, finance,&#13;
monitoring compounds this. Whilst nominally autonomous          and monitoring and evaluation (M&amp;E)â&#128;&#148;benchmarking&#13;
state utilitiesâ&#128;&#153; reliance on state budgets, for investments     Nigeria against its peer countries based on a grouping&#13;
and in many cases to pay salaries of workers, effectively       by gross national income. The related indicators are&#13;
undermines their ability to make autonomous decisions           extracted from the scorecard and presented in charts at&#13;
on investment planning, borrowing, procurement, hiring          the beginning of each section. The scorecards for each&#13;
and firing of manpower. It is also unclear at this stage        subsector are presented in their entirety in Sections 7 to&#13;
whether CLTS and the no-subsidy policy are having any           10. The list of priority actions provided at the beginning&#13;
impact on sanitation uptake; whilst in many of the states       of each section is based on recommendations from the&#13;
there are inadequate numbers of health extension workers        national CSO2 dialogue and the scorecards from the six&#13;
to provide needed promotion, backstopping, awareness            states that participated in the CSO2 process.&#13;
creation, and monitoring. UNICEF is actively supporting&#13;
the states to roll out CLTS.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table 3&#13;
Key dates in the reform of the sector in Nigeria&#13;
&#13;
Year	               Event&#13;
Early C20 	th&#13;
                    Public water supply commences in a few towns managed at the lowest administrative level.&#13;
                    Amongst the early beneficiaries are Lagos, Calabar, Kano, Ibadan, Abeokuta, Ijebu Ode (Ogun&#13;
                    state), and Enugu. Schemes maintained with revenue from water sales with virtually no operational&#13;
                    subvention from government&#13;
1950s	              Financial and technical responsibilities for developing new water schemes assumed by regional&#13;
                    governments&#13;
1966	               First water corporation formed in the Western Region in 1966 to take over assets and liabilities,&#13;
                    and existing staff. Staff of Water Division, Ministry of Works transferred to new corporation&#13;
1970s	              Formation of water corporations spreads to all 36 states and the Federal Capital Territory, with&#13;
                    water boards/corporations or public utilities managing their water supply&#13;
1979+	              Agricultural Development Programs (ADPs) rolled out in many states with rural water supply&#13;
                    components as a means of improving the lives of farmers&#13;
1976	               Federal Ministry of Water Resources and 11 River Basin Development Authorities (RBDAs) created.&#13;
                    RBDAs to provide bulk water for irrigation, drinking water supply, among others&#13;
1993	               Water Decree 101, the principle legislation governing the utilization and pollution control of the&#13;
                    water resources&#13;
2000-06	            Preparation of key policy and strategy documents, guidelines, model laws including: National&#13;
                    Water and Sanitation Policy (2000), National Water Policy (2004), National Water Sanitation Policy&#13;
                    (2006), National Water Resources Strategy (2006), Draft National Water Bill, WIMAG&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
14&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                Water Supply and Sanitation in Nigeria: Turning Finance into Services for 2015 and Beyond&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
4.	 Institutional Framework&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Priority actions for institutional framework&#13;
  â&#128;¢	   Support the completion of the preparation of state water policies.&#13;
  â&#128;¢	   Clearly identify an institutional home for sanitation.&#13;
  â&#128;¢	   Promote the private sector to provide goods and services as government exits service provision.&#13;
  â&#128;¢	   Undertake phased establishment of regulatory commissions in all states (as proposed by the NWP).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Nigeria scores well against scorecard indicators relating        some caution. Figure 5 outlines the key institutions in the&#13;
to the institutional framework for service delivery (Figure      sector and their principle roles.&#13;
4), outperforming the average for its economic peers. But&#13;
it should be appreciated that this is the situation at the       Framework for water supply, sanitation and&#13;
federal level where substantial progress has been made           hygiene delivery: The mandate for water supply is&#13;
to define institutional roles and develop sector policies.       clear at the level of the federal government. To a large&#13;
The situation is different in many states, where there is        extent this is true for water-borne sanitation as well, as&#13;
need for further reformâ&#128;&#148;developing state water policies,         the FMoWR has been assigned that oversight role. Whilst&#13;
setting state level targets, building capacities, reviewing      a few states have ministries dedicated solely to water&#13;
the edicts of state water utilities, among othersâ&#128;&#148;to guide       (for example, Kaduna state), in others the responsibilities&#13;
sector development and drive sector progress. Given that         are less clear and the water portfolio may be combined&#13;
actual service delivery takes place at the state and local       with agriculture, environment, community development,&#13;
levels, these scores should therefore be interpreted with        health or spread over a number of institutions. In such&#13;
                                                                 cases water supply has less visibility and some projects&#13;
                                                                 have made the establishment of ministries responsible&#13;
Figure 4                                                         for water one of their goals, for instance, the European&#13;
Scorecard indicator scores relating to institutional             Unionâ&#128;&#153;s (EUâ&#128;&#153;s) Water Supply and Sanitation Sector Reform&#13;
framework compared to peer group (see                            Programme (WSSSRP). The responsibility for sanitation at&#13;
endnotes)17                                                      the state and local government levels is even less clear and&#13;
                                                                 in most cases it is shared among a number of different&#13;
                          RWS                                    authorities: health, water resources, and environment.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                 Regulation: There is as yet no effective regulation of&#13;
                                                                 service providers in Nigeria. As far as it occurs, service&#13;
                                                                 regulation is undertaken by state ministries and, in many&#13;
    USH                              UWS                         instances, tariffs are set with little regard to the cost of&#13;
                                                                 service provision. Service quality, particularly in urban&#13;
                                                                 utilities, has considerably reduced, with frequent supply&#13;
                                                                 interruptions, high levels of nonrevenue water and poor&#13;
                                                                 customer engagement.18 The NWP seeks to address this&#13;
                          RSH                                    through the establishment of regulatory agencies at&#13;
                                                                 both state and federal levels, with the purpose of clearly&#13;
   Nigeria average scores&#13;
                                                                 separating roles of policy formulation, regulation, and&#13;
   Averages, MICs&#13;
                                                                 service provision, as well complementing the expected&#13;
Source: CSO2 scorecard.                                          involvement of the private sector.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                      15&#13;
&amp;#12;An AMCOW Country Status Overview&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 5&#13;
Institutional roles and relationships in the water supply and sanitation sector&#13;
&#13;
                                          Sewerage and&#13;
                     Water supply        related hygiene        General sanitation and         School         Urban&#13;
                                            promotion            hygiene promotion           sanitation     sanitation&#13;
   Sector            NCWR             FMoWR                         (MoEnv MoH)                MoE                          Federal&#13;
 leadership&#13;
&#13;
 Regulation                         SMoWR&#13;
&#13;
                         RBDA                                                                                               State&#13;
   Service&#13;
development           SWAs            RWSSA&#13;
and provision&#13;
                                    WES Dept                        LGAs                                                    Local&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NCWR, National Council on Water Resources: The highest water               SWAs, State Water Agencies or Boards: Responsible mainly&#13;
resources policy formulating body, chaired by the Federal Minister         for urban and semi-urban water supply. In many states separate&#13;
of Water Resources including representatives from the Federal              agencies exist for rural water supply.&#13;
Ministry of Environment and all State Government Commissioners             RWSSAs, Rural Water Supply and Sanitation Agencies (State&#13;
for Water Resources.                                                       Rural Water and Sanitation Agencies): Provision of potable&#13;
FMoWR, Federal Ministry of Water Resources: Has overall                    water to rural communities and improving sanitation and hygiene&#13;
responsibility for the management of water resources and is the            (latrine construction, hygiene education). Intended roles are&#13;
custodian and implementer of the National Water Policy and water-          facilitation and support to LGAs to implement WSS programs.&#13;
related sanitation. Functions relating to WSS are carried out through      WES Depts, Water and Environmental Sanitation&#13;
the Directorate of Water Supply and Quality Control (WS&amp;QC,                Departments: Established within local governments to oversee the&#13;
not shown).                                                                delivery of water and sanitation services, and provide support to&#13;
Other ministries: The Ministry of Environment (MoEnv) is largely           communities in the facilitiesâ&#128;&#153; management, sanitation promotion,&#13;
responsible for urban sanitation, mostly sewerage. At state level          and hygiene education.&#13;
State Ministries of Environment oversee environmental sanitation.          International and local NGOs: Most NGOs work at the level of&#13;
The Ministry of Health (MoH) and Ministry of Education (MoE) have          the state and local governments. The most visible in water and&#13;
roles in formulating community sanitation and hygiene, and school          sanitation is WaterAid, which has partnered some states/local&#13;
hygiene programs, respectively.                                            governments to build capacity of the WES Departments and to&#13;
NWRI, National Water Resources Institute: Provides training and            deliver water, sanitation and hygiene to rural communities (not&#13;
education, data collection, and dissemination services in the field of     shown).&#13;
water resources development (not shown).                                   LGAs (Local Government Areas): There are 774 LGAs. These are&#13;
RBDAs, River Basin Development Authorities/Boards: Charged                 responsible for the establishment, operation, and maintenance of&#13;
with the development, operation, and management of reservoirs              rural water supply schemes and sanitation facilities.&#13;
within their catchment area and provide bulk water supply for              WESCOMS, Water and Environmental Sanitation Committees:&#13;
water utilities and for irrigation. In the past some RBDAs provided        Responsible for the management of water and sanitation activities&#13;
borehole water to communities.                                             in the LGAs.&#13;
SMoWRs, State Ministries responsible for water resources:                  Private sector: There are three categories of involvement: (a)&#13;
Responsible for drinking water supply at the state level. In some          construction and drilling works; (b) supplying goods and services,&#13;
states these ministries have been engaged in actual implementation         and (c) water service provision. In many states there are a number&#13;
of projects contrary to the policy intentions to keep ministries to        of small-scale water and sanitation services providers. Not shown.&#13;
policy, regulation, and monitoring.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Facilitation: In many states, a range of ministries                        a facilitating role and empowering local councils and&#13;
and state agencies compete for space in implementing                       communities to engage the private sector to play this&#13;
water supply interventions. For example, rural agencies                    role. Commercially oriented entitiesâ&#128;&#148;both the private&#13;
continue to be the main providers of boreholes and                         sector and publicly ownedâ&#128;&#148;are yet to play very active&#13;
rural water and sanitation facilities instead of playing                   roles.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
16&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                Water Supply and Sanitation in Nigeria: Turning Finance into Services for 2015 and Beyond&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
5.	 Financing and its Implementation&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Priority actions for financing and its implementation&#13;
  â&#128;¢	    Agree on achievable national and state WSS targets (with MDG requirements as a minimum).&#13;
  â&#128;¢	    Prepare Strategic Investment Plans to meet state targets, and develop a financing plan.&#13;
  â&#128;¢	    Implement WIMAG to facilitate state-level policy and plan development as well as leverage matching&#13;
        finance for WSS.&#13;
  â&#128;¢	    Clearly indicate budget lines for sanitation for greater visibility and improve financial reporting to track&#13;
        sector investments.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The scorecard indicators relating to financing and its           inadequate funding, in large part explained by low tariffs&#13;
implementation range from the development of a                   and low utilization rates. The difficulty is exacerbated&#13;
Sector-Wide Approach (SWAp) and costed investment                by an absence of stakeholder participation through&#13;
program, to the overall sufficiency of finance and extent        annual subsector reviews, and absence of real autonomy&#13;
of utilization (foreign and domestic). As can be seen            in operational decision making. Additional obstacles,&#13;
from Figure 6, indicator scores are in-line with the peer-       at both federal and state levels, are the absence of&#13;
group average across the sanitation subsectors (though           operationalized subsector investment plans tailored&#13;
these could also be improved) but below average for              towards meeting the MDGs,20 the lack of a SWAp&#13;
the water supply subsectors. For UWS which scores                mechanism and the insufficiency of current financing to&#13;
rather poorly, the main challenge related to financing is        meet the set national targets. In particular, Nigeria could&#13;
                                                                 improve in the following areas:&#13;
&#13;
Figure 6                                                         Planning: Plurality of targets: Nigeriaâ&#128;&#153;s development&#13;
Scorecard indicator scores relating to financing                 agenda is set out in NEEDS. Most of what is articulated in&#13;
and its implementation, compared to peer                         NEEDS refers to actions by the federal government, whilst&#13;
group19                                                          states have prepared their State Economic Empowerment&#13;
                                                                 and Development Strategies (SEEDS). A major issue in&#13;
                          RWS                                    planning water supply and sanitation interventions in&#13;
                                                                 Nigeria is the plurality of national targets that have been&#13;
                                                                 developed at different points in time, as illustrated in&#13;
                                                                 Table 4.&#13;
&#13;
       USH                             UWS                       In addition to the above, the Presidential Water Initiative&#13;
                                                                 (PWI) launched in 2003 also aimed to provide, by the end&#13;
                                                                 of 2007, 100 percent water and sanitation access in state&#13;
                                                                 capitals, 75 percent water and sanitation access in other&#13;
                                                                 urban and semi-urban areas, and 66 percent water and&#13;
                          RSH                                    sanitation access in rural areas. There is no indication that&#13;
   Nigeria average scores                                        national budgeting has ever been linked with any of these&#13;
   Averages, MICs                                                targets. Furthermore, water and sanitation delivery takes&#13;
                                                                 place at the state level where states and local governments&#13;
Source: CSO2 scorecard.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                      17&#13;
&amp;#12;An AMCOW Country Status Overview&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table 4&#13;
Water supply and sanitation coverage estimates and targets from various government sources21&#13;
&#13;
     	 NW&amp;SP (2000)	 NEEDS (2005)	 NW-SP (2005)	                                       MDG Office	          Vision 2020&#13;
     							                                                                             (2007)		              (2009)&#13;
     Base/Target year	 2011	       2015	      2007	     2015	     2010	     2015	      2006	     2015	     2006	      2015&#13;
     Water (%)	     100%	 100%	               75%				                                 64.6%	    82.3%	     50%	       75%&#13;
     Sanitation (%)			                        65%		 65%	 80%	                         76.6%	    88.3%	     35%	       65%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
exercise control over the resources allocated to them. It        (Naira 42.7 billion) in 2001 to US$98 million (Naira 12.5&#13;
is therefore difficult to know to what extent state and          billion) in 2006.&#13;
local level priorities and spending are feeding into the&#13;
achievement of the national targets.                             In respect of funding by state governments, the findings&#13;
                                                                 from the study for 2000â&#128;&#147;07 in respect of the 12 states and&#13;
Budgeting: Directing finance effectively: A Fiscal               the federal capital territory that were covered indicated&#13;
Responsibility Act passed at the end of 2007 provides for a      that an average of US$15 million (highest US$24 million&#13;
comprehensive budgetary planning process derived from            and lowest US$10 million) was allocated to water supply&#13;
the Medium-Term Expenditure Framework (MTEF), and is             annually by the states from their own revenues. In respect&#13;
intended to â&#128;&#156;redirect governments at all levels to imbibe        of sanitation an average of US$3.7 million (highest US$6.1&#13;
a fiscal behavior that will promote prudence and sound           million and lowest US$1.6 million) was allocated. The&#13;
financial management in the systemâ&#128;&#157;. Essentially, the law        percentage of the total annual state budgets allocated to&#13;
sets out a general framework for budgetary planning,             water supply and sanitation ranged between 4.8 percent&#13;
execution, and reporting that is applicable to all levels of     and 9.9 percent in the case of water supply and from&#13;
government. However, the budgeting and channeling of             0.7 percent to 3.1 percent in the case of sanitation. Even&#13;
resources into water supply and sanitation remains a weak        within the individual states the proportions and amounts&#13;
area.22 In addition obtaining budget expenditure figures at      varied considerably from year to year.&#13;
state and local levels is very difficult, as experience during&#13;
the CSO2 process showed.                                         Actual disbursements from allocated budgets varied&#13;
                                                                 considerably among the states, and also from year to year,&#13;
Adequacy of financial commitments: The true                      and in general were below 60 percent. In some cases no&#13;
extent of funding for WSS nationally is difficult to obtain.     more than 10 percent of funds allocated were disbursed.&#13;
Preliminary findings from a Sector Investment Profile            Some states, however, showed consistently high levels&#13;
Study undertaken on behalf of the Nigerian Water and             of disbursements, notably Cross River State (above 90&#13;
Sanitation Monitoring Platform covering the period 2000â&#128;&#147;         percent in some years).&#13;
07 estimated that an average of US$154 million (Naira 20&#13;
billion) is allocated to the states annually by the federal      Aid to the water supply and sanitation sector is quite&#13;
government for WSS. There were, however, considerable            minimal in relation to total domestic sector outlays, as can&#13;
disparities in the allocation made by the federal government     be seen from Figure 7, which provides best estimates of&#13;
to the states, ranging from US$67 million to US$1,827            anticipated contributions from government, donors (and&#13;
million (0.21 percent to 5.7 percent of total allocated          NGOs) and users, relative to requirements. However, donor&#13;
funds) between the years 2003â&#128;&#147;07. As far as could be             funds have contributed significantly to sector reform and&#13;
discerned, no formula is used for the allocation of water        governance.23 There is as yet no SWAp mechanism at either&#13;
supply and sanitation funds to the states. Available figures     the federal level or the state level for donor coordination,&#13;
also show that there was a consistent decline in allocations     harmonization, and alignment. There is also a notable&#13;
to the states from the federal governmentâ&#128;&#148;real and               absence of comprehensive sector investment plans which&#13;
nominalâ&#128;&#148;over 2000â&#128;&#147;07 from a peak of US$427 million               could inform budgetary allocations.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
18&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                        Water Supply and Sanitation in Nigeria: Turning Finance into Services for 2015 and Beyond&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 7&#13;
Overall annual and per capita investment requirements and contribution of anticipated financing by&#13;
source24&#13;
&#13;
Rural water supply:                   Urban water supply:            Rural sanitation:                     Urban sanitation:&#13;
Total: $604,000,000                   Total: $1,110,000,000          Total: $1,050,000,000                 Total: $1,220,000,000&#13;
Per capita (new): $63                 Per capita (new): $90          Per capita (new): $75                 Per capita (new): $88&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Domestic anticipated investment          Assumed household investment&#13;
    External anticipated investment          Gap&#13;
&#13;
Source: CSO2 costing.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Criteria for allocation of finance: As an innovative                     percent) from the federal government. WIMAG sets out&#13;
mechanism awaiting implementation, WIMAG provides                        required actions (in relation to investment management&#13;
guidelines on best practice investment in water supply                   and planning, operational management, PSP contracts,&#13;
services. Its aim is also to provide a single mechanism by               project design, and implementation) and a set of&#13;
which funding for capital works projects in urban water                  performance indicators to be used in assessing overall&#13;
services can be made available from the federal government               performance improvements by water service providers.&#13;
to the states and applied. To support the implementation                 Its implementation will add additional funding to the&#13;
of WIMAG, participating states are required to undertake                 sector and is likely to bring more accountability to sector&#13;
a set of legal and institutional reforms in the water supply             investments, and stakeholders have called for its speedy&#13;
services sector in return for complementary funding (50                  implementation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                              19&#13;
&amp;#12;An AMCOW Country Status Overview&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
6.	 Sector Monitoring and Evaluation&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Priority actions for sector monitoring and evaluation&#13;
  â&#128;¢	    Implement the framework for M&amp;E which remains on the drawing board.&#13;
  â&#128;¢	    Institutionalize an Annual Sector Review dedicated to drinking water and sanitation.&#13;
  â&#128;¢	    Prepare annual consolidated sector output.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
As a federation with 36 states, one federal territory and        to M&amp;E in the water supply subsectors, it nevertheless&#13;
774 local government areas (LGAs), each with considerable        outperforms the group in the sanitation subsectors. User&#13;
fiscal authority and autonomy in service delivery, M&amp;E in        surveys (both by the national statistical authority and&#13;
Nigeriaâ&#128;&#153;s water supply and sanitation sector has been a          the FMoWR) have provided outcome data that are used&#13;
major challenge. A common framework for M&amp;E has been             for planning purposes. A number of weaknesses in the&#13;
designed and sector actors have met to agree indicators          sectorâ&#128;&#153;s M&amp;E are discussed here.&#13;
and definitions in 2008, but it is yet to be rolled out. The&#13;
framework envisages gathering data on assets, planning,          Absence of unit cost data: There is a notable&#13;
operational performance of service providers, and possibly       absence of unit cost data in Nigeria. As WSS services are&#13;
capturing impact (for example, health outcomes) using the        delivered through multiple institutions at different levels&#13;
various agencies at local, state, and federal levels. Figure 9   of government, unit costs for the development of new&#13;
shows the intended flow of information in the framework.         water and sanitation facilities in both rural and urban areas&#13;
Figure 8 indicates that while Nigeria performs below             are needed for benchmarking, planning, and ensuring&#13;
the peer-group average for scorecard indicators related          transparency and accountability in procurement.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                 Water quality: Through the combined efforts of&#13;
Figure 8                                                         UNICEF, the Standards Organization of Nigeria (SON), and&#13;
Scorecard indicator scores relating to sector M&amp;E,               the Federal Ministries of Water, Environment and Health, a&#13;
compared to peer group25                                         major regulatory toolâ&#128;&#148;the Nigerian Standard for Drinking&#13;
                                                                 Water Quality, NIS 554:2007â&#128;&#148;has been established&#13;
                                                                 through extensive consultation with stakeholders. All&#13;
                              RWS&#13;
                                                                 drinking water producers are expected to comply with&#13;
                                                                 the Standard. The FMoWR has also set up a Core Group&#13;
                                                                 on Water Quality, which has initiated the program&#13;
                                                                 â&#128;&#152;Community-Based Water Quality Surveillance, Household&#13;
        USH                              UWS                     Water Treatment and Safe Storageâ&#128;&#153;. The program is&#13;
                                                                 expected to be piloted in the six states of Zamfara, Taraba,&#13;
                                                                 Niger, Cross River, Ebonyi, and Oyo.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                 Reporting on expenditure vs. commitments:&#13;
                              RSH                                The CSO2 review was not able to discern any regular and&#13;
     Nigeria average scores&#13;
                                                                 comprehensive reporting of sector expenditure against&#13;
                                                                 allocations. In 2008, UNICEF, through the Nigeria Water&#13;
     Averages, MICs&#13;
                                                                 and Sanitation Monitoring Platform (an ACP-EU funded&#13;
Source: CSO2 scorecard.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
20&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                            Water Supply and Sanitation in Nigeria: Turning Finance into Services for 2015 and Beyond&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 9&#13;
Proposed M&amp;E data flow in Nigeriaâ&#128;&#153;s water sector&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                     STATE WATER&#13;
                                     URBAN WATER PROGRAMME                                           AGENCY&#13;
                                     National Urban Water Supply                 STATES&#13;
                                     Reform Programme (NUWSRP)&#13;
                                                                                 SWAs                INFORMAL SUPPLIERS&#13;
                                                NUWSRP&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                     PSP OPERATOR&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                          O&amp;M CONTRACTORS&#13;
                                     SMALL TOWNS PROGRAMME&#13;
  MONITORING                         Small Towns Water Supply and                STATES             COMMUNITY             COMMUNITY&#13;
     AND                             Sanitation Programme                                           CWA&#13;
                                                                                 SPCU&#13;
  EVALUATION                                       STWSSP                                                                 NGOs&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     RURAL WATER PROGRAMME&#13;
                                     Fed. Ministry Programme                     STATES                            LGA        VILLAGES&#13;
                                     supported by UNICEF&#13;
                                                                                 RWSSA&#13;
                                               FMWR/UNICEF&#13;
                                                                                 UNDP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                  RIVER BASIN DEV. AUTH.&#13;
                                                                                  RBDA&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Source: FMoWR. 2004. Nigeria: Framework for Monitoring and Evaluation of the Water Supply and Sanitation Sector.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
project) commissioned a study to analyze sector investment                    an indication of (supply-side) coverage, functionality or&#13;
in 12 states (two from each of the geopolitical zones of                      performance of utilities in extending their networks. The&#13;
the country) and three local governments (one from each                       closest to obtaining such information was the one-off&#13;
of the three senatorial districts). There have also been two                  national WSSBS of 2007. Discussions with federal officials,&#13;
Public Expenditure Reviews (PER) undertaken for Kaduna                        nonetheless, indicate a regular interaction with states on&#13;
and Cross River states. All studies reported challenges                       the development of policy and monitoring of reforms.&#13;
with accessing adequate data at state and LGA levels. The                     In the rural water supply and sanitation subsectors,&#13;
Federal Annual Budget Statements capture allocations to                       where UNICEF has been very active supporting states to&#13;
states, but hardly report any sector outputs.                                 implement programs, there is a regular forum for review&#13;
                                                                              of activities at state level.&#13;
Consolidated output reporting: There is no&#13;
consolidated reporting of national output, and in most cases                  Analysis of equity: Nigeria has a formula-based&#13;
this is also missing at state level, where implementation                     Revenue Allocation System which shares revenues&#13;
actually occurs. Consequently there is little data to provide                 from the Consolidated Fund with state and local&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                  21&#13;
&amp;#12;An AMCOW Country Status Overview&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
governments. Much of this revenue has been derived             equal financial allocations.26 Resources were allocated&#13;
from petroleum and mining rents and royalties. In              irrespective of the differing needs of the states.&#13;
relation to allocations to the states made by the federal&#13;
government for WSS, no established or published                Creating a dedicated annual review process&#13;
criteria were found. However, there have been two              for WSS: There is no dedicated annual review for&#13;
projects carried out by the federal government that            the water supply and sanitation sector. An annual&#13;
shared project activities equally between the states,          conference of the National Council on Water Resources&#13;
though this does not necessarily meet the test of equity.      is held, dedicated to a discussion of policy and&#13;
These are: (a) â&#128;&#152;Improved National Access to Water              implementation issues in relation to water resources&#13;
Supply and Sanitation 2000â&#128;&#153;, implemented between               management. Drinking water supply and sanitation are&#13;
2000â&#128;&#147;02, under which states received equal shares of           reported in this forum, but the representation and time&#13;
project components (rehabilitation of boreholes, new           given to WSS is inadequate. A dedicated WSS annual&#13;
handpump boreholes, and motorized boreholes); and              review using the Country Status Overview formatâ&#128;&#148;that&#13;
(b) â&#128;&#152;Constituency Water Supply Projectâ&#128;&#153;, implemented           has been tested in six statesâ&#128;&#148;would enable regular&#13;
through members of the National Assembly between               tracking of state-level reform, implementation, and&#13;
the years 2005 and 2007, and in which states received          operational performance.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     NOTE: Federal level scores mask significant state level variation&#13;
&#13;
     The presentation and discussion of coverage and investments which follow in Sections 7 to 10 are based on&#13;
     the CSO2 costing, using national access data and targets. The subsector scorecard results presented in this&#13;
     report are based on a scorecard assessment undertaken by sector actors at the federal level. They should,&#13;
     therefore, be interpreted with that understanding as they will differ from those at the state level, where&#13;
     service delivery actually takes place, and results also vary widely across states. The teamâ&#128;&#153;s scorecard assessment&#13;
     was not undertaken separately for the urban sanitation and hygiene subsector as there is little to distinguish&#13;
     the urban from rural service delivery pathway for the subsector at the federal level. The urban and rural&#13;
     sanitation service delivery pathways are, however, distinct at state level and conclusions are supported by&#13;
     findings of various underlying state level studies.&#13;
&#13;
     The accompanying commentary on the scorecard relates to those building blocks/factors that are relevant&#13;
     at the federal level, and can in turn help drive/facilitate service delivery at the state and local levels. These&#13;
     include the presence, and implementation, of sector policies and strategies (which should inform state level&#13;
     polices); effective regulation; availability of funding; and effective sector M&amp;E including measurement of sector&#13;
     performance through mechanisms such as annual reporting of outputs, and existence of annual reviews.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
22&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                          Water Supply and Sanitation in Nigeria: Turning Finance into Services for 2015 and Beyond&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
7.	 Subsector: Rural Water Supply&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       Priority actions for rural water supply&#13;
       â&#128;¢	    Establish Rural Water and Sanitation Agencies in states where this has not been done and limit their roles&#13;
             to facilitation and capacity building of LGAs.&#13;
       â&#128;¢	    Increase the pace of implementation of the Framework for Rural Water and Sanitation Delivery,&#13;
             emphasizing community ownership and management.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
RWS in Nigeria was estimated by the WSSBS 2007 at                          currently implement a policy of cost sharing. If rural users&#13;
49.9 percent. This contrasts with the JMPâ&#128;&#153;s estimate of 42                 were required to contribute 10 percent of the investment&#13;
percent in 2008, up from 30 percent in 1990. According                     costs of water supply facilities, total public investment&#13;
to the JMP, over 1990â&#128;&#147;2008, household connections                          requirements could be reduced by some US$60 million.&#13;
decreased from 4 percent of the rural population to 2                      Additional OPEX requirements are estimated at US$92&#13;
percent indicating a greater emphasis on other options                     million per yearâ&#128;&#148;currently this is either a real or deferred&#13;
for improved water supply. As shown in Figure 10 if the                    burden on public finance, since recovery of O&amp;M costs&#13;
current trend continues, Nigeria will miss the rural share                 from user fees is rare for rural and small town schemes.&#13;
of the national (MDG Office) target for water supply by a&#13;
significant margin (22 percentage points).                                 Figure 12 shows the scorecard results for the subsector,&#13;
                                                                           providing a snapshot of the service delivery pathway. The&#13;
The CSO2 cost model estimates a total annual capital                       scorecard uses a simple color code to indicate: building&#13;
investment requirement of US$604 million for RWS,                          blocks that are largely in place, acting as a driver on&#13;
to meet the above-mentioned target, of 69 percent                          service delivery (score &gt;2, green); building blocks that&#13;
coverage by 2015. This figure assumes that there is no                     are a drag on service delivery and require attention (score&#13;
user contribution from users as many of the states do not                  1â&#128;&#147;2, yellow); and building blocks that are inadequate,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 10                                                                  Figure 11&#13;
Rural water supply coverage                                                Rural water investment requirements&#13;
&#13;
           100%&#13;
            80%&#13;
Coverage&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            60%                                                                                 Required CAPEX&#13;
                                                                                                                                        Required&#13;
            40%                                                                                                                          OPEX&#13;
            20%&#13;
            0%&#13;
              1985	 1990	 1995	 2000	 2005	 2010	 2015	 2020              0	             200	            400	             600	            800&#13;
                                                                                                    US$ million/year&#13;
                  WSSBS 2007 estimate          Government target               Public CAPEX (anticipated)&#13;
                  JMP improved                 JMP, piped                      CAPEX deficit&#13;
&#13;
Sources: WSSBS 2007, MDG Office (2007), and JMP 2010 report.               Source: CSO2 costing.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                23&#13;
&amp;#12;An AMCOW Country Status Overview&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 12&#13;
Rural water supply scorecard&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
               Enabling                           Developing                                    Sustaining&#13;
     Policy     Planning   Budget       Expenditure Equity        Output          Maintenance Expansion         Use&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        3            1.5           1         1            1            1.5                1         1             2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Source: CSO2 scorecard.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
constituting a barrier to service delivery and a priority for   Figure 13&#13;
reform (score &lt;1, red).                                         Average RWS scorecard scores for enabling,&#13;
                                                                sustaining, and developing service delivery, and&#13;
The scorecard results as captured in Figure 12 show that        peer-group comparison&#13;
in relation to policy formulation (presence of subsector&#13;
                                                                                     Enabling&#13;
policies, nationally recognized targets and clarity of&#13;
institutional roles), the subsector has made some gains&#13;
at the federal level. However, the translation of policy&#13;
principles into actionable plans and budgets has been&#13;
weak: the scorecard shows lower scores for planning&#13;
and budgets due to the absence of a SWAp, dedicated&#13;
annual review, and inadequate finance. Among states,&#13;
only a few have promulgated state water policies that&#13;
provide direction on critical issues such as cost recovery,                                        Developing&#13;
                                                                     Sustaining&#13;
regulation, and separation of roles between policy making&#13;
and service provision.&#13;
                                                                   Nigeria average scores&#13;
                                                                   Averages, MICs&#13;
The scorecard also indicates the limited progress that&#13;
has been made in putting in place building blocks for           Source: CSO2 scorecard.&#13;
developing new services, and sustaining them once in&#13;
place. Equity of service development is restricted by&#13;
the lack of consistently applied criteria for allocating        expansion of RWS systems are even less likely to be&#13;
funds, or procedures for local participation in planning        obtained from users, and public support and planning for&#13;
and budgeting. Levels of expenditure (that is, budget           this purpose has been limited.&#13;
utilization) are low, insofar as they can be diagnosed.&#13;
Irregular monitoring of functionality, as well as limited       Figure 13 indicates that the average scorecard results&#13;
cost recovery for this purpose from user fees has restricted    for building blocks related to enabling, developing, and&#13;
maintenance of RWS systems. The spare parts supply              sustaining services are slightly lower than the averages&#13;
chain is also considered to be inadequate. Funds for            across Nigeriaâ&#128;&#153;s middle-income country peer-group.  &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
24&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                            Water Supply and Sanitation in Nigeria: Turning Finance into Services for 2015 and Beyond&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
8.	 Subsector: Urban Water Supply&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       Priority actions for urban water supply&#13;
       â&#128;¢	    Review edicts of water agencies to make them consistent with the National Water Policy.&#13;
       â&#128;¢	    Wean urban water utilities off state subsidies for O&amp;M and increase the pace of utility commercialization.&#13;
       â&#128;¢	    Undertake regular review of tariffs to permit O&amp;M cost recovery at a minimum.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 The WSSBS reported urban water access in 2007 at 69.3                       and NGOs, this leaves a financing gap of almost US$0.7&#13;
 percent. According to the JMP, 79 percent (27 million) of                   billion per year. Given the woeful lack of cost recovery,&#13;
 the urban population had access as of 1990, but coverage                    with many utilities dependent on state budgets to even&#13;
 had dropped to 75 percent (54 million) by 2008. Over                        cover salaries of staff, the OPEX requirements of US$0.2&#13;
 the same period 1990â&#128;&#147;2008, the proportion accessing                         billion per year will add to the public finance requirements&#13;
 water through household connections dropped from 32                         and thereby reduce the amount available for infrastructure&#13;
 percent to 11 percent, while the WSSBS reported 12.7                        expansion and renewal.&#13;
 percent as the household connection rate. The lower&#13;
 estimates provided by the WSBSS may be associated with                      Figures 16 and 17 show that scores for UWS are generally&#13;
 the categorization of the population into rural and urban,                  lower than those for the rural subsector in the case of&#13;
 as the rural access figure reported by the JMP in 2008 is                   building blocks associated with enabling and sustaining&#13;
 lower (42 percent) than that reported by the WSSBS for                      services, while the building blocks for developing services&#13;
 2007 (49.9 percent).                                                        score slightly higher.&#13;
&#13;
 Required CAPEX for UWS is estimated at US$1.1 billion                       In terms of enabling services, while policy issues have been&#13;
 annually. Against current best estimates of investments by                  clarified at the federal level, planning scores poorly as a&#13;
 federal, state, and local government, as well as donors                     result of the lack of sector investment plans (derived from&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Figure 14                                                                   Figure 15&#13;
 Urban water supply coverage                                                 Urban water supply investment requirements&#13;
&#13;
           100%&#13;
           80%&#13;
Coverage&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
           60%                                                                        Required CAPEX&#13;
                                                                                                                                         Required&#13;
           40%                                                                                                                            OPEX&#13;
           20%&#13;
            0%&#13;
              1985	 1990	 1995	 2000	 2005	 2010	 2015	 2020                0	                   500	                  1000	               1500&#13;
                                                                                                        US$ million/year&#13;
                  WSSBS 2007 estimates         Government target                 Public CAPEX (anticipated)&#13;
                  JMP, improved                JMP, piped                        CAPEX deficit&#13;
&#13;
 Sources: WSSBS 2007, MDG Office (2007), and JMP 2010 report.                Source: CSO2 costing.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                  25&#13;
&amp;#12;An AMCOW Country Status Overview&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 16&#13;
Urban water supply scorecard&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
               Enabling                             Developing                                    Sustaining&#13;
     Policy     Planning     Budget      Expenditure Equity         Output         Maintenance Expansion           Use&#13;
&#13;
        3            0.5           1          1.5          1.5           1.5                1.5       0.5           1.5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Source: CSO2 scorecard.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
state plansâ&#128;&#148;which are also missing) to inform investment          Figure 17&#13;
decisions. Budgets are inadequate and at present are              Average UWS scorecard scores for enabling,&#13;
not reported in an open and transparent way to enable             sustaining, and developing service delivery, and&#13;
proper monitoring. There are no sector review processes           peer-group comparison&#13;
and no SWAp, even though admittedly, donor aid for the&#13;
                                                                                        Enabling&#13;
sector is very low and does not present major problems&#13;
for coordination.&#13;
&#13;
The slightly stronger scores related to developing new&#13;
services arise from clearer reporting of expenditure by&#13;
some utilities (audited accounts), drinking water quality&#13;
standards, and dedicated pro-poor planning among urban&#13;
utilities. However, there is still no systematic application of   Sustaining                                Developing&#13;
budget allocation criteria or participatory procedures to&#13;
increase the equity of service development, nor is output&#13;
                                                                     Nigeria average scores&#13;
reported in a consolidated format.&#13;
                                                                     Averages, MICs&#13;
&#13;
As in the rural subsector, a particularly critical barrier to     Source: CSO2 scorecard.&#13;
&#13;
sustaining service delivery is the lack of appropriate tariffs&#13;
to meet operation and maintenance requirementsâ&#128;&#148;let&#13;
alone replacement costs. This not only denies service             unserved urban population, estimated at around 18 million.&#13;
providers the funds to meet day-to-day expenditures but           Nigeria underperforms against its peers throughout the&#13;
also compromises the expansion of services to the large           UWS service delivery pathway (Figure 17).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
26&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                           Water Supply and Sanitation in Nigeria: Turning Finance into Services for 2015 and Beyond&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 9.	 Subsector: Rural Sanitation and Hygiene&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       Priority actions for rural sanitation and hygiene&#13;
       â&#128;¢	    State governments to prioritize sanitationâ&#128;&#148;putting in place policies, plans, and budgets for sanitation.&#13;
       â&#128;¢	    Scale up implementation of CLTS and regularly review its contribution to improving access.&#13;
       â&#128;¢	    Improve awareness through advocacy to mobilize the public and private stakeholders on good sanitation&#13;
             and hygiene practices.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Rural access reported by the WSSBS for 2007 was 59.6                       funding from federal, state, and local government&#13;
 percent, whilst the JMP reported coverage of 28 percent                    will be for sanitation and hygiene promotion only. This&#13;
 for 2008, down from 36 percent in 1990. The significant                    theoretical cost share is reflected in Figure 19, which&#13;
 difference is largely explained in the definition of improved              shows household CAPEX contributions fully matching the&#13;
 sanitation under the WSSBS, which includes shared facilities               CAPEX requirement of over US$1 billion per year, to meet&#13;
 considered unimproved by the JMP. If shared facilities are                 the national target. However, there are major caveats.&#13;
 included in the JMP estimate the access figure rises to 42                 Firstly, it is doubtful how far CLTS is being adopted in&#13;
 percent. In relation to open defecation in rural areas, the                practice in different states. The anticipated public CAPEX&#13;
 JMP reports a high rate of 31 percent of rural population                  is in any case largely from donors, who in some cases may&#13;
 resorting to the practice, whilst the WSSBS reports 22.7                   continue to provide subventions for household sanitation&#13;
 percent. The rural share of the national sanitation target                 in their own projects. Second, government resources&#13;
 (MDG Office) of 87 percent (including shared facilities) will              (financial and human) for the necessary sanitation and&#13;
 be missed by a significant margin based on the historic                    hygiene promotion, and other â&#128;&#152;softwareâ&#128;&#153; activities such&#13;
 JMP trend line.                                                            as marketing, cannot be clearly discerned. The substantial&#13;
                                                                            assumed household contributions depicted in Figure 19&#13;
 As per current policy and emphasis on CLTS, households                     are thus likely to be illusory, and insofar as they arise,&#13;
 are required to meet the full cost of sanitation facilities;               cannot be attributed to government encouragement.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Figure 18                                                                  Figure 19&#13;
 Rural sanitation coverage                                                  Rural sanitation investment requirements&#13;
&#13;
           100%&#13;
           80%&#13;
Coverage&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
           60%                                                                             Required CAPEX&#13;
                                                                                                                               Required&#13;
           40%                                                                                                                  OPEX&#13;
&#13;
           20%&#13;
            0%&#13;
              1985	 1990	 1995	 2000	 2005	 2010	 2015	 2020               0	                   500	               1000	                  1500&#13;
                                                                                                    US$ million/year&#13;
              WSSBS 2007 estimate          Government target                    Public CAPEX (anticipated)&#13;
              JMP, improved                JMP, improved + shared               Household CAPEX (assumed)&#13;
&#13;
 Sources: WSSBS 2007, MDG Office (2007), and JMP 2010 report.               Source: CSO2 costing.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                 27&#13;
&amp;#12;An AMCOW Country Status Overview&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 20&#13;
Rural sanitation and hygiene scorecard&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                Enabling                                Developing                           Sustaining&#13;
     Policy      Planning          Budget      Expenditure Equity     Output      Markets       Uptake         Use&#13;
&#13;
       2.5             1                 1.5       2          0.5         1.5           1            0           1.5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Source: CSO2 scorecard.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 21                                                           framework that has addressed issues such as institutional&#13;
Average RSH scorecard scores for enabling,                          arrangements, community participation, funding and cost&#13;
sustaining, and developing service delivery, and                    sharing between different tiers of government. However,&#13;
peer-group comparison                                               these are still at the national level and in most cases have&#13;
                              Enabling                              not been translated to state and local government levels.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                    The most serious barriers are encountered with regard to&#13;
                                                                    equity and uptake of services. There appears to be even&#13;
                                                                    less attention to need when allocating the limited funds&#13;
                                                                    for sanitation, than for water supply. While the policy&#13;
                                                                    notes that households are responsible for investments in&#13;
                                                                    sanitation, there is no strategy on how household uptake&#13;
  Sustaining                                    Developing          is to be encouraged, nor is there a well-defined micro-&#13;
                                                                    finance scheme to support households to build their own&#13;
     Nigeria average scores                                         facilities. The extent of CLTS uptake cannot be ascertained&#13;
     Averages, MICs                                                 at the state level due to lack of a monitoring mechanism,&#13;
Source: CSO2 scorecard.&#13;
                                                                    and a lack of capacity among the local government&#13;
                                                                    WES Departments to undertake any form of planning,&#13;
These estimates do not include CAPEX for schools and                backstopping, and M&amp;E.&#13;
other institutional facilities. There is a relatively small&#13;
additional estimated OPEX requirement of US$94 million              Some of the state-level CSO2 scorecard assessments&#13;
per year, which households might be expected to meet as             depict low sanitation budgets, and often an absence&#13;
part of general upkeep of private facilities.                       of a budget line, as well as lack of clarity in respect of&#13;
                                                                    expenditure.&#13;
Scores for the rural sanitation subsector show several&#13;
critical barriers in the service delivery pathway (Figure           Figure 21 indicates that Nigeriaâ&#128;&#153;s scorecard averages are&#13;
20). As in water supply, the enabling environment for               broadly in line with those for the peer-group of middle-&#13;
service delivery has been strengthened with a policy                income countries participating in the CSO2.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
28&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                           Water Supply and Sanitation in Nigeria: Turning Finance into Services for 2015 and Beyond&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 10.	Subsector: Urban Sanitation and Hygiene&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
           Priority actions for urban sanitation and hygiene&#13;
           â&#128;¢	    Identify clear leader for sanitation service delivery in urban areas.&#13;
           â&#128;¢	    Develop and implement appropriate sanitation approaches in peri-urban and low income communities.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Access to sanitation in urban areas was reported by                        indication of anticipated expenditure and therefore it is&#13;
 the WSSBS at 85.2 percent as of 2007, whilst the JMP                       difficult to establish the true extent of the financing gap.&#13;
 reported coverage of 36 percent for 2008, down from 39                     However, available evidence points to negligible amounts&#13;
 percent in 1990. Over the same period the JMPâ&#128;&#153;s estimate                   of public finance for the sector (US$15 million per year).&#13;
 of the proportion of the urban population using shared                     For the purposes of the CSO2 costing, cost share between&#13;
 facilities fell from 42 percent to 38 percent. The decline                 public and households is assumed to be 50:50 for sanitation&#13;
 in sanitation coverage can, in part, be attributed to the                  hardware, that is, any anticipated expenditure from public&#13;
 effects of rapid urbanization. However, while there was                    sources is expected to leverage an equivalent investment&#13;
 a coverage decrease of 3 percentage points, in absolute                    from households. OPEX requirements are estimated at an&#13;
 terms 13 million people gained access to improved                          additional US$154 million per year for urban sanitation.&#13;
 sanitation. Including those sharing facilities, 26 million                 In the absence of operational cost recovery, this will also&#13;
 people gained access to sanitation. The subsector share of                 need to be subsidized from the public purse, at least in the&#13;
 the national sanitation target, of 89 percent (MDG Office,                 case of networked sanitation.&#13;
 including shared facilities) would only be met if the historic&#13;
 downward trend is reversed.                                                In the absence of detailed information on the urban&#13;
                                                                            sanitation situation at federal level, the scorecard for the&#13;
 To meet the above-mentioned target of 89 percent by 2015                   service delivery pathway mirrors that of the rural sanitation&#13;
 would require an estimated annual capital investment of                    subsector, with low building block scores in almost all&#13;
 US$1.2 billion per year. There is at the moment no reliable                areas (Figure 24). As in the rural subsector, there are clear&#13;
&#13;
 Figure 22                                                                  Figure 23&#13;
 Urban sanitation coverage                                                  Urban sanitation investment requirements&#13;
&#13;
           100%&#13;
            80%&#13;
Coverage&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            60%                                                                              Required CAPEX&#13;
                                                                                                                                         Required&#13;
            40%                                                                                                                           OPEX&#13;
&#13;
            20%&#13;
                0%&#13;
                  1985	 1990	 1995	 2000	 2005	 2010	 2015	 2020           0	                   500	               1000	                  1500&#13;
                                                                                                    US$ million/year&#13;
&#13;
                  WSSBS 2007 estimate         Government target                 Public CAPEX (anticipated)&#13;
                  JMP, improved               JMP, improved + shared            Household CAPEX (assumed)&#13;
                                                                                CAPEX deficit&#13;
 Sources: WSSBS 2007, MDG Office (2007), and JMP 2010 report.               Source: CSO2 costing.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                 29&#13;
&amp;#12;An AMCOW Country Status Overview&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 24&#13;
Urban sanitation and hygiene scorecard&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                 Enabling                              Developing                            Sustaining&#13;
      Policy      Planning       Budget       Expenditure Equity     Output       Markets       Uptake        Use&#13;
&#13;
        2.5               1        1.5             2         0.5         1.5           1            0           1.5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Source: CSO2 scorecard.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 25&#13;
Average USH scorecard scores for enabling,                         Unlike the rural subsector, where UNICEF is assisting many&#13;
sustaining, and developing service delivery, and                   states to roll out CLTS programs, building the capacity&#13;
peer-group comparison                                              of states and LGAs and local artisans to help in service&#13;
                                                                   delivery, among others, the urban sanitation subsector&#13;
                      Enabling                                     appears have been â&#128;&#152;orphanedâ&#128;&#153;, as there are no well-&#13;
                                                                   defined approaches for the promotion of household&#13;
                                                                   sanitation and no champions among the responsible&#13;
                                                                   institutions. For many states, there are no mechanisms for&#13;
                                                                   reporting subsector outputs, (save what periodic surveys&#13;
                                                                   are able to establish) due to â&#128;&#152;low managerial, executive&#13;
                                                                   and institutional capacities at the states and local&#13;
                                                                   government levelsâ&#128;&#153;.27 With a significant reliance on on-site&#13;
 Sustaining&#13;
                                          Developing               sanitation, the private sector plays an important role in&#13;
                                                                   providing services in excreta management, even though&#13;
                                                                   final disposal sites present an additional concern.&#13;
     Nigeria average scores&#13;
     Averages, MICs                                                There is very limited sewerage in Nigeria, except for&#13;
                                                                   Abuja and limited area of Lagos. On the whole only 6&#13;
Source: CSO2 scorecard.&#13;
                                                                   percent of the urban population has access to a sewerage&#13;
                                                                   connection. Being essentially an option that addresses the&#13;
policy statements which have been defined at the federal           immediate needs of the well-to-do (even though with long&#13;
level but these are yet to be rolled out at state and local        term societal benefits) sewerage networks cannot solve&#13;
government levels so as drive service delivery. In addition,       the countryâ&#128;&#153;s pressing urban sanitation challenges. This is&#13;
the policies are yet to be accompanied by well-defined             further compounded by inadequate water supply in most&#13;
implementation strategies. The indicator scores for the            of Nigeriaâ&#128;&#153;s cities. It therefore requires more innovative&#13;
â&#128;&#152;sustainingâ&#128;&#153; building block are particularly low, and are          small- to medium-sized, easier-to-manage technologies,&#13;
well below the score of Nigeriaâ&#128;&#153;s peer-group (Figure 25).          well suited to the needs of the poor.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
30&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                      Water Supply and Sanitation in Nigeria: Turning Finance into Services for 2015 and Beyond&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Notes and References&#13;
&#13;
	 Government of Nigeria. 2007. Water Supply and Sanitation&#13;
1&#13;
                                                                            policy, tools, and guidelines which draw their legitimacy&#13;
  Baseline Study (WSSBS).                                                   from the NWP. These documents have been prepared&#13;
                                                                            from studies and, in some cases, pilots undertaken in&#13;
	 World Bank, Global Economic Monitor. 2010 average.&#13;
2&#13;
                                                                            selected states. It is intended that the policies, strategies,&#13;
                                                                            and guidelines will have national appeal and be applied&#13;
	 The first round of CSOs was carried out in 2006 covering 16&#13;
3&#13;
                                                                            as tools for strengthening the institutional framework for&#13;
  countries and is summarized in the report, â&#128;&#152;Getting Africa&#13;
                                                                            water resources management. It is noted that some of&#13;
  On-Track to Meet the MDGs on Water and Sanitationâ&#128;&#153;.&#13;
                                                                            these documents still have â&#128;&#152;Draftâ&#128;&#153; tags on them. Many of&#13;
	 UNICEF and WHO Joint Monitoring Programme for Water&#13;
4                                                                           the provisions in these documents are being implemented&#13;
  Supply and Sanitation. 2010. Progress on sanitation and                   throughout the states, and do not appear to run foul of&#13;
  drinking water. JMP estimates are based on a linear                       any Act or Law. It is clear, though, that some states may&#13;
  regression of nationally representative household surveys.                be dragging their feet on the implementation of some&#13;
                                                                            aspects of the various policies and strategies because there&#13;
	 Office of the Special Assistant to the President on MDGs.&#13;
5&#13;
                                                                            is no clear direction and leadership from the FMoWR.&#13;
  2008. MDG Needs Assessment and Financing Strategy for&#13;
  Nigeria, p 37.                                                       17&#13;
                                                                         	 Indicators relating to the institutional framework section&#13;
                                                                           are: All subsectors: targets in national development plans/&#13;
	 The CSO2 investment requirement estimates do not&#13;
6&#13;
                                                                           PRSP; subsector policy agreed and approved (gazetted as&#13;
  include the cost of hygiene promotion and other software                 part of national policy or as standalone policy); RWS/UWS:&#13;
  activities, relative to the targets, due to the difficulty of            institutional roles defined; RSH/USH: institutional lead&#13;
  estimating such costs on a per capita basis.                             appointed.&#13;
	 Due to rounding, component figures may not sum to&#13;
7                                                                      18&#13;
                                                                         	 See, for example, the Synthesis Report on the Assessment&#13;
  totals.                                                                  of the Institutional Framework for Water Supply and&#13;
                                                                           Sanitation Provision in Anambra, Cross River and Osun&#13;
	 Targets used in the CSO2 costing model are from MDG&#13;
8&#13;
                                                                           states, funded by the EU and FMoWR. In Anambra the&#13;
  Office, 2007 for water supply and sanitation. Equivalent&#13;
                                                                           Water Board (utility) had not supplied water to the state&#13;
  rural/urban subsector targets are derived using the relative&#13;
                                                                           capital and other urban areas for more than 14 months at&#13;
  coverage of the rural and urban subsectors in 1990, as&#13;
                                                                           the time of the study in 2007 and residents had to depend&#13;
  estimated in the 2010 JMP report.&#13;
                                                                           on small scale providers (for example, tanker operators) as&#13;
	 Federal Ministry of Water Resources (FMoWR). 2006.&#13;
9                                                                          well as self-supply through wells and boreholes.&#13;
  Water Resources Strategy Document.                                   19&#13;
                                                                         	 Indicators relating to the section on financing and its&#13;
10&#13;
    	 Report of the Vision 2020 National Technical Working                 implementation are: All subsectors: programmatic SWAp;&#13;
      Group on Water and Sanitation. 2009, p 46.                           investment program based on MDG needs assessment;&#13;
                                                                           sufficient finance to meet MDG (or subsidy policy for&#13;
11&#13;
    	 FMoWR. 2006. Water Resources Strategy Document, p 1.                 sanitation); percent of official donor commitments utilized;&#13;
                                                                           percent of domestic commitments utilized.&#13;
12&#13;
    	 Final Draft National Water Policy. 2004, p 5.&#13;
                                                                       20&#13;
                                                                         	 Given the fact that there are 37 utilities (including that&#13;
13&#13;
    	 Ibid, p 6.                                                           for the federal territory), the scorecard cannot speak for&#13;
14&#13;
    	 This is articulated in the Draft National Water Policy,              all of them. Whilst the top threeâ&#128;&#148;Lagos, Cross River, and&#13;
      2004.                                                                Kaduna Water Boardsâ&#128;&#148;may score very high in terms of&#13;
                                                                           the scorecard, in a majority of cases performances are&#13;
15&#13;
    	 The CSO2 scorecard methodology and conceptual                        low.&#13;
      framework are discussed in detail in the synthesis report.       21&#13;
                                                                         	 The various targets are based on access data in the year&#13;
16&#13;
    	 As noted in a 2008 study, Water Resources Management In              in which the reports were prepared. For example, to&#13;
      Nigeria: Review of Reform Actions for Finalization of Water          reach Nigeriaâ&#128;&#153;s MDG target for water and sanitation, the&#13;
      Sector Institutional Framework, undertaken on behalf of              MDG Costing Report states a coverage target of 82.31&#13;
      FMoWR by this author, Nigeria has several documents on               percent access to safe drinking water by 2015, â&#128;&#156;based&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                            31&#13;
&amp;#12;An AMCOW Country Status Overview&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      on the existing current access (2006) of 64.62 percent              efforts at promotion, marketing, and other â&#128;&#152;softwareâ&#128;&#153;&#13;
      in 2006, while a target of 88.29 percent was fixed for              activities are significantly scaled up. [QUERY: should this&#13;
      basic sanitation from the current access (2006) of 76.56            be Sections 2 and 3?]&#13;
      percentâ&#128;&#157;. The JMP, however, uses 1990 access as baseline&#13;
      to determine the internationally recognized MDG targets.        	 Indicators relating to the M&amp;E section are: All subsectors:&#13;
                                                                     25&#13;
&#13;
                                                                        annual review setting new undertakings; subsector spend&#13;
22&#13;
     	 UNICEF, Joshua Attah, the Draft Report on Sector                 identifiable in budget (UWS: inc. recurrent subsidies);&#13;
       Investment Profile Study for Water Supply and Sanitation,        budget comprehensively covers domestic/donor finance;&#13;
       2000â&#128;&#147;2007, elaborates on expenditure on water and                RWS, RSH, and USH: domestic/donor expenditure&#13;
       sanitation at different levels of government in 12 states,       reported; UWS: audited accounts and balance sheets&#13;
       and the federal capital territory.                               from utilities; RWS, RSH, and USH: periodic analysis of&#13;
                                                                        equity criteria by CSOs and government; UWS: pro-poor&#13;
23&#13;
     	 The various aid projects by UNICEF, EU, AfDB and the World       plans developed and implemented by utilities; RWS/UWS:&#13;
       Bank have had common featuresâ&#128;&#148;institutional reform               nationally consolidated reporting of output; RSH/USH:&#13;
       and strengthening, private sector participation, capacity        monitoring of quantity and quality of uptake relative to&#13;
       building, support to policy development, in addition to          promotion and subsidy efforts; All subsectors: questions&#13;
       hardware delivery. These are carried out in separate states      and choice options in household surveys consistent with&#13;
       and the National Water Policy and strategy documents             MDG definitions.&#13;
       have been the reference for the reform activities.&#13;
                                                                      	 References were provided by Engineer Mohamed Illyas&#13;
                                                                     26&#13;
24&#13;
     	 As detailed in Section 9, the apparent sufficiency of            of Dal-Hab Consultants, Nigeria, through a note to the&#13;
       finance for rural sanitation is thanks largely to household      author. Actual project documents were not sighted.&#13;
       contributions, which are called for in policy (the CLTS&#13;
       approach) but which will not materialize in practice unless    	 See Note 26.&#13;
                                                                     27&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
32&#13;
&amp;#12;&amp;#12;For enquiries, contact:&#13;
Water and Sanitation Programâ&#128;&#147;Africa Region&#13;
The World Bank, Upper Hill Road&#13;
P.O. Box 30577, 00100, Nairobi, Kenya&#13;
Tel: +(254) 20 322 6300&#13;
E-mail: wspaf@worldbank.org&#13;
Web site: www.wsp.org&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="19188506">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2011/01/19188506/nigeria-water-supply-sanitation-nigeria-turning-finance-services-2015-beyond
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2011/01/19188506/nigeria-water-supply-sanitation-nigeria-turning-finance-services-2015-beyond</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2011/01/19188506/nigeria-water-supply-sanitation-nigeria-turning-finance-services-2015-beyond</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2014-03-03T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2014-03-03T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2014/03/03/000333037_20140303161532/Rendered/INDEX/700610REVISED00BLIC00CSO0Nigeria0En.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2014/03/03/000333037_20140303161532/Rendered/PDF/700610REVISED00BLIC00CSO0Nigeria0En.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2014-03-03T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2011-01-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Revised</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309936</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Nigeria - Water supply and sanitation in
            Nigeria : turning finance into services for 2015 and beyond
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            This analysis aims to help Nigeria
            assess its own service delivery pathways for turning finance
            into water supply and sanitation services, in the subsectors
            of rural and urban water supply, rural and urban sanitation,
            and hygiene. This second Country Status Overview (CSO2)
            compares Nigeria's own estimates of coverage with data
            from the UNICEF/WHO Joint Monitoring Programme (JMP). The
            impact of these different coverage estimates on investment
            requirements is also assessed. The analysis, commissioned by
            the African Ministers Council on Water (AMCOW), has three
            main components: a review of past coverage; a costing model
            to assess the adequacy of future investments; and a
            scorecard which allows diagnosis of particular bottlenecks
            along the service delivery pathway. This Country Status
            Overview's (CSO2) contribution, is to answer not only
            whether past trends and future finance are sufficient to
            meet sector targets, but what specific issues need to be
            addressed to ensure finance is effectively turned into
            accelerated coverage in water supply and sanitation. In this
            spirit, specific priority actions have been identified
            through consultation.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Nigeria - Water supply and sanitation in
            Nigeria : turning finance into services for 2015 and beyond
        </docna>
        <display_title>Nigeria - Water supply and
            sanitation in Nigeria : turning finance into services for
            2015 and beyond</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2011/01/19188506/nigeria-water-supply-sanitation-nigeria-turning-finance-services-2015-beyond</listing_relative_url>
        <projn>3A-Country Status Overviews On Water Supply
            And Sanitation 2010 -- P117854</projn>
        <docty>UNDP-Water &amp; Sanitation Program</docty>
        <subtopic>Town Water Supply and Sanitation,Water Supply and Systems,Urban Water Supply and Sanitation,Water Supply and Sanitation Governance
            and Institutions,Water and Industry</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Water Supply and Sanitation,Water Resources</teratopic>
        <count>Africa</count>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000333037_20140303161532</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <theme>Water resource management</theme>
        <subsc>General water, sanitation and flood
            protection sector</subsc>
        <admreg>Africa,Africa</admreg>
        <colti>An AMCOW country status overview</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Water Supply and Sanitation,Water Resources</historic_topic>
        <prdln>Economic and Sector Work</prdln>
        <sectr>Water, sanitation and flood protection</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            access to safe drinking water, Access to
            sanitation, Access to Water, Access to Water Supply,
            Agricultural Development, allocation of water, Allocation
            System, basic sanitation, Basin Development, boreholes, bulk
            water, bulk water supply, capacity building, catchment,
            catchment area, community development, community
            participation, community sanitation, connection rate, cost
            recovery, cost sharing, costs of water supply, covering,
            cubic meters, dams, decision making, delivery of water,
            drinking water, Drinking Water Quality, drinking water
            supply, Environmental Sanitation, groundwater, groundwater
            resources, high levels, household connection, household
            connections, household sanitation, households, hygiene,
            hygiene education, hygiene promotion, inadequate water,
            investment cost, investment costs, investment decisions,
            investment in water supply, investment planning, investment
            program, investment requirements, investments in sanitation,
            irrigation, latrine, latrine construction, latrines, local
            councils, maintenance requirements, management of water,
            National Water, National Water Policy, National Water
            Resources, National Water Resources Management, nonrevenue
            water, number of people with access, open defecation,
            operational costs, operational management, operational
            performance, operators, oversight role, performance
            improvements, performance indicators, performance of service
            providers, pollution, pollution control, potable water,
            public utilities, Public water, Public water supply, quality
            standards, rapid urbanization, regulatory agencies,
            reservoirs, River Basin, River Water, rural communities,
            Rural sanitation, Rural water, Rural water supply,
            sanitation access, sanitation activities, Sanitation
            Agencies, sanitation coverage, sanitation facilities,
            sanitation investment, Sanitation Policies, Sanitation
            Policy, Sanitation Program, sanitation promotion, Sanitation
            Sector, sanitation service, sanitation service delivery,
            sanitation services, sanitation systems, service delivery,
            Service development, service providers, service provision,
            Service quality, Sewerage, sewerage networks, small scale
            providers, small town, small town schemes, SMALL TOWNS,
            Small Towns Water Supply, spare parts, stakeholder
            participation, supply interruptions, supply Water, surface
            water, sustainable services, sustainable use, towns, urban
            areas, Urban sanitation, urban utilities, Urban water, urban
            water services, Urban water supply, Urban water supply
            coverage, users, utilities, utility staff, Water Board,
            Water Boards, water delivery system, Water Investments,
            water pipelines, water policies, Water Policy, water
            quality, water quality monitoring, water resource, water
            resource infrastructure, water resource management, Water
            Resources, water resources development, Water Resources
            Management, water sales, Water Sanitation, water schemes,
            water sector, water service, water service providers, water
            service provision, water services, Water Supply, water
            supply agencies, water supply facilities, water supply
            services, Water Treatment, water utilities
        </keywd>
        <owner>Water - Water &amp; Sant. Prgrm-AFR (GWASA)</owner>
        <majtheme>Environment and natural resource management</majtheme>
        <repnb>70061</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation and Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Infrastructure (Water and Wastewater)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Water and Small Town Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Basic Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>On-site Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Marketing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Management of Public Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Finance Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Finances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Economics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Economics &amp; Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Town Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural &amp; Small Town Water &amp; Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Boundaries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Copyright</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Resources Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water, Sanitation and Hygiene</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Local Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>