<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>                                   85590&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
An AMCOW Country Status Overview&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Water&#13;
Supply and&#13;
Sanitation in&#13;
The Gambia&#13;
Turning Finance into&#13;
Services for 2015&#13;
and Beyond&#13;
&amp;#12;The first round of Country Status Overviews (CSO1) published in 2006 benchmarked the preparedness of sectors of&#13;
 16 countries in Africa to meet the WSS MDGs based on their medium-term spending plans and a set of â&#128;&#152;success&#13;
factorsâ&#128;&#153; selected from regional experience. Combined with a process of national stakeholder consultation, this&#13;
prompted countries to ask whether they had those â&#128;&#152;success factorsâ&#128;&#153; in place and, if not, whether they should put&#13;
them in place.&#13;
&#13;
The second round of Country Status Overviews (CSO2) has built on both the method and the process developed in&#13;
CSO1. The â&#128;&#152;success factorsâ&#128;&#153; have been supplemented with additional factors drawn from country and regional analysis&#13;
to develop the CSO2 scorecard. Together these reflect the essential steps, functions and results in translating finance&#13;
into services through government systemsâ&#128;&#148;in line with Paris Principles for aid effectiveness. The data and summary&#13;
assessments have been drawn from local data sources and compared with internationally reported data, and, wherever&#13;
possible, the assessments have been subject to broad-based consultations with lead government agencies and country&#13;
sector stakeholders, including donor institutions.&#13;
&#13;
This second set of 32 Country Status Overviews (CSO2) on water supply and sanitation was commissioned by the&#13;
African Ministersâ&#128;&#153; Council on Water (AMCOW). Development of the CSO2 was led by the World Bank administered&#13;
Water and Sanitation Program (WSP) in collaboration with the African Development Bank (AfDB), the United Nations&#13;
Childrenâ&#128;&#153;s Fund (UNICEF), the World Bank, and the World Health Organization (WHO).&#13;
&#13;
This report was produced in collaboration with the Government of The Gambia and other stakeholders during 2009/10.&#13;
Some sources cited may be informal documents that are not readily available.&#13;
&#13;
The findings, interpretations, and conclusions expressed in this volume do not necessarily reflect the views of the&#13;
collaborating institutions, their Executive Directors, or the governments they represent. The collaborating institutions&#13;
do not guarantee the accuracy of the data included in this work. The boundaries, colors, denominations, and other&#13;
information shown on any map in this work do not imply any judgment on the part of the collaborating institutions&#13;
concerning the legal status of any territory or the endorsement or acceptance of such boundaries.&#13;
&#13;
The material in this publication is copyrighted. Requests for permission to reproduce portions of it should be sent to&#13;
wsp@worldbank.org. The collaborating institutions encourage the dissemination of this work and will normally grant&#13;
permission promptly. For more information, please visit www.amcow.net or www.wsp.org.&#13;
&#13;
Photograph credits: Getty Images&#13;
&#13;
Â© 2011 Water and Sanitation Program&#13;
&amp;#12;An AMCOW Country Status Overview&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     Water&#13;
                     Supply and&#13;
                     Sanitation in&#13;
                     The Gambia&#13;
                     Turning Finance into&#13;
                     Services for 2015&#13;
                     and Beyond&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                            1&#13;
&amp;#12;An AMCOW Country Status Overview&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Strategic Overview&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The water supply and sanitation sector in The Gambia has              there is no official policy on cost sharing, though there is&#13;
been evolving gradually in the last two decades, in response          an implicit assumption that households will meet hardware&#13;
to rising demand and the challenges of maintaining sector             costs for on-site sanitation but not for sewerage. This&#13;
related infrastructure constructed as a response to Sahelian          underscores the need for an improved promotion and&#13;
drought in the 1970s and 1980s. An important achievement              marketing program to encourage households to invest in&#13;
has been the formulation and adoption of the National                 sanitation as well as a reassessment of the equity of publicly&#13;
Water Resources Policy in 2006 based on an integrated                 funded sewerage.&#13;
approach to water resources management. The Policy calls&#13;
for institutional restructuring and the development of an             Significant improvements can still be made throughout the&#13;
implementation strategy and regulatory framework. The                 service delivery pathway through which finance is turned&#13;
delay in implementing these and other reforms continues to            into services. Upstream, the formulation of a national&#13;
hamper the sectorâ&#128;&#153;s development. Reforms in sanitation have           policy for sanitation, and completion of the separation and&#13;
been slow, with the first draft policy document formulated            clarification of subsector institutional roles are vital.&#13;
in 2010. As a result, sanitation continues to be fragmented&#13;
among different agencies, with little coordination.                   The country lacks a comprehensive overall water supply&#13;
                                                                      and sanitation sector development programâ&#128;&#148;this makes it&#13;
It is expected that the reforms will create the needed                difficult to establish sector investment priorities and ensure&#13;
enabling environment for improved service delivery both               better coordination with donors. There is also no structured&#13;
in terms of quantity and quality. The Gambiaâ&#128;&#153;s challenge              mechanism for sector monitoring and performance&#13;
is to implement the reforms by developing strategies                  evaluation. It is expected that the introduction of Sector-&#13;
and investment plans, and undertaking the necessary                   Wide Approach (SWAp) as already proposed by the&#13;
institutional restructuring to further clarify roles and              government will help address some of these constraints.&#13;
responsibilities, whilst at the same time significantly scaling&#13;
up resources and systems for better delivery of services.             In addition, coordination, disbursement, and expenditure&#13;
                                                                      of finance can still be improved to make the most of&#13;
The rate of progress on sanitation coverage is slow and at            government and donor allocations to the sector.&#13;
current rates of progress only half of the population will&#13;
have access to safe sanitation by 2015. For the water supply          Moving downstream, aspects for developing and sustaining&#13;
subsector, significant progress has been made but this                services are relatively stronger, although issues such as&#13;
needs to be sustained to ensure sector targets are met.               equity of resource allocationâ&#128;&#148;at local level in rural areas,&#13;
                                                                      and in the absence of a clear strategy for pro-poor urban&#13;
Government financial allocation to water supply is still low          water supplyâ&#128;&#148;can be significantly improved.&#13;
with the bulk of investment funds coming from donors.&#13;
Estimates of investment requirements suggest that                     The second AMCOW Country Status Overview (CSO2) has&#13;
additional funding will be required for capital investment,           been produced in collaboration with the Government of&#13;
particularly rehabilitation of existing facilities. For sanitation,   The Gambia and other stakeholders.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
2&#13;
&amp;#12;                                              Water Supply and Sanitation in The Gambia: Turning Finance into Services for 2015 and Beyond&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Agreed priority actions to tackle these challenges, and ensure finance is effectively&#13;
turned into services, are:&#13;
&#13;
  Rural water supply&#13;
  â&#128;¢	 Develop local government area capacity to assume overall responsibility and better manage provision of water supply&#13;
     facilities in rural communities.&#13;
  â&#128;¢	 Improve subsector coordination and investment planning, and implement measures for periodic (annual) reviews&#13;
     alongside increased subsector funding.&#13;
  â&#128;¢	 Enhance targeting of rural water supply investments by developing and implementing a database to monitor&#13;
     coverage/functionality of rural water supply systems.&#13;
  â&#128;¢	 Build private sector capacity and enhance greater private sector participation in the development, repair, and&#13;
     maintenance of water supply facilities.&#13;
  â&#128;¢	 Promote greater sensitization for full community ownership of facilities and standardize technologies to facilitate&#13;
     availability of spare parts.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Urban water supply&#13;
  â&#128;¢	   Adopt a Sector-Wide Approach for subsector development and to improve subsector coordination.&#13;
  â&#128;¢	   Implement policy provisions regarding institutional roles and responsibilities.&#13;
  â&#128;¢	   Develop a clear pro-poor strategy to facilitate access for the poor including adoption of budget allocation criteria for&#13;
       equitable distribution of available resources.&#13;
  â&#128;¢	   Enhance adoption of corporate governance principles and raise funds from domestic and external sources for&#13;
       increased subsector funding.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Sanitation and hygiene, general&#13;
 â&#128;¢	    Complete preparation and adoption of the national sanitation policy and implementation strategy, ensuring that they:&#13;
 	     o	 Clearly define institutional roles and responsibilities;&#13;
 	     o	 Provide clarity on household subsidy for sanitation;&#13;
 	     o	 Enhance sanitation and hygiene promotion;&#13;
 	     o	 Enhance adoption of needs based investment planning; and&#13;
 	     o	 Emphasize monitoring and evaluation of subsector performance.&#13;
 â&#128;¢	    Increase local participation in investment planning and adopt effective budget allocation criteria.&#13;
 â&#128;¢	    Increase subsector funding and improve budget utilization rates.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Rural sanitation and hygiene&#13;
  â&#128;¢	   Adopt innovative approaches such as community-led total sanitation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Urban sanitation and hygiene&#13;
  â&#128;¢	   Develop decentralized low cost sewerage options in smaller urban centers.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                        3&#13;
&amp;#12;4&#13;
&amp;#12;Contents&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
	                                ........................................................................................................................... 6&#13;
       Acronyms and Abbreviations.&#13;
&#13;
1.	                .................................................................................................................................................... 7&#13;
       Introduction.&#13;
&#13;
2.	                                                ............................................................................................... 8&#13;
       Sector Overview: Coverage and Finance Trends.&#13;
&#13;
3.	                                                  ......................................................................................... 11&#13;
       Reform Context: Introducing the CSO2 Scorecard.&#13;
&#13;
4.	    Institutional Framework................................................................................................................................. 13&#13;
&#13;
5.	                                    .................................................................................................................. 16&#13;
       Financing and its Implementation.&#13;
&#13;
6.	    Sector Monitoring and Evaluation.................................................................................................................. 18&#13;
&#13;
7.	    Subsector: Rural Water Supply....................................................................................................................... 20&#13;
&#13;
8.	                                 ..................................................................................................................... 22&#13;
       Subsector: Urban Water Supply.&#13;
&#13;
9.	    Subsector: Rural Sanitation and Hygiene........................................................................................................ 24&#13;
&#13;
10.	                                          ...................................................................................................... 26&#13;
       Subsector: Urban Sanitation and Hygiene.&#13;
&#13;
	      Notes and References.................................................................................................................................... 28&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                        5&#13;
&amp;#12;An AMCOW Country Status Overview&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Acronyms and Abbreviations&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
AfDB	        African Development Bank                    NAWEC	    National Water and Electricity Company&#13;
AMCOW	       African Ministersâ&#128;&#153; Council on Water         NEA	      National Environment Agency&#13;
CAPEX	       Capital expenditure                         NGO	      Nongovernmental organization&#13;
CLTS	        Community-Led Total Sanitation              O&amp;M	      Operations and maintenance&#13;
CSO2	        Country Status Overviews (second round)     OPEX	     Operations expenditure&#13;
DCD	         Department for Community Development        PRSP	     Poverty Reduction Strategy Paper&#13;
DWO	         District Water Officers                     PURA	     Public Utilities Regulatory Authority&#13;
DWR	         Department of Water Resources               RSH	      Rural sanitation and hygiene&#13;
GDP	         Gross domestic product                      RWS	      Rural water supply&#13;
GNI	         Gross national income                       RWSSI	    Rural Water Supply and Sanitation Initiative&#13;
GUC	         The Gambia Utilities Corporation            SSA	      Sub-Saharan Africa&#13;
HH	          Household                                   SWAp	     Sector-Wide Approach&#13;
JMP	         Joint Monitoring Programme (UNICEF/WHO)     UNICEF	   United Nations Childrenâ&#128;&#153;s Fund&#13;
LGA	         Local Government Area                       USH	      Urban sanitation and hygiene&#13;
LIC	         Low-income country                          UWS	      Urban water supply&#13;
M&amp;E	         Monitoring and evaluation                   VDC	      Village Development Committee&#13;
MDG	         Millennium Development Goal                 VWC	      Village Water Committee&#13;
MICS	        Multiple Indicator Cluster Survey           WASH	     Water, sanitation and hygiene&#13;
MoE	         Ministry of Education                       WDC	      Ward Development Committee&#13;
MoEN	        Ministry of Energy                          WHO	      World Health Organization&#13;
MoF&amp;En	      Ministry of Forestry and Environment        WSP	      Water and Sanitation Program&#13;
MoFWR	       Ministry of Fisheries and Water Resources   WSS 	     Water supply and sanitation&#13;
MoH	         Ministry of Health                          WSWG	     Water Sector Working Group&#13;
MoLG	        Ministry of Local Government&#13;
&#13;
Exchange rate: US$1 = GMB 28.1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
6&#13;
&amp;#12;                                             Water Supply and Sanitation in The Gambia: Turning Finance into Services for 2015 and Beyond&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
1.	 Introduction&#13;
&#13;
The African Ministersâ&#128;&#153; Council on Water (AMCOW) commissioned the production of a second round of Country Status&#13;
Overviews (CSOs) to better understand what underpins progress in water supply and sanitation and what its member&#13;
governments can do to accelerate that progress across countries in Sub-Saharan Africa (SSA).2 AMCOW delegated this&#13;
task to the World Bankâ&#128;&#153;s Water and Sanitation Program and the African Development Bank who are implementing it&#13;
in close partnership with UNICEF and WHO in over 30 countries across SSA. This CSO2 report has been produced in&#13;
collaboration with the Government of The Gambia and other stakeholders during 2009/10.&#13;
&#13;
The analysis aims to help countries assess their own service delivery pathways for turning finance into water supply and&#13;
sanitation services in each of four subsectors: rural and urban water supply, and rural and urban sanitation and hygiene.&#13;
The CSO2 analysis has three main components: a review of past coverage; a costing model to assess the adequacy of&#13;
future investments; and a scorecard which allows diagnosis of particular bottlenecks along the service delivery pathway.&#13;
The CSO2â&#128;&#153;s contribution is to answer not only whether past trends and future finance are sufficient to meet sector&#13;
targets, but what specific issues need to be addressed to ensure finance is effectively turned into accelerated coverage in&#13;
water supply and sanitation. In this spirit, specific priority actions have been identified through consultation. A synthesis&#13;
report, available separately, presents best practice and shared learning to help realize these priority actions.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                       7&#13;
&amp;#12;An AMCOW Country Status Overview&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
2.	 Sector Overview:&#13;
    Coverage and Finance Trends&#13;
&#13;
Coverage: Assessing Past Progress                                                The CSO2 also compares countriesâ&#128;&#153; own estimates&#13;
                                                                                 of coverage with data from the UNICEF/WHO Joint&#13;
In response to the catastrophic effects of the Sahelian                          Monitoring Programme (JMP).4 The JMP coverage figures&#13;
drought that started in the â&#128;&#153;70s, the water sector has been                      are higher for both water supply and sanitation. For water&#13;
receiving government support that has resulted in steady                         supply, the JMP estimates show increasing coverage from&#13;
increase in water coverage. This general trend is confirmed                      74 percent in 1990 to 92 percent in 2008. The 2015&#13;
by various assessment studies, although each provides                            Millennium Development Goal (MDG) target of 87 percent&#13;
slightly different coverage estimates. The most recent                           is lower than that of the government by 8 percentage&#13;
figures are reported by the Multiple Indicator Cluster Survey                    points (Figure 1).5 The current JMP trend line portrays both&#13;
(MICS) 2006â&#128;&#148;a household level user survey which does                             government and MDG targets for water supply being met.&#13;
not take account of water quality and the functionality of                       For sanitation, the JMP estimates indicate a slower rate of&#13;
water supply systems. Due to this limitation, and based on                       increase, from 60 percent in 1993 to 67 percent in 2008.6&#13;
consensus with government and sector professionals, the                          The JMP trend line in Figure 1 shows that the 2015 MDG&#13;
MICS data have been adjusted downwards and adopted as                            target of 80 percent would be missed by 10 percentage&#13;
the current government estimates in the CSO2, resulting                          points based on historic progress, but that the government&#13;
in water coverage of 58 percent (50 percent rural and                            target would be exceeded slightly.&#13;
74 percent urban) in 1990 and 75 percent (70 percent&#13;
rural and 80 percent urban) in 2009â&#128;&#148;an increase of 17                            Investment Requirements: Testing the&#13;
percentage points over a period of 19 years. Coverage                            Sufficiency of Finance&#13;
figures for sanitation are lower and are estimated at 39&#13;
percent in 1990 and 48 percent in 2009 (urban and rural                          The estimates for investment are derived using the&#13;
areas combined). As illustrated in Figure 1, the present                         CSO2 MDG costing model. This incorporates the above&#13;
trends suggest that the 2015 national targets are not                            government coverage estimates and national targets,&#13;
likely to be achieved without substantial acceleration: 95                       together with government financial data obtained from the&#13;
percent for water supply overall (100 percent for urban                          Ministry of Finance (MoF) (national budget), the Ministry of&#13;
and 90 percent for rural areas); 73 percent for sanitation                       Fisheries and Water Resources (MoFWR) and the National&#13;
overall 80 percent for urban, 66 percent for rural).3                            Water and Electricity Company (NAWEC) (anticipated&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 1&#13;
Progress in water supply and sanitation coverage&#13;
&#13;
           100%                                                                             100%&#13;
           80%                                                                              80%&#13;
Coverage&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                 Coverage&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
           60%                                                                              60%&#13;
           40%                                                                              40%&#13;
           20%                                                                              20%&#13;
            0%                                                                               0%&#13;
              1985	 1990	 1995	 2000	 2005	 2010	 2015	 2020                                   1985	 1990	 1995	 2000	 2005	 2010	 2015	 2020&#13;
                    Government estimates             JMP target                                        Government estimates           Government target&#13;
                    JMP estimates                    MDG target                                        JMP estimates                  MDG target&#13;
Sources: Multi-Indicator Cluster Survey (MICS) 2006 (adjusted); Poverty Reduction Strategy Paper (PRSP) II; African Development Bank (AfDB) Rural Water Supply&#13;
and Sanitation Initiative (RWSSI); 2010 JMP report.&#13;
&#13;
8&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                 Water Supply and Sanitation in The Gambia: Turning Finance into Services for 2015 and Beyond&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
investments, additional rehabilitation requirements and                Due to a combination of higher coverage estimates&#13;
unit costs). The capital investment requirements (CAPEX)               and lower targets (at least in the case of water supply),&#13;
to meet the targets for water supply and sanitation are                investment requirements estimated using JMP data and&#13;
consequently compared with anticipated public CAPEX                    the MDG targets would be lower than those presented&#13;
(Figure 2).                                                            in Table 1.&#13;
&#13;
The model estimates the total annual CAPEX requirements                There are a number of reasons why the above depiction of&#13;
to meet the water supply target at US$41 million per year,             investments may be over-optimistic. The first is operation&#13;
of which only about 10 percent (US$4 million per year)                 and maintenance (O&amp;M) requirements (Table 2). As&#13;
is currently anticipated in public finance. This results in a          in many countries, in The Gambia there is an implicit&#13;
CAPEX deficit of US$37 million per year, assuming little               assumption that O&amp;M costs will be recovered from users,&#13;
or no contribution is made by users. However, future                   though in practice this is not always achieved. If any of&#13;
government policy on rural water supply (RWS) is likely to             the annual O&amp;M requirement has to be subsidized from&#13;
allow for some capital contribution by households.                     the public purse, for example, to utilities that do not&#13;
                                                                       achieve operational cost recovery, it reduces the amount&#13;
Total annual capital investment requirements for both                  available for capital investment. The NAWECâ&#128;&#153;s financial&#13;
rural and urban sanitation are estimated at US$7 million               performance improved with the increase in tariffs (about&#13;
per year, for which there are no discernable anticipated               30 percent) in December 2006. However, arrears were&#13;
public investments. The present draft government policy                estimated in October 2007 at 4.45 months of sales,8 and&#13;
on sanitation suggests a 25 percent user contribution for              operational difficulties of the utility continue to suggest&#13;
on-site sanitation (mostly in rural areas) and 0 percent               that public funds will be needed to support its operations.&#13;
for urban sewerage, but the costing model assumes                      In the rural subsector, major problems associated with the&#13;
this cannot be leveraged without public investment.                    large amounts and irregular payment of contributions by&#13;
Identifying how far public funds will be available for                 small rural communities to the rural O&amp;M fund have led to&#13;
sanitation capital investment is difficult. Public investment          the collapse of the maintenance system in the past.&#13;
to date has largely been for hygiene promotion activities,&#13;
such as public sensitization. Furthermore, public sector               The second is the lack of clarity of policy on user&#13;
budgets in The Gambia do not have a separate allocation                contribution, particularly for sanitation. In almost all cases&#13;
for sanitation, with investments lumped together with                  local communities are expected to self-finance on-site&#13;
those of water supply, community development, and                      sanitation in both rural and urban areas. Yet there is no&#13;
health. Stakeholders at the CSO2 consultation identified               clear policy as to how this is to be promoted. The meager&#13;
that a figure of US$7 million may be required for software             budget for the Department of Community Development,&#13;
activities only, let alone capital investment.                         which is responsible for sanitation promotion services, is&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 2&#13;
Required vs. public (anticipated) and household (assumed) expenditure for water supply and sanitation&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                  Required CAPEX                      Required                          Required CAPEX                        Required&#13;
                                                       OPEX                                                                    OPEX&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
0	          10	         20	         30	        40	         50          0	          2	           4	          6	           8	          10&#13;
                        US$ million/year                                                       US$ million/year&#13;
&#13;
     Public CAPEX (anticipated)	           CAPEX deficit                    CAPEX deficit&#13;
Source: CSO2 costing.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                           9&#13;
&amp;#12;An AMCOW Country Status Overview&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table 1&#13;
Coverage and investment figures7&#13;
&#13;
 	 Coverage	 Target	 Population	    CAPEX	      Anticipated	                                         Assumed	 Total&#13;
 			                  requiring	 requirements	 public CAPEX	                                            HH	   deficit&#13;
 			                    access			                                                                     CAPEX&#13;
 	                      1990	 2009	 2015				              Total	 Public	 Domestic	 External	 Total&#13;
 	                    %	   %	   %	 â&#128;&#152;000/year					       US$ million/year&#13;
 									&#13;
 Rural water supply	 50%	 70%	 90%	     42	  15	 15	 0	        3	        3	                                  0	    12&#13;
 Urban water supply	 74%	 80%	 100%	    77	  26	 26	 1	        0	        1	                                  0	    25&#13;
 Water supply total	 58%	 75%	 95%	   117	   41	 41	 1	        3	        4	                                  0	    37&#13;
 Rural sanitation	   37%	 40%	 66%	     46	   2	  1	 0	        0	        0	                                  0	     2&#13;
 Urban sanitation	   41%	 55%	 80%	     73	   6	  6	 0	        0	        0	                                  0	     6&#13;
 Sanitation total	   39%	 48%	 73%	   117	    7	  7	 0	        0	        0	                                  0	     7&#13;
&#13;
Source: CSO2 costing.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
inadequate. Additional funding is required to improve on       Table 2&#13;
the quality of services. User contribution towards urban       Annual O&amp;M, CSO2 estimates&#13;
sanitation (sewerage) appears to be negligible despite the&#13;
                                                                  Subsector	                         O&amp;M&#13;
high investment requirements.&#13;
                                                                  	                             US$ million/year&#13;
                                                                  Rural water supply	                    1&#13;
The third reason for caution is that CAPEX requirements&#13;
                                                                  Urban water supply	                    3&#13;
for both water supply and sanitation are generally                Water supply total	                    3&#13;
estimated based on the current mix of technologies. This          Rural sanitation	                      0&#13;
mix may change with possible increasing demand for                Urban sanitation	                      1&#13;
improved and more expensive technologies in both urban            Sanitation total	                      1&#13;
and rural areas, thereby increasing the overall investment&#13;
                                                               Source: CSO2 costing.&#13;
requirement.&#13;
                                                               should turn into services at the estimated unit costs.&#13;
These considerations are only part of the picture.             Where it is not, the above investment requirements may&#13;
Bottlenecks can, in fact, occur throughout the service         be gross underestimates. The rest of this report evaluates&#13;
delivery pathwayâ&#128;&#148;all the institutions, processes, and actors   the service delivery pathway in its entirety, locating the&#13;
that translate sector funding into sustainable services.       bottlenecks and presenting the agreed priority actions to&#13;
Where the pathway is well developed sector funding             help address them.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
10&#13;
&amp;#12;                                              Water Supply and Sanitation in The Gambia: Turning Finance into Services for 2015 and Beyond&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
3.	 Reform Context:&#13;
	 Introducing the CSO2 Scorecard&#13;
&#13;
The water and sanitation sector has undergone reform                Act and Regulations of 1990 set health standards and&#13;
since the early â&#128;&#153;70s when the government started to put             provided a supervisory framework for sanitation. However,&#13;
in place various policies, set targets, and establish relevant      the only major policy reform specifically addressing the&#13;
institutions to guide development activities in both the            sanitation subsectors is the formulation and adoption of&#13;
urban and rural subsectors. Over a period of more than              the National Water and Sanitation Plan for urban and peri-&#13;
30 years, it became necessary for sector development                urban areas (2006).&#13;
activities to be better coordinated, ultimately resulting in&#13;
the adoption of a National Water Resources Policy in 2006           Further along the service delivery pathway, key challenges&#13;
that provided the framework for integrated management               to developing new services (for which The Gambia also&#13;
of the water resources of The Gambia. This recent history           scores below its peer-group average) include limited&#13;
puts the service delivery pathway in context, which can             spending, absence of criteria for equitable allocation of&#13;
then be explored in detail using the CSO2 scorecard, an             resources, and inadequate promotional activities mainly in&#13;
assessment tool providing a snapshot of reform progress             the rural and urban sanitation subsectors. The downstream&#13;
across the building blocks that make up the service delivery        end of the service delivery pathway relates to sustaining&#13;
pathway.9 The CSO2 scorecard assesses the building                  services. As shown in Figure 3, The Gambiaâ&#128;&#153;s sustaining&#13;
blocks of service delivery in turn: three building blocks           building blocks perform above the peer-group average,&#13;
which relate to enabling services; three which relate to            reflecting gradual and consistent development of markets&#13;
developing new services; and three which relate to                  with evolving private sector participation, and water&#13;
sustaining services. Each building block is assessed against        supply subsectors on track to meet the national and MDG&#13;
specific indicators and scored from 1 to 3 accordingly.             targets (based on JMP data). Progress here can largely&#13;
                                                                    be attributed to the adoption of the Operational Policy&#13;
By the early â&#128;&#153;70s, as a result of serious water shortages&#13;
due to the Sahelian drought, the governmentâ&#128;&#153;s ability&#13;
to provide adequate water supply services in both&#13;
urban and rural areas had been adversely impacted.                  Figure 3&#13;
Exacerbated by a growing population, inadequate sector              Average scorecard results for enabling,&#13;
funding and development activities to meet the growing              sustaining, and developing service delivery, and&#13;
demand, it became necessary for the government to                   peer-group comparison&#13;
take action in creating an enabling policy environment,&#13;
                                                                                              Enabling&#13;
and to follow through with improvements in the physical&#13;
implementation of water infrastructure through the late&#13;
â&#128;&#153;80s. More recently, the government moved to ensure&#13;
integrated and sustainable delivery of services with the&#13;
adoption of Integrated Water Resource Management&#13;
delivery strategies in 2006.&#13;
&#13;
Figure 3 shows that the average score of The Gambiaâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
enabling building blocks is nonetheless lower than that&#13;
of its peer countries (low-income countries, LICs, with a                   Sustaining                    Developing&#13;
per capita GNI of less than US$500). This indicates less&#13;
                                                                       Gambia average scores&#13;
extensive policy and planning reforms with comparatively&#13;
                                                                       Averages, LICs, GNI p.p.&lt;=$500&#13;
limited budget allocation, particularly for the RWS and&#13;
rural and urban sanitation subsectors. The Public Health            Source: CSO2 scorecard.&#13;
                                                                                                                                       11&#13;
&amp;#12;An AMCOW Country Status Overview&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table 3&#13;
Key dates in the reform of the sector in The Gambia&#13;
&#13;
 Year	    Event&#13;
 1972	 Establishment of The Gambia Utilities Corporation Act, 1972&#13;
 1979	 National Water Resources Act, 1979&#13;
 1981	 Creation of the Ministry of Water Resources and the Environment&#13;
 1989	 Adoption of the new Operational Policy Guidelines for Water Supply&#13;
 1990	 Public Health Act, 1990, and Regulations, 1990 set health standards and provide a supervisory framework&#13;
 	     for sanitation&#13;
 1994	 National Environment Management Act, 1994 established the National Environment Agency (NEA)&#13;
 1995	 National Water and Electricity Company replaces The Gambia Utilities Corporation&#13;
 2001	 Establishment of The Gambia Public Utilities Regulatory Authority (PURA)&#13;
 2002	 Local Government Act, 2002 introduces decentralization program&#13;
 2005-	 Formulation and adoption of the National Water and Sanitation Plan for urban and peri-urban areas&#13;
 2006	&#13;
 2006	 Adoption of the National Water Resources Policy&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Guidelines for the National Water Resources Development        Sections 4 to 6 highlight challenges across three thematic&#13;
and Exploitation 1989, that paved the way for private sector   areasâ&#128;&#148;the institutional framework, finance, and&#13;
participation in the RWS sector; transferred responsibility    monitoring and evaluation (M&amp;E). The related scorecard&#13;
for operation and maintenance to users; and standardized       indicators which give an empirical basis for evaluation&#13;
well design, construction techniques, and handpumps to         are highlighted at the beginning of each section. The&#13;
facilitate training and repairs.                               scorecards for each subsector are presented in their&#13;
                                                               entirety in sections 7 to 10.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
12&#13;
&amp;#12;                                             Water Supply and Sanitation in The Gambia: Turning Finance into Services for 2015 and Beyond&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
4.	 Institutional Framework&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Commencing with The Gambia Utilities Corporation (GUC)             Figure 4&#13;
Act, 1972, which established GUC as a public corporation           Scorecard indicator scores relating to&#13;
to provide water supply, power, and sewerage services in           institutional framework compared to&#13;
urban and peri-urban areas, a number of reforms have               peer group (see endnotes)10&#13;
sought to provide institutional strengthening: clarifying                                    RWS&#13;
roles and responsibilities and enhancing investment&#13;
planning for efficient delivery of both urban and rural water&#13;
supply and sanitation services. The establishment of (a)&#13;
the Ministry of Water Resources for orderly development&#13;
and management of the nationâ&#128;&#153;s water resources in                      USH                                     UWS&#13;
1981; (b) the Department of Water Resources (DWR) for&#13;
management of donor-funded RWS program; and (c)&#13;
NAWEC in 1995 to replace GUCâ&#128;&#148;have contributed in&#13;
various ways towards achieving the national and MDG&#13;
sector targets for The Gambia. There are, nonetheless,                                       RSH&#13;
still several gaps and overlaps in terms of responsibilities.&#13;
                                                                      Gambia average scores&#13;
Figure 4 shows that related scorecard indicators, which&#13;
look at the extent to which national targets, policies, and           Averages, LICs, GNI p.p.&lt;=$500&#13;
&#13;
institutional roles have been put in place indicate below-         Source: CSO2 scorecard.&#13;
average performance for the sanitation subsector, while&#13;
the water supply subsectors achieve an average score in            of The Gambia. The Policy defines the responsibility of the&#13;
line with The Gambiaâ&#128;&#153;s peer group. This section considers          DWR in managing the resources, which includes licensing,&#13;
institutional challenges in detail, building on the snapshot       data collection, analysis and dissemination, and provides&#13;
provided by scorecard indicators with in-depth analysis.           for coordination at the regional, subnational, and national&#13;
Figure 7 presents the intended institutional roles and             levels in resource management.&#13;
responsibilities for the sector.&#13;
                                                                   The sanitation subsectors have no national policy in place&#13;
Policies and legislation: Providing guidance. Until                to guide development. Sanitation therefore continues to&#13;
recently, the only legislation guiding the water sector was        be spread across different agencies responsible for water,&#13;
the National Water Resources Council Act, 1979. The                health, education and community development, resulting&#13;
Act originally sought to provide a legal framework for             in fragmentation. The main governing instrument is the&#13;
the orderly development, exploitation, conservation, and           Public Health Act and Regulations of 1990. These set&#13;
preservation of water resources. The Act also provided for         health standards and provide, with respect to sanitation, a&#13;
the formulation of a water supply policy and a regulatory          supervisory framework for maintenance of proper sanitary&#13;
process, but this was not carried out for two-and-a-half           conditions of premises together with adequate measures&#13;
decades, leaving the sector without an overall national            for collection, removal, and sanitary disposal of human&#13;
policy to guide development. Government adoption                   waste. Currently, the lack of subsector policy is being&#13;
of the 2006 National Water Resources Policy, based on              addressed with the recent formulation of a draft Policy&#13;
integrated water resources management principles,                  with the Ministry of Health coordinating. However, longer&#13;
acknowledges that access to water is a common right,               term, a lead agency for the sanitation subsectors needs to&#13;
held in trust by the government on behalf of the people            be formally defined.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                      13&#13;
&amp;#12;An AMCOW Country Status Overview&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 5&#13;
Institutional roles and relationships in the water supply and sanitation sector&#13;
&#13;
                    Water supply         Sewerage and General sanitation and                      School          Urban&#13;
                                        related hygiene hygiene promotion                       sanitation      sanitation&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                  [&#13;
       Sector                              promotion&#13;
     leadership                MoEn &amp; MoFWR                     MoEnv, MoH, MoLG                  MoE                                 National&#13;
&#13;
     Regulation                     PURA&#13;
&#13;
   Service               DWR                        NAWEC &amp; DCD&#13;
development&#13;
and provision                      WDCs                                                                             LGAs          [   Regional&#13;
&#13;
                               VDCs &amp; VWCs                                             DPHOs&#13;
                                                                                                                                  [   Local&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
DCD: Department for Community Development. Community development extension services, including environmental sanitation.&#13;
DPHOs: District Public Health Officers; provide field extension services.&#13;
DWOs: District Water Officers.&#13;
DWR: Department of Water Resources. Supervisory services under MoFWR.&#13;
LGAs: Local Government Areas. Oversight responsibility for the WDC and VWCs at the local level. Supervision of urban sanitation.&#13;
MoE: Ministry of Education. Supervision of ESH in schools.&#13;
MoEn: Ministry of Energy. Policy lead on urban water supply, oversight of the NAWEC.&#13;
MoF&amp;En: Ministry of Forestry and Environment. Policy lead on environment and waste management.	&#13;
MoFWR: Ministry of Fisheries and Water Resources. Policy lead on rural water supply, oversight of DWR (including its sanitation activities); limited service&#13;
provision through WDCs.&#13;
MoH: Ministry of Health. Policy lead on physical health.&#13;
MoLG: Ministry of Local Government. Policy lead on environmental sanitation.&#13;
NAWEC: National Water Supply and Electricity Company. Urban water supply and sewerage services.&#13;
PURA: Public Utilities Regulatory Authority. Technical standards and tariffs.&#13;
WDCs: Ward Development Committees.&#13;
VDCs: Village Development Committees. Ownership of assets.&#13;
VWCs: Village Water Committees. Operation and management.&#13;
&#13;
Source: CSO2 analysis.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Strategic Investment Planning: Improving capacity.                              figures provided by the 2005 WSS Study. The need&#13;
The sector lacks a comprehensive development plan                               for improving capacity for periodic inventories and&#13;
for strategic investments. It is, therefore, difficult to                       functionality studies to update baseline data cannot be&#13;
establish priority areas for investment and ensure better                       overemphasized. Such an inventory is currently under&#13;
coordination with all sector development partners. The                          way for the rural subsector to provide adequate data for&#13;
situation may ultimately be attributed to the absence of                        investment planning.&#13;
adequate, validated, and up-to-date data on coverage.&#13;
At present, there are multiple coverage data sourcesâ&#128;&#148;                           Overall coordination: Defining leadership. Previously,&#13;
MICS3 (2006); the Water Supply and Sanitation (WSS)                             the only body that existed for sector coordination was the&#13;
Study (2005); The Gambia RWSSI Country Sector Situation                         Water and Sanitation Working Group (WSWG). The WSWG&#13;
Assessment Report (2004)â&#128;&#148;which provide different                                established three subcommittees (Water Supply Provision,&#13;
coverage figures based on varying basic definitions.                            Hygiene Education, and Environmental Sanitation) to&#13;
Some donors have used these figures to make investment                          develop subsector strategies. The Group collaborated&#13;
decisions in the sector. The current investment plan for                        with decentralized structures such as the Village Water&#13;
urban water supply (UWS) is based on the lower access                           Committees (VWCs) at the community level to coordinate&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
14&#13;
&amp;#12;                                            Water Supply and Sanitation in The Gambia: Turning Finance into Services for 2015 and Beyond&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
interventions in water supply, sanitation, and hygiene            Private sector participation: Increasing the space for&#13;
education. The WSWG no longer functions but remains               local entrepreneurs. The role of local entrepreneurs is&#13;
an example of workable arrangements in government to              gradually increasing. In the water supply subsector, they&#13;
ensure adequate sector coordination, harmonization, and           are contracted to construct urban and rural facilities and&#13;
alignment of overseas development assistance within a             also supply spare parts for maintenance of rural facilities&#13;
common framework. At present, the DWR appears to play             including solar powered reticulation systems (distribution&#13;
a leadership role and interacts individually with donors          systems for small towns and rural communities). The&#13;
at different times in an unstructured manner that does            market for borehole drilling continues to be dominated&#13;
not encourage setting of sector priorities, assessment of         by a few foreign firms. For sanitation, they provide&#13;
progress in relation to agreed targets or mapping out             construction of on-site sanitation facilities (in both rural&#13;
of future actions. In the present circumstances, donor            and urban areas) and septic tank emptying services (in&#13;
interventions have been project based. The role of the            urban areas). Large-scale private investment is unlikely&#13;
MoFWR in providing leadership for water supply needs to           due to the still-evolving tariff regulation regime. Despite&#13;
be clearly articulated. Also, the sanitation subsector needs      a relatively competitive domestic market in technology&#13;
a leader assigned among the three ministries that currently       and related services, there is limited contracting of private&#13;
carry out subsector functions: Environment, Health, and           enterprises to provide specialized sector related services,&#13;
Local Government.                                                 particularly management and operation of RWS.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                     15&#13;
&amp;#12;An AMCOW Country Status Overview&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
5.	 Financing and its Implementation&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
As can be seen from Figure 6, indicator scores related to         Budgetary allocations to the MoFWR for rural water supply&#13;
finance, which range from the development of a Sector-            are in the form of recurrent and development expenditure.&#13;
Wide Approach (SWAp) and costed investment program,               In the case of sanitation, allocations are fragmented and&#13;
to the overall sufficiency of finance and extent of utilization   not easy to extract from national government budgets as&#13;
(foreign and domestic), are slightly above average for            sanitation-related activities are included in the activities&#13;
rural and urban water supply but negligible for sanitation.       of a number of departments. Also, the majority of donor&#13;
Significant challenges in the way financial resources are         funding for sanitation is combined with funding for&#13;
sourced, allocated, and disbursed are outlined below.             water supply as single line items in the budget, with the&#13;
                                                                  disaggregation between water supply and sanitation only&#13;
Planning: Providing a roadmap for sector progress.                identifiable in detailed project documentation. In addition,&#13;
The lack of subsector investment planning, linked to              the government budget does not include all investment&#13;
available resources and designated targets, has inhibited         funding for the sector, omitting some major donors&#13;
progress. This is because UWS planning for the growth             including the European Union, the Japan International&#13;
centers has been limited until recently, although a master        Cooperation Agency, and the Saudi Fund. This situation&#13;
plan has now been prepared mainly for the Greater Banjul          does not allow a comprehensive analysis of the allocations&#13;
Area. In most such areas, domestic and commercial users           to each subsector from the budget alone, with the&#13;
are increasingly developing private groundwater-based             exception of UWS, where the budget adequately reflects&#13;
systems, which may have adverse impact on groundwater             investment funding.&#13;
availability.&#13;
                                                                  In the medium term, the outlook for investment finance&#13;
Budget allocations: Equity, comprehensiveness, and                for the sector remains positive. The Gambia continues&#13;
adequacy. In general there are no special formulae or             to attract funds to the sector but it is likely that, with&#13;
criteria for allocating public funding for water supply and&#13;
sanitation. However, in the case of RWS, local communities,       Figure 6&#13;
acting through the decentralized planning organs in the           Scorecard indicator scores relating to financing and&#13;
community, participate in investment decisions. The initial       its implementation, compared to peer group11&#13;
request comes from this level. The VWC12 determines                                         RWS&#13;
and submits the sector-related needs and priorities of its&#13;
village to the Village Development Committee (VDC), to&#13;
be included in the ward development plan prepared by&#13;
the Ward Development Committee (WDC). Subsequently,&#13;
these needs and priorities are incorporated into the annual           USH                                UWS&#13;
development plan of the council, which forms the basis of&#13;
community selection and budgetary allocations. In UWS,&#13;
there is no subnational formula-based allocation system.&#13;
The system appears to be open to political intervention,&#13;
however. In view of the importance of water supply in the                                   RSH&#13;
communities it is not surprising to see local community              Gambia average scores&#13;
representatives lobbying, with some measure of success,              Averages, LICs, GNI p.p.&lt;=$500&#13;
for provision of water supply facilities in their areas.          Source: CSO2 scorecard.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
16&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                  Water Supply and Sanitation in The Gambia: Turning Finance into Services for 2015 and Beyond&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 7&#13;
Overall annual and per capita investment requirements and contribution of&#13;
anticipated financing by source&#13;
Rural water supply:                  Urban water supply:            Rural sanitation:                   Urban sanitation:&#13;
Annual Finance Requirements          Annual Finance Requirements    Annual Finance Requirements         Annual Finance Requirements&#13;
Total: $15,400,000                   Total: $25,600,000             Total: $1,560,000                   Total: $5,640,000&#13;
Per capita (new): $48                Per capita (new): $87          Per capita (new): $17               Per capita (new): $51&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   Domestic anticipated investment          Assumed household investment&#13;
   External anticipated investment          Gap&#13;
Source: CSO2 costing model.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
the significant progress made in recent years, previous                 rather than programmatic approaches, often using&#13;
funding levels may not be sustained in the coming years.                parallel project implementation structures. This is partly&#13;
The governmentâ&#128;&#153;s allocations are not likely to increase                 attributed to the existing institutional weaknesses.&#13;
significantly in future because of the current economic                 Since 2006, the number of donors active in the sector&#13;
climate, but in any case the contributions are very low                 has pointed to the need for overall sector coordination;&#13;
in comparison to the level of investment required in the                according to the Second Poverty Reduction Strategy, the&#13;
sector. A comprehensive review of the sector financing                  government is gradually adopting a SWAp in relation to&#13;
is necessary to map out future challenges and develop                   development assistance. SWAps are considered to be an&#13;
strategies to address them.                                             integral part of Governmentâ&#128;&#153;s Aid Coordination Policy&#13;
                                                                        to ensure harmonized and aligned procurement and&#13;
Expenditure: Improving utilization rate. Generally,                     disbursement procedures for donor funding. However,&#13;
projects are observed to experience low budget utilization              while the approach has been introduced in the health and&#13;
rates at project start up, largely due to strict donor                  education sectors, it has yet to be extended to the WSS&#13;
disbursement and procurement procedures which result                    sector. In the absence of adequate capacity for planning&#13;
in disbursement rates of 10 percent to 30 percent. These                and management in WSS it will be difficult to successfully&#13;
initial delays often lead to project extensions. However,               implement a SWAp, and this limitation may explain the&#13;
once these preliminary problems with donor procedures                   gradual extension of SWAps to the other sectors.&#13;
have been resolved disbursements can rise to over 70&#13;
percent within a short period. That notwithstanding, while              Since 2006, total donor commitments amount to a little over&#13;
government allocations appear to be fully utilized, donor               US$94 million, of which 62 percent has been committed&#13;
allocations often have less than 50 percent utilization rate            to improvements in urban areas. Sector allocations from&#13;
overall, and optimizing use of available resources within               the national budget alone constitute less than 10 percent&#13;
planned implementation periods of projects, particularly                of the total anticipated investment in RWS. Thus, donor&#13;
from donors, remains desirable.                                         support is crucial in addressing the challenges facing&#13;
                                                                        the subsector. Figure 7 shows the relative contributions&#13;
Donor finance: Aligning and harmonizing. Donor                          from domestic and external sources for the subsectors,&#13;
assistance to WSS has been characterized by project                     alongside the gap in anticipated funding.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                           17&#13;
&amp;#12;An AMCOW Country Status Overview&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
6.	 Sector Monitoring and Evaluation&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
In The Gambia, the system of M&amp;E is very much focused          Figure 8&#13;
around projects and has yet to be developed into an            Scorecard indicator scores relating to sector M&amp;E,&#13;
integrated sectorwide system. Scorecard indicators             compared to peer group13&#13;
relating to M&amp;E include the existence of an annual review                                RWS&#13;
mechanism for the monitoring of output and consistency&#13;
of household surveys in monitoring water supply and&#13;
sanitation outcomes. Scores for The Gambia suggest&#13;
below average performance for rural water supply and&#13;
sanitation, while performance for the urban subsectors is           USH                               UWS&#13;
broadly in line with the peer group average (Figure 8).&#13;
&#13;
The Gambiaâ&#128;&#153;s modest performance is partly due to&#13;
the absence of a sector review mechanism at the&#13;
national level for providing analysis, strategic direction,                              RSH&#13;
and accountability. Reviews of expenditure against                Gambia average scores&#13;
commitments or nationally consolidated output reporting           Averages, LICs, GNI p.p.&lt;=$500&#13;
are very rare. Individual projects have their own monitoring   Source: CSO2 scorecard.&#13;
arrangements, undertaken by project management units&#13;
against expected outputs, but there are no performance         legal household connections and public standpipes in the&#13;
indicators to monitor sector performance as a whole. A         Greater Banjul Area and provincial growth centers. As a&#13;
sector development plan emphasizing M&amp;E will need to           private company, the NAWEC has its own mechanism&#13;
be developed and capacities strengthened for effective         for annual performance reviews. However, these reviews&#13;
M&amp;E of ongoing and future projects and programs. The           are guided mostly by commercial considerations. Efforts&#13;
ongoing UNICEF sector intervention coordinated through         to improve existing databases through periodic updating&#13;
its WATSAN (water and sanitation) project provides an          may be desirable.&#13;
effective monitoring system that could potentially be&#13;
scaled up to cover the entire country. As explained in the     Strengthening feedback. Figure 9 shows the intended&#13;
following paragraphs, the linkages within and between          M&amp;E cycle, indicating the need to develop and streamline&#13;
different stages in the M&amp;E cycle need to be considered and    the system of sector M&amp;E in The Gambia. Specific M&amp;E&#13;
strengthened, including efforts to foster accountability.      roles have yet to be designated, for example, for auditing&#13;
                                                               or performance monitoring. The links within and between&#13;
Improving database. For RWS, the DWR does not                  different stages of the M&amp;E cycle also need to be considered,&#13;
maintain a regularly updated database on water facilities      to ensure the evaluation is fed back into planning, and&#13;
nor does the Department for Community Development              is used to incentivize enhanced performance. Newly&#13;
have a database on sanitary facilities to aid determination    developed plans and strategies need to be developed in&#13;
of coverage. However, the DWR has just completed a             such a way as to ensure complementarities to existing&#13;
national inventory of water supply points in rural areas,      documents. An annual review covering all subsectors&#13;
which is being analyzed. Once completed, it will provide       would provide a useful forum for discussion of progress&#13;
useful baseline data for the rural subsector. For UWS          against sector plans and targets, and would set and review&#13;
and sewerage, the NAWEC maintains a database of all            undertakings made by sector stakeholders.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
18&#13;
&amp;#12;                                           Water Supply and Sanitation in The Gambia: Turning Finance into Services for 2015 and Beyond&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Accountability:       Improving     information        and       analysis of the national budget allocations to achieve&#13;
participation. Accountability extends beyond effective           human development goals. The Group used the 2000â&#128;&#147;05&#13;
M&amp;E structures, to ensuring that institutions foster the         national budgets to gauge the governmentâ&#128;&#153;s commitment&#13;
civic attitudes that allow them to respond, and be seen          towards attaining the service MDGs in The Gambia.&#13;
to respond to, users and other institutions. In this regard      The results are yet to be released but it is expected&#13;
civil society and nongovernmental organizations (NGOs)           that similar research/analysis will be undertaken in&#13;
have an important role. Recently, UNICEF commissioned            future by interest groups in the quest for transparency,&#13;
the Pro-Poor Advocacy Group, an NGO, to carry out an             accountability, and equity.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 9&#13;
The intended monitoring and evaluation cycle in The Gambian water sector&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Quarterly/annual performance,                  Policies for water and                        Various plans, strategies,&#13;
  accounting and license reports                 sanitation, as well as                        performance contracts&#13;
  provided by DWR to MoFWR, project              government plans                              and investment plans&#13;
  evaluations and sector performance                                                           developed (and being&#13;
  reports provided to donors, quarterly/                                                       developed) by MOFWR,&#13;
  annual public expenditure reviews for                                                        MOE, MoH and MoF&amp;En&#13;
  sector ministries                                             Objectives&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                     Reports                    Plans&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  3MTEFs encompassing WASH services&#13;
  (infrastructure, environment, and                  Budgets                  Indicators&#13;
  health); additional district budgets&#13;
  and special funds at the local level                          Information&#13;
                                                                  Systems&#13;
                                                                                           Proliferation of indicator&#13;
                                                                                           sets; Key Service Indicators,&#13;
                                                                                           Minimum Service Level&#13;
                                                                                           Indicators, WSS Performance&#13;
                                                                                           Indicators, and so on; also&#13;
   Systems to monitor WSS services in urban and rural areas and&#13;
                                                                                           â&#128;&#152;Sector Undertakingsâ&#128;&#153;, agreed&#13;
   provide a sector overview to be developed&#13;
                                                                                           at annual sector review&#13;
&#13;
Source: CSO2 analysis.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                    19&#13;
&amp;#12;An AMCOW Country Status Overview&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 7.	 Subsector: Rural Water Supply&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
           Priority actions for rural water supply&#13;
           â&#128;¢	    Develop Local Government Area capacity to assume overall responsibility and better manage provision of&#13;
                 water supply facilities in rural communities.&#13;
           â&#128;¢	    Improve subsector coordination and investment planning, and implement measures for periodic (annual)&#13;
                 reviews alongside increased subsector funding.&#13;
           â&#128;¢	    Enhance targeting of rural water supply investments by developing and implementing a database to&#13;
                 monitor coverage/functionality of rural water supply systems.&#13;
           â&#128;¢	    Build private sector capacity and enhance greater private sector participation in the development, repair,&#13;
                 and maintenance of water supply facilities.&#13;
           â&#128;¢	    Promote greater sensitization for full community ownership of facilities and standardize technologies to&#13;
                 facilitate availability of spare parts.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
According to government estimates, RWS coverage                        The CSO2 estimates US$15 million per year in capital&#13;
increased by 20 percentage points from 50 percent in 1990              investments (over the next five years) is required to&#13;
to 70 percent in 2009. At the present rate of increase,                achieve the 2015 government target. With an anticipated&#13;
the 2015 government target of 90 percent is likely to                  public investment of US$3 million per year, and little or&#13;
be missed by 14 percentage points. The JMP estimates                   no household contribution, a shortfall of US$12 million&#13;
suggest higher levels of coverage but a similar rate of                per year (Figure 11) is projected. An additional OPEX&#13;
increase over the same period. Thus the JMP trend line                 requirement of US$1 million per year is estimated which&#13;
depicts the 2015 target as likely to be achieved. Access via           may be a real or deferred burden on public finance, as&#13;
piped water supply remains limited in rural areas.                     recovery of O&amp;M costs from user fees is yet to be fully&#13;
                                                                       implemented for rural and small town schemes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Figure 10                                                             Figure 11&#13;
 Rural water supply coverage                                           Rural water supply investment requirements&#13;
           100%&#13;
            80%&#13;
Coverage&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            60%                                                                         Required CAPEX                     Required&#13;
            40%                                                                                                             OPEX&#13;
&#13;
            20%&#13;
                0%&#13;
                  1985	 1990	 1995	 2000	 2005	 2010	 2015	 2020       0	              5	             10	           15	            20&#13;
                                                                                                US$ million/year&#13;
                     Government estimates          Government target        Public CAPEX (anticipated)	            CAPEX deficit&#13;
                     JMP, Improved                 JMP, Piped&#13;
&#13;
Sources: MICS 2006 (adjusted); PRSP II; JMP 2010 report.               Source: CSO2 costing.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
20&#13;
&amp;#12;                                            Water Supply and Sanitation in The Gambia: Turning Finance into Services for 2015 and Beyond&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 12&#13;
Rural water supply scorecard&#13;
&#13;
               Enabling                            Developing                                   Sustaining&#13;
    Policy        Planning    Budget     Expenditure Equity         Output          Maintenance Expansion            Use&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       2.5                0     2            2.5           2              2.5               2            2              2.5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Source: CSO2 scorecard.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The full rural water supply subsector scorecard is shown          Figure 13&#13;
in Figure 12. The scorecard uses a simple color code to           Average RWS scorecard scores for enabling,&#13;
indicate: building blocks that are largely in place, acting       sustaining, and developing service delivery, and&#13;
as a driver on service delivery (score &gt;2, green); building       peer-group comparison&#13;
blocks that are a drag on service delivery and require                                  Enabling&#13;
attention (score 1â&#128;&#147;2, yellow); and building blocks that&#13;
are inadequate, constituting a barrier to service delivery&#13;
and a priority for reform (score &lt;1, red). The scorecard&#13;
indicates that planning, or the lack thereof, constitutes&#13;
a barrier, among the upstream enabling building blocks&#13;
of the service delivery pathway. This is attributable to the&#13;
absence of an overall sectorwide programmatic approach&#13;
and an investment plan, and lack of an adequate&#13;
mechanism for subsector periodic reviews. In addition,                 Sustaining                    Developing&#13;
the present performance in terms of the budget building&#13;
                                                                     Gambia average scores&#13;
block requires some improvement as budgetary allocations&#13;
to the subsector do not comprehensively cover domestic               Averages, LICs, GNI p.p.&lt;=$500&#13;
&#13;
and official donor investmentsâ&#128;&#148;less than 50 percent of            Source: CSO2 scorecard.&#13;
subsector funds are on budget. Compared to its peer&#13;
group, The Gambia scores worse for the enabling building&#13;
blocks, while scores are above average for building blocks        improvements, particularly with regard to maintenance&#13;
related to developing and sustaining services (Figure 13).        and expansion. Indicators for maintenance include&#13;
                                                                  the presence of regular functionality surveys (the first of&#13;
Despite the comparatively better performance downstream           which was commissioned in 2009, though there is no&#13;
in the service delivery pathway, the equity building block        evidence that it will be carried out regularly) and whether&#13;
constitutes a drag according to the CSO2 assessment,              user financing covers O&amp;M costs (rarely for rural schemes,&#13;
mainly due to the lack of measures by government to               but mostly in the case of small towns). With only partial&#13;
ensure consistent application and monitoring of the               operational cost recovery, there is very little finance&#13;
agreed budget allocation criteria in investment decisions         for expansion of rural and small townsâ&#128;&#153; water supply&#13;
at all times. Sustaining existing services also require some      schemes from users.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                     21&#13;
&amp;#12; An AMCOW Country Status Overview&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 8.	 Subsector: Urban Water Supply&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
           Priority actions for urban water supply&#13;
           â&#128;¢	   Adopt a SWAp for subsector development and improve subsector coordination.&#13;
           â&#128;¢	   Implement policy provisions regarding institutional roles and responsibilities.&#13;
           â&#128;¢	   Develop a clear pro-poor strategy to facilitate access for the poor including adoption of budget allocation&#13;
                criteria for equitable distribution of available resources.&#13;
           â&#128;¢	   Enhance adoption of corporate governance principles and raise funds from domestic and external sources&#13;
                for increased subsector funding.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Urban water supply coverage figures provided by the                 According to the CSO2 analyses, total CAPEX required to&#13;
 government show a slight increase from 74 percent in                reach the 2015 government target is about US$26 million&#13;
 1990 to 80 percent in 2009. At the current rate of increase,        per year. Anticipated public investments are a meager&#13;
 the government target of 100 percent coverage by 2015               US$1 million per year, and with little or no user financing,&#13;
 is not likely to be reached. On the other hand, the JMP             additional funds are needed to meet a financing gap of&#13;
 figures for improved water supply indicate a slightly more          US$25 million per year (Figure 15). OPEX requirements&#13;
 positive trend from a higher starting point of 85 percent           are estimated at US$3 million per year, which is a further&#13;
 in 1990, increasing to 96 percent in 2008, which would              drain on public finance as cost recovery from user fees&#13;
 not need to be accelerated to attain the target (Figure 14).        is ineffective.&#13;
 Also, according to the JMP, piped water supply constitutes&#13;
 more than a half of all urban systems; this would increase          The building blocks of the urban water supply service delivery&#13;
 to over two-thirds by 2015 based on the past trend.                 pathway are largely in place, with good scores (Figure 16).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Figure 14                                                           Figure 15&#13;
 Urban water supply coverage                                         Urban water supply investment requirements&#13;
           100%&#13;
           80%&#13;
Coverage&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                         Required CAPEX                                     Required&#13;
           60%&#13;
                                                                                                                                             OPEX&#13;
           40%&#13;
           20%&#13;
            0%&#13;
              1985	 1990	 1995	 2000	 2005	 2010	 2015	 2020         0	                      10	                      20	                   30&#13;
                                                                                                   US$ million/year&#13;
                   Government estimates          Government target        Public CAPEX (anticipated)	                       CAPEX deficit&#13;
                   JMP, improved                 JMP, piped&#13;
 Sources: MICS 2006 (adjusted); PRSP II; JMP 2010 report.            Source: CSO2 costing.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 22&#13;
&amp;#12;                                           Water Supply and Sanitation in The Gambia: Turning Finance into Services for 2015 and Beyond&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 16&#13;
Urban water supply scorecard&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
               Enabling                          Developing                                      Sustaining&#13;
    Policy        Planning   Budget    Expenditure     Equity       Output         Maintenance Expansion           Use&#13;
&#13;
        2.5           2        3            3              0             2.5               2.5          3              2.5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Source: CSO2 scorecard.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Reforms have improved the subsector outlook resulting in         Figure 17&#13;
above peer group average performance for the enabling            Average UWS scorecard scores for enabling,&#13;
and sustaining building blocks as shown in Figure 17.            sustaining, and developing service delivery, and&#13;
Reform of the NAWEC has lead to improving cost recovery          peer-group comparison&#13;
(operating ratio &gt;1.2) and hours of service (&gt;12 hours per&#13;
                                                                                       Enabling&#13;
day) supported by tariff reviews and adjustments by the&#13;
regulator (PURC). That notwithstanding, the planning&#13;
building blockâ&#128;&#153;s score indicates the lack of a sectorwide&#13;
programmatic approach, which could potentially facilitate&#13;
coordination and enhance investments in the subsector.&#13;
In addition, while institutional roles and responsibilities&#13;
among subsector institutions have been identified, they&#13;
need to be operationalized.&#13;
                                                                      Sustaining                    Developing&#13;
The major concern relates to equity. The lack of local&#13;
participation in investment planning and decisions                  Gambia average scores&#13;
&#13;
and, particularly, the absence of criteria for allocating           Averages, LICs, GNI p.p.&lt;=$500&#13;
development budget to the NAWEC in a consistent&#13;
                                                                 Source: CSO2 scorecard.&#13;
manner reduce the effectiveness of sector spending in&#13;
providing access to the unserved.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                    23&#13;
&amp;#12; An AMCOW Country Status Overview&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 9.	 Subsector: Rural Sanitation and Hygiene&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
           Priority actions for rural sanitation and hygiene&#13;
           â&#128;¢	    Complete preparation and adoption of the national sanitation policy and implementation strategy, ensuring that they:&#13;
           	     o	   Clearly define institutional roles and responsibilities;&#13;
           	     o	   Provide clarity on household subsidy for sanitation;&#13;
           	     o	   Enhance sanitation and hygiene promotion;&#13;
           	     o	   Enhance adoption of needs based investment planning; and&#13;
           	     o	   Emphasize monitoring and evaluation of subsector performance.&#13;
           â&#128;¢	    Increase local participation in investment planning and adopt effective budget allocation criteria.&#13;
           â&#128;¢	    Increase subsector funding and improve budget utilization rates.&#13;
           â&#128;¢	    Adopt innovative approaches such as community-led total sanitation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 The governmentâ&#128;&#153;s estimate of rural sanitation coverage                     of public finance means little or no contribution can be&#13;
 suggests an insignificant increase from 37 percent in 1990                 leveraged from households, even if the policy clearly&#13;
 to 40 percent in 2009, and at the present performance                      demanded this. The limited anticipated investments&#13;
 rate may only reach 41 percent (less than two-thirds of the                results in a deficit of US$2 million per year to be met&#13;
 government target of 66 percent) by 2015. As indicated                     through increased subsector funding. It is desirable that&#13;
 in Figure 18, this target is likely to be met according to                 policy on public financing for subsidies versus promotion&#13;
 the JMP data, which suggest 65 percent coverage in                         is clarified. Additional OPEX requirements are estimated to&#13;
 2008 would increase to 68 percent by the 2015 target                       be insignificant, and households are required by policy to&#13;
 year, based on past progress. The disparity between                        be responsible for O&amp;M of rural sanitation facilities.&#13;
 government and JMP estimates may be due to differences&#13;
 in the definition of improved sanitation coverage.                         The service delivery pathway for rural sanitation is&#13;
                                                                            less developed than that for rural water supply and&#13;
 The CSO2 estimates that a total of US$2 million per                        indicates barriers among several upstream enabling and&#13;
 year is required for sanitation hardware alone (that is,                   developing building blocks (Figure 20). The Gambia&#13;
 not including promotion and marketing costs). The lack                     performs much better than its peer group average for&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Figure 18                                                                  Figure 19&#13;
 Rural sanitation coverage                                                  Rural sanitation investment requirements&#13;
           100%&#13;
               80%&#13;
Coverage&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
               60%                                                                           Required CAPEX                   Required&#13;
                                                                                                                               OPEX&#13;
               40%&#13;
               20%&#13;
                0%&#13;
                  1985	 1990	 1995	 2000	 2005	 2010	 2015	 2020            0.0	          0.5	          1.0	           1.5	      2.0&#13;
                                                                                                    US$ million/year&#13;
                       Government estimates       Government target            CAPEX deficit&#13;
                       JMP, improved              JMP, improved + shared&#13;
&#13;
 Sources: MICS 2006 (adjusted); JMP 2010 report; AfDB RWSSI.                Source: CSO2 costing.&#13;
&#13;
 24&#13;
&amp;#12;                                               Water Supply and Sanitation in The Gambia: Turning Finance into Services for 2015 and Beyond&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 20&#13;
Rural sanitation scorecard&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
               Enabling                              Developing                                      Sustaining&#13;
    Policy        Planning    Budget      Expenditure     Equity       Output          Markets          Uptake          Use&#13;
&#13;
       1                  0      0              0              1            1.5                1.5          1.5           2.5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Source: CSO2 scorecard.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
sustaining services, but performs far lower for the                  Figure 21&#13;
enabling and developing building blocks (Figure 21). At              Average RSH scorecard scores for enabling,&#13;
present, there is no government endorsed policy on rural             sustaining, and developing service delivery, and&#13;
sanitation, and though the Department of Community                   peer-group comparison&#13;
Development plays a major role in coordination, subsector                                        Enabling&#13;
leadership appears to be divided among three ministriesâ&#128;&#148;&#13;
Health, Environment and Local Governmentâ&#128;&#148;thereby&#13;
resulting in the low score for the policy building block.&#13;
&#13;
The poor performance of the planning building block&#13;
relates to the lack of a sectorwide approach to rural&#13;
sanitation coupled with an absence of needs-based&#13;
investment planning and mechanisms for periodic&#13;
subsector performance review. The budget building block                        Sustaining                    Developing&#13;
is undermined by issues that include insufficient subsector&#13;
budgetary allocations, and the budget structure itself,                 Gambia average scores&#13;
which does not allow easy identification of subsector                   Averages, LICs, GNI p.p.&lt;=$500&#13;
financial flows and spending.                                        Source: CSO2 scorecard.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Among the building blocks relating to developing services,           The relatively high scores for building blocks relating to&#13;
expenditure and equity require most attention. The score             sustaining services notwithstanding, the existing capacity&#13;
for the former is limited by the fact that, the utilization rate     of the private sector and potential for development to&#13;
of both domestic and external subsector funds is less than           provide subsector services is limited, which has an adverse&#13;
50 percent, and reporting of subsector activities is limited.        impact on provision of goods and services (markets) for&#13;
For equity, the limited local participation in subsector             rural sanitation. Furthermore, the quantity and quality of&#13;
investment planning and development decisions, and the               uptake of sanitation and hygiene behavior by households&#13;
lack of criteria for equitable allocation of the subsectorâ&#128;&#153;s         will need to be improved in order to sufficiently contribute&#13;
budget account for the poor score.                                   towards attainment of the 2015 target of 66 percent.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                        25&#13;
&amp;#12; An AMCOW Country Status Overview&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 10.	Subsector: Urban Sanitation and Hygiene&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
           Priority actions for urban sanitation and hygiene&#13;
           â&#128;¢	    Complete preparation and adoption of the national sanitation policy and implementation strategy, ensuring&#13;
                 that they:&#13;
           	     o	   Clearly define institutional roles and responsibilities;&#13;
                 o	   Provide clarity on household subsidy for sanitation;&#13;
                 o	   Enhance sanitation and hygiene promotion;&#13;
                 o	   Enhance adoption of needs-based investment planning; and&#13;
                 o	   Emphasize monitoring and evaluation of subsector performance.&#13;
           â&#128;¢	    Increase local participation and adopt effective budget allocation criteria.&#13;
           â&#128;¢	    Increase subsector funding and improve budget utilization rates.&#13;
           â&#128;¢	    Develop decentralized low cost sewerage options in smaller urban centers.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Generally, sanitation coverage in urban areas is higher than               where the expected household contribution is insignificant&#13;
 in rural areas. Government figures indicate coverage as                    despite the fact that it is unlikely to benefit the urban&#13;
 41 percent in 1990, increasing significantly to 55 percent                 poor: a third of sanitation coverage in 2015 is expected&#13;
 in 2009 (Figure 22). The resulting trend line suggests 59                  to be sewered though a combination of small bore and&#13;
 percent coverage by 2015. Based on government data,                        traditional sewerage. Meanwhile, there appears to be a&#13;
 reaching the national 2015 target of 80 percent would                      general expectation that households will make major&#13;
 require a massive acceleration of past progress. The JMP                   contributions towards provision of on-site domestic&#13;
 indicates 68 percent coverage in 2008, an increase of 5                    facilities. Anticipated public investments are negligible and&#13;
 percent from the 1990 baseline.                                            only relate to hygiene promotion, thereby resulting in a&#13;
                                                                            finance gap of US$6 million per year (Figure 23). OPEX&#13;
 The CSO2 estimates that a total CAPEX (sanitation                          requirements of US$1 million per year are estimated mainly&#13;
 hardware) requirement of US$6 million per year is needed                   for sewerage, which will require public finance if effective&#13;
 to meet the 2015 target. This is primarily for sewerage                    cost recovery is not secured from users.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Figure 22                                                                  Figure 23&#13;
 Urban sanitation coverage                                                  Urban sanitation investment requirements&#13;
&#13;
           100%&#13;
               80%&#13;
Coverage&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
               60%                                                                         Required CAPEX                    Required&#13;
                                                                                                                              OPEX&#13;
               40%&#13;
               20%&#13;
                0%&#13;
                  1985	 1990	 1995	 2000	 2005	 2010	 2015	 2020            0	             2	            4	            6	         8&#13;
                                                                                                    US$ million/year&#13;
                       Government estimates        Government target             CAPEX deficit&#13;
                       JMP, improved               JMP, improved + shared&#13;
&#13;
 Sources: MICS 2006 (adjusted); JMP 2010 report.                            Source: CSO2 costing.&#13;
&#13;
 26&#13;
&amp;#12;                                           Water Supply and Sanitation in The Gambia: Turning Finance into Services for 2015 and Beyond&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 24&#13;
Urban sanitation scorecard&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                Enabling                          Developing                                      Sustaining&#13;
    Policy        Planning    Budget    Expenditure    Equity        Output         Markets         Uptake         Use&#13;
&#13;
       1                  0     1            0             0             1                 1.5           2             2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Source: CSO2 scorecard.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The scorecard presented in Figure 24 shows that the urban        Figure 25&#13;
sanitation subsector has the lowest scorecard performance        Average USH scorecard scores for enabling,&#13;
and, like rural sanitation, the most severe shortcomings         sustaining, and developing service delivery, and&#13;
are upstream in the pathway, among the enabling and              peer-group comparison&#13;
developing building blocks. Only The Gambiaâ&#128;&#153;s score for                                Enabling&#13;
sustaining building blocks is higher than the peer group&#13;
average (Figure 25).&#13;
&#13;
The overall performance is similar to that found for&#13;
rural sanitation, except that rural sanitation has slightly&#13;
better performance for the equity building block, while&#13;
urban sanitation performs better in terms of the budget&#13;
building block (Figure 20 versus Figure 24). The absence&#13;
                                                                      Sustaining                    Developing&#13;
of a sectorwide approach and needs-based investment&#13;
planning and mechanisms for periodic subsector                      Gambia average scores&#13;
performance review explain the poor performance of                  Averages, LICs, GNI p.p.&lt;=$500&#13;
the planning building block. The score for the budget            Source: CSO2 scorecard.&#13;
building block is determined by the insufficient subsector&#13;
budgetary allocations, though the existing budget structure      are attributable to: the less than 50 percent utilization rate&#13;
allows easy identification of subsector financial flows and      of both domestic and external subsector funds; limited&#13;
spending, unlike in rural sanitation.                            reporting of subsector activities; limited local participation&#13;
                                                                 in subsector investment planning and development&#13;
Among the developing building blocks, expenditure and            decisions; and the inadequate budget allocation criteria&#13;
equity require most attention. At present the poor scores        (for equity).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                    27&#13;
&amp;#12;An AMCOW Country Status Overview&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Notes and References&#13;
&#13;
1&#13;
    	 World Bank Global Economic Monitor. 2010 Average.             	 Abdoulie Jobe. 2007. Water Supply and Sanitation Sector&#13;
                                                                    8&#13;
&#13;
2&#13;
    	 The first round of CSOs was carried out in 2006 covering 16     Assessment.&#13;
      countries and is summarized in the report, â&#128;&#152;Getting Africa    	 The CSO2 scorecard methodology and conceptual&#13;
                                                                    9&#13;
&#13;
      On-Track to Meet the MDGs on Water and Sanitationâ&#128;&#153;.             framework are discussed in detail in the synthesis report.&#13;
3&#13;
    	 Water supply target derived from the separate rural           10&#13;
                                                                         	 Indicators relating to the institutional framework section&#13;
      and urban targets set in the Poverty Reduction Strategy              are: All subsectors: targets in national development plans/&#13;
      Paper II (PRSP II). Using the nonadjusted MICS survey                PRSP; subsector policy agreed and approved (gazetted as&#13;
      results, past coverage trends would suggest that the                 part of national policy or as standalone policy); RWS/UWS:&#13;
      2015 water targets are likely to be achieved. The PRSP               institutional roles defined; RSH/USH: institutional lead&#13;
      II has no target for sanitationâ&#128;&#148;appropriate component                appointed.&#13;
      rural and urban targets were consequently agreed during       11&#13;
                                                                         	 Indicators relating to the section on financing and its&#13;
      CSO2 consultation. The overall sanitation consultation is            implementation are: All subsectors: programmatic SWAp;&#13;
      derived from these separate rural and urban targets. The             investment program based on MDG needs assessment;&#13;
      66 percent target adopted for rural sanitation is that set           sufficient finance to meet MDG (subsidy policy for&#13;
      by the African Development Bankâ&#128;&#153;s regional Rural Water               sanitation); percentage of official donor commitments&#13;
      Supply and Sanitation Initiative, originally for 2010. The           utilized; percentage of domestic commitments utilized.&#13;
      urban target is in fact consistent with the MDG target for    12&#13;
                                                                         	 The Village Water Committee is a subcommittee of the&#13;
      water supplyâ&#128;&#148;stakeholders identified this as potentially&#13;
                                                                           Village Development Committee (VDC) and is responsible&#13;
      achievable in urban areas, if not in rural.&#13;
                                                                           for water and sanitation at the village level. When funding&#13;
4&#13;
    	 UNICEF/WHO Joint Monitoring Programme for Water                      is secured by the government, the DWR formally requests&#13;
      Supply and Sanitation (2010) Progress on Sanitation and              the councils to provide a list of communities with dire need&#13;
      Drinking Water: 2010 Update. JMP estimates are based on              of water supply. With this list, the DWR determines the&#13;
      a linear regression of nationally representative household           communities to benefit from the project using the factors&#13;
      surveys. Notwithstanding the different definition of                 of population and current coverage levels.&#13;
      improved access, the JMP estimates for water supply are       13&#13;
                                                                         	 Indicators relating to the M&amp;E section are: All subsectors:&#13;
      reasonably robust, since the trend line is calculated using&#13;
                                                                           annual review setting new undertakings; subsector spend&#13;
      linear regression of a reasonable number of household&#13;
                                                                           identifiable in budget (UWS: inc. recurrent subsidies);&#13;
      survey results, with few outliers. The sanitation estimates&#13;
                                                                           budget comprehensively covers domestic/donor finance;&#13;
      are based on fewer household surveys&#13;
                                                                           RWS, RSH, and USH: domestic/donor expenditure&#13;
5&#13;
    	 The MDG targets are to halve, by 2015, the proportion                reported; UWS: audited accounts and balance sheets&#13;
      of people without access to improved water supply and                from utilities; RWS, RSH, and USH: periodic analysis of&#13;
      sanitation, relative to 1990 levels. At the international            equity criteria by CSOs and government; UWS: pro-poor&#13;
      level, the MDG targets are determined relative to the                plans developed and implemented by utilities; RWS/UWS:&#13;
      1990 coverage baseline established in the JMP reports.               nationally consolidated reporting of output; RSH/USH:&#13;
6&#13;
    	 Due to the lack of household surveys, the JMP trend line is          monitoring of quantity and quality of uptake relative to&#13;
      extrapolated back only as far as 1993, and is assumed to             promotion and subsidy efforts; all subsectors: questions&#13;
      be flat from 1992 to 1996.                                           and choice options in household surveys consistent with&#13;
7&#13;
    	 Due to rounding, component figures may not sum to                    MDG definitions.&#13;
      totals.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
28&#13;
&amp;#12;&amp;#12;For enquiries, contact:&#13;
Water and Sanitation Programâ&#128;&#147;Africa Region&#13;
The World Bank, Upper Hill Road&#13;
P.O. Box 30577, 00100, Nairobi, Kenya&#13;
Tel: +(254) 20 322 6300&#13;
E-mail: wspaf@worldbank.org&#13;
Web site: www.wsp.org&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="19188487">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2011/12/19188487/water-supply-sanitation-gambia-turning-finance-services-2015-beyond
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2011/12/19188487/water-supply-sanitation-gambia-turning-finance-services-2015-beyond</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2011/12/19188487/water-supply-sanitation-gambia-turning-finance-services-2015-beyond</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2014-03-03T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2014-03-03T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2014/03/03/000442464_20140303150728/Rendered/INDEX/855900UNDP0Box000PUBLIC00CSO0Gambia.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2014/03/03/000442464_20140303150728/Rendered/PDF/855900UNDP0Box000PUBLIC00CSO0Gambia.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2014-03-03T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2011-01-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Water supply and sanitation in the Gambia :
            turning finance into services for 2015 and beyond
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The African Ministers' Council on
            Water (AMCOW) commissioned the production of a second round
            of Country Status Overviews (CSOs2) to better understands
            what underpins progress in water supply and sanitation and
            what its member governments can do to accelerate that
            progress across countries in Sub-Saharan Africa (SSA). AMCOW
            delegated this task to the World Bank's water and
            sanitation program and the African Development Bank who are
            implementing it in close partnership with United Nations
            Children's Fund (UNICEF) and World Health Organization
            (WHO) in over 30 countries across SSA. This CSO2 report has
            been produced in collaboration with the Government of the
            Gambia and other stakeholders during 2009-10. The analysis
            aims to help countries assess their own service delivery
            pathways for turning finance into water supply and
            sanitation services in each of four subsectors: rural and
            urban water supply, and rural and urban sanitation, and
            hygiene. The CSO2 analysis has three main components: a
            review of past coverage; a costing model to assess the
            adequacy of future investments; and a scorecard which allows
            diagnosis of particular bottlenecks along the service
            delivery pathway. The CSO2's contribution is to answer
            not only whether past trends and future finance are
            sufficient to meet sector targets, but what specific issues
            need to be addressed to ensure finance is effectively turned
            into accelerated coverage in water supply and sanitation. In
            this spirit, specific priority actions have been identified
            through consultation. A synthesis report, available
            separately, presents best practice and shared learning to
            help realize these priority actions.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Water supply and sanitation in the Gambia :
            turning finance into services for 2015 and beyond
        </docna>
        <display_title>Water supply and sanitation in
            the Gambia : turning finance into services for 2015 and beyond</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2011/01/19188487/water-supply-sanitation-gambia-turning-finance-services-2015-beyond</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>UNDP-Water &amp; Sanitation Program</docty>
        <subtopic>Wastewater Treatment,Town Water Supply and Sanitation,Urban Water Supply and Sanitation,Water Supply and Sanitation Governance
            and Institutions,Water and Industry</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Water Supply and Sanitation,Water Resources</teratopic>
        <count>Gambia, The</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Sahel!$!80468</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Sub-Saharan Africa!$!80473</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>West Africa!$!80474</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000442464_20140303150728</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>Africa,Africa</admreg>
        <colti>An AMCOW country status overview</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Water Supply and Sanitation,Water Resources</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            access to water, adequate water, adequate
            water supply, allocation system, civil society,
            construction, construction techniques, cost recovery, cost
            sharing, distribution systems, drain, drought, Electricity,
            environmental sanitation, equitable allocation, equitable
            distribution, governance principles, groundwater, hours of
            service, household connections, households, human waste,
            hygiene, Hygiene Education, hygiene promotion, investment
            decisions, investment planning, investment program,
            investment requirements, local communities, local community,
            local entrepreneurs, maintenance of water, maintenance
            Operations, National Water, National Water Resources,
            National Water Supply, performance contracts, performance
            indicators, piped water, project management, provision of
            water, provision of water supply, Public Health, public
            standpipes, Public Utilities, regulatory framework, rural
            communities, Rural sanitation, Rural water, Rural water
            supply, safe sanitation, sanitary conditions, sanitary
            disposal, sanitary facilities, sanitation coverage,
            sanitation facilities, sanitation investment, Sanitation
            Program, sanitation promotion, sanitation sector, sanitation
            services, sanitation Water, School sanitation, septic tank,
            septic tank emptying, service delivery, Service development,
            sewerage, sewerage services, small town, small town schemes,
            small towns, spare parts, supply Water, sustainable
            services, tariff regulation, urban areas, Urban sanitation,
            urban sewerage, urban water, urban water supply, Urban water
            supply coverage, urban water supply service delivery, users,
            Utilities, Utilities Corporation, waste management, water
            coverage, water facilities, water infrastructure, water
            quality, Water Resource, Water Resource Management, water
            resources management, water sector, water shortages, Water
            Supply, water supply facilities, water supply service, water
            supply services, water supply systems
        </keywd>
        <owner>Water - Water &amp; Sant. Prgrm-AFR (GWASA)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Sahel</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Sub-Saharan Africa</geo_region>
            <geo_region>West Africa</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>85590</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Strategy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation and Sewerage</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wastewater Treatment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Infrastructure (Water and Wastewater)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Water and Small Town Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Handwashing Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wastewater Collection and Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Basic Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>On-site Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Marketing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Management of Public Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Finance Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Finances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Economics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Economics &amp; Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Communities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Boundaries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation and Wastewater</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water, Sanitation and Hygiene</ml:concept><ml:concept>Hygiene Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sewerage</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Local Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Africa</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Gambia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>