<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>                           86056&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Psychosocial Distress and&#13;
Well-Being among Acholi Women&#13;
in Northern Uganda&#13;
Working Paper No. 1&#13;
April 2013&#13;
&#13;
Dr. Rebecca Horn&#13;
&amp;#12;The International Bank for Reconstruction and Development / The World Bank&#13;
1818 H Street, NW&#13;
Washington, DC 20433&#13;
All rights reserved&#13;
First published April 2013&#13;
www.logica-wb.net&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    This Working Papers Series disseminates the findings of work in progress to encourage discussion and&#13;
    exchange of ideas on gender and conflict related issues in Sub-Saharan Africa. Papers in this series are not&#13;
    formal publications of the World Bank. The papers carry the names of the authors and should be cited ac-&#13;
    cordingly. The series is edited by the Learning on Gender and Conflict in Africa (LOGiCA) Program of the&#13;
    World Bank within the Fragile States, Conflict and Social Development Department.&#13;
&#13;
    This paper has not undergone the review accorded to official World Bank publications. The findings, in-&#13;
    terpretations and conclusions herein are those of the author and do not necessarily reflect the views of the&#13;
    International Bank for Reconstruction and Development/World Bank and its affiliated organizations, its&#13;
    Executive Directors, or the governments they represent.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
To request further information on the series, please contact ereessmith@worldbank.org LOGiCA. Papers are also&#13;
available on the LOGiCA website: www.logica-wb.net.&#13;
&#13;
Cover and layout design: Duina Reyes&#13;
Photos provided by United Nations photo library&#13;
&amp;#12;Psychosocial Distress and&#13;
Well-Being among Acholi Women&#13;
in Northern Uganda&#13;
&#13;
Working Paper No. 1&#13;
&#13;
Dr. Rebecca Horn&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
April 2013&#13;
&amp;#12;Table of Contents&#13;
&#13;
 Psychosocial Distress and Well-Being among Acholi&#13;
 Women in Northern Uganda.   ..................................................................... 3&#13;
 Introduction................................................................................................................... 3&#13;
 The Psychosocial Well-Being and Mental Health of Women Affected by Conflict........... 3&#13;
 The Psychosocial Effects of Conflict on Women in Northern Uganda............................. 4&#13;
 Measuring Psychosocial Well-Being................................................................................ 6&#13;
 The Objective of this Study............................................................................................. 7&#13;
 Methodology.................................................................................................................. 7&#13;
        Freelisting................................................................................................................................... 7&#13;
        Case Study Interviews................................................................................................................. 8&#13;
        Recruitment and Training of Research Assistants........................................................................ 8&#13;
                 ................................................................................................................................... 8&#13;
        Procedure.&#13;
 Analysis of Data.............................................................................................................. 9&#13;
                        .......................................................................................................................... 9&#13;
        Freelisting Data.&#13;
        Case Study Interview Data.......................................................................................................... 9&#13;
 Results............................................................................................................................ 9&#13;
        Causes of Distress....................................................................................................................... 9&#13;
                          ..................................................................................................................... 10&#13;
        Distressing events.&#13;
        Situational stressors................................................................................................................... 10&#13;
                                 .................................................................................. 13&#13;
 Signs of Distress and Well-Being.&#13;
        Relationships............................................................................................................................ 13&#13;
        Anger and Aggression............................................................................................................... 14&#13;
        Unhappiness............................................................................................................................. 14&#13;
        Fulfilling Responsibilities.......................................................................................................... 14&#13;
        Other........................................................................................................................................ 15&#13;
 Factors that Contribute to Well-Being.......................................................................... 15&#13;
 Discussion.................................................................................................................... 15&#13;
 Limitations................................................................................................................... 16&#13;
 How Conflict Has Contributed to Psychological Distress in Northern Uganda............ 17&#13;
 Implications for Future Programming and Research.................................................... 17&#13;
 References................................................................................................ 19&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                       Exploring Psychosocial Well-being and&#13;
                                                                                                                    Social Connectedness in Northern Uganda    1&#13;
&amp;#12;                    Psychosocial Distress and&#13;
                Well-Being among Acholi Women&#13;
                      in Northern Uganda&#13;
Introduction                                             pacts women differently than men due to their so-&#13;
                                                         cial position, traditional roles, and the dominant&#13;
This paper addresses two main topics:                    gender discourses of the time and place (Sideris&#13;
                                                         2003; Deacon and Sullivan 2010; Womenâ&#128;&#153;s Refu-&#13;
â&#128;¢	 The effects of conflict on the psychological          gee Commission 2009).&#13;
   well-being of women&#13;
                                                         Womenâ&#128;&#153;s traditional role as caretakers, for exam-&#13;
â&#128;¢	 Methodological issues related to the measure-         ple, may be strained by having to raise children&#13;
   ment of psychological well-being                      in unstable environments with few support struc-&#13;
                                                         tures. Without the support networks and conflict&#13;
The literature on these topics is reviewed, and data     resolution systems that may have existed prewar,&#13;
from a qualitative study conducted in northern           women can become more vulnerable to intimate&#13;
Uganda is used to explore them in more depth.            partner violence (Carlson 2005). The dominant&#13;
Finally, the paper considers the ways in which con-      gender discourses in a society also influence wom-&#13;
flict has contributed to womenâ&#128;&#153;s psychological dis-      enâ&#128;&#153;s experiences of conflict. For example, Sideris&#13;
tress in northern Uganda, and the implications of        (2003) found that women who had experienced&#13;
this study for future programming and research.          sexual violence in Mozambique, especially those&#13;
                                                         who had become pregnant as a result, feared rejec-&#13;
&#13;
The Psychosocial Well-Being                              tion due to local social beliefs regarding a childâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
                                                         line of descent from the father, and which position&#13;
&#13;
and Mental Health of                                     women as the property of their husbands.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Women Affected by Conflict                               In some conflict and postconflict settings (for&#13;
                                                         example, Afghanistan, see Cardozo and others&#13;
Until recently, there was little research into the ef-   [2005]; and Sudan, see Roberts and others [2010]),&#13;
fects of war experiences on womenâ&#128;&#153;s psychosocial         women have reported higher rates of mental ill-&#13;
well-being (Igreja, Kleijn, and Richters 2006; An-       ness and psychological distress than men. Roberts&#13;
nan and others 2008), but it is known that wom-          and others (2010) suggest that womenâ&#128;&#153;s increased&#13;
enâ&#128;&#153;s experiences of conflict differ qualitatively from   levels of psychological distress may be partly at-&#13;
those of men. To some extent, this is a function         tributable to the psychological consequences of&#13;
of their experience of conflict itself, which can in-    rape, the violent loss of partners and children, and&#13;
clude not only being combatants and the targets          the experience of becoming a single parent or wid-&#13;
and victims of armed groups in communities, but          ow. Usta, Farver, and Zein (2008) link womenâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
also serving these groups in supportive and do-          increased psychological distress to an increase in&#13;
mestic roles, whether as sexual slaves or â&#128;&#156;wivesâ&#128;&#157;        domestic violence during armed conflicts. Both&#13;
(Annan and Brier 2010). Women and girls are at           cultural and social contexts play a large part in de-&#13;
increased risk of sexual and gender-based violence       termining which groups of people are likely to be&#13;
(SGBV) during and after war. Conflict also im-           most severely affected by conflict&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                  Exploring Psychosocial Well-being and&#13;
                                                                               Social Connectedness in Northern Uganda    3&#13;
&amp;#12;    The Psychosocial Effects                                 family and community relationships (only one in&#13;
                                                             six reported negative family relationships). Hav-&#13;
&#13;
    of Conflict on Women in                                  ing been abducted did not affect overall support&#13;
                                                             or relationships with family and neighbors: More&#13;
&#13;
    Northern Uganda                                          than 90 percent of girls and women who escaped&#13;
                                                             after being abducted by the LRA reported no post-&#13;
    PThe main source of information on how the war           abduction problems with their immediate family&#13;
    in northern Uganda has affected women is the sec-        members. Conflicts were more likely to occur with&#13;
    ond phase of the Survey of War Affected Youth            members of the wider familyâ&#128;&#148;aunts, stepmoth-&#13;
    (SWAY) (Annan and others 2008), which gath-              ers, uncles, and brothers (Annan and Brier 2010).&#13;
    ered data on 619 randomly selected women and             For all females, the likelihood of having family&#13;
    girls aged 14â&#136;&#146;35 in Kitgum and Pader between             problems increased with the number of violent&#13;
    October 2006 and August 2007.                            acts received and perpetrated.&#13;
&#13;
    Annan and others (2008) note that while people           Studies of older women in northern Uganda have&#13;
    throughout northern Uganda have been affected            found that, due to the social disintegration that oc-&#13;
    by the war, males and females have been affected         curred during the war, women have taken on roles&#13;
    differently. They found that males and females           previously reserved for men, particularly in the ar-&#13;
    perpetrated violence at similar rates, but males re-     eas of agriculture and informal trade (Payne 1998;&#13;
    ported experiencing a higher number of acts than         Sideris 2003). Okello and Hovil (2007) report&#13;
    females. More than one-fifth of the female youth         that women in northern Uganda carried much of&#13;
    interviewed reported abduction by the Lordâ&#128;&#153;s Re-         the responsibility for ensuring that their families&#13;
    sistance Army (LRA), whom they served in both            survived and were safe. This shift in gender roles&#13;
    combat and support roles, and one-quarter were           has helped shape a female self-image based on re-&#13;
    given to LRA fighters as forced wives. Forced wives      silience and strength rather than vulnerability; a&#13;
    report significantly more violent events than other      less positive effect has been an increasing tendency&#13;
    female abductees; half gave birth to children. A         among men to spend their days socializing and&#13;
    larger proportion of abducted women experienced          drinking in groups, which further alienates wom-&#13;
    or witnessed violent events, but most women              en (El-Bushra [2000] cited in Sideris [2003]).&#13;
    (whether abducted or not) had experienced loss of&#13;
                                                             Okello and Hovil (2007: 437) note that camps for&#13;
    personal property or of a relative or friend.&#13;
                                                             internally displaced Ugandans became â&#128;&#156;sites for&#13;
                                                             contesting gender norms,â&#128;&#157; and this breakdown in&#13;
    A small but significant percentage of female youth&#13;
                                                             domestic relations is perceived to have contributed&#13;
    were found to struggle with frequent symptoms&#13;
                                                             to an increase in domestic violence. In the SWAY&#13;
    of distress or with troubled family relationships.&#13;
    Overall, girls and women who had been abducted,          study (Annan and others 2008), over one-third of&#13;
    especially those who had been forced wives, re-          women reported that their husbands were often&#13;
    ported higher levels of distress than those who had      drunk; the frequency of the husbandâ&#128;&#153;s intoxica-&#13;
    not been abducted. Previous experience of violence       tion was related to the wifeâ&#128;&#153;s emotional distress.&#13;
    was not the only factor that influenced womenâ&#128;&#153;s          Alcohol was often described by women as being&#13;
    emotional well-being; current life stressors, specifi-   associated with physical or verbal aggression to-&#13;
    cally having fewer household assets and having a         ward them or their dependents, and 13 percent of&#13;
    physical injury, were found to predict higher levels     females reported having been beaten by a family&#13;
    of distress. Positive relationships with families and    member or husband in the previous two months.&#13;
    communitiesâ&#128;&#148;as defined by comfort, closeness,            Community mechanisms that might previously&#13;
    and lack of fightingâ&#128;&#148;were found to be an im-             have protected women and girls from sexual ex-&#13;
    portant protective factor related to lower levels of     ploitation and abuse were eroded by displacement&#13;
    emotional distress. Most females reported positive       and camp conditions.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
4&#13;
&amp;#12;Annan and Brier (2010: 157) describe the mul-                  been mistreated. Cen is seen not only as harmful&#13;
tiple levels of violence experienced by the women              to the individual but many believe that the spirit&#13;
they studied in northern Uganda, including physi-              can pollute families and neighbors, which can re-&#13;
cal and sexual violence by armed groups, verbal                sult in stigmatization of the individual victim.&#13;
and physical abuse from extended families, and&#13;
intimate partner violence. They use the model                  Women in northern Uganda and other parts of the&#13;
presented in figure 1 to show how different experi-            country often express their psychological distress&#13;
ences with war-related violence can interact with              through somatic symptoms, and tend not to talk&#13;
factors at individual, family, social, and structural          about it directly. Bracken, Giller, and Summerfield&#13;
levels, compounding experiences and sustaining                 (1995) found that for women in Luwero (a district&#13;
violence even after the war is over.                           in central Uganda) affected by the conflict in that&#13;
                                                               area, psychological distress was expressed primar-&#13;
Psychological distress was found by Annan and                  ily through somatic symptoms, especially among&#13;
others (2008) to be expressed in a variety of ways,            women who had been raped. Tankink (2004)&#13;
including nightmares, difficulty concentrating,                identifies silence as the most common cultural&#13;
shaking from worrying, crying, feeling lonely, and             response to emotional distress in Uganda, and&#13;
becoming easily irritated. Upon return from ab-                Akello, Reis, and Richters (2010) report similar&#13;
duction, some female youth described nightmares                findings among children in Gulu. The main op-&#13;
and wanted to isolate themselves from others (An-              portunity to express emotions is during religious&#13;
nan and Brier 2010: 155). Most people in this re-              services, when it is perceived to be God who is ex-&#13;
gion have a spiritual interpretation of their symp-            pressing the emotions, rather than the individual&#13;
toms, attributing nightmares and other traumatic               (Tankink 2004).&#13;
reactions to cenâ&#128;&#148;vengeance by a spirit that has&#13;
&#13;
                   Figure 1. Ecological Perspective of Gendered Violence&#13;
                              and Inequality in Armed Conflict&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                  Ex Arm&#13;
                                                                                                    po e&#13;
                                        STRUCTURAL FACTORS                                            su d C&#13;
                                                                                                        re o&#13;
                     Corruption in         Gender Inequality                                              to nfl&#13;
                                                                                                            Vi ict&#13;
                     Legal System                                                   Poverty                   ol&#13;
                                                                                                                 en&#13;
                                                                                                                    ce&#13;
                                           SOCIAL FACTORS&#13;
      Displacement                               Patriarchy&#13;
                                                                            Scarce&#13;
                                                                            Resources&#13;
                  Stygma and&#13;
                  Rejection from                  FAMILY&#13;
                  Neighbors          Scarce&#13;
                                                              Alcohol Use&#13;
                                     Resources&#13;
&#13;
                           Death and&#13;
                           Disruption            INDIVIDUAL&#13;
                                                                            Abuse&#13;
                                                 Distress&#13;
                                                 Insecurity&#13;
                                                 Little economic&#13;
                                                 opportunity&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   Source: Annan and Brier 2010: 157.&#13;
   Note: Dotted lines represent the linkages between the different levels.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                           Exploring Psychosocial Well-being and&#13;
                                                                                        Social Connectedness in Northern Uganda    5&#13;
&amp;#12;    The SWAY team found that while most female             prioritizing psychiatric syndromes that are familiar&#13;
    youth in northern Uganda reported some symp-           to Western practitioners (for example, posttrau-&#13;
    toms of distress, many were able to cope with their    matic stress disorder, or PTSD) but which may be&#13;
    symptoms and continue with their daily activities      of secondary concern, or simply lack meaning, to&#13;
    (Annan and others 2008). It was when the symp-         non-Western populations for whom local idioms&#13;
    toms interfered with daily functioningâ&#128;&#148;when            of psychological distress are more salient (Miller&#13;
    they become an obstacle to education, income           and others 2006; Miller, Kulkarni, and Kushner&#13;
    generation, or relationshipsâ&#128;&#148;that that they were       2006; see Pike and Williams [2006] for an ex-&#13;
    of serious concern.                                    ample of the challenges encountered when using&#13;
                                                           an etic measure of psychosocial well-being inap-&#13;
    There is a gap in terms of research conducted since    propriately). A problem arises, as Fernando (2008)&#13;
    the attacks by the LRA ended and people have be-       points out, when a construct that is defined and&#13;
    gun to leave the internally displaced persons (IDP)    measured in an individualistic culture is then im-&#13;
    camps and return to their home areas. Some have        posed on a very different culture as if it is univer-&#13;
    argued that the postconflict phase is the time when    sal.&#13;
    people are likely to be particularly affected by the&#13;
    traumatic events they have lived through, as they      Bass, Bolton, and Murray (2007: 918) write that&#13;
    take stock of their losses and consider their future   â&#128;&#156;investigation of local syndromes thus becomes&#13;
    (Weyerman 2007).                                       a necessary initial step in the evaluation of the&#13;
                                                           validity and utility of concepts and instruments&#13;
    Measuring Psychosocial                                 developed in different contexts.â&#128;&#157; Where there is&#13;
                                                           evidence that psychological distress is expressed in&#13;
    Well-Being                                             a form similar to that in cultures for which there&#13;
                                                           are standardized instruments, the use of such in-&#13;
    To improve the understanding of the ways in which      struments makes sense (see, for example, Bolton,&#13;
    conflict affects womenâ&#128;&#153;s psychological well-being,     Wilk, and Ngogoni 2004). Where the evidence&#13;
    effective measurement tools are necessary. While       suggests poor agreement, new instruments need&#13;
    there are many measures of mental health and psy-      to be developed. Where there is little or no data&#13;
    chological well-beingâ&#128;&#148;for example, the Hopkins         to gauge such agreement, additional information&#13;
    Symptom Checklist-25 (HSCL), General Health            must be collected. There is now a consensus that&#13;
    Questionnaire (GHQ), Beck Depression Inven-            effective assessment of mental health and psycho-&#13;
    tory, and Structured Clinical Interview for the        social well-being must be based on initial identi-&#13;
    DSM-IVâ&#128;&#148;these have often not been validated in          fication of patterns of distress among the relevant&#13;
    areas affected by conflict, and may not address the    population (Davidson, Murray, and Schweitzer&#13;
    issues of concern to the communities in those ar-      2010; Rasco and Miller 2004).&#13;
    eas (Jordans and others 2009; Summerfield 2007,&#13;
    2008). Etic (or â&#128;&#156;outsideâ&#128;&#157;) measures, which would       Increasingly, efforts are being made to develop cul-&#13;
    include instruments such as the HSCL and GHQ,          turally grounded indicators and measures based&#13;
    are sometimes used because researchers want to be      on local concepts of well-being (for example, Hart&#13;
    able to compare the findings in one setting with       and others 2007; PADHI 2009; Stark and others&#13;
    those in another. They may also be used because        2009; Bolton and others 2007). These measures are&#13;
    they are well known and validated in some settings,    useful because they are able to (i) assess the most&#13;
    and program staff feel more confident using them       pressing mental health concerns of war-affected&#13;
    than creating their own assessment tools. In some      communities, and (ii) identify the particular ways&#13;
    circumstances, etic measures of psychopathology        in which community members understand and&#13;
    may be useful when looking at non-Western popu-        talk about their distress (Miller and others 2006;&#13;
    lations, but a reliance on the language and con-       Miller, Kulkarni, and Kushner 2006). Researchers&#13;
    structs of Western psychiatry risks inappropriately    in this field have had to overcome the widely held&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
6&#13;
&amp;#12;belief that methodological rigor is in opposition        (Bolton 2001b; Wilk and Bolton 2002). Free-&#13;
to maintaining local sensitivity (CPC 2008), but         listing involves asking local people one or more&#13;
there are now sufficient examples of locally mean-       standardized questions to generate a list of what&#13;
ingful, rigorous psychosocial assessments to per-        they perceive as the major problems affecting their&#13;
manently undermine this argument: â&#128;&#156;there is no           community. Respondents are also asked to iden-&#13;
rigor without sensitivity, and no sensitivity with-      tify local people who are consulted about psycho-&#13;
out rigorâ&#128;&#157; (CPC 2008: 16). This is now widely            logical/emotional problems, or are particularly&#13;
acceptedâ&#128;&#148;CPCâ&#128;&#153;s (2008) consultations with se-             knowledgeable about them. These people become&#13;
nior practitioners have consistently highlighted         â&#128;&#156;key informants,â&#128;&#157; who are interviewed in the sec-&#13;
the prime importance of understanding context,           ond stage of the process. Interviews with key in-&#13;
and of developing methodologies that can be used         formants aim to obtain more detailed information&#13;
to identify local concerns and priorities (see also,     about the mental health problems mentioned in&#13;
Davidson, Murray, and Schweitzer 2010).                  the free lists, and to probe for other mental health&#13;
                                                         issues that were not mentioned. The problems&#13;
A number of researchers have described the pro-          listed during the freelisting interviews are col-&#13;
cess of creating culturally meaningful mental            lapsed into a composite list of major problems, as&#13;
health assessment measures for use in conflict and       seen from the communityâ&#128;&#153;s perspective, includ-&#13;
postconflict situations. For example, Jon Hubbard        ing mental and emotional disorders, along with a&#13;
and the Center for Victims of Torture (CVT) de-          rank of how alarming the community prioritizes&#13;
veloped a means of assessing childrenâ&#128;&#153;s well-being       them. This information, together with that gath-&#13;
using locally relevant criteria (Hart and others         ered from key informants, is used to create an in-&#13;
2007). Members of the target group/community             strument designed to measure the extent to which&#13;
are asked to think of a child they know who, in          people are affected by the psychological/emotional&#13;
their view, is doing well, and then list the things      problems listed.&#13;
about that child that indicate to them that he or&#13;
she is doing well. The characteristics that emerge&#13;
from this process can then be used as indicators of      The Objective of this Study&#13;
well-being, which can be used to assess individual&#13;
children. Since participants are asked to describe       This report aims to better understand the causes&#13;
the characteristics of real children, the indica-        and expressions of psychological distress among&#13;
tors are likely to be attainable and realistic, rather   women in northern Uganda. The study also seeks&#13;
than abstract ideals. This method has since been         to identify which factors contribute to womenâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
adapted for use with adults, and has been used as        resilience in conflict and postconflict situations.&#13;
the first stage of developing culturally valid mea-      The study was the first stage in a process of de-&#13;
sures of psychosocial well-being (Miller and others      veloping a structured interview schedule to assess&#13;
2006; Fernando 2008).                                    psychological distress (and other variables) among&#13;
                                                         women in the Acholi region of Uganda.&#13;
Other methods of identifying the salient issues to&#13;
include in an assessment tool include â&#128;&#156;freelistingâ&#128;&#157;&#13;
(Bolton 2001b; Horn 2009), focus group discus-           Methodology&#13;
sions (Dejman and others 2010; Snider and others&#13;
2004), key informant interviews (Deacon and Sul-         Two methods were used to collect information on&#13;
livan 2010; Pedersen and others 2008), and card          psychological distress among women in northern&#13;
sorts (Rasmussen and others 2010).                       Uganda: freelisting and case study interviews.&#13;
&#13;
Paul Bolton and his colleagues (Bass and others          Freelisting&#13;
2006) have frequently used freelisting and key&#13;
informant interviews to develop locally relevant         The freelisting methodology was employed to col-&#13;
instruments to measure mental health problems            lect data on the events and circumstances that may&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                 Exploring Psychosocial Well-being and&#13;
                                                                              Social Connectedness in Northern Uganda    7&#13;
&amp;#12;    contribute to psychological distress. The structured      â&#128;¢	 Signs that indicate that the second woman has&#13;
    question used was: What are the kinds of things              now recovered&#13;
    that worry women in this community?&#13;
                                                              â&#128;¢	 Why they think the first woman recovered&#13;
                                                                 and the second is still having difficulties&#13;
    Case Study Interviews&#13;
    A methodology developed by Jon Hubbard and                Recruitment and Training of Research&#13;
    the CVT (called here â&#128;&#156;case study interviewsâ&#128;&#157;) was&#13;
    used to develop a measure of psychological distress&#13;
                                                              Assistants&#13;
    and the events and circumstances that contribute          Six research assistants were recruited to conduct&#13;
    to it. The methodology, based on that used by             the freelisting and case study interviews. All were&#13;
    Miller and others (2006), involved asking the re-         local to the area and fluent in the local language.&#13;
    spondent to think of two women they know per-             They participated in three days of training in the&#13;
    sonally, both of whom have suffered emotionally           two interview methods prior to the data collection&#13;
    because of difficult life experiences:                    phase.&#13;
&#13;
    â&#128;¢	 One woman should be someone who has re-&#13;
       covered and is now functioning well despite            Procedure&#13;
       the hardships she has endured.                         In the period April 26â&#136;&#146;29, 2011, the research team&#13;
    â&#128;¢	 The other woman should be someone who                  visited four villages in the Acholi region of north-&#13;
                                                              ern Uganda: one in Kitgum, one in Pader, and two&#13;
       has continued to suffer despite the passing of&#13;
                                                              in Gulu district (one rural and one urban). In all&#13;
       time.&#13;
                                                              four villages people were no longer living in IDP&#13;
                                                              camps but had returned to their home areas. A to-&#13;
    The respondent was then asked to tell the inter-&#13;
                                                              tal of 70 freelisting interviews were conducted over&#13;
    viewer about the two women in detail, focusing&#13;
                                                              this 4-day period, and 27 case study interviews.&#13;
    particularly on:&#13;
                                                              Respondents were selected for the interviews on&#13;
    â&#128;¢	 The difficult life events they experienced&#13;
                                                              an opportunity basis. Interviewers approached&#13;
    â&#128;¢	 How they have been affected (thoughts, feel-           people as they were going about their everyday&#13;
       ings, behavior)                                        tasks and invited them to participate in the in-&#13;
                                                              terview. An informed consent sheet was created&#13;
    â&#128;¢	 Signs that indicate that the first woman is still      that contained information about the research and&#13;
       suffering                                              about the interviews. This information was given&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                        Table 1. Summary of Individual Interviews Conducted&#13;
                                                                                     Freelisting     Case study&#13;
      Date                             District      Subcounty           Type&#13;
                                                                                     interviews      interviews&#13;
&#13;
      April 26                          Gulu           Awach             Rural           15               6&#13;
&#13;
      April 27                          Pader         Puranga            Rural           18               7&#13;
&#13;
      April 28                         Kitgum        Namakora            Rural           17               7&#13;
&#13;
      April 29                          Gulu               Bobi         Urban            20               7&#13;
&#13;
      Source: Author.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
8&#13;
&amp;#12;verbally to each potential respondent before he or      When all data had been analyzed, the table was re-&#13;
she was asked whether he or she was willing to          organized, with worries ordered by the frequency&#13;
participate.                                            with which they were mentioned, indicating their&#13;
                                                        importance to the respondents. The final stage&#13;
The two male interviewers approached only men,          was to analyze the descriptions of each concern&#13;
and the four female interviewers approached only        given, to identify the major themes. Throughout&#13;
women. Those conducting freelisting interviews          the analysis, links were identified and recorded be-&#13;
aimed to conduct four interviews per day, and           tween the items.&#13;
those conducting case study interviews aimed to&#13;
conduct three interviews, with each interview-          Case Study Interview Data&#13;
er aiming to include at least one older and one&#13;
younger respondent each day, and those who may          The case study interviews provided information&#13;
be more marginalized (for example, people with          about respondentsâ&#128;&#153; perceptions of:&#13;
disabilities). They conducted all interviews in&#13;
                                                        â&#128;¢	 Events that contribute to psychological&#13;
Acholi, and made notes at the time of the inter-&#13;
                                                           distress&#13;
view either in English or Acholi. These notes were&#13;
added to (and translated into English where neces-      â&#128;¢	 Signs (indicators) of psychological distress&#13;
sary) and given to the lead researcher at the end of&#13;
each day for checking and data entry.                   â&#128;¢	 Signs (indicators) of recovery&#13;
&#13;
                                                        â&#128;¢	 Factors that contribute to recovery&#13;
The average (mean) age of respondents was&#13;
35.8 years for the freelisting interviews (minimum&#13;
                                                        The data obtained from the 27 respondents were&#13;
age = 19, maximum = 70), and 34.8 years for the&#13;
                                                        categorized by these four themes. They were then&#13;
case study interviews (minimum age = 20, maxi-&#13;
                                                        analyzed thematically to identify the key events&#13;
mum = 70). Approximately one-third of respon-&#13;
                                                        believed to contribute to psychological distress,&#13;
dents for both freelisting and case study interviews    the signs of psychological distress and well-being,&#13;
were male, and two-thirds female.                       and the factors that contribute to psychological&#13;
                                                        well-being.&#13;
Analysis of Data&#13;
Freelisting Data&#13;
                                                        Results&#13;
Interviewers listed respondentsâ&#128;&#153; answers to each        Causes of Distress&#13;
question, and wrote a short description of each         Information about the causes of psychological dis-&#13;
item on the list. The data for each of the two ques-    tress was obtained from both the case study inter-&#13;
tions on the freelisting forms was treated sepa-        views and freelisting interviews. In the case study&#13;
rately.                                                 interviews, respondents described women who had&#13;
                                                        suffered emotionally because of the events they&#13;
A table was created and each issue raised by a re-      had experienced, and were asked to describe the&#13;
spondent (each worry or concern) was recorded           causes of this emotional suffering. In the freelist-&#13;
on a separate row, along with a short description.      ing interviews, respondents were asked to describe&#13;
Since the same worries recurred in several lists, the   the things that worried women in their commu-&#13;
frequency with which each worry was stated was          nity. The responses were divided into two types:&#13;
recorded, and the description added to those given      events that occurred in the past and that continue&#13;
by other respondents. Whenever a new worry (not         to affect the women being discussed, and ongoing&#13;
mentioned by previous respondents) was stated, it       situations in which the women mentioned were&#13;
was added to a new row.                                 still living.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                Exploring Psychosocial Well-being and&#13;
                                                                             Social Connectedness in Northern Uganda    9&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                         Case Study 1&#13;
       This woman was abducted and spent four years in the bush. During that time she killed people, was raped by&#13;
       fighters, and became infected with HIV. She also gave birth to two children.&#13;
&#13;
       When she returned from the bush, she believed in killing and saw death as a normal thing. She engaged in&#13;
       prostitution as a way of earning income for survival. She had nightmares, was disrespectful, and grabbed peopleâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
       property by force.&#13;
&#13;
       She spent some time in a reception center run by a nongovernmental organization (NGO), where she received&#13;
       support, advice, and encouragement. She also believes in God and prays. Now she behaves wellâ&#128;&#148;she participates&#13;
       in community work and is very active in community life. She has joined various groups (for example, a savings&#13;
       group) and has gone back to education (adult literacy). She now advises others and is respected by others.&#13;
&#13;
       Source: As told by a 32-year-old man in Gulu.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Distressing events                                           tional distress relate mainly to family relation-&#13;
                                                                  ships. The loss of a husband was frequently said to&#13;
     Past events that caused emotional distress include           cause extreme distress, whether it was through the&#13;
     those related to conflict, such as women being ab-           husbandâ&#128;&#153;s death, the breakdown of the marriage,&#13;
     ducted, raped, being impregnated through rape,               abandonment, or the addition of another wife.&#13;
     witnessing killings, and killing people them-                Other events said to have a significant impact on a&#13;
     selves. They also include significant losses, such           womanâ&#128;&#153;s emotional well-being included the loss of&#13;
     as a womanâ&#128;&#153;s children or husband being abducted              her property or house (whether it was taken from&#13;
     and/or killed:                                               her or she was sent away by her husband or his&#13;
                                                                  family), rape, forced marriage, and the death of&#13;
     â&#128;¢	 Six of her eight children were killed by the              her children.&#13;
        LRA. One of the remaining children is dis-&#13;
        abled (case study interview with 30-year-old&#13;
        woman, Pader).                                            Situational stressors&#13;
     â&#128;¢	 Her son was killed by rebels on his way to                Situational stressors are aspects of a womanâ&#128;&#153;s cur-&#13;
        school, then her husband was knocked down                 rent living situation that contribute to psychologi-&#13;
        by a car and killed on the same road. Her                 cal distress.&#13;
        youngest son went mad and is hospitalized&#13;
        (case study interview with 28-year-old wom-               Poverty and a lack of support were commonly said&#13;
        an, Gulu).                                                to affect the psychological well-being of women,&#13;
                                                                  particularly concerns about how to pay school fees&#13;
     Post-conflict events said to contribute to emo-              and meet childrenâ&#128;&#153;s basic needs (for example, food&#13;
&#13;
                                                         Case Study 2&#13;
       She was 27 years old and happily married when her husband was burned with her three children in camp X. Since&#13;
       then she drinks a lot (she did not drink before), she cries, and calls the names of her husband and children. When&#13;
       drunk, she cries, removes her clothes, and stays naked. She suffers from nightmares and does not want other&#13;
       people to talk about her.&#13;
&#13;
       She continues to suffer with these problems up to now. She has no family support and no way of generating any&#13;
       income. She looks depressed and does not want to remarry because she believes the new husband and children&#13;
       may meet the same fate. She continues to say, â&#128;&#156;If my husband and children were alive, I would have been OK.â&#128;&#157;&#13;
       Source: As told by a 22-year-old man in Kitgum.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
10&#13;
&amp;#12;and clothes). This concern particularly affected                care of the children on the wifeâ&#128;&#153;s shoul-&#13;
women who were responsible for meeting these                    ders. A man can sleep out, or even be gone&#13;
needs without support from others, sometimes                    for days without a word (freelisting inter-&#13;
because their husband was unable or unwilling to                view with 25-year-old woman, Gulu).&#13;
provide for them and their children. Not having&#13;
anybody to help with their work was distressing            Ë&#143;Ë&#143;   Husband neglects her and her children,&#13;
for some women, as were the feelings of isolation               doesnâ&#128;&#153;t help her cultivate, takes what she&#13;
associated with a lack of support. Being overbur-               produces and gives to his other wife (case&#13;
dened by too many responsibilities was a source of              study interview with 34-year-old woman,&#13;
distress for some:                                              Gulu).&#13;
&#13;
â&#128;¢	 Women are overworked in that the men donâ&#128;&#153;t              Ë&#143;Ë&#143;   	Some men donâ&#128;&#153;t want to help women in&#13;
   help them with garden work, and they also                    gardens these days, but instead they go to&#13;
   have to take care of the housework, which                    relax at the trading center from morning&#13;
   makes them very tired (freelisting interview                 to sunset while watching films and foot-&#13;
   with 30-year-old woman in Pader).                            ball matches (freelisting interview with&#13;
                                                                34-year-old woman, Gulu).&#13;
â&#128;¢	 Problems with husbands were most common-&#13;
   ly cited as a cause of psychological distress for   â&#128;¢	 The husband using household resources, in-&#13;
   women. The specific issues referred to include         cluding the womanâ&#128;&#153;s money, to buy alcohol:&#13;
   the following:&#13;
                                                           Ë&#143;Ë&#143;   Getting of money forcefully by men from&#13;
â&#128;¢	 Excessive alcohol use and drunkenness, which                 their women, and they use it for drink-&#13;
   led to abuse and violence; spending household                ing. In such cases, if a man asks for money&#13;
   money on alcohol; neglecting the family; and                 from a woman, she has to give because if&#13;
   frequent quarrels between the husband and                    she refuses, fighting becomes the only so-&#13;
   wife:                                                        lution (freelisting interview with 57-year-&#13;
                                                                old woman, Gulu).&#13;
    Ë&#143;Ë&#143;   Drunkenness in partner, leading to do-&#13;
         mestic violence (slapping, beating) and       â&#128;¢	 Abuse and conflictsâ&#128;&#148;the husband using abu-&#13;
         sale of household property (freelisting in-      sive language toward his wife, frequent misun-&#13;
         terview with 23-year-old woman, Gulu)            derstandings and failures to agree, or the hus-&#13;
                                                          band humiliating and threatening the woman&#13;
    Ë&#143;Ë&#143;   After drinking, they pick fights and end         (often related to drinking):&#13;
         up hurting people. The women then have&#13;
         to pay for the damage caused by their men         Ë&#143;Ë&#143;   Unnecessary quarrelling gives a woman a&#13;
         (freelisting interview with 18-year-old                sense of insecurity (freelisting interview&#13;
         woman, Pader).                                         with 25-year-old woman, Gulu).&#13;
&#13;
â&#128;¢	 he husband not meeting his responsibilities to          Ë&#143;Ë&#143;   Husband doesnâ&#128;&#153;t support her, spends his&#13;
   the family: staying away from the home, not                  salary on alcohol and women and abuses&#13;
   providing for his wife or children, failing to               her, saying she is useless and desperate&#13;
   contribute to household work (for example,                   (case study interview with 30-year-old&#13;
   cultivation, repairing house), or spending                   woman, Gulu).&#13;
   money on alcohol or other women instead of&#13;
   on his family:                                      â&#128;¢	 Husband being unfaithful, which usually in-&#13;
                                                          volves him spending money on other women,&#13;
    Ë&#143;Ë&#143;   Men leave the sole responsibility of taking      and putting his wife at risk of HIV infection:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                Exploring Psychosocial Well-being and&#13;
                                                                             Social Connectedness in Northern Uganda    11&#13;
&amp;#12;         Ë&#143;Ë&#143;   Husband infected her with HIV and he is       ing to the tradition of wife inheritance, who then&#13;
              still sleeping with many women, and de-       neglected them and their children. Relevant obser-&#13;
              mands sex daily from his wife (case study     vations include:&#13;
              interview with 40-year-old women, Kit-&#13;
              gum).                                         â&#128;¢	 Lack of respect and trust between intimate&#13;
                                                               partnersâ&#128;&#148;women can be sent away anytime&#13;
     â&#128;¢	 Polygamy, especially if it involves abuse or           from home (freelisting interview with 45-&#13;
        neglect of the first wife and her children, or         year-old woman, Kitgum).&#13;
        conflict with second wife:&#13;
                                                            â&#128;¢	 Wife inheritanceâ&#128;&#148;men take up widows with&#13;
         Ë&#143;Ë&#143;   Some men bring other wives and forget            the aim of taking away the wealth left by their&#13;
              about the first wife with her children, and      husbands, but fail to take care of such women&#13;
              donâ&#128;&#153;t give support (freelisting interview        and their children. Some people destroy wid-&#13;
              with 30-year-old woman, Kitgum).                 owsâ&#128;&#153; property in revenge of what was done to&#13;
                                                               them by her late husband. Brothers-in-law&#13;
     â&#128;¢	 Domestic violence, usually related to the hus-         insult their late brothersâ&#128;&#153; wives who refuse to&#13;
        band drinking alcohol and having relation-             marry them. Sometimes they send the widow&#13;
        ships with other women, along with trying to           away from their late husbandâ&#128;&#153;s land (freelisting&#13;
        take household resources and listening to gos-         interview with 29-year-old woman, Kitgum).&#13;
        sip about his wife:&#13;
                                                            â&#128;¢	 When widowed, land disputes always arise&#13;
         Ë&#143;Ë&#143;   After getting other women they turn              and women always tend to get thrown out&#13;
              violent against us, for example, abusing,        (freelisting interview with 25-year-old wom-&#13;
              beating us up (freelisting interview with        an, Gulu).&#13;
              23-year-old woman, Pader).&#13;
                                                            Difficult relationships were another significant&#13;
     â&#128;¢	 Husband controlling resources and excluding         cause of emotional distress. Findings revealed&#13;
        the woman from decision making, especially          women who were suffering emotionally because of&#13;
        regarding the use of money:                         problems with their children, who did not respect&#13;
                                                            them; or with their in-laws, who were abusive and&#13;
     â&#128;¢	 Some men do not value womenâ&#128;&#153;s ideas and             insulting, and/or spread gossip about the wife and&#13;
        always want to impose their ideas on women          supported her husband in abusing her:&#13;
        (freelisting interview with 29-year-old wom-&#13;
        an, Kitgum).                                        â&#128;¢	 Some mothers-in-law hate their daughters-&#13;
                                                               in-law and keep abusing them and accusing&#13;
     Other women were said to be suffering emotion-            them falsely, so they are sent away (freelisting&#13;
     ally because of their circumstances following the         interview with 18-year-old woman, Pader).&#13;
     loss of their husbands, either through death or&#13;
     marriage breakdown. For some, just the fear of         â&#128;¢	 Her in-laws were very abusive to her and&#13;
     this was a cause of distress. Some women who had          blamed her for her husbandâ&#128;&#153;s death (case study&#13;
     lost their husbands had been left to fend for them-       interview with 30-year-old woman, Pader).&#13;
     selves and raise children alone, without any finan-&#13;
     cial or emotional support, or any help with house-     â&#128;¢	 Undisciplined children who donâ&#128;&#153;t respect&#13;
     hold work and cultivation. Others were widows             their parents and always ignore their parents&#13;
     who had been sent away from their home and/or             whenever they are talking to them (freelisting&#13;
     land by their in-laws, and whose inheritance rights       interview with 30-year-old woman, Gulu).&#13;
     had been violated. Some widows were reported to&#13;
     have been married to their brother-in-law, accord-     Problems in relationships with neighbors or the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
12&#13;
&amp;#12;community also contributed to distress, includ-                      (freelisting interview with 18-year-old wom-&#13;
ing gossip and abuse (for example, toward single                     an, Pader).&#13;
mothers or women who were formerly abducted),&#13;
quarrelling, or allegations (for example, of witch-             â&#128;¢	 Women who are HIV+ worry so much about&#13;
craft):                                                            the fate of their children after they have died&#13;
                                                                   (freelisting interview with 30-year-old wom-&#13;
â&#128;¢	 She was barren and so was a social outcastâ&#128;&#148;                     an, Kitgum).&#13;
   people treated her badly (case study interview&#13;
   with 36-year-old woman, Pader).&#13;
                                                                Signs of Distress and&#13;
â&#128;¢	 Jealousy, especially with neighbors, is a big&#13;
   problem. Most women here complain of hav-&#13;
                                                                Well-Being&#13;
   ing rough times with neighbors in that some                  Respondents who participated in the case study&#13;
   neighbors donâ&#128;&#153;t want to see others progressing               interviews were asked how they could tell that a&#13;
   in terms of money, childrenâ&#128;&#153;s education, and                 woman was suffering emotionally, and how they&#13;
   so on (freelisting interview with 34-year-old                could tell that she was recovering from her expe-&#13;
   woman, Gulu).                                                riences. Analysis of their responses gives us some&#13;
                                                                understanding of the signs of distress and well-&#13;
â&#128;¢	 Abusive community members to single moth-                    being in the Acholi region of Uganda. The signs&#13;
   ersâ&#128;&#148;they call them prostitutes (freelisting in-              of distress and well-being can be divided into four&#13;
   terview with 23-year-old woman, Pader).                      main areas: relationships, anger and aggression,&#13;
                                                                unhappiness, and fulfilling responsibilities.&#13;
Finally, sickness and disease were further sources&#13;
of emotional distress. These included sickness in               Relationships&#13;
the family, especially of children, and the womanâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
own sickness preventing her from fulfilling her re-             One of the main ways people said they could tell&#13;
sponsibilities. Some womenâ&#128;&#153;s emotional well-being               someone was emotionally distressed, is through&#13;
was affected by a fear of being infected with HIV               the way she behaved with other people. A woman&#13;
by an unfaithful husband, and those who had al-                 who was experiencing emotional distress was said&#13;
ready been affected, worried about the future.                  to commonly withdraw from society and isolate&#13;
                                                                herself (for example, she no longer participated in&#13;
â&#128;¢	 Fear of getting HIV. Men have affairs with                   group activities). She became reluctant to speak to&#13;
   women whose status they are not sure about                   people and did not welcome visitors. Often, such&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                     Case Study 3&#13;
&#13;
  The womanâ&#128;&#153;s son was killed by her brother-in-law due to some family disputes. Then the clan came and took away&#13;
  all her property and even burned her house. She tried to go to the authorities so that her things were brought&#13;
  back, but in vain.&#13;
&#13;
  After this, she cried all the time, she lost weight and was very thin. She talked very bitterly toward the killers and&#13;
  the grabbers. She became a loner and feared company, and started talking to herself.&#13;
&#13;
  She recovered over a period of time. She couldnâ&#128;&#153;t take revenge and time helped her to heal. Now she talks freely&#13;
  with the perpetrators of the crime against her, and goes to the market in the company of other women. She&#13;
  doesnâ&#128;&#153;t cry any more, and laughs freely.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Source: As told by a 30-year-old woman in Pader.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                            Exploring Psychosocial Well-being and&#13;
                                                                                         Social Connectedness in Northern Uganda    13&#13;
&amp;#12;     women did not share with others how they were                 piness in women affected by distressing experi-&#13;
     feeling or listen to advice. Some went further and            encesâ&#128;&#148; they looked sad or cried, and thought a&#13;
     were actively disrespectful: they ignored people;             lot about their concerns. In some cases, they said&#13;
     refused to speak to them; or were abusive, rude,              the woman felt abandoned or victimized by God,&#13;
     or insulting.                                                 wished she were dead, and had become hopeless&#13;
                                                                   and given up on life.&#13;
     Respondents said that they could see when a wom-&#13;
     an had begun to recover by the way she interacted&#13;
     freely and positively with others. A woman who&#13;
                                                                   Fulfilling Responsibilities&#13;
     had recovered from her emotional distress not                 Some of the most visible signs of emotional dis-&#13;
     only respected others and welcomed people to her              tress were said to be related to the woman not tak-&#13;
     home, but she actively helped other people, had               ing care of herself or her surroundings. She might&#13;
     many friends, and advised other women. Sociabil-              become untidy or dirty, and lose weight because&#13;
     ity and assisting others were seen as signs of psy-           she did not eat properly. Often, women who were&#13;
     chological well-being. Such women were also said              emotionally distressed failed to take care of their&#13;
     to have good family relationships (with husband               children, cook for the family, or do other house-&#13;
     and children) and to be able to talk about their              hold work, because they were either unable or un-&#13;
     problems and to listen to advice.                             willing to carry out these normal, everyday tasks.&#13;
&#13;
     Anger and Aggression                                          When a woman recovered from emotional dis-&#13;
                                                                   tress, she was able to carry out the tasks expected&#13;
     In addition to rudeness, some women who were                  of her, such as taking care of her children, keep-&#13;
     psychologically affected by their experiences were            ing the home clean and tidy, and taking care of&#13;
     said to become angry very quickly, and to use                 herself (good personal hygiene, eating well, and&#13;
     violence toward others, including their own chil-             taking care of her health). But signs of recovery&#13;
     dren.                                                         go beyond this, including a woman working hard,&#13;
                                                                   joining groups (digging, sewing), participating in&#13;
     Unhappiness                                                   community activities (for example, work or meet-&#13;
                                                                   ings, including church), and earning money (for&#13;
     Respondents said they also saw signs of unhap-                example, through a small business).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                       Case Study 4&#13;
&#13;
       Her problems began in 2006 when rebels burned village X, and two of her children were burned to death in the&#13;
       house. Her husband then brought another wife, and that was when her two children had just died. The co-wife&#13;
       used to abuse her and when the first wife answered, her husband beat her. Her remaining three children were&#13;
       constantly sick, yet she had no money. Hunger was also a problem.&#13;
&#13;
       She used to always stay alone, and would cry most of the time. She would eat either very little food or not eat at&#13;
       all. She liked talking to herself and blaming God, saying that the Almighty doesnâ&#128;&#153;t like her.&#13;
&#13;
       But today she is somebody patient, and listens to advice from people during difficult times. She also had her hus-&#13;
       band counseled by the clan leaders. After some time the co-wife left her husband, and the man came back to her&#13;
       and they are now staying together. Since he came back, the children are studying because he started paying their&#13;
       fees. The woman now talks freely to people and likes people.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       Source: As told by a 40-year-old woman in Kitgum.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
14&#13;
&amp;#12;Other                                                         the situation was in the past or was ongoing, the&#13;
                                                              womanâ&#128;&#153;s physical health, and her age. Some said&#13;
Other signs of emotional distress mentioned                   that it is easier for younger people to improve their&#13;
by some respondents were women drinking al-                   lives than for older people.&#13;
cohol excessively, talking to themselves, having&#13;
nightmares, leaving home, or moving aimlessly&#13;
around.                                                       Discussion&#13;
                                                              This study found that the causes of psychologi-&#13;
Factors that Contribute to                                    cal distress among women in the Acholi region of&#13;
                                                              northern Uganda include both traumatic events&#13;
Well-Being                                                    that occurred in the past and continue to cause&#13;
                                                              the woman emotional suffering, and difficult situ-&#13;
Respondents were also asked in the case study in-             ations that are ongoing. Events that contribute to&#13;
terviews why they thought some women recovered                distress include those related to conflict (both per-&#13;
from traumatic experiences while others contin-               sonal experience and the losses of loved ones and&#13;
ued to suffer. Their responses gave us some idea              property). Other types mainly involve disrupted&#13;
of the factors that were believed to contribute to            or disturbed relationships with family members,&#13;
well-being.                                                   including children and in-laws and especially hus-&#13;
                                                              bands (for example, death, abandonment).&#13;
The main contributing factors were assistance&#13;
from others (for example, capital and training)               Situations found to contribute to psychological&#13;
and the ability to earn money. This was closely re-           distress mainly centered on poverty and family re-&#13;
lated to whether a woman received support from                lationships. Poverty was a key issue; psychological&#13;
the family (relatives, husband, or children) and the          distress was commonly said to be related to wom-&#13;
womanâ&#128;&#153;s willingness to accept help. Participation             enâ&#128;&#153;s struggles to provide for their families without&#13;
in religious activities, and having faith, were seen          the support of others, and the pressure they felt&#13;
as being helpful to recovery, as was practical help,          under their many responsibilities. This situation&#13;
counseling, or advice received from others.                   was often related to the loss of a husband, or the&#13;
                                                              husband failing to support the family, or actively&#13;
Other factors said to contribute to recovery were             damaging the family by using household resources&#13;
outside the control of the woman or her fam-                  for his own activities and by abusing his wife. Nu-&#13;
ily and community. These included the length of               merous stories were recounted of women suffering&#13;
time since the traumatic event occurred, whether              because their husbands did not take responsibility&#13;
&#13;
                                                     Case Study 5&#13;
&#13;
  During the period when people were in IDP camps, this woman was abandoned by her husband and left with&#13;
  three children. She was unable to take care of her own children and no one tried to assist her during that time. It&#13;
  was not until she left the camp and returned home that she was able to receive support financially.&#13;
&#13;
  She used to be withdrawn from society, and very quietâ&#128;&#148;she rarely spoke to people. She lost a lot of weight and&#13;
  was always ill with nobody to help take care of her. She was very untidy and dirty in appearance.&#13;
&#13;
  When she returned home she was given a loan by an NGO which enabled her to buy items for sale to support her&#13;
  family. Now she has gained weight, speaks to people and is much more happy, and laughs a lot. As well as being&#13;
  assisted with the loan, she recovered because she was supported by her family and was active in the church.&#13;
&#13;
  Source: As told by a 29-year-old woman in Pader.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                          Exploring Psychosocial Well-being and&#13;
                                                                                       Social Connectedness in Northern Uganda    15&#13;
&amp;#12;     for their families. This resulted in women being         by Annan and others (2008), who find that posi-&#13;
     chronically stressed, and also fearful (for example,     tive relationships with families and communities&#13;
     that they would be unable to provide for their chil-     are an important protective factor for formerly ab-&#13;
     dren, that their husband would abandon them, or          ducted girls and women.&#13;
     would infect them with HIV). These findings sup-&#13;
     port those of Payne (1998), Sideris (2003), Okello&#13;
     and Hovil (2007), and others who have highlighted        Limitations&#13;
     the ways in which the conflict in northern Uganda&#13;
                                                              This study gathered information from a relatively&#13;
     has contributed to social disintegration which, in       small number of respondents, which limits the ex-&#13;
     turn, negatively affects the psychosocial well-being     tent we can generalize from the findings. In the&#13;
     of those living in the affected communities.             freelisting interviews people were asked to de-&#13;
                                                              scribe the concerns of women in general; in the&#13;
     Problems in other relationships, including with          case study interviews they were asked to describe&#13;
     community members, were also said to contribute          the behavior of people other than themselves. As a&#13;
     to womenâ&#128;&#153;s psychological distress. This was espe-        result, the signs of psychological distress and well-&#13;
     cially true of women who were unable to fulfill          being that were identified are mainly behavioral,&#13;
     cultural expectations of them (for example, wom-         with relatively few thoughts or feelings included.&#13;
     en who were barren, single mothers, or had been          This should not, therefore, be seen as a compre-&#13;
     abducted).                                               hensive set of indicators of psychological distress&#13;
                                                              and well-being, but as indicators of external, ob-&#13;
     The main signs of psychological distress observed        servable signs of distress and well-being.&#13;
     by others were changes in relationships and social&#13;
     behavior, emotional distress (particularly anger         The causes of distress identified are assumed by&#13;
     and sadness), and the neglect of responsibilities.       the respondent, rather than reported by the per-&#13;
     Common signals of distress were withdrawing              son experiencing the distress. Since people were&#13;
     from others and becoming isolated, and some-             not asked to discuss their own experiences (for&#13;
     times being rude and disrespectful if they came          ethical reasons), it is not certain that the events&#13;
     into contact with others. The main outward sign          and situations described were really the cause of&#13;
     of recovery was described as a change in social          the observed distress; it is possible that private&#13;
     behaviorâ&#128;&#148;namely, free and positive interactions          events also played a role but were unknown to the&#13;
     with others.                                             respondents.&#13;
&#13;
     The other main sign of psychological distress and        It may have been possible to overcome this limi-&#13;
     well-being was the extent to which a woman un-           tation by asking women directly about their own&#13;
     dertook her responsibilities, including family and       experiences of psychological distress. But this&#13;
     self-care. A woman who was suffering emotion-            would have raised ethical issues concerning the&#13;
     ally was said to often neglect these responsibilities,   appropriateness of asking women to talk about&#13;
     while a woman who had recovered not only car-            very distressing experiences, and exposing them to&#13;
     ried out the tasks expected of her in the home, but      thoughts and feelings that they may not be ready&#13;
     also involved herself in community activities and        to confront in this direct way. Previous research&#13;
     undertook some income-generation activity.               has shown that many women in Uganda cope with&#13;
                                                              distress by not talking about it, so to ask a woman&#13;
     The factors that distinguish women able to recover       to describe her experiences for the purposes of this&#13;
     from distressing events and situations include their     research would have risked undermining her ex-&#13;
     ability to earn money, receive support from fam-         isting coping strategies. While personal questions&#13;
     ily and community members (including practical           may be necessary for in-depth qualitative stud-&#13;
     support, counseling, and advice), and accept help.       ies, potential negative effects can be minimized&#13;
     This finding is in line with the research conducted      through appropriate study design and the provi-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
16&#13;
&amp;#12;sion of psychological support. The risks were not       The conflict-related factors affecting women in&#13;
felt to be justifiable for the current study, which     the Acholi region can be considered using Annan&#13;
aimed only to gather the information required to        and Brierâ&#128;&#153;s (2010) model of gendered violence&#13;
develop a structured interview schedule.                in conflict situations (see figure 1). At the indi-&#13;
                                                        vidual level, the security situation has improved,&#13;
                                                        but women still struggle with economic issues, al-&#13;
How Conflict Has                                        though this will improve as women return home&#13;
                                                        and are able to cultivate their land. At the fam-&#13;
Contributed to Psychological                            ily level, all the factors identified continue to have&#13;
                                                        an impact: death and disruption, scarce resources,&#13;
Distress in Northern Uganda                             alcohol use, and abuse. Social factors were also&#13;
                                                        mentioned frequently by the respondents: the im-&#13;
This study shows clearly that the psychologi-           pact of patriarchy was evident in the discussion of&#13;
cal well-being of women in the Acholi region of         problematic marital relations, and the challenges&#13;
Uganda has been affected by events both spe-            faced by widows in maintaining ownership of&#13;
cifically conflict related (for example, abduction,     their land and property. Stigma and rejection from&#13;
rape, death of loved ones) but also by events that      neighbors was also discussed, particularly affecting&#13;
were not related to the conflict, and by long-term      women who were barren, single mothers, or who&#13;
situations that developed â&#128;&#147; sometimes because of        had been abducted. Scarce resources at the social&#13;
the conflict, and sometimes for other reasons. It is    level might include disputes over land as people&#13;
well known that events that occur due to conflict       return home from the camps, but little was heard&#13;
have a variety of related, long-term effects. For ex-   about this in the discussions of the factors contrib-&#13;
ample, women whose husbands are killed in con-          uting to womenâ&#128;&#153;s psychological distress. The main&#13;
flict struggle not only with grief, but also with an    structural factor identified as affecting womenâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
ongoing lack of practical and material support.         psychological well-being was gender inequality,&#13;
                                                        particularly as it affects the womanâ&#128;&#153;s role in the&#13;
Many types of events and situations can contrib-        family and her circumstances if she loses her hus-&#13;
ute to a womanâ&#128;&#153;s distress. It is extremely difficult,   band (through death or abandonment) or he takes&#13;
therefore, to identify the impact that the conflict     a second wife.&#13;
itself had on affected womenâ&#128;&#153;s psychological well-&#13;
being. For example, the story was recounted of a&#13;
woman whose son was abducted on his way to              Implications for Future&#13;
school, and whose husband was killed by a speed-&#13;
ing car on the same road some time later. One of        Programming and Research&#13;
these events was related to the conflict, the other     The findings of this study suggest that efforts to&#13;
was not. It would be impossible to try to tease out     improve womenâ&#128;&#153;s psychological well-being should&#13;
the effect of conflict on this womanâ&#128;&#153;s psychological    focus on the impact of both traumatic past events&#13;
well-being.                                             and ongoing situations. The practical effects of loss&#13;
                                                        are important, as well as feelings of grief. The find-&#13;
But it is clear that family relationships and poverty   ings indicate that poverty and family relationships&#13;
have a particularly significant impact on womenâ&#128;&#153;s       have a particularly significant effect on womenâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
psychological distress, and conflict is known to        psychological well-being in the Acholi region of&#13;
have a negative effect on both of these aspects of      Uganda, but this finding may be an effect of the&#13;
life. In addition, problematic relationships within     particular methodology that was used, which re-&#13;
the community were also said to contribute to           lied on reports of third parties. Meanwhile, con-&#13;
psychological distress, and the damaging effects        sistent reports of men failing to take responsibil-&#13;
of conflict and displacement on community well-         ity for their families and taking advantage of their&#13;
being has been well documented.                         culturally dominant role to abuse their wives and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                 Exploring Psychosocial Well-being and&#13;
                                                                              Social Connectedness in Northern Uganda    17&#13;
&amp;#12;     use household resources for their own activities         ing with the womanâ&#128;&#153;s family or other community&#13;
     strongly suggests a need for programs to address         members to enable supportive relationships to be&#13;
     male attitudes and behavior. It is not possible to       established and/or strengthened.&#13;
     effect change in womenâ&#128;&#153;s lives solely by working&#13;
     with women; it is also necessary to work with the        This study also has implications for further re-&#13;
     men who live with women and have considerable            search into the psychological effects of conflict on&#13;
     influence over their lives (see Womenâ&#128;&#153;s Refugee          women, and on how these effects can best be al-&#13;
     Commission 2009). There are now a number of              leviated. First, any study of the psychological ef-&#13;
     programs being implemented in postconflict set-          fects of conflict must find a way of dealing with&#13;
     tings that aim to change the attitudes and behavior      the fact that women in such situations experience&#13;
     of men and boys; if these programs are effective,        a range of challenging and distressing events, some&#13;
     the current research suggests they would positively      of which are related to the conflict and some of&#13;
     impact the lives of women.                               which are not. In some cases, everyday stressors&#13;
                                                              may have more impact on a womanâ&#128;&#153;s psychologi-&#13;
     The two factors said to play the greatest role in aid-   cal well-being than a conflict-related traumatic&#13;
     ing womenâ&#128;&#153;s recovery from psychological distress         event that occurred some years earlier. Research&#13;
     are: (i) the ability to earn an income, and (ii) sup-    must identify and measure all the factors that may&#13;
     portive relationships within the family and com-         contribute to womenâ&#128;&#153;s psychological well-being,&#13;
     munity. Programs could usefully facilitate wom-          not only those that appear to be conflict related.&#13;
     enâ&#128;&#153;s access to these, but should bear in mind that       This study, like many others conducted in simi-&#13;
     all community relationships are not necessarily          lar situations, emphasizes the importance of un-&#13;
     supportive. While positive relationships have an         derstanding what psychological distress and well-&#13;
     extremely beneficial effect, it was noted that some      being mean in the given context before trying to&#13;
     relationships in the community can be damaging,          measure them.&#13;
     especially where women struggle to meet cultural&#13;
     expectations.                                            Two classes of observable signs of psychological&#13;
                                                              distress (and recovery) in the Acholi region have&#13;
     It was reported that some women find it difficult        been highlighted and could be used in further re-&#13;
     to accept help from family and community mem-            search that aims to measure such signs. Observa-&#13;
     bers. Such women may need professional support           tions of womenâ&#128;&#153;s relationships and social behaviors,&#13;
     to achieve a state where they are able to benefit        including their ability to carry out their normal&#13;
     from family and community relationships. They            responsibilities, could be used to complementâ&#128;&#148;or&#13;
     may be particularly isolated and marginalized in         as an alternate toâ&#128;&#148;self-reporting.&#13;
     their communities, and intensive but informal&#13;
     contact is likely to be required over a consider-        Finally, this study suggests that there is a need&#13;
     able period of time by a psychosocial worker. A          for a better understanding of male behavior post-&#13;
     skilled professional would be able to cope with the      conflict, especially within the family. It is not clear&#13;
     womanâ&#128;&#153;s initial resistance and, over time, to build      whether the behavior patterns described by inter-&#13;
     a trusting, constructive relationship with her that      viewees as distressing to women are related to the&#13;
     could form the basis for more therapeutic con-           experience of conflict in some way. This is an area&#13;
     versations and activities. This may include work-        that could be explored further.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
18&#13;
&amp;#12;                                       References&#13;
Akello, G., R. Reis, and A. Richters. 2010. â&#128;&#156;Si-              sessment of Depression Prevalence in Ru-&#13;
        lencing Distressed Children in the Con-               ral Uganda Using Symptom and Function&#13;
        text of War in Northern Uganda: An                    Criteria.â&#128;&#157; Social Psychiatry and Psychiatric&#13;
        Analysis of its Dynamics and its Health               Epidemiology 39: 442â&#128;&#147;47.&#13;
        Consequences.â&#128;&#157; Social Science and Medi-&#13;
        cine 71: 213â&#136;&#146;20.                              Bolton, P., J. Bass, T. Betancourt, L. Speelman, G.&#13;
                                                              Onyango, K. F. Clougherty, R. Neuge-&#13;
Annan, J., C. Blattman, K. Carlson, and D. Ma-                bauer, L. Murray, and H. Verdeli. 2007.&#13;
       zurana. 2008. The State of Female Youth in             â&#128;&#156;Interventions for Depression Symptoms&#13;
       Northern Uganda: Findings from the Survey              among Adolescent Survivors of War and&#13;
       of War Affected Youth (Phase II). Uganda:              Displacement in Northern Uganda: A&#13;
       SWAY. http://www.sway-uganda.org.                      Randomized Controlled Trial.â&#128;&#157; Journal&#13;
                                                              of the American Medical Association 298:&#13;
Annan, J., and M. Brier. 2010. â&#128;&#156;The Risk of Re-               519â&#136;&#146;27.&#13;
       turn: Intimate Partner Violence in North-&#13;
       ern Ugandaâ&#128;&#153;s Armed Conflict.â&#128;&#157; Social Sci-      Bracken, P. J., J. E. Giller, and D. Summerfield.&#13;
       ence and Medicine 70: 152â&#136;&#146;59.                          1995. â&#128;&#156;Psychological Responses to War&#13;
                                                              and Atrocity: The Limitations of Current&#13;
Bass, J. K., P. Bolton, and L. K. Murray. 2007. â&#128;&#156;Do           Concepts.â&#128;&#157; Social Science and Medicine&#13;
          Not Forget Culture When Studying Men-               40: 1073â&#128;&#147;82.&#13;
          tal Health.â&#128;&#157; The Lancet 370: 918â&#136;&#146;19.&#13;
                                                      Carlson, S. 2005. Contesting and Reinforcing Patri-&#13;
Bass, J. K., R. Neugebauer, K. F. Clougherty, H.              archy: An Analysis of Domestic Violence in&#13;
         Verdeli, P. Wickramaratne, L. Ndogoni,               the Dzaleka Refugee Camp (Rep. No. 23).&#13;
         L. Speelman, M. Weissman, and P. Bol-                Oxford: Refugee Studies Centre, Univer-&#13;
         ton. 2006. â&#128;&#156;Group Interpersonal Psycho-              sity of Oxford.&#13;
         therapy for Depression in Rural Uganda:&#13;
         Six-Month Outcomes.â&#128;&#157; British Journal of      CPC (Care and Protection of Children) in Crisis&#13;
         Psychiatry 188: 567â&#136;&#146;73.                            Affected Countries. 2008. A Good Prac-&#13;
                                                            tice Policy Change Initiative. New York:&#13;
Bolton, P. 2001a. â&#128;&#156;Cross-Cultural Validity and              Columbia University.&#13;
        Reliability Testing of a Standard Psychi-&#13;
        atric Assessment Instrument without a         Davidson, G. R., K. E. Murray, and R. D. Sch-&#13;
        Gold Standard.â&#128;&#157; The Journal of Nervous               weitzer. 2010. â&#128;&#156;Review of Refugee Men-&#13;
        and Mental Disease 189: 238â&#136;&#146;42.                      tal Health Assessment: Best Practices and&#13;
                                                             Recommendations.â&#128;&#157; Journal of Pacific&#13;
â&#128;&#148;â&#128;&#148;â&#128;&#148;. 2001b. â&#128;&#156;Local Perceptions of the Men-                   Rim Psychology 4: 72â&#128;&#147;85.&#13;
    tal Health Effects of the Rwandan Geno-&#13;
    cide.â&#128;&#157; The Journal of Nervous and Mental          Deacon, Z., and C. Sullivan. 2010. â&#128;&#156;An Ecologi-&#13;
    Disease 189: 243â&#136;&#146;49.                                     cal Examination of Rural Mozambican&#13;
                                                             Womenâ&#128;&#153;s Attainment of Postwar Wellbe-&#13;
Bolton, P. C. Wilk, and L. Ndogoni. 2004. â&#128;&#156;As-               ing.â&#128;&#157; Journal of Community Psychology 38:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                              Exploring Psychosocial Well-being and&#13;
                                                                           Social Connectedness in Northern Uganda    19&#13;
&amp;#12;             115â&#128;&#147;30.                                        Miller, K. E., M. Kulkarni, and H. Kushner. 2006.&#13;
                                                                     â&#128;&#156;Beyond Trauma-Focused Psychiatric&#13;
     Dejman, M., A. S. Forouzan, S. Assari, M. Ra-                   Epidemiology: Bridging Research and&#13;
            soulian, A. Jazayery, H. Malekafzali, M.                 Practice with War-Affected Populations.â&#128;&#157;&#13;
            Baradaran Eftekhari, K. Falahat, and S.                  American Journal of Orthopsychiatry 76:&#13;
            Ekblad. 2010. â&#128;&#156;How Iranian Lay People                    409â&#128;&#147;22.&#13;
            in Three Ethnic Groups Conceptualize&#13;
            a Case of a Depressed Woman: An Ex-             Miller, K. E., P. Omidian, A. S. Quraishy, N.&#13;
            planatory Model.â&#128;&#157; Ethnicity and Health                  Quraishy, M. N. Nasiry, S. Nasiry, N.&#13;
            15: 475â&#128;&#147;93.                                             M. Karyar, and A. A. Yaqubi. 2006. â&#128;&#156;The&#13;
                                                                    Afghan Symptom Checklist: A Culturally&#13;
     Fernando, G. A. 2008. â&#128;&#156;Assessing Mental Health                 Grounded Approach to Mental Health&#13;
            and Psychosocial Status in Communities                  Assessment in a Conflict Zone.â&#128;&#157; American&#13;
            Exposed to Traumatic Events: Sri Lanka                  Journal of Orthopsychiatry 76: 423â&#128;&#147;33.&#13;
            as an Example.â&#128;&#157; American Journal of Or-&#13;
            thopsychiatry 78: 229â&#128;&#147;39.                       Okello, M. C., and L. Hovil. 2007. â&#128;&#156;Confronting&#13;
                                                                    the Reality of Gender-Based Violence in&#13;
     Hart, J., A. Galappatti, J. Boyden, and M. Arm-                Northern Uganda.â&#128;&#157; International Journal&#13;
              strong. 2007. â&#128;&#156;Participatory Tools for                of Transitional Justice 1(3): 433â&#128;&#147;43.&#13;
              Evaluating Psychosocial Work with Chil-&#13;
              dren in Areas of Armed Conflict: A Pi-        PADHI. 2009. A Tool, a Guide and a Framework.&#13;
              lot in Eastern Sri Lanka.â&#128;&#157; Intervention 5:          Colombo, Sri Lanka: University of Co-&#13;
              41â&#128;&#147;60.                                              lombo.&#13;
&#13;
     Horn, R. 2009. â&#128;&#156;A Study of the Emotional and           Payne, L. 1998. â&#128;&#156;Food Shortages and Gender&#13;
            Psychological Wellbeing of Refugees in                 Relations in Ikafe Settlement, Uganda.â&#128;&#157;&#13;
            Kakuma Refugee Camp, Kenya.â&#128;&#157; Inter-                    Gender and Development 6: 30â&#128;&#147;36.&#13;
            national Journal of Migration, Health and&#13;
            Social Care 5 (4): 20â&#128;&#147;32.                       Pike, I. L., and S. R. Williams. 2006. â&#128;&#156;Incorporat-&#13;
                                                                      ing Psychosocial Health into Biocultural&#13;
     Igreja, V., W. Kleijn, and A. Richters. 2006. â&#128;&#156;When              Models: Preliminary Findings from Tur-&#13;
               the War Was Over, Little Changed: Wom-                 kana Women of Kenya.â&#128;&#157; American Jour-&#13;
               enâ&#128;&#153;s Posttraumatic Suffering after the War             nal of Human Biology 18: 729â&#128;&#147;40.&#13;
               in Mozambique.â&#128;&#157; Journal of Nervous and&#13;
               Mental Disease 194: 502â&#128;&#147;09.                  Rasco, L. M., and K. E. Miller. 2004. â&#128;&#156;Innova-&#13;
                                                                    tions, Challenges and Critical Issues in&#13;
     Jordans, M. J. D., I. H. Komproe, W. A. Tol, and               the Development of Ecological Mental&#13;
              J. T. de Jong. 2009. â&#128;&#156;Screening for Psy-              Health Interventions with Refugees.â&#128;&#157; In&#13;
              chosocial Distress amongst War-Affected               The Mental Health of Refugees: Ecological&#13;
              Children: Cross-Cultural Construct Va-                Approaches to Healing and Adaptation, eds.&#13;
              lidity of the CPDS.â&#128;&#157; Journal of Child Psy-            K. E. Miller and L. M. Rasco, 375â&#128;&#147;416.&#13;
              chology and Psychiatry 50: 514â&#128;&#147;23.                    Mahwah, NJ: Lawrence Erlbaum Associ-&#13;
                                                                    ates.&#13;
     Lopes Cardozo, B. L., O. O. Bilukha, C. A. Got-&#13;
            way, M. I. Wolfe, M. L. Gerber, and             Rasmussen, A., L. Nguyen, J. Wilkinson, S. Vund-&#13;
            M. Anderson. 2005. â&#128;&#156;Mental Health of                   la, S. Raghavan, K. E. Miller, and A. S.&#13;
            Women in Postwar Afghanistan.â&#128;&#157; Journal                 Keller. 2010. â&#128;&#156;Rates and Impact of Trau-&#13;
            of Womenâ&#128;&#153;s Health 14: 285â&#128;&#147;93.                          ma and Current Stressors among Dar-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
20&#13;
&amp;#12;         furi Refugees in Eastern Chad.â&#128;&#157; American                the Knowledge Base of Global Mental&#13;
         Journal of Orthopsychiatry 80: 227â&#128;&#147;36.                  Health?â&#128;&#157; British Medical Journal 336:&#13;
                                                                 992â&#128;&#147;94.&#13;
Roberts, B., E. Y. Damundu, O. Lomoro, and E.&#13;
        Sondorp. 2010. â&#128;&#156;The Influence of De-             Tankink, M. 2004. â&#128;&#156;Not Talking about Traumatic&#13;
        mographic Characteristics, Living Con-                  Experiences: Harmful or Healing? Cop-&#13;
        ditions, and Trauma Exposure on the                     ing with War Memories in Southwest&#13;
        Overall Health of a Conflict-Affected                   Uganda.â&#128;&#157; Intervention: International Jour-&#13;
        Population in Southern Sudan.â&#128;&#157; BMC                      nal of Mental Health, Psychosocial Work&#13;
        Public Health 10.                                       and Counselling in Areas of Armed Conflict&#13;
                                                                2: 3â&#128;&#147;17.&#13;
Sideris, T. 2003. â&#128;&#156;War, Gender and Culture: Mo-&#13;
         zambican Women Refugees.â&#128;&#157; Social Sci-           Usta, J., J. A. M. Farver, and L. Zein. 2008.&#13;
         ence and Medicine 56: 713â&#128;&#147;24.                            â&#128;&#156;Women, War, and Violence: Surviving&#13;
                                                                  the Experience.â&#128;&#157; Journal of Womenâ&#128;&#153;s Health&#13;
Snider, L., C. Cabrejos, E. H. Marquina, J. J. Tru-&#13;
                                                                  17: 793â&#128;&#147;804.&#13;
         jillo, A. Avery, and H. A. Aguilar. 2004.&#13;
         â&#128;&#156;Psychosocial Assessment for Victims of&#13;
                                                         Weyermann, B. 2007. â&#128;&#156;Linking Economics and&#13;
         Violence in Peru: The Importance of Lo-&#13;
                                                               Emotions: Towards a More Integrated&#13;
         cal Participation.â&#128;&#157; Journal of Biosocial Sci-&#13;
                                                               Understanding of Empowerment in Con-&#13;
         ence 36: 389â&#128;&#147;400.&#13;
                                                               flict Areas.â&#128;&#157; Intervention: International&#13;
Stark, L., A. Ager, M. Wessells, and N. Boothby.               Journal of Mental Health, Psychosocial&#13;
         2009. â&#128;&#156;Developing Culturally Relevant                 Work and Counselling in Areas of Armed&#13;
         Indicators of Reintegration for Girls, For-           Conflict 5: 83â&#128;&#147;96.&#13;
         merly Associated with Armed Groups, in&#13;
         Sierra Leone Using a Participative Rank-        Wilks, C. M., and P. Bolton, 2002. â&#128;&#156;Local Per-&#13;
         ing Methodology.â&#128;&#157; Intervention: Interna-                ceptions of the Mental Health Effects of&#13;
         tional Journal of Mental Health, Psycho-                the Uganda Acquired Immunodeficiency&#13;
         social Work and Counselling in Areas of                 Syndrome Epidemic.â&#128;&#157; The Journal of Ner-&#13;
         Armed Conflict 7: 3â&#128;&#147;16.                                 vous and Mental Disease 190: 394â&#128;&#147;97.&#13;
&#13;
Summerfield, D. 2007. â&#128;&#156;â&#128;&#152;Major Depressionâ&#128;&#153; in             Womenâ&#128;&#153;s Refugee Commission. 2009. Peril or&#13;
      Ethiopia: Validity is the Problem.â&#128;&#157; British              Protection: The Link between Livelihoods&#13;
      Journal of Psychiatry 190: 362.                          and Gender-Based Violence in Displace-&#13;
                                                               ment Settings. New York: Womenâ&#128;&#153;s Refu-&#13;
â&#128;&#148;â&#128;&#148;â&#128;&#148;. 2008. â&#128;&#156;How Scientifically Valid is                        gee Commission.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                 Exploring Psychosocial Well-being and&#13;
                                                                              Social Connectedness in Northern Uganda    21&#13;
&amp;#12; THE WORLD BANK&#13;
 1818 H, Street N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433&#13;
www.logica-wb.org&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="19253701">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2013/04/19253701/psychosocial-distress-well-being-among-acholi-women-northern-uganda
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2013/04/19253701/psychosocial-distress-well-being-among-acholi-women-northern-uganda</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2013/04/19253701/psychosocial-distress-well-being-among-acholi-women-northern-uganda</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2014-03-17T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2014-03-17T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2014/03/17/000333037_20140317121657/Rendered/INDEX/860560NWP0Box30GICA0WorkingPaperNo1.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2014/03/17/000333037_20140317121657/Rendered/PDF/860560NWP0Box30GICA0WorkingPaperNo1.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2013-04-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2014-03-17T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Psychosocial distress and well-being among
            Acholi women in Northern Uganda
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            This paper addresses two main topics:
            the effects of conflict on the psychological; and well-being
            of women methodological issues related to the measurement of
            psychological well-being. The literature on these topics is
            reviewed, and data from a qualitative study conducted in
            northern Uganda is used to explore them in more depth.
            Finally, the paper considers the ways in which conflict has
            contributed to women's psychological distress in
            northern Uganda, and the implications of this study for
            future programming and research.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Psychosocial distress and well-being among
            Acholi women in Northern Uganda
        </docna>
        <display_title>Psychosocial distress and
            well-being among Acholi women in Northern Uganda</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2013/04/19253701/psychosocial-distress-well-being-among-acholi-women-northern-uganda</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Working Paper (Numbered Series)</docty>
        <subtopic>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation,Gender and Development,Gender and Health,Gender and Law,Population Policies</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Health, Nutrition and Population,Gender</teratopic>
        <count>Uganda</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Horn, Rebecca</author>
        </authors>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>East Africa!$!80458</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Sub-Saharan Africa!$!80473</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000333037_20140317121657</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>Africa,Africa</admreg>
        <colti>Logica working paper series ; no. 1</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Health, Nutrition and Population,Gender</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            abduction, abuse, abuses, Acquired
            Immunodeficiency Syndrome, adult literacy, aged, Armed
            Conflict, armed conflicts, basic needs, beating, clan
            leaders, Community mechanisms, community work, conflict
            resolution, Corruption, Counselling, crime, decision making,
            Depression, descent, disease, domestic violence, economic
            opportunity, emotional support, Empowerment, Epidemic,
            Epidemiology, Ethnic Groups, extended families, families,
            family members, family relationships, family support,
            father, female, female interviewers, females, focus group
            discussions, forced marriage, gender, Gender Inequality,
            gender norms, Gender Relations, gender roles, gender-based
            violence, Genocide, girls, grief, Health Consequences,
            Health Effects, Health Interventions, Health of Women,
            health problems, HIV, HIV infection, home, household assets,
            household property, household work, husband, husbands,
            Immunodeficiency, Inequality, informed consent, inheritance,
            inheritance rights, injury, Intervention, isolation, Journal
            of Women, Justice, Knowledge Base, laws, life events,
            literacy, lives of women, Living Conditions, male attitudes,
            Medicine, Mental, Mental Health, Mental Health of Women,
            mental illness, Migration, older people, older women,
            patient, Patriarchy, people with disabilities, personal
            hygiene, physical abuse, physical health, Policy Change,
            Polygamy, postconflict settings, practitioners, progress,
            prostitutes, prostitution, Protection of Children,
            psychiatry, psychological support, Psychology, Psychosocial
            Work, Psychotherapy, Public Health, rape, Refugee, Refugees,
            respect, Scarce Resources, Screening, security situation,
            self-image, sex, sexual exploitation, sexual violence,
            single mothers, Social Development, SOCIAL FACTORS, Social
            Science, Trauma, United Nations, victims, Victims of
            Violence, violence, vulnerability, war, widow, widows, wife,
            will, wives, woman, Women Refugees, Women's Health, Youth
        </keywd>
        <owner>Post Conflict &amp; Soc Dev Prac Grp (AFTCS)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>East Africa</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Sub-Saharan Africa</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>86056</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fragility, Conflict and Violence</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Alternative Sentencing Options</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community based Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Correctional Services and Facilities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corrections</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime and Society</ml:concept><ml:concept>Defense Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Detention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enforcement Policies and Oversight Mechanism</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigative Task Force Police</ml:concept><ml:concept>Juvenile Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Law Enforcement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Offender Reintegration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Administration and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Problem solving Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Prosecution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Restorative Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Therapeutic Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Assistance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim-Offender Mediation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Asset Recovery</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>GBSV</ml:concept><ml:concept>GBV</ml:concept><ml:concept>Gender-based Violence</ml:concept><ml:concept>Gender-based and Sexual Violence</ml:concept><ml:concept>Foreign Direct Investments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Linkages</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Armed Conflict</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Criminal Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Injury</ml:concept><ml:concept>Mental Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Youth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>Domestic Violence</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transitional Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Youth and Gender-Based Violence</ml:concept><ml:concept>FDI Spillovers</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>