<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>ï»¿                                                  86251&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Agriculture and Water Policy: Toward Sustainable&#13;
Inclusive Growth&#13;
Syud Amer Ahmed and Madhur Gautam&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                    Policy Paper Series on Pakistan&#13;
                                                          PK 16/12&#13;
                                                        March 2013&#13;
&amp;#12;_______________________________________________&#13;
&#13;
This publication is a product of the South Asia Poverty Reduction and Economic&#13;
Management Unit. It is part of a larger effort by the World Bank to provide open access to its&#13;
research and make a contribution to development policy discussions in Pakistan and around&#13;
the world. Policy Working Papers are also posted on the Web at http://econ.worldbank.org.&#13;
The authors may be contacted at sahmed20@worldbank.org and mgautam@worldbank.org.&#13;
&amp;#12;Abstract&#13;
This paper reviews Pakistanâ&#128;&#153;s agriculture performance and analyzes its agriculture and water&#13;
policies. It discusses the nature of rural poverty and emphasizes the reasons why agricultural&#13;
growth is a critical component to any pro-poor growth strategy for Pakistan. It supports&#13;
these arguments by summarizing key results from recent empirical analysis where the&#13;
relative benefits of agricultural versus non-agricultural led growth are examined. The results&#13;
also provide an illustration of farm and non-farm linkages. It summarizes recent&#13;
performance of the agriculture sector, and discusses key characteristics of its sluggish&#13;
productivity growth. Three key issues related to increasing productivity are discussed:&#13;
namely technology, water use and water management, and policy reforms related to markets&#13;
and trade that can strengthen the enabling environment and contribute to the promotion of&#13;
diversification towards high value agriculture&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The Policy Research Working Paper Series disseminates the findings of work in progress to&#13;
encourage the exchange of ideas about development issues. An objective of the series is to get&#13;
the findings out quickly, even if the presentations are less than fully polished. The papers&#13;
carry the names of the authors and should be cited accordingly. The findings,&#13;
interpretations, and conclusions expressed in this paper are entirely those of the authors.&#13;
They do not necessarily represent the views of the International Bank for Reconstruction and&#13;
Development / World Bank and its affiliated organizations, or those of the Executive&#13;
Directors of the World Bank or the governments they represent.&#13;
&amp;#12; Agriculture and Water Policy: Toward Sustainable Inclusive&#13;
                          Growth&#13;
&#13;
                 Syud Amer Ahmed and Madhur Gautam&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The authors would like to thank Simeon Ehui, Jose Lopez Calix, Muhammad Riaz and&#13;
Anthony Cholst (World Bank) for helpful feedback; to Keith Fuglie (USDA) for sharing the&#13;
global productivity database; Dario Debowicz, Paul Dorosh, and Sohail Malik (IFPRI) for&#13;
sharing their modeling results; and to the authors of the many background papers used&#13;
extensively as resources for this policy note.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                      4&#13;
&amp;#12;                                Agriculture and Water Policy: Toward Sustainable Inclusive Growth&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table of Contents&#13;
&#13;
Executive Summary                                                                           6&#13;
Introduction                                                                               12&#13;
Rural Poverty and Role of Agriculture in Inclusive Growth                                  14&#13;
Agricultural Performance                                                                   20&#13;
Key Issues and Challenges                                                                  29&#13;
Policy Recommendations                                                                     40&#13;
References                                                                                 43&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figures&#13;
&#13;
Figure 1       Poverty Head Count Ratio at National Poverty Line                           14&#13;
Figure 2       Distribution of Poverty by Household Type                                   15&#13;
Figure 3       GDP Growth and Value Added by Broad Sector                                  17&#13;
Figure 4       Distributional Impacts on Per Capita Incomes of 1% GDP Growth               18&#13;
Figure 5       Average National Yields and Yield Gaps                                      20&#13;
Figure 6       Composition of Total Agricultural Production                                20&#13;
Figure 7       Average Annual Agriculture Output Growth Rate in Pakistan                   23&#13;
Figure 8       Decomposition of Output Growth in Agricultural Land by Sector               24&#13;
Figure 9       Average Annual TFP Growth Rates for Agriculture in Pakistan                 24&#13;
Figure 10      Average Annual Growth Rates of Inputs in the Agriculture Sector             25&#13;
Figure 11      Irrigated Area as Share of Cropland and Harvested Area                      26&#13;
Figure 12      Agricultural R&amp;D Spending as a Share of Agriculture GDP in South Asia       30&#13;
Figure 13      Ratio of the Area Equipped for Irrigation to Cropland Area                  32&#13;
Figure 14      Average Annual Growth Rates of Irrigated and Cropland Area                  32&#13;
Figure 15      Exports of High Value Agricultural Products from Pakistan                   38&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Tables&#13;
&#13;
Table 1        HH Sensitivities of Per Capita Income                                       18&#13;
Table 2        Average Annual GDP Growth and Agriculture GDP Growth                        21&#13;
Table 3        Composition of Agricultural GDP in Pakistan                                 22&#13;
Table 4        Production Growth Rates of Select Major Crops                               22&#13;
Table 5        Average Annual Output, Input and TFP Growth                                 24&#13;
Table 6        Average Annual Growth Rates in Factor Productivity in Punjab                27&#13;
Table 7        Seepage Losses in Irrigation System                                         34&#13;
Table 8        Seed Supply for Major Crops in 2010                                         39&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                5&#13;
&amp;#12;                               Agriculture and Water Policy: Toward Sustainable Inclusive Growth&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Executive Summary&#13;
1.      Pakistanâ&#128;&#153;s economy has grown substantially over the past decade, with an average&#13;
real GDP growth rate of about 4.9 percent per year. Growth in agricultural value added has&#13;
been lower at 3.3 percent per year. As is the case in transforming economies, the transition&#13;
from an agrarian economy to a developed economy is accompanied by a decline in the share&#13;
of primary agriculture with a commensurate increase in the share of manufacturing and&#13;
services. Pakistan has also experienced this trend, with the share of agriculture value added&#13;
in real GDP declining from 46 percent in 1960 to 26 percent in 2000 and 21 percent in 2010&#13;
(World Bank, 2011a).&#13;
&#13;
2.      Nevertheless, the agricultural sector is important for inclusive growth. Only 17.5&#13;
percent of the poor are in urban areas, with the remainder representing a range of different&#13;
rural households. 39 percent of the poor are rural non-farm income dependent households,&#13;
9.7 percent are from households of landless farmers, 11.8 percent are from households of&#13;
agricultural wage laborers, 20.1 percent are small farm households, and 1.9 percent of the&#13;
poor coming from medium to large farm households. The performance of the agricultural&#13;
sector also has a strong impact on non-farm activity growth in reducing poverty. Studies of&#13;
growth linkages have suggested that non-farm incomes rise by an additional 0.35 to 0.85&#13;
dollars for every dollar increase in agricultural income (Haggblade et al., 1991; Hazell et al.,&#13;
2012).&#13;
&#13;
3.      While Pakistanâ&#128;&#153;s poverty rate has continued to fall over the decade, agricultureâ&#128;&#153;s poor&#13;
performance in recent years has limited its contributions to poverty reduction. The&#13;
percentage of the population below the national poverty line declined from 34.7 percent to&#13;
21.9 percent between 2001-02 and 2005-06, and this declining trend continued till 2007-08&#13;
to 17.2 percent (World Bank, 2012a). Of the 12.8 percentage point decline in the poverty&#13;
headcount ratio between 2001-02 and 2005-06, growth in farm income accounted for 2.8&#13;
percentage points (Inchauste and Winkler, 2012). When the poverty reduction between&#13;
2001-02 and 2007-08 is considered, farm income growth was responsible for 3.2 percentage&#13;
points of the reduction.&#13;
&#13;
4.      Economy wide modeling work by IFPRI (2012) suggests that there is potential for&#13;
agriculture-led growth to be more poverty reducing than non-agriculture-led growth. An&#13;
economic growth strategy focusing on TFP growth in crop and livestock sectors is found to be&#13;
more inclusive than a strategy targeting TFP growth in industry or services alone.&#13;
Households that depend on agricultural wages do almost as well as in any other scenario. A&#13;
livestock focused growth strategy tends to benefit households with large farms. In contrast,&#13;
growth led by productivity improvements in services appears to be harmful to incomes for&#13;
rural households that do not own farms. To put these in context, note that less than 2&#13;
percent of the poor are from medium to large farm households, while rural non-farm&#13;
households and rural households involved in agriculture represent 39 percent and 42&#13;
percent of the poor, respectively.&#13;
&#13;
5.      A strategy to promote broad based agricultural growth can directly improve&#13;
agricultural incomes (especially among the landless and smallholder farmers) by narrowing&#13;
the wide yield gaps that currently exist and by diversifying towards high-value agricultural&#13;
products. The Planning Commission (2009) estimates that average yields tend to be far&#13;
below the Progressive Farmer yields that represent the achievable upper bound. The national&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                               6&#13;
&amp;#12;                               Agriculture and Water Policy: Toward Sustainable Inclusive Growth&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
average yields of major crops like wheat and rice are currently only about 55 percent of&#13;
Progressive Farmer yields, which represent the highest achievable yields in Pakistan. These&#13;
yield gaps are even greater for some commercial crops like sugarcane in Sindh (73 percent).&#13;
Despite the large potential for improvement, yield growth has been steadily declining over&#13;
the years. For example, rice yields grew at an average annual rate of 5.24 percent in 1960s&#13;
and 3.16 percent in 1990s, whereas they have only been growing at 1.68 percent per year this&#13;
past decade. A similar pattern can be seen in the case of wheat, which had average annual&#13;
yield growth of 2.92 percent in 1960s and 1.99 percent in 1990s. This growth rate is now only&#13;
1.1 percent per year.&#13;
&#13;
6.      Pakistanâ&#128;&#153;s agricultural output growth rate has been decelerating, and is reflected in&#13;
its declining TFP growth rate. In earlier decades, Pakistanâ&#128;&#153;s average annual output growth&#13;
rate was as high as 4.8 percent (in the 80s), making it a global leader in agricultural growth.&#13;
In the past decade, however, agricultural output growth rate has shrunk to a more modest&#13;
3.34 percent. In earlier decades, Pakistanâ&#128;&#153;s TFP growth was responsible for a substantial&#13;
share of the output growth. For example, in the 1960s, 1980s, and 1990s TFP accounted for&#13;
44 percent, 67 percent, and 37 percent, respectively, of the output growth. In contrast, TFP&#13;
now accounts for less than a fifth of the output growth. Relative to other countries,&#13;
agricultural TFP growth since the 1990s has been very slow, but has mildly picked up more&#13;
recently. Pakistanâ&#128;&#153;s TFP growth has gone from being among the best in the world in the&#13;
1980s to being the lowest among regional and Asian comparators (Bangladesh, India, Sri&#13;
Lanka, and China).&#13;
&#13;
7.      Closing current yield gaps are also the best strategy to adapt to climate change, which&#13;
is expected to put additional stress on the agriculture sector. Yu et al. (2012) consider a range&#13;
of climate change scenarios to estimate impacts on the economy. Production impacts in the&#13;
crop sub-sector vary by crop and region. Crop production declines are greatest in Sindh,&#13;
where it declines by 10 percent on average. In the most extreme case, Sindhâ&#128;&#153;s crop&#13;
production shrinks by 36 percent. In contrast, Punjabâ&#128;&#153;s crop production shrinks by only 5&#13;
percent in the worst case scenario. Yu et al. (2012) estimate that if crop yields were to&#13;
improve by 20 percent over the next two decades, then GDP, agricultural GDP, and&#13;
household incomes would rise by 2.6 percent, 11.6 percent, and 3.4 percent, respectively,&#13;
more than compensating for the effects of climate change. Furthermore, the 20 percent yield&#13;
improvement over 20 years is a realistic goal, given that wheat and rice yields improved by 1-&#13;
2 percent per year over the 1989-99 period. Even after a 20 percent improvement in wheat&#13;
and rice yields, there would still be a substantial yield gap between the average achieved yield&#13;
and what is currently achievable in the best case scenario.&#13;
&#13;
8.      Much of the high historical growth in yields and productivity can be attributed to&#13;
major scientific breakthroughs in technology, as during the Green Revolution, resulting from&#13;
the investments in agricultural research undertaken by the national agricultural research&#13;
system. Agricultural R&amp;D in Pakistan has historically been led by the public sector, and has&#13;
proven to be a good investment. Estimated internal rates of return from investments in&#13;
agricultural research have ranged between 57 percent to 65 percent, with most of the returns&#13;
coming from Green Revolution research. However, there are severe technical capacity&#13;
constraints to the current agricultural research system. According to ASTI data, public&#13;
investment in agricultural research has been on the decline. It is currently about 0.21 percent&#13;
of agricultural GDP and ranks at the bottom of agricultural R&amp;D spending as a share of&#13;
agricultural GDP in the region. Only 15 percent of agricultural research staff trained holds&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                               7&#13;
&amp;#12;                               Agriculture and Water Policy: Toward Sustainable Inclusive Growth&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
PhDs, which is low relative to the educational attainment of researchers in the rest of South&#13;
Asia (Beintema et al. 2007). Qualified research staff is discouraged from public research&#13;
agencies due to institutional disincentives such as limited promotion opportunities and low&#13;
salaries.&#13;
&#13;
9.      The technical capacity constraints are compounded by inefficiencies generated by the&#13;
institutional environment. The Pakistan Agricultural Research Council (PARC) coordinates&#13;
the activities of a large agricultural research network of public national and provincial&#13;
agricultural research bodies, institutes and experimental stations. PARC does not conduct&#13;
agricultural research itself although the National Agricultural Research Center is under its&#13;
administration. With the passing of the 18th Amendment to the Constitution, the public&#13;
agricultural system has now devolved from the federal to the provincial level, allowing&#13;
research to have a greater focus on the needs of local farmers and environmental conditions.&#13;
&#13;
10.      In addition to technology, a critical factor in improving the crop yields is water&#13;
availability and the performance of the irrigation system. About 95 percent of Pakistanâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
arable land is currently irrigated, up from 64 percent in 1960 and 72 percent in 1980.&#13;
However, farmersâ&#128;&#153; access to water is less than it could be due to major limitations of the&#13;
water allocation system. At the farm level, access to canal water is determined by physical&#13;
location along the canal and through the warabandi water allocation system of&#13;
administratively set rotations. Access to canal water then becomes contingent on access to&#13;
land, and the location of that land. There might not be enough water by the time it gets to&#13;
land at the tail end of distributaries or watercourses, especially if upstream farmers have&#13;
illegally access to water (Yu et al., 2012).&#13;
&#13;
11.     Another critical challenge to the irrigation system under the current water&#13;
management system is that it is financially unsustainable. The canal irrigation management&#13;
system recovers only a quarter of its annual operating and maintenance costs, with the&#13;
shortfall expected to increase with rising costs and stagnant Abiana (water charges per acre&#13;
of crops irrigated) (Planning Commission, 2012). The collection rate of assessed Abiana is&#13;
also lowâ&#128;&#148;at only 60 percent of assessed valuesâ&#128;&#148;and the resulting budget gap is about Rs. 5.4&#13;
billion annually. The system is thus subsidized by the federal government. The current&#13;
Abiana for different crops might also be distorting farmer decisions, since they do not reflect&#13;
the relative profitability of each crop. For example, comparing the Abiana for rice and&#13;
cottonâ&#128;&#148;two major export cropsâ&#128;&#148;it can be seen that their irrigation charges per acre are&#13;
about the same, even though rice requires 60 percent more water than cotton. There might&#13;
thus be possible overproduction of rice.&#13;
&#13;
12.     Recognizing the importance of a robust and efficient water management system, the&#13;
Government of Pakistan implemented reforms in the 1990s to enhance water use efficiency,&#13;
streamline water resources management, and facilitate participation by users. However, the&#13;
reforms have not been completely successful. At the provincial level, the devolution of&#13;
autonomy from the Public Irrigation Departments (PIDs) to Provincial Irrigation and&#13;
Drainage Authorities (PIDAs) is incomplete, with the PIDs maintaining managerial control&#13;
over the PIDAs through a range of mechanisms. At the local level, Farmersâ&#128;&#153; Organizations&#13;
(FOs) that are meant to help manage distributor and minor canals have no input into the&#13;
Abiana setting process. FOs also vary widely in their role as charge collectors, since charges&#13;
are set by management and the FOs may or may not have any voice in this process. The lack&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                               8&#13;
&amp;#12;                               Agriculture and Water Policy: Toward Sustainable Inclusive Growth&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
of clarity in the role and mandate of the FOs has contributed to the inefficiencies in Abiana&#13;
collection that are damaging the financial sustainability of the system.&#13;
&#13;
13.     The irrigation system is highly inefficient as is demonstrated by the substantial&#13;
seepage losses which occur in almost every component of the delivery system. The overall&#13;
efficiency of the system is 35 percent, and improving the canal systemâ&#128;&#153;s efficiency from 35&#13;
percent to 50 percent could boost growth substantially. Yu et al. (2012) estimated that GDP&#13;
and GDP from the agriculture sector would decline by 1.1 percent and 5.1 percent on average,&#13;
under climate change. Even modest improvement to the canal systemâ&#128;&#153;s efficiency would&#13;
increase GDP by 0.94 percent and agricultural GDP by 4.22 percent, on average.&#13;
&#13;
14.     Another limitation to water access is at the provincial level due to institutional&#13;
features such as the 1991 Provincial Water Allocation Accord. Since 1991, water inflows have&#13;
been apportioned among the provinces by the Indus Water Accord, allocating flows among&#13;
the provinces based on a 5-year record of pre-Accord historical canal diversions. Relaxation&#13;
of the institutional rigidities of the Accord can allow for a more market-based allocation of&#13;
water leading to aggregate economic benefits. Yu et al. (2012) estimate that by relaxing the&#13;
allocation constraints of the Accord, Punjab and Sindh would gain Rs. 83 billion and Rs. 82&#13;
billion in revenue, respectively, although other provinces would collectively lose about Rs. 7&#13;
billion. Relaxing the conditions of the Accord by itself, without complementary policy may&#13;
thus lead to outcomes that are not necessarily pro-poor. The complementary policy would&#13;
need to compensate groups that the Accord relaxation would harm, such as farmers in&#13;
Baluchistan and Khyber Pakhtunkhwa, or producers of crops that are not irrigated.&#13;
&#13;
15.    International and domestic trade are critical to improving agricultural production,&#13;
but face challenges to their growth. Agricultural exports directly account for more than 11&#13;
percent of Pakistanâ&#128;&#153;s exports, with exports of downstream industries like textiles accounting&#13;
for more than another 40 percent of export revenue (Planning Commission, 2009).&#13;
&#13;
16.      However, policies introduced in the past five years have steadily eroded the effects of&#13;
trade liberalization that Pakistan implemented between 1996 and 2003. Pakistan had&#13;
simplified its tariff structure and state trading monopolies for agricultural products had been&#13;
abolished. However, exceptions were introduced in 2006, and a number of the more&#13;
important reforms in agriculture were reversed, especially with regard to wheat, sugar and&#13;
fertilizer. The use of SROs (Statutory Regulatory Orders) has also expanded since 2006.&#13;
SROs and new regulatory duties have been used to provide exemptions to normal tariffs in&#13;
some cases, while increasing tariffs for others. The resulting trade regime is thus highly&#13;
discretionary and uncertain, leading to significant and unpredictable output and input price&#13;
distortions.&#13;
&#13;
17.    Major crops like wheat, rice, sugar, and cotton are implicitly taxed by various policy&#13;
induced price distortions introduced in most years. The implicit tax on crop production&#13;
depresses production despite implicit net input subsidies. For example, basmati rice had&#13;
negative ERPs between 2008 and 2010, when farm income would have been higher by 21&#13;
percent to 40 percent under a no-intervention regime. The case of sugar also illustrates the&#13;
same. The significant increase in the world price of refined sugar raised the parity price, but&#13;
the increase in general sales tax applied to sugar offset the higher border prices. Sugarâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
parity prices are thus approximately double the observed farm gate price discouraging&#13;
production.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                               9&#13;
&amp;#12;                              Agriculture and Water Policy: Toward Sustainable Inclusive Growth&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
18.     The benefits of some domestic trade policies have also been unclear, as is illustrated&#13;
by the public procurement of wheat. Government procurement of wheat is extensive, and&#13;
involves federal, provincial and district level agencies. The government sets the procurement&#13;
price with expected procurement targets that the Pakistan Agricultural Storage and Services&#13;
Corporation (PASSCO) and Provincial Food Departments are responsible for meeting.&#13;
Provincial governments (mainly Punjab and Sindh) and PASSCO procure about 20 percent&#13;
of total wheat production each year (Prikhodko and Zrilyi, 2012). All procured wheat is then&#13;
sold to flour millers in the same wheat marketing year, with the government absorbing the&#13;
costs of procurement, storage, and financing. Millers are able to buy the subsidized wheat at&#13;
below market prices, and then sell the flour at open market prices, which are the prices faced&#13;
by consumers. This price stabilization role is perhaps one reason that wheat stocks have&#13;
risen in the recent past, which has led to exports at subsidized prices in years of high wheat&#13;
production.&#13;
&#13;
19.     The impact of these procurement policies on consumer welfare needs to be carefully&#13;
analyzed. On the one hand the wheat market interventions have insulated the domestic&#13;
market from global price volatility, but the rise in real prices of wheat over time has likely&#13;
hurt net buyers while benefiting the net-sellers. Furthermore, the market intervention is&#13;
often fiscally costly and can also lead to perverse outcomes like subsidized exports.&#13;
&#13;
20.     There is substantial scope for accelerating broad-based agricultural growth to fully&#13;
exploit its potential for poverty reduction. To achieve this, policy actions are required to&#13;
promote technology and innovation, improve water use management and put in place the&#13;
right trade policies.&#13;
&#13;
   1. Technology and innovation are critical to improve agricultural productivity. Key&#13;
      actions required for this are substantial reforms to the current national agricultural&#13;
      research system. First, the system requires fundamental institutional reforms to&#13;
      make it more efficient and effective. With efforts under way to develop provincial&#13;
      agricultural research institutions, the role of PARC and the NARC needs to be&#13;
      adjusted to exploit their comparative advantage of being federal institutions able to&#13;
      facilitate federal funding, intra-provincial knowledge, and capacity building. Second,&#13;
      with the shift in primary activities from the federal to the provincial levels and from&#13;
      policy coordination to agricultural research, then there is a need to reflect these&#13;
      activities human resource and performance incentives. This may require moving&#13;
      personnel from the center to the provincial institutions, or even changing the&#13;
      composition of the staff, to increase the percentage of scientific research staff for&#13;
      example. Third, these reforms will require additional spending in agricultural&#13;
      research and development, whether for supporting agricultural research in provincial&#13;
      research centers or capacity building of science staff, with the exact composition of&#13;
      additional spending depending on the nature of the institutional reforms.&#13;
&#13;
   2. To improve water use efficiency, the most important intervention would be&#13;
      institutional reform of the entire management system. Given the systemâ&#128;&#153;s high&#13;
      dysfunction, clarifying the institutional environment would be a prerequisite for any&#13;
      other intervention under consideration, such as revising the Abiana. The reforms to&#13;
      the water management system include completely devolving authority to the relevant&#13;
      scale, clarifying the roles and mandates of each authority, and providing sufficient&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                            10&#13;
&amp;#12;                           Agriculture and Water Policy: Toward Sustainable Inclusive Growth&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   resources and capacity building to allow the devolved authorities to fulfill their&#13;
   mandates.&#13;
&#13;
3. To improve international trade of agricultural products, the trade regime must be&#13;
   simplified. This will require removing unpredictable and discretionary instruments&#13;
   like SROs, shifting to a lower set of uniform tariffs, and simplifying the trade regime&#13;
   by removing alternative trade policy instruments like export taxes. These would&#13;
   reduce uncertainty, volatility, and the policy bias against agricultural products like&#13;
   rice and sugar. From a practical perspective, the reforms will require the&#13;
   identification of a realistic timetable for reform, as well as the identification of WTO&#13;
   compliant instruments that may still be appropriate to protect national interests.&#13;
&#13;
4. To improve domestic trade of agricultural products while protecting food security,&#13;
   distortions in domestic markets of commodities like wheat need to be removed. The&#13;
   simplest set of reforms would be to reduce the wheat procurement volume, while&#13;
   designing and implementing complementary social safety net programs. The wheat&#13;
   procurement contraction would reduce the effective subsidy to wheat producers and&#13;
   decrease the fiscal burden. If food price stability is important, price bands can be&#13;
   implemented using rules-based adjustable tariffs that set floor and ceiling prices to&#13;
   follow world prices. In parallel, social safety net programs that target food insecure&#13;
   groups can be established, with the programs having clearly defined triggers and&#13;
   graduation requirements.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                         11&#13;
&amp;#12;                                     Agriculture and Water Policy: Toward Sustainable Inclusive Growth&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Introduction&#13;
21.    Pakistanâ&#128;&#153;s economy has grown substantially over the past decade with an average real&#13;
GDP growth rate of about 4.9 percent per year between 2000 and 2010, while agricultural&#13;
value added has grown at a lower rate of 3.3 percent per year (World Bank, 2011a). As is the&#13;
case in transforming economies, the transition from an agrarian economy to a developed&#13;
economy is accompanied by a decline in the share of primary agriculture with a&#13;
commensurate increase in the share of manufacturing and services. Pakistan has also&#13;
experienced this trend, with the share of agriculture value added in real GDP declining from&#13;
46 percent in 1960 to 26 percent in 2000 and 21 percent in 2010 (World Bank, 2011a).&#13;
&#13;
22.      Nevertheless, agriculture remains a socio-economically and politically important&#13;
sector at the current stage of Pakistanâ&#128;&#153;s transformation process. Agriculture accounts for&#13;
more than 40 percent of total employment1 (World Bank, 2011a), though the sectorâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
contribution to overall employment is likely to be much higher considering downstream&#13;
activities through supply chains, transportation, and the processing sectors it contributes to.&#13;
Agriculture also contributes substantially both directly and indirectly to foreign exchange&#13;
revenue. Agricultural exports directly account for more than 11 percent of Pakistanâ&#128;&#153;s exports,&#13;
with exports of downstream industries like textiles accounting for more than another 40&#13;
percent of export revenue2.&#13;
&#13;
23.     Historically, the sector has done well at the national level due to technologies of&#13;
Green Revolution. A combination of expanded input use, investments in land and water&#13;
resources, and rapid improvements in total factor productivity over the years have been the&#13;
main sources of past growth. The slowdown since 1995, however, is a cause for concern. This&#13;
is of particular importance going forward because global markets have become much more&#13;
unreliable (with high and volatile prices), resource degradation (of soil and water in&#13;
particular) has increased, and the uncertainty associated with the impact of climate change&#13;
on agricultural production poses a serious threat to food security. Pakistan has made&#13;
substantial progress in reducing food insecurity, most recently illustrated by the recent&#13;
downgrading of its status from â&#128;&#152;Alarmingâ&#128;&#153; to â&#128;&#152;Seriousâ&#128;&#153; in the Global Hunger Index3 (IFPRI,&#13;
2011). Yet, substantial food and nutrition security challenges remain. For example, 26&#13;
percent of the population is estimated to be undernourished, with the rate of&#13;
undernourishment higher among children at 38 percent (Food Security Portal, 2012).&#13;
&#13;
24.     While Pakistanâ&#128;&#153;s poverty rate has continued to fall over this period, agricultureâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
sluggish performance in recent years has limited its contributions to poverty reduction. The&#13;
percentage of the population below the national poverty line declined from 34.7 percent to&#13;
21.9 percent between 2001-02 and 2005-06, and this declining trend continued till 2007-08&#13;
to 17.2 percent (World Bank, 2012a)4. Of the 12.8 percentage point decline in the poverty&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
1 Employment in agriculture as a share of total employment was 44 percent in 2008 (World Bank, 2011a)&#13;
2 Based on data for 2006-07 from Planning Commission (2009)&#13;
3 The GHI is a weighted index based on the proportion of undernourished as a percentage of the population, the&#13;
prevalence of underweight children under the age of five; and the mortality rate of children under the age of five.&#13;
4 The poverty headcount rates at the national poverty line are very similar to the poverty headcount rates&#13;
measured at the $1.25 a day (PPP) poverty line. For example, the poverty rate was 35.87 percent in 2002 and 21.4&#13;
percent in 2008 at the $1.25 a day line, versus 34.7 percent and 17.2 percent at the national poverty line (World&#13;
Bank, 2011a). Poverty rates are substantially higher when the $2 a day (PPP) poverty line is considered, with&#13;
poverty rates of 73.9 percent in 2002 and 60.2 percent in 2008.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                12&#13;
&amp;#12;                               Agriculture and Water Policy: Toward Sustainable Inclusive Growth&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
headcount ratio between 2001-02 and 2005-06, growth in farm income accounted for 2.8&#13;
percentage points (Inchauste and Winkler, 2012). When the poverty reduction between&#13;
2001-02 and 2007-08 is considered, farm income growth was responsible for 3.2 percentage&#13;
points of the reduction.&#13;
&#13;
25.     Robust growth of the agricultural sector as part of a broader strategy that enhances&#13;
both farm and non-farm income and employment is imperative for inclusive, pro-poor&#13;
growth. The performance of the agricultural sector also has a strong impact on the ability of&#13;
non-farm activity growth in reducing poverty. So, if the local economy is growing slowly, this&#13;
will be reflected in the non-farm sectorâ&#128;&#153;s growth. Rural non-farm activities also tend to be&#13;
closely related to the agricultural sector at lower-income levels, since higher agricultural&#13;
incomes would translate into higher spending on local non-farm goods and services. Studies&#13;
of growth linkages have suggested that non-farm incomes rise by an additional 0.35 to 0.85&#13;
dollars for every dollar increase in agricultural income (Haggblade et al., 1991; Hazell et al.,&#13;
2012).&#13;
&#13;
26.     This paper reviews some of the key issues to stimulate such growth. The paper&#13;
discusses rural poverty in more detail, and emphasizes the reasons why agricultural growth&#13;
is a critical component to any pro-poor growth strategy in Pakistan. It supports these&#13;
arguments by summarizing key results from recent empirical analysis where the relative&#13;
benefits of agricultural versus non-agricultural led growth are examined. The results also&#13;
provide an illustration of farm and non-farm linkages. It then summarizes recent&#13;
performance of the agriculture sector, and discusses key characteristics of its sluggish&#13;
productivity growth. It moves on to describe the three key issues related to increasing this&#13;
productivity: namely technology, water use and water management, and policy reforms&#13;
related to markets and trade that can strengthen the enabling environment and contribute to&#13;
the promotion of diversification towards high value agriculture. While it is important to also&#13;
understand the dynamics of the rural labor markets, especially as it relates to inclusive&#13;
agricultural growth, a detailed analysis is beyond the scope of this paper, and is thus not&#13;
addressed here.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                             13&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                           Agriculture and Water Policy: Toward Sustainable Inclusive Growth&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Rural Poverty and Role of Agriculture in Inclusive Growth&#13;
27.     Pakistanâ&#128;&#153;s poverty headcount has been steadily declining over the past decade,&#13;
although there are substantial and persistent differences between poverty rates in urban and&#13;
rural areas. Pakistanâ&#128;&#153;s overall poverty rate has declined from 34.5 percent in 2001-02 to 17.2&#13;
percent in 2007-08. This poverty reduction has not been equal across urban and rural areas&#13;
with rural poverty remaining much higher than urban poverty (Figure 1). The discrepancies&#13;
between rural and urban poverty are particularly pronounced in some provinces. For&#13;
example, the 2008 rural poverty rate tends to be double the urban poverty rate in Punjab&#13;
and more than two and half a times in Sindh.&#13;
&#13;
28.    Despite a fall in the national poverty rate, the rate of rural poverty reduction has&#13;
tended to lag behind urban poverty reduction, with rural poverty still twice as high as urban&#13;
poverty. IFPRI (2012) estimates that only 17.5 percent of the poor live in urban areas; the&#13;
remainder representing a range of different rural households. About 39 percent of the poor&#13;
are rural non-farm income dependent households, 9.7 percent are from households of&#13;
landless farmers, 11.8 percent from households of agricultural wage laborers, 20.1 percent&#13;
are small farm households, and 1.9 percent of the poor come from medium to large farm&#13;
households.&#13;
&#13;
  Figure 1                                Poverty Head Count Ratio at National Poverty Line&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     40&#13;
&#13;
                                     35&#13;
       Poverty Headcount Ratio (%)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     30&#13;
&#13;
                                     25&#13;
&#13;
                                     20&#13;
&#13;
                                     15&#13;
&#13;
                                     10&#13;
&#13;
                                      5&#13;
                                             1998-99        2001-02        2004-05         2005-06         2007-08&#13;
&#13;
                                                             Pakistan        Urban         Rural&#13;
&#13;
Source: World Bank (2012a)&#13;
&#13;
29.     About half of the rural poor tend to be in non-farm activities (Figure 2), and there is a&#13;
close relationship between land ownership and rural poverty. Many of the rural poor are&#13;
landless or own only small amounts of land. Anwar et al. (2004) estimated the poverty&#13;
headcount of rural non-farm households to be about 48 percent, second only to that of&#13;
landless farmers (55 percent), but greater than that of farmers with less than a hectare of&#13;
land (32 percent). There is virtually no poverty among farm households with more than a&#13;
hectare of land, emphasizing the strong relationship between land ownership and poverty.&#13;
This is exacerbated by the highly unequal distribution of land in Pakistan. The Gini&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                         14&#13;
&amp;#12;                                  Agriculture and Water Policy: Toward Sustainable Inclusive Growth&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
coefficient of land holdings in Pakistan is about 0.66 â&#128;&#147; a figure which has remained relatively&#13;
constant between 1970 and 2000 (World Bank, 2007a). This estimate does not account for&#13;
the fact that 63 percent of households were landless in 2000. When these landless&#13;
households are accounted for in the Gini coefficient estimation, the value rises to 0.86,&#13;
higher than that of other South Asian countries. Relating land ownership to farm size, World&#13;
Bank (2007a) also found that in 2000, 61 percent of farm households owned less than 2.0&#13;
hectares of holdings, representing about 15 percent of total land holdings. In contrast, 2&#13;
percent of households owned holdings greater than 20.2 hectares, representing 30 percent of&#13;
total land holdings.&#13;
&#13;
  Figure 2       Distribution of Poverty by Household Type&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                    Large, medium&#13;
                                                         farm&#13;
                                                         1.9%&#13;
                                    Urban&#13;
                                    17.5%&#13;
                                                        Small farm&#13;
                                                          20.1%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                        Landless farmers&#13;
                                                             9.7%&#13;
                             Rural non-farm&#13;
                                 39.0%                  Rural agric&#13;
                                                         laborer&#13;
                                                          11.8%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Source: IFPRI (2012)&#13;
&#13;
30.     The current characteristics of rural poverty and the land rights regime in Pakistan&#13;
pose a major challenge to faster poverty reduction. The majority of rural poor are landless,&#13;
and even among those farming, poverty is significantly higher among sharecroppers (i.e.,&#13;
landless who are operating land under tenancy arrangements) than landowners (Malik,&#13;
2005). However, land is rarely bought and sold, and the status quo of unequal land&#13;
distribution tends to be maintained. The World Bank (2007a) noted that the inequality in&#13;
landholdings by province5 remained relatively unchanged from the 1970s to 2000s. The&#13;
study argues that the low rate of transactions is due in large part to high transactions costs&#13;
and prices in excess of the discounted value of potential agricultural earnings from the land.&#13;
Since the landless do not have access to creditâ&#128;&#148;with land being the most commonly accepted&#13;
collateral for formal loansâ&#128;&#148;they are unable to generate financing to acquire land in the first&#13;
place. This is characteristic of the barriers to land acquisition, and contributes to the status&#13;
quo of highly unequal distribution of land.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
5 Inequality in land holdings was measured as a Gini coefficient. Punjab tended to have the lowest Gini&#13;
coefficients, while North West Frontier Province (now Khyber Pakhtunkhwa) tended to have the highest.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                    15&#13;
&amp;#12;                                    Agriculture and Water Policy: Toward Sustainable Inclusive Growth&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
31.     Pakistanâ&#128;&#153;s population growth rate can be expected to contribute to the steady rise of&#13;
small farms as land is divided into smaller plots in successive generations. In 1973, the&#13;
average farm size was 5.3 ha and there were 1.06 million small (less than two hectare) farms.&#13;
By 2000, the average farm size had shrunk to 3.1 ha, while the number of small farms had&#13;
more than tripled (Headey et al., 2010; Hazell et al., 2012). The evidence on the impact of&#13;
declining farm sizes on land productivity is mixed (Kiani, 2008, finds a negative but&#13;
insignificant correlation between farm size and productivity). Small and large farms are&#13;
more productive than medium farms, with the smaller farms associated with higher intensity&#13;
and irrigation and large farms with capital intensive production. Despite potentially higher&#13;
productivity per se (that is higher output per cultivated unit of land ) of smaller farms, say&#13;
through better access to technology and more intensive cultivation, the impact on household&#13;
incomes may be limited due to limited scope for diversification and limited access to&#13;
resources (Malik, 2005). Given that small farm households also tend to have a higher&#13;
poverty rate, with no significant changes in access to services, technology, markets and&#13;
credit, the growth in the number of small farms could result in continuing high levels of&#13;
poverty.&#13;
&#13;
32.      The high population growth rate and slow transition of labor out of agriculture also&#13;
puts pressure on rural economy to produce sufficient employment for new workers. Hazell et&#13;
al. (2012) estimate the necessary labor exit rates out of agriculture6 given varying levels of&#13;
agricultural growth. The authors use a stylized partial equilibrium model where the exit rate&#13;
from agriculture is a function of the employment share of rural workers in agriculture, the&#13;
rural growth rate, the growth rate of the agricultural sector, and an agricultural employment&#13;
elasticity of 0.2. It is then estimated that if the average annual agricultural growth rate was&#13;
3.88 percent per year, then the exit rate for labor out of the sector would have to be 1.88&#13;
percent in the 2010-20 period, and 1.49 in the 2020-30 period, in order to maintain full&#13;
rural employment. If the agricultural growth rate is a more sluggish 1.94 percent per year,&#13;
then these exit rates would need to be 2.3 percent and 1.91% per year for the 2010-20 and&#13;
2020-30 periods, respectively.&#13;
&#13;
33.    Expansion of the rural non-farm sector would contribute towards generating&#13;
employment and reducing poverty although its contributions depend to a large extent on the&#13;
success of the agricultural sector as well. There are several constraints to the development of&#13;
the rural non-farm sector. The rural non-farm sector tends to be largely services, essentially&#13;
serving local markets. So, if the local economy is growing slowly, this will be reflected in the&#13;
non-farm sectorâ&#128;&#153;s growth.&#13;
&#13;
34.     A balanced approach that expands incomes of both farm and non-farm incomes is&#13;
thus necessary, as is illustrated by a recent analysis7 carried out by IFPRI (2012). The&#13;
analysis suggests that there is potential for agriculture-led growth to be more poverty&#13;
reducing than nonagriculture-led growth by comparing the economic impacts of historical&#13;
total factor productivity (TFP) growth to the economic impacts under counterfactual&#13;
scenarios where TFP growth is accelerated. IFPRI (2012) considers five counterfactual&#13;
&#13;
6 The exit rate is defined as the sum of labor absorption into the rural nonfarm economy and out-migration to&#13;
urban areas, and must be equal to the difference between growth rate in the rural work force and the projected&#13;
growth rate in agricultural employment.&#13;
7 The analysis uses a comparative static single-region computable general equilibrium simulation model of&#13;
&#13;
Pakistan based on a 2007-08 Social Accounting Matrix and HIES survey data.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                           16&#13;
&amp;#12;                                     Agriculture and Water Policy: Toward Sustainable Inclusive Growth&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
scenarios that test the sensitivity of the Pakistani economy to rapid growth (through&#13;
increases in TFP) in four broad sectors: crops, livestock, industry, and services. In the first&#13;
four scenarios, total factor productivities of sectors in each of these broad groups are&#13;
increased by 10 percent, individually. So, the first scenario increases TFP of only crops, the&#13;
second of only livestock, the third of only industry, and the fourth of only services. The fifth&#13;
scenario increases the productivity of all sectors simultaneously.&#13;
&#13;
35.     A 10 percent TFP increase in services sector would lead to a 5.4 percent increase in&#13;
GDP, while 10 percent TFP increases in crops and livestock lead to GDP increases of 1.8&#13;
percent and 1 percent, respectively (Figure 3). The impacts on overall GDP is not surprising,&#13;
because of the relative sizes of the various subsectors. Services account for 53 percent of the&#13;
2010 value added (share of total GDP), while crops and livestock only account for 9.43&#13;
percent and 11.43 percent, respectively (IFPRI, 2012). To make the relative contributions&#13;
more comparable, it is necessary to neutralize the scale effect. This is done by normalizing&#13;
the poverty and income results by the GDP changes arising in each of the scenarios, in order&#13;
to have a fair comparison of marginal impacts given the relative differences in the sizes of the&#13;
crop, livestock, industry, and services sectors.&#13;
&#13;
36.      This approach allows an assessment of the sensitivity of household per capita&#13;
incomes by household type to a one percent GDP improvement from each of the five&#13;
counterfactual scenarios. They show that GDP growth originating in crop and livestock&#13;
sectors tends to be the most poverty reducing among the alternative scenarios. The growth&#13;
â&#128;&#152;elasticityâ&#128;&#153; of household per capita income for all households is 1.22 and 1 for the crop TFP&#13;
and livestock TFP led scenarios. In contrast, the growth elasticities of household per capita&#13;
income are only 0.25 and 0.8 when industry and services TFP led growth are considered&#13;
(Table 1). These distributional impacts suggest that targeting crop and livestock sectors can&#13;
lead to more inclusive growth relative to an approach that targets industry or services. This is&#13;
more clearly shown in Figure 4 which compares the distributional impacts for the two&#13;
extreme cases of crops and services on different categories of households.&#13;
&#13;
   Figure 3      GDP Growth &amp; Value Added by Broad Sector due to 10% TFP Improvements in Sectors&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         9&#13;
         8&#13;
         7&#13;
         6&#13;
         5&#13;
         4&#13;
     %&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         3&#13;
         2&#13;
         1&#13;
         0&#13;
         -1       Crop Led Growth     Livestock Led Growth    Industry Led Growth    Services Led Growth&#13;
&#13;
                 Total GDP     Primary Value Aded     Industry Value Added     Services Value Added&#13;
&#13;
Source: IFPRI (2012)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                           17&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                        Agriculture and Water Policy: Toward Sustainable Inclusive Growth&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   Table 1       HH Sensitivities of per Capita Incomes due to 1% GDP Growth Arising from TFP&#13;
                 Improvements&#13;
           Household Type*                                                                Crop                   Livestock                            Industry                    Services&#13;
  Medium-Large Farms(241.7)                                                               -1.3                      1.6                                  1.8                        1.2&#13;
  Small-Dry Farms (67.0)                                                                   0.9                      0.3                                  1.7                        0.5&#13;
  Agricultural Wage Laborers (48.0)                                                        2.4                      1.6                                  2.5                        -0.4&#13;
  Non-Farm Poor (38.0)                                                                     2.2                      1.5                                  1.9                        -0.1&#13;
  Non-Farm Non-Poor (66.2)                                                                 2.1                      1.7                                  1.3                        -0.1&#13;
  Urban Poor (37.0)                                                                        1.4                      1.4                                  0.8                        0.4&#13;
  Urban Non-Poor (158.8)                                                                   1.2                      0.8                                 -1.9                        1.5&#13;
  Total (88.2)                                                                             1.2                      1.0                                  0.3                        0.8&#13;
Note: *Numbers in parentheses indicate base level household income per capita in 1000s of Rs.&#13;
Source: Authorsâ&#128;&#153; calculations from IFPRI (2012) model simulation result.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Figure 4      Distributional Impacts on per capita incomes of 1% GDP growth&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     2.5&#13;
&#13;
     2.0&#13;
&#13;
     1.5&#13;
&#13;
     1.0&#13;
&#13;
     0.5&#13;
&#13;
     0.0&#13;
                                                                                                 Non-farm poor&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                         Urban poor&#13;
                                      Small-dry farms&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                 Urban non-poor&#13;
                 Medium-large farms&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                             Agricultural wage laborers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                     Non-farm non-poor&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     -0.5&#13;
&#13;
     -1.0&#13;
&#13;
     -1.5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                           Crop Scenario                                 Services Scenarios&#13;
&#13;
Source: Authorsâ&#128;&#153; calculations from IFPRI (2012) model simulation results&#13;
&#13;
37.     GDP growth being led by improvements in the crop sector will thus lead to the&#13;
greatest improvements in household income per capita for rural non-farm households and&#13;
the urban poor. Households that depend on agricultural wages do almost as well as in any&#13;
other scenario. When growth is due to livestock sector TFP improvements, households with&#13;
large farms tend to experience substantial improvements in income. In contrast, growth led&#13;
by productivity improvements in services will be harmful to incomes for rural households&#13;
that do not own farms. To put these into context, recall from Figure 2 that less than 2 percent&#13;
of the poor are from medium to large farm households, while rural non-farm households and&#13;
rural households involved in agriculture represent 39 percent and 42 percent of the poor,&#13;
respectively. Growth led by productivity in the crop and livestock sectors would thus be a&#13;
powerful mechanism of poverty reduction.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                         18&#13;
&amp;#12;                               Agriculture and Water Policy: Toward Sustainable Inclusive Growth&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
38.      IFPRI (2012) conducts additional simulations which suggest that investment&#13;
strategies that focus on non-agricultural sectors while ignoring the agriculture sector may&#13;
exacerbate income inequality. The study considers three additional simulations, comparing&#13;
the relative benefits of a development strategy that focuses on growth in non-agricultural&#13;
sector versus one that relies on all sectors, thereby estimating the additional effect of&#13;
agricultural investments. The non-agricultural sector investment scenario doubles the rate of&#13;
historical productivity in those sectors, while the all-sector scenario doubles productivity in&#13;
all sectors, including agriculture. In the non-agricultural investments scenario, household&#13;
per capita incomes increase by 9.3 percent on average, while medium to large farms and&#13;
urban non-poor have income increase of 11.7 percent and 10.3 percent, respectively. These&#13;
are in contrast to the income increases of 6.7 percent for agricultural wage laborers, 7.6&#13;
percent for non-farm poor and 8.6 percent for urban poorâ&#128;&#148;the types of households most&#13;
likely to be in poverty. In the scenario where investments are made in all sectors, household&#13;
incomes increase by 11.2 percent to 12.6 percent, and are much more uniform across&#13;
household types.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                             19&#13;
&amp;#12;                                             Agriculture and Water Policy: Toward Sustainable Inclusive Growth&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Agricultural Performance&#13;
39.    Broad based agricultural growth can directly improve agricultural incomes (especially&#13;
among the landless and smallholder farmers) by narrowing the wide yield gaps that currently&#13;
exist and by diversifying towards high-value agricultural products. The Planning&#13;
Commission (2009) estimates that average yields tend to be far below the Progressive&#13;
Farmer yields that represent the achievable upper bound (Figure 5). The yield gaps range&#13;
from 31 percent in the case of cotton to 73 percent in the case of sugarcane grown in Sindh.&#13;
These crops represent major shares of Pakistanâ&#128;&#153;s crop production ( Figure 6) and narrowing&#13;
the yield gap for major cereals (rice and wheat) and for high value crops (cotton and&#13;
sugarcane) would substantially boost agricultural GDP.&#13;
&#13;
   Figure 5         Average National Yields and Yield Gaps as Percentages of Progressive Farmer Yields&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    100%&#13;
      90%&#13;
                                      0.8 T/ha&#13;
      80%           2 T/ha                                                                                           1.7 T/ha&#13;
      70%                                                                     80 T/ha              4 T/ha&#13;
                                                          145 T/ha&#13;
      60%&#13;
      50%&#13;
      40%&#13;
                                       1.8 T/h&#13;
      30%          2.6 T/ha                                                                                           2.1 T/h&#13;
      20%                                                                      50 T/h             2.9 T/h&#13;
                                                           55 T/h&#13;
      10%&#13;
        0%&#13;
                    Wheat              Cotton            Sugarcane           Sugarcane             Maize                Rice&#13;
                                                          (Sindh)             (Punjab)&#13;
&#13;
                                                       National Average           Gap&#13;
&#13;
 Note: Numbers on bars indicate yield for crop for national average and for difference from Progressive Farmer yields in T/ha.&#13;
 Source: Planning Commission (2009)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Figure 6         Composition of Total Agricultural Production&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Note: Irr=Irrigated, Source: IFPRI (2012)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                 20&#13;
&amp;#12;                                         Agriculture and Water Policy: Toward Sustainable Inclusive Growth&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
40.     In light of Pakistanâ&#128;&#153;s high population growth, robust agricultural growth has to be&#13;
maintained to also generate sufficient rural employment. Table 2 shows how agricultural&#13;
GDP growth has decelerated, while overall GDP growth rate has accelerated since the 1990s.&#13;
At the same time, the GDP growth rates per worker have declined, severely in the case of&#13;
agricultural GDP. In the 1990s, the average annual agricultural GDP per worker was 2.67&#13;
percent, but had fallen to 0.28 percent in the 2000-08 period. There are thus pressures on&#13;
the rural labor market that are being exacerbated by the sluggish agricultural sector growth.&#13;
&#13;
       Table 2      Average Annual GDP Growth and Agricultural GDP Growth Rates per Worker (%)&#13;
&#13;
                                                         Mean                          Standard Deviation&#13;
                                               1990-99          2000-08            1990-99           2000-08&#13;
     Real GDP growth rate                        3.92             4.76               2.02              2.19&#13;
     Ag-GDP growth rate                          4.37             3.17               5.04              3.05&#13;
     GDP Growth Rate per worker                  1.24             1.09               2.94              1.50&#13;
     Ag-GDP growth rate per worker               2.67             0.28               7.71              5.19&#13;
    Source: Authorsâ&#128;&#153; estimates from World Bank (2011a)&#13;
&#13;
41.     Pakistanâ&#128;&#153;s value added in agriculture has almost doubled in real terms over the past&#13;
two decades, going from USD 11.6 billion (constant 2000 dollars) in 1990 to USD 23.1 billion&#13;
in 2009. It had sluggish growth in the 1990s and early part of the decade, but the growth rate&#13;
has picked up since 2004-05. In 1990s, the average annual growth rate of the value added&#13;
from agriculture was 4.37 percent per year, but fell to 3.17 percent per year in the 2000 to&#13;
2008 period. Given that the overall economy was growing in real terms by more than 4.76&#13;
percent a year on average over this latter period, the contribution of agricultural sector to the&#13;
overall economy has been declining. For example, in 1990s, value added from agriculture&#13;
accounted for about 26 percent of GDP. In the 2000s this share had dropped to 21.2 percent&#13;
(World Bank, 2011a).&#13;
&#13;
42.     Livestock and major crops8 like wheat, basmati and IRRI rice, cotton, and sugarcane,&#13;
account for more than 85 percent of agricultural GDP. In 2010, livestock contributed to 53&#13;
percent of agricultural GDP, and 11 percent of total GDP, while major crops contributed 33&#13;
percent to the sectoral GDP and 7 percent to the total GDP, as can be seen in Table 3 (IFPRI,&#13;
2012; World Bank, 2007). Since 2005-06, the shares of livestock and minor crops in total&#13;
agricultural output have grown, while the share of major crops has shrunk. At the same time,&#13;
the growth of real value added for major and minor crops, as well as livestock, has also&#13;
slowed down. In 1990s, the average annual growth rates of real value added for major and&#13;
minor crops were 2.7 and 4.8 percent per year, respectively. However, the growth rates&#13;
declined to 1.3 percent per year for minor crops, while staying about the same for major&#13;
crops. The growth rate of real value added in livestock decline, from 7.0 percent per year to&#13;
4.8 percent per year.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
8   Major crops include wheat, basmati and IRRI rice, gram, sugarcane, cotton, and tobacco (IFPRI, 2012).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                               21&#13;
&amp;#12;                                      Agriculture and Water Policy: Toward Sustainable Inclusive Growth&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Table 3       Composition of Agricultural GDP in Pakistan&#13;
&#13;
                                                    Share of Agricultural GDP           Real Value Added Growth&#13;
                        Share of Total GDP (%)&#13;
                                                               (%)                               Rate (%)&#13;
                          2005-06        2010        2005-06            2010            1990-00           2000-10&#13;
Major Crops                    7.6        7.0          35.2             32.8               2.7              2.8&#13;
Minor Crops                    2.7        2.4          12.3             11.1               4.8              1.3&#13;
Livestock                     10.7       11.4          49.6             53.2               7.0              4.8&#13;
Fishing                        0.3        0.4           1.3              1.8               2.7              5.2&#13;
Forestry                       0.3        0.3           1.6              1.2              -3.0             -6.8&#13;
Total Agriculture             21.6       21.5           100              100               4.4             3. 4&#13;
Source: IFPRI (2012) and World Bank (2007a) estimated from Pakistan Economic Survey FY 2006 and FY 2010&#13;
&#13;
43.     The relative sizes of the fishing and forestry subsectors have remained almost the&#13;
same over time, even though their real value growth rates have been declining. The growth&#13;
rate of real value added from forestry continued to shrink from -3.0 percent a year in the&#13;
1990-00 period to -6.8 percent per year in the 2000-10 period. The growth rate of value&#13;
added from fishing grew slightly, from an average of 2.7 percent per year in the 1990s to 5.2&#13;
percent per year in the past decade.&#13;
&#13;
44.     The production growth rates of several major crops have been declining over the past&#13;
decade. The production growth rates of rice, sugarcane, tobacco, and wheat were higher in&#13;
the 1990s than in the 2000s (Table 4). In case of sugarcane, the average annual growth has&#13;
become negative in the past decade. Rice is an exception, with a rising average annual&#13;
growth rate over the past two decades. This has been driven almost completely by&#13;
improvements in its yield. Rice yields have grown at a much faster rate in the 2000s relative&#13;
to the 1990s, while the harvested area has been shrinking.&#13;
&#13;
45.     The case of wheat, one of the most important crops for domestic consumption&#13;
illustrates some key features of current trends in crop production. Wheat production has&#13;
been increasing, but at a decreasing rate since 1990s. When the average annual yield growth&#13;
and area expansion rates for the crop are examined, it can be seen that the rate of area of&#13;
expansion has been increasing from 0.86 percent per year in the 1990s to 0.98 percent per&#13;
year in the past decade. The slowdown in production growth can thus be traced back to yield,&#13;
where the growth rate has slowed from 2.84 percent per year to 1.75 percent per year.&#13;
&#13;
   Table 4      Production Growth Rates of Select Major Crops&#13;
&#13;
                               Production                         Yield                               Area&#13;
                                   Avg.    Avg.                    Avg.          Avg.                  Avg.         Avg.&#13;
                     2010        Growth Growth         2010      Growth        Growth      2010      Growth       Growth&#13;
                     Value        Rate,   Rate,       Value       Rate,         Rate,      Value      Rate,        Rate,&#13;
                     (â&#128;&#152;000        1990-   2000-      (tonnes      1990-         2000-      (â&#128;&#152;000      1990-        2000-&#13;
                    tonnes)       2000    2010         /ha)       2000          2010        ha)       2000         2010&#13;
                                   (%)     (%)                     (%)           (%)                   (%)          (%)&#13;
 Maize              3,341.0        3.18    7.44        3.6         2.28          7.38      939.0       0.84        -0.12&#13;
 Rice               7,235.0        4.26    0.55        3.1         2.81          0.19     2,365.0      1.21        -0.11&#13;
 Sugarcane          49,372.9       2.66   -0.13        52.4        0.96          0.95      942.8       1.50        -1.21&#13;
 Tobacco             119.3         4.12    1.44        2.1         1.09          1.11       55.8       2.92         0.22&#13;
 Wheat              23,310.8       3.76    2.85        2.6         2.84          1.75     9,131.6      0.86         0.98&#13;
Source: Estimates from FAOSTAT data&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                    22&#13;
&amp;#12;                                     Agriculture and Water Policy: Toward Sustainable Inclusive Growth&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
46.     Pakistanâ&#128;&#153;s agricultural output growth rate has been decelerating, and is reflected in&#13;
its declining TFP growth rate. Pakistanâ&#128;&#153;s agriculture did exceptionally well in the 1980s with&#13;
an average annual output growth rate of 4.8 percent, making it a global leader in agricultural&#13;
growth (Figure 7). However, the agricultural output growth rate has shrunk to a more&#13;
modest 3.34 percent in the past decade. The decline in growth is driven by more complex&#13;
changes in input use and TFP.&#13;
&#13;
47.    Decomposition of growth and relative shares of inputs and TFP provide insight into&#13;
the sources of growth. The sources of growth have shifted significantly. In the 1980s, TFP&#13;
growth was the prime driver, while in the 1990s and 2000s, TFP has progressively slowed&#13;
down and growth has been increasingly driven by input use (fertilizer, labor, livestock and&#13;
machinery) and irrigation.&#13;
&#13;
48.    In earlier decades, Pakistanâ&#128;&#153;s TFP growth was responsible for substantial shares of&#13;
the output growth (Figure 8). For example, in the 1960s, 1980s, and 1990s TFP accounted&#13;
for 44 percent, 67 percent, and 37 percent, respectively, of the output growth. In contrast,&#13;
TFP accounts for less than a fifth of the growth.9 Relative to other countries, agricultural TFP&#13;
growth since the 1990s has been very slow (Figure 9).&#13;
&#13;
    Figure 7      Average Annual Agricultural Output Growth Rate in Pakistan, 1961-2009 (%)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     6.00&#13;
&#13;
     5.00&#13;
&#13;
     4.00&#13;
&#13;
     3.00&#13;
&#13;
     2.00&#13;
&#13;
     1.00&#13;
&#13;
     0.00&#13;
                  1961-70           1971-80            1981-90             1991-00            2001-09&#13;
    -1.00&#13;
&#13;
                             Bangladesh       India    Pakistan     Sri Lanka     China&#13;
&#13;
Source: Fuglie (2012)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
9It is important to note that growth in agricultural TFP was higher in Pakistan than China till the mid-1990s, and&#13;
grew at almost the same pace as Brazilâ&#128;&#148;two of the outstanding long-term performers globally. Since the mid-&#13;
1990s, however, TFP for Pakistan has been flat while the comparators (including the high performing East Asia&#13;
countries like Thailand, Vietnam and Indonesia) have performed markedly better.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                               23&#13;
&amp;#12;                                      Agriculture and Water Policy: Toward Sustainable Inclusive Growth&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   Table 5       Average Annual Output, Input and TFP Growth Rates (%) for Agriculture in Pakistan&#13;
&#13;
                            Output Growth                    Input Growth                   TFP Growth&#13;
                        2001-05       2006-09           2001-05        2006-09         2001-05      2006-09&#13;
  Bangladesh              3.6           4.8               1.6            0.5             1.9           4.2&#13;
  India                   2.2           3.5               1.1            1.2             1.1           2.4&#13;
  Pakistan                2.8           3.3               2.6            2.2             0.2           1.1&#13;
  Sri Lanka               1.5           2.8               0.9            1.1             0.6           1.8&#13;
  China                   3.2           3.5               0.8            0.5             2.4           3.0&#13;
  Indonesia               4.7           4.7               1.3            1.5             3.4           3.2&#13;
  Thailand                2.8           2.8               0.5            0.4             2.3           2.4&#13;
Source: Fuglie (2012)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Figure 8       Decomposition of Output Growth in Agricultural Sector by Land, Input Intensity &amp; TFP%&#13;
&#13;
      6&#13;
&#13;
      5&#13;
&#13;
      4&#13;
&#13;
      3&#13;
&#13;
      2&#13;
&#13;
      1&#13;
&#13;
      0&#13;
               1961-1970            1971-1980           1981-1990          1991-2000         2001-2009&#13;
     -1&#13;
                                        Irrig   New land      Input/Area   TFP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Note: Land Quality Adjusted&#13;
  Source: Fuglie (2012)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Figure 9       Average Annual TFP Growth Rates for Agriculture in Pakistan, 1961-2009&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   5.00&#13;
&#13;
   4.00&#13;
&#13;
   3.00&#13;
&#13;
   2.00&#13;
&#13;
   1.00&#13;
&#13;
   0.00&#13;
                 1961-70              1971-80              1981-90               1991-00         2001-09&#13;
  -1.00&#13;
&#13;
  -2.00&#13;
&#13;
                                Bangladesh      India      Pakistan    Sri Lanka     China&#13;
&#13;
  Note: Land Quality Adjusted&#13;
  Source: Fuglie (2012)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                              24&#13;
&amp;#12;                                       Agriculture and Water Policy: Toward Sustainable Inclusive Growth&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
49.     Even though growth in non-land inputs in agriculture has been rising, the changes in&#13;
use vary by specific input. Figure 10 reveals that fertilizer, livestock, and machinery use, all&#13;
grew faster in the past decade than they did in the 1990s. This is concurrent with lower use of&#13;
labor and land, since less land and labor are needed due to the adoption of labor augmenting&#13;
technologies (e.g. mechanization and draft animals) and fertilizers which can enhance yields&#13;
substantially when used under the right conditions, like sufficient irrigation (FAO, 2012).&#13;
Total cropped area grew at an average annual rate of 0.72 percent per year in the 1991-2000&#13;
period with this growth rate rising to 0.83 percent per year in the 2001-2009 period10. This&#13;
acceleration in the cropped area expansion rate is reflected in the greater use of land as an&#13;
input in the two time periods.&#13;
&#13;
     Figure 10      Average Annual Growth Rates of Inputs in the Agricultural Sector&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       14.00&#13;
       12.00&#13;
       10.00&#13;
        8.00&#13;
        6.00&#13;
        4.00&#13;
        2.00&#13;
        0.00&#13;
                     Labor       Irrigation    New Land       Livestock     Machinery       Fertilizer&#13;
&#13;
                                               1991-2000     2001-09&#13;
&#13;
     Source: Fuglie (2012)&#13;
&#13;
50.     A critical factor in improving the yields of these crops is water availability and the&#13;
performance of the irrigation system. About 95 percent of Pakistanâ&#128;&#153;s arable land is currently&#13;
irrigated, up from 64 percent in 1960 and 72 percent in 1980, following decades of rapid&#13;
expansion of irrigation. Given the arid/semi-arid conditions, access to water is absolutely&#13;
essential to agricultural production. Irrigation expansion has thus been central to improving&#13;
yields, as illustrated by Figure 11, which describes how the area equipped for irrigation has&#13;
steadily grown, as a share of cropland and as a share of harvested area. What can be seen is&#13;
that the irrigated area-cropland ratio was previously lower than the irrigated area-harvested&#13;
area ratio. Over time, these two ratios have converged, highlighting the growing importance&#13;
of irrigation in successful harvests. However, supply constraints and inefficiencies within the&#13;
irrigation system threaten the continuing contributions of irrigation to crop production, with&#13;
the threats expected to increase under climate change. Between 1990 and 2009, there was&#13;
virtually no growth in harvested area or cropland11.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
10Authorsâ&#128;&#153; estimates from FAOSTAT cropped area data.&#13;
11Based on Fuglie (2012) data, the average annual growth rate was 0.7 percent in cropland, and 0.3 percent in&#13;
harvested area.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                          25&#13;
&amp;#12;                                               Agriculture and Water Policy: Toward Sustainable Inclusive Growth&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Figure 11        Irrigated Area as a Share of Cropland and Harvested Area&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   1.00&#13;
&#13;
   0.90&#13;
&#13;
   0.80&#13;
&#13;
   0.70&#13;
&#13;
   0.60&#13;
&#13;
   0.50&#13;
&#13;
   0.40&#13;
&#13;
   0.30&#13;
                                1993&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                             2004&#13;
           1990&#13;
&#13;
                  1991&#13;
&#13;
                         1992&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       1994&#13;
&#13;
                                              1995&#13;
&#13;
                                                     1996&#13;
&#13;
                                                            1997&#13;
&#13;
                                                                   1998&#13;
&#13;
                                                                          1999&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                 2000&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                        2001&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                               2002&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                      2003&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                    2005&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                           2006&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                  2007&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                         2008&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                2009&#13;
                  Pakistan - Irrigated Area/Cropland                                South Asia - Irrigated Area /Cropland&#13;
                  Pakistan - Irrigated Area/Harvested Area                          South Asia - Irrigated Area /Harvested Area&#13;
&#13;
 Note: Irrigated area is the area equipped for irrigation; area harvested is the total area harvested for all crops, both&#13;
 temporary and permanent; cropland is arable land and land in permanent crops; the values for South Asia are&#13;
 determined by aggregating data for Afghanistan, Bangladesh, Bhutan, India, Nepal, Pakistan, and Sri Lanka.&#13;
 Source: Authorsâ&#128;&#153; estimates from Fuglie (2012)&#13;
&#13;
51.     The case of wheat in Punjab can illustrate some of the key factors, such as irrigation&#13;
use, affecting yield growth. Punjab is responsible for almost 63 percent of Pakistanâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
agricultural output (IPP, 2012). Murgai et al. (2001) and Ali and Byerlee (2002) examine the&#13;
TFP in crop agriculture from 1966 to 1994 in Punjab, and find that overall output growth in&#13;
the sector was over 3 percent annually for nearly three decades, with TFP growth of 1.26&#13;
percent per year (Table 6). However, land productivity growth rates had declined since the&#13;
Green Revolution while the labor productivity growth rate had risen due to the adoption of&#13;
labor augmenting technologies (e.g. tractors).&#13;
&#13;
52.     There is substantial variation in productivity growth by wheat production system&#13;
with much of the TFP declines attributed to resource degradation. Ali and Byerlee (2002)&#13;
also found that TFP growth had been strong in wheat-cotton and wheat-mung bean&#13;
production systems, and negative in wheat-rice system. The study suggests that the negative&#13;
TFP growth in wheat-rice system was due to degradation in soil and water quality&#13;
throughout the province and there is evidence that some of this depletion is related to the&#13;
use of inputs considered to be important components of modern high-productivity&#13;
agricultural practices. On average, this deterioration in resource quality lowered annual&#13;
productivity growth by 0.53 percent in the province. Thus TFP growth could have been much&#13;
higher in the absence of resource degradation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                       26&#13;
&amp;#12;                                     Agriculture and Water Policy: Toward Sustainable Inclusive Growth&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   Table 6      Average Annual Growth Rates in Factor Productivities in Punjab, 1966-1994 (%)&#13;
&#13;
  Production                                                                       Total Factor Productivity for&#13;
                   Time Period              Partial Factor Productivity&#13;
    System                                                                               Crop Sub-Sector&#13;
                                        Water          Land           Labor       Output      Input        TFP&#13;
                    1966-1994            -1.9          2.09            n.a.        2.29        1.42        0.87&#13;
                      Green&#13;
                                        -3.08           2.54          -5.09         3.35        4.46      1.12&#13;
                    Revolution&#13;
   Wheat-&#13;
                  Intensification&#13;
   Mixed                                 -1.5           3.51          1.67          2.25        0.75       1.5&#13;
                      Period&#13;
                    Post-Green&#13;
                                         -0.9           0.02          2.66          1.87        1.4       0.46&#13;
                    Revolution&#13;
                    1966-1994           -3.03           0.89          1.03          1.79        2.3        -0.5&#13;
                      Green&#13;
                                        -7.31           0.76          -2.11         3.44        5.88      -2.43&#13;
                    Revolution&#13;
  Wheat-Rice      Intensification&#13;
                                        -3.65           0.88           0.8          1.24        1.84       -0.6&#13;
                      Period&#13;
                    Post-Green&#13;
                                         0.14           1.85          3.01          2.04        1.17      0.88&#13;
                    Revolution&#13;
                    1966-1994           -0.25           2.98          3.44          3.65        2.08      1.57&#13;
                      Green&#13;
                                        -4.99           3.18          -1.81         3.66        3.96       -0.3&#13;
                    Revolution&#13;
   Wheat-&#13;
                  Intensification&#13;
   Cotton                                0.1            2.32          3.48          3.55        1.77      1.79&#13;
                      Period&#13;
                    Post-Green&#13;
                                         1.96           2.9            4.3          2.7         0.92      1.77&#13;
                    Revolution&#13;
                    1966-1994           -3.49           1.89          3.08          3.68        2.36      1.32&#13;
                      Green&#13;
                                        -7.85           4.36          0.95          6.79        4.55      2.24&#13;
                    Revolution&#13;
   Wheat-&#13;
                  Intensification&#13;
  Mungbean                              -2.81          -1.26           0.7          1.31        2.02       -0.7&#13;
                      Period&#13;
                    Post-Green&#13;
                                        -0.48           3.68           7.7          4.8         1.56      3.24&#13;
                    Revolution&#13;
                    1966-1994           -1.41           2.43          2.51          3.23        1.97      1.26&#13;
                      Green&#13;
                                        -5.14           2.75          -2.85          4          4.49      -0.49&#13;
                    Revolution&#13;
      All         Intensification&#13;
                                        -1.29           2.22          2.33          2.77        1.5       1.27&#13;
                      Period&#13;
                    Post-Green&#13;
                                         0.61           1.96          4.14          2.85        1.25       1.6&#13;
                    Revolution&#13;
 Note: Green Revolution 1966-1974; Intensification Period 1975-1984; Post-Green Revolution 1985-1994&#13;
 Source: Adapted from Ali and Byerlee (2002)&#13;
&#13;
53.      Input intensities jumped substantially during and after the Green Revolution, when&#13;
modern varieties were adopted (Ali and Byerlee, 2002; Murgai et al. 2001). For example,&#13;
fertilizer use jumped from an average of 14.1 kg/ha during the Green Revolution to an&#13;
average of 86.1 kg/ha in the post-Green Revolution period. Pesticide use also increased&#13;
rapidly, especially for cotton in the post-Green Revolution period. Water supply and&#13;
availability greatly improved through investment (largely private) in tube wells, especially&#13;
during the Green Revolution and intensification periods. However, water productivity is&#13;
negative because of inefficient use of irrigation water, partially due to subsidies on canal&#13;
water prices, and fixed electricity rates on tube wells (Farquee, 1995).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                  27&#13;
&amp;#12;                                     Agriculture and Water Policy: Toward Sustainable Inclusive Growth&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
54.     While labor productivity generally grew in the 1966-94 period, it shrank during the&#13;
Green Revolution (1966-74). The technologies being adopted increased average labor use for&#13;
crops from 85 person-days/ha in the Green Revolution period to 99 person-days/ha in the&#13;
intensification period (Ali and Byerlee, 2003; Murgai et al., 2001). Eventually, the additional&#13;
labor demand together with non-farm demands, raised wages and induced mechanization,&#13;
which then led to a decline in labor use and a rapid improvement in labor productivity.&#13;
&#13;
55.     There are a range of other factors that have also contributed to the sluggish TFP&#13;
growth rate for wheat in Punjab. These include severe droughts and reduced effectiveness of&#13;
agricultural research and extension. Increasingly frequent power disruptions are also major&#13;
constraints to Punjabâ&#128;&#153;s agricultural production (IPP, 2012).&#13;
&#13;
56.    Climate change is anticipated to put additional stress on agricultural production, with&#13;
the impacts varying by region and crop. Yu et al. (2012) consider a range of climate change&#13;
scenarios12 to estimate impacts on the economy. Production impacts in the crop sub-sector&#13;
vary by crop and region. Crop production declines are greatest in Sindh, where it declines by&#13;
10 percent on average. In the most extreme case, Sindhâ&#128;&#153;s crop production shrinks by 36&#13;
percent. In contrast, Punjabâ&#128;&#153;s crop production shrinks by only 5 percent in the worst case&#13;
scenario. In terms of crops being affected, the IRRI rice and sugarcane production&#13;
experience the largest declines, with about 6 percent decline on average. If the monthly&#13;
hydrograph shifts forward by a monthâ&#128;&#148;April inflows becoming March inflowsâ&#128;&#148;then the&#13;
negative impacts are exacerbated.&#13;
&#13;
57.     Most of the negative real income effects of climate change in Punjab and Sindh are&#13;
expected to be on households outside of the agriculture sector, since those households will be&#13;
facing higher food prices without any corresponding increase in income that agricultural&#13;
households would experiences. GDP, agriculture GDP and household income are estimated&#13;
to decrease by 1.1 percent, 5.1 percent, and 2 percent respectively. GDP, agriculture GDP and&#13;
household income are estimated to decrease by 2.7 percent, 12 percent, and 5.3 percent,&#13;
respectively in the most extreme climate future. Percent declines in agricultural production&#13;
are smaller than the percent increases in prices, leading to a positive change in farm income.&#13;
Households that do not depend on farm-income as their primary source of income, however,&#13;
will have to pay more for food, and will thus see their real incomes decline.&#13;
&#13;
58.     Sufficiently high crop yield improvements can be the best way to adapt to climate&#13;
change. Yu et al. (2012) estimate13 that if crop yields were to improve by 20 percent, then&#13;
GDP, agricultural GDP, and household incomes would rise by 2.6 percent, 11.6 percent, and&#13;
3.4 percent, respectively, more than compensating for the effects of climate change.&#13;
Furthermore, the 20 percent yield improvement is a realistic goal, given that wheat and rice&#13;
yields improved by 1-2 percent per year over the 1989-99 period. Even after a 20 percent&#13;
improvement in wheat and rice yields, there would still be a substantial yield gap between&#13;
the average achieved yield and what is currently achievable in the best case scenario (as&#13;
illustrated by Figure 5).&#13;
&#13;
12 The study considered 70 different possible climate scenarios which were characterized by river inflows varying&#13;
from 10 percent to 90 percent exceedance probability and temperature changes ranging from 1Â°C to 4.5Â°C.&#13;
13 Yu et al. (2012) use the CGE economic simulation model of IFPRI (2012), described earlier, to examine the&#13;
&#13;
effects of three different counterfactual adaptation policiesâ&#128;&#148;improving crop yields, improving the efficiency of&#13;
the irrigation system, and building new dams.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                              28&#13;
&amp;#12;                                     Agriculture and Water Policy: Toward Sustainable Inclusive Growth&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Key Issues and Challenges&#13;
59.     Spurring inclusive growth in the agriculture sector will thus require improvements in&#13;
productivity, and this section discusses some of the major policy and technical barriers to the&#13;
necessary improvements. It starts with a description of some of the areas of improvement in&#13;
agricultural research, development, and extension. It then moves on to a discussion of the&#13;
institutional and technical inefficiencies of the water management and irrigation system.&#13;
Finally, it reviews the range of policies that distort agricultural output and input markets,&#13;
and discourage diversification.&#13;
&#13;
Technology&#13;
&#13;
60.     As discussed earlier, there is substantial room for improvement in Pakistanâ&#128;&#153;s crop&#13;
yields. The national average yields of major crops like wheat and rice are currently only&#13;
about 55 percent of Progressive Farmer yields, which represent the highest achievable yields&#13;
in Pakistan (Figure 5). These yield gaps are even greater for some commercial crops like&#13;
sugarcane in Sindh. Despite the large potential for improvement, yield growth has been&#13;
steadily declining over the years. For example, rice yields grew at an average annual rate of&#13;
5.24 percent in the 1960s and 3.16 percent in the 1990s, whereas they have only been&#13;
growing at 1.68 percent per year this past decade14. A similar pattern can be seen in the case&#13;
of wheat, which had average annual yield growth of 2.92 percent in the 1960s and 1.99&#13;
percent in the 1990s. This growth rate is now only 1.1 percent per year.&#13;
&#13;
61.     Much of the high historical growth in yields can be attributed to major scientific&#13;
breakthroughs in technology, as during the Green Revolution, resulting from investments in&#13;
agricultural research undertaken by the national agricultural research system. Agricultural&#13;
R&amp;D in Pakistan has historically been led by the public sector, and has proven to be a good&#13;
investment. But this research has also been biased towards technologies focused on the use&#13;
of modern inputs, while ignoring public goods such as integrated crop management,&#13;
sustainable production systems, efficient input use, and the balancing of external input use&#13;
and internal nutrient sources. About half of the public research expenditure is on crops,&#13;
followed by a quarter on natural resources, about 14 percent on livestock and fisheries, and&#13;
about 9 percent on social sciences (World Bank, 2011d).&#13;
&#13;
62.     The historical review of Ahmad and Nagy (2001) shows Pakistanâ&#128;&#153;s public agricultural&#13;
research system has been successfulâ&#128;&#148;estimated internal rates of return from investments in&#13;
agricultural research have ranged from 57 percent to 65 percent, with most of the returns&#13;
coming from Green Revolution research. Following a period of nationalization of large and&#13;
medium sized private agribusiness firms in the mid-1970s, there was a slow process of&#13;
denationalization and deregulation of these entities. Investment in private agricultural&#13;
research and development was thus severely curtailed for a long time, with only recent&#13;
outreach to the private sector through programs like the Science and Technology for&#13;
Development program.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
14Authorsâ&#128;&#153;   estimates using FAOSTAT data.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                   29&#13;
&amp;#12;                                              Agriculture and Water Policy: Toward Sustainable Inclusive Growth&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
63.      However, there are severe technical capacity constraints to the current agricultural&#13;
research system. According to ASTI data, public investment in agricultural research has been&#13;
on the decline. It is currently about 0.21 percent of agricultural GDP and ranks at the bottom&#13;
of agricultural R&amp;D spending as a share of agricultural GDP in the region (Figure 12). The&#13;
Planning Commission (2009) notes that persistent funding constraints may have&#13;
contributed to limited technology advancements even in major cultivars. Only 15 percent of&#13;
agricultural research staff trained holds PhDs, which is low relative to the educational&#13;
attainment of researchers in the rest of South Asia (Beintema et al. 2007). Qualified research&#13;
staff is discouraged from public research agencies due to institutional disincentives such as&#13;
limited promotion opportunities and low salaries.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Figure 12        Agricultural R&amp;D Spending as a Share of Agricultural GDP in South Asia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        0.6&#13;
&#13;
       0.55&#13;
&#13;
        0.5&#13;
&#13;
       0.45&#13;
&#13;
        0.4&#13;
&#13;
       0.35&#13;
&#13;
        0.3&#13;
&#13;
       0.25&#13;
&#13;
        0.2&#13;
&#13;
       0.15&#13;
&#13;
        0.1&#13;
                                                                                        2005&#13;
               1996&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                        1997&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                1998&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       1999&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 2000&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                            2001&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                   2002&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                          2003&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                 2004&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                               2006&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                         2007&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                  2008&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                         2009&#13;
                               Bangladesh               India         Nepal        Pakistan           Sri Lanka&#13;
&#13;
Source: ASTI (2012)&#13;
&#13;
64.      The technical capacity constraints are compounded by inefficiencies generated by the&#13;
institutional environment. Beintema et al. (2007) identified a total of 111 agencies involved in&#13;
agricultural R&amp;D, employing more than 3,600 researchers and spending nearly Rs. 2.4&#13;
billion (constant 2000 Rupees). Of these, 37 were federal agencies, 98 were provincial&#13;
agencies, and 13 were private sector entities. The Pakistan Agricultural Research Council&#13;
(PARC) coordinates the activities of a large network of public national and provincial&#13;
agricultural research bodies, institutes and experimental stations. PARC does not conduct&#13;
agricultural research itself, though the National Agricultural Research Center (NARC) is&#13;
under its administration. With the passing of the 18th Amendment to the Constitution15 in&#13;
2010, the public agricultural system has been devolving from the federal to the provincial&#13;
level, creating new opportunities for re-energized public agricultural research. By moving the&#13;
research agenda to the provincial and local levels, research can have a greater focus on the&#13;
needs of local farmers and environmental conditions.&#13;
&#13;
15   The 18th Amendment switched the government from a semi-presidential system to a parliamentary republic.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                30&#13;
&amp;#12;                                   Agriculture and Water Policy: Toward Sustainable Inclusive Growth&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
65.     Diversification is also influenced by changes in technology affecting the relative&#13;
profitability and risk, among other factors16 (Pingali and Rosegrant, 1995). The analysis of&#13;
diversification in India from Joshi et al. (2003) illustrates these factors to be in play. Aside&#13;
from the essential improvements in markets and roads, the study found that there were&#13;
complex interactions between technological improvements and technology absorption of&#13;
different commodities. For example, they found that greater adoption of technology for&#13;
cereals was related to less diversification in favor of high value commodities. Similarly,&#13;
diversification towards horticulture and livestock production, relatively more profitable&#13;
products than cereals, was greater in areas that benefited less from the Green Revolution,&#13;
such as rain-fed areas. These rain-fed areas were found to diversify into non-cereals away&#13;
from cereals, and were found to be growing faster than regions specializing in cereals. This&#13;
growth also had distributional implications since high-value commodities were grown more&#13;
by small holder farms.&#13;
&#13;
66.    Agricultural extension services need to be developed in parallel to R&amp;D for greater&#13;
uptake of relevant information to target groups. Extension services have suffered from weak&#13;
linkages to agricultural research institutions, reflected in low technical capacity of the&#13;
services (World Bank, 2011d). Administrative devolution has further weakened these&#13;
services, with greater budgetary pressures and unclear linkages to the bureaucracy.&#13;
&#13;
67.     The focus of extension services needs to expand even as it improves targeting.&#13;
Historically, the extension services have focused on disseminating technology to farmers.&#13;
However, there is a range of additional information that may be helpful to the farmer, such&#13;
as advice on quality standards in production and marketing, which is currently not being&#13;
provided. There is also a disproportionate uptake of extension services by larger farms&#13;
relative to small and medium sized farms. Focusing on the case of sugarcane technologies,&#13;
Abbas et al. (2003) found that information on varieties was taken up by 73 percent of large&#13;
farms, relative to 64 percent of small farms. This discrepancy is even greater when advice on&#13;
sowing methods and fertilizer application were considered. 73 percent of large farms adopted&#13;
sowing methods from extension services, compared to about 40 percent of small and&#13;
medium sized farms. Given that increasing small holder productivity is critical to enhancing&#13;
agricultural production, agricultural extension will need to expand on improving adoption&#13;
among this group.&#13;
&#13;
Inefficient Water Use and Water Resource Management&#13;
&#13;
68.     Pakistanâ&#128;&#153;s irrigated land as a proportion of cropland is the highest in South Asia, with&#13;
about 95 percent of arable land being equipped for irrigation (Figure 13). Pakistan has been&#13;
able to accelerate the rate of expansion of areas under irrigation, from an average annual rate&#13;
of 1.24 percent in the 1960s to 1.44 percent in the 2000s (Figure 14). Pakistan has an&#13;
irrigation potential of 21.3 million ha of land, of which 19.3 million ha is equipped for&#13;
irrigation: 35.9 percent is for surface water, 21.4 percent for groundwater, and 41.3 percent&#13;
for a mix of surface and groundwater sources (FAO, 2010). The Indus Basin Irrigation&#13;
System (IBIS) supports this irrigation system, with about 106 million-acre-feet (MAF) of&#13;
water flows diverted from the river system to canals.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
16These other factors include changes per capita income and urbanization, improvements in infrastructure, and&#13;
changes in factor endowments&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                          31&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                          Agriculture and Water Policy: Toward Sustainable Inclusive Growth&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Figure 13            Ratio of the Area Equipped for Irrigation to Cropland Area&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 1.00&#13;
 0.90&#13;
 0.80&#13;
 0.70&#13;
 0.60&#13;
 0.50&#13;
 0.40&#13;
 0.30&#13;
 0.20&#13;
 0.10&#13;
 0.00&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                      1983&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                           1989&#13;
        1961&#13;
               1963&#13;
                      1965&#13;
                             1967&#13;
                                    1969&#13;
                                           1971&#13;
                                                   1973&#13;
                                                          1975&#13;
                                                                 1977&#13;
                                                                        1979&#13;
                                                                               1981&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                             1985&#13;
                                                                                                    1987&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                  1991&#13;
                                                                                                                         1993&#13;
                                                                                                                                1995&#13;
                                                                                                                                       1997&#13;
                                                                                                                                              1999&#13;
                                                                                                                                                     2001&#13;
                                                                                                                                                            2003&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                   2005&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                          2007&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                 2009&#13;
                                                  Bangladesh                   India                Pakistan                    South Asia&#13;
&#13;
Note: Cropland is the FAO arable land and land in permanent crops; the values for South Asia are determined by&#13;
aggregating data for Afghanistan, Bangladesh, Bhutan, India, Nepal, Pakistan, and Sri Lanka.&#13;
Source: Authorsâ&#128;&#153; estimates from Fuglie (2012)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Figure 14           Average Annual Growth Rates of Irrigated Area and Cropland&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Note: Cropland is the FAO arable land and land in permanent crops; the values for South Asia are determined by&#13;
aggregating data for Afghanistan, Bangladesh, Bhutan, India, Nepal, Pakistan, and Sri Lanka.&#13;
Source: Authorsâ&#128;&#153; estimates from Fuglie (2012)&#13;
&#13;
69.     Farmersâ&#128;&#153; access to water however is less than it could be due to major limitations of&#13;
the water allocation system. At the farm level, access to canal water is determined by physical&#13;
location along the canal and through the warabandi water allocation system of&#13;
administratively set rotations. Access to canal water then becomes contingent on access to&#13;
land, and the location of that land. There might not be enough water by the time it gets to&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                   32&#13;
&amp;#12;                               Agriculture and Water Policy: Toward Sustainable Inclusive Growth&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
land at the tail end of distributaries or watercourses, especially if upstream farmers illegally&#13;
access the water (Yu et al., 2012).&#13;
&#13;
70.     Another critical challenge to the irrigation system under the current water&#13;
management system is that it is financially unsustainable. The canal irrigation management&#13;
system recovers only a quarter of its annual operating and maintenance costs, with the&#13;
shortfall expected to increase with rising costs and stagnant Abiana (water charges per acre&#13;
of crops irrigated) (Planning Commission, 2012). The collection rate of assessed Abiana is&#13;
also lowâ&#128;&#148;at only 60 percent of assessed values. The overall budget gap is about Rs. 5.4&#13;
billion annually, with the system thus being subsidized by the federal government.&#13;
&#13;
71.    The current Abiana for different crops might also be distorting farmer decisions. The&#13;
national average Abiana per acre over the 2000-09 period for different crops were between&#13;
Rs. 126 and 214 for cotton, Rs. 185 and 428 for sugarcane, Rs. 125 and 210 for rice, Rs. 69 to&#13;
136 for maize, and Rs. 75 to 131 for wheat, respectively. Comparing the Abiana for rice and&#13;
cottonâ&#128;&#148;two major export cropsâ&#128;&#148;it can be seen that their irrigation charges per acre are&#13;
about the same, even though rice requires 60 percent more water than cotton. These charges&#13;
may not reflect relative profitability of the two crops, leading to a possible overproduction of&#13;
rice.&#13;
&#13;
72.     Availability of groundwater has an even higher impact on yields than the availability&#13;
of canal water, but less than 10 percent of cultivating households owned tube wells in 2001-&#13;
02. Groundwater markets significantly improve access for small farmers, landless tenants&#13;
and younger households who often lack the resources (or land and water rights) to install&#13;
their own tube well (World Bank, 2007). However, water purchasers do not have full access&#13;
rights to the water, and in times of energy or water scarcity can be denied access. Access to&#13;
groundwater also depends on the distance to the tube well, in addition to the existence and&#13;
efficiency of the channels to distribute that water.&#13;
&#13;
73.     Recognizing the importance of a robust and efficient water management system, the&#13;
Government of Pakistan implemented reforms in the 1990s. As reviewed in World Bank&#13;
(2011b), these reforms restructured the Public Irrigation Departments (PIDs) to Provincial&#13;
Irrigation and Drainage Authorities (PIDAs); Area Water Boards (AWBs) to manage main&#13;
and branch canals; and Farmersâ&#128;&#153; Organizations (FOs) and Water User Associations (WUAs)&#13;
to manage distributor and minor canals. The goal of these reforms was to enhance water use&#13;
efficiency, streamline the water resources management, and facilitate participation by users.&#13;
&#13;
74.     These reforms however have not been completely successful, due to problems at both&#13;
the provincial and local levels. At the provincial level, the devolution of autonomy from the&#13;
PIDs is incomplete. World Bank (2011b) illustrates by describing the case of Punjabâ&#128;&#153;s PID&#13;
and PIDA, where the Secretary of the PID is also the Managing Director of the PIDA.&#13;
Another example is from Sindh, where even though the posts of PIDâ&#128;&#153;s Secretary and PIDAâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
Managing Director are held by different people, the latter has a direct reporting relationship&#13;
to the former.&#13;
&#13;
75.     At the local level, the FOs either do not have the resources or the capacity to fulfill&#13;
their roles. As noted by World Bank (2011b), FOs have no input into the Abiana setting&#13;
process, even though they might be responsible for collecting the charges. FOs also vary&#13;
widely in regard to their role as charge collectors, since this is a determination made by&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                             33&#13;
&amp;#12;                                        Agriculture and Water Policy: Toward Sustainable Inclusive Growth&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
management, which in turn, they may or may not have any voice in. The lack of clarity in the&#13;
role of FOs and their widely varying mandate across local governments has contributed to&#13;
inefficiencies in Abiana collection that are damaging the financial sustainability of the&#13;
system.&#13;
&#13;
76.     The Planning Commission (2012) recognizes these challenges, and has proposed a&#13;
series of recommendations. These recommendations include the revision of Abiana rates to&#13;
be economically reasonable (i.e. reflecting the profitability of irrigated crops), reviewing the&#13;
Abiana collection mechanisms, improving service provision, and water trading at the Indus&#13;
River System Authority (IRSA) level, inter alia. The most important intervention however&#13;
would be institutional reform of the entire management system to a) complete devolution of&#13;
authority to the relevant scale; b) clarify the roles and mandates of each authority; c) provide&#13;
sufficient resources and capacity building to allow devolved authorities to fulfill their&#13;
mandates. It would be difficult and potentially detrimental to implement specific reforms,&#13;
such as revision of Abiana or introducing water trading, in current dysfunctional&#13;
institutional environment. Institutional clarity and ownership of reforms are thus key&#13;
prerequisites to any other intervention.&#13;
&#13;
77.     The irrigation system is highly inefficient as is demonstrated by substantial seepage&#13;
losses which occur in almost every component of the delivery system. Only 41 MAF of&#13;
irrigation water reach crops out of the 106 MAF that is in the system, equivalent to about 61&#13;
percent of the initial water delivered at the head17 (Table 7). 25 MAF and 17 MAF are lost in&#13;
watercourses and in fields, which are the most vulnerable components of the irrigation&#13;
system. The overall efficiency of the system is about 35 percent, and improving the canal&#13;
systemâ&#128;&#153;s efficiency from 35 percent to 50 percent could boost growth substantially. Yu et al.&#13;
(2012) estimated that GDP and GDP from the agriculture sector would decline by 1.1 percent&#13;
and 5.1 percent on average, under climate change. An improvement to the canal systemâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
efficiency that saved just an additional 12 MAF would improve GDP by 0.94 percent and&#13;
agricultural GDP by 4.22 percent, on average, even under climate change.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      Table 7     Seepage Losses in Irrigation System&#13;
&#13;
             Location                 Delivery at Head                                    Losses&#13;
                                            MAF                        Percentage*                         MAF&#13;
     Main and branch canals                 106                             15                              16&#13;
     Distributaries and Minors               90                             8                               7&#13;
     Watercourses                            83                             30                              25&#13;
     Fields                                  58                             30                              17&#13;
     Crop Use                                41&#13;
     Total                                                                 61**                             65&#13;
Note: *Percentage loss estimates are based on losses in MAF for that location and the delivery delivered at location head;&#13;
**Total percentage loss = 100*(65/106)&#13;
Source: Yu et. al. (2012)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
17The 61 percent seepage loss is in the ballpark of seepage losses in surface water irrigation in South Asia. Global&#13;
Water Partnership (2011) synthesizes discussion that argue that over 49 percent of water passing through surface&#13;
water irrigation systems is lost through seepage, with another 12 percent lost through evaporation. The synthesis&#13;
also argues that some of water lost through the seepage is recovered because it recharges groundwater.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                         34&#13;
&amp;#12;                               Agriculture and Water Policy: Toward Sustainable Inclusive Growth&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
78.    Another limitation to water access is at the provincial level due to institutional&#13;
features such as the 1991 Provincial Water Allocation Accord. Since 1991, water inflows have&#13;
been apportioned among the provinces by the Indus Water Accord, allocating flows among&#13;
the provinces based on a 5-year record of pre-Accord historical canal diversions. It assumes&#13;
average flow of 114.35 MAF of water in the Indus system, and allocates 55.94 MAF to Punjab&#13;
and 48.76 MAF to Sindh, with remainder going to Balochistan and Khyber Pakhtunkhwa.&#13;
The Accord accounts for the possibility of surplus water in the system, allocating 37 percent&#13;
of the surplus to Punjab and Sindh each, with the remainder being distributed to other&#13;
provinces. The agreement does not, however, have a mechanism to deal with extremely low&#13;
flow conditions or agreed-upon transfers across provinces (Yu et al., 2012).&#13;
&#13;
79.      Relaxation of the institutional rigidities of the Accord can allow for a more market-&#13;
based allocation of water leading to aggregate economic benefits. Yu et al. (2012) estimate&#13;
that by relaxing the allocation constraints of the Accord, an additional 14 MAF of water&#13;
enters the system, with both Punjab and Sindh experiencing increases in canal diversions&#13;
with the effects varying by agro-climatic zone. Punjab and Sindh gain Rs. 83 and Rs. 82&#13;
billion in revenue, while other provinces collectively lose about Rs. 7 billion.&#13;
&#13;
80.     Relaxing the conditions of the Accord by itself, without complementary policy may&#13;
lead to outcomes that are not necessarily pro-poor. The complementary policy would need to&#13;
compensate groups that the Accord relaxation would harm, such as farmers in Baluchistan&#13;
and Khyber Pakhtunkhwa, or producers of crops that are not irrigated. One possibility would&#13;
be to collect a part of the gains in Punjab and Sindh through revenue, and then transfer them&#13;
to affected groups through targeted transfers. Such a policy would need to first identify the&#13;
magnitude of the gains and losses by group, construct appropriate collection and transfer&#13;
instruments, and establish a federal body that can regulate this process.&#13;
&#13;
Markets, Trade and Diversification&#13;
&#13;
81.    Pakistan experienced considerable growth in both exports and imports over the past&#13;
decade. Export receipts grew by 13.9 percent per year during this period, while import&#13;
payments rose by 12.8 percent per year. Total export receipts changed by USD 33.48 billion,&#13;
while import payments changed by USD 29.65 billion (IFPRI, 2012). There is a notable&#13;
concentration of both imports and exports in very few products: wheat and palm oil account&#13;
for almost half of all agricultural imports, while rice is the largest export item and generates&#13;
well over half of agricultural export earnings.&#13;
&#13;
82.      Policies and policy reversals introduced in the past five years have steadily eroded the&#13;
effects of trade liberalization that Pakistan implemented between 1996 and 2003. Pakistan&#13;
had simplified its tariff structure and state trading monopolies for agricultural products had&#13;
been abolished. However, exceptions were introduced in 2006, and a number of more&#13;
important liberalizing reforms in agriculture were reversed, especially in regard to wheat,&#13;
sugar and fertilizer. The use of SROs (Statutory Regulatory Orders) has also expanded since&#13;
2006. SROs and new regulatory duties have been used to provide exemptions to normal&#13;
tariffs in some cases, while increasing tariffs for others. The resulting trade regime is thus&#13;
highly discretionary and uncertain, leading to high variable output and input price&#13;
distortions.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                              35&#13;
&amp;#12;                                   Agriculture and Water Policy: Toward Sustainable Inclusive Growth&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
83.     Major crops like wheat, rice, sugar, and cotton are implicitly taxed by various price&#13;
distortions introduced by policies in most years. Valdes et al. (2012) estimates nominal and&#13;
effective rates of protection for output of major crops as well as for inputs used in these&#13;
sectors. Nominal rates of protection (NRP) reflect output price distortions, which is relevant&#13;
to buyers and consumers. Effective rates of protection (ERP) account for the effects of the&#13;
trade regime and other policies on costs as well as output price. Tradable inputs have a net&#13;
subsidy, driven by the subsidy on fertilizer. The subsidy rate on fertilizer is about 35 percent,&#13;
and overwhelms any taxes on other inputs. It also represents a substantial fiscal cost.&#13;
&#13;
84.     The policy-induced implicit tax on crop production serves to depress production,&#13;
despite implicit net input subsidies. For example, basmati rice had negative ERPs between&#13;
2008 and 2010, when farm income would have been higher by 21 percent to 40 percent&#13;
under a no-intervention regime. The case of sugar is also similar. The significant increase in&#13;
the world price of refined sugar increased the parity price, but the increase in the general&#13;
sales tax applied to sugar offsets higher border prices. The NRP on sugarcane at the farm&#13;
gate is negative and highâ&#128;&#148;the parity prices are approximately double the observed farm gate&#13;
price. The wedge driven between the parity price and the farm gate price leads to lower&#13;
effective production.&#13;
&#13;
85.     Government procurement of wheat is extensive, and involves federal, provincial and&#13;
district level agencies. The government sets the procurement price with expected&#13;
procurement targets that the Pakistan Agricultural Storage and Services Corporation&#13;
(PASSCO) and Provincial Food Departments are responsible for meeting. Provincial&#13;
governments (mainly Punjab and Sindh) and PASSCO procure about 20 percent of total&#13;
wheat production each year (Prikhodko and Zrilyi, 2012).&#13;
&#13;
86.     The government maintains high domestic wheat procurement prices. The objective of&#13;
these high prices is to support farm incomes, and encourage sufficient production for the&#13;
domestic needs. However, domestic prices can exceed the import price parity levels, as&#13;
happened in 2009-10, since wheat can only be imported under special circumstances and by&#13;
specific parties, such as for supply to Afghanistan under the auspices of international&#13;
humanitarian missions.&#13;
&#13;
87.     Wheat procurement policies have a price stabilizing effect. Valdes et al. (2012) note&#13;
that in spite of high volatility in border prices, both wholesale and farm gate wheat prices&#13;
appear relatively stable. It is suggested that federal procurement through PASSCO and&#13;
Provincial Food Departments are absorbing the price transmission that would otherwise&#13;
prevail in open markets. Indeed, since the government controls domestic wheat prices and&#13;
procurement volumes, as well as international wheat trade, there is very little price&#13;
transmission from world markets to domestic markets.&#13;
&#13;
88.    However, the impact of these procurement policies is negative on the welfare of net&#13;
buyers (the majority of the landless poor, will be negatively affected)â&#128;&#148;they are fiscally&#13;
unsustainable, and can lead to perverse outcomes like subsidized exports.18 The ERP on&#13;
wheat has fluctuated from negative to positive values over the past few years. Valdes et al.&#13;
(2012) explain that this is mainly due to shifts in implicit NRP on the product price, which&#13;
18The full distributional impact of different categories of households, in particular the producer-consumer&#13;
households, needs to be carefully analyzed.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                        36&#13;
&amp;#12;                               Agriculture and Water Policy: Toward Sustainable Inclusive Growth&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
was negative over the three years, but small in 2009-10. The implicit NRP on tradable input&#13;
costs was negativeâ&#128;&#148;implying a subsidy to farmersâ&#128;&#148;and relatively stable compared to that on&#13;
output price. The negative ERP in 2008-09 accompanied an effective subsidy to consumers,&#13;
since the cost of imported wheat was greater than the issue price wheat at which the&#13;
government releases grain to flour mills through its public procurement mechanisms. All&#13;
procured wheat is bought and then sold to flour millers in the same wheat marketing year,&#13;
with the government absorbing the costs of procurement, storage, and financing. Millers are&#13;
able to buy the subsidized wheat at below market prices, and then sell the flour at open&#13;
market prices, which are the prices faced by consumers.&#13;
&#13;
89.     Reforming Pakistanâ&#128;&#153;s wheat procurement is thus a key area for domestic trade policy.&#13;
The simplest reform would be to reduce the wheat procurement volume. This would reduce&#13;
the fiscal burden of the subsidy as well as the effective subsidy to wheat producers. Valdes et&#13;
al. (2012) also argue that reduction of the wheat procurement does not have to jeopardize&#13;
food security (through price management) objectives. The study argues that rules-based&#13;
adjustable tariffs that set floor and ceiling prices to follow world prices and social safety net&#13;
programs can be implemented in parallel to a scale back in wheat procurement. These&#13;
policies would address the food security concern, while reducing the scope for extreme&#13;
distortions caused by the procurement policies (e.g. exports of subsidized wheat).&#13;
&#13;
90.     An enabling policy environment can also encourage the growth of high value&#13;
agriculture (HVA), which can maximize returns to scarce factors of production, like land and&#13;
water. Higher value agriculture would include crops like oilseeds, fruits, vegetables, and&#13;
livestock, while low value agriculture would include cereals. Domestic demand for these&#13;
products will continue to rise rapidly as incomes increase and diets become more diversified&#13;
if marketing channels function efficiently (World Bank, 2007a).&#13;
&#13;
91.     Pakistan, like the rest of South Asia, has been slowly diversifying towards HVA. As&#13;
estimated in Joshi et al. (2003), Pakistanâ&#128;&#153;s crop sub-sector has diversified between 1991 and&#13;
2000. The study estimated the Simpson Index of Diversity, and found that Pakistanâ&#128;&#153;s index&#13;
had risen from 0.56 to 0.57 over the periodâ&#128;&#148;a minor increase that is consistent with the&#13;
average improvement for South Asia, which rose from 0.66 to 0.67. Decomposing the source&#13;
of Pakistanâ&#128;&#153;s diversification, it was found that more than three-quarters of this&#13;
diversification occurred through utilization of fallow lands, rehabilitation of degraded lands,&#13;
or increasing cropping intensity. Much of the area expansion also came from deforestation,&#13;
which may have long run environmental implications. The remainder of the diversification&#13;
was through crop substitution.&#13;
&#13;
92.     Pakistanâ&#128;&#153;s high value agricultural exports are growing rapidly. Currently high value&#13;
agriculture (HVA) account for less than a quarter of annual export revenue. However,&#13;
exports of these products are growing rapidly. In 1990, there were virtually no exports of&#13;
dairy and eggs, or of meat (Hazell et al., 2012). However, in 2011 Pakistanâ&#128;&#153;s exports of dairy&#13;
and eggs were valued at USD 30.1 million (real 2000 dollars), while that of meat and&#13;
livestock were valued at USD 106 million, as estimated from UN COMTRADE data. The&#13;
growth of HVA exports has been rapid, with some products like fisheries and fruits,&#13;
vegetables, and oilseeds experiencing average annual growth rates of 45 percent and 15&#13;
percent, respectively, between 2008 and 2011 (Figure 15).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                              37&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                         Agriculture and Water Policy: Toward Sustainable Inclusive Growth&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Figure 15                           Exports of High-value Agricultural Products from Pakistan&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                               700&#13;
                               650&#13;
                               600&#13;
                               550&#13;
 Millions of USD (real 2000)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                               500&#13;
                               450&#13;
                               400&#13;
                               350&#13;
                               300&#13;
                               250&#13;
                               200&#13;
                               150&#13;
                               100&#13;
                                50&#13;
                                 0&#13;
                                     Dairy and Eggs   Fruits, Vegetables and    Fishery Products   Meat and Livestock&#13;
                                                              Oilseeds&#13;
                                                             2008     2009     2010   2011&#13;
&#13;
Source: Authorsâ&#128;&#153; Calculation from UN COMTRADE&#13;
&#13;
93.     Protection of low value crops may stifle the diversification process. In India, there is a&#13;
high degree of support to wheat and rice through price support and water subsidies go to&#13;
these crops, with the result being that diversification away from cereals has been slower in&#13;
the north-west (Gulati and Pursell, 2007; Hazell et al., 2012). Pakistanâ&#128;&#153;s policy environment&#13;
can be similarly constraining, as illustrated by the wheat procurement policies and the&#13;
irrigation water charges that favor rice production. Improvement and enforcement of&#13;
sanitary and phytosanitary (SPS) regulations are also necessary to meet international trade&#13;
standards. These require establishment of testing facilities, training and capacity building,&#13;
and active representation in international standard formulating agencies (Hazell et al., 2012;&#13;
Joshi et al. 2007).&#13;
&#13;
94.     Access to credit has the potential to enhance agricultural productivity, and would&#13;
help facilitate a shift from cereal-based to high value agriculture by providing the necessary&#13;
investment. Households with credit constraints had a 23 percent reduction in value of yields&#13;
(World Bank, 2007a). Access to formal credit markets in rural areas is generally limited to&#13;
landowners, since land is the most acceptable collateral for loans. World Bank (2007a)&#13;
reports that only 11 percent of farmers obtained formal sector loans in 2001-02. Access to&#13;
informal credit markets is more widespread, but approximately 40 percent of rural&#13;
households are unable to access as much credit as they need at existing interest rates.&#13;
Khandker and Faruqee (2001) find that farm credit schemesâ&#128;&#148;such as those delivered by the&#13;
Agricultural Development Bank of Pakistanâ&#128;&#148;tend to have a higher impact on small holder&#13;
production and welfare.&#13;
95.     Weakness in the seed sector constrains the crop sub-sector, including high value&#13;
crops. In 1997-98, only 10.1 percent of the potential demand for seed for various crops was&#13;
met. However, the seed sector in Pakistan has undergone several reforms and a national seed&#13;
policy was developed in 1994. By 2007-08, 16 percent of potential demand was met. Seed for&#13;
major crops like wheat and cotton saw some substantial improvement. The supply of wheat&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                        38&#13;
&amp;#12;                                        Agriculture and Water Policy: Toward Sustainable Inclusive Growth&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
seed rose by 126 percent from 78,554 T between 1998 and 2008, while the supply of cotton&#13;
seed rose by 37 percent from 23,128 T over the same period (Seed Info, 2010).&#13;
&#13;
96.     The private sector has taken the initiative in seed supply for several crops, but there is&#13;
still a substantial gap between total supplied and potential demand. The private sector&#13;
supplies more than 69 percent to 84 percent of the seed for wheat, rice, and cotton (Table 8),&#13;
while imports are responsible for 66 to 88% of total seed supply for less popular crops like&#13;
maize, vegetables, and potatoes. The public sector only has a substantial role in seed supply&#13;
for wheat, where it is has an elaborate public procurement program.&#13;
&#13;
   Table 8       Seed Supply of for Major Crops in 2010&#13;
&#13;
                     Seed Supplied                                                     Supply to Potential&#13;
       Crop                                           Source of Supply (%)&#13;
                          (T)                                                          Demand Ratio (%)&#13;
                                             Public         Private          Import&#13;
  Wheat                 177,792               31.2           68.8              0.0             17&#13;
  Rice                   13,868               17.1           71.9             11.0             35&#13;
  Maize                  9,785                2.2            31.4             66.4             33&#13;
  Vegetables             6,340                4.0             7.7             88.3            115&#13;
  Potato                 8,200                7.2             8.9             84.0              3&#13;
  Cotton                 31,691               15.9           84.1              0.0             49&#13;
Source: Adapted from Seed Info (2010)&#13;
&#13;
97.     Reforming the regulatory environment can thus enhance seed supply. Seed&#13;
registration requirements impose restrictions on seed imports. Given the low domestic&#13;
supply in the formal markets, farmers often resort to obtaining uncertified seed through&#13;
informal markets and through retention. Due to the resulting heavy reliance on the informal&#13;
sector, research and development to enhance seed production is constrained (World Bank,&#13;
2011c).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                        39&#13;
&amp;#12;                               Agriculture and Water Policy: Toward Sustainable Inclusive Growth&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Policy Recommendations&#13;
&#13;
98.     Broad-based agricultural growth can be achieved through narrowing the wide yield&#13;
gaps and diversifying toward high-value agricultural products. This growth can improve the&#13;
agricultural incomes of farmers (and especially of smallholders), as well as improve rural&#13;
incomes more generally, through higher returns on land and labor â&#128;&#148;the latter benefiting the&#13;
many rural landless poor. Actions are needed in the areas of agricultural productivity, water&#13;
use efficiency, and trade and marketing policies to enhance agricultural growth and improve&#13;
farm incomes (see Policy Matrix below).&#13;
&#13;
99.     Substantial reforms to the national agricultural research system are needed. First, the&#13;
system requires fundamental institutional reforms to make it more efficient and effective.&#13;
With efforts underway to develop provincial agricultural research institutions, the roles of&#13;
the PARC and the NARC need to be adjusted to exploit their comparative advantage of being&#13;
federal institutions able to facilitate federal funding, intraprovincial knowledge, and capacity&#13;
building. Second, with the shift in primary activities from federal to provincial levels and&#13;
from policy coordination to agricultural research, there is a need to reflect these activities in&#13;
human resource and performance incentives. This may require moving personnel from the&#13;
center to provincial institutions, or even changing the composition of the staff, to increase&#13;
the proportion of scientific research staff, for example. Third, these reforms will require&#13;
additional spending in agricultural R&amp;D, whether for supporting agricultural research in&#13;
provincial research centers or capacity building of science staff, with the exact composition of&#13;
the additional spending depending on the nature of the institutional reforms.&#13;
&#13;
100. These reforms to the R&amp;D architecture, by their nature, would be very wide ranging&#13;
and require substantial groundwork prior to execution. The first step (of two) â&#128;&#148;a stocktaking&#13;
of the current agricultural research systemâ&#128;&#148;would need to include a detailed institutional&#13;
audit that examines the system as a whole and to clearly delineate the roles, functions, and&#13;
mandates of the public federal and provincial bodies that govern and conduct agricultural&#13;
research. More broadly, this stocktaking would also need to account for the current roles of&#13;
(and environment for) private R&amp;D, including those of domestic and multinational&#13;
agribusinesses. It should then lead to a strategic road map for overhauling the national&#13;
agricultural research system, with particular emphasis on future budgets, human resources,&#13;
and capacity building. In keeping with the spirit of the 18th Amendment, this strategic&#13;
planning would need to have the input and buy-in of provincial and local government&#13;
institutions and should not be left to just the PARC and the NARC. The second step would be&#13;
to roll out the appropriate reforms over the next one or two budget cycles&#13;
&#13;
101.    To improve water use efficiency, the most important intervention would be&#13;
institutional reform of the entire water management system. Given the systemâ&#128;&#153;s high&#13;
dysfunction, clarifying the institutional environment would be a prerequisite for any other&#13;
intervention under consideration, such as revising the Abiana. The reforms to the water&#13;
management system include completely devolving authority to the relevant scale, clarifying&#13;
the roles and mandates of each authority, and providing sufficient resources and capacity&#13;
building to allow the devolved authorities to fulfill their mandates.&#13;
&#13;
102. As with the reforms to the national agricultural research system, reforms to the whole&#13;
water management system will require action over multiple years and will need to be&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                              40&#13;
&amp;#12;                                             Agriculture and Water Policy: Toward Sustainable Inclusive Growth&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
carefully considered. Water management systems show wide divergence in budgets, capacity,&#13;
and extent of devolution from the federal to provincial level. The reforms need to first&#13;
identify their current state, from public irrigation departments down to the Farmersâ&#128;&#153;&#13;
Organizations (FOs) and Water User Associations (WUAs), which will help clarify the roles&#13;
and mandate of each authority and outline a devolution plan for each area where devolution&#13;
has not occurred (such as the public irrigation and drainage authority still managing public&#13;
irrigation departments). For entities that require capacity building and management reform&#13;
(such as FOs), budgets to train and support personnel are needed.&#13;
&#13;
103. To promote trade and agricultural diversification, the trade regime must be&#13;
simplified. This will require removing unpredictable and discretionary instruments like the&#13;
SROs, shifting to a lower set of uniform tariffs, and simplifying the trade regime by removing&#13;
alternative trade policy instruments like export taxes. These three measures would reduce&#13;
uncertainty, volatility, and the policy bias against agricultural products like rice and sugar.&#13;
Valdes et al. (2012) also point out that equalizing tariffs across agricultural products, while&#13;
necessary, is not sufficient for equal effective protection across products, because protection&#13;
or support in the input markets could still be substantial, at varying levels. Their study&#13;
argues that the best approach to reducing the variation in effective protection across outputs&#13;
is to also reduce the variation in protection of all inputs, including raw materials, capital, and&#13;
tradable inputs. From a practical perspective, the measures will require a realistic timetable,&#13;
as well as instruments compliant with the World Trade Organization that may still be able to&#13;
protect national interests.&#13;
&#13;
104. To improve domestic trade of agricultural products while protecting food security,&#13;
distortions in domestic markets of commodities like wheat need to be removed. The simplest&#13;
set of reforms would be to reduce the wheat procurement volume while designing and&#13;
implementing complementary social safety net programs. The wheat procurement&#13;
contraction would reduce the effective subsidy to wheat producers and thus the fiscal&#13;
burden. If food price stability is important, price bands can be implemented using rules-&#13;
based adjustable tariffs that set floor and ceiling prices to follow world prices19. In parallel,&#13;
social safety net programs that target food-insecure groups can be established, with clearly&#13;
defined triggers and graduation requirements.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
19&#13;
   Valdes et al. (2012) suggest this approach for wheat and sugar, based on the moving averages of border prices. By keeping the basis of&#13;
the price band delinked from domestic prices, the policy remains a World Trade Organization â&#128;&#147;compliant instrument as a variable levy.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                        41&#13;
&amp;#12;                                    Agriculture and Water Policy: Toward Sustainable Inclusive Growth&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
POLICY MATRIX&#13;
            Objective                     Short Run Action (&lt;1 year)             Medium/Long Run Action&#13;
Improve agricultural productivity    Initiate reform of the national        Carry out reforms of national&#13;
                                     agricultural research system to        agricultural research system&#13;
                                     make it more efficient and             (clarify mandate, shift personnel&#13;
                                     effective                              from federal to provincial&#13;
                                                                            institutions, shift budget, provide&#13;
                                     Develop plan for building scientific   appropriate performance&#13;
                                     research capacity                      incentives)&#13;
&#13;
                                                                            Increase budget for agricultural&#13;
                                                                            research&#13;
&#13;
                                                                            Plan and implement long run&#13;
                                                                            capacity building program for&#13;
                                                                            scientific research capacity&#13;
&#13;
Improve water use efficiency         Identify mechanisms for                Implement institutional reform&#13;
                                     institutional reform of the&#13;
                                     management system:                     Provide sufficient federal and&#13;
                                                                            provincial resources for transition&#13;
                                     ï&#130;·   Complete devolution of             and capacity building&#13;
                                         authority to the relevant scale&#13;
                                         (including provincial              Set up third party watchdog to&#13;
                                         authorities and farmersâ&#128;&#153;           evaluate state of institutional&#13;
                                         organizations)                     reform and monitor for rent&#13;
                                     ï&#130;·   Clarify the roles and mandates     seeking behavior&#13;
                                         of each authority&#13;
&#13;
Remove protection variability and    Identify timetable for removal of      Remove statutory regulator&#13;
bias against agricultural exports    statutory regulator orders, tariff     orders, reduce and harmonize&#13;
                                     reduction and harmonization, and       tariffs, and dismantle export&#13;
                                     export barrier removal.                barriers.&#13;
&#13;
                                     Identify WTO compliant&#13;
                                     instruments that may be&#13;
                                     appropriate to use instead, e.g.&#13;
                                     special safeguard mechanisms&#13;
&#13;
Reduce distortions in domestic       Identify minimum volume of public      Implement rules-based adjustable&#13;
grains markets while protecting      wheat procurement, accounting          tariffs to maintain designated price&#13;
food security                        (federal and provincial                bands&#13;
                                     procurement programs).&#13;
                                                                            Develop and roll out social&#13;
                                     Identify floor and ceiling prices to   protection programs for food&#13;
                                     follow world prices for wheat          security, with clear triggers and&#13;
                                     prices                                 graduation requirements.&#13;
&#13;
                                     Identify food insecure groups for&#13;
                                     social protection programs&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                42&#13;
&amp;#12;                              Agriculture and Water Policy: Toward Sustainable Inclusive Growth&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
References&#13;
Abbas, M., S. Mohammad, I. Nabi, and A.D. Sheikh. 2003. â&#128;&#156;Farmer-Extension Interaction&#13;
and the Dissemination of Recommended Sugarcane Production Technologies in the Central&#13;
Punjab (Pakistan)â&#128;?. International Journal of Agriculture &amp; Biology. Vol. 5(2).&#13;
&#13;
Ahmad, M. and J.H. Nagy. 2001. Chapter 2 in Pray, C.E. and K. Fuglie (eds.) Private&#13;
Investment in Agricultural Research and International Technology Transfer in Asia ,&#13;
Agricultural Economic Report No. AER-805. Economic Research Service, US Department of&#13;
Agriculture. Washington, DC.&#13;
&#13;
Ali, M. and D. Byerlee. 2002. â&#128;&#156;Productivity Growth and Resource Degradation in Pakistanâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
Punjab: A Decomposition Analysisâ&#128;?. Economic Development and Cultural Change. Vol. 50.&#13;
pp: 839-863.&#13;
&#13;
Anwar, T., S.K. Qureshi, and H. Ali. 2004. â&#128;&#156;Landlessness and Rural Poverty in Pakistanâ&#128;?. The&#13;
Pakistan Development Review. Vol.43. pp: 855-874.&#13;
&#13;
ASTI . 2012. â&#128;&#156;ASTI Data Toolâ&#128;?. Agricultural Science and Technology Indicators. &lt;Available:&#13;
www.asti.cgiar.org/data/&gt;: Accessed November 13, 2012)&#13;
&#13;
Beintema, N.M., W. Malik, M. Sharif, G.J. Stads, and U. Mustafa. 2007. Agricultural&#13;
Research and Development in Pakistan: Policy, Investments, and Institutional Profile. ASTI&#13;
Country Report. International Food Policy Research Institute and Pakistan Agricultural&#13;
Research Council.&#13;
&#13;
FAO. 2002. Water and Fertilizer Use in Selected Countries, Discussion Paper Food and&#13;
Agriculture Organization, Rome. &lt;Available:&#13;
ftp://ftp.fao.org/agl/agll/docs/watfertuse.pdf&gt;: Accessed August 16, 2012&#13;
&#13;
FAO. 2010. AQUASTAT Pakistan Country Profile. Food and Agriculture Organization, Rome.&#13;
&#13;
Faruqee, R. 1995. Government's role in Pakistan Agriculture: Major Reforms are Needed,&#13;
Policy Research Working Paper No 1468. Washington D.C.: World Bank.&#13;
&#13;
Fuglie, K.O. 2012. "Productivity Growth and Technology Capital in the Global Agricultural&#13;
Economy." in: Fuglie K., Wang, S.L. and Ball, V.E. (eds.), Productivity Growth in&#13;
Agriculture: An International Perspective, CAB International, Wallingford, Oxon, UK&#13;
(forthcoming).&#13;
&#13;
Food Security Portal. 2012. Pakistan. IFPRI. Washington D.C.                        &lt;available&#13;
http://www.foodsecurityportal.org/pakistan&gt;: Accessed November 1, 2012&#13;
&#13;
Global Water Partnership. 2011. Climate Change, Food and Water Security in South Asia:&#13;
Critical Issues and Cooperative Strategies in an Age of Increased Risk and Uncertaintyâ&#128;&#147;&#13;
Synthesis of Workshop Discussions. Global Water Partnership (GWP) and International&#13;
Water Management Institute (IWMI) Workshop. 23-25 February 2011, Colombo.&#13;
&#13;
Gulati, A. and G. Pursell. 2009. â&#128;&#156;India and other South Asian Countriesâ&#128;? in Anderson, K.&#13;
(ed) Distortions to Agricultural Incentives: A Global Perspective, 1955-2007. Houndmills,&#13;
Basingstoke, Hampshire: Palgrave Macmillan.&#13;
&#13;
Haggblade, S., J. Hammer and P.B.R. Hazell. 1991. â&#128;&#156;Modeling Agricultural Growth&#13;
Multipliersâ&#128;?. American Journal of Agricultural Economics. Vol. 73(2). pp: 361-74, 1991.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                            43&#13;
&amp;#12;                               Agriculture and Water Policy: Toward Sustainable Inclusive Growth&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Hazell, P., D. Headey, A. Pratt, and D. Byerlee. 2011. â&#128;&#156;Structural Imbalances and Farm Non-&#13;
Farm Employment Prospects in Rural SouthAsiaâ&#128;?. Background study for World Bank,&#13;
(2012b), More and Better Jobs in South Asia. World Bank: Washington, DC.&#13;
&#13;
Headey, D., D. Bezemer, and P.B.Hazell. 2010. Agricultural Employment Trends in Asia and&#13;
Africa: Too Fast or Too Slow? World Bank Research Observer. Vol.25. pp: 57-89.&#13;
&#13;
IFPRI. 2011. 2011 Global Hunger Index. International Food Policy Research Institute,&#13;
Washington, DC. &lt;available: www.ifpri.org/publication/2011-global-hunger-index&gt;.&#13;
Accessed October 20, 2012&#13;
&#13;
IFPRI. 2012. Agricultural Growth and Poverty Reduction in Pakistan: Preliminary&#13;
Economy-Wide Assessment. International Food Policy Research Institute. Washington, DC.&#13;
&#13;
Inchauste, G. and H. Winkler. 2012. â&#128;&#156;Decomposing Distributional Changes in Pakistanâ&#128;?.&#13;
Background Paper to Fostering Employment with Inclusive Growth Report. World Bank:&#13;
Washington D.C.&#13;
&#13;
IPP. 2012. The State of the Economy: The Punjab Story. 5th Annual Report. Institute of&#13;
Public Policy. Beaconhouse National University: Lahore.&#13;
&#13;
Joshi, P.K., A. Gulati, P.S. Birthal, and L. Tewari. 2003. â&#128;&#156;Agriculture Diversification in South&#13;
Asia: Patterns, Determinants, and Policy implicationsâ&#128;?. MSSD Discussion Paper No. 57,&#13;
International Food Policy Research Institute: Washington D.C.&#13;
&#13;
Joshi, P. K., A. Gulati and R. Cummings Jr. (eds.). 2007. Agricultural Diversification and&#13;
Smallholders in South Asia. New Delhi: Academic Foundation&#13;
&#13;
Khandker, S. and R. Faruqee. 2001. â&#128;&#156;The Impact of Farm Credit on Pakistanâ&#128;?. Policy&#13;
Research Working Paper Series WPS 2653. World Bank: Washington D.C.&#13;
&#13;
Murgai, R., M. Ali, and D. Byerlee. 2001. â&#128;&#156;Productivity Growth and Sustainability in Post-&#13;
Green Revolution Agriculture: The Case of the Indian and Pakistan Punjabsâ&#128;?. World Bank&#13;
Research Observer. Vol.16(2). pp:199-218.&#13;
&#13;
Pingali, P.L., and M.W. Rosegrant. 1995. 1995. â&#128;&#156;Agricultural Commercialization and&#13;
Diversification: Processes and Policiesâ&#128;?. Food Policy. Vol.20(3). pp:171-186.&#13;
&#13;
Planning Commission. 2009. â&#128;&#156;Task Force on Food Security- Final Reportâ&#128;?. Government of&#13;
Pakistan, Islamabad.&#13;
&#13;
Planning Commission. 2012. â&#128;&#156;Canal Water Pricing for Irrigation in Pakistanâ&#128;&#147;Assessment,&#13;
Issues, and Optionsâ&#128;?. Government of Pakistan, Islamabad.&#13;
&#13;
Prikhodko, D. and O. Zrilyi. 2012. â&#128;&#156;Review of the Wheat Sector and Grain Storage Issuesâ&#128;? .&#13;
WB Agriculture Policy Priorities Work in the Islamic Republic of Pakistan.&#13;
&#13;
Seed Info. 2010. Seed Info No. 38. Official Newsletter of the WANA Seed Network. January&#13;
2010.&#13;
&#13;
Valdes, A., M. Ashraf, A.Khan, and M. Waheed. 2012. â&#128;&#156;Agricultural Trade and Price Policy in&#13;
Pakistanâ&#128;?. Agricultural Chapter of Country Economic Memorandum, World Bank,&#13;
Washington D.C.&#13;
&#13;
World Bank. 2003. India: Revitalizing Punjab's Agriculture. World Bank: Washington D.C.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                             44&#13;
&amp;#12;                             Agriculture and Water Policy: Toward Sustainable Inclusive Growth&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
World Bank. 2004. â&#128;&#156;Rural Factor Markets Policy Reforms for Growth and Equityâ&#128;?. Report&#13;
No. 30381-PK. World Bank: Washington D.C.&#13;
&#13;
World Bank. 2007a. â&#128;&#156;Promoting Rural Growth and Poverty Reductionâ&#128;?.Report No. 30381-&#13;
PK. World Bank: Washington D.C.&#13;
&#13;
World Bank. 2007b. â&#128;&#156;World Development Report 2008: Agriculture for Developmentâ&#128;?.&#13;
World Bank: Washington D.C.&#13;
&#13;
World Bank. 2011a. â&#128;&#156;World Development Indicatorsâ&#128;?. World Bank: Washington D.C.&#13;
&#13;
World Bank. 2011b. â&#128;&#156;Pakistan Water Resource Notesâ&#128;?. Internal discussion note, SASDA.&#13;
World Bank: Washington D.C.&#13;
&#13;
World Bank. 2011c. â&#128;&#156;Pakistan Seedsâ&#128;&#153; Sector Notesâ&#128;?. Internal discussion note, SASDA. World&#13;
Bank: Washington D.C.&#13;
&#13;
World Bank. 2011d. â&#128;&#156;Pakistan Agriculture Research and Extension Notes.â&#128;? Internal&#13;
discussion note, SASDA. World Bank: Washington D.C.&#13;
&#13;
World Bank. 2012a. â&#128;&#156;Pakistan Poverty Assessmentâ&#128;?. (forthcoming). World Bank:&#13;
Washington D.C.&#13;
&#13;
World Bank. 2012b. â&#128;&#156;More and Better Jobs in South Asiaâ&#128;?. World Bank: Washington D.C.&#13;
&#13;
World Bank. 2012c. â&#128;&#156;Fostering Employment with Inclusive Growthâ&#128;&#147;Synthesisâ&#128;?. World Bank:&#13;
Washington D.C.&#13;
&#13;
Yu, W., Y.C. Yang, A. Savitsky, D. Alford, C.Brown, J. Wescoat, D. Debowicz, and S.&#13;
Robinson. 2012. â&#128;&#156;Climate Risks on Water and Food Security in the Indus Basin of Pakistanâ&#128;?.&#13;
World Bank: Washington D.C.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                           45&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="19311313">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2013/03/19311313/agriculture-water-policy-toward-sustainable-inclusive-growth
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2013/03/19311313/agriculture-water-policy-toward-sustainable-inclusive-growth</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2013/03/19311313/agriculture-water-policy-toward-sustainable-inclusive-growth</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2014-03-28T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2014-03-28T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2014/03/28/000456286_20140328165452/Rendered/INDEX/862510NWP0Worl00Water0Policy0final.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2014/03/28/000456286_20140328165452/Rendered/PDF/862510NWP0Worl00Water0Policy0final.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2013-03-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2014-03-28T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Agriculture and water policy : toward
            sustainable inclusive growth
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            This paper reviews Pakistan's
            agriculture performance and analyzes its agriculture and
            water policies. It discusses the nature of rural poverty and
            emphasizes the reasons why agricultural growth is a critical
            component to any pro-poor growth strategy for Pakistan. It
            supports these arguments by summarizing key results from
            recent empirical analysis where the relative benefits of
            agricultural versus non-agricultural led growth are
            examined. The results also provide an illustration of farm
            and non-farm linkages. It summarizes recent performance of
            the agriculture sector, and discusses key characteristics of
            its sluggish productivity growth. Three key issues related
            to increasing productivity are discussed: namely technology,
            water use and water management, and policy reforms related
            to markets and trade that can strengthen the enabling
            environment and contribute to the promotion of
            diversification towards high value agriculture.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Agriculture and water policy : toward
            sustainable inclusive growth
        </docna>
        <display_title>Agriculture and water policy :
            toward sustainable inclusive growth</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2013/03/19311313/agriculture-water-policy-toward-sustainable-inclusive-growth</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Working Paper (Numbered Series)</docty>
        <subtopic>Rural Poverty Reduction,Regional Economic Development,Agricultural Research,Crops and Crop Management Systems</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth,Poverty Reduction,Agriculture</teratopic>
        <count>Pakistan</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Ahmed, Syud Amer</author>
            <author>Gautam, Madhur</author>
        </authors>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Asia!$!80451</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>South Asia!$!80470</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000456286_20140328165452</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>South Asia,South Asia</admreg>
        <colti>World Bank Policy Paper Series on Pakistan ;
            no. PK 16/12</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth,Poverty Reduction,Agriculture</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            access to credit, access to services, access
            to technology, agrarian economy, agribusiness, Agricultural
            Development, agricultural diversification, Agricultural
            Economy, agricultural employment, agricultural export,
            Agricultural exports, Agricultural extension, Agricultural
            extension services, agricultural growth, agricultural
            households, agricultural incomes, agricultural investments,
            agricultural output, agricultural practices, agricultural
            production, agricultural productivity, agricultural
            research, Agricultural Research Center, agricultural
            research institutions, agricultural research network,
            Agricultural Science, agricultural sector, agricultural
            sectors, agricultural system, agricultural wage,
            agricultural wages, Agriculture, Agriculture Organization,
            animals, arable land, average yields, Basin Irrigation,
            bean, border prices, canal irrigation, capacity building,
            capacity constraints, capita incomes, cereals, climate
            change, climatic zone, commercial crops, commodities,
            cotton, cotton seed, counterfactual, credit markets, credit
            schemes, crop, crop agriculture, crop management, Crop
            production, crop yields, cropland, cropping, crops,
            cultivars, cultivation, deforestation, degradation, degraded
            lands, distribution of land, domestic prices, Drainage,
            economic growth, eggs, Employment in agriculture, expansion
            of irrigation, export crops, fallow lands, FAO, farm
            activities, farm activity, Farm Employment, farm income,
            farm income and employment, farm income growth, farm
            incomes, farm sector, farm size, Farmer, farmers, farming,
            fertilizer, fertilizer use, fertilizers, fisheries, flour,
            flour mills, food insecurity, Food Policy, food price, food
            prices, food security, forestry, fruits, global markets,
            grain, Green Revolution, groundwater, harvests, high crop
            yield, high value commodities, high-value agricultural
            products, horticulture, household income, household incomes,
            household per capita income, IFPRI, income inequality,
            innovation, International Food Policy Research Institute,
            investment in agricultural research, IRRI, irrigation,
            Irrigation expansion, irrigation systems, labor demand,
            labor markets, labor productivity, land acquisition, land
            distribution, land holdings, land ownership, land
            productivity, Land Quality, land rights, landholdings,
            landless households, lands, large farm, large farms,
            livestock, livestock production, livestock sector, local
            farmers, maize, meat, national agricultural research,
            national agricultural research system, national poverty,
            national poverty line, national poverty rate, natural
            resources, nutrition, oilseeds, palm oil, Pesticide,
            Pesticide use, population growth, potatoes, poverty
            headcount rates, poverty rate, Poverty rates, poverty
            reducing, Poverty Reduction, price stabilization, price
            volatility, private agricultural research, produce,
            production growth, production system, productivity growth,
            productivity improvements, public agricultural research, raw
            materials, research centers, rice, rice yields, rural, rural
            areas, rural economy, rural employment, rural growth, rural
            households, rural incomes, rural labor, rural labor market,
            rural poor, rural poverty, rural poverty rate, rural poverty
            reduction, rural work, rural workers, safety net, safety net
            programs, scientific research, seed supply, sharecroppers,
            small farm households, small farmers, small farms,
            smallholder farmers, sowing, sugar, sugarcane, sustainable
            production systems, targeted transfers, targeting,
            Technology Transfer, tobacco, trade liberalization, urban
            poverty, urbanization, vegetables, water availability, water
            resources, water resources management, water scarcity, Water
            supply, water use, water use efficiency, wheat, wheat
            prices, wheat producers, wheat production, wheat seed, wheat trade
        </keywd>
        <owner>Econ. Policy &amp; Poverty Sector (SASEP)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>South Asia</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>86251</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Poverty Reduction Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Extension &amp; Research</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Policy Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Policy Formulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Policy Implementation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Productivity-Led Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crops</ml:concept><ml:concept>Livestock</ml:concept><ml:concept>Livestock and Animal Husbandry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Research and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Food Security and Nutrition</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shared Prosperity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wage Setting</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages, Compensation and Benefits</ml:concept><ml:concept>Foreign Direct Investments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Linkages</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Lines</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Use</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Research</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fertilizers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Animal Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inclusive Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages</ml:concept><ml:concept>FDI Spillovers</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Pakistan</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Southern Asia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>