<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>﻿OFFICIAL            Woyirty&#13;
DOCUMENTS&#13;
The World Bank                                      1818 H Street N.W.       (202) 473-1000&#13;
INTERNATIONAL BANK FOR RECONSTRUCTION AND DEVELOPMENT  Washington, D.C. 20433  Cable Address: INTBAFRAD&#13;
INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPMENT ASSOCIATION               U.S.A.                   Cable Address: INDEVAS&#13;
Date: A42~l/2    _2lop&#13;
Dr. Stevan Lee&#13;
Team Leader and Senior Economist&#13;
Growth Research Team&#13;
Department for International Development&#13;
Government of the United Kingdom of Great Britain&#13;
and Northern Ireland&#13;
22 Whitehall&#13;
London, SWIA 2EG&#13;
United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland&#13;
Trust Fund Administration Arrangement between the Government of the United&#13;
Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland, represented by the Department&#13;
of International Development, and the International Bank for Reconstruction&#13;
and Development and the International Development Association concerning the&#13;
Multi-Donor Trust Fund for Sustainable Urban Development (TF 071544).&#13;
Dear Dr. Lee:&#13;
1.     We are pleased to acknowledge on behalf of the International Bank for Reconstruction and&#13;
Development ("IBRD") and the International Development Association ("IDA") (collectively, the&#13;
"Bank") that the Government of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland,&#13;
represented by the Department for International Development ("DFID") (the "Donor") shall make&#13;
available as a grant the sum of four million eight hundred sixty two thousand Pounds Sterling&#13;
(f4,862,000) (the "Contribution") for the Multi-Donor Trust Fund for Sustainable Urban&#13;
Development (TF 071544) (the "Trust Fund") in accordance with the terms of this Arrangement (the&#13;
"Arrangement"). Other donors are also expected ic contribute to the Trust Fund on the terms and&#13;
conditions specified in the Annexes to this Arrangement.&#13;
2.     The Contribution shall be used to finance the activities and the categories of expenditure set&#13;
forth in the "Description of Activities, Expenditures and Governance Terms for the Multi-Donor&#13;
Trust Fund for Sustainable Urban Development" attached hereto as Annex 1, and shall be&#13;
administered by the Bank on behalf of the Donor in accordance with the terms of this Arrangement,&#13;
including the "Standard Provisions Applicable to the Multi-Donor Trust Fund for Sustainable Urban&#13;
Development" (the "Standard Provisions") attached hereto as Annex 2.&#13;
3.     The Donor shall deposit the Contribution into such bank account designated by the Bank in&#13;
installments in accordance with the following schedule:&#13;
(a)   promptly following countersignature of this Arrangement by the Donor and submission of a&#13;
payment request by the Bank, two million Pounds Sterling (GBP 2,000,000);&#13;
(b)  on or before December 1, 2014, and upon submission of a payment request by the Bank, seven&#13;
hundred fifteen thousand five hundred Pounds Sterling (GBP 715,500);&#13;
(c)   on or before June 1, 2015, and upon submission of a payment request by the Bank, seven&#13;
hundred fifteen thousand five hundred Pounds Sterling (GBP 715,500);&#13;
(d)  on or before December 1, 2015, and upon submission of a payment request by the Bank, seven&#13;
hundred fifteen thous;ind five hundred Pounds Sterling (GBP 715,500); and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿(e)   on or before June 1, 2016. and upon submission of a pa) ment request by the Bank, seven&#13;
hundred fifteen thousand five hundred Pounds Sterling (GBP 715,500).&#13;
4.     When making each such deposit, the Donor shall instruct its bank to include in its payment&#13;
details information (remittance advice) field of its SWIFT payment message, information indicating:&#13;
the amount paid, that the payment is made by the Donor for TF071544 (Multi-Donor Trust Fund for&#13;
Sustainable Urban Development), and the date of the deposit (the "Deposit Instruction"). In addition,&#13;
the Donor shall provide a copy of the Donor's Deposit Instruction to the Bank's Accounting Trust&#13;
Funds Division by e-mail sent to tfremitadvice@worldbank.org or by fax sent to (202) 614-1315.&#13;
5.     The Bank shall convert the Contribution funds into the holding currency of the Trust Fund,&#13;
namely United States Dollars. promptly upon receipt of the Contribution funds and the Deposit&#13;
Instruction containing the information specified in paragraph 4 at the exchange rate obtained by the&#13;
Bank on the date of the conversion. If the Contribution proves to be insufficient to complete the&#13;
activities as a result of exchange rate fluctuations, neither the Bank nor the Donor shall bear any&#13;
responsibility for providing any additional financing.&#13;
6.     Except as provided for in paragraph 4 above, any notice, request or other communication to&#13;
be given or made under this Arrangement shall be in writing and delivered by mail, facsimile or e-&#13;
mail to the respective party's address specified below or at such other address as such party notifies in&#13;
writing to the other party from time to time:&#13;
For the Bank:&#13;
Mr. Sameh Wahba&#13;
Sector Manager .&#13;
Urban Development and Resilience Unit&#13;
Sustainable Development Network&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
1818 H Street, NW&#13;
Washington, DC 20433&#13;
U.S.A.&#13;
Tel: +1 202 458 8671&#13;
Fax: +1 202 522 3232&#13;
E-mail: swahba@aworldbank.org&#13;
For the Donor:&#13;
Dr. Stevan Lee&#13;
Team Leader and Senior Economist&#13;
Growth Research Team&#13;
Department for International Development&#13;
Government of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland&#13;
22 Whitehall&#13;
London, SWIA 2EG&#13;
United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland&#13;
Tel.: +44 020 7023 0908&#13;
Fax: +44 744 6631 1811&#13;
E-mail: S-Lee@dfid.gov.uk&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-3 -&#13;
7.     It is understood that the amount of US$ 35,000 reflected in paragraph 3.1 of Annex 2 to this&#13;
Arrangement has already been charged to the Trust Fund.&#13;
8.     All annexes hereto constitute an integral part of this Arrangement. This Arrangement may be&#13;
amended only in writing between the Bank and the Donor; provided, however, that such annexes may&#13;
be amended only with the agreement of all donors contributing to the Trust Fund.&#13;
9.     Please confirm your agreement with the foregoing, on behalf of the Donor, by signing,&#13;
dating, and returning to us the enclosed copy of this Arrangement. Upon receipt by the Bank of the&#13;
copy of this Arrangement countersigned by you, this Arrangement will become effective as of the&#13;
date of the countersignature.&#13;
Sincerely,&#13;
INTERNATIONAL BANK FOR RECONSTRUCTION AND DEVELOPMENT&#13;
INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPMENT ASSOCIATION&#13;
Zou IaAllaoua&#13;
Director&#13;
Urban and Disaster Risk Management Department&#13;
CONFIRMED AND AGREED:&#13;
GOVERNMENT OF THE UNITED KINGDOM OF GREAT BRITAIN AND NORTHERN&#13;
IRELAND, represented by the Department for International Development&#13;
By:                                              Date:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-4-&#13;
ANNEX 1&#13;
Description of Activities, Expenditures and Governance Terms for the Multi-Donor Trust Fund&#13;
for Sustainable Urban Development&#13;
This Annex shall be applicable to and form an integral part of all agreements entered into between the&#13;
Bank and entities (collectively, the "Donors") that provide contributions (the aggregate of all&#13;
contributions from the Donors, the "Contributions") to be administered by the Bank for the Trust&#13;
Fund.&#13;
A.     BACKGROUND&#13;
For the first time in history more than half the world's people live in cities. Over 90 percent of urban&#13;
growth is occurring in the developing world, adding an estimated 70 million new residents to urban&#13;
areas each year. Successful cities change their ways, improve their finances, attract private investors,&#13;
and take care of the poor. However, the demands of poverty alleviation, climate change and&#13;
sustainable growth will put today's developing country cities to the test. Within cities of developing&#13;
countries, a sharper focus on climate change adaptation and the expected positive impacts and&#13;
outcomes associated with the implementation of related measures will require retooling approaches to&#13;
urban management and investment planning. This Multi-Donor Trust Fund for Sustainable Urban&#13;
Development (the "MDTF") contributes to the operationalization of the Bank's 2009 Urban Strategy,&#13;
which emphasizes sustainable urban development and equity and inclusion for growth and poverty&#13;
alleviation.&#13;
B.     DESCRIPTION OF ACTIVITIES&#13;
The objectives of the MDTF are to: (1) support the design, implementation and knowledge&#13;
management of analytical and diagnostic work on urban poverty that wili help fill knowledge gaps&#13;
and provide the basis for better designed programs and policies; (2) support work on reducing&#13;
vulnerability and increasing resilience to climate change for the urban poor; and (3) promote&#13;
knowledge partnerships with universities, think tanks, and development organizations on sustainable&#13;
urban development.&#13;
The MDTF will finance global, national, and regional initiatives through analytical work for project&#13;
development, institutional strengthening and knowledge partnerships on urban poverty and&#13;
sustainable urban development.&#13;
I.     Activities related to climate change adaptation and resilience of the urban poor, including.&#13;
(a) Preparation of a framework for city level analysis focusing on exposure to risk, food&#13;
security, access to basic services, energy efficiency, location issues (precarious and&#13;
overcrowded settlements), gender specific vulnerability etc.&#13;
(b) Identification, documentation and di semination of good practice examples where shelter&#13;
and social and basic services for the urban poor have improved while vulnerability to&#13;
climate change and carbon emissions have been reduced.&#13;
(c) Development of investment programs and new financing instruments that reduce the&#13;
vulnerability and increase resilience of the urban poor.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿2.     Preparation and roll out of a urban risk assessment methodology, including:&#13;
(a) Preparation of a standardized framework to allow flexibility in application dependent on&#13;
available resources and institutional capacity.&#13;
(b) Development of cost effective, low-tech approaches to digitally mapping urban slums for&#13;
improved understanding of local impacts of climate change and natural hazards.&#13;
(c) Elaboration of training materials for non-government organizations and community&#13;
groups to perform digital mapping.&#13;
(d) Piloting of urban risk assessment in approximately fifteen (15) cities .&#13;
3.     Preparation of an urban poverty analysis, with particular focus in Africa, South Asia, and East&#13;
Asia regions, including:&#13;
(a) Spatial estimates of poverty and related characteristics for use in analytical, projects and&#13;
diagnostic.&#13;
(b) Preparation of urban poverty reduction strategies to leverage analytical work and develop&#13;
projects.&#13;
4.     Carrying out analytical work to help countries scale up policies and programs for slum&#13;
upgrading and slum prevention, particularly in Africa and South Asia, such as an analysis of legal and&#13;
regulatory issues on land policy, tenure regularization; proactive slum prevention policies and&#13;
analysis of the emerging role for the private sector in slum upgrading activities through approaches&#13;
such as output-based aid and new innovative uses of financial instruments; and analysis and policy&#13;
recommendation options for countries' consideration on social inclusion in cities' cultural heritage&#13;
regeneration and conservation.&#13;
5.     Carrying out knowledge partnership activities including:&#13;
(a) Provision of support to ongoing work and participation in key events.&#13;
(b) Participation in missions and programs that will enable the Bank to support and take&#13;
advantage of the knowledge and experience of university networks, community based&#13;
non-governmental organizations (NGOs) through workshops, study tours, and exchange&#13;
programs.&#13;
(c) Establishment of partnerships with developing country and developed country&#13;
universities in cutting edge urban development research.&#13;
(d) Carrying out a scholar in residence program to bring researchers and practitioners with&#13;
specific skills into the Bank to benefit country programs.&#13;
6.     Carrying out analysis and propose policy recommendation options for countries'&#13;
consideration on food security in urban areas and urban land development planning on arable lands in&#13;
the outskirt of the cities.&#13;
7.     Provision of support to cities and national governments in developing countries in balancing&#13;
environmental, economic and social tradeoffs in order to achieve sustainable, inclusive and pro-poor&#13;
urbanization and growth by supporting: diagnostics tools on policy and investment constraints;&#13;
investment programs; development of a knowledge base; and capacity for sustainable urbanization.&#13;
In particular, support will focus on:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-6-&#13;
(a) Policy tools: carrying out analytical work on o urbanization and urbanization reviews,&#13;
including expanding engagement with policy makers on core policy diagnostics and&#13;
developing new tools on sustainability and climate change;&#13;
(b) Promoting the Urbanization Review Policy Framework in World Bank lending and&#13;
policy dialogue: supporting project preparation activities for urban multi-sectoral projects&#13;
building on completed or ongoing urbanization reviews; and&#13;
(c) Global partnerships and data: collecting and making publicly available urbanization&#13;
related data at the global, regional and local scales, and supporting and strengthening&#13;
activities under World Bank supported knowledge initiatives.&#13;
C.     CATEGORIES OF EXPENDITURE&#13;
The Contributions may be used to finance (a) staff cost; (b) extended term consultants; (c)&#13;
consultant fees; (d) contractual services; (e) temporary support staff cost;  (f) travel expenses; (g)&#13;
media and workshop costs; and (h) associated overheads.&#13;
D.     GOVERNANCESTRUCTURE&#13;
1.    The task team leader (TTL) for the MDTF will be appointed by the Director of the Urban and&#13;
Disaster Risk Management Department (UDR) of the Bank and will be responsible for the&#13;
administration and management of the MDTF, including coordinating and reporting to the Steering&#13;
Committee. The TTL will also be responsible for approving proposals up to US$75,000 consistent&#13;
with the objectives of the MDTF and the criteria agreed with the Steering Committee.&#13;
2.     Steering Committee. The Steering Committee will be responsible for; (i) providing overall&#13;
strategic guidance in the implementation of the MDTF; and (ii) reviewing annual work plans.&#13;
The Steering Committee members consist of:&#13;
(a) one (1) representative from each Donor; and&#13;
(b) three (3) representatives from the Bank, consisting of the Director of the UDR, the Sector&#13;
Manager of the Urban and Resilience Management Unit (UDRUR), and the TTL.&#13;
The Steering Committee will be chaired by the Bank. The decisions of the Steering&#13;
Committee are made by consensus. The Steering Committee will meet initially at least annually and&#13;
other meetings will be organized as needed. All meeting may be held either in person and/or by&#13;
audio/video. During the annual meetings, the Steering Committee will review progress on the&#13;
implementation of the activities and discuss strategic priorities.&#13;
3.     Funding. The selection and approval of proposals under the MDTF will be carried out by the&#13;
Bank. Proposals in an amount up to US$75,000 will be reviewed and approved by the TTL.&#13;
Proposals exceeding US$ 75,000 will be reviewed and approved in accordance with eligibility criteria&#13;
agreed with the Steering Committee.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-7-&#13;
ANNEX 2&#13;
Standard Provisions Applicable to the Multi-Donor Trust Fund for Sustainable Urban&#13;
Development&#13;
This Annex shall be applicable to and form an integral part of all agreements entered into&#13;
between the Bank and the Donors that provide Contributions to be administered by the Bank for the&#13;
Trust Fund.&#13;
1.     Administration of the Contributions&#13;
1.1.   The Bank shall be responsible only for performing those functions specifically set forth in&#13;
this Arrangement and shall not be subject to any other duties or responsibilities to the Donors,&#13;
including, without limitation, any duties or obligations that might otherwise apply to a fiduciary or&#13;
trustee under general principles of trust or fiduciary law. Nothing in this Arrangement shall be&#13;
considered a waiver of any privileges or immunities of the IBRD and IDA under their Articles of&#13;
Arrangement or any applicable law, all of which are expressly reserved.&#13;
1.2.   The Contribution shall be administered in accordance with the Bank's applicable policies and&#13;
procedures, as the same may be amended from time to time, including its framework to prevent and&#13;
combat fraud and corruption and its screening procedures to prevent the use of Bank resources to&#13;
finance terrorist activity, in line with the Bank's obligations to give effect to the relevant decisions of&#13;
the Security Council, taken under Chapter VII of the of Charter of the United Nations. The Donor&#13;
acknowledges that this provision does not create any obligations of the Bank under the anti-terrorist&#13;
financing and asset control laws, regulations, rules and executive orders of an individual member&#13;
country that may apply to the Donor, nor shall it be deemed a waiver, express or implied, of any of&#13;
the privileges and immunities of the Bank.&#13;
2.     Commingling, Exchange and Investment of the Contributions&#13;
2.1.   The Contributions shall be accounted for as a single trust fund and shall be kept separate and&#13;
apart from the funds of the Bank. The Contributions may be commingled with other trust fund assets&#13;
maintained by the Bank.&#13;
2.2.   The Contributions may be freely exchanged by the Bank into other currencies as may&#13;
facilitate their disbursement.&#13;
2.3.   The Bank shall invest and reinvest the Contributions pending their disbursement in&#13;
accordance with the Bank's policies and procedures for the investment of trust funds administered by&#13;
the Bank. The Bank shall credit all income from such investment to the Trust Fund to be used for the&#13;
same purposes as the Contributions.&#13;
3.     Administrative Cost Recovery&#13;
3.1.   In order to assist in the defrayment of the costs associated with the establishment of the Trust&#13;
Fund, the Bank may, following deposit of the first Contribution from any Donor to the Trust Fund,&#13;
deduct and retain for its own account from that Contribution an amount equal to and not greater than&#13;
thirty-five thousand United States Dollars (US$35,000).&#13;
3.2.   In order to assist in the defrayment of the costs of administration and other expenses incurred&#13;
by the Bank under this Arrangement, the Bank may deduct and retain for its own account an amount&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-8-&#13;
equal to five percent (5%) of each Contribution. If the contributions increase beyond what was&#13;
originally expected at the time of counter-signature of the first administration agreement, and the&#13;
administrative costs increase as a result, the Donors acknowledge that an additional administrative fee&#13;
may be applied to such new contributions.&#13;
4.     Procurement&#13;
4.1.   For Bank-executed activities, the employment and supervision of any consultants and the&#13;
procurement of any goods financed by the Contributions shall be the responsibility of the Bank and&#13;
shall be carried out in accordance with its applicable policies and procedures.&#13;
5.    Accounting and Financial Reporting&#13;
5.1.   The Bank shall maintain separate records and ledger accounts in respect of the Contributions&#13;
deposited in the Trust Fund account and disbursements made therefrom.&#13;
5.2.   The Bank shall furnish to the Donors current financial information relating to receipts,&#13;
disbursements and fund balance in the holding currency of the Trust Fund with respect to the&#13;
Contributions via the World Bank's Trust Funds Donor Center secure website. Within six (6) months&#13;
after all commitments and liabilities under the Trust Fund have been satisfied and the Trust Fund has&#13;
been closed, the final financial information relating to receipts, disbursements and fund balance in the&#13;
holding currency of the Trust Fund with respect to the Contributions will be made available to the&#13;
Donors via the World Bank's Trust Funds Donor Center secure website.&#13;
5.3.   The Bank shall provide to the Donors, within six (6) months following the end of each Bank&#13;
fiscal year, an annual single audit report, comprising (1) a management assertion together with an&#13;
attestation from the Bank's external auditors concerning the adequacy of internal control over cash-&#13;
based financial reporting for all cash-based trust funds as a whole; and (2) a combined financial&#13;
statement for all cash-based trust funds together with the Bank's external auditor's opinion thereon.&#13;
The cost of the single audit shall be borne by the Bank.&#13;
5.4.   If a Donor wishes to request, on an exceptional basis, a financial statement audit by the&#13;
Bank's external auditors of the Trust Fund, the Donor and the Bank shall first consult as to whether&#13;
such an external audit is necessary. The Bank and the Donor shall agree on the appropriate scope and&#13;
terms of reference of such audit. Following agreement on the scope and terms of reference, the Bank&#13;
shall arrange for such external audit. The costs of any such audit, including the internal costs of the&#13;
Bank with respect to such audit, shall be paid by the requesting Donor.&#13;
6.     Progress Reporting&#13;
6.1.   The Bank shall provide the Donors with an annual report on the progress of activities&#13;
financed by the Contributions. Within six (6) months of the final disbursement date specified in&#13;
paragraph 7.1, the Bank shall furnish to the Donors a final report on the activities financed by the&#13;
Trust Fund.&#13;
6.2.   Any Donor may review or evaluate activities financed by the Trust Fund. The Donor and the&#13;
Bank shall agree on the scope and conduct of such review or evaluation, and the Bank shall provide&#13;
all relevant information within the limits of its policies and procedures. All associated costs shall be&#13;
borne by the Donor. It is understood that any such review or evaluation will not constitute a&#13;
financial, compliance or other audit of the Trust Fund.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-9-&#13;
7.     Disbursement: Cancellation Refund&#13;
7.1.   It is expected that the Contributions will be fully disbursed by the Bank by December 31,&#13;
2016. The Bank shall only disburse Contributions for the purposes of this Arrangement after such&#13;
date with the written approval of the Donors.&#13;
7.2.   Any Donor or the Bank may, upon three (3) months' prior written notice, cancel all or part of&#13;
the Donor's pro rata share, of any remaining balance of the Contributions that is not committed&#13;
pursuant to any agreements entered into between the Bank and any consultants and/or other third&#13;
parties for the purposes of this Arrangement prior to the receipt of such notice.&#13;
7.3.   Following the final disbursement date specified in paragraph 7.1, the Bank shall return any&#13;
remaining balance of the Contributions to the Donors or to the relevant Donor Balance Account on a&#13;
pro rata basis based on the Donors' paid Contributions. In the event of a cancellation the Bank shall&#13;
promptly return to the relevant Donor or Donors or to the relevant Donor Balance Account the&#13;
Donor's pro rata share of uncommitted Contributions in accordance with paragraph 7.1.&#13;
8.     Disclosure&#13;
The Bank will disclose this Arrangement and related information on this Trust Fund in&#13;
accordance with the World Bank Policy on Access to Information. By entering into this Arrangement,&#13;
Donors consent to disclosure of this Arrangement and related information on this Trust Fund.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="19416339">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2013/11/19416339/official-documents--administration-arrangement-dfid-contribution-tf071544
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2013/11/19416339/official-documents--administration-arrangement-dfid-contribution-tf071544</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2013/11/19416339/official-documents--administration-arrangement-dfid-contribution-tf071544</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2014-04-21T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2014-04-21T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <docm_id>090224b0823f7a8c</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b0823f7a8c</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/SDN/2014/04/21/090224b0823f7a8c/1_0/Rendered/INDEX/Official0Docum0ibution0to0TF0715440.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/SDN/2014/04/21/090224b0823f7a8c/1_0/Rendered/PDF/Official0Docum0ibution0to0TF0715440.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2013-11-26T15:02:10Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2014-04-21T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docna>
            Official Documents- Administration
            Arrangement with DFID for Contribution to TF071544
        </docna>
        <display_title>Official Documents-
            Administration Arrangement with DFID for Contribution to TF071544</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/2013/11/19416339/official-documents--administration-arrangement-dfid-contribution-tf071544</listing_relative_url>
        <projn>MX-Sustainable Urban Dev. In Mexican Cities:
            A Hands-On Approach -- P127214</projn>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <docty>Trust Fund Administrative Agreement</docty>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Pardo De La Pena,Maria Lourdes</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>HQBOCS</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <owner>Urban Development and Resilience (UDRUR)</owner>
        <trustfund>TF071544-Multi-Donor Trust Fund for
            Sustainable Urban Development</trustfund>
        <lang>English</lang>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sustainable Climate Business</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sustainable Energy Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Arts and Culture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Climate Change</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Strategy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Food Security and Nutrition</ml:concept><ml:concept>Green Growth and Sustainability</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sustainable Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy Conservation &amp; Efficiency</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy Conservation and Efficiency</ml:concept><ml:concept>Adaptation to Climate Change</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social and Economic Inclusion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Remittances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Migration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Slums Upgrading</ml:concept><ml:concept>Disaster Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Hazard Risk Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Contract Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Arrangements in Public Procurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Capacity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legal Regulatory Framework</ml:concept><ml:concept>State-Society Relations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Housing and Land</ml:concept><ml:concept>Housing and Planning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Housing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Land</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Land Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Media</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Policy Framework</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urbanization Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Green Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy Efficiency</ml:concept><ml:concept>Climate Change Adaptation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Inclusion in Cities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Movement of Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urbanization and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Slum Upgrading</ml:concept><ml:concept>Disaster Risk Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Land Supply and Markets</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>