<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>                                              87802&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Kyrgyz Republic:&#13;
Growth Rebounds, Risks Remain&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                      Kyrgyz Republic Economic Report No.5&#13;
                                               March 2014&#13;
&amp;#12;&amp;#12;Kyrgyz Republic:&#13;
Growth Rebounds, Risks Remain&#13;
Kyrgyz Republic Economic Report No.5&#13;
March 2014&#13;
&amp;#12;KYRGYZ REPUBLIC ECONOMIC REPORT NO.5â&#128;&#131; â&#128;&#147;â&#128;&#131; MARCH 2014&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Government Fiscal Year:	           January 1â&#128;&#147;December 31&#13;
Currency Equivalents:	             Exchange rate effective as of September 30, 2013&#13;
		                                 Currency Unit = Kyrgyz Som (KGS)&#13;
		                                 USD 1.00 = KGS 48.6197&#13;
Weights and Measures:	             Metric System&#13;
&#13;
Abbreviations&#13;
&#13;
BOP	                         Balance of Payments&#13;
BKR Customs Union	           Belarus-Kazakhstan-Russia Customs Union&#13;
CAR	                         Capital Adequacy Ratio&#13;
CIS	                         Commonwealth of Independent States&#13;
FDI	                         Foreign Direct Investments&#13;
GDP	                         Gross Domestic Product&#13;
HDI	                         Human Development Index&#13;
KGS	                         Kyrgyz Som&#13;
NATO	                        North Atlantic Treaty Organization&#13;
NBKR	                        National Bank of the Kyrgyz Republic&#13;
NPL	                         Non-Performing Loan&#13;
NSSD	                        National Strategy for Sustainable Development&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
iiâ&#128;&#131;   â&#148;&#130;â&#128;&#131;&#13;
&amp;#12;                                           KYRGYZ REPUBLIC: GROWTH REBOUNDS, RISKS REMAIN&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Contents&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Abbreviations&amp;#8;ii&#13;
&#13;
Acknowledgments&amp;#8;iv&#13;
&#13;
Overview&amp;#8;v&#13;
&#13;
A. Recent Political Developments&amp;#8;                                                         1&#13;
&#13;
B. Recent Economic Developments&amp;#8;  2&#13;
    Economic Growth&amp;#8;              2&#13;
    Inflation&amp;#8;3&#13;
    External Accounts&amp;#8;            5&#13;
    Employment and Labor Markets&amp;#8; 7&#13;
    Poverty &amp;#8;                     9&#13;
&#13;
C. Economic and Structural Policies&amp;#8;                                                      10&#13;
    Fiscal Policy&amp;#8;                                                                        10&#13;
    Monetary and Exchange Rate Policies&amp;#8;                                                  11&#13;
    Structural Reforms&amp;#8;                                                                   12&#13;
&#13;
Outlook&amp;#8;15&#13;
&#13;
Appendix&amp;#8;17&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                 â&#128;&#131;   â&#148;&#130;â&#128;&#131;   iii&#13;
&amp;#12;KYRGYZ REPUBLIC ECONOMIC REPORT NO.5â&#128;&#131; â&#128;&#147;â&#128;&#131; MARCH 2014&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
List of Figures&#13;
&#13;
Figure 1. Growth was broad-based in 2013&amp;#8;                                                                2&#13;
Figure 2. The non-gold economy has been growing at 5â&#128;&#147;6 percent in recent years&amp;#8;                          2&#13;
Figure 3. Remittances inflows continued growing in 2013, albeit at a slower pace&amp;#8;                        3&#13;
Figure 4. Private consumption remains the most dominant component of aggregate demand&amp;#8;                   3&#13;
Figure 5. Headline inflation slowed in 2013&amp;#8;                                                             4&#13;
Figure 6. The FAOâ&#128;&#153;s food price index came down in 2013, mainly due to a fall in cereal prices&amp;#8;           4&#13;
Figure 7. The current account deficit remains sizeable&amp;#8;                                                  5&#13;
Figure 8. Gold exports pushed up exports during the last quarter of the year&amp;#8;                            5&#13;
Figure 9. Administrative employment data suggest labor participation is improving&amp;#8;                       7&#13;
Figure 10. A freeze on public sector wages brought down average real wages in 2013&amp;#8;                      7&#13;
Figure 11. Agriculture is the only sector to employ fewer people in 2012 than 2002&amp;#8;                      8&#13;
Figure 12. Labor productivity has fallen across most sectors between 2002 and 2012&amp;#8;                      8&#13;
Figure 13. Wages in the Kyrgyz Republic are loosely tied to labor productivity&amp;#8;                          8&#13;
Figure 14. The self-employed and children are most at risk of being in poverty&amp;#8;                          9&#13;
Figure 15. Completion of secondary and tertiary education helps reduce the risk of poverty&amp;#8;              9&#13;
Figure 16. The fiscal deficit was lower than originally projected in 2013&amp;#8;                              10&#13;
Figure 17 . The REER is broadly appropriate&amp;#8;                                                            12&#13;
Figure 18. The performance of the Kyrgyz Republic against the Doing Business indicators is mixed&amp;#8;       13&#13;
Figure 19. There has been a mild improvement in the Kyrgyz Republicâ&#128;&#153;s â&#128;&#156;control of corruptionâ&#128;&#157;â&#128;¦&amp;#8;         14&#13;
Figure 20. â&#128;¦as well as their implementation of the â&#128;&#156;rule of lawâ&#128;&#157;&amp;#8;                                       14&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
List of Tables&#13;
&#13;
Table 1. Selected Fiscal Indicators&amp;#8;                                                                    11&#13;
Table 2. Selected banking and monetary sector indicators&amp;#8;                                               12&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
List of Boxes&#13;
&#13;
Box 1. The impact of international food prices on domestic inflation in the Kyrgyz Republic*&amp;#8;            4&#13;
Box 2. Changes in labor productivity 2002â&#128;&#147;2012&amp;#8;                                                          8&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Acknowledgments&#13;
&#13;
The World Bank regular economic reports on the Kyrgyz Republic are published every six months. This report&#13;
was prepared by a team comprising of Evgenij Najdov (Senior Economist), Bakyt Dubashov (Economist) and&#13;
Helen Edmundson (Economist). The report benefited from the guidance of Ivailo Izvorski (Sector Manager) and&#13;
Alexander Kremer (Country Manager).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ivâ&#128;&#131;   â&#148;&#130;â&#128;&#131;&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                              KYRGYZ REPUBLIC: GROWTH REBOUNDS, RISKS REMAIN&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Overview&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Political stability has been maintained. The Kyrgyz Republicâ&#128;&#153;s threeâ&#128;&#147;party coalition has tackled a number&#13;
of events during 2013, including mayoral elections in the countryâ&#128;&#153;s biggest citiesâ&#128;&#148;Bishkek and Oshâ&#128;&#148;road&#13;
blockages around Kumtor, the countryâ&#128;&#153;s largest gold mine, as well as tense negotiations on the future of the&#13;
mine; and clashes in the south of the country. The government has navigated through these difficult times,&#13;
quashing a motion of no confidence in Parliament.&#13;
&#13;
An agreement between the Kyrgyz Republic and Centerra Inc.â&#128;&#148;the majority stakeholder in Kumtorâ&#128;&#148;was&#13;
accepted by Parliament in early 2014. While the details of the agreement still need to be worked through, this&#13;
is a positive development, which will hopefully ease political tensions and create more certainty for investors.&#13;
&#13;
A surge in gold output and solid growth in the non-gold sectors contributed to an impressive 10.5 percent&#13;
expansion of the Kyrgyz economy in 2013. This is the highest growth the country has seen since independence.&#13;
Gold output soared in the second half of the year, bringing 2013 output to almost double 2012 levels, partly due&#13;
to the low base effect created by disruptions to gold production at Kumtor. The non-gold economy expanded&#13;
at 5.8 percent, with the services sectors and construction performing particularly well. Domestic demand&#13;
continues to play an important role, as a result of rising private sector wages and remittances inflows (both&#13;
growing, albeit at a slower rate than in 2012), and faster growth in credit to the private sector.&#13;
&#13;
Smaller increases in food prices than in recent years, and relatively stable energy prices helped bring&#13;
inflation down. Consumer prices inflation slowed to 4 percent in the 12-months through December 2013,&#13;
down from 7  .5 percent in 2012. Net of food and energy-related prices, core inflation also fell, but to an elevated&#13;
7.2 percent.&#13;
&#13;
Expenditure controls and robust revenue outturns have brought the fiscal deficit down to 3.5 percent&#13;
of GDP   . A wage freeze for most of the public sector was the main cost saving measure. Controls on goods&#13;
and services spending, alongside lower capital expenditures helped bring expenditures down further. Strong&#13;
growth and changes to tax policy supported a small increase in revenues as a share of GDP    . The resulting fiscal&#13;
deficit is much lower than the originally estimated 5.2 percent of GDP  . However, the sustainability of the fiscal&#13;
deficit is uncertain, given the pressure government is likely to face to increase wages, and the potential fall in&#13;
revenues from the closure of the Manas transit center in 2014.&#13;
&#13;
Preliminary estimates suggest the trade deficit and current account deficit remained high in 2013. While&#13;
gold exports grew strongly, especially during the final quarter of the year, non-gold formal exports fell by&#13;
6 percent year-on-year. Meanwhile, imports grew at 13 percent, partly supporting the governmentâ&#128;&#153;s investment&#13;
program, and partly as a result of strong domestic demand. The current account deficit is expected to stay high&#13;
in 2013, although less than the 15 percent of GDP recorded in 2012.&#13;
&#13;
The nominal exchange rate has come under pressure in 2014. The National Bank of the Kyrgyz Republic has&#13;
intervened four times this year, compared to just once during 2013. This follows a 20 percent devaluation of&#13;
the Kazakhstan tenge. The real exchange rate remains appropriate although additional downward fluctuations&#13;
in regional currencies could affect the competitiveness of Kyrgyz goods and services.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                            Overviewâ&#128;&#131;   â&#148;&#130;â&#128;&#131;   v&#13;
&amp;#12;KYRGYZ REPUBLIC ECONOMIC REPORT NO.5â&#128;&#131; â&#128;&#147;â&#128;&#131; MARCH 2014&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Medium term growth is expected to moderate to 5 percent, however, a number of risks remain. The&#13;
exceptional performance of gold output in 2013 is unlikely to be repeated in 2014. The rest of the economy is&#13;
expected to continue expanding at 5â&#128;&#147;6 percent. A slowdown in the Russian economy, declining gold prices,&#13;
and uncertainty created by the recent fluctuations in the exchange rate could adversely affect this outcome.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
viâ&#128;&#131;   â&#148;&#130;â&#128;&#131;Overview&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                              KYRGYZ REPUBLIC: GROWTH REBOUNDS, RISKS REMAIN&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
A. Recent Political Developments&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Half-way in its tenure, the government of the Kyrgyz Republic continues to navigate a number of&#13;
challenging political situations. The authorities appear to be making progress on the Kumtor issue. In&#13;
addition, a motion calling for a vote of no confidence of the government was easily knocked back. However, the&#13;
December protests in Osh following the jailing of an opposition Member of Parliament over fraud and corruption&#13;
allegations, and a recent armed incident on the border with Tajikistan, are reminders of the countryâ&#128;&#153;s fragility.&#13;
&#13;
The protracted negotiations between the Kyrgyz Republic and Centerra appear to have been resolved.&#13;
At the end of December 2013, the government sent a draft agreement, outlining a new deal with the Canadian&#13;
investors Centerra, Inc., to Parliament, which was subsequently passed in February 2014. The agreement&#13;
replaces the 33 percent shares of the Kyrgyz Republic in Centerra for a 50 percent share in Kumtor and also&#13;
recognizes the validity of the 2009 contract between the country and Centerra, including the tax regime. As&#13;
part of the new deal, Centerra has agreed to forfeit a $100 million payment from the Kyrgyz Republic and at&#13;
the end of the mineâ&#128;&#153;s planned life in 2026, the country will have the right to increase its ownership by up to&#13;
67 percent for a price equal to fair market value. The number of Kyrgyz nationals in management positions in the&#13;
joint venture will also increase. The Parliament has set some conditions for the full ratification of the agreement,&#13;
including on environmental and mining issuesâ&#128;&#148;limiting the area of the mine. The Government and Centerra,&#13;
Inc. are yet to comment on the decision of the Parliament. While tensions are still present, the recent resolution&#13;
should help appease resentment that has been brewing among both politicians and the general public, as well&#13;
as send out positive signals to investors.&#13;
&#13;
Progress on accession to the Customs Union (CU) has slowed, following a request from the Kyrgyz&#13;
authorities for additional concessions from the CU members. A roadmap for the accession of the Kyrgyz&#13;
Republic to the CU was developed by the Eurasian Economic Commission (EEC) in late-2013. The Kyrgyz&#13;
government subsequently announced that the â&#128;&#156;road mapâ&#128;&#157; was prepared without the involvement of the Kyrgyz&#13;
side and did not address important demands of the Kyrgyz authorities, including exemptions from the common&#13;
external tariff (CET) for around 2,600 goods; granting free economic zone treatment for the large wholesale&#13;
markets in the Kyrgyz Republic; guaranteed investments; improved labor mobility; and resources to upgrade&#13;
border-crossing points. While acknowledging in his annual address that â&#128;&#156;(the Kyrgyz Republic),â&#128;¦ does not have&#13;
many choices â&#128;¦â&#128;&#157;    , President Atambayev was also quoted during a December 24, 2013 high-level meeting of&#13;
the EEC that the Kyrgyz Republic would join the CU only if the countryâ&#128;&#153;s economic interests are considered.&#13;
Discussions are ongoing between both sides.&#13;
&#13;
Clashes erupted between Kyrgyz and Tajik border guards in January 2014. Both sides have since agreed to&#13;
work towards resolving the outstanding issues but tensions remain high.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                     A. Recent Political Developmentsâ&#128;&#131;   â&#148;&#130;â&#128;&#131;   1&#13;
&amp;#12;KYRGYZ REPUBLIC ECONOMIC REPORT NO.5â&#128;&#131; â&#128;&#147;â&#128;&#131; MARCH 2014&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
B. Recent Economic Developments&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Economic Growth&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Growth rebounded strongly in 2013 to 10.5 percent, with production at Kumtor, the countryâ&#128;&#153;s main gold&#13;
mine, contributing almost half. After a slow start, gold production from Kumtor exceeded expectations. At&#13;
over 600 thousand ounces, gold output was almost double the amount mined in 2012, when production fell&#13;
because of a glacier movement. Over 50 percent of gold was mined during the last quarter of the year once the&#13;
high-grade deposit was reached.&#13;
&#13;
In general, the non-gold sectors of the economy performed well, especially construction and services.&#13;
Non-gold growth for 2013 is estimated at 5.8 percent, up from 5.0 percent in 2012. While lower than last&#13;
year, growth in construction continued in the double digits in 2013 contributing close to 1 percentage point&#13;
of total growth, supported partly by the governmentâ&#128;&#153;s investment program. Meanwhile, continued growth&#13;
of the tourism sector, combined with strong domestic demand, helped keep growth in hospitality services&#13;
above 11 percent. Domestic demand also supported growth in trade, and transport and communicationsâ&#128;&#148;each&#13;
contributed around 1.3 percentage points to total GDP growth. Subdued external demand for Kyrgyz products&#13;
(especially textiles) kept non-Kumtor industry growth (mainly driven by manufacturing) at a modest 3.5 percent.&#13;
Finally, the agriculture sector expanded moderately, at 2.9 percent, despite more favorable weather conditions&#13;
than in 2012, suggesting structural issues could be impeding faster growth in the sector (Figure 1).&#13;
&#13;
For the third year running, the non-gold economy has expanded in the range 5â&#128;&#147;6 percent. This highlights&#13;
the â&#128;&#156;enclave-likeâ&#128;&#157; nature of gold production relative to the rest of economy as well as the increasing importance&#13;
of domestic demand due in part to robust remittance inflows, and increasing credit to the private sector (Figure&#13;
2). Continued growth in the non-gold economy will help reduce the volatility that currently characterizes the&#13;
Kyrgyz economy, as well as reduce the countryâ&#128;&#153;s vulnerability to shocks.&#13;
&#13;
Figure 1. Growth was broad-based in 2013                                                Figure 2. The non-gold economy has been growing&#13;
                                                                                        at 5â&#128;&#147;6 percent in recent years&#13;
in percentage points                                                                    in percent                                                                      in percent&#13;
 12                                                                                      12                                                                                       100&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                         10                                                                                       80&#13;
  8&#13;
                                                                                          8                                                                                       60&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                          6                                                                                       40&#13;
  4&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                          4                                                                                       20&#13;
&#13;
  0&#13;
                                                                                          2                                                                                        0&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                          0                                                                                       -20&#13;
 -4&#13;
                                                                                         -2                                                                                       -40&#13;
&#13;
 -8                                                                                      -4                                                                                       -60&#13;
           2008          2009           2010           2011          2012   2013 est.          2005     2006      2007     2008     2009     2010      2011    2012   2013 est.&#13;
JJ Agriculture                  JJ Construction               JJ Industry               JJ GDP growth          JJ Non-gold real growth â&#150;¬â&#150;¬ Kumtor growth, rhs&#13;
&#13;
JJ Trade                        JJ Transport &amp; comms          JJ Other&#13;
Source: Kyrgyz authorities.                                                             Source: Kyrgyz authorities.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
2â&#128;&#131;    â&#148;&#130;â&#128;&#131;   B. Recent Economic Developments&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                                 KYRGYZ REPUBLIC: GROWTH REBOUNDS, RISKS REMAIN&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Private consumption was behind most of the increase in aggregate demand in 2013. Growth in private&#13;
sector wages helped offset a fall in public sector earnings. Wage growth, combined with rising inflows of&#13;
remittances continued to stimulate private consumption in 2013 (Figure 3). Increased credit to the private&#13;
sector further stimulated strong domestic demand, especially in manufacturing (93 percent credit growth year&#13;
on year), and agriculture (54 percent credit growth year on year). In 2013, loans with a maturity of at least three&#13;
years grew faster than all other loan types (close to 50 percent of GDP), which could suggest growing investor&#13;
confidence.&#13;
&#13;
Figure 3. Remittances inflows continued growing                                  Figure 4. Private consumption remains the most&#13;
in 2013, albeit at a slower pace                                                 dominant component of aggregate demand&#13;
in millions                                                         in percent   in percentage points&#13;
 2,500                                                                     40     20&#13;
&#13;
                                                                           35     15&#13;
 2,000                                                                            10&#13;
                                                                           30&#13;
                                                                                   5&#13;
                                                                           25&#13;
 1,500&#13;
                                                                                   0&#13;
                                                                           20&#13;
                                                                                  -5&#13;
 1,000&#13;
                                                                           15&#13;
                                                                                 -10&#13;
                                                                           10&#13;
  500                                                                            -15&#13;
                                                                            5    -20&#13;
&#13;
    0                                                                       0    -25&#13;
                2010              2011               2012   2013 est.                      2008           2009          2010          2011          2012         2013 est.&#13;
JJ US dollars                 â&#150;¬â&#150;¬ y-o-y growth, rhs                               JJ Net export         JJ Investment           JJ Public consumption JJ Private consumption&#13;
Source: Kyrgyz authorities.                                                      Source: Kyrgyz authorities.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
After a sluggish start to the year, investment levels and exports picked up. In December 2013, investment&#13;
was up 2.3 percent, year-on-year (y-o-y), mainly driven by higher foreign direct investment as a result of&#13;
transactions made by Kumtor. The mining sector accounted for the largest share of investment in fixed assets&#13;
(around a third of total investment), followed by transport and communications, manufacturing and energy.&#13;
Public sector investment remained strong, mostly financed through foreign loans and grants. The contribution&#13;
to growth from net exports continues to be negative, although faster growth in gold exports during the final&#13;
quarter of 2013 helped moderately reduce its drag on growth (Figure 4).&#13;
&#13;
The strong growth experienced in 2013 has trickled into 2014. The year has started well, with preliminary data&#13;
for January showing 9.1 percent growth y-o-y. Aside from gold, the non-gold economy expanded 6.7 percent&#13;
with domestic demand continuing to drive growth.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Inflation&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Headline inflation slowed in 2013, because of lower domestic fuel prices and a fall in international food&#13;
prices. Inflation stayed in the single digits throughout 2013, concluding at a yearly average rate of 6.6 percent&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                        B. Recent Economic Developmentsâ&#128;&#131;             â&#148;&#130;â&#128;&#131;      3&#13;
&amp;#12;KYRGYZ REPUBLIC ECONOMIC REPORT NO.5â&#128;&#131; â&#128;&#147;â&#128;&#131; MARCH 2014&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 5. Headline inflation slowed in 2013                                                           Figure 6. The FAOâ&#128;&#153;s food price index came down in&#13;
                                                                                                      2013, mainly due to a fall in cereal prices&#13;
in percent, year on year change                                                                       index: 2002â&#128;&#147;2004=100&#13;
 15                                                                                                    200&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                       190&#13;
 10&#13;
                                                                                                       180&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                       170&#13;
  5&#13;
                                                                                                       160&#13;
&#13;
  0                                                                                                    150&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                       140&#13;
 -5&#13;
                                                                                                       130&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                       120&#13;
-10&#13;
                                                                                                       110&#13;
&#13;
-15                                                                                                    100&#13;
       Jan           Apr        Jul     Oct        Jan        Apr        Jul         Oct                      Jan       Apr         Jul         Oct    Jan    Apr    Jul    Oct&#13;
      2012          2012       2012    2012       2013       2013       2013        2013                     2012      2012        2012        2012   2013   2013   2013   2013&#13;
â&#150;¬â&#150;¬ Core inflation          â&#150;¬â&#150;¬ Food            â&#150;¬â&#150;¬ Headline           â&#150;¬â&#150;¬ Fuel                           â&#150;¬â&#150;¬ Food price index     â&#150;¬â&#150;¬ Cereal price index&#13;
Source: The National Bank of the Kyrgyz Republic.                                                     Source: FAO.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
(Figure 5).1 Declining international food prices, especially wheat, helped limit the effect of domestic food price&#13;
increases due to the large share of imported food in the Kyrgyz Republicâ&#128;&#153;s overall consumption basket (Box 1).&#13;
Prices of locally produced fruit, meat and dairy products all increased during 2013, compared to a 0.8 percent&#13;
fall in local bread prices following a fall in global cereal prices: the FAOâ&#128;&#153;s Food Price Index in 2013 was on&#13;
average 1.6 percent lower compared to 2012, mainly as a result of declining cereal (by 7     .2 percent), sugar (by&#13;
17.9 percent) and oils (by 13.8 percent) prices (Figure 6). At the same time, stable global energy prices and a&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      Box 1. The impact of international food prices on domestic inflation in the Kyrgyz Republic*&#13;
&#13;
      Food and fuel account for around 64 percent of the consumer price index (CPI) in the Kyrgyz Republic. Food&#13;
      represents the largest share at close to 57 percent, with bread, at 20 percent of overall CPI, the largest food&#13;
      component. Compared to countries in Central Asia, particularly Tajikistan and Uzbekistan, the Kyrgyz Republic&#13;
      has relatively similar food and fuel shares in the CPI. Compared to the median rate in other developing and&#13;
      emerging economies (31 percent), this rate is exceptionally high.**&#13;
&#13;
      Food staples account for around 50 percent of the Kyrgyz Republicâ&#128;&#153;s food basket. The country is a net food&#13;
      importer, relying in particular on imports of wheat, potatoes and vegetable oils. Domestic prices of food stuffs&#13;
      linked to these products are therefore heavily influenced by global prices. The prices of the other food staples&#13;
      (fruits, dairy, meat) are mainly determined locally.&#13;
&#13;
      There is a strong correlation between global food prices and headline inflation. During 2004â&#128;&#147;2011, domestic&#13;
      food inflation was found to be heavily influenced by international food prices (correlation of 0.87). Given the&#13;
      importance of food in the overall CPI, this also translates into a strong correlation with headline inflation (0.80).&#13;
&#13;
      The Kyrgyz Republic generally employs administrative measures to offset the impact of rising food prices.&#13;
      Measures to offset higher prices of imported goods have included import duty reductions on the main food&#13;
      staples as well as export bans for flour and grain. To soften the blow on household incomes, blanket increases&#13;
      to public sector salaries and pensions were introduced during the food price shock in 2007â&#128;&#147;8.&#13;
                                                                                                                     , IMF Working Paper 12/86.&#13;
      *Largely drawn from Al-Eyd, A., et al (2012), â&#128;&#156;Global Food Price Inflation and Policy Responses in Central Asiaâ&#128;&#157;&#13;
      **World Economic Outlook, 2011, p109, IMF.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
1	    Annual inflation peaked in April 2013 (compared to April 2012) at 8 percent, and then moderated afterwards to 4 percent by December 2013 (compared to&#13;
      December 2012).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
4â&#128;&#131;    â&#148;&#130;â&#128;&#131;     B. Recent Economic Developments&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                                         KYRGYZ REPUBLIC: GROWTH REBOUNDS, RISKS REMAIN&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
fall in local prices (coal prices declined by around 6 percent) have dampened domestic energy and fuel inflation.&#13;
Notably, crude oil prices have been remarkably stable during the past 3 years, hovering around $105 a barrel.2&#13;
&#13;
Net of food and fuel prices, core inflation eased to an elevated and above headline inflation level of&#13;
7.8 percent on average in 2013. Strong domestic demand, driven by increasing credit to the private sector&#13;
and rising remittances, are key factors supporting high core inflation. Twelve-month core inflation fell into single&#13;
digits for the first time since September 2010.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
External Accounts&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The current account deficit is expected to remain high in 2013. The recovery of gold exports in the last&#13;
quarter of 2013, in addition to robust services exports and remittances, is expected to have slightly improved&#13;
the current account compared to 2012. However, the deficit is likely to remain in the double-digits and above&#13;
levels registered prior to 2012 (Figure 7.).&#13;
&#13;
Figure 7. The current account deficit remains                                             Figure 8. Gold exports pushed up exports during&#13;
sizeable                                                                                  the last quarter of the year&#13;
in percent of GDP                                                                         in millions, US dollars&#13;
     0                                                                                     6,000&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
-10                                                                                        5,000&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
-20                                                                                        4,000&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
-30                                                                                        3,000&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
-40                                                                                        2,000&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
-50                                                                                        1,000&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
-60                                                                                           0&#13;
             2008        2009         2010           2011       2012    2013 est                    2008          2009          2010          2011      2012    2013 est&#13;
JJ Current account balance                   JJ Trade balance                             JJ Export of goods    JJ Import of goods&#13;
Sources: Kyrgyz authorities and World Bank staff estimates.                               Sources: Kyrgyz authorities and World Bank staff estimates.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Export growth rebounded in 2013, mainly due to the surge in gold shipments. Merchandise exports rose&#13;
3.8 percent in 2013, with gold exports up 31 percent following a 44 percent decrease in 2012 (Figure 8). Most&#13;
of this increase came during the last quarter of the year following exceptional gold production at Kumtor. Terms&#13;
of trade losses because of lower gold pricesâ&#128;&#148;that fell to $1,412 per troy ounce on average in 2013 from $1,670&#13;
per troy ounce in 2012â&#128;&#148;amounted to $135 million, or 1.9 percent of GDP     .3&#13;
&#13;
Officially recorded exports of non-gold products fell by 6 percent in 2013, with a particularly strong&#13;
decline for electricity, textiles and dairy products. Electricity exports fell by more than 67 percent in 2013&#13;
compared to a year ago, which resulted in a loss of more than $20 million of export earnings. This was due to&#13;
&#13;
2	       The World Bankâ&#128;&#153;s Commodity Markets Outlook, January 2014, provides a useful overview of the causes of volatility in oil prices during 2011 and 2013.&#13;
3	       Average gold prices are taken from the World Bankâ&#128;&#153;s Commodity Price Database.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                B. Recent Economic Developmentsâ&#128;&#131;    â&#148;&#130;â&#128;&#131;     5&#13;
&amp;#12;KYRGYZ REPUBLIC ECONOMIC REPORT NO.5â&#128;&#131; â&#128;&#147;â&#128;&#131; MARCH 2014&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
strong domestic demand reducing the amount of energy available for export. At the same time, 2013 was a&#13;
difficult year for Kyrgyz textiles producers, with Turkey and China pushing down the Kyrgyz Republicâ&#128;&#153;s market&#13;
share in Russia, following Russiaâ&#128;&#153;s accession to the WTO. Finally, an import ban introduced by the Kazakh&#13;
authorities against Kyrgyz milk processing companies (due to product safety issues) adversely affected dairy&#13;
exports.&#13;
&#13;
Strong domestic demand kept imports, and the trade deficit high in 2013. Imports increased 13 percent&#13;
y-o-y in US dollar terms in 2013. Russia remained the most important import partner, accounting for 30 percent&#13;
of official imports, mostly reflecting the Kyrgyz Republicâ&#128;&#153;s reliance on Russian energy. Around 20 percent of&#13;
official imports came from China (garments, machinery and electric equipment and metals) and around 10&#13;
percent from neighboring Kazakhstan (minerals, foodstuffs and chemicals). Russia and China continue to&#13;
provide imports to complement the infrastructure projects they are helping finance in road construction and&#13;
energy. The officially recorded trade deficit was $4,050 million or 56 percent of GDP in 2013, 0.8 percentage&#13;
points of GDP higher than in 2012.&#13;
&#13;
A relatively successful tourism season has helped improve the services balance. According to preliminary&#13;
data, services exports increased by 28 percent, while services imports increased by 8.5 percent in 2013. Aside&#13;
from hospitality and catering, the transport and communications sectors contributed positively towards an&#13;
almost positive service trade balance during this period.&#13;
&#13;
Despite relatively lackluster growth in the Russian economyâ&#128;&#148;the destination for most Kyrgyz migrantsâ&#128;&#148;&#13;
remittances continued growing in 2013. While the Russian economy only expanded 1.3 percent in 2013,&#13;
unemployment remained low at 5.6 percent; real wages and expenditures in retail trade continued growing&#13;
(albeit at a slower pace); and housing construction reported double-digit growth. These factors help explain why&#13;
Kyrgyz migrants, who are mainly employed in construction (male workers) or in retail or as domestic-workers&#13;
(female workers), continue to find income generating opportunities in Russia.4&#13;
&#13;
Capital inflows remained adequate to finance the countryâ&#128;&#153;s large current account deficit. Reinvested&#13;
earnings (mainly from Kumtor) and loans from parent companies help explain the 72 percent (y-o-y) growth in&#13;
FDI in the first 9 months of 2013. Net borrowing by the public sector amounted to $295 million.&#13;
&#13;
The Kyrgyz Republic remains at moderate risk of debt distress with the external debt to GDP ratio&#13;
expected to decline over the medium term. The most recent Bank-Fund Debt Sustainability Assessment&#13;
(DSA) confirmed that the risk of debt distress in the Kyrgyz Republic is â&#128;&#156;moderateâ&#128;&#157;   .5 While none of the debt&#13;
indicators exceed their thresholds, the country remains vulnerable to large shocks reflecting a combination of&#13;
growth, exchange rate, and overall external demand deterioration. In 2013, total external debt is estimated to&#13;
have increased slightly to around 83 percent of GDP from 81.3 percent a year ago, largely due to higher liabilities&#13;
based on foreign direct investments. At the same time, external public and publicly guaranteed debt (PPG) is&#13;
estimated to have declined to around 44 percent of GDP by the end of 2013 from 46 percent at the end of&#13;
2012, mostly due to stronger economic growth and debt forgiveness arrangement with the Russian Federation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
4	   Information on employment destinations for Kyrgyz nationals is taken from Heleniak, T. (2011). Harnessing the Diaspora for Development in Europe and Central&#13;
     Asia. Washington, DC: The World Bank.&#13;
5	   The latest DSA was conducted in October 2013.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
6â&#128;&#131;   â&#148;&#130;â&#128;&#131;   B. Recent Economic Developments&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                                           KYRGYZ REPUBLIC: GROWTH REBOUNDS, RISKS REMAIN&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Employment and Labor Markets&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Headline indicators suggest there were marginal improvements in employment during 2013. The number&#13;
of registered people in employment increased by around 8,500 during Januaryâ&#128;&#147;November 2013, and at the&#13;
same time the number of registered unemployed fell by around 2,100 (Figure 9).6 More comprehensive survey&#13;
data, which is based on a wider assessment of firms and businesses than official registrations, is only available&#13;
for 2012. While the absolute numbers between the two labor market sources are different, the trends are&#13;
generally similar, suggesting the positive results observed in the administrative data for 2013 are reason for&#13;
cautious optimism.&#13;
&#13;
Figure 9. Administrative employment data suggest                                            Figure 10. A freeze on public sector wages brought&#13;
labor participation is improving                                                            down average real wages in 2013&#13;
thousands of people                                                thousands of people      in percent&#13;
 522                                                                                   62                    Trade&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                       62      Transport &amp; Comms.&#13;
 520&#13;
                                                                                       61      Power, gas &amp; water&#13;
&#13;
 518                                                                                   61             Construction&#13;
                                                                                                        Hospitality&#13;
                                                                                       60&#13;
 516&#13;
                                                                                                      Public admin&#13;
                                                                                       60&#13;
 514                                                                                              Financial &amp; other&#13;
                                                                                       59         business services&#13;
                                                                                             Agriculture &amp; ï¬&#129;sheries&#13;
 512                                                                                   59&#13;
                                                                                                    Manufacturing&#13;
                                                                                       58&#13;
 510                                                                                            Education &amp; health&#13;
                                                                                       58&#13;
                                                                                                            Mining&#13;
 508                                                                                   57&#13;
         Jan    Feb   Mar       Apr   May     Jun    Jul   Aug    Sep     Oct   Nov&#13;
        2013   2013   2013     2013   2013   2013   2013   2013   2013   2013   2013                              -15           -10          -5           0               5&#13;
JJ Unemployed          â&#150;¬â&#150;¬ Employed, rhs&#13;
Sources: Kyrgyz authorities.                                                                Sources: Kyrgyz authorities.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Wage trends between the public and private sector diverged in 2013. Public sector employment accounts&#13;
for around 15 percent of total employment and while there were some wage increases for low paid civil&#13;
servants (who represent less than 1 percent of all public employees) most other public salaries were held&#13;
constant in 2013. This freeze had a noticeable effect on average real wages in the public sector, which in the&#13;
first eleven months of 2013, were down by 4.7 percent compared to a year ago. On the other hand, wages in&#13;
the private sector increased by 7.9 percent (1 percent increase in real teams), mainly in the trade and transport&#13;
sectors (Figure 10).&#13;
&#13;
Despite being one of the lowest paid sectors, labor productivity in agriculture has improved. Output&#13;
per worker in the agriculture sector is about 75 percent of industry, a vast improvement compared to 2000,&#13;
when the output of an agricultural worker was around 33 percent of their industry counterparts. Indeed,&#13;
agriculture has seen one of the biggest improvements in labor productivity over the past 10 years, increasing&#13;
by over 50 percent. The sector outperforms labor productivity in hospitalityâ&#128;&#148;over twice as productiveâ&#128;&#148;while&#13;
agriculture workers are paid half the average salary as someone who works in a restaurant or a hotel (Box 2).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
6	     While at first glance these figures suggest more people may have entered the labor market, the administrative data used for these indicators omits several&#13;
       important sectors, notably in the private sector. Movements in the sizeable informal economy are not captured under these official statistics either.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                  B. Recent Economic Developmentsâ&#128;&#131;   â&#148;&#130;â&#128;&#131;   7&#13;
&amp;#12;KYRGYZ REPUBLIC ECONOMIC REPORT NO.5â&#128;&#131; â&#128;&#147;â&#128;&#131; MARCH 2014&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Box 2. Changes in labor productivity 2002â&#128;&#147;2012&#13;
&#13;
     The employment structure in the Kyrgyz Republic has changed over the past 10 years, with people moving&#13;
     out of agriculture and into more urban based occupations in construction, hospitality, trade, and transport and&#13;
     communications (Figure 11). During the period 2002â&#128;&#147;2012, agriculture is the only sector where fewer people&#13;
     now work, with all other sectors gaining employees. Construction and hospitality have both witnessed a&#13;
     16 percent growth in employment.&#13;
&#13;
     Figure 11. Agriculture is the only sector to                                                       During this structural change, labor productivity (as&#13;
     employ fewer people in 2012 than 2002                                                              measured by average annual output per worker)&#13;
                                                                                                        has increased in the agriculture sector as well as in&#13;
     share of total employment&#13;
                                                                                                        mining, trade, and transport and communications. In&#13;
      120&#13;
                                                                                                        all other sectors, labor productivity has deteriorated&#13;
      100&#13;
                                                                                                        (Figure 12). This is particularly noticeable in&#13;
                                                                                                        manufacturing, where output per worker has fallen&#13;
          80                                                                                            to two thirds of its level in 2002. Most of this&#13;
                                                                                                        decline happened in the mid-2000s, and while labor&#13;
          60                                                                                            productivity was starting to pick up again in 2010&#13;
                                                                                                        and 2011, the contraction in output in the Kumtor&#13;
          40                                                                                            gold mine pushed labor productivity back down&#13;
                                                                                                        again in 2012.&#13;
          20&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
           0&#13;
                                                                                                        A basic decomposition of labor productivity&#13;
                                    2002                                       2012                     between 2002 and 2012 shows that most of the&#13;
     JJ Agriculture &amp; fisheries JJ Industry                 JJ Power, gas &amp; water     JJ Construction   improvements in labor productivity have come&#13;
     JJ Trade JJ Hospitality         JJ Transport &amp; comms.JJ Finance &amp; other business services&#13;
                                                                                                        from within sector improvements, rather than gains&#13;
     JJ Public admin.                JJ Education, health, housing &amp; other social services&#13;
                                                                                                        from people moving to more productive sectors.&#13;
     Source: Kyrgyz authorities, Bank staff calculations.&#13;
                                                                                                        This suggests there may be rigidities in the Kyrgyz&#13;
                                                                                                        labor market that are preventing people from&#13;
&#13;
     Figure 12. Labor productivity has fallen across                                                    Figure 13. Wages in the Kyrgyz Republic are&#13;
     most sectors between 2002 and 2012                                                                 loosely tied to labor productivity&#13;
     average annual output per worker, soms, 2000 prices                                                annual average output per worker, in thousand soms (2000 prices), 2012&#13;
          Power, gas &amp; water                                                                             120&#13;
                       Trade&#13;
                                                                                                                                                      Power, gas &amp; water&#13;
               Manufacturing                                                                             100&#13;
&#13;
          Transport &amp; Comms.&#13;
                                                                                                          80&#13;
                     Mining                                                                                                                                                                   Transport&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                             &amp; Comms.&#13;
           Financial &amp; other                                                                                                                                                     Trade&#13;
           business services                                                                              60&#13;
                                                                                                                                                Manufacturing&#13;
      Agriculture &amp; ï¬&#129;sheries                                                                                                                                                     Financial&#13;
                                                                                                                    Agriculture                                  Construction      &amp; other      Mining&#13;
                Construction                                                                              40        &amp; ï¬&#129;sheries                                                   business&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                        Public    services&#13;
                Public admin                                                                                                                                            admin&#13;
                 Hospitality                                                                              20             Education, health, housing             Hospitality&#13;
          Education, health,                                                                                                &amp; other social services&#13;
      housing &amp; other social&#13;
                   services                                                                                0&#13;
                               0                   50,000                100,000              150,000          0        1,000         2,000           3,000         4,000           5,000         6,000&#13;
     JJ 2012                       JJ 2002                                                                                 Average wages, soms (2000 prices), 2012&#13;
     Source: Kyrgyz authorities, Bank staff calculations.                                               Source: Kyrgyz authorities, Bank staff calculations.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     moving between jobs. A comparison of wages against labor productivity and employment size suggests&#13;
     that people are not fully migrating towards those sectors with higher compensation (Figure 13). This could&#13;
     be due to restrictions on the mobility of labor or the limited ability of people to transfer or change skills into&#13;
     different sectors. Furthermore, while there is a mild correlation between labor productivity and wages, it is&#13;
     not particularly pronouncedâ&#128;&#148;construction and hospitality workers are paid almost twice as much as people&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
8â&#128;&#131;   â&#148;&#130;â&#128;&#131;    B. Recent Economic Developments&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                                                             KYRGYZ REPUBLIC: GROWTH REBOUNDS, RISKS REMAIN&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         employed in agriculture, and yet their output is equivalent to only 75 percent or 50 percent of agriculture&#13;
         respectively.&#13;
&#13;
         These initial findings provide a snap shot of how the labor market in the Kyrgyz Republic is evolving. Further&#13;
         analysis is required to understand the drivers of these changes in labor productivity, which could include price&#13;
         effects (e.g. higher real food prices in 2012 compared to the early 2000s); improved application of knowledge&#13;
         and sector specific skills; inefficient use of capital; the impact of non-wage sources of income (e.g. food for&#13;
         people working in agriculture) and data errors whereby employment data has omitted people working in the&#13;
         informal sector.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Poverty&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Broad-based growth in 2013 suggests poverty could have stabilized. Poverty levels have deteriorated since&#13;
2008, following a number of shocks, including political upheaval, contraction in growth and increases in food&#13;
prices. Strong growth in 2013, combined with low food prices, stable energy prices, and resilient remittances,&#13;
should have helped halt, if not reverse the negative trends of earlier years. In addition, the government&#13;
introduced increases to pensions, and some social allowances, which may have helped those households&#13;
most at risk of falling into poverty.&#13;
&#13;
Aside from children, the self-employed, or people detached from the formal labor market, are most at&#13;
risk of falling into poverty in the Kyrgyz Republic. Over half of all self-employed people are living in poverty,&#13;
reflecting the subsistence nature of employment of most self-employed people in the Kyrgyz Republic.7&#13;
Estimates show that almost half of all under-14 year olds were living in poverty in 2010; this compares to between&#13;
20â&#128;&#147;25 percent of 45+ years old. At the same time, 30 or 40 percent of people with basic or little educationâ&#128;&#148;&#13;
general education or belowâ&#128;&#148;are also likely to be living on less than $2.50 a day. Ensuring opportunities for&#13;
Kyrgyz Republicâ&#128;&#153;s young people therefore remains essential, so as to avoid losing a generation to poverty&#13;
(Figures 14 and 15).&#13;
&#13;
Figure 14. The self-employed and children are most                                                             Figure 15. Completion of secondary and tertiary&#13;
at risk of being in poverty                                                                                    education helps reduce the risk of poverty&#13;
in percent, poverty rate                                                                                       in percent, poverty rate&#13;
 60                                                                                                             45&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                40&#13;
 50&#13;
                                                                                                                35&#13;
 40                                                                                                             30&#13;
&#13;
 30                                                                                                             25&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                20&#13;
 20&#13;
                                                                                                                15&#13;
&#13;
 10                                                                                                             10&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                 5&#13;
     0&#13;
               ent         yee         ed       al          LF             ed         ren                 ed&#13;
           tud         plo        etir      Tot        t of            loy       hild                 loy        0&#13;
          S          Em          R                   Ou             mp          C&#13;
                                                                                               f-em&#13;
                                                                                                   p&#13;
                                                                 Une                        Sel                        None &lt; 4       General education    Incomplete 5â&#128;&#147;12   Special secondary   Tertiary&#13;
Source: http://datavizint.worldbank.org, 2010 data.                                                            Source: http://datavizint.worldbank.org, 2010 data.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
7	       A large proportion of people classed as self-employed live in rural areas and work on small plots of land or farms. The food they produce is mainly subsistence&#13;
         rather than cash crops.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                          B. Recent Economic Developmentsâ&#128;&#131;          â&#148;&#130;â&#128;&#131;      9&#13;
&amp;#12;KYRGYZ REPUBLIC ECONOMIC REPORT NO.5â&#128;&#131; â&#128;&#147;â&#128;&#131; MARCH 2014&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
C. Economic and Structural Policies&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Fiscal Policy&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Restrained government spending and robust revenues helped bring the fiscal deficit down to 3.5 percent&#13;
of GDP in 2013. This is much lower than the 5.2 percent of GDP the authorities targeted in the 2013 budget, and&#13;
the 5.3 percent of GDP recorded in 2012 (Figure 16). Financing sources exceeded the financing requirements,&#13;
resulting in an increase in government deposits and improvement in the budgetâ&#128;&#153;s liquidity. The IMF   , the World&#13;
Bank, ADB, and China were the main sources of finance for the fiscal deficit.&#13;
&#13;
A combination of higher growth and tax policy changes helped keep revenues high in 2013. The&#13;
government introduced a number of tax policy changes in 2013, including: an increased sales tax on mobile&#13;
telecommunications, changes to income tax in the mining sector, and higher excise duties on alcohol and&#13;
tobacco. Income tax collection in 2013 fell to 4.9 percent of GDP  , from 6.2 percent of GDP a year ago, owing to&#13;
lower income taxes from the Kumtor gold mineâ&#128;&#148;Kumtor made an advanced tax payment in 2012 against tax&#13;
liabilities in 2013. This was largely off-set by the robust performance of customs and excises, which grew by&#13;
0.3 percentage points of GDP each, to reach 3.4 and 1.2 percent of GDP respectively. Value added tax continues&#13;
to be the largest single source of revenues providing 8.6 percent of GDP (same as in 2012), while the sales tax&#13;
contributed 1.9 percent of GDP to the budget. Social contributions added 4.8 percent of GDP to government&#13;
revenues, largely unchanged from 2012.&#13;
&#13;
A nominal wage freeze for most of the public              Figure 16. The fiscal deficit was lower than&#13;
sector was a key factor in the 2013 fiscal                originally projected in 2013&#13;
adjustment. Wages were held constant for most of          in percent of GDP&#13;
&#13;
the public sector in 2013, bringing total wages and         45&#13;
&#13;
salaries expenditures down to 7      .9 percent of GDP      40&#13;
                                                            35&#13;
from 8.7 percent of GDP in 2012. Lower paid public          30&#13;
servants, especially those in the civil service, were       25&#13;
&#13;
granted a pay rise in the second half of the year, but      20&#13;
                                                            15&#13;
this did little to the overall impact of a freeze on the    10&#13;
rest of the public sector. Capital spending fell from        5&#13;
&#13;
7.7 percent of GDP in 2012 to 7    .0 percent of GDP in      0&#13;
&#13;
2013, which is still high compared to the levels seen       -5&#13;
                                                           -10&#13;
throughout most of the 2000s. While spending on                     2008           2009         2010          2011     2012 2013&#13;
&#13;
goods and services also declined (by 0.3 percentage       JJ Expenditures       JJ Revenues &amp; grants â&#150;¬â&#150;¬ Fiscal balance&#13;
&#13;
points of GDP), due to controlled spending on             Sources: Kyrgyz authorities.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
utilities and transport, a large part of the reduction&#13;
reflects the wage freeze in the health sectorâ&#128;&#148;health services are financed through output-based mechanisms&#13;
and are recorded as purchases of goods and services in the state budget (Table 1).&#13;
&#13;
There are concerns that the reduction in the fiscal deficit in 2013 may be temporary, given the one-off&#13;
nature of public sector wage freezes. The government is likely to come under pressure to increase wages&#13;
given inflation is averaging around 5â&#128;&#147;7 percent. Furthermore, ad hoc wage freezes could impact the public&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
10â&#128;&#131;   â&#148;&#130;â&#128;&#131;   C. Economic and Structural Policies&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                  KYRGYZ REPUBLIC: GROWTH REBOUNDS, RISKS REMAIN&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
sectorâ&#128;&#153;s ability to attract and retain qualified staff. The   Table 1. Selected Fiscal Indicators&#13;
government has introduced a civil-service reform              in percent of GDP&#13;
package which should help improve the transparency                                                             2012         2013*&#13;
and planning of future wage decisions. However,               Total revenues and grants                        33.8          34.0&#13;
the package will take time to fully implement. At the             Tax revenues                                 25.5          25.6&#13;
same time, significant infrastructure gaps suggest                Non-tax revenues                               5.6             5.6&#13;
capital spending will need to stay around 7 percent&#13;
                                                                  Grants                                         2.5             2.6&#13;
if public services, such as electricity provision and&#13;
                                                              Total expenditure (incl. net lending)            39.0              37.4&#13;
road quality, are to be improved.&#13;
                                                                  Current expenditures                          31.8         30.5&#13;
                                                                  Wages                                          8.7              7.9&#13;
Structural reforms remain imperative for&#13;
                                                               Transfer and subsidies                3.5      3.5&#13;
medium fiscal sustainability and improved public&#13;
service delivery. Reducing the fiscal deficit over             Transfer to SF                        3.4      3.8&#13;
&#13;
the medium-term remains one of the key objectives              Interest                              0.9      0.9&#13;
of the governmentâ&#128;&#153;s mid-term economic program.                 Goods and services                    9.1      8.8&#13;
The 2014 budget targets a slight widening of the               Capital     expenditure               7.7      7.0&#13;
deficit to 4.3 percent of GDP  , mostly reflecting the         Net lending                          -0.4     -0.1&#13;
decline in revenues due to the close of the Manas         Overall balance                           -5.3     -3.5&#13;
Transit Center. The deficit is projected to decline to    Source:  Kyrgyz Republic authorities.&#13;
                                                          * 2013 figures are preliminary&#13;
3.6 percent and 2 percent of GDP in 2015 and 2016,&#13;
respectively. While fiscal adjustment is expected to&#13;
come from restraining current spending, the policies required to bring the fiscal deficit down have not yet been&#13;
developed. There are a number of areas where expenditures could be brought down and social outcomes&#13;
improved e.g. better targeting of social welfare programs, but these reforms could take time to implement.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Monetary and Exchange Rate Policies&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The central bank tightened monetary policy during the second half of the year to bring down core&#13;
inflation. The National Bank of the Kyrgyz Republic (NBKR) increased its key policy rate from 2.6 percent in&#13;
December 2012 to 4.2 percent in December 2013. Despite this increase, the rate still remains negative in real&#13;
terms. Money and credit have yet to be impacted by the rate change, reflected in the slowdown in growth of&#13;
broad money (M2)â&#128;&#148;a key intermediate target for the central bankâ&#128;&#148;from 23.8 percent in December 2012 to&#13;
20.8 percent in December 2013 (y-o-y). Growth in credit to the private sector increased to 34.5 percent (y-o-y)&#13;
in December 2013 from 28.5 percent a year earlier, with most of the expansion in industry and agriculture. The&#13;
impact of the credit expansion over monetary aggregates was off-set by increased deposits of the government&#13;
in the NBKR.&#13;
&#13;
The nominal exchange rate has come under pressure in early 2014. Interventions in the foreign exchange&#13;
market were limited during 2013 with the central bank making a single intervention in April 2013. However, the&#13;
NBKR has already intervened four times in 2014. While the exchange rate depreciated by 3.8 percent against&#13;
the US dollar during the whole of 2013, it lost 4.9 percent of its value during the first 6 weeks of 2014. The&#13;
NBKR has modest capacity to defend its value. Foreign exchange reserves only cover around 3 months of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                     C. Economic and Structural Policiesâ&#128;&#131;   â&#148;&#130;â&#128;&#131;   11&#13;
&amp;#12;KYRGYZ REPUBLIC ECONOMIC REPORT NO.5â&#128;&#131; â&#128;&#147;â&#128;&#131; MARCH 2014&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
imports of goods and services. The coverage of monetary aggregates at around 90 percent of broad money&#13;
(M2) and 180 percent of currency in circulation (M0) are more re-assuring.&#13;
&#13;
While the real effective exchange rate is broadly           Figure 17. The REER is broadly appropriate&#13;
appropriate, the recent devaluations of currencies          index 2000=100&#13;
in the region could put it under pressure.                   120&#13;
&#13;
According to the most recent IMF assessment, the             118&#13;
&#13;
real effective exchange rate is appropriate and in line      116&#13;
&#13;
                                                             114&#13;
with macroeconomic fundamentals (Figure 17). The&#13;
                                                             112&#13;
adjustment in the nominal som exchange rate has              110&#13;
kept the real exchange rate in line with the Russian         108&#13;
&#13;
ruble and Kazakhstan tengeâ&#128;&#148;which devalued by                 106&#13;
&#13;
20 percent on 11 February, 2014. However if the              104&#13;
&#13;
som were to devalue faster than its neighbors,               102&#13;
&#13;
                                                             100&#13;
this could push up the price of imports, adversely                  Jan&#13;
                                                                   2011&#13;
                                                                          May&#13;
                                                                          2011&#13;
                                                                                    Sep&#13;
                                                                                    2011&#13;
                                                                                             Jan&#13;
                                                                                             2012&#13;
                                                                                                      May&#13;
                                                                                                      2012&#13;
                                                                                                             Sep&#13;
                                                                                                             2012&#13;
                                                                                                                     Jan&#13;
                                                                                                                    2013&#13;
                                                                                                                            May&#13;
                                                                                                                            2013&#13;
                                                                                                                                   Sep&#13;
                                                                                                                                   2013&#13;
affecting businesses relying on imports, as well as         â&#150;¬â&#150;¬ REER               â&#150;¬â&#150;¬ NEER&#13;
&#13;
households consuming mostly imported food. On               Source: National Bank of the Kyrgyz Republic.&#13;
&#13;
the upside, the competitiveness of Kyrgyz products&#13;
would be restored in traditional markets.                   Table 2. Selected banking and monetary sector&#13;
                                                            indicators&#13;
The banking sector remains sound and able to                in percent, unless otherwise indicated&#13;
&#13;
support growth. While the capital to risk-weighted                                                                         2012    2013*&#13;
asset ratio fell to 25 percent in 2013 owing to an          Gross official reserves (millions US dollars)                  2,067   2,238&#13;
increase in credit to the private sector, it remains well   Gross official reserves (months of imports)                      3.9      3.3&#13;
above the legal minimum threshold of 12 percent,            Nominal exchange rate (som per US$ p.a.)                       47.01   48.44&#13;
suggesting there is significant capacity in the sector      Real effective exchange rate                                    -0.1     -0.4&#13;
should opportunities for growth emerge. Other               (annual change)&#13;
financial indicators also indicate improvements in          Credit to the private sector (annual change)                    26.2    34.5&#13;
the stability of the sector. Non-performing loans           Nonperforming loans                                              7.2      5.5&#13;
(NPLs) for example, declined to 5.5 percent in 2013,        (as a share of total loans)&#13;
the lowest level since 2009 (Table 2).                      Return on equity                                                18.5    18.0&#13;
                                                            Return on assets                                                 3.0      2.8&#13;
                                                            Source: Kyrgyz Republic authorities.&#13;
                                                            * 2013 figures are preliminary&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Structural Reforms&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The Kyrgyz Republic scores relatively well on â&#128;&#156;the ease of doing businessâ&#128;&#157;          , as measured under the World&#13;
Bankâ&#128;&#153;s Doing Business (DB) survey, however there is variability across the indicators. The Kyrgyz Republic&#13;
was ranked 68 in the 2014 DB publication. This places the Kyrgyz Republic at 12 in the Eastern Europe and&#13;
Central Asia (ECA) region (second in Central Asia to Kazakhstan) and second out of the low income countries&#13;
assessed by the DB team.8 While registering a business, getting credit, registering a property and protecting&#13;
investors are all ranked within the top 25 countries, getting electricity, paying taxes and the trading environment&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
8	   Rwanda is the best performing low-income country.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
12â&#128;&#131;   â&#148;&#130;â&#128;&#131;   C. Economic and Structural Policies&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                                KYRGYZ REPUBLIC: GROWTH REBOUNDS, RISKS REMAIN&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
continue to hamper the business environment                                            Figure 18. The performance of the Kyrgyz Republic&#13;
(Figure 18).9                                                                          against the Doing Business indicators is mixed&#13;
                                                                                       Rank, 1= best performing, 189 = worst performing&#13;
&#13;
Recent reforms in tax administration and                                                          Ease of Doing Business Rank&#13;
inspections should help ameliorate some of                                   Resolving insolvency&#13;
                                                                                                            200&#13;
                                                                                                                             Starting a business&#13;
                                                                                                            150&#13;
the burden facing businesses. Tax administration                                                            100&#13;
&#13;
is a major constraint in the Kyrgyz Republic with&#13;
                                                                      Enforcing contracts                    50&#13;
                                                                                                                                       Dealing with construction&#13;
                                                                                                                                       permits&#13;
                                                                                                             25&#13;
32 percent of firms identifying it as a barrier to                                                            0&#13;
&#13;
do business, compared to only 20 percent in the                  Trading across borders                                                 Getting electricity&#13;
&#13;
rest of ECA. An Asian Development Bank (ADB)&#13;
funded project to automate tax returns has recently                             Paying taxes                                      Registering property&#13;
&#13;
concluded, and while not yet fully operational, the                                  Protecting i nvestors            Getting credit&#13;
&#13;
systemâ&#128;&#153;s e-filling capabilities could vastly reduce&#13;
the time taken by businesses filing tax receipts          Source: National Bank of the Source: Doing Business 2014, Understanding Regulations for&#13;
                                                          Small and Medium-Size Enterprises. Kyrgyz Republic.&#13;
as well as the possibility for corrupt activities. The&#13;
reduction in the number of tax forms, and simplified&#13;
accounting rules for small and micro enterprises represents another positive step towards more efficient tax&#13;
administration. Progress is also being made in the area of risk-based inspections, although more needs to be&#13;
done to improve the accountability and transparency of the existing system.&#13;
&#13;
Despite progress in customs automation, the trade facilitation environment remains difficult to navigate.&#13;
The introduction of ASYCUDA based software is a welcome addition to the borders and trading posts of the&#13;
Kyrgyz Republic. The automation of checks and balances should help reduce corruption, as well as improve&#13;
transparency and reduce the time taken by importers and exporters. In addition, the Ministry of Justice&#13;
has issued a resolution reducing the number of documents needed to trade down to 2 from 8. While these&#13;
measures are praiseworthy, more needs to be done to address the poor trading environment, as reflected in&#13;
the Logistics Performance Indicators (ranked 130 out of 155 in 2012), and the Doing Business trading across&#13;
borders indicator (182 out of 189).&#13;
&#13;
The World Trade Organizationâ&#128;&#153;s (WTO) 2013 Trade Policy Review noted several positive developments in&#13;
the Kyrgyz Republic, while also highlighting areas for improvement and issues relating to the Customs&#13;
Union. The WTO praised the Kyrgyz Republic for the reforms put in place so far, including the countryâ&#128;&#153;s open&#13;
trade regimeâ&#128;&#148;the average MFN tariff at 5 percent is one of the lowest among WTO members. At the same&#13;
time, they also flagged issues that need further reform, including reducing the number of bound tariff rates&#13;
(currently over 90 lines) and improving the way SPS measures are managed. Following the Kyrgyz Republicâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
confirmed intention to accede to the Russia, Kazakhstan, Belarus Customs Union, the WTO stressed the&#13;
importance of remaining open and minimizing any disruptions to the trading environment, which could be&#13;
significant given the enormity of the endeavor.10&#13;
&#13;
Improvements in governance and transparency indicators suggest public finance management reforms&#13;
could be taking effect, though overall scores still remain low. The Kyrgyz Republicâ&#128;&#153;s rankings under&#13;
Transparency Internationalâ&#128;&#153;s corruption index and the rule of law and control of corruption sub-scores under the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
9	   The Kyrgyz Republic was ranked 127 in the 2014 Doing Business report for Paying Taxes. While this is a large improvement from the 168 rank in 2013, the shift is&#13;
     due to a change in how the DB team calculates the total tax rate in the Kyrgyz Republic, rather than a reflection of a tax policy change.&#13;
10	 The Kyrgyz Republicâ&#128;&#153; Trade Policy Review was released in November 2013, and can be found at : http://www.wto.org/english/tratop_e/tpr_e/s288_e.pdf&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                   C. Economic and Structural Policiesâ&#128;&#131;      â&#148;&#130;â&#128;&#131;   13&#13;
&amp;#12;KYRGYZ REPUBLIC ECONOMIC REPORT NO.5â&#128;&#131; â&#128;&#147;â&#128;&#131; MARCH 2014&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Worldwide Governance Indicators all registered an improvement in 2012 (Figures 19 and 20).11 This is possibly&#13;
a reflection of recent reforms including the introduction of e-procurement; the open budget portal; and the&#13;
ongoing process of declaring and verifying assets of senior public officials.&#13;
&#13;
Figure 19. There has been a mild improvement in                                      Figure 20. â&#128;¦as well as their implementation of the&#13;
the Kyrgyz Republicâ&#128;&#153;s â&#128;&#156;control of corruptionâ&#128;&#157;â&#128;¦                                       â&#128;&#156;rule of lawâ&#128;&#157;&#13;
percentile ranking score: -1 (worst) to 1 (best)                                     percentile ranking score: -1 (worst) to 1 (best)&#13;
 45                                                                             0     30                                                                             0&#13;
&#13;
 40                                                                                                                                                                -0.2&#13;
                                                                              -0.2    25&#13;
 35&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                   -0.4&#13;
                                                                              -0.4&#13;
 30                                                                                   20&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                   -0.6&#13;
 25                                                                           -0.6&#13;
                                                                                      15                                                                           -0.8&#13;
 20                                                                           -0.8&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                   -1.0&#13;
 15                                                                                   10&#13;
                                                                              -1.0&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                   -1.2&#13;
 10&#13;
                                                                              -1.2     5&#13;
  5                                                                                                                                                                -1.4&#13;
&#13;
  0                                                                           -1.4     0                                                                           -1.6&#13;
      1996 1998 2000 2002 2003 2004 2005 2006 2007 2008 2009 2010 2011 2012                1996 1998 2000 2002 2003 2004 2005 2006 2007 2008 2009 2010 2011 2012&#13;
JJ Percentile ranking   â&#150;¬â&#150;¬ Score                                                     JJ Percentile ranking   â&#150;¬â&#150;¬ Score&#13;
Source: Worldwide Governance Indicators.                                             Source: Worldwide Governance Indicators.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Anti-corruption measures continue to be at the top of the governmentâ&#128;&#153;s agenda. The President of the&#13;
Kyrgyz Republic signed a decree in November 2013 â&#128;&#156;On measures to address the causes of the political and&#13;
systemic corruption in government structures.    â&#128;&#157; This decree mandates 15 key ministries to present their anti-&#13;
corruption plans and initial results to the Defense Council. Alongside these measures, the State Television and&#13;
Radio Corporation have been authorized to launch a public education campaign to cultivate zero tolerance of&#13;
corruption among the countryâ&#128;&#153;s citizens. The agenda on controlling corruption does however remain large and&#13;
will require continued commitment.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
11	 The Kyrgyz Republic moved up to 150 (out of 177 countries) in Transparency Internationalâ&#128;&#153;s corruption index in 2013, from 154 (out of 176) in 2012. The score&#13;
    however remains the same.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
14â&#128;&#131;    â&#148;&#130;â&#128;&#131;   C. Economic and Structural Policies&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                            KYRGYZ REPUBLIC: GROWTH REBOUNDS, RISKS REMAIN&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Outlook&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
GDP growth is expected to moderate to 5 percent in 2014, as expansion in the mining sector slows.&#13;
Previous GDP forecasts were around 6 percent for 2014, with strong contributions from gold output. These earlier&#13;
projections assumed the recovery of gold production from 2012 would continue into 2014. The unprecedented&#13;
output from Kumtor in the last half of 2013, however, suggests growth from gold will be flat in 2014.&#13;
&#13;
Domestic demand is expected to continue driving growth in the non-gold sector to around 5â&#128;&#147;6 percent.&#13;
Growth of credit issued to the private sector, increases to social allowances, rising wages, and strong workersâ&#128;&#153;&#13;
remittances are likely to continue driving private consumption in the medium-term. Public investment will also&#13;
play a role, as government continues ramping up capital spending to address significant infrastructure gaps&#13;
(the 2014 budget envisages a 17 percent increase in investments). A preliminary assessment of the external&#13;
environment; the potential of the banking sector; and preliminary budget projections, suggests these factors&#13;
will continue stimulating domestic demand and thus non-gold growth for the next 2â&#128;&#147;3 years.&#13;
&#13;
While external forecasters expect gold prices to stabilize in 2014, there are number of downside risks.&#13;
Recent industry estimates project a mild increase in the annual average gold price in 2014 (around 2 percent,&#13;
compared to a 20 percent fall a year ago). A slightly weaker outlook of emerging markets has reduced their&#13;
attractiveness, meaning investors could turn their attention back to gold. There are however, relatively large&#13;
differences between industry forecasts, possibly as a result of a number of uncertainties. In particular, a rise&#13;
in US interest rates following improved growth prospects, combined with more optimistic views of emerging&#13;
marketsâ&#128;&#153; financial systems could push down demand and therefore the price for gold. If gold prices were to&#13;
drop below $1,000 per troy ounce, Kumtorâ&#128;&#153;s profitability could suffer.&#13;
&#13;
A slowdown in the Russian economy would dampen growth prospects in the Kyrgyz Republic. GDP is&#13;
forecast to expand around 2.5 percent in the Russian Federation in 2014, however, volatility during January&#13;
may mean turbulences are set to continue, bringing forecasts down. Growth rate projections may be adversely&#13;
affected by lower than anticipated growth in China, and a continuation of tapering in the US, putting additional&#13;
pressure on the ruble. This would negatively affect the Kyrgyz Republic, as a country that relies heavily on&#13;
Russia as a consumer of Kyrgyz products, and as an employer of Kyrgyz workers. While remittances have&#13;
remained strong in recent years, stalling investment activities could reduce the number of jobs available for&#13;
migrant workers.&#13;
&#13;
On the upside, the recent resolution with Kumtor should help restore investor confidence. Centerraâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
share prices have fallen by around 30 percent since September 2013, in part because of the uncertainties&#13;
surrounding the Kumtor gold mine. Business leaders have expressed concerns that the protracted debate about&#13;
the potential nationalization of the countryâ&#128;&#153;s largest gold mine has harmed the broader investment climate.&#13;
Despite significant mineral reserves of gold, uranium and coal, Kumtor remains the only operational mine in&#13;
the Kyrgyz Republic. New gold minesâ&#128;&#148;Ishtamberdy and Bosumâ&#128;&#148;have been in the pipeline for the past three&#13;
years but have yet to come online. Perhaps now the uncertainty alongside Kumtor has, for the moment, been&#13;
resolved, other investors may feel more assured that their property rights will be protected.&#13;
&#13;
Investment in infrastructureâ&#128;&#148;roads and energyâ&#128;&#148;will also continue to support both short and medium&#13;
term growth. The largest investment projects include the rehabilitation of the Bishkek-Naryn-Torugart road, the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                         Outlookâ&#128;&#131;   â&#148;&#130;â&#128;&#131;   15&#13;
&amp;#12;KYRGYZ REPUBLIC ECONOMIC REPORT NO.5â&#128;&#131; â&#128;&#147;â&#128;&#131; MARCH 2014&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Osh-Batken-Isfana road and the Taraz-Talas-Suusamyr road; and the construction of the Kambar-Ata 1 and Upper&#13;
Naryn hydro power plants. Aside from stimulating short term demand through standard investment multiplier&#13;
effects, these investments should help improve both the quality and magnitude of medium-term growth.&#13;
&#13;
The 4.3 percent of GDP target for the budget deficit in 2014 may not be achieved given the closure of&#13;
the Manas Transit center, and limited progress on structural spending cuts. Until 2013, the Manas transit&#13;
center contributed $120 million a year to the budget, approximately 5 percent of total revenues. Its closure,&#13;
combined with estimated lower gold export receipts in 2014 compared to 2013, will bring revenues down.&#13;
Furthermore, the government is likely to come under pressure to increases wages in 2014 following the freeze&#13;
for most public sector workers in 2013. Unless systematic expenditure cuts can be found elsewhere, the fiscal&#13;
deficit could exceed the target of 4.3 percent of GDP.&#13;
&#13;
Low international food prices should help keep inflation around 6â&#128;&#147;7 percent in 2014. Global food prices&#13;
are expected to stay low in 2014, as the effects of the good harvests in 2013 roll into 2014. Low imported grain&#13;
and wheat prices should help offset any price increases of locally produced foods in the Kyrgyz Republic. Core&#13;
inflation is expected to remain elevated with monetary policy tightening having a limited effect on private sector&#13;
credit growth.&#13;
&#13;
Inflationary pressures could materialize if larger adjustments are made to the exchange rate in response&#13;
to developments in the region. This could easily put inflation back into the double-digit levels. A 2005 study&#13;
estimated the average long-run pass-through from exchange rate changes in a sample of developing countries&#13;
at around 0.6â&#128;&#147;0.8 (meaning a 10 percent exchange rate change will increase inflation by 6â&#128;&#147;8 percent).12 The&#13;
Kyrgyz Republic shares some of the characteristics (including small size, import dependent, limited domestic&#13;
production) of countries that had higher pass-through rates, suggesting the impact could be even greater.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                              â&#128;&#157; Economics Bulletin, Vol. 3, No.&#13;
12	 Karim, BARHOUMI, (2005) â&#128;&#156;Exchange Rate Passâ&#136;&#146;Through Into Import Prices In Developing Countries: An Empirical Investigation.&#13;
    26 pp. 1â&#136;&#146;14&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
16â&#128;&#131;   â&#148;&#130;â&#128;&#131;Outlook&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                          KYRGYZ REPUBLIC: GROWTH REBOUNDS, RISKS REMAIN&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Appendix&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Appendix 1. Economic and Social Indicators â&#128;&#147; Kyrgyz Republic 2008â&#128;&#147;2015&#13;
                                                               2008     2009     2010       2011     2012      2013      2014        2015&#13;
                                                                                                                 (e)    projections&#13;
Income and Economic Growth&#13;
GDP growth (percent change)                                      8.4      2.9      -0.5         6      -0.1     10.5       5.0           5.0&#13;
GDP per capita (US dollars)                                     972      864       875     1,120     1,157    1,305     1,403       1,553&#13;
Private consumption growth (percent change)                     12.6    -14.4      2.7        9.3     14.2      13.0       5.4            7.2&#13;
Gross domestic investment (percent of GDP)                      20.2     22.9     23.9      24.1      26.7      26.9      27.0           27.0&#13;
   Public                                                        4.2      5.0      5.4        5.5       7.7      7.0        7.3           7.4&#13;
   Private                                                      16.1     17.8     18.5       18.6       19      19.9      19.7       19.6&#13;
Gross national savings (percent of GDP)                          4.7     20.4      17.5      17.5      11.7     16.5      18.6        19.3&#13;
Money and Prices&#13;
Consumer price inflation (percent change, year-end)             20.1        0     19.2        5.7       7.5      4.0          7             7&#13;
Consumer price inflation (percent change, annual average)       24.5      6.8       7.8      16.6      2.8       6.6       5.5              7&#13;
Nominal exchange rate (som per dollar, end-year)              39.42     44.09     47.1     46.48       47.4     49.2        â&#128;¦              â&#128;¦&#13;
Real exchange rate (2000=100)                                  111.0    103.0     111.3     112.5    112.6     113.4        â&#128;¦              â&#128;¦&#13;
Fiscal&#13;
Revenues                                                        29.9     32.1     30.5       31.8     33.8        34      32.1       30.8&#13;
Expenditures                                                    29.3     36.1     36.6       36.3       39      37.4      36.4       34.4&#13;
   Current                                                      24.8     28.4       31       30.9     31.8      30.5      28.8       26.3&#13;
   Capital                                                       4.2        5      5.4        5.5       7.7       7.0       7.3           7.4&#13;
Fiscal balance before grants                                     -1.9    -8.6      -9.1       -7.8     -7.9     -6.1       -6.4          -5.2&#13;
Fiscal balance after grants                                        0     -3.5      -6.3      -4.6      -5.3     -3.5       -4.3          -3.6&#13;
External debt (millions of US dollars)                        2,569     3,114    4,381     4,872     5,403    5,790         â&#128;¦              â&#128;¦&#13;
External public debt                                            41.2     52.8     55.1       45.9     45.9      43.7        â&#128;¦              â&#128;¦&#13;
Total public debt                                               48.5       58     60.3       50.1     50.5      47.8        â&#128;¦              â&#128;¦&#13;
Public debt service ratio (percent of revenues)                  5.3      5.5      6.1         7.0    12.3      13.7        â&#128;¦              â&#128;¦&#13;
External Accounts                                           (In millions of US dollars unless otherwise indicated)&#13;
Export growth (percent change, constant prices)                  9.1      -1.1    -11.7      16.5    -36.4      12.1      10.9            8.2&#13;
Import growth (percent change, constant prices)                 13.6    -19.4      -6.9      13.7     35.9      12.8       6.0            6.7&#13;
Merchandise exports                                            1,874    1,694    1,833     2,365     1,951    2,447      2,525      2,610&#13;
   of which: gold                                               464      530       668     1,006       525      737        675           644&#13;
Merchandise imports                                            3,767    2,828    2,993     4,022     4,897    5,407      5,678      6,024&#13;
Services, net                                                  -96.8     -9.1    -231.1     -20.9 -253.3          â&#128;¦          â&#128;¦             â&#128;¦&#13;
Workersâ&#128;&#153; remittances, net                                      1,430    1,012    1,313     1,755     1,917    2,200          â&#128;¦             â&#128;¦&#13;
Current account balance after grants                            -843     -313     -384       -453     -757      -743      -619           -599&#13;
   as percent of GDP                                           -16.4     -6.7        -8       -7.3    -11.7    -10.4       -8.4           -7.7&#13;
Foreign direct investment                                        410     190       438       694       292     535*        396           421&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                        Appendixâ&#128;&#131;   â&#148;&#130;â&#128;&#131;   17&#13;
&amp;#12;KYRGYZ REPUBLIC ECONOMIC REPORT NO.5â&#128;&#131; â&#128;&#147;â&#128;&#131; MARCH 2014&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Population, Employment and Poverty&#13;
Population (millions)                                                                               5.3           5.4          5.5          5.5          5.5          5.5     5.6      5.6&#13;
Population growth (percent change)                                                                     1          2.7          1.1           1.1          1.1          1.0     1.0     1.0&#13;
Unemployment rate (percent of labor force)                                                          8.2           8.4          8.6          8.5          8.4           â&#128;¦       â&#128;¦       â&#128;¦&#13;
Poverty headcount (percent of the population)&#13;
     national poverty line1                                                                        31.7         31.7         33.7         36.8            38           â&#128;¦       â&#128;¦       â&#128;¦&#13;
     At US$ 1.25 a day PPP                                                                          6.4           6.2          6.7          5.0            â&#128;¦           â&#128;¦       â&#128;¦       â&#128;¦&#13;
     At US$ 2 a day PPP                                                                            20.7         21.7         22.9          21.6            â&#128;¦           â&#128;¦       â&#128;¦       â&#128;¦&#13;
Gini coefficient (income)                                                                          37.3         36.2         36.5         33.4             â&#128;¦           â&#128;¦       â&#128;¦       â&#128;¦&#13;
Life expectancy (years) 2                                                                          68.5         69.1         69.4         69.6            70           â&#128;¦       â&#128;¦       â&#128;¦&#13;
Other&#13;
GDP (billions of local currency units)                                                              188          201          220          286           310          350     391     438&#13;
GDP (millions of US dollars) 3                                                                   5,131        4,683        4,794        6,199         6,605          7,226   7,848   8,776&#13;
Doing Business Rank 4                                                                                68            41           44           70           70           68      â&#128;¦       â&#128;¦&#13;
Human Development Index ranking 5                                                                0.616        0.617        0.615        0.621         0.622            â&#128;¦       â&#128;¦       â&#128;¦&#13;
CPIA (overall rating)                                                                                3.7          3.7          3.7          3.6          3.6           â&#128;¦       â&#128;¦       â&#128;¦&#13;
      Economic Management                                                                            4.2          4.2          4.2          4.2             4          â&#128;¦       â&#128;¦       â&#128;¦&#13;
      Structural Policies                                                                            4.2          3.8          3.8          3.7          3.7           â&#128;¦       â&#128;¦       â&#128;¦&#13;
      Social Inclusion and Equity Policies                                                           3.6          3.6          3.6          3.6          3.6           â&#128;¦       â&#128;¦       â&#128;¦&#13;
      Public Sector Management and Institutions                                                      3.0          3.0          3.0          3.0          3.1           â&#128;¦       â&#128;¦       â&#128;¦&#13;
                                    ...&#13;
(e) Indicates Bank Staff estimates, â&#128;&#156; â&#128;&#157; indicates not available.&#13;
* Data is only available for the first 9 months of 2013&#13;
1/ Nationally reported poverty lines were re-estimated in 2008 and 2012&#13;
2/ As reported by the Kyrgyz Republic National Statistics Committee&#13;
3/ Based on a constant som per dollar exchange rate of 49.2&#13;
4/ This indicator is ranked out of 175 countries in 2006 and 2007, 178 in 2008, 181 in 2009, 183 in 2010 and 2011, 185 in 2012 and 189 in 2013.&#13;
5/ The HDI ranking in 2001 is in relation to 175 countries; from 2005 to 2008, to 177; in 2009, to 181; in 2010, to 169 countries; and, in 2011, to 187 countries.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
18â&#128;&#131;    â&#148;&#130;â&#128;&#131;Appendix&#13;
&amp;#12;&amp;#12;&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="19456167">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2014/03/19456167/kyrgyz-republic-growth-rebounds-risks-remain
        </url>
        <availablein>Russian,English</availablein>
        <fullavailablein>
            <available_in lang="Russian" entityid="000442464_20140501115730" node_id="19456167"/>
        </fullavailablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2014/03/19456167/kyrgyz-republic-growth-rebounds-risks-remain</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2014/03/19456167/kyrgyz-republic-growth-rebounds-risks-remain</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2014-05-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2014-05-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2014/05/01/000442464_20140501115430/Rendered/INDEX/878020WP0ECSP100Box385200B00PUBLIC0.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2014/05/01/000442464_20140501115430/Rendered/PDF/878020WP0ECSP100Box385200B00PUBLIC0.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2014-03-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2014-05-01T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Kyrgyz Republic - Growth rebounds, risks remain
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The Kyrgyz Republic's three party
            coalition has tackled a number of events during 2013,
            including mayoral elections in the country's biggest
            cities Bishkek and Osh road blockages around Kumtor, the
            country's largest gold mine; as well as tense
            negotiations on the future of the mine; and clashes in the
            south of the country. The government has navigated through
            these difficult times, quashing a motion of no confidence in
            parliament. An agreement between the Kyrgyz Republic and
            Centerra Inc. the majority stakeholder in Kumtor was
            accepted by parliament in early 2014. A surge in gold output
            and solid growth in the non-gold sectors contributed to an
            impressive 10.5 percent expansion of the Kyrgyz economy in
            2013. Smaller increases in food prices than in recent years,
            and relatively stable energy prices helped bring inflation
            down. Expenditure controls and robust revenue outturns have
            brought the fiscal deficit down to 3.5 percent of gross
            domestic product (GDP). Preliminary estimates suggest the
            trade deficit and current account deficit remained high in
            2013. Medium term growth is expected to moderate to 5
            percent, however, a number of risks remain. The exceptional
            performance of gold output in 2013 is unlikely to be
            repeated in 2014. The rest of the economy is expected to
            continue expanding at 5 to 6 percent. A slowdown in the
            Russian economy, declining gold prices, and uncertainty
            created by the recent fluctuations in the exchange rate can
            adversely affect this outcome. This report presents recent
            political developments; recent economic developments; and
            economic and structural policies.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Kyrgyz Republic - Growth rebounds, risks remain
        </docna>
        <display_title>Kyrgyz Republic - Growth
            rebounds, risks remain</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2014/03/19456167/kyrgyz-republic-growth-rebounds-risks-remain</listing_relative_url>
        <subtopic>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Currencies and Exchange Rates,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Emerging Markets,Debt Markets</subtopic>
        <docty>Working Paper (Numbered Series)</docty>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth,Environment,Private Sector Development</teratopic>
        <count>Kyrgyz Republic</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Najdov, Evgenij</author>
            <author>Dubashov, Bakyt</author>
            <author>Edmundson, Helen</author>
        </authors>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Asia!$!80451</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Central Asia!$!80456</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Commonwealth of Independent States!$!80457</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Eastern Europe!$!107233</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000442464_20140501115430</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>Europe and Central Asia,Europe and Central Asia</admreg>
        <colti>Kyrgyz Republic economic report ; no. 5</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth,Environment,Private Sector Development</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            accounting, accounting rules, aggregate
            demand, Agriculture, asset ratio, assets, Balance of
            Payments, banking sector, barrier, broad money, budget
            deficit, business environment, Capital Adequacy, Capital
            inflows, central bank, checks, coal, coal prices, Commodity,
            Commodity Markets, Commodity Price, competitiveness,
            consumer price index, Consumer price inflation, consumption
            basket, consumption growth, core inflation, CPI, credit
            expansion, credit growth, Currency, current account, Current
            account balance, current account deficit, Customs Union,
            debt forgiveness, debt service, debt service ratio, Debt
            Sustainability, deposit, deposits, devaluation,
            devaluations, developing countries, Development Bank, dollar
            exchange rate, Domestic demand, domestic inflation, Domestic
            prices, drag on growth, Economic Developments, Economic
            Growth, Economic Outlook, Economics, emerging economies,
            emerging markets, environmental, equipment, equity Return,
            Exchange rate, Exchange Rate Policies, Expenditure,
            expenditures, export earnings, Export growth, exporters,
            exports, external debt, external demand, fair market value,
            farms, financial systems, financing requirements, Fiscal
            balance, fiscal deficit, Fiscal Policy, fisheries, fixed
            assets, food price, food prices, forecasts, foreign direct
            investment, Foreign Direct Investments, foreign exchange,
            foreign exchange market, Foreign exchange reserves, foreign
            loans, fraud, GDP, GDP per capita, Gini coefficient, gold,
            gold price, gold prices, Governance Indicators, government
            revenues, government spending, Gross Domestic Product, Gross
            national savings, growth in trade, Growth rate, household
            incomes, Human Development, import, Import growth, Import
            Prices, imports, income, income tax, income taxes,
            Inflation, Inflationary pressures, informal economy,
            infrastructure projects, interest rates, investment
            activities, investment climate, investment levels,
            investment projects, investor confidence, joint venture,
            labor force, labor market, Labor Markets, Labor
            productivity, Life expectancy, liquidity, local currency,
            low-income country, M2, market share, market value,
            maturity, metals, micro enterprises, mines, monetary
            aggregates, monetary policy, multiplier effects, National
            Bank, national savings, net exports, nominal exchange rate,
            nominal wage, Non-Performing Loan, Non-performing loans,
            Nonperforming loans, NPL, oil, oil prices, output, outturns,
            pensions, Policy Responses, Political stability, political
            upheaval, Population growth, Poverty levels, price
            increases, price index, Price Inflation, Private
            consumption, private sector credit, producers, productivity,
            property rights, public debt, public finance, Public
            investment, real effective exchange rate, real exchange
            rate, real wages, remittance, Remittances, Return, Return on
            assets, returns, rule of law, share of investment, share
            prices, slowdown, structural change, Structural Reforms,
            Sustainable Development, tax, tax collection, tax
            liabilities, tax policy, tax rate, tax regime, Tax revenues,
            telecommunications, Terms of trade, total external debt,
            total investment, Trade balance, trade deficit, trade
            facilitation, trade losses, Trade Policy, trade regime,
            trading, traditional markets, transparency, Treaty,
            uncertainties, uncertainty, unemployment, Unemployment rate,
            value added, volatility, vulnerability to shocks, Wage
            growth, wages, Weights, wholesale markets, World Trade,
            World Trade Organization, WTO
        </keywd>
        <owner>Macroeconomics 1 (ECSP1)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Central Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Commonwealth of Independent States</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Eastern Europe</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>87802</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics and Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shocks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Foreign Direct Investment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Remittances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Migration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Checks on Executive Power</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen User Satisfaction Survey</ml:concept><ml:concept>Independent Commissions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ombudsmen</ml:concept><ml:concept>Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Parliament</ml:concept><ml:concept>Procurement Complaints Review Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supreme Audit Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Employment and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Improving Labor Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Labor Market Interventions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Labor Markets, Job Creation and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wage Setting</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages, Compensation and Benefits</ml:concept><ml:concept>Foreign Direct Investments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Linkages</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fuels</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Current Account</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shocks and Vulnerability</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inflation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investment Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Movement of Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Accountability Mechanisms</ml:concept><ml:concept>Labor Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages</ml:concept><ml:concept>FDI Spillovers</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>State Associations</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Central Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Kyrgyzstan</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>