<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>﻿ F6F I L                                                            17&#13;
VN TS,&#13;
The World Bank                                   1818 H Street N.W.           (202) 477-1234&#13;
INTERNATIONAL BANK FOR RECONSTRUCTION AND DEVELOPMENT  Washington, D.C. 20433  Cable Address: INTBAFRAD&#13;
INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPMENT ASSOCIATION            U.S.A.                       Cable Address: INDEVAS&#13;
A D   ,2014&#13;
H.E. Hussein Abdi Halane&#13;
Minister of Finance&#13;
Ministry of Finance and Planning&#13;
Villa Somalia&#13;
Mogadishu, Somalia&#13;
Your Excellency:&#13;
Re:    SPF MDTF Grant No. TF017370&#13;
Information and Communication Technology Project&#13;
I am writing on behalf of the International Development Association (the World Bank or&#13;
Bank) to indicate the World Bank's agreement, as administrator of grant funds provided by various&#13;
donors ("Donors") under the Multi Donor Trust Fund for State- and Peace- Building Fund (SPF)&#13;
("TF071021"), to make a grant in an amount not exceeding one million, two hundred thousand&#13;
United States Dollars (US$1,200,000) (the Grant) to the Federal Republic of Somalia (the&#13;
Recipient).&#13;
The Grant is made in response to the Recipient's request for financial assistance and for the&#13;
purposes and on the terms and conditions set forth in the Annex to this Letter Agreement. The&#13;
Recipient hereby confirms its request that the Bank carry out the activities described in paragraph I&#13;
of the Annex to this Letter Agreement, and represents that it is authorized to contract the Grant for&#13;
the said purposes and on the said terms and conditions.&#13;
Please note that it is the Bank's policy to make publicly available this Letter Agreement&#13;
and any information related thereto, after this Letter Agreement has become effective and the&#13;
Recipient has given its consent to such disclosure. The Recipient, by countersigning this Letter&#13;
Agreement, confirms its consent to such disclosure.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿Please confirm your agreement with the foregoing, on behalf of the Recipient, by signing,&#13;
dating, and returning to us the enclosed copy of this Letter Agreement. Upon receipt by the Bank&#13;
of the copy of this Letter Agreement countersigned by you, this Letter Agreement will become&#13;
effective as of the date of the countersignature.&#13;
Very truly yours,&#13;
INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPMENT ASSOCIATION&#13;
By&#13;
ella ird&#13;
Country Director for Somalia&#13;
Africa Region&#13;
AGREED:&#13;
FEDERAL REPUBLIC OF SOMALIA&#13;
By&#13;
Authorized Representative&#13;
Name                         A        1&#13;
Title     AY    30' 20 I&#13;
Date:  tvIAi     5'Zo 21.j&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿ANNEX&#13;
Purposes, Terms and Conditions of the Grant&#13;
1.     The Activities for which the Grant is given are as follows:&#13;
(a) Carrying out of a program of activities to facilitate the implementation of the&#13;
communications law, such program to include inter alia, stakeholder consultations&#13;
on the communications law, and provision of advisory services on the&#13;
implementation of the law.&#13;
(b)  Carrying out of a program of activities to build the capacity of the Somalia&#13;
Communications Commission, such program to include inter alia, provision of&#13;
technical assistance for the harmonization of spectrum allocations; provision of&#13;
training to staff including in-situ training, supporting South-South knowledge&#13;
exchange initiatives, mounting training workshops and facilitating study tours&#13;
including in neighboring countries; provision of technical assistance for the&#13;
establishment of a data collection unit and the carrying out of surveys and studies;&#13;
support for the development of a website for the Ministry of Posts and&#13;
Telecommunications and the Somalia Communications Commission, and collecting&#13;
baseline telecommunication and information and communication technology data.&#13;
(c)  Carrying out of a program of activities to support the implementation of the&#13;
information and communication technology licensing framework, such program to&#13;
include inter alia, provision of technical assistance for the development of licensing&#13;
agreements for mobile operators and internet service providers including establishing&#13;
fee structures, and facilitating consultations with operators and other private sector&#13;
players on the proposed licenses.&#13;
(d)  Carrying out of a program of activities to build capacity of the Recipient and&#13;
enhance donor coordination, such program to include inter alia, conducting a&#13;
training needs assessment of the Ministry of Posts and Telecommunications and&#13;
Somalia Communications Commission and developing a training plan; supporting&#13;
the implementation of the training plan, and supporting donor coordination activities.&#13;
(e)  Carrying out of a cost-benefit analysis of the contribution of the telecoms to public&#13;
finance including inter alia, assessing potential of various revenue generation&#13;
scenarios for the telecommunication and information and communication technology&#13;
sector and preparing a report on the benefits that accrue to operators.&#13;
2.     The Grant shall be used to finance associated overheads, consultants' services (including&#13;
short term and extended term consultant fee and salary and benefits), contractual services,&#13;
equipment lease or purchase cost, study tours (including travel), media and workshop and travel&#13;
costs required for the Activities.&#13;
3.     The Bank shall carry out the Activities on behalf of the Recipient. The Recipient shall&#13;
cooperate with the Bank to the extent necessary to permit the Bank to carry out the Activities&#13;
promptly and effectively, and to evaluate the results of the Activities. The Recipient shall&#13;
indemnify the Bank against any costs or liabilities incurred by the Bank as a result of claims&#13;
against the Bank in connection with the Activities, except those resulting from the gross negligence&#13;
or willful misconduct of its staff or external consultants.&#13;
4.     The Bank shall carry out the Activities pursuant to this Letter Agreement only to the extent&#13;
that the Grant funds required for such Activities are available to the Bank from the Donors.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿5.     The Activities shall be completed by not later than March 31, 2016, or such later date as&#13;
the Bank may establish by notice to the Recipient (the Closing Date). After the Closing Date, the&#13;
Bank may at any time cancel the remaining balance of the Grant.&#13;
6.     The engagement and supervision of the consultants (the Consultants) required to assist in&#13;
the carrying out of the Activities shall be the responsibility solely of the Bank and shall be done&#13;
according to the Bank's applicable procedures.&#13;
7.     The Recipient may at any time request the Bank in writing to terminate the Activities.&#13;
Whether or not the Recipient has made such a request, the Bank may at any time suspend or, after&#13;
consultation with the Recipient, terminate the right of the Recipient to receive Grant funds for the&#13;
Activities if any of the following events has occurred and is continuing: (a) the Recipient has failed&#13;
to perform any of its obligations under this Letter Agreement; or (b) the right of the Recipient&#13;
or any other entity to which the International Bank for Reconstruction and Development (the&#13;
IBRD) has made a loan with the guarantee of the Recipient, to make withdrawals under any loan&#13;
agreement with the IBRD or any development credit, grant or financing agreement with IDA has&#13;
been suspended.&#13;
8.     The Bank is not an agent of, or trustee for, the Recipient and shall not have any fiduciary&#13;
relationship with the Recipient. The Recipient shall have no right to any portion of the Grant that&#13;
is not expended by the Bank pursuant to this Letter Agreement.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="19670732">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2014/05/19670732/official-documents--agreement-spf-mdtf-grant-tf017370
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2014/05/19670732/official-documents--agreement-spf-mdtf-grant-tf017370</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2014/05/19670732/official-documents--agreement-spf-mdtf-grant-tf017370</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2014-06-13T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2014-06-13T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <docm_id>090224b0824f6c13</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b0824f6c13</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/AFR/2014/06/13/090224b0824f6c13/1_0/Rendered/INDEX/Official0Docum0MDTF0Grant00TF017370.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/AFR/2014/06/13/090224b0824f6c13/1_0/Rendered/PDF/Official0Docum0MDTF0Grant00TF017370.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2014-05-30T14:46:05Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2014-06-13T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docna>
            Official Documents- Agreement for SPF MDTF
            Grant, TF017370
        </docna>
        <display_title>Official Documents- Agreement for
            SPF MDTF Grant, TF017370</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/2014/05/19670732/official-documents--agreement-spf-mdtf-grant-tf017370</listing_relative_url>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <docty>Trust Fund Administrative Agreement</docty>
        <count>Somalia</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Mukaindo,Stephen Mugendi</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>HQBOCS</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <trustfund>TF017370-Somalia: Support to the
            Information and Communication Technologies Sect</trustfund>
        <lang>English</lang>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT for Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies (ICT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Arts and Culture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure and Networks (National; State; Local)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunication and Network Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunications</ml:concept><ml:concept>Leasing law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Continuing Judicial Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Judicial Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Judicial Education, Training and Professional Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Judicial Training Curriculum</ml:concept><ml:concept>Training Needs Assessments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Media</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunications and Broadband Access</ml:concept><ml:concept>Leasing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Judicial Education and Training</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Africa</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Somalia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>