<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Water and&#13;
Sanitation&#13;
Sanitation in Wonosobo:&#13;
Two Evaluation Approaches Compared&#13;
I~~~~~~~~~~~S -&#13;
_13 L~~~~~~~~~~~1&#13;
Water and Sanitation Program  tf -&gt; t1'1_.....................  - &#13;
for East Asia and the Pacific&#13;
Field Note&#13;
Prepared by:&#13;
Ruth Walujon                                                        S&#13;
Richard M. Hopkins&#13;
Arie Istandar       -&#13;
April 2002 s&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
'I  -&gt;    &gt;    This study was financed by the Government of Australia through&#13;
/A AID  the Australian Consultants Trust Fund executed by the World Bank&#13;
Photographs by Richard M. Hopkins (WSP-EAP)&#13;
This document is published by the Water and Sanitation Program - East Asia and the Pacific. Copies are&#13;
available from the Water and Sanitation Program; Jakarta Stock Exchange Building, Tower 2, 13th floor;&#13;
Ji. Jenderal Sudirman Kav. 52-53, SCBD, Jakarta 12190, Indonesia. Phone: (62-21) 5299-3003.&#13;
Fax: (62-21) 5299-3004. E-mail: wspeap@worldbank.org. Website: http://www.wsp.org&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Sanitation in Wonosobo:&#13;
Two Evaluation Approaches Compared&#13;
A        recent comparative case study on two program  such as latrine ownership and latrine benefits as perceived&#13;
evaluation approaches found out that both the  by the village residents and leaders, the results varied, due&#13;
conventional survey method used by UNICEF and  to differences in the methodology design and sampling&#13;
the participatory method employed by WASPOLA' yielded  process.&#13;
comparable outcomes in the assessment of UNICEF's&#13;
sanitation program in sample villages in Wonosobo district,  The design of each evaluation methodology was quite&#13;
Indonesia. This field note presents a summary of the  distinct. The conventional surveycollected data by measuring&#13;
comparison of results produced by the two evaluation  individual responses to a series of questions about sanitation&#13;
approaches.                                           and latrine uses; the survey provided limited discussion&#13;
opportunities with its respondents to clarify unclear issues&#13;
Contrary to prevailing belief that participatory methods are  or solve problems. In contrast, the participatory method&#13;
more complex, more time-consuming and more expensive  emphasized focus group discussions to help empower the&#13;
than conventional survey methods, the study showed that  participants in identifying, discussing, clarifying, and&#13;
the total costs involved in the preparation and       resolving problems within their own communities. Data&#13;
implementation of both assessment activities were similar.  recorded represented group conclusions reached collectively&#13;
However, the completion of the participatory method   by the participants.&#13;
required a smaller team of better trained field staff and less&#13;
implementation time than the conventional survey.     Both approaches methods produced diverse data sets&#13;
because the sampling pool differed. The conventional survey&#13;
Further comparison of results generated other similarities  targeted individual members of certain groups in the village&#13;
and differences. In the assessment of latrine use, for example,  to extract certain information, but it excluded social&#13;
the outcomes were rather similar although the respective  background considerations of its respondents. In contrast,&#13;
methodology implementation differed. In other assessments,  the participatory method aimed to gather information&#13;
1 WASPOLA is the Water Supply and Sonitation Formulation and Action Planning Project implemented by the World Bank's Water and Sanitation Program-&#13;
East Asia and the Pacific (WSP-EAP) in conjunction with the Government of Indonesia, led by the National Development Planning Agency (BAPPENAS), with&#13;
majority funding by the Government of Australia through AusAID.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
from focus group discussions where the sampling design&#13;
took into account the representation of both gender and .&#13;
socio-economic factors. Data obtained from the two methods&#13;
therefore reflected the different viewpoints of the sample                       -&#13;
groups.&#13;
Project Background&#13;
The study was conducted within the context of UNICEF's&#13;
stimulant latrine package distribution program in four&#13;
villages in the Wonosobo district of Central Java: Sawangan,&#13;
Rejosari, Mergosari, and Kagungan. The UNICEF program&#13;
was aimed at improving the health and hygiene of rural      ; '                    .;, -&#13;
residents by encouraging latrine construction at the                        -&#13;
household level through the distribution of stimulant&#13;
packages, typically consisting ofa water-seal closet, a length  respective implementation details (see Figure 1). When&#13;
of PVC pipe, and a sack of cement. Villages were selected  program assessment results were different, both the&#13;
based on the existence of previously implemented    approach design and implementation process were&#13;
government sanitation and diarrhea reduction programs,  evaluated to identify the possible reasons for the different&#13;
the community's potential to support the stimulant program,  outcomes. When the assessment results were similar, both&#13;
and the establishment of at least two community programs,  approaches were determined to be providing comparable&#13;
such as community health centers and children education  data of village conditions.&#13;
projects.&#13;
UNICEF and WASPOLA agreed to collaborate in conducting&#13;
Objectives of the Comparative Case Study          a case study in the Wonosobo district of Central Java to&#13;
compare the results of using the conventional survey by&#13;
* To compare the design and implementation       applying questionnaire surveys and the participatory&#13;
approaches of thetwo evaluation methodologies in  evaluation method by using tools derived from the&#13;
collecting data and producing results.         Methodology for Participatory Assessment (MPA) and the&#13;
* To compare the results of the two methodologies  Participatory Hygiene and Sanitation Transformation&#13;
whenever adequate and suitable results or data are  (PHAST).&#13;
available for comparison.&#13;
* To focus on the quantitative data comparison since  The conventional survey consisted of two phases. The first&#13;
almost all outputs of the conventional survey method  phase, in August-September 1999, included a baseline&#13;
are quantitative.                              survey prepared by CIDA2 consultants and implemented&#13;
by a local NGO to assess village conditions prior to the&#13;
As indicated in the box, the comparative study of the two  distribution of latrine packages. The second phase, in July&#13;
methodologies analyzed not only the results, but also the  2000, entailed an evaluation survey prepared and&#13;
design aspects of the data collection processes, and the  implemented by the same local NGO to evaluate village&#13;
2 CIDA = Canadian International Development Agency&#13;
2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
conditions and program     results after the package     Research Process&#13;
disbursement.&#13;
Both the conventional survey and the participatory methods&#13;
The participatory evaluation method was implemented once  employed field personnel for methodology implementation.&#13;
in April 2001 to assess program results and conditions. Tools  In the conventional survey, enumerators equipped with&#13;
for the participatory evaluation activities were designed by  questionnaires interviewed respondents at the household&#13;
WSP-EAP staff and implemented by a local NGO.            level. In the participatory method, field staff facilitated&#13;
Comparative Analysis Flowchart&#13;
Step IComparison of Result&#13;
Comparison of Results&#13;
* If similar, then list results.&#13;
* If different, then proceed to Step 2.&#13;
Similar                   Different&#13;
Results        .           Results&#13;
Step 2                                                                    Comparison of&#13;
Comparison of Methodology Design                                       M            D&#13;
* If the methodology design used was invalid,&#13;
then such application most likely caused the&#13;
results disparity highlighted in Step 1.&#13;
* If methodology design used was valid,                             Valid                Invalid&#13;
but results remained totally different,                       Methodology           Methodology&#13;
then proceed to Step 3.                                            4&#13;
COmpari son of&#13;
Methodology&#13;
Implementation&#13;
Step 3&#13;
Comparison of Methodology Implementation&#13;
* If the methodology was improperly applied,&#13;
then such conduct most likely caused the            Proper                   Improper&#13;
results discrepancy noted in Step 1.           Implementation            Implementation&#13;
* If the methodology was properly used,&#13;
but results remained totally different, &#13;
then the change in village conditions        |  Verification of&#13;
most probably caused the discrepancy.         Village Condition&#13;
3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
interactive and participatory assessments,by community  respondents, thus allowing little flexibility in clarifying any&#13;
groups, and organized focus group discussions.      vague questions or uncertain responses.&#13;
The participatory method was designed to gather&#13;
How Was Information Collected?                    information from the village residents' groups segregated&#13;
by gender and socio-economic levels. The exact number of&#13;
Enumerators of the conventional survey interviewed  participants was not as crucial as the representativeness of&#13;
respondents including village leaders, heads of  the groups. In some exercises, women's participation was&#13;
household, and school children using a standard   more significant because women represented the&#13;
questionnaire. The survey was also designed to cover  beneficiaries; in other activities, participation of the various&#13;
an equal number of male and female respondents. The  poor-rich and men-women groups in the village was more&#13;
responses reflected individual preferences.       important. The participatory method provided ample time&#13;
for discussions with participants, and offered opportunity to&#13;
In the participatory method, information was collected  include various responses which were locally relevant. The&#13;
from focus group activities and discussions as well as  method relied on group participation and the recording of&#13;
individual interaction. The method allowed every  group conclusions, thus minimizing individual respondent&#13;
community memberto express his/herviews and discuss  biases.&#13;
issues, and opened opportunities for collective problem-&#13;
solving and decision-making. The method also included&#13;
observation at and interaction with individual&#13;
households to verify the collected information, such as&#13;
the actual use and maintenance of household latrines.&#13;
By design, the conventional survey targeted as many  L       v   -&#13;
households as possible and balanced the respondents by&#13;
gender, but not by socio-economic groupings. Households                                      I&#13;
were selected randomly from a list of village residents in&#13;
each respective village provided by the Village Chiefs; it&#13;
was assumed that each household was readily represented&#13;
by one household member. Three different questionnaires&#13;
were developed to cater three different respondent  *&#13;
categories: village leaders/cadres, community/ordinary  I  !-- -                      ,&#13;
residents, school children/students. The data collected were&#13;
highly sensitive to who participated in answering which&#13;
questions in the questionnaires. By nature, the survey                  -&#13;
implementation provided minimal discussion with the  --         -&#13;
4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The participatory method at times encountered difficulties  Different Designs, Similar Results&#13;
in implementation. For example in some of the exercises,                                      -   -&#13;
the participants were not fully representative of the village  Both methods evaluated the use of sanitation facilities&#13;
because only certain groups, like the rich, attended the  installed after the latrine packages distribution. Although&#13;
discussions. Data generated from these exercises were  each method used a distinct approach to assess latrine use&#13;
recorded and identified during the course of the study.  among the village residents, the results were comparable.&#13;
Emphasis on Equity                                 In the conventional questionnaire survey, latrine use (referred&#13;
to here as use of toilets or neighbor's facility) questions were&#13;
The pariic,poior meilhod iends .isel! lo promoting equity  linked to ownership. During the survey implementation, the&#13;
in community voice through iis focus group discussions  enumerators assumed that well-maintained latrines observed&#13;
and communiry ascessmnent aci-,les, with separate  in the households were synonymous with effective use; there&#13;
men's and women's -groups, arnd poor and non-poor  was no discussion to clarify whether the clean latrines were&#13;
household groups.- By.doing- so, the.design and    used by all or only selected household members.&#13;
implementation of sanitation -p-rogramns- can be more  Respondents were limited to choose their answers from a&#13;
focused, not only on prorviding' ihe sanitation facilities&#13;
focused, not only on providing h- sanioton facilitis  .preconceived list of latrine use responses prepared by others.&#13;
and services that the people .,anl' but alsb on promoting&#13;
and  services that the  people n bu aloon prSurvey  results  in  three  of the four villages  indicated  that use&#13;
equitable access to improved- sonif6fion within the&#13;
equitable access to improve- sanitation wti th ':.'of private, public, or a neighbor's toilet was overshadowed&#13;
community. -&#13;
communit.  -.  -by the use of rivers and fishponds (see Figure 2).&#13;
Use of Sanitation Facilities after&#13;
Package Disbursement: Conventional Survey&#13;
Toilet&#13;
Use of neighbor's&#13;
facility                                                             FE] Sawangan&#13;
Public toilet  l&#13;
*l Rejosari&#13;
; -                                        i                   g Kagungan&#13;
River / pond                                                              F .&#13;
Open space / bush       X        iF&#13;
0        20         40        60        80        100&#13;
% of Total Respondents&#13;
5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
In some respects, the results of the participatory evaluation  |&#13;
were similar although the participatory method yielded more&#13;
information on the extent (or lack thereof) in community&#13;
sanitation behavior. The participatory exercise asked men                            I&#13;
and women participants which facilities they used before                                       A&#13;
and after the package distribution. In the exercise, the       -                        / / ,,f&#13;
facilitator's interactive role was crucial to obtain honest and&#13;
representative responses. Site visits were then performed to               /                 ,&#13;
confirm the data. Figure 3 summarizes various types of                    -     -&#13;
sanitation facilities used by the participants.&#13;
In the participatory method, the greater variety of answers&#13;
resulted from the participants being able to identify and&#13;
discuss freely the facilities they used; the participants were  together significant sites such as rivers and fishponds (which&#13;
not restricted to a pre-determined set of answers and instead  have different environmental and behavioral implications&#13;
came up with eight different sites. The questionnaire survey  for sanitation programs). While this restriction highlights the&#13;
restricted respondents to only five possible sites in the same  inherent difficulty in designing questionnaires, at the same&#13;
communities and lost important information by lumping  time it illustrates a strong advantage of the participatory&#13;
-__lUl:ff  |           Use of Sanitation Facilities Before and&#13;
After Package Disbursement: Participatory Method&#13;
Before                             After&#13;
Toilet inside                                 I          I&#13;
the house&#13;
Toilet outside                               _&#13;
the house&#13;
Public toilet&#13;
Pit latrine&#13;
Fish pond        l&#13;
Open space/&#13;
bush        l  1     -   --                  - 23&#13;
River  _    -  _ _ _                    __&#13;
100   80     60    40     20      0     20     40    60     80   100&#13;
% of Total Participants&#13;
nl Sowongan   El Mergosari   [3 Rejosori   El Kogungan&#13;
6&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
method generally in allowing participants the freedom to  conventional survey only obtained information on the current&#13;
describe their outcomes, and thus the structure of the  behavior pattern. For instance, although toilet use increased&#13;
evaluation results.                                 after package distribution and fishpond use decreased,&#13;
fishpond uses remained common.&#13;
The survey results, however, were similar to the 'after package&#13;
distribution' results of the participatory method. Both methods&#13;
revealed that fishponds were commonly used, both directly  Different Designs, Different Results&#13;
and as the final discharge points of latrines instead of septic&#13;
tanks or pits. Fishponds were generally used more frequently  Both approaches assessed latrine ownership after package&#13;
than privote (inside and outside) and public toilets in three  distribution by interviewing village residents in the&#13;
of the four villages (after package distribution).  conventional survey, and engaging them in focus group&#13;
discussions in the participatory method. The assessment&#13;
In addition, the participatory method produced a comparison  results from the two methods were different, but they were&#13;
of community sanitation behovior before and after latrine  consistent in identifying villages with the lowest to the&#13;
package distribution, whereas (at least in this case) the  highest latrine ownership (see Table 1).&#13;
Table 1 Comparison of Latrine Ownership&#13;
Ownership (%)&#13;
Village           Conventional Survey                   Participatory Method&#13;
After             Rich         Middle        Poor      After (Total)&#13;
Kagungan                   12               21             6           0.5           7&#13;
Rejosari                  38               53            31            9            16&#13;
Sawangan                   48               93            34            3            30&#13;
Mergosari                  55               100           77           46            59&#13;
The discrepancies in latrine ownership results were attributed  usage; those who answered "No" were not asked further&#13;
to the different methodology design. The conventional  questions. The survey questionnaire did not leave much room&#13;
evaluation survey was insensitive to the socio-economic  for discussion to clarify latrines that were "owned but not&#13;
backgrounds of the village households. Consequently, the  installed" vs. "owned and installed". While the survey's intent&#13;
survey may have unintentionally targeted more non-poor  was to collect data of owned latrines, meaning installed&#13;
respondents who typically already owned latrines, thus  and used, it did not consider instances of residents who&#13;
resulting in a higher ownership rate in three of the four  received latrine packages but had not installed the latrines,&#13;
villages.                                           and thus had not used them, or those who installed them&#13;
but instead used the public or their neighbor's latrines. As a&#13;
In addition, the survey used questions that were closed-ended  result, respondents who owned latrines, whether built or&#13;
and multi-staged. Survey respondents who replied "Yes" to  not, responded positively to latrine ownership, thus&#13;
latrine ownership were further questioned about latrine  increasing the ownership rate.&#13;
7&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The participatory method discussed latrine ownership and  in most villages, they had the lowest access to latrines. Due&#13;
use issues among village residents in focus group discussions,  to its design, the conventional survey was not able to capture&#13;
and assessed household demand for latrines through cost/  this information.&#13;
benefit perception assessments. Vague ownership definitions&#13;
were discussed and clarified to avoid any misinterpretation.&#13;
The method also considered local conditions as part of its  Different Designs, Different Results&#13;
design, in particular the different socio-economic groups&#13;
within a village, and distinguished recipients of the UNICEF  Both approaches gathered data on the user's perceptions&#13;
program from other development projects and from those  of the benefits of owning and using latrines. The results&#13;
who built the latrines all by themselves. Ownership data  arising from the two methods however were different;&#13;
were then verified with actual household visits. Results from  community perceptions obtained through the participatory&#13;
the method suggested that different socio-economic groups  method were more varied. In the conventional survey&#13;
had different rights and privileges, and received different  method, only village leaders/cadres were interviewed about&#13;
benefits, although they were part of the same community.  benefits of latrines after latrine package disbursement (see&#13;
Although the poor formed the major socio-economic group  Figure 4).&#13;
1   ;; -Benefits of Latrines as Perceived&#13;
by Village Leaders: Conventional Survey&#13;
Hygiene improvement&#13;
Clean environment                              _   ___&#13;
zi-I&#13;
Proper defecation site&#13;
Increase household-&#13;
owned latrines&#13;
Increose of diarrhea&#13;
knowledge _&#13;
Do not know&#13;
0              25             50              75            100&#13;
% of Total Respondents&#13;
|E Sawangon   [l Mergosari     l Rejosari   E3 Kagungan&#13;
8&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
According to the respective village leaders/cadres of the  The participatory method involved a cross-section of thevillage&#13;
survey, greater knowledge of diarrhea and cleaner         residents, namely the poor and women, to express what they&#13;
environment were the two most common perceived benefits.   perceive as the benefits of owning and using private latrines.&#13;
Field assessments, however, documented that most village  The participants not only had to identify the benefits, but they&#13;
residents continued to use fishponds as the final discharge  also had to rank them (see Figure 5).&#13;
points of private latrines instead of septic tanks or pits after&#13;
the latrine packages were distributed. Using fishpond water  Participants ranked the following benefits from  most to&#13;
for bathing/washing is a common source for the transfer of  least: better hygiene, better for health, cleaner environment,&#13;
diseases. Contrary to what the village leaders noted,     easier access (proximity), greater privacy, greater comfort&#13;
residents seemed no more aware of the causes of diarrhea  and safety (protected from    rain, ample space), and&#13;
after package distribution than before distribution.      convenience/better image for guests.&#13;
-tq6B-s   |          Benefits of Latrines as Perceived&#13;
by Village Residents: Participatory Method&#13;
Hygiene improvement&#13;
Clean environment                                l     l      l I&#13;
_       _~~         ~     ~ -  .,       -. .s  _____ &#13;
i-                       I&#13;
Proper defecation site                      l&#13;
_i Sawangon&#13;
Better for heolth    e-_ l        i                                                   O   Mergosari&#13;
- I       I      I __ I       [            |                   O  Rejosari&#13;
Comfort and safety&#13;
-r 7_ - i . C~~~~~~~~~ Kagungan&#13;
Easy access                                                                             a&#13;
Privacy                                 I     I&#13;
Convenience/better&#13;
imoge for guest  _&#13;
o     1     2      3     4      5     6      7     8      9    10&#13;
Ranking (1-10)&#13;
Note: Ranking Process: once the perceived benefits were mentioned in separate men's and women's groups, they were ranked with a scoring&#13;
system between 10 (highest) and 1 (lowest) using beans or seeds. The ranking scores in Figure 5 represented the average scores of both gender&#13;
groups. For instance, men and women in Mergosori ranked privacy as the highest benefit of using latrines relative to those in Kagungan, who did&#13;
not rank privacy as a main benefit.&#13;
9&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The disparity of the results can be attributed to the sampling  respondents had to choose their responses from regarding&#13;
process and the methodology design, namely the research  the benefits; they were restricted to the provided answers.&#13;
tool selection. To identify the benefits of latrines, the&#13;
conventional survey asked only village leaders/cadres while  Relative to conventional survey results, the participatory&#13;
the participatory method asked a greater cross-section of  method outcomes were more diverse due to the more varied&#13;
residents, particularly the poor and women. Assessment  nature of the participants. The participants had full freedom&#13;
resultsindicatedthatvillageleadershaddifferentperceptions  to mention the kinds of benefits they perceived, which&#13;
relative to the residents. Also, the survey questionnaire  generated a more varied range of responses; they were not&#13;
provided a pre-determined list of answers from which the  limited to choose from a pre-determined list.&#13;
Table 2     Comparison of Costs and Resources to Implement the Conventional Survey&#13;
and Participatory Activities&#13;
Parameters                  Conventional Survey                         Participatory Method&#13;
1 national consultant,   48 person weeks&#13;
48 weeks&#13;
1 survey coordinator,    12 person weeks    1 coordinator, 5 weeks   5 person weeks&#13;
12 weeks&#13;
STUDY          2 field coordinators,    40 person weeks&#13;
TEAM          20 weeks&#13;
&amp;           16 field researchers,     48 person weeks   7 field researchers,      14 person weeks&#13;
STUDY          3 weeks in the field                        2 weeks in the field&#13;
PERIOD         4 weeks for material      76 person weeks   1 week for material       8 person weeks&#13;
and field preparation,                      preparation and training&#13;
and training (19 persons)                   (8 persons/team)&#13;
5 weeks reporting         15 person weeks   2 weeks reporting         14 person weeks&#13;
(by 3 coordinators)                         (7 persons)&#13;
TOTAL&#13;
INPUTS                     239 person-weeks                              41 person-weeks&#13;
TOTAL&#13;
COST*                        100 million                                    82 million&#13;
(Rp.)&#13;
Note: * Total cost was inclusive of reimbursables (travel), material preparation, training, field implementation, data consolidation/analysis, and&#13;
report preparation. In addition, the costs and resources of the external consultant who prepared the baseline survey questionnaire were assumed&#13;
equivalent with those incurred by various WSP-EAP personnel involved in the initial planning stages of the comparative study. These costs were&#13;
omitted from the total costs of both methodologies.&#13;
10&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Despite the differences in overall results, both the village  The conventional survey consisted of baseline and evaluation&#13;
leaders and residents interestingly perceived better health  surveys that were implemented at two different time periods;&#13;
and a cleaner environment as important benefits of owning  the baseline survey was an inherent part of the entire survey.&#13;
and using latrines.                                  The survey incorporated fees for a local consultant to perform&#13;
project preparation and design tasks to aid UNICEF in the&#13;
preparation of detailed project Terms of Reference for the&#13;
Different Methodologies,                             participating NGO (for baseline survey), design of detailed&#13;
Comparable Costs                                     baseline survey questionnaires, and upfront contract&#13;
preparation. In the evaluation survey, data were estimated&#13;
from the baseline survey parameters. Based on the smaller&#13;
The total costs to prepare and implement the conventional&#13;
number of participants in the evaluation survey relative to&#13;
the baseline, it was assumed that the overall evaluation&#13;
Table 2 provides a summary of the overall inputs and costs&#13;
survey preparation and implementation required 2/3 of the&#13;
of implementing the two methods in the four villages in  time needed for the baseline.&#13;
the Wonosobo district of Central Java. It shows that the&#13;
conventional survey used more, but cheaper enumerators,  The participatory method was conducted once and its total&#13;
whereas the facilitators for the participatory method were  cost did not significantly differ from that of the conventional&#13;
more expensive, but smaller in number and better trained.  survey.&#13;
*\'                ..e1.,X                                            ,&#13;
4-             .%       ~        ~&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Key Findings&#13;
* The case study shows the two approaches produced both similar and different assessment&#13;
results. However, it is also clear that the use of different approaches can provide comparable&#13;
results if sufficient attention is given to their design and implementation processes,&#13;
particularly with respect to the sample selection and the questionnaire development.&#13;
a The sampling process was a key attribute in the discrepancies of the assessment results.&#13;
The participatory method was sensitive to the representation of men-women and rich-&#13;
poor groups in the respective communities to reflect differences in village conditions,&#13;
such as latrine ownership, use, and benefits. The conventional survey results were&#13;
sensitive to the total number of respondents in order to properly represent the village&#13;
conditions. Identifying a representative sample requires a lot of effort, especially when&#13;
village households show more diversity. Therefore, by excluding considerations of village-&#13;
level variations during the design of the sampling process, assessment results may be&#13;
biased toward certain groups within the village.&#13;
* The participatory method encouraged village residents to voice their ideas, opinions,&#13;
issues, and add local knowledge to the response categories, thus resulting in a broader&#13;
picture of sanitation conditions in their villages, such as latrine benefits and latrine uses.&#13;
The conventional survey entailed a pre-determined set of response categories, thus&#13;
restricting the respondents' preferences to those listed. In theory, this problem in the&#13;
conventional survey technique could be overcome by extensive field testing of the survey&#13;
questionnaire. But in practice, as the study shows, inadequate time was invested in&#13;
undertaking this part of the survey, resulting in a less accurate picture of village conditions.&#13;
* The total costs of the participatory method were comparable to the costs of the conventional&#13;
survey. The conventional survey employed more, less expensive enumerators, whereas&#13;
the participatory method used fewer, better trained facilitators. The participatory method&#13;
required less time to implement and was easier to manage because of its one-time&#13;
application to assess both before and after village conditions, whereas the conventional&#13;
approach required two separate surveys (baseline and evaluation) to measure and assess&#13;
the pre- and post-project conditions.&#13;
12&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Water and Sanitation Program East Asia and the Pacific&#13;
Jakarta Stock Exchange Building, Tower 2, 13th floor&#13;
JI. Jend. Sudirman Kav. 52-53, SCBD, Jakarta 12190, Indonesia&#13;
Phone: (62-21) 5299-3003, Fax: (62-21) 5299-3004&#13;
Website: http://www.wsp.org&#13;
WASPOLA Project Office&#13;
E-mail: waspola 1 @cbn.net.id, Website: www.waspola.org&#13;
/AusAID&#13;
This activity and publication were funded&#13;
WASPOLA, a policy initiative with suppo&#13;
from AusAID&#13;
The Water and Sanitation Program is an international partnership to help&#13;
the poor gain sustained access to improved water supply and sanitation&#13;
services. The program's funding partners are the Governments of&#13;
Australia, Belgium, Canada, Denmark,- Germany, Italy, Japan, Luxemburg,&#13;
the Netherlands, Norway, Sweden, Switzerland, and the United Kingdom;&#13;
the United Nations Development Programme and the World Bank&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1979364">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2002/04/1979364/sanitation-wonosobo-two-evaluation-approaches-compared
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2002/04/1979364/sanitation-wonosobo-two-evaluation-approaches-compared</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2002/04/1979364/sanitation-wonosobo-two-evaluation-approaches-compared</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2002/09/07/000094946_02082104034281/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2002/09/07/000094946_02082104034281/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2002-04-30T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2002-09-07T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Sanitation in Wonosobo : two evaluation
            approaches compared
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The field note compares two approaches
            in the design of each evaluation methodology in providing
            sanitation, through the Wonosobo case study: the
            conventional survey data collection, measures individual
            responses to questions on sanitation, and latrine uses, but
            provides limited discussion opportunities to clarify
            unsolved issues; in contrast, the participatory method
            emphasizes focus group discussions, to help empower
            participants in identifying, discussing, clarifying, and
            resolving problems within their own communities. Key
            findings suggest the two approaches produced both similar,
            and different assessment results. However, it became also
            clear that the use of different approaches can provide
            comparable results, if attention is given to their design,
            and implementation processes. The sampling process was a key
            attribute in the discrepancies of the assessment results:
            while the participatory method was sensitive to the
            representation of men-women, and rich-poor groups, the
            conventional survey results were sensitive to the total
            number of respondents in order to properly represent the
            village conditions. Thus, by excluding considerations of
            village-level variations during the design of the sampling
            process, assessments may result biased toward certain
            village groups. However, inadequate time was invested in
            undertaking the participatory method, resulting in a less
            accurate picture of village conditions.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Sanitation in Wonosobo : two evaluation
            approaches compared
        </docna>
        <display_title>Sanitation in Wonosobo : two
            evaluation approaches compared</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2002/04/1979364/sanitation-wonosobo-two-evaluation-approaches-compared</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>UNDP-Water &amp; Sanitation Program</docty>
        <subtopic>Social Analysis,Civic Participation and Corporate Governance,Urban Water Supply and Sanitation,BD-Legal Fees  Bd--Closed -- 2031288,TF054599-PHRD-KYRGYZ REPUBLIC: WATER
            MANAGEMENT IMPROVEMENT PROJECT</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Water Supply and Sanitation</teratopic>
        <count>Indonesia</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Walujan, Ruth</author>
            <author>Hopkins, Richard M.</author>
            <author>Istandar, Arie</author>
        </authors>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Asia!$!80451</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Southeast Asia!$!80471</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000094946_02082104034281</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Sanitation</subsc>
        <admreg>East Asia and Pacific,East Asia and Pacific</admreg>
        <colti>Water and Sanitation Program field note</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Water Supply and Sanitation</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Case studies; Sanitation services; Latrines;
            Evaluation methodology; Survey data; Participatory methods;
            Assessments; Socioeconomic conditions; Gender differences;
            Community participation; Time factor; Comparative analysis
            access to latrines,Action
            Planning,beneficiaries,change,Comparative Analysis,data,data
            collection,enumerators,facilitators,flexibility,focus
            group,focus group discussions,health
            surveys,hygiene,interviewing,latrine,latrine
            construction,latrines,local conditions,local
            knowledge,opinions,Participatory Activities,participatory
            approaches,Participatory Assessment,participatory
            assessments,participatory evaluation,participatory
            methods,perception,perceptions,Photographs,Pit
            latrine,pits,preparation,quantitative
            data,questionnaire,questionnaires,Ranking,sample
            selection,Sanitation,Sanitation Program,sanitation
            services,survey,survey implementation,survey
            questionnaires,survey results,village
        </keywd>
        <owner>EAP</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Southeast Asia</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>24655</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Basic Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>On-site Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Marketing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civic Participation and Corporate Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corporate Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nationalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Enterprise Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>State Owned Enterprise Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>State-Owned Enterprise Restructuring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Assessment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corporate Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enterprise Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enterprise and Commercial Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply</ml:concept><ml:concept>Diseases</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water, Sanitation and Hygiene</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Social Impact Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>State Owned Enterprises</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enterprise and Corporate Law</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Eastern Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Indonesia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>