<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>      STRICTLY C                                                         89489&#13;
McD                                      INTERNATIONAL BANK FOR&#13;
                                     RECONSTRUCTION AND DEVELOPMENT&#13;
             il&#13;
             i'&#13;
&#13;
             :1&#13;
             ;;&#13;
             !I&#13;
             i1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
             il                   THREE HUNDRED FOURTH REDULAR MEETING&#13;
             i:&#13;
             ,;&#13;
                                                   of&#13;
             II&#13;
             II&#13;
             11&#13;
             ,I                            EXECUTIVE DIRECTORS&#13;
             'i&#13;
             IÂ·&#13;
             JI&#13;
&#13;
             11&#13;
             1!&#13;
             11&#13;
             q&#13;
             l                                      Board Room&#13;
             11&#13;
             1,&#13;
             !1&#13;
                                                    International Bank Building&#13;
                                                    Washington, D. c.               l&#13;
                                                                                    !&#13;
             1,                                     Thursday, November 13, 1958&#13;
             lj                                                                     I&#13;
              I&#13;
&#13;
              i&#13;
              I&#13;
              I            The meeting was convened at 10:07 a.m., Mr. Eugene Black I&#13;
             1:       President, presiding â&#128;¢&#13;
             .I&#13;
             1:&#13;
                  i&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
             ,,&#13;
             11&#13;
             ti&#13;
             11&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
             i&#13;
             r&#13;
             11&#13;
             I'&#13;
             11&#13;
             IiI&#13;
              )&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
             11&#13;
&#13;
              I&#13;
&amp;#12;       '1&#13;
&#13;
                                                                   2&#13;
&#13;
STRICTLY C&#13;
                                     --------&#13;
                                     CONTENTS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       :I&#13;
          Joint Operations&#13;
                               ... .. .. â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ .. . ..&#13;
       i:&#13;
       L       South Arrica â&#128;¢&#13;
       "&#13;
       I&#13;
        l&#13;
               Austria â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢&#13;
                               ..... ...â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢&#13;
               Lu.x embou rg â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢&#13;
                                      . ...            . . .   3&#13;
                                                               6&#13;
                                                               9&#13;
       'i&#13;
       1.&#13;
&#13;
       I&#13;
       !1&#13;
       I.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       I                              * * *&#13;
&#13;
        I:&#13;
        jl&#13;
       l&#13;
        !1&#13;
&#13;
        iI&#13;
         I&#13;
         I&#13;
        ii&#13;
&#13;
       I!&#13;
       II&#13;
        11&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        ii&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                              3&#13;
STRICTLY C&#13;
&#13;
                  THE CHAIRMAN:     The first item of business is the minutes&#13;
            of the 303rd Regular and 162nd, 163rd, 164th and 165th&#13;
             Special Meetings held on September 9, 12, 16, 19 and October&#13;
            3, respectively.      If there are no corrections, they stand&#13;
        i&#13;
        I&#13;
            adopted.&#13;
       r          In order to try to do everything possible to stimulate&#13;
       I&#13;
            the flow of international private capital, we have from time&#13;
            to time arranged loans in conjunction with public offerings&#13;
             of bonds by the borrowers from the Bank in New York.     The&#13;
             first one of those was about four years ago, and last year&#13;
            there were three or these joint transactions, where the loan&#13;
       1!&#13;
       ,,&#13;
            that we were proposing to make was divided up between us and&#13;
        l&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
             the New York market.     I am very glad to report that recently&#13;
            this type of business is increasing, and at todayts meeting&#13;
            you have before you papers describing three more operations&#13;
             of this sort.    Because of a last-minute legal hitch, we may&#13;
            not ask you today to consider the Luxembourg ope!'ation.        As a&#13;
            matter of fact, we have some people on the telephone now&#13;
            checking with New York to see whether they want us to get&#13;
            approval 1n principle of the Luxembourg loan, and we may do i&#13;
            and we may not.&#13;
                 As you know from previous cases, the underwriters in&#13;
            New York have to register these issues that are floated&#13;
            publicly with the Securities and Exchange Commission, and&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                              4&#13;
STRICTLY Cthey have to file a very elaborate registration statement.&#13;
&#13;
              In that statement they have to say something about the part&#13;
              of the financing that is going to be handled by the Bank,&#13;
         i\&#13;
         1.&#13;
         1:   in other words, about the Bank loan tbat will be made con-&#13;
         11&#13;
&#13;
         !I&#13;
         11&#13;
              currently with this public issue.     Because of that, before&#13;
         i&#13;
         Ii&#13;
         I!   they file this registration statement they ask us to give&#13;
         II&#13;
         Ii&#13;
         ii&#13;
         ,,   them assurance that in the absence of any serious adverse&#13;
         'I&#13;
         I&#13;
         'j   development the Bank would in principle be prepared to go&#13;
          !&#13;
              ahead and make the loan.&#13;
          I&#13;
         '!        Today we are not asking you to pass resolutions giving&#13;
              final approval to this South African and Austrian loan and&#13;
         I&#13;
              possibly the Luxembourg loan.     This final approval would not&#13;
         I    be done until the final terms of the public issues have been&#13;
         I&#13;
              fixed and we have agreed with the borrowers on the remaining&#13;
&#13;
         I    terms of the loan.   As a matter of fact, one of those things&#13;
         11&#13;
              woul,d be the rate of interest.&#13;
         !j&#13;
                   The first of these concerns South Africa, and in this&#13;
         I&#13;
              case the public offering by the bankers of $25 million is&#13;
         !,&#13;
         !1   planned for the 3rd of December.    We have had two operations&#13;
         11&#13;
         Â·1   like this involving South Africa, and I donâ&#128;¢t propose to say&#13;
         11&#13;
         11&#13;
         t'&#13;
         d any more about it except to point out that the underwriters,&#13;
         II   Dillon, Reed &amp; Company, have already filed with the SEC a&#13;
         11&#13;
&#13;
          I&#13;
          !   preliminary registration statement for an issue of $25&#13;
          I&#13;
          i&#13;
          I   million.   Then they propose to file an amendment to this         I&#13;
         II   registration statement, and in tbat amendment they will     state I&#13;
&#13;
         II                                                                       I&#13;
         'I                                                                       I&#13;
         11&#13;
                                                                                  I&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                        5&#13;
STRICTLY Cthat they understand that the Bank is proposing also to lend&#13;
&#13;
                  $25 million, but they wonrt know that until after they have&#13;
                  heard from us after this meeting today.&#13;
                       Are there any questions on this?         You have the papers&#13;
                  on this, and all I want to do today is to see whether or not&#13;
                  from those papers that you have read if you see any reason&#13;
          !! why we should not go ahead with this, provided there are no&#13;
          d&#13;
&#13;
          ii&#13;
          Ii      undue adverse developments between now and the 1st of&#13;
          11      December.   we will call a special meeting on the 1st or&#13;
              i&#13;
                  December, at which final approval of this loan will be re-&#13;
              I&#13;
          1!      quested.&#13;
          11&#13;
                       MR. MACHADO:    Mr. Chairman, I see no reason why we&#13;
          I       should not in principle agree to consider these loans and&#13;
          I&#13;
          !       approve them at the proper time.      It seems to me::that this&#13;
         11&#13;
         I.&#13;
                  is more than a project loan.      It is sort of a program loan,&#13;
          I&#13;
          I and that is a new feature that I would like to invite your&#13;
              I&#13;
              I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                  comments on.    I think it is progress in a way.        So far the&#13;
         Ii       Bank has specialized in financing specific projects. and&#13;
&#13;
         If       this is more of a loan to finance a program rather than a&#13;
         I!       project, although projects are mentioned along with the&#13;
          : program.&#13;
          l&#13;
                       THE CHAIRMAN:    I am sorry, but I cannot encourage you&#13;
         I&#13;
         11&#13;
         II too much on that. I think it is a railroad project involving&#13;
         11       a subs tant 1a l program of the ra 1lroad â&#128;¢    It l.s a t ran sporta t io&#13;
         11&#13;
         11       program, but we look upon this as a project of the&#13;
&#13;
         !1&#13;
         il&#13;
         11&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                  6&#13;
STRICTLY C transportation system of South Africa.           So if you call it a&#13;
              program, meaning by that a general governmental program, I&#13;
              would say it was not that.     It is more of a transportation&#13;
              program, but we look upon this as the railroad ts transporta-&#13;
              tion system.     It is a very big project.     It is a very big&#13;
              system, and incidentally it ls an extremely well run system,&#13;
              very efficiently run system; but it ls not what you would&#13;
              call a general program loan.&#13;
                   MR. MACHADO:     I agree it is not a general program loan&#13;
              and not a specific project loan either.        It ls sort of in&#13;
              between, and I think it ls a very interesting feature of the&#13;
         1:&#13;
         !I   loan,because it shows that in approving this loan we are&#13;
         I!&#13;
         lj&#13;
         Ii&#13;
         'I&#13;
              considering some new financing avenues or possibilities&#13;
         Ii&#13;
         JI&#13;
              which I think some of our countries would welcome.&#13;
         II&#13;
         ,,&#13;
                   THE CHAIRMAN:     Any other questions?     If there are no&#13;
&#13;
         11   more questions, then I would propose to give the underwriters&#13;
         11&#13;
              the assurance that they request that, barring some ma.jor&#13;
         lj&#13;
         l1&#13;
              adverse development, in principle we plan to go ahead with&#13;
         II&#13;
              this loan.     We will ask your final approval on the 1st of&#13;
         II&#13;
              December.&#13;
                   The second ls Austria.     This happens to be the first&#13;
         I&#13;
              joint operation we have had with the Austrian Governmento&#13;
              Incidentally, this ma.rks the first Austrian public issue to&#13;
&#13;
              be ma.de in this market since the war.       Our part of it, the        I&#13;
              Bank loan, will be similar to our previous loans for Austria,&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                      I&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                              7&#13;
STRICTLY C&#13;
             power development.   It will be nade to the Austrian Electric&#13;
&#13;
             Power Company, Verbundgesellschaft, and the Danube Power&#13;
             Company as joint borrowers, and the proceeds will be used&#13;
&#13;
             for the Aschach project on the Danube.        The bond issue, which&#13;
&#13;
             will be floated by Kuhn, Loeb and I.adenburg, Thalnann, of&#13;
&#13;
             New York, is expected to be twenty to twenty-five million&#13;
                                                     -to&#13;
             dollars, and this loan will be made l:q' the Government and           ~&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
             not to the power company, as I mentioned, as ours will be,&#13;
&#13;
             and the Austrian Government will use about half the proceeds&#13;
&#13;
             for its own program of public investment and will relend the&#13;
&#13;
             rest of it to the power company, which will then use it for&#13;
&#13;
             the Aschach project, which is our project.&#13;
       ii&#13;
       Ii&#13;
       1'&#13;
                  This bond issue is also planned for December 3rd, and&#13;
       11&#13;
       ,j&#13;
       I     this is a very important occasion for Austria.        I think this&#13;
       Ii&#13;
             reflects the real solid economic progress and stability of&#13;
       1:&#13;
             Austria and is a very important step in establishing Austria'&#13;
       II&#13;
       ii    credit in this country and in Europe.&#13;
       j!&#13;
       I,I&#13;
       11&#13;
       11         As in the case of the South African issue, we plan to&#13;
       1!&#13;
       I&#13;
       I&#13;
       i     bring this up for final approval on December 1st.       Are there&#13;
       I.&#13;
       'I    any questions on this?&#13;
&#13;
       Ii         MR. LARRE:   Mr. Chairman, considering there have been&#13;
&#13;
       I     some difficulties in the servicing of the loan of the Danube&#13;
       I&#13;
       I     Electric, which was referred   t~   when this loan was under&#13;
&#13;
             discussion during the summer, I have not heard anything since&#13;
       i&#13;
       I     that time, and I expect that due note has been taken of that&#13;
       11&#13;
       !I&#13;
       Ii&#13;
       i&#13;
       !Â·&#13;
       ti&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                              8&#13;
STRICTLY C&#13;
            and the Austrian Government will be willing to help with&#13;
            the solution of this difficulty which has lasted for many&#13;
            years.&#13;
&#13;
                 MR. COPE:    Mr. Chairman, we lmew about this discussion&#13;
&#13;
            and this problem and have had it in mind throughout the&#13;
                                              ~u..fe....rle â&#128;¢' 11...&#13;
            negotiations, and when Dr. Feiestei&amp; was here on behalf of                                ~&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            the Austrian Government he gave us a                   Â·~11    report about the       Â· J&lt;.&#13;
&#13;
             current status of the various negotiations which are going                       on~&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            He was quite optimistic that the negotiations now going on&#13;
            would soon be cleared up.&#13;
&#13;
       'i        THE CHAIRMAN:       Are there any other questions?&#13;
        '&#13;
       !I&#13;
       :1&#13;
       !:        MR. LIEF"l1 INCK:    Mr. Chairman, from the paper before us&#13;
             it appears that only part of the public issue will be made&#13;
&#13;
            available for financing of the Aschacb project.                       Can inf'orna-   i&#13;
            tion be given that will indicate how far this project will                            '&#13;
&#13;
            be financed partly by the Bank and partly by the New York&#13;
&#13;
            market?&#13;
                 THE   CHAIRMAN:     Hal:f'   or it.&#13;
                 MR. LlEFTil'WK:      Half' of it?&#13;
&#13;
                 TF..E CHAIRMAN:     That rs right.&#13;
&#13;
                 Any other questions?&#13;
&#13;
                 MR. BASYN:    Mr. Chail"t'll8n, the Board is giving agreement&#13;
&#13;
            in principle in these particular cases.                       Therefore, why dontt&#13;
&#13;
            we hear the technical reports?&#13;
&#13;
                 THE   CHAIRMAN:     We   plan to do that at the December meetin â&#128;¢&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                      9&#13;
STRICTLY C&#13;
                    ft"iR.BASYN:    Eut we are giving our agreement in principle&#13;
&#13;
             now.    It seems to me logically it should be the proper thing&#13;
&#13;
             to hear the exposition.&#13;
&#13;
                    THE CHAIRMAN:         We havenâ&#128;¢t done that in the past on this&#13;
&#13;
             kind of thing.         We have no objection to doing it if they a re&#13;
&#13;
             completed.&#13;
&#13;
                    MR. BASYN:          It would seem logical.&#13;
                       s1'rit-11JSotJ                                                     ill&#13;
                    MR. fte8!:'n:       The South African report is not ready, and&#13;
&#13;
             in the South African case it is relatively simple because you&#13;
&#13;
             have had severa 1 reporÂ·ts on the South African system in the&#13;
&#13;
       ii&#13;
       l!&#13;
       11           THE CHAIRMAN:          I think we can do this in the future if&#13;
       ii&#13;
       i'&#13;
       11&#13;
       ii    they are ready.            I think in the past when we have done this&#13;
       II&#13;
       II    there has always been some small point that hadn't been                      I&#13;
       I                                                                                  i&#13;
                                                                                          I&#13;
       I&#13;
       i&#13;
             settled and we werentt ready to do it.&#13;
       ii&#13;
       ii           MR. BASYN:          I think it is more sensible for the Board to      I&#13;
       I&#13;
       IIJ   base its decision afterÂ· having heard the technical report.&#13;
&#13;
                    THE CHAIRMAN:          I agree with you, if it is ready.   I th1.n&#13;
&#13;
             we will try to nake an effort in the future to do it and try&#13;
       II&#13;
       Â·!    to get it ready.&#13;
       IÂ·&#13;
       i            Any other questions?          If there are no other questions 1&#13;
&#13;
             I would propose to give the underwriters the assurance that&#13;
&#13;
       I they request on this.&#13;
       11&#13;
       j1           In the case of Luxembourg, we will not ask you to do&#13;
&#13;
       IÂ·I   that, and Mr. Cope might tell the Board what bas happened in&#13;
       I&#13;
       I&#13;
       I,&#13;
       ii&#13;
        I'&#13;
        ,j&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                  10&#13;
STRICTLY C&#13;
             Luxmebourg at the last minute.&#13;
                  I would like to say if we are asked to do this same kind&#13;
             of thing on Luxembourg let ts try to give it the full-dress&#13;
             treatment, just as if we were approving the loan, if we&#13;
             possibly can, 1I1 that and any other case.&#13;
                  MR. COPE:   Mr. Chairman and members of the Board, as&#13;
             you know we were hoping to be in a position to ask the Board&#13;
             for approval in principle of the Luxembourg operation.         All&#13;
             substantive points in the negotiation have been cleared and&#13;
             the underwriters were proposing to file tomorrow.       Preparatory&#13;
             to that filing, the underwriters got into touch with the&#13;
             Luxembourgers at the end of last week to ask for formal&#13;
             authority to file.   They got back a reply to the effect that&#13;
             there had been a last-minute hitch in connection with the&#13;
             legislation which was necessary 1n the Rhineland Palatinate               I&#13;
                                                                                       I&#13;
             legislature to approve the water rights treaty.       This has&#13;
       :i                                                                              I&#13;
       !l always been regarded both by the market and us as an essentia~&#13;
       1'&#13;
       JI&#13;
                                                                                       I&#13;
       II    step in this particular operation.      A number of telephone&#13;
       Ii&#13;
       q&#13;
        t!   conversations and cables have been exchanged on this point.&#13;
       11&#13;
       ti&#13;
       II The underwriters still do not know why it did not appea1Â· on&#13;
       II    the agenda of the Rhineland Palatinate legislature on Tuesday&#13;
       11    and therefore didnâ&#128;¢t come   up   for approval.   This may be&#13;
             merely a procedural hitch, and it may come up at the next&#13;
         I&#13;
       â&#128;¢I&#13;
             meeting of the legislature in a few weekst time.      On the&#13;
       11&#13;
       1!&#13;
       11    other hand, it is just possible that there may be something&#13;
       \!&#13;
       11&#13;
       I,&#13;
&#13;
       II&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                             11&#13;
STRICTLY C&#13;
             more in it than this.   At any rate, the underwriters a re not&#13;
&#13;
             in a position t o file f or two reasons.   First of all, they&#13;
             havenrt been authorized to do so by their principals in&#13;
&#13;
             Luxembourg; and, secondly, they 1n any case would not want to&#13;
&#13;
             file until they were sure this question was out of the way.&#13;
&#13;
             This may be cleared up quite soon.    It may mean as much as&#13;
&#13;
             several weeksâ&#128;¢ delay, which would mean the offering would not&#13;
&#13;
             take place until the middle of December.    We dontt know that&#13;
&#13;
             at the moment, and I think all we can do, Mr. Cha1rm3n, is&#13;
&#13;
             just to withhold action at todayis meeting and have in mind&#13;
&#13;
             that it might be necessary to call a further meeting on a few&#13;
&#13;
             days 1 notice.&#13;
&#13;
                  llIE CHAIRMAN:   Thank you.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       r!&#13;
       I&#13;
       ,I&#13;
       li&#13;
                                                                                  (&#13;
                                                                                  I&#13;
       I&#13;
       :Â·&#13;
&#13;
        i&#13;
       Ii                                                                         I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        !i&#13;
        i&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                  15&#13;
STRICTLY&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     MR. CALLAGHAN:      I would like to go back to the point&#13;
&#13;
                made by Mr. Basyn which you commented on yourself, the&#13;
&#13;
                question of whether when we approve in principle a loan&#13;
&#13;
                allied to a market operation we should have the full dis-&#13;
&#13;
                cussion of the economic aspects and the technical aspects&#13;
&#13;
                of the operation so far as the Bank is concerned.      I dontt&#13;
&#13;
                want to derogate 1o any way from the point rrade by Mr. Basyn . :&#13;
&#13;
                I agree with that entirely, and I think if I interpret your&#13;
&#13;
                position correctly it was that we shall do this wherever&#13;
                possible.      I would just like to emphasize that latter part,&#13;
&#13;
                that it should be done wherever possible, but to add also&#13;
&#13;
                this, that I think we should be careful that we donrt put&#13;
&#13;
                ourselves in the position that the Bank is in the position&#13;
                that it   i~   determining the flotation date of the public issue&#13;
&#13;
                if something has to be held up because of the technical&#13;
       ,,   I&#13;
                report or mission rs return, and ao on.     I think we can leave&#13;
            I&#13;
       ..   :&#13;
            '   it to you to watch that, but I would just like to emphasize&#13;
       "&#13;
&#13;
                the point there could be occasions when it wouldn1t be&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                             16&#13;
STRICTLY C possible, -- I think the South African case is one example&#13;
&#13;
            because the mission has ooly just been back a short time.&#13;
            It wouldntt be possible to produce the documents at this&#13;
            stage 1r the flotation is to be undertaken at the time the&#13;
            New York bankers think it appropriate.&#13;
&#13;
                   THE CHAIRMAN:    Well, I agree with botb Mr. Basyn and&#13;
&#13;
            you.    I think if it is possible we should give all the infor-&#13;
&#13;
            mation.    On the other hand, I think there may be cases where&#13;
            we cantt do it, and as a matter of fact it is very difficult&#13;
&#13;
            to adapt our operations to the market.       The invest merit bankers&#13;
&#13;
            try to pick good spots to sell their bonds, and they may want&#13;
&#13;
            to do it very quickly and we find it very difficult to try to&#13;
&#13;
            meet their time schedule.      But we will do our best to meet&#13;
&#13;
            your point and try to givE: you all the inform'!tion we can.&#13;
&#13;
                   MR. MACHADO:    For my information, since this joint&#13;
&#13;
            operation is really a new thing we are experimenting with,&#13;
&#13;
            when we are participating 1n a loan of this type does the&#13;
&#13;
            Bank have a separate loan     cont~ct,   or do we buy bonds of the&#13;
            bonds issued to the public, and what is our position as to&#13;
            the collateral of the entire tra.nsactton?&#13;
                   THE CHAIRMAN:   Well, we have no liability 1n what is&#13;
&#13;
            done in the market.      It nay be a part of the same project.&#13;
&#13;
            In the case of the Austrian one, part of the money coming&#13;
&#13;
            from the market would go to our project and part of it would&#13;
&#13;
            go for some other purpose.     That is about the answer.     We do&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                               17&#13;
STRICTLY Chave a separate contract        in each case, and in both the&#13;
&#13;
              Austrian and South African deal they plan to of fer their&#13;
&#13;
              bonds on December 3.     Now, on December 2, I plan to be in&#13;
&#13;
              New York, and at that time I will sign for the Bank with the&#13;
&#13;
              representative of the South African Government, and at the&#13;
&#13;
              same time the bankers will sign a separate agreement.       We make&#13;
&#13;
              it a joint operation, and the bankers want us in there at the&#13;
&#13;
              flame time.    They insist in most cases that we come into the&#13;
&#13;
              transaction.&#13;
&#13;
                   MR. MACHADO:     In the event of a default on a loan of that&#13;
&#13;
              type, what would be our position?     Wouli we stand as a&#13;
&#13;
              preferred creditor?&#13;
&#13;
                   THE CHAIRMAN:     No, we wouldntt be preferred.   We wouldntt&#13;
&#13;
              be preferred at all.     We would be 1n the same position, no&#13;
&#13;
              preference.    We haventt got any prior lien or anything of&#13;
&#13;
              that kind.     There was one case in Rhodesia where we had a&#13;
&#13;
              joint operation with the bankers, and in our loan to&#13;
&#13;
              Rhodesia we had the guarantee of the British Government and&#13;
&#13;
              the bankers did not have that.     So there nay be some cases&#13;
&#13;
              where it might be the same project but for one reason or&#13;
&#13;
              another we might have a preferential position, either a&#13;
&#13;
              guarantee or something of that sort.&#13;
&#13;
                   MR. MACHADO:    We may find a country which meets its&#13;
&#13;
              obligation to the International Bank and defaults on the&#13;
         i:&#13;
         i'   other part of the issue, or vice versa.     These are now&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                 18&#13;
STRICTLY C&#13;
              problems that we have to face in making new types of trans-&#13;
              actions.&#13;
                     THE CHAIRMAN:   I think it is possible that a country&#13;
              might default to other creditors and still pay the Bank.       I&#13;
&#13;
              have felt for a long time that about the last place anybody&#13;
              would want to default would be to the Bank, but I am not&#13;
              sure that that would apply where you have a joint operation.&#13;
&#13;
              I would think likely where you have got the same project that&#13;
              a country might be in the same position, although possibly&#13;
&#13;
              not.    But we would have no prior security, if thatts what&#13;
              you mean, no extra security, unless we had a case like the&#13;
&#13;
              Rhodesian where we had the u. K. guarantee and they did not&#13;
              have that.&#13;
&#13;
                     I would like to mention that we may have to have a short         1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
              meeting before next Thursday to give final approval to the&#13;
&#13;
              bond issue.    I think it will be on Tuesday, where we will&#13;
              fix the final details on price and so forth.     I will give you&#13;
&#13;
              the date just as soon as I can.&#13;
                     If there is no further business at this meeting, this&#13;
       Iiii   meeting is adjourned, and after a few minutest recess there&#13;
       Ii&#13;
       11     will be a meeting of the Board of Directors or the IFC.&#13;
       11&#13;
         1           This meeting is now adjourned.&#13;
       1&#13;
&#13;
       II            (Whereupon, at 10:40 a .m., the meeting was adjourDed.)&#13;
       I.&#13;
       "I&#13;
       !i&#13;
       II&#13;
&#13;
       II&#13;
       11&#13;
       11&#13;
       11&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="19792936">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1958/11/19792936/transcript-three-hundred-fourth-regular-meeting-executive-directors-held-thursday-november-13-1958-south-africa-austria-luxembourg
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1958/11/19792936/transcript-three-hundred-fourth-regular-meeting-executive-directors-held-thursday-november-13-1958-south-africa-austria-luxembourg</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1958/11/19792936/transcript-three-hundred-fourth-regular-meeting-executive-directors-held-thursday-november-13-1958-south-africa-austria-luxembourg</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2014-07-15T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2016-01-14T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <docm_id>090224b0828c1648</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b0828c1648</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2014/07/15/000469775_20140715174238/Rendered/INDEX/894890TSCP0Box385280B00PUBLIC0.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2014/07/15/000469775_20140715174238/Rendered/PDF/894890TSCP0Box385280B00PUBLIC0.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>1958-11-13T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <bdmdt>1958-11-13T00:00:00Z</bdmdt>
        <datestored>2014-07-15T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Transcript of three hundred fourth regular
            meeting of Executive Directors, held on Thursday, November
            13, 1958 : South Africa - Fifth Transport Project, Austria -
            Aschach Hydropower Project, Luxembourg - Viandem Pumped
            Storage Hydro Power Project
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            This partial transcript, from the
            session of the Executive Directors held on Thursday,
            November 13, 1958, covers only three proposed loans to:
            South Africa for the Fifth Transport Project; to Austria for
            the Aschach Hydropower Project; and to Luxembourg for the
            Viandem Pumped Storage Hydro Power Project. All three loans
            represent joint operations in which a Bank loan is arranged
            in conjunction with public offerings of bonds by the
            borrowers on the New York market. This meeting focused on
            the terms of the public issues and scheduled final loan
            approvals for a future session. In addition, a legislative
            issue regarding the Luxembourg project was discussed.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Transcript of three hundred fourth regular
            meeting of Executive Directors, held on Thursday, November
            13, 1958 : South Africa - Fifth Transport Project
        </docna>
        <display_title>Transcript of three hundred
            fourth regular meeting of Executive Directors, held on
            Thursday, November 13, 1958 : South Africa - Fifth Transport
            Project, Austria - Aschach Hydropower Project, Luxembourg -
            Viandem Pumped Storage Hydro Power Project : Transcript of
            three hundred fourth regular meeting of Executive Directors,
            held on Thursday, November 13, 1958 : South Africa - Fifth
            Transport Project</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/1958/11/19792936/transcript-three-hundred-fourth-regular-meeting-executive-directors-held-thursday-november-13-1958-south-africa-fifth-transport-project-austria-aschach-hydropower-project-luxembourg-viandem-pumped-storage-hydro-power-project-transcript-three-hundred-fourth-regular-meeting-executive-directors-held-thursday-november-13-1958-south-africa-fifth-transport-project</listing_relative_url>
        <topic>Government Bond Markets m1326721 335,Private Participation in Infrastructure
            m1326086 414,Hydropower m1327326 527,PPP Legal Framework m1327077 2257,Railways m1327400 166,Rail Transport m1326012 1800</topic>
        <projn>ZA-Transport-294859 -- P037478,AT-Aschach Power -- P037355</projn>
        <subtopic>Sustainable Land and Crop Management,Education for the Knowledge Economy,Bankruptcy and Resolution of Financial Distress,Debt Markets,Microfinance</subtopic>
        <docty>Transcript</docty>
        <teratopic>Rural Development,Education,Finance and Financial Sector Development</teratopic>
        <count>South Africa,Austria</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>Sub-Saharan Africa!$!Sub-Saharan Africa</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Europe!$!517190</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!517191</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Southern Africa!$!517195</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000469775_20140715174238</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>(Historic)Electric power and other energy adjustment,Railways</subsc>
        <admreg>Europe and Central Asia,Europe and Central Asia</admreg>
        <colti>Board transcript</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Rural Development,Education,Finance and Financial Sector Development</historic_topic>
        <prdln>IBRD/IDA</prdln>
        <topicv3>Government Bond Markets m1326721 335,Private Participation in Infrastructure
            m1326086 414,Hydropower m1327326 527,PPP Legal Framework m1327077 2257,Railways m1327400 166,Rail Transport m1326012 1800</topicv3>
        <sectr>(Historic)Electric Power &amp; Other Energy,Transportation</sectr>
        <majdocty>Board Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Bank loan, bond, bond issue, bonds,
            collateral, Company, creditor, creditors, defaults, Exchange
            Commission, INTERNATIONAL BANK, liability, lien, loan,
            negotiation, negotiations, private capital, public
            investment, public offering, public offerings, registration
            statement, return, Securities, transaction, treaty, underwriters
        </keywd>
        <owner>N/A</owner>
        <lndinstr>
            Sector Investment and Maintenance Loan
            Specific Investment Loan
        </lndinstr>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>Sub-Saharan Africa</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Europe</geo_region>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Southern Africa</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>89489</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sustainable Land and Crop Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation and Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Alternative Sentencing Options</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community based Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Correctional Services and Facilities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corrections</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime and Society</ml:concept><ml:concept>Defense Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Detention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enforcement Policies and Oversight Mechanism</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigative Task Force Police</ml:concept><ml:concept>Juvenile Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Law Enforcement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Offender Reintegration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Administration and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Problem solving Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Prosecution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Restorative Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Therapeutic Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Assistance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim-Offender Mediation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Knowledge Economy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sustainable Land Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Criminal Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Treaties</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Africa</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>South Africa</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Central Asia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>