<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>,er and                                                                                             ___&#13;
4_2tation&#13;
a rural think tank&#13;
August 2001&#13;
F O R E W O R D 9                               LkS0gSCO                                             eom&#13;
FOREWORD                           ~~~La           1,In           Se            o~r Reforms&#13;
The Government of India has initiated&#13;
policy reforms to improve the sustainability of  Supporting         Government of India pilot demand-&#13;
rural water supply and sanitation services.     responsive appro       cbw   to rural water supply and sanitation&#13;
Drinking Water Sector Reforms Projects with&#13;
demand-responsive approaches are being&#13;
implemented in 63 pilot districts in 26 states&#13;
throughout the country. A community-based                            -                                           I|&#13;
participatory approach has been adopted to&#13;
promote the management of water supply&#13;
services at the village level, that is, local self-&#13;
governments and communities. The scale of&#13;
the program (Rs 1,820.45 crore for 61 districts&#13;
over three years) demonstrates the strong&#13;
desire of the Central Government for reforms            ;nIsr,4V            ;.-    tw        ' &#13;
within the sector. If the pilot projects&#13;
succeed, the potential exists for scale-up to&#13;
other districts across the country. This&#13;
experiment in the drinking water and sanitation                                         --JA          ;&amp;       If//&#13;
sector can lead the way in the capacity- &#13;
building of Panchayati Raj Institutions.&#13;
The Sector Reforms Pilot Projects&#13;
reorient the very fundamentals of rural water&#13;
supply and sanitation delivery systems and&#13;
processes in India. The capacity-building of&#13;
the people's organizations - like the                  ,'_&#13;
Panchayati Raj Institutions at the district and       '.                                            .&#13;
village level-will be the foundation for these        ,I,.&#13;
projects. In this context, there is a role for      f;         Iv&#13;
External Support Agencies to supplement the                                                                                       J&#13;
efforts of the Government of India.&#13;
The Government of India has renewed&#13;
the Strategic Alliance with the Water and&#13;
Sanitation Program-South Asia for a period of&#13;
three years to provide support to the Sector&#13;
Reforms Projects. An important activity of this&#13;
partnership relates to the organization of a&#13;
series of Jal Manthan workshops for spreading&#13;
the philosophy and principles of community&#13;
participatory and demand-responsive&#13;
strategies in these Sector Reforms Projects to&#13;
every nook and cranny of the country.&#13;
Shri S.K. Tripathi&#13;
Secretary&#13;
Department of Drinking Water Supply                                      h        . &#13;
Government of India                                  a   c           t manag                                    u&#13;
Em powering local governments and communities to manage water and sanitation services.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
BACKGROUND                                           Sanitation Mission (DWSM). Users are expected to pay 10&#13;
percent of the capital cost as community contribution and&#13;
The reform program of the Government of India (GOI)  100 percent of the operation and maintenance costs. It is&#13;
makes a paradigm shift from a supply-driven to a demand-  estimated that up to 70 million people, predominantly poor,&#13;
driven approach. Despite a large investment in the Rural  will benefit from this program.&#13;
Water Supply and Sanitation (RWSS) sector to the extent of&#13;
Rs 32,000 crorel since 1954; the sustainability of drinking  JAL  M ANTHAN&#13;
water supply sources and systems and poor coverage of&#13;
rural sanitation is the reason for such a paradigm shift.  \/W ORKSHOPS&#13;
Although there are many reasons for not adequately meeting&#13;
the challenge of delivering these basic services, such as  The sector reform program pilots a significant shift in&#13;
major environmental problems due to over-exploitation of  the approach of the Union Government to RWSS service&#13;
water sources and competing use from the irrigation sector,  delivery. In order to launch the program, with the key&#13;
many believe the primary problem is the supply-driven  policy reforms and to seek feedback from state and district&#13;
approach taken by the state implementing agencies.   officials responsible for implementation, a series of work-&#13;
In response to this challenge, the GOI has embarked  shops (called Jal Manthans) were held by the GOI, in&#13;
on a program of RWSS 'sector reforms'. The primary aim of  collaboration with the Water and Sanitation Program (WSP)&#13;
sector reform is to shift to more demand-responsive and  (see Table 1 for information on the workshops).&#13;
participatory approaches by empowering local governments  A national-level workshop was held in Delhi on&#13;
and community groups to fully manage their own services.  10 July 2000, convened by the Minister for Rural Develop-&#13;
This entails operating, maintaining and repairing their own  ment, where State Secretaries from 26 states and their chief&#13;
water supply and sanitation facilities in a financially and  engineering advisors participated in the launching of the&#13;
environmentally sustainable manner without the need for  GOI sector reforms program and heard presentations about&#13;
outside support.                                     key design issues and lessons from projects demonstrating&#13;
The GOI has earmarked 20 percent of the Accelerated  'best practice'.&#13;
Rural Water Supply Programme (ARWSP) fund to support     The then Minister of Rural Development, Shri Sundar&#13;
sector reforms projects in 63 pilot districts in 26 states. To  Lal Patwa, explained "the concern for the Government in&#13;
date, over Rs 1,820 crore has been sanctioned for the  the rural water supply sector is sustainability of the&#13;
implementation of 61 district drinking water pilot projects.  sources and of the systems" and described that in the&#13;
In addition, the same districts receive funds under the  sector reform program "the emphasis will be on demand-&#13;
Restructured Centrally Sponsored Rural Sanitation Pro-  driven approaches, community participation and decen-&#13;
gramme (RCSRCP) for the sanitation component. The pilot  tralization of powers for implementing drinking water&#13;
projects will have an implementation period of three years  supply programs". He explained how "the policy changes&#13;
and are funded by the GOI directly to district level institu-  enabling these projects hope to bring about a paradigm&#13;
tions - like the Zila Parishad (ZP) or a District Water and  shift in the sector ... if successful, they could be used as a&#13;
model for expansion to other districts&#13;
GOI RWSS sector reform program - Fact file                              of the country".&#13;
In his welcome address, Shri S.K.&#13;
3umnber of states      26 (of 28 in India and 7 Union Territories)-  1  Tripathi, Secretary, Department of&#13;
Drinking Water Supply, GOI, empha-&#13;
blumber of districts  63 (of 532 in India)                            sized that "these reforms intend to&#13;
Population of India    1,013 million (2000) (approximate)           I   institutionalize community participa-&#13;
____________________________________________________________           tion in the rural water supply sector&#13;
Total rural population  94 million                                     by enabling the beneficiaries of water&#13;
ithin pilot districts                                                 supply schemes themselves to plan,&#13;
,__tal beneficiary     40-70 miln              _                  __ partially fund, implement, operate,&#13;
Total beneficiary      40-70 million                                '  maintain, manage and also provide&#13;
population       ________ _______- ___________                         for replacement of their schemes". He&#13;
Total annual GOI       Rs 2,010 crore as the Central Plan Outlay for the  stressed that under the sector reform&#13;
investment in RWSS     year 2001-2002 (this is matched by state funding)  agenda "the Government will function&#13;
primarily as a facilitator". He urged&#13;
External Support       3-5% of total capital investment per year       district representatives to "rise to the&#13;
Agencies                                                               occasion and sincerely try to fulfill this&#13;
Funds sanctioned       Rs 1,820 crore ($ 387 million)                  cherished objective [sustainability] as&#13;
to date               (61 districts sanctioned at the time of publishing)  the whole world, and the nation in&#13;
particular, are looking towards you&#13;
'1 crore = 1 0,000,000; $1 = Rs 47; Rs 1 crore = $213,000              with expectation".&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Table 1: Jal Mantha a                      s&#13;
National Workshop (Delhi, 10 July 2000) - Co-hosted                 North India (Nainital, 5-6 .Oc'tober 2000),'- Co-hosted&#13;
with the Governrnent.of lndia                 .with the Governmentiof Uttar Pradesh'..&#13;
- State Secretaries and chief engineering advisors from all 26 states  . Haryana .'imachal Pradesh&#13;
;(I6rnal,-Yamuna Nagar) .'  (Sirmour)  ..    -&#13;
r ,   i   ¢          N &gt;                     '~~~~~~~~~ 1I  v*~tE j&amp;K,d --k.      6 Punjab      - &#13;
.South India (Mangalore, 29 July 2000) - Co-hosted            .-      2(Srinagar, Udhampurj      (Bhatinda, Moga) (Muktsar)&#13;
with the Government of. Karnataka                                 I   6 Uttar Pradesh,, .-                             : :         4&#13;
~Andhra Pradesh         44.4 :'' Karnataka  . .    -         ,- .   . (Agra;,Chindauli Luckrow, Mirzapur, Sonebhadra)Y(Haridwar)*"&#13;
(Chittoor, Khammam,        *(Bellary, Mangalore, Mysore)              4               .       '          2   0- ;I&#13;
Nalgonda' Prakasam) (Nellore)*               L                    East India (GiWahati,.31-'0ctober 200           0) Co'-hosted&#13;
a Kerala                    . Tamil Nadu                          with the Government of Assam&#13;
(Kasaragod) (Kollam)'      (Coimbatore, Cuddalore,    . .             Assam                    ,Arunachal Pradesh;&#13;
Vellore, Perambalur)                  ' Oorhat, Kamrup, Sonitpur).  (Lohit, West Siang)  '&#13;
*Bih~~~i~~          aMizoram&#13;
West India (Udaipur, 1 September 2000) - Co-hosted'                   (D"abad Vaishali) '  'Serchhip)&#13;
with the Government of -Rajasthan                                    .a Nagailand                  Oi. 'Ossa&#13;
* Gujarat        '      -  m Madhya-Pradesh               -. (Dimapur)-               -    ..(Sundergarh Balasore) 6Ga njam'&#13;
(Mehsana, Rajkot, Surat) . .  (Gwalior, Sehore,            . .        Sikki                 *..Tripura&#13;
Hoshangabad, Narsinghpur, Raisen)    *   (Sikki South, Sikkim West)  (West Tripura)' "&#13;
4g                                         BengalSmSu  k&#13;
. Maharashtra.. iRajasthan                                 . |        West   ngal-.&#13;
(Amravati, Dhule, Nanded; '- '(Alwar, Jaipur, Sikkar) .             iNrnh 24 Pjrjg3nas r%i,.dnlpuri  .&#13;
Raigad)                           ;&#13;
_~~~~~~~~~RA WATU 3S U 111                                                                                          1|, T-&#13;
_ _a            .    Representatives from many states and districts participated in the&#13;
/al Manthan workshops and endorsed the Goternment of India -&#13;
sector reform program.am.&#13;
* These districts were added to the reform program post the Jal Manthan workshop series&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
W   hy   are    reforms needed?                           An important project rule to promote financial&#13;
sustainability is in increasing the role of communities in&#13;
Although water is a state subject, the central govern-  the planning and management of their own facilities and&#13;
ment plays an important role in financing state RWSS  requiring the users to pay all operation and maintenance&#13;
programs through the Accelerated Rural Water Supply   costs and at least 10 percent of the capital cost.&#13;
Programme (this is matched by funding through the state   These principles, first articulated in the GOl Eighth&#13;
resources). The Rajiv Gandhi National Drinking Water  Five Year Plan, are being taken forward in the Ninth Five&#13;
Mission was established in 1986 to give focussed attention  Year Plan (1997-2002) and have shaped the thinking&#13;
for accelerating coverage and now is in the Department of  behind the Guidelines for Implementation of the Rural&#13;
Drinking Water Supply (Department of DWS) of the      Water Supply Programme (RGDNWM, 2000).&#13;
Ministry of Rural Development.                            The program contains an incentive scheme for states&#13;
The coverage of drinking water supply in habitations  to reform. Whereas ARWSP funds are transfers from center&#13;
throughout the country - measured at 40 liters per capita  to state, the sector reform program (20 percent of the&#13;
per day - indicates that 86.9 percent of all habitations are  ARWSP funds) is reserved for states promoting reforms.&#13;
'fully covered', 11.7 percent are 'partially covered' and  Districts have been selected based on demand from the&#13;
only 1.4 percent are 'not covered'. However, many habita-  states and the challenge now exists in the implementation&#13;
tions have problems of water quality, shortages in the  of these projects.&#13;
summer months or defunct infrastructure due to poor&#13;
maintenance. Many of these schemes are usually imple-&#13;
mented through a 'supply-driven approach' in which the  Have    these     approaches&#13;
technical aspects of planning, design and construction are&#13;
given priority and little attention is paid to the preference  been  tried  elsewhere?&#13;
of the end users and the long-term management of the      The design of the sector reform program has been&#13;
scheme. Sector reforms attempt to change the focus of  influenced by lessons from successful projects from&#13;
government investments from coverage to the sustainability  within India and abroad. It has adopted state-of-the-art&#13;
of systems and sources. The program advocates the belief  principles of decentralization and community-driven&#13;
that sustainability of the systems can be improved if  development in the program design. Through a central&#13;
technical, financial and institutional decisions are made at  grant system, the GOI provides states with fiscal incen-&#13;
the appropriate grassroot level, that is, local governments  tives to reform and an opportunity to build the capacity of&#13;
or community groups.&#13;
A recent review of the sector by the World Bank and&#13;
the GOI (World Bank, 1 999) estimates the total investment i&#13;
required to fully cover all rural populations and restore  Some key events leading to&#13;
functionality in existing schemes is Rs 1 70-200 billion. If  the sector reform program&#13;
current capital outlay were increased by two-and-a-half&#13;
times, it would take the GOI 10 years to provide opera-&#13;
tional schemes to the entire population. An estimated   1. Global sector knowledge-on commufity manage-&#13;
Rs 29 billion is required annually for O&amp;M, excluding  ment disseminated and influenced&lt;rnulti-lateral and&#13;
provision for depreciation of the assets - representing 12  bilateral, donor projects in lndiat('&amp;6s and '90s).&#13;
times the current levels of funding. In addition, the sector  2. The WSP-managed JAKPASfprsojecti~nNepalvswas&#13;
has experienced rising per capita costs due to increased  z  the first RWSS project in the region to demnonstrate&#13;
investment in more expensive piped water supply schemes.  fiscal devolution directly to community&#13;
fisal evluton  irctl tocomuntygroups&#13;
(early '90s).&#13;
W   hat are the        key   principles?            I  3. The World Bank-assisted Swajal'project successfully&#13;
In order to implement sustainable RWSS systems, the  |pilots demanresponsive approaches in 1,000 villages&#13;
whole sector needs to be gradually reformed. Key reformr  in Uttar Pradesh (1996-2002) (see box).&#13;
principles - embodied in the 'demand-responsive approach' -  4. The GOl develops policy and guidelines for&#13;
as stated in the 'Cochin Declaration' (adopted at the State  adopti_g demand-r6espnsive approaches (1999,&#13;
Minister's workshop in December 1999 - WSP, 2000) are:  revised 2000)  r  '&#13;
4 adopting demand-responsive approaches and the use of  5 Guidelines aieXused in 63 pilot districts across the&#13;
participatory processes;                               c&#13;
6 changing the role of the Government from provider     ountry &#13;
to facilitator;                                     I6. Lessons from the pilot projects need to be fed back&#13;
4 establishing financial viability and sustainability of rural  into national and state policy debate to scale-up&#13;
water supply services;                                  nationwide and influence 6ther rural development&#13;
* promoting integrated water resource management.      sectors (future).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
l  lowest appropriate level. Therefore, if at all possible,&#13;
The 'Swajal' Project*               sector reform projects should be implemented through&#13;
The 'Swaial' Project*                                  the Panchayati Raj Institutions. PRIs are three-tier local&#13;
government structures with elected representatives in&#13;
The Government of Uttar Pradesh, with World Bank       the Zila Parishad (district); Block (or taluka or mandal)&#13;
assistance, is implementing an integrated rural water   Panchayat and Gram Panchayat (village level). In states&#13;
supply and environmental sanitation project in 1,000    where PRls are not fully empowered, implementation&#13;
villagesin9districts of the state, 1 2 districts of the  can be done through a DWSM that has explicit linkages&#13;
villages In 1 9 districts of the state, 12 districts of tneto the ZP. Although the guidelines offer detailed advice&#13;
Kumaon and Garhwal hills and seven districts of the     on the desired institutional arrangements, states them-&#13;
Bundelkhand region. These villages are being selected  selves can apply to the center for variants on the&#13;
on the basis of transparent criteria (such as demand,  1  suggested norms in order to be flexible to reform&#13;
need, technical factors, etc). Initially, single village  processes within each state.&#13;
schemes are being taken up. Shortlisted NGOs (Sup-          This is a major diversion from current practices&#13;
port Organizations) are assisting village communities  2  whereby implementation is through state engineering&#13;
porthe Oranizations)areassising vndcon tilheir'scemmues   departments. The various models for delivery at&#13;
In the planning and construction of their schemes.      district, block and Cram Panchayat level were dis-&#13;
The project is a major innovative demonstration in      cussed at length in the workshops. Although the&#13;
community participation, community procurement          district institution (ZP or DWSM) is the nodal agency&#13;
and partial capital cost recovery in water supply      for implementation, actual implementation will need&#13;
systems. The total project cost is US$ 71 million to be  to be done at village level: either through the GP or&#13;
used over the project duration from 1996 to 2002.      through Village Water and Sanitation Committees or&#13;
(http://www.swajal.org/index.htm)                       local users committees. Community contracting,&#13;
whereby the communities themselves procure goods&#13;
and services for construction and O&amp;M is an essential&#13;
'The name 'Swajal' was adapted from the Hindi words 'swa' meaning  principle of the program (see WSP publication, 2001:&#13;
'self' or 'our' and 'jal', 'water'&#13;
'Community Contracting in Rural Water and Sanita-&#13;
tion'). NGOs can be contracted to assist local institu-&#13;
tions in developing their capacity for the implementa-&#13;
the Panchayati Raj Institutions (PRIs). The objective of  tion and management of the system. Adopting these new&#13;
financially and environmentally sustainable rural water  institutional arrangements will take some time and will&#13;
supply systems through management at the lowest appro-  provide a platform for decentralized delivery, but will&#13;
priate level also provides a long-term incentive to states to  need extensive capacity support to be effective. Institu-&#13;
relieve them of their current burden of recurrent costs and  tional analysis and strengthening will need to be state-&#13;
dysfunctional systems.                               specific in order to adapt to the local environment.&#13;
Projects designed with demand-responsive&#13;
approaches have had successes abroad and in India. One  Ho    are&#13;
notable example in India is the World Bank-assisted Uttar  w         activities&#13;
Pradesh Rural Water Supply and Environmental Sanitation  sequenced?&#13;
Project (or 'Swajal' Project: see box). Other countries have&#13;
had some success in implementing DRA projects (for       The program is to be implemented in a phased&#13;
example, the Ghana Community Water and Sanitation    manner. As it will take these new institutions time to&#13;
Project, 'Prosabar' RWSS in Bolivia, WSSLIC in Indonesia,  develop the capacity for implementation, it is envisaged&#13;
The Mvula Trust, South Africa and others). However, none  that implementation will take place in batches, for&#13;
of these projects have been able to scale-up to a national  example, in any particular district, four batches may be&#13;
level. Indeed little is known globally by water sector  taken up, first, with a small number (50 villages or&#13;
professionals on how to scale-up these approaches.   habitations) and three larger batches (for example, 1 00&#13;
villages each). As one batch moves from the first phase&#13;
W   ho   are the                                     of awareness creation and community mobilization to&#13;
the second phase of planning and design, the next batch&#13;
can start on phase one. Each district will need to&#13;
primary       actors?                                develop the 'scheme cycle' through which individual&#13;
The GOI guidelines (RGNDWM, 2000) support the    village projects will need to proceed. The guidelines&#13;
wider decentralization agenda of the Union Government  suggest four phases of (i) institutionalizing (3 months)&#13;
consistent with the 73rd Constitutional Amendment and  (ii) sensitization and village identification (12 months)&#13;
globally accepted best practice (as articulated in the  (iii) planning and design (9 months) and (iv) implemen-&#13;
Dublin-Rio Principles) for service delivery of RWSS at the  tation and commissioning (12 months).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-&#13;
ISSUES         EMERGING             FROM              (Information, Education, Communication), hygiene&#13;
promotion and training. The guidelines indicate that up to&#13;
TLl  I AE I  A /1 t 'THANS                  one-third of the total project cost can be spent on these&#13;
THE r      AL   MANTHANS 1                            'non-hardware' activities. However, many district teams&#13;
Institutional framewor *may not be able to make full use of these funds, as they&#13;
may not fully appreciate the value of these activities.&#13;
As PRIs are not fully empowered in many states,   Therefore support is also needed to catalyze the demand&#13;
projects may be implemented through District Societies  for capacity-building.&#13;
(DWSMs). Although this is a means to achieve delivery, the  Workshop participants identified the need for resource&#13;
long-term sustainability of these institutions is questionable.  centers that can assist state and district training institutions&#13;
The future role of State Engineering Departments (for  frame their capacity-building strategy to be consistent with&#13;
example, Public Health Engineering Departments (PHEDs),  the national program and ensure that the piloting process&#13;
Water Boards, etc) was a topic that generated extensive  informs the wider reform debate within each state. Guide-&#13;
discussion at the workshops and will continue to be a  lines on financial aspects, implementation, O&amp;M, training,&#13;
major challenge for each state to address. Reorienting and  monitoring and IEC aspects need to be issued to flesh-out&#13;
restructuring these institutions to be able to adapt to the  the existing guidelines. As capacity requirements will vary&#13;
new approaches is an option that needs substantive    among states and even between districts, a flexible frame-&#13;
research -'this is already happening in some states.  work of support needs to be developed to respond to&#13;
specific demands.&#13;
Political commitment to                               Integration with&#13;
reform process                                        s                 cm        i&#13;
Politicians at every level - center, state, district and  sanitation  campaign&#13;
sub-district - need to be sensitized to the stark reality of  Parallel to the sector reform program in drinking&#13;
the state of the RWSS sector. They also need to be con-  water supply, the Department of Drinking Water Supply,&#13;
vinced that solutions may lie in adopting the reform  GOI, is implementing the Total Sanitation Campaign&#13;
principles as articulated by the GOI. The concept that  under RCSRSP. The program, supported by both the GOI&#13;
sustainability can be improved if users themselves have a  and state governments, is being implemented in 150&#13;
major stake in managing their own supply and therefore  districts across the country, including districts of the&#13;
also share the cost of supply needs to be discussed and  Drinking Water Supply Reforms Pilot districts. The&#13;
debated. This requires a shift in many political messages:  program introduces a 'low' subsidy policy (subsidy for&#13;
moving away from supplying a poor service, free; to   household latrines are reduced from Rs 2,000 to Rs 500)&#13;
providing adequate&#13;
services, albeit at some&#13;
cost to consumers and&#13;
hence recognizing that&#13;
water is an economic as&#13;
well as a social good.&#13;
Capacity-&#13;
building&#13;
The sector reforms&#13;
program advocates a     -TU&#13;
new approach to RWSS&#13;
Implementing institu-&#13;
tions need substantial      (                               nV &#13;
to fuilytake up their                _ 7~f&#13;
capacity support in order  _ .&#13;
new role. Each district                  _F&#13;
project has significant                                        * ;&#13;
funds budgeted within    ,       '-&#13;
the project for 'soft-&#13;
ware', for example,&#13;
awareness creation, IEC   A&#13;
Benefits of community-managed water supply services are enacted for a village audience&#13;
during a 'kalajatha' in Andhra Pradesh.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
5. Give up to three subjects/issues in the Water Supply and Sanitation sector that interest you and you would like to&#13;
know more about:&#13;
i)&#13;
ii)&#13;
iii)&#13;
6. Do you know anyone else who might benefit from receiving our publication?&#13;
If yes, provide the following details (optional)&#13;
Name:&#13;
Designation:&#13;
Organization:&#13;
Address:&#13;
Phone Numbers:&#13;
E-mail:&#13;
Area of work: Government/ NGO/ Private Sector/Academia / Consultant/ Bilateral Agency / Dev Bank/ any other&#13;
7. Provide your particulars (if different from address on envelope)&#13;
Name:&#13;
Designation:&#13;
Organization:&#13;
Address:&#13;
Phone Numbers:&#13;
E-mail:&#13;
Area of work: Government / NGO / Private Sector / Academia / Consultant / Bilateral Agency / Dev Bank / any other&#13;
8. Indicate your area of interest:&#13;
D Water&#13;
0 Sanitation&#13;
0 Rural&#13;
0 Urban&#13;
Water and Sanitation Program-South Asia&#13;
55 Lodi Estate, New Delhi 110 003 * Tel: 91-11-4690488/89 - Fax: 91-11-4628250&#13;
* E-mail: wspsa@worldbank.org * Website: www.wsp.org&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
h0o                                             JAL MANTHAN 4&#13;
Water and&#13;
Sanitation&#13;
FEEDBACK FORM&#13;
1. Is the format of this publication easy to read?                    OYes                          O No&#13;
2. Is the publication a comfortable length to read?                   OYes                          DNo&#13;
3. If no, would you prefer                                            O more details/data           Oless details/data&#13;
4. Do you find the information contained in this publication relevant to your work?                 DYes        0 No&#13;
If yes, how would you use this informotion in your work? (Use extra sheets of paper if required)  If no, give reasons why&#13;
(Use extra sheets of paper if required)&#13;
Whot impact, if any, does this information hove on:&#13;
*You:&#13;
*Your organization:&#13;
*Your colleagues:&#13;
What are the main lesson(s) you have learnt from the information contained in this publication?&#13;
Would you like to shore any study/research similar to the information in this publication?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
to move towards more demand-responsive approaches    piloting needs to be conducted to test out new models&#13;
and ensure maximum subsidy to the least cost unit.  for demand-responsive multi-village schemes.&#13;
It is universally accepted that for drinking water&#13;
projects to have any significant impact in improving public  LEA I NG    BY    SEEING&#13;
health (for example, reduction in diaorrhoeal and other  LEARNING        BY    SEEING&#13;
water-related disease), they need to be accompanied by   WSP in partnership with the Center for Development&#13;
sanitation and hygiene promotion initiatives. Although  Studies (CDS) of the Uttar Pradesh Academy of Administra-&#13;
there are two separate schemes at a central level, both  tive, Nainital. organized Observation Study Tours of the&#13;
programs are implemented at the district level.      Swajal project for all the sector reform districts between&#13;
In principle, the same district institutions can imple-  November 2000 and June 2001. CDS are the principal&#13;
ment both schemes, although this will not necessarily be  software' trainers for the Swajal project and have been&#13;
the case unless states and districts opt for this arrangement.  closely associated with other community-based develop-&#13;
This integration at the district level can be mutually  ment projects. Key personnel (District Collectors, PHED&#13;
beneficial to both schemes in reaching their objectives.  Engineers, Zila and Gram Panchayat Presidents, Zila&#13;
Many activities of the two programs are complemen-  Panchayat CEOs, etc) from the pilot districts and state&#13;
tary, for example, the IEC Campaigns, Human Resource  representatives attended a three-day training visit in the UP&#13;
Development, community mobilization and many others.  hills and plains as exposure to the 'Swajal model' that has&#13;
WSP, along with the Department of DWS, is preparing a  been so influential in the design of the GOI program. The&#13;
capacity framework for sector reforms that complements  visits combined frank workshop discussions with visits to&#13;
the RCSRSP and ensures integration in implementation in  projects directly managed by community groups.&#13;
the districts and gram panchayats.                       Although many participants were skeptical about the&#13;
sustainability and scalability of community-based&#13;
M   ulti-village      schemes                        approaches, the visits had noticeable effects on changing&#13;
the perception of many participants. Some lessons learnt&#13;
Demand-responsive projects have been more       from the feedback from participants include:&#13;
successful in areas where local sources are available -  6 system of community action planning could be a power-&#13;
due to the relative simplicity of community-based   ful means of ensuring peoples' active involvement in&#13;
operation and maintenance. Often when local sources  decision-making;&#13;
are not available - due to inadequate quantity or quality  6 system of tripartite  NE&#13;
- engineers have designed multi-village schemes (or  agreement among district  K&#13;
regional schemes), that is, many villages served by a piped  project management&#13;
water network conveying&#13;
water from a remote source.&#13;
These schemes are techni-&#13;
cally and institutionally more&#13;
complex and entrusting the&#13;
management of the scheme to&#13;
the community, as envisaged-&#13;
in the sector reform program,                                   iI|&#13;
may be more challenging                              .&#13;
(although the decision- aking  p      -&#13;
about the management option&#13;
should still be at the lowest&#13;
appropriate level).&#13;
Many regional workshop&#13;
participants indicated&#13;
that demand-responsive&#13;
approaches to more complex&#13;
multi-village schemes would&#13;
be more difficult to imple-&#13;
ment. It is clear that sector&#13;
reforms will be easier in&#13;
single source villages and&#13;
districts should be encour-&#13;
aged to select habitations&#13;
with this in mind; however,&#13;
substantive research and                              z-&#13;
Participants on a study tour observing how villages constructed, and now operate, their own water supply.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
O B           110  R d   0              The Jal Manthan (meaning 'churning of water' in Hindi) is a think tank&#13;
PEO   waa(w DO&amp; Why an d            on rural water supply and sanitation. It is a travelling forum that aims to be&#13;
an open network encouraging frank and informal policy-level dialogue&#13;
o WO MtM1   n ZI 02M:               between sector practitioners and professionals. Prior to this series of&#13;
M(W WanQw MP8O* md unuworkshops, three Jal Manthans have been held.&#13;
nmnqpnwo. cwrhtl, bu) 0y&#13;
o DAO           30 Rao Wacw&#13;
INJO§S#  W e$°Efow /O&#13;
wacf,ow X #faomo &#13;
unit (DPMU), support organization (SO) and villa e water  approaches within the state; lessons learnt of best practice&#13;
and sanitation committees (VWSC), as adopted in e      and direct technical assistance in implementation are all&#13;
Swajal project, could be suitably modified and adopt   areas that need support.&#13;
in reform projects as well;                                External Support Agencies have been supporting&#13;
6 release of payment could be output-based to ensure  similar reform principles for decades, but never at this&#13;
efficient financial allocation and use of available resources;  scale. This program offers a significant opportunity for&#13;
6 hiring of specialized service agencies for IEC, capacity-  furthering those very principles. Although the program is&#13;
building and quality control could be adopted;         fully funded by the GOI, a role does exist for donors to&#13;
6 system of maintaining proceedings register, cash book  support the process and assist in capacity-building. WSP&#13;
and other account books could be encouraged at the     has developed a framework for capacity support through&#13;
village level;                                         which donor support can be coordinated.&#13;
6 use of participatory tools and techniques for community&#13;
mobilization could be adopted to create community interest  @       ¢&#13;
and involvement at each stage of the scheme cycle.       e&#13;
1. Rajiv Gandhi National Drinking Water Mission (2000)&#13;
WAY         [FURIW   ARD                               Guidelines for Implementation of Rural Water Supply&#13;
Programme (Revised and updated 2nd Edition).&#13;
If succesful, the sector reform pilots could lead the  2. Tripathi, S.K. and Kumar, A. (2000) Rural Water&#13;
way for all rural areas in India in demand-responsive  Supply Programme in India. People's Participation in&#13;
delivery,qf water supply and sanitation. The potential for  Drinking Water Supply Sector Reforms: The emerging&#13;
strengthening local government and thereby opening the  scenario. Paper presented at the 26th WEDC conference&#13;
door for more effective delivery of other services is also  in Dhaka, Bangladesh.&#13;
vast. If carefully implemented, the program could be   3. WSP (2000) Politicians for Reform. Proceedings of the&#13;
considered global 'best practice'.                     State Water Ministers' workshop on rural water supply and&#13;
The Jal Manthan workshops raised important areas of  sanitation reforms in India, Cochin, Kerala (India),&#13;
support needed to ensure the success of this ambitious  December 7-8, 1999.&#13;
program. Building capacity of local governments and    4. World Bank (1999) Rural Water Supply and Sanitation&#13;
communities to manage their own services; supporting   Report. India - Water Resource Management Sector&#13;
policy debate in state governments to scale-up these   Review in collaboration with the Government of India.&#13;
For more information on the Rural Think Tank, please contact:&#13;
jal manthan: a rural think tank                                                      August 2001&#13;
c/o India Country Team, Water and Sanitation Program-South Asia                      Created by Write Media&#13;
55 Lodi Estate, New Delhi 110 003                                                    E-mail: writemedia@vsnl.com&#13;
Tel: 469 0488/89 Fax: 462 8250 e-mail: wspsa@worldbank.org                           Printed at Thomson Press&#13;
www.wsp.org&#13;
The Water and Sanitation Program is an international partnership to help the poor gain sustained access to improved water supply and sanitation services&#13;
The Program's funding partners are the Governments of Australia, Belgium, Canada, Denmark, Germany, Italy, Japan, Luxembourg, the Netherlands,&#13;
Norway, Sweden, Switzerland, and the United Kingdom; the United Nations Development Programme, and The World Bank&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="1993698">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2001/08/1993698/launching-sector-reforms-supporting-government-india-pilot-demand-responsive-approaches-rural-water-supply-sanitation
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2001/08/1993698/launching-sector-reforms-supporting-government-india-pilot-demand-responsive-approaches-rural-water-supply-sanitation</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2001/08/1993698/launching-sector-reforms-supporting-government-india-pilot-demand-responsive-approaches-rural-water-supply-sanitation</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2002/09/24/000094946_02090604122988/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2002/09/24/000094946_02090604122988/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2002-09-24T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2001-08-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Launching sector reforms : supporting the
            Government of India pilot demand-responsive approaches to
            rural water supply and sanitation
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The Government of India has embarked on
            a program of Rural Water Supply and Sanitation 'sector
            reforms', to shift to more demand-responsive and
            participatory approaches by empowering local governments and
            community groups to fully manage their own services. The
            program is to be implemented in a phased manner and
            implementation will take place in batches. The primary
            actors will include the district institution, local users
            committees, and nongovernmental organizations. If
            successful, the sector reform pilots could lead the way for
            all rural areas in India in demand-responsive delivery of
            water supply and sanitation. The potential for strengthening
            local government and thereby opening the door for more
            effective delivery of other services is also vast. Although
            fully funded by the government, a role does exist for donors
            to support the process and assist in capacity-building.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Launching sector reforms : supporting the
            Government of India pilot demand-responsive approaches to
            rural water supply and sanitation
        </docna>
        <display_title>Launching sector reforms :
            supporting the Government of India pilot demand-responsive
            approaches to rural water supply and sanitation</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2001/08/1993698/launching-sector-reforms-supporting-government-india-pilot-demand-responsive-approaches-rural-water-supply-sanitation</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>UNDP-Water &amp; Sanitation Program</docty>
        <subtopic>Town Water Supply and Sanitation,Water and Industry,Water Supply and Sanitation Governance
            and Institutions,Health Economics &amp; Finance,Water Conservation</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Water Resources</teratopic>
        <count>India</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>South Asia!$!80470</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Asia!$!80451</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000094946_02090604122988</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>South Asia,South Asia</admreg>
        <subsc>Water supply</subsc>
        <colti>Water and sanitation program</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Water Resources</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Demand-driven; Rural water supply; Pilots;
            Nongovernmental organizations; Community-based development;
            Government role; Water management; Workshops; Donors;
            Capacity building; Community participation; Local government
            adequate services,Central
            Government,community action,community contribution,community
            groups,community interest,community participation,Community
            Water,construction,conveying,cost recovery,district drinking
            water,diversion,Drinking Water,Drinking Water
            Sector,Drinking Water Supply,environmental
            sanitation,financial viability,hygiene promotion,least
            cost,maintenance costs,management of water,management of
            water supply,management of water supply
            services,participatory approaches,piped water,Private
            Sector,programs,project management,Public Health,Rural
            Drinking Water,rural sanitation,rural water,rural water
            supply,sanitation component,sanitation facilities,Sanitation
            sector,sanitation services,service delivery,Urban
            Water,Water Boards,water projects,water quality,water
            resource,water resource management,water sources,water
            supply services
        </keywd>
        <owner>SACIN - India CMU (SACIN)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>South Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Asia</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>24700</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Science and Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Capacities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Staffing Needs Assessments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutritional supplements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Vitamins</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Basic Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>On-site Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Marketing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deconcentration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delegation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Devolution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sub-National Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subnational Government and Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Foreign Direct Investments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Linkages</ml:concept><ml:concept>Town Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Engineering</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Growth and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural &amp; Small Town Water &amp; Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supplements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water, Sanitation and Hygiene</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports &amp; Waterways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Local Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Administrative Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>FDI Spillovers</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>India</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Southern Asia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>