<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>                                                                                                      92590&#13;
&#13;
      Capacity Development&#13;
                                                                     briefs&#13;
             S h a r i n g      k n o w l e d g e           a n d   L e ss o n s      L e a r n e d&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The Need for a Conceptual and Results-Oriented Framework&#13;
in Capacity Development: Discussion of a New Approach&#13;
By Samuel Otoo, Natalia Agapitova, Jenny Gold, and Sharon Fisher&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   Efforts to develop capacity are being hindered by disparate methodologies, insufficient focus on outcomes&#13;
   and indicators, and a lack of concrete results to show improved capacity. The authors examine the need&#13;
   for a new resource to guide, capture, and communicate capacity development efforts. They outline a&#13;
   results-driven and systematic frameworkâ&#128;&#148;based on rigorous needs assessment, innovative change process&#13;
   logic, and participatory implementationâ&#128;&#148;that is driven by local ownership, adaptive management, and&#13;
   measurable results. This resource could fill a critical gap in capacity development design and reporting, as&#13;
   well as fuel further discussion in the development community.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  In Kenya, a capacity development project to mitigate       work, such as the number of people trained and anec-&#13;
the adverse impact of HIV/AIDS as part of a multisec-        dotal information, rather than the tangible evidence&#13;
toral response has been deemed a success. The project        required to demonstrate whether the program reduced&#13;
team, which consisted mainly of international consul-        the adverse impact of HIV/AIDS.&#13;
tants, created a social support network for people liv-        As the demand for capacity development programs&#13;
ing with HIV/AIDS and trained more than 300 network          increases around the globe, examples such as this&#13;
members as counselors to distribute educational mate-        hypothetical case could proliferate. To orient capac-&#13;
rials and provide support to infected persons and their      ity development toward successful promotion of local&#13;
families.                                                    ownership and measurable results, continuing dia-&#13;
  However, the implementation reveals underlying             logue is needed.&#13;
capacity constraints that were not properly assessed&#13;
and addressed by project design. The team disregarded&#13;
                                                             Consequences of Poor Design and Measurement&#13;
stigma-related issues that prevent people from seeking&#13;
counseling. Other challenges included the low com-&#13;
mitment of local HIV/AIDS service providers and com-           Capacity development has revolutionized the busi-&#13;
munity leaders to support the initiative, unaddressed        ness of international assistance with its paradigm shift&#13;
links between psychosocial and other HIV/AIDS-related        to accelerating development by unleashing the poten-&#13;
support needs, and limited stakeholder ownership and         tial that is already available within countries rather&#13;
motivation to sustain or further develop the network.        than simply resource transfer from abroad. Donors&#13;
Moreover, the team did not collect evidence on key           now spend more than $20 billion a year on a range of&#13;
outcomes, such as on the creation of the network, par-       capacity development activities.&#13;
ticipation of stakeholders in the network, use of skills       However, results have not met expectations, leading&#13;
built through training, delivery of counseling services,     some policymakers and development practitioners to&#13;
and changes in the behavior of community members.            question the merit of such efforts. Why have expecta-&#13;
  As the team prepares to depart, it sees its efforts        tions not been met?&#13;
unraveling while community requests for continued              Evaluations, critical reviews, and working groups&#13;
resources increase. They also realize their report to the    note a failure of current practice to build a more ana-&#13;
donor agency contains only basic outputs from their          lytic and rigorous approach to needs assessments,&#13;
&#13;
       APRIL 2009&#13;
       NUMBERâ&#128;&#130; 31&#13;
&amp;#12;program design, and the definition and measurement                capacity development and support a community of&#13;
of results.1 The problem begins with a lack of consen-            practice?&#13;
sus on the meaning of capacity development and the          â&#128;¢	    Evidence of aid-effectiveness: A central part of&#13;
results that can be expected from such programs. This             the capacity development programâ&#128;&#148;monitoring&#13;
lack of clarity makes it difficult to evaluate outcomes,          and evaluationâ&#128;&#148;has been largely neglected. How&#13;
understand impact, and determine accountability.                  then can one resolve weaknesses in program&#13;
  Capacity development operations frequently lack a               design and better deploy capacity resources?&#13;
conceptual framework. Programs tend to adopt a tech-&#13;
nical approach without understanding local knowledge&#13;
and practice and the sociopolitical, policy, and orga-      Laying the Groundwork for a New Approach&#13;
nizational factors that affect capacity. Strategically&#13;
important questions are also often overlooked: How            The World Bank Institute designed the Capacity for&#13;
will activities create impact and thereby contribute to a   Development Results Framework to respond to these&#13;
development goal? How will the program engage local         issues, by bringing together existing thinking and&#13;
partners and stakeholders to drive the change process       practice into a results-oriented resource that can guide&#13;
needed to improve capacity? Are local stakeholders          capacity development efforts. Development practi-&#13;
committed to allocating resources (time, energy, and        tioners can iteratively adapt its elements to specific&#13;
enthusiasm) to a development goal?                          contexts to improve the design, implementation, and&#13;
  Such challenges are compounded by a poorly                evaluation of capacity development programs from the&#13;
articulated results chain, that is, weak links among        needs assessment stage to the adaptive management&#13;
needs assessments, capacity development activities,         of results to the sharing of lessons learned.&#13;
outcomes, and impact toward development goals. As             According to the framework, capacity development&#13;
a result, programs regularly fail to capture capacity       is a locally driven process by which change agents&#13;
impact within monitoring and evaluation systems. The        affect sociopolitical, policy, and organizational fac-&#13;
lack of evidence of what changes actually take place in     tors to achieve a development goal. The framework&#13;
different contexts means that potentially inappropriate     describes the elements of a capacity development pro-&#13;
interventions persist.                                      gram (see diagram), as follows:&#13;
  These issues present far-reaching consequences:&#13;
                                                            â&#128;¢	    A specified development goal that has stakeholder&#13;
â&#128;¢	   Results: Current capacity development analysis               ownership and motivates the capacity develop-&#13;
     tends to focus on the immediate outputs of activi-           ment effort in that local context&#13;
     tiesâ&#128;&#148;such as the number of people trainedâ&#128;&#148;with         â&#128;¢	    Sociopolitical, policy, and organizational capacity&#13;
     little information about outcomes or impact and              factors that can be used to assess capacity needs,&#13;
     lack of accountability to stakeholders. How then             inform design, and measure impact&#13;
     can anyone convince clients, donors, and col-&#13;
     leagues of the viability of these approaches, much&#13;
     less build their own confidence in capacity devel-&#13;
     opment efforts?&#13;
â&#128;¢	   Comparability: The absence of consistent results            A New Approach to Capacity Development&#13;
     frameworks and performance indicators makes it&#13;
     difficult to compare capacity development activi-                       Capacity for Achieving a Development Goal&#13;
     ties and identify best practices. How then can&#13;
     one avoid falling into the pitfalls of previous pro-           Local Ownership, Effectiveness and Efficiency of Resource Use&#13;
     grams?&#13;
                                                                                          Capacity Factors&#13;
â&#128;¢	   Sustainability: Sustainable development requires&#13;
                                                                    Conduciveness of        Efficiency of        Effectiveness of&#13;
     a genuine partnership, with a mutual understand-                 Sociopolitical            Policy           Organizational&#13;
     ing of the change process and evaluation terms.                  Environment           Instruments           Arrangements&#13;
     Without an underlying framework for the capac-&#13;
                                                                               Change Process driven by Change Agents&#13;
     ity development process, how can one inclusively&#13;
     consider goals, strategy, and results with part-                                        Outcomes&#13;
     ners?&#13;
                                                                              Capacity Development Program Activities&#13;
â&#128;¢	   Learning: The potential for learning among&#13;
     development practitioners is not being fully real-&#13;
     ized because of a lack of common terminology&#13;
     and mechanisms for exchange. How then can one            1&#13;
                                                                See, for example, OECD (2005, 2006), Taylor and Clarke&#13;
     establish a global knowledge architecture around       (2008), and World Bank (2005, 2006).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        APRIL 2009&#13;
        NUMBERâ&#128;&#130; 31&#13;
&amp;#12;â&#128;¢	   A change process through which capacity factors         for example, changes in consensus building, coalitions&#13;
     are made more favorable to achieving a develop-         and networks, and the formation and implementation&#13;
     ment goal                                               of policy and strategy instruments.&#13;
â&#128;¢	   The role of change agents, that is, influential indi-&#13;
     viduals or groups                                       Targeting the Needs of Development Practice&#13;
â&#128;¢	   Measurable outcomes for capacity development&#13;
     activities (in particular, technical assistance,&#13;
     knowledge exchange, and structured learning)              This innovative framework emerged from analysis&#13;
                                                             of capacity development practice and consideration for&#13;
                                                             the current needs of the development community. The&#13;
  How the above elements fit within the framework is&#13;
                                                             framework was designed to be the following:&#13;
further described below:&#13;
                                                             â&#128;¢	    Practical: The framework is a user-friendly&#13;
   Capacity impact: Local ownership and the effi-&#13;
                                                                   resource applicable in different contexts. Various&#13;
ciency and effectiveness with which countries pursue&#13;
                                                                   materials to support its application are being con-&#13;
development goals are determined by three factors:&#13;
                                                                   tinuously refined based on feedback from pilot&#13;
(1) conduciveness of the sociopolitical environment,&#13;
                                                                   teams and stakeholder consultations.&#13;
(2) efficiency of the policy instruments used by gov-&#13;
ernment and other sectors, and (3) effectiveness of the      â&#128;¢	    Flexible: The framework is not a blueprint to&#13;
organizational arrangements. Development practitio-                control processes; rather, it is a set of recommen-&#13;
ners can use these factors to design a capacity devel-             dations compatible with a range of situations and&#13;
opment program that addresses targeted development                 change management methods. Its components can&#13;
challenges and brings about measurable change in                   be applied across sectors and programs, promoting&#13;
these factors.                                                     a â&#128;&#156;learn as you goâ&#128;&#157; mentality for a more adaptive&#13;
                                                                   approach to interventions.&#13;
   Change process: The framework can help to iden-&#13;
tify how capacity development activities can lead to         â&#128;¢	    Results driven: The framework facilitates bench-&#13;
gains toward development goals by linking activities               marking and the harmonization of monitoring and&#13;
and outcomes from these activities to their impact                 evaluation practices. This continuous and careful&#13;
on capacity factors. This link creates a change pro-               attention to results helps one to deliver quantita-&#13;
cess logic that is based on building blocks amenable               tive and qualitative proof of the value and efficacy&#13;
to the development of indicators and measurement                   of programs.&#13;
of results. Although change processes can occur              â&#128;¢	    Collaborative: The framework encourages can-&#13;
through many channels, the framework focuses on                    did discussion of sociopolitical forces and incen-&#13;
adaptation on the part of people or organizations                  tives. By promoting a voice for all stakeholders&#13;
within a given institutional context in response to                and anchoring the development effort in a specific&#13;
new information, redefinition of institutional rules               goal, the framework helps to further local commit-&#13;
and structures, and shifts in belief systems, power                ment and country ownership.&#13;
balances and relations. Such changes can be fostered&#13;
and accelerated through interventions that enhance&#13;
the use of knowledge and information, rather than&#13;
through resource inputs (human, financial capital,&#13;
technology, and so on).&#13;
   Change agents: The framework casts individuals                 How the Framework Can Be Applied&#13;
in terms of change agents who can initiate or lead&#13;
the capacity development process. Thus, development               In the context of a capacity development program, one can&#13;
practitioners should concentrate on the potential role            use the framework to&#13;
of local individuals or groups in bringing about favor-&#13;
                                                                  â&#128;¢	 inclusively engage stakeholders in the program cycleâ&#128;&#148;&#13;
able change in capacity factors to achieve development               starting from the needs assessment stageâ&#128;&#148;and ensure&#13;
goals.                                                               local ownership&#13;
   Capacity development activities and outcomes:                  â&#128;¢	 define a capacity development strategy to apply at the&#13;
                                                                     community, regional, or country level&#13;
The framework provides a typology of outcomes to                  â&#128;¢	 identify intermediate points along the change path for&#13;
guide the design of capacity development programs                    adaptive management of the change process&#13;
and capture their results. Outcomes may refer to the              â&#128;¢	 build indicators into program design to monitor progress&#13;
effects of changes that occur in an individual, includ-              and, when necessary, adjust the program&#13;
                                                                  â&#128;¢	 communicate results to donors and stakeholders&#13;
ing changes in awareness and skills. Outcomes may                 â&#128;¢	 compare programs and determine what does and does&#13;
also refer to altered processes and new products and                 not work to improve practice.&#13;
thus the broader organizational or social environment,&#13;
&amp;#12;Conclusion                                                   measurementâ&#128;&#148;such as the frameworkâ&#128;&#148;can only&#13;
                                                             enrich the practice for the ultimate benefit of country&#13;
                                                             partners.&#13;
  Why do we need a new systematic framework for&#13;
                                                               The authors encourage your comments via&#13;
capacity development? Capacity development has&#13;
                                                             capacity4change@worldbank.org&#13;
become the focus of international development efforts.&#13;
Enormous amounts of funding are invested every&#13;
yearâ&#128;&#148;estimated at 25 percent of global expenditure           References&#13;
on overseas development assistance. Yet, development&#13;
                                                             OECD. 2005. The Paris Declaration on Aid&#13;
practitioners still lack consensus on capacity develop-&#13;
                                                               Effectiveness. Paris.&#13;
ment: what it is, what it can do, and what the steps&#13;
                                                             OECD. 2006. Survey on Monitoring the Paris&#13;
are to attain it.&#13;
                                                               Declaration: Overview of the Results. Paris.&#13;
  A systematic framework that permits examination&#13;
                                                             Taylor, P. and P. Clarke. 2008. Capacity for a Change.&#13;
of the strengths and weaknesses of capacity develop-&#13;
                                                               Institute of Development Studies. Sussex.&#13;
ment programs and sharing of experiences is much&#13;
                                                             World Bank Independent Evaluation Group (IEG).&#13;
desired to satisfy accountability needs and meet the&#13;
                                                               2005. Capacity Building in Africa: An IEG&#13;
need for learning as the basis for improvement. No&#13;
                                                               Evaluation of World Bank Support. Washington,&#13;
longer is it feasible to launch programs, declare them&#13;
                                                               D.C.&#13;
a success, and then leave without concrete proof of&#13;
                                                             World Bank Independent Evaluation Group (IEG).&#13;
the achievement of objectives and strong country&#13;
                                                               2006. Annual Review of Development Effectiveness.&#13;
ownership. Those able to show results will get the&#13;
                                                               Washington, D.C.&#13;
resources, which will create incentives for improved&#13;
monitoring and evaluation.&#13;
  The Capacity for Development Results Framework&#13;
builds on such thinking for a new working definition&#13;
and approach that can move development practitio-&#13;
ners and stakeholders toward a more comprehensive              Peer reviewers&#13;
understanding of capacity development. The frame-              Geeta Batra, head, Country Partnerships and&#13;
work also underscores evaluation as an ongoing man-            Advisory Services Monitoring and Evaluations,&#13;
agement and learning tool, providing a flexible, yet           International Financial Corporation; Kebour&#13;
basic, structure to improve capacity development in            Ghenna, lead capacity development and gover-&#13;
operation and scope.                                           nance advisor to Initiative Africa, and Institute on&#13;
  As capacity development continues to evolve, an              Governance and Innovative Leadership, Ethiopia.&#13;
ongoing dialogue on fresh approaches to design and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 About World Bank Institute (WBI): Unleashing the Power of Knowledge to Enable a World Free of Poverty&#13;
 The World Bank Institute (WBI) helps countries share and apply global and local knowledge to meet development&#13;
 challenges. WBI's capacity development programs are designed to build skills among groups of individuals involved&#13;
 in performing tasks, and also to strengthen the organizations in which they work, and the sociopolitical environ-&#13;
 ment in which they operate.&#13;
 WBI Contact:&#13;
 Mark Nelson; program manager, Capacity Development Resource Center&#13;
 Tel: 202-458-8041, e-mail: mnelson1@worldbank.org&#13;
 Ajay Tejasvi; program coordinator, Capacity Development Resource Center&#13;
 Tel: 202-458-4064, e-mail: anarasimhan@worldbank.org&#13;
 Visit our website for more information and download the electronic copies of all Capacity Development Briefs at&#13;
 http://www.worldbank.org/capacity&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       APRIL 2009&#13;
       NUMBERâ&#128;&#130; 31&#13;
&amp;#12; Different Approach, Improved Results&#13;
&#13;
What would happen if the Capacity for Development Results Framework was applied throughout the hypothetical case described in the first&#13;
paragraph of this CD Brief, starting from the needs assessment stage? The framework could improve the program by changing the design to&#13;
address a more complete set of capacity constraints on the ground and reinforcing the monitoring and evaluation system.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Development Goal          Reduce adverse impact of HIV/AIDS in targeted communities&#13;
&#13;
Capacity Factor           Constraints in sociopolitical environment to meeting development goal identified by stakeholders through capacity&#13;
                          needs assessment:&#13;
                          â&#128;¢	 Limited community trust, engagement, and commitment of local leaders to HIV/AIDS programs&#13;
                          â&#128;¢	 Prejudices and stigma toward people living with HIV/AIDS that prevent them from getting tested for HIV and&#13;
                             seeking support services&#13;
&#13;
Measurable Impact         Commitment of social and political leaders:&#13;
                          â&#128;¢	 Extent to which community leaders demonstrate support to HIV/AIDS programs&#13;
                          Compatibility with social norms:&#13;
                          â&#128;¢	 Percent of community households that accept living with family members with HIV/AIDS&#13;
                          â&#128;¢	 Percent change in uptake of HIV testing in targeted communities&#13;
&#13;
Change Process and        Change process will be assisted through:&#13;
Change Agents&#13;
                          â&#128;¢	 Raised awareness of local leaders on benefits of an HIV/AIDS program for the community&#13;
                          â&#128;¢	 Creation of regional action network of community leaders and service providers, with referral network to existing&#13;
                             HIV/AIDS services in the community&#13;
                          â&#128;¢	 Formulation of participatory plan to deliver community-based counseling and confidential HIV testing and referral&#13;
                             services for HIV/AIDS care and support&#13;
                          â&#128;¢	 Enhanced skills of community members to deliver counseling on HIV/AIDS to support implementation of the par-&#13;
                             ticipatory plan&#13;
                          Change agents will be community champions who deliver community-based services and form the network core.&#13;
                          Program will also engage local leaders, community members, and service providers.&#13;
&#13;
Measurable                Proportion of local leaders who report increased motivation in supporting community HIV/AIDS programs&#13;
Outcomes&#13;
                          Proportion of community leaders and service providers involved in regional network on provision of resources to the&#13;
                          network and monthly progress updates&#13;
                          Percent of communities who developed action steps and committed resources to support the participatory plan&#13;
                          Proportion of trained community members who deliver counseling&#13;
&#13;
Tools for Data            Reports from network meeting and consultations, stakeholder interviews and surveys, reports from skills-building&#13;
Collection                activities, field visit reports, testimonies from community members, and budget reports and proposals&#13;
&#13;
Activities                â&#128;¢	 Series of structured roundtables that engage local leaders in discussions of HIV/AIDS impact on community&#13;
                             welfare&#13;
                          â&#128;¢	 Consultative meetings with local leaders and other stakeholders to develop network and coordination mechanism&#13;
                          â&#128;¢	 National workshop to create and launch action network&#13;
                          â&#128;¢	 Peer-to-peer learning on organization and delivery of community-based HIV/AIDS counseling, HIV testing, and&#13;
                             referral services&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      APRIL 2009&#13;
      NUMBERâ&#128;&#130; 31&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="20371716">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2009/04/20371716/need-conceptual-results-oriented-framework-capacity-development-discussion-new-approach
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2009/04/20371716/need-conceptual-results-oriented-framework-capacity-development-discussion-new-approach</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2009/04/20371716/need-conceptual-results-oriented-framework-capacity-development-discussion-new-approach</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2014-11-12T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2014-11-12T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2014/11/12/000442464_20141112110211/Rendered/INDEX/925900WBIWP0Bo0B00PUBLIC00CDBrief31.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2014/11/12/000442464_20141112110211/Rendered/PDF/925900WBIWP0Bo0B00PUBLIC00CDBrief31.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2014-11-12T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2009-04-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            The need for a conceptual and
            results-oriented framework in capacity development :
            discussion of a new approach
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Efforts to develop capacity are being
            hindered by disparate methodologies, insufficient focus on
            outcomes and indicators, and a lack of concrete results to
            show improved capacity. The authors examine the need for a
            new resource to guide, capture, and communicate capacity
            development (CD) efforts. They outline a results-driven and
            systematic framework - based on rigorous needs assessment,
            innovative change process logic, and participatory
            implementation that is driven by local ownership, adaptive
            management, and measurable results. This resource can fill a
            critical gap in CD design and reporting, as well as fuel
            further discussion in the development community.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            The need for a conceptual and
            results-oriented framework in capacity development :
            discussion of a new approach
        </docna>
        <display_title>The need for a conceptual and
            results-oriented framework in capacity development :
            discussion of a new approach</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2009/04/20371716/need-conceptual-results-oriented-framework-capacity-development-discussion-new-approach</listing_relative_url>
        <topic>Health Facility Management m1326575 1397,Health Equity and Access m1326151 1288,Health Facilities Restructuring m1326824 1319,Results-Based Financing for Health
            m1326324 1298,Health Economics and Finance m1326577 625</topic>
        <docty>WBI Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>Regional Rural Development,Early Child and Children's Health,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Development Economics &amp; Aid Effectiveness,Knowledge for Development</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Education,Health, Nutrition and Population,Rural Development,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Otoo, Samuel</author>
            <author>Agapitova, Natalia</author>
            <author>Gold, Jenny</author>
            <author>Fisher, Sharon</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000442464_20141112110211</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>Capacity development briefs ; no. 31</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Education,Health, Nutrition and Population,Rural Development,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</historic_topic>
        <topicv3>Health Facility Management m1326575 1397,Health Equity and Access m1326151 1288,Health Facilities Restructuring m1326824 1319,Results-Based Financing for Health
            m1326324 1298,Health Economics and Finance m1326577 625</topicv3>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            adverse impact, aid, belief systems,
            benchmarking, best practices, Capacity Building, CD, change
            agents, change management, change process, communities,
            community members, community of practice, conceptual
            framework, consensus building, data Collection, development
            activities, development assistance, development goals,
            development process, development programs, development
            strategy, disCussioN, discussions, donor agency, global
            knowledge, HIV testing, HIV/AIDS, households, international
            development, leading, Learning, logic, overseas development
            assistance, performance indicators, practitioners,
            Sustainability, Sustainable development, Targeting,
            technical assistance, thinking, use of knowledge
        </keywd>
        <owner>Macro &amp; Fiscal Mgmt - GP (GMFDR)</owner>
        <repnb>92590</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>AIDS HIV</ml:concept><ml:concept>HIV AIDS</ml:concept><ml:concept>HIV/AIDS</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fuels</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Regional Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>HIV and AIDS</ml:concept><ml:concept>Examinations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Support Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Adaptation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>