<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Document of&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Report No: T7569&#13;
TECHNICAL ANNEX FOR A PROPOSED TRUST FUND GRANT&#13;
OF US$20 MILLION&#13;
TO&#13;
WEST BANK &amp; GAZA&#13;
FOR AN&#13;
EMERGENCY MUNICIPAL SERVICES REHABILITATION PROJECT&#13;
NOVEMBER 22, 2002&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
CURRENCY EQUIVALENT&#13;
(Exchange Rate Effective October 1, 2000)&#13;
Currency Unit = ILS (New Israeli Sheqalim)&#13;
ILS I =US$.211 USS&#13;
US$ I = 4.73 ILS&#13;
FISCAL YEAR&#13;
January to December&#13;
Abbreviations and Acronyms&#13;
CAS           Country Assistance Strategy&#13;
CDP           Community Development Project&#13;
CIDA          Canadian Intemational Development Agency&#13;
DANIDA        Danish Intemational Development Assistance&#13;
ED            Executive Director&#13;
EMP           Environmental Management Plan&#13;
EMSRP         Emergency Municipal Services Rehabilitation Project&#13;
EPA           Emergency Program Assistance&#13;
ERSP          Emergency Responses Program&#13;
ESSP          Emergency Services Support Project&#13;
EU            European Union&#13;
FC            Fund Commission&#13;
IBRD          Intemational Bank for Reconstruction and Development&#13;
ICB           Intemational Competitive Bidding&#13;
ICR           Implementation Completion Report&#13;
IDA           International Development Association&#13;
ILO           Intemational Labor Organization&#13;
IMF           Intemational Monetary Fund&#13;
LG            Local Govemment&#13;
LGUs          Local Govemment Units&#13;
MA            Management Agent&#13;
MF            Municipal Fund&#13;
MIDP          Municipal Infrastructure Development Project&#13;
MNA           Middle East and North Africa&#13;
MOF           Ministry of Finance&#13;
MOLG          Ministry of Local Govemment&#13;
MOPIC         Ministry of Planning and Intemational Cooperation&#13;
NBF           Not Bank financed&#13;
NCB           National Competitive Bidding&#13;
NGO           Non Govemmental Organization&#13;
OM            Operations Manual&#13;
OP            Operational Policy&#13;
PA            Palestinian Authority&#13;
PCBS          Palestinian Central Bureau of Statistics&#13;
PCU           Project Coordination Unit&#13;
PEACE         Palestinian Economic Assistance and Cooperation Expansion&#13;
PIP           Project Implementation Plan&#13;
PSC           Project Steering Committee&#13;
QBS           Quality Based Selection&#13;
QCBS          Quality and Cost Based Selection&#13;
TA            Technical Assistance&#13;
TAU           Technical Assistance Unit&#13;
TFGWB         Trust Fund for Gaza and the West Bank&#13;
WBG           West Bank and Gaza&#13;
Vice President:      Jean-Louis Sarbib&#13;
Country Director:    Nigel Roberts&#13;
Country Coordinator.  Nicholas Krafft&#13;
Sector Director:     Emmanual Forestier&#13;
Sector Manager:      Hedi Larbi&#13;
Task Team Leaders:   Majed El-Bayya and Stephen Karam&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
EMERGENCY MUNICIPAL SERVICES REHABILITATION PROJECT&#13;
TECHNICAL ANNEX&#13;
Table of Contents&#13;
Page&#13;
Section A. Background &amp; Donor Response Strategy                       1&#13;
Section B. Bank Response and Strategy                                 5&#13;
Section C. Detailed Project Description                               7&#13;
Section D. Studies and Technical Assistance                          12&#13;
Section E. Institutional Arrangements and Project Implementation     13&#13;
Section F. Financial and Economic Justification                      27&#13;
Section G. Action Plan                                               27&#13;
ANNEXES:&#13;
1. Summary Financing and Cost Tables&#13;
2. Responsibility Matrix&#13;
3. Chart Depicting Project Institutional Arrangements&#13;
4. Phase I to II Transition Chart&#13;
5. Process Flow Chart&#13;
6. Logframe with Key Performance Indicators&#13;
7. Action Plan&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
1&#13;
SECTION A. BACKGROUND AND DONOR RESPONSE STRATEGY&#13;
1.    With the launching of the Israeli-Palestinian Peace Process in September 1993, the hope&#13;
of resolving one of the past centuries' most intractable conflicts was set in motion. An ambitious&#13;
reconstruction effort was initiated with broad donor economic support to underpin the political&#13;
process and jump-start the Palestinian economy. Because of its still unresolved political status,&#13;
however, the Palestinian governance framework remains undetermined, allowing for very limited&#13;
Palestinian control of land, and lack of control over water, transport of goods and people or&#13;
access to external markets. Since the Oslo agreements, the Palestinian Authority has begun to&#13;
acquire jurisdiction in varying degrees, in the small areas under its control, for delivery of public&#13;
services, law enforcement and legislative power. It has not, on the other hand, the full attributes&#13;
of a state and is limited in its ability to authoritatively allocate or mobilize resources.&#13;
2.     Reemergence of Conflict Sets Back Development &amp; Economic Growth. The outbreak&#13;
of the Palestinian Intifada in September 2000 and subsequent imposition of closures and curfews&#13;
by the Government of Israel on the West Bank and Gaza have caused many of the development&#13;
gains achieved over recent years to suffer significant setbacks. The nature of the conflict has&#13;
been one of low-level but protracted violence that has continued over a span of more than two&#13;
years. The Palestinian economic recovery that began in 1998 came to an abrupt halt with the&#13;
outbreak of violence, as political instability and security concerns have driven investors away,&#13;
while closures and curfews have imposed significant transaction costs on Palestinian businesses&#13;
that have eroded their competitiveness. Correspondingly, Palestinian incomes have witnessed a&#13;
sharp decline. Per capita real income in WBG declined by 12 percent in 2000 and by a further 19&#13;
percent in 2001. Unemployment is now estimated by the Bank to be just under 50 percent, and&#13;
this does not include that portion of the labor force that has ceased looking for work due to&#13;
depressed economic activity.&#13;
3.     Fiscal Crisis. Since September 2000, PA fiscal accounts have deteriorated markedly,&#13;
causing a severe fiscal crisis. There are essentially three main causes of the present fiscal deficit.&#13;
First, there has been a sharp decline in PA revenue collections associated with the decline in&#13;
economic activity and the disruption of tax administration; second, tax revenue collected on the&#13;
PA's behalf by the Government of Israel have been suspended' during the period December 2000&#13;
- June 2002, having resumed in July 2002 only on an irregular basis; and third, expenditures&#13;
associated with the emergency have increased over the past two years. Central government&#13;
revenue fell from a monthly average of US$83 million in 1999 to US$23 million by the First&#13;
Quarter of 2002 and further declined to US$15.7 million in the Second Quarter of this year.&#13;
Domestic tax revenue collection has shrunk to half the pre-Intifada monthly average and, with the&#13;
exception of transfers made since June 2002 clearance revenue, which had averaged US$45&#13;
million per month prior to the crisis, has been withheld. Despite the severe cutback in non-wage&#13;
expenditures (Second Quarter 2002 non-wage spending was 63 percent the level of the First&#13;
Quarter, and 46 percent when compared with monthly non-wage spending in 2001), the PA was&#13;
running an average monthly deficit of approximately US$20 million, even after taking into&#13;
account donor-provided budgetary support. This has been managed through a combination of&#13;
accumulating arrears to suppliers, borrowing from domestic banks, and delaying the payment of&#13;
salaries and pensions. Since July 2002, the Ministry of Finance has further reduced the PA&#13;
'Three transfers in the amount of NIS 70 million each have been made in July, August and October for a&#13;
total of NIS 210 million since June. However, no formal agreement has been reached to resume transfers&#13;
on a regular basis and to reinstate the pre-existing transfer system.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
2&#13;
austerity budget of US$90 million to US$70 million per month to reduce the further accumulation&#13;
of arrears.&#13;
4.     By the end of June 2002, the PA had accumulated US$527 million in arrears, of which&#13;
US$295 million is due to suppliers and US$232 million in wages (including pensions). This level&#13;
of arrears has had a pernicious impact on the private sector, resulting in an acute liquidity&#13;
shortage, mounting non-performing loans in the banking system, and increasing cases of&#13;
insolvency2. Vendors have felt compelled to continue providing credit, but many have reached&#13;
the point where they are no longer willing or able to do so. Settling these arrears is a matter of&#13;
top priority for the PA once Israel transfers the withheld clearance revenue (estimated by the IMF&#13;
to be US$681 million in gross terms owed as of end-June 2002) and resumes regular transfers.&#13;
5.    Impact of the Crisis. Following nearly 18 months of protracted exchanges of violence,&#13;
the conflict intensified in the West Bank at the end of March, 2002, causing severe damages to&#13;
physical and institutional infrastructure, including housing, public facilities, as well as water,&#13;
wastewater and electrical networks, particularly in the northern region of the West Bank. This&#13;
was coupled with a tightening of movement restrictions on the Palestinian population. A Damage&#13;
Assessment was conducted with broad-based donor support immediately following the intensified&#13;
violence in March-April and developed an estimate of damages to infrastructure and institutions&#13;
of over US$330 million; this is in addition to an estimate of damages of US$300 million,&#13;
prepared by the Bank, that were incurred prior to March, between September 2000 and December&#13;
2001. In addition, tightened closures have increased travel time, which has multiplied by at least&#13;
two times the average prior to the Intifada when closures and mobility restrictions were first&#13;
imposed. Correspondingly, travel costs have also dramatically increased during this period, as&#13;
transport routes have been segmented within and between areas.&#13;
6.     Vulnerability of the Palestinian People. Closures and movement restrictions have had a&#13;
profound impact on the lives and livelihoods of the Palestinian people. Monthly household&#13;
income decreased by 50 percent in the first 18 months of the Intifada, placing 66 percent of&#13;
Palestinian households below the poverty line of US$2 per day. According to the Palestinian&#13;
Central Bureau of Statistics as many as 84 percent of Gaza households are now estimated to be&#13;
below the poverty line. Nearly 55 percent of households lost more than 50 percent of their&#13;
income during the first half of this year compared to 47 percent by March 2001, signaling the&#13;
deepening nature of the crisis. More than 55 percent of the population has decreased the quantity&#13;
of food consumed since the beginning of the Intifada. This has invariably had its impact on the&#13;
health status of vulnerable segments of the Palestinian population. A nutritional assessment&#13;
carried out under the auspices of Johns Hopkins University in July 2002 estimates the current rate&#13;
of malnutrition among children under the age of 5 to be about 20 percent, which is deemed an&#13;
emergency in most parts of the world. The study also found high levels of anemia among young&#13;
children and women in reproductive ages.  Food security is not only threatened by the&#13;
population's lack of resources - 65 percent of households that cut back on food consumption&#13;
reported lack of money as the reason - but also by shortages of supplies in Palestinian shops. The&#13;
Johns Hopkins study found that movement restrictions have severely disrupted the availability of&#13;
key high protein foods like meat and dairy products, and in particular infant formula and&#13;
powdered milk.  Palestinians have come to rely on informal social safety nets during&#13;
economically depressed periods, as most assistance is being provided by family, relatives or&#13;
neighbors (60 percent of food assistance and 11 percent of cash assistance). Many families have&#13;
resorted to selling gold and other household assets to endure the difficult times. But coping&#13;
2 See Fifteen Months - Intifada, Closures and Economic Crisis: An Assessment, The World Bank, March&#13;
2002.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
3&#13;
strategies such as these, which have been relied on for the past two years, are unsustainable and&#13;
quickly being exhausted.&#13;
7.    Impact on Local Government Finances &amp; Service Delivery.     With widespread&#13;
unemployment and the precipitous decline of a majority of Palestinian households into poverty,&#13;
local government revenues, generated largely from service and user fees, have suffered dramatic&#13;
declines. World Bank survey data indicates that between September 2000 and June 2002, local&#13;
government revenues have declined on average by just under 44 percent.  While local&#13;
governments, particularly municipalities, were accumulating significant liabilities initially, as&#13;
they attempted to sustain services by deferring payments, they are now resorting to reducing&#13;
expenditures on services (an average decline of 41.5 percent for the same period) in order to avert&#13;
accumulation of further arrearages.&#13;
8.     Service quality and coverage has deteriorated markedly as a result of the reduction in&#13;
municipal expenditures. In Gaza City, solid waste collection has been reduced to one shift per&#13;
week from two or three shifts prior to the crisis. Moreover, because of closures of some areas,&#13;
many landfill sites are no longer accessible. Municipalities in northern Gaza, including Jabalia,&#13;
Beit Lahia, and Beit Hanoun, for example, are forced to use a landfill site at Juhr Al-Deik (south&#13;
of Gaza City) as a temporary solution. But this arrangement increases hauling distances and&#13;
involves the use of unpaved roads to gain access to the sites, accelerating the depreciation of&#13;
already worn-down vehicles. Temporary transfer sites are also being used but because of the&#13;
random and uncontrolled manner in which they are set up health hazards are increasing, in&#13;
addition to the risk of negative environmental impacts. Road safety is impaired because many&#13;
municipalities lack the funds to maintain street lighting, either because of the cost of repairing&#13;
damaged lights or because they simply do not have resources to pay for the electricity.&#13;
9.     Reduced expenditures on services will also have a longer term impact, as routine&#13;
maintenance activities are being deferred. Many water wells and wastewater pumping stations&#13;
are operating at sub-optimal levels because of a lack of spare parts. Electricity shortages have led&#13;
to an overuse of standby diesel generators at water and wastewater stations, increasing the&#13;
operating costs to municipalities and often causing damage to sensitive equipment due to frequent&#13;
power surges and cuts. The depreciation of roads throughout WBG is accelerating, as they are no&#13;
longer being properly cleaned and maintained because of municipal revenue shortfalls and the&#13;
need to focus expenditures on only the most essential services.&#13;
10.    Several meetings with key representatives from the Palestinian Authority, municipalities&#13;
and village councils, and key NGOs have taken place in the past three months. Some informal&#13;
consultations have also been conducted through discussions with school principals, heads of&#13;
health clinics and hospitals and key figures in the service sectors. One of the top priorities&#13;
identified was the need for a mechanism that can provide an equitable and transparent basis for&#13;
intergovernmental transfers, whether from the central government or from donors, to LGUs to&#13;
support the continued provision of essential municipal services, including operational costs for&#13;
water and electricity supply, waste collection and disposal, and other public related services.&#13;
Other priorities include (i) the need to create employment opportunities for the many unemployed&#13;
Palestinian workers who lost their jobs in Israel and those who are unable to access work&#13;
opportunities in the West Bank and Gaza due to closures and mobility restrictions, and (ii) the&#13;
repair of damaged infrastructure necessary for the provision of essential municipal services.&#13;
11.   Collective Donor Response to the Emergency. A number of initiatives are underway to&#13;
assist the PA, and local governments in particular, in responding to the emergency. An elaborate&#13;
donor aid coordination structure was already in place and was revived in response to the crisis.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
4&#13;
Regarding damages caused in March-April 2002, most donors began reallocating funds to finance&#13;
infrastructure and building repairs, as well as other emergency assistance to restore institutional&#13;
capacity and the provision of essential services both nationally and locally. This exercise was&#13;
informed by a coordinated donor-PA Physical and Institutional Damage Assessment completed at&#13;
the end of May in which several donors assumed responsibility for gathering data in different&#13;
segmented areas of the West Bank. The findings of this Assessment have helped guide the PA&#13;
and donors in reallocating financing toward prioritized emergency needs, while avoiding&#13;
duplication of effort.&#13;
12.   A Political Roadmap to Peace. Although it is premature to consider any new political&#13;
initiative an indicator of a future outcome, there has been some movement on the diplomatic&#13;
front. The Quartet, a newly-established apex-level political coordination mechanism comprised&#13;
of the US, the European Union, Russia, and the United Nations, met on September 17 to agree on&#13;
a plan which in three phases would lead to the establishment of a Palestinian State. The first&#13;
phase, which runs until mid-2003, includes Palestinian security reform under US and regional&#13;
auspices; an Israeli military withdrawal to positions held in September 2000; and support of "free,&#13;
fair and credible elections" early next year in the Palestinian areas. The Second Phase, which is&#13;
scheduled to begin in mid-2003, "should focus on the option of creating a Palestinian State with&#13;
provisional borders and based on a new Constitution." The Final Phase, proposed to be&#13;
implemented from 2004 to mid-2005, includes permanent status talks and a final peace agreement&#13;
between the two sides. In parallel a Task Force on Palestinian Reform was established to which&#13;
the Bank provides vital analytical support, particularly in three areas of focus: (i) civil service&#13;
reforms, (ii) local government reforms, and (iii) financial accountability reforms.&#13;
13.   A Renewed Focus on Palestinian Reforms. The Palestinian Authority is in the midst of&#13;
a broad-based reform movement which was launched in June with a cabinet reshuffling and the&#13;
announcement of a Palestinian 100 Day Reform Program. Supporting this reform effort is a&#13;
newly formed Task Force on Palestinian Reform, which includes an active role for donors. The&#13;
Bank is deeply involved in two sector areas - Local Government Reform and Public&#13;
Administration/Civil Service Reform. The most notable reforms to date have been initiated at the&#13;
Ministry of Finance (MOF) by its newly appointed minister. Since June, MOF has:&#13;
i.     Adopted a more disciplined approach to the budget with a reduction of budgetary&#13;
expenditures to about US$70 million per month, down from an average expenditure&#13;
level of US$90 million, in part to avoid further accumulation of arrears;&#13;
ii.    Consolidated all PA revenues, including those of the PA petroleum and tobacco&#13;
agencies, into a single Treasury account;&#13;
iii.  Installed controls to prevent issuance of checks without adequate cover;&#13;
iv.    Resumed transfers of civil servant contributions to the Government Pension Fund in&#13;
Gaza, which were previously accumulating as arrears; and&#13;
v.     Consolidated the payroll function in Gaza at the Ministry of Finance to exert tighter&#13;
controls over civil service recruitment.&#13;
14.   In addition to these reforms, MOF has also initiated central transfers due to local&#13;
governments based on their share of revenue from traffic fines and vehicle licensing fees. The&#13;
first such transfer of NIS 15 million was made in September, representing a renewed attempt to&#13;
realign intergovernmental fiscal transfer practices with the local government law.  This&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
5&#13;
represents a significant step forward in terms of intergovernmental fiscal relations, as previously&#13;
shared revenues were withheld by MOF and used to cover accumulating local government arrears&#13;
to foreign creditors. However, in making the September transfer, MOF also informed LGUs that&#13;
it was in the process of assessing cross arrears and that when this assessment is completed it&#13;
would begin to reschedule municipal debt to the PA.&#13;
SECTION B. BANK RESPONSE AND STRATEGY&#13;
15.   In the absence of a CAS, the Executive Directors approved on February 28 the "Status&#13;
Report to the Board on the Trust Fund for Gaza and the West Bank and Strategic Outlook." This&#13;
document outlines the Bank's proposed strategy in WBG for 2002, which aims to continue laying&#13;
the institutional foundation for statehood through knowledge-based analytical and policy work,&#13;
and operations that encourage the development of sound governance institutions at the central and&#13;
sector levels; and, in the context of the current crisis, continue providing analytical and&#13;
programmatic leadership to the collective donor effort to cope with the emergency, while&#13;
initiating multi-donor operations to support the delivery of essential social services and the&#13;
maintenance/recovery of private sector activity.  The proposed Project supports the latter&#13;
objective by assisting municipalities in delivering essential services, providing a mechanism to&#13;
better coordinate donor assistance, and strengthening Palestinian central and local institutional&#13;
capacity to more ably respond to emergency needs.&#13;
16.   As its contribution to the collective donor response, the Bank carried out a&#13;
comprehensive portfolio review in May-June 2002 and reallocated US$19.9 million from its&#13;
active portfolio, of which US$12.9 million was reallocated for emergency purposes, while a&#13;
further US$7 million was cancelled from one project and returned to TFGWB for future&#13;
emergency or development assistance. This assistance, comprising the Bank's most immediate&#13;
response, is now under implementation through existing project implementation mechanisms. In&#13;
addition, the Bank prepared an Emergency Services Support Project (US$20 million), which&#13;
became effective in March 2002 to provide budgetary support to line ministries to sustain&#13;
essential health, education and social services in response to the widening PA revenue-&#13;
expenditure gap. This operation has leveraged over US$45 million in co-financing from seven&#13;
donors and has proven to be an important instrument in mobilizing donor assistance and in&#13;
leveraging the Bank's contribution.&#13;
17.   Rationale for the Bank's Involvement. The Bank has considerable global and WBG-&#13;
specific experience in designing and implementing emergency operations in response to natural&#13;
disasters and emergencies arising in conflict-affected settings, and, in WBG in particular, is often&#13;
relied upon to lead such efforts. The first three operations implemented by the Bank in WBG4&#13;
were all emergency in nature and benefited from simplicity in design, while contributing toward&#13;
the establishment of Palestinian implementation capacity in the absence of such capacity at the&#13;
outset. Moreover, the Bank has demonstrated an ability to respond rapidly to emergency needs&#13;
through its US$12 million contribution to the Emergency Response Program5, launched in&#13;
December 2000 - only two months after the start of the Intifada -- in which the Bank and five&#13;
4Emergency Rehabilitation Project I and II (November 1994 and May 1996 respectively) and the&#13;
Education and Health Rehabilitation Project (February 1998).&#13;
5The Bank's contribution to the Emergency Response Program (ERSP) channeled a contribution of US$12&#13;
million through the Bank-administered Holst Fund and leveraged a further US$25 million in joint co-&#13;
financing through the PEACE Facility in support of emergency job creation through infrastructure micro-&#13;
projects.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
6&#13;
other donors provided over US$37 million to create temporary employment opportunities through&#13;
small-scale infrastructure microprojects. Furthermore, the Bank's ability to mobilize resources&#13;
and to contribute by providing a framework for other donor assistance is illustrated by the&#13;
Emergency Services Support Project, which has mobilized over US$45 million in donor&#13;
cofinancing. Similarly, the proposed operation has been prepared in close coordination with the&#13;
European Commission and the Government of Belgium, among other donors, and would leverage&#13;
at its inception over US$37 million in parallel cofinancing, with other donor cofinancing expected&#13;
to follow once the Municipal Fund is established. In addition, the Bank's Country Office is&#13;
staffed with highly skilled and experienced national and international staff - both in West Bank&#13;
and Gaza - which enables it to more effectively administer and supervise emergency programs&#13;
than many of the smaller bilateral donors. This is the principal reason - in addition to the&#13;
leveraging effect -- that many bilateral donors have sought the Bank's assistance in administering&#13;
their cofinancing.&#13;
18.   Lessons Learned from Previous Similar Operations. A major lesson learned from&#13;
recent emergency operations supported by the Bank is that developing countries are becoming&#13;
increasingly aware of the need to put in place measures to prevent or reduce risks arising due to&#13;
crises. The past ten years have seen an increase in the number of Bank-supported emergency&#13;
recovery projects, and also a steep learning curve in the Bank's own understanding of how to&#13;
operationalize sustainable interventions.&#13;
19.   With respect to Bank experience in WBG, ESSP I demonstrated that centralization of&#13;
service administration and delivery can result in implementation delays. In addition, ESSP I was&#13;
designed to rely on line ministry staff to administer their components of the Project, which proved&#13;
to be difficult and slow-moving at MOLG due to capacity weaknesses and overburdened staff.&#13;
For this reason, the municipal component of ESSP I has been spun off and restructured separately&#13;
in the proposed operation, allowing for focused attention on emergency assistance, sector&#13;
dialogue, and reform at the local government level. Implementation would be managed on a day-&#13;
to-day basis by a fully staffed PCU based at MOLG with branch offices in Gaza and the West&#13;
Bank in order not to overburden MOLG staff. To ensure project flexibility and responsiveness to&#13;
different community needs and to circumvent prevailing mobility restrictions, the design of&#13;
EMSRP is based upon a demand-driven arrangement and decentralized implementation, whereby&#13;
local governments, in consultation with their communities, would determine their own emergency&#13;
assistance priorities and would implement projects at the local level, including preparation of&#13;
emergency programs, tendering, contracting and supervising implementation. This approach has&#13;
been highly effective in other WBG programs, e.g. Community Development Projects I &amp; II, and&#13;
would be supported by four regionally-based teams of technical consultants. Moreover, MOLG&#13;
would be authorized to make 30 day advance transfers to local govemment accounts for up to 10&#13;
percent of their emergency allocation against which funds could be disbursed quickly. In&#13;
addition, streamlined Bank procurement procedures would be used to facilitate the flow of funds.&#13;
20.    Another key lesson learned from ESSP I and other related emergency operations is the&#13;
importance of maintaining close coordination with other donors. In the preparation of EMSRP,&#13;
every donor providing assistance to the local government sector was consulted to inform the&#13;
Project's design. Agreement was reached to design the Municipal Fund with maximum&#13;
flexibility to take into account other donors' financing requirements as well their respective&#13;
comparative advantages. It was further agreed with the two identified EMSRP donor co-&#13;
financiers - the European Union and the Government of Belgium - that a common Project&#13;
Steering Committee (and in the second year, the Fund Commission) would serve as the PA&#13;
counterpart for decision-making and overall project guidance. In addition, a Donor Consultative&#13;
Forum (DCF) is in the process of being established, which both the EU and Belgium Government&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
7&#13;
have agreed to join, to strengthen partnerships and coordination in programming interventions. It&#13;
is expected that the DCF will expand in membership as other donors consider channeling&#13;
contributions through the Municipal Fund once commitments can be made in subsequent donor&#13;
aid commitment cycles.&#13;
21.    Considerable learning has also taken place through a recent review of donor-financed&#13;
emergency employment creation programs in WBG; this exercise was financed by the Bank and&#13;
carried out in coordination with all donors providing this form of assistance through the Sector&#13;
Working Group on Employment Generation. Many such programs have relied on conventional&#13;
works-based, largely capital intensive project designs to create temporary employment&#13;
opportunities and placed much of the burden on contractors to find ways of ensuring maximum&#13;
labor content. However, because these sub-projects by design are not labor intensive, many of&#13;
the subprojects featured labor content of no more than 20 percent, thus limiting impact. In&#13;
response, the PA, the Bank and other donors have agreed to adopt a labor-intensive approach in&#13;
the design and implementation of these projects in the future. Informed by ILO and technical&#13;
consultant recommendations in the referenced review report, an employment generation&#13;
component of the proposed Project would be designed to support subprojects implemented by&#13;
local governments with a minimum labor content of 50%. Technical assistance in project&#13;
identification, selection, preparation and implementation would be supported through training&#13;
workshops and capacity building as further detailed under Component I of the proposed Project.&#13;
SECTION C. DETAILED PROJECT DESCRIPTION&#13;
22.    Project Objectives and Development Outcomes. The main objectives of the proposed&#13;
Project correspond to those expressed in the Palestinian Authority's request for Bank assistance&#13;
and are aimed at: (a) mitigating further deterioration in the quality and coverage of municipal&#13;
services, particularly solid waste collection, electricity, water and sanitation services; (b)&#13;
generating temporary employment opportunities for unemployed workers who have lost jobs&#13;
inside Israel or due to the economic contraction in WBG; and (c) introducing a mechanism - a&#13;
Municipal Fund - to link central and local government budgetary planning processes to&#13;
strengthen Palestinian emergency response capacity, enhance mobilization of donor assistance,&#13;
and improve the efficiency and equity of resource transfers to local governments.&#13;
23.    Project Components and Estimated Costs6 The total cost of the proposed Project is&#13;
currently estimated to be about US$70 million, out of which US$20 million is proposed to be&#13;
financed by TFGWB. A two year Emergency Recovery Grant would include the following&#13;
components: (a) Emergency Program Assistance; (b) Municipal Fund Design and Performance&#13;
Monitoring; and (c) Technical Assistance and Capacity Building, as further detailed below.&#13;
24.    Component 1: Emergency Program Assistance. (Total component cost: US$68.0 million,&#13;
IDA financing US$18.5 million).  This component would finance (i) local government&#13;
expenditures for essential service provision, including operating costs, goods and services, (ii)&#13;
temporary labor-intensive employment generation micro-projects, and (iii) damage repair to local&#13;
government facilities and service infrastructure, as further described below:&#13;
6 Project costs are estimates as of October 2002. A summary project cost table is attached under Table D in&#13;
Annex 1.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
8&#13;
Local Government Service Expenditures. (Total sub-component cost: US$31.5&#13;
million, IDA financing US$14.5 million) This sub-component would finance local&#13;
government operating costs, goods and services related to municipal service&#13;
provision over a period of two years. Because this subcomponent is designed to&#13;
respond to local government defined priorities, the following is an indicative list of&#13;
prospective financing requirements and is intended to illustrate the types of activities&#13;
or expenses that are likely to be financed, based on prior consultations with LGUs.&#13;
a) Water and wastewater services. Maintenance and rehabilitation of existing water&#13;
and sewerage networks, wells and reservoirs; provision of chemicals for water&#13;
purification; repair and maintenance of equipment, such as pumps, generators,&#13;
vacuum tanks, and vehicles; purchase of spare parts, goods, vehicles and fuel;&#13;
payment of water and wastewater bills, and equipment;&#13;
b) Solid waste services. Service contracts for solid waste collection, as well as&#13;
labor, dumping fees, solid waste containers, tools and trucks, spare parts for solid&#13;
waste trucks, fuel, vehicle lubricants, insurance, equipment, materials, and other&#13;
related running costs;&#13;
c) Road rehabilitation and maintenance services.  Goods and works for&#13;
maintenance, rehabilitation and reconstruction of existing internal roads,&#13;
including traffic signs, road line demarcations, safety rails, traffic signals, street&#13;
lighting, sidewalks, fuel, vehicle insurance and road maintenance tools and&#13;
equipment;&#13;
d) Electricity services. Supply and replacement of transformers and electrical&#13;
panels, electrical cables and poles, accessories, spare parts, maintenance tools&#13;
and equipment, vehicle insurance, fuel, vehicle lubricants and electricity bills.&#13;
This financial support will take the form of a transfer from the central government&#13;
and would be allocated to LGUs serving 1,000 or more inhabitants in amounts&#13;
corresponding to their share of the population in WBG, or approximately 260 LGUs.&#13;
Coverage would extend to 96 percent of the population through this allocation&#13;
formula. Smaller LGUs would become eligible for emergency program assistance&#13;
provided they work through joint service councils or other mechanisms to jointly&#13;
represent village clusters with an aggregate population of greater than 1,000.&#13;
Allocations would be linked to the annual budgetary preparation cycle and would be&#13;
based on the submission of emergency programs prepared by LGUs in consultation&#13;
with their communities. Standard forms would be used to prepare LGU emergency&#13;
program submissions and LGUs would be required to prepare their programs in&#13;
consultation with the communities they represent.  US$7 million of IDA's&#13;
contribution would be allocated in the first year under this sub-component with the&#13;
balance disbursed in the second year. IDA's contribution would finance non-wage&#13;
service-related expenditures, including goods, services and operating costs.  A&#13;
portion of this sub-component -- US$10 million (equivalent) -- would be provided by&#13;
the EU through an integrated allocation mechanism that could finance either wage or&#13;
non-wage expenditures.&#13;
Labor-intensive Empioyment Creation. (Total sub-component cost: US$ 4.2 million,&#13;
IDA financing US$3.00 million). This sub-component would finance labor-intensive&#13;
temporary employment sub-projects that are identified and implemented by LGUs in&#13;
coordination with locally-based community groups. Past experience has shown that&#13;
pre-designed schemes often lack ownership and acceptance at the community level,&#13;
due to different local circumstances, customs and practices, among other factors.&#13;
Funds would be made available to regions based on their relative share of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
9&#13;
unemployment (annualized data), thus targeting those areas in greatest need of&#13;
assistance with a greater share of resources. Distribution of grant proceeds would be&#13;
linked to the annual budget preparation cycle in which US$2 million would be made&#13;
available under the proposed grant in year I of the Project and US$1 million in year&#13;
2. Based on past experience, it is expected that this sub-component would mobilize&#13;
other donor co-financing to leverage the Bank's contribution. To be eligible for&#13;
financing made available under this subcomponent, LGUs would be required to&#13;
complete a section of the Emergency Assistance Program application form, which&#13;
has been prepared and is included in the Project Operations Manual. Allocations&#13;
would be designated for regions based on a ratio of regional share of unemployment&#13;
to population, against which applications would be reviewed by the PCU. To&#13;
become eligible, project designs would need to ensure a minimum of 50% labor&#13;
content. Sub-projects in a variety of sectors, including agriculture, NGO-based&#13;
services, etc., would be eligible for financing, provided they meet the labor intensive&#13;
criteria. A list of model projects with high labor content would be provided as&#13;
guidance to LGUs in making choices, based on the recommendations of the Bank-&#13;
financed assessment of donor-financed emergency employment creation programs.&#13;
Assistance to LGUs in preparing their sub-projects would be provided by specialized&#13;
consultants, possibly including support from the ILO, and would include preparation&#13;
of simplified standard bidding documents, training and public awareness regarding&#13;
labor-intensive project design and implementation. Financing for this technical&#13;
support would be provided under Component 3 of the proposed Project. The&#13;
Ministry of Planning and International Cooperation (MOPIC) is responsible for&#13;
coordinating donor-financed responses to employment creation needs and has agreed&#13;
to support implementation of this sub-component through its planning, monitoring&#13;
and evaluation department. The approach adopted under the Project is in line with&#13;
MOPIC's emergency employment creation strategy. Implementation would be&#13;
coordinated with the Ministry of Labor (MOL).&#13;
iii.  Damage Repair to Facilities &amp; Infrastructure. (Total sub-component cost: US$ 32.3&#13;
million, IDA financing US$1.00 million) As part of its assistance to local&#13;
governments for damage repair and upgrading facilities and public infrastructure, this&#13;
central government allocation would complement the other two sub-components&#13;
through a parallel but linked allocation mechanism. For the EU portion of the&#13;
assistance (US$20 million equivalent), allocations would be made for sub-projects&#13;
identified and managed within a project database agreed upon by LGUs.  After the&#13;
first year of implementation, it is expected that this sub-component would be fully&#13;
integrated with the other two through the Municipal Fund instrument.&#13;
25.    Component 2: Municipal Fund Desig'n. Management &amp; Performance Monitoring. (Total&#13;
component cost: US$1.10 million, IDA financing US$1.10 million. This component would&#13;
finance the cost of a Project Coordination Unit (PCU) with two branch offices - one in West&#13;
Bank and one in Gaza - for the duration of the proposed Project and the contract of a&#13;
management agent, who would be responsible for designing the Municipal Fund (MF) and&#13;
monitoring the PCU's management of it on behalf of the PSC/FC. The contract of the&#13;
Management Agent is expected to cover a period of 18 months.&#13;
i.    Project Coordination Unit (PCU). (Total sub-component cost: US$0.3 million, IDA&#13;
financing US$0.3 million). The PCU would operate throughout the duration of the&#13;
Project and would have the principal implementation responsibility on MOLG's&#13;
behalf. It would be composed of two branch offices (one in Gaza and one in the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
10&#13;
West Bank), which exist at present and serve as PCUs for MOLG emergency&#13;
employment creation projects that are financed by Bank-administered donor&#13;
cofinancing trust funds. During appraisal, these PCUs were reviewed in terms of&#13;
their capacity and adequacy for the proposed Project and deemed acceptable. The&#13;
PCU's main functions in Phase I would be to disseminate information regarding the&#13;
Emergency Program Assistance mechanism and application forms to be prepared by&#13;
LGUs. The PCU would review applications, assisted by four regionally based&#13;
technical consulting units who would be responsible for pre-screening applications&#13;
and assisting LGUs in filling applications according to prepared guidelines, and&#13;
would make technical recommendations to the Project Steering Committee, to whom&#13;
they are accountable. In Phase II (the Project's second year), the PCU would retain&#13;
responsibility for implementing the Project but would be supported by a Management&#13;
Agent as the Emergency Program Assistance is expected to evolve to a Municipal&#13;
Fund. While in Phase I the PCU would be responsible for implementing the Bank's&#13;
contribution, as well as donor cofinancing, in accordance with standard procedures, it&#13;
is expected that the Municipal Fund will mobilize additional donor financing and&#13;
require a streamlined mechanism for managing a number of different donor&#13;
contributions. The role of the Management Agent regarding design of the Municipal&#13;
Fund and monitoring the PCU's performance in managing the Fund is further&#13;
detailed below. The PCU operating costs, including consultant services, office&#13;
supplies, utility costs, rent, communication costs, local travel, equipment and&#13;
furniture would be financed under this component.&#13;
ii.   Municipal Fund Management Agent Contract. (Total sub-component cost: US$0.8&#13;
million, IDA financing US$0.8 million). The Management Agent (MA) is expected&#13;
to be contracted by July 2003 and would be responsible for designing and setting-up&#13;
the Municipal Fund. The MA would be contracted by MOLG and would report to&#13;
the Project Steering Committee, which is chaired by MOLG. The Management&#13;
Agent would review the performance of the allocation mechanism and process in&#13;
Phase I and make recommendations regarding any necessary regulatory actions&#13;
needed to enable the Municipal Fund to function effectively.  The Management&#13;
Agent would also propose the institutional arrangements necessary to establish the&#13;
Fund Commission, the governance body, and the Municipal Fund, and would make&#13;
recommendations regarding any necessary regulatory actions needed to ensure&#13;
effective management of the Fund. It would also be the Management Agent's&#13;
responsibility to: (i) establish a Municipal Financial Information System to include a&#13;
database with budgetary and actual expenditure and revenue data collected from&#13;
LGUs as a requirement for eligibility to receive funds in Phase II of the Project; (ii)&#13;
develop the operating guidelines and procedures for the MF; (iii) provide capacity&#13;
building to the PCU in scaling up the Emergency Program Assistance to a Municipal&#13;
Fund, and (iv) monitor the performance of the PCU in managing the MF, including&#13;
reporting to the Fund Commission and to donors on aspects of financial management&#13;
and internal controls employed in administering the Municipal Fund.&#13;
26.    Component 3: Technical Assistance and Capacitv Building. (Total component cost:&#13;
US$0.90 million, IDA financing US$0.40 million). This component would finance the costs of&#13;
consultant services necessary for technical support, training, and capacity building, primarily&#13;
targeting small municipalities and village councils. Recognizing implementation limitations&#13;
caused by movement restrictions, delivery of assistance would be decentralized through three&#13;
regionally-based technical consultant teams in the West Bank and one in Gaza. The technical&#13;
consultants would assist LGUs in preparing emergency programs, facilitate processing by pre-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
11&#13;
screening emergency program applications, and provide assistance in tendering and contracting&#13;
small goods, works and service contracts. In addition, this component would finance local&#13;
financial consultants to assist LGUs in preparing financial statements and in preparing their 2004&#13;
budgets in order for them to meet eligibility requirements for funding in Year 2 of the program.&#13;
Support for the design of labor intensive temporary employment projects would be provided&#13;
through a separate contracting arrangement involving the ILO or other specialized technical&#13;
consultants under this component. Financing would also be made available for locally-based&#13;
NGOs to foster community participation and to conduct surveys in order to obtain community&#13;
feedback on the process and the effectiveness and transparency in which the process is&#13;
administered by LGUs.&#13;
27.    Environmental Aspects. This proposed emergency Project, prepared in accordance with&#13;
OP 8.50, would contribute to environmental improvements by increasing municipal service&#13;
quality and coverage, including solid waste collection and management and wastewater services,&#13;
among other local community identified priorities. A limited number of micro civil works sub-&#13;
projects are expected to be financed under the Project, depending on demand, similar to those&#13;
implemented under previous projects in WBG, including the Emergency Services Support&#13;
Project, Municipal Infrastructure Development Project, Emergency Response Program, and&#13;
Community Development Projects I and II. Given that most of the likely investment activities&#13;
would support rehabilitation and improvements to existing infrastructure and service delivery&#13;
with a sub-project value that may not exceed US$150,000 and would not require land acquisition&#13;
or resettlement, the Project has been placed in environmental screening "Category B" in&#13;
accordance with World Bank Operational Policy 4.01 (January 1998) and requires preparation&#13;
and implementation of an Environmental Management Plan (EMP). In order not to jeopardize&#13;
quick project preparation and implementation to respond to the needs of affected populations, as&#13;
allowed under OP 8.50, the Project would not be subject to clearances or disclosures before&#13;
appraisal. However, the Bank team, as best practice recommends, will assist the client in&#13;
preparing an EMP prior to negotiations. The EMP will be prepared by the client in close&#13;
coordination with the Environmental Quality Authority (EQA) and will be monitored through&#13;
Bank supervision missions and reviewed during the Project mid-term review. The EMP will give&#13;
general guidance on environmental issues, as well as on site assessments and designs that will be&#13;
prepared for infrastructure sub-projects to be rehabilitated and improved under this Project. The&#13;
EMP will also elaborate potential environmental impacts and recommend mitigation measures.&#13;
The need for mitigation measures is likely to be limited. If any, the costs would be financed out&#13;
of the allocation provided to local government units through their EPA allocations.&#13;
28.    Social Aspects.  The increased tightening of closure, movement restrictions and&#13;
unpredictable curfews imposed on urban areas for indefinite periods have severely impacted&#13;
Palestinian society. As a result, many Palestinians have been denied access to essential services&#13;
and sources of emergency and development assistance.&#13;
29.    The proposed activities that would be financed through the EPA would be determined on&#13;
a demand-driven basis and be prepared by LGUs in close consultation with their communities.&#13;
Impact is expected to be quite broad, as over 260 communities constituting 96 percent of the&#13;
population would directly and indirectly benefit from the proposed Project, based on a PA&#13;
determination to allocate resources to all LGUs with populations of 1,000 or more. This is&#13;
consistent with the PA's existing transfer allocation criteria. Although other Bank and donor-&#13;
financed projects are aimed at addressing the needs of very small villages, such as the Integrated&#13;
Community Development Project, provision is made under the proposed Project to assist these&#13;
LGUs as well provided that they combine efforts and organize themselves in village clusters Joint&#13;
Service Councils or other means to&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
12&#13;
30.    As an emergency Project financing mainly service-related operating costs, potential&#13;
adverse social impacts are likely to be few, if any, under this operation. However, as a means of&#13;
ensuring appropriate safeguards are in place, regionally-based Technical Consultants (3 in the&#13;
West Bank and I in Gaza) will be staffed with one part-time social assessment specialist who will&#13;
screen all emergency program assistance requests and identify any that may have a potential&#13;
adverse social impact. Appropriate mitigation measures would be designed to address these and&#13;
implementation of them would be monitored by the social assessment specialist.&#13;
31.    Building on past and current experience and work financed through the Bank in WBG, it&#13;
is assumed that no negative social impacts would be encountered.  This has been well&#13;
documented through Bank projects including: the Municipal Infrastructure Development Project,&#13;
the Emergency Response Program, the first and second Community Development Projects, and&#13;
the Emergency Services Support Project which all contributed in various ways to the&#13;
rehabilitation and improvement of basic infrastructure services and other essential municipal&#13;
services.&#13;
32.    Key Project Performance Indicators7. The Project Implementation Plan describes the&#13;
process of monitoring the outcomes and outputs of the Project. The sector indicators (setup of a&#13;
Municipal Fund, increase of center/local transfers, increased donor aid mobilization and&#13;
coordination, and improvement of essential services coverage) will be monitored during Bank&#13;
supervision missions The Development Objective performance indicators (e.g., feedback from&#13;
the local communities, quality and environmental surveys, equitable allocation of funds, level of&#13;
dialogue between the LGUs and PA, and use of labor-intensive techniques) will be monitored&#13;
based on more specific surveys conducted during the Project period. There will be reports issued&#13;
on (i) impact of public awareness training and the community consultation process through social&#13;
impact surveys, (ii) environmental impact surveys, (iii) surveys on the impact of the Project on&#13;
quality of service delivery. PCU reports, supervision missions and an ICR will complement this&#13;
process. As for the Output indicators, a MIS system including a project database will be in place&#13;
to gather information on the improvement of service delivery, municipal finances, and&#13;
employment generation (e.g., reduction of shortfalls, new household connections, rehabilitation&#13;
of existing connections, cost of O&amp;M, reduced number of uncontrolled dump sites, status of solid&#13;
waste management plans, and number of direct and indirect man-days generated).&#13;
SECTION D. STUDIES &amp; TECHNICAL ASSISTANCE&#13;
33.    While the majority of the proposed Project's financing is aimed at providing assistance to&#13;
LGUs in sustaining essential services, there would also be support in establishing the Municirza!&#13;
Fund and in strengthening central and local government implementation capacity. In addition,&#13;
the Bank is preparing to undertake analytical work in parallel with this proposed Project to&#13;
support and inform the municipal reform process and to ensure appropriate linkages are&#13;
established with the proposed-Project. This work would be undertaken in partnership with other&#13;
donors. DFID has already expressed its interest in working with the Bank on a policy note&#13;
addressing key decentralization and governance issues. In addition, a Bank team has applied for&#13;
financing from a donor-financed Consultant Trust Fund to carry out a comparative assessment of&#13;
local government finance and governance issues in three regional countries. Complementing this&#13;
analytical work, the Project would finance the services of a specialized entity responsible for the&#13;
design and setup of the Fund Commission and the Municipal Fund. Given the need to draw on&#13;
7See Project Logframe with key performance indicators under Annex 5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
13&#13;
global experience, the PA has expressed an interest in engaging a Management Agent with&#13;
sufficient expertise to assist it in this task. The Management Agent would propose criteria for (i)&#13;
allocation of funds, (ii) eligibility, (ii) project submission forms and all additional necessary&#13;
mechanisms. The Management Agent would propose the institutional arrangements for the&#13;
Municipal Fund and for the Fund Commission including an MIS, rules and regulations,&#13;
procedures, staffing and training. In addition to financing the Management Agent contract, the&#13;
Grant would finance regionally-based technical consulting units that will support LGUs in&#13;
implementing their programs. The Grant would also finance NGOs and other community-based&#13;
institutions in conducting service delivery surveys and to promote community participation in the&#13;
preparation of LGU emergency programs. For the employment creation sub-component, a&#13;
consultant would be contracted to raise awareness about labor-intensive design approaches to job&#13;
creation, prepare template bidding documents and contracts and to organize training sessions and&#13;
workshops targeting LGU officials, contractors, NGOs and other agencies likely to play a role in&#13;
implementing this component of the proposed Project.&#13;
SECTION E. INSTITUTIONAL ARRANGEMENTS &amp; PROJECT IMPLEMENTATION&#13;
34.    Though there are about 440 LGUs in WBG (including municipalities, village councils&#13;
and small hamlets) with a total population of about 3.2 million, key stakeholders agreed that the&#13;
proposed Project would provide financing to LGUs with populations of 1,000 and over, which&#13;
represent just over 260 communities. It was further agreed that this criteria would be realistic, fair&#13;
and transparent since it covers about 96% of the total population and since allocations would be&#13;
made to each LGU on the basis of its share of the population.8&#13;
35.    There are four government entities whose mandate directly or indirectly affects the local&#13;
government sector. These are the Ministry of Local Government (MOLG), the Ministry of&#13;
Finance (MOF), the Ministry of Planning and International Cooperation (MOPIC), and Local&#13;
Government Units (LGUs). MOF oversees the setup of the inter-governmental transfer system&#13;
and monitors overall resource allocation at the local government level; MOPIC has the dual&#13;
responsibility for overall planning and donor coordination, and plays a central role in&#13;
coordinating emergency assistance planning under the current circumstances.&#13;
36.    MOLG has overall regulatory responsibility for the sector and provides policy guidance&#13;
and support, as well as coordination among donors active in the sector, including monitoring and&#13;
evaluation of donor-financed programs. In accordance with the Local Government Law, MOLG&#13;
also receives and reviews annual budgets prepared by LGUs. Because of the absence of a well-&#13;
functioning intergovernmental financial transfer system in the past, however, only 60 percent of&#13;
LGUs actually submit annual budgets, anticipating that submission would have a little or no&#13;
impact on transfers, as no regular, systematic transfer system has ever been put in place. As a&#13;
result, most LGUs have come to rely on service charges and user fees to cover their operating&#13;
expenses. In the past, only 30 percent of LGUs submitted fiscal year financial statements for the&#13;
same reason. Enabling the setup of an intergovernmental transfer system through the Municipal&#13;
Fund will provide MOF and MOLG with an important instrument to ensure LGU compliance&#13;
with the law, as eligibility for Phase II financial support through the Municipal Fund would&#13;
require these submissions. With a higher percentage of LGUs submitting this information,&#13;
' In the absence of expenditure data for services provided by all LGUs, population, as an allocation criteria,&#13;
was deemed to be an appropriate proxy based on a strong correlation between population and service&#13;
expenditures (.98), as determined by the Bank mission using Bank survey data from a sample of LGUs.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
14&#13;
MOLG and MOF will be in a better position to analyze revenue and expenditure data and provide&#13;
advisory support to those LGUs who need to better manage costs related to service provision.&#13;
This would be enabled under the proposed Project by the establishment of a Municipal Financial&#13;
Data Information System.&#13;
37.    Project Steering Committee. In light of the complementary roles performed by the&#13;
different governmental bodies involved in the sector and recognizing the need for coordination at&#13;
the central government level, a Project Steering Committee (PSC) was formed by the Minister of&#13;
Local Government in October 2002 comprised of MOLG, MOF and MOPIC to ensure a&#13;
coordinated programmatic response to emergency assistance needs at the local government level.&#13;
The Project Steering Committee would provide overall policy guidance and direction in the&#13;
administration of the proposed Project and would authorize allocations based on a technical&#13;
review and recommendation prepared by the Project Coordination Unit (PCU). The PSC would&#13;
not be involved in day-to-day implementation issues, as this will be handled by the PCU.&#13;
However, it would be responsible for ensuring that guidelines are adhered to and would be&#13;
accountable to donor financiers regarding overall Project performance, either as Emergency&#13;
Program Assistance or through the Municipal Fund. The PSC would serve as the governance&#13;
body responsible for both the proposed Project and for the EU co-financed Emergency Municipal&#13;
Support Project. During implementation of Phase I, a Management Agent would be contracted to&#13;
review the performance of the PSC and recommend measures needed to be taken to&#13;
institutionalize the body as a Fund Commission in Phase II. Establishment of the Fund&#13;
Commission is intended to support a more programmatic approach to intergovernmental fiscal&#13;
relations and the administration of financial transfers in particular. Other ministries (e.g., the&#13;
Ministry of Public Works, through its involvement in the EU-financed project) would serve as&#13;
adjunct members dealing with specific issues regarding their respective sectors. In its oversight&#13;
capacity, the PSC would: a) ensure proper implementation of the Project in accordance with the&#13;
provisions of the proposed Project's legal agreements, the PIP and the Project Operation Manual;&#13;
b) ensure that effective monitoring and evaluation of project activities takes place; c) review the&#13;
technical recommendation of the PCU regarding LGU submissions; and d) approve LGU&#13;
emergency programs against budgets established based on the population allocation criteria.&#13;
38.    Project Coordination Unit. Day-to-day implementation would be the responsibility of a&#13;
Project Coordination Unit (PCU) at MOLG. Implementation would take place in two phases over&#13;
a two year period starting on January 1, 2003 and completing on December 31, 2004 . The first&#13;
phase would be implemented in the first calendar year of the Project and would be linked to the&#13;
budgetary preparation cycle, as would the second phase, which would be implemented over the&#13;
second year. Two existing PCUs, housed in MOLG (one in Gaza and one in the West Bank), and&#13;
responsible for implementing other Bank-administered projects, would be merged into one PCU&#13;
with two branch offices and designated the task of implementing the proposed Project. The&#13;
present responsibilities of these two PCUs are expected to be completed by the end of 2002,&#13;
ensuring a dedicated commitment to implementing the proposed Project. The staff of the two&#13;
PCUs were recruited in accordance with IDA Guidelines for the selection of consultants and have&#13;
gained valuable experience in administering previous Bank-financed operations. The merged&#13;
PCU would be comprised of three key staff at the Gaza Branch office, including a Project Branch&#13;
Manager, a Deputy, and one Accountant, while the West Bank Branch, where the FMS would be&#13;
established to manage the Special Account, would be comprised of a Project Branch Manager, a&#13;
Financial Officer, and two assistant accountants. A Project Director is in the process of being&#13;
recruited to ensure appropriate linkages are established and coordination in implementation and&#13;
reporting to the PSC/FC and to donors. All PCU staff that are not financed under other projects,&#13;
9 See Annex 4 for a chart illustrating the Project's transition from Phase I to Phase 11.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
15&#13;
would be paid under the Project. Two other technical staff will be seconded to the PCU by&#13;
MOLG to assist in LGU proposal screening, monitoring and reporting. MOLG engineers in&#13;
district offices would also have a role in monitoring and evaluating implementation of LGU&#13;
activities.&#13;
39.    The PCU would be responsible for all project accounting, disbursement, monitoring and&#13;
evaluation, and would ensure timely implementation of Project activities, reviewing LGU&#13;
proposals, and makings recommendations to the PSC regarding approval of LGU emergency&#13;
programs. The PCU would also be responsible for the selection of consultants and preparation of&#13;
contracts for the local/international technical consulting firms/consultants, as well as procurement&#13;
of PCU goods and equipment. The PCU would be required to submit quarterly progress reports&#13;
for IDA review. These reports would cover the status of physical progress in implementing LGU&#13;
programs and would include updated commitment/disbursement data and variation orders, and&#13;
the status of direct and indirect temporary employment created in man-days, noting deviations, if&#13;
any, from the implementation plan. The quarterly progress reports would also highlight key&#13;
issues and constraints, mitigation measures planned and taken, updated LGU financial data and&#13;
updated assessments of the quality of service delivery at the participating LGUs. The PCU would&#13;
prepare a detailed midterm report that will serve as the basis for a Project Mid-Term Review in&#13;
December 2003. The PCU would also prepare and submit an Implementation Completion Report&#13;
(ICR) to IDA within four months of the closing date of the Project.&#13;
40.    The PCU would be assisted by MOLG district technical staff (DTS) in evaluating and&#13;
monitoring implementation of LGU programs. DTS would report to the MOLG project&#13;
department heads, copying the PCU. DTS would coordinate fully with the PCU in conducting&#13;
their monitoring and evaluation of LGU programs. Local consulting firms will be recruited by&#13;
the PCU according to IDA Guidelines for Selection of Consultants to monitor implementation of&#13;
LGU programs, provide pre-screening of proposed LGU emergency programs, advise LGUs on&#13;
procurement and improvement of quality of work, report on employment generation, provide&#13;
environmental screening of sub-projects and conduct social assessments, as necessary. To further&#13;
clarify implementation arrangements, a detailed responsibility matrix was prepared as shown in&#13;
Annex 2. A chart depicting institutional arrangements and another one depicting process flow are&#13;
provided in Annex 3 and 4 respectively.&#13;
41.    Local Government Units. Participating LGUs would be responsible for a) consulting&#13;
with their communities in order to identify priority public service needs to include in the LGU&#13;
emergency program; b) submitting program proposals using standardized forms; and c)&#13;
implementing their approved programs directly, including preparation of bidding documents,&#13;
tendering, receiving, opening and evaluating bids, and requesting no objections from the PCU for&#13;
projects subject to prior review. They would also be responsible for awarding and signing&#13;
contracts with suppliers and contractors, supervising execution of their sub-projects, receiving&#13;
requests for payment from vendors and contractors, reviewing them and issuing payment&#13;
certificates. LGUs would also be responsible for reporting back to the PCU on work progress,&#13;
accounting for and providing status reports on the use of financial allocations from the project&#13;
proceeds.&#13;
42.    Management Agent. A Management Agent (MA) would be recruited to design and&#13;
establish the Municipal Fund. The main value added of the MA would be in helping to scale up&#13;
the Emergency Program Assistance provided to LGUs into an institutionalized mechanism for&#13;
intergovernmental financial transfers. The MA is expected to be contracted and mobilized by&#13;
July 2003 and would review the performance of the Project over its first year and take into&#13;
account these observations in proposing arrangements for the transition to a Municipal Fund. The&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
16&#13;
MA would also propose the structure, functions and legal basis for the establishment of the Fund&#13;
Commission, as it transitions from a Project Steering Committee. The MA's proposed MF design&#13;
and institutional arrangements would be reviewed by IDA and discussed with the PSC at length&#13;
during this period. Following this review, the Bank would undertake a more detailed assessment&#13;
at the Project's Mid-Term review (toward the end of 2003) at which time a decision would be&#13;
made as to whether the institutional basis was in place to support the transition to Phase II.&#13;
However, anticipating possible difficulties in successfully identifying and mobilizing the&#13;
Management Agent, including a possible escalation of violence, the Project structure would&#13;
remain intact and the PSC and PCU would continue implementing the Project in the second year&#13;
essentially along the same lines as it did in the first year. This arrangement recognizes the need&#13;
to be flexible in the Project's design, providing an option to scale up, as a means of supporting&#13;
longer-term institution building, while acknowledging that the circumstances in WBG are highly&#13;
unpredictable, thus requiring alternative implementation options.&#13;
43.   If advancement to Phase II is feasible, the Management Agent (MA) would be&#13;
responsible for providing capacity building to the PCU in administering the Municipal Fund,&#13;
including establishment of sound internal financial controls and reporting systems. This would&#13;
include establishment of a Municipal Financial Data Management System to enable better&#13;
monitoring and tracking of LGU financial data so as to improve responsiveness to emergency&#13;
assistance needs. This System would also make available to MOLG comparative data on service&#13;
delivery expenditures by different LGUs, which it can in turn share with interested LGUs seeking&#13;
alternative service delivery options to improve efficiency. The MA would also act as the Fund&#13;
Commission's agent in the Project's second year by monitoring the Fund's performance and&#13;
supporting the Commission in its efforts to report to donor contributors on the uses and impact of&#13;
the assistance they have provided.&#13;
44.    PA-Donor Coordination. A Donor Consultation Forum would be formally established&#13;
prior to the launch of the proposed Project to coordinate international assistance provided as&#13;
transfers through the Municipal Fund and will liaise with the PSC periodically. The European&#13;
Commission and Government of Belgium, as donors providing co-financing to the proposed&#13;
Project, have agreed to participate in this Forum and view it as an essential means of&#13;
coordinating donor interventions in the sector. It is expected that other donors would join as they&#13;
make commitments to the Municipal Fund, which is expected to take place in the coming year in&#13;
conjunction with the next round of donor assistance consultations and commitments agreed with&#13;
the PA. The PCU would prepare for these meetings and quarterly reports would be distributed to&#13;
donors in advance of the meeting.&#13;
45.    PA-LGU Consultations.   On a bi-annual basis, MOLG would meet with LGU&#13;
representatives to exchange information on project implementation and to discuss measures&#13;
required to strengthen processes. The PCU would prepare for these meetings. Briefings of the&#13;
main issues discussed at these meetings and recommendations reached would be reported in the&#13;
next quarterly reports to the Bank and other donor cofinanciers.&#13;
46.    Project Implementation Plan (PIP) &amp; Project Operation Manual (POM). A draft&#13;
Project Implementation Plan was prepared by MOLG and discussed during appraisal. Its purpose&#13;
is to detail how the Palestinian Authority intends to carry out the Project to its completion. The&#13;
PIP complements the MOP and Technical Annex and expands on important implementation&#13;
arrangements. It is seen by the PA as a flexible implementation tool that will be reviewed&#13;
periodically and adjusted when warranted. The PIP describes MOLG as a focal point, fully&#13;
accountable for Project oversight and coordination. It details the responsibilities of MOLG, the&#13;
Project Steering Committee (that will evolve into a Fund Commission in the second phase of the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
17&#13;
Project) and the Management Agent during the two phases of the Project. Staffing and key staff&#13;
positions for all the units involved in implementation are described in the PIP. The PIP also&#13;
describes the role of the other participants in the process (municipalities, communities, various&#13;
ministries and donors), as well as the coordination mechanism between these various actors. To&#13;
streamline and facilitate implementation of the Project, a Project Operational Manual (POM) has&#13;
been prepared in draft form and will be finalized by the conclusion of Negotiations. The POM&#13;
would include procedures for submitting proposals by LGUs, screening proposals, fund allocation&#13;
criteria, as well as guidelines relating to disbursements, accounting, procurement, reporting and a&#13;
detailed responsibility matrix.&#13;
47.    There will be a Project launch workshop organized within one month after the Project is&#13;
declared effective. Bank supervision staff are located in the field for close monitoring of the&#13;
Project and to provide timely assistance to the client. Supervision missions will take place&#13;
according to Project requirements. The Project midterm review is scheduled by December 2003,&#13;
when the first phase of the Project will come to an end. At that time, all arrangements regarding&#13;
the Municipal Fund and the Fund Commission should be in place and the Municipal Fund ready&#13;
to be operational for the second phase of the Project (a dated covenant under the Project). The&#13;
penultimate supervision mission (June-July 2004) will be used to launch with the PA the&#13;
preparation of the ICR.&#13;
Major Benefits and Risks&#13;
48.    Benefits. The principle benefit of the Project will be improvements in the delivery of&#13;
essential municipal services including solid waste collection, water supply and sanitation&#13;
services, and electricity supply to a significant portion of the Palestinian population. Improved&#13;
service coverage and quality would help mitigate deteriorating health and sanitary conditions,&#13;
reducing health risks while generating some economic activity. In addition, targeted assistance to&#13;
communities with higher incidences of unemployment and poverty through labor-intensive&#13;
temporary employment generation activities would ameliorate some of the harshest effects of the&#13;
economic contraction.  The process of preparing municipal emergency programs through&#13;
participatory methods involving communities would signal the desire of local governments to&#13;
respond to urgent community needs, while strengthening the social compact with their&#13;
constituents. Establishment of a Municipal Fund will, in the short term, provide a mechanism to&#13;
better mobilize emergency assistance, improve targeting and allow for greater equity in the&#13;
allocation of resources at the local government level. As such, the Municipal Fund would serve&#13;
as an important instrument in facilitating central-local coordination in response to emergency&#13;
needs in the future. At the same time, it would provide an important institutional foundation&#13;
linking central and local budgetary planning processes and facilitating improved resource&#13;
allocation.&#13;
49.    Risks.  Project risks include a volatile political and security situation that could&#13;
jeopardize smooth implementation, particularly if closures and curfews remain in place for an&#13;
indefinite period of time. In addition, with a Cabinet reshuffling in process and local elections&#13;
scheduled for early next year, there is a possibility that the priorities of the political leadership&#13;
may change and not necessarily be in line with the reforms that serve as a basis for this Grant.&#13;
This risk is widely acknowledged by the donor community and is addressed in part through the&#13;
Task Force on Palestinian Reform. The Bank's active participation in this reform effort, with&#13;
particular focus on municipal reforms, should serve to mitigate this risk. The proposed operation,&#13;
in turn, would provide an operational vehicle to translate agreed reform actions into meaningful&#13;
change. Specific risks include: (i) Logistical constraints: Curfews and closures that impede&#13;
movement within Gaza and West Bank, thus limiting the impact of capacity building and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
18&#13;
technical assistance support, and increased transaction costs and delays in the delivery of essential&#13;
equipment, spare parts and other externally-sourced goods that are essential to improving service&#13;
provision; (ii) Prolonged political stalemate: Delayed progress in achieving a political settlement&#13;
will have a determining effect on the ability of the Project to contribute toward long-term reforms&#13;
and institution building; and (iii) Delays in mobilizing the Management Agent or inability to&#13;
identify a suitably qualified Agent would impact the transition to Phase II. As a mitigation&#13;
measure against this risk, Phase I is designed to continue as the Project implementation structure&#13;
through Phase II. Moreover, the general risks to the Project are manageable with sustained donor&#13;
commitment to support emergency needs and improve coordination, in particular through the&#13;
Municipal Fund established under the proposed operation, through close supervision and&#13;
decentralized delivery of technical assistance and capacity building support, as proposed under&#13;
this operation. Where international expertise is needed, firms would be encouraged to form&#13;
partnerships with local organizations and to rely on the relatively strong human resource base in&#13;
WBG to take responsibility for implementation at the local level.&#13;
Procurement Arrangements&#13;
50.    The Project will finance, services, goods, operating costs and civil works. Procurement&#13;
will be conducted in accordance with IDA guidelines for "Procurement under IBRD Loans and&#13;
IDA Credits", January 1995 (revised in January and August 1996, September 1997, and January&#13;
1999); as well as those for "Selection and Employment of Consultants by World Bank&#13;
Borrowers," January 1997 (revised September 1997 and January 1999, revised May 2002). The&#13;
components not financed by IDA would be procured in accordance with PA regulations or&#13;
guidelines of co financing institutions. A General Procurement Notice (GPN) would be issued in&#13;
"United Nations Development Business" (UNDB) prior to the publication of the first Specific&#13;
Procurement Notice (SPN) and bidders who have expressed an interest would be notified directly&#13;
by the PCU.&#13;
51.   Procurement Responsibilities.  The PCU    would bear    overall procurement&#13;
responsibility during all phases of the project. The Municipal Fund Design and Management&#13;
component and the Technical Assistance and Capacity Building component would be procured by&#13;
the PCU at the MOLG. Procurement of the Emergency Program Assistance component&#13;
(US$17.5 million IDA financing) would be decentralized to LGUs, as was the case under ESSP&#13;
I and PEACE Facility co-financing trust funds (which were administered by the Bank), to&#13;
expedite the implementation of this emergency Project. Building on the experience under the&#13;
PEACE facility, technical assistance on procurement from locally-based consulting firms (three&#13;
in the West Bank and one in Gaza) and from MOLG's regional offices would be provided to the&#13;
LGUs. The consulting firms would report directly to the PCU on their review of procurement&#13;
process at LGUs and advise on timely corrective measures, if any, to be taken to avoid faulty&#13;
procurement decisions at the level of LGUs. With the assistance of these consultants, LGUs&#13;
would prepare bidding documents, tender, receive bids, evaluate bids, award and sign contracts&#13;
with the lowest evaluated bidders. For those contracts subject to prior review, LGUs would&#13;
request a 'no objection' from the PCU before signing contracts. The PCU would review the&#13;
recommendation and provide its 'no objection' to the requesting LGU. If required by the TFA,&#13;
the PCU would first seek IDA's 'no objection' to award the contract. A copy of all contracts,&#13;
purchase orders and bid evaluation reports would be retained and filed at the PCU. An Project&#13;
Operational Manual (POM) has been prepared which includes detailed information on&#13;
procurement with samples forms, bidding documents, bid evaluation forms and sample&#13;
communications letters. The POM would be finalized by negotiations.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
19&#13;
52.    Because of the emergency nature of the Project, simplified procurement procedures will&#13;
apply. Simplified bidding documents (in Arabic language) will be used to procure small civil&#13;
works and goods, and simplified NCB and shopping procedures will be used to procure goods.&#13;
53.    Procurement Methods.    The procurement arrangements described below  are&#13;
summarized under Table A. Thresholds for procurement methods and prior review arrangements&#13;
are summarized under Table B.&#13;
54.    Civil Works (US$2.0 million).  Bid packages with an estimated contract value of&#13;
US$100,000 equivalent or more, would be procured using NCB procedures and documents and&#13;
advertisements in at least two local newspapers. NCB contracts would be open to eligible foreign&#13;
bidders if they wish to participate. Bid evaluations would be submitted on IDA's Standard Bid&#13;
Evaluation Forms for Procurement of Goods and Works of April 1996. Works contracts&#13;
estimated to cost below US$100,000, up to an aggregate amount of US$1,000,000, would be&#13;
procured in accordance with simplified bidding procedures acceptable to IDA, including&#13;
simplified bidding and contract documents with a basic description and specifications of the&#13;
required small works and incidental material and labor, posting invitation to bid in a public place&#13;
within the community, transparent procedures for accepting sealed bids, public bid opening, bid&#13;
evaluation and contract award to the lowest evaluated responsive bid price offered by a bidder&#13;
with the necessary skills and equipment and other proper resources to complete the contract&#13;
satisfactorily. Works contracts estimated to cost less than US$10,000, up to an aggregate amount&#13;
of US$200,000, would be procured by obtaining three competitive proposals from capable local&#13;
contractors and awarding the contract to the contractor offering the lowest price. Under&#13;
exceptional circumstances requiring IDA's prior clearance, these very small works may be&#13;
carried out by Government Forces, as per paragraph. 3.8 (Force Account) of IDA Guidelines.&#13;
55.    Goods (US$9.0 million). Goods, such as solid waste collection containers and vehicle&#13;
spare parts, necessary construction materials, i.e. cement, reinforcing steel rods, base course,&#13;
asphalting material, tiles and other materials, water and sewage pipes and fittings, electric cables&#13;
and transformers, street lighting poles, electrical bulbs, etc., fuel, lubricants, office equipment and&#13;
furniture would be financed out of the Emergency Program Assistance Component. To the extent&#13;
possible, goods would be grouped together in lots of similar items. Packages with an estimated&#13;
contract value of US$100,000 or more would be procured using National Competitive Bidding&#13;
(NCB) procedures and documents acceptable to the Bank. These contracts would require&#13;
advertisement in at least two local newspapers. NCB contracts would be open to eligible foreign&#13;
bidders if they wish to participate. Goods contracts estimated to cost less than US$ 100,000 up to&#13;
an aggregate amount of US$3,500,000 would be procured using National or International&#13;
Shopping (NS/IS) procedures and would require soliciting, receiving and evaluating competitive&#13;
quotations from at least three qualified suppliers. Goods costing less than US$5,000 up to an&#13;
aggregate amount of US$500,000 would be procured through direct purchase from the nearest&#13;
available source.&#13;
56.    Services (US$5.0 million). For services costing US$200,000 or more the Quality and&#13;
Cost Based Selection (QCBS) method would be used and would require advertisement of an&#13;
Expressions of Interest in UN Development Business and the use of IDA's Standard RFP and&#13;
Evaluation Report. For services costing less than US$200,000 up to an aggregate amount of&#13;
US$500,000, the selection method would be QCBS or QBS. For services provided by firms&#13;
costing less than US$50,000, up to an aggregate amount of US$500,000, the selection method&#13;
would be Consultants' Qualifications (CQ).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
20&#13;
57.     For individual consultant contracts estimated to cost US$50,000 or less, the selection&#13;
method would be based on Section V. of World Bank Guidelines for Selection and Employment of&#13;
Consultants by World Bank Borrowers, published in January 1997 and revised in September&#13;
1997, January 1999, and May 2002. Single Source Selection (SS) would be used under&#13;
exceptional cases and require IDA's prior review and 'no objection'.&#13;
58.     Contracts for non-intellectual and advisory services, such as payments for labor-intensive&#13;
service providers including solid waste collection, cleaning contracts, painting, operations and&#13;
maintenance of public facilities and infrastructure, laboratory tests, etc. would be procured using&#13;
procurement for works and goods procedures.&#13;
Table A: Project Costs by Procurement Arrangements&#13;
(US$ million equivalent)&#13;
Procurement Method'&#13;
Expenditure Category      ICB           NCB           Other          N.B.F.        Total Cost&#13;
1. Works                  0.00          0.60            1.40          6.00            8.00&#13;
(0.00)        (0.60)         (1.40)         (0.00)         (2.00)&#13;
2. Goods                  0.00           5.00           4.00          21.3           30.30&#13;
(0.00)        (5.00)         (4.00)         (0.00)          (9.00)&#13;
3. Services               0.00           0.00           5.00          0.00            5.00&#13;
(0.00)        (0.00)         (5.00)         (0.00)          (5.00)&#13;
6. Operating              0.00           0.00           4.00          22.70          26.70&#13;
Expenditures and          (0.00)        (0.00)         (4.00)        (0.00)          (4.00)&#13;
Maintenance&#13;
Total                   0.00          5.60          14.40          50.00           70.00&#13;
(0.00)        (5.60)         (14.40)        (0.00)         (20.00)&#13;
1/ Figures in parenthesis are the amounts to befinanced by the Bank All costs include contingencies. Because of the&#13;
emergency and demand driven nature of the Project, the allocated amounts are tentative.  During Project&#13;
implementation, flexibility in reallocation between the different categories would be exercised to ensure smooth&#13;
Project implementation.&#13;
2/ Includes civil works and goods to be procured through national/international shopping, direct purchase, direct&#13;
contracting of consulting services, auditing cost, services of contracted staff of the Project Coordination Unit,&#13;
training, technical assistance services, and incremental operating costs related to solid waste disposal fees, rent,&#13;
utility charges, communication costs, travel costs, labor and office supply and equipment.&#13;
59.     Prior Review. (Table B provides information on all prior review arrangements). Th._&#13;
first three contract packages in each category and each procurement method (works, goods and&#13;
services), irrespective of the estimated contract value, would be subject to IDA's prior review, in&#13;
accordance with the applicable guidelines. Thereafter, all contracts for works with an estimated&#13;
contract value above US$200,000 equivalent and any contract for goods with an estimated&#13;
contract value above US$100,000 equivalent would be subject to IDA's prior review. All Force&#13;
Account works would be subject to IDA's prior review. Contracts with individual consultants in&#13;
excess of US$50,000 equivalent and with consulting firms in excess of US$100,000 equivalent,&#13;
as well as all single-source contracts will be subject to prior review. All other contracts would be&#13;
subject to post-review on a random basis during supervision missions and procurement audits.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
21&#13;
Table B. Thresholds for Procurement Methods and Prior Review&#13;
Contract Value                               Contracts Subject to&#13;
Expenditure          Threshold            Procurement             Prior Review&#13;
Category        (US$ thousand)             Method                (US$ million)&#13;
1. Works               &gt;= 100,000               NCB              First three contracts and&#13;
then each contract above&#13;
200,000&#13;
&lt;100,000            Simplified NCB         First three contracts&#13;
&lt;10,000               Shopping             First three contracts&#13;
2. Goods               &gt;=100,000                NCB                   All contracts&#13;
&lt;100,000                NS/IS              First three contracts&#13;
&lt;5,000             Direct Purchase           All Contracts&#13;
3. Services&#13;
Firm:                  &gt;=200,000                QCBS                All contracts&#13;
&lt;200,000              QCBS, QBS            First three RFPs and&#13;
&lt;50,000                  CQ            contracts and then all TORs,&#13;
evaluation reports and&#13;
contracts&#13;
Individual:&#13;
&gt;=50,000            see section V of          All contracts&#13;
Guidelines&#13;
&lt;50,000             see section V of       First three contracts&#13;
Guidelines&#13;
Total value of contracts subject to prior review:            US$10.00 million&#13;
60.    Overall Procurement Risk Assessment: High.&#13;
61.    Frequency of procurement supervision missions proposed: One every four months&#13;
(including special procurement supervision for post-review/audits) in the first year and six&#13;
months thereafter. This frequency is based on the procurement assessment report. Staff would be&#13;
trained under the Project in procurement planning.&#13;
62.    Procurement Planning. For items to be procured by the PCU, the PCU would prepare a&#13;
procurement plan for the first year prior to Effectiveness. The procurement plan would include&#13;
information on main procurement steps (date of advertisement, bid document date, bid evaluation&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
22&#13;
date, awarded bidder, estimated and actual cost, progress to date versus planned).  The&#13;
procurement plan would be revised on a quarterly basis.&#13;
63.    Summary of Procurement Assessment. Since it was established, the MOLG has been&#13;
working bilaterally with a number of donor countries and international agencies including the&#13;
Bank. It has capable and experienced staff who have carried out and performed procurement&#13;
processes in accordance with different donor rules and regulations. The capacity of LGUs to&#13;
manage procurement processes vary. Large LGU's have been working bilaterally with the Bank&#13;
and other donors, and have experienced staff capable of managing procurement, while some of&#13;
the very small LGU's have little experience with donor procurement policies and procedures.&#13;
Nevertheless, under the Project these LGU's would be assisted by regionally based technical&#13;
consulting firms and by the PCU or MOLG staff to implement procurement. At the same time,&#13;
Procurement training will also be provided for LGUs, in order to build up their long-term&#13;
capacity in support of future decentralization of procurement. It is worth mentioning that all&#13;
LGUs in Gaza and a very large number of LGUs in the West Bank have acquired procurement&#13;
experience under Bank-financed or administrated projects such as ESSP I, ERSP, PEACE facility&#13;
cofinancing trust funds, and MIDP I. Several workshops were conducted in Gaza to train LGU&#13;
staff on procurement procedures based on IDA procurement guidelines. A more detailed&#13;
procurement assessment is in the Project files.&#13;
64.    Procurement Training. To strengthen procurement capacity at the LGUs, the PCU&#13;
would arrange for procurement training during the first quarter of the first year to help those&#13;
LGUs which are not familiar with Bank procurement guidelines. The training would include&#13;
preparation of bidding documents and bid evaluation reports for goods, works and services. The&#13;
training could be conducted by local universities or experienced training consultants. During the&#13;
Project launch workshop, the basic principles of procurement methods and IDA guidelines would&#13;
be discussed with the participating LGUs. At the same time, their training needs would be&#13;
addressed in a training schedule prepared by the PCU. The PCU would also draft standard&#13;
bidding documents, sample specifications for commonly procured goods and templates of&#13;
evaluation reports. These documents would be distributed to LGUs to use in administrating their&#13;
procurement processes. Based on the result of Midterm review and the post review in the first&#13;
year, the PCU would assess the sufficiency of training provided to the LGUs and its beneficial&#13;
effects on procurement capacity. If necessary, training of the LGUs would be increased until their&#13;
capacity has reached a satisfactory level. Procurement coaching in the form of continuous&#13;
dialogue between the PCU and the LGUs would be assured during the life of the project. The&#13;
PCU would also be encouraged to have a plan to train the trainers on procurement for future&#13;
sustainability.&#13;
Financial Management&#13;
65.    MOLG, through the two existing Project Coordination Units (PCUs) in its branch offices&#13;
in West Bank and Gaza, will have the responsibility for project implementation as well as all&#13;
aspects of financial management. Both of the PCUs are already established and they will be&#13;
responsible, inter alia, for the project's overall financial administration, including accounting,&#13;
monitoring, and reporting throughout the duration of the project. In Phase II, the Management&#13;
Agent (MA), if successfully identified and mobilized, will provide technical advice and support&#13;
to upgrade the financial management arrangements where appropriate in anticipation of the&#13;
increased volume of donor assistance flows through the Municipal Fund. The financial&#13;
management system (FMS) of the accounting unit at MOLG was assessed according to IDA&#13;
guidelines for the purpose of determining compliance with IDA minimum requirements&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
23&#13;
OB/BP 10.02 and the ability to generate reliable quarterly financial monitoring reports (FMR).&#13;
The assessment concluded that the FMS is adequate for presenting the Project to the Board.&#13;
66.    The Project Accounting Unit at MOLG will play a key role in the financial management&#13;
of the Project being responsible for accounting within the PCU. It is well structured and staffed&#13;
(staff salaries are being paid under other Bank projects and would continue to be financed under&#13;
the proposed Project). It has a computerized accounting system (Audit) developed by a local&#13;
software company. The system can accommodate several on-going projects and has a reliable&#13;
built-in security log-in system. It also has flexible reporting tools which, with minor modification&#13;
and setting of the proper chart of accounts, would allow generation of FMRs.. The system also&#13;
facilitates proper budgeting as it links budgeting with accounting and shows movements on&#13;
budget lines. The accounting unit is adequately staffed with three qualified accountants. Another&#13;
accountant would be located in the Gaza branch office who would assist the PCU. The&#13;
accountant is professionally qualified and has experience with IDA financial and disbursement&#13;
procedures (he is the accountant for the DANIDA cofinanced project administered by IDA under&#13;
the PEACE facility). The PCU-Gaza branch has an accounting system already established by&#13;
an international accounting firm and a computerized accounting system (Asseel) developed by a&#13;
local software firm. There is a properly documented accounting procedural manual and clear&#13;
segregation of duties among all incompatible functions. Dual check signatory arrangements are&#13;
already in place. The PCU-Gaza branch will report on financial matters to the PCU West Bank&#13;
branch. The PCU will prepare annual financial statements, which will be audited by a qualified&#13;
independent auditor acceptable to IDA. Quarterly Financial Monitoring Reports will be prepared&#13;
by the PCU and sent un-audited to IDA within 45 days from the reporting period end date.&#13;
67.    Financial Management Assessment. The financial management assessment conducted&#13;
for the MOLG/PCU revealed that the financial management systems in place are adequate and&#13;
meet the minimum requirements of IDA. The operational manual of the project provides an&#13;
adequate level of segregation of duties and clear division of authorities and responsibilities. Also,&#13;
the FMS is capable of producing reliable project financial statements and FMRs in a timely&#13;
manner.&#13;
68.    Accounting System. The project's primary accounting responsibility will be based at the&#13;
PCU - West Bank branch office, while the PCU - Gaza branch office will follow on all&#13;
accounting aspects related to the operations in Gaza and prepare monthly reports for the PCU&#13;
West Bank office for review and consolidation of the project accounts. The PCU's accounting&#13;
responsibilities will include maintaining all accounting records, supporting documents, undertake&#13;
bookkeeping of all financial transactions, prepare monthly bank reconciliation for the Special&#13;
account quarterly FMR, prepare annual financial statements, examine supporting documents for&#13;
the purpose of replenishing the LGU advance or sending payments to contractors and third&#13;
parities, verify cash replenishment requests from LGUs and process such requests, and transfer&#13;
funds from the Special Account. Accounting for the project will be on a cash basis in line with&#13;
PA and LGU accounting practices. However, year-end adjustments for accounts payable and&#13;
accounts receivable will be properly made as required under intemational accounting standards.&#13;
69.    The PCU would maintain supporting documentation for expenditures on activities&#13;
managed under the Project. Books of accounts will be maintained on double-entry bookkeeping&#13;
principles for the activities under the Project. Each LGU would provide the PCU with a monthly&#13;
summary statement of expenditures based on the books of accounts, along with other information&#13;
and documents, to enable proper accounting for these expenditures. Each participating LGU&#13;
would maintain separate books and records in respect of transactions for activities under the&#13;
Project. They should not be commingled with transactions not related to the Project. Project&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
24&#13;
records should be kept in auditable condition all the time. For those expenditures made at the&#13;
LGUs level, the original invoices would be maintained at the PCU whereas copies of the invoices&#13;
will be kept in files at the LGUs.&#13;
70.    Each LGU would establish a separate bank account for the purpose of the advance&#13;
account and will send monthly bank statements to the PCU to allow proper monitoring. The PCU&#13;
will be responsible for the Special Account and would facilitate preparation of bank&#13;
reconciliation and check accuracy and completeness of transactions incurred. Detailed accounting&#13;
and disbursement procedures, as well as procurement, will be part of the project operation&#13;
manual.&#13;
71.    Budgeting System.  The budgeting system is in place and is separate from the&#13;
government budgeting system. The PCU would prepare an annual budget plan and update it on&#13;
quarterly basis to reflect actual implementation and latest forecasts. Where feasible, LGU&#13;
proposals for funding would be accompanied by a proposed budget. This would facilitate better&#13;
planning and control. These plans would be periodically reviewed and updated along with the&#13;
progress of the project.&#13;
72.    Procedures of Internal Control. The Internal Control Procedures in place at MOLG are&#13;
based upon the governmental system as set by applicable laws and the regulations, and are&#13;
accepted by the Bank and do not present any issue of authorities or of responsibilities. Current&#13;
policies and procedures have been set already in MOLG to provide reasonable assurance of (a) a&#13;
proper authorization of transactions; (b) access to and use of assets and records; and (c)&#13;
separation of custody of cash from authorization and record keeping, and separation of&#13;
authorization from record keeping. For the objectives of the project, the project operation manual&#13;
will define the procedures of control and the relation between MOLG, LGUs and the PCU, which&#13;
is in charge of the financial management of the project.&#13;
73.    Flow of Funds. MOF will establish a Special Account at a commercial bank according&#13;
to IDA's terms and conditions. The PCU under the authority of the PSC/FC will be responsible&#13;
for managing the Special Account, including preparation of applications for withdrawal,&#13;
reconciliation of the account to IDA's records, cooperate with IDA's supervision missions and&#13;
coordinate with external auditors. The PA is providing a US$3.0 million contribution to the&#13;
Project in the form of central transfers to local government units. At the same time MOF has&#13;
agreed to apply zero VAT invoicing to the Project, and local service providers will be exempt&#13;
from income taxes for payments made to them from the Project. As a result, the PA contribution&#13;
would not be used for payment of any portion of any activity financed with IDA's funds under&#13;
the Project.  Disbursement would be on transaction-based disbursement methods using&#13;
applications for direct payment, reimbursed to the Special Account accompanied by SOEs and/or&#13;
summary sheets with full supporting documents. Each participating LGU and the PCU/MA will&#13;
maintain all supporting documents for year-end auditing and supervision missions reviews. All&#13;
documents would be kept for at least one year after the completion of the Project.&#13;
74.    Financial Monitoring  Reports  (FMR).      The  PCU   would   prepare the&#13;
Financial Management Reports and would send them non-audited to IDA within the 45 days&#13;
following every end-of-quarter. The Financial Management Reports would include (a) a general&#13;
progress report about project implementation, (b) the cost by component for the quarter, (c) the&#13;
costs incurred by type of expenses, (d) the project balance sheet, and (e) the acquisitions incurred&#13;
on contracts under the established threshold. The project statement of accounts would be put in&#13;
place to facilitate the automatic generation of the reports of financial controls. The contents and&#13;
the format of the reports are already prepared by the PCU and would be agreed during&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
25&#13;
negotiations. The FMR will be reviewed by the project team and the financial management&#13;
analyst in the Country Office, and would form the basis for the Country Office's periodic review&#13;
of the project's financial management activities.&#13;
75.    Audit. The project accounts and the annual financial statements (project balance sheet,&#13;
the flow of funds, and the statement of the Special Account) would be subjected to an annual&#13;
audit, while expenditures incurred under Statement of Expenditures (SOE) would be audited on a&#13;
semi-annual basis as the associated risk with SOEs is higher. The Audit would be conducted in&#13;
accordance with international standards, by an independent auditor acceptable to IDA, and under&#13;
terms of reference acceptable to IDA. The audit would examine all sources of funds of the&#13;
project, including the IDA grant. In the same way, it would also examine all incurred expenses&#13;
including those related to the statements of the expenditures (SOEs) by ascertaining their&#13;
conformity with the Grant Agreement. An auditor would express an opinion on the project&#13;
financial statements. In addition, the auditor would supply a separated viewpoint on the eligibility&#13;
of all incurred expenses that are included in the SOEs. The Audit report should be sent to IDA&#13;
not later than four months after the end of the year. In addition to extemal auditing, SOEs at the&#13;
PCU and a sample of LGUs would be reviewed by supervision missions and by the FMA at the&#13;
IDA Country Office to substantiate adequate supporting documentation and accuracy and to&#13;
ensure consistent and efficient application of the financial management system.&#13;
76.    Risks.  The project's financial management risk is considered moderate. This&#13;
consideration is mainly the result of the following: (a) involvement of large number of LGUs in&#13;
the project implementation (up to 260 LGUs), where some smaller LGUs lack adequate FM&#13;
capacity, (b) a large number of transactions with relatively small amounts which requires&#13;
intensive review and auditing, (c) using advance payments procedures for selected LGUs, and (d)&#13;
assurances needed that services or goods were supplied at the agreed quality/quantity and to&#13;
intended beneficiaries. These risks would be mitigated through (i) centralization of financial&#13;
management of the project at the PCU level, which is well established with two branch offices&#13;
with adequate FM systems (each participating LGU would have a separate ledger account and&#13;
files); (ii) using the one-month cash advance system by LGUs is voluntarily, and it would be&#13;
available only for LGUs with an acceptable FM system; (iii) the PCU would determine eligibility&#13;
of LGUs to receive cash advances based on criteria established in the operational manual&#13;
approved by IDA; (iv) PCUs will conduct regular visits to LGUs to ensure continuity of&#13;
satisfactory performance; (v) SOE reviews will be conducted twice a year; and (vi) the audit&#13;
scope will explicitly include ensuring satisfactory delivery of services and supplies as planned.&#13;
Also, in addition to regular supervision missions, the financial management analyst at the&#13;
Country Office will review the quarterly FMR, periodically review a sample of SOEs and&#13;
conduct visits to the PCUs. The PCU would maintain supporting documentation for expenditures&#13;
on activities. The overall financial management risk of the Project is considered moderate. The&#13;
Project will be properly supervised by the financial management analyst in the country office who&#13;
will also provide technical support and explanation to the PCU and provide assistance with&#13;
disbursements. Also, the Project will be supervised through regular supervision missions by a&#13;
financial management specialist from HQ.&#13;
Disbursement&#13;
77.    Disbursements would follow transaction-based disbursement methods using applications&#13;
for direct payment, reimbursement and replenishment to the Special Account accompanied by&#13;
SOEs and/or summary sheets with full supporting documents. To facilitate implementation, each&#13;
eligible LGU will receive maximum of 10% as an advance payment of its expected expenditures.&#13;
The advance payment should be settled within one month following agreed-upon procedures&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
26&#13;
stipulated in the operation manual. Eligibility of LGU to receive advance payments will be&#13;
determined by the PCU based on transparent criteria. Ineligible LGUs (or those not interested to&#13;
receive advances) will remain entitled to conduct their own procurement; however, payments to&#13;
contractors and suppliers would be made by the PCU based on proper supporting documentation.&#13;
78.    Retroactive Financing. IDA would make available retroactive financing of up to US$&#13;
1.0 million out of the Grant proceeds effective September 1, 2002 (to be finalized during&#13;
negotiations). Under the retroactive financing clause, payments made by the participating LGUs&#13;
and by the PCU out of its own resources before the date of the signing of the Grant Agreement&#13;
but after September 1, 2002 are eligible for financing under the proposed Grant. The funds&#13;
available under retroactive financing could be used for reimbursement of payments of eligible&#13;
expenditures incurred by participating LGUs and by the PCU, and which have been procured in&#13;
accordance with IDA procurement guidelines.&#13;
79.    Disbursement Arrangements. The proposed Grant of US$20.0 million equivalent&#13;
would be disbursed over a period of two years, starting January 1, 2003 and up to the closing date&#13;
of December 31, 2004. Table C below describes the allocation of the Grant proceeds according&#13;
to each expenditure category. Retroactive financing would be available for eligible expenditures&#13;
incurred after September 1, 2002, up to a maximum of US$1.0 million equivalent.&#13;
Table C: Allocation of Grant Proceeds&#13;
Expenditure Category          Amount in US $ million   Financing Percentage&#13;
1. Works                                 2.0                   100%&#13;
2. Goods                                 9.0                   100%&#13;
3. Services                              5.0                   100%"&#13;
4. Operating Costs(""                    4.0                   100%&#13;
Total Grant Costs                       20.00&#13;
(i) Consulting services financing percentage was set at 100% based on a letter from MOF dated&#13;
November 18, 2002 indicating that an income tax waiver would be applied for all contracts financed&#13;
under this Project.&#13;
(ii) Operating costs would include: municipal services operating costs such as fuel, solid waste&#13;
dumping fees, office supplies, equipment and goods, vehicle insurance, utility bills, rent, laboratory&#13;
tests, communication costs, travel costs, labor, etc.&#13;
80.    Use of Statements of Expenditures (SOEs). Disbursement from the Grant Special&#13;
Account would be fully documented for all contracts for works with values above US$200,000,&#13;
goods and consulting firm contracts with values above US$100,000, and individual consultants&#13;
contracts with values above US$50,000. Disbursement for all other expenditures would be made&#13;
against SOEs with supporting documentation retained at the PCU premises and made available&#13;
for IDA's review during supervision. SOEs would be subject to an annual audit and semi-annual&#13;
review by an independent auditor, as well as periodic review by the Financial Management&#13;
Analyst at the Country Office.&#13;
81.    Special Account. One SA will be opened by the MOF at a commercial bank acceptable&#13;
to IDA in order to facilitate disbursements against eligible expenditures under the Grant. The SA&#13;
will be operated by the PCU under terms satisfactory to IDA. IDA will, upon request, make an&#13;
authorized allocation of 10%  of the Grant.  This percentage will be reviewed once&#13;
implementation has commenced for a possible increase depending on the speed of disbursement.&#13;
82.    To further facilitate disbursement by LGUs and to mitigate potential delays in payment&#13;
due to closures or other mobility restrictions, LGUs would be eligible to open municipal accounts&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
27&#13;
for the exclusive purpose of managing funds advanced by the PCU. After informing the PCU and&#13;
verifying that the account setup complies with Bank guidelines, the PCU would then be in a&#13;
position to make a 30 day advance of an amount not to exceed 10% of the given LGU allocation.&#13;
LGUs will be required to disburse these funds within 30 days of their receipt. All supporting&#13;
documentation would be sent by the LGU to the PCU for review before further replenishment of&#13;
the municipal account could be made.&#13;
83.    The SA replenishment applications will be documented according to IDA guidelines,&#13;
including a bank statement of the SA and a reconciliation bank statement of the SA against IDA&#13;
records. Replenishment applications would be submitted regularly (preferably bimonthly, but not&#13;
less than monthly).&#13;
SECTION F. FINANCIAL AND ECONOMIC JUSTIFICATION.&#13;
84.    The proposed emergency Project is being prepared under emergency recovery assistance&#13;
procedures (OP 8.50). Time limitations and limited availability of economic data prevent more&#13;
detailed analysis, a recognized constraint in preparing such operations. However, the main&#13;
justification for the Project is that it will prevent the outright collapse of local governments, while&#13;
enabling them to sustain the provision of essential services to their communities. The increased&#13;
quality and coverage of services enabled through this operation is expected to improve the health&#13;
and living conditions of a vast majority of the Palestinian population. In addition, introduction of&#13;
an intergovernmental financial transfer system through the Municipal Fund will help to realign&#13;
and reinforce central-local government emergency response capacity in the short-term. It would&#13;
also establish a mechanism to more effectively gather and analyze key local government financial&#13;
data, enabling knowledge sharing and optimization of service delivery through identification of&#13;
the most cost effective methods of service provision. Thus, the Project is justified in terms of its&#13;
contribution to immediate as well as long-term improvements in living conditions of people and&#13;
efficiency and economic sustainability in the provision of municipal services.&#13;
SECTION G. ACTION PLAN.&#13;
85.    Other than the standard condition concerning the provision of a legal opinion by the PA,&#13;
there are no conditions of negotiations, board presentation and effectiveness for the proposed&#13;
Grant.&#13;
86.    The Palestinian Authority agreed that the following documents would be prepared by the&#13;
Palestinian Authority and submitted to IDA. The Project Implementation Plan (PIP) and Project&#13;
Operations Manual (POM) have already been prepared in solid draft form, and it was agreed that&#13;
they would be completed to the satisfaction of IDA by December 15, 2002. An Environmental&#13;
Management Plan (EMP) was submitted to IDA on November 14, 2002 and determined to be&#13;
acceptable. has been prepared in draft form and submitted to IDA; it would be completed to the&#13;
satisfaction of IDA by the conclusion of Negotiations. While no conditions of effectiveness have&#13;
been agreed, a dated covenant and agreements noted in the Minutes of Negotiations have been&#13;
included. Among the most important ones is a covenant requiring the establishment of the&#13;
Municipal Fund and the Fund Commission by January 31, 2004 in order to proceed with&#13;
implementation in the second year (Phase II) of the Project.&#13;
87.    Action Plan. The PCU will first focus on contracting four regionally-based technical&#13;
consultant firms to help the LGUs in preparing their programs, and to prescreen them to facilitate&#13;
approvals by the PCU. Two other parallel assignments would be contracted shortly after project&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
28&#13;
effectiveness, the first of which would be to launch the technical assistance support for the labor&#13;
intensive employment creation sub-component, and the second would be to contract firms to&#13;
support LGUs in preparing their budgets and financial statements to become eligible for Phase 11&#13;
financing. The PCU will also contract consultants or locally-based NGOs to facilitate community&#13;
participation through advocacy, public information dissemination, and implementation of&#13;
community feedback surveys. By June-July 2003, the Management Agent (responsible for the&#13;
design of the Municipal Fund and for the setup of the Municipal Fund and Fund Commission)&#13;
will also be selected. A detailed Action Plan is attached as Annex 7.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Annex 1&#13;
Page 1 of 3&#13;
TABLE A: PROJECT SUMMARY COST&#13;
US$ Million&#13;
Project Component                 Local    Foreign    Total&#13;
1. Emergency Program Assistance                   14.50     4.00     18.50&#13;
2. Municipal Fund Design, Management &amp; Monitoring  0.30      0.80      1.10&#13;
3. Technical Assistance &amp; Capacity Building        0.30      0.10      0.40&#13;
Total                                             15.10     4.90     20.00&#13;
TABLE B: FINANCING PLAN BY PROJECT COMPONENTS (US$ Million)&#13;
Total    TFGWB      Other        Central     Financing&#13;
Project Component              Cost      Grant     Donor      Government      Gap&#13;
Grants       Transfers&#13;
1. Emergency Program Assistance  68.00   18.50     37.20          3.00        9.30&#13;
2. Municipal Fund Design,      1.10       1.10      0.00          0.00        0.00&#13;
Management &amp; Monitoring&#13;
3. Technical Assistance &amp;      0.90      0.40       0.50          0.00        0.00&#13;
Capacity Building&#13;
Total                         70.00      20.00      37.70         3.00         9.30&#13;
TABLE C: ESTIMATED SCHEDULE OF DISBURSEMENT&#13;
US$ Million                2002         2003&#13;
Annual                     8            12&#13;
Cumulative Total           8           20.0&#13;
Percent Total          40%          100%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Annex 1&#13;
Page 2 of 3&#13;
Table D: Summary Project Cost Estimate&#13;
Estimated costs  IDA funding&#13;
Sub-componentsUSmilo&#13;
US$ million&#13;
1. Emergency Assistance Program&#13;
Non-wage Municipal Service Costs            18.50           14.50&#13;
Wages for Municipal Service Departments     13.00            0.00&#13;
Employment Generation Subprojects            4.00            3.00&#13;
Infrastructure/ Facilities Damage Repair    32.50            1.00&#13;
Sub-total: Emergency Assistance Program         68.00           18.50&#13;
2. Municipal Fund Design/Management&#13;
PCU Operating Expenses                       0.30            0.30&#13;
Management Agent Contract                    0.80            0.80&#13;
Sub-total: Municipal Fund Design/Management      1.10            1.10&#13;
3. Technical Assistance &amp; Capacity Building*&#13;
Consultant services                          0.40            0.20&#13;
LGU Capacity Building                        0.40            0.10&#13;
NGO Participation Support                    0.10            0.10&#13;
Sub-total: T.A. &amp; Capacity Building              0.90            0.40&#13;
GRAND TOTAL                                       70.00           20.00&#13;
* This component includes the budget for strengthening, inter alia, all activities related to environmental&#13;
management and social assessments, and procurement training.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Annex 1&#13;
Page 3 of 3&#13;
Schedule/Table: Timetable of Key Project Processing Events&#13;
Timetable:&#13;
Sequence                                Timing&#13;
Time taken to prepare and process the project  4 months&#13;
Identification and preparation mission  July 2002&#13;
Appraisal                               October 2002&#13;
Negotiations                            November 2002&#13;
Board Presentation                      December 2002&#13;
Planned Effectiveness                   January 2, 2003&#13;
Planned Closing Date                    June 30, 2005&#13;
Names of staff/consultants who worked on the project:&#13;
Name              Function&#13;
Majed El-Bayya    Task Team Leader&#13;
Stephen Karam     Co-Task Team Leader, Urban Economist&#13;
Jacques Bure      Consultant&#13;
Ibrahim Dajani    Operations Officer, Environmental Engineer&#13;
George Awwad      Operations Officer, Procurement&#13;
Ayman Abu-Haija   Senior Financial Management Specialist&#13;
Hisham Labadi     Consultant, Procurement&#13;
Ahmed Basti       Consultant, Municipal Fund Specialist&#13;
Hadi Abushakra    MNA Country Lawyer&#13;
Thao Le Nguyen    Disbursement Officer&#13;
Kanthan Shankar   Environmental Specialist&#13;
Arbi Ben-Achour   Senior Social Scientist&#13;
Tuyet Chuppe      Program Assistant&#13;
Karim Gigler      Program Assistant&#13;
Samira Hillis     Administrative Assistant&#13;
Huda Skaik        Administrative Assistant&#13;
Ad Hoc Advisory Committee:&#13;
Name             Function&#13;
Hedi Larbi      MNA Urban and Transport Sector Manager&#13;
Majed El-Bayya  EMSRP Task Team Leader&#13;
Nicholas Kraffl  WBG Country Program Coordinator&#13;
Aloysius Ordu    NNA Operations Quality Advisor&#13;
Fred Kranz      MNA Procurement Advisor Representative&#13;
Hadi Abushakra   WBG Country Lawyer&#13;
Alfred Nickesen  OPCS Representative&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Annex 2&#13;
Page 1 of 3&#13;
EMSRP&#13;
Responsibility Matrix&#13;
PSC&#13;
MOLG               /                              Tech&#13;
(PCU)    MOF      FC    LGU    Bank     Audit   Consult&#13;
ACTIVITIES                                           =        =      =      =       =_=_=&#13;
FINANCE, ACCOUNTING, MONITORING,&#13;
1.00   REPORTING&#13;
1.01   Open Project Special Account (SA)             N        E       N      _      N       N&#13;
1.02  Open Municipality Accounts                     N               S       E              N&#13;
Establish Accounting, Reporting &amp; Auditing&#13;
1.03   Procedures                                    E                R      E      R       N&#13;
Transfer Funds, max. 10% of LGU approved&#13;
1.04  allocation to municipality accounts            S               E      N               N&#13;
1.05   Appoint Project Auditor                        S       E       N      N      R        N        N&#13;
1.06   Appoint Project Technical Consultants         E                N      N      R&#13;
Request replenishment of/withdrawals from the&#13;
1.07   SA                                             S       E*      E             R        R&#13;
1.08   Transfer Funds from IDA to SA                 N        N       N      N       E       N&#13;
Fund Allocation and Project Selection&#13;
Establish Fund Allocation Criteria &amp;&#13;
1.09   Procedures for Phase II                        S       N       E      N      R        N        N&#13;
1.10   Establish Project Selection Criteria           S       N       E      N      R        N        N&#13;
Assign Fund Allocation to LGUs based on&#13;
1.11   population                                     S               E      N      N        N        N&#13;
Establish Local Project Preparation,&#13;
Implementation, Technical Monitoring &amp;&#13;
1.12   Reporting Procedures                           S               E      N      R        N        N&#13;
Request No objection from PCU on list of sub-&#13;
1.13   projects and method of procurement            R                N      E      N        N        N&#13;
Request No objection from IDA on list of sub&#13;
projects and method of procurement for those&#13;
1.14   sub-projects subject to Bank prior review     E                N             N&#13;
Issue No objection to PCU to proceed on LGUs&#13;
1.15   list of projects that subject to Bank prior review  N          N          _  E&#13;
Consult with local Workers Council and MOL&#13;
1.16   and prepare list of unemployed workers        N                       E&#13;
2.00    Sub Project ID Preparation &amp; Implementation&#13;
Consult with local community on their priority&#13;
2.01   needs through workshops etc.                  N                       E&#13;
2.02   Prepare an Emergency Program with brief       N                N      E&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Annex 2&#13;
Page 2 of 3&#13;
PSC&#13;
MOLG             P                               Tech&#13;
(PCU)    MOF     FC     LGU    Bank    Audit   Consult&#13;
=______ description                                                         =&#13;
2.03   Submit Emergency Program to PCU              N              N       E           _&#13;
2.04   Review LGU program for Implementation        R               A      N                        N&#13;
Prepare projects data sheets and brief appraisal&#13;
2.05   report                                       N                      S                        E&#13;
Detailed Selection and Implementation&#13;
Emergency Program Identification in&#13;
2.06   consultation with community                                         E&#13;
2.07   Preliminary Emergency Program Estimate                              E                        R&#13;
2.08   Preliminary Preparation, design and drawings                        E                        S&#13;
2.09   Review Designs and Drawings                                         E                        S&#13;
Ensure consistency with overall strategy,&#13;
2.10   guidelines and selection criteria            S                       S                       E&#13;
Undertake Technical, Economical and Social&#13;
2.11   Appraisal                                    N                      S                        E&#13;
2.12   Final check for sub projects documents proposal                     E                        S&#13;
2.13   Approval of projects selection               S               E      N              N         N&#13;
Prepare Standard bidding and contractual&#13;
2.14   documents                                    E                      N      R       N         S&#13;
Invite Bids/quotes through local&#13;
2.15   newspapers/invitations/Force Acc./Direct. Co.  N                    E              N         N&#13;
2.16   Evaluate Bids                                                       E                        S&#13;
2.17   Award Contracts and sign contract            N        N             E              N         S&#13;
2.18   Send copy of contract to PCU                 R                      E&#13;
Work/Goods delivery Authorization to&#13;
2.19   contractor/vender                            N                      E                        N&#13;
2.20   Daily Site Supervision                                              E&#13;
2.21   Overall Monitoring                           S               E                      S        S&#13;
Project Finance, Accounting, Monitoring&#13;
and Reporting                                                     _&#13;
2.22   Preparation of certificates for payment      N                       E                       S&#13;
2.23   Review of claims and payment Authorization                           E              S        N&#13;
Payments within 10 working days of receipt of&#13;
2.24   claim                                        N                      E                        N&#13;
send documentation to PCU within max. 30 days&#13;
2.25   from transfer of fund to municipality account                       E&#13;
2.26   Monitor payments with regards to time        E                       S                       E&#13;
2.27   Accounting                                   E                       S                       N&#13;
2.28   Monthly Reporting (Technical, Financial)     E       N               S     N                 S&#13;
3.00   Financial Monitoring Reporting and Auditing&#13;
3.01   Review LGUs Fund Allocation                  E       N              N               S        S&#13;
3.02   Review LGUs Procurement Procedure            E                      N               S        S&#13;
3.03   Prepare monthly LGUs Financial Reports       S                      E&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Annex 2&#13;
Page 3 of 3&#13;
PSC&#13;
MOLG              P                               Tech&#13;
(PCU)      MOF    FC    LGU    Bank    Audit    Consult&#13;
3.04   Prepare Quarterly program Financial Reports    E       N       R      S      R        S&#13;
3.05   Conduct Annual Program Audit                   R       R       R      S      R        E&#13;
Technical Monitoring, Reporting and Auditing&#13;
3.06   Review LGUs Program                            E                      N                        S&#13;
Review LGUs Technical Documentation,&#13;
3.07   Contractors Budgets and work programs         N                       E                        s&#13;
3.08    Review Employment Generation Estimates       N                       S               N        E&#13;
3.09   Review Technical Quality of work              N                       S                        E&#13;
Advise on techniques to increase labor content&#13;
3.10   in job creation projects                      S                       N                        E&#13;
Review Numbers and categories of workers&#13;
3.11   Employed.                                     N                       S               N        E&#13;
Where necessary recommend to managers to&#13;
improve implementation procedure, quality of&#13;
3.12   work and job creation                         N                       N                        E&#13;
Conduct Monthly Technical, environmental and&#13;
3.13   Social Audits                                  R                      S                        E&#13;
3.14   Prepare Detailed Monthly Report                R                       S      R                E&#13;
3.15   Prepared brief monthly Reports for WBG         E               R      S       R       S         S&#13;
Publish Monthly Summery Report in local&#13;
3.16   newspapers                                     E               R              R&#13;
3.17   Weekly site visits to sub projects/LGUs                               N                        E&#13;
Prepare a combine quarterly progress report for&#13;
3.18   WBG                                            E       N       R       S      R                 S&#13;
3.19   Spot site visits to sub projects/LGUs          E               S      N       E&#13;
R = Review/Clear; E = Execute; E* = Sign replenishment applications within 72 hrs; N = Notified; S =&#13;
Support; A = Approve.&#13;
PCU: Project Coordination Unit; MOF: Ministry of Finance;&#13;
PSC/FC: Project Steering Committee / Fund Commission; LGU: Local Govermnent Unit;&#13;
Audit: Financial Auditor; Tech Consult: Technical Consultant&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Annex 3&#13;
Page 1 of 2&#13;
EMSRP Organizational Chart&#13;
First Phase&#13;
Project Steering&#13;
Donor                   Committee&#13;
Consultation            MOLG (Chair),                   Adjunct Members&#13;
Forum                  MOPIC, MOF&#13;
PCU Project Manager&#13;
PCU        PCU&#13;
Gaza     West Bank&#13;
Auitors         -B ranch               Branch&#13;
MF Special Account&#13;
Technical&#13;
Consultants&#13;
(program pre-&#13;
screening and&#13;
zzz  zi LZ] [~~] LGU   technical&#13;
EE- LGU               _    ] LGU           _    I      L      GU _ LGU | LGU_support to&#13;
LGUs in West&#13;
Bank and&#13;
Advocacy, public information community feedbacks                           Gaza)&#13;
and cross-programming, (consultants/NGOs based)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Annex 3&#13;
Page 2 of 2&#13;
EMSRP Organizational Chart&#13;
Second Phase&#13;
Donor Consultation Forum                Fund Commission (FC)              . .&#13;
(DCF)                       MOLG (Chair), MOPIC, MOF                Adjunct Members&#13;
(to be determined)&#13;
contributing to the MF                * Provides overall policy             PA line ministries and&#13;
* Convenes regularly to discuss           guidance                          . agencies consulted on&#13;
program performance                   * Responsible for approving              as-needed basis&#13;
* Reviews Reports submitted by          allocations                           regarding relevant&#13;
FC                                                                               sector issues&#13;
MOLG PCU reports&#13;
Management Agent (MA)                    up on MF&#13;
* Supports MOLG PCU in administering MF&#13;
* Serves as FC agent in monitoring MFfinancial/&#13;
programmatic performance against guidelines&#13;
agreed in Phase I&#13;
* Prepares Quarterly Monitoring Report for FC      FC authorization&#13;
and DCF                                          decisionflows down&#13;
Municipal Fund (MF)&#13;
* Administered by MOLG PCU through branch offices                 Conical&#13;
in West Bank and in Gaza, including Special Account            Consultants&#13;
External Auditor        * Provides overall guidance to LGUs regarding                   4 regional field-&#13;
eligibility, process andproceduresfor assistance               based units in&#13;
* Conducts technical review ofsubmissions and                   WBG, providing&#13;
recommends decision to FC                                      pBGr pre-&#13;
* Establishes Municipal Finance Database with                    program pre-&#13;
support of AIA                                                screening, data&#13;
collection and&#13;
i                                management&#13;
Funds flow down                               Accountability flows up  advice/support to&#13;
LGUs&#13;
| G           G LGU           G |LGU   GU |I | LGUZ&#13;
* Responsible for preparing emergency program submissions on forms&#13;
provided by MF, assisted by Technical Consultants&#13;
* Responsible for holding community consultations, responding to community-&#13;
prioritized needs, and publicizing MF budget allocation&#13;
* Responsible for implementing subprojects and reporting on uses offunds&#13;
* Responsible for submittingfinancial statements and nextyear annual budget&#13;
to be eligible for MFfinancing&#13;
Advocacy, public information, community opinion surveys, and cross-&#13;
programming support provided by community-based NGOs in&#13;
cooperation with LGUs&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 4&#13;
EMRSP Project Transition Chart&#13;
Trlansitioinal IlemlIent          lPlhase I                      Phia:se 11&#13;
C;aleniidar Y'ar* 21003       C:lendiar Ye^ear 20014&#13;
Project Steering Committee         Fund Commission&#13;
The PSC has already been      The Fund Commission would be&#13;
established, including MOLG,  established to institutionalize&#13;
Governance Responsibility  MOF and MOPIC, and would     multi-sector coordination at the&#13;
serve on a temporary basis as the  central government level. It would&#13;
main policy level/decision-making  serve as the main interlocutor with&#13;
body and counterpart to donors.  donors regarding coordination of&#13;
assistance provided to local&#13;
governments.&#13;
Project Coordination Unit      Project Coordination Unit&#13;
Responsible for day-to-day    Retains responsibility for day-to-&#13;
Implementation       administration, management of the  day administration of the Project&#13;
Responsibility      Special Account, andproviding  but is assisted by the Management&#13;
support to LGUs through technical  Agent in managing the Municipal&#13;
units established at the regional  Fund and setting up the Municipal&#13;
level.                        Financial Data Management&#13;
System through capacity building&#13;
support.&#13;
Emergency Program Assistance         Municipal Fund&#13;
The EPA would provide financial  In parallel with Bank financing&#13;
support to LGUs in the firstyear,  channeled through the Special&#13;
Financing Instrument    along with other donor co-    Account, the MF would provide a&#13;
financing administered in parallel.  mechanism for mobilizing,&#13;
managing and reporting on other&#13;
donor assistance at the local level&#13;
through a common framework.&#13;
Design of Municipal Fund &amp;     Monitoring Municipal Fund&#13;
Fund Commission&#13;
Management Agent      Assists the Project Steering   Contracted by the Fund&#13;
Committee in designing the     Commission to monitor&#13;
Municipal Fund and in         performance of the Municipal&#13;
establishing the Fund Commission  Fund, ensuring transparency and&#13;
consistent with appropriate laws  accountability, and providing&#13;
and regulations                capacity building support to the&#13;
PCU&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ANNEX 5&#13;
EMSRP Process Flow Chart&#13;
Allocation                              ALLOCATION&#13;
based on ~ ~ ~    ~    ~   bse o&#13;
population                           p&#13;
\  ak financing  || Other Donor Financing &#13;
Employment      oService            Employment          Servn&#13;
Generation  J    Suppr          r   Generation  __      Suppr&#13;
\                           0Allocation&#13;
MUNICPbased on&#13;
\                 ~~~~~~population&#13;
Allocation per&#13;
region, depending&#13;
s tfl ron unemployment&#13;
t              (D   S      QO     O &#13;
|-&gt; l~~&gt; ;m | MUNICIPALITIES&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Annex 6&#13;
Page 1 of 5&#13;
Key Performance Indicators&#13;
Narrative Summary          Key Performance        Data Collection Strategy  Critical Assumptions and&#13;
Indicators                                            Risks&#13;
Sector-related WBG        Sector indicators:        Sector / country report:  (from Goal to Bank&#13;
Assistance Strategy Goal:                                                     Mission)&#13;
1. Encourage the          - Intergovernmental fiscal  - Bank supervision mission  - Continued commitment of&#13;
development of sound      transfer mechanism        reports, midterm review and  the PA, MOLG, MOF,&#13;
governance institutions at  established (Municipal  ICR; PCU Progress Reports; MOPIC and local&#13;
the central and sector levels.  Fund) to ensure greater  Management Agent     governments to reforming&#13;
equity, efficiency and    quarterly reports.        intergovernmental systems;&#13;
transparency in resource&#13;
allocation within the sub-                          - Failure of the new&#13;
national sector.                                   regulatory system to ensure&#13;
long term financial&#13;
2. Continue providing     - Donor Consultative Forum  - Midterm review by Dec.  sustainability of municipal&#13;
analytical and programmatic  established, linked to the  2003, once the first phase of  Service provision;&#13;
leadership to the collective  Municipal Fund to serve as  the project is completed&#13;
effort to cope with the   a programmatic framework  (end of first fiscal year);  - Favorable political climate&#13;
emergercy, while initiating  for mobilizing and     - ICR by the end of the   and continued commitment&#13;
multi-donor operations to  coordinating donor       second fiscal year.;      of donors to support the&#13;
support delivery of essential  assistance to local  - MOPIC quarterly donor   Palestinian people.&#13;
social services.          governments;              aid reports;&#13;
- Increased intergovern-  - Project database;&#13;
mental transfers and      - Users surveys.&#13;
increased donor aid&#13;
mobilized through the&#13;
Municipal Fund;&#13;
- Improved service&#13;
coverage.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Annex 6&#13;
Page 2 of 5&#13;
Project Development       (outcome / impact         (projects reports)        (from Objective to Goal)&#13;
Objective:                indicators)&#13;
1. Mitigating further     - Percentage of surveyed  - Report on public        - Level of violence does not&#13;
deterioration in the quality  people reporting satisfactory  awareness campaign and  escalate and mobility of&#13;
and coverage of Municipal  and highly satisfactory  social impact surveys;    staff and workers allow&#13;
services.                 improvements in service   - Report on environmental  implementation of the&#13;
delivery;                 improvement following     project;&#13;
- Percentage increase in  investments measured&#13;
coverage (number of people  through surveys;        - Non-domestic goods and&#13;
served) and services      - Report on surveys to    construction material are&#13;
delivered;                assess the impact on quality  able to enter Gaza and the&#13;
- Avg. increase in revenue  of service delivery;    West Bank;&#13;
collection for municipal  - PCU quarterly reports,&#13;
services;                 supervision missions and  - Gradual improvement in&#13;
- Improved health and     ICR;                      the economy to enable&#13;
environment conditions.   - Municipal revenue,      incremental increase in&#13;
expenditure, and service  payment for services.&#13;
delivery data compiled in&#13;
Project database.&#13;
2. Generating temporary   - Number of man-days of   - PCU quarterly reports   - Same as above&#13;
employment opportunities;  temporary direct and&#13;
indirect employment created&#13;
(it is expected that increased&#13;
use of domestic goods will&#13;
generate indirect&#13;
employment)&#13;
3. Introduce a mechanism to  - Number of local      - Bank supervision and    - Sufficient resources at the&#13;
link central and local    governments supported     Management Agent          government and donor level&#13;
government budgetary      through service support   quarterly reports;        to support municipalities&#13;
planning processes and    allocations;              -MOPIC quarterly report on  through the Municipal Fund&#13;
strengthen municipal cost  - Number of donors and   aid mobilization;         - PA commitment to adopt&#13;
management.               amount of cofinancing being  - Annual Statistics of the  sound governance&#13;
channeled through joint   Palestinian Central Bureau  arrangement for the setup&#13;
mechanism;                of Statistics             of the Municipal Fund and&#13;
- Amount of additional    - Report on representation  Fund Commission.&#13;
assistance provided to areas  of the LGUs at the Fund&#13;
most affected by          Commission&#13;
unemployment and&#13;
economic hardship through&#13;
unemployment generation&#13;
targeting mechanism;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Annex 6&#13;
Page 3 of 5&#13;
Outputs for each         Output indicators:        Project reports:         (from Outputs to&#13;
component:                                                                  Objective)&#13;
1. Emergency support to  Water supply:            - Sanitary reports;       - MF established and&#13;
improve municipal service  -Reduction in shortfalls  - User survey reports;  implementation progressing&#13;
coverage and quality     C%);                      - PCU / Management Agent  smoothly; violence does not&#13;
through contracting and  -New household            quarterly reports;       escalate; sub-projects will&#13;
labor-intensive employment  connections _% of total);  - Bank supervision mission  have positive impact on the&#13;
generating activities.   -Rehabilitation of existing  reports;              quality and coverage of&#13;
connections (-% of total);  - LGU progress reports;  infrastructure and quality of&#13;
-Amount of water supplied                         living in the West Bank and&#13;
by tankers to non-network                          Gaza.&#13;
communities                                        - Donor financing made&#13;
available on time and&#13;
Sanitation:                                        allocated to LGUs based on&#13;
-New household                                    transparent criteria and&#13;
connections _% of total);                          according to MF guidelines.&#13;
-Rehabilitations of existing&#13;
connections (-% of total);                         - Need to train adequately&#13;
LGU staff to run annual&#13;
Solid Waste:                                       budgeting exercise.&#13;
-Increased volume of solid&#13;
waste collection (tons);&#13;
- Increased number of&#13;
garbage collectors (-%);&#13;
-Reduced number of&#13;
uncontrolled dumpsites.&#13;
Electricity:&#13;
-Reduction of shortfalls&#13;
UK);&#13;
-Reduction of hazards&#13;
caused by the presence of&#13;
dangerous installations in&#13;
the public domain;&#13;
Temporary employment:&#13;
- Number of direct and&#13;
indirect man-days&#13;
generated;&#13;
- Increased labor content&#13;
over conventional physical&#13;
works project (amount);&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Annex 6&#13;
Page 4 of 5&#13;
2. Improved capacity of   - Duration of various stages  - PCU / Management Agent  -Participating LGUs take&#13;
LGUs to prepare municipal  of programming, appraisal,  quarterly reports;     their responsibilities&#13;
budgets and to program,   preparation, tendering,   - Municipality evaluation  seriously and are willing to&#13;
appraise, implement and   awarding, and             reports and progress report;  accept technical assistance;&#13;
manage sub-projects and   implementation of sub     - Bank supervision mission  - Coordination and&#13;
delivery of municipal     projects;                 reports and ICR.          assistance leveraged through&#13;
services                                                                      field-based technical&#13;
-Degree to which                                    consultants and regional&#13;
implementation is leveraged                        institutional mechanisms,&#13;
and coordinated through                             e.g. Joint Services Councils,&#13;
regional institutional                              Micro-regional planning&#13;
mechanisms, e.g., Joint                             units, etc.&#13;
Services Councils, Microl&#13;
Regional Planning Centers&#13;
etc;&#13;
- Rate of physical progress;&#13;
- Frequency and quality of&#13;
community consultation and&#13;
degree to which joint&#13;
programming exercises ares&#13;
implemented with local&#13;
NGOs;&#13;
- Degree to which O&amp;M&#13;
cost management is&#13;
introduced in LGU-planning&#13;
and implementation.&#13;
3. Improved efficiency,   - Municipal Fund          - Management Agent        -Management Agent&#13;
equity and transparency in  established with guidelines,  quarterly reports; Bank  engaged in a timely manner;&#13;
allocating resources to the  including mobilization of  supervision mission reports  MF design completed&#13;
sub-national sector.      donor co-financing;       and ICR                   swiftly; processes and&#13;
- Municipal Fund project                            guidelines involving&#13;
database established to   - Data collection by the  emergency program&#13;
improve targeting of the  PCU / MA and management   submissions clear and easy&#13;
areas affected by         of a database regarding   to follow.&#13;
unemployment and to       average cost for essential&#13;
improve donor coordination; municipal services.     - LGUs willing to cooperate&#13;
- Degree to which capacity                          and share experience.&#13;
weaknesses at local&#13;
govemment level identified&#13;
and targeted for&#13;
strengthening through&#13;
technical assistance;&#13;
- Effective cost management&#13;
achieved for essential&#13;
services delivery. MOLG&#13;
knowledge sharing based on&#13;
best practices.&#13;
-Increased percentage of                            _____________&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Annex 6&#13;
Page 5 of 5&#13;
budgets / annual financial&#13;
statements submitted by&#13;
LGUs to MOLG&#13;
Project Components/Sub-   Inputs: (budget for each  Project reports:          (from Components to&#13;
components:               component)                                          Outputs)&#13;
1. Emergency Program      - US$68 million           - PSRs;                   - Participating LGUs are&#13;
Assistance / Municipal Fund  (IDA: US$18.5 million of  - Midterm review;      able to plan, design,&#13;
which US$14.5 million for  - ICR                    procure, and implement sub&#13;
Budget Support to 260                               projects;&#13;
LGUs, US$3 million for                              - Goods and construction&#13;
Labor-intensive                                     material are available&#13;
employment creation, and                            locally, at reasonable cost&#13;
US$1 million for                                    and on a timely basis;&#13;
infrastructure/facilities                           - Workers and staff are able&#13;
damage repair.)                                     to travel to project site;&#13;
- Substantial donor co-&#13;
financing leveraged through&#13;
Municipal Fund framework;&#13;
2. Municipal Fund Design,  - US$1.1 million         - PSRs;                   - Hiring of management&#13;
Management &amp; Monitoring   (IDA: US$ 1.1 million)    - Midterm review;         agent on time and with&#13;
- ICR                     qualified experienced staff;&#13;
- Timely engagement of&#13;
Management Agent with&#13;
qualified, experienced staff;&#13;
3. Technical Assistance and  - US$0.9 million       - PSRs;                   - Auditor and technical&#13;
Capacity Building:        (IDA: US$0.40 million)    - Midterm review;         consultants are hired on&#13;
- ICR                     time.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Annex 7&#13;
Page 1 of 3&#13;
ACTION PLAN&#13;
Key Implementation Activity                    By Whom     By When    Indicator&#13;
1. Setup of the Steering committee             MOLG        Nov. 2002  Send to the Bank&#13;
2. Subsidiary Agreement between the PA and MOLG  PA        Dec. 2002  Send to the Bank&#13;
3. Legal Opinion                               MOLG        Dec. 2003  Send to the Bank&#13;
4. Project Launch Workshop                     Bank        Jan. 2003  Aide-memoire&#13;
5. Setup of the Special Account                MOF         Jan. 2003  Bank Disbursement&#13;
letter issued and first&#13;
replenishment in&#13;
place.&#13;
6. Setup of LGUs municipal accounts            LGUs        Jan. 2003  Aide-memoire&#13;
7. Development of the Municipal Fund and Fund&#13;
Commission&#13;
- shortlist and RFP for MA                  PCU         Jan. 2003  Sent to Bank for N-O&#13;
- proposals and evaluation                  PCU         Apr. 2003  Sent to Bank for N-O&#13;
- finalization of MA contract               PCU         Jun. 2003  Sent to Bank&#13;
- review of LGU capacity and legal framework  MA        Jul/Oct    MA report to PCU/&#13;
for MF and FC by MA                                     2003       PCU quarterly report&#13;
- draft arrangement for MF and FC by MA     MA          Dec. 2003  MA send proposal to&#13;
Steering committee.&#13;
Bank copied&#13;
- setup of MF and FC                        MA          Dec. 2003  Mid-term review&#13;
8. Development of technical assistance to the LGUs&#13;
- selection of local consulting firms to provide  PCU   Dec. 2002  Post review by Bank&#13;
assistance to the LGUs                                             in Jan. 2003&#13;
- deployment of local consulting firms      Firms /     Jan. 2003  Reviewed at project&#13;
PCU                    launch workshop&#13;
9. Measuring the impacts of the Project:&#13;
- Environmental survey                      Firm/PCU    Dec. 2003  Documentation ready&#13;
for midterm review.&#13;
A second series of&#13;
surveys will be&#13;
launched by the end&#13;
of the project (inputs&#13;
to ICR)&#13;
- Social survey                             Firm /PCU   Dec. 2003  Same as above&#13;
- Quality survey                            Firm/PCU    Dec.2003   Same as above&#13;
- User Survey                               Firm/PCU    Dec. 2003  Same as above&#13;
- Employment generation survey              Firm/PCU    Dec. 2003  Same as above&#13;
10. Dialogue with Donors, dialogue between central&#13;
and local governments and within LGUs community&#13;
- Setup a donor forum                       MOLG        Nov. 2002  Correspondence&#13;
copied to Bank&#13;
- Organize for LGUs general assembly        MOLG        Nov. 2003  Letter of invitation&#13;
sent to Bank&#13;
- organize cross-experience based on best   Firm/ PCU   Entire     Bank supervision&#13;
practice for service provision              / MA        duration   mission findings&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Annex 7&#13;
Page 2 of 3&#13;
Key Implementation Activity                   By Whom    By When    Indicator&#13;
of project&#13;
11. Dialogue with the local communities&#13;
- selection of local consultants/NGOs     PCU         Dec. 2002  Post review by the&#13;
Bank&#13;
- conduct periodic user survey            Firmn       Entire     PCU quarterly reports&#13;
project&#13;
duration&#13;
- organizing for communities feedbacks    Firm        Entire     PCU quarterly&#13;
project   reports.&#13;
duration&#13;
12. Implementation of the firstyear program(EPA&#13;
component)&#13;
- draft a form that can be used for listing each  MOLG  Nov. 2002  n-a&#13;
LGU proposals&#13;
- testing the form                        MOLG        Nov/Dec.   Updated form sent to&#13;
2002       Bank reflecting test&#13;
findings&#13;
- sending the form to LGUs and informing the  PCU     Dec. 2003  n-a&#13;
LGUs about their potential allocation for the year&#13;
- prescreening of LGUs proposals           Firms      Jan. 2003  n-a&#13;
- review of LGUs proposals and send to Steering  PCU  Jan-Feb.   n-a&#13;
Committee                                             2003&#13;
- approval of proposals and issuing letter  Steering  Jan-Feb    First approval for&#13;
informing LGUs about the approved list to be  Committee  and then  Steering Committee&#13;
financed during the year                              during     sent to the Bank.&#13;
2003       Bank supervision&#13;
missions findings.&#13;
- procurement and implementation of       LGUs        Entire     Bank supervision&#13;
works/goods/services by the LGUs                      project    missions&#13;
duration&#13;
- TA provided to the LGUs during           Firms      Entire     Bank supervision&#13;
implementation of their programs                      project    mission&#13;
duration&#13;
- monitoring LGUs activities              PCU         Entire     PCU quarterly&#13;
project   reports.&#13;
duration&#13;
- gathering information on unit cost for essential  PCU  Entire  PCU reports and&#13;
services provision and compute the data in a          project    MOPIC GIS database&#13;
database                                              duration   updated&#13;
- informing the donors on outcomes and    Steering    Sep./ Nov. Midterm review&#13;
preparing with them the financing of the second  Committee  2003&#13;
year program&#13;
- prepare a mid-term review report        PCU         Nov. 2003  Send to the Bank&#13;
13. Implementation of the second year program by&#13;
the Management Agent&#13;
- refine allocation mechanism for Service  MA         Nov. 2003  Midterm review&#13;
Support and Employment Generation&#13;
- refine form to be sent to LGUs for listing their  PCU  Nov. 2003  Draft sent to Bank&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Annex 7&#13;
Page 3 of 3&#13;
Key Implementation Activity                    By Whom    By When    Indicator&#13;
proposals&#13;
- testing the form                         PCU         Nov. 2003  n-a&#13;
- sending the form to LGUs and informing the  PCU      Dec. 2003  n-a&#13;
LGUs about their potential allocation for the year&#13;
- prescreening of LGUs proposals           Technical   Jan. 2004  n-a&#13;
Firms&#13;
- review of LGUs proposals and send to Fund  PCU       Jan-Feb    n-a&#13;
Commission                                             2004&#13;
- approval of proposals and issuing letter  FC         Jan-Feb    Sample sent to Bank&#13;
informing LGUs about the approved list to be           2004&#13;
financed during the year&#13;
- procurement and implementation of        LGUs        Entire     MA quarterly reports&#13;
works/goods/services by the LGUs                       project    and Bank supervision&#13;
duration   aide-memoire&#13;
- TA to the LGUs during implementation of their  Firms  Entire    Same as above&#13;
programs                                               project&#13;
duration&#13;
- monitoring LGUs activities               PCU/Firms   Entire     Same as above&#13;
project&#13;
duration&#13;
- collecting data regarding LGUs service   PCU         Entire     Same as above&#13;
provision to MOPIC to be entered in GIS                project&#13;
duration&#13;
- prepare a contribution to the Implementation  PCU    April      Send to the Bank.&#13;
Completion Report (ICR)                                2005&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Report No.: T       7569  GZ&#13;
Type:     TAN&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="2068492">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2002/11/2068492/west-bank-gaza-emergency-municipal-services-rehabilitation-project
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2002/11/2068492/west-bank-gaza-emergency-municipal-services-rehabilitation-project</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2002/11/2068492/west-bank-gaza-emergency-municipal-services-rehabilitation-project</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2002/12/14/000094946_02112704031632/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2002/12/14/000094946_02112704031632/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2002-12-14T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2002-11-22T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            West Bank and Gaza - Emergency Municipal
            Services Rehabilitation Project
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The Emergency Municipal Services
            Rehabilitation Project will help mitigate further
            deterioration in the quality, and coverage of municipal
            services by: a) providing budgetary support for non-wage
            municipal operating costs, associated with essential service
            delivery; b) creating temporary labor-intensive employment
            opportunities; and, c) introducing a mechanism to link
            central, and local government budgetary planning processes,
            to strengthen Palestinian emergency response capacity,
            enhance mobilization of donor assistance, and improve the
            efficiency, and equity of resource transfers to local
            governments. It is expected that funds be fully disbursed by
            December 31st, 2004.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            West Bank and Gaza - Emergency Municipal
            Services Rehabilitation Project
        </docna>
        <display_title>West Bank and Gaza - Emergency
            Municipal Services Rehabilitation Project</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/2002/11/2068492/west-bank-gaza-emergency-municipal-services-rehabilitation-project</listing_relative_url>
        <projn>GZ-Emergency Municipal Services
            Rehabilitation Project -- P078212</projn>
        <docty>Technical Annex</docty>
        <subtopic>Banks &amp; Banking Reform,Public Sector Economics,Health Economics &amp; Finance,Municipal Financial Management,National Governance</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Health, Nutrition and Population</teratopic>
        <count>West Bank and Gaza</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Middle East!$!80463</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000094946_02112704031632</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>Middle East and North Africa,Middle East and North Africa</admreg>
        <subsc>Sub-national government administration</subsc>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Health, Nutrition and Population</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Urban Development</sectr>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Emergency recovery loan; Municipal services;
            Grant agreements; Service delivery; Coverage; Budgetary
            support; Operating costs; Temporary employment; Labor
            intensity; Local government budgets; Budget process;
            Capacity building; Donor finance; Resources utilization
            accountability,assets,Authority,Bank
            supervision,banking system,banks,borrowing,budgetary
            expenditures,budgetary support,cash assistance,Central
            government,central transfers,centralization,civil
            service,civil service reforms,clinics,Community
            Development,community participation,Competitive
            Bidding,Constitution,councils,debt,decision-making,depreciation,Economic
            Assistance,Economic Growth,economic
            recovery,electricity,Electricity
            services,employment,Employment
            Generation,expenditure,financial accountability,Financial
            Information,financial management,financial
            support,FISCAL,Fiscal Crisis,fiscal deficit,FISCAL
            YEAR,government level,Government Reform,government
            revenue,health status,housing,income,Institutional
            Arrangements,institutional
            capacity,insurance,intergovernmental fiscal
            relations,intergovernmental transfers,internal controls,Key
            Performance Indicators,labor force,legislative
            power,liquidity,Local Government,local government
            expenditures,local government revenues,local government
            sector,local governments,Ministry of Finance,municipal
            debt,Municipal Infrastructure,municipal revenue,Municipal
            Services,municipalities,Nations,operating
            costs,pensions,political instability,private sector,public
            infrastructure,public
            services,Rehabilitation,representatives,revenue
            collection,roads,Service Delivery,social assessment,social
            safety,social safety nets,social services,solid waste
            collection,tax,tax administration,tax revenue,Technical
            Assistance,transaction
            costs,transparency,transport,Treasury,trust funds,urban areas,wages
        </keywd>
        <owner>FFPSI Group (MNSIF)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Middle East</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>T7569</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banks and Banking Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Solid Waste Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Solid Waste Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Market Research and Surveys for Public Contracts</ml:concept><ml:concept>Procurement Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>EMMP</ml:concept><ml:concept>EMP</ml:concept><ml:concept>Bank Supervision</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance &amp; Risk Mitigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pensions &amp; Retirement Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Assessment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wage Setting</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages, Compensation and Benefits</ml:concept><ml:concept>Local Finance Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Local Government Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Municipal Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Lines</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banks &amp; Banking Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fuels</ml:concept><ml:concept>Landfills</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Solid Waste</ml:concept><ml:concept>Procurement Planning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Local Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Management and Mitigation Plans</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Municipality</ml:concept><ml:concept>Bank Regulation and Supervision</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pensions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages</ml:concept><ml:concept>Local Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>