<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>﻿                                                            OFFICIAL                   Tr o&#13;
                                                        DOCUMENTS&#13;
The World Bank                                                       1 i STr'e6t              (202) 473-1000&#13;
INTERNATIONAL BANK FOR RECONSTRUCTION AND DEVELOPMENT              Washington, D.C. 20433     Cable Address: INTBAFRAD&#13;
INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPMENT ASSOCIATION                              U.S.A.                     Cable Address: INDEVAS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                              PJ      20   1q&#13;
&#13;
            Mr. Erik Brogger Rasmussen&#13;
            Head of Mission&#13;
            Royal Danish Embassy&#13;
            2, Arden Road&#13;
            Highlands&#13;
            Harare&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            Dear Mr. Rasmussen,&#13;
&#13;
              Administration Agreement between the Government of Denmark, represented by the&#13;
             Danish Ministry of Foreign Affairs and the International Bank for Reconstruction and&#13;
            Development and the International Development Association concerning the Multi-Donor&#13;
                        Trust Fundfor the Zimbabwe Reconstruction Fund (TFO72201)&#13;
&#13;
            1.     The International Bank for Reconstruction and Development and the International&#13;
            Development Association (collectively, the "Bank") acknowledge that the Government of&#13;
            Denmark represented by the Danish Ministry of Foreign Affairs (the "Donor", and together&#13;
            with the Bank, the "Parties" and each a "Party") has decided to provide the sum of five&#13;
            million seven hundred fifteen thousand five hundred Danish Krone (DKK 5,715,500) (the&#13;
            "Contribution") for the Multi-Donor Trust Fund for the Zimbabwe Reconstruction Fund&#13;
            ('TF072201") (the "Trust Fund") in accordance with the terms of this Administration&#13;
            Agreement. Other donors are also expected to contribute to the Trust Fund on the terms and&#13;
            conditions specified in the Annexes to this Administration Agreement.&#13;
&#13;
             2.      The Contribution shall be used to finance the activities set forth in the "Multi-Donor&#13;
             Trust Fund for the Zimbabwe Reconstruction Fund Description" attached hereto as Annex 1,&#13;
             and shall be administered by the Bank on behalf of the Donor in accordance with the terms&#13;
             of this Administration Agreement, including the "Standard Provisions" attached hereto as&#13;
             Annex 2 and "Governance" attached hereto as Annex 3.&#13;
&#13;
             3.     The Donor shall deposit the Contribution promptly following countersignature in the&#13;
             full amount and currency ("Contribution Currency") specified in Section I above into such&#13;
             bank account designated by the Bank upon submission of a payment request by the Bank&#13;
             (such deposit being an "Installment").&#13;
&#13;
             4.      When making any deposit, the Donor shall instruct its bank to include in its deposit&#13;
             details information (remittance advice) field of its SWIFT deposit message, information&#13;
             indicating: the amount deposited, that the deposit is made by the Donor for the TF072201&#13;
             (the Multi-Donor Trust Fund for the Zimbabwe Reconstruction Fund), and the date of the&#13;
             deposit (the "Deposit Instructions"). In addition, the Donor shall provide a copy of the&#13;
             Deposit Instructions to the Bank's Accounting Trust Funds Division by e-mail sent to&#13;
             tfremitadvice@worldbank.org or by fax sent to +1 (202) 614-1315.&#13;
&#13;
                                            RCA 248423. O WUI 64145 1 FAX (202) 477-6391&#13;
&amp;#12;                                            -2-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
5.      The Donor has stated its preference that the Contribution be used to finance&#13;
Window 4: Analytical and Policy Support with the understanding that the Bank will not be&#13;
in a position to ensure that the Contribution will be used for such purpose and that the Bank&#13;
will not have any obligation to the Donor if such preference cannot be achieved.&#13;
&#13;
6.     Except with respect to the Deposit Instructions, any notice, request or other&#13;
communication to be given or made under this Administration Agreement shall be in writing&#13;
and delivered by mail, fax or e-mail to the respective Party's address specified below or at&#13;
such other address as such Party notifies in writing to the other Party from time to time:&#13;
&#13;
       For the Bank (the "Bank Contact"):&#13;
&#13;
       Ms. Camille Nuamah&#13;
       Country Manager for Zimbabwe&#13;
       Zimbabwe Country Office&#13;
       The World Bank&#13;
       Harare, Zimbabwe&#13;
       Tel: 263 4 701233&#13;
       E-mail: clampart@worldbank.org&#13;
&#13;
       For the Donor (the "Donor Contact"):&#13;
&#13;
       Mr. Erik Brogger Rasmussen&#13;
       Head of Mission&#13;
       Royal Danish Embassy Office&#13;
       2, Arden Road, Highlands&#13;
       Harare, Zimbabwe&#13;
       Tel: +263 782 709 280&#13;
       E-mail: hreamb@um.dk&#13;
&#13;
7.     In the event any amounts are to be returned to the Donor under this Administration&#13;
Agreement, the Bank shall transfer such amounts to the Donor's applicable donor balance&#13;
account with the Bank, unless otherwise agreed with the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
8.     All annexes hereto constitute an integral part of this Administration Agreement,&#13;
whose terms taken together shall constitute the entire agreement and understanding between&#13;
the Donor and the Bank. Unless otherwise specified in an annex hereto, this Administration&#13;
Agreement may be amended only by written amendment between the Bank and the Donor;&#13;
provided, however, that any annexes to this Administration Agreement may be amended&#13;
only by written amendment of all donors contributing to the Trust Fund.&#13;
&#13;
9.      Each of the Parties represents, by confirming its agreement below, that it is&#13;
authorized to enter into this Administration Agreement and act in accordance with these&#13;
terms and conditions. The Parties are requested to sign and date this Administration&#13;
Agreement, and upon possession by the Bank of this fully signed Administration&#13;
Agreement, this Administration Agreement shall become effective as of the date of the last&#13;
signature.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                            -3-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
INTERNATIO              BANK FOR RECONSTRUCTION AND DEVELOPMENT&#13;
INTERNATIO              DEV LOPMENT ASSOCIATION&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
By: :                                             Date:   ?L   Nov   zo/I(&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Name:    6a Vv' I        AA        1   t1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Title:       01               Av&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
GOV                 OF DENMARK, REPRESENTED BY THE DANISH MINISTRY&#13;
OFF RE            A FAIRS&#13;
&#13;
By:                                               Date:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Name: ERIK RASWSSEN&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Title:   r          4     /   4&#13;
&amp;#12;                                             -4-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                     ANNEX 1&#13;
&#13;
      Multi-Donor Trust Fund for the Zimbabwe Reconstruction Fund - Description&#13;
&#13;
This Annex will be applicable to and form an integral part of all administration agreements&#13;
for the Trust Fund (collectively, the "Administration Agreements" and each an&#13;
"Administration Agreement") between the Bank and any entities that provide any funds to&#13;
the Trust Fund (collectively, the "Donors").&#13;
&#13;
1. Objectives&#13;
&#13;
The objective of the Trust Fund is to contribute to strengthen the Recipient's systems for&#13;
reconstruction and development with a focus on stabilization and reform, reconstruction,&#13;
development and poverty alleviation.&#13;
&#13;
The Zimbabwe Reconstruction Fund ("ZIMREF") would also foster donor coordination.&#13;
The objectives of the ZIMREF will be achieved through:&#13;
&#13;
      (i) Support to analytical work on key Zimbabwe development challenges.&#13;
      (ii) Support to investments in economic and social reconstruction.&#13;
      (iii)Support to national and local efforts to improve the business environment in the&#13;
           Recipient's territory, with a special focus on employment generation and poverty&#13;
           reduction strategies led by the private sector.&#13;
      (iv) Strengthening public sector management systems, institutional reforms and&#13;
           capacities for greater efficiency, relevance effectiveness, and accountability in&#13;
           service delivery; with a special emphasis on demand-side approaches.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
2. Activities&#13;
&#13;
The activities (which may be described as "components" of activities) to be financed by the&#13;
Trust Fund are:&#13;
&#13;
2.1      Bank-executed activities, for which the Bank has implementation responsibility:&#13;
&#13;
         *   Analytical and advisory work&#13;
         *   Impact evaluations&#13;
         *   Project supervision&#13;
&#13;
2.1.2     Recipient-executed activities, for which one or more Recipients (as defined in&#13;
Annex 2) have implementation responsibility:&#13;
&#13;
         *   Activities leading to private sector development; Activities leading to capacity&#13;
             development;&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                -5-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            *   Activities leading to improved livelihoods and resilience;&#13;
            *   Investments in economic and social reconstruction and development;&#13;
            *   Activities leading to improved transparency and accountability.&#13;
&#13;
3. Eligible Expenditures&#13;
&#13;
3.1         For Bank-executed activities, the Trust Fund funds may be used to finance:&#13;
&#13;
      (a)   Associated Overheads&#13;
      (b)   Consultant Fees Individuals and Firms - with Indirect costs&#13;
      (c)   Contractual Services&#13;
      (d)   Equipment and Office Premises Lease Cost&#13;
      (e)   Extended Term Consultants - With Indirect Costs&#13;
      (f)   Field Assignment Benefits&#13;
      (g)   Media, Workshop, Conference and Meeting&#13;
      (h)   Staff Costs - with Indirect Cost&#13;
      (i)   Temporary Support Staff Costs - With Indirect Costs&#13;
      (j)   Travel Expenses&#13;
&#13;
3.1.2       For Recipient-executed activities, the Trust Fund funds may be used to finance:&#13;
&#13;
      (a)   Civil works&#13;
      (b)   Consultants Services&#13;
      (c)   Non-consulting Services&#13;
      (d)   Goods&#13;
      (e)   Operating Costs&#13;
      (f)   Training&#13;
&#13;
4. Program Criteria&#13;
&#13;
4.1    Activities are to be financed in accordance with the program and Operational&#13;
Guidelines to be developed in consultation with the Recipient and the Donors.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                            -6-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                   ANNEX 2&#13;
&#13;
                                    Standard Provisions&#13;
&#13;
This Annex will be applicable to and form an integral part of all Administration Agreements&#13;
between the Bank and the respective Donors.&#13;
&#13;
1.     Administration of the Contributions&#13;
&#13;
1.1     The Bank will be responsible only for performing those functions specifically set&#13;
forth in this Administration Agreement and will not be subject to any other duties or&#13;
responsibilities to the Donors, including, without limitation, any duties or obligations that&#13;
might otherwise apply to a fiduciary or trustee under general principles of trust or fiduciary&#13;
law. Nothing in this Administration Agreement will be considered a waiver of any&#13;
privileges or immunities of the Bank under its Articles of Agreement or any applicable law,&#13;
all of which are expressly reserved.&#13;
&#13;
1.2      Each Donor's Contribution (collectively, the "Contributions") will be administered&#13;
in accordance with the Bank's applicable policies and procedures, as the same may be&#13;
amended from time to time, including its procurement, financial management, disbursement&#13;
and safeguard policies, its framework to prevent and combat fraud and corruption and its&#13;
screening procedures to prevent the use of Bank resources to finance terrorist activity, in&#13;
line with the Bank's obligations to give effect to the relevant decisions of the Security&#13;
Council taken under Chapter VII of the of Charter of the United Nations. The Donors&#13;
acknowledge that this provision does not create any obligations of the Bank under the anti-&#13;
terrorist financing and asset control laws, regulations, rules and executive orders of an&#13;
individual member country that may apply to a Donor.&#13;
&#13;
2.     Management of the Contributions&#13;
&#13;
2.1    The funds deposited in the Trust Fund will be accounted for as a single trust fund&#13;
and will be kept separate and apart from the funds of the Bank. The funds deposited in the&#13;
Trust Fund may be commingled with other trust fund assets maintained by the Bank. The&#13;
Bank, in its capacity as trustee, has legal title to the funds deposited in the Trust Fund.&#13;
&#13;
2.2     The currency in which the funds in the Trust Fund will be held is United States&#13;
Dollars (the "Holding Currency").&#13;
&#13;
2.3     Donors agree to deposit their Contributions in the Contribution Currency stated in&#13;
their respective Administration Agreements.       In the case of deposits received in a&#13;
Contribution Currency other than the Holding Currency, promptly upon the receipt of such&#13;
amounts and the accompanying Deposit Instructions, the Bank will convert such amounts&#13;
into the Holding Currency at the exchange rate obtained by the Bank on the date of the&#13;
conversion. Where deposits prove to be insufficient to complete activities as a result of&#13;
exchange rate fluctuations, neither the Bank nor the Donor will bear any responsibility for&#13;
providing any additional financing.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                           -7-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
2.4    The funds deposited in the Trust Fund may be freely exchanged by the Bank into&#13;
other currencies as may facilitate their disbursement at the exchange rate obtained by the&#13;
Bank on the date of the conversion.&#13;
&#13;
2.5     The Bank will invest and reinvest the funds deposited in the Trust Fund pending&#13;
their disbursement in accordance with the Bank's applicable policies and procedures for the&#13;
investment of trust funds administered by the Bank. The Bank will credit all income from&#13;
such investment to the Trust Fund to be used for the same purposes as the Contributions.&#13;
&#13;
3.     Trust Fund Fees and Costs&#13;
&#13;
3.1     The Bank will deduct and retain for its own account, as a deduction from each&#13;
Installment, an amount equal to two percent (2%) per Installment as an administrative fee&#13;
for the Trust Fund.&#13;
&#13;
3.2     In addition, costs incurred by the Bank for other expenses, such as for program&#13;
management and Trust Fund administration, that are: (i) not covered by the percentage&#13;
deduction specified above as an administrative fee; and (ii) not included under Annex 1 of&#13;
the Administration Agreements in accordance with the Bank's applicable policies and&#13;
procedures will be charged to the Trust Fund on an actual basis up to a maximum of ten&#13;
percent (10%) of the total Contributions under all Administration Agreements.&#13;
&#13;
3.2 3 Each Donor acknowledges and agrees that the percentage deductions for fees in this&#13;
Trust Fund Fees and Costs section are estimated on the basis of anticipated Contributions.&#13;
If actual Contributions significantly differ from what was originally anticipated at the time&#13;
of signature of the first Administration Agreement, or if other circumstances affecting Trust&#13;
Fund fees or costs change, the Bank reserves the right to request a change to the terms of&#13;
this Trust Fund Fees and Costs section, which would be effectuated by amendments made to&#13;
the Administration Agreements of all Donors and which would thereafter be applicable to&#13;
all new Contributions that are provided either as amendments to supplement existing&#13;
Administration Agreements or from new Donors under new Administration Agreements.&#13;
&#13;
4.     Accounting and Financial Reporting&#13;
&#13;
4.1     The Bank will maintain separate records and ledger accounts in respect of the funds&#13;
deposited in the Trust Fund and disbursements made therefrom.&#13;
&#13;
4.2     The Bank will furnish to the Donors current financial information relating to&#13;
receipts, disbursements and fund balance in the Holding Currency with respect to the&#13;
Contributions via the World Bank's Trust Funds Donor Center secure website. Within six&#13;
(6) months after all commitments and liabilities under the Trust Fund have been satisfied&#13;
and the Trust Fund has been closed, the final financial information relating to receipts,&#13;
disbursements and fund balance in the Holding Currency with respect to the Contributions&#13;
will be made available to the Donors via the World Bank's Trust Funds Donor Center secure&#13;
website.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                            -8-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
4.3     The Bank will provide to the Donors via the World Bank's Trust Fund Donor Center&#13;
secure website,  within six (6) months following the end of each Bank fiscal year, an annual&#13;
single audit report, comprising: (i) a management assertion together with an attestation from&#13;
the Bank's external auditors concerning the adequacy of internal control over cash-based&#13;
financial reporting for all cash-based trust funds as a whole; and (ii) a combined financial&#13;
statement for all cash-based trust funds together with the Bank's external auditor's opinion&#13;
thereon. The cost of the single audit will be borne by the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
4.4     If a Donor wishes to request, on an exceptional basis, a financial statement audit by&#13;
the Bank's   external auditors of the Trust Fund, the Donor and the Bank will first consult as&#13;
to whether such an external audit is necessary. The Bank and the Donor will agree on the&#13;
appropriate scope and terms of reference of such audit. Following agreement on the scope&#13;
and terms of reference, the Bank will arrange for such external audit. The costs of any such&#13;
audit, including the internal costs of the Bank with respect to such audit, will be borne by&#13;
the requesting Donor.&#13;
&#13;
4.5     The Bank will make available to the Donors copies of all financial statements and&#13;
auditors' reports received by the Bank from Recipients pursuant to any Grant Agreements&#13;
(as defined below) in accordance with the Bank's Access to Information Policy.&#13;
&#13;
5.     Progress Reporting&#13;
&#13;
5.1     The Bank will provide the Donors with annual reports on the progress of activities&#13;
financed by the Contributions. Within six (6) months of the End Disbursement Date (as&#13;
defined below), the Bank will furnish to the Donors a final report on the activities financed&#13;
by the Trust Fund.&#13;
&#13;
5.2     Any Donor may review or evaluate activities financed by the Trust Fund at any time&#13;
up to six (6) months following the End Disbursement Date. The Donor and the Bank will&#13;
agree on the scope and conduct of such review or evaluation, and the Bank will provide all&#13;
relevant information within the limits of the Bank's applicable policies and procedures. All&#13;
associated costs, including any costs incurred by the Bank, will be borne by the Donor. It is&#13;
understood that any such review or evaluation will not constitute a financial, compliance or&#13;
other audit of the Trust Fund.&#13;
&#13;
6.      Disbursement; Cancellation; Refund&#13;
&#13;
6.1     It is expected that the funds deposited in the Trust Fund will be fully disbursed by&#13;
the Bank by December 31, 2019 (the "End Disbursement Date"). The Bank will only&#13;
disburse funds deposited in the Trust Fund for the purposes of this Administration&#13;
Agreement (other than returns to Donors) after such date to the extent such date is changed&#13;
in accordance with amendments made to the Administration Agreements of all the Donors.&#13;
Following the End Disbursement Date, the Bank will return any remaining balance of the&#13;
Trust Fund to each Donor in the Holding Currency in the manner specified in its respective&#13;
Administration Agreement on a pro rata basis with regard to the total funds deposited in the&#13;
Trust Fund by such Donor relative to the total funds deposited in the Trust Fund by all&#13;
Donors, all calculated as Holding Currency amounts.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                            -9-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
6.2     Any Donor may cancel all or part of such Donor's pro rata share, and the Bank may&#13;
cancel all or any Donors' pro rata shares, upon three (3) months' prior written notice, of any&#13;
Contributions (paid and not yet paid) that are not committed pursuant to any agreements&#13;
entered into between the Bank and any consultants and/or other third parties for the&#13;
purposes of this Administration Agreement, including any Grant Agreements, prior to the&#13;
receipt of such notice. In the event of a cancellation, the Bank will return to the relevant&#13;
Donor or Donors in the Holding Currency in the manner specified by each such Donor in its&#13;
respective Administration Agreement the pro rata share(s) of any such uncommitted balance&#13;
of the Trust Fund, in accordance with any additional terms that may be agreed between the&#13;
Bank and each such Donor.&#13;
&#13;
7.     Disclosure; Dispute Resolution&#13;
&#13;
7.1     The Bank will disclose the Administration Agreements and related information on&#13;
this Trust Fund in accordance with the Bank's Policy on Access to Information. By entering&#13;
into Administration Agreements, the Donors consent to such disclosure of their respective&#13;
Administration Agreements and such related information.&#13;
&#13;
7.2    The Donors and the Bank will use their best efforts to amicably settle any dispute,&#13;
controversy, or claim arising out of or relating to the Administration Agreements.&#13;
&#13;
8.      Grants to Recipients&#13;
&#13;
8.1     In accordance with the governance structure provided in Annex III of this&#13;
Administration Agreement, the Bank will, as administrator of the Trust Fund on behalf of&#13;
the Donors, enter into one or more grant agreements (the "Grant Agreements") with&#13;
recipients (the "Recipients") consistent with the purposes of this Administration Agreement&#13;
and on the terms and conditions set forth in the Grant Agreements. Grant Agreements may&#13;
be entered into up to the maximum amount of the Contributions that all Donors have agreed&#13;
to make available under the Administration Agreements between the Bank and the Donors.&#13;
&#13;
8.2    The Bank will be responsible for the supervision of the activities financed under any&#13;
Grant Agreements. Subject to the consent of any relevant Recipients, representatives of the&#13;
Donors may be invited by the Bank to participate in Bank supervision missions related to&#13;
the Trust Fund.&#13;
&#13;
8.3     The Bank will promptly inform the Donors of any significant modification to the&#13;
terms of any Grant Agreements and of any contractual remedies that are exercised by the&#13;
Bank under any Grant Agreements. To the extent practicable, the Bank will afford the&#13;
Donors the opportunity to exchange views before effecting any such modification or&#13;
exercising any such remedy.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                           -10-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                   ANNEX 3&#13;
&#13;
                                        Governance&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
This Annex will be applicable to and form an integral part of all Administration Agreements&#13;
between the Bank and the respective Donors.&#13;
&#13;
A two-tier governance structure is proposed for the Zimbabwe Reconstruction Fund: (a) a&#13;
policy oversight committee responsible for policy oversight, resource mobilization, and&#13;
project/grant approvals; and (b) technical working groups responsible for technical and&#13;
eligibility screening of project/grants. The two structures will be supported by a secretariat&#13;
based in Harare and project support teams. The effectiveness of the governance structure&#13;
would be assessed after 6-12 months of Trust Fund operation. In its role as ZIMREF&#13;
administrator, the Bank would be responsible for, among others: overall management of the&#13;
Trust Fund; technical oversight and quality control for Trust Fund funded projects in&#13;
accordance with Bank policies and procedures; and establishment and management of the&#13;
secretariat.&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="21431507">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2014/11/21431507/official-documents--administration-agreement-danish-ministry-foreign-affairs-contribution-tf072201
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2014/11/21431507/official-documents--administration-agreement-danish-ministry-foreign-affairs-contribution-tf072201</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2014/11/21431507/official-documents--administration-agreement-danish-ministry-foreign-affairs-contribution-tf072201</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2014-12-08T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2014-12-08T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <docm_id>090224b0828f0866</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b0828f0866</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/AFR/2014/12/08/090224b0828f0866/1_0/Rendered/INDEX/Official0Docum0ribution0to0TF072201.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/AFR/2014/12/08/090224b0828f0866/1_0/Rendered/PDF/Official0Docum0ribution0to0TF072201.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2014-12-08T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2014-11-27T09:12:23Z</docdt>
        <docna>
            Official Documents- Administration Agreement
            with the Danish Ministry of Foreign Affairs for Contribution
            to TF072201
        </docna>
        <display_title>Official Documents-
            Administration Agreement with the Danish Ministry of Foreign
            Affairs for Contribution to TF072201</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/2014/11/21431507/official-documents--administration-agreement-danish-ministry-foreign-affairs-contribution-tf072201</listing_relative_url>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <docty>Trust Fund Administrative Agreement</docty>
        <count>Zimbabwe</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Kolovou,Zoe</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>HQBOCS</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <lang>English</lang>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Arts and Culture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutritional supplements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Vitamins</ml:concept><ml:concept>Impact Evaluations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Randomized Control Trials</ml:concept><ml:concept>Organisational Structures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Organizational Assessments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>Freedom of Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>Bank Supervision</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Leasing law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Business Regulation for Enterprise Creation and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legal Regulation and Business Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Administrative and Civil Service Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Management and Employment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Remittances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Migration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Contract Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Arrangements in Public Procurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Capacity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legal Regulatory Framework</ml:concept><ml:concept>State-Society Relations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Checks on Executive Power</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen User Satisfaction Survey</ml:concept><ml:concept>Independent Commissions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ombudsmen</ml:concept><ml:concept>Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Parliament</ml:concept><ml:concept>Procurement Complaints Review Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supreme Audit Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enforcement of Judgements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Informal Dispute Resolution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Business Environments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Media</ml:concept><ml:concept>Impact Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supplements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Impact Assessment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance Structures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Right to Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>External Audit</ml:concept><ml:concept>Bank Regulation and Supervision</ml:concept><ml:concept>Leasing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Business Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Movement of Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Accountability Mechanisms</ml:concept><ml:concept>Dispute Resolution</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Africa</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Zimbabwe</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>