<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>﻿THE WORLD BANK GROUP STAFF ASSOCIATION&#13;
ORAL HISTORY PROGRAM&#13;
Transcript of interview with&#13;
BENGT SANDBERG&#13;
February 3, 1988&#13;
Washington, D.C.&#13;
Interview by: Charles Ziegler&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿1&#13;
[Begin Tape 1, Side A]&#13;
ZIEGLER: Today is February 3, 1988. My name is Charles Ziegler of the World Bank&#13;
Oral History Program, and I have with me here at the Headquarters of the World Bank&#13;
Mr. Bengt Sandberg, who, among other things, was a founding member of the Staff&#13;
Association of the World Bank. We are doing this interview in the context of the Staff&#13;
Association Oral History Project.&#13;
Mr. Sandberg, if you could cast your mind back to, I suppose it was 1971, what were the&#13;
factors which impelled the staff to create the Staff Association in the first place?&#13;
SANDBERG: That's a long time ago. And of course my memory is hazy. I also got into&#13;
the Staff Association work rather by happenstance, and I guess well come to that in a&#13;
minute. I joined the Bank the first time in 1961, 10 years earlier, when the Bank was very&#13;
small. I left the Bank in 1964. It was a very patriarchal organization. When I first joined&#13;
the Bank, for example, the Bank staff did not discuss salary. Salaries were individual&#13;
salaries. They were individually negotiated. And so nobody really knew what anybody&#13;
else was making. There were no grades. There was nothing of that kind.&#13;
I think by 1971 the Bank had grown. There were staff who had joined from many parts of&#13;
the world. And there was a growing resentment, if you will, of the patriarchal system run&#13;
by the Bank. By that time salaries were very good in the Bank. The benefits were good.&#13;
But the whole atmosphere was one of where the management gave this to the staff. And&#13;
staff really had no input and there was no way, or there was no mechanism under which&#13;
the management could or would consult with staff on, for example, how they wanted the&#13;
medical plan structured, how they wanted the pension system set up. There was no way&#13;
for the staff to be represented on pension committees or in anything that had to do with&#13;
the management.&#13;
Now, the Bank was very good. Everybody knew that if you were in trouble on a mission&#13;
or if your family had trouble, the Bank would always make sure that you were taken care&#13;
of, totally outside all the personnel rules, all of those things. The Bank was a very sort of,&#13;
very patriarchal organization.&#13;
My own recollection is that there had also been some questions raised, possibly at the&#13;
Board, possibly in some other connection, where management was asked why there was&#13;
no staff association. In any case, somewhere in the last half of 1970 or thereabouts there&#13;
was a group of staff members in the Bank who began talking about the need for a staff&#13;
association.&#13;
ZIEGLER: But not in the context of some mass discontent or ...&#13;
SANDBERG: No, there was just this general malaise. Ill come later to a very typical&#13;
example, one that really sort of blew the lid on this. But anyway, they had been talking&#13;
about this. And I have in the back of my mind some recollection of hearing that the&#13;
Bengt Sandberg&#13;
February 3, 1988 - Final Edited&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿2&#13;
management was actually considering establishing a staff association. And this rumor, or&#13;
whatever it was, caused these six people--I think it was six of them--to approach the&#13;
management and say something to the effect that for management to establish a staff&#13;
association would be disastrous. Let us try. Because we believe that this should be done.&#13;
Now, the one who can tell you exactly what went on, the one I know who was a member&#13;
of this group was Jim [James] Chaffey. And he would be able to tell you exactly why&#13;
they approached management. I was not involved in this at all. Although one of the&#13;
leaders this movement was Mr. [Mats] Hultin, who is a countryman of mine. But I guess&#13;
we'd spoken about this. I had just come back to the Bank; I was a new division chief. I&#13;
was not involved. I was trying to settle into the Bank in 1970.&#13;
Then what happened was I came back from a mission and found there was a lot of uproar&#13;
in the department because there was all this talk about establishing a staff association.&#13;
How it happened I dont know, but I found myself having been elected a Delegate to the&#13;
Delegate Assembly.&#13;
ZIEGLER: You werent there to defend yourself!&#13;
SANDBERG: No. I can't remember if they asked me if I wanted to stand and I said yes&#13;
when I came back or whether it was a fait accompli when I came back. In any case, I&#13;
found myself propelled into the Constituent Assembly from what was then called the East&#13;
Asia and the Pacific Area Department. This was before the 1972 reorganization.&#13;
And then I guess, again for reasons which I dont know, I didnt stand for election. But a&#13;
group of the members of the Delegate Assembly decided that we needed to have some&#13;
kind of executive during the transition period when the Constitution was being researched&#13;
and written. And so Jim Chaffey was elected Chairman of the Executive Committee. And&#13;
he sort of went around and asked who might want to serve. And he asked me if I wanted&#13;
to serve on that. So I did that.&#13;
ZIEGLER: This was in the pre-Constitution period?&#13;
SANDBERG: This was what we called the Constituent Assembly which I guess was in&#13;
office from early 71 until the votes were counted on the establishment which must have&#13;
been somewhere in the winter of 1972.&#13;
Now, again I do not remember when it was. But I think it was in the spring of 1971 when&#13;
the management announced a major package of improved benefits without consultation&#13;
with anyone. I think it must have been while we were in the Constituent Assembly. I&#13;
remember it was several pages of improvements. But I think it was 1971. It contained a&#13;
number of significant improvements, and it really was a very good package. But it caused&#13;
an uproar in the Bank among staff. And the reason for this was that there was one benefit&#13;
that was taken away. That was the right after a certain period to travel by ship on home&#13;
leave, and that this was taken away without consultation just caused havoc.&#13;
Bengt Sandberg&#13;
February 3, 1988 - Final Edited&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿3&#13;
Now, as it was explained when this was then discussed, the reason it was done was&#13;
because after a certain point there werent going to be any ships. Now, you know they&#13;
started all the shipping again later on. But at that point the lines were going to stop all&#13;
passenger traffic across the Atlantic.&#13;
So it just showed the insensitivity of the management to the staff. If they had explained it&#13;
there probably would have been no uproar. Again, what it shows is that if they had had&#13;
somebody to consult with they could have avoided this flap, which I think is one of the&#13;
reasons why there was this overwhelming support for the staff association. That incident&#13;
focused attention on what was going on. So after the work on the Constituent Assembly&#13;
had been completed, you probably know that the agreement with the management was&#13;
and this is what we wanted--that the Staff Association would only be established if it had&#13;
the support of at least 50 percent of the staff. And this was interpreted to me that what we&#13;
needed was a 50 percent positive vote by all staff members. Not 50 percent of the ballots&#13;
cast, but 50 percent of the vote had to be for the Staff Association.&#13;
So in early 1972 we mounted a major effort in the Provisional Executive Committee to&#13;
get the vote out. We were given the opportunity to send cables to all people who were on&#13;
mission, to all resident missions. I still remember sitting--I cant remember if it was in the&#13;
Board Room, but upstairs somewhere--counting the ballots. And we were very nervous.&#13;
We really were not sure that we could get 50 percent of the Bank staff actually voting for&#13;
the Staff Association. As I remember now it was just totally overwhelming as we were&#13;
going through constituency after constituency, and counting the votes and seeing 100&#13;
percent participation, 90 percent. It was just totally fantastic. You had people on mission&#13;
who had cabled in. You had resident missions who sent long cables, you know, listing 20&#13;
people who were voting. I remember that evening after we'd counted. It was just&#13;
fantastic.&#13;
So there was this need among the staff to find a way to communicate the Bank staff&#13;
views and feelings to the management without going through the normal management&#13;
structure.&#13;
ZIEGLER: Would you say that, basically, the attitude of management towards the&#13;
creation of a staff association was cooperative?&#13;
SANDBERG: Oh, absolutely.&#13;
ZIEGLER: And responsive.&#13;
SANDBERG: Oh, absolutely. Absolutely.&#13;
ZIEGLER: Including Mr. [Robert S.] McNamara?&#13;
SANDBERG: Oh, absolutely. In fact, my feeling is that the management felt a lack of. .&#13;
. As I said, my recollection is that they were actually talking about establishing one&#13;
themselves, which would have been in character for McNamara. He sees a gap. He sees&#13;
Bengt Sandberg&#13;
February 3, 1988 - Final Edited&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿4&#13;
something that needs to be done and he does it. But that would never have worked,&#13;
because it would never have had any credibility.&#13;
ZIEGLER: Was there any significant opposition from the staff? I know even today any&#13;
hint of, quote, "unionism" would alienate a very large proportion of staff. So in&#13;
formulating the Staff Association and in your campaign for its establishment, did you&#13;
encounter any significant opposition from among staff? Or was it just largely isolated to&#13;
few people?&#13;
SANDBERG: At the time, I think there were two issues that we felt could kill the whole&#13;
idea. One was the question of dues. A lot of people felt that if we were going to charge&#13;
dues, then forget it. People would not be prepared to pay, because they didnt feel that&#13;
strongly. But this was the feeling. And, again, dues had something to do with a union.&#13;
You have to remember that in the early 1970s the Bank staff still contained large&#13;
numbers of people who'd come out of, say, the British colonial service, who had been&#13;
civil servants in other countries. And many, many people who had had management&#13;
positions. The technical staff in the Bank in those days to a very large extent were&#13;
recruited from among people who had been the general managers of power enterprises&#13;
and this sort of thing. And the judgment was that there was a very strong anti-union bias.&#13;
I remember one friend of mine, a Brit, who was in fact Fabian and a Labour Party man.&#13;
But you mention the question of belonging to a union to him. He would say, "No, no, no.&#13;
Absolutely not. That's fine for the workers and the common man and they should have&#13;
their unions. But, you know, I'm a professional, and I couldn't possibly belong to a&#13;
union."&#13;
So I think this was one of the issues. And it was very clear the way the Staff&#13;
Association was originally established that it was . . . In fact, I think we even used to call&#13;
it a channel of communication rather than a union. So the idea was to have a mechanism&#13;
for collecting and funneling in an authoritative way the views of the Bank staff. And that&#13;
then became reflected in the whole structure of the Staff Association, where the key&#13;
element in the structure is the Delegate Assembly. Because they, the Delegates, are&#13;
supposed to reflect the views of their constituents. And they are supposed to control the&#13;
executive which is then supposed to be the arm of the Assembly, and not the other way.&#13;
So it was built with an Executive Committee that derived its power from the constituents&#13;
represented in the Assembly. It was an extremely democratic type of institution that we&#13;
built.&#13;
ZIEGLER: That differs from the way the International Monetary Fund's Staff&#13;
Association Committee works.&#13;
SANDBERG: I don't really know the Fund's Association very well. But the alternative,&#13;
of course, is to have a strong executive with a direct election of president and so on and&#13;
so forth. We did not follow that line.&#13;
Bengt Sandberg&#13;
February 3, 1988 - Final Edited&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿5&#13;
ZIEGLER: Very deliberately?&#13;
SANDBERG: Very deliberately. Because I think that the view was that we have no&#13;
negotiating power; we have power of persuasion in our dealings with the management.&#13;
We are only as strong as the management perceives us to be. And only if the Executive&#13;
Committee is seen as representing the views of the overwhelming majority of Bank staff&#13;
will they carry credibility. And that was the view that I think prevailed at the time.&#13;
Now you can argue whether this is still valid 15 years later. Maybe even now we need a&#13;
union. I dont know. But I think at the time this was correct. And given the overwhelming&#13;
majority that we got for the Constitution we probably could have had a more centralized&#13;
Staff Association. But chances are if we had we might also have lost a good portion of&#13;
the Bank staff. And you have to remember in the early days after the Staff Association&#13;
was established I dont think there were more than 40 people who wrote in and said we&#13;
dont want to belong. So even people who voted against it, and there were very few--I&#13;
think five percent of the vote--even many of those didnt feel strongly enough to take the&#13;
step of actually resigning. There were very few people who did that. Now, if we'd had&#13;
dues, or had we been a union, we might not have lost the Staff Association, but we&#13;
certainly would have lost a lot of people.&#13;
ZIEGLER: Were there any particularly thorny organizational issues? I know there was a&#13;
working group set up, and it seems that these issues had been studied pretty thoroughly&#13;
before they were actually sent to any sort of voter deliberations.&#13;
SANDBERG: As I remember the process, we started by having lengthy discussions in&#13;
the Assembly about general principles. And then after a long period of time and there&#13;
were reports, people went to visit other organizations with staff associations and studied&#13;
other constitutions such as that of the UN Staff Association.&#13;
And then at some point, a drafting committee was appointed. And I guess now there's&#13;
only one person on that drafting committee who's still in the Bank.&#13;
ZIEGLER: I'm going to talk to Jill [Gillian R.] Kaplan.&#13;
SANDBERG: Well, the other one was Tom [Thomas A.] Blinkhorn. It was interesting&#13;
because one of the key members on that drafting committee was [Sydney] Raymond&#13;
Cope, who was then the Director of the European Department and Executive Chairman of&#13;
the Loan Committee, so he was very senior.&#13;
They then sat down and drafted the Constitution. I dont remember any major clash over&#13;
this question of the Assembly and the Executive Committee. I think everybody agreed on&#13;
that.&#13;
ZIEGLER: Obviously, there was some discussion as to the best way to go. But what I&#13;
had more in mind was whether there was anything that sticks in your mind, a particularly&#13;
Bengt Sandberg&#13;
February 3, 1988 - Final Edited&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿6&#13;
contentious issue regarding organization. Because in the record, as I read it, it pretty&#13;
clearly set out what the alternatives were, and what the recommendations were.&#13;
SANDBERG: Right.&#13;
ZIEGLER: And what some of the discussions were.&#13;
SANDBERG: I dont remember if there was any major discussion of the question of the&#13;
length of service. You know, there are very tight limits both on the number of years that&#13;
you can serve on the Executive Committee and the number of years you can serve as a&#13;
Delegate. And there were a lot of people who were worried about coups and small groups&#13;
being able to run and make the Staff Association a kind of general parish, you know, like&#13;
Tammany Hall. And that's why these things were put in there, to limit the ability of&#13;
people to pull a coup and to limit the ability of people to serve for many, many years. We&#13;
did not want to have dynasties, self-perpetuating Executive Committees.&#13;
At the time there was tremendous enthusiasm. If you were to go back and go through the&#13;
roster and see who was in the Assembly, there was a whole group of people who today&#13;
are directors and what not in the Bank. It was some of the most respected people in the&#13;
Bank, generally speaking, who were prepared to serve the Staff Association.&#13;
ZIEGLER: I dont want to leave that. That's very interesting. So, when the Staff&#13;
Association was founded it enjoyed the support of very, very many reputable and&#13;
respected people on the Bank staff.&#13;
SANDBERG: Absolutely, absolutely, very senior people. We had wide grassroots&#13;
support. There were never any problems--well, I suppose there were problems in filling&#13;
some of the Alternate spots. But the meetings of the Assembly were always extremely&#13;
well attended. In most parts of the Bank, Delegates were holding meetings prior to the&#13;
Assembly meetings, circulating the documents for comments and discussion. Mind you,&#13;
after a couple of years it wasnt that easy to do so. Jill Kaplan and I were the two&#13;
delegates from East Asia, and before every Delegate Assembly meeting we used to call in&#13;
our constituents to discuss the agenda so that we would be able to represent them. We&#13;
never had any problems with getting temporary Alternates to serve for us if we happened&#13;
to be away. And these meetings were always extremely well attended.&#13;
And the other thing you have to remember too is that partly because of the issue of dues,&#13;
there was a very strong feeling among the people who started the Staff Association that&#13;
this was something we did not want to get mixed up with the management. We did not&#13;
want any favors. As I remember, every single meeting of the Delegate Assembly that I&#13;
can remember attending was always after working hours. We would then borrow the&#13;
Board Room, and we would meet in the Board Room.&#13;
Executive Committee meetings were always at lunch or after work. All work was done&#13;
during working hours with the agreement of your boss. The idea was that you would then&#13;
work overtime to do your job. For example, the year when Jill Kaplan was the Chairman,&#13;
Bengt Sandberg&#13;
February 3, 1988 - Final Edited&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿7&#13;
she was my secretary. She was basically allowed to run the Staff Association during&#13;
office hours. In those days we didnt have a staff assistant. We had nothing. The only&#13;
thing was that we could use the Telex if we needed to have an election and get votes and&#13;
that sort of thing. I'm not even sure if we had desk to desk distribution. I think we&#13;
circulated most things through the delegates. And they made copies and gave them to&#13;
their constituents.&#13;
ZIEGLER: The idea was to keep ...&#13;
SANDBERG: The idea was to keep it separate from management. We didnt have an&#13;
office. I think we probably met in some conference rooms here and there. So it was a&#13;
totally voluntary effort. And as I said, we had a lot of people who were on the rise in the&#13;
Bank and all kinds of enthusiastic people who participated in this effort.&#13;
As I recall it, the only organizational issue that was contentious was when the Executive&#13;
Committee took exception to the recommendation of the constitution drafting committee&#13;
on the question of the Chairman of the Assembly. The idea behind the proposal that they&#13;
made was that it's difficult to both be an impartial Chairman of the Assembly meeting&#13;
and at the same time represent the Executive Committee before the Assembly.&#13;
The idea was that you would have a separate Chairman. I dont remember how I voted on&#13;
this issue. But in retrospect I think that was correct. That became obvious fairly soon,&#13;
because the first chairman, Jim Chaffey, used to run his Assembly meetings with an iron&#13;
hand. We had some very obstreperous people, very articulate people, in the Assembly,&#13;
and there used to be quite a bit of grumbling about the dictatorial way in which these&#13;
meetings were run. But, of course, he had an agenda; he wanted to get through it and so&#13;
on and so forth. Then it becomes difficult to be impartial in the amount of time you allow&#13;
people to speak and when to cut them off and that sort of thing.&#13;
ZIEGLER: The idea is more like the Speaker of the House of Commons.&#13;
SANDBERG: Exactly. I dont know whose idea it was. It may well have been Raymond&#13;
Cope's. But I dont know. In retrospect, why we in the Executive Committee went against&#13;
this proposal would probably have something to do with the power and strength of the&#13;
executive vis-d-vis the Assembly and so on. But Jim was the one I guess who basically&#13;
went against this, I'd say. I don't want to say that he killed it, but the Executive&#13;
Committee at that point was feeling its oats. It had been in office for a year and had&#13;
gotten used to running things. So that was really, as I remember it anyway, the only&#13;
contentious issue.&#13;
ZIEGLER: You've covered the founding of the Staff Association pretty well. Is there&#13;
anything else you want to add?&#13;
SANDBERG: You asked me what capacities I served in. Maybe I can just list them. As I&#13;
said, I was a member of the Constituent Assembly; I was a member of the Executive&#13;
Committee. Then in the first election for Chairman, I ran against Jim for Chairman. The&#13;
Bengt Sandberg&#13;
February 3, 1988 - Final Edited&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿8&#13;
only reason I did that was I believed one should not have an election for Chairman&#13;
without a contest. In fact, I was on mission when the election took place. I never had any&#13;
particular wish or hope to be Chairman.&#13;
ZIEGLER: But you didnt win.&#13;
SANDBERG: No, I didnt. I think I was Treasurer in his administration. That's when I&#13;
wrote the Treasurer's report saying the Staff Association has neither income nor&#13;
expenditures, period. End of story. After the first year the elections took place for the&#13;
second Chairman of the Staff Association. That was interesting because the Chairman&#13;
was Jill Kaplan. I think it says something about the people, both the constituents and the&#13;
Staff Association generally.&#13;
ZIEGLER: Was that before or after you ran. That's before, right?&#13;
SANDBERG: No. The first elected Staff Association Delegate Assembly elected Jim&#13;
Chairman. And I think Jill was Vice Chairman. And I was Treasurer.&#13;
ZIEGLER: So you ran against him?&#13;
SANDBERG: I ran against him. But that was more on principle.&#13;
ZIEGLER: And that was after the Constitution?&#13;
SANDBERG: This was in 1972, after the Constitution had been adopted and we then&#13;
had elections. But then after that Jill Kaplan, of course, became the Chairman for the&#13;
second year, which was interesting, because she was a support staff member, and she was&#13;
a woman in an organization which is totally dominated by men.&#13;
ZIEGLER: You were involved in a similar situation some years later, as I recall.&#13;
SANDBERG: That's right. But what made it interesting was towards the very end. We&#13;
didnt have all these elaborate procedures then for making speeches. These were things&#13;
that came later. In those days for the election of an Executive Committee you simply had&#13;
a nominating speech and a seconding speech and then there was an election. So they&#13;
didnt ask the people standing for election to give their platform.&#13;
But in the days just before the second election there was quite a campaign to stop her&#13;
election. And, of course, they picked the wrong candidate to run against her, because they&#13;
tried to convince me to run against her.&#13;
ZIEGLER: You're saying there was a campaign to stop the election. Quite frankly, was&#13;
it based on the fact that Jill was female?&#13;
SANDBERG: Of course it was. Of course it was. I mean, nobody ever said that. But it&#13;
was by innuendo saying it should be a professional. That kind of thing. I dont remember&#13;
Bengt Sandberg&#13;
February 3, 1988 - Final Edited&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿9&#13;
how many telephone calls I got. But there were people in the Assembly who were trying&#13;
to build a movement, of which I wouldnt have any part. They may have tried others, that&#13;
I dont know. But in any case they didnt succeed. I think that speaks very highly for the&#13;
Staff Association, because I think it shows that we were a fairly progressive organization.&#13;
Anyway, I served. And this is when we had this interesting situation where I was the&#13;
Secretary in her administration. So we had a situation where my secretary was the&#13;
Chairman and I was the Secretary, which confused a lot of people. But we had a lot of&#13;
fun with that one.&#13;
Then after that I think I may have served on one more Delegate Assembly. But I'm not&#13;
sure. I dont even remember.&#13;
I had this view that if you had been Chairman of the Executive Committee one year, you&#13;
should not serve on the Executive Committee the following year, because that would tend&#13;
to undercut the status of your successor. And in a sense I also felt, although not as&#13;
strongly, that maybe once you serve on the Executive Committee, you shouldnt serve in&#13;
the Assembly. You should let other people.&#13;
Anyway, since then I have served on, or tried to serve the Staff Association. For many&#13;
years I was a member of the Outside Activities Committee. And about a year after we&#13;
went out of office, or a couple of years after, I served on the Appeals Committee.&#13;
But I guess in a sense I may even be the only one of the original group who has served&#13;
the Staff Association continuously. So I got into it by happenstance, but I've never&#13;
managed to get out of it.&#13;
ZIEGLER: I think we can shift gears now for a bit. We have discussed basically the&#13;
founding of the Staff Association. And for the second part we can discuss your more&#13;
activist period, which is towards the beginning of the Staff Association. One of the big&#13;
issues that I see coming out of your second term in 1973 was the two salary increases in&#13;
that year. Presumably they were a result of the inflationary pressures. Could you perhaps&#13;
relate some of the issues surrounding these two salary increases? For example--and this is&#13;
something still very much with us--a differential in the increase for what were then called&#13;
Professional staff level on one hand and for what was then two other groups, Special&#13;
Services and General Services staff on the other.&#13;
SANDBERG: As I remember, there were two issues. One was how do you deal with&#13;
salary adjustments in a period of rapid inflation? And, of course, what we managed to&#13;
get the Bank to do and the management to do was to have two salary increases that year. I&#13;
can't remember what the increase in the consumer price index was that year. But I&#13;
remember we were trying to argue for more or less automatic salary increases when we&#13;
had a certain rise in the consumer price index. There would be an automatic trigger&#13;
mechanism. In fact, I guess we were trying to argue in terms of real salary increases,&#13;
arguing that if there was an increase in the consumer price index, then there would&#13;
automatically be a salary increase. Looking back at it that was not something that the&#13;
Bengt Sandberg&#13;
February 3, 1988 - Final Edited&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿10&#13;
management really could agree to. But certainly we wanted to have a more or less&#13;
automatic trigger mechanism.&#13;
The other issue was this business of the differentiation presented ...&#13;
[Tape defect]&#13;
[End Tape 1, Side A]&#13;
[Begin Tape 1, Side B]&#13;
SANDBERG: I dont think it was just the support staff problem. There was also sort of a&#13;
top level problem. Because I remember for a number of years the senior people got much&#13;
less. They were complacent. But those were really the issues.&#13;
I looked at the Chairman's Report, and I guess in a sense we lost on both of them. But&#13;
those were--both of them were really matters of principle, and I think we came back to&#13;
them time after time. But I really dont remember.&#13;
ZIEGLER: Later on the question of--there was also the question of equal access to&#13;
benefits.&#13;
SANDBERG: Yes. On the question of access to benefits as distinct from salaries, on that&#13;
point we won and we won big. That was a major issue of principle. Because all the Bank&#13;
benefits had been discriminating against lower level staff.&#13;
They discriminated against single staff. There were many parts of the packages that had&#13;
what was then called major income earner test which in a sense would block a lot of&#13;
lower level staff out of the benefits such as home leave. I think a secretary had to be in&#13;
the Bank for seven years before she got home leave or something like that. There were&#13;
parts of the medical plan which were clearly discriminatory against single females. The&#13;
idea of a single female becoming a mother was just not covered anywhere. The Bank&#13;
being such a patriarchal organization, there was also a good bit of uncalled for morality&#13;
involved in quite a few of the Bank's benefits and the way the Bank looked at staff. It&#13;
came up. It was an issue that we fought in the early days of the Outside Activities&#13;
Committee.&#13;
If you go back and look at the "Rules of Conduct" as they're written back in 1971 or&#13;
1972, they talked about Bank staff not behaving in such a way as to be an embarrassment&#13;
to the Bank. And a lot of people interpreted this in all kinds of ways that had to do with&#13;
people's sexual preferences and private lives generally.&#13;
No, I think that on the issue of access to benefits I think probably the Executive&#13;
Committee in 1973 was the one that played the major role. Also, I think it was Mr.&#13;
McNamara who put out a memorandum to all staff abolishing the categorization of staff.&#13;
About 15 years later it still has not been abolished. Because somehow ...&#13;
Bengt Sandberg&#13;
February 3, 1988 - Final Edited&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿11&#13;
ZIEGLER: It's still very much alive.&#13;
SANDBERG: Still very much alive. But also, of course, you have to remember in 1972,&#13;
1973, the way that staff treated each other was so different.&#13;
ZIEGLER: From now.&#13;
SANDBERG: Well, it's gotten better. In Sweden, I'd gotten used to the revolution that&#13;
took place in the late 1960s. Everybody suddenly started calling everybody by their first&#13;
name. And Sweden went from being a very formal, Mr. and Mrs. type of operation to a&#13;
totally informal system. When I came back I must have been one of the first division&#13;
chiefs in the Bank, you know, where we're all on a first name basis. It was always Mr.&#13;
Sandberg and secretaries being called by their first names. They were extremely unhappy&#13;
about this. And this was part of sort of a general attitude. And this is why this support&#13;
staff element in the Assembly and in the Executive Committee were so emotional about&#13;
abolishing these categories and getting equal access to benefits. Because it was&#13;
discriminatory. No question about that.&#13;
ZIEGLER: My next question specifically is what negotiating tactics or strategy did you&#13;
use with management? But coupled with that, I'm also interested in what may have&#13;
caused management to, quote, "see the light," unquote, especially this equal access to&#13;
benefits. Did they see a payoff for themselves? Or were they swayed by moral arguments,&#13;
perhaps? I say that tongue in cheek, of course. I think it's two sides of the same thing.&#13;
Obviously, you presented your issues to management. How did you present them? And&#13;
what would have caused them to agree with you on this particular and very important&#13;
issue?&#13;
SANDBERG: I would like to believe that they just saw the force of the argument. That&#13;
this was just right. That what was going on was just not right. That you as a higher level&#13;
staff member would arrive in Washington with your family. And you would be installed&#13;
in one of the finest hotels in Georgetown for a month, as I was put in a duplex with my&#13;
three kids and my wife at the Bank's expense and collecting substantial amounts of&#13;
money in relocation grants and what not. And a secretary would arrive here with no&#13;
relocation, with no movement of furniture, a suitcase and be put in a hotel and be given&#13;
$20.00 a day for ten days and then that's it. You take care of yourself. You know, that&#13;
sort of thing. It was so blatant.&#13;
Now, of course, on the issue of the major income earner test, there were big fights. And I&#13;
don't think that was removed immediately. Because that was kind of something that&#13;
affected everybody. So that hung around for a long, long time. And, I guess, in that case&#13;
it was only when the Bank discovered that it wasn't really saving them all that much&#13;
money and was causing a lot of unhappiness that they did away with it. And, I guess,&#13;
maybe at that point, too, there may have been many more spouses of higher level staff&#13;
who were earning larger salaries. I don't know. But that one hung around for a long time.&#13;
And I don't think that all benefits were suddenly equalized. As I remember, it was a little&#13;
bit of a process. But basically I think that [Reginald A.] Clarke and McNamara and the&#13;
Bengt Sandberg&#13;
February 3, 1988 - Final Edited&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿12&#13;
management and the Board probably saw this as an issue of equity and simply--what is&#13;
right.&#13;
ZIEGLER: As well as being an exercise in history, this series of interviews, of which&#13;
yours is the first, is sort of a "how to" for current and future members of the Staff&#13;
Association. And so it would be interesting to find out what sort of tactics or strategies&#13;
you used in negotiating with management. Was it hard at it, a hammer and tongs sort of&#13;
thing? Or gentle persuasion? Obviously, any group who negotiates with management has&#13;
to attune its approach to the manager who's sitting across from the table and the issue&#13;
involved. But over time maybe we can see what has worked effectively in various ways.&#13;
SANDBERG: Well, as I said, we saw it primarily as a channel of communication. So&#13;
that obviously one way of persuading management was to get the backing of the&#13;
Assembly. If we felt strongly we would have a resolution passed which would give the&#13;
mandate to the Executive Committee. But basically we tried to work it out with&#13;
management through the consultative process. We had an agreement that before they put&#13;
out circulars on benefits or announced new benefits they would consult with us. And we&#13;
would then discuss it and we would give our views on how they presented it, on how they&#13;
split benefits and so on. And that was the process in which we could then make known&#13;
our views. I dont remember now exactly what agreement we had with them. But they&#13;
used to send to us draft circulars on education benefits. Particularly, they'd go through&#13;
with this revision of these things from time to time.&#13;
We then had working groups on various issues, too. Say on the pension plan. They&#13;
basically were collecting evidence, collecting views from other staff members, and sitting&#13;
and working with members of the management on these and coming up with&#13;
recommendations on improvements that might be considered the next time.&#13;
ZIEGLER: So it's fair to say early on you established a consultative sort of relationship?&#13;
SANDBERG: That's right. It was a consultative relationship. And I think a very&#13;
interesting example of that was the reorganization of 1972. Here again my memory is&#13;
hazy exactly on how this happened, but my memory is that we in the Executive&#13;
Committee played a major role, if not the major role, in coming up with the system of&#13;
compensation for Bank staff who were downgraded or lost their jobs in that&#13;
reorganization. Now, there weren't very many of them. But this was an issue that the&#13;
management had forgotten about. Or hadnt thought about. And I can remember some of&#13;
us in the Executive Committee sitting in late a couple of evenings and trying to work out&#13;
a system or commenting on a system, whether we took the initiative or whatever it was.&#13;
But one of the points that we made to the management in the reorganization is that people&#13;
have got to be treated fairly. You have the right to reorganize. Maybe people will become&#13;
redundant. But they should be fairly compensated. And I think that we came up with the&#13;
idea of being particularly generous to people who are in the age span between 45 and 55.&#13;
Because before 45 it's easier to find a job. After 55 you can take a pension. So you need&#13;
to have a differentiated system of compensation.&#13;
Bengt Sandberg&#13;
February 3, 1988 - Final Edited&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿13&#13;
And, in fact, I've looked in my files and I have there copies of Reg Clarke's draft circular&#13;
on this issue with my marginal comments, even crossing out and inserting language. I&#13;
dont have the final versions, and of course others were also commenting.&#13;
But it was this kind of a process. It's absolutely certain that before those policies were&#13;
issued to staff, not only had the policies been discussed with us and we'd had&#13;
consultations, but we even had an input in the way that they were presented to staff.&#13;
So I think that was a fairly typical kind of operation. The arguments that we had with&#13;
them were that they always came too late, always under pressure. We really didnt have a&#13;
chance to consult with the Assembly. They didnt have a chance to consult with&#13;
constituents. So, therefore, there was always the question of the demands of the&#13;
consultation process that we had set up in the structure of the Staff Association and the&#13;
need for them to move quickly and expeditiously.&#13;
Now, obviously if you have a consultative process like that, you cant expect to have your&#13;
views accepted every time. But I think that in those years in the beginning there was a&#13;
good bit of cleaning up of a lot of Bank policies. And a lot of discrimination and stuff&#13;
was eliminated.&#13;
ZIEGLER: Well, earlier on you mentioned about getting a resolution in the Delegate&#13;
Assembly. I do have a question about your means of mobilizing staff support. From what&#13;
you say, presumably you didnt feel the need to get the masses, so to speak, behind you.&#13;
Your primary expression of support from the staff at large was by means of the Delegate&#13;
Assembly.&#13;
SANDBERG: No, we never ever considered either calling a strike or calling a general&#13;
meeting. The Constitution provides for general meetings. But I have always been and I'm&#13;
still extremely skeptical about general meetings, because even if you collect a thousand&#13;
people in the courtyard and you get them all to shout "yea," they are still only expressing&#13;
the view of a thousand out of six thousand. And the idea behind the structure that was&#13;
adopted was that the Executive Committee, after having gotten the backing of the&#13;
Delegate Assembly, would in fact be speaking for six thousand people. Because the&#13;
process would be such that everybody would have had a chance to express his views to&#13;
his Delegate who would have reported and expressed this view in the Assembly. And the&#13;
Executive Committee would go to management and say we've gone through this process,&#13;
and this is the view of the overwhelming majority of the staff.&#13;
Now, mind you the big problem that you have and that we had as an Executive&#13;
Committee and that every Executive Committee has is the one of apathy.&#13;
ZIEGLER: That's a very good point. We've discussed it as of the last few years. But&#13;
this is something that is not new, from what I gather just reading in the early Staff&#13;
Association annual reports.&#13;
Bengt Sandberg&#13;
February 3, 1988 - Final Edited&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿14&#13;
SANDBERG: No, no, no. The membership of the Staff Association swings between&#13;
apathy and belligerence. And the Assembly and the Executive Committee is in the&#13;
middle, so to speak, and needs to maintain momentum in times of apathy. But they need&#13;
to be there to channel the belligerence when it occurs. It can be triggered at a moment's&#13;
notice by a report that the management is going to the Board and asking for 2 percent&#13;
instead of 5 percent. And you suddenly have the whole staff up in arms and very&#13;
frustrated. And they need then to have a channel for their frustration.&#13;
Now, the Executive Committee has to be in a position of being able to judge what the&#13;
reaction of the staff is going to be, so that they are not taken by surprise or make the&#13;
wrong move. They have to be prepared. And the only way that they can be prepared is to&#13;
keep their ear to the ground at all times.&#13;
You know, you can go through two years without anything ever happening. And the Staff&#13;
Association is then the sandbox for the Executive Committee. And they can play there to&#13;
their heart's content, and they can have their own agendas. And they can have all this sort&#13;
of thing. You know, that's very easy. That's not very difficult.&#13;
But then one day something happens. And if the Executive Committee doesnt react on&#13;
behalf of staff but tries to play their own games and all the rest of it, at that point, then&#13;
you have a disaster. And this is the frustrating part of working for the Staff Association.&#13;
Because you can literally go through years without getting any sort of response or getting&#13;
any feedback. And youll have to the whole time kind of guess and act as best you can on&#13;
behalf of staff. But, God help you if you get into one of these crisis situations and you&#13;
misjudge.&#13;
ZIEGLER: I recall sitting in various Staff Association meetings lately and people would&#13;
harken back to the palmy days of 1973, for instance, when the staff was interested in the&#13;
Staff Association, being united and all this. What you're saying, it seems to me, is that&#13;
you had apathy even in 1973.&#13;
SANDBERG: Of course we did. Of course we did. There are certain events that trigger a&#13;
lot of emotions. But among the staff generally you always have groups of people who are&#13;
particularly interested in a single issue. And those are the ones that you've got to watch so&#13;
that they dont take over. Because they are not going to be able to act on behalf of the&#13;
staff as a whole if something happens or when something happens. You know, they're&#13;
very good at pushing for a day care center or dealing with women's issues and that's fine.&#13;
But then what happens when you suddenly have a big confrontation over salaries, when&#13;
the whole staff expects them to do something. It's a very tricky business.&#13;
ZIEGLER: It is indeed.&#13;
SANDBERG: I can remember being called to meetings by a constituency somewhere, a&#13;
department perhaps, where the people were absolutely abusive in their expressions of&#13;
frustration. You know, why aren't you doing something? Stand up to management.&#13;
Bengt Sandberg&#13;
February 3, 1988 - Final Edited&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿15&#13;
ZIEGLER: More easily said than done.&#13;
SANDBERG: Exactly. And that's the time when you've got to keep your cool, but at the&#13;
same time be able to channel all this energy into something constructive for the staff as a&#13;
whole.&#13;
ZIEGLER: All very useful I must say.&#13;
You did have to deal with various higher level managers. Who were the ones who stuck&#13;
in your mind? What sort of relationship did you have with them--I'm speaking primarily&#13;
of when you were on the Executive Committee in 1972-1973--obviously McNamara was&#13;
President. And probably Bernard Chadenet was the person you dealt mostly with on these&#13;
administrative issues.&#13;
SANDBERG: I would think that we probably dealt on most issues with Reg Clarke and&#13;
Martijn Paijmans.&#13;
ZIEGLER: So Martijn Paijmans'involvement goes way back to ...&#13;
SANDBERG: Martijn was Deputy Director of Personnel. The Chairmen had different&#13;
ways of doing this. Jim [Chaffey] liked to deal directly with Clarke and then report to the&#13;
Executive Committee. Jill [Kaplan] had the system of always going as a fivesome; she&#13;
used the officers, as she called us, as the smaller group of the Executive Committee to&#13;
deal with management. When Clarke was away it was Martijn on certain issues. It was&#13;
delegated to Martijn. And on all the administrative stuff it was Jim [James E.] Twining,&#13;
who was then the Director of Administration. And also then there used to be two or three&#13;
meetings a year with McNamara with all his cohorts, or whatever they're called, present.&#13;
But he used to do all of the talking.&#13;
I always found Martijn very, very easy to deal with. Reg tended to be a little more rigid, a&#13;
little more formalistic than Martijn. I never really dealt with any of those issues so I never&#13;
really dealt with Twining.&#13;
ZIEGLER: One issue that brought you to the fore, so to speak, in the Staff Association&#13;
rather late in your career was in 1986. I well remember there was an election controversy.&#13;
Though involved in it as a candidate for the Executive Committee, I really didnt get&#13;
involved in the nuts and bolts of your role in it all, although I must say from my own&#13;
personal observation you handled it splendidly. This is one of the reasons I wanted to get&#13;
you for this series of interviews. It was a potentially very divisive period in the Staff&#13;
Association. All things considered, I think the Staff Association weathered it rather well.&#13;
Would you mind saying just a bit about your involvement in this particular controversy?&#13;
Because I think it's a good example of how to handle things properly once they do fall&#13;
apart. You can put them back together again.&#13;
SANDBERG: Well, what happened was somebody called me and asked me could I&#13;
come to a meeting. Because there was a big snafu over the election of Chairman of the&#13;
Bengt Sandberg&#13;
February 3, 1988 - Final Edited&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿16&#13;
Staff Association, of the Executive Committee. And I walked over there and I found, as I&#13;
remember, two parties very much at loggerheads with each other. Basically, you know,&#13;
accusing each other of election fraud. And there were all kinds of threats being issued&#13;
and walking out and so on and so forth. I can't remember who called me. Maybe it was&#13;
[Lucien] Moreau. I dont know.&#13;
And I remember I would sort of listen to all of this. Now, exactly how it happened or who&#13;
came up with the idea of somebody arbitrating this thing, I frankly dont remember. I&#13;
remember maybe somebody said to me--or maybe I suggested that this was the way to do&#13;
it--to have an impartial person look into it. Maybe I suggested it and then somebody&#13;
asked if I would do it. I do remember saying that I would only do it if it had the full&#13;
support and cooperation of both sides, both the [Christopher J.] Redfern camp and&#13;
Donneve Rae's camp. And, you know, the tone was very high as I remember. People&#13;
were very upset. And they saw this as higher level male staff against support level female&#13;
staff, and they saw it all in that kind of a light.&#13;
Now, why I agreed to do it I dont know. But I did. And I think that when I took it on I&#13;
had two objectives. One, I believed that this had to be resolved very fast. Secondly, I&#13;
decided that to look into questions of fraud or of packing of the Assembly, that sort of&#13;
thing, should if possible be avoided. I mean, if you get into that you can go on for weeks&#13;
and you can take evidence. And in any case it's not clear what it says about the validity of&#13;
the election.&#13;
So I decided I think almost immediately to just sort of look at this purely as a very&#13;
formalistic election process question, to look and see if the election procedures and the&#13;
Constitution had been properly followed. And there were telephone calls. There were&#13;
memoranda written to me on various other aspects. I just put all of that aside and just&#13;
looked simply at this question: how was the election conducted? It was a fairly legalistic&#13;
point of view. But on the other hand, I think that sort of cuts through it. Because it then&#13;
became clear that they had not. Because people who were not really allowed to cast votes&#13;
had cast votes. People had cast absentee ballots. And there were various things. There&#13;
were irregularities. And the election was so close that there was no way in which you&#13;
disqualify certain votes because you didnt know who they were cast for. Because this is a&#13;
secret ballot.&#13;
So there was no way of saying that Mr. X shouldnt have been allowed to cast a vote. You&#13;
couldnt take it out, throw that vote out, because you didnt know which one it was. There&#13;
was really only one way of dealing with the issue. And that was to say forget it.&#13;
Now, the other thing was that I looked at it also procedurally. I had been asked by the&#13;
Chairman of the Polling Officers to look into the election.&#13;
ZIEGLER: The Chairman of the Polling Officers was really roughly handled, by the&#13;
way.&#13;
Bengt Sandberg&#13;
February 3, 1988 - Final Edited&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿17&#13;
SANDBERG: My report, I think, was written to her. And, of course, she had blown it.&#13;
But it was unfair to her. Because again it was one of these positions where somebody&#13;
called her up and said, would you be Chairman of the Polling Officers. It's a very simple&#13;
job. So she really didnt know what she was getting. I thought it was a bit unfair to her.&#13;
ZIEGLER: I recall that very well, yes.&#13;
SANDBERG: So anyway, I wrote my report to her. And then we held the election--they&#13;
then asked me to run that election. We tried to make it absolutely, scrupulously--and I&#13;
brought in my own [unclear] to make sure that there wouldn't be any arguments&#13;
afterwards. And my impression is that by and large the outcome of this was accepted with&#13;
relatively good grace by everybody.&#13;
ZIEGLER: It was indeed. I was deeply involved in the election as one of the candidates.&#13;
Although it wasn't from my point of view all that contentious. But I think everybody was&#13;
very favorably surprised as to how well things ultimately did work out, given the very&#13;
explosive nature of the whole issue.&#13;
[End Tape 1, Side B]&#13;
[Begin Tape 2, Side A]&#13;
SANDBERG: But I think that possibly one reason for that was that I never tried to&#13;
investigate the specific charges.&#13;
ZIEGLER: That was smart.&#13;
SANDBERG: You see, if I had done that, I think we could have gone on for two weeks,&#13;
and then there could well have been all kinds of disagreements with my findings. On the&#13;
findings that I had, I dont think there could be any argument. But anyway, it was an&#13;
interesting experience.&#13;
ZIEGLER: But not one you care to repeat, no doubt.&#13;
SANDBERG: No, thank you very much. I dont think it should have to be repeated&#13;
because I think what had happened was that under pressure of apathy, under pressure of&#13;
these various other things the Executive Committee had become sloppy. Procedure may&#13;
not have been important, in the early years. My impression was that this was not the first&#13;
time this election procedure was used. It just so happened that this particular year the&#13;
whole thing was contentious.&#13;
ZIEGLER: It was close enough to be challenged.&#13;
SANDBERG: It was close enough to be challenged and contentious. In earlier years they&#13;
had probably used the same system but there had been no objection to the results, so&#13;
therefore it had worked. And I think what this accomplished in the longer run was to&#13;
Bengt Sandberg&#13;
February 3, 1988 - Final Edited&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿18&#13;
focus attention on some of the forms that have to be observed by people who run large&#13;
organizations of this kind.&#13;
ZIEGLER: Just speaking from my own personal point of view in this whole affair, I&#13;
gather very clearly that you were perceived to be impartial and having the best interest of&#13;
the Association at heart. I think that it went a long way to resolving the issue as neatly as&#13;
possible. All things considered, I thought that it was wrapped up rather well.&#13;
SANDBERG: The Staff Association survived, right? And I think in my view did not do a&#13;
bad job during the reorganization.&#13;
ZIEGLER: There are a few more points I'd like to cover with you, two questions which&#13;
are essentially two sides of the same coin. What do you feel was your greatest&#13;
accomplishment in your involvement with the Staff Association, or what are you most&#13;
happy in having participated in or having a hand in? And what, perhaps, would you like&#13;
to have done better or differently, again, in view of your Staff Association involvement&#13;
over the years?&#13;
SANDBERG: Now you're opening up a big subject. I trust we have time.&#13;
ZIEGLER: We do.&#13;
SANDBERG: I've had, you know, a couple of pet themes that I have tried to push ever&#13;
since I got involved in the Staff Association. I guess we have succeeded at least partially&#13;
on both of them. One was access of staff to their own personnel files. When we started,&#13;
files were not accessible to the staff. I could not go and look at my own file. I had&#13;
absolutely no idea what was on that file. There were innumerable stories around the Bank&#13;
of people who for inexplicable reasons had been given bad assignments, not given any&#13;
work, being bypassed, and who through the grapevine heard that there was something on&#13;
their file that was derogatory. People were not given a chance to respond to things. It was&#13;
well known that anybody could write a memo to anybody's personnel file. If you and I&#13;
were on a mission and you got drunk one evening I could write a memorandum to the&#13;
Personnel Department that Mr. Ziegler got drunk and misbehaved. This is behavior that&#13;
does not befit a Bank staff member. And it would go on your file and nobody would ever&#13;
ask you a question about it. It would just be there. And anybody who was looking at you&#13;
for a promotion or whatever would see it.&#13;
And this, you know, to my mind was always so grossly unfair. I argued for many years of&#13;
the need to open up the personnel files and give people the opportunity to know and to&#13;
defend themselves. And I think that has been a very contentious issue because, as&#13;
somebody put it once, many Bank managers have written things on people's personnel&#13;
records on the understanding that it would not come to the knowledge of the person they&#13;
were writing about. And therefore, these files could not be opened.&#13;
Exactly what the policy is today I frankly dont know. But certainly they've gone a long&#13;
way in the process of annual performance reviews.&#13;
Bengt Sandberg&#13;
February 3, 1988 - Final Edited&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿19&#13;
Of course, the other side of this is that when these things are opened they become less&#13;
honest. But that's the Bank's problem. For the staff member it's important that he know&#13;
what is formally on his record and what people are saying about him. And it seems to me&#13;
to be a basic issue of fairness that you should be allowed to refute allegations against you.&#13;
And I think that now happens. I dont think that things can go on people's records without&#13;
them being given a chance to defend themselves.&#13;
Of course, again, the other side of this is that a lot of things now probably dont go on&#13;
people's records, and instead you have the telephones and the word of mouth which may&#13;
be worse. I dont know. But at least in the formal sense everybody knows or should know&#13;
what is going on his record. I never looked at my personnel file, so I have no idea what&#13;
may be on there from 1970, 1971, 1972. That's issue number one.&#13;
The second issue about which I have been very concerned of course is the whole question&#13;
of the ability of Bank staff to get management decisions reviewed, the whole appeals&#13;
process. And I guess if there's anything I feel good about, it has been my involvement&#13;
with the Appeals Committee. Well, in fact it's in the report that we wrote for 1973. I&#13;
didnt realize it was that long ago that Reg Clarke established an ad hoc review committee&#13;
to hear the case of a man who had been dismissed from the Bank, an economist who had&#13;
been fired. And I guess he wanted it to test an appeals committee system. So he by letter&#13;
appointed three members to hear this case. That was in 1973. Do you know who the&#13;
Chairman was of that group?&#13;
ZIEGLER: No.&#13;
SANDBERG: Ernest Stem. Ernest Stern was then the Director of Economic Policy in&#13;
[Hollis] Chenery's office. And the other member was Guy Pfefferman. And I represented&#13;
the Staff Association. That was very interesting because in essence we really didnt know&#13;
what the hell we were doing. We met in camera. We talked to the parties. And we&#13;
reviewed the documents. It was a question of performance. The documentation that this&#13;
man had produced. Whether he was up to the quality of the Bank. But the interesting&#13;
thing was that at the end of the first round here, Pfefferman and I had come to the&#13;
conclusion that the man should be given another chance. And Stem went along with that.&#13;
I've never been quite sure whether he did that because he wanted to have a unanimous&#13;
view or whether he really felt that way. He seemed reluctant at the time. But he went&#13;
along and we had this consensus.&#13;
And then after we had reached this conclusion we learned that some of the reports that we&#13;
had been reviewing as being the work of this man were in fact AID [U.S. Agency for&#13;
International Development] or some other reports that he had simply changed the name&#13;
on and presented as his own. So unfortunately we were then of course forced to agree that&#13;
there was no place for this man in the Bank as this was not conduct that we could accept.&#13;
At the time I was very upset because I had hoped that we would test the management's&#13;
commitment to an appeals process by having a case where we would find for the&#13;
appellant. So I had been very pleased when we had reached a consensus. But in retrospect&#13;
Bengt Sandberg&#13;
February 3, 1988 - Final Edited&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿20&#13;
when I thought about it today, maybe it was lucky it turned out this way. Because maybe&#13;
if we had found for the appellant, that Reg Clarke and company would never have agreed&#13;
to set up an Appeals Committee. 1 dont know.&#13;
But anyway, then of course the Staff Association put me on the Appeals Committee. I've&#13;
served on it ever since. That has been very, very interesting. One of the interesting things&#13;
about the Appeals Committee is that when people get on it they tend to become--let me&#13;
put it this way--men of principle. Even people who you think you're worried about,&#13;
saying I'm not sure that this guy is really prepared to be critical of the management.&#13;
When they come and get on the Appeals Committee somehow there's something in the&#13;
atmosphere and they feel the weight of sort of being here, sitting in judgment or&#13;
whatever, whatever it is that makes them really become much more fair and open minded&#13;
than you would ever believe and much more courageous. That's also interesting to see.&#13;
And ever since the first two cases that I sat on, I can't recall a single case where there's&#13;
been a divided opinion. It's always been unanimous. The very first one I wrote the&#13;
minority opinion. And in the second case I managed to get one of my two panel members&#13;
to agree with me and the third one was forced to write the minority opinion. But since&#13;
then it's all been unanimous.&#13;
I must say that I am very worried about it at the moment. You know, the Appeals&#13;
Committee is only advisory. And the idea is that it's supposed to be advisory to the&#13;
President. And the President has delegated the final decision to the Vice President-&#13;
Administration. At least in cases where the Vice President-Administration has not been&#13;
himself directly involved, in which case he should excuse himself, and the report then&#13;
goes to the President.&#13;
Now, early in the history of the Appeals Committee we had a major confrontation. There&#13;
was a major issue that had to do with the way the process was working. And Paijmans&#13;
was then the Director of Administration.&#13;
ZIEGLER: He's never been the Director ...&#13;
SANDBERG: No, he was Vice President. He was the Vice President concerned.&#13;
Anyway, what Paijmans did in some of the early cases was that he took the report of the&#13;
Committee and before he made his decision, he consulted with his staff. He sent it to&#13;
them for comments. Now, in most cases, they were of course the people who the appeal&#13;
was against. They were a party to the appeal. The members of the Appeals Committee&#13;
got extraordinarily upset. They felt if this was the way he was going to do it, then for&#13;
God's sake let him go and do his own investigation. Why have an Appeals Committee?&#13;
And I remember there were mutterings about mass resignations if this situation persisted.&#13;
He then changed his method of operation. And for the rest of his tenure, at least as far as I&#13;
was able to determine--and in a formal sense I'm sure he did this--he wore one hat as&#13;
Vice President-Administration, having this delegated from the President. And he took the&#13;
reports and he looked at them. And maybe he consulted files. But whatever he did he&#13;
Bengt Sandberg&#13;
February 3, 1988 - Final Edited&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿21&#13;
reached a decision on the basis of the documentation as given to him by the Appeals&#13;
Committee. And I think he also tried very hard to delegate to his subordinates most issues&#13;
that were likely to lead to an appeal so that he would not have to excuse himself in the&#13;
process. Because that would obviously have caused a problem if the President himself&#13;
had gotten these reports. He wouldnt have known how to handle them.&#13;
Now, the problem is that we now have a new Senior Vice President for Personnel and&#13;
Administration. And I am not sure, because we have not been able to talk to him, I'm not&#13;
sure how he sees his role in the appeals process and how he sees the role of the&#13;
Committee. I know that this is an issue that is disturbing the Staff Association. And I&#13;
think it's going to be a subject of discussion. But I think it's a terribly, terribly important&#13;
issue at this particular point in time.&#13;
ZIEGLER: I know recently there have been discussions with Mr. [Willi A.] Wapenhans,&#13;
so presumably this would be among the items ...&#13;
SANDBERG: But I think it's very important that there be full openness and full&#13;
agreement on what the role of the Appeals Committee is and what his role is in this&#13;
process. If that isn't sorted out then we can have all kinds of confusion. And, of course, in&#13;
those early cases we also didnt have the Administrative Tribunal. Now, I guess maybe it&#13;
makes less of a difference if he does this, consults with [William J.] Cosgrove [Vice&#13;
President - Personnel] or whatever, and then reaches a decision which is contrary to the&#13;
Appeals Committee's recommendation. Then the appellant can always go to the Tribunal.&#13;
In the old days the appellant had no place to go after Paijmans had made his decision. So&#13;
I guess maybe the issue was more important then than it is today.&#13;
The other thing that I guess was also more important then than it is today, although I still&#13;
think it's very important, is that the Appeals Committee then being the only forum for&#13;
appeals, we thought and I thought that it was rather important that we follow certain&#13;
forms. We couldn't just be a group of three people chit-chatting around the table. We had&#13;
to have a certain legal or judicial or whatever, framework within which to do this. This is&#13;
one of the reasons, I guess, why we became fairly formal. But, you know, one of the&#13;
reasons why people go to the Appeals Committee, the reason they go is that they believe&#13;
that they have not been given due process in the Bank. So the function of the Appeals&#13;
Committee is to ensure that the appellant, the staff member, gets due process, that he is&#13;
heard. You can't begin to count the number of people where it's so clear when they come&#13;
to the Appeals Committee the complaint is that nobody has listened to them.&#13;
ZIEGLER: Do you find that frequently?&#13;
SANDBERG: Oh, that's the common denominator. And you'll find that the six or seven&#13;
hours of hearing that we have in the Appeals Committee probably is a longer period of&#13;
time than this appellant has ever had to discuss his problem with anybody in the Bank.&#13;
Because nobody's listening.&#13;
Bengt Sandberg&#13;
February 3, 1988 - Final Edited&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿22&#13;
So all I want to say is there's a lot of discussion about trying to make the process more&#13;
informal and all the rest of it which is all well and good. But I think that if the Appeals&#13;
Committee is going to fulfill its function it does need to have a certain formal process and&#13;
formality around it. So that's the Appeals Committee.&#13;
Now, the other thing I'm proud of is the institution of Ombudsman, because that was&#13;
established as a result of work by something called the Jennings Committee, which was a&#13;
group of people which was appointed to review the rules of procedure and the Staff Rule&#13;
surrounding the Appeals Committee, the whole appeals process, at a time when the&#13;
Tribunal had just been established. And one of the results of this was that either Hultin or&#13;
I or both of us suggested the establishment of an ombudsman. Which incidentally the&#13;
chairman, as I recall it at least at the beginning, was adamantly against.&#13;
ZIEGLER: Chairman of the Staff Association?&#13;
SANDBERG: The chairman of the Jennings Committee, Mr. [James H.] Jennings, who&#13;
was then the Deputy Director of Personnel. He didn't like the idea at all. But anyway,&#13;
that's where it came up. Again, one interesting thing about that is I think Hultin and&#13;
certainly I pushed very hard for making the Ombudsman an appointee of the Board rather&#13;
than of management. Because, similar to the OED Director General, we felt that the&#13;
Ombudsman needed to be separate from the management of the Bank. Ultimately that&#13;
didnt come to pass. But I think that doesnt seem to have affected the effectiveness of the&#13;
Ombudsman.&#13;
One other issue on which I have felt strongly is the right of the staff member to organize&#13;
and live his life, his private life, without interference from the Bank. I mentioned before&#13;
this kind of morality that was kind of prevalent in the Bank. I remember one time this&#13;
came up, where we sort of laughed about this, was in the Outside Activities Committee.&#13;
Do you remember when Congressman Wilbur Mills was down by the Tidal Basin with&#13;
Fanne Fox, and Fanne Fox jumped in? Well, according to the newspaper reports at the&#13;
time, very far down, evidently a secretary in the Bank was present in the car at the time.&#13;
ZIEGLER: I didnt know that.&#13;
SANDBERG: And one of the questions that was raised by somebody at one of our&#13;
meetings was whether being associated with such activities was to be considered conduct&#13;
embarrassing to the Bank and subject to disciplinary action. More legitimately the Bank&#13;
was always concerned about financial transactions by Bank staff, and properly so, or&#13;
political and all kinds of other things.&#13;
But one of the things that I did also contribute to was the revision of the Administrative&#13;
Manual Statement entitled "Duties and Obligations of Staff Members." We managed to&#13;
make them more precise in these areas of personal conduct.&#13;
ZIEGLER: Ones that could definitely affect one's performance.&#13;
Bengt Sandberg&#13;
February 3, 1988 - Final Edited&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿23&#13;
SANDBERG: Exactly. Performance in the institution and financial embarrassment,&#13;
of course embezzlement, these sorts of things that are much more important to the Bank&#13;
than if a Bank staff member conducts his sexual life in a way that has nothing to do with&#13;
his activities in the Bank. In the field of financial dealings, we tried to make it much more&#13;
of a disclosure type of requirement rather than to forbid a lot of things.&#13;
But there was one incident in that context which may be interesting here because it also&#13;
shows something about the way that McNamara viewed the Bank. When we set up the&#13;
Appeals Committee or the Outside Activities Committee, we argued that staff members&#13;
needed some place to go to get an authoritative opinion about what is allowed and what is&#13;
not allowed in certain respects. And if whoever it was in the Bank said yes, then the staff&#13;
member should not be punished later.&#13;
This is something we have in Sweden in the tax field where you can get an opinion&#13;
before you take a certain action, buy stocks or whatever. You can get an opinion as to&#13;
what the tax effect of this is. And if you then do what you're told, you cannot be taxed.&#13;
Staff members need to know that if they invest in a certain stock or if they agree to do&#13;
certain things and they get this approval and then they do it, then somebody else says, no&#13;
you cant do that, they cant be disciplined for that.&#13;
So that was the idea. The Committee should have final authority in certain cases to say&#13;
yea or nay to a proposal by a staff member. That was incorporated in the early rules under&#13;
which that Committee operated until the famous Chenery case. You remember the&#13;
Chenery case?&#13;
ZIEGLER: Is this the one about the race horse?&#13;
SANDBERG: No, no. He was owner of the race horse. He and his sister owned&#13;
Secretariat. That's true. Chenery was then the Vice President of Economics and Chief&#13;
Economics Advisor. This was in 1974, in connection with the oil crisis. His father had&#13;
made investments and made a lot of money in oil pipelines. It was a pipeline company,&#13;
somewhere in the south. I cant remember which it was. It was heavily involved in&#13;
transportation of natural gas and may even have been in exploration. I dont remember.&#13;
But it was an energy-related company. And Chenery represented the family on the board&#13;
of directors of this company. This was something that Mr. McNamara knew about when&#13;
Chenery came to the Bank and it had in fact been approved by the Board of Executive&#13;
Directors of the World Bank that he could maintain his stock holdings and represent the&#13;
family on the board of directors of the company.&#13;
But then came the rules of conduct of outside activities. And under these no Bank staff&#13;
member was allowed to serve on the board of directors of any profit making--I think it&#13;
was profit making--company or organization without the approval of the Committee.&#13;
Chenery came to the Committee and asked for the Committee's approval as a matter of&#13;
form, as he said, to serve on this Board. In the meantime, you'd had the oil crisis. The&#13;
Bank was in the midst of collecting all kinds of information and analyzing the world&#13;
energy market. And the one who was in charge of all this work was Chenery. So the&#13;
Bengt Sandberg&#13;
February 3, 1988 - Final Edited&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿24&#13;
situation had changed dramatically when he came to the Committee. We had various&#13;
meetings with him. At one point I remember there was a front page story in the Wall&#13;
Street Journal where they raised this question of Chenery's position in the Bank and his&#13;
stock holdings and his board membership.&#13;
Ultimately, the Committee ruled that Chenery could not sit on the board because of his&#13;
position in the Bank. He could not sit on this board. He had to resign, which he ultimately&#13;
did. But Mr. McNamara, who I think had come to the same conclusion before the&#13;
Committee reached its decision, discovered that here was a Committee that had the power&#13;
to decide on something which could greatly embarrass the Bank. And if the Committee.&#13;
had said, Mr. Chenery, yes, you can be a member of this board, there wasn't a damn thing&#13;
that McNamara could have done about it under the rules as they were then set up. And&#13;
this upset him. I never talked to him myself. But the result of this was that he&#13;
immediately had the rules and the composition of the Committee changed and made the&#13;
Committee advisory to the Vice President for Personnel and Administration. And made&#13;
the Vice President for Personnel and Administration an ex officio member of the&#13;
Committee to make sure that the Committee would never reach ...&#13;
Now, as I said we found the way he wanted us to find. And, of course, he had approved&#13;
this long before.&#13;
ZIEGLER: So before that the Committee had binding power.&#13;
SANDBERG: That's right. That's right. But that was then taken away. And this led to,&#13;
again, a major confrontation. I had a major confrontation with Chadenet on this issue&#13;
because I thought this was ridiculous.&#13;
This experience is one of the reasons why the Appeals Committee is also advisory.&#13;
Because McNamara just simply could not live with any group of staff members being&#13;
able to decide on an issue of importance to the Bank against his wishes.&#13;
ZIEGLER: Or potentially against his wishes.&#13;
SANDBERG: Potentially against his wishes. It doesn't show very much trust in the&#13;
judgment of these Bank staff members involved in this. Normally I would have argued,&#13;
maybe I did, but I would have argued that an Appeals Committee of this kind that we&#13;
have in the Bank should be deciding and not advisory. But the fact that it is advisory goes&#13;
back to this experience in the other Committee with the Chenery case and McNamara's&#13;
personality. That's why it is the way it is.&#13;
ZIEGLER: McNamara was somewhat authoritarian in his conduct.&#13;
SANDBERG: Yeah, control was very important to him. And, of course, by giving&#13;
authority to somebody else to reach a binding decision, you lose control.&#13;
Bengt Sandberg&#13;
February 3, 1988 - Final Edited&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿25&#13;
ZIEGLER: The other side of the coin is, what would you like to have done better? Let's&#13;
not make it quite so personal. We can phrase it differently. In the areas that you were&#13;
involved in, what do you think the Staff Association could have done better than it did?&#13;
We can even go all the way back to the beginning in 1972, 1973. You gave quite a full&#13;
account of the issues involved in the Appeals Committee. But are there things that&#13;
retrospectively you might have suggested or advised or even personally done differently&#13;
looking back on it now as opposed to what in fact was done?&#13;
SANDBERG: I dont think so. That's not because I think that everything was perfect. I&#13;
think what distressed me most over the last few years has been the erosion of the status&#13;
and the credibility of the Staff Association both vis-d-vis the management and vis-a-vis&#13;
the staff. In 1986 I remember people telling me that the Staff Association was down to a&#13;
membership of 54 or 55 percent of Bank staff. Now, you know, that's terrible.&#13;
ZIEGLER: It's better now.&#13;
SANDBERG: Yes. Well, that's good. But that was pretty terrible. But I don't know.&#13;
Structurally I don't see that one could really have done anything to ensure greater and&#13;
more continuous support of the Staff Association. I still think that the structure we have is&#13;
in a kind of a formal sense probably as good as it can get if you want to have a structure&#13;
that makes it possible for the Staff Association to represent the vast majority of the staff&#13;
[End Tape 2, Side A]&#13;
[Begin Tape 2, Side B]&#13;
SANDBERG: But the question is how do you inspire and activate the structure, and in&#13;
particular how do you inspire and activate the Delegates, and how do you avoid having&#13;
the Assembly and, more in particular, the Executive Committee, be a playground for&#13;
special narrow interests? I think that some of the uproar--although I guess it didn't&#13;
become all that vocal--over the day care center a couple of years ago may have been&#13;
symptomatic of this, where a lot of people felt that a few people in the Executive&#13;
Committee and the Staff Association had managed to lay their hands on a good piece of&#13;
the dues paid by the membership as a subsidy and that this was done without complete . .&#13;
But how do you activate the Delegates? How do you get Delegates who are really&#13;
concerned what their constituents think? And how do you activate the constituents? As I&#13;
said, the constituents take the Staff Association for granted. They really only have use for&#13;
it when there's a crisis. But it's the responsibility of the Delegates and of the Executive&#13;
Committee to inspire or to maintain this thing so that it is available in case of a crisis.&#13;
And keep it oiled so that it functions in a crisis.&#13;
ZIEGLER: Just following onto that very point, what then should be the role of the Staff&#13;
Association in the Bank? And I'm thinking of this both vis-d-vis management and the&#13;
institution on the one hand and its constituents on the other? The reason I'm asking this&#13;
one is I think a lot of people join the Staff Association--or not join, but get involved in&#13;
Bengt Sandberg&#13;
February 3, 1988 - Final Edited&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿26&#13;
the Staff Association--for very particular reasons. I certainly have my own. And I think a&#13;
lot of the motivation here is colored by the view that you have. What should it be doing?&#13;
What is the nature of its relationship between these two entities, the&#13;
management/institution on the one hand and the staff on the other, the constituents?&#13;
SANDBERG: Well, this may be a little naive. But I've always believed that there is a&#13;
tremendous amount of congruence between the interests of the staff and of the institution.&#13;
Most people who work for the Bank really dont see themselves as being apart from the&#13;
institution. They see themselves as a part of the institution. And in a sense the Bank&#13;
works because of its staff, almost despite its management.&#13;
ZIEGLER: Yes.&#13;
SANDBERG: You know, sometimes you almost have that feeling. That's why you dont&#13;
worry about reorganizations because you know it will work. Because the staff will make&#13;
it work. Whether it's stupid or not they will make it work. But that leads me to the&#13;
conclusion that you're not really talking about--if you look at the interest of the Bank&#13;
staff, the majority of the Bank staff, I dont think that they are interested in or well served&#13;
by confrontation with the management. I think it's a cooperative effort to try to make this&#13;
a better place and a better place to work. I'm prepared to believe that by and large the&#13;
management is still fairly patriarchal. They really feel protective of the staff. They dont&#13;
deliberately try to--you know, they are beset by budget problems and all these other&#13;
things. But it seems to me anyway that it's a cooperative venture for both Management&#13;
and staff to try to make this a better institution.&#13;
Now, the problem with management is that they have no way of really gauging what the&#13;
Bank staff feels and thinks on issues that affect them directly. The hierarchical system&#13;
doesn't work. The suspicion of the Personnel Department is so deeply ingrained that if the&#13;
management goes to the Personnel Department to try to get a feel for the mood of the&#13;
staff on a particular issue there's no way they can get any ...&#13;
ZIEGLER: The attitude survey is perhaps a bit cumbersome.&#13;
SANDBERG: Yes, and the question is of course also of interpretation. So you need--the&#13;
management needs a sounding board to get a response, to get a feel for how things will be&#13;
received. You know, they can make horrible mistakes purely in presentation of some&#13;
things. And they really need to have somebody to talk to who can speak with authority on&#13;
behalf of the staff, but on behalf of all the staff. And the only one that they can do that&#13;
with is the Staff Association.&#13;
Because in the past and even now sometimes you have these edicts going out to all&#13;
directors to hold staff meetings and to get the staff views on something or other. You&#13;
must have been to those staff meetings. They never get any ... They go back and they&#13;
report everybody's happy as a clam. But then if you've been to the staff meeting you&#13;
know that maybe two people who are concerned about the way the director views their&#13;
performance would speak up and say, yes, this is fine. But all the people who were&#13;
Bengt Sandberg&#13;
February 3, 1988 - Final Edited&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿27&#13;
grumbling will just be sitting there and looking at their shoes. This happens around the&#13;
Bank all the time. So that system doesnt work.&#13;
Then they tried, as in the reorganization, task forces and holding meetings and all the rest&#13;
of it. That also doesnt work very well. You do need to have a separate channel of&#13;
communication where people can express their views anonymously and where they can&#13;
be aggregated and where you get the weight of the views of the Bank staff as a whole.&#13;
That is very powerful.&#13;
ZIEGLER: And it's also outside the hierarchical system.&#13;
SANDBERG: That's it exactly. And that doesnt mean that the department managers are&#13;
bad managers or anything of that kind. I think the staff members need to know that there&#13;
is some way in which they can communicate with management without sticking their&#13;
personal neck out in a staff meeting or something of that kind.&#13;
ZIEGLER: That can be an unhappy experience.&#13;
SANDBERG: Yes, that's right. You can meet with your colleagues separately. You can&#13;
instruct your Delegates ex officio who sits in a Delegate Assembly or in the Executive&#13;
Committee. They go to management and, you know, they're not saying that I believe&#13;
department X is being badly run and so on and so forth. But they can say, well, this is the&#13;
view of the staff as expressed through these various means. And I'm only the messenger.&#13;
I think staff needs that. As I said, when there's a crisis, the frustration builds up. So it's&#13;
like the management also needs the Staff Association because the Staff Association can&#13;
act as a lightening rod for this sort of thing. So instead of everybody just being generally&#13;
mad you can channel things in a constructive discussion between the two. But neither&#13;
party is or should be interested in confrontation. That I dont believe. And I think that any&#13;
time that you try to coerce the management through strikes or sit downs or this sort of&#13;
thing, they're just not going to listen.&#13;
ZIEGLER: Is there any particular advice that you would leave for your successors? Or&#13;
anything we haven't covered? Let's put it that way. Anything we haven't covered that you&#13;
might like to incorporate here?&#13;
SANDBERG: I can't think of anything other than you know I come back to this question&#13;
of communication. That really is the key.&#13;
ZIEGLER: Communication.&#13;
SANDBERG: Communication. You know, the key problem for the Executive&#13;
Committee is to crank this machine up and get it to work and keep it oiled. Except that it&#13;
may be frustrating for long periods of time. But the machine better be in working order.&#13;
Bengt Sandberg&#13;
February 3, 1988 - Final Edited&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿28&#13;
ZIEGLER: Well, thank you very much. This has been a very constructive and&#13;
informative interview. And I appreciate you participating in this special project with the&#13;
Staff Association.&#13;
[End Tape 2, Side B]&#13;
[End of interview]&#13;
Bengt Sandberg&#13;
February 3, 1988 - Final Edited&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="23016484">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1988/02/23016484/transcript-oral-history-interview-bengt-sandberg-held-february-3-1988
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1988/02/23016484/transcript-oral-history-interview-bengt-sandberg-held-february-3-1988</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1988/02/23016484/transcript-oral-history-interview-bengt-sandberg-held-february-3-1988</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2014-12-12T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2014-12-12T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <docm_id>090224b082c2593f</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b082c2593f</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2014/12/12/000406484_20141212143030/Rendered/INDEX/931590TSCP0San0385395B00PUBLIC00rev.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2014/12/12/000406484_20141212143030/Rendered/PDF/931590TSCP0San0385395B00PUBLIC00rev.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2014-12-12T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1988-02-03T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Transcript of oral history interview with
            Bengt Sandberg held on February 3, 1988
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            On February 3, 1988 Bengt Sandberg was
            interviewed on behalf of the World Bank Group Archives oral
            history program by Charles Ziegler in Washington, D.C.  Mr.
            Sandberg was a founding member of the Staff Association.  In
            his interview he discusses the early days of the Staff
            Association.  He also discusses two projects he was involved
            in- allowing staff access to their personnel files and the
            ability for staff to get management decisions reviewed.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Transcript of oral history interview with
            Bengt Sandberg held on February 3, 1988
        </docna>
        <display_title>Transcript of oral history
            interview with Bengt Sandberg held on February 3, 1988</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/1988/02/23016484/transcript-oral-history-interview-bengt-sandberg-held-february-3-1988</listing_relative_url>
        <majdocty>Board Documents</majdocty>
        <docty>Transcript</docty>
        <count>World</count>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000406484_20141212143030</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <owner>Knowledge &amp; Information Services (ITSKI)</owner>
        <colti>World Bank Group Archives oral history program</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <repnb>93159</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>PPP</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public-Private Partnerships</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public-Private Partnerships (PPP)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Alternative Sentencing Options</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community based Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Correctional Services and Facilities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corrections</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime and Society</ml:concept><ml:concept>Defense Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Detention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enforcement Policies and Oversight Mechanism</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigative Task Force Police</ml:concept><ml:concept>Juvenile Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Law Enforcement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Offender Reintegration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Administration and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Problem solving Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Prosecution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Restorative Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Therapeutic Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Assistance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim-Offender Mediation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Policy Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Policy Formulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Policy Implementation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Productivity-Led Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Asset Recovery</ml:concept><ml:concept>Immunity Provisions and Protections</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pensions &amp; Retirement Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government Performance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Managing for Results</ml:concept><ml:concept>Outcomes Based Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Drivers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Results Based Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Checks on Executive Power</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen User Satisfaction Survey</ml:concept><ml:concept>Independent Commissions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ombudsmen</ml:concept><ml:concept>Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Parliament</ml:concept><ml:concept>Procurement Complaints Review Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supreme Audit Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Criminal Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Working Hours</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pipelines</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inflation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pensions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Accountability Mechanisms</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>