<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>                                                                     93161 v2&#13;
&#13;
                Summary of Oral History Transcript&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             Cope, Sydney R.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Interview conducted by Professor Robert W. Oliver, Brookings&#13;
Institution, on 1961-08-09&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Cope covers briefly his background prior to joining the Bank's&#13;
Loan Department in December 1947 at the invitation of then assistant&#13;
director, Walter Hill, to serve in its Northwest European Division.&#13;
This was at a time when the Marshall Plan had just been formulated&#13;
[June'47 and introduced in April '48] and the Bank was uncertain as to&#13;
how it would adjust its operations. Policies were being formulated&#13;
and, in 1948, tentative steps were being taken towards a policy of&#13;
development lending. The Research Department was renamed the Economics&#13;
Department and Cope talks of overlapping between the work of the&#13;
Economics and Loan Departments and its effect on staff.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Also, policy issues concerning assessment of creditworthiness of&#13;
a country at a time when most major currencies of the world, apart&#13;
from the U.S. dollar, were inconvertible and saddled with exchange&#13;
restrictions common among the principal trading nations. He elaborates&#13;
on the implications of judging projects in terms of only their direct&#13;
impact on the foreign exchange earnings of a country as in the first&#13;
loan to Yugoslavia, and briefly talks of the gradual release of the&#13;
18-percent subscription funds and the relation to international&#13;
competitive bidding.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Cope addresses the policy problems involved in the Bank's lending&#13;
for local expenditure, the Articles of Agreements being obscure on the&#13;
matter and P.N. Rosenstein-Rodan--then on the economic staff--&#13;
advocating the Bank take advantage of the "exceptional circumstances"&#13;
provision. He continues with the Bank's attitude toward local&#13;
&amp;#12;expenditure financing and the many discussions this prompted over the&#13;
years including impact lending. He elaborates on a series of related&#13;
loans undertaken by the Bank in the 1950s in the light of these&#13;
discussions some of which included: loans to Belgium and the Belgian&#13;
Congo in 1951 for $70 million, loans to the Italian Cassa per il&#13;
Mezzogiorno in 1951 and 1954 for $20 million, as well as loans to&#13;
Australia totaling $308.5 million between 1951 and 1957; carried out&#13;
as Australia's economy was considered by the Bank to be mature,&#13;
however, these were subsequently seen as a precedent by other&#13;
prospective borrowers. In stressing the importance of the policy of&#13;
financing projects, Cope covers various aspects of project/program&#13;
approach including stabilization loans, general-purpose loans,&#13;
specific loans with part of the Bank's emphasis directed at satisfying&#13;
market confidence, as well as the disbursement of loans.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Cope resumes discussing the negotiations for the release of the&#13;
18 percent subscription funds by member countries, the difficulties&#13;
encountered in obtaining the release and Mr. Black's persistent&#13;
efforts. The Bank's interpretation of the Articles of Agreement and&#13;
the 18 percent subscription release as intended to provide it with&#13;
usable funds. Various phases of the 18 percent release, Cope's&#13;
involvement and the relatively successful drive of 1957 with most, not&#13;
all, of the remaining countries considered unable to make the release.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Cope concludes in commenting on the staffing changes during the&#13;
McCloy presidency ('47-'49) between the Economics and Loan Departments&#13;
as due to the inevitability of trial and error when starting something&#13;
new such as the World Bank.&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="23024060">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1961/08/23024060/transcript-oral-history-interview-sydney-cope-held-august-9-1961-vol-2-summary
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1961/08/23024060/transcript-oral-history-interview-sydney-cope-held-august-9-1961-vol-2-summary</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1961/08/23024060/transcript-oral-history-interview-sydney-cope-held-august-9-1961-vol-2-summary</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2014-12-15T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2014-12-15T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2014/12/15/000333037_20141215032146/Rendered/INDEX/931610v20TSCP000Summary0Sydney0Cope.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2014/12/15/000333037_20141215032146/Rendered/PDF/931610v20TSCP000Summary0Sydney0Cope.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2014-12-15T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1961-08-09T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>2</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>2</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Transcript of oral history interview with
            Sydney Cope held on August 9, 1961
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            In August 9 1961, Sydney Cop was
            interviewed on behalf of the World Bank Group Archives oral
            history program by Robert Oliver. Cope covers briefly his
            background prior to joining the Bank's Loan Department
            in December 1947 at the invitation of then assistant
            director, Walter Hill, to serve in its Northwest European
            Division. This was at a time when the Marshall Plan had just
            been formulated [June'47 and introduced in April
            '48] and the Bank was uncertain as to how it would
            adjust its operations. Policies were being formulated and,
            in 1948, tentative steps were being taken towards a policy
            of development lending. The Research Department was renamed
            the Economics Department and Cope talks of overlapping
            between the work of the Economics and Loan Departments and
            its effect on staff. Also, policy issues concerning
            assessment of creditworthiness of a country at a time when
            most major currencies of the world, apart from the U.S.
            dollar, were inconvertible and saddled with exchange
            restrictions common among the principal trading nations. He
            elaborates on the implications of judging projects in terms
            of only their direct impact on the foreign exchange earnings
            of a country as in the first loan to Yugoslavia, and briefly
            talks of the gradual release of the 18-percent subscription
            funds and the relation to international competitive bidding.
            Cope concludes in commenting on the staffing changes during
            the McCloy presidency (47-49) between the Economics and Loan
            Departments as due to the inevitability of trial and error
            when starting something new such as the World Bank.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Summary
        </docna>
        <display_title>Transcript of oral history
            interview with Sydney Cope held on August 9, 1961 (Vol. 2) : Summary</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/1961/08/23024060/transcript-oral-history-interview-sydney-cope-held-august-9-1961-vol-2-summary</listing_relative_url>
        <topic>Debt Management m1327211 451,Microfinance m1327227 367,Access to Finance m1327464 1249,Debt m1326503 450,Debt Funds m1327683 1748</topic>
        <docty>Transcript</docty>
        <subtopic>Microfinance,Public Sector Corruption &amp;
            Anticorruption Measures,Financial Intermediation,Bankruptcy and Resolution of Financial Distress,Debt Markets</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Public Sector Development,Finance and Financial Sector Development</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000333037_20141215032146</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>World Bank Group Archives oral history program</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Public Sector Development,Finance and Financial Sector Development</historic_topic>
        <topicv3>Debt Management m1327211 451,Microfinance m1327227 367,Access to Finance m1327464 1249,Debt m1326503 450,Debt Funds m1327683 1748</topicv3>
        <majdocty>Board Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            competitive bidding, creditworthiness,
            disbursement, Economics, expenditure, foreign exchange,
            Loan, market confidence, negotiations, prospective
            borrowers, trading, trial
        </keywd>
        <owner>Knowledge &amp; Information Services (ITSKI)</owner>
        <repnb>93161</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>