<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>                                                    93163&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
DECLASSIFIED&#13;
  APR 02 2012&#13;
WBO ARCHIVES&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                THE WORLD BANK GROUP ARCHIVES&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    ORAL HISTORY PROGRAM&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     Transcript of interview with&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                        W. DAVID HOPPER&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                      April 2 and May 12, 2004&#13;
                         Washington, D.C.&#13;
&#13;
                     Interview by: Kelly Feltault&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                    1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         Session 1&#13;
                                       April 2, 2004&#13;
                                      Washington, D.C.&#13;
&#13;
[Begin Tape 1, Side A]&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: I'm David Hopper, or William David Hopper, to be entirely formal. I grew up in a&#13;
family where you call everybody by their second name rather than the first name. Born on&#13;
February 22 nd , 1927. Today is April the 2nd , 2004. I was born in Ottawa, Canada, and I'm still a&#13;
Canadian.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: You never became a U.S. citizen?&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: No. I've been a long-term permanent resident of the United States. Someday I'll&#13;
get around to citizenship, but ...&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: Okay. It looks like we're registering just fine.&#13;
&#13;
So today what I thought we'd do is start with some of the background information on you and&#13;
move into your work in India in the '60s and the [Bernard R.] Bell Mission and then up through&#13;
the '70s. Then I thought we'd possibly stop there, and then the second interview we would move&#13;
into your work.&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: Do you want to shut that off just for a minute, and I'll introduce you, too?&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: Sure. Okay.&#13;
&#13;
[Interruption1&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: So you said you were born in Ottawa.&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: Canada.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: Canada. And what were your parents' names and their occupations?&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: My father was Wilbert Clayton Hopper, called Bert. My mother was Eva Louella&#13;
Hill, the maiden name. My father was an agriculturalist, first degree in agriculture, and then he&#13;
moved to do his master's in agronomy and his Ph.D. at Cornell [University] in agricultural&#13;
economics. I spent my first years of my life--they went down to Ithaca, New York, and Cornell&#13;
when I was one and a half. He then joined the faculty at Cornell and started to work for USDA&#13;
[U.S. Department of Agriculture], returned to Canada in 1938. My mother was a contralto&#13;
soloist and then became very active in building houses and real estate. My father died in 1965.&#13;
My mother died in 1986. My father had ALS, Lou Gehrig's disease, when he died. They're&#13;
buried in a family burial plot up in Ottawa.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        W. David Hopper&#13;
                              April 2 and May 12, 2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                  2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
My father, the last years in his life, was, worked in Australia and then was high commissioner--&#13;
which is the equivalent of ambassador in the British Commonwealth system--high commissioner&#13;
to New Zealand and then came down here to Washington and spent the last ten years of his&#13;
activity in Washington at the Canadian embassy.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: Okay. So that would have been '55 through '65?&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: This was--no. He retired in '59 from the Canadian foreign service.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAUL T: Okay. Well, it's interesting: [know that you also went to Cornell and got your&#13;
Ph.D. in agricultural economics.&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: And cultural anthropology.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: So was it a double?&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: It was a double major.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAUL T: Double major. Let me ask you how much your father influenced you on going&#13;
into that, that field.&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: A bit, but not--I grew up playing around with white rats, earning money producing&#13;
white rats down in the basement, which was a very stinky business.&#13;
&#13;
FEL TAULT: And what were the rats for?&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: I sold them to the National Research Council. They were genetically pure lines, and&#13;
the National Research Council bought them at fifty cents a rat, which was a lot of money in those&#13;
days, which I then invested in radios. I was a radio amateur. I never got on the air because the&#13;
war broke out in 1939 in Canada, and 1 was banned. But I had a deep interest in radios and was&#13;
determined to be a radio engineer. I spent some time at the edge of the Canadian artillery and so&#13;
on.&#13;
&#13;
But when the German--the Second World War kind of broke up, I found I was out of high school&#13;
without really a proper high school diploma. I went to work in Toronto for a pollster outfit. I&#13;
got interested in the fact that one of the polls I had to do was down in the wine growing area, the&#13;
Niagara escarpment, which creates Niagara Falls. It's a big rock rise at the end of Lake Ontario,&#13;
and I found myself involved in what they could do with the land, the farm areas, orchard areas,&#13;
under the Niagara escarpment. Got interested in that, decided that the firm 1 was with was&#13;
unlikely to survive (I was wrong), but I didn't--and pressure from family, you know: "Go get&#13;
yourself a degree somewhere." And so 1 went to--tried Ontario Agricultural College, where my&#13;
father graduated from back in 1920. And they were very kind, but I wasn't interested in the&#13;
course work. I found ..&#13;
&#13;
FEL TAULT: Why not?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        W. David Hopper&#13;
                              April 2 and May 12, 2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                       3&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: There wasn't enough science in it. It was--you moved in and you studied bee-&#13;
keeping and you studied vegetable growing and you studied this and you studied that. But my&#13;
radio things had put me--during my period in high school, for example, the physics teacher in&#13;
high school refused to teach anything on electronics if I was sitting in the classroom. I taught it.&#13;
This was part of it.&#13;
&#13;
But I went to McGill University. I took a B.S.C. in agriculture. But the first two years in that is&#13;
physics, mathematics, chemistry, and so on. I found this very, very suitable. And the last two&#13;
years I studied economics and agricultural economics. Then I worked at Cornell one summer. I&#13;
worked in Saskatchewan another summer. I went to different places. And I went back to&#13;
Cornell to do a Ph.D.--well, to do my master's degree, actually.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: So you were only thinking master's at that time?&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: I was only thinking master's at that time. It was 1950. And I got assigned to milk&#13;
marketing, and I worked in New York. I worked in New York one summer for milk marketing.&#13;
Another summer I toured Europe on behalf ofthe--Iooking at the activities ofthe reconstruction&#13;
of Europe. Was down in Italy, was impressed with the north Italians, had an Italian person who&#13;
was working with me or traveling with me. The north was booming, Milan, et cetera, and as we&#13;
moved south in Italy, it was, kept getting poorer and poorer. I had never seen such poverty as I&#13;
saw in Naples and this kind of thing.&#13;
&#13;
And we were sitting in a cafe in Palermo down in Sicily, and I said to Luigi, "I don't understand&#13;
this. The north: booming economically. Down here: nothing. Same country, same language,&#13;
same history. What's the problem?"&#13;
&#13;
He said, "It's simple, it's simple. In the north you have to have money to get power. Down here&#13;
you have to have power to get money." This was the home of the Mafia and so on. And that&#13;
kind of stuck in my mind for some time.&#13;
&#13;
I went to Cornell. This had occurred before I got to Cornell; it was in '49. I went to Cornell and&#13;
got into milk marketing and decided that that isn't really what I wanted to do. And in the course&#13;
of this, I worked with a man by the name of Forrest [Frosty] Hill, who was the head of ag&#13;
economics at Cornell, one of my mentors, and he asked me what I thought was the most&#13;
important thing in agriculture, global agriculture, over the course of the next twenty years. I said&#13;
I didn't know. So he sent me offto read Frank Notestein, who was a demographer at Princeton&#13;
[University] and so on. And it was quite clear that the demographers had taken a look at this.&#13;
Notestein had, particularly, had taken a look at what occurred in our society, Western culture, as&#13;
medicine improved and as our ability to handle things like smallpox and so on increased, and as&#13;
incomes increased, that the numbers of children born into families was increasing and there was&#13;
a population expansion, that birth issues before that, were pretty much forty per thousand for&#13;
women/children and death rates were about forty per thousand, and we had a stability. Then&#13;
suddenly death rates began to drop, but birth rates were culturally determined, and they stayed&#13;
high, up at the forty per thousand, and you had a population expansion. And what was now clear&#13;
was that the medical capabilities, our capabilities to handle death rates, was moving to the&#13;
developing countries increasingly, and birth rates were culturally determined and remained high,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        W. David Hopper&#13;
                              April 2 and May 12, 2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                    4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
and that you're going to have a major expansion and a demographic transition before the birth&#13;
rates would begin to drop.&#13;
&#13;
One of the places that had always interested me as a kid and so on, I used to read about India,&#13;
British India. This seemed to apply to all of this, so I decided, in a discussion with Hill, to drop&#13;
my milk marketing and pursue to a master's degree and to move over into taking a look at some&#13;
other things. I went down and studied politics, political science, anthropology, did some work in&#13;
law and slopped around the campus a bit.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: So it was very multi-disciplinary.&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: It was a multi-disciplinary search. And at the end of six months, I came and began&#13;
to discuss all of this again with Hill. We decided that cultural anthropology and agricultural&#13;
economics would mix. I did some work in soils, and I did some work in some other areas.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAUL T: Now let me just interrupt you here for one second. It's interesting because&#13;
economics and anthropology have not always been the best of friends as disciplines.&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: I'll tell you about that in a minute. All right?&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: Okay. Good.&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: With anthropology, I went out and worked among the Navajo Indians and the&#13;
Papago Indians out in the West and took a look at the work that Ruth Benedict and a series of&#13;
others were doing in anthropology and found myself kind of deeply engrossed in anthropology.&#13;
The decision was made that I should not do a master's degree but go directly for a Ph.D., and I&#13;
got a Social Science Research Council grant to go live in India.&#13;
&#13;
So I went and lived in a Village. There was a man from this village who was a student at Cornell,&#13;
and it was his village I went to. The anthropology department of Cornell had a substantial grant&#13;
from the Social Science Research Council and from other sources to do work in Peru and in .&#13;
Thailand and in India. So I had those connections. And I went off and lived in this village in&#13;
India, a remote part of India, not--it's an agricultural part. It's close to Benares. I was thirty&#13;
miles from Benares and so on.&#13;
&#13;
FEL TAUL T: Can you remember the name of it?&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: Oh, yeah, the village was called Senapur. It was in Kerakat tehsil and Jaunpur&#13;
district. Jaunpur was an old Muslim area, but this was a Hindu village. And it was a very&#13;
interesting thing. It was in the interior. It was four miles to the nearest road and six miles to the&#13;
nearest market town. I lived there for two years. I was married and had my first wife. She was&#13;
a nurse, so I was known as Dr. Sabb's [phonetic] husband because she kind of tended the people.&#13;
&#13;
I struggled with what I was finding, trying to relate culture and agriculture. I did some farming,&#13;
didn't know anything about rice but grew wheat. My first year growing wheat, I got it from the&#13;
best farmer in the village, used his animals. I lived in a house, and there's a connection between&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        W. David Hopper&#13;
                              April 2 and May 12,2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                        5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
the workers and the landlords, the purjans and the jajmans. The purjans connected with my&#13;
house did the work but [used] his animals, and I planted wheat. I had grown--my grandfather&#13;
was a farmer and so on, so I had grown up partly on a farm. I knew what all this was about, and&#13;
I did wheat. The understanding was that he was growing it in a field right beside mine, small&#13;
plots, and if! got a good yield, then he would take my wheat, and that was that. If! didn't make&#13;
at least what he got, then I'd pay him the difference. And the first year I paid him quite a bit. I&#13;
discovered that you plant wheat when it's warm in India, and then you wait until the ground&#13;
cools down enough. In Canada you plant wheat after the ground warms up enough. As my&#13;
grandfather said, "You have to feel it through the soles of your feet," and I didn't feel it properly.&#13;
&#13;
I then visited every research station across north India, all the agricultural research stations, and&#13;
found that they were not getting nearly the yield my farmer was getting.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: Why was that?&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: Just the lack of-I mean, the research community was over here and they worked&#13;
amongst themselves and so on. They didn't bother looking out what was going on among the&#13;
agriculturalists. And I say the best farmer in the village. Look, there were farmers who were&#13;
making a half, some of them less than a half, of the yields he was getting. He was just a very,&#13;
very competent guy. The top twenty percent of the farmers were doing better than the&#13;
agricultural research stations were. I wrote Hill about this, and we debated it back and forth.&#13;
And I did some work otherwise.&#13;
&#13;
My father, I told you, was in the foreign service. The High Commissioner to India, a man by the&#13;
name of Escott Reid, was a good friend of my father's. He was a former professor at University&#13;
of Toronto. During the Second World War, there was quite a number of these people from&#13;
Toronto and many academic institutions who moved into Ottawa as part of the crew of building&#13;
the Canadian participation in the Second World War or World War II.&#13;
&#13;
Escott was there, and I visited Escott in Delhi, at both his request and per my father's suggestion:&#13;
"You ought to go down and say hello to Escott." So I did. Escott--I went down dressed in&#13;
basically Indian clothes, and Escott suggested that he'd like to give me a lunch for me, a whole&#13;
lunch for me. I went to lunch, and Pandit [Jawahadal] Nehru was at the lunch and S. K. Dube,&#13;
who was head of community development, was at the lunch, and a series of other people. Nehru&#13;
suggested--he was prime minister--Nehru suggested that I go visit his daughter in Allahabad. I&#13;
was seventy miles from Allahabad, and there's a big agricultural institute at Allahabad that was&#13;
founded by the churches here, particularly the Methodist and Presbyterian here in the United&#13;
States.&#13;
&#13;
I went down to Allahabad. I bought a motor bike and kind of traveled around. I was only twenty&#13;
miles from Sarnath, where Buddha preached his first sermon. I spent some time over there,&#13;
beautiful old temples. It was the Ashokan capital back in 2000 BC or 250 BC. I spent time&#13;
there. I spent a good deal of time in Benares. I went down every month and cashed some money&#13;
and brought back medicine for my wife and other things and so on. Benares is a Hindu town,&#13;
and I got to know Benares India University and so on.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         W. David Hopper&#13;
                               April 2 and May 12, 2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                   6&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
And I met Mrs. [Indira] Gandhi, before she was president of the Congress Party, at Nehru's&#13;
suggestion, at her home in Allahabad. That was the family home, Nehru's home, her father's. I&#13;
then--periodically I'd go.&#13;
&#13;
Hill wrote me a letter to say that a man by the name of Art [Arthur T.] Mosher was coming,&#13;
former director at Allahabad, a [University of] Chicago graduate in agricultural economics but&#13;
before that an agriculturalist from University of Illinois. But he had been director of the&#13;
Allahabad Agricultural Institute for many years. So I biked down to Allahabad to see Mosher.&#13;
Mosher and I found that we were great, great--I mean, I'd been six months in the village and I&#13;
hadn't sorted anything out. It was just culture and so on. Mosher had also done a Ph.D. at&#13;
Chicago, focused on this issue of the villages in India and agriculture and so on, not from the&#13;
demographic point of view, which was my main concern, but as how do you feed the people.&#13;
&#13;
Mosher and I took a trip and sat in the back of a truck while they drove up to Lucknow, which is&#13;
the capital of Uttar Pradesh. And we sat back there and talked all the way up to Lucknow, which&#13;
is about a five-hour drive. They did what they had to do, and then we drove back--or were&#13;
driven back by the others from the Institute but sat in the back of the truck and talked for another&#13;
five hours. Mosher just really was the light in sorting out the difference between economics and&#13;
anthropology.&#13;
&#13;
Now, this comes back to the story, because when I gave my Ph.D. thesis, the anthropologists at&#13;
the table were concerned that I was talking about economic man too much in this.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: In the sense of Adam Smith's ...&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: In the sense of Adam Smith's and in the sense of [David] Ricardo and so on and so&#13;
forth and the others, that there is an economic response that's here. And the anthropologists&#13;
were concerned that there wasn't enough culture, that I really didn't spend the time on the&#13;
culture. I did. I did both in the thesis, but there was an economic trend running through it as&#13;
well as a cultural trend.&#13;
&#13;
Example: storage of grain. They had primitive storage. This was a mud village. It was&#13;
basically mud houses. There were a few--a couple, three, four, five, six brick houses, but this&#13;
was because they had income from outside. People wanted our glass bottles that we finished.&#13;
They would break them and they would put the glass into the mud that was around the grain&#13;
storages, so that if the rats came at it, they would get their paws to bleed and so on and they&#13;
would no longer try to--they would drill holes in this thing that held the grain. You had grain&#13;
storages. They were primitive, yes. Why did you have grain storage? I mean, why not sell it?&#13;
Well, number one, you had drought potential, so you had to carry it through. Number two, if you&#13;
had a marriage, you wanted to serve the baraal, the male, the groups that came along with the&#13;
groom to be married to the local woman--you wanted to feed them last year's grain because you&#13;
wanted to make it quite clear that you were sufficiently affluent to be able to provide your&#13;
daughter and receive him as a son-in-law by serving last year's grain because you had enough&#13;
grain to do this. So all of this was part of the cultural element of it.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        W. David Hopper&#13;
                              April 2 and May 12,2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                  7&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
There was a guy digging a well. I wanted him to go down the--India was advertising. I had a&#13;
radio, all-India radio, a radio that was fixed-tuned to the local radio stations. I had a guy from&#13;
the local town come in and ask me if I could keep my canned goods for him because we did use&#13;
some cans, and he heard that we had, we used a toilet. Now, the toilet's another story, but the--it&#13;
was in this house, and I said yes. Well, he said, the toilet paper comes wrapped in a cardboard&#13;
roll. I said yes. He'd like me to save those for him because he was wrapping--he was in the&#13;
market town six miles away--he was wrapping these and creating what is known in the radio&#13;
trade as a tank circuit. Well, I knew immediately what it was. This is a variable condenser and a&#13;
coil, and you loop it through and you get different frequencies than you have, and this is how you&#13;
adjust the frequency on a radio. And what he wanted to do was to go around to the villages&#13;
where you had this all-India radio battery-driven machine, which got only one station, namely,&#13;
India station, but he wanted to convert it so that they could listen to a short-wave station that&#13;
came in from Ceylon, Radio Ceylon, which all India listened to because it's sort of movie music&#13;
and so on. But on the India radio station, what you got were deadly, deadly speeches and&#13;
discussions of ...&#13;
&#13;
FELTAUL T: Government type.&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: That's right, of how to do this and how to do that. But one of the things they wanted&#13;
to do was, when you dug a well, make sure that you put a cement wall around the well down&#13;
through the first aquifer that came in because everybody used the fields. I was unique in that the&#13;
villagers built a little septic tank and a toilet for me, and you flushed it with a bucket, because&#13;
they didn't want my wife exposed to--we were the pink race, and sitting out in the fields doing&#13;
your morning duties and so on was not what they felt that she ought to have. So we flushed it&#13;
with a bucket and out it went. But the upper aquifer had a lot of human waste on it, particularly&#13;
on the fields around the village, because that was a good manure and this is what you did.&#13;
&#13;
But I said to this guy that, you know, I was digging a well, and I said, "Let's put the wall around&#13;
it like the government radio was saying you ought to do, a cement wall so that you got it from&#13;
the second aquifer." In other words, the water had been filtered a little more and so on so some&#13;
of this stuff came into it.&#13;
&#13;
Now, the Indian at that time really didn't believe-I mean, diseases (malaria, et cetera) were&#13;
caused by bhoots. These were old crone women who paddled the fields at night. They walked in&#13;
translucent garments, and their feet were pointed backwards. And if you saw one on the path,&#13;
you better get off fast because she'd latch onto you and then you'd bring her home, latched onto&#13;
you. Then she'd sit at the head of the bed--not so that you could see her--but she just sat at the&#13;
head of the bed, and you had malaria. You got your illnesses. And so this was the belief.&#13;
&#13;
I said to him, "You've got to build your cement wall."&#13;
&#13;
He said, "Why?"&#13;
&#13;
And I told him about the germs in the aquifers and so on.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        W. David Hopper&#13;
                              April 2 and May 12,2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                    8&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
He looked at me, and he said finally, "Hopper, you believe in the germ theory of disease?" in&#13;
effect. I mean, it was in Bhojpuri, which is the local dialect.&#13;
&#13;
And I said, "Yes, I do."&#13;
&#13;
He said, "Have you ever seen a germ?"&#13;
&#13;
Now, there's no point in getting into microscopes and so on and so forth and wee beasties and&#13;
the rest of it. I said, "Well, no."&#13;
&#13;
He said, "Aha!" He said, "I've seen a bhoot." But he did put in a cement wall. [Laughter]&#13;
&#13;
Another farmer, who in discussing this I was saying about using some fertilizer, and he said,&#13;
"Well, is it the right thing to do?"&#13;
&#13;
I said, "What do you mean by the right thing to do?"&#13;
&#13;
He said, "You know, is this what God would have told"--not God but one of the incarnations of&#13;
God, Lord Krishna--"told to the charioteer," in a very, very long Hindu poem, several thousand&#13;
verses. And the charioteer--the Hindus at that time believed that you started battle at sunrise and&#13;
stopped at sunset. You cleared the battlefield and so on and so forth, and the next day it was the&#13;
other man's turn to be the attacker and you would be the defender, and the lord was out there&#13;
ready to move his troops, and he just didn't do it and he didn't do it, and the charioteer turned to&#13;
him and said, "Why are you not moving?" He said, "Well, because is this really worth it, all the&#13;
blood and the death and so on and so forth?" The charioteer more or less said--and the charioteer&#13;
was an impersonation of Lord Krishna--the charioteer said, "That's my problem. I'm God. You&#13;
just do it. And the right thing to do is to bring those troops together." And that's what was done.&#13;
&#13;
So the old farmer tells me, "Is using fertilizer the right thing to do?"&#13;
&#13;
1 discussed it with him and so on and so forth. 1 said I really didn't know in Lord Krishna's&#13;
terms whether it was the right thing to do.&#13;
&#13;
He said, "Well, I'd have to sort that out."&#13;
&#13;
I said, "Well, you know, it will make a big difference in terms of your yield."&#13;
&#13;
We talked about that, and he finally looked at me and said, "You know, I'm an imperfect man.&#13;
I'm an imperfect man." He said, "I really want to do the right things, but then you come along&#13;
and tell me this might be a way to increase yield. 1 don't know whether that's the right thing to&#13;
do or not." He said, "It sounds like a good idea." [Laughter]&#13;
&#13;
So it was this kind of balance between culture and economic man.&#13;
&#13;
FEL TAULT: Economic man is also, you know, feeding a few more people.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                          W. David Hopper&#13;
                               April 2 and May 12, 2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                     9&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: Feeding a few more people and so on and so forth.&#13;
&#13;
This came up at my Ph.D. thesis. Mosher was on my committee now. He was on the faculty at&#13;
Cornell. And the anthropologists had some questions as to whether that I really hadn't done the&#13;
proper thing on the culture side. And the economists at my table--because it was agricultural&#13;
economics as my mother major and economics as my minor--the economists at the table were&#13;
saying, well, I found too much culture. [Laughter] And Mosher kind of got into it and said,&#13;
"Well, Dave, what you're really saying is that there's a balance between culture."&#13;
&#13;
I said, "Yes."&#13;
&#13;
And the anthropologists said, "But that's not adequate. I mean, it's got to be culturally focused."&#13;
&#13;
Mosher took on my side with this balance. The economists kind of lined up because they were&#13;
unhappy with the culture components in it. Mosher kind of took them on, and it was an hour&#13;
debate, which I was out of. The decision was finally made, "Well, okay. All right, we'll give&#13;
him the degree. " [Laughter] So there you are.&#13;
&#13;
It's that balance that was there, and that balance I brought pretty much to what I do. I take a&#13;
look--you go down through the Bell Mission report, and you'll find I wrote several of the papers&#13;
in it. [Sir John] Crawford--I wrote with Crawford. Crawford did the main draft for the&#13;
agricultural section. It has been a balance that I've sought between the culture element, the way&#13;
this is evolving, and the economic element.&#13;
&#13;
You'll find that I had problems with the Swadeshi movement in India, which is "let's build&#13;
everything at home and not rely on the outside" and so on, and "if we didn't invent it ourselves&#13;
or patent it ourselves, then we don't want it," et cetera, that kind of dominates a good deal of&#13;
even Hinduism today, the VHP [Vishwa Hindu Parishad] and the shrine of Babri Masjid and BJP&#13;
[Bharatiya Janata Party] government in India. It's a very difficult thing that India had to struggle&#13;
with, and at the Bank and in Delhi when I was a vidyarti or a student in this thing, I was&#13;
struggling with just that, that set of issues. It was Mosher who kind of defended me, but it was&#13;
Mosher who clarified it.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: Let me back up and ask you just some clarifying questions. Okay, so who at&#13;
Cornell was in the anthropology department at that time?&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: Ah. A man by the name of Morris Opler was the--Opler, O-P-L-E-R. He was the&#13;
anthropologist who was most deeply involved in India. Opler and I battled whenever he came&#13;
out to India because I was not doing what he wanted to do. I wasn't chasing the Brahmins&#13;
around trying to find out what they were doing and, well, renting and so on and so forth. I was&#13;
out in the field looking at soil types. I analyzed the whole ofthe soils in the village and got maps&#13;
made and so on and so forth of the village plots and what the [inaudible] were looking after. He&#13;
just was not--he didn't feel I was being an anthropologist.&#13;
&#13;
When I returned to Cornell after I left the village--I was in the village about two years. I got&#13;
there in September of 1953, and I left when it began to get hot in July of '55. I spent the better&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        W. David Hopper&#13;
                              April 2 and May 12, 2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                   10&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
part of a month over at the Maharaja of Benares, at his place doing some work that he wanted&#13;
done but really organizing my notes and getting ready to go home. It took about eleven trunks to&#13;
come back with the paper that I had because I did huge amounts of questionnaire work in the&#13;
village: economics, what were they doing, what were their labor relations, and so on. I wrote&#13;
several articles while I was there on this.&#13;
&#13;
The return back, and went back to Cornell, and Opler and I met, and he told me that he found my&#13;
work interesting but not--it wasn't anthropology.&#13;
&#13;
I went to the head of the anthropology department and said, "Look, I've put a fair amount of&#13;
money into this or a fair amount of work into this."&#13;
&#13;
He said he understood Opler's problems. He said, "We'll change you." So he changed me over&#13;
to a man who was working at that time in Peru and who had been an anthropologist in Brazil&#13;
when he was young, did his Ph.D. on a tribal group in Brazil that had never really been studied&#13;
and so on. He was quite an amazing guy. But they needed somebody who had expertise on&#13;
India, and Mosher was fortunately on the faculty then. So I got Art Mosher to come in on my&#13;
committee. And that was the mixture. Qpler opposed it all the way through.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: He remained on the committee then?&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: No, no. He did not. He was dropped. But the other guy was very, very&#13;
understanding and so on. That was how the anthropologist played out.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: Was he expecting you to do obviously some structuralist ...&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: No. What he was interested in was, quote, "the disappearing values in the society."&#13;
There was changes occurring. They had built a school back in 1865. After the mutiny, there'd&#13;
been a meeting ofthe--in 1857-there'd been a--British troops had come in and had disrupted a&#13;
wedding party that was out on the road four miles away from this village. The village is&#13;
Senapur, which means "the Place of the Army." And it was settled back in the 17th century, mid-&#13;
I i h century, by a family, a large family group, that came in, and that was their thing, because the&#13;
Dacoits or the tribals, et cetera, were all outsiders. This was where they did, and they built a&#13;
community that moved around and so on. But that's where the main group were. This village&#13;
was, had that main group in it, six Bhatis [phonetic] or six tribal families, if you want--related&#13;
but nevertheless independent. So the village was important.&#13;
&#13;
The British came back after this battle of the troops. These were sepoys, primarily, Indian troops&#13;
that were working for the East India Company before Britain came in as an official thing. They&#13;
came back into the village and they hung, or hanged, fourteen people in that village for what they&#13;
had done to the troops. And that garden where this hanging took place is still there. It's a very&#13;
important point in the village. But the village decided, the villagers decided, the landlords in this&#13;
village and the aristocracy group, the Kshatriyas or Rajput, decided that they would--their young&#13;
people had to get income, and the British are now going to tum against them, so we better get&#13;
them educated.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        W. David Hopper&#13;
                              April 2 and May 12,2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                   11&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 So they built a school in 1865. It was only Rajputs who went to that school. That's all, their&#13;
 sons, only Rajput males. They had a school. This is the young man that I met at Cornell who&#13;
 was also studying for a Ph.D. He was older than I was. He had finished up at [Balwant] Rajput&#13;
 College in India in Agra. They had a group that came from either that village or the surrounding&#13;
 villages. The head of the Indian civil service was one of these. The dean of the Lucknow law&#13;
 school was another one, et cetera. It was quite an educated group.&#13;
&#13;
 When I went to the villagers, the school was still there. It was still active. But this is part of&#13;
 where the change was, and it was moving. And Opler was unhappy that we weren't getting what&#13;
 was it. What was the culture? Yeah, now we're modernizing, but really what was this cultural&#13;
 base? And what I was interested in was the modernizations and how did I get them to, instead of&#13;
 producing, in the case of my best farmer, two tons per hectare of wheat and two and a half tons&#13;
 of rice per hectare, how did I get them producing four tons of wheat per hectare which, you&#13;
 know, nobody in India was producing, but that's a reasonable yield where I came from. So&#13;
 Opler and I just disagreed. I was looking to the future and he was looking to the past. And that's&#13;
 where it was.&#13;
&#13;
  One of the things I did when I got to the village, I met with the elders and said, "Okay, one of the&#13;
  things you're going to have to confront is the fact that I'm going to be here. I'm going to be here&#13;
. for a couple of years, and I'm going to be asking a lot of damn fool questions to people. These&#13;
  are going to be randomly selected households." It wasn't quite random because I had to put the&#13;
  important ones in but, basically, and randomly selected households. "I'm going to be quizzing&#13;
  them every month on what they ate and what they did and so on and so forth, and I'm going to be&#13;
  out every day quizzing people in the fields on what they're doing, where they're working, et&#13;
  cetera. And I'll be doing about fifteen people a day." I hired some young villagers, one guy&#13;
  from a market town who was an untouchable. I hired a local villager who was a Thakur, had&#13;
  been right up through college and spoke very good English. I hired another one who also spoke&#13;
  English but of the middle caste and so on. They did the work for me. They filled in the forms. I&#13;
  got forms; I printed them off in Benares and this sort of thing.&#13;
&#13;
 I went to the villagers and said, "Now what do I do? Do I provide money to the people? I mean,&#13;
 I have to do something. Do I give it to the village?" and so on. And they said they'd come back&#13;
 and talk to me. They called me up. They never came to the house. Occasionally they did, but in&#13;
 general I went up to them because I was no caste. I mean, there's high caste, there's medium&#13;
 caste, there's low caste, there's outcast, and there's no caste, and that's really down at the&#13;
 bottom. No caste is when you're not born in India. This is one of the problems right now with&#13;
 the Congress Party, because Sonia [Maino], who took over the Congress Party, married Rajiv&#13;
 Gandhi when he was a pilot in Italy--she's an Italian--she is continually criticized for being a&#13;
 foreigner, an outsider, even though she speaks Hindi and so on and so forth. But she's no caste&#13;
 because she hadn't been born in India. But they respected me because I was white-skinned and a&#13;
 vidyarthi, a student.                                .&#13;
&#13;
 But what did occur was that the villagers did call me in about three days' time and said, "What&#13;
 you will do is get books and copies" --this is the scribblers that you use in school-"and books"--&#13;
 because you had to buy those--"and give them to the low caste." This is the Chamars, the&#13;
 untouchables, in the village, which were the biggest chunk ofthe population but very few--they&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                          W. David Hopper&#13;
                               April 2 and May 12, 2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                 12&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
only had small plots if they had them, but they were the purjans who worked for the landlords,&#13;
the jajmans. "We want those children to go to school."&#13;
&#13;
FEL TAULT: So the village decided.&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: The village elders decided this, the village elder village group, the panchayat, if you&#13;
want, which means "five people," but it's a bigger group from each of the clans and so on and so&#13;
forth. And I said, okay, I'd do that. "But I know that there are two Chamars now working in&#13;
school, and they have to sit outside the classroom. They have to sit below the window outside.&#13;
They're not allowed into the classroom."&#13;
&#13;
FEL TAULT: Into the classroom.&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: That's right. And this is it. They said, "That has changed. We have changed that.&#13;
They will be accepted at an equal basis, but they need books and copies they can't afford." So I .&#13;
went out to Bhargava Bhushan Press in Benares where I had gotten my cards made and so on,&#13;
questionnaires--I had punch cards, punches around the edges of them and I could sort them with&#13;
needles going through, sort out the cards and this sort of thing. I talked with Mr. Bhargava, and&#13;
he said he would give me a very cut rate on this, and he did. I brought the books and copies in&#13;
and passed them out, and the Chamar boys went to school. I got the Chamar leaders to meet, and&#13;
they sent virtually everyone of the Chamar boys to school.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: Well, let me ask you this. I mean, it's often said that one ofIndia's obstacles to&#13;
modernization is the lack of equity among the castes.&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: Among the castes.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: So how do you explain the village deciding this, making this particular decision?&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: Why? Why? Why? Ask the question. Why? Before I got to that village, back in&#13;
the 1920s, there were 300--sorry--930,000 people in that village. When I got there in the 1950s,&#13;
there were 2,500 people in the village. The people were beginning to demand land--"Zamin,&#13;
zamin, zamin" --to use, the Chamars. They just kept pounding the land. "We need land. We&#13;
need land, because we don't have"--I mean, what did they do? They worked for their landlords.&#13;
The landlords were 25 percent of the village population, and there were some poor landlords&#13;
among them, but they got books and copies, too, by the way.&#13;
&#13;
[End Tape 1, Side A]&#13;
[Begin Tape 1, Side B]&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: "We have too many people. We cannot provide jobs for them. We cannot employ&#13;
them here. They've got to get educated. They've got to get out." That's the same argument that&#13;
you had against the British back in 1965, that we need to build a school to get our kids out, and&#13;
they wanted now to do this with the Chamars. And that was where it was. This is why. "We&#13;
have got to expand the school. We've got to change the whole position."&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       W. David Hopper&#13;
                             April 2 and May 12,2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                  13&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: So they had no problem with the possibility oflosing their labor pool?&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: None whatsoever.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: How were they going to replace it?&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: Well, because, you know, there were various ways of doing it. Besides, they knew&#13;
that there was a mechanized system that you can bring in. I mean, you know, they had seen&#13;
tractors. They saw me riding around in a motor bike. Cornell--because this was a, quote, "part&#13;
of their village structure," had ajeep out at the roadway that 1 could go to Allahabad in if!&#13;
needed to and so on, and I took villagers with me in that jeep to see the institute in Allahabad, to&#13;
visit other places and so on.&#13;
&#13;
And it was--one of the experiences that 1 had. The jeep broke down on a trip to Allahabad. We&#13;
climbed out of the jeep, and there it was. We walked over to the side. We left very early in the&#13;
morning. It was a hot, hot day. It was in May. It was about 120 degrees or so in the shade. No&#13;
it wasn't; it didn't get up to 120; about 115 or so. We walked over, and these guys, out from&#13;
underneath their dhotis came little Iotas and string. They went to the local well and sloshed the&#13;
mosquitoes offthe top of it and so on and so forth and pulled out water. It was brackish water.&#13;
Every time a bullock cart would go by this jeep (because we sent the driver on into town to get&#13;
some help), they'd nudge me and say, "[speaks phrase in Hindi]." "It's slow, but it goes."&#13;
[Laughter] "Very, very slow going, but it goes." 1 mean, this [inaudible] piece of Detroit iron&#13;
sitting out there on the road.&#13;
&#13;
At about--oh, 1 don't know; it was after twelve--one of the guys said to me (I only used boiled&#13;
water in the village, and they knew this) one of the guys said to me, "Hopper." This was an elder&#13;
who said to me, "You haven't had anything to drink since we left at six 0' clock in the morning."&#13;
He said, "1 know that this is not very good water, and 1 know that if you drink it you'll get sick.&#13;
But this is our country, and we know that if you don't drink it, you'll die." He handed me the&#13;
Iota.&#13;
&#13;
Now, you drank a Iota this way, through your hand and you suck it. You didn't put your lips to&#13;
the Iota. I drank it and it felt good. But in touching that Iota, it was contaminated. I knew that.&#13;
He would have to take it back and put it through a cleansing operation, which meant to put it in a&#13;
fire and put some Brahmin prayers to it and so on.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAUL T: And just for people listening, it would be contaminated because you were not a&#13;
Brahmin.&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: Because I was not a Kshatriya and so on. So I knew I was doing it, and it was being&#13;
contaminated, and 1 protested a bit. He said, "Drink, drink, drink," so 1 drank. He grabbed the&#13;
Iota. Now, he was the eldermost and considered to be the pukka leader, the top guy. He took&#13;
that Iota, put it up, and drank from it. And there was a total transformation among this group.&#13;
There were seven of us, eight of us. My Hindi approved. They relaxed because Ramdari&#13;
[phonetic] had drunk from the Iota, the contaminated Iota. 1 was now one of them. We walked&#13;
dO\\&gt;TI the road. "What the hell are we standing here for waiting for them to come and take us?"&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        W. David Hopper&#13;
                              April 2 and May 12, 2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                    14&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
We walked down the road to a place and we went in. I drank water and ate food. We all ate&#13;
together and so on and so forth.&#13;
&#13;
Well, that was in May of'54. When I left in July of'55, Ramdari [phonetic] and I were good&#13;
friends. I did what I normally have to do when you do this, and that is, I touched the feet of the&#13;
people. I bent to touch Ramdari's [phonetic] feet as a departure gesture, and he pulled me up and&#13;
said, "No, no, no, no." He said, "You taught me something. You remember the Iota on the trip&#13;
to Allahabad?"&#13;
&#13;
And I said, "Yes."&#13;
&#13;
He said, "You know, Gandhi had always said that all humans are equal. Buddha said the same&#13;
thing." He said, "1 never believed it until you demonstrated it, what it meant, what it really was."&#13;
He said, "I need to touch your feet." [t was just one ofthese situations. But this is a cultural&#13;
kind of thing. It's not economic or economic man.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: Right. Well, culture is always changing.&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: It is. So th~s was part of it, and this was where things went. And the school was an&#13;
important component.&#13;
&#13;
When [Robert S.] McNamara came to the village--because 1 took him to the village in '81 before&#13;
he left the Bank--when he came to the village, the villagers built a road in. We didn't have a&#13;
road before then. The government built a road. It was known as the McNamara Road in that&#13;
village now. He opened up another chunk ofthe school.&#13;
&#13;
And in 19701 was in Canada at the IDRC [International Development Research Center], first&#13;
president ofthe IDRC. I got a little packet from India, which I opened up, and there was an&#13;
ivory stature of Saraswati, the goddess Saraswati, the goddess of learning and the arts and so on.&#13;
There are two goddesses, Saraswati and Lakshmi. No orthodox Hindu will ever have the both in&#13;
the same house. You're either learned and artistic and intelligent or you're with Lakshmi, and&#13;
she's the goddess of wealth. (You know, this is the Republican Party today in this country.)&#13;
[Laughter] I opened this thing up. Here is a little ivory statue of Saraswati. It was from the--a&#13;
note, a delightful note in English--from the first Chamar girl to have graduated from college.&#13;
And what she said is I gave the books and copies to her father, who went to grade six, became a&#13;
teacher at the primary school level, and insisted that she had to go to college. And she had just&#13;
graduated, and he insisted that she send me a token of this graduation, and this was the statue of&#13;
Saraswati.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: That's amazing.&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: So today in Uttar Pradesh there are political parties, which are exceedingly&#13;
important, of the lower castes, the Chamars and so on. And these are the ones that I predicted in&#13;
the village when I was there, that this caste structure is going to collapse, and it is in the process&#13;
of collapsing. And you already have young people in India saying, "What the hell are we doing&#13;
with this caste business?" Now, you know, in the Christian tables--and I don't know whether&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         W. David Hopper&#13;
                               April 2 and May 12,2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                  15&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
you're a Christian or not--but in the Christian tables, you come out with, you know, "we will--&#13;
the sins of the father shall be put to the children and even to the tenth generation" kind of thing.&#13;
Not in Hinduism. In Hinduism, you go up and down. There's a life and death--life, rebirth, life,&#13;
death, rebirth, life, death, rebirth cycle, depending upon your performance in your previous life.&#13;
And if you are a Chamar, an untouchable at the bottom, for--or a Shudra (there is the Sanskrit&#13;
term)--there are four castes in India. The Brahmins are at the top--teachers, intellectuals, and so&#13;
on. There is the Kshatriyas in the middle, the second one, which are the warriors, the political&#13;
sources, and that sort of thing. There are the Vaishyas, the next one, which are the artisans and&#13;
the laborers, the workers, the artists, and the rest of it. Then there are the Shudra at the bottom.&#13;
Those are the untouchables. And the Chamars are part of the Shudra. They deal with dead&#13;
animals. They strip the hides off them. They deal with dead materials and so on. And below&#13;
them are the Doms. Those are the ones who look after the burning ghats and bum the corpses of&#13;
people and this kind of thing. And there's a whole array ofthese untouchable castes. In some&#13;
parts of India there are unseeables, and there's others where their shadow on you will be&#13;
contaminating and this kind of thing.&#13;
&#13;
All right. Those are now in the process of alteration and change. And what's emerging is a very,&#13;
very different kind of Hinduism. And there's a battle now in the Indian election between the BJP&#13;
(the Hindu fascist party, basically) and fifty different political groups that have now clustered in&#13;
India, some of whom are Muslim, some of whom are high Hindus, some--and many, many of&#13;
them are the low castes. And when I lived in the village, it was just a matter of time; the low&#13;
castes were, you know, a group that knew they were downtrodden. They had the leadership that&#13;
was--every time you talk with them, "Zamin, zamin. What we need is land, land."&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: Now, how much did you think--I know that in 1969 Indira Gandhi split the&#13;
Congress [Party], right, and created a new electorate. How much did that kind of play into this?&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: No, it didn't play into this. Well, we can get to that later because it's a long story.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: It's a long story. Okay. All right. So it's 1955.&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: I left in 1955, and I came back to finish up my Ph.D., got it in '57, was secretary to a&#13;
development group at Cornell and so on, bringing together economists and anthropologists and&#13;
agriculturalists and the rest of it as to what we could do. And it was financed from various&#13;
sources, including what is now U.S. AID [Agency for International Development]--at that time it&#13;
was the Technical Cooperation Administration and so on. I didn't know what I was going to do.&#13;
What do you do? I went to Guelph University in Canada or the Ontario Agricultural College, to&#13;
be exact, in '57 and was there in '59. I was not very happy. I was a land economist because&#13;
that's what I did my agricultural economics in. I was basically a land economist and didn't do&#13;
much on India.&#13;
&#13;
And then I got a telephone call from--I was just about ready to move into the radio business&#13;
because I had worked very extensively among farmers at Guelph at the Ontario Agricultural&#13;
College. And my father had been offered the presidency of Guelph back in 1949 and turned it&#13;
down, and that was all right. It wasn't an exciting place to be, but the students liked me and had&#13;
lots of fun. My wife had been with me in India, and we had a daughter. I got a call from Mosher&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         W. David Hopper&#13;
                              April 2 and May 12, 2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                  16&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
first and then from Hill to say that Hill was now with the Ford Foundation. He was Vice&#13;
President for International Activities at Ford. And Mosher had left and formed a corporation&#13;
supported by the Rockefeller Foundation on agricultural development. Ford and Rockefeller did&#13;
this.&#13;
&#13;
In '58 I had gone down, at Hill's request, to New York to listen to him and George Harrar, who&#13;
was then the head of agriculture at the Rockefeller Foundation. They discussed back in 1943--&#13;
I'm taking you way back on this--back in 1943 or 1941, when [Franklin D.] Roosevelt won his&#13;
term in the 1940 election, a third term--nobody had ever heard ofthis, a president with a third&#13;
term. He won in '32 and he won in '36 and he won in '40. He appointed Henry Wallace as his&#13;
vice president. Henry Wallace was famous for having produced hybrid com and hybrid&#13;
chickens. But Roosevelt confronted the fact that the Germans in '39 were opening up very, very&#13;
strong ties with Mexico, so he sent Wallace down to Mexico-I mean, he couldn't go--he sent&#13;
Wallace down to Mexico in early '41 to discuss aUofthese German ties with the Mexican&#13;
government. And Wallace went down. Before he went down, he was approached by then head&#13;
ofthe Rockefeller Foundation, president--I'll think of his name in a moment; I've got senior&#13;
moments that afflict me--at a meeting ofthe Council on Foreign Affairs [Relations]. 'Henry was&#13;
discussing that he was going with the Council members, and he was approached by Raymond&#13;
Fosdick and the Rockefeller head. He was approached by Fosdick, who was told, "Henry, while&#13;
you're down there, why don't you take a look at the rural health clinics that we've put up,"&#13;
because the Rockefeller Foundation began as a health group, and it was always very strongly&#13;
focused on health.&#13;
&#13;
So Raymond went down--or Wallace went down and came back. He didn't talk with Henry.&#13;
But in 1943, they met again at another meeting ofthe--now with the U.S. at war. They met again&#13;
at another meeting of the Council on Foreign Relations. Wallace said to Fosdick, "You know,&#13;
Henry, what I saw--I looked at your health clinics, but let me tell you something. You'd do more&#13;
for the health of the people of Mexico if you could raise com yields one bushel per acre and&#13;
wheat yields one bushel per acre than you will with all your dam health clinics."&#13;
&#13;
And Fosdick, never one to pass up a bad idea, proceeded to build, starting in 1943, a--he got&#13;
Miles Brady from--I'm sorry, Dick [Richard] Bradfield from Cornell, and he got geneticists from&#13;
Harvard, and he got pathologists, plant pathologists, from Minnesota to kind of consult with him.&#13;
And they formed what is known as the Office of Special Studies, the OSS. And they moved&#13;
down Norm Borlaug and a series of others into this thing to look at com, wheat, beans, and&#13;
potatoes. And Borlaug went up to Sonora and began working on wheats and the rest of it and&#13;
didn't do very well. Neither did any of the rest of them, but they got some hybrid maize in, but&#13;
hybrid maize, there's no way that the peasants could afford to buy the new seed every year,&#13;
which you need to do with hybrid maize, et cetera, et cetera, et cetera. And it didn't go very far.&#13;
&#13;
It did after' 46, and particularly the work of a man by the name of Skelton [So Cecil Salmon],&#13;
who went to Japan and came back with the USDA and brought with him various grains that the&#13;
Japanese had had, including among them a dwarf wheat, which Borlaug was looking for up in&#13;
Sonora to do it, because the whole focus of the--the other thing was how do we get rid of the&#13;
pests and the diseases and so on, and Borlaug decided the hell with the diseases. Wheat rust is&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        W. David Hopper&#13;
                              April 2 and May 12, 2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                  17&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
going to be there. It comes down from the US and there's nothing we can do about it, but let's&#13;
get wheat that'll grow.&#13;
&#13;
He and a guy by the name of [Orville] Vogel up in the Palouse area of Washington State took a&#13;
look at this stuff that came back into USDA out at Beltsville. And here was this funny little&#13;
wheat that the Japanese had found, and they were really after in the searches of the 1930s. You&#13;
know, they're little dwarf wheats and they're like little Japanese, little dwarf Japanese, and they&#13;
like these wheats, and this is it. So Borlaug picked those up in the Palouse area, and they found&#13;
they produced a very, very rigid straw but low, and they withstood the winds blowing in the&#13;
Palouse area down here. And Borlaug really transformed--by 1955, Mexico was totally self-&#13;
sufficient in wheat, not buying from the U.S. And the same thing in the U.S. with these dwarf&#13;
wheats.&#13;
&#13;
The dwarf wheats came to India in 1962 when I was working with the Ford Foundation, and&#13;
that's a totally different story. But I was following--I had decided and Hill had decided that we&#13;
needed research from my previous work in the village. And in '59 Hill gave me a call.&#13;
&#13;
In '58 1 went down, and Hill had a lunch at the University Club with Harrar, who was down on&#13;
this Mexican thing, and said, "George, you know, you guys are working in Mexico on beans and&#13;
potatoes and com and wheat. What are you doing about rice? Half the world eats rice."&#13;
&#13;
And Harrar said--and I was at the table--Harrar said, "Well, we're not doing anything."&#13;
&#13;
Frosty said, "Why not? Halfthe world eats rice."&#13;
&#13;
And Harrar said, "I haven't got the money."&#13;
&#13;
And Hill said something that the Rockefeller Foundation has never lived down and neither has&#13;
Ford, and that is, "Look, I got the money, you got the brains, why don't we meet?" [Laughter]&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: The start of all great relationships.&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: So they proceeded to do--they went to produce rice, and the International Rice&#13;
Research Institute in the Philippines was the outcome of this.&#13;
&#13;
And in '59 I was all set to leave Guelph and go work for the Canadian Broadcasting Corporation&#13;
on agriculture. I got a call. I called in my secretary to dictate my resignation from Guelph, and I&#13;
got a call on the telephone while I was in the middle of this from Moser saying, "Hill's going to&#13;
give you a call. He wants you to go to Chicago."&#13;
&#13;
So I said, "Okay."&#13;
&#13;
I told the secretary to go away, and the call came through. It was Frosty Hill. He offered me--&#13;
I'm sorry, it was Ted [Theodore W.] Schultz from Chicago to say that Hill had spoken to him&#13;
about me and they would like me to come to Chicago to join the faculty in economics. He was&#13;
an agricultural economist and very famous, won a Nobel Prize in economics.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        W. David Hopper&#13;
                              April 2 and May 12, 2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                  18&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: Didn't he write Transforming Traditional Agriculture?&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: That's right, yeah. He wanted me to come to Chicago and be there to take a look at&#13;
some of these issues that I had been raising in India. Ford Foundation paid for it. I went, gave a&#13;
seminar, had a hell of a time in the seminar because I came from a land grant college where&#13;
everything is very, you know, "I am very interested in this, but are you not going a little too far&#13;
on that and the rest of it?" I go to Cornell [Chicago], and, my God, they sliced me up and spread&#13;
me around the room. It was nothing, nothing kind about it.&#13;
&#13;
And I went down and saw the dean afterwards, Gale Johnson. And he said, "We want to offer&#13;
you ajob."&#13;
&#13;
I said, "After that performance?" I said, "Look, I suggest that you get in touch with one man&#13;
named Morris Opler, who used to be at Cornell and whom I had had big differences with,&#13;
because I'm not sure that I'm the guy you want," because it was a joint appointment. Economics&#13;
would pay for it, but I'd have an operation over in anthropology as well.&#13;
&#13;
And there was a long pause, and suddenly Johnson opens the drawer and says, "Look, we don't&#13;
usually show the private communications we have with somebody, but I think you might be&#13;
interested in reading this," and he handed me a letter. And it was four pages ofthe damnedest&#13;
diatribe against me you ever saw, signed by Morris Opler.&#13;
&#13;
I said--I handed it back to him. I said, "Well, he's right on every point."&#13;
&#13;
And Johnson looked at me and said, "Yes, and we decided that a man of his eminence, if he&#13;
really says these things about you, that's the kind of man we want on our faculty." So I joined&#13;
Chicago.&#13;
&#13;
And in late '61, I got another call from Hill to say that the Ford Foundation had a big operation&#13;
in India; he wanted me to go out and really analyze it. That meant I had to join it--I became the&#13;
historian for what was known in the Ford Foundation as a book that they wrote, material that&#13;
they had presented, called India's Food Crisis and Steps to ideet It. Now, that crisis started in&#13;
1957. After the British left, between '48 or '47--they officially left '48 when it became a&#13;
republic--and '57, agriculture had been sufficient. Then they had a very, very bad drought year&#13;
in '56, '57, and they had to import.&#13;
&#13;
Now, that particular year was very important from several perspectives. First of all, [Eugene R]&#13;
Black at the World Bank--India had been borrowing money, because they were at the Bretton&#13;
Woods conference. They were part of this Bank structure, even though they were a British&#13;
colony, and when they left, the British left, India signed on as a country. They had been&#13;
borrowing from the Bank but at the same rates that everybody else borrowed at the Bank, and&#13;
India no longer could pay their debt. So Black decided that there would have to be something&#13;
else, and IDA, the International Development Association, is what was created for poor&#13;
countries. And India's debt was eased and excused and transferred, basically, to IDA. And the&#13;
first Indian consortium was held in 1958, and Black chaired it. Twenty-five years later, I held&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        W. David Hopper&#13;
                              April 2 and May 12, 2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                      19&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 the next Indian consortium. I chaired all of them when I went to the Bank after '78. Black&#13;
 chaired the first few Indian consortiums.&#13;
&#13;
 The Pakistanis complained, and there was a Pakistan consortium then created in ' 62.&#13;
&#13;
  But the first one was the Indian consortium. And he brought the donors to the table, and he&#13;
. demanded that they say what they are going to give to India and deliver. There was no welshing&#13;
  or anything else. That was what you had to put in.&#13;
&#13;
 The second thing they did was resurrect PL-480. It was sitting in the U.S. books for a long&#13;
 period of time. That's Public Law 480, which allowed the U.S. to provide food for, really, just&#13;
 writing IOUs, transferring food to India. And the PL-480 came into India, wheat and so on.&#13;
&#13;
 The third thing that the World Bank did in this particular venture: they had extended this to&#13;
 India, so they had to extend it to Pakistan. They had to extend to it a series of other countries,&#13;
 and that was the IDA arrangement, that they got out of the heavy debt relationships.&#13;
&#13;
 But the other thing the World Bank did, they opened up an office in India, not as powerful as&#13;
 they are today, but they were there. And visits were made and so on and so forth.&#13;
&#13;
 FEL TAULT: Now, this was about when?&#13;
&#13;
 HOPPER: This was '58, following the--'58, '59.&#13;
&#13;
 FELTAULT: There's no record of that in any of the files.&#13;
&#13;
 HOPPER: No, there isn't. There isn't. But this is what Black did, and they were critical. This&#13;
 is the creation oflDA. That's the file you would have to ask for, what the hang happened and so&#13;
 on and what happened to the Indian debt, because India suddenly was now there and the Bank&#13;
 was involved. And it--it was critical on this thing.&#13;
&#13;
 So the consortium, the meetings, the development of this was kind of Black's idea. It wasn't just&#13;
 kind of, you know, World Bank people going and seeing what we could pledge you for and this&#13;
 sort of business.&#13;
&#13;
 All right. The Ford Foundation sent somebody in to look at the food problem, and they created a&#13;
 report called India's Food Crisis and Steps to Meet It. The head ofthe Ford Foundation there at&#13;
 the time was a man by the name of Doug [Douglas] Ensminger. And I met Doug when I was a&#13;
 student or a vidyarti in the area. I was not highly impressed with Doug, but he was a very nice&#13;
 guy. Doug was head of the USDA, the United States Department of Agriculture'S really&#13;
 community programs, and he was a rural sociologist. He tried to do the same thing in India. He&#13;
 was very active in community development in India. And it was community development not&#13;
 focused on economics of the community but how do we get the community to unite and be part&#13;
 of it and so on. And I used to tease him and say, "Well, Doug, you know, your problem with&#13;
 communities is that you were doing this back in the 1930s when it was important that you got the&#13;
 farmers to continue to vote with ballots not with bullets," because we had a desperate problem,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         W. David Hopper&#13;
                               April 2 and May 12, 2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                  20&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
and people moving out of Oklahoma to California and so on and so forth. It was huge poverty.&#13;
And there wasn't much we could do about it. There wasn't all that much money, et cetera.&#13;
&#13;
So Doug and community development were very important. And the issue was: how do you get&#13;
them to meet? How do you get them to bring them together? He helped the community&#13;
development movement that developed in India, and he got the panjayats going and so on and so&#13;
forth, and all of this was part of this structure.&#13;
&#13;
And this was what the Ford program was about, and the Ford program agreed to take on seven&#13;
districts in India. Ford would put up several million dollars, and the government oflndia would&#13;
put up some money, and they would have Ford people go in and they would really try to get the&#13;
communities to activate and begin to plant properly and that sort of thing.&#13;
&#13;
I was skeptical and so was Hill. Now, Hill in '58 was talking about rice research because I had&#13;
kept hammering at the fact that there wasn't any damn research. We didn't know what to do.&#13;
But Ensminger's whole approach was get the farmers to unite, and the big farmers will tell the&#13;
little farmers what to do and so on and so forth. I didn't--Christ, the grain wasn't there. The&#13;
soils weren't there. The soils were heavily depleted. The fertilizer wasn't available.&#13;
&#13;
I went and talked with the head ofthe--at one point, a little later when I was there--the secretary&#13;
of finance or the deputy minister of finance, why didn't he bring in fertilizer.&#13;
&#13;
His comment was, "Hopper, why should I bring in fertilizer? We have the fields, the farms of&#13;
Kansas and Saskatchewan, count on the Canadian aid, food aid, PL-480, et cetera. And we can't&#13;
afford to bring in fertilizer. Forget it." This was the attitude in government.&#13;
&#13;
Okay, I come in. The first speech I gave when I got there in January 1960--or February '62--to&#13;
the Ford group--I'd said, yes, I'd leave Chicago. Schultz was disappointed. I was offered&#13;
tenure. I went off to India. My wife joined me; my first wife joined me. She spoke Hindi very&#13;
well and so on, and we had servants. We had a couple of children. They were kids. And it was&#13;
a very good thing.&#13;
&#13;
But in my first speech to the Ford group was, "You're short of research. I mean, you're going&#13;
into the communities; you don't know what to do. You tell them to line up the thing so that the&#13;
crop lines are north and south so they get the sun in both the east and west sides. They haven't&#13;
got the grain. Their wheat is Punjab 591. There's no fertilizer for it. It grows up, wind blows in,&#13;
it lodges"--that is, it falls over-"the straws break, and that's it." Now, '62 was there, and '62,&#13;
the autumn of '62--you plant wheat in India in the fall when the ground cools down enough--and&#13;
, 62 Borlaug brought in his wheats from Mexico, and we had the first time.&#13;
&#13;
But that was with the Rockefeller Foundation not the Ford Foundation, and Ford would not listen&#13;
to this. Ensminger was absolutely thunderstruck with me, wanted to--they told Hill to take me&#13;
back.&#13;
&#13;
Hill said, "No, no. Leave him there." I was known as the historian of the project, and I was&#13;
known as the guy, the odd guy out. But it's surprising because he had a staff of thirteen&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        W. David Hopper&#13;
                              April 2 and May 12, 2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                  21&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Americans who were there, and half of them were kind of on my side: "We don't have the&#13;
research. We don't have the varieties. We don't have this."&#13;
&#13;
I worked as much with Rockefeller as 1 did with Ford in doing this. Borlaug came in '63, and he&#13;
and 1--1 had seen his wheats. They hadn't done very well on this agricultural--at the Indian&#13;
Agricultural Research Institute or up at Ludhiana, the Punjab University. Both of--the&#13;
Agricultural Research Institute had been developed by the British outside--that was first of all&#13;
down at Bihar and then moved up to Delhi. I went to that place several times and had a lot to do&#13;
with them, eventually became a visiting professor. The Punjab up at Ludhiana was controlled by&#13;
Michigan State. I had been a--not Michigan State, sorry. Ohio State. And I had been at Ohio&#13;
State as a visiting professor before when I was at Guelph, talking about agriculture in India and&#13;
so on. They had people there that I had met in Columbus who were up at Punjab.&#13;
&#13;
And they tested out the wheats. They didn't look very good. They didn't work very well.&#13;
&#13;
I went out to visit some farmers, and the first thing I got from the farmers is, "Sahib, get us some&#13;
of those new wheats, those short ones."&#13;
&#13;
And I said, "Well, they didn't do very well."&#13;
&#13;
"Oh, Sahib, they don't know how to plant and irrigate over there at the university. You get us&#13;
some of those wheats, we'll see what you can do."&#13;
&#13;
Well, we did. We brought in a few more. The next year we got some more, and we did this sort&#13;
of thing. They were red wheats, and Indians like white wheat and so on. And eventually they&#13;
got a radiation chamber, some uranium, to radiate red wheats, and we got white wheats out of&#13;
them and that kind of thing.&#13;
&#13;
By 1964 India was producing more wheat and doing better, and these new varieties were&#13;
beginning to move out, but not in large numbers. '64-'65--well, '63, no, '64-'65 India got one of&#13;
the best wheat crops they'd ever had. And in part this was because of an extension of these new&#13;
wheats, but in part it was a good year, and in part we got some fertilizer in. Now, this was when&#13;
the Bell Mission got going in '65, and I went out. Sir John Crawford came in, and I had known--&#13;
my father had known Crawford. I hadn't met him. I went out to the airport to meet him.&#13;
&#13;
[Interruption]&#13;
&#13;
Sir John came in, and I went out to the airport to meet him. I didn't know who the hell he was.&#13;
mean, I knew who he was, but I hadn't met him. A little short guy. He came in. I had&#13;
hammered at research. Hill believed it. Rockefeller believed it. Ford didn't believe it. The&#13;
World Bank didn't believe it. And Crawford's first question to me: "What kind of research have&#13;
they got?" [Laughter] You know.&#13;
&#13;
"Lousy."&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         W. David Hopper&#13;
                              April 2 and May J 2, 2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                    22&#13;
&#13;
It turns out that he just--we became awfully close friends. He had been here--during the Second&#13;
World War, Crawford had been the Deputy Minister for the Secretary for Agriculture, the&#13;
Deputy Minister for Agriculture in Australia. And the Second World War came; he had been&#13;
totally unable in Australia, with all the efforts, to increase food production. The U.S. here had&#13;
started back--the first use of fertilizer was the Germans in the First World War when they put&#13;
ammonium nitrate from the munitions operations--later to blow up, the Oklahoma bombers and&#13;
so on--but they put ammonium nitrate to grow turnips and potatoes because they had--the Allies&#13;
had cut off a good deal of their food supplies and so on. And they blew the lid off these crops by&#13;
putting them out.&#13;
&#13;
We sent virtually all our Ph.D.s in agriculture and agricultural economics to Germany for their&#13;
Ph.D.s, and our Ph.D. program is not a D.Phil. program, i.e., the British--or e.g., the British. The&#13;
Ph.D. programs that we have now are German Ph.D. This is what you did in Germany. You&#13;
wrote yourself a dissertation. You appeared before the committee and so on and so forth. And&#13;
what we did was to go to Germany to take a look at what they were doing on science, and we&#13;
found an agricultural group who were really advancing science. They came back, filled our&#13;
universities in the '20s and so on. We did a hell ofa lot of research. The '30s came; there was&#13;
just--there was no market for it, so it sat on the shelves.&#13;
&#13;
The Second World War breaks out; we increase food production by forty percent within a few&#13;
years. We doubled it virtually before the end of the war. We diverted munitions; we diverted&#13;
other stuff to fertilizer. We built the Tennessee Valley Authority and the fertilizer unit down at&#13;
Mussel Shoals, Alabama, so they were close to power and the rest of it, which now the&#13;
International Fertilizer Development Center is down there.&#13;
&#13;
We did a whole series of things to get fertilizer out. We diverted from building Ford cars and so&#13;
on and so forth, Model Ts and the rest of it, to work on tractors. We designed combines. That&#13;
had been developed back in the--or the grain harvester had been developed back in the 19th&#13;
century, but we now could add a gasoline engine to it and do a series of other things. We had a&#13;
whole lot of stuff on the shelf which we were able to dump into it.&#13;
&#13;
Crawford found they didn't have it in Australia. So he came back to Australia. He came over&#13;
here. He did a Ph.D. over here. He spent time looking at all of this. He returned to Australia in&#13;
the early '50s, late '40s and recast the whole of the Australian scientific council to move them&#13;
into agriculture. They did soils analysis. They found that Australia was desperately short of&#13;
some trace minerals. They doubled their--they began dumping the trace minerals from aircraft&#13;
and so on and so forth. In the process, they doubled yields. They began developing--instead of&#13;
the rabbits taking everything--the rabbits, yeah, were out there and all the rest of it--but they just&#13;
expanded agriculture immensely. And by the mid-'50s, they had increased their agricultural&#13;
output globally by 53,56, up to 80 percent of this thing.&#13;
&#13;
And Crawford was now brought in to India in '64, and the first question he had is what did they&#13;
do on research. Nothing. So he and I became kind of a bastion for research.&#13;
&#13;
Now, Ford also brought in Wolf Ladejinsky, who is another old friend, and Wolfwas very, very&#13;
dedicated to the Russian proposal. He was a Russian Jew, left Russia at the time of Lenin or&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         W. David Hopper&#13;
                               April 2 and May 12,2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                    23&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
after Lenin. And as he pointed out, Lenin--the Russians succeeded by Lenin looking at the serfs&#13;
at the time of the naval uprising in St. Petersburg and announced, you know, "Go horne. Claim&#13;
yourself a piece. Take your guns. Claim yourself a piece of land, and we'll protect you." And&#13;
this is what broke the whole of the feudal system in Russia. There was a battle, yes, between the&#13;
Reds and the traditional ones. The tsar was killed and so on and so forth, and the Lenin bunch&#13;
took over.&#13;
&#13;
Ladejinsky was firmly convinced that the issue in India was you had too many talkers out here,&#13;
too many high caste, owning the land, and we need to break it up. Now, India did break up some&#13;
ofthat land after the British had left. They didn't break it up in Bihar, and it's still a major&#13;
problem in Bihar. They did in eastern Uttar Pradesh, but they still had the Charnars, and they're&#13;
not going to break it down into the small plots. But that was his solution.&#13;
&#13;
The Bell Mission wanted to look at agriculture. Crawford kind of went away from what Bernie&#13;
Bell was doing, which was basically macroeconomics. We all got involved. I worked for him.&#13;
Ford has assigned me to him, Ensminger's objections notwithstanding. Hill absolutely&#13;
demanded I had to go. I made a speech in Mexico to a group ofthe Ford resident&#13;
representatives, of which Ensminger was one, which I said, you know, it had to be research.&#13;
This was before we got involved with the Bell Mission. Except for the fact that Hill and the then&#13;
head of the Rockefeller Foundation, then president, were very impressed with me, nobody else&#13;
was.&#13;
&#13;
Carne my, the end of my Ford contract, which was 1965 December, Ensminger called me in in&#13;
September '65 and said, "Well, you know, Hill is 65 as of December." And he was; he was born&#13;
in late December 1900. "The president ofthe Rockefeller Foundation is leaving. There are a lot&#13;
oflame ducks in the Rockefeller Foundation. Dave, you're one of them." [Laughter] So in&#13;
other words, he's not going to renew. Ford paid me quite well.&#13;
&#13;
George Harrar carne into town. The head of the Rockefeller office kind of waylaid him. And he&#13;
was looking for an economist. He needed to get an economist, and Harrar hated economists.&#13;
Harrar had been head of this Mexican thing. He couldn't stand economists. They carne in and&#13;
were always kind of bitching about this and that and the other thing. So he agreed with Ralph&#13;
Cummings, who was the head of the Rockefeller Foundation there, the late Ralph Cummings&#13;
now. His son just retired from U.S. AID.&#13;
&#13;
Ralph got me to go see George. George said, "How much are they paying you?"&#13;
&#13;
I said, "I'm getting 16,000 a year from Ford."&#13;
&#13;
He said, "I can only pay you twelve."&#13;
&#13;
I said, "George, I'll do a deal with you. I'll take the twelve, and I'll quit in two years if you're&#13;
not satisfied. But if you are satisfied, I'm going to ask then for 24,000." I said, "I'll expect it to&#13;
start as of now. So let's take a look. You pay twelve. At the end of two years, if you're not&#13;
satisfied, 1 step out. At the end of--ifyou're satisfied, fine. Then we move to 24."&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         W. David Hopper&#13;
                               April 2 and May 12,2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                24&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
He thought a moment and said, "It's a deal. That's a deal."&#13;
&#13;
So I moved to Rockefeller and paid out [inaudible] I had--and so on and so forth--and moved to a&#13;
different place. I had a lovely house with Ford. I had to get an apartment with Rockefeller and&#13;
so on. But I proceeded to teach.&#13;
&#13;
But Frosty and I--Sir John and I and the Bell Mission were there. I came back to here in '64 and&#13;
wrote a fair amount of the Bell Mission reports on agriculture.&#13;
&#13;
[End Tape 1, Side B]&#13;
[Begin Tape 2, Side A]&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: The Bell Mission worked satisfactorily, and I think we gave a reasonable report.&#13;
This was it.&#13;
&#13;
In early 1967--I'm sorry--March 1966, India had two periods of drought. The crops were way&#13;
down. Nehru died in '64. In '65, fall of '65, there was a bad year. '64-'65 was a very bad year,&#13;
and India had to import about ten percent of its food grain requirements. Lal Bahadur Shastri&#13;
had taken over as the prime minister. Lal Bahadur is an interesting guy. I had met him down at&#13;
Allahabad back when I was a vidyarti. He came from near there. He was really a scholar and&#13;
Buddhist and kind of Hindu tradition of intellectuals, very, very spare and so on. I have a picture&#13;
of him walking down the street, Metcalf Street, actually, in Canada with the parliament buildings&#13;
is behind him in January with snow everywhere, walking out in sandals and a dhoti. [Laughter]&#13;
I mean, this was Lal Bahadur.&#13;
&#13;
I had written an article for an Indian paper on "Not "After Nehru, Who?" It's' After Nehru,&#13;
What?'" I predicted that Lal Bahadur would be Nehru's successor, and he was when Nehru died&#13;
in May '64. I saw Nehru just two weeks before he died or, no, about a month before he died. I&#13;
had just come back from Rajasthan. He had heard I had been there. He invited me over. His&#13;
aide-de-camp called me and said could I come over. I said yes. He said, "Can you come over&#13;
fairly early in the morning because he's not quite himself after eleven?" I did.&#13;
&#13;
We had some breakfast and tea out on the porch at seven 0' clock. He wanted to know about&#13;
Rajasthan. I said, "I was over there. I was in Gandhinagar." I said, "The farmers were&#13;
complaining bitterly because they were being asked to produce pigs and some other grains that&#13;
they didn't like and didn't know by the government of Rajasthan." I said, "You know, I don't&#13;
understand it, Pandit-ji. It just doesn't seem to make any difference that they're there." By the&#13;
way, "ji" at the end of a name is an honorific in India.&#13;
&#13;
His statement was, "You know, our problem is we have to get people to want to plan."&#13;
&#13;
And I said, "What do you mean, Pandit-ji?"&#13;
&#13;
He said, "Well, we've got to get people to want to plan."&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        W. David Hopper&#13;
                              April 2 and May 12,2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                      25&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
I said, "Pandit-ji, you wrote the book The Discovery of India. And the marvelous thing about the&#13;
book there is the eclecticism of India, all the beliefs that were here, the great montage of beliefs&#13;
and statements and so on and so forth. How are you going to get them to want to plan?"&#13;
&#13;
He said, "Look, Pitamber knows exactly"--Pitamber Pant at the Planning Commission, physicist;&#13;
I liked Pitamber but--"Pitamber knows exactly what we require." He said, "We have to get&#13;
people to want that."&#13;
&#13;
I said, "Pandit-ji, they're never going to want it. This is still the eclectic thing that you wrote&#13;
about in The Discovery of India." And we talked about it, and it didn't go anywhere. And he&#13;
died a month later.&#13;
&#13;
Lal Bahadur came in. He fought the war in '65, and he died up in Tashkent in early '66. And I&#13;
wept because he wasjust--he was one of my heroes. He died in January '66.&#13;
&#13;
In ' 65 we had this very low thing. We needed to bring in more food and so on. And there was a&#13;
dispute going on between me, the Ministry of Food and Agriculture, the chief statistician,&#13;
USDA. Our estimates were that they got about 76 million tons of food in '65, which wasn't&#13;
good, wasn't bad. The previous year, the best year, had been 81 million tons, the previous year.&#13;
It dropped to 76. The states reported in the amount of food they had in each of the states, and&#13;
they did this by crop cuts and so on and so forth. They reported in they got 68 million tons. I&#13;
took a look at the reports, and it was quite clear that the food surplus states were underestimating&#13;
because they didn't want to be held responsible for all of that food that had to go elsewhere, and&#13;
the food deficit states were underestimating because that put them in line to receive more food&#13;
from the central sources and the PL-480, et cetera.&#13;
&#13;
So we went--I went, sat at the back. [J. S.] Sarma went up to the table as the, in the Ministry of&#13;
Food and Agriculture statisticians, and we got the minister of agriculture to agree--this was&#13;
Subramaniam, K. [Chidambaram] Subramaniam. Subramaniam agreed. We made these&#13;
presentations. But each of the states was around the table, and each state said that this is the data&#13;
they had and so on and so forth. And we couldn't move them. I mean, we couldn't move them.&#13;
&#13;
"68."&#13;
&#13;
"76."&#13;
&#13;
And finally Lal Bahadur banged down the gavel, and I learned the difference between statistical&#13;
truth and political truths. And he said, "All right, I'll call a meeting ofthe chief ministers of&#13;
India, and we will decide what we produced." And he did, and in the official record today it's 72&#13;
million tons. [Laughter] It's political truth. You see it going on now over the issue of [Richard&#13;
A.] Clarke and Condi [Condoleezza] Rice and so on and so forth.&#13;
&#13;
So Subramaniam decided that he had to do something, and I had a brief conversation with him.&#13;
He visited several of our wheat demonstration plots that we had scattered around now and&#13;
brought in more wheats and saved some of the other stuff and so on.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         W. David Hopper&#13;
                               April 2 and May 12,2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;/&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                26&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
And 1 got a call in May of '64-well, it was March '64 or '66--from Ralph Cummings (I was&#13;
now with Rockefeller with Ralph Cummings) to say that he had just got a call from&#13;
Subramaniam, and he's sending a mission off to Mexico to buy 25,000 tons of Mexican wheat. I&#13;
said, "Ralph, not a hope. There's no way he can get 25,000. No way he can get the money for&#13;
that. It'll be five or six million dollars that they're going to need. Forget it."&#13;
&#13;
FELTAUL T: This was that special wheat that had been created there in Mexico.&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: That's right, which we were short of. That was a Sunday--no, Saturday, Saturday. I&#13;
got a call Sunday afternoon to say that--no, I got a call Monday morning from Ralph Cummings&#13;
to say that five Indians had just left on Air India for New York with five million dollars to buy&#13;
wheat from Mexico. And Subramaniam had convinced Mrs. Gandhi that this is what they ought&#13;
to do. They bought-he'd phoned, Ralph had phoned Borlaug in Mexico, and Borlaug said,&#13;
"Get them in here fast, because we're harvesting and we need to harvest the best, ifthat's what&#13;
they want."&#13;
&#13;
They brought in 16,000 metric tons of wheat to India. They couldn't get 25. They brought it in.&#13;
It came in by ship. There was--Subramaniam held a meeting of the Tonnage Club. This is a&#13;
group of farmers, wealthy farmers, big farmers, who had formed a club to kind of increase&#13;
yields, and they had bought fertilizer and so on. And the Tonnage Club met. I went down to sit&#13;
and listen. And there was a discussion about what should they charge for this. And it was&#13;
decided by the government that they would charge what it cost, what we had to pay in Mexico,&#13;
the shipping charges, and so on and so forth. And they came up with--there's a unit in India&#13;
called a maund, which is 82 pounds; a bushel of wheat is 60 pounds--they came up with a sum&#13;
of, I don't know, 120 rupees or something, 128 rupees, per maund. And one of the members of&#13;
the Tonnage Club pulled out a checkbook and said, "I'll take the entire 16,000 tons at that price."&#13;
There was absolute consternation. [Laughter]&#13;
&#13;
                                             a&#13;
Eventually they settled on about 250 rupees maund for the wheat. It came in, and it went out.&#13;
It went out to big farmers. And the understanding was that they would not sell it. They would&#13;
not harvest it--I mean, they would not harvest it for sale. It could be harvested for seed. The&#13;
seed corporation of India, which had been formed earlier for other seeds--castor seeds and so on,&#13;
specialized crop seeds--would take it.&#13;
&#13;
And the harvest in ' 67 was a bumper harvest of this material. That meant there was enough to&#13;
put out for planting in autumn of '67. You harvest in March before the ground gets too hot.&#13;
&#13;
Before this occurred, the economics group at Delhi University under V.K.R.V. Rao, the head of&#13;
economics at Delhi University, decided to hold a meeting as to what we did on the food. And&#13;
Subramaniam came. He sat up at the back. It was hot. There were no fans on, no air-&#13;
conditioning or anything, just hot as hell and sweaty. This is the beginning of the hot season in&#13;
Delhi. And they brought in the economists, an array of economists, and every one of them&#13;
except for two, as Subramaniam pointed out--Hopper, and a guy by the name of Khilone&#13;
[phonetic], Professor Khilone [phonetic] from Punjab University--got up and said, "We do not&#13;
want the outside wheats. Don't bring them in." This was before we bought them, before&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        W. David Hopper&#13;
                              April 2 and May 12,2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                    27&#13;
&#13;
Subramaniam decided to buy them. And Subramaniam sat quiet throughout the entire thing up at&#13;
the back.&#13;
&#13;
And Khilone [phonetic] and I were saying, "Yes, you need it. You need the food. It's the only&#13;
way you're going to do it. Yeah, you've got to get fertilizer for them. Agreed. Yes, they need&#13;
water, because they need extra irrigation, et cetera. Yes; all ofthat's correct."&#13;
&#13;
The economists were saying, "Look, this country was built on equality, and all that's going to&#13;
occur is that the Punjab, Haryana, these places that have water, western Uttar Pradesh, are going&#13;
to be way ahead of them on farmers. The people in Madhya Pradesh, et cetera, are going to be&#13;
still poor because they can't afford the water. It isn't there. They can't afford the fertilizer. It&#13;
isn't there," et cetera. This sort of thing. This was one thing.&#13;
&#13;
The other thing was, "Well, we don't know if they're going to really do it. We bring them in and&#13;
we pay all ofthis money, and they plant them, and then we have a bad year or the diseases get in&#13;
or we" et cetera, et cetera, et cetera. "Don't do it. Don't do it. Don't do it. Don't do it."&#13;
&#13;
Khilone [phonetic] and I just kind of commiserated and said, "Well, this isn't going to work. I&#13;
mean, it just isn't going to work."&#13;
&#13;
This is when Subramaniam got up in the back, and it was a Friday noon and said, well, he&#13;
appreciated very much being here. He had listened to the various arguments and so on. But he&#13;
said, "There are only two people in this room, Professor Khilone [phonetic] of Punjab and Dr.&#13;
Hopper of the Rockefeller Foundation, who addressed my problem, which is how do I feed my&#13;
people." And he walked out. That was Friday.&#13;
&#13;
Sunday, Cummings calls me and says, "He's going to send a mission. I just talked with Borlaug,&#13;
and they had better get there." They left. They came back. And in ' 68, India increased its wheat&#13;
production by 50 percent. The fall of '68 we harvested--wheat everywhere. God, the Punjab&#13;
was--in the schools and the railroad stations, everywhere, there was wheat.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: What was India's plan to sort of distribute and ...&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: They got it. They got it. It went to the--they created a food corporation to handle it.&#13;
They needed to build storage. The World Bank was there to help them build storage and so on.&#13;
This was it.&#13;
&#13;
Then the question was where do you get fertilizer because you need the fertilizer for it. I had&#13;
traveled every six weeks out of Delhi for a year and a half, visiting the U.S., Britain, Germany,&#13;
France, Canada and so on to get fertilizer. We got the fertilizer in for the '68.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: What kind of fertilizer?&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: We needed urea in large quantities. That's nitrogen. We needed potash and&#13;
potassium--not potassium, god--NPK.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        W. David Hopper&#13;
                              April 2 and May 12, 2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                28&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: That's what I was just thinking.&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: It's NPK. It's potassium, yeah. We got it in. We brought in 250 million dollars&#13;
worth of fertilizer. The World Bank--I got the World Bank here; Crawford was involved in this-&#13;
-to switch its thing that they wouldn't finance an annual usable, and the World Bank put up&#13;
money. This wasn't--this was under-god, I forget his name; I'll think of it.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: Was it Woods?&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: Yes. George Woods as the president. And he agreed; he got the Board [of&#13;
Executive Directors] to agree that they'd put in long-term IDA grant for this annual usable. We&#13;
got Canada to put up fertilizer. We got Germany to put up fertilizer. We got the French to put in&#13;
fertilizer. We got the Brits to put up some. We got it from various places. And we got 250&#13;
million dollars worth of fertilizer. And that went out to--and you'll find a paper in the--and I&#13;
don't recommend reading all that junk, but a paper in the Bell Mission report said, estimated it to&#13;
be around that, 250 million. This was when I went to the--actually, it was 280 million, I guess&#13;
we got, because it said 250 million--this is when I went to the secretary of finance earlier to ask&#13;
him about it and he said, "We fann the fields of Kansas and Saskatchewan. Don't be silly.&#13;
We're not going to produce our own food."&#13;
&#13;
The promissory notes were there and so on. The U.S. wrote off three and a half billion dollars&#13;
worth of promissory notes; Canada wrote off basically about a billion and a half. They built an&#13;
embassy or a new consulate--not a new consulate but a new High Commissioner building,&#13;
Canadian High Commission Buildin,g in Delhi. They created an institute called the Shastri Indo-&#13;
Canadian Institute in Canada with this money. I was instrumental in getting that done, and my&#13;
first wife signed the papers for it. I couldn't, but she did. This is how it worked. That was it.&#13;
&#13;
In '69--McNamara was impressed. He came out and saw this wheat and had a discussion with&#13;
me. That's when I first met him. He was now at the Bank. In '67, he came. He was very&#13;
impressed with what had been done on the wheat. We were doing this, now, the same thing with&#13;
some of the new rices coming in from the Rice Institute. They were a little more difficult&#13;
because it took irrigated land and so on and so forth and the rest of it.&#13;
&#13;
From then on, three A.M. in the morning, twice a week, the telephone would ring. I'd get up and&#13;
McNamara'd be on the line, wanting to know what things were going and what things were&#13;
doing, what's Mrs. Gandhi doing, and the rest of it.&#13;
&#13;
 By 1969, 1970, it was clear the Rockefeller function was pretty much done. And Harrar was&#13;
 now President of the Rockefeller, well, was President of the Rockefeller Foundation in New&#13;
 York, and he was not at all sure that we needed another role there. We'd moved the stuff in.&#13;
 The research was going. There were research institutions. India had good research institutions.&#13;
 The U.S. AID had built a whole series of Indian universities in India back, starting back in the&#13;
 '50s--Pantnagur in Uttar Pradesh, Ludhiana, and the others, down in Orissa, and so on and so&#13;
.forth. A lot of these kids were trained and a lot of the professors were trained in the United&#13;
 States. Many returned to India only to find that there wasn't really anything to do in India. They&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        W. David Hopper&#13;
                              April 2 and May 12, 2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                  29&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
continued their Ph.D. theses they had written in the U.S. and so on. Some of them went back to&#13;
the U.S.&#13;
&#13;
But Subramaniam had changed this. He was defeated in the '67 elections and was out and came&#13;
back in the '74 elections--or '72 elections--with Mrs. Gandhi and became finance minister.&#13;
&#13;
And in 1974 I was with the IDRC in Canada; I was asked to come back and head this thing up by&#13;
the Prime Minister, Maurice Strong. It was Canada's answer to the fact that, as I like to say, that&#13;
they didn't have a Mr. Ford or Mr. Rockefeller in Canada, so the Canadian government created a&#13;
government corporation--not a crown corporation, a government corporation--that would be--it&#13;
was called the International Development Research Center, or in French, the Centre de&#13;
Recherche pour la Developpement Internationale. I was brought in as the first president to set&#13;
this thing up, get it to function. I was there until McNamara invited me to the Bank. He'd made&#13;
the noises about my coming to the Bank as soon as I left India.&#13;
&#13;
FEL TAUL T: I was just going to ask, why did it take from ...&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: Well, because I had this IDRC thing, and what he wanted me to do in the Bank was&#13;
to substitute for Warren Baum or something else. I--my own feeling was that this was&#13;
Machiavelli's The Prince, that there were courtiers and there were barons in that institution. And&#13;
the president dares not take on the barons as a group; otherwise, it's King John and Runnymede&#13;
and the Magna Carta again. But then the jobs he offered me--he offered me two jobs. Both were&#13;
courtiers' jobs, and I just didn't want to be a courtier. I was a baron sitting up in Canada. I had&#13;
my own budget, and I had a bunch of parliamentarians who were strong believers in what I was&#13;
doing, and I got, you know, votes in Parliament that were unanimous and so on and so forth.&#13;
&#13;
But he did offer me--he said, "Well, what can I offer you?"&#13;
&#13;
I said, "Well, South Asia. That's the one place I'd come for."&#13;
&#13;
He offered me South Asia in '77, and I came down in '78. I'd had seven years at IDRC; that was&#13;
sufficient.&#13;
&#13;
But the--Subramaniam. 1974 I was with IDRC. I went to see Mrs. Gandhi, was in India. I went&#13;
to India frequently because I had a little office there, personal office, still functioning and so on&#13;
under IDRC, maintaining touch. I wanted to see Mrs. Gandhi, and I walked into her office. She&#13;
said, "Dave, do you know what that man said?" I didn't know who "that man" was, much less&#13;
worry about what he said. She said, "He said he might use food as a weapon. Now, you've been&#13;
telling me for years we can grow our own food. How do we do it?"&#13;
&#13;
"That man" was Henry Kissinger. And he said this after Saudi Arabia joined OPEC&#13;
[Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries]. And the U.S. was putting a lot of food into&#13;
Saudi Arabia as part of the balance in the oil deals and so on, and now Saudi Arabia was raising&#13;
the price of oil to us substantially. I mean big price increases. And Kissinger was just mad as&#13;
hell: "And, my God, sometimes I may have to use it as weapon."&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        W. David Hopper&#13;
                              April 2 and May 12, 2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                 30&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Now Mrs. G's concern was not Kissinger and his oil. Mrs. G's concern was that India was very&#13;
close to the Russians, and it could very well be that, you know, India's tete-a-tete with the&#13;
Russians--because a lot ofIndian stuff went to Russia, cashew nuts and you bought them tea and&#13;
so on and so forth. You bought them in London via the Russians and so on.&#13;
&#13;
And India had--she blew off a nuclear bomb after I'd warned her that she was going to have it--&#13;
or not warned her. I had warned Canada and the United States that they were working on a&#13;
nuclear bomb down in Calcutta--down in Bombay. I went down to put in a new computer that&#13;
Kenny [J. Kenneth] Galbraith had done, and I was one of the only ones around India that had&#13;
experience on computers that had more than one central processor. The one that I cut my eye&#13;
teeth on was the ILIAC out at Illinois. I went out and spent some time out there looking at how&#13;
they were doing it and so on and so forth when I was in Toronto at Guelph--at Chicago. I had&#13;
done some programming on multiple processor computers. I'd brought in some small computers&#13;
to Guelph, smaller ones. This was before the desktop was created and all the other stuff.&#13;
&#13;
But I got down to Bombay and went to the Tata Institute down there, research institute. They&#13;
had this computer. It was supposed to go to the statistical institute in Calcutta, the Indian&#13;
Statistical Institute in Calcutta, and that's where Galbraith thought it was going to go to, the&#13;
ambassador. And I went down and spent two weeks and came back. I went to see him and said,&#13;
"You know, they're going to build an atom bomb. That's what they want. They're using that&#13;
computer to handle higher-order differential equations. Now, there are no higher-order&#13;
differential equations in statistics that India does. There are higher-order differential equations&#13;
on uranium and so on and so forth and how you get it and what's the physics, but not Indian&#13;
statistics. "&#13;
&#13;
He couldn't accept it. Canada couldn't accept it. But when she blew the bomb off, we held an "I&#13;
told you so" party down at the Pearson Building in Canada, because some of my other friends&#13;
did accept it, that that's what was going on. [Homi Jehangir] Bhabha was killed--the physicist&#13;
handling this was killed in an airplane crash. An Air India plane hit Mont Blanc in Switzerland.&#13;
It was a major loss.&#13;
&#13;
I remember teasing Bhabha after the Chinese war in '62, you know: "Be careful."&#13;
&#13;
Bhabha said, "Well, we have to build an atom bomb."&#13;
&#13;
And I said, "Well, you haven't got enough--no engineering physicists to really do this. You only&#13;
have four in the country."&#13;
&#13;
And he said, "Four? We've got fifty abroad. We'll bring them back."&#13;
&#13;
And when I reported this to Galbraith, they put special CIA [U.S. Central Intelligence Agency]&#13;
people--or the equivalent of such--on those four. They never left their jobs and so on and so&#13;
forth, and this was it. This was where the intelligence was. They never took a look at the&#13;
number coming in. I warned them. I saw them, you know.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        W. David Hopper&#13;
                              April 2 and May 12, 2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                 31&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Well, she blew the bomb off in order to knock off the railroad strike in India. But she was very&#13;
concerned in '74--she blew it off in '74. This was before--this was the issue with Kissinger. I&#13;
remember I went to the telephone and I called Bob McNamara and said, "Bob, I just left Mrs.&#13;
Gandhi. We had a long conversation. I think she's ready for really moving on this, rather than&#13;
just farming the fields of Kansas and Saskatchewan."&#13;
&#13;
McNamara said, "You go back and tell her I'm willing to put two billion dollars over the next&#13;
five years into Indian agriculture."&#13;
&#13;
Well, I couldn't get to her. She had left elsewhere and I had other things to do, but Bob did.&#13;
They formed a committee consisting of Indians, senior Indians, and the Bank appointed Sir John&#13;
Crawford as their candidate, and he was the chairman of this committee. They met, Indians and&#13;
Bank people, under Sir John until I wrapped it up in the 1980s.&#13;
&#13;
Now, they moved from ..&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: Was this the Consultative Group [for International Agricultural Research]?&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: No, no, totally different. The CGIAR--that's another story and I'll come ba'ck to&#13;
that, if you will.&#13;
&#13;
I'm talking Indian food. This was an Indian commission. And they moved from the tonnages&#13;
that you had in ' 68--wheat expansion and so on, 100 to 125 million tons and so on--they moved&#13;
up to what is today a billion tons. I mean, they're feeding a billion people. When I left--there&#13;
were not a billion tons of food--when I left there were 490 million people in 1970. They're now&#13;
a billion, 100 million or close to that. A billion, 70 million is the official statistic. They're&#13;
exporting. They're growing more wheat than the United States. They're growing more--the&#13;
second largest rice producer, after China. They are able to export wheat. Right now they had a&#13;
bumper, bumper year just finished, about 230 million tons or so total, total food grains.&#13;
&#13;
This is historic. It's, quote, "the Green Revolution," unquote. That's what it was. It rests&#13;
basically--the term "green revolution" (I once looked it up) was a revolution of the peasantry in&#13;
Poland back in the 15th century. But the term was used by L((e magazine when they visited the&#13;
Rice Institute and talked ..&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: In the Philippines.&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: In the Philippines. They had got some dwarf rices, thanks to the Japanese, through&#13;
Taichung, Taiwan, Japanese left some dwarf material. They brought that in. They developed the&#13;
dwarf rice, which--IR8 blew the lid off yields in rice. They continue to handle these dwarf&#13;
materials and so on. Eventually, those are the ones that have moved in on the rice areas and&#13;
greatly added to them.&#13;
&#13;
Now, Consultative Group. In 1969 we had this wheat story. Hill and Harrar had now built-&#13;
they'd converted the Rockefeller group into CIMMYT [International Maize and Wheat&#13;
Improvement Center]. They'd built the Rice Institute in the Philippines in '62. Hill had to--a&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       W. David Hopper&#13;
                             April 2 and May 12, 2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                  32&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
very, very--first meeting of the board, Hill was--Harrar was in the chair. Hill kind of went&#13;
around and said, "Okay, what do you do?" "I'm a beet scientist," that was there. They brought&#13;
in various scientists from all over: Taiwan, from various other places, India, and so on, and the&#13;
United States. And Hill went around the table and asked each one of them.&#13;
&#13;
One of them, an American scientist from South Carolina--Hill said what did he think. He said,&#13;
"This is the institute, this is the Rockefeller University for rice."&#13;
&#13;
Hill said, "What do you mean by that?"&#13;
&#13;
He said, "Well, you know, there's a lot ofthings interesting about rice. Rice has more silicon in&#13;
its cellular structure. It's a high silicate. How does it get the silica? Where does it get it from?&#13;
It gets it from the soiL How does it separate out silica? That's a very, very--that's sand. It's a&#13;
very difficult thing. It has silicon and carbon, but it mixes the silicon with the carbon. Where&#13;
does it get it? Secondly, rice is anaerobic. It really doesn't rely on the water environment, but&#13;
it's not an environment in which there's going to be a lot of microorganisms and so on and so&#13;
forth available. How does it get this? Where does it get its oxygen from? At least in the forest&#13;
plants where you get oxygen and so on, they put up leaves from the roots to take the oxygen out.&#13;
Where does it get its oxygen from? How does it get its oxygen?" And he went through a series&#13;
of these things.&#13;
&#13;
Hill looked at him and said, "Look, the job ofthis thing is to double rice yields in Asia in the&#13;
next ten years. If you think it's going to be done with knowing about oxygen and knowing about&#13;
silicon and so on, fine, but you're going to have to convince me. What we want to do is double&#13;
rice yields."&#13;
&#13;
And the press were absolutely--they opened it up, and the press were there.&#13;
&#13;
And they took four plots outside the Rice Institute in the Philippines. The first plot: the way the'&#13;
Filipino farmers farm rice. The second plot: the way the college of agriculture tells them to&#13;
farm rice. The third plot: the way we do it in Texas, Hank [Henry M.] Beachell, Mr. Rice in the&#13;
United States, Hank had his sign out. The fourth plot was Sterling Wortman, who was the&#13;
Deputy Director, and Sterling was a very good guy.&#13;
&#13;
Sterling had visited me in India. As he came through, he said, "I'm not going to let you damned&#13;
economists tell me what to do." Sterling was head of the Pineapple Institute in Hawaii; before&#13;
that he was with CIMMYT, with the Rockefeller program in Mexico, the early Rockefeller&#13;
program. "I'm going to show you what rice will do. I'm going to really show you what rice will&#13;
do."&#13;
&#13;
And I said, "Fine."&#13;
&#13;
Okay, the press arrived for the opening salvoes and so on. All these little plots were out here,&#13;
and the rice was around about yay-high. That's what they took pictures of. Then they did what&#13;
the press should never do: they followed it up. They harvested. They were there when they cut&#13;
these plots. And the first plot was four tons per hectare of rice, a good Filipino yield. The&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        W. David Hopper&#13;
                              April 2 and May 12,2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                  33&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
second plot was three tons per hectare, but we always knew the college of agriculture wasn't all&#13;
that good. Hank Beachell's plot, Mr. Rice from Texas A&amp;M [University], was one ton per&#13;
hectare. So much for the Americans. Wortman's plot--they harvested the damnedest crop of&#13;
straw and not one head of rice, not one grain of rice. The press had a ball with this, you know,&#13;
10 billion dollar Institute, these highly-paid gringos that are here and so on, all they did was&#13;
demonstrate that the Filipino farmer knew how to farm rice. And it was-it was blind.&#13;
&#13;
Frosty--I was in New York, fertilizer again--Frosty asked me to go back to the Rice Institute and&#13;
go back through there to see what's going on. When I arrived, everybody was in the doldrums.&#13;
God, it was ...&#13;
&#13;
Okay. What they did was to get their geneticist--who was the guy who said, "This is what we&#13;
needed to know, how to get the silicon, and the rest of if'--to talk with the Japanese that they got&#13;
on. Now, the Japanese came from Hokkaido, up in northern Japan, and was considered to be&#13;
quite eminent in the rice field, but his English wasn't very good. The more scotch you poured&#13;
into him, the better his English was. They dumped about, I guess--Chivas Regal is what he&#13;
wanted to drink--they dumped, I don't know, a case of Chivas Regal into him or something. He&#13;
began talking about what they did in Taiwan. They had a Taiwanese on the staff that they&#13;
brought in from Taiwan, Taichung. He said, "Yes, yes, the Japanese rice--the dwarf rices--the&#13;
Japanese--that's in Taichung."&#13;
&#13;
So they brought the Taichung genes down. They crossed those with an Indonesian rice, and they&#13;
produced IR8. They did a whole series of these crosses. And as Beachell would tell you, what&#13;
Borlaug would tell you also, and that is, that when you're dealing in these developing countries,&#13;
you can get 25,000 crosses, whereas the best you could do in the United States is maybe two&#13;
hundred because it's expensive to trace them. They crossed all over the place. I went out with&#13;
Beachell to look at some of this stuff that was crossed, and it was-he was cutting them and so&#13;
on and so forth.&#13;
&#13;
But they separated out the IR8 from the others, a little short plant like this that just stood up to&#13;
the winds and produced rice like crazy. Nobody had ever heard of eight tons--not even in Texas-&#13;
-and that's what they got. So that became one ofthe things. But this was later. This was in the&#13;
60s--'64, '65, et cetera. Borlaug's wheats had come in '62, and we got them.&#13;
&#13;
Okay, rice and wheat are now well in hand in India. We did the same thing with sorghums. We&#13;
did the same thing with jowar or the different plant foods and so on and so forth. The&#13;
Rockefeller program was a big program, and it just passed it over to the Indians.&#13;
&#13;
In '69, Hill and--and they had formed two other institutes. They had the Rice Institute they&#13;
formed out of the Mexican thing. They created another one down at CIA T [International Center&#13;
for Tropical Agriculture], which was the Columbia program, the old Columbia program of the&#13;
Rockefeller Foundation. And this is the agriculture in-it's in, oh god, names--anyway, it's in&#13;
CIA T. CIA T' s in Columbia outside of Bogota but--down to Cali; if s in Cali, just outside of&#13;
Cali. And they created a new one in Ibadan, Nigeria, called liTA, the International Institute for&#13;
Tropical Agriculture. And it was going to deal with rain forests and not so--the northern areas,&#13;
which are desert. And the two foundations--Hill said twenty years to the Rockefeller Foundation&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        W. David Hopper&#13;
                              April 2 and May 12, 2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                    34&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
for IRRI [International Rice Research Institute], and then he added these other three institutes.&#13;
Harrar did the same thing, and then they decided this was getting pretty rich for their blood, so&#13;
Hill decided let's do something.&#13;
&#13;
They got a hold of McNamara and they got a hold of--oh, what's his name, who was with the,&#13;
the head of the UNDP [United Nations Development Program]. (I'll think of his name, too.)&#13;
They got them to sponsor, along with the World Bank, a meeting at Bellagio in Italy, in which&#13;
the Rockefeller--there's a Rockefeller villa that they hold up in Bellagio. It was given to them by&#13;
the Rockefeller Foundation back in the 1950s. It's a beautiful villa, absolutely gorgeous. It sits&#13;
on Lake Bellagio. It sits up high and so on. And they brought the heads of the donor agency,&#13;
had Maurice Strong from Canada, and the French, and the Norwegians, and the Brits, the U.S.,&#13;
and so on--to this meeting&#13;
&#13;
They brought a group of us in to present the thing. I was with the group. Hill brought somebody&#13;
in from Madison Avenue, an advertising agency, to check us out. We gave a scientific&#13;
presentation, had 150 slides and so on.&#13;
&#13;
The guy from Madison A venue said, "How many?" because we met with him first.&#13;
&#13;
We said, "150."&#13;
&#13;
He said, "ISO? Twenty!"&#13;
&#13;
We went through this--we worked until two a.m. in the morning going through this damn&#13;
presentation. Well, he just--"What are you saying? It's either this way or it's not." It was a very&#13;
simpleton--Oeorge Bush "You're either with me or agin' me," you know. "Don't keep&#13;
modifying it. 'The evidence seems to be,' et cetera." He said, "It's either there or it isn't there.&#13;
You either have the wheat or you didn't have it." We had pictures of the wheat, so we have it.&#13;
&#13;
We made the presentation the next day. It went over magnificently, a lot of discussion over the&#13;
lunch period late in the afternoon and so on. That evening they had a pianist come in and play&#13;
the piano and so on. We had things to drink after dinner. And the discussions got tighter and&#13;
tighter, as the outside agencies are saying, "How do we do it? I mean, we give money to&#13;
countries. We don't give money to institutes and so on."&#13;
&#13;
And the next day, it just boiled up. And suddenly McNamara banged the table and said, "Damn&#13;
it! We've all been concerned with agriculture. We've all failed on it. Here's the one thing we&#13;
have that's succeeded. Now let's do something about it, and we can't let it go."&#13;
&#13;
And Maurice Strong from Canada was sitting there, and Maurice said, "Bob, you've got a CO&#13;
for just about everything. Why don't you have one for agricultural research?"&#13;
&#13;
And McNamara looked at him and said, "That's a good idea. Would you support it?"&#13;
&#13;
And around the table was, "Yeah, we would." The Bank would run this.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        W. David Hopper&#13;
                              April 2 and May 12, 2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                      35&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
So McNamara came back. This was '69. We had a meeting, another meeting of the technicians.&#13;
I was now with IDRC--I was with Rockefeller at that time--I was now with the IDRC in Canada,&#13;
just starting it. We had a meeting with the technicians, others around the table, to how do we&#13;
create this and what do we do. February of '70. Then we met two or three times. McNamara&#13;
had a hell of a time getting it through his board, getting it through the countries, and so on.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: Why do you think that was?&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: Well, because it was different. I mean, you know, a consultative group for--the&#13;
consortium that India had and Pakistan had was replaced by the aid groups. The aid groups, they&#13;
didn't want the pledges, so we didn't have pledges. Then we moved from that point to--well, we&#13;
didn't--the first aid groups met and no pledges. And everybody said, "Well, what are we doing&#13;
really? What are we doing? We've got to have pledges."&#13;
&#13;
So the aid group, they came down and they said, "Are you really going to put the money up or&#13;
are you not?"&#13;
&#13;
Well, then there was complaining: "if you move to Africa and the rest of it, how are we going to&#13;
pledge this? We've got problems. We don't know what's going on," et cetera, et cetera.&#13;
&#13;
So that became consultative group, CGs. So we now had a consultative group for this. This is&#13;
where the donors meet and sit around and consult as to what they were going to put into these&#13;
centers and create new ones.&#13;
&#13;
He got it through the board eventually. And we had a meeting in December of '70 up in the Ford&#13;
Foundation in New York, in which it was all set to go. And the major meeting then was to be&#13;
done with the countries in March of '71, and that's when the CG was created basically.&#13;
&#13;
And we've added to them. It's now sixteen institutes.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: I went on their web site and noticed there's now a fisheries institute.&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: Yes. Well, there's a fisheries institute. There's a couple of forestry institutes. I was&#13;
chairman of the CG when the forestry institute was created, and we didn't want another CG, so&#13;
we kind of added it in. And the foresters lined up and an awful lot of others did to protect the&#13;
tropical forests and all the rest of it.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: Okay. One question I had-I mean, just speaking of the Green Revolution&#13;
there's been a lot of talk back and forth about the pros and cons and critiques of it and all that.&#13;
How did you feel in the' 80s when it got criticized and all the work that you had seen done and&#13;
the accomplishments that had happened?&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: I ignored it, and I still ignore it. I mean, I pick these things up. I read about them&#13;
and so on and so forth. There's good friends of mine who have been involved and so on and so&#13;
forth.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        W. David Hopper&#13;
                              April 2 and May 12, 2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                       36&#13;
&#13;
Look, the population growth is still there. And if you listen to Lester Brown and read his Plan B,&#13;
"We've got two years before we run into global food shortage again." Well, all right. We've got&#13;
a global food surplus at the present moment.&#13;
&#13;
We're putting three billion dollars--or, sorry, 312 billion dollars a year into food or agricultural&#13;
subsidies in this country, Europe, and Japan. The developing countries are raising hell with&#13;
Cancun [trade negotiations] and the WTO [World Trade Organization] and so on and so forth&#13;
because the one export that they've got, they can't export. You've got a bunch of sugar guys&#13;
who are moving the candy manufacturing out of Chicago and elsewhere because they can buy&#13;
sugar more cheaply someplace else than they can in the United States because we've got a big,&#13;
big sugar subsidy, going down to Florida to build sugar.&#13;
&#13;
Canada is sitting on oranges because, thank God, we don't produce oranges and we can buy them&#13;
in from BraziL The US is raising hell because it's outside of the Canadian agreement with the&#13;
U.S. Well, we blended that agreement into NAFTA [North American Free Trade Agreement].&#13;
"So can we buy the oranges from Mexico?"&#13;
&#13;
"No," because they've got a subsidy going to oranges in California and Texas--Texas&#13;
particularly--and Florida.&#13;
&#13;
[End Tape 2, Side A]&#13;
[Begin Tape 2, Side B]&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: We're going to have GM [genetically modified] crops, regardless of what you say.&#13;
Eventually, in my view, agriculture is going to be "Why the hell do we need a cow to get beef&#13;
when we know the chemicals and the genes that are going to produce it? Why don't we just put&#13;
those genes into a mill, feed in the appropriate materials, and slice it off the beef steaks coming&#13;
off the bottom of this? What do you have to have a cow for?" That's far-fetched, but this is--no,&#13;
we're going to do far more than this. The Europeans--the Africans can't take GM crops because,&#13;
you know, it may affect what they're doing. They'll get around this. The Indians are now well&#13;
into it. We have the whole issue of trade relations and money going off to the side, saying, you&#13;
know, "The Indians should not be growing these new soybeans that they've got or the soy&#13;
materials because they're stealing our patented and trademarked or copyrighted materials, and&#13;
that's ours." The Indians are going like this.&#13;
&#13;
So it's now into a global, whole global set of relationships. And the globalization is just adding&#13;
to this. The U.S. just announced on the AIDS thing that the pharmaceuticals don't want to be&#13;
seen using genetic material on AIDS materials. Well, that's fine. India has a big pharmaceutical&#13;
industry. They're going to produce it, and they're going to sell it, and they're going to sell it&#13;
cheap. And here we are. "Okay, we'll go to court," Okay, this is great for the lawyers. My&#13;
wife's a lawyer, my present wife's a lawyer, so we'll go to court and watch it. And I have a son&#13;
who's an intellectual property lawyer down in Austin. We're going down to see our&#13;
grandchildren down there very shortly.&#13;
&#13;
But it's a, it's a--regardless of what we say, this is going to move forward. And we are going to&#13;
be moving into higher yields. You can say, "Okay, India has reached the peak ofthis." I don't&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         W. David Hopper&#13;
                               April 2 and May 12,2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                   37&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
think India has reached the peak at all. But it's going to mean a very different kind of fertilizer.&#13;
It's going to mean a very different kind of game. I'm not an organic food buff. I really do feel&#13;
that soils need some organic materials, and it's not going to be easy to get the way we got them&#13;
before, which is just let the straw lie and put the cattle in and run sheep across them and so on.&#13;
That's what the Indian farmers did when I lived in the village. You brought the shepherds in,&#13;
and they ran the sheep in the field and proceeded to make sure that they did their droppings on&#13;
the field so that you had it. All right. We now can do it with dust and fertilizer.&#13;
&#13;
Back in 1957 there was a meeting of the International Agricultural Economics Society. I didn't&#13;
have any way to go to it, so I didn't go to it. But Earl Heady was there from the University of&#13;
Iowa, and Earl gave me a call and could I send him somewhere. So I sent him in to talk with&#13;
Ramdari Baba [phonetic] in myoId village. Earl went in. He had a chat with Ramdari Baba&#13;
[phonetic], and he asked Ramdari [phonetic] did he use fertilizer. Ramdari [phonetic] said no.&#13;
Now, he went in with the agricultural officer ofthe district and so on and so forth and a big&#13;
entourage and the rest of it. What did I say? ' 57 is when. The entourage. He walked into the&#13;
Village. They had a good conversation with Ramdari Baba [phonetic] through an interpreter and&#13;
soon.&#13;
&#13;
Then he called me to say that he had spoken with Ramdari [phonetic]. He asked if Ramdari&#13;
[phonetic] used fertilizer, and Ramdari [phonetic] said no.&#13;
&#13;
Heady said, "Why not?"&#13;
&#13;
Ramdari [phonetic] said, "I can't afford it. I can't buy it."&#13;
&#13;
Heady came back to call me to say, "What was the price and why was this?"&#13;
&#13;
I said, "Ead, Ramdari [phonetic] could buy you out tomorrow. He's got more damn gold&#13;
bangles around the house and the rest of it than you can shake a stick at." I said, "He's worth at&#13;
least ten million dollars. What do you mean he can't afford it? I'll tell you why he doesn't use&#13;
it, because it doesn't work." I said, "I tried it on my field when I was there. He was very&#13;
interested. I didn't--the second crop that I took, I didn't pay as him much. I still paid him&#13;
because the plant I used was Punjab 591, which is the accepted plant, and the fertilizer caused it&#13;
to grow up and it lodged. The same that happened down at IRRI with the rice: put on the&#13;
fertilizer, and the rice fell over. So I paid him another go-round on this. The fertilizer doesn't&#13;
work, and he knows it doesn't work."&#13;
&#13;
So I go back to the village in '62, and I'm sitting down with Ramdari [phonetic]. I say to him,&#13;
"You know, you had Professor Heady here."&#13;
&#13;
"Yeah. It was a good discussion."&#13;
&#13;
I said, "What did you tell him you couldn't afford fertilizer for?"&#13;
&#13;
"Oh," he said, "it's simple." He said, "IfI said I can't get it, the agriculture guys would have it&#13;
down here. I don't want it. IfI said that it's very--that it doesn't work, then I'm going to get a&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         W. David Hopper&#13;
                               April 2 and May 12, 2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                 38&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
debate from Heady or from the agriculture people. 'Yes, yes, it works. It works. It works. The&#13;
Americans tell me it works. '" He said, "Tell them you're poor. Everybody knows an Indian&#13;
farmer is poor." [Laughter] So here we are.&#13;
&#13;
Now this iSM-the Green Revolution guys in this part of the world are writing not in objection to&#13;
the Green Revolution--I'm sorry, in objecting to the Green Revolution. It's done by American&#13;
scholars, et cetera, who either visit or don't or whatever else. Go to India. India, the Green&#13;
Revolution is still talked about. It's still working. It's still doing things. It's demanding of the&#13;
government better irrigation, demanding of the government more water, demanding of the&#13;
government more fertilizer. India is the second-largest user of high-quality fertilizer. China uses&#13;
more fertilizer, but it's not the real quality that India is getting. India is importing it.&#13;
&#13;
You go up into the Punjab, and what are they doing? They're producing strawberries for export,&#13;
a whole series of things. They're into fancier crops. They're not growing grain anymore up&#13;
there. They use the irrigation water for a whole set of vegetables, of other things. They're&#13;
exporting. They're exporting into Pakistan. That's illegal. No, what occurs--they go down.&#13;
They take the ships and they move over to Dubai and the Emirates, and they bring all of that into&#13;
Karachi and they sell it. And what you can buy a big chunk of fertilizer for, or what you can buy&#13;
strawberries for in India--the equivalent oftwenty-five cents a can or something else, or aseer,&#13;
two pounds, two and a half pounds--you buy in Karachi for a buck twenty-five. It comes in via&#13;
Dubai, and everybody's happy. Sure. But it's--this is the game. And that's what's going on in&#13;
India in agriculture. It's totally revolutionizing it.&#13;
&#13;
Now, the rural areas are poor, yes. You've got a billion, 100 million people, seventy percent of&#13;
them live in the rural areas still. The others have all moved into the urban centers, and the urban&#13;
centers are now our call centers, and we bitch about the off-shore and the rest of it, and I feel&#13;
sorry for the Americans that get screwed on this. But the out-sourcing is there. It's there for&#13;
intellectual property. It's there for IT [information technology]. The World Bank does all its&#13;
checks and so on and so forth out of India. They're all transmitted. IT&amp;T makes a hell of a lot&#13;
of money on their transmission cables, the optical fiber cables that they put in connecting India,&#13;
Hong Kong, and the rest of it into the United States and so on. And all of that goes out. This is&#13;
where the call centers operate through. So it's, it's--the changes are huge.&#13;
&#13;
And today's election in India is now being built on the youth. The BJP, this great Hindu fascist&#13;
party that I was always frightened of, et cetera--the BJP are now torn between young people who&#13;
are saying, "Forget it. Let's go after the rural areas. What do the rural people want? Bijli,&#13;
sarak,pani." This is power, roads, water, telecommunications, satellite things, opportunities to&#13;
hook onto Internet, and so on. You now have TV serving 200-well, about 500,000 villages.&#13;
There's 550,000 villages in India. Some ofthe others up in the hills don't quite get it.&#13;
&#13;
But, you know, when Rajiv Gandhi was assassinated in Tamil Nadu by this woman from Sri&#13;
Lanka who blew herself up and blew him up, as the prime minister and the rest of it, the&#13;
government oflndia said, "Okay, nOM-nothing on the TV, nothing on the radio with regard to&#13;
Gandhi's assassination for twelve and a half hours while we move troops because there may be&#13;
riots." 350,000 villages had TV sets. They were fix-tuned to an Indian satellite up over the&#13;
Indian Ocean. And like my little guy living in the village, I told them when they did this, told&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        W. David Hopper&#13;
                              April 2 and May 12,2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                 39&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
[V. K. Krishna] Menon, "Forget it, because what's going to occur is these guys are going to&#13;
come in, take your dish satellite and put a worm gear onto it to hook it into the American and the&#13;
British and Russian satellites down here." And that's exactly what happened. A bunch of guys&#13;
came in, shifted the satellites.&#13;
&#13;
Madonna and that group are one of the favorite programs in the Indian villages, all right? So&#13;
they sit and listen, and what broke into Madonna? Rajiv's assassination. India knew about the&#13;
assassination within three minutes of the assassination, and the government ofIndia sits there&#13;
and wanted to know how did they know this. People are talking about it. There's no news.&#13;
There's nothing. Well, you know ...&#13;
&#13;
And [Lal Krishna] Advani decided he was going to do a great Hindu trek around India. This is&#13;
the Deputy Prime Minister and the basic one of the Hindu group. Advani--this is all planned out&#13;
and so on-and the youthjust simply said, "No." They don't want to go to these things. There's&#13;
no point in holding great Hindu ceremonies and Brahmins doing their, painting your forehead&#13;
and lighting their fires and making all the mantras and the rest of it that go with this. And they&#13;
forced him to cut it down. He didn't cut it out, no, but they forced him to greatly cut it down and&#13;
to go talk economics. That reminds me of old [William J.] Clinton's slogan on the wall, "It's the&#13;
economy, stupid." [Laughter]&#13;
&#13;
FEL TAULT: It might be revived. [Laughter]&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: Anyway, we got away from the World Bank, and I've been talking long.&#13;
&#13;
FEL TAUL T: Well, World Bank and development. I mean, I have questions specifically on the&#13;
World Bank but also just, you know, development ideas and concepts and that kind of stuff. But&#13;
I think what we probably should do is maybe stop here and set a time in May to do the second&#13;
one and talk about the latter period. And that way you'll also get to see the transcript ofthis and&#13;
make any notes or comments or fill anything out that you want.&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: Yeah. What we talked about here is not my period at the Bank, really.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: But I think it's a formative period of you getting to the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: That's right. That's exactly what it is.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: And the sociology of knowledge that comes along.&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: And this is--I mean, it was McNamara who invited me in. We worked like that. It&#13;
was really very good. I didn't have any deep arguments with him or anything else.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAUL T: Right. And that was something that I wanted to get into, I think, in the second&#13;
one, talking about, you know, his development philosophy, your development philosophy, and&#13;
how they worked together to kind of move forward, and then what happened in the' 80s when he&#13;
left.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        W. David Hopper&#13;
                              April 2 and May 12, 2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                             40&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: Okay.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: Good.&#13;
&#13;
[End Tape 2, Side B]&#13;
[End of session]&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                 W. David Hopper&#13;
                       April 2 and May 12, 2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                 41&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                           Session 2&#13;
                                         May 12,2004&#13;
                                        Washington, D.C.&#13;
&#13;
[Begin Tape 1, Side A]&#13;
&#13;
 HOPPER: I'm W. David Hopper. It's the l2th of May, 2004. You asked about the Bank&#13;
 archives having relatively little on my personal activities as Vice President of South Asia. There&#13;
 are three reasons for this. One is that I came to theM-accepted the position of Vice President for&#13;
 South Asia after having known Bob McNamara, who was then the President, since, for about a&#13;
.decade. He took over at the Bank in 1967. I saw him in India in 1968. I was connected with&#13;
 some other activities that he had through the Rockefeller Foundation, and I was working for the&#13;
 Rockefeller Foundation at the time, 1969, but I was living in New Delhi. I used to get telephone&#13;
 calls from him about every--about twice a week, 3 A.M. in the morning my time, as we&#13;
 discussed the issue of food production in India.&#13;
&#13;
I was quite close, as I think I said before, to Mrs. Gandhi, who was then Prime Minister, and to&#13;
members of her cabinet. I had been an advisor to the Ministry of Food and Agriculture in India&#13;
and the Planning Commission. I had been on two or three Indian committees that took a look at&#13;
different things, everything from energy to food production and so on. I was known to the&#13;
Reserve Bank of India, and I was down in Bombay several times on the issues of that kind and at&#13;
Bombay University.&#13;
&#13;
When I came to the Bank in January 1978, McNamara as President had offered me two other&#13;
posts as potentially in--neither post intrigued me because they were both what I'm going to call,&#13;
using Machiavelli's The Prince in which Machiavelli divides up the courtiers from the barons-&#13;
and the posts which he wanted me or had offered me or asked if I was interested in were both&#13;
courtier posts.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAUL T: Okay. What were those posts?&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: One was the general supervision of project activities that were going on. The other&#13;
was related to the general stance of the Bank under his new reorganization which created vice&#13;
presidencies for different areas. We had talked about a Vice President for Africa, and I had said,&#13;
well, I might be interested, but I didn't speak French sufficiently well to feel that I was&#13;
comfortable there. I had been in Africa. I had been in several countries in Africa--Nigeria,&#13;
Kenya, Ethiopia, and so on--when I was with the Rockefeller Foundation and before that with&#13;
the Ford Foundation. But Asia was much more my field, and the Asia post was not open. But he&#13;
wanted somebody to kind of take a look at the broad issues that related to planning projects and&#13;
that sort of thing, and that did not intrigue me. This was kind of in-house, and I would be a&#13;
courtier.&#13;
&#13;
The Bank at that time was divided between the courtiers and the barons. I was Vice President&#13;
for South Asia. It was an area I knew very well. I spoke Bhojpuri and Hindi. I could get along&#13;
in what is Urdu or Hindustani and kutcha Urdu. I used the term kutcha and pukka. I'll use that&#13;
periodically. Kutcha means a mud house, an unpaved road, a dessert that doesn't taste very&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        W. David Hopper&#13;
                              April 2 and May 12, 2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                 42&#13;
&#13;
good. It's kutcha. Pukka means a brick house, a paved road, a dessert that is really very good,&#13;
or a meal that is very good. It's a pukka meal; it's a pukka this; it's a pukka that. Hindustani&#13;
was, as a language, kind of borrowed from the Portuguese, the British, the Dutch, and so on and&#13;
Indian terms. This was what they generally spoke. All India kind of knew Hindustani, one form&#13;
or another. Urdu was an Arabic written language but was close to Hindustani. You understood&#13;
it back and forth. So I spoke some Hindustani, and I spoke a more pukka Hindi, and I spoke a&#13;
village dialect known as Bhojpuri. In all these cases, I spoke in kutcha terms.&#13;
&#13;
But the--I did not feel it necessary to--I traveled to India with some frequency. I visited Pakistan&#13;
with frequency. I was on first-name basis with not just th~ prime minister but the President of&#13;
Pakistan, [Muhammad] Zia-ul-Haq, flew around in his airplane, saw different things going on. I&#13;
was aware of Tarbela Dam before Pakistan--before I came to the Bank. I had visited Asia with a&#13;
great deal of activity. Sri Lanka, Bangladesh, et cetera, were kind of home countries that I knew.&#13;
And I didn't feel it necessary in dealing with my staff or otherwise to put out memos or anything&#13;
else with regard to this.&#13;
&#13;
I went to the aid consortiums. I knew more about what was going on in these countries and with&#13;
the country delegations than any other delegation around the table. It wasn't necessary. I ran the&#13;
consortiums. I had a reputation of being a very, very balanced but tough chairman. I could talk&#13;
to the Indian or Pakistani or Sri Lankan or Bangladeshi, et cetera, groups that came to these aid&#13;
group meetings or consortium meetings. And India and Pakistan were consortiums; the others&#13;
were aid groups. And there was a difference in supposedly what was done, but under me there&#13;
wasn't much difference.&#13;
&#13;
FELT AULT: Lending practices or ...&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: No. The consortium started off in 1958 with-oh, god. I suffer from what is now&#13;
known as double-A-M-I. It used to be called M-C-I, mild cognitive impairment, but they've&#13;
decided that M-C-I was kind of the beginning of Alzheimer's. But it occurs with older people.&#13;
It is now called double-A-M-I because it doesn't necessarily lead into Alzheimer's. Double-A-&#13;
M-I is age-associated memory impairment. And I have difficulty remembering names,&#13;
particularly, not geography but names. I can find my way around in a great many areas. And I'll&#13;
think of them very frequently after you go. [Laughter]&#13;
&#13;
FEL T AULT: Just write them down. [Laughter]&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: The President of the World Bank at the time, Gene Black, Eugene Black--India had&#13;
a crisis, Pakistan had a crisis in 1957 when the food production dropped, and I think I mentioned&#13;
that before. This led the Bank then, under Black, to be concerned because they had loaned&#13;
money to India on fairly high interest rates and so on, standard interest rates in the Bank, and&#13;
India made it quite clear that they were having difficulty paying it off. So Black worked with the&#13;
U.S. government to create what is known as IDA. IDA came out of this, and India was an IDA&#13;
country. And that's where we put long-term loans, three-quarters of one percent interest rates,&#13;
ten-year grace, forty-year repayment period, a fifty-year loan, basically.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        W. David Hopper&#13;
                              April 2 and May 12, 2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                   43&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
He also decided to create a consortia for India of aid donors who were interested in coming to&#13;
India. That was the consortia. It was created in 1958, and I was there at its 25 th anniversary.&#13;
&#13;
[Interruption]&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: Okay. He established the consortia. He built IDA. He arranged for the Bank to do&#13;
something it had never done before, which was to lengthen the loan periods on original loans for&#13;
poorer countries, low-income countries, and India was one of these. Now that the Bank has&#13;
denied kind of providing it to individual countries, but he just moved it blanket-wise, and the&#13;
Board, governing Board agreed to this. He opened up an office in Delhi, which was the first real&#13;
office outside of the World Bank. It was never a very powerful office; at least it wasn't then.&#13;
That's changed with Jim [James D.] Wolfensohn. But it was an office that kept a dialogue going&#13;
with the government of India, and I was part of that.&#13;
&#13;
I found it easy to go. I mean, I could arrive in India or in Pakistan, et cetera, and have private&#13;
conversations with them and decide this is where we want to go, come back and tell my staff,&#13;
and this was it. It wasn't necessary, or at least I didn't feel it necessary, to make substantial&#13;
notes or to dictate that this was my conversation with Zia-ul-Haq, et cetera. Indeed, there were&#13;
conversations with several of these people that they would be upset and distressed if they'd&#13;
known that I had put them down in notes because it's not part of what was there.&#13;
&#13;
The records that you have on South Asia in the archives are records that occurred when we did&#13;
projects, when we did other things, and where my advice and working with my Bank staff&#13;
closely was, "Okay, I'll check this out or I'll discuss it or this is what I'm getting when my&#13;
feedback is in there."&#13;
&#13;
An example of this, which is a story that--I'm not sure I want to put this in the notes, but&#13;
anyway, I may strike out some ofthese things. But Zia-ul-Haq was a military man who had&#13;
taken over when Pakistan got into deep difficulty with the elected representatives and so on.&#13;
Zulfiqar Ali Bhutto had taken over, and Bhutto--one of the first things that Bhutto did (and I was&#13;
then in Canada at Ottawa at the IDRC) was to call a meeting, a first meeting, of the Islamic&#13;
states. You'd had Arab groups. You'd had others. This was a big, big Islamic conference that&#13;
brought everybody from Indonesia to Morocco into the picture and up into Afghanistan and&#13;
Turkmenistan and so on, central Asia. They were part of the Russian picture, but they sent&#13;
delegates to this. It was held in Lahore.&#13;
&#13;
And Bhutto called for the establishment of an Islamic group. Roosevelt had called the United&#13;
States the "Arsenal of Democracy" in the Second World War, and that the U.S. then provided the&#13;
airplanes and so on. It wasn't until Pearl Harbor that they actually entered the war, but they were&#13;
doing an awful lot of support to Britain and the rest of it after the fall of France. It was the&#13;
arsenal of democracy. What he wanted was an arsenal for Islam, an Islamic arsenal. That would&#13;
mean that he put in a steel mill, which they didn't have in any of the Islamic countries. And they&#13;
did; they put one down at Karachi or outside of Karachi. It meant that--among the things that he&#13;
said is that, "You know, we have a Christian bomb"--United States, Britain, and so on--"We&#13;
have an atheist bomb"--this is the Russians' hydrogen bomb or the--not a hydrogen bomb, but,&#13;
oh, anyway, whatever the metal is; I'll think of it in a moment--"We have an Oriental bomb,"&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        W. David Hopper&#13;
                              April 2 and May 12,2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                   44&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
namely, China's discovery of the bomb. This is '74, so everything went back to this area. "We&#13;
have a French bomb, a European bomb. What we need is an Islamic bomb."&#13;
&#13;
That led them then to start negotiations under Bhutto with China in terms of building a potential&#13;
Pakistani bomb or Islamic bomb. And the discussions that you're reading now about [Abdul&#13;
Qadeer] Khan providing materials for a bomb, just an ordinary bomb to, that is a--what's the&#13;
term I want? Uranium bomb--providing uranium materials, U-235, which is a separated thing, or&#13;
even plutonium, which is a step up in the uranium, natural uranium. Providing those bombs was&#13;
all part of this Islamic bomb thing--Libya, et cetera, et cetera, et cetera.&#13;
&#13;
Okay, Bhutto was a pain in the neck of the army. He began to try to build too much. He was a&#13;
Sindhi, and the bulk of the army is Punjabi, and there is no love lost between the Sindhisand the&#13;
Punjabis. The Punjabis came in from the west and came in from British India and so on and so&#13;
forth. The Sindhis were kind of very comfortable in the southern area around the Indus River&#13;
and Islamic but not--they didn't feel the muscles. They were not the military group; the Punjabis&#13;
were. And when Bhutto began mucking around with this and beginning to hit the army et cetera,&#13;
the army decided he had to go.&#13;
&#13;
He was--Zia-ul-Haq came in, and one of his main problems was getting rid of Bhutto. I once&#13;
advised Zia-ul-Haq that he ought to send him offto--as they did with a good friend of mine in&#13;
Egypt, send him to Finland as the Egyptian ambassador to Finland and picked up his passport so&#13;
he had to sit there. I suggested to Bhutto that he might send--or said to Zia-ul-Haq that he might&#13;
send Bhutto, oh, maybe to Cyprus or Norway or somewhere and just let him sit. Unfortunately,&#13;
the army said no, and he was hanged for, as far as I was concerned, a rather stupid accident that&#13;
he got into, and somebody was killed, and Bhutto was considered the cause of it. By the way,&#13;
his daughter has recently been in Washington.&#13;
&#13;
But Haq wanted--they built Tarbela Dam; they wanted to build Kalabagh. This is a big dam that&#13;
the Bank had gone on, we had gone with, et cetera. It was on the Indus River. It would have&#13;
been a marvelous addition. But I couldn't get them to sign some agreements, so I went to&#13;
Pakistan and said, "You know, the Bank is prepared to set this up. We're prepared to provide it.&#13;
We have other donors who are willing to join us the consortium." And I told them the story of&#13;
an old Jewish merchant, who every Saturday went to the synagogue and prayed that this coming&#13;
week, "Lord, please let me win the lottery. I want to win the lottery. God, please let me win the&#13;
lottery." And he never won the lottery. He was getting old. His wife was ailing. His kids had&#13;
left home. He was alone. His business was not booming. And he went to the synagogue and&#13;
said, "God, every week I've asked you. I've been here. I've been a good Jew. God, I've been&#13;
such a good Jew I've never even eaten a ham sandwich. What are we doing? I've asked and&#13;
asked and asked to win the lottery, and I've never won the lottery. God, ifI don't win the lottery&#13;
this week, you won't see me here again. I will have lost my faith." Suddenly the synagogue&#13;
clouds over, and a sonorous voice says, "Moise, Moise. Give me a break. Buy a ticket!" I said&#13;
to Zia-ul-Haq, "You know, on Kalabagh give me a break. Buy a ticket." He laughed and there&#13;
was a long pause.&#13;
&#13;
He said, "Look, my plane will be ready in half an hour. You go out to the airport. We'll get a&#13;
car to get you out to the airport. I want you to fly up to Peshawar and talk with the governor."&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        W. David Hopper&#13;
                              April 2 and May 12, 2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                  45&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
So I got on the plane, flew up to Peshawar and talked with the governor. The governor met me&#13;
at the airport. I said I was here. He said, "I know exactly why you're here. Let's go to the fort."&#13;
We went to the old British fort in Peshawar. And he said, "Mr. Hopper, I'll tell you there isn't&#13;
going to be a Kalabagh."&#13;
&#13;
And I said, "Well, why not? We need the water. You need the water. You need the power.&#13;
You need the irrigation systems that come from it. It's part ofthe Indus Treaty. It's part of the&#13;
things that were worked on that the Bank was a signatory to, the Indus Treaty in 1960."&#13;
&#13;
He said, "Mr. Hopper, let me tell you. Do you know what happened at Tarbela?" Tarbela was&#13;
the other big dam, the second biggest--well, the biggest earth-filled dam in the world at the&#13;
present time, holding back the Indus River. He said, "You know, that's a big reservoir behind&#13;
that dam." And he said, "The people were never paid." There was a big rumor circulating that&#13;
the government wasn't going to pay them. The water was going to rise, they closed off the&#13;
coffer dams, the water was beginning to come up, the government hasn't made any&#13;
announcement to reimburse them for the land that would be flooded and so on. He said, "About&#13;
three months as the water was rising a group of people came in and said, 'Look, the government&#13;
is not doing anything, but we're willing--this is a charity--we're willing to buy the land. We&#13;
can't pay you very much, but we can pay you now for it. Just sign it over.' And they signed&#13;
over 85 percent of the land that would be affected by this flooding. The peasantry were moved&#13;
off the land. They had these small returns. One month before the major closing to raise the&#13;
water, the government announced a big, big payment for the land. It was done. Five families&#13;
had arranged to buy this land, including the family ofthe then President." He said, "The outcry&#13;
was immense." He said, "Mr. Hopper, until they say to the people at Kalabagh who will be&#13;
displaced by the reservoir that's there, until they offer them a very, very handsome sum for the&#13;
land they will lose, there will not be a Kalabagh." He said, "I tell you this because there will be a&#13;
revolt."&#13;
&#13;
So I went back to see Zia, and I said, "Well, this is what I was told."&#13;
&#13;
He said, "I know, I know. I've heard it. I've heard it. I've heard it. You don't need to tell me."&#13;
But he said, "Mr. Hopper, I will tell you that there is no way that I can arrange that kind of a&#13;
thing." He said, "The situation in Pakistan is such that I cannot do it." Kalabagh was never&#13;
built.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: It's interesting because ..&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: Now, just a minute. I come back to the Bank. Do I go through this with the Bank?&#13;
I did with McNamara, but I mean he's gone now. This was in the days of [Alden W.] Clausen. I&#13;
don't go to talk with Clausen. I just simply tell my friends that, "Look, Kalabagh is out; we're&#13;
not in it."&#13;
&#13;
Now, this is a good deal of what I was doing as the Vice President for South Asia. We got an&#13;
awful lot done, including the Outfall Bank on the lower Indus River, a bunch of poya [phonetic]&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        W. David Hopper&#13;
                              April 2 and May 12,2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                   46&#13;
&#13;
lakes in which you took the salty material off and let it evaporate so that the salt was there but it&#13;
didn't affect the land that you had, et cetera.&#13;
&#13;
I go through this merely to point out that I was an activist, and I didn't kind of do this. I got&#13;
along very well with McNamara. I got along well with Clausen, once he understood my role in&#13;
all of this. I didn't spend time writing notes for him, et cetera. I didn't need to. He was a bright&#13;
person, and it wasn't necessary. My colleagues, in traveling with him, were continuously&#13;
preparing this for him, preparing that for him, writing this, writing that, writing something else. I&#13;
didn't. I took him into Pakistan, I took him into India, I took him into Bangladesh, I took him&#13;
into various places. And I would arrange for him to go to places, took McNamara to this mud&#13;
village I lived in in India and trotted him around to meet people, et cetera. No, I did not. I was&#13;
not a: "This is what we ought to do: one, two, three, four, five six." It was: "How do you make&#13;
the adjustment over what we are doing and what we're talking about to the circumstances which&#13;
they face?"&#13;
&#13;
Now, this did lead to a series of things. On Bangladesh, for example, I was very, very concerned&#13;
about how they held a democratic union in Bangladesh. This was after they'd had two or three&#13;
military men. Ziaur Rahman, who was the guy in Bangladesh that took over after the slaughter&#13;
in '76, '75, I developed a very close relation with Ziaur Rahman as the military commander in&#13;
this. He was assassinated in 1980, and I was very, very upset by it. But one ofthe things he&#13;
wanted to do was to move this country slowly back to a democracy.&#13;
&#13;
Okay, I had people in the Bank who were saying, "Okay, now he's gone. Now let's, we'll get&#13;
the democratic elements running here. We're away," and the rest of it. I was very, very&#13;
concerned that we not--that we not move in and try to be the dictator with our money that says,&#13;
"This is what we do." 1 got into lots of trouble with Ernie [Ernest] Stem and a series of others.&#13;
who wanted things done this way. But I didn't have any difficulty in moving either McNamara&#13;
or Clausen that this is how we ought to do it. We do it slowly. We do it the way it goes.&#13;
&#13;
Bangladesh is a mess today, yes, but it's a democratic mess, in one sense. The military are not in&#13;
there. You have two women, Ziaur Rahman's widow and the daughter ofthe man who was the&#13;
sheik who took over after the separation of East Pakistan, which is now Bangladesh, from the&#13;
West Pakistan. He was killed and his family all shot down except that the daughter was out in&#13;
Britain. These two women are at each other's throats. Their parties change every election&#13;
period. It's not a balanced country. It's not the kind of place you'd like to see, but it has met its&#13;
food requirements. It has done a series of other things. And they remain being poets and so on&#13;
because Bangladeshis are nothing if not poets.&#13;
&#13;
All right, I don't know whether this explains ...&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: Yeah, no, this is good, because it was kind of funny. I was just curious why there&#13;
weren't similar files for the two positions. And, you know, it was hard for me to find out what&#13;
your role was as, you know, the Vice President of South Asia, so maybe you could talk a little bit&#13;
more about how you saw--when you came in, what were the portfolios like and what did you see&#13;
as strategies?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         W. David Hopper&#13;
                               April 2 and May 12, 2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                 47&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: I saw a very good portfolio group. I think that I altered some things that had been&#13;
there. I held quite a few more meetings. I dug into the--the Bank under McNamara had a&#13;
projects unit and a, basically, program policy unit. I found the program policy unit very, very&#13;
kind of much more, you know, "This is what we ought to do; this is how we ought to do it," and&#13;
so on and so forth, than I felt was relevant. I felt that they didn't really understand--and many&#13;
times many of them did; it would be wrong to say that this was--but they really were much more&#13;
kind of "This is how we function, this is what we do in this institution, and this is what we expect&#13;
from them," et cetera. This was kind of the program policy unit.&#13;
&#13;
The project group were, I found to be extraordinarily good. They had an irrigation guy who&#13;
really knew a hell of a lot about irrigation, an Israeli. They had a very, very good power group,&#13;
electric power group. They had a first-rate group dealing with education, roads, the&#13;
infrastructure, the railroad issues, and so on. And I found that they were blocked many times by&#13;
the program unit and by a separate unit that was outside of this, under Warren Baum, that kind of&#13;
reviewed everything and made sure that the numbers were there and that the rates of return were&#13;
adequate, and so on and so forth. And I used to tease McNamara in that, you know, ifhe wanted&#13;
a rate of return, I can give him a rate of return. So what? If they wanted ten percent, would you&#13;
like it eleven percent or twelve percent? I can do that, too. All it is is mucking around with&#13;
numbers. And I used to tease Bob on these things. You know, I'd get a telephone call from him&#13;
saying, "I just noticed this." I'd say, "Yes, yes, I know. We're doing our best."&#13;
&#13;
In Delhi, in the Delhi office and in the Pakistan office--because there was a Pakistan office at&#13;
that time--I opened up a Bangladesh office; I opened up a small office in Sri Lanka. The general&#13;
attitude is, "What Washington doesn't know won't hurt them. Now let's get on with the job."&#13;
And that's what we did. I became very close to [Junius Richard] Jayawardene in Sri Lanka. He&#13;
wasn't doing what the World Bank wanted him to do, so he and I had some conversations about&#13;
it. And the World Bank adjusted their position, he adjusted his, and we got along fine.&#13;
&#13;
In part, Kelly, it--there was a repetition ofthis. There was one more. There was a man from&#13;
Panama who became Vice President for Latin America, and he and I just worked exactly the&#13;
same way. You have to know what's going on in these countries. You can't go in from the&#13;
outside. You can't move in. And one of my problems since leaving the vice presidency for&#13;
South Asia was that Joe [D. Joseph] Wood took over. Joe I knew very, very well, but he was a&#13;
monetary specialist in the Bank, much more over in the Treasury, and he came in as Vice&#13;
President for South Asia. He didn't know South Asia. I mean, he didn't know how the Nepalese&#13;
think. He didn't know how they worked. He didn't know what it was. I'd traveled over Nepal&#13;
with the crown prince before he became King Birendra, and I was the first foreigner to be&#13;
received by Birendra after his father died, King Mahendra died. I was in Canada then. I was&#13;
with the IDRC in Canada.&#13;
&#13;
I take a look at the group now. I mean, if I can go down the vice presidents since then: a&#13;
Japanese girl who I hired and put into Bangladesh and who was suddenly made Vice President&#13;
for South Asia. She knew nothing about South Asia. The guy they have now, [Praful C.] Patel,&#13;
he come,s from an Indian family, but he comes from Uganda. It was one of the families booted&#13;
out by Idi Amin when he booted out the Indians. He was a Gujarati family. He went to Britain.&#13;
The British allowed--brought in Indians into Kenya, Uganda, Tanzania--or it became&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        W. David Hopper&#13;
                              April 2 and May 12, 2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                     48&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Tanganyika, but now Tanzania. They stayed, and these are the offspring. But Patel, if I have&#13;
any difficulty with him, it's not that he doesn't speak Gujarati; he does. But there is a feel that&#13;
you can only get when you really move around in these circumstances, and you've got to be alert&#13;
to it.&#13;
&#13;
I was asked some years ago after I left the Bank by Manmohan Singh, who is a very good friend&#13;
of mine--he was the Minister of Finance then--could I come in and do basically the same thing&#13;
that was done by Crawford, Sir 10hn Crawford from Australia, on agriculture that led to the&#13;
Green Revolution, which now seemed to be drifting. I said yes, I'd be delighted to do this, and I&#13;
had a supporter from here who was willing to pay for it, not the Bank. But I went to see the ag&#13;
minister, and it was quite clear in the conversation with the agriculture minister, who was a&#13;
Punjabi, that he didn't feel there was any necessity for an outsider to come in and take a look at&#13;
it. They could handle it. We talked about it. We visited--I visited some of his secretaries and so&#13;
on and so forth, and I came away with the feeling that the finance ministry may be concerned,&#13;
but clearly the ag ministry isn't, and that it isn't necessary. It just wasn't. They'll find a way out&#13;
of it. It won't necessarily be the way I'd recommend, but it's where it is.&#13;
&#13;
And I think, again, we're dictating now from the Bank. I mean, let's-you know, we're going to&#13;
do this, the millennial goals, and we're going to do that, and we're going to do something else,&#13;
and here we go. And this election which is just winding up is a clear mandate that--well, it isn't&#13;
so clear, the mandate. But the issue is that the B1P, who felt they were going to take this thing--&#13;
this is the Bharatiya Janata Party, which is a kind of a Hindu group, not a radical but a group of&#13;
kind of orthodox Hindus who decided it's going to be Hinduism that we've got and so on. They&#13;
have now a billion, 70 million people at last estimate. I was told the other day it's now a billion,&#13;
90 million, but plus or minus a couple million doesn't really make a difference, or 20 million.&#13;
The election has tossed out the B1P, and the Congress has come back in. It will be a hung&#13;
parliament. We'll see what occurs.&#13;
&#13;
Well, what was the swing? The swing was the fact that 70 percent of the people still live in rural&#13;
areas, and they have not built the roads. The position that many, many have taken is, you know,&#13;
this is an election on, to use a Hindi term, bijli, sarak,pani and so on. It's electricity, it's water,&#13;
it's roads, it's telecommunications, it's schools, it's health posts.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: Infrastructure.&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: It's infrastructure, and rural infrastructure. The gains in their economy, this eight&#13;
percent growth rate that they've had, have been to the call centers and to a whole series of things&#13;
in the IT games, the computer programming, and so on.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: It's really urban.&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: Which is strongly urban, very heavily kids who went to school and learned English.&#13;
South India it's among the Dravidians in south India, and what occurred with the Dravidians&#13;
when Nehru said he wants Hindi to be the only language in his constitution of 1954, the south&#13;
rebelled. The Dravidians in the south--a totally different ethnic group, speaking a different&#13;
language--they rebelled. They blew up railroads, trains. They said absolutely no and introduced&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         W. David Hopper&#13;
                               April 2 and May 12, 2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                  49&#13;
&#13;
English into kindergarten. They were not going to be hooked with Hindi, which is a Sanskritic&#13;
derivative. The Dravidians were in there when the Indo-Europeans crossed the Hindu Kush in&#13;
2000 BC or so, or BCE if I'm to be perfectly correct, Before the Common Era. They found a&#13;
civilization that was there and an advanced civilization--the Indus civilization, as the Pakistanis&#13;
like to call it. They went down a river called the Saraswati and so on, and everybody decided&#13;
that it was gone. It wasn't. It was filled in with the desert, the Rajasthan desert, and we now&#13;
know where it is by digging out old mounds and this sort of thing. But the Dravidians in the&#13;
south have held English. It is in Bangalore. It is in Plupanpur [phonetic]. It is in a whole series&#13;
of, Secunderabad outside of Hyderabad, and so on that you get this intellectual ferment.&#13;
&#13;
Now, the north is behind them in this thing. But the northerners are saying, "Why the hey are we&#13;
not down there?" The north adopted Hindi, and it was--taking Clausen to visit Uttar Pradesh, the&#13;
chief minister of Uttar Pradesh is an old friend, Rajah, proceeded to conduct the meeting in Hindi&#13;
with interpreters. Periodically I'd interrupt the interpreters and say, "I think what you really&#13;
wanted to say was this." [Laughter] The chief minister finally decided, "Okay, Hopper, let's&#13;
talk English."&#13;
&#13;
But it's this game that's going on, and it's this game that the election is there. And it's the rural&#13;
population, basically, that decided that the BJP slogan of "Shining India" or "India Shines"&#13;
affected only about a million people on the economy and there's this huge number of people&#13;
sitting out here in the rural areas that were not affected and who want to be. Water shortages are&#13;
now immense, drinking water shortages. The agricultural thing has been a very, very good year&#13;
last year because the rains were heavy and about 68 percent of your agriculture is related to rains.&#13;
We've got to get them. They want power, and they're desperately short of it, but where do we&#13;
get it from? The government has not been open to this kind ofthing. And bluntly, my dear, the&#13;
W orId Bank has not been open to it.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAUL T: To rural development?&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: Not open to rural development. They're not open to big dams. They don't like big&#13;
dams.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: Well, they got burned on a couple of them.&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: What do you mean they got burned on a couple of them?&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: Well, I'm thinking of Narmada, particularly.&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: Well, okay, let's take Mir Narmada, all right? There was no burning there.&#13;
Narmada was a dam that should have been built. It was part of it--the whole damn river. It was&#13;
the one river that flows from the east to the west. It comes up through Madhya Pradesh, down&#13;
into Andhra Pradesh. It crosses Madhya Pradesh, comes into Gujarat, hitting a little bit&#13;
Maharashtra, comes into Gujarat, and goes down to the ocean. All right, they've got a site to put&#13;
this thing in, at the mountainous interior. We went along with Narmada. It was a sensible,&#13;
sensible dam. It would have provided irrigation for over half of Gujarat. We did the studies and&#13;
so on and so forth.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        W. David Hopper&#13;
                              April 2 and May 12,2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                .50&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
What occurred? What occurred was that as they began to close--began to build the Narmada&#13;
dam, there was a bunch of environmentalists from outside here. And I started the first&#13;
environmental organization at the Bank, the first environmental department, when I was Senior&#13;
Vice President, okay?&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: [inaudible]&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: I used to classify them as the greens, the genuine greens and the goofy greens. And&#13;
the goofy greens took root. They decided that, well, because this thing would proceed to flood&#13;
land below, behind the dam, that was occupied by tribals, then they would move in. Ninety-four&#13;
percent of the tribals said, yes, yes, they wanted to relocate up in the irrigated areas. That six&#13;
percent that wasn't, they brought here, they brought elsewhere. They had a couple of graduates&#13;
among them who spoke English, and they began raising hell about it.&#13;
&#13;
And [Barber B.] Conable kept saying, "Now, what about this? What about this? What about&#13;
this?"&#13;
&#13;
I said, "Barber, forget it. I mean, it's not going to elect anybody to Congress. That's what&#13;
you're concerned with. Let's proceed to move with it."&#13;
&#13;
As soon as I retired, he establishes the--oh, whatever it is, the investigative council or committee&#13;
or whatever this thing is.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: With Bradford Morse.&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: Yes. Brad Morse and my good friend from Canada--god, what's his name?-&#13;
anyway, who, back when I was in Canada in the 1970s, early '70s, the Canadians decided that&#13;
they would check the North Sea area up off the gulf of McKenzie River, which flows north up&#13;
from Alberta up to the north slope. You were getting oil, the U.S. was getting oil, from Alaska.&#13;
All right, you were just starting this. There was some searches done along the mouth ofthe&#13;
McKenzie and so on, and they found out that there was natural gas, about 13 trillion cubic feet&#13;
they estimate. So there was then a big, big outcry on the part of the environmentalists that if you&#13;
put that in, you're going to run into problems with the caribou and all the rest of it. We don't&#13;
need it. We don't need to tap that gas. Let's keep the caribou.&#13;
&#13;
So they appointed a one-man royal commission, which you do in Canada. You have difficulty&#13;
within the government and there's kind of some problems, you appoint a royal commission and&#13;
give it to them. The royal commissioner was an ex-supreme court justice from British Columbia.&#13;
Our supreme court justices don't--it's not a lifetime appointment; it's a ten-year kind of thing.&#13;
&#13;
[End Tape 1, Side A]&#13;
[Begin Tape 1, Side B]&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: In 1971 I had lunch with one of Pierre Trudeau's main people in his office as Prime&#13;
Minister in Canada, and I said to him, "What about this guy? Supposing there had been 60&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        W. David Hopper&#13;
                              April 2 and May 12,2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                  51&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
trillion cubic feet of gas. Would you have appointed him as a royal--would that have made any&#13;
difference?"&#13;
&#13;
He said, "Oh, if it had been 60 trillion cubic feet, we never would have appointed him as the&#13;
royal commissioner."&#13;
&#13;
Okay, he's the guy who got appointed to go up on this thing on Narmada with what's-his-name.&#13;
You may have mentioned his name.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAUL T: Bradford Morse.&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: Bradford Morse. Brad Morse was then so old that he couldn't basically do very&#13;
much. He was in his eighties. So this guy took really the brunt of it. They wrote a report that&#13;
said, "Don't do it." Conable went with it, decided not to do it.&#13;
&#13;
Now, I had pressed Conable not to do this. "Let's go ahead. The government of India wants it.&#13;
Gujarat wants it. The land has already been allocated. The people who want it--the location was&#13;
established. People had been moved from this area down there up to settlements that the&#13;
government was paying for until the water was available." It would have been a huge addition to&#13;
Gujarat's agricultural development.&#13;
&#13;
I appeared before a group in Canada that were--the Parliament in Canada. I appeared here,&#13;
saying that this was a very good decision. They kept it back.&#13;
&#13;
Eventually, it was handled through the [inaudible] courts and the government ofIndia, and the&#13;
government of India and their supreme courts, et cetera, just take an awful long time to do&#13;
anything. Eventually they decided to build the dam. And Wolfensohn goes out and sees the dam&#13;
and said, "What a marvelous thing we're doing. It's a good thing," and so on and so forth. But&#13;
it was delayed by, what, fifteen years. It would have been a huge addition and will be. That's&#13;
one thing.&#13;
&#13;
Okay, we got hauled up on Arun IlIon the same basis. We wanted to build a road in. And 10&#13;
and behold, there's something in the ILO agreements, International Labor Organization, that you&#13;
should not upset the lifestyle of the people if you are--when your development activities.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAUL T: Isn't that the nature of development activities?&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: Precisely.&#13;
&#13;
FEL TAULT: It's social engineering.&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: But the thing is that the road was to be built, we were all set to go with the road, and&#13;
then the--whatever it's called--the group that does this. I have a good friend who was the&#13;
chairman of it, a Canadian, who started the word "sustainable development," by the way, one of&#13;
the first to use it. He got involved, and they decided that this would upset the lifestyle of the&#13;
people.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       W. David Hopper&#13;
                             April 2 and May 12, 2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                    52&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Wolfensohn phoned the then prime minister of Nepal, said he wasn't going to do it.&#13;
&#13;
The prime minister had just been in a helicopter crash and said, "But why?"&#13;
&#13;
Wolfensohn said, "I'm asking my people to send you our press release." And so Arun III was&#13;
knocked out.&#13;
&#13;
This wasn't a dam. It was a glacial lake that was up there, and they'd just used it as run of the&#13;
stream, tap it in the river coming down. But they needed to get into the lake. To get into the&#13;
lake, you needed to build a road. And the people were absolutely incensed, because they&#13;
expected the road.&#13;
&#13;
Now, what do you do now in Nepal? You walk for two weeks, three weeks, one week, with 82&#13;
pounds on your back on a tumpline, down through the hills and so on and so forth and then walk&#13;
back with what you've got. "Wouldn't it be great to have a road? Then we don't need to walk.&#13;
We can move our grain down. We can bring our stuff back," the people argued.&#13;
&#13;
So Wolfensohn kind of gave in and said, "Okay, you can build a temporary road, one that works&#13;
not in the rainy season but in the dry season."&#13;
&#13;
That didn't answer it. It didn't answer it in terms of Arun III, and the power wasn't there.&#13;
&#13;
Okay, so big dams, the big dam commission was there. The big dam commission said, "No, no,&#13;
no. No more big dams." What does a developing country do if they need power? We say that&#13;
they can't produce it. We don't like the Kyoto Treaty ourselves, but we love it on them, so that&#13;
they're not going to befoul the atmosphere. The U.S. said, "No, no. We're not going to do&#13;
Kyoto. I mean, we're producing all kinds of CO2 in the Midwest. Let's not change that."&#13;
Canada says, "Okay, we'll go along with CO2,'' but not recognizing that the bulk of Canadian&#13;
power is generated with hydro-sites, so there isn't any C02. They had agreed to adopt a big, big&#13;
CO2 requirement at Kyoto which doesn't affect Canadian power or very little on Canadian&#13;
power.&#13;
&#13;
All right, right now I'm bang in the middle of what the hell do we do with big dams, so let's go&#13;
ahead. India is about 100,000 megawatts short of electric power. Where are they going to get it&#13;
from? Okay, they're talking about damming the Brahmaputra and bringing the water up over the&#13;
Vindhayas and down the hills and so on and so forth. Then you bring Ganga Jal, which is&#13;
something the BJP will like because it's the holy Hindu water, the Ganges water, down to the&#13;
Kaveri, the very lowest river in South India. This is a nutty idea. It's an idea that old M. S. Rao&#13;
had years and years and years ago-K.O. Rao, I'm sorry--had years and years and years ago and&#13;
which was stupid then and is stupid now. Bangladesh will complain bitterly because they want&#13;
the water coming down from the Brahmaputra (becomes the Jumna when it crosses the boundary&#13;
into Bangladesh), meaning Friday, which is the holy day among the Muslims. Okay, this is&#13;
where it goes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        W. David Hopper&#13;
                              April 1 and May 11, 1004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                 53&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
And I sat in the middle of this, knowing a great deal about what was going on in different places&#13;
and parts of India. I didn't write notes about it. I brought people together, and we talked about&#13;
it, and that was that. They went off and did what they were, what we going to do. We came to&#13;
agreements.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: Okay. I mean, when you started it was kind of the end of McNamara's term--he&#13;
had only three years left--it was also the winding down of his poverty reduction plans, because&#13;
when Clausen came in, those kind of were subdued, but so was rural agriculture and rural&#13;
development when Clausen arrived. So how did that affect your strategies and your policies for&#13;
South Asia at the time? I mean, you knew this was integral to these countries, so how did you&#13;
deal with this conflict of interest, shall we call it?&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: I didn't. I didn't. Ijust ignored it. Look, you had to feed India, for god's sakes. I&#13;
went through the period of time when they were coming in. The India consortium that I was&#13;
chairing from '78 onward was a consortium in which we were discussing this. But in '74, as I&#13;
think I told you, I had Mrs. Gandhi tell me, "How do we do it?" I phoned McNamara, and&#13;
McNamara agreed. I followed with McNamara throughout this whole thing. That's why when&#13;
he finally said, "How can I get you here," it was to tell him that Vice President for South Asia is&#13;
the only thing I was interested in.&#13;
&#13;
But I got into the Vice President for South Asia, and, you know, Clausen--I liked Tom very&#13;
much, because the--I knew India. He knew I knew India. I took him down to Benares. I took&#13;
him to different places. I let him see what India really was like. From then on, I did what I had&#13;
to do, and there was never any real argument about it. I had more arguments with Stem than I .&#13;
did with his deputy than I had otherwise.&#13;
&#13;
Stem had learned that what Machiavelli had said is that, "Never take the barons on in full&#13;
number." In other words, you've got a bunch of barons here, and the barons are basically the&#13;
vice presidents for the regions. And if you took them on together, you lost; I mean, it's King&#13;
John and Runnymede all over again. Sign the Magna Carta. [inaudible] resign instead. So Stem&#13;
would wait and then jump on you individually. I mean, periodically I would get hell for what&#13;
was going on in Pakistan because Stem had been in Pakistan, and he knew what the heck it was&#13;
about. He had been Vice President for South Asia before I came in. I replaced him. He had&#13;
very, very strong views as to what they should do on population and what they should do on&#13;
other things and the rest of it, and they needed to get these things into effect.&#13;
&#13;
FEL TAUL T: What were his views?&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: He felt that they needed to bring in systems of birth control, and that they needed to&#13;
do more things to try to improve the--Iower the birth rates in the country and the rest of it. And I&#13;
knew damn well that you weren't going to lower the birth rates in the country. You weren't&#13;
going to affect the birth rates in the country; I mean, what you are affecting is the death rates in&#13;
the country. The death rates are beginning to drop. Birth rates are determined culturally up here.&#13;
The graph is this way, if you want. Birth rates are up here, 40 per 1,000 or so. Death rates were&#13;
dropping, and we had a population explosion. Going out and telling a bunch of peasant women&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        W. David Hopper&#13;
                              April 2 and May 12, 2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                  54&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
or in villages, et cetera, that they ought to have fewer children wasn't going to get you anywhere.&#13;
Merely introducing condoms and so on and so forth--it's cheaper to buy cigarettes.&#13;
&#13;
So this was there. I just ignored it, you know. r d get hell for it, but so what. He'd jump on me.&#13;
He'd jump on us individually as barons, and we'd just ignore him and go back to your baronetcy&#13;
and say that's that. I was a baron.&#13;
&#13;
The later job, when I got kicked up to being Senior Vice President for Policy, Planning, and&#13;
Research, that was a courtier's job, and I hated it. I mean, I just wasn't pleasant with it at all.&#13;
Fortunately, it was Conable. He got trapped by several others, and I never knew what the hell I&#13;
was supposed to be doing anyway. [Laughter] Dealing with the goofy greens.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: That we have lots of information on, so I'll get to that in a little bit. Let's see.&#13;
You mentioned that you altered a few things when you started as Vice President for South Asia.&#13;
What were some of those things?&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: I had less-I had a very, very good project group, and I kind of encouraged them to&#13;
go do what they had to do in their areas: Let's get this thing going. Let's get it out on the table.&#13;
Let's see where we are. Let's take a look at the irrigation in Gujarat, for example, and make sure&#13;
that we've got, we know what we're doing in terms of canal developments and the rest of it.&#13;
Let's try to improve the irrigation systems that we have. There were too many end-users that&#13;
weren't getting the water and too many were putting it out up here and so on. A whole set of&#13;
these things that these guys were very, very good at.&#13;
&#13;
Now, one of the criticisms I had with McNamara on the nighttime telephone calls was, "You&#13;
know, Bob, you phone me to find out about India. God damn it, I know the Bank people that&#13;
come here--Iet's take your irrigation team that was just in here. They came from South Africa&#13;
and before that they were in Brazil. The only reason you call me is because I happen to be&#13;
sitting here in India and you're concerned about India. You've got to alter this. They've got to&#13;
do it."&#13;
&#13;
And he did. His structural reorganization was to put the project groups and the program groups&#13;
into the different baronetcies, the different regional offices under the vice presidents, so that I&#13;
had a group of people who knew Pakistan, who knew India, who knew Bangladesh, who knew&#13;
Sri Lanka, et cetera, and we could get together and see what's going on. And there was no&#13;
hesitation on this. I had a very, very good technical group, and if they weren't good, I got rid of&#13;
them.&#13;
&#13;
The program group were a different group. The program group were kind of in there. And what&#13;
occurred in Sri Lanka is a very good example. I went out to Sri Lanka and found that the&#13;
program guy--this is after I had come in, and I had been in only a few months--the program guy&#13;
had gone out to tell the Sri Lankan government that they couldn't, they shouldn't undertake this&#13;
big power development, irrigation development, et cetera, along one of the major rivers that&#13;
comes out of the hills and goes north in Sri Lanka. It was a multi-, multi-billion dollar project,&#13;
and the Bank was very, you know, deeply concerned that Sri Lanka was not doing what they&#13;
should be doing and all the rest of it.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         W. David Hopper&#13;
                              April 2 and May 12, 2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                    55&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
I arrived there. I discovered that he had gone catatonic because he'd that I was coming in and&#13;
there was-so we sent him home. I sat down with Jayawardene to find out about this thing. I&#13;
organized a meeting with the others. I supported it fully. I did some travel up and down the&#13;
river to take a look at it and all the rest of it. And the net effect was that at the aid group meeting&#13;
I got other people to finance it and the World Bank was into it, but we were not into it with a&#13;
great deal of money, but we put in a fair amount of outside assistance to Sri Lanka on it.&#13;
&#13;
What it was, Kelly, was--listen, Jayawardene and I walked around his building. This is the new&#13;
prime minister who was elected in '77; he was a right-winger. And we had a meeting at 11&#13;
0' clock. I was there at 11 in the morning. He came in, sat down, said, "This is an interesting&#13;
building." It was built by the Dutch as the presidential palace, built by the Dutch. He said, "You&#13;
might like to walk with me just to take a look at it." What he wanted to find out was what did I&#13;
know about Sri Lanka. Did I know anything? Well, it turns out I knew a hell of a lot about Sri&#13;
Lanka. I'd been there. I had been up to Kandy, I had been up in the tea areas, I had been&#13;
elsewhere, as part of the Rockefeller mission and as part of IDRC. That eased it.&#13;
&#13;
Then we got down to what do we do about this. And I said, "Well, okay, it's a 9 to 10 billion&#13;
dollar project. You're going to have to get assistance." So I got the Canadian High&#13;
Commissioner, the equivalent of ambassador, to Sri Lanka--the High Commissioners come from&#13;
the Commonwealth countries, and Canada is a Commonwealth country, so it's a High&#13;
Commissioner--I got the Canadian High Commissioner to hold a meeting that afternoon with the&#13;
Brits and the others that were there, the Danes and the Germans and so on and so forth. And we&#13;
hammered out an agreement as to how this thing was going to be done, and how it was going to&#13;
be done with minimal cost to the Bank. And we'd carryon our normal project and financing to&#13;
Sri Lanka, about 400 million dollars a year. They would go forward in putting in the dams,&#13;
Victoria Dam and the rest of it on this river.&#13;
&#13;
It's that game that I spent time playing, but it's a game that you can only spend this way if you're&#13;
not a neophyte. And that's where I was. Whether it's with Clausen or whether it's Conable or&#13;
whether it was McNamara, it was kind of a, "Okay, you know what you're doing. You know&#13;
what you're dealing with." So that it was, "Well, let's do this. Let's do that. Let's do something&#13;
else." Ifit didn't fit, you know, what Washington didn't know wouldn't hurt them.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAUL T: And the program folks, I mean they mostly were supposed to be doing&#13;
implementation ofthe projects?&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: The program folks--you had your group who were--there was a group, a program&#13;
group, who were taking a look at the macroeconomics of this; that sort of thing was going on.&#13;
But you had the others who were saying, "Okay, this is where the bids are coming in. This is&#13;
what we've got to do. This is how we've got to deal with the Treasury over here. It's how we&#13;
have to take a look at how the projects are going." You had a code for, you know, that you had&#13;
to report monthly on the nature of the project-I mean, item one, item two, item three. Three&#13;
level was a very bad level, one was going well, this sort of thing. You went through these, and&#13;
they kind of looked after them for you.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         W. David Hopper&#13;
                               April 2 and May 12, 2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                    56&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  FEL TAUL T: Well, now, Ernie Stem did come up throughout all of these files, even if it was&#13;
 just the loan files at the time, and then later on. So I'm wondering if you can talk a little bit&#13;
  about--I know he was originally hired under McNamara. Wasn't he Deputy Chief Economist at&#13;
. first?&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: That's right. But came in, he was, he was--look, I first nmt~m:india. He&#13;
was the U.S. AID guy in India.                                   WBG ARCHIVES&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 FELTAULT: Why was that?&#13;
                                                                            APR 02 2012&#13;
                                                                       Exception   J t ~-LtiIat~ '/:14.;(;'&#13;
HOPPER: Well, because he--Ernie is bright as hell, a very, very competent guy, Buchenwald&#13;
graduate, et cetera. He was Dutch. He survived the German concentration camps and so on and&#13;
so forth. He is a master at feeling which way the wind is blowing and then influencing the wind&#13;
to blow from another direction. He is a good economist, much more in the macroeconomics than&#13;
he is in the microeconomics, but the microeconomics is not bad either.&#13;
&#13;
Kelly, I don't know what you do if you don't take a look at the cultural issues that you're dealing&#13;
with. I mean, if you want to tear apart the Iraq situation now, whether it's in the prisons and so&#13;
on, the anthropologists have contributions to make if you can get them to make them. My&#13;
problem with the anthropologists as a graduate student at Cornell was that they were more&#13;
interested in the culture and where it came from than the culture and where it's going to. My two&#13;
years living in a mud village and traveling to other villages and other areas and the research&#13;
communities in India and so on convinced me more than anything else that I wasn't dealing with&#13;
a bunch of fools. And it wasn't a question of dictating it. It wasn't a question of sitting outside:&#13;
"I'm superior." It's a question of getting to understand what their concerns are and how do we&#13;
blend those with kind of a sense of what modernity is.&#13;
&#13;
Now, there are two or three areas that--it's very different. In talking with a farmer once in the&#13;
village about using fertilizer, he said, "Well, is it the right thing to do?" This is basically almost&#13;
a religious position.&#13;
&#13;
And I say, "Yes, I think it is. It's the right thing to do."&#13;
&#13;
He said, "Well, I've got to know that it's the right thing to do."&#13;
&#13;
I said, "You know, you were discussing with me how can you raise yields in the last&#13;
conversation. Now I'm telling you that one of the ways you might do this."&#13;
&#13;
"Well, yes," he said, "you know, I'm an evil man." He said, "I'm interested in things like the&#13;
yields and that sort of thing, and I shouldn't be. I should be concerned about it being the right&#13;
thing to do," the religious right thing to do. I add the religiousness. "But," he said, "you know,&#13;
I'm imperfect, so it's wise to tell me that fertilizer is good, too."&#13;
&#13;
And it's this game that you're constantly in. You can't move in a way that kind of says that,&#13;
"Okay, I'm superior; you're inferior."&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                          W. David Hopper&#13;
                                April 2 and May 12, 2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                57&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
If I had to put the label onto Stem, it would be that his view was, "This is what they ought to&#13;
do." My view was, "It would be nice if we could get them to move in those directions." In&#13;
agriculture, it's relatively easy. There's a market, there's factors, and so on. Okay, there isn't&#13;
that much roads in and they haven't got this and they haven't got that and a bunch of other&#13;
things. They built a road in for McNamara to visit my mud village; today it's known as the&#13;
McNamara Road. It was four miles from the nearest other road. It went across fields.&#13;
Somebody gave up their land to put this road in and to maintain it. Okay, land is expensive, and&#13;
land is what they go by. So was this the right thing to do? I don't know. The government did it.&#13;
I didn't. I told Bob we'd walk in; well, that would have been fine with him.&#13;
&#13;
Tum to health. That's a totally different one because in health you've got a wide range of beliefs&#13;
that are not easily shed. It took us what, as I think I told you last time, 400 years to agree that&#13;
bacteria, the wee beasties that we saw under the microscope in the 14th century, it was to the 19th&#13;
century before we decided that they were really sources of disease and even then the medical&#13;
profession took another 50 years to believe it. It took us another 50 years to do viruses, and it's&#13;
taking us more than 50 years to agree on prions, the sources of mad cow disease or variant&#13;
Creuzfeldt-Jakob disease. We've started a whole new scientific structure in prion protonomics&#13;
as to proteins, because it turns out our genome didn'thave nearly as many genes as we thought it&#13;
would have to have to produce 100,000 different proteins that make up the human body. There's&#13;
only 30,000 genes. So suddenly we discover that these proteins--the genes must be generating&#13;
something else that in tum generates the proteins. And here we are.&#13;
&#13;
I was talking with a farmer one day. He was out building a well--I think I told you this in the&#13;
previous one--and put it down, you know--they believe that malaria, et cetera, is caused by&#13;
bhoot. These are old women who walk the paths in translucent clothes at night. Their feet tum&#13;
backwards. And if you meet one on a path, you'd better jump off the path and get out the hell of&#13;
the field, because she'll latch onto you, and then you carry her home, and this brings in the&#13;
malaria or brings in other problems that you have as your source of disease, and therefore you've&#13;
got to bring in some kind of Brahmin from outside or somebody else who's got mystical powers&#13;
to get rid of the bhoot.&#13;
&#13;
And I told him, "Okay, put this cement wall down so that the first aquifer doesn't come into your&#13;
drinking water well. You take the second aquifer, the third aquifer, and bring that water in&#13;
because it's been filtered down through the soil and so on."&#13;
&#13;
He looks at me and says, "Hopper, you believe in the germ theory of disease?"&#13;
&#13;
I said, "Well, yes, I do."&#13;
&#13;
"Have you ever seen a germ?"&#13;
&#13;
"Well, no, I haven't."&#13;
&#13;
"Aha!" he said. "I've seen a bhoot."&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        W. David Hopper&#13;
                              April 2 and May 12, 2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                   58&#13;
&#13;
How do you get around this? The cultural barriers to change are far less on the agricultural side&#13;
than they are on the health side. Now, it doesn't mean that there aren't differences; there are.&#13;
One of the things that you have as an item in India is that you save--it's to serve to a guest or to a&#13;
marriage party or to whatever else--a grain that you harvested last year, not this year. It's a great&#13;
thing, because that meant you had enough grain to last through the family and for your--who are&#13;
known as the jajmans or the--I'm sorry, the purjans around you, the native workers that you&#13;
have, the low caste workers that you're responsible for. Okay, our farmers wouldn't think about&#13;
saving last year's grain: get the damn stuff out and get it to market and so on and so forth. Ifwe&#13;
run into problems, go to the bank the next year. But this is all part of it.&#13;
&#13;
But when it comes to health, boy, it's a very, very different picture. My first wife was a nurse.&#13;
She worked in this village as a nurse. She got it so that I was known as Dr. Sabb's [phonetic]&#13;
husband. She was a doctor. People would bring somebody down with a cut. She'd put some&#13;
sulfa on it or something else, put a bandage on it, and that was that. They'd bring the child back&#13;
or the person would come back in a couple of weeks and say, "Look at it. It's a lovely, lovely,&#13;
beautiful cut. It hasn't gone white. It hasn't gone pus-y." She said, "It shouldn't go pus-yo You&#13;
come here and it won't go pus-y." But to them, the pus was getting out the evil that was coming&#13;
into the body. Okay, this whole thing is kind of a game.&#13;
&#13;
We had a kerosene heater, stove, that we used to use just to heat up things and boil them and so&#13;
on and so forth. The local vayd, the local person, medical man, would come in and put his&#13;
syringes into this little thing and heat it up and count to twenty minutes that was necessary, and&#13;
then he carefully lifted it out with tools and put it together. He'd say, "Okay, this is fine." Now&#13;
he's got himself a thing done. Then he'd run his thumb up the needle to take the water off.&#13;
Okay, there it is. And the health game is still there, and it's a very different game. It's one in&#13;
which the cultural elements, the belief structures, are just different.&#13;
&#13;
Agriculture was easy. Now, the thing that they want in agriculture now is power, is telephone, is&#13;
health posts because they do see health, is schools in the rural areas and the rest of it. And it's&#13;
not something that the present government is meeting, but it's not something that the World&#13;
Bank hasn't been meeting either. Wolfensohn, this is like--just Wolfensohn. How much time&#13;
has Wolfensohn ever spent in a developing country? Zilch.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: Wasn't that characteristic of Clausen and Conable, too?&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: Well, I mean, Clausen went and very quickly would decide whether or not he could&#13;
rely on you to guide him, and I think he found that he could rely on me. There was never any&#13;
differences between us, none whatsoever. And Ijust built--I mean, I moved the thing from&#13;
something like a billion or a billion and a half dollars a year up to 4 billion dollars a year with&#13;
projects, and there was never any complaint. We visited different places. I took him up to&#13;
Peshawar. I took him down to Benares. I went to different places with him, he and his wife, to&#13;
Lucknowand so on. And it was clear: I was kind of home and what I said we needed to do on&#13;
the Ganges River was to begin to clean it up and so on and so forth.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         W. David Hopper&#13;
                               April 2 and May 12, 2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                59&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
With Conable, I didn't have any problems at all except that he booted me out of being a baron&#13;
and moved me into being a--because he wanted to consolidate both South Asia and East Asia,&#13;
China and so on, and make it one. It was a dumb idea.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: Yes. Those are actually two very different regions.&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: He did the same thing on Africa. He took East and West Africa and made it one.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: And there's sub-Saharan and northern Africa [inaudible] completely different.&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: Yes. Well, the North Africa one he stuck with, but we had divided because of the&#13;
French angle on the western side. South Africa was still a pariah at the time.&#13;
&#13;
FEL TAULT: What you are really talking about is taking sort of those individual cultural&#13;
relations and that knowledge and turning it into policy. And I know that's always difficult. Part&#13;
ofthe other issue was the World Bank didn't have a lot of cultural social scientists working with&#13;
them. They had a lot of economists but not a lot of ...&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: Yes. But we had far more--I mean, the proportion of staff was economists were&#13;
fewer at that time, in the '80s, late '70s and '80s. McNamara had brought in a lot of technical&#13;
people, so we had a good technical staff. And the economists were over in the Treasury and&#13;
working with others there, but the economists were not--I had a very good chief economist, two&#13;
ofthem, one after the other. The second was exceedingly good.&#13;
&#13;
And I moved some computers at that time--they weren't called computers then. I couldn't buy&#13;
computers myself, that was [inaudible] the limits ofthe Bank, but I could buy calculators. So we&#13;
moved what were early computers in as calculators into Delhi, and our, the economists in Delhi&#13;
worked directly with the Indians and so on, did the same thing in Pakistan and in Bangladesh and&#13;
got things going very well in these countries. That was for the aid groups and this sort of thing,&#13;
to see what was going on.&#13;
&#13;
The program people were very good once they understood that this is what had to be done, and it&#13;
was a question, then, of making up, you know, the call for project investments and this kind of&#13;
thing and working with the purchasing group and the different ones in the Bank that handled&#13;
bids, project bids and so on, and who were in India who were engaged in this sort ofthing. And&#13;
I was, again, back to the reserve bank, back to the various Indian banking groups that were&#13;
involved in it, the ICICI [Industrial Credit and Investment Corporation ofIndia], the Indian&#13;
center for investment activity. I knew what was going on in those places. I had good friends at&#13;
the reserve bank that would warn me about what was occurring here. And the Indian reserve&#13;
bank handled Bhutan's money and so on. There were problems with Nepal. Nepal had its own&#13;
reserve bank, but I could go in there and talk with them. It was just a kind of--sure, I went out,&#13;
you know, three or four times a year for one, two, three weeks to see what was going on and&#13;
talking with people who were part of it.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        W. David Hopper&#13;
                             April 2 and May 12, 2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                  60&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: One thing I did notice is that after you started with the South Asia region,&#13;
suddenly there were a lot more research reports being done and issued. I'm wondering was that&#13;
a policy shift on your part or when you started, was there a lack of research that had been done?&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: No, there wasn't a lack of it. We had to make justifications. When Stern ran South&#13;
Asia, and before him, when--another name. AAMI; I'll think of it--anyway, a Brit who was in&#13;
there looking after the South Asia desk, it was before McNamara created South Asia, or it was&#13;
the early stages ofthis, he'd spent many years there with the British in Asia. He knew it well.&#13;
He didn't trust research reports or want them. Stern would more or less say, "What's going on?&#13;
What were really here?" and so on and the rest of it.&#13;
&#13;
I was more concerned with making sure that we knew what the hell we were talking about, and&#13;
that meant getting some people to report on irrigation, on power, on transport, on rail lines, on a&#13;
whole array of things, private investments and that kind of thing. And I didn't want them too&#13;
long; they shouldn't have been. But it was the ones who made visits and came back and said,&#13;
"Okay, this is what we think ought to be done," those were the ones that I would hold a meeting&#13;
on and go through and check and that sort of thing.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAUL T: Was this something that the other vice presidents for the regions were doing as&#13;
well?&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: Not generally. I think that what you have to recognize is that, with the exception of&#13;
the Latin American vice president, the others were all strangers to their areas. McNamara tried&#13;
to bring in people who had been--had some knowledge of what was there. But the knowledge&#13;
was not--look, how did I first meet Bob McNamara? Okay, I knew nothing about him except the&#13;
Vietnam War. I had been a couple oftimes to Vietnam during the war and this sort of thing,&#13;
looking at agriculture and so on. But I was a Canadian, so I was not deeply involved, although&#13;
there were Canadian troops there.&#13;
&#13;
The issues which I brought was that both the Canadian High Commissioner and the American&#13;
ambassador, if they had high-level people who came out, would try to get me to give them some&#13;
kind of run-down on what India was about. And I would give a lecture ranging from half an&#13;
hour to two hours with maps on the history, geography, geology, et cetera, ofIndia, right up&#13;
through partition and so on. And I was asked to do this for McNamara and did so, and that&#13;
opened up a set of conversations. He wanted to know more about the Green Revolution or the&#13;
new crops that were coming in because he had heard about them from Rockefeller Foundation&#13;
and so on, and I was working with Rockefeller then when he came in, and we talked about this.&#13;
I had taken others out to Indian Agricultural Research Institute where I was a visiting professor&#13;
to visit some of these plots and this sort of thing, and there was a battle going on in India as to&#13;
whether they should get fertilizer or manufacture fertilizer in India. Was this the kind of thing&#13;
you wanted? And there was a great deal of discussion, and I was in the middle of all of this and I&#13;
was writing reports out there on it.&#13;
&#13;
Okay, what McNamara saw in this thing was somebody who knew something about India, and&#13;
what he hears from others was that, yeah, I was doing a good job and so on. We went on from&#13;
there. I didn't come down on the first offer because I was at IDRC and I had just taken over. I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        W. David Hopper&#13;
                              April 2 and May 12, 2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                             61&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
took over in 1970 in Canada, and I was not prepared to move, had a good organization that was&#13;
moving, and so on and so forth.&#13;
&#13;
The reason you're in this house is that 1976 I was down here with Ruth, and we had dinner with&#13;
McNamara and a group. McNamara asked me to stay on. He said had we been looking. Ruth&#13;
said, yes, we had been looking. We were looking at an apartment over here. He said, "Don't&#13;
buy it. Don't buy it. It's a cooperative. Don't buy it. Buy a house. Buy a house." So we saw&#13;
this place. This was a year before--almost two years before he offered me a job, the job I&#13;
wanted-or about a year and a half. So this is where we moved to when we came down.&#13;
&#13;
FEL TAULT: So you bought this about two years before you moved down here?&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: We bought it in '76, the tail end of '76, and I came down in January of '78.&#13;
&#13;
FEL TAULT: And other than the fact that it was South Asia which you were offered, I mean&#13;
what were the other reasons for leaving IDRC in Canada?&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: I had been there seven years, and I really felt that seven years was long enough. It&#13;
was built. It had built a reputation. The Parliament was happy, and they were getting increased&#13;
budgets, and so on and so forth. But the issue was--I had an old friend, Frosty Hill, who I&#13;
mentioned to you on the previous one. Frosty said, "Always go where the money is." There was&#13;
more money at the Bank. [Laughter] Not as payment. The reimbursement was basically the&#13;
same. But you were dealing with billions here, and I was dealing with a few hundred million--or&#13;
a few millions. It was tens of millions. It was 30 million, I think, was my annual budget or&#13;
something or my final annual budget.&#13;
&#13;
FELT AULT: So you could really-I mean, could you see yourself doing more, having more&#13;
impact at the Bank than at IDRC?&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: Sure, sure, sure. At IDRC I was welcome and it was very nice to see me and so on&#13;
and so forth, but I was not dangling potential funds of any kind. [Laughter]&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: Well, more sort of the context of the '70s when you came into the Bank and the&#13;
climate of the environmental movement, which we sort of mentioned, the women's movement,&#13;
the start of the indigenous movement, so all of these movements that ended up having a great&#13;
impact on development and its changing paradigms in the '80s and '90s.&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: The environmental movement--I didn't have any problem with, quote, "genuine"&#13;
greens. I was very much for them. And I was very much, in a real sense, for the greens. Now,&#13;
the genuine greens are the ones that I said balance off the realities of human existence and an&#13;
expanding population, and how do you feed them, how do you handle them, how do you provide&#13;
jobs for them, where do they move from here, because that's what we were confronting. I went&#13;
to India--275 million in the mid-'50s. There was 400 million when I went back in '62. There&#13;
was 470 million when I began to move out of it. Today there's a billion, 70 million or 90&#13;
million.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       W. David Hopper&#13;
                             April 2 and May 12, 2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                  62&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
[End Tape 1, Side B]&#13;
[Begin Tape 2, Side A]&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: .. and to find a group of people who were saying, "No, no, you can't do this. You&#13;
can't, you know, build dams. We shouldn't do this. You're upsetting the balance of human&#13;
existence or whatever else. Is this something that we should be doing, the Nannada Dam being a&#13;
case in point? Should we irrigate up here? Should we protect the fish that are coming in on the&#13;
lower area? The water was going to be behind the dam and you're going to see trees being&#13;
destroyed down in this area," et cetera. Those are all questions that did have to be debated. I&#13;
don't mind the debate, but let's ..&#13;
&#13;
[Interruption]&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: .. those are all debates. There is no--to me, the issue is the balance in here. The&#13;
Rene Dubos group, where the late Rene Dubos at Rockefeller University in New York really&#13;
spent a great deal of time trying to balance off the human requirements with the environment,&#13;
whether it's trees or animals or whatever else, and how do you strike the balance between these?&#13;
&#13;
[Interruption]&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: I'm not quite certain where we were.&#13;
&#13;
FEL T AUL T: Balancing human and environmental requirements.&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: Yes. The human environment with the others. I found that in dealing with the&#13;
genuine greens there is a balance that you can strike and it's very, very good to hit, but it's not a&#13;
balance that many others are prepared to do. And one of my favorite stories is that I began to get&#13;
petitions in, tens ofthousands of signatures on them, from groups that wanted to do in furs. "We&#13;
shouldn't have furs, fur coats and so on. This is destroying animals."&#13;
&#13;
FEL TAULT: What does the Bank have to do with it?&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: But this was part of the environment. But equally, another balanced group that were&#13;
very, very concerned that--the fur bunch were negative in terms of killing seals, which happens&#13;
to be the major income source to Eskimos or Inuit, as they like to call themselves. "Eskimo" is a&#13;
word meaning "raw meat eater" that the Crees said about the northern people. The word "Inuit"&#13;
means "the people." They would go out and kill seals, and this killing seals had to stop, and the&#13;
World Bank had to be involved, and no more of this and so on.&#13;
&#13;
Now, you put this on at a time when--you put this on at a time when the Pope made a visit to the&#13;
United States, then went up to Canada, and he was asked--went up right up to the north into the&#13;
Inuit country. They had put on fur vestments for him to do his holy words and so on and so&#13;
forth, and there were groups of people there who took pictures of the Pope in fur vestments. And&#13;
there was a great outcry on the part of, one, a group who says, you know, "Keep the furs. Don't&#13;
worry about the seals. They eat cod anyway, and we need the cod. So keep that going. The&#13;
World Bank should be strong supporters of this kind of activity." And then you've got the other&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        W. David Hopper&#13;
                              April 2 and May 12, 2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                     63&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
group saying, you know, "This was a gross mistake. The Pope was embarrassed. They gave him&#13;
furs to put on, and he put on, and there shouldn't be any more furs, and we should knock this&#13;
out."&#13;
&#13;
This is an example of two that came into the office, not simultaneously. And I had this from&#13;
people who were concerned with C02 and the global warming, and I had it from people who&#13;
were concerned about SOx and NOx, nitrous oxides and the sulfur oxides that are coming from&#13;
power plants, and we should be into just wind and solar. We certainly shouldn't build any more&#13;
dams because they affect the fish that are dO\vnstream from the dams and the salmon are not&#13;
really looked after properly that are going upriver in these areas, et cetera, et cetera, et cetera.&#13;
This was just a big maze, and not one in which my particular view is, "Yes, yes, we do our best&#13;
is to preserve as much of our culture as we have, but we have to recognize that"--at that time&#13;
there was about five billion people, today there's six-"but there are five billion people in the&#13;
world that have got to be fed and got to be housed and got to be looked after because they're part&#13;
ofthe human race."&#13;
&#13;
Well, that's, you know, almost back to the position that the Nazis took that you had to be a&#13;
proper Aryan and full mentally alert, et cetera, otherwise cut their throats, at least castrate them&#13;
so that they're not reproducing. And this is where we go.&#13;
&#13;
Well, it was this balance. I didn't enjoy it I didn't like it, but there it was, and I engaged in it. I&#13;
met with environmental groups in a great many places to talk about this. Okay, that was one side&#13;
of it&#13;
&#13;
And I never did and I still don't feel comfortable with this balance. I see countries that&#13;
desperately need power, and the whole purpose of the Kyoto Treaty and what [Albert A., Jr.]&#13;
Gore did in the Kyoto was to say, "Okay, we will cut our CO2 emissions in terms of global&#13;
warming. The developing countries should be given some time to do it"&#13;
&#13;
The Malaysian group that were in this who were jumped on by several groups for not looking&#13;
after their tropical rainforest, Malaysia said, "Well, yes, yes, we're quite willing to look after&#13;
tropical rainforests, but recognize that 75 percent ofwhat"--or sorry-"95 percent of what we&#13;
cut is sold to the industrial countries, 55 percent to Japan. We're a poor country; we need&#13;
money. We're willing to stop it if you pay for it"&#13;
&#13;
And we're in exactly the same position with regard to a lot of other things, whether it's drugs&#13;
from Colombia or wherever else. "You stop it. We're willing to give you money for the&#13;
military, and we're willing to give you help, and we're willing to send down people, but you stop&#13;
the drugs." We're the demanders, yes, but, you know, we can't jump on our own people,&#13;
obviously.&#13;
&#13;
It's this game that the Bank got trapped between, and it's this game that I think the Bank is&#13;
trapped now on much of this, quote, "globalization" and many of the millennial goals.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: It's also similar to a lot of criticism on the Green Revolution as well, particularly&#13;
on the shrimp farming [inaudible] mangrove.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         W. David Hopper&#13;
                               April 2 and May 12,2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                               64&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: Yes. Swamps. That's right.&#13;
&#13;
FEL TA UL T: But the demand for shrimp in the West ..&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: Is colossal.&#13;
&#13;
FEL TAUL T: It's colossal.&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: And we have over-fished the cod. They're opening up the cod fishing in the Gulf of&#13;
St. Lawrence, both north and south, a little bit this year. But we'll see what happens. The seals&#13;
did eat an awful lot of cod. Then you've got poachers from Spain and Portugal coming in and&#13;
taking more. We're--okay, the salmon fish--this is the Atlantic salmon now, which turns out not&#13;
to be a salmon by the same elements as a Pacific salmon; it's a different family group. The&#13;
Atlantic salmon is really a red trout that happens to go to sea. But the salmon fish farms are now&#13;
being examined, and the environmentalists are after them as well. And in a sense, they should be&#13;
because there is a lot of chemical problems that they have and there's a lot of other things&#13;
[inaudible].&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: Most of that is management because I have read a couple of articles and seen&#13;
some reports where there's one company and then also China itself has all this fish farming,&#13;
agricultural [inaudible].&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: The China fish farming--there was an article in Wired not too long ago on this. The&#13;
China fish farming is very, very, very much on land.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: Right. Exactly.&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: It's in rice paddies and elsewhere. They grow three or four species, one bottom&#13;
feeder and up to the top.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: So it stays clean.&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: Supposedly.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: Supposedly [inaudible] What made you uncomfortable with trying to deal with&#13;
this balance and deal with the various environmental groups and their demands? And was there&#13;
a protocol at the Bank for having to answer these kinds of requests, because ..&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: No. Under Conable--Conable put this in with, in part because of his experience in&#13;
Congress where a great many Congressional people were opposing the Bank or angry with the&#13;
Bank because of what they were, the Bank was doing that affected, quote, "the environment,"&#13;
unquote.&#13;
&#13;
When I asked Barber one time--it was a particular guy from Wisconsin--"What's he talking&#13;
about? There's all kinds of problems in Wisconsin."&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       W. David Hopper&#13;
                             April 2 and May 12, 2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                   65&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
He said, 'That's exactly what he's talking about, is that he doesn't want to do it in Wisconsin,&#13;
but he wants to be able to tell the people of Wisconsin, 'Yes, yes, yes, I've been very&#13;
instrumental in getting the Bank not to do this in Brazil or Argentina. Therefore, I am really&#13;
working with the environmentalists. ,,,&#13;
&#13;
We were deeply concerned about Brazil's forests. Maggie [Margaret H.] Thatcher went down&#13;
from Britain, talked with the Brazilian president about the forests. He said, "Yes, madam." He&#13;
understood this.&#13;
&#13;
She said, "Well, it's a great global resource."&#13;
&#13;
He said, "Madam, let me just simply say, 'It's a Brazilian resource.'''&#13;
&#13;
And she said, "Yes, yes, I know, but you know the globe really depends on it."&#13;
&#13;
He said, "Madam, Brazil depends on it." [Laughter]&#13;
&#13;
Shortly thereafter, I was in Britain, and the head of the environment group was there, and we&#13;
were talking with him. He's now in the ED [European D nion], former governor in Hong Kong,&#13;
he was there when Hong Kong was moved over to the Chinese. And he said, "What does he do?&#13;
I've got Maggie--a half an hour with her, and I don't really know what to talk to her."&#13;
&#13;
I said, "But she was a chemist, so I would suggest you write some stuff out in chemistry. Start&#13;
with the ozone layer over the Antarctic and opening that up. Do some work on chemistry."&#13;
&#13;
My God, it lasted an hour and a half, and she became an environmentalist at the end of it because&#13;
she'd never really looked at all of this in terms of the chemical relationships and the maintenance&#13;
of ozone and the rest of it. So it's--that was one.&#13;
&#13;
But there were a whole series of other policy questions that had to be resolved. What Barber&#13;
wanted to do when he created the Policy Planning and Research was to get some strategic&#13;
planning done. Well, strategic planning--I brought in Francisco Sagasti from Peru, who was an&#13;
old friend and very good at it. And he wanted Francisco to do the strategic planning, and I had&#13;
told Barber that if you're going to do strategic planning, this is not something you share widely.&#13;
You share it with the head of the institution, and you can agree on strategies, but, well, Barber&#13;
insisted that it go to the full kind of upper echelon of the Bank. And Sagasti presented it, and&#13;
among the things Sagasti said was that the Russians are going to be into the Bank. They're&#13;
going to be tearing down the wall and so on and so forth, and they're going to be there. And&#13;
Stem just hit the roof. I mean, he: "Don't do any of that. Don't say it to anybody because all I&#13;
have to do to lose my IDA grants or IDA things from the Congress is to say, 'Russia is going to&#13;
be part ofthis institution.' Ignore it."&#13;
&#13;
What Sagasti was saying is that when the Russians come in, it's going to be a very different kind&#13;
of Bank because their whole structure of how they contract with things and so on and so forth is&#13;
not to put it out saying, you know, "Bring it in and you design it." The Russians designed it, and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         W. David Hopper&#13;
                              April 2 and May 12,2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                 66&#13;
&#13;
you put the thing out, and that's how you--it was just going to be--we're going to have a real&#13;
problem in getting through to a bureaucracy that handles everything from health through to&#13;
agriculture to farming to power plants to you name it. It's going to be a different Bank, and&#13;
we're going to have now to prepare for this kind ofthing in terms of the dialogue we have and&#13;
where we go to. And it was just, "No, absolutely, we're not to mention Russia, we're not to do&#13;
anything about Russia," and so on.&#13;
&#13;
Sagasti was, just laughed. I mean, he continued this way and did it. The Russians did tear it&#13;
down. The Russians--he predicted Russia in '92. The Russians came in--or '92, '94--and the&#13;
Russians came in in '90. The Berlin Wall came down in '89. It was starting in '91, '92. It did&#13;
change things very mightily.&#13;
&#13;
FEL TAULT: Let me ask how.&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: Because, first of all, you had the split up of the Russian group, so that we now had to&#13;
work with Romania, Bulgaria. Yugoslavia went to hell after [Josip Broz] Tito and was now into&#13;
various pieces and parts. And Tito had warned his followers not to put [Slobodan] Milosevic in&#13;
charge when he died because he's nothing but an ethnic Serb, and that's exactly what occurred&#13;
and still is occurring in Yugoslavia.&#13;
&#13;
When it came to Romania, the issue was how do we get into a discussion and dialogue. The&#13;
Russians had put in a big power plant in Romania, which was under very difficult conditions.&#13;
We found that nobody was willing to bid on going in to work on this power plant because the&#13;
way that the power plant was designed, it was the Russians who said, "This is what you will&#13;
have, the tubing you will have. This is where the generators are going to be, et cetera, et cetera,&#13;
et cetera. They're all going to be in these sizes." Well, these sizes, nobody was producing in the&#13;
West. They would have done it differently, but then how do you get in? The Romanians still&#13;
are: "Well, this is what we need. This is what we have." And suddenly the costs go up through&#13;
the roof.&#13;
&#13;
The entire discussion of how you handle these things, what you do, you send in a team, you work&#13;
with given contractors, with the private sectors and so on, and saying, "This is where we have to&#13;
go and what we need to do. Here is the private sector. This is what we put out to bid." In this&#13;
thing, you look to say, "Well, okay, this is what the private sector has to do, or the bidders have&#13;
to do, da-de-da-de-da-de-da-de." And they say, "Well, yes, but that's not our thing. We don't&#13;
have those metals. We don't have these kinds of things." And this is part of this dialogue.&#13;
&#13;
So it's easier to shift then to, "Okay, what do we do on structural adjustment, put things into the&#13;
box?" And the problem with structural adjustment is we have no way of controlling it. Money&#13;
is fungible. Structural adjustment, they can come back and say, "This is what we did--education&#13;
and roads and so on and so forth." But at the same time, we're driving Mercedes Benzes and&#13;
helping our bunch coming out. And I have been critical of structural adjustment right from the&#13;
beginning when it came in after the Belgrade conference in 1980. And Stern was very, very&#13;
strong for it.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        W. David Hopper&#13;
                              April 2 and May 12,2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                 67&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
What's occurred is that the Bank has now shifted to economists and MBAs. The MBA is now&#13;
kind of the method by which you get in. And we've lost--and I warned in the '80s that we were&#13;
going to lose our technical personnel. They were brought in by McNamara, the tail end of his,&#13;
early in his' reign. They came in at their forties; it's now twenty years later; they're up to&#13;
retirement age, and they're going to disappear. That's fine. Ernie had no problem. He just&#13;
thought they were a pain in the neck, these guys who knew it. We need economists in here, so&#13;
let's have economists. When Wolfensohn came in, let's have MBAs. This is what you've got.&#13;
And you just cut your engineering competencies to virtually nil. And I just find that--would find&#13;
that an extremely difficult institution to work in.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: I had a couple of friends who just left the Bank and said the same thing. It's&#13;
difficult.&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: It's very difficult. I got working on power issues with the IFC [International&#13;
Finance Corporation] and on the possibility of putting in photovoltaic farms because one of the&#13;
problems in a developing country is that we built dams--they built dams back in the days and so&#13;
on and so forth--but most developing countries and tropical regions have periods of rainfall and&#13;
then periods of no rain. So you fill up behind this reservoir with your water, and this is enough&#13;
to drive the turbines to produce your power for Bangkok or the city or whatever else through the&#13;
dry season. Then you get your rains in and you begin again, except that the demand for power is&#13;
going up. People are putting air-conditioning in, they never did before. People are doing a wide&#13;
range of other things, and power demands are immense.&#13;
&#13;
So what do you do? Do you increase the size of the dam? Do you put another dam in? In many&#13;
cases, you can't. The reservoir is there and the rest of it. So let's put in photovoltaic farms. You&#13;
say, "Well, okay, let's put in wind farms." The problem with wind farms is you can't rely on the&#13;
winds. Like sitting out there today, you can have as much windmills as you want; you're not&#13;
going to keep the lights going or the air-conditioning going, because the windmills aren't&#13;
turning.&#13;
&#13;
You have this situation you had in California where the Californians decided they wanted to put&#13;
more wind farms in and found the Sierra Nevada mountains, the western end side of the Sierra--&#13;
east side of the mountains--got a wind sweep off the Pacific that came in, and they would spin&#13;
the windmills up there very, very well. This was great. The Sierra Club had backed: "Let's&#13;
have more wind farms and so on." Then they discovered that they were going to be on the Sierra&#13;
Nevada hills, and the Sierra Club just hit the roof. "No, no, no. We can't put them up there.&#13;
That's scenic. All you're going to do is destroy the view." They put a referendum out.&#13;
Everybody turned it down. So there you are.&#13;
&#13;
So we put in these solar voltaic farms. You can put them anywhere you want--up in the hills or&#13;
anything else, but that feeds in. So you've got twelve hours of--because in the tropics it's twelve&#13;
hours of darkness, twelve hours of sunshine. You've got twelve hours of sunshine, producing'&#13;
wattages that you then feed into the cities, and you close off your turbines in the hydro dams and&#13;
rely on a good chunk of this for the daytime and the other things. You may put a little through&#13;
one or two turbines just to keep the thing going, but that's where it is. And it darkens down, so&#13;
you open up more turbines and get the evening power going into the city, and it balances off.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        W. David Hopper&#13;
                              April 2 and May 12,2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                    68&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
And you store--because one of the problems with solar voltaics is where the heck do you store&#13;
the power? I mean, do we put big, big lead acid batteries out here by the tens of thousands and&#13;
feed them into this? How do you store it? Okay, you store it behind the reservoir. We've got it&#13;
built. You just don't pump as much water.&#13;
&#13;
Okay, this is something we did. The environmentalists hit the roof. There was a whole series of&#13;
things. We got going in the IFC on it, but nobody was prepared to do it and the rest of it. It's&#13;
now been shifted from the IFC to the--and I pressed Canada to go ahead on this thing, but&#13;
Canada doesn't produce much photovoltaic power, so they were not deeply involved. But the&#13;
former head of the Canadian International Development Agency is now down here heading the&#13;
GEF [Global Environment Facility], and I learned last night that he is really quite interested in&#13;
doing it, and they're probably going to be meeting up in Canada to pursue this further, except&#13;
that now we're talking big, big solar farms.&#13;
&#13;
Now, big solar farms take a heck of a lot of land; I mean it's--so you're going to have to get up&#13;
into the hills. You're going to have to somehow or other shade it or cut the trees around them&#13;
and the rest of it, and I don't know that they've gone far enough on this. You can go out to the&#13;
desert, but then the desert sandstorms come in and just cover up the voltaics. And as one guy&#13;
said when I said the desert, "Well," he said, "Just take some water and wash it off." Yeah, well,&#13;
that's fine, but one of the things in the desert you're short of is water. [Laughter] So my&#13;
reaction is, you know, "Why don't we get some engineers who really know about these things&#13;
and put them into place?" [Laughter]&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: So let me ask you, how were you offered the new position of Policy, Planning,&#13;
and Research, and what made you accept it?&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: This is one thing that Conable wanted to do. At the same time, he wanted to blend&#13;
South Asia with East Asia and Pacific. He had a Turk who was here, a very competent&#13;
economist and so on, to kind of take that over. He thought that would be very good. So I was&#13;
either going to take--as I said, "There's gold in them thar hills. Give me the departure thing and&#13;
I'll leave."&#13;
&#13;
And he said, "What about being a senior vice president for Policy, Planning, and Research?"&#13;
&#13;
I said, "Well, what does this entail?" We talked about it, and I said, "All right, I'll do that."&#13;
&#13;
That's what we did. And I've waited 'til--that was '87. I had to retire when I was sixty-two, so&#13;
it was '89 and I stayed on 'til '90.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: As part of the Policy, Planning, and Research, you helped set up the&#13;
environmental department.&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: That's right. The environmental department was one of these. I got some things&#13;
going on the strategic planning thing. I ran into some very, very real battles within the&#13;
organization. Ernie Stem took over the Treasury, the money side of the Bank, was now prepared&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         W. David Hopper&#13;
                               April 2 and May 12, 2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                                  69&#13;
&#13;
                to go to the U.S. system of handling things; that is, it will be an annual budget, if you don't spend&#13;
                it in the year you've got it, you lose it. I opposed that because one of the things we were doing in&#13;
                Policy, Planning and Research was getting some research going outside of the Bank and getting&#13;
                some universities, India and so on and so forth, to do the research, but I'm not about to give them&#13;
                a full grant. I want something coming in; you start off and maybe it's a five-year period, but I'm&#13;
                not going to pay anything to them unless we do it. And Stern just insisted, "Well, if you don't&#13;
                spend it in that first year, it's gone."&#13;
&#13;
                Well, what I had to do was to dribble it, the same way as I did it at IDRC or anyone ofthe&#13;
                foundations--I was on the Rockefeller Foundation board at the time, and that's the way you did&#13;
                it. You put the money out, and then they respond, and as they respond, you add some more to it,&#13;
                but you just don't give them a grant and let them go buy a Mercedes and travel around the world&#13;
                and say, "Oh, yes, yes, yes. I forgot about that." Well, we had battles about this.&#13;
&#13;
                We had battles about whether or not this whole strategic thing was something that we should be&#13;
                doing. Barber really didn't understand what the role of strategic planning was, which is kind of&#13;
                an upper echelon thing that you share with the president. He gives you his reactions. You don't&#13;
                share it with others.&#13;
&#13;
6"              When it came to policy, the Senior Vice President for&#13;
(""o.,f                        's a Pathan or a Pashtun.&#13;
:;;;;                                                            He Just SImply went to Conable and said he's not&#13;
0::: ~                                                    s responsible for what's going on in terms of the Bank's&#13;
~         .,8   activities, and he will take that over. That's his policy area. So Barber kind of, okay, that was&#13;
          8'    fine. So we just got cut out. So the whole ofthe lending policy question just disappeared. So&#13;
          &amp;l    that went by the board. They changed the title on the next guy but the ...&#13;
&#13;
                It--this was Barber Conable's kind of introduction to the Bank. He didn't take very long. He&#13;
                came in following Clausen in '86 basically. And he wanted things changed fast, and he got&#13;
                things going, and by , 87 we had his new vision of what the Bank was to be about, and this was&#13;
                the amalgamation of Africa. It turns out that Kim [Edward V. K.] Jaycox is the one who did this,&#13;
                and one of Barber's strongest supporters up in his own district was Jaycox's mother who had&#13;
                money and supported Barber as a Republican and the rest of it. And he spent many years--he&#13;
                was a country lawyer--and he spent many years in Congress and was the ranking Republican&#13;
                member during the [Jimmy] Carter era and the House Appropriations Committee and so on.&#13;
                This is what he brought to the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
                FEL TAUL T: And in creating the environmental department, I found a lot of correspondences&#13;
                between you and the Bank and the Nature Conservancy as assisting in kind of getting the&#13;
                department up and running. And what role exactly did they play in ..&#13;
&#13;
                HOPPER: They were among the more genuine ofthe greens, as far as I was concerned, Nature&#13;
                Conservancy. There were two or three others that were involved, but they were quite vocal in&#13;
                what they wanted to see done and so on and so forth. And I had to talk this stuff over with my&#13;
                own staff.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                        W. David Hopper&#13;
                                              April 2 and May 12,2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                     70&#13;
&#13;
 We brought in a,J'Jew Zealander who had a very, very high reputatiQ!}i!L4ealing with the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 I brought Danny [Daniel] Hillel in to the environment department. He was an irrigation&#13;
 specialist and one of the world's leading irrigation people, an Israeli.                                 C)&#13;
                                                                                                     M..I'.)&#13;
&#13;
 FELTAUL T: Now, had he been on your staff in South Asia?                                            t: g&#13;
  HOPPER: No, but I knew Danny from way back. He'd worked with the Rehovot Institute,                ~  ....&#13;
  water institute in Israel. On a visit that I had made--I made a couple of visits into Israel before ~&#13;
  then when I was with IDRC and the rest of it. On one trip I went over to Syria to take a look at ~&#13;
  the Euphrates activities that they were doing. I was amazed to find that they were--well, I drove .&#13;
. over with the minister of irrigation from Damascus on this thing and looked at it, spent about the&#13;
  better part of a day visiting the Euphrates Dam and then going up to--they were pumping it up to&#13;
  Syria.&#13;
&#13;
 At the end of it, he said, well, what did I think of it.&#13;
&#13;
 I said, "I think it's Utah circa the 1930s. It isn't modem irrigation."&#13;
&#13;
 He said, "Yes, I know. Where do we get the modem irrigation?"&#13;
&#13;
 I pointed over to the Golan Heights and said, "Over there, Israel."&#13;
&#13;
 He said, "Yeah, well," he said, "I know. We tried a couple oftimes and haven't succeeded.&#13;
 How do I get it?"&#13;
&#13;
 So I went back to IDRC and got all the stuffwe wanted from Rehovot, had it all translated into&#13;
 Arabic and dropping all references to Israel and began sending it out to Egypt, to Syria, to a&#13;
 whole series of things. We published all of this stuff out of Rehovot, in terms of modem&#13;
 irrigation.&#13;
&#13;
 And I wanted Hillel to bring that in to this environment department, and he did. He just found&#13;
 them just useless in the Bank. They were just unable to talk about it. The ex-Israeli who was on&#13;
 my staff, who I still correspond with--and I do with Danny--but, you know, the Bank has not yet&#13;
 come to grips with--and I've done this. I've seen EDs [executive directors]. I've seen them&#13;
 within the institution, but the institution is not geared for it. Jim Wolfensohn is a very strong&#13;
 practicing Jew, and I have no problem on th~t. I think it's great. But he has not turned to the&#13;
 Israeli experience on this, and the result is that we're using a huge amount of the globe's water&#13;
 for irrigation purposes on crops.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                           W. David Hopper&#13;
                                 April 2 and May 12,2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                    71&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
When I was in Senegal on another occasion with an FAO [Food and Agriculture Organization]&#13;
group, the Senegal River was being put out at about 40,000 cubic meters-sorry--yeah, about&#13;
40,000 cubic meters of water per hectare per wheat crop. And I asked Danny, you know, what&#13;
did they do in Israel, and it's about 10,000 cubic meters, about a quarter of it. The issue is that it&#13;
costs a heck of a lot more. It costs us now about 3200 dollars a hectare in India to irrigate it the&#13;
old British style with canals and so on and so forth down to the root zone. It would have cost&#13;
you about, what, 15, 20,000 dollars a hectare to put it under the Israeli irrigation systems where it&#13;
goes out a long pipe that has a pulse. It goes only around the root crop. It doesn't fill the whole&#13;
root zone of the horizon and so on.&#13;
&#13;
But this is what we're confronting, and we're confronting it in India. We're confronting it in&#13;
Pakistan immensely and elsewhere. We just don't have the water. In Pakistan, the area behind&#13;
Tarbela Dam, which is very important, has about 500--600 now--600 million cubic meters of just&#13;
sludge, silt, mold in the thing because what they did above Tarbela, which was a mountainous&#13;
area, they've now stripped off the trees and they're grazing cattle and goats and so on and so&#13;
forth, and the rain comes in and just flows down and washes out the soil and down it goes and it&#13;
sits behind Tarbela Dam. There's no place you can move it because the Indus River--it's way up&#13;
the Indus River, and anytime you try to move the silt down, the guys downstream holler like hell.&#13;
"We don't want all of this stuff." So you could say, "Put some shovels in and take it out," but&#13;
where do you put it? I mean, you know, where do you throw it? I mean, it's--this is the issue&#13;
that they're confronting.&#13;
&#13;
Drinking water in India is now desperately short in the rural areas. This is when I said, "Bijli,&#13;
sarak, pani, "power, roads, water, because they haven't got them. And I've taken this up with&#13;
the Indian ED's. I've taken it up with Wolfensohn and so on. "Yes, yes, yes. We'll get around&#13;
to these sorts of things," But in the meantime, what do you do?&#13;
&#13;
Last year the estimate that I got from [Callisto E.] Madavo, the Vice President for Africa--and I&#13;
haven't seen the Bank's report; I'll see it in the autumn--but last year, 2002 to 2003, they put out&#13;
about 3.6 billion dollars for sub-Saharan Africa; 2.8 of it was for structural adjustment, and there&#13;
was some for HIV, and there was some for, you know, some other things. But--and why&#13;
structural adjustment? Well, there were country reports that, "We used your money for schools&#13;
and for roads and for women's needs and so on and so forth," and that looks all very good except&#13;
that the dollars that we gave them--because that's what we gave them--is fungible, and they&#13;
bought Mercedes Benzes and took trips around the globe and reinforced the arms to their&#13;
armories and armaments and armies and so on. What's there?&#13;
&#13;
And when you talk with the Africans who are here on the issue we are dealing with--grain in&#13;
Africa or the fact that there's big food shortages in Africa, et cetera--what they point to is the fact&#13;
that, okay, it goes to structural adjustment. It's not going to really building what are the essences&#13;
that we built in South Asia with the Green Revolution, where the money did go for roads, for&#13;
irrigation--not modern irrigation, mind you, but irrigation--expanding markets, helping market&#13;
towns, opening up rural credit, not for farmers particularly but for the buyers of the fertilizer, et&#13;
cetera. If they hit a drought, then they've got some kind of credit protection on it. We built the&#13;
food corporation of India that took the excess food off, a whole array of transport questions and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         W. David Hopper&#13;
                               April 2 and May 12, 2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                        72&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
so on and so forth, that got opened. Seed, seed production. And all of these components were&#13;
pieces of this thing called the Green Revolution. Now I read stuff coming out in Science and so&#13;
on and so forth saying, "Well, the Green Revolution wasn't all that much a success and the rest&#13;
of it," but totally forgetting the entire set of other institutions that you built--fertilizer plants and&#13;
all the rest of it--that were absolutely critical to getting this thing out to the farms and getting it&#13;
used.&#13;
&#13;
FEL TAULT: Most of the critiques that I have read on the Green Revolution have more to do&#13;
with equity issues, which I know was a big topic in the '70s and '80s.&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: Listen, this was a big topic in the '60s, my dear, when V.K.R.V. Rao at Delhi&#13;
University, an economist, proceeded to hold a meeting in 1966, March '66, and brought all&#13;
together all the economists from around India, top economists, to discuss what do we do we do&#13;
about--do we bring in wheat from Mexico and rice and urea and so on for Indian agriculture?&#13;
Without question, the economists as a bloc said no. Why? Because the whole of the Indian&#13;
development movement is built upon equity. You do this and, by god, the Punjab is going to&#13;
move way ahead of the rest ofIndia, Madhya Pradesh and the rest of it where they don't have&#13;
irrigation and they'll be left behind. "No. How can we trust this material, and it comes in and&#13;
handled? No. We need the money to build our own industrial infrastructure and so on. Right&#13;
now we're getting money from--we're farming the fields of Kansas and Saskatchewan. Let's&#13;
continue to do that. They're doing it under promissory notes and so on, so we don't need to&#13;
worry about it. But that is what we should be focusing on, is building the industry of India," et&#13;
cetera, et cetera, et cetera.&#13;
&#13;
There were two people there--a guy by the name of Dave Hopper and a guy by the name of&#13;
Khilone [phonetic], something Khilone [phonetic]--who got up and said, "You've got to feed&#13;
your country. The only way we're going to do this is to break out of the present thing. The&#13;
wheats that we were demonstrating--the wheats are very, very much more productive, and the&#13;
rices that we know are available and which we have tested and have scattered arQund are very&#13;
productive." Khilone [phonetic], from the Agricultural University in the Punjab up at Ludhiana,&#13;
and Hopper from the Rockefeller Foundation.&#13;
&#13;
A guy sitting way up at the back--it's hot as blazes in the end of March it gets hot in Delhi--&#13;
sitting way up at the back the whole three days of watching this, was a man by the name of C.&#13;
Subramaniam, who was the minister of agriculture. Subramaniam, at the end of this discussion--&#13;
it was two and a half days--got up and just said, "Well, I thank you very much, Professor Rao.&#13;
This was a very edifying thing. But I want you to know that out of this entire group, only two&#13;
people have addressed my problem, Professor Khilone [phonetic] and Dr. Hopper." He said,&#13;
"My problem is how do I feed my people." And he walked out.&#13;
&#13;
That was a Friday. On Sunday I got a call from Ralph Cummings at the Rockefeller Foundation,&#13;
the head of the Rockefeller unit which I was working for. Ralph said he had just received a call&#13;
from Subramaniam, and they're putting a group on an airplane to go to Mexico to bring back&#13;
wheat, seed wheat. I said, "Ralph, never on God's earth. They won't bring back 25,000 tons.&#13;
The government of India will never be able to scrape up that money in that period of time.&#13;
Finance will be opposed to it and so on. But see what happens."&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                          W. David Hopper&#13;
                                April 2 and May 12, 2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                      73&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
On Wednesday, four guys got on an airplane, Pan Am flight to New York out of Delhi, to go to&#13;
Mexico to buy wheat. They had 5 million dollars. They bought 16,000 tons of wheat, came in&#13;
by ship. This was--wheat is planted in November, as I think I told you last time, and harvested it&#13;
in March. We got our seed then in November. March of '66--we planted in November '66,&#13;
harvested in March '67. We got a massive amount of seed. That got out in March of '67 and&#13;
was harvested in--sorry, November '67 and was harvested in March of '68, and they beat&#13;
Canada's amount of wheat, and we were away. Since then, they produce more wheat than the&#13;
United States does, second only to China on rice.&#13;
&#13;
But it took a while to build all of this. It took a huge number of institutions to be put in place.&#13;
And I don't get the sense now at the Bank that those institutions are being put in place.&#13;
&#13;
FELT AULT: Like fertilizer plants.&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: The fertilizer plants, the factor markets.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: And that's what most of the loans [inaudible].&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: The roads, the et cetera that you do. And we're off over here-kind of, you know,&#13;
poverty alleviation, sustainable development, a whole series of other things that are in this thing,&#13;
and that you have to weigh all your projects against them, and is this really what we're going to&#13;
be doing. HIV at this point--I have no problem with HIV, but that's not going to do these things.&#13;
It's not going to feed people.&#13;
&#13;
[End Tape 2, Side A]&#13;
[Begin Tape 2, Side B]&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: The one areas that aren't away is sub-Saharan Africa. I discovered the other day&#13;
that sub-Saharan Africa, nobody is working on soils. Okay, Borlaug made a speech on soils. He&#13;
wrote something on this, and there's been other things, and I've been working with FAO. But&#13;
somehow or other, African soils are very, very old soils. They're totally depleted.&#13;
&#13;
And the example I used the other day-I don't know whether I used with you before or not--was&#13;
what the Australians did. During the Second World War, we managed to increase agricultural&#13;
production by about 44,45 percent in this country. Australia couldn't do anything. Sir John&#13;
Crawford came--well, he was John Crawford then, he wasn't Sir John Crawford--but John&#13;
Crawford came here to take a look at the U.S. from the Australian agriculture ministry. And he&#13;
found that the US had an awful lot of research that was done back in the '20s and 'JOs which&#13;
wasn't applied until the Second World War, the Depression of the '30s and so forth. Australia&#13;
hadn't done this. But he found most importantly that they had done a lot of work on soils and&#13;
what were the trace minerals required and so on and so forth in soils to get agriculture really&#13;
moving.&#13;
&#13;
And he returned to Australia. He organized--reorganized, got the government to reorganize the&#13;
Australian Scientific Council to take a look at agriculture, which they never looked at before, and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                          W. David Hopper&#13;
                               April 2 and May 12,2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                    74&#13;
&#13;
soils. They found that the Australian soils were grossly depleted of nutrients. It doesn't make&#13;
any difference how much fertilizer you put on, you didn't have enough selenium to let things&#13;
grow. And they began aerial bombardments, basically, with aerial planes flying over dropping&#13;
materials on these soils. And within five years, Australia almost doubled its agricultural output,&#13;
cheap land and so on, from this soils thing.&#13;
&#13;
We've got to do the same thing in Africa. We haven't done it. The International Fertilizer&#13;
Development Center has a thing out on African soils, but nQne of it going down deep enough&#13;
into the--not in just the depth of the soil; that's important--but in terms of just the trace minerals&#13;
that have been lost over time. The slash and bum agriculture adds some of this back to the soil&#13;
again, and this is the agriculture that was used in Africa, still is used in parts of Africa. You&#13;
know, you go in, you plant grain for a couple of years on this land, trees grow up on the others,&#13;
then you go off and cut that, let it bum down. You do this, and you keep shifting around so that&#13;
every five, eight years, you're back to where you started in this thing and cutting down the trees&#13;
again and burning them up.                             .&#13;
&#13;
The difficulty is that--that's great if you've got a relatively small population that can move&#13;
around. You don't anymore. And the population growth is very, very substantial. And again,&#13;
we're back to the fact that birth rates are culturally determined in expected times, and the death&#13;
rates are dropping because we are bringing in modem medical systems and so on and so forth.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: And as you took over Policy Planning, I mean that was a new position that&#13;
Conable had created.&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: Yes.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: It seems like you had a variety of duties in that position, not just some, you know,&#13;
research and strategic planning, but there were personnel and administrative issues as well. So it&#13;
seems like a rather all-encompassing position.&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: It was.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: Can you tell me how you dealt with that and what were some of the issues?&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: We had regular meetings. I had the-Stan [Stanley] Fischer I appointed as my&#13;
economist and head of the economics thing. We held weekly meetings in terms of what was&#13;
going on, where they were, and what they were doing. And these were broad-based in the sense&#13;
that other directors that I had under me would come to them and we would hold our discussions.&#13;
I had the budget group. Bob [Robert] Picciotto was running the budget group. There was a&#13;
whole set of budget issues that needed to be done. I had to project forward in a way that the&#13;
Bank hadn't done in the past in terms of expenses and incomes and the rest of it. Conable was&#13;
an old hand at the budget in Congress, and he wanted to see not dissimilar kind of budget&#13;
projections as to what we were going to do. And Picciotto was very, very capable in handling&#13;
this. I got, brought in some people, a partner from Price Waterhouse and so on and so forth,&#13;
part-time to take a look at this and to see if we couldn't get the thing balanced up and a different&#13;
kind of budget arrangement than we'd had before.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                          W. David Hopper&#13;
                               April 2 and May 12, 2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                   75&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
I did work with--the same thing with the irrigation with a whole series of other things we have in&#13;
agriculture, but this was far more broadly based, and it was globally based, and what needed to&#13;
be done. The issue of the Brazilian rainforest came up, and the questions that you had there, the&#13;
problems of industrial investments which you had in things like Sao Paolo and so on, and the&#13;
slum issues that you had in Rio and up into the northern part of Brazilian east, et cetera, arose. It&#13;
was just a collection of the whole range of activities.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAUL T: How did you determine what your research agenda would be? Did that go by the&#13;
calendar year or the needs of the Bank?&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: No. It pretty much came out of what were the issues that they were discussing in&#13;
various levels in the institution. It was a broad-based sort of thing. I didn't-I mean, once the&#13;
decision was made that I was not going to do policy for the project people, I didn't feel at all&#13;
constrained as to what else we were going to be doing, and so, you know, we got into a wide&#13;
range of different activities.&#13;
&#13;
But, as I say, it was as a courtier and not as a baron. I think I preferred being a baron.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: In that case, on paper it looks like it's a baron position, let me put it that way--on&#13;
paper. So what in your mind made it not that?&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: The issue with the baron is that there is a great deal of detail that is occurring, that&#13;
you're watching, that is being reported, et cetera, and you have different perspectives that you're&#13;
going to get on it. The position of the courtier, your answer went up to this larger group above,&#13;
and they're coming in with various kinds ofthings that they want to do. Conable would hold&#13;
meetings and say, "Well, this is--what about this?" and so on and so forth. You'd have a debate&#13;
around the table with the senior vice presidents and such others as you wanted to bring in. Then&#13;
Conable would say, "That's fine," and we'd go on to the next issue. Then Conable would go,&#13;
typical lawyer, and write his judgment, and two days later you'd get the judgment, or three days&#13;
later you'd get the judgment as to what we were going to do. This was it.&#13;
&#13;
None of the barons were subject to this. [Laughter] It was the upper level group that was&#13;
engaged in it. This is where it was. And you had everything from issues of democracies to&#13;
issues of what do we do with apartheid rules in South Africa, how do we handle the Lesotho&#13;
business that has to be looked at because we're not lending to South Africa because of their&#13;
apartheid, and the UN, and, and, and, and, and.&#13;
&#13;
And I had to go up to the UN with some frequency, talk to them in the UNDP. It used to be that&#13;
I'd go to the South Asia guy, but now it was the Director General at the UN, drop in and talk&#13;
with whoever he was, the secretary general up there, and this sort of business, and UNESCO-I&#13;
remember we had all of these things lined up.&#13;
&#13;
I brought, bluntly--I was two years from retirement, and, okay, this was all right, but it wasn't. It&#13;
wasn't really what I wanted to be doing.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        W. David Hopper&#13;
                              April 2 and May 12, 2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                    76&#13;
&#13;
FEL TAUL T: Right. But that first year, didn't Conable reorganize the whole entire Bank?&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: Yeah, he did.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: So how was that in respect to what you were trying to do?&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: Okay, I had to figure out what needed to be done. One of the things was the&#13;
environment issue. One of the other was the strategic planning. Another one was the question of&#13;
getting the research group and economics group kind of in line and so on and so forth. And I did&#13;
some things there. They were weak on much of this before. They had some good economists&#13;
and that sort of thing, but the statistical base wasn't really very serious, and I got going on that. I&#13;
got going on some others. It was a participatory sort of activity, that's all&#13;
&#13;
At the same time, we were dealing with how do we restructure the Bank and the rest of it, and I&#13;
was fairly active on the fact that I felt the competency to assess this restructuring game--we had&#13;
to knock down the old 1818 H Building. It was built back in 1941. By 1975 the DC government&#13;
were no longer checking the boilers and so on because they couldn't be replaced. Well, then the&#13;
question was, do we lower them from the ceiling down, put them into the basement, leave the&#13;
building intact? Well, then we found there was asbestos all through the building, so it had to be&#13;
knocked out and the rest of it. You know, it just plodded on.&#13;
&#13;
I found the legal department were very, very jealous ofthe fact that they were not--they would&#13;
write the contract with Hyman [Construction Company], who were the ones to build it. I had a&#13;
son who was working for another part of Hyman--it's now Clark Construction; it was then&#13;
owned by Clark as well but another side of Hyman--who just phoned me and said, "Did you&#13;
know what the Bank is going to offer? They're laughing all the way to the bank, all the way to&#13;
our bank, to Riggs, on this, because the World Bank contract is just nuts." Well, it turns out, it&#13;
was nuts, because we didn't get a lawyer who understood American things. I mean, when I&#13;
suggested that we get a lawyer for this--oh, what's his name? an Egyptian who was our legal&#13;
friend and an old friend of mine; we served on a couple of boards together--he just about reached&#13;
across the table to throttle me, the idea that I would suggest that his lawyers couldn't do this.&#13;
Well, it turns out they couldn't do it. They had no conception of what was required from an&#13;
American lawyer thing.&#13;
&#13;
Equally, I was thunderstruck by the fact that we didn't hire an outside firm to be the client's&#13;
supervisor in all of this. We gave that to one of our people in general services, an Indian, who&#13;
knew nothing about what to do on these things, and the result being that what we estimated to be&#13;
a 90 million dollar thing with all the changes and so on and so forth turned out to be 170 million&#13;
bucks. The A building, the main building or the central concourse, is still in difficulty because&#13;
they didn't have anybody to go around and check the balances and the rest of it. Every time I go&#13;
into it, you know, the doors are not hung properly and the settlement and so on and so forth.&#13;
Well, I put all of this down in memos and forget it.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: I guess I'll just ask a couple of questions about CGIAR [Consultative Group for&#13;
International Agricultural Research], since you were president of that at the time, and then we&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         W. David Hopper&#13;
                               April 2 and May 12,2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                77&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
can see if we want to have another session maybe in June ifthere's something else you want to&#13;
talk about. So you took over the--is it a presidency or a chairmanship?&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: No. It's chairman of the CG group. I had been a factor--l mean, I had worked on&#13;
the CG before it was the CG. I think I outlined that to you the last time. The CG came into&#13;
being as a result of a discussion in Bellagio in 1969 and then followed up in early '70. And I&#13;
was at IDRC then; in '69 I was there for the Rockefeller Foundation because it was sponsored by&#13;
the Rockefeller and Ford Foundations. Bellagio was the Rockefeller conference center.&#13;
&#13;
And I followed the CG subsequently when I was at IDRC, and I followed a little bit when I got&#13;
to the Bank though it wasn't one of my CG things. I did work with some of the others to get CG&#13;
recognition and so on. There's a CG center in India that was put up before I got to the Bank, but&#13;
it was there.&#13;
&#13;
I have long felt that the CG needed either some kind of shift in focus or some kind of a sunset&#13;
clause, but that never came into being. I moved in as--I became chairman because I was&#13;
interested in the CG and I wanted to see it develop. And there was moves to create a CG for&#13;
forestry and a CG for fisheries and so on, and I decided all of that could come under the present&#13;
CG, there was no need to have the other, and Barber Conable agreed with that. He didn't want to&#13;
see further additions made. So it became a much, much bigger center. And I have maintained&#13;
since then that we should still have a sunset clause and let the damn thing go over the next ten&#13;
years or whatever else. The point is that when we built the CGs initially, when we built these&#13;
centers--IRRI at the Rice Institute, the first one in '62, and then picked up the Rockefeller Group&#13;
that were engaged in wheat, maize and beans and potato work in Mexico, we picked up them and&#13;
created CIMMYT. And then we took the Rockefeller program in Colombia and made CIAT out&#13;
of it. Then we put a new one into Africa at lIT A. This was Ford and Rockefeller and IDRC.&#13;
This was the mix. I was working with Ford and with Rockefeller when those four centers were&#13;
created.&#13;
&#13;
The centers got too much for the blood of the Rockefeller and Ford Foundations continuously, so&#13;
in ' 69 they held a meeting of the aid donors, bilateral aid donors, and the World Bank.&#13;
McNamara supported it and so on. Out of that grew the CG system. Nobody knew how it was&#13;
going to work. McNamara picked it up. We created the CG. And in November--or, sorry, in&#13;
December of '70, it was kind of--now it was on the docket, and March of '71 the first meeting of&#13;
the CG took place, and I was there representing IDRC.&#13;
&#13;
I then got put on the TAC, so I left--the Technical Advisory Committee to this group--and I&#13;
stayed on the TAC for several years. I followed the CG indirectly in the Bank. I knew what was&#13;
going on elsewhere. And when it came time, and I was now Senior Vice President, and I was no&#13;
longer just South Asia, I felt I could take the CG over as chairman, and I did. We added the&#13;
forestry and fisheries to it and added some other things.&#13;
&#13;
But I warned people then that we were going to be--that when it began, the research capability in&#13;
most of these better, the larger developing countries was relatively small. It was now&#13;
substantially larger. We had educated a lot more people and sent them back and so on and so&#13;
forth. U.S. AID had put a lot of money into ag universities in India and Pakistan and the rest of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        W. David Hopper&#13;
                              April 2 and May 12, 2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                     78&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
it. And is this something that the Bank needed to keep going? Well, the general feeling was,&#13;
yes, we did. The donors that came were very, very there. I left the CG in what I thought was&#13;
reasonable shape but still concerned that we should say that, "Okay, ten years we should be out&#13;
of it."&#13;
&#13;
Then you have the IT revolution, and the question is, "Can you do this?" Okay, the CG centers&#13;
communicate with each other and so on. Have they communicated with the centers in the&#13;
developing countries? The answer is generally no. The dialogue is not easily there.&#13;
Furthermore, the centers have become increasingly kind of taking up 90 percent of the budget to&#13;
just pay their staff and so on. It's not going out elsewhere, and I've been very critical of this.&#13;
&#13;
Uma Lele has written quite a long report on it. Borlaug had a letter--this was the guy who won&#13;
the Nobel Prize on the basis of his wheat. And Borlaug doesn't write. He sent a cable off once&#13;
to the Rockefeller Foundation years and years before, 1955 or so, when they kept pressing him to&#13;
contribute because anybody who worked for the Rockefeller Foundation has to send in an annual&#13;
report that is included in the annual report of the Rockefeller Foundation. Borlaug kept ignoring&#13;
it and so on. They finally, you know, insisted, and Borlaug finally sent a cable which I found in&#13;
the Rockefeller archives, you know: "What do you want? Paper or bread? Borlaug."&#13;
[Laughter]&#13;
&#13;
Borlaug has a letter in the February issue of Science, the February 20 issue of Science this year,&#13;
really castigating the CGs, that they've just gone way out of whack, and they have. There are a&#13;
lot of reasons for that, and I won't go into them here, but the CGs have become bureaucratic to&#13;
the eyeballs. What was a secretariat, a little secretariat in the Bank has now become a big, big&#13;
secretariat with all kinds of paper being written and so on and so forth and support the Hunger&#13;
Foundation or whatever else it's called and the rest of it. And the costs are in the hundreds of&#13;
millions, 3 to 400 million dollars that have been going into this, and the developing countries are&#13;
not any better off. I mean, it's--you can get this stuffthere, but there is still no discussion as to&#13;
what you do about it.&#13;
&#13;
This is my problem at F AO. They've got test plots all over the place but no way to make it&#13;
national, no way to expand it.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: To tum it into policy or operationalize it.&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: That's right. Or to get the countries to do it. I mean, it's the countries that have to&#13;
do it. As long as you've got the food corporations there and as long as you've got the Europeans&#13;
willing to dump food into Africa relatively inexpensively and you're fighting the WTO now on&#13;
cotton here in the United States, which the developing countries are saying, "We can grow over&#13;
here. Why the hell are you growing it there?" And sugar--we're growing our own and charging&#13;
a high price for it, et cetera, et cetera, et cetera. It was what, 312 billion dollars went to subsidies&#13;
in agriculture--Europe, Japan, and the United States--last year, and the developing countries&#13;
can't compete with it, and that's what's going on.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: They're also not allowed to subsidize their own industries, are they?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         W. David Hopper&#13;
                               April 2 and May 12, 2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                 79&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: Agriculture. That's right.&#13;
&#13;
I ran into this thing the other day in Ethiopia. The Ethiopians are having very grave difficulty&#13;
right now, and they're going to have to be on food thing again. One of the reasons is that they&#13;
need 300 million dollars worth of fertilizer, and the World Bank and the IMF have told them no.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: On what grounds?&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: It hurts your budget. You have to subsidize it to the farmers because it's a long&#13;
haul, transport haul, et cetera. They can't afford to pay for it. And here you are.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAUL T: That is the effect of structural adjustment programs.&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: It's the effect of structural adjustment, and it's is the effect of--what does the&#13;
government do. The State Department wants it to be a democracy. The farmers are saying,&#13;
"What the hell? Why should we have this when we can't get any help from our government?"&#13;
and so on and so forth.&#13;
&#13;
FELTAULT: It's interesting. You have to question what's carrying more weight--their balance&#13;
of payments or their food security at this point?&#13;
&#13;
HOPPER: And on the food security, the last time they had a bumper crop, Ethiopia refused to&#13;
put it into storage because we told them not to. Markets would look after it. The markets would&#13;
look after it. Prices dropped, and farmers just quit, saying, "Well, the hell with this. I'm not&#13;
going to put that in again. I'll put in much, much smaller amounts." They were hit by a drought.&#13;
Here we are now dumping food--or were then dumping food into it. But instead of creating a&#13;
food corporation in India, which we did, to take the surpluses off and to hold them in high&#13;
quality storages so that if the drought does hit, they've got it: no way. This is just not in that--&#13;
it's not on that horizon. And again, you're back to the MBAs and the economists, not to people&#13;
who know how to grow food or handle it.&#13;
&#13;
FELT AULT: Why don't we stop here and see if we need to have a third session to talk more&#13;
abdut the Policy Planning and Research or ifthere is anything-it might be good after you read&#13;
the two transcripts, if there's anything you want to add.&#13;
&#13;
[End Tape 2, Side B]&#13;
[End of interview]&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        W. David Hopper&#13;
                              April 2 and May 12,2004 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="23023468">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2004/05/23023468/transcript-oral-history-interview-w-david-hopper-held-april-2-may-12-2004
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2004/05/23023468/transcript-oral-history-interview-w-david-hopper-held-april-2-may-12-2004</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2004/05/23023468/transcript-oral-history-interview-w-david-hopper-held-april-2-may-12-2004</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2014-12-15T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2014-12-15T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <docm_id>090224b082c25a76</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b082c25a76</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2014/12/15/000442464_20141215121500/Rendered/INDEX/931630TSCP0Hop00Box385395B00PUBLIC0.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2014/12/15/000442464_20141215121500/Rendered/PDF/931630TSCP0Hop00Box385395B00PUBLIC0.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2004-05-12T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2014-12-15T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Transcript of oral history interview with
            W. David Hopper held on April 2 and May 12, 2004
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            In April and May, 2004, W. David Hopper
            was interviewed on behalf of the World Bank Group Archives
            oral history program by Kelly Feltault. He worked as
            chairman of the consultative group (CG) when the forestry
            institute was created. He worked in South Asia as vice
            president in 1977. This transcript concerns his education
            and experience prior working with the Bank. It concerns the
            Bell Mission.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Transcript of oral history interview with W.
            David Hopper held on April 2 and May 12, 2004
        </docna>
        <display_title>Transcript of oral history
            interview with W. David Hopper held on April 2 and May 12, 2004</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/2004/05/23023468/transcript-oral-history-interview-w-david-hopper-held-april-2-may-12-2004</listing_relative_url>
        <topic>Agricultural Credit m1327605 1962,Agricultural Laws and Regulations m1327358 171,Agricultural Policies m1326884 170,Agricultural Finance m1326892 1059,Agribusiness m1326896 2179</topic>
        <subtopic>Technology Industry,Sustainable Land and Crop Management,Crops and Crop Management Systems,Agricultural Research,Food &amp; Beverage Industry</subtopic>
        <docty>Transcript</docty>
        <teratopic>Rural Development,Agriculture,Industry</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000442464_20141215121500</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>World Bank Group Archives oral history program</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Rural Development,Agriculture,Industry</historic_topic>
        <topicv3>Agricultural Credit m1327605 1962,Agricultural Laws and Regulations m1327358 171,Agricultural Policies m1326884 170,Agricultural Finance m1326892 1059,Agribusiness m1326896 2179</topicv3>
        <majdocty>Board Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Agricultural College, agricultural
            development, agricultural economics, agricultural institute,
            agricultural output, agricultural research, Agricultural
            Research Institute, agriculture, agronomy, ammonium nitrate,
            animals, beans, bottles, bullock, bushel of wheat, cashew
            nuts, CGIAR, CIMMYT, communities, components, computers,
            crop, dam, dead animals, Development Research, differential
            equations, diseases, dwarf rice, electronics, engineering,
            farm, farmer, farmers, farming, farms, feed, fertilizer,
            food aid, food as a weapon, food grains, food production,
            food supplies, food surplus, Ford Foundation, germs, grain,
            grain harvester, grain storage, Green Revolution, harvest,
            harvesting, hybrid maize, IDRC, International Agricultural
            Research, International Development Research Center,
            International Fertilizer Development Center, International
            Maize and Wheat Improvement Center, International Rice
            Research Institute, irrigation, manure, milk, milk
            marketing, National Research, National Research Council,
            pests, physics, Pineapple, planting, potatoes, produce,
            programming, punch cards, rice, rice areas, Rice Research,
            rice yields, Rockefeller Foundation, roots, seed, seeds,
            soil types, soils, straw, tea, the Consultative Group,
            turnips, University of Illinois, wheat, wheat crops, wheat
            yields, wine,
        </keywd>
        <owner>Knowledge &amp; Information Services (ITSKI)</owner>
        <repnb>93163</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT for Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies (ICT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Industry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Science and Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Extension &amp; Research</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crops</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Research and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Checks on Executive Power</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen User Satisfaction Survey</ml:concept><ml:concept>Independent Commissions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ombudsmen</ml:concept><ml:concept>Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Parliament</ml:concept><ml:concept>Procurement Complaints Review Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supreme Audit Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Anthropology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Economics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Engineering</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Research</ml:concept><ml:concept>Technology Industry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Diseases</ml:concept><ml:concept>Malaria</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fertilizers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forests</ml:concept><ml:concept>Airports</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Satellites</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Accountability Mechanisms</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>