<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>﻿OFFICIAL           T   c4 cr&#13;
DOCUMENTS&#13;
Administration Agreement betweeJhe[iqglg2tfV o fNAerlands, as represented by the Minister for&#13;
Foreign Trade and Development Cooperation and the International Bank for Reconstruction and&#13;
Development and the International Development Association concerning the Multi-Donor Trust Fund&#13;
for Middle-Income Countries for the Financial Sector Reform and Strengthening Initiative&#13;
(TF No. 070723)&#13;
1.    The International Bank for Reconstruction and Development and the International Development&#13;
Association (collectively, the "Bank") acknowledge that the Kingdom of Netherlands, as represented by&#13;
Minister for Foreign Trade and Development Cooperation (the "Donor", and together with the Bank, the&#13;
"Parties" and each a "Party") agrees to provide the sum of one million and nine hundred and forty thousand&#13;
United States Dollars (USD 1,940,000) (the "Contribution") for the Multi-Donor Trust Fund for Middle-&#13;
Income Countries for the Financial Sector Reform and Strengthening Initiative (TF No. 070723)&#13;
(the "Trust Fund") in accordance with the terms of this Administration Agreement. Other donors are also&#13;
expected to contribute to the Trust Fund on the terms and conditions specified in the Annexes to this&#13;
Administration Agreement.&#13;
2.     The Contribution shall be used to finance the activities set forth in the "Description of Activities,&#13;
Expenditures and Governance for the Multi-Donor Trust Fund for Middle-Income Countries for the FIRST"&#13;
attached hereto as Annex 1, and shall be administered by the Bank on behalf of the Donor in accordance with&#13;
the terms of this Administration Agreement, including the "Standard Provisions" attached hereto as Annex 2.&#13;
3.     The Donor shall deposit the Contribution in the currency specified in Section 1 above ("Contribution&#13;
Currency") into such bank account designated by the Bank promptly following countersignature of this&#13;
Agreement and upon submission of a payment request by the Bank.&#13;
4.     When making any deposit, the Donor shall instruct its bank to include in its deposit details&#13;
information (remittance advice) field of its SWIFT deposit message, information indicating: the amount&#13;
deposited, that the deposit is made by the Donor for TF No. 070723 (Multi-Donor Trust Fund for Middle-&#13;
Income Countries for the Financial Sector Reform and Strengthening Initiative), and the date of the deposit&#13;
(the "Deposit Instructions"). In addition, the Donor shall provide a copy of the Deposit Instructions to the&#13;
Bank's Accounting Trust Funds Division by e-mail sent to tfremitadvice@worldbank.org or by fax sent to&#13;
+1 (202) 614-1315.&#13;
5.     Except with respect to the Deposit Instructions, any notice, request or other communication to be&#13;
given or made under this Administration Agreement shall be in writing and delivered by mail, fax or e-mail&#13;
to the respective Party's address specified below or at such other address as such Party notifies in writing to&#13;
the other Party from time to time:&#13;
For the Bank (the "Bank Contact"):&#13;
Consolate Rusagara&#13;
Senior Program Manager&#13;
FIRST Program Management Unit&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington DC 20433, U.S. A.&#13;
Tel. 202-473-2765&#13;
Fax: 202-522-0277&#13;
E-mail: crusagara@worldbank.org&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-2-&#13;
For the Donor (the "Donor Contact"):&#13;
Peter Le Poole&#13;
Senior Policy Advisor Financial Sector&#13;
Sustainable Economic Development Department DDE/VF&#13;
Ministry of Foreign Affairs&#13;
POB 20061&#13;
2500 EB The Hague&#13;
The Netherlands&#13;
Tel. 31 70 348 6041&#13;
Fax 31 70 348 5956&#13;
E-mail: peter-le.poole@minbuza.nl&#13;
6.    In the event any amounts are to be returned to the Donor under this Administration Agreement, the&#13;
Bank shall transfer such amounts to the Donor, unless otherwise agreed with the Bank.&#13;
7.     All annexes hereto constitute an integral part of this Administration Agreement, whose terms taken&#13;
together shall constitute the entire agreement and understanding between the Donor and the Bank. Unless&#13;
otherwise specified in an annex hereto, this Administration Agreement may be amended only by written&#13;
amendment between the Bank and the Donor; provided, however, that any annexes to this Administration&#13;
Agreement may be amended only by written amendment of all donors contributing to the Trust Fund.&#13;
8.     Each of the Parties represents, by confirming its agreement below, that it is authorized to enter into&#13;
this Administration Agreement and act in accordance with these terms and conditions. The Parties are&#13;
requested to sign and date this Administration Agreement, and upon possession by the Bank of this fully&#13;
signed Administration Agreement, this Administration Agreement shall become effective as of the date of&#13;
the last signature.&#13;
INTERNATIONAL BANK FOR RECONSTRUCTION AND DEVELOPMENT&#13;
INTERNATIONAL       EVELOPMENT ASSOCIATION&#13;
By:                                                    Date:    (&#13;
GIltia M. Gra olini&#13;
Se ior Director&#13;
Fi   ce and Ma kets Global Practice&#13;
THE KINGDO      OF,    THERLANDS, acting through&#13;
THE MINISTE O OREIGN TRADE AND DEVELOPMENT COOPERATION&#13;
By:                                                    Date:&#13;
Remo Zee w&#13;
Minister (Econo&#13;
Royal Netherl ds Embassy&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-3-&#13;
ANNEX 1&#13;
Description of Activities, Expenditures and Governance for the Multi-Donor Trust Fund for Middle-&#13;
Income Countries for the Financial Sector Reform and Strenzthenin2 Initiative&#13;
This Annex shall be applicable to and form an integral part of all administration agreements for the Trust&#13;
Fund (collectively, the "Administration Agreements" and each an "Administration Agreement") between the&#13;
Bank and any entities that provide any funds to the Trust Fund (collectively, the "Donors").&#13;
1.     Objectives and Governance Arrangements&#13;
The objectives of the Trust Fund is to support low-income countries to improve the stability, efficiency,&#13;
inclusiveness and depth of their financial sectors by providing short and medium-term technical assistance to&#13;
strengthen their financial systems or implement standards in advance of Financial Sector Assessment&#13;
Programs ("FSAPs") or Reports on Standards and Codes ("ROSCs"), and facilitate systematic follow-up of&#13;
related recommendations.&#13;
The Trust Fund supports FIRST, whose objectives, basic principles, activities and governance arrangements&#13;
are described in the charter, which was adopted on July 6, 2007, and amended on July 11, 2013, as such&#13;
charter may be amended from time to time in accordance with its terms (the "FIRST Charter"). The Trust&#13;
Fund is governed by the terms of this Administration Agreement and the FIRST Charter. The current charter&#13;
for FIRST is provided as Attachment 1 of this Annex 1 for informational purposes only. Any amendments to&#13;
the FIRST Charter, made in accordance with its terms, will become applicable to this Administration&#13;
Agreement as such amendments take effect without further need to amend this Administration Agreement;&#13;
provided that, in the event of any conflict with other parts of Administration Agreement, the terms of this&#13;
Administration Agreement shall prevail.&#13;
2.     Activities&#13;
The activities financed by the Trust Fund will be implemented by: (a) the Bank ("Bank-executed Activities")&#13;
and (b) the International Monetary Fund ("IMF Activities").&#13;
2.1    Bank-executed Activities include:&#13;
(a)    Reform and strengthen financial sector regulation, supervision and development&#13;
(i)    Conduct analysis using prior international standards' assessments and prepare&#13;
reports on options to develop policies, legal and regulatory frameworks, institutions,&#13;
products and services, and capacity building and training programs to reform,&#13;
strengthen, and develop the financial sector.&#13;
(ii)   Provide technical assistance to government agencies and regulatory bodies on&#13;
options for designing and implementing policies, legal, regulatory, supervisory&#13;
frameworks, capacity building and training programs, products and services to&#13;
reform, strengthen, and develop the financial sector, in response to country demand.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-4-&#13;
(b)    Knowledge Management and Dissemination&#13;
(i)    Carry out activities related to dissemination and knowledge management, including&#13;
disseminating trust fund activities and results; prepare reports and publications on&#13;
lessons learned from trust fund activities; design and deliver workshops, seminars&#13;
and trainings on financial sector reform and strengthening; coordinate and provide&#13;
technical support to Bank teams; and support research on and dissemination of best&#13;
practices and useful tools related to financial sector reform and development in low-&#13;
income countries.&#13;
(ii)   Disseminate information on technical assistance being provided by the development;&#13;
community; and share information with international standard-setting bodies and&#13;
other relevant institutions with respect to financial sector reform efforts.&#13;
(c)    Technical Assistance Impact&#13;
Assess and analyze the impact of the technical assistance provided by the development&#13;
community to countries, including the outcome of the recommendations provided.&#13;
2.2    IMF Activities will be decided upon in accordance with the Charter and will be consistent with the&#13;
objectives of the Trust Fund.&#13;
3.     Eligible Expenditures&#13;
3.1    For Bank-executed Activities, the Trust Fund funds may be used to finance:&#13;
(a)    Associated Overheads&#13;
(b)    Consultant Fees for Firms&#13;
(c)    Short Term Consultant Costs - with indirect costs&#13;
(d)    Contractual Services&#13;
(e)    Equipment and Office Premises Lease Cost&#13;
(f)    Extended Term Consultants - with indirect costs&#13;
(g)    Media, Workshop, Conference and Meeting&#13;
(h)    Staff Costs - with indirect costs&#13;
(i)    Temporary Support Staff Costs - with indirect costs&#13;
(j)    Travel Expenses&#13;
4.     Taxes&#13;
4.1    The foregoing activities and categories of expenditures may include the financing of taxes in&#13;
accordance with the Bank's applicable policies and procedures.&#13;
5.     Reporting&#13;
5.1    With respect to reporting under paragraph 6.1 of Annex 2, the progress reports will be provided with&#13;
reference to the results framework agreed by the Governing Council, as may be reviewed by the Governing&#13;
Council from time to time.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-5-&#13;
Attachment 1&#13;
Financial Sector Reform and Strengthening Initiative Charter&#13;
Adopted on July 6, 2007 and amended on July 11, 2013&#13;
(provided for informational purposes only)&#13;
1.     Introduction&#13;
1.1    The International Bank for Reconstruction and Development ("IBRD") and the International&#13;
Development Association ("IDA") (collectively, the "Bank"), the International Monetary Fund ("IMF") and&#13;
all donors ("Donors") to one or more trust funds (collectively, the "Trust Fund") for the Financial Sector&#13;
Reform and Strengthening Initiative ("FIRST") have adopted the present charter (the "Charter").&#13;
1.2    Launched in 2002, FIRST is a collaborative arrangement providing for a technical assistance ("TA")&#13;
facility designed to support growth and poverty reduction in low- and middle-income countries by promoting&#13;
stable, deep and diverse financial sectors. The FIRST arrangement is built upon close collaboration between&#13;
the Bank and the IMF, both to leverage institutional expertise, and as the designated implementing agencies&#13;
for FIRST TA. This arrangement also seeks to promote collaboration among a wide range of institutions,&#13;
including other bilateral agencies and multilateral development banks.&#13;
1.3    The Charter sets out the governance arrangements of FIRST that encapsulate this collaborative&#13;
arrangement.&#13;
2.     Basic Principles&#13;
2.1    Following are basic principles that will guide FIRST (the "Basic Principles"):&#13;
2.1.1  A demand-driven approach with open access&#13;
FIRST aims to be demand-driven and open in its approach, as a strong advocate of financial sector&#13;
development, and seeks to identify effective new ideas and modalities in the delivery of TA. To this end,&#13;
FIRST accepts technical assistance requests from a wide range of sources for the benefit of client countries.&#13;
As the designated implementing entities, the Bank and the IMF will prepare funding proposals to be&#13;
considered for FIRST financing.&#13;
2.1.2 Additionality&#13;
FIRST seeks to ensure that it funds activities that are complementary to those being funded from other&#13;
sources and that its funding does not substitute for or displace more suitable or appropriate assistance&#13;
available from other sources. FIRST seeks to excel in efforts to promote learning and knowledge sharing in&#13;
the area of financial sector TA.&#13;
2.1.3  Harmonization, transparency, and accountability&#13;
FIRST promotes a model of partnership in line with the principles of: ownership, alignment, harmonization,&#13;
managing for results and mutual accountability. For FIRST, this involves introducing clear accountabilities&#13;
in program management, setting targets, assessing effectiveness, and monitoring results. FIRST's partnership&#13;
model also seeks to promote learning and knowledge sharing.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-6-&#13;
2.1.4  TA Beneficiaries&#13;
(a)    Beneficiaries of FIRST TA are policy makers, regulatory bodies, government agencies,&#13;
international financial institutions, and, under limited circumstances, quasi-public institutions (such&#13;
as self-regulatory organizations and industry associations).&#13;
(b)    Beneficiaries of FIRST assistance must be from either low- or middle-income countries at&#13;
the time project proposals receive final approval. "Low-income countries" are those defined by the&#13;
Bank as eligible to receive low or no interest credits or grants from IDA. "Middle-income countries"&#13;
are those defined by the Bank as eligible to receive IBRD financing.&#13;
3.     Objectives&#13;
3.1    FIRST's overall objective is to help strengthen financial systems in low- and middle-income&#13;
countries so that they make a strong and positive contribution to economic growth and help reduce poverty&#13;
and income inequality. FIRST's activities are currently only those financed by the Trust Fund.&#13;
3.2    FIRST's specific areas of focus are to:&#13;
3.2.1  Finance TA in the areas of financial sector regulation, supervision and development in response to&#13;
country demands, provide support to countries to strengthen their financial systems or implement standards&#13;
and codes in advance of Financial Sector Assessment Programs ("FSAPs") or Reports on Standards and&#13;
Codes ("ROSCs"), and facilitate systematic follow-up of related recommendations.&#13;
3.2.2  Advise on the preparation and implementation of action plans, development programs and reforms in&#13;
the financial sector.&#13;
3.2.3  Promote coordination in the delivery of financial sector TA and capacity building, drawing&#13;
particularly on private sector expertise.&#13;
3.2.4  Support research on and the dissemination of best practices and useful tools related to financial&#13;
sector reform and development in low- and middle-income countries.&#13;
3.2.5  Work with international standard-setting bodies and other relevant partners to broaden the base of&#13;
providers supporting countries' efforts to implement standards and codes in accordance with FSAP and&#13;
ROSC recommendations and strengthen their financial systems.&#13;
3.2.6  Support capacity building and local knowledge exchange.&#13;
4.     Governance Structure&#13;
4.1    The Governing Council&#13;
4.1.1  FIRST is guided by a Governing Council comprising one representative of each of FIRST's Main&#13;
Donors (as defined below), a representative from the Bank and a representative from the IMF (the Main&#13;
Donors, Bank and IMF together being the "Council Members," and each a "Council Member"). "Main&#13;
Donors" are defined as Donors who have committed at least US$ 2,000,000 (two million United States&#13;
dollars) to FIRST over any three year period.&#13;
4.1.2  The chair and the vice-chair of the Governing Council will be selected from among the Council&#13;
Members. The chair and vice-Chair serve for a two year term.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-7-&#13;
4.1.3  The Governing Council meets annually and may meet more often as necessary and agreed by the&#13;
Council Members.   The Secretariat provides each Council Member with written notice of a Governing&#13;
Council meeting not less than sixty (60) days before the date of the meeting unless such notice period has&#13;
been waived by the Council Members. Such notice states the date, place and time of the proposed meeting&#13;
and, in the case of a special meeting, the purpose(s) for which the meeting is being called.&#13;
4.1.4  Decisions by the Governing Council will be made by consensus of its Council Members&#13;
representatives. Any decisions of the Governing Council will be made by (i) consensus of all its Council&#13;
Members representatives physically present at an in-person meeting or in attendance by video or telephone&#13;
conferences; or (ii) affirmative approval or no objection within ten (10) days on the part of all the Council&#13;
Members by email correspondence. The Bank and the IMF must abstain from voting in the Governing&#13;
Council on any project proposals to be financed by the Trust Fund, submitted by the Bank or the IMF.&#13;
4.1.5  The Governing Council is responsible for:&#13;
(i)    Approving FIRST strategy, priorities and operating procedures.&#13;
(ii)   Establishing selection criteria and processing guidelines for approval of FIRST projects.&#13;
(iii)  Selecting the Governing Council chair and vice-chair.&#13;
(iv)   Approving FIRST's annual strategic plan and budget, receiving progress updates on its&#13;
results and monitoring its achievement and implementation.&#13;
(v)    Approving fundraising strategies for FIRST and participating in resource mobilization for&#13;
FIRST.&#13;
(vi)   Establishing the selection criteria and requirements for project proposals for consideration for&#13;
funding from the Trust Fund.&#13;
(vii)  Approving project proposals to be financed by the Trust Fund.&#13;
(viii)  Delegating project approval to the Bank and IMF for their respective project proposals.&#13;
(ix)   Reviewing and evaluating FIRST's overall performance, including commissioning&#13;
evaluations.&#13;
(x)    Approving quality standards and approving monitoring and evaluation frameworks for&#13;
Bank-executed activities and IMF executed-activities.&#13;
(xi)   Providing inputs to the terms of reference and feedback on the shortlist of candidates and the&#13;
two final candidates for the recruitment of the head of the Secretariat (the "Program&#13;
Manager"). The Governing Council will provide feedback to the Bank on the performance of&#13;
the Program Manager.&#13;
(xii)  Defining criteria for joining FIRST as a Donor and making decisions on the composition of&#13;
FIRST and its governing bodies, including the Project Advisory Committee.&#13;
(xiii)  Adopting and amending this Charter in accordance with the provisions set forth below.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-8-&#13;
4.2.   Project Advisory Committee&#13;
4.2.1  The Project Advisory Committee (PAC) consists of one senior Bank staff, one senior IMF staff and&#13;
the Program Manager.&#13;
4.2.2  PAC provides information to the Governing Council reflecting recommendations by the Bank and&#13;
the IMF for their respective proposals and coordinates the respective selection and implementation of Bank&#13;
and IMF activities.&#13;
4.3    Secretariat&#13;
4.3.1  The Bank administers FIRST's day-to-day operations, through the Secretariat, as described in this&#13;
Charter. The Secretariat is located in Washington, DC housed in the Bank's headquarters. The Secretariat is&#13;
comprised of professional and administrative staff employed by the Bank and headed by a Program Manager.&#13;
The Program Manager is responsible for supervising the staff of the Secretariat.&#13;
4.3.2  The Secretariat operates under Bank's management and applicable Bank's policies and procedures&#13;
and is also accountable to the Governing Council for carrying out its work program, compiling results of&#13;
FIRST activities against targets, and abiding by the Charter.&#13;
4.3.3  The key responsibilities of the Secretariat, under the supervision of the Program Manager, include:&#13;
(i)    Managing FIRST's day-to-day operations, including coordinating with Donors and IMF.&#13;
(ii)   Providing administrative support to the Governing Council including coordination of&#13;
meetings, and maintaining records of Governing Council business, including meeting&#13;
minutes, decisions and amendments to the Charter.&#13;
(iii)  Identifying opportunities for FIRST assistance by working with key stakeholders.&#13;
(iv)   Facilitating preparation of project proposals for prospective beneficiaries to be implemented&#13;
by the Bank.&#13;
(v)    Recommending strategies, priorities, operational procedures, and monitoring and evaluations&#13;
systems to the Governing Council.&#13;
(vi)   Reviewing funding proposals to determine if they meet the eligibility criteria for FIRST&#13;
funding, prior consideration by the PAC.&#13;
(vii)  Convening meetings of and providing support for the PAC.&#13;
(viii)  Monitoring project implementation progress of FIRST projects executed by the Bank.&#13;
(ix)   Monitoring and evaluation of Bank implementation of FIRST activities in accordance with&#13;
the monitoring and evaluation framework approved by the Governing Council.&#13;
(x)    Compiling information on monitoring and evaluation by the IMF of its activities in&#13;
accordance with the monitoring and evaluation framework approved by the Governing&#13;
Council, for submission to the Governing Council.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-9-&#13;
(xi)   Preparing drafts of FIRST's annual strategic plan and budgets, with inputs from IMF for&#13;
IMF-executed activities, for submission to the Governing Council for approval.&#13;
(xii)  Providing periodic reports to the Governing Council on the status of the FIRST portfolio,&#13;
including compiling information received from IMF.&#13;
(xiii)  Organizing and coordinating meetings and workshops for participation of donors and&#13;
stakeholders in the financial sector from time to time, to discuss the broad financial sector&#13;
development agenda and strategies.&#13;
(xiv)  Disseminating and promoting best practices in financial sector reform and the delivery of&#13;
financial sector technical assistance.&#13;
(xv)   Maintaining the FIRST website.&#13;
5.     Trustee of FIRST Trust Fund&#13;
5.1    The Bank will serve as trustee of one or more trust funds (the Trust Fund) established by the Bank to&#13;
support FIRST activities. Donor contributions are made to the Trust Fund under administration&#13;
agreements/arrangements entered into by the Bank and each of the donors.&#13;
5.2    As trustee, the Bank will hold in trust and administer the funds, assets and receipts that constitute the&#13;
trust fund in accordance with the terms of the administration agreements/arrangements entered into with the&#13;
donors with respect to their contributions to FIRST.&#13;
5.3    FIRST funds are received by the Bank for the Trust Fund and fifteen percent (15%) of each such&#13;
contribution is transferred to the IMF's Subaccount for FIRST contributions established by the IMF under&#13;
the Instrument for Framework Administered Account for Selected Fund Activities (SFA Framework&#13;
Instrument), in accordance with the understandings set forth in the documents agreed between the Bank and&#13;
the IMF and approved by the Donors.&#13;
5.4    Upon the transfer of funds to the IMF, the Bank has no responsibility, fiduciary or otherwise, for&#13;
the use of these funds including the implementation of projects financed by such funds.&#13;
6.     The Trust Fund&#13;
6.1    As set out in more detail in the applicable documentation, the Trust Fund finances the following:&#13;
(i)    Eligible expenditures incurred in connection with Bank-executed activities, in accordance&#13;
with Bank policies and procedures, as the same may be amended from time to time.&#13;
(ii)   Eligible expenditures incurred by the IMF  in connection with management and&#13;
implementation of IMF-executed activities, in accordance with the SFA Framework&#13;
Instrument governing the Subaccount and other relevant IMF policies and procedures, as&#13;
these may be amended from time to time.&#13;
(iii)  Bank costs associated with the management and administration of FIRST, as incurred (a)&#13;
through the Secretariat and (b) as trustee, will be submitted each year as an annual budget to&#13;
the Governing Council for approval, provided that such amounts will be adjusted as&#13;
necessary at the end of each calendar year based on actual costs incurred for activities&#13;
carried out.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-10-&#13;
(iv)  In addition, the maximum percentage of Bank staff cost to be charged to each trust fund for&#13;
the implementation of activities will be approved by the Governing Council from time to&#13;
time, in accordance with paragraph 4.1.4 (i).&#13;
7.     Miscellaneous&#13;
7.1    Nothing in this Charter shall be considered a waiver of, or impair or limit, any privileges or&#13;
immunities of the IBRD, IDA or the IMF under their respective Articles of Agreement or any applicable law,&#13;
all of which are expressly reserved.&#13;
7.2     This Charter may be adopted or amended by the Governing Council by consensus. Any&#13;
amendments to this Charter will become applicable to the administration agreements/arrangements and IMF&#13;
Subaccount as applicable as such amendments take effect through Governing Council decisions without&#13;
further need to amend the administration agreements/arrangements or IMF Subaccount documents, provided&#13;
that such amendments do not conflict with other terms of the administration agreements/arrangements or&#13;
Bank policies and procedures.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿- 11 -&#13;
ANNEX 2&#13;
Standard Provisions&#13;
This Annex shall be applicable to and form an integral part of all Administration Agreements between the&#13;
Bank and the respective Donors.&#13;
1.    Administration of the Contributions&#13;
1.1   The Bank shall be responsible only for performing those functions specifically set forth in this&#13;
Administration Agreement and shall not be subject to any other duties or responsibilities to the Donors,&#13;
including, without limitation, any duties or obligations that might otherwise apply to a fiduciary or trustee&#13;
under general principles of trust or fiduciary law. Nothing in this Administration Agreement shall be&#13;
considered a waiver of any privileges or immunities of the Bank under its Articles of Agreement or any&#13;
applicable law, all of which are expressly reserved.&#13;
1.2   Each Donor's Contribution (collectively, the "Contributions") shall be administered in accordance&#13;
with the Bank's applicable policies and procedures, as the same may be amended from time to time,&#13;
including its procurement, financial management, disbursement and safeguard policies, its framework to&#13;
prevent and combat fraud and corruption and its screening procedures to prevent the use of Bank resources to&#13;
finance terrorist activity, in line with the Bank's obligations to give effect to the relevant decisions of the&#13;
Security Council taken under Chapter VII of the of Charter of the United Nations. The Donors acknowledge&#13;
that this provision does not create any obligations of the Bank under the anti-terrorist financing and asset&#13;
control laws, regulations, rules and executive orders of an individual member country that may apply to a&#13;
Donor.&#13;
2.     Management of the Contributions&#13;
2.1    The funds deposited in the Trust Fund shall be accounted for as a single trust fund and shall be kept&#13;
separate and apart from the funds of the Bank. The funds deposited in the Trust Fund may be commingled&#13;
with other trust fund assets maintained by the Bank. The Bank, in its capacity as trustee, has legal title to the&#13;
funds deposited in the Trust Fund.&#13;
2.2    The currency in which the funds in the Trust Fund shall be held is United States Dollars (the&#13;
"Holding Currency").&#13;
2.3    Donors agree to deposit their Contributions in the Contribution Currency stated in their respective&#13;
Administration Agreements. In the case of deposits received in a Contribution Currency other than the&#13;
Holding Currency, promptly upon the receipt of such amounts and the accompanying Deposit Instructions,&#13;
the Bank shall convert such amounts into the Holding Currency at the exchange rate obtained by the Bank on&#13;
the date of the conversion. Where deposits prove to be insufficient to complete activities as a result of&#13;
exchange rate fluctuations, neither the Bank nor the Donor shall bear any responsibility for providing any&#13;
additional financing.&#13;
2.4    The funds deposited in the Trust Fund may be freely exchanged by the Bank into other currencies as&#13;
may facilitate their disbursement at the exchange rate obtained by the Bank on the date of the conversion.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿- 12 -&#13;
2.5    The Bank shall invest and reinvest the funds deposited in the Trust Fund pending their disbursement&#13;
in accordance with the Bank's applicable policies and procedures for the investment of trust funds&#13;
administered by the Bank. The Bank shall credit all income from such investment to the Trust Fund to be&#13;
used for the same purposes as the Contributions.&#13;
3.     Trust Fund Fees and Costs&#13;
3.1    The Bank shall deduct and retain for its own account, as a deduction from each Installment, an&#13;
amount equal to two percent (2 %) per Installment as an administrative fee for the Trust Fund.&#13;
3.2   In addition, costs incurred by the Bank for other expenses, such as for program management and&#13;
Trust Fund administration, that are (i) not covered by the percentage deduction specified above as an&#13;
administrative fee and (ii) not included under Annex 1 of the Administration Agreements in accordance with&#13;
the Bank's applicable policies and procedures shall be charged to the Trust Fund on an actual basis up to a&#13;
maximum of eleven point seventy six percent (11.76%) of the total Contributions under all Administration&#13;
Agreements. The Donors acknowledge and agree that such costs will be approved each year on the basis of&#13;
annual budget amounts presented to the Governing Council.&#13;
3.3    Each Donor acknowledges and agrees that the percentage deductions for fees in this Trust Fund Fees&#13;
and Costs section are estimated on the basis of anticipated Contributions. If actual Contributions&#13;
significantly differ from what was originally anticipated at the time of signature of the first Administration&#13;
Agreement, or if other circumstances affecting Trust Fund fees or costs change, the Bank reserves the right to&#13;
request a change to the terms of this Trust Fund Fees and Costs section, which would be effectuated by&#13;
amendments made to the Administration Agreements of all Donors and which would thereafter be applicable&#13;
to all new Contributions that are provided either as amendments to supplement existing Administration&#13;
Agreements or from new Donors under new Administration Agreements.&#13;
4.     Transfers to the International Monetary Fund (IMF)&#13;
4.1    The Bank shall enter into a transfer agreement (the "Transfer Agreement") with the IMF to set forth&#13;
the terms and conditions of any Trust Fund funds transferred to them. Following the transfer of funds by the&#13;
Bank from the Trust Fund to the IMF (the "Transferred Funds"), IMF shall be responsible for the use of such&#13;
funds, and the Bank shall have no further responsibility with respect of such funds.&#13;
4.2    The Donors acknowledge and agree that the Bank has no responsibility, under the Administration&#13;
Agreement or otherwise for: (i) the use of the Transferred Funds; (ii) the implementing, monitoring,&#13;
supervising, evaluating, or providing quality assurance for activities financed by the Transferred Funds; (ii)&#13;
providing Donors with financial, progress, results or impact reporting for activities financed by the&#13;
Transferred Funds; and (iii) any misuse or misprocurement with respect to the Transferred Funds; or (iv)&#13;
pursuing any Donor interests or IMF undertakings with respect to the Transferred Funds.&#13;
4.3    The Donors further acknowledge and agree that any financial reports with respect to the Trust Fund&#13;
funds transferred to the IMF and the reports with respect to the progress of the implementation of IMF&#13;
activities are the responsibility of the IMF.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿- 13 -&#13;
5.     Accounting and Financial Reporting&#13;
5.1    The Bank shall maintain separate records and ledger accounts in respect of the funds deposited in the&#13;
Trust Fund and disbursements made therefrom.&#13;
5.2    The Bank shall furnish to the Donors current financial information relating to receipts, disbursements&#13;
and fund balance in the Holding Currency with respect to the Contributions via the World Bank's Trust&#13;
Funds Donor Center secure website. Within six (6) months after all commitments and liabilities under the&#13;
Trust Fund have been satisfied and the Trust Fund has been closed, the final financial information relating to&#13;
receipts, disbursements and fund balance in the Holding Currency with respect to the Contributions shall be&#13;
made available to the Donors via the World Bank's Trust Funds Donor Center secure website.&#13;
5.3    The Bank shall provide to the Donors via the World Bank's Trust Fund Donor Center secure&#13;
website, within six (6) months following the end of each Bank fiscal year, an annual single audit report,&#13;
comprising (i) a management assertion together with an attestation from the Bank's external auditors&#13;
concerning the adequacy of internal control over cash-based financial reporting for all cash-based trust funds&#13;
as a whole; and (ii) a combined financial statement for all cash-based trust funds together with the Bank's&#13;
external auditor's opinion thereon. The cost of the single audit shall be borne by the Bank.&#13;
5.4   If a Donor wishes to request, on an exceptional basis, a financial statement audit by the Bank's&#13;
external auditors of the Trust Fund, the Donor and the Bank shall first consult as to whether such an external&#13;
audit is necessary. The Bank and the Donor shall agree on the appropriate scope and terms of reference of&#13;
such audit. Following agreement on the scope and terms of reference, the Bank shall arrange for such&#13;
external audit. The costs of any such audit, including the internal costs of the Bank with respect to such&#13;
audit, shall be borne by the requesting Donor.&#13;
6.     Progress Reporting&#13;
6.1    The Bank shall provide the Donors with annual reports on the progress of activities financed by the&#13;
Contributions. Within six (6) months of the End Disbursement Date (as defined below), the Bank shall&#13;
furnish to the Donors a final report on the activities financed by the Trust Fund.&#13;
6.2    Any Donor may review or evaluate activities financed by the Trust Fund at any time up to six (6)&#13;
months following the End Disbursement Date. The Donor and the Bank shall agree on the scope and&#13;
conduct of such review or evaluation, and the Bank shall provide all relevant information within the limits of&#13;
the Bank's applicable policies and procedures. All associated costs, including any costs incurred by the&#13;
Bank, shall be borne by the Donor. It is understood that any such review or evaluation will not constitute a&#13;
financial, compliance or other audit of the Trust Fund.&#13;
7.     Disbursement; Cancellation; Refund&#13;
7.1   It is expected that the funds deposited in the Trust Fund will be fully disbursed by the Bank by&#13;
May 31, 2018 (the "End Disbursement Date"). The Bank shall only disburse funds deposited in the Trust&#13;
Fund for the purposes of this Administration Agreement (other than returns to Donors) after such date to the&#13;
extent such date is changed in accordance with amendments made to the Administration Agreements of all&#13;
the Donors. Following the End Disbursement Date, the Bank shall return any remaining balance of the Trust&#13;
Fund to each Donor in the Holding Currency in the manner specified in its respective Administration&#13;
Agreement on a pro rata basis with regard to the total funds deposited in the Trust Fund by such Donor&#13;
relative to the total funds deposited in the Trust Fund by all Donors, all calculated as Holding Currency&#13;
amounts.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-14-&#13;
7.2    Any Donor may cancel all or part of such Donor's pro rata share, and the Bank may cancel all or any&#13;
Donors' pro rata shares, upon three (3) months' prior written notice, of any Contributions (paid and not yet&#13;
paid) that are not committed pursuant to any agreements entered into between the Bank and any consultants&#13;
and/or other third parties for the purposes of this Administration Agreement, including any Grant&#13;
Agreements, prior to the receipt of such notice. In the event of a cancellation, the Bank shall return to the&#13;
Donor its pro-rata share in the Holding Currency as specified in the Administration Agreement; unless&#13;
otherwise agreed between the Bank and the Donor.&#13;
8.     Disclosure; Dispute Resolution&#13;
8.1    The Bank shall disclose the Administration Agreements and related information on this Trust Fund&#13;
in accordance with the Bank's Policy on Access to Information. By entering into Administration&#13;
Agreements, the Donors consent to such disclosure of their respective Administration Agreements and such&#13;
related information.&#13;
8.2    The Donors and the Bank shall use their best efforts to amicably settle any dispute, controversy, or&#13;
claim arising out of or relating to the Administration Agreements.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="23066107">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2014/11/23066107/official-documents--administration-agreement-kingdom-netherlands-contribution-tf070723
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2014/11/23066107/official-documents--administration-agreement-kingdom-netherlands-contribution-tf070723</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2014/11/23066107/official-documents--administration-agreement-kingdom-netherlands-contribution-tf070723</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2014-12-22T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2014-12-22T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <docm_id>090224b082946037</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b082946037</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/FPD/2014/12/22/090224b082946037/1_0/Rendered/INDEX/Official0Docum0ibution0to0TF0707230.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/FPD/2014/12/22/090224b082946037/1_0/Rendered/PDF/Official0Docum0ibution0to0TF0707230.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2014-11-20T12:04:11Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2014-12-22T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docna>
            Official Documents- Administration Agreement
            with the Kingdom of Netherlands for Contribution to TF070723
        </docna>
        <display_title>Official Documents-
            Administration Agreement with the Kingdom of Netherlands for
            Contribution to TF070723</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/2014/11/23066107/official-documents--administration-agreement-kingdom-netherlands-contribution-tf070723</listing_relative_url>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <docty>Trust Fund Administrative Agreement</docty>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Pardo De La Pena,Maria Lourdes</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>HQBOCS</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <owner>FFSFT,Finance &amp; Markets - Sector Rfrm (GFMFS)</owner>
        <trustfund>TF070723-Multi Donor Trust Fund for
            Middle-Income Countries for the Financial Se</trustfund>
        <lang>English</lang>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT for Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies (ICT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Arts and Culture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutritional supplements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Vitamins</ml:concept><ml:concept>Organisational Structures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Organizational Assessments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Strategic Planning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>Freedom of Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>Leasing law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government Performance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Managing for Results</ml:concept><ml:concept>Outcomes Based Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Drivers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Results Based Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Remittances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Migration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enforcement of Judgements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Informal Dispute Resolution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Law and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Law and Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legal and Regulatory Framework</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Media</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supplements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance Structures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Strategic Policy Planning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Right to Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>External Audit</ml:concept><ml:concept>Leasing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Knowledge Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Movement of Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Dispute Resolution</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>