<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>﻿OFFICIAL&#13;
OCUMENTS&#13;
The World Bank                                       1818 H Street N.W       (202) 473-1000&#13;
NTERNAT:ONAL BANK FOR RECONSTRUCTION AND DEVELOPMENT  Washinon, D  433      Cable Address: INTBAFRAD&#13;
INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPMENT ASSOCIATION               O.S.A                     Cable Address: INDEVAS&#13;
December 02, 2014&#13;
Mr. Miroslav Kosek&#13;
Head of Mission&#13;
Embassy of the Czech Republic&#13;
Street n.10, House Nr.337&#13;
Wazir Akbar Khan, Kabul&#13;
Afghanistan&#13;
Trust Fund Administration Agreement between the Czech Republic acting&#13;
through Ministry of Foreign Affairs and the International Bank for&#13;
Reconstruction and Development and the International Development&#13;
Association concerning the Afghanistan Reconstruction Trust Fund (TF&#13;
No.050576)&#13;
Dear Mr. Miroslav Kosek,&#13;
With reference to your government's recent pledge, we are pleased to acknowledge, on&#13;
behalf of the International Bank for Reconstruction and Development ("IBRD") and the&#13;
International Development Association ("IDA") (collectively, the "Bank"), the intention of Czech&#13;
Republic, acting through its Ministry of Foreign Affairs (the "Donor") to make available to the&#13;
Bank the sum of twenty million Czech Koruna (CZK20,000,000) (the "Grant Funds") as a grant&#13;
for the purpose of contributing to the Afghanistan Reconstruction Trust Fund (the "Trust Fund").&#13;
The standard terms and conditions governing contributions to the Trust Fund are specified in the&#13;
Annex to this letter (hereinafter referred to as this or the "Letter Agreement") and constitutes an&#13;
integral part hereof.&#13;
Without prejudice to the provisions of paragraph 7(a) of the Annex to this Letter&#13;
Agreement, we acknowledge the Donor's expression of preference, as set out below:&#13;
Amount                Preference expressed&#13;
CZK 5,000,000         Afghanistan Skills Development Project&#13;
CZK 5,000,000         Afghanistan Agricultural Inputs Project&#13;
CZK 10,000,000        No preference expressed&#13;
The Bank will use its discretion to ensure that the Grant Funds support the preference&#13;
expressed by the Donor under the Trust Fund.&#13;
The Donor shall deposit the Grant Funds into such bank account designated by the Bank&#13;
promptly following countersignature of this Agreement by the Donor and submission of a&#13;
payment request by the Bank. When making such deposit, the Donor shall instruct its bank to&#13;
include in its payment details information (remittance advice) field of its SWIFT payment&#13;
message, information indicating: the amount paid, that the payment is made by the Donor for&#13;
TF050576 (the Afghanistan Reconstruction Trust Fund), and the date of the deposit (the "Deposit&#13;
Instruction"). In addition, the Donor shall provide a copy of the Donor's Deposit Instruction to&#13;
the Bank's Accounting Trust Funds Division by e-mail sent to tfremitadvice@worldbank.org or&#13;
by fax sent to (202) 614-1315. Upon receipt of the funds, the Bank will convert them into United&#13;
States dollars.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-2-&#13;
The offices responsible for coordination of all matters related to the implementation of&#13;
this agreement are:&#13;
For the Bank:&#13;
Afghanistan Country Management Unit&#13;
South Asia Region&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
1818 "H" Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C., 20433&#13;
Telephone:   (202) 473-3047&#13;
Fax:          (202) 522-3707&#13;
For Czech Republic:&#13;
Embassy of the Czech Republic&#13;
Street No.10, House No.337&#13;
Wazir Akbar Khan, Kabul&#13;
Afghanistan&#13;
Telephone:   (+93) 793 420 137&#13;
All annexes hereto constitute an integral part of this Agreement. This Agreement may be&#13;
amended only in writing between the Bank and the Donor; provided, however, that such annexes&#13;
may be amended only with the agreement of all donors contributing to the Trust Fund.&#13;
All references made in the Annex to "shall" will have the same meaning as the term&#13;
"will" herein.&#13;
Please confirm your agreement with the foregoing, on behalf of the Donor, by signing,&#13;
dating, and returning to us the enclosed copy of this Agreement. Upon receipt by the Bank of the&#13;
copy of this Agreement countersigned by you, this Agreement will become effective as of the&#13;
date of the countersignature.&#13;
Sincerely,&#13;
INTERNATIONAL BANK FOR RECONSTRUCTION AND DEVELOPMENT&#13;
INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPMENT ASSOCIATION&#13;
Stephen N. Ndegwa&#13;
Act   Cuntry Director for Afghanistan&#13;
/1 oSouth Asia Region&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-3-&#13;
AGREED:&#13;
CZECH REPUBLIC&#13;
acting through its Ministry of Foreign Affairs&#13;
By: 0ue--co          or-'              6.e,cC&#13;
Name: ti "  -?, v   Ce&#13;
Title: 4ecxS o_   __&#13;
Date:            1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-4-&#13;
ANNEX&#13;
Amended and Restated&#13;
Standard Terms and Conditions Governing Contributions to the&#13;
Afghanistan Reconstruction Trust Fund&#13;
1.     General&#13;
The following terms and conditions will govern all agreements entered into between the&#13;
Bank and donor countries or agencies (individually referred to herein as the "Donors"; each a&#13;
"Donor") that provide grants to the Bank as contributions to the Trust Fund (the "Grant Funds").&#13;
2.     Objective of the Trust Fund&#13;
The objective of the Trust Fund is to provide a vehicle for Donors to pool resources and&#13;
coordinate their support to the programme of the Government of the Islamic Republic of&#13;
Afghanistan for the reconstruction of Afghanistan.&#13;
3.     Definitions&#13;
Unless the context otherwise requires, the several terms defined in the Letter Agreement&#13;
and in paragraph I above have the respective meanings therein set forth, and the following&#13;
additional terms have the following meanings:&#13;
(a)    "Administration" means the Administration of the Islamic Republic of&#13;
Afghanistan or any successor thereto;&#13;
(b)     "Category" means any of the categories of expenditures set forth in the table in&#13;
paragraph 4 of this Annex.&#13;
(c)     "Capital Expenditures" means expenditures on account of goods, including,&#13;
without limitation, office furniture and equipment, as set forth in the&#13;
Administration's budget, the eligibility for financing of which will have been&#13;
approved by the Management Committee;&#13;
(d)     "Financing Strategy" means a three year rolling framework for planning the use&#13;
of Grant Funds, agreed annually by the Steering Committee on the basis of a&#13;
recommendation from the Strategy Working Group;&#13;
(e)     "Incentive Program" means a performance based program that allocates a&#13;
certain portion of recurrent cost financing based on the Administration's&#13;
meeting of reform benchmarks, set and reviewed by the Incentive Program&#13;
Working Group;&#13;
(f)     "Incentive Program Working Group" means the technical advisory body whose&#13;
responsibilities are described in paragraph 5(b)(ii) of this Annex, and whose&#13;
membership consists of representatives of (i) the Bank; (ii) the Ministry of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-5-&#13;
Finance, and (iii) representatives of no more than six Donors to be reviewed on&#13;
an annual basis by the Steering Committee;&#13;
(g)     "Investment and Program Activity" means activities, the purpose of which will&#13;
be to meet a recognized development objective and which is part of an&#13;
investment or sector program of the Administration that will have been&#13;
approved by the Management Committee. Such activities will include, without&#13;
limitation, activities in agriculture, infrastructure, micro-finance and the social&#13;
sectors, as well as reintegration of combatants into society and programs to&#13;
facilitate the return of private business to Afghanistan, together with pre-&#13;
feasibility and other studies related thereto. The expression "Investment and&#13;
Program Activity" includes a Law and Order Project (as this expression is&#13;
hereinafter defined);&#13;
(h)    "Law and Order Project" means an Investment Project, the purpose of which, in&#13;
whole or in part, will be the carrying out, in connection with the civil branch of&#13;
the police force of the Government of the Islamic Republic of Afghanistan, of&#13;
one or more of the following activities: (i) payment of salaries and benefits; (ii)&#13;
provision of uniforms; (iii) provision of non-military or non-paramilitary&#13;
vehicles; (iv) provision of computer and two way communications equipment;&#13;
(v) provision of fuel; and (vi) payment of operating and maintenance costs&#13;
associated with said vehicles and computer and communications equipment;&#13;
(i)    "Management Committee" means the committee whose responsibilities are&#13;
described in paragraph 5(a)(ii) of this Annex, and whose membership will consist&#13;
of representatives of the Asian Development Bank, the Islamic Development&#13;
Bank, the Ministry of Finance, the United Nations Development Programme and&#13;
the Bank;&#13;
(j)    "Ministry of Finance" means the Administration's Ministry of Finance or any&#13;
successor thereto;&#13;
(k)    "Monitoring Agent" means an independent firm to be engaged by the Bank in&#13;
accordance with the provisions of paragraph 6 (a) of this Annex.&#13;
(1)    "Recurrent Expenditures" means those recurrent expenditures set forth in the&#13;
Administration's budget, whose eligibility for financing hereunder will have&#13;
been determined by the Management Committee, relating to wages, benefits and&#13;
other payments for civil servants, pension payments, debt service obligations,&#13;
including the payment of interest, fees and other charges, and operation and&#13;
maintenance costs, but excluding military and paramilitary expenditures and&#13;
police-related expenditures, other than the activities contemplated under&#13;
paragraph 3 (h);&#13;
(m)    "Steering Committee" means the committee whose responsibilities are described&#13;
in paragraph 5 (a) (iii) of this Annex, and whose membership (to be reviewed on&#13;
an annual basis) consists of representatives of: (i) the Bank; (ii) each Donor; (iii)&#13;
the Ministry of Finance; and which may be attended by the other members of the&#13;
Management Committee as observers;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-6-&#13;
(n)    "Strategy Working Group" means the technical advisory body whose&#13;
responsibilities are described in paragraph 5 (b) (i) of this Annex, and whose&#13;
membership (to be reviewed on an annual basis) consists of representatives of: (i)&#13;
the Bank; (ii) the Ministry of Finance; (iii) Donors whose contribution to the&#13;
Trust Fund equals or exceeds ten million United States dollars (US$10,000,000)&#13;
per annum and that have adequate technical expertise at the local level; and (iv)&#13;
any such sector Ministries of the Administration as the Strategy Working Group&#13;
may decide to invite to its meetings on an ad hoc basis;&#13;
(o)    "Sub-grant" means a grant made or proposed to be made by the Bank using&#13;
Trust Funds allocated to Category (3), herewith to any public or private entity to&#13;
carry out an Investment and Program Activity;&#13;
(p)    "Sub-grant Recipient" means a public or private entity to which the Bank&#13;
proposes to make, or has made, a Sub-grant; and&#13;
(q)    "Sub-grant Agreement" means an agreement entered into, or proposed to be&#13;
entered into, between the Bank and a Sub-grant Recipient.&#13;
4.     Categories of Expenditure&#13;
The categories of expenditure that are eligible for financing from the Trust Fund,&#13;
together with the percentages of expenditures to be financed, are as follows:&#13;
Percentage of&#13;
Expenditures&#13;
Category                                       to be Financed&#13;
(1)    Recurrent and                                  100%&#13;
Capital Expenditures&#13;
(2)    Expert services and training                   100%&#13;
(3)    Sub-grants for Investment Projects             100%&#13;
5.     Governance Structure of the Trust Fund&#13;
(a)       The Trust Fund will have the following three-tier governance structure:&#13;
(i)    The Bank will be the administrator of the Trust Fund. In this capacity, the Bank&#13;
will establish and maintain appropriate records and accounts to identify the contributions to the&#13;
Trust Fund, the commitments to be financed out of the Grant Funds and the receipt and&#13;
disbursement of the Grant Funds. The Bank will also be responsible to supervise the performance&#13;
of the Monitoring Agent(s) subject to the proviso set forth at the end of paragraph 8 (a) of this&#13;
Annex.&#13;
(ii)   The Management Committee will be responsible, inter alia, for resource&#13;
allocation decisions with respect to the Trust Fund. In allocating Grant Funds, the Management&#13;
Committee will be guided by the Financing Strategy. The Management Committee will be&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-7-&#13;
chaired by the Bank as administrator and, on a monthly basis, meet in Kabul, Afghanistan, or in&#13;
such other location as the Management Committee may decide from time to time, or by&#13;
teleconference and, will following such meeting, report in writing to each Donor on operations&#13;
and activities financed by disbursements made by the Trust Fund and decisions taken by the&#13;
Management Committee. The Management Committee will, on a quarterly basis, prepare and&#13;
submit to the Steering Committee a report which will describe in detail the operations of the Trust&#13;
Fund, including the receipt and use of donor contributions to the Trust Fund and the activities&#13;
financed therefrom, together with minutes of the monthly meetings of the Management&#13;
Committee. The Management Committee will act collectively and, to the extent practicable,&#13;
make decisions by consensus.&#13;
(iii)  The Steering Committee will be responsible for overseeing and supervising the&#13;
performance of the Management Committee. The Steering Committee will, on a quarterly basis,&#13;
meet in Kabul, Afghanistan, or in such place as the Committee may decide to review progress in&#13;
the implementation of activities financed under the Trust Fund, and approve the Financing&#13;
Strategy to provide guidance to the Management Committee on Grant Fund allocation. At the&#13;
start of each solar year and on the basis of a proposal from the Strategy Working Group, the&#13;
Steering Committee will (A) review and assess how well funding decisions on individual&#13;
projects, recurrent cost support and the Incentive program met the existing Financing Strategy,&#13;
and (B) revise the Financing Strategy as needed to guide Grant Fund allocations for the upcoming&#13;
annual period.&#13;
(b)    The following technical advisory bodies will report to the Steering Committee:&#13;
(i)    The Strategy Working Group, which will meet from time to time in Kabul,&#13;
Afghanistan, under the chairmanship of the Bank, to: (A) make recommendations to the Steering&#13;
Committee on the Financing Strategy at the start of each solar year; (B) inform the annual review&#13;
(by the Steering Committee) of the implementation of the Financing Strategy, and highlight&#13;
issues that arose in the course of implementation; (C) hold ad-hoc review meetings as needed to&#13;
discuss particular issues or bottlenecks; (D) ensure that the Financing Strategy is coordinated with&#13;
the Ministry of Finance Fiscal Policy unit (and therefore the Medium Term Fiscal Framework) as&#13;
well as with the Ministry of Finance Budget Department; and (E) support the development of a&#13;
results matrix for the Financing Strategy, and&#13;
(ii)   The Incentive Program Working Group, which will meet from time to time in&#13;
Kabul, Afghanistan, under the chairmanship of the Bank, to discuss policy benchmarks with the&#13;
Administration and report thereon to the Steering Committee as part of the Incentive Program&#13;
Framework.&#13;
6.    Implementation of Activities under the Trust Fund&#13;
(a)    The Administration will be responsible for implementing the activities to be&#13;
financed under Categories (1) and (2). Implementation of the activities to be financed under&#13;
Category (3) is governed by the provisions of paragraph 9 of this Annex. The Bank will engage&#13;
one or more Monitoring Agents to monitor expenditures related to the activities financed under&#13;
Categories (1), (2) and (3). Each Monitoring Agent will be selected and retained by the Bank on&#13;
the basis of terms of reference/scope of work agreed by the Management Committee and the&#13;
Bank. The responsibilities of each Monitoring Agent will include monitoring the procurement of&#13;
goods, services and other items, screening and recommending withdrawal applications for the&#13;
Bank's approval and payment, monitoring all expenditures financed by the Grant Funds and pre-&#13;
screening the financial management capacity of potential Sub-grant Recipients so as to ensure&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-8-&#13;
that Grant Funds are disbursed only for the purposes specified in paragraph 4 of this Annex and&#13;
according to applicable Bank procedures.&#13;
(b)    Monitoring Agents will report to the Bank. Subject to the approval of the&#13;
Management Committee, the Bank will have the authority to change the terms of reference/scope&#13;
of work of each Monitoring Agent and, where justified, to replace each Monitoring Agent with&#13;
another firm or agency. The Bank will give advance notice to the Administration, the&#13;
Management Committee and the Donors of changes to the terms of reference/scope of work of&#13;
each Monitoring Agent. The Bank will perform ex-post evaluations of the activities undertaken&#13;
by the Monitoring Agents, and will, upon completion of the activities financed under the Trust&#13;
Fund, arrange for an independent review of the performance of the Monitoring Agents and report&#13;
its findings to the Donors.&#13;
(c)    The Grant Funds may be used by the Bank to: (i) pay the reasonable fees, travel&#13;
and other reimbursable costs of Monitoring Agents; and (ii) pay the cost of goods, services and&#13;
other items of expenditure in furtherance of the Trust Fund activities, all in accordance with the&#13;
provisions of the Grant, including this Annex.&#13;
(d)    The selection and recruitment of Monitoring Agents by the Bank, and the&#13;
procurement and financing of expenditures for goods and services to be carried out by the&#13;
Administration, in connection with goods and services financed under Categories (1) and (2), and&#13;
by each Monitoring Agent, will take place on an untied basis, in accordance with the Bank's&#13;
"Guidelines for Procurement under IBRD Loans and IDA Credits" and the "Guidelines for the&#13;
Use of Consultants by World Bank Borrowers and by the World Bank as Executing Agency".&#13;
7.     The Bank's Use of Grant Funds and Administrative Cost Recovery&#13;
(a)    The Grant Funds will be accounted for as part of a single Trust Fund which will&#13;
be kept separate and apart from other funds of the Bank. Donor contributions to the Trust Fund&#13;
may not be earmarked for one or more specific Categories and will instead be allocated among all&#13;
Categories in accordance with the decisions of the Management Committee. A Donor may state a&#13;
preference that its contribution be used to finance one or more Categories, or certain activities in&#13;
a given sector, with the understanding that neither the Management Committee nor the Bank will&#13;
be in a position to guarantee that total spending with respect to any given Category or sector will&#13;
match or exceed the level of the contribution in connection with which a preference will have&#13;
been stated. Undesignated contributions will be allocated among Categories in accordance with&#13;
the decisions of the Management Committee. No contribution to the Trust Fund will be accepted&#13;
unless it equals or exceeds two hundred thousand United States dollars (US$200,000).&#13;
(b)    The Bank may invest the Grant Funds pending disbursement in any instrument in&#13;
which the Bank is authorized to invest its own funds. The investment income earned on the Grant&#13;
Funds pending disbursement will be added to the account to be used for purposes of the Trust&#13;
Fund.&#13;
(c)    In order to assist in the defrayment of its administrative costs, the Bank may, as&#13;
of February 18, 2011 following deposit of the Grant Funds, deduct from the T-Account and&#13;
transfer to itself an amount equivalent to two percent (2.0%) of the amount of the Grant Funds.&#13;
The Bank may also deduct from the T-Account and transfer to itself the actual costs of the Bank's&#13;
contract with the Monitoring Agent(s), as well as the cost of the independent review of the&#13;
Monitoring Agent(s)'s performance referred to under paragraph 6(b) of this Annex.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-9-&#13;
8.     Fiduciary Responsibilities of the Bank&#13;
(a)    The Bank will be responsible only for performing those functions specifically set&#13;
forth in this Letter Agreement, including this Annex, and will not be subject to any other duties or&#13;
responsibilities to Donors, including, without limitation, any duties or obligations that might&#13;
otherwise apply to a fiduciary or trustee under general principles of trust or fiduciary law.&#13;
Nothing in this Letter Agreement will be considered a waiver of any privileges or immunities of&#13;
the Bank under its Articles of Agreement or any applicable law, all of which are expressly&#13;
reserved. The Bank will have no responsibility to Donors with respect to the performance of the&#13;
Monitoring Agent(s) and will have no obligation to reimburse the Trust Fund or provide any&#13;
compensation to any Donor if the Grant Funds are not disbursed for the purposes specified in this&#13;
Annex as a result of actions of the Monitoring Agent(s).&#13;
(b)    Unless otherwise provided in this Letter Agreement, the Bank will apply its&#13;
normal financial management procedures to the Trust Fund. Such procedures applicable to the&#13;
operation of the Trust Fund will be communicated to the Donors without delay.&#13;
(c)    Unless otherwise provided in this Letter Agreement, the Bank will apply to the&#13;
Trust Fund its framework to prevent and combat fraud and corruption and its screening&#13;
procedures to prevent the use of bank resources to finance terrorist activity, in line with the&#13;
Bank's obligations to give effect to the relevant decisions of the Security Council, taken under&#13;
Chapter VII of the Charter of the United Nations. The Donor acknowledges that this provision&#13;
does not create any obligations of the Bank under the anti-terrorist financing and asset control&#13;
laws, regulations, rules and executive orders of an individual member country that may apply to&#13;
the Donor, nor will it be deemed a waiver, express or implied, of any of the privileges and&#13;
immunities of the Bank.&#13;
9.     Terms and Conditions Governing Sub-Grants under Category (3)&#13;
In the event that the Bank deems it necessary execute a sub-grant to carry out an&#13;
Investment and Program Activity eligible for financing under Category (3), the following&#13;
provisions will apply:&#13;
(a)    The Bank will conclude a Sub-grant Agreement with each "Sub-grant Recipient".&#13;
(b)    Except as provided in paragraph (c) below, responsibility for the accounting and&#13;
administration of Grant Funds made available by the Bank to Sub-grant Recipients will be&#13;
decided upon on a case-by-case basis by the Management Committee, considering, inter alia, the&#13;
recommendations made by the Monitoring Agent(s). Accordingly, the Management Committee&#13;
will review proposals to carry out activities eligible for financing under Category (3) and award&#13;
Sub-grants in connection with proposals deemed by the Management Committee to be suitable&#13;
for financing and consistent with the Financing Strategy. Proposals for financing under Category&#13;
(3) will be submitted for approval to the Administration which, when approved, will forward&#13;
them to the Management Committee for consideration.  Only proposals vetted by the&#13;
Administration in the manner described in this sub-paragraph will be considered by the&#13;
Management Committee. A proposal submitted to the Management Committee, through the&#13;
Administration, will include an appraisal of the Investment and Program Activity sought to be&#13;
financed. For those proposals that do not include an appraisal of the Investment Project sought to&#13;
be financed, the Bank will carry out the appraisal of the Investment Project. The representative of&#13;
a member organization of the Management Committee will recuse him or herself from&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿-10-&#13;
deliberations over the suitability of proposal(s) submitted or co-financed by the organization that&#13;
he or she represents.&#13;
(c)    Notwithstanding the provisions of sub-paragraph (b) of this paragraph 9,&#13;
proposals to carry out a Law and Order Project may only be made and carried out by the United&#13;
Nations Development Programme. The latter will be the sole organization authorized to carry out&#13;
Law and Order Projects financed hereunder. Sub-grants to finance Law and Order Projects will&#13;
be made in accordance with terms and conditions acceptable to the Bank including, without&#13;
limitation, those set forth in sub-paragraphs (a), (d), (e), (f) and (g) of this paragraph 9 whose&#13;
provisions shall apply, mutatis mutandis, to any Sub-grant made or to be made by the Bank to the&#13;
United Nations Development Programme for purposes of carrying out a Law and Order Project.&#13;
UNDP, the Bank and the Management Committee will agree on detailed procedures including&#13;
procurement, disbursements and audits for processing Law and Order Projects.&#13;
(d)    Sub-grants will be used to finance expenditures for goods, works and services, as&#13;
the case may be, in accordance with the Bank's "Guidelines for Procurement under IBRD Loans&#13;
and IDA Credits" and the "Guidelines for the Use of Consultants by World Bank Borrowers and&#13;
by the World Bank as Executing Agency", as in effect at the date of the relevant Sub-grant&#13;
agreement (hereinafter collectively referred to as the "Bank's Guidelines"). Any departure from&#13;
the Bank's Guidelines will have to be pre-approved by the Bank.&#13;
(e)    The fiduciary arrangements for an Investment and Program Activity to be&#13;
financed under Category (3) will be carried out in accordance with the guidelines and procedures&#13;
specified in paragraph 8 (b) including but not limited to an environmental and social screening&#13;
and assessment framework approved by the Bank. Any departure from the guidelines contained&#13;
in said framework will have to be pre-approved by the Bank.&#13;
(f)    As required under regular Bank lending operations, a Sub-grant Agreement will&#13;
obligate a Sub-grant Recipient, among other things, to maintain an appropriate and adequate&#13;
financial management system, including records and accounts, and prepare financial statements&#13;
adequate to separately reflect the operations, resources and expenditures related to the Investment&#13;
and Program Activity financed under the Sub-grant. Within ninety (90) days of each June 30 and&#13;
December 31, the Sub-grant Recipient will prepare unaudited financial statements with respect to&#13;
such Sub-grant and forward a copy to the Bank. All financial statements appropriate to the size&#13;
and purpose of the Sub-grant, as indicated in the Sub-grant agreement will be expressed in the&#13;
currency in which the Sub-grant is made, as indicated in the Sub-grant Agreement, and will show&#13;
the allocation of such funds among the activities financed by the Sub-grant. In addition, the Sub-&#13;
grant Recipient will: (i) have the above-mentioned records, accounts and financial statements&#13;
audited, in accordance with auditing standards acceptable to the Bank, by independent auditors&#13;
acceptable to the Bank; (ii) furnish to the Bank, as soon as available, but in any case not later than&#13;
six (6) months after the end of each calendar year: (a) certified copies of the financial statements&#13;
referred to above for such year as so audited, and (b) an opinion on such statements, records and&#13;
accounts and report of such audit, by said auditors, of such scope and in such detail as the Bank&#13;
will have reasonably requested; and (iii) furnish to the Bank such other information concerning&#13;
said records and accounts, and the audit thereof, as the Bank will from time to time reasonably&#13;
request. In such cases where the Sub-grant is &lt; US$100,000 the Bank has the discretion to&#13;
specify in the Sub-grant agreement that attestation from the Monitoring Agent will be sufficient&#13;
to comply with the audit procedures above.&#13;
(g)    The Bank will report quarterly to the Donors on the status of Trust Funds made&#13;
available to a Sub-grant Recipient under a Sub-grant Agreement. In addition, at a Donor's&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿- 11 -&#13;
request, the Bank will also make available, in accordance with its Policy on Access to&#13;
Information, audited and unaudited financial statements of Sub-grant Recipients furnished under&#13;
paragraph (f), above.&#13;
10.    Accountin2 and Financial Reporting Responsibilities of the Bank&#13;
(a)    The Bank will maintain separate records and ledger accounts in respect of the&#13;
aggregate Grant Funds for the agreed activities and disbursements made therefrom to the&#13;
Monitoring Agent(s). Within one hundred eighty (180) days of the completion of the activities&#13;
financed by the Grant Funds, the Bank will prepare unaudited financial statements in United&#13;
States dollars with respect to the Grant Funds and forward a copy to each Donor. The Bank will&#13;
provide the Donors annually with a management assertion together with an attestation from the&#13;
Bank's external auditors on the satisfactory performance of the procedures and controls used by&#13;
the Bank in administering the Grant Funds.&#13;
(b)    If a Donor wishes to request, on an exceptional basis, a financial statement audit&#13;
by the Bank's external auditors of the Trust Fund, the Donor and the Bank shall first consult as to&#13;
whether such an external audit is necessary. The Bank and the Donor shall agree on the&#13;
appropriate scope and terms of reference of such audit. Following agreement on the scope and&#13;
terms of reference, the Bank shall arrange for such external audit. The costs of any such audit,&#13;
including the internal costs of the Bank with respect to such audit, shall be paid by the requesting&#13;
Donor.&#13;
11.    Progress Reporting Responsibilities of the Bank&#13;
(a)    The Bank will maintain close consultation and coordination with the Donors.&#13;
The Bank will provide each Donor with quarterly reports on its quarterly ex-post evaluation of&#13;
the activities undertaken by the Monitoring Agent(s) including disbursements made out of the&#13;
Grant Funds. Within (6) six months of the completion of the activities, or of full disbursement of&#13;
the Grant Funds, whichever comes later, the Bank will provide a final progress report to each&#13;
Donor, together with a copy of the independent review of the performance of the Monitoring&#13;
Agent(s). Upon request by any Donor, the Bank will send to such Donor the draft and final&#13;
reports received by the Bank from each Monitoring Agent on the activities financed by the Grant&#13;
Funds.&#13;
(b)    Any Donor may review or evaluate activities financed by the Trust Fund. The&#13;
Donor and the Bank shall agree on the scope and conduct of such review or evaluation and the&#13;
Bank shall provide all relevant information within the limits of its policies and procedures. All&#13;
associated costs shall be borne by the Donor. It is understood that any such review or evaluation&#13;
will not constitute a financial, compliance or other audit of the Trust Fund and will be separate&#13;
from any independent evaluation of the Trust Fund to be arranged by the Bank.&#13;
12.    Termination&#13;
Unless otherwise agreed by the Donors and the Bank, the Trust Fund arrangement provided for&#13;
under the Letter Agreement and this Annex will expire on June 30, 2020. If at any time, either&#13;
party determines that the purposes of the Letter Agreement and this Annex can no longer be&#13;
effectively or appropriately carried out, this Letter Agreement may be terminated at the initiative&#13;
of either party by giving the other party thirty (30) days prior notice to this affect. Upon&#13;
termination, unless otherwise agreed by the Donors and the Bank: (i) any agreement entered into&#13;
among the Bank, the Monitoring Agent(s), and/or other third parties will not be affected by the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿- 12-&#13;
termination, and the Bank will be entitled to continue permitting withdrawals of Grant Funds in&#13;
respect of such agreements as if this arrangement had not been so terminated; and (ii) any&#13;
remaining Grant Funds will be returned to the Donors on a pro-rata basis, and the Bank's&#13;
functions pursuant hereto will be considered terminated. Within six (6) months following such&#13;
termination, the Bank will furnish to the Donors an unaudited financial statement with respect to&#13;
the aggregate amount contributed by all Donors.&#13;
13.    Legal Documentation&#13;
For purposes of channeling Grant Funds to their intended beneficiaries in accordance the terms&#13;
and conditions of the Letter Agreement and this Annex, the Bank will enter into a grant&#13;
agreement with the Administration concerning Trust Funds allocated to Categories (1) and (2).&#13;
Grant Funds allocated to Category (3) will be governed by separate sub-grant agreements to be&#13;
entered into between the Bank, on the one part, and sub-grant Recipients, on the other part, with&#13;
each such agreement relating to one or more Investment and Program Activity. Without&#13;
prejudice to the foregoing, Grant Funds allocated to Category (3) for the specific purpose of&#13;
financing Law and Order Projects will be governed by one or more grant agreements, as the case&#13;
may be, to be entered into between the Bank, on the one part, and the United Nations&#13;
Development Programme, on the other part.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="23072505">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2014/12/23072505/official-documents--administration-agreement-czech-republic-contribution-tf050576
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2014/12/23072505/official-documents--administration-agreement-czech-republic-contribution-tf050576</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2014/12/23072505/official-documents--administration-agreement-czech-republic-contribution-tf050576</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2014-12-23T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2014-12-23T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <docm_id>090224b08294bfdf</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b08294bfdf</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/SAR/2014/12/23/090224b08294bfdf/1_0/Rendered/INDEX/Official0Docum0ribution0to0TF050576.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/SAR/2014/12/23/090224b08294bfdf/1_0/Rendered/PDF/Official0Docum0ribution0to0TF050576.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2014-12-23T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2014-12-02T13:23:18Z</docdt>
        <docna>
            Official Documents- Administration Agreement
            with the Czech Republic for Contribution to TF050576
        </docna>
        <display_title>Official Documents-
            Administration Agreement with the Czech Republic for
            Contribution to TF050576</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/2014/12/23072505/official-documents--administration-agreement-czech-republic-contribution-tf050576</listing_relative_url>
        <projn>AF-Afghanistan Reconstruction Trust Fund -- P078069</projn>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <docty>Trust Fund Administrative Agreement</docty>
        <count>Afghanistan</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Bo,Giovanni</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>HQBOCS</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <owner>Afghanistan Anchor Unit (SACAA)</owner>
        <trustfund>TF050576-Afghanistan Reconstruction
            Trust Fund</trustfund>
        <lang>English</lang>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fragility, Conflict and Violence</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Organisational Structures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Organizational Assessments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal &amp; Monetary Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Consolidation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Governance and Structural Fiscal Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Rules</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Sustainability</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macro-Fiscal Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pensions &amp; Retirement Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Expenditures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Investment Plan</ml:concept><ml:concept>Remittances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Migration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking and Finance Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wage Setting</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages, Compensation and Benefits</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fuels</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance Structures</ml:concept><ml:concept>External Audit</ml:concept><ml:concept>Paramilitaries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pensions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Investment Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Movement of Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Laws and Regulations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Afghanistan</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>