<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>ï»¿OFFC~L    /~o72/7/&#13;
111IMENW,&#13;
Administration Arrangement betw een the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland,&#13;
represented by the Department for International Development (DFID)and the International Bank for&#13;
Reconstruction and Developm nt and the International Development Association concerning&#13;
the South Asia Food and Nutrition S,'ecurity Initiative, Phase H (SA FANSIII) Multi-Donor Trust Fund&#13;
(No. 072171)&#13;
(Donor Reference No. 201093)&#13;
1.    The International Bank for Leconstruction and Development and the International Development&#13;
Association (collectively, the "Bank") acknowledge that the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern&#13;
Ireland, represented by the Departme it for International Development (DFID) (the "Donor", and together&#13;
with the Bank, the "Parties" and ea h a "Party") has decided to provide the sum of twelve million six&#13;
hundred thousand Pounds Sterling (GBP 12,600,000) (the "Contribution") for the South Asia Food and&#13;
Nutrition Security Initiative, Phase II (SAFANSI II) Multi-Donor Trust Fund, No. 072171 (the "Trust Fund")&#13;
in accordance with the terms of this A Iministration Agreement. Other donors are also expected to contribute&#13;
to the Trust Fund on the terms and cor ditions specified in the Annexes to this Administration Agreement.&#13;
2.     The Contribution will be use I to finance the activities set forth in the "SAFANSI II Trust Fund&#13;
Description" attached hereto as Anne &lt; 1, and will be administered by the Bank on behalf of the Donor in&#13;
accordance with the terms of this Adn inistration Arrangement, including the "Standard Provisiens" attached&#13;
hereto as Annex 2.&#13;
3.     The Donor will deposit the Zontribution in accordance with the following schedule and in the&#13;
currency specified in Section 1 above ("Contribution Currency") into such bank account designated by the&#13;
Bank (each amount deposited herein Lfter referred to as an "Installment") upon submission of a payment&#13;
request by the Bank:&#13;
(A)    By 30 November 2014 - GBP 1,400,000&#13;
(B)    By 20 June 2015-GBP 875,0C&#13;
(C)    By 15 December 2015 - GBP 875,000&#13;
(D)    By 15 June 2016 - GBP 1,575,000&#13;
(E)    By 15 Dec 2016 - GBP 1,575,)00&#13;
(F)    By 15 June 2017 - GBP 1,575 000&#13;
(G)    By 15 Dec 2017 - GBP 1,575.000&#13;
(H)    By 15 Jun 2018 - GBP 1,575,(00&#13;
(I)    By 15 Dec 2018 - GBP 1,575,)00&#13;
4.     When making any deposit, the Donor will instruct its bank to include in its deposit details&#13;
information (remittance advice) field of its SWIFT deposit message, information indicating: the amount&#13;
deposited, that the deposit is made by the Donor for TF No. 072171 (the SAFANSI II Trust Fund), and the&#13;
date of the deposit (the "Deposit Instiuctions"). In addition, the Donor will provide a copy of the Deposit&#13;
Instructions to the Bank's Accounting Trust Funds Division by e-mail sent to tfremitadvice@worldbank.org&#13;
or by fax sent to +1 (202) 614-1315.&#13;
5.     Except with respect to the D .posit Instructions, any notice, request or other communication to be&#13;
given or made under this Administrati n Arrangement will be in writing and delivered by mail, fax or e-mail&#13;
to the respective Party's address specified below or at such other address as such Party notifies in writing to&#13;
the other Party from time to time:&#13;
For the Bank (the "Bank Cont ict"):&#13;
1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Simeon Ehui&#13;
Sector Manager, Agriculture&#13;
South Asia Sustainable Development Department&#13;
H STREET 1818&#13;
Zip code 20433 WASHINGTON DC&#13;
US - United States&#13;
sehui@worldbank.org&#13;
For the Donor (the "Donor Contact"):&#13;
Saul Walker&#13;
Senior Regional Health Advisor&#13;
Asia Regional Team&#13;
Department for International Development&#13;
22 Whitehall&#13;
London&#13;
SWIA 2EG&#13;
Tel: +44 20 7023 0239&#13;
Fax: +44 20 7023 0012&#13;
E-mail: s-walker@dfid.gov.uk&#13;
6.    In the event any amounts are to be returned to the Donor under this Administration Arrangement, the&#13;
Bank will transfer such amounts to the Donor, unless the Donor and the Bank decide otherwise.&#13;
7.    In providing funds under this Administration Arrangement, the Donor does not intend to accept any&#13;
responsibility or liability towards any third parties for any claims, debts, demands, damage or loss as a result&#13;
of the implementation of the activities under the Trust Fund.&#13;
8.     All annexes hereto constitute an integral part of this Administration Arrangement, whose terms taken&#13;
together will constitute the entire arrangement and understanding between the Donor and the Bank. Unless&#13;
otherwise specified in an annex hereto, this Administration Arrangement may be amended only by written&#13;
amendment between the Bank and the Donor ; provided, however, that any annexes to this Administration&#13;
Arrangement may be amended only by written amendment of all donors contributing to the Trust Fund.&#13;
9.    It is understood that this Administration Arrangement, including any annexes, is not an international&#13;
treaty. It is an administrative arrangement between the Trustee and the Donor.&#13;
10.    All references made in the Annexes to "shall", "Administration Agreement", and "Project"/&#13;
"MDTF" will have, respectively, the same meaning as the term "will", "Administration Arrangement", and&#13;
"Trust Fund" herein.&#13;
11.    Each of the undersigned represents, by confirming its acceptance below, that it is authorized to enter&#13;
into this Administration Arrangement and act in accordance with its provisions. The Bank and the Donor are&#13;
each requested to sign and date this Administration Arrangement, and upon possession by the Bank of this&#13;
fully signed Administration Arrangement, this Administration Arrangement will become carried out as of the&#13;
date of the last signature.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿INTERNATIONAL BANK FOR RICONSTRUCTION AND DEVELOPMENT&#13;
INTERNATIONAL EVELOPMENT ASSOCIATION&#13;
By:&#13;
Name         A/1&#13;
Date: P.-ev   2014&#13;
UNITED KINGDOM OF GREAT BRITAIN AND NORTHERN IRELAND, REPRESENTED BY&#13;
THE DEPARTMENT FOR INTER]4ATIONAL DEVELOPMENT&#13;
By:&#13;
Name: Jenny Yates&#13;
Title: Team Leader, Asia Regional Te im&#13;
Date:       (  (&#13;
3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿ANNEX 1&#13;
SAFANSI II Trust Fund Description&#13;
This Annex shall be applicable to and form an integral part of all administration agreements for the Trust&#13;
Fund (collectively, the "Administration Agreements" and each an "Administration Agreement") between the&#13;
Bank and any entities that provide any funds to the Trust Fund (collectively, the "Donors").&#13;
Introduction and Context&#13;
1. The South Asia region has both the highest prevalence of malnutrition and the largest numbers of&#13;
undernourished children in the world. Malnutrition slows economic growth and perpetuates poverty.&#13;
The combined effect of malnutrition on cognitive development (hence school performance), health status&#13;
and cost to the health system, and productivity leads to a significant loss in GDP. Under-nutrition has&#13;
been attributed to between 30 and 45 under-five mortality2,3&#13;
2. In addition, the region has the largest number of people (over 295 million) who are routinely&#13;
hungry; that is, they do not have daily access to adequate calories (FAO 2009)4. India, for example,&#13;
ranks 66 (out of 88) on the Global Hunger Index. The region has succeeded in increasing aggregate food&#13;
production. However despite this achievement the poor and marginalized groups in the SAR countries&#13;
face severe constraints to regular access and availability of food. Adding further pressures to this&#13;
constrained food availability is the region-wide slowing agricultural growth, inefficient markets and&#13;
restrictive trade practices.&#13;
3. Progress in improving nutrition has been unacceptably slow (given positive economic trajectories).&#13;
Given the current high levels and slow progress in the reduction of malnutrition during the past decade,&#13;
most South Asian countries are unlikely to achieve the Millenium Development Goal (MDG) for&#13;
nutrition (target Ic of MDG 1) of halving, between 1990 and 2015, the proportion of people who suffer&#13;
from hunger. Although there are declining trends in malnutrition compared to the rates 5 years ago,&#13;
these rates are still alarmingly high. India, Bangladesh, Pakistan, Afghanistan, and Nepal are among the&#13;
36 countries in the world which account for 90% of the global malnutrition burden.5 The World Health&#13;
Organization's global database on Body Mass Indices estimates that over a third of adult women in&#13;
Bangladesh, India and Pakistan are underweight, and the prevalence of iron deficiency anemia ranges&#13;
between 55% and 81% across the region.&#13;
4. Improving the food and nutrition security (FNS) status of both children and adults is a key human&#13;
development challenge for the South Asia Region. The lack of food and nutrition security - the&#13;
foundation for human development - increases susceptibility to infections, increases related morbidity,&#13;
disability and mortality burden (SAR also has a high burden of non-communicable diseases and the&#13;
rising problem of obesity), and lowers lifelong learning capacities and adult productivity. Within this, a&#13;
specific area of concern is inadequate nutrition for mothers and infants, especially in the "one thousand&#13;
day" window - roughly the 1000 days from the first day of pregnancy through the first two years of life -&#13;
since it imposes extensive, and largely irreversible, costs in terms of damage to physical growth, brain&#13;
development, and consequent cognitive capacities and life-time human capital formation. This core focus&#13;
on improving the nutritional status of infants (by directly targeting children in the vulnerable age group,&#13;
'The Section 'Introduction and Context' is included for information purposes only to reflect the main considerations taken into account by the Parties&#13;
in agreeing to support the Project.&#13;
2 UNICEF 2013:Improving Child Nutrition, The achievable imperative for global progress&#13;
'Black et al, Lancet 2013; 382: 427-51&#13;
FAO 2009: The State of Food Insecurity in the World 2009&#13;
s China, Thailand and Brazil have taken bold actions to successfully accelerate reductions in under-nutrition, and are on track to reach the first&#13;
Millennium Development Goal on target, by 2015. India is expected to do so only in 2043 at the present pace of actions.&#13;
4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿their mothers as well as pregnan women) is absolutely essential to accelerate the reduction of child&#13;
malnutrition, and decrease the ove -all burden of malnutrition over time.&#13;
5. The challenge of hunger and malnutrition in South Asia is multi-faceted, and requires a multi-&#13;
pronged approach, including inlrventions that: (i) expand availability, accessibility and diversity of&#13;
food through improved agricultur, d production; (ii) enhance livelihoods; (iii) increase access to quality&#13;
education; (iv) expand access to :lean water and sanitation; (v) empower women; (vi) improve social&#13;
protection; and (vii) focus on infai t and child care, amongst other relevant areas. The region's economic&#13;
growth has only had marginal p )sitive correlation with improved nutritional status as evident from&#13;
several country examples.&#13;
Objective of the Project&#13;
6. The objective of the Project is to i riprove FNS for individuals and communities in South-Asia through a&#13;
strengthened commitment and increased capacity for more effective and integrated FNS actions across&#13;
South Asia.&#13;
Description of the Project Activities&#13;
7. The Project will fund activities that are demand-driven, focus on priority countries (as determined from&#13;
time to time by the Donors Comm ttee referred to in para. 21 below) and contribute to one or more of the&#13;
following pillars:&#13;
Pillar 1: Improved Evidence and Ana,ysis&#13;
8. This pillar is concerned with stre igthening the substantive (evidential) and analytical basis for greater&#13;
and more effective investments to improve FNS, including supporting thematic groups for better&#13;
exchange of data and knowledge, re-orienting existing programs and innovating with cross-cutting,&#13;
multi-sectoral approaches. Activiti 2s will be financed within this pillar under the following clusters:&#13;
*   Credible evidence base genercted on specific FNS issues. Activities under this cluster may include,&#13;
inter alia: identification of te precise channels through which undernutrition occurs in different&#13;
contexts (shocks and vulnerability; Low Birth Weight pathways; early feeding and care practices;&#13;
micro-nutrient deprivation; co itinuous re-infection due to poor sanitation and water, food pathogens,&#13;
access to primary health care etc.) as well as its impact on welfare, both inter and intra-&#13;
generationally; analysis of ir novative approaches that link safety net programs with nutritional&#13;
security - such as the early chi d development programs - will also be considered;&#13;
*  Improved data collection, ana 'sis and management on key FNS issues. Activities under this cluster&#13;
may include, inter alia: support for making data on nutrition more frequent, more accessible, and&#13;
producing data of higher quali y for larger areas.&#13;
*   Improved testing! impact assi ssment of FNS programs. Activities under this cluster may include,&#13;
inten alia: activities resulting i i better understanding of relative causal significance of various factors&#13;
affecting undernutrition, or o  policy trade-offs that obtain; investing in systematic evaluations of&#13;
existing FNS-related program: to ensure timely learning to assess efficacy to help identify elements&#13;
of feasible reform and to allow policy makers to consolidate of support for these programs.&#13;
* Improved analytics on specif c FNS issues. Activities under this cluster may include, inter alia:&#13;
Programming guidance (on va -ious aspects of program formulation, implementation and monitoring)&#13;
for country level partners, and other toolkits that tan support government operations (e.g., supporting&#13;
the updating of Food Composition Systems, which provide information on nutritive value of foods,&#13;
and the basis for planning a sa isfactory diet).&#13;
5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Pillar 2: Enhanced Awareness and Commitment&#13;
9. This pillar relates to building regional and country-level commitment to invest further in programs&#13;
delivering FNS outcomes by increasing emphasis on it in various policies, development strategies and&#13;
action plans. In particular, country policy makers and development partners have highlighted the need to&#13;
understand and address the incentives for uptake and implementation of evidence based and integrated&#13;
policy and programs to improve FNS. Activities will be financed within this pillar under the following&#13;
clusters:&#13;
0 Improved Political Economy Analysis to inform strategies and action plans for promoting change.&#13;
Activities under this cluster may include, inter alia: political economy analysis to understand the&#13;
incentives and barriers for policy reform in FNS-related programs; analysis in each of the SAFANSI&#13;
countries with the aim of identifying the underlying political economy dynamics and incentives&#13;
structures that restrain or support effective multisectoral FNS action.&#13;
*  Networks established to build policy support and momentum for FNS actions. Activities under this&#13;
cluster may include, inter alia:: creation of networks at the local, national and regional levels to&#13;
function as "brokers" of credible research, analysis and information; selectively supporting high&#13;
profile and high level events helps bring prominence and sustainability to such networks.&#13;
*  Strategic Communication and Outreach including through high profile events. Activities under this&#13;
cluster may include, inter alia: a comprehensive Strategic Communications strategy to sensitize&#13;
stakeholders to the need for action and mobilize public interest in the issue and create a public&#13;
accountability mechanism.for service delivery; a range of activities intended to identify, engage and&#13;
reach key audiences; developing a regional network of 'Ambassadors for Change' - influential&#13;
policy makers or thought leaders committed to FNS - and equipping them with the means to&#13;
influence others through statements in public fora and in the media; web-enabled dissemination of&#13;
evidence and analysis.&#13;
Reports! Assessments of FNS status and actions at various level. Activities under this cluster may&#13;
include, inter alia: analysis of the 'State of Food and Nutrition' in SAFANSI countries to be used as&#13;
a baseline assessment for the Project and as an in-house strategy document that guides a developing&#13;
work program at the country level.&#13;
Pillar 3: Building Systems and Capacity&#13;
10. This pillar relates to strengthening institutional capacities at regional, national and local community&#13;
levels to help, on the demand side, by organizing and articulating community demands and, on the&#13;
supply side, improving the quality and effectiveness of public programs. Furthermore, this component is&#13;
expected to fill gaps such as: capacity to plan programs at scale (using evidence), capacity to implement&#13;
programs at scale, capacity to manage in an evidence-based manner (generating and using data), capacity&#13;
to advocate using evidence and political intuition. Activities will be financed within this pillar under the&#13;
following clusters:&#13;
*  Improved monitoring and evaluation and learning (MEL) sy4tems operational. Activities under this&#13;
cluster may include, inter alia: the establishment of "Social Observatories " in a range of livelihoods&#13;
programs to provide real time monitoring systems to substantially improve the practice and&#13;
implementation of FNS-related interventions for community-based livelihoods programs.&#13;
Networks of development partners established/ strengthened! trained! operational. Activities under&#13;
this cluster may include, inter alia: establishment of a technical network of development partners -&#13;
comprising entities in the UN system, Multilateral Development Banks, Bilateral Agencies,&#13;
Government, civil society and philanthropic organisations where appropriate - will be built to&#13;
contribute to the human resource needs of the system.&#13;
Improvement in (existing) systems / capacities for technical stewardship program development!&#13;
management and implementation. Activities under this cluster may include, inter alia: development&#13;
6&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿and strengthening of systems for tracking comparative data across the region, such as gender and&#13;
nutrition sensitive statistics 1or agriculture development and Codex Alimentarius data for food&#13;
products in the region; prov sion of capacity support for the client countries through providing&#13;
quality, experienced, technical personnel to work within government ministries.&#13;
Pillar 4: Fostering Innovations&#13;
11. Fostering innovations on the grou ad. The Project will seek to support three kinds of activities aimed at&#13;
increasing innovations on the groi nd: (i) introduction or increased emphasis on FNS in existing project&#13;
designs / operations; (ii) analy ical and feasibility studies to support design of promising new&#13;
interventions; and (iii) analysis, e:.perience sharing, learning, program customization / contextualization&#13;
etc. design to improve implement, tion approaches. Activities will be financed within this pillar under the&#13;
following cluster:&#13;
*  Innovations in FNS-related projects and programs supported. Activities under this cluster may&#13;
include, inter alia: facilitation of changes in the design of existing FNS programs or programs which&#13;
want to add FNS interventions in their scope; financial support to pilot FNS programs.&#13;
* Design of new FNS intervent ons supported. Activities under this cluster may include, inter alia:&#13;
combating micro-nutrient defi.iencies through food based approaches, bio-security risk management&#13;
and food safety through the fo d chain, introducing different animal and fish protein sources in diets.&#13;
* Development of new implen entation approaches supported. Activities under this cluster may&#13;
include, inter alia: effectivei ess studies to test the impact of existing interventions, under normal&#13;
operating conditions, includii ig in challenging geographical environments and varied social and&#13;
cultural environments, such as studies on interventions to address low birth weight&#13;
12. The Project strategy will add value to on-going efforts by exploiting gaps or overlooked opportunities for&#13;
strengthening the FNS agenda anc its operationalization. As such a necessary element of the Project will&#13;
be exploitation of opportunities a, they present themselves (rather than following through a rigid, time-&#13;
bound plan which is characteristic of most projects). Effort will be made, therefore, to structure and&#13;
resource the evaluation of the Project activities accordingly, i.e., to focus on the impact and value-for-&#13;
money aspect of the activity rather than consistency with strictly pre-specified target values.&#13;
Implementation Arrangements&#13;
Multi-Country and Multi-3ector Approach&#13;
13. The Project will promote an integrated and cross-sectoral approach to cover the critical issues involved&#13;
in ensuring improved FNS. In th. context of the rqgional level, a food and nutrition matrix with key&#13;
indicators to monitor over a longcr-term time horizon (10 to 15 years) will provide means for tracking&#13;
the regional outcomes on achievin nutritional improvements for populations of interest. At country level&#13;
'State of FNS' baseline studies aid their conclusions on entry points and opportunities, will inform a&#13;
series of tasks each of which will demonstrably coqtribute to one or more of the four pillars described&#13;
above. These tasks will either be Recipient Executed grants or Bank Executed tasks made in response to&#13;
specific needs.&#13;
Links and synergies with other initiatives&#13;
14. The Project will complement and supplement other initiatives in the region. In particular the Project will&#13;
(i) be cognisant of the FNS statt s in each of the countries of operation and at the regional level (ii)&#13;
7&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿explicitly work with existing networks of development partners and especially civil society networks and&#13;
develop new networks where needed.&#13;
Role of the various actors and stakeholders&#13;
15. ReLional bodies represent important partners in developing FNS policies, setting norms and standards&#13;
regionally and making the countries adopt consistent approaches to FNS issues.&#13;
16. Development Partners. Partners actively contributing to implementation of and investments in a multi-&#13;
sectoral approach to under-nutrition. These may include bi-lateral and multi-lateral donors and other&#13;
international organizations.&#13;
17. Governments. At central level, the partner governments from South Asian countries (Afghanistan,&#13;
Bangladesh, Bhutan, India, Maldives, Nepal, Pakistan, Sri Lanka) mainly through their sectoral&#13;
Ministries and in particular the Ministries of Health and Social Welfare will be key partners for more&#13;
effective and integrated food and nutritional security-related policies and investments.&#13;
18. Civil Society. The civil society is required as redoubtable partner to active support to raise their&#13;
awareness and capacities to participate in public food and nutritional security-related programs.&#13;
19. Universities and Policy Institutes. Universities and institutes can provide significant resources to&#13;
addressing the capacity gaps of the current system.&#13;
20. Private Sector. Finally, the private sector is also a critical stakeholder involved in agricultural inputs, and&#13;
the storage, transportation, processing and marketing of food. The private sector is the source of income&#13;
for many individuals, an important requirement for food security, and their policies and supply chains&#13;
can have a substantial effect on availability, quality and price of food.&#13;
NMTF Governance Structure&#13;
21. The governance structure for the MDTF will comprise a Donor Committee, the Secretariat and country&#13;
focal points.&#13;
22. The Donor Committee will include each donor contributing to the MDTF and the Bank. The Donor&#13;
Committee will provide strategic guidance and will review the annual work-plan and the overall progress&#13;
and implementation of the Project. The Donor Committee will meet annually in person or virtually.&#13;
Other stakeholders may be invited to participate in the donor committee meetings as needed.&#13;
23. The Secretariat will comprise the program manager supported by a small team of Bank staff. The&#13;
Secretariat will be responsible for the day-to-day management and administration of the MDTF. In&#13;
addition, the Secretariat will organize Donor Committee meetings, coordinate the allocation of funds and&#13;
prepare annual reports.&#13;
24. A country focal point will be selected for each country in the South Asia region. The country focal point&#13;
will be responsible for in-country coordination of FNS activities and partnership development.&#13;
25. In addition, the structure will also include designated Country Focal Points as "knowledgy brokers" - one&#13;
in each country - who will be responsible for portfolio management, coordination, and partnership&#13;
development. Similarly, the FNS Spokespersons / Champions would be identified in each of the&#13;
countries as senior opinion leaders with convening power to influence policy making and set the&#13;
direction for highlighting FNS issues in each country.&#13;
Preliminary Risk analysis and mitigation plan&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿26. The preliminary anticipated risks and the mitigation plan for the Project, which may be reviewed and&#13;
updated from time to time by thc Donor Committee and do not create any right or obligation on the&#13;
Parties, can be categorized as folk ws:&#13;
*   Regional Level: (i) propensit, to act nationally; (ii) lack of sufficient regional platforms/ "space" to&#13;
plan and coordinate regional actions; (iii) lack of established mechanisms for follow-through on&#13;
regional agreements reached; (iv) logistical barriers in implementation coordination across national&#13;
boundaries6. However, favorir g the Project is the fact that even at the regional level (e.g. SAARC) it&#13;
is widely appreciated that foo I and nutrition security offers one of the best prospects for closer and&#13;
more integrative regional worn.&#13;
*   National/ Subnational Level lack of adequate response by governments due to political economy&#13;
factors such as; (i) other spe iding priorities and short-term goals; (ii) systemic inertia preferring&#13;
existing arrangements; (iii) i. sufficient learning from\traction of Project messages; or (iii) deep&#13;
institutional barriers to effec ive multi-sectoral work on FNS. Mitigation measures include: (a)&#13;
actionable political economy Lnalysis (PEA), focused at understanding and navigating around these&#13;
constraints; (b) a PEA-inforr ied outreach/communications strategy to empower a broad front of&#13;
stakeholders and "champion s" for change, at all levels; (c) enhanced learning from other&#13;
countries'(cross-cutting) expe -iences to enlarge the (perceived) zone of feasible actions (notably&#13;
from South-South exchanges).&#13;
*   Local Level: lack of adopt on due to weaknesses in understanding Project messages and/or&#13;
weaknesses in program desi gn and implemqntation capacity. As such, Project design includes&#13;
mitigation measures against t iese factors, including better learning and more accessible messages,&#13;
and attention to design and im ,lementation issues.&#13;
Strategic Communications and I tKnowledge Management&#13;
27. The Project will have a multi-pror ged communications strategy. The strategy would focus on promoting&#13;
cross-sectoral learning, generatin), awareness amongst various stakeholders at country and regional&#13;
levels, maintaining visibility amo igst key stakeholders, and focus on communication and outreach of&#13;
key messages through periodic kntwledge products and events.&#13;
Monitoring&#13;
28. The World Bank, as the administn .tor of the MDTF, will have responsibilities for monitoring the Project,&#13;
in accordance with the provisions )f this Administration Arrangement.&#13;
29. The Project will support activities at regional, national and community/household levels with indicative&#13;
results, as follows:&#13;
(a) At the regional level it is expected that (i) an emerging set of standards (e.g. Food and Nutrition&#13;
Matrix of Key Indicators. Food Safety guidelines) will provide regional public goods; and (ii) a&#13;
network for cross-countr) learning can facilitate change at the national level.&#13;
(b) At the national and sub-national level, the Project will focus on development policies and plans&#13;
that can; (i) expand the s.ale/scope and effectiveness of food nutrition safety (FNS) operations,&#13;
or (ii) facilitate improven ents in the design of delivery mechanisms.&#13;
(c) At the community level, the Project results will relate to; (i) 'best practice' learning through&#13;
community projects, (ii) mproved demand-side accountability for FNS-related public services,&#13;
6 These risks are to be regarded as "given conditions', since any mitigation measure will be beyond the reach any such program.&#13;
9&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿(iii) support implementation of local service providers that improve their systems and capacities,&#13;
and (iv) foster innovations in FNS program and service to better address community and&#13;
culture-specific needs. The cross-cutting foundation of this approach will be to create a&#13;
conducive environment that allows a range of partners to increase the scale, scope and&#13;
effectiveness of the FNS programs.&#13;
30. The Donor and the Bank agree that the above mentioned indicative results (as such may be reviewed,&#13;
refined and updated from time to time) will be utilized by the Bank to assess the progress achieved by&#13;
the Project and will be referred to in the reports prepared by the Bank pursuant to paragraph 5 of Annex&#13;
2 (Standard Provisions) to this Administration Arrangement.&#13;
31. Furthermore, the Project is intended to finance a program of activities, of which some will be executed&#13;
by the Bank and others by third party recipients, including Bank's member countries, public/private&#13;
sector entities and non-governmental organizations. The Donor and the World Bank accept that: (i) any&#13;
indicators and results developed for the Project shall be indicative only in nature and subject to change&#13;
for reasons beyond the World Bank's control and responsibility such as, but not limited to, policy or&#13;
managerial actions or decisions of third party recipients of financing under this Project; (ii) such&#13;
indicative indicators and results are to be used exclusively for monitoring purposes; and (iii) progress&#13;
against such indicative indicators or results does not constitute a ground for the Donor to: withhold any&#13;
amount of its contribution; withhold any payment under the schedule set out in paragraph 3 of this&#13;
Administration Arrangement; or request a refund of any amount of its contribution already disbursed to&#13;
the World Bank.&#13;
Operations Manual&#13;
32. The Project is going to be implemented, in accordance with an operations manual to be adopted by the&#13;
Donor Committee, which will set out, inter alia: (i) detailed management and governance structures and&#13;
arrangements; (ii) eligibility criteria/eligible sectors or themes, etc. along with details on the procedures&#13;
for accessing funding; (iii) a logical framework matrix including baseline data and indicators and a&#13;
methodology for monitoring progress under the Project and expected results; and (iv) multiannual&#13;
indicative work-plan; (v) a strategy for communication and visibility.&#13;
Eligible Expenditures&#13;
33. For Bank-executed activities, the Trust Fund funds may be used to finance:(i) Associated overheads; (ii)&#13;
Consultants fees individuals and firms; (iii) Contractual services; (iv) Extended term consultants (no&#13;
indirect); (v) Extended term consultants (vi) Media, workshop, conference and meeting costs; (vii) Staff&#13;
Costs (with indirect costs); (viii) Staff costs (no indirect costs); (ix) Temporary staff costs (no indirect);&#13;
(x) Temporary staff costs; and (xi) Travel expenses related to the Project, incurred by regular Bank staff&#13;
and consultants.&#13;
34. For Recipient-executed activities, the Trust Fund funds may be used to finance: (i) Works; (ii) Goods;&#13;
(iii) Consultant Services; (iv) Training and Workshops; (v) Sub-grants; and (vi) Operating Costs.&#13;
Taxes&#13;
35. The foregoing activities and categories of expenditures may include the financing of taxes in accordance&#13;
with the Bank's applicable policies and procedures.&#13;
10&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿ANNEX 2&#13;
Standard Provisions&#13;
This Annex shall be applicable to an( form an integral part of all Administration Agreements between the&#13;
Bank and the respective Donors.&#13;
1.     Administration of the Contr butions&#13;
1.1    The Bank shall be responsib e only for performing those functions specifically set forth in this&#13;
Administration Agreement and shall not be subject to any other duties or responsibilities to the Donors,&#13;
including, without limitation, any dut es or obligations that might otherwise apply to a fiduciary or trustee&#13;
under general principles of trust or fiduciary law. Nothing in this Administration Agreement shall be&#13;
considered a waiver of any privilege:, or immunities of the Bank under its Articles of Agreement or any&#13;
applicable law, all of which are expres ;ly reserved.&#13;
1.2    Each Donor's Contribution (collectively, the "Contributions") shall be administered in accordance&#13;
with the Bank's applicable policies and procedures, as the same may be amended from time to time,&#13;
including its procurement, financial nanagement, disbursement and safeguard policies, its framework to&#13;
prevent and combat fraud and corrupti n and its screening procedures to prevent the use of Bank resources to&#13;
finance terrorist activity, in line with the Bank's obligations to give effect to the relevant decisions of the&#13;
Security Council taken under Chapter VII of the of Charter of the United Nations. The Donors acknowledge&#13;
that this provision does not create an / obligations of the Bank under the anti-terrorist financing and asset&#13;
control laws, regulations, rules and e, ecutive orders of an individual member country that may apply to a&#13;
Donor.&#13;
2.     Management of the Contributions&#13;
2.1    The funds deposited in the Tr st Fund shall be accounted for as a single trust fund and shall be kept&#13;
separate and apart from the funds of t e Bank. The funds deposited in the Trust Fund may be commingled&#13;
with other trust fund assets maintained by the Bank. The Bank, in its capacity as trustee, has legal title to the&#13;
funds deposited in the Trust Fund.&#13;
2.2    The currency in which the f .nds in the Trust Fund shall be held is United States Dollars (the&#13;
"Holding Currency").&#13;
2.3    Donors agree to deposit their Contributions in the Contribution Currency stated in their respective&#13;
Administration Agreements. In the :ase of deposits received in a Contribution Currency other than the&#13;
Holding Currency, promptly upon the receipt of such amounts and the accompanying Deposit Instructions,&#13;
the Bank shall convert such amounts ii ito the Holding Currency at the exchange rate obtained by the Bank on&#13;
the date of the conversion. Where c eposits prove to be insufficient to complete activities as a result of&#13;
exchange rate fluctuations, neither the Bank nor the Donor shall bear any responsibility for providing any&#13;
additional financing.&#13;
2.4    The funds deposited in the Tn st Fund may be freely exchanged by the Bank into other currencies as&#13;
may facilitate their disbursement at the exchange rate obtained by the Bank on the date of the conversion.&#13;
2.5    The Bank shall invest and reir vest the funds deposited in the Trust Fund pending their disbursement&#13;
in accordance with the Bank's applicable policies and procedures for the investment of trust funds&#13;
11&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿administered by the Bank. The Bank shall credit all income from such investment to the Trust Fund to be&#13;
used for the same purposes as the Contributions.&#13;
3.     Trust Fund Fees and Costs&#13;
3.1    The Bank shall deduct and retain for its own account, as a deduction from each Installment, an&#13;
amount equal to two percent (2%) per Installment as an administrative fee for the Trust Fund.&#13;
3.2   In addition, costs incurred by the Bank for other expenses, such as for program management and&#13;
Trust Fund administration, that are (i) not covered by the percentage deduction specified above as an&#13;
administrative fee and (ii) not included under Annex 1 of the Administration Agreements in accordance with&#13;
the Bank's applicable policies and procedures shall be charged to the Trust Fund on an actual basis up to a&#13;
maximum of five percent (5%) of the total Contributions under all Administration Agreements.&#13;
3.3    Each Donor acknowledges and agrees that the percentage deductions for fees in this Trust Fund Fees&#13;
and Costs section are estimated on the basis of anticipated Contributions.  If actual Contributions&#13;
significantly differ from what was originally anticipated at the time of signature of the first Administration&#13;
Agreement, or if other circumstances affecting Trust Fund fees or costs change, the Bank reserves the right to&#13;
request a change to the terms of this Trust Fund Fees and Costs section, which would be effectuated by&#13;
amendments made to the Administration Agreements of all Donors and which would thereafter be applicable&#13;
to all new Contributions that are provided either as amendments to supplement existing Administration&#13;
Agreements or from new Donors under new Administration Agreements.&#13;
4.     Accounting and Financial Reporting&#13;
4.1    The Bank shall maintain separate records and ledger accounts in respect of the funds deposited in the&#13;
Trust Fund and disbursements made therefrom.&#13;
4.2    The Bank shall furnish to the Donors current financial information relating to receipts, disbursements&#13;
and fund balance in the Holding Currency with respect to the Contributions via the World Bank's Trust&#13;
Funds Donor Center secure website. Within six (6) months after all commitments and liabilities under the&#13;
Trust Fund have been satisfied and the Trust Fund has been closed, the final financial information relating to&#13;
receipts, disbursements and fund balance in the Holding Currency with respect to the Contributions shall be&#13;
made available to the Donors via the World Bank's Trust Funds Donor Center secure website.&#13;
4.3    The Bank shall provide to the Donors via the World Bank's Trust Fund Donor Center secure&#13;
website, within six (6) months following the end of each Bank fiscal year, an annual single audit report,&#13;
comprising (i) a management assertion together with an attestation from the Bank's external auditors&#13;
concerning the adequacy of internal control over cash-based financial reporting for all cash-based trust funds&#13;
as a whole; and (ii) a combined financial statement for all cash-based trust funds together with the Bank's&#13;
external auditor's opinion thereon. The cost of the single audit shall be borne by the Bank.&#13;
4.4   If a Donor wishes to request, on an exceptional basis, a financial statement audit by the Bank's&#13;
external auditors of the Trust Fund, the Donor and the Bank shall first consult as to whether such an external&#13;
audit is necessary. The Bank and the Donor shall agree on the appropriate scope and terms of reference of&#13;
such audit. Following agreement on the scope and terms of reference, the Bank shall arrange for such&#13;
external audit. The costs of any such audit, including the internal costs of the Bank with respect to such&#13;
audit, shall be borne by the requesting Donor.&#13;
12&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿4.5    The Bank shall make availabl to the Donors copies of all financial statements and auditors' reports&#13;
received by the Bank from Recipients pursuant to any Grant Agreements (as defined below) in accordance&#13;
with the Bank's Access to Information Policy.&#13;
5.     Progress Renorting&#13;
5.1    The Bank shall provide the D mors with annual reports on the progress of activities financed by the&#13;
Contributions. Within six (6) month ; of the End Disbursement Date (as defined below), the Bank shall&#13;
furnish to the Donors a final report on :he activities financed by the Trust Fund.&#13;
5.2    Any Donor may review or evaluate activities financed by the Trust Fund at any time up to six (6)&#13;
months following the End Disbursen ent Date. The Donor and the Bank shall agree on the scope and&#13;
conduct of such review or evaluation, mrd the Bank shall provide all relevant information within the limits of&#13;
the Bank's applicable policies and pi ocedures. All associated costs, including any costs incurred by the&#13;
Bank, shall be borne by the Donor. It is understood that any such review or evaluation will not constitute a&#13;
financial, compliance or other audit of the Trust Fund.&#13;
6.     Disbursement; Cancellation; Refund&#13;
6.1   It is expected that the funds deposited in, the Trust Fund will be fully disbursed by the Bank by&#13;
September 30, 2019 (the "End Disbui sement Date"). The Bank shall only disburse funds deposited in the&#13;
Trust Fund for the purposes of this Ac ministration Agreement (other than returns to Donors) after such date&#13;
to the extent such date is changed in .ccordance with amendments made to the Administration Agreements&#13;
of all the Donors. Following the End Disbursement Date, the Bank shall return any remaining balance of the&#13;
Trust Fund to each Donor in the Holeing Currency in the manner specified in its respective Administration&#13;
Agreement on a pro rata basis with iegard to the total funds deposited in the Trust Fund by such Donor&#13;
relative to the total funds deposited in the Trust Fund by all Donors, all calculated as Holding Currency&#13;
amounts.&#13;
6.2    Any Donor may cancel all or part of such Donor's pro rata share, and the Bank may cancel all or any&#13;
Donors' pro rata shares, upon three (^) months' prior written notice, of any Contributions (paid and not yet&#13;
paid) that are not committed pursuant to any agreements entered into between the Bank and any consultants&#13;
and/or other third parties for the )urposes of this Administration Agreement, including any Grant&#13;
Agreements, prior to the receipt of su -h notice. In the event of a cancellation, the Bank shall return to the&#13;
Donor its pro-rata share in the Holcing Currency as specified in the Administration Agreement; unless&#13;
otherwise agreed between the Bank an I the Donor.&#13;
7.     Disclosure; Dispute Resoluti n&#13;
7,1    The Bank shall disclose the A dministration Agreements and related information on this Trust Fund&#13;
in accordance with the Bank's Policy on Access to Information. By entering into Administration&#13;
Agreements, the Donors consent to st. ch disclosure of their respective Administration Agreements and such&#13;
related information.&#13;
7.2    The Donors and the Bank shall use their best efforts to amicably settle any dispute, controversy, or&#13;
claim arising out of or relating to the Administration Agreements.&#13;
8.     Grants to Recipients&#13;
13&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿8.1    The Bank shall, as administrator of the Trust Fund on behalf of the Donors, enter into one or more&#13;
grant agreements (the "Grant Agreements") with recipients (the "Recipients") consistent with the purposes of&#13;
this Administration Agreement and on the terms and conditions set forth in the Grant Agreements. Grant&#13;
Agreements may be entered into up to the maximum amount of the Contributions that all Donors have agreed&#13;
to make available under the Administration Agreements between the Bank and the Donors.&#13;
8.2    The Bank shall be responsible for the supervision of the activities financed under any Grant&#13;
Agreements. Subject to the consent of any relevant Recipients, representatives of the Donors may be invited&#13;
by the Bank to participate in Bank supervision missions related to the Trust Fund.&#13;
8.3    The Bank shall promptly inform the Donors of any significant modification to the terms of any Grant&#13;
Agreements and of any contractual remedies that are exercised by the Bank under any Grant Agreements.&#13;
To the extent practicable, the Bank shall afford the Donors the opportunity to exchange views before&#13;
effecting any such modification or exercising any such remedy.&#13;
14&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="23812942">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2014/12/23812942/official-documents--administration-arrangement-dfid-grant-tf072171
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2014/12/23812942/official-documents--administration-arrangement-dfid-grant-tf072171</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2014/12/23812942/official-documents--administration-arrangement-dfid-grant-tf072171</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2015-01-16T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2015-01-16T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <docm_id>090224b0829c2f53</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b0829c2f53</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/SAR/2015/01/16/090224b0829c2f53/1_0/Rendered/INDEX/Official0Docum0DFID00Grant0TF072171.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/SAR/2015/01/16/090224b0829c2f53/1_0/Rendered/PDF/Official0Docum0DFID00Grant0TF072171.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2015-01-16T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2014-12-04T12:27:51Z</docdt>
        <docna>
            Official Documents- Administration
            Arrangement for DFID, Grant TF072171
        </docna>
        <display_title>Official Documents-
            Administration Arrangement for DFID, Grant TF072171</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/2014/12/23812942/official-documents--administration-arrangement-dfid-grant-tf072171</listing_relative_url>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <docty>Trust Fund Administrative Agreement</docty>
        <count>South Asia</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Roosa,Danielle Malek</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>HQBOCS</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <trustfund>TF072171-South Asia Food and Nutrition
            Security Initiative Phase II (SAFANSI-II)</trustfund>
        <lang>English</lang>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Gender</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shocks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Organisational Structures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Organizational Assessments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Basic Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>On-site Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Marketing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Continuous Vocational Training (CVT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Lifelong Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Strengthening Technical Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Strengthening Vocational Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Technical Vocational Education and Training Policies and Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Technical and Vocational Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Vocational Education and Training</ml:concept><ml:concept>Vocational Training</ml:concept><ml:concept>Adult Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Adult Education, Literacy, and Lifelong Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Continuing Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition – Community Based Interventions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition – Raising Awareness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition – Training</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civil Service Employment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civil Service Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Capital</ml:concept><ml:concept>Managing People</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Employment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Remittances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Migration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Political Economy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Political Economy Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Safety Nets and Transfers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civil Society</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Treaties</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shocks and Vulnerability</ml:concept><ml:concept>Obesity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance Structures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resources Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Movement of Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Political Economy of Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Safety Nets</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Southern Asia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>