<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>                     43738 V2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
RESHAPING&#13;
ECONOMIC&#13;
GEOGRAPHY&#13;
OVERVIEW&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
E   THE WORLD BANK&#13;
&amp;#12;?&#13;
J&#13;
&amp;#12;world development repo2,QQ9&#13;
&#13;
Reshaping Economic&#13;
Geography&#13;
&#13;
Overoiew&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
THE WORLD BANK&#13;
Washington, DC&#13;
&amp;#12;Â© 2008 The International Bank for Reconstruction and Development I The World Bank&#13;
1818 H Street NW&#13;
Washington DC 20433&#13;
Telephone: 202-473-1000&#13;
Internet: www.worldbank.org&#13;
E-mail: feedback@worldbank .org&#13;
&#13;
Al l rights reserved&#13;
&#13;
2 3 4 5 11 10 09&#13;
&#13;
This document summarizes the World Development Report 2009. It is a product of the&#13;
staff of the International Bank for Reconstruction and Development I The World Bank.&#13;
The findings, interpretations, and conclusions expressed in this volume do not necessarily&#13;
reflect the views of the Executive Directors of The World Bank or the governments they&#13;
represent.&#13;
   The World Bank does not guarantee the accuracy of the data included in this work. The&#13;
boundaries, colors, denominations, and other information shown on any map in this work&#13;
do not imply any judgement on the part of The World Bank concerning the legal status of&#13;
any territory or the endorsement or acceptance of such boundaries.&#13;
&#13;
Rights and Permissions&#13;
T he material in this publication is copyrighted. Copying and/or transmitting portions or&#13;
all of this work without permission may be a violation of applicable law. The International&#13;
Bank for Reconstruction and Development I The World Bank encourages dissem ination of&#13;
its work and will normally grant permission to reproduce portions of the work promptly.&#13;
For permission to photocopy or reprint any part of this work, please send a request with&#13;
complete information to the Copyright Clearance Center Inc., 222 Rosewood Drive, Dan-&#13;
vers, MA 01923, USA; telephone: 978-750-8400; fax: 978-750-4470; Internet: www.copy-&#13;
right.com.&#13;
    All other queries on rights and licenses, including subsidiary rights, should be addressed&#13;
to the Office of the Publisher, The World Bank, 1818 H Street, NW, Washington , DC 20433,&#13;
USA; fax: 202-522-2422; e-mail: pubrights@worldbank.org.&#13;
&#13;
Cover design and interior navigational graphics by Zefyr Design, info@zefyr.co.uk.&#13;
&#13;
Typesetting and page layout by Precision Graphics.&#13;
&amp;#12;Contents of the&#13;
World Development Report 2009&#13;
&#13;
    Geography in motion: The Report at a Glance-Density, Distance,&#13;
    and Division&#13;
&#13;
Overview&#13;
&#13;
Navigating This Report&#13;
    Geography in motion: Overcoming Distance in North America&#13;
&#13;
     Part One      Seeing Development in 3-D&#13;
&#13;
1 Density&#13;
&#13;
2 Distance&#13;
&#13;
3 Division&#13;
    Geography in motion: Overcoming Division in Western Europe&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Part Two      Shaping Economic Geography&#13;
&#13;
4   Scale Economies and Agglomeration&#13;
&#13;
5 Factor Mobility and Migration&#13;
&#13;
6 Transport Costs and Specialization&#13;
    Geography in motion: Distance and Division in East Asia&#13;
&#13;
     Part Three      Reframing the Policy Debates&#13;
&#13;
7 Concentration without Congestion:&#13;
  Policies for an inclusive urbanization&#13;
                                                                     iii&#13;
&amp;#12;iv   CONTENTS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     8   Unity, Not Uniformity:&#13;
         Effective approaches to territorial development&#13;
&#13;
     9 Winners without Borders:&#13;
       Integrating poor countries with world markets&#13;
         Geography in motion: Density, Distance, and Division&#13;
         in Sub-Saharan Africa&#13;
&#13;
     Bibliographical Note&#13;
&#13;
     Endnotes&#13;
&#13;
     References&#13;
&#13;
     Selected Indicators&#13;
&#13;
     Index&#13;
&amp;#12;Foreword&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Production concentrates in big cities, leading provinces, and wealthy nations. Half the world's&#13;
production fits onto 1.5 percent of its land. Cairo produces more than half of Egypt's GDP,&#13;
using just 0.5 percent of its area. Brazil's three south-central states comprise 15 percent of&#13;
its land, but more than half its production. And North America, the European Union, and&#13;
Japan-with fewer than a billion people-account for three-quarters of the world's wealth.&#13;
    But economic concentration leaves out some populations. In Brazil, China, and India,&#13;
for example, lagging states have poverty rates more than twice those in dynamic states.&#13;
More than two-thirds of the developing world's poor live in villages. A billion people, liv-&#13;
ing in the poorest and most isolated nations, mostly in Sub-Saharan Africa and South and&#13;
Central Asia, survive on less than 2 percent of the world's wealth.&#13;
    These geographically disadvantaged people cope every day with the reality that develop-&#13;
ment does not bring economic prosperity everywhere at once; markets favor some places&#13;
over others. But dispersing production more broadly does not necessarily foster prosperity.&#13;
Economically successful nations both facilitate the concentration of production and insti-&#13;
tute policies that make people's living standards-in terms of nutrition, education, health,&#13;
and sanitation-more uniform across space. Getting the benefits of both economic concen-&#13;
tration and social convergence requires policy actions aimed at economic integration.&#13;
    Integration should begin with institutions that ensure access to basic services such as&#13;
primary education, primary health care, adequate sanitation, and clean drinking water for&#13;
everyone. As integration becomes more difficult, adaptive policies should include roads, rail-&#13;
ways, airports, harbors, and communication systems that facilitate the movement of goods,&#13;
services, people, and ideas locally, nationally, and internationally. For places where integration&#13;
is hardest, for social or political reasons, the response should be commensurately comprehen-&#13;
sive, with institutions that unite, infrastructure that connects, and interventions that target,&#13;
such as slum upgrading programs or incentives for producers to locate in certain areas.&#13;
    Using these principles, World Development Report 2009, the 31st in the series, reframes&#13;
the policy debates on urbanization, territorial development, and regional integration. The&#13;
report analyzes the early experience of developed countries and draws practical implications&#13;
for urbanization policies in today's developing countries. For the poorest countries in Africa&#13;
and Asia that are landlocked or otherwise isolated from world markets, the Report discusses&#13;
promising approaches to regional integration that combine institutional cooperation, shared&#13;
infrastructure, and special incentives. In growing middle-income economies, general pros-&#13;
perity can camouflage areas of persistent poverty. For such countries, the Report outlines&#13;
strategies to foster domestic integration and help the poor in the least fortunate places.&#13;
    I expect that Reshaping Economic Geography will stimulate a much-needed discussion&#13;
on the desirability of "balanced growth," which has proved elusive. And by informing&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                              8,,d{,cl(&#13;
some important policy debates, it will point the way toward more inclusive and sustain-&#13;
â&#128;¢bledmlopm&lt;nt.                                                   12~.J&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                         Robert B. Zoellick&#13;
                                                         President                                   v&#13;
&amp;#12;&amp;#12;     Geography in motion&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                            The Report at a Glance-Density, Distance,&#13;
                                            and Division&#13;
&#13;
Growing cities, ever more mobile people, and increasingly specialized products are integral to development. These changes have&#13;
been most noticeable in North America, Western Europe, and Northeast Asia. But countries in East and South Asia and Eastern&#13;
Europe are now experiencing changes that are similar in their scope and speed. World Development Report 2009: Reshaping Eco-&#13;
nomic Geography concludes that such transformations will remain essential for economic success in other parts of the developing&#13;
world and should be encouraged.&#13;
&#13;
Seeing development in 3-0                   the start of winter in some parts of the               cans change states every year, migrating&#13;
These transformations bring prosper-        co untry, so flights often are canceled.               to reduce their distance to economic&#13;
ity, but they do not happen without         But Americans put up with the pain of                  opportunity. The most striking feature&#13;
risk and sacrifice. Look at three of the    leaving friends and family, because eco-               of this map is distance.&#13;
world's most prosperous places:             nomic activity is concentrated in a few                   Across the Atlantic, in Western&#13;
                                            parts of the country (see map G0.2). To                Europe, another massive movement&#13;
  The first is Tokyo, the largest city in   get a part of this wealth, you have to get             takes place every day-not of people&#13;
  the world with 35 million people,         closer to it. That is why 8 million Ameri-             but of products. One example is Airbus,&#13;
  a quarter of Japan's population,&#13;
  packed into less than 4 percent of its    Map G0.1    Density-why it pays to be close to Tokyo&#13;
                                            Economic production per square kilometer in Japan&#13;
  land.&#13;
â&#128;¢ The second is the United States, the&#13;
  largest economy in the world and&#13;
  perhaps also the most mobile, where&#13;
  about 35 million people change resi-&#13;
  dences each year.&#13;
â&#128;¢ The third is Western Europe, the&#13;
  most connected continent in the&#13;
  world today, where countries trade&#13;
  about 35 percent of th eir gross&#13;
  domestic product (GDP), more than&#13;
  half among neighbors.&#13;
    Visitors to Tokyo can see people&#13;
being crushed into trains by profes-&#13;
sional train-packers. Millions of peo-&#13;
ple willingly subject themselves to the&#13;
unpleasantness of such a crush. A map&#13;
of Japan's economic density shows why.&#13;
Tokyo generates a big part of Japan's&#13;
wealth-to get a share of it, people&#13;
have to live close by (see map GO.I).&#13;
The most striking feature of this map&#13;
is density-the concentration of wealth&#13;
in Tokyo and Osaka.&#13;
    In the United States, each year in&#13;
the days before the Thanksgiving holi-&#13;
day, about 35 million people try to get     Source:WDR 2009 team and World Bank Development Research Group based on subnational GDP estimates for&#13;
back to their families and friends. It is   2005. See also Nordhaus 12006).&#13;
&amp;#12;x                                                 WORLD DEVELOPMENT REPORT 2009&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Map G0.2 Distance- why America ns must be mob ile                                                       tage of economic density. Despite the&#13;
Economic production per square kilometer in the United States&#13;
                                                                                                        crush among commuters and in such&#13;
                                                                                    UNITED STATES&#13;
                                                                                                        slums as Dharavi, Mumbai's popula-&#13;
                                                                                                        tion has doubled since the 1970s. Since&#13;
                                                                                                        the 1990s, millions of Chinese work-&#13;
                                                                                                        ers have migrated to get closer to eco-&#13;
                                                                                                        nomic opportunity concentrated along&#13;
                                                                                                        the coast. Just as Americans travel dur-&#13;
                                                                                                        ing Thanksgiving, more than 200 mil-&#13;
                                                                                                        lion people in China travel during the&#13;
                                                                                                        Chinese New Year. Regional produc-&#13;
                                                                                                        tion networks in East Asia are spread&#13;
                                                                                                        far wider than Airbus sites in Western&#13;
                                                                                                        Europe. East Asian countries may not&#13;
                                                                                                        trade airplane parts, but nations that&#13;
                                                                                                        once were enemies now trade parts of&#13;
Source:WDR 2009team and World Bank Development Research Group based on subnational GDP estimates for&#13;
                                                                                                        cars and computers with the same fre-&#13;
2005. See also Nordhaus (2006).                                                                         quency and speed.&#13;
                                                                                                           And what is the payoff? We can&#13;
which makes parts of planes and assem-                     a region that was divided not so long        again recognize the shapes of China,&#13;
bles them in France, Germany, Spain, and                   ago now trade with former enemies to         India, and Southeast Asian countries&#13;
the United Kingdom as weU as in other                      become an ever-more-integrated Euro-         on the map of the world's economic&#13;
countries. Huge sections of aircraft are                   pean Union (EU ). As this integration        geography (see map G0.4). Contrast&#13;
loaded onto ships and planes, as places                    has increased, economic divisions have       these shapes with that of the mighty&#13;
specialize in making different parts and                   decreased, making specialization and         continent of Africa, which shows up as&#13;
producing them in scale. Countries in                      scale possible (see map G0.3).               a slender peninsula.&#13;
                                                               What is the payoff for this pain? A         The World Developmen t Report&#13;
Map G0.3 Division- what prevents prog ress                 map of economic geography, which             argues that some places are doing well&#13;
in Africa does not in Western Europe                       resizes the area of a country to reflect     because they have promoted transfor-&#13;
Border restrictions to flows of goods, capital,&#13;
people, and ideas                                          its GDP, shows the benefits of big cit-      mations along the three dimensions of&#13;
                                                           ies, mobile people, and connected            economic geography:&#13;
                                                           countries. The United States, Western&#13;
                                                                                                          Higher densities, as seen in the&#13;
                                                           Europe, and Japan dominate the world's&#13;
                                                                                                          growth of cities.&#13;
                                                           economy (see map G0.4).&#13;
                                                                                                          Shorter distances, as workers and&#13;
                                                               Cities, migration, and trade have&#13;
                                                                                                          businesses migrate closer to density.&#13;
                                                           been the main catalysts of progress in&#13;
                                                                                                        â&#128;¢ Fewer divisions, as countries thin&#13;
                                                           the developed world over the past two&#13;
                                                                                                          their economic borders and enter&#13;
                                                           centuries. These stories are now being&#13;
                                                                                                          world markets to take advantage of&#13;
                                                           repeated in the developing world's most&#13;
                                                                                                          scale and specialization.&#13;
                                                           dynamic economies.&#13;
                                                                                                           The United States and Japan&#13;
                                                             Mumbai is not the largest city in&#13;
                                                                                                        reshaped their economic geography&#13;
                                                             the world, but it is the most densely&#13;
                                                                                                        along these lines in the past. China is&#13;
                                                             populated. And it keeps growing.&#13;
                                                                                                        reshaping its economic geography now.&#13;
                                                             China is not the largest economy in&#13;
                                                                                                        This Report proposes that these will be&#13;
                                                             the world, but it is the fastest growing&#13;
                                                                                                        the changes that will help developing&#13;
                                                             and may be among the most mobile.&#13;
                                                                                                        nations in other parts of the world,&#13;
                                                             Southeast Asia may not have formed&#13;
                                                                                                        most notably Africa,&#13;
                                                             a political union like Europe, but it&#13;
                                                             trades parts of goods back and forth       Unbalanced growth, inclusive&#13;
Source: WDR 2009 team (see chapter 3 for details).           as the EU does.&#13;
Note: The width of borders is proportional to a sum-                                                    development&#13;
mary measure of each country's restrictions to the&#13;
flow of goods, capital, people, and ideas with all other&#13;
                                                             People risk loss of life or limb on        That is what this World Development&#13;
countries.                                                 Mumbai's packed trains to take advan -       Report proposes, and the Report is&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                           Geography in Motion                                                         xi&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Map G0.4      How markets view the world&#13;
A country's size shows the proportion of global gross domestic product found there&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                       .Â·&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                   (    ..                                                             .-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Source: WDR 2009 team using 2005 GDP (constant U.S. dollars).&#13;
Note: The cartogram was created using the method developed by Gastner and Newman (2004). This map shows the countries tha t have the most wealth when GDP is compared using currency&#13;
exchange rates. This indicates international purchasing power-what someone's money is worth if spent in another country.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
structured to bring out the message (see                       interest all countries-small and large,                         Africa is how to make a better economic&#13;
figure GO.l ).                                                 low income and middle income. The                               union that benefits both the landlocked&#13;
                                                               chapters on distance, factor mobility,                          and the coastal countries, the poorest&#13;
    Part one describes the changes along&#13;
                                                               and regional development may be of                              and the more prosperous.&#13;
    the dimensions of density, distance,&#13;
                                                               most interest to larger middle-income                               As the geographic scale increases&#13;
    and division-taking up each in&#13;
                                                               countries. And the chapters on division,                        from local to national to international,&#13;
    turn. It summarizes the experience&#13;
                                                               transport costs, and regional integration                       the specific policy issue changes. But&#13;
    of the past century or so.&#13;
                                                               may be of most interest to low-income                           the underlying problem is the same-&#13;
    Part two analyzes the drivers of these&#13;
                                                               and smaller economies.                                          some places do well, others do not. And&#13;
    transformations-the market forces&#13;
                                                                  Four spotli ghts on Geography in                             it is difficult for anyone to accept this as&#13;
    of agglomeration, migration, and&#13;
                                                               Motion examine the interplay between                            inevitable.&#13;
    specialization and trade. It distills&#13;
                                                               market forces and government policies                               The Report's main message is that&#13;
    the findings of policy research dur-&#13;
                                                               in North America, Western Europe,                               economic growth will be unbalanced.&#13;
    ing the past generation or so.&#13;
                                                               East Asia, and Sub-Saharan Africa. By                           To try to spread out economic activ-&#13;
    Part three discusses the policy impli-&#13;
                                                               highlighting the interactions among the                         ity is to discourage it. But development&#13;
    cations of the experience and analy-&#13;
                                                               three dimensions, they also connect the                         can still be inclusive, in that even people&#13;
    sis in the first two parts. It provides&#13;
                                                               Report's different parts.                                       who start their lives far away from eco-&#13;
    a common framework for reframing&#13;
                                                                  Seen another way, the Report exam-                           nomic opportunity can benefit from&#13;
    three policy debates-on urbaniza-&#13;
                                                               ines the most important policy issues                           the growing concentration of wealth in&#13;
    tion, on lagging areas within coun-&#13;
                                                               of economic geography, from local, to                           a few places. The way to get both the&#13;
    tries, and on regional integration&#13;
                                                               national, to international. Locally, the                        benefits of uneven growth and inclu-&#13;
    and globalization.&#13;
                                                               policy issue in areas such as Lagos state                       sive development is through economic&#13;
   The Report is structured and written                        in southern Nigeria is how to manage                            integration.&#13;
in such a way that people interested in                        urbanization. Nationally, the policy&#13;
only one of these debates can read just                        issue in Nigeria is how to manage the                           Economic integration-local,&#13;
some of it. That is, it can be read verti-                     disparities in resources and living stan-                       national, and international&#13;
cally. The chapters on density, agglom-                        dards in the north and the south. And                           The Report makes it clear what eco-&#13;
eration, and urbanization should                               internationally, the policy issue in West                       nomic integration means. It means one&#13;
&amp;#12;xii                                       WORLD DEVELOPMENT REPORT 2009&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure G0.1   The Report can be read by part or by policy&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                   1&#13;
                                                                DENSITY&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                4&#13;
                                        AGGLOMERATION&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                            7&#13;
                      URBANIZATION&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Source: WDR 2009 team .&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
thing to integrate rural and urban areas,                   In places urbanizing rapidly, gov-      integrate areas within nations, while&#13;
and slums with other parts of cities. It                    ernments must put in place, in          reducing poverty everywhere.&#13;
means another to integrate lagging                          addition to institutions, connective        Lagging areas have one thing in&#13;
and leading provinces within a nation.                      infrastructure so that the benefits     common-they are economically dis-&#13;
And it means yet another to integrate                       of rising economic density are more     tant from places doing well. But besides&#13;
isolated and well-connected countries.                      widely shared. A good example is        this, the economic geography of differ-&#13;
These notions of economic integration                       Chongqing, China.                       ent areas is not the same:&#13;
are central to three debates in develop-                    In places where urbanization has&#13;
ment-urbanization, territorial devel-                       advanced, in addition to institutions     In some countries, such as China,&#13;
opment, and international integration.                      and infrastructure, targeted inter-       lagging areas are sparsely populated.&#13;
                                                            ventions may be necessary to deal         It does not make a lot of sense to&#13;
Urbanization&#13;
                                                            with slums. But these interventions       spread expensive infrastructure into&#13;
The arguments and evidence in World&#13;
                                                            will not work unless institutions for     these places-or to give firms incen-&#13;
Development Report 2009 can set pri-&#13;
                                                            land and basic services are reason-       tives to move to them. What makes&#13;
orities for policies at different stages of&#13;
                                                            ably effective and transport infra-       much more sense is to provide basic&#13;
urbanization, essentially providing the&#13;
                                                            structure is in place. A good example     services everywhere, even if it costs&#13;
elements of an urbanization strategy.&#13;
                                                            is Bogota, Colombia.                      more to reach these distant areas.&#13;
Each territory or area within a nation&#13;
                                                                                                      Encouraging mobility of people is&#13;
has a specific geography. But the prin-&#13;
                                                     Territorial development                          the priority, and institutions that&#13;
ciples are quite universal.&#13;
                                                     The principles also can reshape the              make land markets work better and&#13;
      In places mostly rural, governments            debate on territorial or regional develop-       provide security, schools, streets, and&#13;
      should be as neutral as possible and           ment. The tools of geography can iden-           sanitation should be the mainstay of&#13;
      should establ ish the institutional            tify which places are poor-the lagging           integration policy.&#13;
      foundation for possible urbaniza-              areas-and where most of the poor live.         â&#128;¢ In other countries, such as Brazil,&#13;
      tion in some places. Good land poli-           Often, the two are not the same, because         lagging areas are densely populated.&#13;
      cies are central, and so are policies to       the poor have the most reason to move            As in China, poor people have moved&#13;
      provide basic services to everyone. A          from poor places. The Report discusses           in the millions from the northeast&#13;
      good example is Costa Rica.                    how governments can tailor policies to           to the southeast. Everyone speaks&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                Geography in Motion                                   xiii&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  the same language, and domestic                 possibility is providing incentives to        markets attractive to investors, face a&#13;
  mobility is not difficult. But many             agriculture and allied activities that        more difficult challenge. Good insti-&#13;
  poor people still live in the north-            are appropriate for states that are           tutions and regional infrastructure&#13;
  east. Encouraging mobility of people            still mostly rural.                           can help them access these markets.&#13;
  from the northeast is important, but                                                          Examples include East Asia and,&#13;
                                               Regional integration&#13;
  so is enabling access to markets in                                                           increasingly, South Asia . Southern&#13;
                                               Finally, the principles developed in this&#13;
  the dynamic southeast. In such cases,                                                         Africa and South America can also&#13;
                                               Report inform the debates on how to&#13;
  both institutions and infrastructure                                                          integrate globally by making their&#13;
                                               make globalization work for all coun-&#13;
  to connect the two coastal areas are                                                          home markets bigger and more spe-&#13;
                                               tries. The same logic applied at the&#13;
  necessary for economic integration.                                                           cialized through regional institu-&#13;
                                               local and national levels can be used at&#13;
â&#128;¢ In a third group of countries, such as                                                        tions and infrastructure.&#13;
                                               the international level to classify world&#13;
  India, lagging areas are densely pop-                                                       â&#128;¢ Integration is hardest for countries&#13;
                                               regions by the difficulty of economic&#13;
  ulated-almost 60 percent ofindia's                                                            in regions that are divided, are dis-&#13;
                                               integration in these regions. The com-&#13;
  poor live in these poor places-and                                                            tant from world markets, and lack&#13;
                                               mon problem is division-thick eco-&#13;
  people can find it difficult to migrate                                                       the economic density provided by a&#13;
                                               nomic borders. Aside from this, the task&#13;
  to places doing well, such as the cap-                                                        large local economy. These countries&#13;
                                               of integration varies in different parts&#13;
  ital area and the south. Language                                                             include those nicknamed the "bot-&#13;
                                               of the developing world:&#13;
  and cultura l differences within                                                              tom billion"-East, Central, and West&#13;
  some areas can be considerable. In           â&#128;¢ Countries in regions close to world            Africa; Central Asia; and the Pacific&#13;
  such cases, institutions and infra-            markets, such as Central America ,             Islands. For these countries, all three&#13;
  structure could be complemented by             North Africa, and Eastern Europe,              instruments are needed-regional&#13;
  incentives to producers to locate in           face a relatively straightforward task         institutions that thin borders, regional&#13;
  these lagging states. But these incen-         of integration. Common institutions            infrastructure that connects countries,&#13;
  tives should be carefully designed to          can help them become extensions of             and such incentives as preferential&#13;
  avoid offsetting the unifying effects          these large markets.                           access to world markets, perhaps con-&#13;
  of common institutions and con-              â&#128;¢ Countries in regions distant from              ditioned on ensuring that all countries&#13;
  nective infrastructure. A promising            world markets, but with large home             strengthen regional cooperation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    One thing is common to the policy debates on urbanization, area development, and globalization. In their current form, they over-&#13;
emphasize geographic targeting-what to do in rural areas or in slums, what to do in lagging states or remote areas, and what to do&#13;
in the most poor or landlocked countries. The Report reframes these debates in a way that better conforms to the reality ofgrowth and&#13;
development. The reality is that the interaction between leading and lagging places is the key to economic development. The reality is&#13;
that spatially targeted interventions are just a small part of what governments can do to help places that are not doing well. The reality&#13;
is that, besides place-based incentives, governments have far more potent instruments for integration. They can build institutions that&#13;
unify all places and put in place infrastructure that connects some places to others.&#13;
    The Report calls for rebalancing these policy discussions to include all the instruments of integration-institutions that unify,&#13;
infrastructure that connects, and interventions that target. And it shows how to use the three dimensions of density, distance, and&#13;
division to tailor the use of these policy instruments to address integration challenges that range from the relatively straightforward&#13;
to the most complicated.&#13;
&amp;#12;4   WORLD DEVELOPMENT REPORT 2009&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Map 1 The biggest development challenges- at the local, national, and international geographic scales&#13;
                                                      a. A billion in slums&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
             Â·~&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  b. A billion in remote areas&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
             Â·~&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                      c. The bottom billion&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       Populati on (millions)     [=:J WDR regions&#13;
                                                &gt; 250&#13;
                                                 50-100 100-250&#13;
                                                &lt; 25     25- 50&#13;
&#13;
    Sources: Panel a: United Nations 2006a ; panel b: WDR 2009 team, based on household survey data; panel c: Collier 2007.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                             Overview     5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     concentration-essentially urbanites in            is that they also had more than half of the&#13;
     prosperous neighborhoods-and those left           world's population; the European Union&#13;
     behind in villages and those living in slums,     (EU), Japan, and the United States have less&#13;
     estimated to number about 1 billion in the        than one-sixth.&#13;
     developing world (see map 1, panel a). The            Today, the worry at the international&#13;
     (ineffective) policy responses so far have        level is the high poverty, illiteracy, and&#13;
     been to try to slow down urbanization .           mortality in some parts of the world, set&#13;
         At the national scale, economic growth        against the prosperity, literacy, and longev-&#13;
     displays a similar unevenness, as places close    ity in others. The policy responses include&#13;
     to large markets prosper sooner than places       foreign aid and multilateral efforts to ease&#13;
     more distant. In China the coastal provinc-       international trade and investment flows .&#13;
     es-mainly in the three areas known as the         But barriers to the agricultural exports of&#13;
     Bohai Basin, the Pearl River Delta, and the       developing countries remain considerable,&#13;
     Yangtze River Delta-accounted for more            and apathy for people distant or distinct&#13;
     than half of the country's GDP in 2005,           renders aid flows miniscule. Aid will be a&#13;
     with less than a fifth of its area. In Brazil     small part of the solution. Even in the Euro-&#13;
     the south-central states of Minas Gerais,         pean Union, with a combined GDP of about&#13;
     Rio de Janeiro, and Sao Paulo account for         â&#130;¬8 trillion, annual aid through the struc-&#13;
     more than 52 percent of the country's GDP,        tural and cohesion funds will average less&#13;
     with less than 15 percent of its land area.       than â&#130;¬50 billion between 2007 and 2013.&#13;
     Greater Cairo produces 50 percent of the          Foreign aid is less than 0.5 percent of the&#13;
     Arab Republic of Egypt's GDP, using just          gross national income of giving countries,&#13;
     0.5 percent of its land area.                     and not even a large fraction of the GDP&#13;
         Politicians generally view this economic      of countries home to the "bottom billion"&#13;
     imbalance disapprovingly. In communist            who have 12 percent of the world 's popula-&#13;
11   Russia the government labored to reduce           tion, but less than 1 percent of its GDP (see&#13;
II&#13;
"&#13;
     the economic share of the old industrial          map 1, panel c). 2&#13;
     area of St. Petersburg, the Center, and the           A billion slum dwellers in the developing&#13;
     mid-Urals from 65 percent to 32 percent,          world's cities, a billion people in fragile lag-&#13;
     forcibly shifting production to the eastern       ging areas within countries, a billion at the&#13;
I    areas. It boosted the share of the east in eco-   bottom of the global hierarchy of nations-&#13;
     nomic production from 4 percent in 1925           these overlapping populations pose today's&#13;
l    to 28 percent at the end of communism,            biggest development challenges. Seemingly&#13;
     whose demise probably was hastened by the         disparate, they share a fundamental feature:&#13;
     spatial inefficiency that these efforts engen-    at different spatial scales, they are the most&#13;
     dered. Because governments care so much           visible manifestation of economic geogra -&#13;
     about domestic disparities, they jeopardize       phy's importance for development.&#13;
     competitiveness and risk collapse. Policies           Concern for these intersecting 3 billion&#13;
     to reduce interstate or provincial dispari-       sometimes comes with the prescription that&#13;
     ties in production and living standards are       economic growth must be made more spa-&#13;
     commonplace-but largely ineffective.              tially balanced. The growth of cities must&#13;
     About 1 billion people continue to live in        be controlled. Rural-urban gaps in wealth&#13;
     these inhospitable lagging areas (see map 1,      must be reduced quickly. Lagging areas and&#13;
     panel b).                                         provinces distant from domestic and world&#13;
         At the international scale, economic          markets must be sustained through territo-&#13;
     growth has concentrated global produc-            rial development programs that bring jobs&#13;
     tion in a few regions, with commensurate          to the people living there. And growing&#13;
     differences in incomes. In 2000 about             gaps between the developed and developing&#13;
     three-quarters of world GDP was concen-           world must be addressed through interven-&#13;
     trated in North America, Western Europe,          tions to protect enterprises in developing&#13;
     and Northeast Asia. This concentration is         countries until they are ready to compete.&#13;
     not new. Three centuries ago, China and               World Development Report 2009 has&#13;
     India accounted for about two-thirds of           a different message: economic growth&#13;
     the world's wealth. What was different then       is seldom balanced. Efforts to spread it&#13;
&amp;#12;6                                        WORLD DEVELOPME N T REPORT 2009&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    BOX 2     The three dimensions of development: density, distance, and division&#13;
    This Report uses t hree geographic dimen -       area's economic density (GDP per square            Division. But the journey is not yet&#13;
    sions to describe t he transformation of         kilometer) was 35 times that of Nigeria         comp lete. The goods must surmount&#13;
    economies as they develop (part one)             in 1990. The capacity of the tanneries in       the division caused by differences in&#13;
    and the conditions to keep in mind when          and around the city even makes it worth -       currencies and conventions between&#13;
    formulating policies (part three). The           while to illegally import live animals-the      Nigeria and Europe. Between December&#13;
    words are easy metaphors, since density,         most important intermediate input-              2007 and March 2008, Nigeria's currency&#13;
    distance, and division summon images of          from neighboring countries. But Kano is         depreciated from 170 naira to â&#130;¬1 to             .&#13;
    human, physical, and pol itical geography.       neither large enough, nor rich enough,          180 naira, but appreciated from 246 naira&#13;
    But they can be measured . Consider this         to consume more than a little of what is        to the British pound in November 2007&#13;
    ill ustration.                                   produced. The goods must be exported            to 235 naira in March 2008. Buyers and&#13;
        In 2003 Nigeria had 45 million goats and     to people willing to pay enough to make         sellers of leather goods have to contend&#13;
    kids, 28 mill ion sheep and lambs, and 15        production worthwhile.                          wit h these fluctuations. They must also&#13;
    million catt le. In a typical year 8 million        Distance. Wealthy Europeans want             deal with two sets of laws and customs.&#13;
    sheep, 7 mill ion goats, and 0.5 mill ion        goods made with "Morocco leather," a            The Un ited Kingdom has 30 procedures&#13;
    cattle are sla ughtered, mostly in five north-   lot of which comes from Kano. To get to         for enforcing a contract, Nigeria 39. These&#13;
    ern states including Kano. More than half        Europe, Kano's bulky exports must travel        divisions multiply the costs of doing&#13;
    the hides are consumed as porno. The rest        through Lagos, which along highways             business. Few cargo ships make landfall&#13;
    are sold to tanneries. The demand from           and railways is about 1,000 kilometers          in Lagos, so it costs much more to trans-&#13;
    tan neries exceeds local supply, so animals      away. It might as well be 4,000 kilome-         port goods from Lagos than from busier&#13;
    are imported from nearby Chad, Niger,            ters. A railway goes to Lagos through           places such as Shanghai. It costs less than&#13;
    and Cameroon. Goat and sheep skins are           the cities of Kaduna and Ibadan, but it is      $400 to ship a container to the United&#13;
    good business-in 2001 Nigeria produced           narrow gauge and poorly maintained .            Kingdom from China, more than $1,000&#13;
    30 million to 35 mi ll ion of them, exporting    Most commerce is by road, obstructed by         from Nigeria.&#13;
    almost all to Europe.                            roadblocks and piracy. Shipping compa -            Low local density, costly internal dis-&#13;
        Density. Consider t he market condi -        nies charge more than $1,200 for a 30 -ton      tances, and international divisions consp ire&#13;
    tions for a ta nnery t hat produces leather      trailer from Kano to Lagos. Once the            against Kano. Making matters more difficult&#13;
    in the city of Ka no in Northern Nigeria .       goods get to Lagos, there are port fees,        are rel igious and other divisions within&#13;
    Officia ll y, the population of Kano State is    pilferage, and delays. It takes 26 days to      Nigeria.&#13;
    about 9 mi llion, large enough to provide        get the goods onto a ship. The economic&#13;
    the skilled labor and infrastructure for         distance from Kano to Lagos, measured           Sources: World Bank 2007; Phillips, Taylor,&#13;
    its t anneries. Due to the concentration         as money, is several times the Euclidean        Sanni, and Akoroda, (FAO 2004); Govern-&#13;
                                                                                                     ment of Nigeria 2003.                           '&#13;
    of people in and around Kano city, the           (straight-line) 829 kilometers.                                                                 t&#13;
                                                                                                                                                     '&#13;
                                                                                                                                                     t&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         prematu rely will jeopard ize progress. Two              convergence. Part three proposes the prin-&#13;
                                         centu ries of economic development show                  ciple of eco nomic integration-between&#13;
                                         that spatial disparities in income and pro-              places th at producers prefer and places&#13;
                                         duction are inev itable. A generation of eco-            where people live- to guide poli cy making.&#13;
                                         nomic resea rch confir ms this: t here is no             Using thi s principle, it refra mes the debates&#13;
                                         good reason to expect eco nom ic growth to               on urbanization, territorial development,&#13;
                                         sp read smoothly across space. The exper i-              and internationa l integration, calling fo r a&#13;
                                         ence of successful developers shows th at                change in orientation of policies away from&#13;
                                         pro duction becomes more co ncent rated                  geographic targeting towa rd integration.          â&#128;¢&#13;
                                         spatially. The most successfu l nations also                 By using a well-calibrated blend of insti-&#13;
                                         in stitute poli cies th at make basic livin g            tutions, infrastructu re, and interventions,&#13;
                                         standards more unifor m across space. Eco-               today's developers ca n reshape their eco-&#13;
                                         nomic production concentrates, while liv-                nomic geography. W hen they do this well,&#13;
                                         ing sta ndards converge.                                 t hey wi ll experience unbalanced grow th&#13;
                                             Part one of the Report describes the                 and inclusive development.&#13;
                                         geographic transformations that are neces-&#13;
                                         sary for development. Part two analyzes the              The three dimensions of development&#13;
                                         drivers of these changes and ide ntifies the             T he geographic transformations fo r eco-&#13;
                                         markets that deliver both concentration and              nom ic development can be characterized in&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                                    Overview                                                   7&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
three dimensions-density, distance, and                               and workers reduce their distance from&#13;
division. These three words are not just met-                         density. The main mechanisms are the&#13;
aphors for the policy challenges just outlined.                       mobility of labor and the reduction of&#13;
They conform closely to the more technical                            transport costs through infrastructure&#13;
notion of "market access" (see box 2). And                            investments. Divisions within coun-&#13;
they represent the dimensions of economic                             tries-differences in language, currency,&#13;
geography that have to be reshaped if the                             and culture-tend to be small, though&#13;
development challenges are to be met.                                 large countries such as India and Nigeria&#13;
   Understanding the transformations                                  may be geographically divided because&#13;
along the dimensions of density, distance,                            of religion, ethnicity, or language.&#13;
and division helps to identify the main                           â&#128;¢ Division is the most important dimen-&#13;
market forces and the appropriate policy                            sion internationally. But distance and&#13;
responses at each of the three geographic                           density are also relevant. Economic pro-&#13;
scales-local, national, and international                           duction is concentrated in a few world&#13;
(see table 1) .                                                     regions-North America, Northeast&#13;
â&#128;¢ Density is the most important dimension                           Asia, and Western Europe-that are&#13;
  locally. Distances are short, and cultural                        also the most integrated. Other regions,&#13;
  and political divisions are few and shal-                         by contrast, are divided. While dis-&#13;
  low. The policy challenge is getting den-                         tance matters at the international level,&#13;
  sity right-harnessing market forces to                            for access to world markets, divisions&#13;
  encourage concentration and promote                               associated with the impermeability of&#13;
  convergence in living standards between                           borders and differences in currencies&#13;
  villages and towns and cities. But dis-                           and regulations are a more serious bar-&#13;
  tance can be important as rapid urban-                            rier than distance. Having a large and&#13;
  ization leads to congestion, and divisions                        dynamic economy within the neigh-&#13;
  within cities can be manifest in slums                            borhood can help smaller countries,&#13;
  and ghettos.                                                      especially in regions distant from world&#13;
                                                                    markets. For economies in other regions&#13;
â&#128;¢ D istance to density is the most impor-&#13;
                                                                    such as Central Africa and Central Asia,&#13;
  tant dimension at the national geo-&#13;
                                                                    international integration is hardest.&#13;
  graphic scale. Distance between areas&#13;
  where economic activity is concentrated                            But the potential problem at each of&#13;
  and areas that lag is the main dimension.                       these geographic scales is the same-people&#13;
  The policy challenge is helping firms                           in one place, production in another. Places&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table 1 Density is most important locally, distance nationally, an d division internationally&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                           Geographic scales&#13;
                                 Local                                        National                                    International&#13;
 Unit                            Area                                         Country                                     Region&#13;
 Exampl es                       Guangdong (178,000 km' )                     China (9.6 million km' )                    East Asia (15.9 mill ion km' )&#13;
                                 Rio de Janeiro State (44,000 km' )           Brazil (8.5 million km ' )                  South America (1 7.8 million km' )&#13;
                                 Lagos State (3,600 km' )                     Nigeria (933,000 km' )                      West Africa (6. 1 million km ' )&#13;
                                 Greater Cairo (86,000 km' )                  Egypt, Arab Rep. of (995,000 km' )          North Africa (6.0 million km' )&#13;
 Most important                  Density                                      Di stance                                   Division&#13;
 dimension                       Of rural and urban settlements               Between lagging and leading areas           Between countries&#13;
 Second-most important           Distance                                     Density                                     Distance&#13;
 dimension                       Because of congestion                        Of population and poverty in lagging        To major world markets&#13;
                                                                              areas&#13;
&#13;
 Third-most important            Division                                     Division                                    Density&#13;
 dimension                       Between formal settlements and slums         Between areas within countries              Absence of large cou ntry in the neig hborhood&#13;
&#13;
Source:WDR 2009 team.&#13;
Note: Throughout the Report, "areas" are within-country economic neighborhoods or administrative units such as states or provinces, and "regions" are groupings of countries&#13;
based on geographic proximity.&#13;
&amp;#12;8   WORLD DEVELOPMENT REPORT 2009&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    attract production and people at different           $10,000-$11,000, about the threshold for&#13;
    speeds, and these differences determine             crossing into high incomes. This is the&#13;
    geographic disparities in income. Across            experience of successful developers. The&#13;
    provinces, nations, and the world, develop-         implication is that developing countries&#13;
    ment comes in waves and leaves behind a             should expect rising subnational dispari-&#13;
    bumpy economic landscape-prosperity in              ties in income and production when they&#13;
    some places, poverty in others.                     still have underdeveloped infrastructure&#13;
                                                        and institutions.&#13;
    The world is not flat                             â&#128;¢ Concentration is slowest internation-&#13;
    Development is neither smooth nor lin-              ally, and it continues longer. Production&#13;
    ear-at any geographic scale. Growth                 and wealth continue to concentrate in&#13;
    comes earlier to some places than to others.        countries beyond per capita incomes of&#13;
    Geographic differences in living standards          $25,000, the upper reaches of the inter-&#13;
    diverge before converging, faster at the local      national income distribution . Neighbor-&#13;
    scale and slower as geography exercises its         hoods of nations seem to grow or stagnate&#13;
    influence. These are the styli zed facts, based     together-nearness to prosperity helps,&#13;
    on the experiences of successful developers         while nearness to poor nations hurts. The&#13;
    over the last two centuries.                        implication is that growth strategies for&#13;
                                                        later developers are not the same as the&#13;
    Economic production becomes                         strategies that worked for those who have&#13;
    more concentrated                                   already grown to high-income levels; for&#13;
    As countries develop, people and economic           today's developing countries, economic&#13;
    activities become more concentrated. But            integration with the rest of the world-&#13;
    the speed varies, depending on the spatial          neighbors and distant countries-is even&#13;
    scale-economic forces do not operate in             more essential.&#13;
    a geographic vacuum. The concentration&#13;
    of people and production is fastest locally,          Local concentration (in towns and cit-&#13;
    slowest internationally.                          ies) happens quickly. Consider first the rising&#13;
                                                      concentration of people in towns and cities.&#13;
    â&#128;¢ Concentration is fastest locally. Economic      As countries develop, the economic density&#13;
      concentration at the local scale is most        in some places increases as more people move&#13;
      conveniently measured by the rate of            to live in or near towns and cities (see figure&#13;
      urbanization-the growth of economic             1, panel a). The urban share of the population&#13;
      and population density in towns and cit-        rises sharply- from about 10 percent to 50&#13;
      ies. A large part of this geographic trans-     percent-as countries grow from low income&#13;
      formation has been completed when               to lower-middle incomes of about $3,500.&#13;
      countries reach per capita incomes of           (It is difficult to make international com-&#13;
      about $3,500, roughly the threshold for         parisons because countries define "urban"&#13;
      crossing into upper-middle incomes. The         differently. 3 ) Between 2000 and 2005, the&#13;
      speed of this transformation is no differ-      average urban population growth for low-&#13;
      ent from what was seen in today's devel-        income countries was 3 percent a year, more&#13;
      oped countries when they transformed.           than twice the rate for middle-income coun-&#13;
      The implication is that all nations must        tries and more than three times the rate for&#13;
      manage a rapid growth of cities when            high-income countries. Sometimes, this can&#13;
      they still have low incomes and nascent         mean rapid growth of a single city, such as&#13;
      institutions.                                   Bangkok, Thailand, producing even greater&#13;
    â&#128;¢ Concentration is steadier nationally.           concentration.&#13;
      Here, it can best be measured by area               The share of urban residents in total&#13;
      development indicators-the accumula-            household consumption rises too. Urbanites&#13;
      tion of production and people in leading        in Malawi, Jordan, and Panama-countries&#13;
      areas. A large part of this transforma-         with per capita GDPs of about $160, $1,600,&#13;
      tion generally is completed when coun-          and $5,600 respectively-account for 36, 63,&#13;
      tries reach per capita incomes of about         and 80 percent of aggregate consumption.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                           Overview                                                 9&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    These spatia l transformat ions are          Figure 1          At all three geographic scales, the patterns of concentration of economic activity are&#13;
                                                 similar&#13;
closely related to the sectoral transfor-&#13;
mation of countries from agrarian to                                       a. As nations start to develop, people concentrate in towns and cities&#13;
industrial and t hen, in a postind ustrial          Agglomeration index&#13;
economy, to services . Today's high-in-             1.0&#13;
                                                                                                      â&#128;¢                    â&#128;¢&#13;
come countries experienced a similar                                   â&#128;¢      â&#128;¢                                                  â&#128;¢â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢&#13;
rush to urbanize as they industrialized                                                                â&#128;¢         â&#128;¢               â&#128;¢&#13;
                                                                             â&#128;¢                                             â&#128;¢&#13;
 (see chapter 1). All the evidence indicates&#13;
                                                    0.8              # â&#128;¢&#13;
                                                                      â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢                          â&#128;¢                â&#128;¢       â&#128;¢.â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢                       â&#128;¢&#13;
that the shift from farming to industry is                         â&#128;¢â&#128;¢                                                                     â&#128;¢&#13;
                                                                     â&#128;¢ 1. ~ â&#128;¢                                 â&#128;¢&#13;
helped, not hurt, by healthy agriculture,&#13;
which helps towns and cities prosper.4&#13;
People move to make their own lives bet-&#13;
                                                    0.6&#13;
                                                              -:~.Â·&#13;
                                                               ~:Â·~.&#13;
                                                                      â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢&#13;
                                                                            . .â&#128;¢ ~Â·                        â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢&#13;
                                                                                                           â&#128;¢&#13;
                                                                                                                                â&#128;¢â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢&#13;
                                                                                                                                    â&#128;¢&#13;
                                                                                                                                    â&#128;¢                      â&#128;¢&#13;
                                                    0.4       â&#128;¢â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢â&#128;¢&#13;
ter. But when agriculture is doing well,                      #.       â&#128;¢â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢        â&#128;¢&#13;
m igration makes not just them better off,&#13;
but also the villages they leave and the&#13;
cities in which they settle.&#13;
                                                    0.2&#13;
                                                              ,..&#13;
    Nationa l concentration (in leading&#13;
                                                                   â&#128;¢&#13;
areas) continues for longer. What is true of                   0                        10          15          20         25         30                       35&#13;
cities is also true of areas within countries,                                        GDP per capita !PPP, constant 2000 US$, thousands)&#13;
but at a slower speed. With development,&#13;
people and production become concen-                                             b. Nationally, production concentrates in leading areas&#13;
trated in some parts of countries, called           Concentration Index&#13;
                                                    10&#13;
"leading" areas . Economic density grows in          9&#13;
                                                                                                                        France, 1801 - 1999&#13;
these parts-Marmara in Turkey, for exam-&#13;
ple-whi le incomes in places economically            7                                                                                         Japan, 1900- 2000&#13;
distant-such as southeastern Anatolia in             6&#13;
                                                                                                                                  Canada, 1890-2006&#13;
the east-can lag far behind. This concen-&#13;
                                                     4                                                                         Netherlands, 1850-2006&#13;
tration is hard to quantify, but it appears to&#13;
                                                     3&#13;
slow or stop at per capita incomes between           2&#13;
$10,000 and $15,000 (see figure 1, panel b).         1&#13;
    Initially, the concentration increases           02                               10                         20                           30&#13;
rapidly. The share of total consumption of&#13;
                                                                                           GDP per capita !constant 2000 US$, thousands)&#13;
the leading areas in countries with incomes&#13;
ranging between $500 and $7,500-Tajik-                                           c. Internationally, wealth concentrates in some regions&#13;
istan, Mongolia, El Salvador, and Argen -           % share of global GDP !log scale)&#13;
tina-increases from 30 percent to 65&#13;
percent. Comparing GDP concentrations&#13;
                                                    20                                                                                        Western "offshoots "&#13;
in countries with the same land area- Lao                                                                                                     !United States; Canada)&#13;
PDR, Ghana, Poland, and Norway-but                  10&#13;
with incomes from $600 to $27,000 shows&#13;
concentration rising as incomes increase.&#13;
    This is nothing new. Production in&#13;
today's developed economies grew more&#13;
concentrated until they reached high&#13;
incomes. Concentration in France's leading           1&#13;
area quadrupled between 1800 and 1960,                    0                                     10               15               20                  25&#13;
and French incomes grew from $1,000 to                                                         GDP per capita 11990 int'I $, thousands)&#13;
$6,000. But at some point, nations continue&#13;
                                                 Sources: Panel a: WDR 2009 team !see chapter 1 for details); panel b: WDR 2009 team !see chapter 2 for&#13;
to grow wealthier but not more concentrat-       details); panel c: WDR 2009 team (see chapter 3 for deta ils).&#13;
ed-about when they enter the ranks of&#13;
high-income countries. There are no rea-&#13;
sons to expect greatly different patterns&#13;
today (see chapter 2).&#13;
&amp;#12;10   WORLD DEVELOPMENT REPORT 2009&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        International concentration (in some              ging and leading areas of a country as it&#13;
     world regions and leading countries) con-            grows through low and lower-middle&#13;
     tinues for a while. A similar concentration          incomes, the same range of per capita&#13;
     of economic mass has occurred internation-           incomes needed for territorial concentra-&#13;
     ally. Today, a quarter of the world's GDP            tion to increase. And global divergence&#13;
     can fit into an area the size of Cameroon,           in wages and wealth appears to go on&#13;
     and a half into one the size of Algeria. In          for much longer. East Asia saw per capita&#13;
     1980 the shares of the EU15, North Amer-             incomes diverge between 1950 and 1970&#13;
     ica, and East Asia added up to 70 percent;           as Japan pulled ahead. Then, Japan's pros-&#13;
     in 2000 the sum was 83 percent. 5 Within             perity spilled over into the neighborhood,&#13;
     these regions, economic activity became              and incomes converged as countries in&#13;
     more concentrated in a few countries over            the region that integrated internationally&#13;
     time before it became more dispersed. The            prospered. Among the countries of West&#13;
     shares of France, Germany, and the United            Asia, by contrast, there was no divergence&#13;
     Kingdom in the EU15 regional GDP rose to             in incomes-nor was there rapid growth.&#13;
     about two-thirds by 1940, before fal ling to&#13;
     about ha lf today. In East Asia, the share of         Convergence in living standards, like con-&#13;
     Japan in the region's GDP rose to 83 percent      centration of economic activity, takes place&#13;
     in 1975 and then fell to 62 percent by 2000.      faster at the local geographic scale and slow-&#13;
         There is no reason to expect that, when       est at the international. But this happens only&#13;
     they prosper, other parts of the world will not   in prosperous neighborhoods. Even in such&#13;
     experience the same patterns-a rising con-        places, some measures of living standards&#13;
     centration in some countries, before over-        (such as per capita consumption, income,&#13;
     flowing to their neighbors (see chapter 3).       or earnings) take a long time to converge,&#13;
                                                       sometimes even with an initial divergence&#13;
     Living standards diverge before                   (see figure 2). For others, such as education&#13;
     converging                                        and health indicators, it can be quicker.&#13;
     As incomes increase, living standards con-           Locally, convergence in basic living stan-&#13;
     verge between places where economic mass          dards sets in early. Urban-to-rural gaps in&#13;
     has concentrated and where it has not, but        consumption levels rise until countries reach&#13;
     not before diverging.                             upper-middle-income levels (see figure 2) .&#13;
                                                       But they fall soon after, and become small&#13;
     â&#128;¢ Essential household consumption converges       even before they get to high-income levels of&#13;
       soonest. Rural-urban gaps in essential          around $10,000 per capita. Access to water&#13;
       household consumption diminish quite            and sanitation in urban areas is more than&#13;
       rapidly. Even for countries that have urban     25 percent higher in urban areas for the less&#13;
       shares of about 50 to 60 percent, these dif-    urbanized countries. For countries with&#13;
       ferences can be small. Area differences in      urbanization rates of about 50 percent, such&#13;
       poverty rates are more persistent, inter-       as Algeria, Colombia, and South Africa, the&#13;
       national differences even more so. But as       disparity in access is about 15 percent. For&#13;
       the world has developed, these gaps have        such countries as Brazil, Chile, Gabon, and&#13;
       diminished at all geographic scales.            Jordan, the disparity is less than 10 percent.&#13;
     â&#128;¢ Access to basic public services converges           This pattern is also seen within countries.&#13;
       next. Rural-urban gaps in basic educa-          Provinces that are more prosperous and&#13;
       tion, health, drinking water, and sani-         urbanized have smaller rural-urban gaps in        '&#13;
       tation persist until countries reach            living standards. This is true even in coun-&#13;
       upper-middle incomes. But within-city           tries at low levels of income, such as China,&#13;
       d isparities in these services-most vis-        India, and the Philippines. But within highly&#13;
       ible as slums-persist well past high lev-       urbanized areas, gaps in basic living stan-&#13;
       els of urbanization and upper-middle            dards such as sanitation and schools tend to&#13;
       incomes.                                        persist. Despite the best efforts of govern-&#13;
     â&#128;¢ Wages and incomes converge last. Indeed,        ments, for example, slums mark the urban&#13;
       wages and incomes diverge between lag-          landscape in countries well after they reach&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                           Overview                                               11&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
high-income levels. It is common for one-         Figure 2      At all three geographic scales, the patterns of convergence in living standards are&#13;
                                                  similar&#13;
third of a developing city's population to live&#13;
in slums.                                                               a. Locally, first divergence, then convergence, in rural-urban gaps&#13;
&#13;
    Nationally, divergence in living stan-         Ratio of urban to rural per capita consumption&#13;
&#13;
dards happens quickly, but convergence&#13;
is slower. At early levels of income, provin-       3&#13;
                                                         â&#128;¢â&#128;¢&#13;
cial or interarea disparities in basic living&#13;
&#13;
                                                         Â·- . . ..&#13;
                                                                   â&#128;¢                                                   \&#13;
                                                            I&#13;
standards can be small. But they increase&#13;
quickly as countries grow. In low-income&#13;
Cambodia, for example, the gap between                   r~&#13;
                                                            ~&#13;
                                                                    â&#128;¢â&#128;¢.A...&#13;
                                                                            â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢&#13;
                                                                              â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢                          .~     ..        â&#128;¢   â&#128;¢â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢&#13;
leading and lagging areas in consumption                Â·.:..â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ ..Â·.'4:Â·Â·     â&#128;¢â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢                                        â&#128;¢                â&#128;¢&#13;
                                                                                                                                                    â&#128;¢&#13;
of otherwise-simi lar households is almost                â&#128;¢ &lt;4'"''"'                                                                 â&#128;¢      â&#128;¢&#13;
90 percent. In middle-income Argentina,&#13;
the gap is 50 percent; but in contemporary          1&#13;
                                                        0                                                         4                             6&#13;
Canada, it is just 20 percent. In the rapidly                                                GDP per capita (2000 US$, thou san ds)&#13;
growing East Asia n and Easte rn European&#13;
co untries, for example, these gaps have                b. Nationally, divergence, then convergence, in incomes between leading and lagging areas&#13;
increased rapidly.                                Coefficient of variation of regional wages or income&#13;
     A few countries such as Chile have been      0.6&#13;
exceptions. Between 1960 and 2000, it                                              /,,..., Sweden, 1920--1l1&#13;
experienced geographic convergence while&#13;
                                                  0.5 Sp ai n,&#13;
                                                      1860- 1975          /&#13;
                                                                               /          ',  ......&#13;
its GDP per capita more than doubled to           0.4&#13;
about $10,500. In Colombia, the ratio of&#13;
                                                  0.3&#13;
GDP of leading Bogota to lagging Choco&#13;
fe ll from 10 to 3 between 1950 and 1990.         0.2&#13;
Less exceptional is convergence in poverty,&#13;
basic health, nutrition, and education lev-       0.1&#13;
els between areas withi n countries. Fast-&#13;
growing countries everywhere have been                              2                 4                6                        10          12             14     16&#13;
able to quickly translate economic progress                                        GDP per capita (constant int'I Geary-Khamis $,thousands)&#13;
into spatial equity in these more basic liv-&#13;
ing standards.                                                  c. Internationally, divergence, then convergence-but only in growing regions&#13;
   Internationally, divergence in incomes         Coefficient of variation of GDP per capita&#13;
continues a while, and convergence                2.0&#13;
is slowest. Globa l GDP per capit a has           1.9&#13;
increased almost tenfold since 1820. Life         1.8&#13;
expectancy has doubled. Literacy rates have       1.7&#13;
increased from less than 20 to more than&#13;
                                                  1.6&#13;
80 percent. But these gains have not been&#13;
                                                  1.5&#13;
shared equally. Europe and its offshoots-&#13;
Australia, Canada, New Zea land, and the          1.4&#13;
United States-and more lately Japan and           1.3&#13;
its neighbors have seen enormous increases        1.2&#13;
in income and living standards.                     1950                1960                1970                1980                 1990           2000        2010&#13;
                                                                                                                Year&#13;
    For incomes, the convergence has hap-&#13;
                                                  Source: Panel a: WDR 2009 team estimates from more than 120 household surveys for more than 75 cou ntries;&#13;
pened only in the fastest-growing regions         Panel b: WDR 2009 team (see chapter 2); Pane l c: WDR 2009 team (see chapter 3).&#13;
of the world . The pattern has been uneven&#13;
within these countries-a few countries&#13;
lead, resulting in divergence within the          these regions have been falling behind&#13;
neighborhood, and then growth appears             Europe, the Europ ean offshoots, and&#13;
to spi ll over into their neighbors. In other     Japan. The importance of neighborhoods&#13;
regions such as Western Asia, there is            is shown most graphically by a compari-&#13;
no divergence-cold comfort because                son of the sout hern cone nations of Latin&#13;
&amp;#12;12   WORLD DEVELOPMENT REPORT 2009&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     America-Argentina, Brazil, Chile, and            and persist for longer in today's develop-&#13;
     Uruguay-with Italy, Portugal, and Spain          ing countries. Not all parts of a country&#13;
     in southern Europe. Between 1950 and             are suited for accessing world markets, and&#13;
     2006, convergence within southern Europe         coastal and economically dense places do&#13;
     took place at 1 percent per year, but in South   better. China's GDP per capita in 2007 was&#13;
     America at just 0.3 percent.                     the same as that of Britain in 1911. Shang-&#13;
         In contrast to incomes, global inequal-      hai, China's leading area, today has a GDP&#13;
     ity in access to basic living standards-life     per capita the same as Britain in 1988, while&#13;
     expectancy and education-has been fall-          lagging Guizhou is closer to Britain in 1930.&#13;
     ing since 1930. These improvements have          China's size, the openness of coastal China&#13;
     picked up pace since 1960 and have been          to world trade, and Shanghai's location are&#13;
     shared across all regions.                       the reasons.&#13;
                                                          More borders. While markets are becom-&#13;
     The world is different today,                    ing more international because of better&#13;
     but the past provides useful lessons             transport and communications, the world&#13;
     The general patterns of concentration and        has become more politically fragmented.&#13;
     convergence are likely to remain the same        In 1900 there were about 100 international&#13;
     for today's developing countries as they         borders (see figure 3, panel c). Today, there&#13;
     were for early developers. But there are         are more than 600, as nations in Asia and&#13;
     some differences because of reasons that         Africa gained independence from Euro-&#13;
     are technological and political.                 pean colonizers, and the Soviet Union and&#13;
        Bigger cities. Thanks to better medicine      other communist countries broke up into&#13;
     and transport, the world is now more pop-        smaller nations. The fragmentation of the&#13;
     ulated and cities are much larger. Between       world into more nations means smaller&#13;
     1985 and 2005, the urban population in           domestic markets. But at the same time, the&#13;
     developing countries grew by more than           potential for accessing foreign markets has&#13;
     8.3 million a year, almost three times the       been growing. In any case, thinner borders&#13;
     annual increase of 3 million for today's         between countries now bring greater pay-&#13;
     high-income countries between 1880 and           offs for producers and workers.&#13;
     1900, when their incomes were comparable.            Do such differences in technology mean&#13;
     If China and India are excluded, though ,        that the past provides no lessons? Are cit-&#13;
     the annual increase is less than 4.5 million,    ies in developing countries too large, and&#13;
     about 50 percent more than a century ago.        would these countries be better off if&#13;
     The big difference is that the world 's larg-    urbanization were slowed? Should today's&#13;
     est cities are today much larger. London         developing countries be more concerned&#13;
     had fewer than 7 million people in 1900;         about regional disparities in production&#13;
     the largest city among low-income coun-          and income than developed countries were&#13;
     tries today (Mumbai) is three times that         at a comparable stage of development? Is it&#13;
     size. So is Mexico City, the largest city in     easier today for all developing countries to&#13;
     middle-income countries. The average size        access globa l markets and offset the disad-&#13;
     of the world 's largest 100 cities has grown     vantages associated with greater fragmenta-&#13;
     to almost 10 times their size in 1900 (see       tion? This Report shows why the answer to&#13;
     figure 3, panel a), and almost two-thirds of     all these questions is no.&#13;
     these cities are in developing countries.&#13;
         Wider markets. Because of advances in        Markets shape the economic&#13;
     communications and transport technol-            landscape&#13;
     ogy, the notion of markets is more global.       Rising densities of human settlements,&#13;
     Global trade as a share of production is now     migrations of workers and entrep reneurs to&#13;
     more than 25 percent, almost five times          shorten the distance to markets, and lower&#13;
     more than in 1900 (see figure 3, panel b).       divisions caused by differences in curren-&#13;
     The openness to trade and capital flows          cies and conventions between countries are&#13;
     that makes markets more global also makes        central to successful economic develop-&#13;
     subnational disparities in income larger         ment. The spatial transformations along&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                  Overview    13&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 3     Later developers face a different world         changing the econom ic landscape of today's&#13;
                     a. Cities are more populous             most success ful developing countries, in&#13;
Millions of people, world's largest cities                   ways similar in scope and speed. Growing&#13;
7.0                                                          cities, mobile people, and vigorous trade&#13;
                                                       6.3&#13;
6.0                                                          have been the cata lysts for progress in the&#13;
5.0&#13;
                                                             developed world over the last two centuries.&#13;
                                                             Now these forces are powering the develop-&#13;
4.0&#13;
                                                             ing world's most dynamic places.&#13;
3.0&#13;
                                        2.0                  The realm of "agglomeration&#13;
2.0&#13;
                                                                     . "&#13;
&#13;
       - â&#128;¢ I&#13;
                                                             economies&#13;
1.0                       0.7&#13;
           0.2                                               A trip on National Highway 321 east from&#13;
  0&#13;
           1820          1900          1950           2000   Chengdu in Sichuan province to Shenzhen&#13;
                                Year                         in Guangdong is a journey through eco -&#13;
                  b. Markets are more international          nomic development. Migrating workers&#13;
 Global trade as share of global GDP(%)                      who travel these highways often leave their&#13;
 30&#13;
                                                             famil ies behind. But they also help their&#13;
                                                       26&#13;
 25                                                          families escape poverty and propel China&#13;
                                                             through the ranks of middle-income coun-&#13;
 20&#13;
                                                             tries. As they travel eastward, they leave&#13;
 15                                                          an agrarian realm in wh ich they receive&#13;
                                        12&#13;
                                                             few benefits from working in proximity&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       I&#13;
 10&#13;
                           6                                 to others. Instead, they enter the realm of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  0&#13;
       -1820&#13;
                        I1900&#13;
                                Year&#13;
                                       1950&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                 c. But the world is more fragmented&#13;
                                                      2000&#13;
                                                             "agglomeration economies," in wh ich being&#13;
                                                             near other people produces huge benefits.&#13;
                                                                 Shenzhen attracts young workers-90&#13;
                                                             percent of its 8 million residents are of&#13;
                                                             working age . It specializes in electronic&#13;
Number of borders                                            goods. But it makes them in enormous&#13;
700&#13;
                                                       600&#13;
                                                             quantities. In 2006 its exports exceeded&#13;
600                                                          India's, making its seaport the fourth busi-&#13;
500                                                          est in the world. Propelled by the forces of&#13;
400                                                          agglomeration, migration, and specializa-&#13;
                                                             tion, and helped by its nearness to Hong&#13;
300&#13;
                                       200&#13;
                                                             Kong, China, Shenzhen has grown the fast-&#13;
200                                                          est of all cities in China since 1979, when it&#13;
100&#13;
&#13;
  0&#13;
       â&#128;¢&#13;
           75&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        1820&#13;
                        II&#13;
                          104&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                         1900&#13;
                                Year&#13;
                                       I&#13;
                                       1950           2000&#13;
                                                             was designated a special economic zone.&#13;
                                                                 This story is being replayed in India. In&#13;
                                                             1990 Sriperumbudur was known mostly as&#13;
                                                             the place where Prime Minister Rajiv Gan-&#13;
Source: WDR 2009 team.&#13;
                                                             dhi was assassinated. In 2006 his widow,&#13;
                                                             Son ia Ga ndhi , watched as Nokia's tele-&#13;
these three dimensions-density, distance,                    phone plant churned out its 20-millionth&#13;
and division-have been most noticeable                       hand set. 6 The plant had begun produc-&#13;
in Japan, North America, and Western                         tion just earl ier that year. With neither&#13;
Europe. Fast and frequent movements of                       Shenzhen's favored administrative status&#13;
people and products have helped North                        nor its infrastructure, Sriperumbudur&#13;
America, Western Europe, and Northeast                       may be on its way to becoming a national,&#13;
Asia account for about three-fourths of                      perhaps even regional, hub for electronic&#13;
global production with less than a sixth of                  goods. The key is the town's proximity to&#13;
the world's people.                                          Chennai, just as Shenzhen's proximity to&#13;
   The same market forces of agglomera-                      Hong Kong, China, was instrumental in&#13;
tion, migration, and specialization are                      its growth.&#13;
&amp;#12;14                                          WORLD DEVELOPMENT REPORT 2009&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                In 1965, when independence was thrust        first three chapters of the most influential&#13;
                                            on Singapore, it was not near any prosper-       economics text ever written, Adam Smith's&#13;
                                            ous or peaceful place. Instead, it lay between   The Wealth of Nations.&#13;
                                            Malaysia and Indonesia, two poor countries           The economies of scale emphasized by&#13;
                                            that had been ravaged by war between colo-       Smith can be categorized into three types-&#13;
                                            nizers. Three-quarters of Singapore's popu-      those exclusive to firms, those shared by&#13;
                                            lation lived in tenements . By 1980 it had       firms in the same industry and location,&#13;
                                            industrialized, specializing in electronics,     and those more generally available to pro-&#13;
                                            much as Shenzhen is doing now. By 1986 it        ducers in a larger urban area.&#13;
                                            was the world's busiest container port and&#13;
                                                                                             â&#128;¢ With fewer than 17,000 people, Sriper-&#13;
                                            Southeast Asia's financial hub. Along the&#13;
                                                                                               umbudur was large enough for Hyun-&#13;
                                            way, by instituting land markets, building&#13;
                                                                                               dai to set up a big plant there in 1999.&#13;
                                            efficient transport infrastructure, and inter-&#13;
                                                                                               By 2006 the town had helped Hyundai&#13;
                                            vening to improve housing, it cleaned up its&#13;
                                                                                               produce its millionth automobile. Basic&#13;
                                            slums. Prosperity spilled over into neighbor-&#13;
                                                                                               education and health services, proximity&#13;
                                            ing Malaysia. Malaysia's manufacturing-led&#13;
                                                                                               to a port, and basic infrastructure were&#13;
                                            prosperity in turn helped more than 2 mil-&#13;
                                                                                               all it needed to facilitate plant-level scale&#13;
                                            lion Indonesians who streamed in to fill jobs&#13;
                                                                                               economies. The evidence is that internal&#13;
                                            in construction and services. Singapore's&#13;
                                                                                               scale economies are high in such heavy&#13;
                                            businessmen jet around Asia, fueling growth&#13;
                                                                                               industries as shipbuilding, and low in&#13;
                                            in places farther than Shenzhen and Sriper-&#13;
                                                                                               such light industries as garments. The&#13;
                                            umbudur. The "little red dot" on a map-as&#13;
                                                                                               town has enough workers to enable&#13;
                                            reportedly derided by a neighboring pres-&#13;
                                                                                               matching workers and jobs in big plants.&#13;
                                            ident7-has transformed itself, integrated&#13;
                                                                                               So towns like Sriperumbudur are large&#13;
                                            its neighborhood, and overtaken Britain, its&#13;
                                                                                               enough to facilitate internal economies.&#13;
                                            former colonizer (see map 2).&#13;
                                                Singapore, Shenzhen, and Sriperum-           â&#128;¢ Shenzhen Special Economic Region-&#13;
                                            budur show how scale economies in pro-             with an area of just 300 square kilometers&#13;
                                            duction, movements of labor and capital,           but a population of almost 3 million-is&#13;
                                            and falling transport costs interact to pro-       home to a bustling electronics industry.&#13;
                                            duce rapid economic growth in cities and           With a ready supply of skilled and semi-&#13;
                                            countries both large and small. These are          skilled yo ung workers, the area is invest-&#13;
                                            the engine of any economy, with a role so          ing in better education and research&#13;
                                            fundamental in prosperity and poverty              facilities to ensure that the city supplies&#13;
                                            reduction that they are the subject of the         what the industry needs. Its port ships in&#13;
                                                                                               intermediate inputs and ships out final&#13;
                                                                                               products. It shares expensive facilities,&#13;
Map 2      Settlements of varying size facilitate different scale economies                    such as top-notch container ports and&#13;
                                                                                               convention centers, and matches work-&#13;
                                                                                               ers to the growing number of jobs as&#13;
                                                                                               firms rapidly expand their operations.&#13;
                                                                                               Proximity to Hong Kong, China, pro-&#13;
                                                                                               vides access to finance, though Shenzhen&#13;
                                                                                               is home to a rapidly expanding financial&#13;
     Ban   loreâ&#128;¢                                                                               sector. And competition for customers&#13;
                                           .~&#13;
                       Chennai&#13;
                      Sriperumbudur                                                            among the multiple suppliers of inputs&#13;
                                           â&#128;¢                                                   produces cost savings. The area excels in&#13;
                                                                                               providing, in economic jargon, localiza-&#13;
                                                                                               tion economies.&#13;
                                                                                             â&#128;¢ Singapore has passed through these&#13;
                                                                                               stages and is now one of the world's&#13;
                                                                                               top centers of commerce. By providing&#13;
Source: WOR 2009 team .                                                                        a stable economic environment, excel-&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                      Overview    15&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   lent transport links, livability, and effi-   of all inputs to production-land-must&#13;
   cient finance, it provides services to the    become mobile between uses. Access to&#13;
   entire Asia-Pacific region. These ser-        oceans and rivers might be the reason a&#13;
   vices are used by a wide range of indus-      place is settled, but the nimbleness of its&#13;
   tries, from shipping to manufacturing,        land markets will largely determine how&#13;
   to education, and to finance, insurance,      much it will grow. Governments may not be&#13;
   and real estate. They thrive on eco-          good at picking places that will prosper. But&#13;
   nomic density. With fewer than 5 mil-         how well they institute regulations, build&#13;
   lion people packed into less than 700         infrastructure, and intervene to make land&#13;
   square kilometers of space, Singapore         use efficient wil 1decide the pace of prosper-&#13;
   is the world's most densely populated         ity for the entire neighborhood.&#13;
   country. In 2006 its exports of $300              Depending on what type of agglomera-&#13;
   billion approached those of the Russian       tion economies they deliver, places can be&#13;
   Federation, which has more than 16            large or small. Function is far more impor-&#13;
   million square kilometers. Singapore's        tant than size. But locating farther away&#13;
   diversity facilitates sharing, matching,      from economic density generally reduces&#13;
   and learning, providing what econo-           productivity. Doubling this distance in&#13;
   mists call urbanization economies.            Brazil apparently reduces productivity by&#13;
                                                 15 percent and profits by 6 percent. Better&#13;
    In most countries, such towns and cit-       infrastructure reduces economic distance.&#13;
ies coexist. Brazil's Rio de Janeiro state has   But in a developing country, the most nat-&#13;
about 14.5 million people. Volta Redonda,        ural way for workers and entrepreneurs to&#13;
not too far from Rio city, originally supplied   close this distance is to move closer.&#13;
goods and services just to meet the needs of&#13;
CSN, the largest steel plant in Latin Amer-      Migrating to profit from proximity&#13;
ica. Duque de Caixas, about 15 kilometers        Agglomeration economies attract people&#13;
from Rio, meets the needs of an industry         and finance. Today, capital tends to move&#13;
producing petrochemicals. And the diversi-       quickly over long distances to exploit&#13;
fied Rio de Janeiro metropolis, with about       opportunities for profit. People also move,&#13;
6 million people, supplies financial services    but they move more quickly to nearby&#13;
to settlements that surround it. And with        agglomerations than to those far away.&#13;
other metropolises like Sao Paulo, Rio con-      Once plants and people come to a place,&#13;
nects Brazil to the rest of Latin America and    others follow.&#13;
the world. The pattern is so familiar that it&#13;
is almost a law of urban economics.              â&#128;¢ Locally, the move toward density is quick&#13;
    The functions and fortunes of settle-          in fast-growing economies, manifest&#13;
ments are linked. Industrialized places are        in a rapid rural-urban migration that&#13;
different from their agrarian predecessors         accompanies the shift from agriculture to&#13;
not just because they are more concentrated        industry. As the Republic of Korea grew&#13;
but also because they are more specialized.        between 1970 and 1995, the urban share&#13;
The largest cities may be well suited for          of population quadrupled to 82 percent,&#13;
startup enterprises; the smaller ones may be       with migration accounting for more than&#13;
better suited for those more established. In       half the increase in the 1960s and 1970s.&#13;
agriculture, sowing and reaping must hap-        â&#128;¢ Nationally, workers move to reduce dis-&#13;
pen in the same place. Not so for industry         tance to markets in parts that are pros-&#13;
and business services. Falling transport and       pering. About 3 million people moved&#13;
communications costs allow firms to spa-           in the second half of the 1990s from&#13;
tially separate sowing and reaping. Prod-          the lagging Indian states of Bihar and&#13;
ucts may be designed and financed in large         Uttar Pradesh to leading Maharashtra&#13;
cities-and produced in small towns.                and prosperous Punjab (see map 5). In&#13;
    As fi rms adjust to changing market con-       Vietnam, a much smaller country, more&#13;
ditions, places have to perform different          than 4 million people migrated inter-&#13;
functio ns or risk decay. The most immobile        nally during the same period.&#13;
&amp;#12;16   WOR L D DEVELOPM ENT RE PORT 2 009&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     â&#128;¢ Intern ationally, regional migration is                              among the top 10 sending countries. But&#13;
       a big part of labor mobility. M igration                             interregional migration is sluggish. Fewer&#13;
       am ong neighbors is considerable. Cote                               than 200 million of the world's 6.7 billion&#13;
       d 'Ivoire, India, and the Islamic Republic                           people live o utside their region of birth.&#13;
       of Iran have been among the top desti-                               And just 2 million people m ove from&#13;
       nation s fo r their neighbors. Germ a ny,                            poorer countries to the developed ever y&#13;
       Italy, and the United Kingdom still rank                             yea r, half of them to the United States.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Map 3 Migrating to reduce distance to density: Despite the obstacles, Chinese workers have migrated in the&#13;
     millions&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
             Migration tot al s&#13;
                                               Migrati on from&#13;
                                               western region to&#13;
        2,000,000&#13;
                                               coastal region&#13;
        1,000,000 _ _ _,..           ---!&gt;..... Migrati on from&#13;
                                     - - , r central region to&#13;
          500,000   ==-...&#13;
                        ~                      coastal region&#13;
          250,000 ===--~&#13;
          100,000---                 ==&gt;       Migration within th e&#13;
                                               coastal region&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                               ....&#13;
                                                                                                       ,,_,J&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                        CHINA&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Source: Hu ang and Luo 2008, using data from the population census of China .&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                                      Overview                                                17&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   This sum is not likely to increase, even                     Map 4 Migrating to reduce distance to density: Brazil's young workers move in thousands to&#13;
                                                                get closer to economic density&#13;
though the gains from greater migration&#13;
from developing to developed countries are&#13;
considerable. 8 International migrat ion has&#13;
been high in the past: fully 20 percent of                                                                                                                  BRAZIL&#13;
Europeans emigrated to new lands in the&#13;
Americas, Australia, and South Africa.&#13;
Today, these movements have slowed. Just&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                       -&#13;
500,000 Chinese emigrated abroad in 2005.                                                            N 0 RTH&#13;
But internal migration has picked up in t he&#13;
developing world. More than 150 million&#13;
people moved internally in China despite&#13;
restrictions (see map 3). In Brazil's high-                                                           , ---&#13;
growth years during the 1960s and 1970s,                                                              1&#13;
almost 40 million people left the coun-&#13;
tryside for cities; even today, young work-&#13;
ers migrate in large numbers (see map 4) .&#13;
Vigorous internal migration is not new.&#13;
Between 1820 and 2000 per capita incomes&#13;
in the United States multiplied 25-fo ld,&#13;
and Americans earned the reputation of&#13;
                                                                                    Population that did not migrate&#13;
being among the most footloose of people.&#13;
In Japan internal migration peaked in the                                           â&#128;¢    1991   0   2000_ 300,000&#13;
1960s, as it grew to become the world's                                                                   - 200,000                                   1991    &lt;::=   2000&#13;
second-largest economy.                                                                                   - 100,000                                            - - - - Â· 15,000&#13;
   Despite aggressive area development                                                                                                                            - --10,000&#13;
                                                                                                          -- 30,000&#13;
policies, 1.7 million people-more women                                                                                                                              -- 5,000&#13;
than men-have left East Germany for&#13;
the West, helping to make incomes more&#13;
                                                                                                                l                                                      - 2,000&#13;
&#13;
                                                                Source: WDR 2009 team, based on census data from the lnstituto Brasileiro de Geografia e Estatistica.&#13;
equa l. Since the transition to market&#13;
economies, firms and people have picked&#13;
places better suited for production. More&#13;
than a million people-about 12 percent of&#13;
&#13;
Map 5 Migrating to reduce distance to density: Migration in India has been less frenetic&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  INDIA                     ' '"''"" I Number of withi n-state migrants                  Migration totals&#13;
                                                                                                                                        . . 1,000,000         . . . 500,000&#13;
                                                                                                                                        -      100,000        -      50,000&#13;
&#13;
Source:WDR 2009 team, based on census data from the Census of India .&#13;
&amp;#12;18   WORLD DEVELOPMENT REPORT 2009&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     residents-have left Siberia and the Russian      should facilitate labor mobility. For&#13;
     North and Far East for the western parts of      decades since independence, India treated&#13;
     Russia.                                          its 40 million emigrants as "not required&#13;
         West Africa has sustained regional labor     Indians." Encouraged by a change in atti-&#13;
     mobility through institutional coopera-          tude since the 1990s, expatriate Indians are&#13;
     tion. But independent Africa is generally        pulling distant places like Bangalore and&#13;
     less integrated. Africans-especially the         Hyderabad closer to world markets, just as&#13;
     most skilled-have been leaving the conti-        the overseas Chinese did for Shanghai and&#13;
     nent, seeking and getting higher rewards in      Guangzhou more than a decade earlier.&#13;
     the North. Other parts of the world show         Falling costs of transport and communica-&#13;
     how to deal with this brain drain. Educated      tions have helped greatly.&#13;
     workers will be pulled toward places where&#13;
     other skilled people agglomerate. This is        Specializing and trading as transport&#13;
     beneficial for both places. But when people      costs fall&#13;
     are pushed out by the lack of security or        Transport and communication costs have&#13;
     basic services, migration is beneficial for      indeed fallen rapidly over the last century,&#13;
     the migrant but not always for the nation.       especially in the last 50 years. Since the&#13;
     Pull migration is better than push, but both     1970s, railroad freight costs are down by&#13;
     are hard to stop or slow. Policy makers are      half. Road transport costs, despite higher&#13;
     realizing that the challenge is not how to       energy and wage costs, are down by about&#13;
     keep people from moving, but how to keep         40 percent. For worldwide air freight, the&#13;
     them from moving for the wrong reasons.          price has fallen to about 6 percent of its 1955&#13;
         China illustrates the benefits. Except for   level. The price for tramp shipping services&#13;
     a brief period during the Cultural Revolu-       is half that in 1960. A three-minute phone&#13;
     tion, China has treated its diaspora well,       call from New York to London was almost&#13;
     according them both rights and respect. 9        $300 in 1931. Today, the same call can be&#13;
     Internally, its policies have gone back and      made for just a few cents.&#13;
     forth, but now they are shifting from trying         With falling domestic transport costs,&#13;
     to discourage people from moving to deliv-       economic production should have become&#13;
     ering basic services to people wherever they     more evenly spread within countries. With&#13;
     live. The policies are paying dividends. As      lower costs of transporting and commu-&#13;
     Chinese migrants are moving to the coast         nicating internationally, countries should&#13;
     by the million, many of the 57 million           have traded more with distant partners.&#13;
     overseas Chinese are bringing finance and        What happened was the opposite. Falling&#13;
     expertise back to some of the same places.       transport costs have coincided with greater&#13;
     Internal and international migrants are          economic concentration within countries.&#13;
     coming together in a way that is not acci-       And while countries now trade more with&#13;
     dental. The willingness of the Chinese to        everyone-exports as a share of world pro-&#13;
     move-leaving the country for other parts         duction quadrupled to 25 percent over the&#13;
     of the world to escape war and squalor in the    last three decades-trade with neighbors&#13;
     first part of the twentieth century and then     became even more important.&#13;
     bringing finance and know-how to coastal             Why did this happen? The answer lies in&#13;
     China during the last quarter-promises           the growing importance of scale economies&#13;
     to bring to southeast China a "reversal of       in production and transport (see chapter&#13;
     fortune" rivaling the U.S. Northeast (see        6). As transport costs have fallen, they have&#13;
     "Geography in Motion: Overcoming Dis-            allowed greater specialization and radically&#13;
     tance in North America").                        altered the location of firms and the nature&#13;
         Countries do not prosper without             of trade. With high transport costs, firms&#13;
     mobile people. Indeed, the ability of people     had to be near consumers. But as transport&#13;
     to move seems to be a good gauge of their        costs fall, they can avail of internal, local,&#13;
     economic potential, and the willingness to       and urban economies of scale, and trans-&#13;
     migrate appears to be a measure of their         port the product to consumers. Internation-&#13;
     desire for advancement. Governments              ally, the same thing. With high transport&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                         Overview                                               19&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
costs, England imported only what it could      Figure 4 Intraindustry trade is high in North America, Western Europe, Oceania, and East Asia&#13;
not grow or produce at reasonable cost-&#13;
spices from India and beef from Argentina                              Southern Africa ~&#13;
&#13;
in exchange for British textiles and china.                            Western Africa                                                    1962&#13;
                                                                                                                                       â&#128;¢ 1975&#13;
As transport costs fell, it imported more                                Central Africa                                                â&#128;¢ 1990&#13;
spices and beef. But it also traded more with                                                                                          â&#128;¢ 2006&#13;
                                                                       Northern Africa&#13;
France and Germany-Scotch whisky for&#13;
French wine, English ale for German beer.           Central Asia, Caucasus &amp; Turkey ~&#13;
&#13;
Trade to fulfill basic needs was joined and                             Eastern Africa&#13;
soon overtaken by trade to satisfy a variety                             Western Asia&#13;
of wants.&#13;
                                                                            South Asia&#13;
   Falling costs of transportation and com-&#13;
munication have made the world smaller.&#13;
But they have also made economic activity&#13;
more geographically concentrated.&#13;
&#13;
â&#128;¢ Locally, with falling costs of commut-&#13;
  ing and a greater potential for exploit-&#13;
  ing scale economies, towns and cities can&#13;
                                                                      Western Europe&#13;
  grow bigger and denser.&#13;
â&#128;¢ Nationally, as leading and lagging areas                  Australia &amp; New Zealand       ~~~~~~---Â·â&#128;¢â&#128;¢â&#128;¢--&#13;
  within countries are connected through                                North America      _   ,   -~o&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                              _,_,.._,~,,&#13;
                                                                                                           '   ~&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                   '     ~&#13;
                                                                                                                             M   &lt;"       '.f"'.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  better modes of transport, production                                                   0         0.1            0.2            03    0.4        0.5   0.6   0.7&#13;
  is more concentrated in the more eco-                                                              Grubel-Lloyd Index, 3-digit, intraregiona l trade&#13;
  nomically dense areas to take advantage       Source: Brulhart 2008 for this Report.&#13;
  of agglomeration economies.                   Note: The Grubel-Lloyd Index is the fraction of total trade that is accounted for by intraindustry trade .&#13;
&#13;
â&#128;¢ Internationally, countries that have&#13;
  lowered the costs of transport more           world, explaining why the friction of bor-&#13;
  have benefited most from greater trade.       ders on trade has fallen. Aided by a deep-&#13;
  Greater specialization has made these         ening integration, the intraregiona l share&#13;
  countries more competitive still, con-        of trade in the EU has risen above 60 per-&#13;
  centrating trade and wealth in a few          cent (see "Geography in Motion: Overcom-&#13;
  parts of the world.                           ing Division in Western Europe"). In East&#13;
                                                Asia, the fastest-growing region, the share of&#13;
   Scale economies are evident in the trans-    regional trade is now more than 55 percent&#13;
port sector, too. More trade means lower        (see "Geography in Motion: Distance and&#13;
costs of transportation, which in turn          Division in East Asia").&#13;
means more trade. This is especially true           Development in a world of greater spe-&#13;
for intraindustry trade, which has been the     cialization and concentration is even more&#13;
most rapidly growing part of international      challenging. Developing countries have&#13;
trade during the last half-century. Since       higher transport costs and small markets,&#13;
1960 the share of intraindustry trade in the    which do not support specialization. But&#13;
world's total has doubled from 27 percent       several countries-mainly in East Asia-&#13;
to 54 percent. Within-region intraindustry      have shown that these markets are acces-&#13;
trade is low in most regions, and high in a     sible for low-income countries. The answer&#13;
few. It is close to zero for Central Africa,    lies in the fastest-growing component of&#13;
Central Asia, East Africa, Northern Africa,     intraindustry trade: trade in "intermediate&#13;
South Asia, and Southern Africa . It is high-   inputs" of production (see box 3).&#13;
est for Australia, East Asia, New Zealand,          In agriculture, industry, and services,&#13;
North America, and Western Europe (see          the potential for fragmenting production&#13;
figure 4).                                      is almost without limit. Thailand may not&#13;
   Regional cooperation has advanced            be able to make a television set better than&#13;
much faster and further in these parts of the   Japan, but it could make parts of televisions&#13;
&amp;#12;20                                                  WORLD DEVELOPMENT R EPORT 2009&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     eox    3     Intraindustry trade and intermediate inputs&#13;
     More than half of world trade today is                    final and intermediate goods, with both          est increase is in food and live animals.&#13;
     intraindustry trade, with industries clas-                having increased considerably over the           Consumers like variety for farm produce,&#13;
     sified in 177 (3-digit) categories, up from               last SO years. This rise in intraindustry        and that means profit in trade between&#13;
     about a quarter in 1962. So countries                     trade is not just for manufacturing. Intra-      two countr ies th at rai se similar food and&#13;
     are becoming more simi lar in their eco-                  industry trade in machines and transport         animals (see figure at left).&#13;
     nomic structures. This trade consists of                  equipment is the highest, but the larg-             But the largest rise is for intermediate&#13;
                                                                                                                inputs-the produced means of produc-&#13;
     Intraindustry trade has risen for primary, intermediate, and final goods                                   tion. Marginal intraindustry trade- a&#13;
                                                                                                                rel iable measure of change- is highest&#13;
     Grubel-Lloyd Index, 3-digit                                                                                in intermediate inputs. This is not j ust for&#13;
     0.6                                                                                                        manufacturing. Agriculture needs inputs,&#13;
                                                                                                                too. And falling communications costs&#13;
     0.5                                                                                                        have resulted in greater fragmentation&#13;
                                                                                                                of services into "components," supplied&#13;
                                                                                                                to final con sumers from different parts of&#13;
     0.4                                                                                                        the world .&#13;
                                                                                                                   Trade in intermediate goods is more&#13;
                                                                                                                sensitive to transport costs than is trade&#13;
     0.3&#13;
                                                                                                                in final goods. Con sider the follo w ing&#13;
                                                                                                                illustration: if intermediate inputs are&#13;
     0.2                                                                                                        two-third s of the value added for a good,&#13;
                                                                                                                a 5-percent increase in tran sport costs&#13;
                                                                                                                can mean the equivalent of a SO -percent&#13;
     0.1&#13;
                                                                                                                ta x. Little wonder that intermediate&#13;
                                                                                                                goods trade has increased fastest in parts&#13;
       0                                                                                                        of the world that have reduced trade and&#13;
       1962       1966      1970      1974       1978   1982      1986   1990   1994   1998    2002    2006&#13;
                                                                                                                transport costs the most.&#13;
                                                           Year&#13;
     Source: Briilhart 2008, fo r this Report.                                                                  Source: WDR 2009 tea m.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                   equally well and much cheaper. Anchored                    tra nsport costs have occupied the inte rest&#13;
                                                   by China and Japan, countries in East Asia                 of researchers (see box 4).&#13;
                                                   have developed production networks that                        Their insights should cha nge what to&#13;
                                                   trade intermed iate goods back and fo rth .                expect fro m the ma rkets. They should also&#13;
                                                   By specia lizing in a small part of the pro-               info rm what govern ments ca n do to pro-&#13;
                                                   duction chain , they have broken into thi s                mote the geographic transformations nec-&#13;
                                                   most lucrative and fas test-growing compo-                 essary for development.&#13;
                                                   nent of trade in manufactures.&#13;
                                                        Co untries in oth er reg ions ca n also               Putting development in place&#13;
                                                   benefit from the grow ing trade in inter-                  Prosperity will not come to every place at&#13;
                                                   mediate goods. The key fo r most is m ak-                  once, but no pl ace should remain mired in&#13;
                                                   ing a concerted effort to lower t he costs of              poverty. With good policies, the co ncen -&#13;
                                                   t ra nsport. Thi s mea ns more co ncen tra-                tration of economic activity and the con-&#13;
                                                   tion within developing co untr ies, but- by                vergence of liv ing standards can happen&#13;
                                                   allowing them to specialize at earlier stages              together. The challenge for governments is&#13;
                                                   of develop ment and exploit economies of                   to allow-even encourage- "unbalanced "&#13;
                                                   scale-it wi ll help them converge to the                   economic growth, and yet ensure inclusive&#13;
                                                   incomes and living stand ards in the devel-                development. They can do this th ro ugh&#13;
                                                   oped world. Over th e last two decades,                    econom ic integ ratio n-by bringing lag-&#13;
                                                   such interac tions between sca le eco no-                  ging and leading places closer in economic&#13;
                                                   m ies, mobility of capita l and labor, and                 terms.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                        Overview                                           21&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   sox   4    New insights from a generation of analysis&#13;
   Researc hers have been t akin g a fres h           thi ck in put market s, but not fo r "urban-         Falling transport costs increase trade&#13;
   look at industri al org anization, eco-            izati on" economies-especially th ose              more with neighboring, not distant,&#13;
   nomic growth, intern at ion al t ra de, and        invol ving knowl edge spill overs-gener-           countries. With a decline in transport costs,&#13;
   economi c geog raphy, having incorpo-              at ed mai nly by larg e cities (see chapter 4).    countries should trade more with countries&#13;
   rated th e effects of sca le economies in             Th e implicatio n: policy makers should         that are farth er away. But trade has become&#13;
   produc t io n. Th e results ca n be surp ris-      foc us on th e fun ct ions of citi es.             more localized than globalized. Countries&#13;
   ing for th ose sch oole d in co nventi onal          Human capital moves to where it is               t rade more with countries that are similar,&#13;
   economic analys is. Here are som e of th e         abundant, not scant. Conventional eco -            because increasingly the basis of trade is&#13;
   new insig hts:                                     nomic analysis implies that people should          th e exploitation of economies of scale, not&#13;
     Plants have to be big to exploit econ-           move to w here th eir skills are scant. But        the differences in natural endowments.&#13;
   omies of scale, but places do not have             t he opposite seems to happen: educated                The rea son: falling transport costs make&#13;
   to be big to generate them. Increasin g            migrants seek places w here many others            specialization possible (see chapter 6).&#13;
   return s to scal e ari se beca use of fixed        have similar skill s. Among th e 100 largest           The implication : fa lling tran sport costs&#13;
   cost s of production (internal to a firm)          met ropolitan areas in th e United States,         change the composition of international&#13;
   and prox imity t o wo rke rs, cust omers,          the 25 cities w ith th e highest share of          trad e and make it even more sen sitive to&#13;
   and peo pl e wi t h new id eas (extern al to a     co llege graduates in 1990 had, by 2000,           such costs. Policies to reduce trade and&#13;
   firm , even an industry). Th e size of settl e-    attracted gra duates at twice th e rate of th e    transport costs should be a big part of&#13;
   ments matters less th an th eir f unct ion .       oth er 75.                                         growth strategies for late developers.&#13;
      Th e reason : with reason able transport           Th e reason: educat ed workers gain                 Recognizing scale economies and their&#13;
   co st s, t ow ns can be large enough to            from prox im ity to oth ers (see ch apter 5).      interaction with the mobility of people and&#13;
   fac il itate intern al sca le econ omi es. Medi-      Th e implicat io n: poli cies should not        products implies changing long-held views&#13;
   um-size citi es are ofte n large enough for        figh t th e market force th at pull s ski lled     about what is needed for economic growth.&#13;
   "localiza t ion" econ omies t hat co me from       peop le t ogeth er.                                Source: WDR 2009 team.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   T hi s integratio n ca n best be done by               â&#128;¢ Tur key is t ry in g to ch ange neighbor-&#13;
unleashing the m arket fo rces of agglom -                  hoods too, in a different way. The&#13;
eration, migration, and specializatio n, not                country of 70 m illion has been looking&#13;
by fi ght ing or opposing them . How well                   towa rd integration with the EU. Because&#13;
markets a nd governments work togeth er                     of higher agglom eration economies and&#13;
determines the speed and sustai nability of                 lower tra nsport costs, areas near Istanbul&#13;
geographi c transform ations. Look at what                  and Izmi r m ay be better suited fo r inte-&#13;
is happening in Bogota, Turkey, and West                    grat ing with Eu ro pe. T he m ore d istant&#13;
Africa :                                                    areas of eastern and southeastern Anato-&#13;
                                                            li a and the Black Sea have 40 percent of&#13;
â&#128;¢ Bogota has alm ost 7 million citizens, but                the la nd but less than 20 percent of the&#13;
  migration from rural Colom bia contin -                   national product, with a GDP per capita&#13;
  ues. A third of its pop ulation growth is                 abo ut half that of the western areas. The&#13;
  due to rural migrants, who m ostly settl e                di spa rities persist despite government&#13;
  in poor, crowded neighborhoods as the                     efforts to spread economic m ass toward&#13;
  city grows denser. Since 2000 a new public                the east. Mea nwhile, public investm ents&#13;
  transportation system, the TransMilenio,                  in soc ial se rvices help laggin g areas,&#13;
  has eased co nges tion, now carrying a                    while fi scal incentives for firm s to locate&#13;
  million passengers a m onth. For the poo r                in t hose a reas seem ineffective. 10&#13;
  neighborhoods especially, it has red uced               â&#128;¢ T he Economic Community of West Afr i-&#13;
  the distance to eco no mic opportunities.                 ca n States (ECOWAS) has a pro tocol that&#13;
  But many people still live in slum s, and                 allows free movement of its 250 million&#13;
  crim e and violence are getting wo rse.                   people between m ember states . T his&#13;
  A muni cip al initi ative has addressed                   has helped the neighborhood m aintain&#13;
  these social divisions since 2003, helping                regional labor m obil ity at preindepen-&#13;
  alm ost a mill io n people integrate into the             dence levels, even as it fell in East a nd&#13;
  city and change their neigh borhoods.                     Southern Africa. But trade is ano ther&#13;
&amp;#12;22                                             WORLD DEVELOPME                      T REPORT 2009&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                   story. In the most dynamic parts of the                  trade similar goods and services, moti-&#13;
                                                   world, the exchange of similar goods and                 vated more by the benefits of special-&#13;
                                                   services-intraindustry trade-has been                    ization and scale than by differences in&#13;
                                                   rising rapidly. But in West Africa, inter-               natural endowments. Trade can only&#13;
                                                   national borders are thickened by red tape               partially offset the immobility of land&#13;
                                                   and illicit checkpoints, which divide the                and labor, but it will help convergence&#13;
                                                   region and thwart the efforts ofECOWAS                   when developing countries can tap into&#13;
                                                   members to specialize and trade.                         the most rapidly growing component:&#13;
                                                                                                            trade in intermediate goods.&#13;
                                                 As the lens of economic geography is&#13;
                                               widened, different movements, stresses,                       Private motives are the main shapers&#13;
                                               and strains come into view.                               of the economic landscape, but it can be&#13;
                                                                                                         reshaped by collective action, most potently&#13;
                                               â&#128;¢ Locally, in places like Bogota, land must               by governments. Seen through the lens of&#13;
                                                 accommodate more and more people.                       economic geography, land use, labor mobil-&#13;
                                                 If land markets work well, land will be                 ity, and intermediate goods trade come into&#13;
                                                 mobile between uses and allocated pro-                  focus (see table 2). Governments should pay&#13;
                                                 ductively. The cities that do this best                 special attention to land, labor, and product&#13;
                                                 will grow, and even more people will be                 markets. When they do not work well, the&#13;
                                                 attracted to their economic density.                    forces of agglomeration, migrat ion, and&#13;
                                               â&#128;¢ People and products move much faster                    specialization weaken, and the economy&#13;
                                                 in and around Bogota than they do in                    stagnates. When they do, land, labor, and&#13;
                                                 Turkey. But even in Turkey, the western                 input markets bring the economic efficiency&#13;
                                                 areas will become more prosperous and                   that comes with geographic concentration,&#13;
                                                 dense, if at a slower pace. Spatial dis-                and the equity associated with converging&#13;
                                                 parities in incomes and poverty rates                   living standards.&#13;
                                                 between the west and the east will likely&#13;
                                                 rise and then diminish as people move                   A rule of thumb for economic&#13;
                                                 to take advantage of economic density. If               integration&#13;
                                                 labor markets in Turkey are fluid, peo-&#13;
                                                                                                         The concern of policy makers is that pro-&#13;
                                                 ple will reduce their economic distance&#13;
                                                                                                         duction will concentrate in some places,&#13;
                                                 to these agglomerations.&#13;
                                                                                                         people in others. Cities will have economic&#13;
                                               â&#128;¢ Internationally, these movements are                    density, and the countryside most of the&#13;
                                                 likely to be fewer and even slower. If                  poor. Leading areas will have the economic&#13;
                                                 regional and global markets were inte-                  mass, while the poor are massed in lagging&#13;
                                                 grated, countries in West Africa would                  areas. Some countries will have much of the&#13;
                                                 specialize in a few tasks and become                    world's wealth, others most of the world's&#13;
                                                 competitive in world markets. As divi-                  poor. Even if this were temporary, it seems&#13;
                                                 sions diminish, neighboring countries                   unfair. But the disparities may be long last-&#13;
                                                                                                         ing, destabilizing parts of a country, entire&#13;
Table 2 Agglomeration, migration, and specialization are the most important forces-                      nations, and even some world regions.&#13;
and land, labor, and intermediate inputs the most sensitive factor markets&#13;
                                                                                                            Governments have many reasons to&#13;
                                                     Geographic scales                                   worry about disparities in welfare in and&#13;
                     Local                        National                      International            among countries. They also have many pol-&#13;
 Economic            Agglomeration                 M igration                   Specialization           icy instruments for promoting economic&#13;
 force               Speeded by migration,         Influenced by                Aided by agglomeration   integration to reduce those disparities.        "&#13;
                     capital mobility, and         agg lomeration and           and factor mobility&#13;
                     trade                         specialization                                        â&#128;¢ Institutions-shorthand in the Report&#13;
 Key factor of       Land                          Labor                        Intermediate inputs        for policies that are spatially blind in&#13;
 production          Immobile                      Mobile within countries      Mobile within and          their design and should be universal in&#13;
                                                                                between countries&#13;
                                                                                                           their coverage. Some of the main exam-&#13;
Source: WO A 2009 team .&#13;
Note: Throughout the Report, "areas" are within-country economic neighborhoods or administrative units&#13;
                                                                                                           ples are regulations affecting land, labor,&#13;
such as states or provinces, and regions are groups of countries based on geographic proximity.            and international trade and such social&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                                   Overview                                                 23&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  services as education, health, and water                        the least developed countries can end up&#13;
  and sanitation financed through tax and                         dominating policy discussions.&#13;
  transfer mechanisms.                                                This Report cal ls for a rebalancing of&#13;
â&#128;¢ Infrastructure-shorthand for policies                           these debates to include all t he elements&#13;
  and investments that are spatially connec-                      of a successful approach to spatia l inte-&#13;
  tive. Examples include roads, railways,                         gration-institutions, infrastructure, and&#13;
  airports, harbors, and communication                            incentives. Using the findings in part one&#13;
  systems that facilitate the movement of                         and the analysis of market forces in part&#13;
  goods, services, people, and ideas locally,                     two, part three reframes these debates,&#13;
  nationally, and internationally.                                calling for a shift from spatia l targeting to&#13;
â&#128;¢ Interventions-shorthand for the spa-                            spatial integration.&#13;
  tially targeted programs that often dom-                            The world is complicated, and the prob-&#13;
  inate the policy discussion. Examples                           lems of economic integration defy simple&#13;
  include slum clearance programs, fis-                           solutions. But the principles need not be&#13;
  cal incentives for manufacturing firms                          complex. The bedrock of integration poli-&#13;
  offered by state governments, and pref-                         cies should be spatially blind institutions.&#13;
  erential trade access for poor countries                        Where the integration challenge spans more&#13;
  in developed country markets.                                   than one geographic dimension, institutions&#13;
                                                                  must be augmented by public investments&#13;
   Today, policy debates often begin and                          in spatially connective infrastructure. Spa-&#13;
end with discussions of spatially targeted                        tially targeted interventions are not always&#13;
incentives. The debate on how to pro-                             necessary. But where the problem is low&#13;
mote healthy urbanization is polarized                            economic density, long distances, and high&#13;
between those who emphasize villages,                             divisions, the response must be comprehen-&#13;
where a majority of the world's poor still                        sive, involving spatially blind, connective,&#13;
live, and those who believe the way out of                        and targeted policies.&#13;
poverty lies in cities, where much of the                             For each spatial dimension, an instru-&#13;
world's wealth is generated. As urban pov-                        ment of integration (see table 3). The rule&#13;
erty increases, the focus is shifting from                        of thumb: "an I for a D."&#13;
villages to slums. Motivated by within-&#13;
country geographic disparities in living                          â&#128;¢ For a one-dimens ional problem, the&#13;
standards, the debate on territorial devel-                         mainstay of the policy response should&#13;
opment is similarly fixated on economic                             be (spatially blind) institutions.&#13;
growth in lagging areas. At the interna-                          â&#128;¢ For a two-dimensional challenge, both&#13;
tional level, preferential market access for                        institutions and (spatially connective)&#13;
                                                                    infrastructure are needed .&#13;
&#13;
Table 3 .. An I for a D?.. A rule of thumb for calibrating the policy response&#13;
                                                                                                                       Policy priorities for economic integration&#13;
                                                                                                                  Institutions        Infrastructure        Interventions&#13;
                                   Place type- local (U, national (NI, and international (0                         Spatially            Spatially             Spatially&#13;
 Complexity of challenge           geographic scales                                                                 blind              connective             targeted&#13;
 One-dimensional problem           L. Areas of incipient urbanization&#13;
                                   N. Nations with sparse lagging areas&#13;
                                   I. Regions close to world markets&#13;
                                                                                                                       â&#128;¢&#13;
 Two-dimensional                   L. Areas of intermediate urbanization&#13;
 challenge                         N. Nations with dense lagging areas&#13;
                                   I. Regions distant from world markets&#13;
                                                                                                                       â&#128;¢                     â&#128;¢&#13;
 Three-dimensional                 L. Areas of advanced urbanization that have within-city divisions&#13;
 predicament                       N. Nations with dense lagging areas and domestic divisions&#13;
                                   I. Regions distant from markets with small economies&#13;
                                                                                                                       â&#128;¢                     â&#128;¢                    â&#128;¢&#13;
Source: WDR 2009 team.&#13;
Note: Throughout the Report, areas are within-country economic neighborhoods or administrative units such as states or provinces, and regions are groupings of countries based&#13;
on geographic proximity.&#13;
&amp;#12;24                                             WORLD DEVELOPMENT REPORT 2009&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                               â&#128;¢ For a three-dimensional predicament,                   behind a misplaced density of populations&#13;
                                                 all three instruments are needed-in-                   in lagging areas, so that in some countries&#13;
                                                 stitutions, infrastructure, and (spatially             (such as Brazil) lagging areas have higher&#13;
                                                 targeted) interventions.                               poverty rates and high population densi-&#13;
                                                                                                        ties. Internationally, develop ing regions&#13;
                                                   The primary dimension at the local                   are all deeply divided, but some also may&#13;
                                               geographic sca le is density; nationally, it             be distant from world markets. Even if&#13;
                                               is distance; internationally, division. At               regional institutions take hold and make&#13;
                                               each of these geographic scales, policies                South Asia a more integrated region, some&#13;
                                               designed without explicit consideration to               countries (such as Nepal) may need con-&#13;
                                               space should be seen as the primary instru-              certed policy action to improve the infra-&#13;
                                               ment. In some places, these can be a large               structure to reach growing regional and&#13;
                                               part of integration policies. The task of                international markets. For places that&#13;
                                               integration is relatively straightforward in             face two-dimensioned integration chal-&#13;
                                               areas of incipient urbanization (as in lag-              lenges, investments in infrastructure that&#13;
                                               ging states in many low-income countries),               connects lagging to lead ing places and&#13;
                                               in countries with mobile labor and capital               aid market access should supp lement the&#13;
                                               (such as Chile), or in regions that are close            institutions that bring people together.&#13;
                                               to world markets (such as North Africa).                     The integration challenge is greatest where&#13;
                                               In such places, the integration challenge                adverse density, distance, and division com-&#13;
                                               can be seen as one dimensional. Explicit ly              bine to pose a "three-dimensional challenge."&#13;
                                               spatia l policies are not generally necessary.           In highly urbanized areas (such as Bogota),&#13;
                                               Universal or spatially blind institutions-               the fear is that economic density and popu-&#13;
                                               made available to everyone regardless of                 lation density may not coincide. Within-city&#13;
                                               location-form both the bedrock and the                   divisions may prevent the integration of slums&#13;
                                               mainstay of an effective integration policy.             and spawn problems of crime and grime. In&#13;
                                                   As the task becomes more complicated,                some countries (such as India), ethnic, reli-&#13;
                                               th ese institutions must be assisted by                  gious, or linguistic divisions discourage the&#13;
                                               infrastructure. Locally, rapid urbanization              poor in densely populated lagging areas from&#13;
                                               can congest the area, increasing economic                seeking their fortunes elsewhere. And in the&#13;
                                               distance and choking off agg lomeration                  most fragmented and remote regions (such as&#13;
                                               economies. In places such as Mumbai,                     Central Africa or Central Asia), a clustering&#13;
                                               whose population has doubled since the                   of small and poor nations can lead to spill-&#13;
                                               1970s, rising congestion has to be met by                overs of the wrong kind-disease, conflict,&#13;
                                               investments in transport infrastructure,                 or corruption.&#13;
                                               so that the benefits of density are shared                   Slums in large cities, densely populated&#13;
                                               more widely. Nationally, changing eco-                   poor areas in divided nations, and the "bot-&#13;
                                               nomic and political fortunes can leave                   tom billion" countries-approximating the&#13;
                                                                                                        three billions discussed at the beginning-&#13;
Figure 5 In charted waters: the pace of urbanization today has precedents                               are the most difficult challenges for inte-&#13;
Ch an ge in urban shares since 1800                                                                     gration. The policy responses should not be&#13;
Developing economies !median). 1985 - 2005 â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢&#13;
                                                                                                        timid. But they should also be deliberate.&#13;
High-income economies !mean). 1880-1900 â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢&#13;
                                                                                                        Efficient and inclusive urbanization&#13;
 Developing economies !mean). 1985-2005 â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢&#13;
                                                                                                        No country has grown to middle income&#13;
                   United States, 1800-1900    ::::::::~                                                without industrializing and urbanizing.&#13;
                        Denmark, 1800-1900&#13;
                                                                                                        None has grown to high income without&#13;
                   United Kingdom, 1830-50 â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢&#13;
                                                                                                        vibrant cities. The rush to cities in develop-&#13;
                           Germa ny, 1830-50 â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢&#13;
                                                                                                        ing countries seems chaotic, but it is nec-&#13;
                          Canada, 1880-1900 â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢ â&#128;¢&#13;
                                                                                                        essary. It seems unprecedented, but it has&#13;
                                              0                      10          15        20      25   happened before (see figure 5). It had to&#13;
                                                     Percentage point difference in urban shares        have, because the move to density that is&#13;
Source: WDR 2009 team calculations based on data from various sources (see figure 1.13).                manifest in urbanization is closely related&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                                  Overview                                25&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
to the transformation of an economy from                               establish the institutional foundation&#13;
agrarian to industrial to postindustrial.                              of possible urbanization in some places.&#13;
    Governments can facilitate the spatial                             Good land policies are central, and so&#13;
transformations that lie behind these sec-                             are policies to provide basic services&#13;
toral changes. Depending on the stage of                               to everyone. For example, the univer-&#13;
urbanization, sequencing and priority-                                 salization of land rights in Denmark&#13;
setting require paying attention to different                          at the turn of the eigh teenth century&#13;
aspects of the geographic transformation.                              contributed greatly to the nation's take-&#13;
What does not change is that a foundation                              off into industrialization a few decades&#13;
of institutions must be universal and come                             later. Indeed, policies to strengthen rural&#13;
first, investments in connective infrastruc-                           property rights are seen as instrumental&#13;
ture should be both timed and located well                             for higher agricultural productivity in&#13;
and come second, and spatially targeted                                sixteenth-century England, which freed&#13;
interventions should be used least and last.                           workers to migrate to towns to work&#13;
    The approach requires the discipline of                            in manufacturing and services. A close&#13;
following the integration principle set out                            complement to the institutions for bet-&#13;
earlier. The payoff is a spatial transforma-                           ter land markets is the universal provi-&#13;
tion that is both efficient and inclusive (see                         sion of basic social services-security,&#13;
chapter 7) .                                                           education, health services, and sanita-&#13;
    The principles outlined in the Report                              tion. In 1960, the Republic of Korea had&#13;
help to prioritize policies for different stages                       a per capita income level that Benin has&#13;
of urbanization, providing the elements                                today. Seventy-five percent of its people&#13;
of an urbanization strategy. Map 6 shows                               lived in rural areas, more than a third&#13;
three areas in Colombia, each with a spe-                              of Korean adults had no schooling, and&#13;
cific geography. But the principles are quite                          fewer than 5 percent of children had&#13;
universal.                                                             been immunized against preventable&#13;
                                                                       diseases such as measles. By 2000, more&#13;
â&#128;¢ Incipient urbanization. In places that                               than 80 percent had urbanized, almost&#13;
    are mostly rural, governments should                               everyone was literate and immunized,&#13;
    be as neutral as possible and should                               and the Republic of Korea's income had&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Map 6    As urbanizat ion advances, polici es must evolve&#13;
&#13;
                a. Inci pient urbanization                                b. Intermediate urbanization                        c. Advanced urbanization&#13;
                   in Cauca, Colombia                                        in Santander, Colombia                          in Colombia's Capital Area&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                  â&#128;¢â&#128;¢ cuNDINA ~ ~ ..&#13;
                                                                                                                                      MAR CA â&#128;¢;. ,.&#13;
                                                                                                                                                i:&#13;
&#13;
                        CAUCA                                                                       "t\&#13;
                                                                                                    Bucaram;nga                  ...,. ,&#13;
                                                                                                                                 ~.~             '&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                    ,.."\~ ..    Bogota&#13;
                           Popayan ll!.                                                                                               ,,.&#13;
                                                                                                                                       Â·'&#13;
                                  ""'                                                SANTANDER&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                '   I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Source: WDR 2009 team, using data from Schneider, Friedl, and Pote re 2008.&#13;
&amp;#12;26                                          WORLD DEVELOPMENT REPORT 2009&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                    of rising economic density are more&#13;
                                                                                                    widely shared. Industrialization involves&#13;
     sox s Concentration without congestion in western&#13;
                                                                                                    changing land use patterns as activities&#13;
           China: Chongqing and Chengdu                                                             concentrate, and requires moving goods&#13;
     An experiment in China might chang e               Better institutions. The emphasis           and services around quickly. Land use&#13;
     the future of urbanization policy in            is on coordination across governm ent          regulations can affect location decisions,&#13;
     the developing world. Policy makers             levels to manage land use and co n-            and they continue to be the institutional&#13;
     should take notice.                             version. In th e co untryside, th e pl an&#13;
                                                                                                    priority. Spatially blind social services&#13;
        China is taking inland the urbaniza-         concentrates rura l land by transfer-&#13;
                                                     ring use rights to firm s and farm ers .&#13;
                                                                                                    should continue as part of rural-urban&#13;
     tion strategy that wa s successful in&#13;
     the leading coastal areas in the 1980s          In town s and cities, the creation of          integration, so that people are pulled to&#13;
     and 1990s. The "area approach" is               industrial zon es is a key part of th e        cities by agglomeration economies, not&#13;
     being implemented in two places-                wider framework. Large and medium              pushed out by the lack of schools, health&#13;
     Chongqing and Chengdu, both                     cities are developing high valu e-             services, and public security in rural&#13;
     located in the near west . At about 40          added manufacturing, while smaller             areas. But even if these services are pro-&#13;
     percent, they have the same urbaniza-           cities and town s are specializing in&#13;
                                                                                                    vided, transport costs can rise quickly&#13;
     tion ratio as the average for China . The       labor-intensive industries, pulling in&#13;
                                                     labor from nearby villages, and facil i-&#13;
                                                                                                    because of growing congestion, affecting&#13;
     aim is to increase that to 70 percent by&#13;
     2020, promoting both concentration              tating localization economies.                 the location choices of entrepreneurs.&#13;
     and rural-urban convergence.                       More infrastructure. Massive trunk          Connective infrastructure is needed to&#13;
        Chongqing has a population of                infrastructure is planned . Chongqing          keep such areas integrated. State and cen-&#13;
     about 40 million, with a portfolio of           will spend billion s on infrastructure,        tral governments that work well together&#13;
     a capital city, six large citi es, 25 small     from the central government and                can provide the trunk infrastructure&#13;
     and mid-size citi es, 95 central town -         through increased private invest-&#13;
                                                                                                    necessary to ensure that prosperity is&#13;
     ships, and 400 townships. Chongq ing            ment from Hong Kong, Chin a, and&#13;
                                                     from Singapore. In Chengdu, about&#13;
                                                                                                    widely shared. Making the administra-&#13;
     has been accorded the status of&#13;
     a special municipality, as Beijing,             117 billion yu an will be invested in          tive jurisdiction wider can help in coor-&#13;
     Shanghai, and Tianjin have had for              71 infrastructure projects, including          dinating infrastructure investments. A&#13;
     some years. Like them, it will enjoy            rural -urban tran sport networks, and          good example is Chongqing in western&#13;
     greater financial autonomy. Chengdu             water and sanitation projects in both          China (see box 5).&#13;
     is smaller, a sprawling metropolitan            rural and urban area s. Another 16.5&#13;
                                                                                                 â&#128;¢ Advanced urbanization. In highly urban-&#13;
     area with 11 million people. Along              billion yuan will be invested in 34&#13;
                                                     social projects to improve the living         ized areas, besides institutions and infra-&#13;
     with the 2,000-year-old capital city of&#13;
     Sichuan province, it has eight medi-            standards of lagging rural residents.         structure, targeted interventions may be&#13;
     um-size cities, 30 central town ships,             If markets favor th e two pl aces as       necessary to deal with the problem of&#13;
     60 townships, and 600 vill ages.                much as th e government has, th ey            slums. Services and learning require peo-&#13;
        The urbanization strategy involves           will improve th e lives of millions in        ple to be in proximity to livable surround-&#13;
     "three concentrations" of land,                 the Chinese hinterland . The integra-         ings. This is the stage in which slums can&#13;
     industry, and farmers. The idea is to           tion already has had a local impact.&#13;
                                                                                                   compromise a city's ability to deliver the&#13;
     reap the benefits of scale economies,           In Chongqing, rural incomes in 2007&#13;
                                                     increased fa ster than those of urban         economies that come from proximity.&#13;
     promote the mobility of goods and&#13;
     workers, and improve th e w ell-being           residents. In Chengdu, farm er con -          Slum-improvement programs may not&#13;
     of new migrants to cities. Consistent           centration s are believed to have led         be a priority at earlier stages of urbaniza-&#13;
     with the policy priorities outlined for         to a productivity increase of 80 per-         tion, but at this stage they become nec-&#13;
     areas with intermediate urban shares            cent, as industry has been absorbing          essary. The lesson from assessments of&#13;
     of about 40-SO percent, the emphasi s           about 100,000 farmers a year.                 slum-improvement initiatives is that tar-&#13;
     in both places is on universal institu-&#13;
                                                                                                   geted interventions will not be enough&#13;
     tions and connective infrastructure,&#13;
                                                     Source: WDR 2009 tea m.&#13;
                                                                                                   by themselves. These interventions will&#13;
     not spatially targeted interventions.&#13;
                                                                                                   not work unless institutions related to&#13;
                                                                                                   land and basic services are reasonably&#13;
                                                                                                   effective, and transport infrastructure.is&#13;
                                                   reached that of modern-day Portugal.            in place. A three-dimensional challenge&#13;
                                                   Another good example is Costa Rica.             must be met by a three-pronged policy&#13;
                                            â&#128;¢ Intermediate urbanization. In places                 response, requiring coordinated policies&#13;
                                              where urbanization has picked up                     at the central, state, and city levels of gov-&#13;
                                              speed, in addition to these institutions,            ernment. Singapore's success shows the&#13;
                                              governments must put in place connec-                advantages of such coordination in a city-&#13;
                                              tive infrastructure so that the benefits             state. More recent examples are Shanghai&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                    Overview                                     27&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   and Guangzhou in China. An even more          figure 6   Quicker geographic convergence in basic living stand ards in Malaysia&#13;
   recent (and perhaps more generally appli-     % difference between min. and max. poverty rates among Malaysian states&#13;
   cable) example is Bogota in Colombia.         70&#13;
&#13;
    The experience of successful urban-          60                             1976&#13;
izers indicates that the basis of successful&#13;
rural-urban transformations is a set of spa-     50&#13;
tially blind policies-"institutions" in the                            1970&#13;
                                                 40&#13;
shorthand of this Report. Investments in&#13;
infrastructure that connects places form         30&#13;
the second tier. Geographically targeted&#13;
interventions should be used only when the       20&#13;
                                                                                                                                        2002&#13;
challenge is especially difficult, but should&#13;
                                                 10&#13;
always be used together with an effort to&#13;
improve institutions and infrastructure.&#13;
                                                             500       1,000       1,500         2,000    2,500        3,000   3,500   4,000   4,500&#13;
                                                                                           GDP per capita (2000 US$)&#13;
Area (territorial) development policies&#13;
                                                 Source: Malaysia Economic Planning Unit 2008.&#13;
that integrate nations&#13;
Some parts of a country are better suited&#13;
                                                 in the slower-growing states, implying that&#13;
for agriculture, others for industry, and&#13;
                                                 tax and transfer mechanisms worked well.&#13;
still others for services. And as industry&#13;
                                                 Such impatience with spatial inequality&#13;
and services flourish, the spatial distribu-&#13;
                                                 in living standards is paying off in other&#13;
tion of economic activities must change. 11&#13;
                                                 countries such as China, Egypt, Indonesia,&#13;
No country has grown to riches without&#13;
                                                 Mexico, Thailand, and Vietnam.&#13;
changing the geographic distribution of its&#13;
                                                     But not all countries have experienced&#13;
people and production.&#13;
                                                 geographic convergence in the Millennium&#13;
    A rising concentration of people and&#13;
                                                 Development Indicators, such as child mor-&#13;
production in some parts of a country has&#13;
                                                 tality, maternal health, basic education, safe&#13;
marked economic growth over the last&#13;
                                                 water, and sanitation. What should they do?&#13;
two centuries. To fight this concentration&#13;
                                                     The answer lies in integrating lagging and&#13;
is to fight growth itself, and policy makers&#13;
                                                 leading areas, using policies that are tailored&#13;
must show patience in dealing with these&#13;
                                                 to the level of difficulty of integration. While&#13;
imbalances. But aided by government poli-&#13;
                                                 economic motives are important, social and&#13;
cies, successful development also has been&#13;
                                                 political conditions influence t~e spee~ of&#13;
marked by falling disparities in living stan-&#13;
                                                 these spatial changes. The location cho!Ces&#13;
dards between places favored by markets&#13;
                                                 that people make reflect the strengths and&#13;
and those less fortunate. Policies can speed&#13;
                                                 inclinations of societies and political struc-&#13;
up the convergence in basic living stan-&#13;
                                                 tures. Poverty maps provide a snapshot of&#13;
dards, so that people in the least-fortunate&#13;
                                                 where the poor are concentrated (high pov-&#13;
places do not have to wait for basic pu~lic&#13;
                                                 erty mass-that is, the "poor people"), and&#13;
amenities until their nations reach high&#13;
                                                 which places are the poorest (high poverty&#13;
income levels. The experience of success-&#13;
                                                 rate-that is, the "poor places"). These maps&#13;
ful developers also justifies impatience in&#13;
                                                 can tell us a lot about the social and politi-&#13;
equalizing basic living standards.&#13;
                                                 cal conditions in a country: the movement of&#13;
    Consider Malaysia. Economic growth&#13;
                                                 poor people may best reflect the constraints to&#13;
and government policies have reduced&#13;
                                                 mobility, because they have the most reason&#13;
poverty and improved living. standar~s ,&#13;
                                                 to move and the fewest resources to do so.&#13;
speeding progress toward meetmg the Mil-&#13;
                                                     Using information on where poor people&#13;
lennium Development Goals. But in the&#13;
                                                 are located and which places are poor, the&#13;
early years of growth (between 1970 and&#13;
                                                 policy response can be calibrated to coun-&#13;
1976), poverty rates between different states&#13;
                                                 try conditions.&#13;
diverged briefly, to later converge as they&#13;
declined for all states (see figure 6). Health   â&#128;¢ Countries with sparsely populated lagging&#13;
indicators (infant mortality) declined more        areas. In China the highest poverty rates&#13;
&amp;#12;28   WORLD DEV E LOPMENT REPORT 2009&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Map 7      Three types of countries, differing challenges for area development&#13;
&#13;
                               a. China: Poverty rates are high in the west, but most poor people are in the east&#13;
&#13;
      Proportion&#13;
      of poor(%)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          0      &lt; 17.5&#13;
                 17.6- 35.9&#13;
          -      36.0-51 .6&#13;
          -      51 .7- 70.3&#13;
                                                                          Each dot represents&#13;
                                                                          50,000 poor persons&#13;
          -      70.4--81.1&#13;
&#13;
                 b. Brazil : Poverty rates are high in the north and northeast, but most poor people live along the coast&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   0       &lt; 12&#13;
                           12- 25&#13;
                           25- 35&#13;
                                                                                                               Each dot represents&#13;
                   -       35-45&#13;
                   -       &gt;45                                                                                 5,000 poo r pe rsons&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                           c. India: Poverty rates are high i n the central states, and many poor people live there&#13;
&#13;
     Proportion&#13;
     of poor(%)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      0       6.4-9.7&#13;
              9.8- 16.7&#13;
              16.8- 24.8                                                                                       Poverty density&#13;
      -       24.9- 35.4&#13;
      -       35.5-46.6                                                                                        Each dot represents&#13;
      O no data                                                                                                50,000 poor persons&#13;
&#13;
     Source: WDR 2009 team (see chapter 8 for details).&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                        Overview     29&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  are in the western provinces, but the poor         ging states, home to more than 60 percent&#13;
  are concentrated in the southeast and cen-         of the nation's poor (see map 7, panel c).&#13;
  tral areas (see map 7, panel a). Economic          People live there for a reason: it is a fer-&#13;
  density and population density overlap.            tile plain and was the cradle of Indian&#13;
  The country has few divisions-linguistic           civilization. But their location is less for-&#13;
  and other barriers are not high-and peo-           tunate now, as the world has changed.&#13;
  ple, including the poor, can move to reduce        Labor mobility is limited because of lin-&#13;
  their distance to density. Spatially blind         guistic and class divisions. Mobility has&#13;
  institutions that ensure well-functioning          not been helped by policies that sought to&#13;
  land markets, enforce property rights, and         revive growth in these lagging provinces&#13;
  deliver basic social services such as school-      through subsidized finance and preferen-&#13;
  ing and health care can be the mainstay of         tial industrial licensing. The debate is now&#13;
  an economic integration strategy to reduce         shifting toward economic integration-&#13;
  the economic distance between lagging              policies more consistent with mobility of&#13;
  and leading areas. Chile, Egypt, Honduras,         labor such as interregional infrastructure&#13;
  Indonesia, Russia, Uganda, and Vietnam             and better health and education services.&#13;
  are other examples of countries where the          These policies and the interstate migra-&#13;
  area development challenge is unidimen-            tion they encourage will, if given time,&#13;
  sional-the main problem is distance.               reduce the divisions that have made the&#13;
â&#128;¢ Undivided countries with densely popu-             distances long between leading areas&#13;
  lated lagging areas. In Brazil the poverty         and densely populated lagging areas.&#13;
  rates are highest in the north and north-          In the meantime, these areas may need&#13;
  east: eight of the ten poorest states are in       a helping hand-from geographically&#13;
  the northeast, the other two are in the            targeted incentives that encourage local&#13;
  north (see map 7, panel b). But the eco-           production. Another country with a&#13;
  nomic mass and the concentration of                three-dimensional integration agenda of&#13;
  poverty are highest in the urban agglom-           distance, densely populated poor areas,&#13;
  erations near the coast, from the poor             and domestic divisions may be Nigeria.&#13;
  northeast to the thriving southeast. Eco-          In such places, the policy response has to&#13;
  nomic and population densities coincide            be a blend of spatially blind, connective,&#13;
  only partially. The poverty-related symp-          and targeted policies.&#13;
  toms are those of a country where within-          Governments should not be faulted&#13;
  country divisions such as ethnolinguistic       for being impatient with markets, and&#13;
  differences and political fragmentation         for trying to help lagging areas. But tar-&#13;
  are low, but where population densities         geted interventions should be designed to&#13;
  are-for historical and policy-related           work with the institutional reforms and&#13;
  reasons-in the "wrong places." Bangla-          the investments in infrastructure. Expe-&#13;
  desh, Colombia, Ghana, and Turkey have          rience suggests that incentives should not&#13;
  similar conditions. In such places the          be provided for activities that depend on&#13;
  pull of agglomeration economies in lead-        agglomeration economies or international&#13;
  ing areas and the mobility of labor may         market access. Incentives for agriculture&#13;
  not be strong enough to induce concen-          are prime candidates in these largely rural&#13;
  tration and convergence. The problems           and agrarian areas. Relying mainly on tar-&#13;
  of "long distance and wrong density"            geted incentives for industry-as India&#13;
  must be met by a two-pronged policy             did for decades-will not help the lagging&#13;
  of economic integration: spatially blind        states improve living standards to levels in&#13;
  institutions should be augmented by spa-        the leading states.&#13;
  tially connective infrastructure, such as&#13;
  interregional highways and railroads and        Regional integration to increase access&#13;
  improved telecommunications.                    to global markets&#13;
â&#128;¢ Divided countries with densely popu-            The merits of global versus regional trade&#13;
  lated lagging areas. In India more than         agreements have been debated for years.&#13;
  400 million people live in the central lag-     The debate is now largely concluded. Where&#13;
&amp;#12;30                                        WORLD DEVELOPMENT REPORT 2009&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 7 Northeast, Southeast, and South Asia have been catching up to developed nat ions       if the scale of production is big, and that&#13;
Average annual growth rates of GDP per capita, 1960-2006&#13;
                                                                                                requires reaching the big markets of the&#13;
                     Northeast Asia                                                             Northern Hemisphere.&#13;
        Other high-income countries                                                                 What do late developers have to do to&#13;
            Southeast Asia &amp; Pacific                                                            accelerate development? The common con-&#13;
                           South Asia&#13;
                                                                                                dition is division-that is, thick borders.&#13;
                     DECO countries&#13;
                                                                                                What differs is their distance from large&#13;
                     Northern Africa&#13;
                                                                                                world markets and whether or not there is&#13;
                                                                                                a large country in their neighborhood (see&#13;
     Central Asia, Caucasus &amp; Turkey&#13;
                                                                                                map 8, panel b).&#13;
        Central America &amp; Caribbean&#13;
Eastern Europe &amp; Russian Federation&#13;
                                                                                                â&#128;¢ Countries in regions near large world&#13;
                        Western Asia&#13;
                                                                                                  markets. For countries near large mar-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                           -&#13;
                     South America&#13;
                                                                                                  kets, regional and global integration does&#13;
                     Southern Africa                                                              not require geographic differentiation.&#13;
                        Eastern Africa                                                            Spatially blind measures such as improv-&#13;
                     Western Africa                                                               ing economic policies and the invest-&#13;
                        Central Africa&#13;
                                     -1&#13;
                                          â&#128;¢0                        3    4                  6&#13;
                                                                                                  ment climate will attract capital and&#13;
                                                                                                  technology from the more sophisticated&#13;
                                                          Percent                                 markets nearby. Their underused talent&#13;
Source:WDR 2009 team.                                                                             and cheaper labor are powerful draws .&#13;
                                                                                                  Whether they lag or lead within the&#13;
                                          regional or bilateral pacts do not discourage           region is hardly relevant; the presence of&#13;
                                          trade with countries in other regions, and              a sun nearby makes them all small plan-&#13;
                                          where they are accompanied by measures                  ets. Mexican exports to the United States&#13;
                                          to facilitate the flows of goods, people, and           are about 1. 7 percent of the U.S. econ-&#13;
                                          finance-such as infrastructure and com-                 omy. Mexico should build even stron-&#13;
                                          pensatory mechanisms-they can help.                     ger links with the United States. But for&#13;
                                          Otherwise, they are not worth the trouble.              other countries in Central America, the&#13;
                                             This Report does not reopen that                     payoffs to infrastructure connections to&#13;
                                          debate. Instead, it takes up the question               Mexico are small-the market in North&#13;
                                          of how developing countries can best gain               America dwarfs all of Central America's.&#13;
                                          access to markets within their neighbor-                And market access likely depends most&#13;
                                          hoods and across the world. Geography                   on economic stability. Spatially blind&#13;
                                          matters greatly in deciding what is needed,             institutions should be able to integrate&#13;
                                          what is unnecessary, and what will fail. But            Central America with world markets .&#13;
                                          with the right mix of policy actions, even              The same is true for Eastern Europe and&#13;
                                          countries in parts of the world that have               North Africa. Countries in these regions&#13;
                                          been left far behind can overcome their                 have better-than-average market access,&#13;
                                          geographic disadvantage. The way to tell if             though depending on their economic&#13;
                                          the actions are paying dividends is whether             policies and regulations, this access is&#13;
                                          market access improves noticeably.                      not uniform even within these regions&#13;
                                             Some regions of the world have done                  (see map 8, panel c) .&#13;
                                          better than others (see figure 7) . Countries         â&#128;¢ Cou n tries in regions d ista n t f rom&#13;
                                          in these regions now have thinner eco-                  large world markets that have a large&#13;
                                          nomic borders (see map 8, panel a). They                economy. To integrate regions more&#13;
                                          can afford to have thin borders, because                distant from large world markets but&#13;
                                          their neighbors are prospering too. For                 with a sizable economy-East Asia,&#13;
                                          them, regional markets are world markets.               Latin America, Southern Africa, and&#13;
                                          Others, like the East Asians, have allowed              South Asia-such spatially blind mea-&#13;
                                          production relationships to grow strong                 sures are just as necessary, but they may&#13;
                                          and cut paths even through thick borders.               not be sufficient. For lagging countries&#13;
                                          But specializing can increase efficiency only           in these regions, such as Mongolia,&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                                      Overview   31&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Map 8        Market access distinguishes world regions&#13;
&#13;
                                            a. Borders are thicker in developing regions&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        Â·~&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  b. The size and access to markets differs greatly by region&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                           c. The three D's suggest a simple taxonomy of the world's neighborhoods&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    RegiÂ°ilns with                      ~:;;.. I.&#13;
   CJ High-income countries                    Â·&#13;
   CJ Countries close to&#13;
             worl~   markets&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
             Small countries far from&#13;
             world markets&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sources: Panel a: WDR 2009 team !see chapter 3 for details); panel b: Mayer 2008 lsee chapter 9 for details); panel c: WDR&#13;
2009 team !see chapter 9 for details).&#13;
&amp;#12;32   WORLD DEVELOPMENT REPORT 2009&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       Nepal, Paraguay, and Zimbabwe, some                can hardly be blamed for worrying&#13;
       of the paths to world markets may go               most about their own poor, and not&#13;
       through their larger neighbors. Brazil,            their less fortunate neighbors such as&#13;
       China, and India are attractive to inves-          Burkina Faso or Burundi. Indeed, see-&#13;
       tors because of their potential market             ing the benefits of regional cooperation,&#13;
       size, and these " home market effects"             they have made repeated efforts to fos-&#13;
       can generate the impetus for special-              ter integration in their neighborhoods .&#13;
       iza tion and help their enterprises com-           The ECOWAS even includes a clause&#13;
       pete in world markets. A qualification:            that allows workers to cross borders, a&#13;
       for market access, the relevant measure            stage of integration rivaled only (and&#13;
       of distance is economic, not Euclidean.            only recently) by the EU. It also has&#13;
       With a combination of bilateral accords,           tried to share regional infrastructure.&#13;
       inspired transport policies, and aggres-           Other such regions are Central Africa,&#13;
       sive specialization in primary products,           Central Asia, and the Pacific Islands.&#13;
       Chile reduced distance to North Amer-              Countries in such regions face a three-&#13;
       ica and built global rather than regional          dimensional challenge (see "Geogra-&#13;
       links. But such cases are exceptions. For          phy in Motion: Density, Distance, and&#13;
       the smaller countries in these regions,            Division in Sub-Saharan Africa"). A&#13;
       both institutional reforms and regional            combination of efforts to improve insti-&#13;
       connectivity will be necessary for eco-            tutional cooperation and regional infra-&#13;
       nomic integration.                                 structure investments is needed-but it&#13;
     â&#128;¢ Countries in regions distant from world            is not enough. Targeted incentives also&#13;
       markets without large economies. The               will be necessary, through preferential&#13;
       most difficult challenges are for the              access to developed country markets,&#13;
       countries in parts of the world divided            perhaps made conditional on regional&#13;
       by thick borders, distant from world               collaboration to improve institutions&#13;
       markets, and without a large country               and infrastructure.&#13;
       that can serve as a regional conduit&#13;
       to world markets, as Brazil and India              Everyone should support the efforts of&#13;
       might. For these regions, economic              these " bottom billion" countries to inte-&#13;
       geography poses a three-dimensional             grate their economies, with in and across&#13;
       cha Ilenge. Cote d ' Ivoire or Tanzania         borders. A billion lives depend on it.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         We are familiar with the sectora l transformations needed for economic growth-the&#13;
     changes in work and organization as agrarian economies become industrialized and service&#13;
     oriented. This Report discusses the spatial transformations that also must happen for coun-&#13;
     tries to develop. Higher densities, shorter distances, and lower divisions will remain essential&#13;
     for economic success in the foreseeable future. Th ey should be encouraged. With them will&#13;
     come unbalanced growth. When accompanied by policies for integration calibrated to the&#13;
     economic geography of nations, these changes also will bring inclusive development-sooner,&#13;
     not much later.&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                            Overview                                      33&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Endnotes                                                                Fujita, Masahisa, ed. 2007. Regional Integration in East Asia: From&#13;
   1. Clemens, Montenegro, and Pritchett (2008) , background              the Viewpoint of Spatial Economics. New York: Pal grave Mac-&#13;
paper for this Report.                                                    millan.&#13;
   2. Collier 2007.                                                     Government of Nigeria, Federal Ministry of Science and Technol-&#13;
   3. In Zambia a person in a settlement with more than 5,000             ogy. 2003. Multi-Disciplinary Committee Report of the Techno-&#13;
people is considered urban; in India the threshold is 20,000. To          Economic Survey on Wood and Wood Products Sector, 2003, 4th&#13;
compare urbanization across countries, this Report pioneers a new         Update. Lagos: Government of Nigeria, Federal Ministry of Sci-&#13;
measure of population density6the "agglomeration index" (see              ence and Technology.&#13;
chapter 1).                                                             Khanna, Tarun. 2008. Billions of Entrepreneurs: How China and&#13;
   4. See World Development Report 2008 Agriculture for Develop-          India Are Reshaping Their Futures-and Yours. Boston, MA:&#13;
ment.                                                                     Harvard Business School Press.&#13;
   5. Fujita 2007.                                                      Koh, Tommy, and Li Lin Chang, eds. 2005. The Little Red Dot:&#13;
   6. Mukherjee 2007.                                                     Reflections by Singapore's Diplomats. Singapore: World Scientific&#13;
   7. Koh and Chang 2005.                                                 Publishing.&#13;
   8. de Blij 2005.&#13;
                                                                        Malaysia Economic Planning Unit. 2008. Malaysia Achieving the&#13;
   9. Khanna 2008.&#13;
                                                                         MDGs. Kuala Lumpur: Malaysia Economic Planning Unit,&#13;
   10. World Bank 2008.&#13;
                                                                          Primer Minister's Office.&#13;
   11. Throughout this Report, what is often called " regional devel-&#13;
                                                                        Mayer, Thierry. 2008. "Market Potential and Development." Back-&#13;
opment" or "territorial development" is referred to as "area devel-&#13;
                                                                         ground paper for the WDR 2009.&#13;
opment." These policies must contend with even greater spatial&#13;
unevenness as their scope widens to encompass countries.                Mukherjee, Andy. 2007. "India's Answer to Shenzhen Needs Politi-&#13;
                                                                         cal Will." Bloomberg.com. Mar. 15, 2007.&#13;
References                                                              World Bank. 2003. World Development Report 2003: Sustainable&#13;
                                                                         Development in a Dynamic World: Transforming Institutions,&#13;
Brulhart, Marius. 2008. "Intra-Industrial Trade and Trade in Inter-&#13;
                                                                         Growth and the Quality of Life. New York: Oxford University&#13;
  mediate Goods." Background paper for the WDR 2009.&#13;
                                                                         Press.&#13;
Clemens, Michael, Claudio Montenegro, and Lant Pritchett. 2008.&#13;
                                                                        - - - . 2007. Doing Business in 2008. Washington, DC: World&#13;
  "The Great Discrimination: Borders as a Labor Market Barrier."&#13;
                                                                          Bank.&#13;
  Background paper for the WDR 2009.&#13;
                                                                        - - - . 2008. Turkey: Country Economic Memorandum. Sustain-&#13;
Collier, Paul. 2007. The Bottom Billion: Why the Poorest Countries&#13;
                                                                          ing High Growth. Selected Issues. Washington, DC: World Bank.&#13;
  are Failing and What Can Be Done About It. New York: Oxford&#13;
  University Press.&#13;
de Blij, Harm. 2005. Why Geography Matters: Three Challenges Fac-&#13;
  ing America: Climate Change, the Rise of China, and Global Ter-&#13;
  rorism. New York: Oxford University Press.&#13;
&amp;#12;                          World Development Report 2009&#13;
                                       Reshaping Economic Geography&#13;
 PRODUCT                                                                             STOCK#         PRICE       QTY     SUBTOTAL&#13;
 World Development Report 2009&#13;
 Reshaping Economic Geography&#13;
 Paperback: ISBN 978-0-8213-7607-2                                                    017607        US$26&#13;
 Hardcover: ISBN 978-0-8213-7640-9                                                    017640        US$50&#13;
 * Geographic discounts apply - depending on ship-to country. See                   Subtotal&#13;
 http://publications.worldbank.orgldiscounts&#13;
                                                                                    Geogra phic discount*&#13;
 ** Within the U.S., charges on prepaid orders are $8.00 per order. Institutional&#13;
 customers using a purchase order will be charged actual shipping costs.&#13;
 Outside of the U.S., customers have the option to choose between non-              Shipping a nd Ha ndling**&#13;
 trackable airmail delivery (US$7 per order plus US$6 per item) and trackable&#13;
 couriered airmail delivery (US$16.50 per order plus US$8 per item) . Non-&#13;
 trackable delivery may take 4-6 weeks, trackable delivery takes about 2 weeks.     Total $US&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                              ORDER ONLINE AT www.worldbank.org/publications&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Customers in the United States                                             Customers outside the United States&#13;
Complete this form and mail it to World Bank                               Contact your local distributor for information on&#13;
Publications, P.O. Box 960, Herndon , VA 20172-                            prices in local currency and payment terms&#13;
0969 or fax it to 703-661-1501. To charge by credit                        (http://publications.worldbank.org/booksellers). If&#13;
card , either order online or call 800-645-7247 or                         you do not have a distributor, order online or fax&#13;
703-661-1580.                                                              this form to +1-703-661 -1501 or mail it to World&#13;
                                                                           Bank Publications , P.O . Box 960, Herndon , VA&#13;
                                                                           20172-0969, U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
MAILING ADDRESS                                                          METHOD OF PAYMENT&#13;
&#13;
                                                                         D Charge my&#13;
Organization _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ __                                0 Visa      0          MasterCard      0   American Express&#13;
&#13;
Address _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ __ _ _ _ __                                      Credit card number _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ __ __&#13;
&#13;
City _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ __                                    Expiration date _ _ _ __ _ _ _ _ _ _ __&#13;
&#13;
State _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _.Zip _ _ _ __                                 Name _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ __ _ __ __&#13;
&#13;
Country _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ __                                       Signature _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ __&#13;
&#13;
Phone _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ _ __&#13;
                                                                         0    Enclosed is my check in U.S. dollars, drawn from a&#13;
Fax   ------------------                                                      U.S. bank, and made payable to the World Bank&#13;
&#13;
Email _ _ _ _ _ _ __ _ _ _ _ _ _ __&#13;
                                                                                                                    Source Code&#13;
                                                                                                                    OWDR09&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
~&#13;
~&#13;
             WORLD BANK&#13;
             Publications&#13;
                                        I    The reference of choice on development&#13;
&amp;#12;&amp;#12;RESHAPING&#13;
ECONOMIC&#13;
GEOGRAPHY&#13;
Places do well when they promote transformations along the dimensions&#13;
of economic geography: higher densities as cities grow; shorter&#13;
distances as workers and businesses migrate closer to density; and&#13;
fewer divisions as nations lower their economic borders and enter&#13;
world markets to take advantage of scale and trade in specialized&#13;
products . World Development Report 2009 concludes that the&#13;
transformations along these three dimensions-density, distance, and&#13;
division-are essential for development and should be encouraged.&#13;
&#13;
The conclusion is controversial. Slum-dwellers now number a billion,&#13;
but the rush to cities continues. A billion people live in lagging areas of&#13;
developing nations, remote from globalization's many benefits. And poverty&#13;
and high mortality persist among the world 's "bottom billion," trapped&#13;
without access to global markets, even as others grow more prosperous&#13;
and live ever longer lives. Concern for these three intersecting billions often&#13;
comes with the prescription that growth must be spatially balanced.&#13;
&#13;
This report has a different message: economic growth will be unbalanced.&#13;
To try to spread it out is to discourage it-to fight prosperity, not poverty. But&#13;
development can still be inclusive, even for people who start their lives distant&#13;
from dense economic activity. For growth to be rapid and shared, governments&#13;
must promote economic integration, the pivotal concept, as this report argues,&#13;
in the policy debates on urbanization, territorial development, and regional&#13;
integration. Instead , all three debates overemphasize place-based interventions.&#13;
&#13;
Reshaping Economic Geography reframes these debates to include&#13;
all the instruments of integration-spatially blind institutions, spatially&#13;
connective infrastructure, and spatially targeted interventions. By&#13;
calibrating the blend of these instruments, today's developers can&#13;
reshape their economic geography. If they do thi s well , their growth&#13;
will still be unbalanced, but their development will be inclusive .&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
â&#128;¢        THE WORLD BANK                                                             SKU 32125&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="24016188">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2008/11/24016188/world-development-report-2009-reshaping-economic-geography-vol-2-overview
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2008/11/24016188/world-development-report-2009-reshaping-economic-geography-vol-2-overview</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2008/11/24016188/world-development-report-2009-reshaping-economic-geography-vol-2-overview</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2015-02-18T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2015-02-18T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <docm_id>090224b082c25c96</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b082c25c96</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2015/02/18/000477144_20150218104139/Rendered/INDEX/437380v20WDR0B0erview0200900PUBLIC0.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2015/02/18/000477144_20150218104139/Rendered/PDF/437380v20WDR0B0erview0200900PUBLIC0.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2015-02-18T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2008-11-04T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>2</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Revised</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309936</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>2</volnb>
        <repnme>
            World development report 2009 : reshaping
            economic geography
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Economic growth will be unbalanced, but
            development can still be inclusive-that is the message of
            this year's World development report, the thirty-first
            in the series. As economies grow from low to high income,
            production becomes more concentrated spatially. Some places,
            cities, coastal areas, and connected countries-are favored
            by producers. As countries develop, the most successful ones
            also institute policies that make living standards of people
            more uniform across space. The principle for a successful
            spatial transformation, getting the immediate benefits of
            concentration of production, and the long term benefits of a
            convergence in living standards, is economic integration.
            The report first describes the spatial transformations
            needed for development. It analyzes these changes using the
            insights from economic history and recent research. Then it
            revisits the policy debates on urbanization, regional
            development, and international integration.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            overview
        </docna>
        <display_title>World development report 2009 :
            reshaping economic geography (Vol. 2) : overview</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2008/11/24016188/world-development-report-2009-reshaping-economic-geography-vol-2-overview</listing_relative_url>
        <count>World</count>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <sectr>Agriculture, fishing, and forestry,Public Administration, Law, and Justice,Industry and trade,Education</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            agglomeration economies, agriculture, air,
            air freight, aircraft, airports, automobile, barrier, basic
            education, basic infrastructure, basic needs, big cities,
            brain drain, capital flows, cars, catalysts, citizens,
            commuters, competitiveness, concern of policy makers,
            Congestion, consumers, consumption levels, Copyright
            Clearance, Copyright Clearance Center, costs of transport,
            costs of transportation, country markets, countryside,
            crime, crossing, currency, developing countries, developing
            country, Developing economies, development policies,
            dividends, domestic markets, domestic transport, drinking
            water, drivers, dynamic economies, dynamic economy, economic
            activity, economic concentration, economic development,
            economic efficiency, ECONOMIC GEOGRAPHY, economic growth,
            economic imbalance, economic integration, economic
            opportunity, economic progress, economic prosperity,
            economic structures, economies of scale, educated migrants,
            efficient transport, efficient transport infrastructure,
            exchange rates, expensive facilities, exports, financial
            sector, financial services, foreign markets, freight,
            freight costs, GDP, GDP per capita, ghettos, global gross
            domestic product, global markets, globalization, government
            policies, gross domestic product, gross national income,
            health services, high transport, Highway, highways,
            household surveys, households, housing, Human capital, human
            settlements, illiteracy, important policy, income, income
            levels, inefficiency, infrastructure investments, insurance,
            internal migration, international borders, international
            markets, international migrants, international trade,
            interventions, journey, kids, labor markets, labor mobility,
            land use, large cities, legal status, Life expectancy,
            Literacy rates, living standards, local economy, low-income
            countries, market access, market conditions, market
            economies, middle-income countries, middle-income economies,
            migrant, migrants, Migration, Mobility, mobility of labor,
            modes of transport, mortality, movements of people, national
            income, national levels, natural endowments, neighborhood,
            neighborhoods, nutrition, pace of urbanization, passengers,
            per capita incomes, persistent poverty, policy discussions,
            policy implications, Policy makers, policy research, policy
            response, population census, population densities,
            population density, population growth, preferential access,
            primary education, primary health care, product markets,
            public services, public transportation, purchasing power,
            railroad, railway, railways, rapid economic growth, rapid
            growth, real estate, red tape, regional cooperation,
            regional development, regional disparities, regional
            integration, regional trade, remote areas, remote regions,
            reputation, residences, respect, road, Road transport,
            roads, rural areas, sanitation, savings, slum, slum
            dwellers, slums, small economies, small towns, speeds,
            startup, state governments, streets, tax, television, towns,
            trades, trains, Transport, Transport Costs, transport
            equipment, transport infrastructure, transport sector,
            transport technology, transportation system, trip, true,
            underlying problem, urban area, urban areas, urban
            economies, urban migration, urban population, urban
            population growth, urban poverty, urban settlements,
            urbanization, urbanized countries, value added, villages,
            wages, war, wealth, world markets, world trade
        </keywd>
        <majtheme>Economic management,Urban development,Public sector governance,Rural development,Financial and private sector development</majtheme>
        <alt_title>
            Informe sobre el desarrollo mundial 2009
            : una nueva geografia economica
            Rapport sur le developpement dans le
            monde 2009 : repenser la geopraphie economique
            Iaporan pembangunan dunia 2009 : menata
            ulang geografi ekonomi
        </alt_title>
        <projn>1W-World Development Report 2009: Spatial
            Disparities  And  Develo -- P106679</projn>
        <topic>Macroeconomic Stability and Growth
            m1326923 1088,Private Sector Development m1326060 1921,Transport m1326661 135,Health, Nutrition and Population m1327755 621</topic>
        <subtopic>Population Policies,Housing &amp; Human Habitats,Transport Economics Policy &amp; Planning,Emerging Markets,Economic Theory &amp; Research</subtopic>
        <docty>World Development Report</docty>
        <teratopic>Communities and Human Settlements,Health, Nutrition and Population,Transport,Private Sector Development,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</teratopic>
        <authors>
            <author>Coulibaly, Souleymane</author>
            <author>Deichmann, Uwe</author>
            <author>Freire, Maria Emilia</author>
            <author>Gill, Indermit S.</author>
            <author>Goh, Chorching</author>
            <author>Kopp, Andreas</author>
            <author>Lall, Somik V.</author>
            <author>Montenegro, Claudio E.</author>
            <author>Packard, Truman</author>
            <author>Ross-Larson, Bruce</author>
            <author>Uchida, Hirotsugu</author>
            <author>Ross-Larson, Bruce [ editor ]</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000477144_20150218104139</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <subsc>General agriculture, fishing and forestry sector,Sub-national government administration,Other industry,Other domestic and international trade,General education sector</subsc>
        <theme>Urban services and housing for the poor,Analysis of economic growth,Decentralization,Infrastructure services for private sector development,Other rural development</theme>
        <colti>World development report</colti>
        <historic_topic>Communities and Human Settlements,Health, Nutrition and Population,Transport,Private Sector Development,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</historic_topic>
        <prdln>World Development Report</prdln>
        <topicv3>Macroeconomic Stability and Growth
            m1326923 1088,Private Sector Development m1326060 1921,Transport m1326661 135,Health, Nutrition and Population m1327755 621</topicv3>
        <owner>World Development Report (DECWD)</owner>
        <trustfund>TF090153-JAPAN CTF - FY07: GENERAL BBMC
            (ALL BANK BORROWING MEMBER COUNTRIES/ALL,TF090474-WDR 2009 SPATIAL AND DISPARITY DEVELOPMENT</trustfund>
        <repnb>43738</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts/><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>