<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Water and                                                                               25695&#13;
Sanitation&#13;
tiff&gt; I   l l iM&#13;
partnership to help                                    - ;                  rarialrl- U            iG01i        ttailk&#13;
the poor gain sustained&#13;
access to improved                                                        -__&#13;
water supply and&#13;
sanitation services                          -       a    ]                         _      _     _     _      _     _      _&#13;
._  - 1 _   .,   .~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~-- --- &#13;
June 2002                                                    _XX&#13;
F O R E W O R D 6                                ImpIem nting Sector Reforms&#13;
The reforms currently undertaken by the&#13;
Government of India in the rural drinking water  i A  review        of selected           state      experiences&#13;
and sanitation sector mark a major departure&#13;
from the conventional allocation-based rural&#13;
water supply and sanitation services to one that  :                                       -   .&#13;
adopts a community-oriented and participative       - -s_&#13;
approach. Significant progress has been                              --..-.&#13;
achieved in mobilizing proposals and               Z5.                     '        '      S       -      -' &#13;
substantial funds (Rs. 5,720 million) have been                                    *-              v.&#13;
disbursed to 65 districts of 26 states towards&#13;
implementing the 'Sector Reform Program'                                              = E  -                                       3&#13;
(SRP). At the request of the Drinking Water&#13;
Supply Department, GOI, the Water and&#13;
Sanitation Program-South Asia conducted an      -       _&#13;
independent rapid review of the implementation  4-r&#13;
of the program in October 2001 across five&#13;
randomly selected districts each in different                                                          L&#13;
states. The intent of monitoring the SRP&#13;
implementation process was to assess the&#13;
progress in terms of the reform principles&#13;
and guidelines, identify the constraints and&#13;
issues and make recommendations for the&#13;
program as a whole.                                                                                      di&#13;
By disseminating the findings and&#13;
recommendations of the review, the&#13;
lal Manthan has built a consensus around issues&#13;
which are critical to the future success of the&#13;
SRP. The implementation process has witnessed&#13;
some innovations attempted by stakeholders in&#13;
order to adopt this reform-oriented program.&#13;
Critical issues of capacity-building, IEC&#13;
strategies, the role of the Panchayati Raj&#13;
Institutions, criteria for habitation selection and&#13;
prioritization, community participation and        f'&#13;
management of schemes have emerged. The&#13;
implementing states accept the centrality of&#13;
these concerns and intend to actively adopt the&#13;
proposed recommendations.                                           A      -&#13;
The Government of India appreciates the&#13;
role of WSP-SA in carrying out the review&#13;
which has proved to be extremely useful and&#13;
timely. The RGNDWM will work out a road map                                                                                           &lt;&#13;
for a more extensive review in the current year.&#13;
A.K. Coswami&#13;
Secretary&#13;
Department of Drinking Water Supply&#13;
Ministry of Rural Development                                                                                           &gt;&#13;
Government of India&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
BACK(GROUND                                                    Rajiv Gandhi National Drinking Water Mission&#13;
Department of Drinking Water Supply  x&#13;
The Government of India (GOI) is implementing a                          and&#13;
program of reforms in the Rural Water Supply and               WVater and Sanitation Program - South Asia&#13;
Sanitation (RWSS) sector carved out of the Accelerated&#13;
Rural Water Supply Programme to pilot demand-responsive            Jal    Manthan&#13;
approaches to RWSS. The Sector Reform Program (SRP) is  Sector Reform    Projects Implementation&#13;
probably the world's largest Central Government-supported               Z6 February 2002&#13;
rural drinking water and sanitation program based on                India Habitat Center, New Delhi&#13;
demand-responsive principles. The program, launched in&#13;
April 1999, has so far sanctioned US$ 4001 million of&#13;
Government of India budgeted resources - with no external ' *-- -   .  - -&#13;
assistance involved - for 65 districts spread across&#13;
26 states covering a population of over 70 million.                                                     &lt;&#13;
The following principles drive the program:                                                    v&#13;
7 subsidiarity, that is, services should be delivered at the  .-_&#13;
lowest appropriate level;&#13;
t7 adoption of a demand-driven and participatory      JNItHA             X    ..OWt1 &#13;
approach;                                                                                               &lt;&#13;
6 focus on village level capacity-building;&#13;
6 integrated approach to water supply, sanitation and    The Drinking Water Supply Department (DWSD),&#13;
hygiene promotion;                                   GOI, requested WSP to conduct an independent rapid&#13;
o partial capital cost recovery and full operations and  review of the progress of the SRP. The review was&#13;
maintenance (O&amp;M) financing by users; and            conducted in October 2001 and included field visits (to the&#13;
6 promotion of groundwater conservation and          State Government, district level implementing agencies&#13;
rainwater harvesting.                                and selected villages) and a review of secondary data.&#13;
The program demonstrates a real paradigm shift in     The findings and recommendations of the review were&#13;
governments thinking on rural water supply: moving from a  disseminated and discussed at a workshop in Delhi on&#13;
centralized, supply-driven approach to a people-centered,  February 26, 2002. The workshop was chaired by the&#13;
demand-driven approach that focuses on decentralized  Secretary, DWSD and enjoyed participation from 11&#13;
delivery through local governments. Under this program,  State Governments (the five participating in the review&#13;
ownership of the assets by local communities and local  plus another six states), some district level implementers,&#13;
governments is promoted. The primary objective of the  officials from the RGNDWM, External Support Agencies&#13;
program is to achieve environmental, institutional and  and resource persons. The full proceedings are with&#13;
financial sustainability of systems and sources. The Water  WSP-SA. This field note summarizes the key findings&#13;
and Sanitation Program-South Asia (WSP-SA) has a      and recommendations.&#13;
strategic alliance with the Rajiv Gandhi National Drinking&#13;
Water Mission (RGNDWM) to provide technical assistance  S1~ U  V,~ ~R            F~ND     NG&#13;
to the SRP to improve the effectiveness and efficiency       I b .        'l'U   UUU\JLNIUUNJ   \&#13;
of implementation.                                    0 FT       E RE VDEW2&#13;
The objective of the rapid review was to get quick&#13;
feedback on the implementation of the Sector Reform&#13;
Program in the states. It was not intended to be&#13;
. _--                 (-     comprehensive - in geographical coverage or subject&#13;
9&gt; \ &gt;-.-     ~              tc t ;, _- ~teL; matter - just a 'snapshot' view at how the program was&#13;
7.1 ik_2  ip - ,'  w |  _;_  being taken up. Five districts in five states were randomly&#13;
!        ,i p i t .  tW |  ;   selected for the study: Agra (Uttar Pradesh), Coimbatore&#13;
(Tamil Nadu), Kamrup (Assam), Medinipur (West Bengal),&#13;
&lt;;     &gt; _   -n.q-           4&gt;---     _   :    1   1  and Moga (Punjab). During October 2001, meetings were&#13;
O ' '   '       %                    7i0r ,.  t t'~i/'',Sq  held with state officials and the District Water and&#13;
u      j    -S3' g1                   n   U 4;,t,,     Sanitation Mission and a few field visits were conducted.&#13;
No debriefing was conducted; however, state and district&#13;
officials were requested to comment at the Delhi workshop&#13;
&lt;:                                                     in February 2002.&#13;
One United States dollar (US$) = Rs. 49 (INR) (as on May 2002)&#13;
2 The detailed review of each state and district has been docuimented in the review report available from RGNDWM&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Sixth Jul Manthan: List of Participants&#13;
Implementing Sector Reforms: A review of selected state experiences&#13;
Februory 26, 2002, New Delhi, India&#13;
PUNJAB             _                                  P K Gopalakrishnan Member Secretary of DWSM&#13;
Chellamuthu Co-opting NGOs&#13;
CHANDIGARH&#13;
Gurbinder Chahal Principal Secretary, DPH             CUDDALORE&#13;
D Indra Bhupal Reddy Member Secretary&#13;
PATIALA                                               Antony Samy BLESS, NGO&#13;
Manmohanjit Singh Chief Engineer&#13;
VELLORE&#13;
MOGA                                                  S Govindarajan Member Secretary&#13;
S Kanwal Bir Singh Sindhu Deputy Commissioner-cum-    M Sillupan Co-opting NGOs&#13;
Chairman, District Water &amp; Sanitation Mis.&#13;
S C Gupta Superintending Engineer, Public Health      ARIYALUR&#13;
B K Singla Executive Engineer, Public Health          S Nagamalal Executive Engineer&#13;
BATHINDA                                              PERAMBALUR&#13;
Additional Deputy Commissioner                        N Selvam Member Secretary&#13;
S S Ubhi Superintending Engineer&#13;
ASSAM&#13;
UTTAR PRADESH                                         P K Duraah Commissioner-cum-Secretary (PHED)&#13;
Naren Konwar Senior Engineer&#13;
LUCKNOW                                              Akshay Pathak Senior Engineer&#13;
Ajit Seth Principal Secretary, Rural Development      R Sharma Assistant Engineer&#13;
Arun Arya Director, Swajal Project                    R Burman Assistant Engineer&#13;
AGRA                                                  WEST BENGAL       _=&#13;
Ms. Rita Singh Chief Development Officer              S Chaudhuri Principal Secretary&#13;
A K Singh District Development Officer                D K Chakraborty Deputy Director&#13;
Arun Kumor&#13;
SONBHADRA&#13;
Arvind Kumar Dwedi Chief Development Officer&#13;
Kripa Ram Singh District Development Officer&#13;
MIRZAPUR&#13;
Deenkar Prakash Dubey Chief Development Officer&#13;
Krishan Chandra Swarnkar District Development Officer&#13;
CHANDOLI&#13;
Amar Bahadur Singh&#13;
TAMILNADU                                   ___&#13;
CHENNAI&#13;
K Deenabandu Member Secretary of SWSM&#13;
COIMBATORE&#13;
N Murugananda'm District Collector and&#13;
Chairman of DWSM&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
M0XIAPORE                                             MADHYA PRADESH |           _:&#13;
Ashoke oGY Executive Engineer&#13;
BHOPAL&#13;
MHA1AASHTRA .            .                            Satyanand Mishrcy Principal Secretary, PHED&#13;
B C Khatua Secretory                                  S K Verma Advisor, PHED&#13;
Sudhir ThakGre Deputy Secretary&#13;
GWALIOR&#13;
MAN^DED                                               Devendra Ahuja Chief Executive Officer&#13;
Vijaykumar Mahata Chief Executive Officer&#13;
RESOURCE PERSONS =&#13;
UTTARANCHAL r_       =                                Balachandra Kurup&#13;
J K NAGu Director, PMU                                 Preminda Kundra&#13;
ANDHRA PRADESH E                                      DONORS                 =&#13;
Ncsrasimha Rao Commissioner, APARD                    Nigel Kirby DFID&#13;
G Krishnay Murty Chief Engineer, Panchayati Rai&#13;
WORLD BANK                -&#13;
PRAlKASAM                                             G V Abhyankar&#13;
Ibrahim Executive Secretory&#13;
UNICEF              _&#13;
G2SS;Q LM_ =enk van Norden&#13;
BALASORE                                              GOVERNMENTOFINDIA |             :.&#13;
C 1 Mohanty Executive Engineer                        A K Goswami Secretory&#13;
1 C Panda Joint Secretary, RGM&#13;
SUNDARGARM                                            M V Kutty Director, RGM&#13;
2N Nayyak Executive Engineer                           Marish Kumar Deputy Director&#13;
Gayafri Sharma Deputy Secretary&#13;
Kumar Alok Deputy Secretary&#13;
Chakravorty Additional Advisor&#13;
C Ganapaty Deputy Advisor&#13;
1 M Deshpancdy Deputy Advisor&#13;
Dinesh Chand Deputy Advisor&#13;
A K Jain Deputy Director&#13;
Y K Sood Under Secretary&#13;
N T Joseph Under Secretary&#13;
WSP-SA IZ_&#13;
Junaid Ahmad Regional Team Leader&#13;
Vivek Srivastava India Team Leader&#13;
Mike Webster Rural Development Specialist&#13;
Risha Join Finance Specialist&#13;
Vandana Mehra Communication Specialist&#13;
Soma Ghosh Moulik Urban Institutional Specialist&#13;
C S Renjit Sector Reform Co-ordinator&#13;
Ajit Kumar Sector Reform Co-ordinator&#13;
J V R Muvuy Sector Reform Co-ordinator&#13;
M Kullappa Sector Reform Co-ordinator&#13;
Suseel Samuel Sector Reform Co-ordinator&#13;
-  . : . -- -      i        Sayan9ani Gaddam Consultant&#13;
Prosun Bhanacharjee Consultant&#13;
Poonam Chihkara Program Assistant&#13;
John Prakash Program Assistant&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Activity Phase       Assam           Punjab          Tamil Nadu       Uttar Pradesh   West Bengal&#13;
Institutionalizing   Partial         Partial         Completed        Partial         Started&#13;
Sensitizing and      Started         Partial         Partial          Started         Yet to Start&#13;
Identification&#13;
Planning             Yet to Start    In Progress      In Progress     Yet to Start    Yet to Start&#13;
Implementation       Yet to Start    In Progress     In Progress      Yet to Start    Yet to Start&#13;
and Handover&#13;
Notes&#13;
6 The activity phases pertain to those defined in Section 4.3 of the RGNDWM guidelines&#13;
6 'Started' denotes low coverage of sub-activities; 'Partial' is above medium but not full coverage of sub-activities;&#13;
and 'In Progress' indicates that the phase has initiated final sub-activities in the sequence, but not finished&#13;
sub-activities before&#13;
Overall find'ings                                    Some distinguishing features&#13;
The SRP has achieved progress in mobilizing           Although the overall finding of the review is of poor&#13;
proposals and disbursing substantial funds to districts.  progress, each district displayed some positive features.&#13;
Some awareness about reforms and the SRP is evident in  Some of these are recorded here. Table 2 displays a&#13;
each of the states, however on the whole, progress in  simplified representation of the institutional structure of the&#13;
implementation is poor. Table 1 gives a snapshot of  five states at the state, district and village level.&#13;
progress in each of the reviewed states using the phases  Baseline and 'demand generation' surveys in Assam:&#13;
laid out in the RGNDWM guidelines. This indicates that  In Kamrup district the PHED has undertaken two sets of&#13;
most states are clearly behind schedule.             surveys. The first is a census conducted earlier in each of&#13;
Some common features in implementation in all the  the habitations to document the status of water and&#13;
states are listed here:                              sanitation at the household level, apart from other&#13;
6 The progress of SRP has been patchy. With the exception  demographic details. This has provided information on the&#13;
of Coimbatore and Moga, progress in the other three  coverage of habitations and their categorization into fully&#13;
districts was found to be tardy;                      covered, partially covered and not covered categories&#13;
6 In most states the state engineering department continues  using current, not historic, data. A second baseline survey&#13;
to be at the center in the implementation of the SRP;  seeks to cover about 500 habitations. Entitled 'Demand&#13;
6 No clear demarcation has been followed between policy  Generation for Water Supply and Sanitation', this survey&#13;
and implementation of the SRP process by the newly   seeks to collect household level data on current&#13;
formed state and district level bodies;              arrangements and preferences of the respondent&#13;
6 Present monitoring formats were found to be inadequate  households and whether and how much will they be&#13;
for capturing process issues;                        willing to pay for water supply and sanitation.&#13;
6 Shortcomings in IEC strategies, capacity-building and   Transfer of funds to villages in Punjab: In Moga&#13;
village level participatory processes remain;         district, bank accounts have been opened for the District&#13;
6 No development of well laid-out and transparent criteria  Water and Sanitation Mission (DWSM) and 38 of the&#13;
for habitation selection and prioritization;          proposed 302 Village Water and Sanitation Committees&#13;
6 Real choice of technology and cost options have not  (VWSCs). GOI funds for the SRP are routed to the DWSM&#13;
been fully explored and offered to communities;      account. The Executive Engineer-RWS disburses the funds&#13;
6 Operation and maintenance (O&amp;M) cost implications  to the agencies and VWSCs after sanction is accorded by&#13;
(life cycle costs, energy costs) have not been       the District Water and Sanitation Committee (DWSC).&#13;
fully considered;                                    Although the DoPW (PH) is uncomfortable with the fact&#13;
6 Source sustainability options have not been        that there are no control mechanisms provided in the&#13;
fully explored;                                      guidelines, independent fund management by the VWSC&#13;
6 The goal of community planned, designed, implemented  has been suggested for the future; however at the time of&#13;
and managed schemes has been partially realized; and  the review, no VWSC had taken up independent&#13;
6 The Total Sanitation Campaign (TSC) has not been    management of funds. These transfers are in line with the&#13;
integrated with the SRP in any of the states.        recommendations of the RGNDWM finance manual.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
! ., : --     ,                - ~ ,    ,     ,- , , -  :;i  . '   '!,--w.\ -  il  -r,1. *-  l ! lli,- -@ ^v.'&#13;
Level    Assam                   Punjab             Tamil Nadu       Uttar Pradesh     West Bengal&#13;
State   Public Health           Department of      Tamil Nadu       Department of     PHED&#13;
level   Engineering             Public Works       Water and        Rural&#13;
Department              (Public Health)    Drainage Board   Development&#13;
(PHED)                  DoPW (PH)          (TWAD)           (RD)&#13;
District  PHED                   DoPW (PH)          TWAD             District         Zilla Parishad&#13;
level                                                                Programme         (ZP)&#13;
Management Unit&#13;
(DPMU)&#13;
Village  Anchalic Panchayat      Village Water &amp;    VWSC             VWSC/Jal          Panchayat&#13;
level    Water &amp; Sanitation      Sanitation                          Prabandhan        Samiti (PS)/GP&#13;
Mission (APWSM)         Committee                           Samiti (JPS)&#13;
Gram Panchayat (GP)     (VWSC)&#13;
Efficiency and pace of execution in Tamil Nadu:  hence, providing the basis for the long-term institutional&#13;
Coimbatore district has made significant physical and  sustainability of the SRP.&#13;
financial progress by setting up about 100 drinking water&#13;
supply schemes, organizing VWSCs as a standing        T=iHiG7NG             OSSU     ES&#13;
committee of the Gram Panchayat (GP) and by utilizing&#13;
nearly three-quarters of the funds released by GOI. The   Some of the key constraints and issues which emerged&#13;
community's response to the SRP has been good. The   through the review process and the Jal Manthan&#13;
State Government's earlier program with participatory  deliberations are summarized here.&#13;
approaches, requiring the community to contribute a&#13;
minimum of 25 per cent of the costs, could have acted as a  (CapzdKy B   du]0fldhg  znd      K&#13;
catalyst for the community's willingness to adopt the SRP.  Capacity-building has not received adequate&#13;
Priority has been given to IEC activities through the  importance. The nodal agency and state/district institutions&#13;
effective engagement of NGOs and self-help groups.    of the SRP need active assistance from the center to&#13;
The latter are working as catalysts to promote the    (a) interpret the guidelines; and (b) recognize the centrality&#13;
role of women.                                       of the 'software component' of the SRP. DWSMs (and&#13;
Amendment of the Panchayati Raj Act in            DWSCs) need to absorb a mix of skills within their&#13;
Uttar Pradesh: The Panchayati Raj Act has been suitably  organizations, especially in the areas technical, financial,&#13;
amended to enable the formation of VWSCs.3 Under the  community mobilization, communications and&#13;
new arrangement, the Jal Prabandhan Samiti (JPS), which is  participation competencies.&#13;
a sub-committee of the GP, will function as the VWSC. The  At the heart of the program, GOI is trying to enhance&#13;
representative of the village water-user group will be  the capacity of local institutions (GPs and communities) to&#13;
co-opted in the JPS. This will link the GP with the water  manage their own services. Intensive and innovative&#13;
user group of each revenue village which carries out the  capacity-building programs will need to be developed in&#13;
spot selection. Bank accounts maintained by the JPS will  each district to effect such a change. These can use a&#13;
be jointly operated, with authority vested in one elected  combination of 'supplied' training programs - through&#13;
member of the JPS and one water-user group member. With  NGOs, training institutions or the private sector - and&#13;
effect from April 2002, all handpumps are to be transferred  institutions that can respond to local demands.&#13;
to the GPs and maintained by them.                        A critical component of the SRP is an IEC&#13;
Potenitial integrat,ion with PRls in West, Bengal: West  (Information, Education and Communication) strategy&#13;
Potentihasawell ntegration withl PRosinmWest Bysteng   which targets the community's needs and dilutes the role of&#13;
Bengal has a well developed local government system  politically motivated resource allocation decisions. GOI&#13;
ideally suited to implementing the SRP. No constraints  can give a good lead by focusing on mass media&#13;
have been reported in the flow of funds from the DWSM to  campaigns and by creating a political platform in support&#13;
Gram Panchayats. With the success of the sanitation  of reforms. The IEC strategies should specifically target&#13;
programs being undertaken actively by the PRIs in the  women, poorer communities, water quality affected&#13;
district there exists an opportunity for integrating water  habitations and multi-village schemes. Awareness of these&#13;
supply and sanitation provision to the PRI system and  issues would enhance the communities willingness to pay&#13;
3At the time of the review an ongoing confusion was found in Uttar Pradesh regarding the statUs of VWSCs. However, during the Jal Manthan workshop this problem was&#13;
found to he solved&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
_                                                   JAL MANTHAN 6&#13;
Water and                                             June 2002&#13;
Sanitation&#13;
1. Is the format of this publication easy to read?                       OYes                            O No&#13;
2. Is the publication a comfortable length to read?                      O Yes                           O No&#13;
3. If no, would you prefer                                               O more details/data             0 less details/data&#13;
4. Do you find the information contained in this publication relevant to your work?                      D Yes       0 No&#13;
If yes, how would you use this information in your work? (Use extra sheets of paper if required)  If no, give reasons why&#13;
(Use extra sheets of paper if required)&#13;
..................   .   . .   . .   . .   . .   . .   . .   . .   . .   . .   . .   . .   . .   . .  .   . .   .   . .   . .   . ......&#13;
What impat, if any, does this information have an:                                            .    .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .&#13;
Yo.   ..  . .   . .   . .   . .   . .   . .   . . . . ... . . .   . .   . .   . . . . .   .   . ,   . ,   . ,   . ,   . ,   .   .   .   .   .   .   . .   .&#13;
OYour org niz tion: .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .   .   .   .  .   .  .  .  .  .  .  .&#13;
Y o u r .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .&#13;
What are the main lesson(s) you have learnt from the information contained in this publication?&#13;
.       .  .&#13;
Would you like to share any study/research similar to the information in this publication?&#13;
. . ..  .  .  .  . , .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .   .   .   .   .   .   .&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
5    { u!u rO   . to 1 bj3e    in ihnV Wnter oitpply .rid Sauintationi sertor thot interest you citacd you would liko to&#13;
i':10'~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ .m r                  .   ...    ..     ..                    ..   &#13;
ii)&#13;
iii)  .                                                            .&#13;
6. Do you know anyone else who might benefit from receiving our publication?&#13;
If yes, provide the following detoils (optional)&#13;
Name: .&#13;
Designation:   . . .&#13;
Organization: .&#13;
Address:&#13;
Phone Numbers: . .       ............................................&#13;
E-mail:.&#13;
Area of work: Government / NGO / Private Sector / Academia / Consultant / Bilateral Agency / Dev Bank / any other&#13;
7. Provide your particulars (if different from address on envelope)&#13;
Name: .&#13;
Designation: . . . .&#13;
Organization:&#13;
Address:.&#13;
Phone Numbers: .............................................&#13;
E-mail: .. .&#13;
Area of work: Government / NGO / Private Sector / Academia / Consultant / Bilateral Agency / Dev Bank / any other&#13;
8. Indicate your area of interest:&#13;
I Water&#13;
D Sanitation&#13;
Rural&#13;
U Urbc,n&#13;
Water and Sanitation Program-South Asia&#13;
55 Lodi Estate, New Delhi 110 003 * Tel: 91-11-4690488/89 * Fax: 91-11-4628250                    *&#13;
* E-mail: wspsa@worldbank.org * Website: www.wsp.org&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
for the services. In addition, making communities fully        =-                   i.&#13;
aware of payment issues, future implications of scheme        - .&#13;
ownership and maintenance would play an important role  -v         ____i&#13;
in the sustainability of the program. The implementers of  * .&#13;
SRP should appreciate the role of support organizations,  .-.&#13;
NGOs and external aid agencies in developing systematic                                    t&#13;
communication strategies.                           .         Eis                                 -&#13;
Habitation selection&#13;
and prioritization&#13;
The criteria for habitation selection and prioritization  .   ;   .&#13;
is critical to the sustainability, equity and coverage aspects&#13;
of the RWSS. Each district will need to balance the&#13;
competing objectives of coverage and sustainability and&#13;
develop transparent selection criteria that give appropriate                     i&#13;
weight to each component. A good lead has been taken in&#13;
Assam on conducting village level household-based&#13;
benchmark surveys for assessing need and demand for the&#13;
services. Surveys of this detail would complement the  .- &#13;
traditional NC/PC/FC categories of habitation selection to  .. .   - .1&#13;
reflect dynamic categories based on demand. Use of&#13;
households as units for measuring coverage and demand can  IEC is a critical component of the Sector Reform Program&#13;
mitigate the potential bias of the SRP schemes toward richer&#13;
households as reported in Punjab. Village development  service providers (UP being the exception to this). Limited&#13;
plans generated through PLA exercises can be used to  adjustments have been made to create new institutions at&#13;
improve habitation selection, service levels and provide  the village and district levels.&#13;
more equitable and transparent criteria for selection.  The real challenge in the SRP is not to deliver the taps&#13;
but to generate institutions to take forward the delivery of&#13;
e      els 44+  44{s  |           4.          water services. The program gives immense flexibility to&#13;
.I.n.s.ltitutional arrangemen ts                    districts in the use of various service providers. There is&#13;
There have been delays in setting up institutions and  little experience in India of the private sector being&#13;
their proper functioning in most of the states. The  contracted to provide RWSS services, however officials&#13;
distinction between the state and district level missions (for  from Haryana reported that some preliminary work is being&#13;
policy guidance and supervision) and executive      done in this area. Other actors at the community level who&#13;
committees (for implementation/execution) has not been  have proven to work as catalysts and can be included in&#13;
followed in most cases. The newly formed bodies also  the SRP institutional frame are : (a) parent teacher&#13;
reflect a de facto predominance of the conventional  associations to provide water supply and sanitation to&#13;
In October 2001, Shri M. Venkaiah Naidu, the Union Minister of Rural Development, chaired a two-day conference of&#13;
State Ministers In Charge Of Rural Water Supply, in New Delhi.&#13;
The conference recommended that once the coverage of all rural habitations in any state is achieved, the norms&#13;
for coverage may be relaxed to provide for 55 lpcd with a source within 0.5 km in the plains or 50 meters elevation in&#13;
the hills. The criteria for allocation of funds to states to be modified as: weightage for the NC/PC habitations to be&#13;
increased from 10 per cent to 15 per cent and that of quality-affected habitations to be increased from 5 per cent to&#13;
1 0 per cent.&#13;
The concept of community participation is to be adopted in normal RWS programs after full coverage of&#13;
habitations as per the present norms. Community contributions of a minimum of 10 per cent of the capital cost and&#13;
the O&amp;M management and financing will be necessary for service level augmentation beyond the existing norms.&#13;
States were also in favor of carrying out a re-survey of all habitations for making a realistic assessment of the situation.&#13;
The conference directed that the on-going survey of quality-affected habitations should be completed. In such&#13;
habitations a concept of dual water supply is to be considered to provide treated water up tol 0 Ipcd for drinking and&#13;
cooking and untreated water for other purposes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
schools; (b) anganwadis and SHGs for ensuring greater  burdened them beyond their capacity, affected process&#13;
participation of women; (c) the introduction of annual  quality (especially software inputs) and restricted the entry&#13;
maintenance service providers in the O&amp;M, and        of other capable agencies (GO/NGO) in the SRP. The&#13;
(d) contracting out of O&amp;M management services.      division of roles and responsibilities between state, district,&#13;
sub-district, village and scheme/user levels remains&#13;
.-   7 -.                                 unclear to most actors in the SRP. Therefore, the program&#13;
20 '   '   j ' ':has tended to be internalized in a select technical agency&#13;
The role of the Public Health Engineering        and has been viewed and implemented essentially as an&#13;
Departments (PHEDs - or the equivalent body          engineering project. Uttar Pradesh is an exception&#13;
conventionally responsible for rural water supply)   where the SRP is being implemented by the&#13;
remains central in most of the reviewed states. This 'nodal'  Department of Rural Development.&#13;
agency plays multiple roles within the institutional&#13;
framework created in the states. This agency is involved in  Uhe  p a ) (D)   7',1$&#13;
all facets of scheme implementation right from inception    JU-          U&#13;
till completion:                                         With the exception of West Bengal (where currently&#13;
6 The PHED is responsible for selecting habitations  there are intentions of integration), the role of the&#13;
according to supply-driven criteria;                 Panchayati Raj Institutions (PRIs) has not been adequately&#13;
6 The agency is represented in the governing and     strengthening in implementing the SRP. The SRP provides&#13;
executive institution at the state and district levels, holds  an opportunity for strengthening PRIs and integrating water&#13;
the responsibility of fund drawal and disbursement,  supply and sanitation provision to the PRI system and&#13;
prepares the designs and estimates and also carries out  hence, providing the basis for long-term institutional&#13;
village mobilization, IEC and HRD activities; and    sustainability. The SRP guidelines now prescribe that the&#13;
6 After the DWSC approves schemes, the agency takes up  VWSC should be explicitly linked to the GP.&#13;
execution or contracts out works, certifies the executed&#13;
scheme and then hands them over to the VWSC.          ( I-. '- 0.            )/r (\)&#13;
Translation of the SRP as another scheme         (   L GIL' .. -~L'J K, -&#13;
implemented by PHEDs has arisen out of their incentive to  The review revealed that communities remain&#13;
'speedily implement works', retain management control  marginalized at all levels of scheme planning, designing,&#13;
and to internalize financial resources. This has, however,  implementation and management due to the dominance of&#13;
1 ,   4I.b.  , . .   -  . I  , -   -&#13;
The Odanthurai Panchayat, Coimbatore district (Tamil Nadu) is a large Panchayat comprising seven habitations&#13;
located near the town of Mettupalayam in Coimbatore district. Under the Sector Reform Program, a piped water&#13;
supply system tapping water from the river Bhavani with a sedimentation tank and slow sand filtration unit has been&#13;
constructed in the village. It was the first Panchayat that saw an opportunity in the program and contacted TWAD to&#13;
design a system to meet their requirements. They identified the in-take point, the land where the sand filter tanks and&#13;
pumping station could be located and the alignment of the piped supply system. The village collected contributions&#13;
from potential users while TWAD designed the Rs. 48 lakh scheme as per the requirements expressed by the Sarpanch&#13;
and was commissioned in February 2001. The community contributed Rs. 6.2 lakh (13 per cent). In the village, a&#13;
VWSC was formed with all nine members of the Panchayat and three other nominated members - the school teacher,&#13;
a tribal woman and another woman representative. The VWSC members collected the household contributions that&#13;
varied from house to house, depending on affordability. This money was deposited with the DWSC. The scheme,&#13;
although designed to provide 450 individual connections, at present provides only 1 75 individual connections. The&#13;
VWSC collects a connection charge of Rs. 1,000.&#13;
In Odanthurai, Sintex tanks have been provided to distribute water from the SRP scheme and an income of&#13;
Rs. 1,500 is anticipated from such stand post users. While this accounts for about 10 per cent of the cost of operations,&#13;
the VWSC/Panchayats face a challenging task in regular collection of tariffs from such consumers who in the past have&#13;
not been charged for the use of stand posts.&#13;
The village agriculture depends on ground water. Drinking water is accessed from the surface water source, thus&#13;
eliminating the possibility of conflict between different end-users of water. It is unlikely that a large diversion structure&#13;
will be constructed upstream; therefore there is little risk to the sustainability of the source.&#13;
Local strategies to arrive at the right mix of connection types (including group connections) and tariffs for equity&#13;
in the provision and financial viability of the system are yet to emerge, although the skills and political space to design&#13;
such systems appear to exist in the village.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
the nodal agencies (PHED and equivalent). Existing   technologies believed to be appropriate for rural villages.&#13;
participatory planning tools have not been used and there  This is fine in a supply-driven paradigm where the state&#13;
have been no instances of the use of PLA in preparing a  finances most of the costs of supply. Under SRP, it is&#13;
village plan. The SRP has so far focused on implementing  essential to provide habitations different technology&#13;
schemes based on a community's ability to pay and    options - with associated capital and recurrent costs - for&#13;
consequently supply-driven processes are predominant. At  them to make informed choices about suitable levels of&#13;
the community level, the requirement of a minimum of  service. Communities need to be taken through a process&#13;
10 per cent capital cost contribution in the SRP is not  whereby they consider all feasible technical options&#13;
perceived as a constraint. As regards equity, the early  (handpumps, rainwater harvesting, piped schemes,&#13;
involvement of the poorest communities will enhance the  stand posts, house connections, wells, etc. ) in order&#13;
successful foundation of any participatory program.  to develop their own system which they are able to&#13;
finance and manage.&#13;
Operation and                                        WAYFORWARD&#13;
Maintenance (O&amp;M)                                    WAYoFORWaRD&#13;
The O&amp;M financing and management aspects of the  Recommendations&#13;
SRP need scrutiny. The workshop reported instances of  of the   review&#13;
third party contribution to cover capital cost and O&amp;M&#13;
financing. Such contribution should not be accepted other  The review identified the difficulties in transforming a&#13;
than in addition to the community contribution. The  scheme-oriented and allocation-based institutional&#13;
VWSCs must reiterate the message that full O&amp;M financing  structure in the states and districts to one that delivers a&#13;
and management is the community's responsibility. O&amp;M  reform-oriented program. Specific recommendations were&#13;
financing must consider all life cycle costs, implications of  made under the following three broad areas:&#13;
power sector reforms, differential user tariffs and phasing  Issues to be addressed at the national level&#13;
out of agency management. The issue of energy costs at  4 Prepare detailed guidelines on capacity-building&#13;
the state level is contentious. There are several state  measures and participatory techniques;&#13;
electricity boards which do not charge the rural users.  * Clarify the role of support organizations and local&#13;
States will have to develop a comprehensive strategy for  government institutions;&#13;
implementing the O&amp;M guidelines at the village level  4 Outline approaches for integrating drinking water supply,&#13;
by removing the existing competing paradigms.        household sanitation and environmental sanitation;&#13;
Complementing this, exit policies must be formulated  * Improve the monitoring mechanism for future review&#13;
for the supply-oriented institutions to be systematically  and evaluation; and&#13;
phased out.                                          4 Field support and supervision missions to monitor&#13;
effective implementation of the SRP activities at the&#13;
Technology   choice                   ~~~~~~~~~state level.&#13;
Technology          choice                               Issues to be addressed at the state level&#13;
and    cost options                                  * Develop a clear policy on RWSS;&#13;
4 Bring PRIs to the centerstage of the program and build&#13;
RWS agencies in the past have prescribed set    the necessary capacity to implement;&#13;
4 Develop transparent selection criteria for habitation&#13;
As the Minster for Rural Development for the       prioritization and selection;&#13;
Government of India, I have the responsibility to  associated costs;&#13;
facilitate local government delivery of a number of  4sDevelop capacity-building plans and IEC and community&#13;
important rural services including water supply,     Develop  st t&#13;
education, health, rural roads, electricity, etc. If  mobilization strategies;&#13;
through the reforms in the water sector we can create  b Share best practices and reform experiences&#13;
robust institutions for good local governance, these  between districts; and&#13;
can be effectively used for the delivery of a host of  4 Assess implications of future energy costs for technology&#13;
other local public initiatives and services which will  options as this is a significant input of the O&amp;M costs&#13;
have a positive impact on rural development and    (typically around 60-70 per cent).&#13;
poverty reduction.                                     Second generation issues&#13;
(Presentation made by the Honorable Minister       4 Develop a plan for states to scale-up the reform process&#13;
for Rural Development, Shri M. Venkaiah Naidu at   and eliminate competing paradigms; and&#13;
Water Forum 2002, World Bank, Washington DC, May 6, 2002)  4 Develop a framework for assessing sustainability of water&#13;
resources and SRP institutional mechanisms.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
* Jal Maith,in 1: kestrLCtLiri ng&#13;
I'HEI)s/Water B3oards: Why and          The Jal Manthan (meaning 'churning of water' in Hindi) is a think tank&#13;
[low? Delhi, May 1999               on rural water supply and sanitation. It is a travelling forum that aims to be&#13;
al watr1 M ahly 2: aecentrsaiztaed  an open network encouraging frank and informal policy-level dialogue&#13;
IrLrrl water supply 111dl saniltation1&#13;
management. Cochlin, July 1999      between sector practitioners and professionals.&#13;
* Iail Mant han 3: State Water&#13;
Minister's workshop, Cochin,&#13;
Decembher 1 999&#13;
* Jal Manthan 4: Launching Sector&#13;
Reforms&#13;
* lal Manthan 5: People's Initiative&#13;
for Total Sanitation. B3angladesh,              J&#13;
FebrUary 2002                                     Xr&#13;
(f-o(c(dij,,s of t l/t ,iJove workshops            _I r-J&#13;
(n he)( oblt,ioeI Ii frn)il thu' tA,ie W r ,ind&#13;
Sanif.ition i'rwr,ini)&#13;
Rajiv Gandhi National Drinking Water Mission  addition, it will consider formulating MOUs with&#13;
Department of Drinking Water Supply           participating states;&#13;
Department  and                    \, States must prepare capacity-building plans in the areas&#13;
Water and Sanitation Program - South Asia     of IEC, social mobilization, gender sensitization and PLA&#13;
&lt;               Jal    M     nth                          processes for PRIs and other agencies involved in&#13;
6  S    t   Rm                                            implementation. The RGNDWM will develop a national&#13;
I  Sector Reform  Projects Implementation             core team of professionals who will advise and train on&#13;
&lt;                    26 February 2002                     specific needs of the states;&#13;
India Habitat Center, New Delhi          6 The RGNDWM will support the states' closer integration&#13;
&lt;                                                         of the PRIs into the implementation process; and&#13;
6 States must conform to the GOI policy guidelines on&#13;
L/\ y  ZiCO              n I                            community capital cost contributions and O&amp;M financing&#13;
and management.&#13;
Based on the findings and recommendations of the     \   e    nc     $&#13;
review and deliberations in the workshop, the Secretary,  1. Rajiv Gandhi National Drinking Water Mission (2000),&#13;
Drinking Water Supply Department, laid down key action  Guidelines for implementation of Rural Water Supply&#13;
points for moving ahead with the SRP. These included:&#13;
6 Similar rapid reviews be done for all states          Programme (Revised and updated 2nd Edition)&#13;
implementing the SRP;                                   2. Rajiv Gandhi National Drinking Water Mission (2001),&#13;
6 The monitoring template used for the review to be     Conference of State Ministers on Rural Drinking Water&#13;
adopted for half-yearly reviews by the RGNDWM. States   Supply (Agenda Notes and Press Release)&#13;
are encouraged to use this template for their interim   3. WSP-SA (November 2001), Rapid Review of the GOI&#13;
reviews. Video-conferencing may be a useful medium for  Rural Water Supply Sector Reform Programme,&#13;
the center to communicate with all the states on a more  Vol. 1 &amp; 2 (Draft Report)&#13;
regular basis;                                          4. WSP-SA (April 2002), Proceedings of the Jal Manthan&#13;
6 The RGNDWM will support states in adopting a          Workshop (February 26, 2002, India Habitat Center,&#13;
minimum policy agenda on key reform principles. In      New Delhi, India)&#13;
For more information on the Rural Think Tank, please contact:&#13;
jal manthan: a rural think tank                                                        June 2002&#13;
c/o India Country Team, Water and Sanitation Program-South Asia                         Created by Write Media&#13;
55 Lodi Estate, New Delhi 110 003                                                       E-mail: writemediatvsnl.com&#13;
Tel: 469 0488/89 Fax: 462 8250 e-mail: wspsa@worldbank.org                             Printed at Thomson Press&#13;
www.wsp.org&#13;
The Water and Sanitation Program is an international partnershiip to help the poor gain sustained access to improved water supply and sanitation services.&#13;
The Program's funding partners are the Governments of Australia, Belgium, Canada, Denmark, Germany, Italy, Japan, Luxembourg, the Netherlands,&#13;
Norway, Sweden, Switzerland, and the United Kingdom; the United Nations Development Programme, and The World Bank.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="2438377">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2002/06/2438377/rural-think-tank-jal-manthan-implementing-sector-reforms-review-selected-state-experiences
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2002/06/2438377/rural-think-tank-jal-manthan-implementing-sector-reforms-review-selected-state-experiences</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2002/06/2438377/rural-think-tank-jal-manthan-implementing-sector-reforms-review-selected-state-experiences</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/07/26/000094946_03071603091562/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/07/26/000094946_03071603091562/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2003-07-26T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2002-06-30T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            A rural think tank jal manthan implementing
            sector reforms : a review of selected state experiences
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The reforms currently undertaken by the
            Government of India in the rural drinking water and
            sanitation sector mark a major departure from the
            conventional allocation-based rural water supply and
            sanitation services to one that adopts a community-oriented
            and participative approach. Significant progress has been
            achieved in mobilizing proposals and substantial funds have
            been disbursed to 65 districts of 26 states towards
            implementing the Sector Reform Program (SRP). At the request
            of the Drinking Water Supply Department, GOI, the Water and
            Sanitation Program-South Asia conducted an independent rapid
            review of the implementation of the program in October 2001
            across five randomly selected districts each in different
            states. The intent of monitoring the SRP implementation
            process was to assess the progress in terms of the reform
            principles and guidelines, identify the constraints, and
            issues and make recommendations for the program as a whole.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            A rural think tank jal manthan implementing
            sector reforms : a review of selected state experiences
        </docna>
        <display_title>A rural think tank jal manthan
            implementing sector reforms : a review of selected state experiences</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2002/06/2438377/rural-think-tank-jal-manthan-implementing-sector-reforms-review-selected-state-experiences</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>UNDP-Water &amp; Sanitation Program</docty>
        <subtopic>Town Water Supply and Sanitation,Water and Industry,Water Supply and Sanitation Governance
            and Institutions,Health Economics &amp; Finance,Water Conservation</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Water Resources</teratopic>
        <count>India</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>South Asia!$!80470</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Asia!$!80451</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000094946_03071603091562</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>(Historic)Sector not applicable</subsc>
        <admreg>South Asia,South Asia</admreg>
        <colti>Water and Sanitation Program</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Water Resources</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Sector not applicable</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Rural areas; Reforms; Drinking water
            standards; Sanitation; Water supply; Stakeholders; Capacity
            building; Community participation; Hygiene; Groundwater;
            Rainwater; Environmental issues; Financial resources
            augmentation,Central Government,community
            contribution,community participation,connection
            charge,conservation,cost recovery,diversion,Drinking Water
            Supply,environmental sanitation,financial viability,ground
            water,groundwater,households,hygiene
            promotion,income,individual connections,local
            communities,PH,piped water,private sector,programs,Public
            Health,Public Works,pumping,pumping
            station,rainwater,rainwater harvesting,rural drinking
            water,rural villages,rural water,rural water
            supply,sand,Sanitation Committee,sanitation
            sector,sanitation services,service providers,slow sand
            filtration,social mobilization,surface water,town,water
            quality,water resources,water sector,water services,water
            source,water supply,water supply system,wells
        </keywd>
        <owner>Water- Water and Sanit Prgrm (GWASP)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>South Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Asia</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>25695</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Science and Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Arts and Culture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Handwashing Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Basic Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>On-site Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Marketing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Alternative Service Delivery</ml:concept><ml:concept>Contracting out</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Arms Length Agencies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen Mapping</ml:concept><ml:concept>Contracting Out</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Chains</ml:concept><ml:concept>Service Delivery Arrangements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Service Standards, Service Fees</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Town Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Engineering</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Growth and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Media</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water, Sanitation and Hygiene</ml:concept><ml:concept>Hygiene Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Outsourcing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Local Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Service Delivery</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Drainage</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>India</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Southern Asia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>