<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>﻿Administration Agreemen between the Republic of Korea, acting through the Korea&#13;
Development Institute, and the international Bank for Reconstruction and Development and th&#13;
International Development A. sociation concerning Korea Development Institute and World&#13;
Bank Leadership, Learning ai nd Innovation Learning Partnership Single-Donor Trust Fund&#13;
(No. TFO72350)&#13;
1. The International Banl for Reconstruction and Development and the Internation I&#13;
Development Association (collectively, the "Bank") acknowledge that the Republic of Kore; ,&#13;
acting through the Korea Devel pment Institute (the "Donor", and together with the Bank, ti:&#13;
"Parties" and each a "Party") a,;rees to provide the sum of Two Billion Four Hundred Millic i&#13;
Korean Wons (2,400,000,000 K RW) (the "Contribution") for Korea Development Institute an 1&#13;
World Bank Leadership, Learnir g and Innovation Learning Partnership Single-Donor Trust Fun( ,&#13;
No. TF072350 (the "Trust Fund" in accordance with the terms of this Administration Agreement.&#13;
2.     The Contribution shall be used to finance the activities set forth in the "Koria&#13;
Development Institute and World Bank Leadership, Learning and Innovation Learning Partnershi )&#13;
Trust Fund Description" attache I hereto as Annex 1, and shall be administered by the Bank o i&#13;
behalf of the Donor in accordan e with the terms of this Administration Agreement, including ti.&#13;
"Standard Provisions" attached h -reto as Annex 2.&#13;
3.     Upon receipt of each payment request from the Bank, the Donor shall promptly conve&#13;
each installment requested by Euch payment request into United States Dollars ("Contributic 1&#13;
Currency") at an exchange rate obtained by the Donor (the "USD Amount") and immediate] /&#13;
thereafter deposit the USD Am)unt into the bank account designated in such payment reque t&#13;
(each amount deposited herein ifter referred to as an "Installment") in accordance with tf:&#13;
following schedule:&#13;
(A)    Promptly following coiintersignature of this Agreement, the USD amount of Eig] t&#13;
Hundred Million Korean Wons (800,000,000 KRW)&#13;
(B)    By December 31, 201:;, the USD amount of Eight Hundred Million Korean Wor s&#13;
(800,000,000 KRW)&#13;
(C)    By December 31, 2016, the USD amount of Eight Hundred Million Korean Wor s&#13;
(800,000,000 KRW)&#13;
4. When making any deposit, the Donor shall instruct its bank to include in its deposit detai s&#13;
information (remittance advice) field of its SWIFT deposit message, information indicating: tIf:&#13;
amount deposited, that the dep )sit is made by the Donor for TF072350 (Korea Developmel t&#13;
Institute and World Bank Leade -ship, Learning and Innovation Learning Partnership Trust Fund j,&#13;
and the date of the deposit (the " )eposit Instructions"). In addition, the Donor shall provide a cof !&#13;
of the Deposit Instructions to ihe Bank's Accounting Trust Funds Division by e-mail sent 1:)&#13;
tfremitadvice@worldbank.org or by fax sent to +1 (202) 614-1315.&#13;
5.     Except with respect to the Deposit Instructions, any notice, request or other communicatic n&#13;
to be given or made under this A Iministration Agreement shall be in writing and delivered by mai .,&#13;
fax or e-mail to the respective 'arty's address specified below or at such other address as suc .&#13;
Party notifies in writing to the ot ier Party from time to time:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿For the Bank (the "Bank Contact"):&#13;
Ms. Susan Shen&#13;
Manager, Opera'ions and Partnerships&#13;
Tel: (202)458-2430&#13;
E-mail: sshen@i,orldbank.org&#13;
For the Donor (the "Don,r Contact"):&#13;
Dr. Taejong Kirr&#13;
Managing Direc or&#13;
Korea Development Institute School ofPublic Policy and Management&#13;
Tel: +822 3299 -'085&#13;
E-mail: tjkim@A dischool.ac.kr&#13;
6.     In the event any amou its are to be returned to the Donor under this Administratio &#13;
Agreement, the Bank shall trans "er such amounts to the Donor, unless otherwise agreed with ti.:&#13;
Bank.&#13;
7.     All annexes hereto constitute an integral part of this Administration Agreement, whos!&#13;
terms taken together shall const tute the entire agreement and understanding between the Don( r&#13;
and the Bank. Unless otherwise ;pecified in an annex hereto, this Administration Agreement ma.'&#13;
be amended only by written amei idment between the Bank and the Donor.&#13;
8.     Each of the Parties repr sents, by confirming its agreement below, that it is authorized t &gt;&#13;
enter into this Administration A),reement and act in accordance with these terms and condition .&#13;
The Parties are requested to sign and date this Administration Agreement, and upon possession I,&#13;
the Bank of this fully signed tidministration Agreement, this Administration Agreement sha I&#13;
become effective as of the date o 'the last signature.&#13;
INTERNATIONAL BANK FOR RECONSTRUCTION AND DEVELOPMENT&#13;
INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPMENT ASSOCIATION&#13;
By:       :_     _   _&#13;
Name: Sanjay Pradhan&#13;
Title: Vice President&#13;
Leadership, Learning and Innovation&#13;
Date:    &lt;k   . w0ver    120. 2 olL,&#13;
KOREA DEVELOPMENT IN 3TITUTE&#13;
By:    P&#13;
Napr6'Dr-1o-Kyung'1ttK&#13;
Title:  President, Korea Deve(o )ment Institute&#13;
Date:  N     -   2_             o i&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿ANNEX I&#13;
Korea Development Institt te and World Bank Leadership, Learnin! and Innovation&#13;
Learning Partnership&#13;
Trust Fund Description&#13;
This Annex shall be applicable to and form an integral part of the Administration Agreement ft r&#13;
the Trust Fund between the Bank and the Donor.&#13;
1. Objectives&#13;
The objective of the Trust Fund i;: to assist effective learning of the Bank's client countries to&#13;
address development challenges n the area of inclusive growth and shared prosperity, and public&#13;
finance and expenditure manager lent, through knowledge dissemination and exchange.&#13;
2. Activities&#13;
The activities (which may be des :ribed as "components" of activities) to be financed by the Trust&#13;
Fund are:&#13;
2.1    Bank-executed activities for which the Bank has implementation responsibility:&#13;
(a) capacity developmer t support, including training and preparation of case studies and&#13;
papers, for formulati m and implementation of policy tools in the area of inclusive&#13;
growth and shared pi osperity;&#13;
(b) capacity developmer t support, including training and preparation of case studies and&#13;
papers, to provide st, te of art knowledge in the area of public finance and expenditure&#13;
management; and&#13;
(c) strategic outreach an I consultation to form knowledge-sharing networks, and&#13;
knowledge events to disseminate lessons learned.&#13;
3. Eliible Expenditures&#13;
3.1    For Bank-executed activ ties, the Trust Fund funds may be used to finance:&#13;
(a) Associated overheads&#13;
(b) Consultant fees for ir dividuals with indirect costs&#13;
(c) Consultant fees for fi -ms&#13;
(d) Contractual services&#13;
(e) Media, Workshops, ( onference and Meeting&#13;
(f) Staff costs with indirt ct costs&#13;
(g) Travel expenses&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿4. Taxes&#13;
4.1    The foregoing activities md categories of expenditures may include the financing of taxt&#13;
in accordance with the Bank's applicable policies and procedures.&#13;
5. Program Criteria&#13;
5.1    Activities are to be finan .ed in accordance with the following program criteria:&#13;
(a) The activity falls unc er the strategy and the work program of Leadership, Learning an I&#13;
Innovation Vice Presidency or Governance Global Practice of the Bank.&#13;
(b) The activity falls un er one of the Bank's knowledge products: Technical Assistance,&#13;
External Training or Economic Sector Work.&#13;
(c) The activity address s development challenges in the following areas: health sector&#13;
policy and social saf !ty nets, drivers of growth and competitiveness, public policy and&#13;
management, role of science and technology in development, or public finance and&#13;
expenditure managei ient.&#13;
(d) Targeted countries o 'the activity are those eligible to receive World Bank financing.&#13;
(e) Bank staffs' travel e. penses under paragraph 3(g) of Annex 1 for the activity do not&#13;
exceed fifty percent (50%) of its total cost.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿ANNEX':&#13;
Standard Provisions&#13;
This Annex shall be applicable to and form an integral part of the Administration Agreement ft r&#13;
the Trust Fund between the BanK and the Donor, it being understood that any plural references ii&#13;
the annexes to Donors, Administ -ation Agreements, Contributions and pro rata shares shall be rea I&#13;
as singular references to the Don ar, its Administration Agreement, its Contributions thereunder an I&#13;
the remaining uncommitted balat ce of the Trust Fund, respectively.&#13;
1.     Administration of the ( ontributions&#13;
1.1    The Bank shall be respo isible only for performing those functions specifically set forth i&#13;
this Administration Agreement a id shall not be subject to any other duties or responsibilities to tl&#13;
Donors, including, without limitation, any duties or obligations that might otherwise apply to t&#13;
fiduciary or trustee under gei eral principles of trust or fiduciary law.  Nothing in th !&#13;
Administration Agreement shall be considered a waiver of any privileges or immunities of ti.&#13;
Bank under its Articles of Agreei nent or any applicable law, all of which are expressly reserved.&#13;
1.2    Each Donor's Contribution (collectively, the "Contributions") shall be administered ii&#13;
accordance with the Bank's appl cable policies and procedures, as the same may be amended froi i&#13;
time to time, including its procurement, financial management, disbursement and safeguai I&#13;
policies, its framework to prevert and combat fraud and corruption and its screening procedures 1.)&#13;
prevent the use of Bank resourcei to finance terrorist activity, in line with the Bank's obligations 1.&gt;&#13;
give effect to the relevant decisions of the Security Council taken under Chapter VII of the ( F&#13;
Charter of the United Nations. The Donors acknowledge that this provision does not create anr&#13;
obligations of the Bank under th,e anti-terrorist financing and asset control laws, regulations, rubs&#13;
and executive orders of an indivi lual member country that may apply to a Donor.&#13;
2.     Management of the Contributions&#13;
2.1    The funds deposited in he Trust Fund shall be accounted for as a single trust fund ar 1&#13;
shall be kept separate and apart I om the funds of the Bank. The funds deposited in the Trust Fur .1&#13;
may be commingled with other t ust fund assets maintained by the Bank. The Bank, in its capacil,/&#13;
as trustee, has legal title to the fu ids deposited in the Trust Fund.&#13;
2.2    The currency in which tie funds in the Trust Fund shall be held is United States Dollas&#13;
(the "Holding Currency").&#13;
2.3    Donors agree to deposit their Contributions in the Contribution Currency stated in the r&#13;
respective Administration Agree nents. In the case of deposits received in a Contribution Current v&#13;
other than the Holding Currency, promptly upon the receipt of such amounts and the accompanyir q&#13;
Deposit Instructions, the Bank shall convert such amounts into the Holding Currency at tf e&#13;
exchange rate obtained by the Ilank on the date of the conversion. Where deposits prove to I e&#13;
insufficient to complete activitie, as a result of exchange rate fluctuations, neither the Bank nor tl e&#13;
Donor shall bear any responsibil ty for providing any additional financing.&#13;
2.4    The funds deposited in the Trust Fund may be freely exchanged by the Bank into oth r&#13;
currencies as may facilitate thei- disbursement at the exchange rate obtained by the Bank on tl e&#13;
date of the conversion.&#13;
15&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿2.5    The Bank shall invest a id reinvest the funds deposited in the Trust Fund pending the r&#13;
disbursement in accordance with the Bank's applicable policies and procedures for the investmei t&#13;
of trust funds administered by th. Bank. The Bank shall transfer all income from such investmet&#13;
to the Donor's applicable donor I alance account with the Bank.&#13;
3.     Trust Fund Fees and C,sts&#13;
3.1    The Bank shall deduct - nd retain for its own account, as a one-time deduction from t6.&#13;
funds in the Trust Fund, an amot nt equal to and not greater than thirty-five thousand United Stat;&#13;
Dollars (US$35,000) as a set-up -ee for the Trust Fund upon receipt of funds in the Trust Fund.&#13;
3.2    The Bank shall additionally deduct and retain for its own account, as a deduction froi&#13;
each Installment, an amount equa l to five percent (5%) per Installment as an administrative fee f&#13;
the Trust Fund.&#13;
3.3    Each Donor acknowledg -s and agrees that the percentage deductions for fees in this Tru t&#13;
Fund Fees and Costs section ar,e estimated on the basis of anticipated Contributions. If actu; I&#13;
Contributions significantly diffei from what was originally anticipated at the time of signature ( F&#13;
the first Administration Agreem -nt, or if other circumstances affecting Trust Fund fees or cosi;&#13;
change, the Bank reserves the right to request a change to the terms of this Trust Fund Fees an .1&#13;
Costs section, which would be ef fectuated by amendments made to the Administration Agreemen ;&#13;
of all Donors and which would 1 hereafter be applicable to all new Contributions that are provide 1&#13;
either as amendments to suppl ment existing Administration Agreements or from new Donoi:;&#13;
under new Administration Agree nents.&#13;
4.     Accounting and Financial Reporting&#13;
4.1    The Bank shall maintai i separate records and ledger accounts in respect of the func&#13;
deposited in the Trust Fund and ( isbursements made therefrom.&#13;
4.2    The Bank shall furnish to the Donors current financial information relating to receipt ,&#13;
disbursements and fund balance in the Holding Currency with respect to the Contributions via tt -&#13;
World Bank's Trust Funds Donor Center secure website. Within six (6) months after a I&#13;
commitments and liabilities undcr the Trust Fund have been satisfied and the Trust Fund has bee i&#13;
closed, the final financial inforn ation relating to receipts, disbursements and fund balance in tl&#13;
Holding Currency with respect t the Contributions shall be made available to the Donors Via tf&#13;
World Bank's Trust Funds Dono - Center secure website.&#13;
4.3    The Bank shall provide to the Donors via the World Bank's Trust Fund Donor Centl r&#13;
secure website, within six (6) mi inths following the end of each Bank fiscal year, an annual sing -&#13;
audit report, comprising (i) a m magement assertion together with an attestation from the Bank s&#13;
external auditors concerning the adequacy of internal control over cash-based financial reportir g&#13;
for all cash-based trust funds as a whole; and (ii) a combined financial statement for all cash-bast d&#13;
trust funds together with the Ban &lt;'s external auditor's opinion thereon. The cost of the single aud t&#13;
shall be borne by the Bank.&#13;
4.4   If a Donor wishes to re luest, on an exceptional basis, a financial statement audit by tf e&#13;
Bank's external auditors of the T rust Fund, the Donor and the Bank shall first consult as to wheth, r&#13;
such an external audit is necessary. The Bank and the Donor shall agree on the appropriate scol e&#13;
15&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿and terms of reference of such au,dit. Following agreement on the scope and terms of reference, t&#13;
Bank shall arrange for such external audit. The costs of any such audit, including the internal cos,:;&#13;
of the Bank with respect to such tudit, shall be borne by the requesting Donor.&#13;
5.     Progress Reporting&#13;
5.1    The Bank shall provide the Donors with annual reports on the progress of activitic(&#13;
financed by the Contributions. Within six (6) months of the End Disbursement Date (as define .1&#13;
below), the Bank shall furnish to the Donors a final report on the activities financed by the Tru t&#13;
Fund.&#13;
5.2 Any Donor may review or evaluate activities financed by the Trust Fund at any time up t i&#13;
six (6) months following the En Disbursement Date. The Donor and the Bank shall agree on th.&#13;
scope and conduct of such re view or evaluation, and the Bank shall provide all releval t&#13;
information within the limits ol the Bank's applicable policies and procedures. All associate .1&#13;
costs, including any costs incurrt d by the Bank, shall be borne by the Donor. It is understood th; t&#13;
any such review or evaluation will not constitute a financial, compliance or other audit of the Tru t&#13;
Fund.&#13;
6.     Disbursement; Cancellition; Refund&#13;
6.1   It is expected that the fur ds deposited in the Trust Fund will be fully disbursed by the Ban&#13;
by April 30, 2018 (the "End Disbursement Date"). The Bank shall only disburse funds deposite .1&#13;
in the Trust Fund for the purposes of this Administration Agreement (other than returns to Donor )&#13;
after such date to the extent such date is changed in accordance with amendments made to if-&#13;
Administration Agreements of all the Donors. Following the End Disbursement Date, the Bar ,&#13;
shall return any remaining balance of the Trust Fund to each Donor in the Holding Currency in tf,&#13;
manner specified in its respectiv- Administration Agreement on a pro rata basis with regard to tf&#13;
total funds deposited in the Tru, t Fund by such Donor relative to the total funds deposited in tf&#13;
Trust Fund by all Donors, all caltulated as Holding Currency amounts.&#13;
6.2    Any Donor may cancel z11 or part of such Donor's pro rata share, and the Bank may canc I&#13;
all or any Donors' pro rata share: , upon three (3) months' prior written notice, of any Contributior s&#13;
(paid and not yet paid) that are n)t committed pursuant to any agreements entered into between tf&#13;
Bank and any consultants and or other third parties for the purposes of this Administratic i&#13;
Agreement, including any Grant Agreements, prior to the receipt of such notice. In the event of a&#13;
cancellation, the Bank shall ret im to the Donor its pro-rata share in the Holding Currency  s&#13;
specified in the Administration Agreement; unless otherwise agreed between the Bank and tt e&#13;
Donor.&#13;
7.     Disclosure; Dispute Re,.olution&#13;
7.1    The Bank shall disclose the Administration Agreements and related information on th s&#13;
Trust Fund in accordance with the Bank's Policy on Access to Information. By entering in o&#13;
Administration Agreements, t ie Donors consent to such disclosure of their respectil e&#13;
Administration Agreements and ;uch related information.&#13;
7.2    The Donors and the Bank shall use their best efforts to amicably settle any disput :,&#13;
controversy, or claim arising out of or relating to the Administration Agreements.&#13;
7&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="24697041">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2014/12/24697041/official-documents--ibrd-ida-administration-agreement-republic-korea-totf072350
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2014/12/24697041/official-documents--ibrd-ida-administration-agreement-republic-korea-totf072350</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2014/12/24697041/official-documents--ibrd-ida-administration-agreement-republic-korea-totf072350</new_url>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2015-06-25T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <docm_id>090224b082f8353a</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b082f8353a</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/CTR/2015/06/24/090224b082f8353a/1_0/Rendered/INDEX/Official0Docum00of0Korea0toTF072350.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/CTR/2015/06/24/090224b082f8353a/1_0/Rendered/PDF/Official0Docum00of0Korea0toTF072350.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2015-06-24T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2014-12-17T10:08:53Z</docdt>
        <docna>
            Official Documents- IBRD and IDA
            Administration Agreement with Republic of Korea toTF072350
        </docna>
        <display_title>Official Documents- IBRD and IDA
            Administration Agreement with Republic of Korea toTF072350</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/2014/12/24697041/official-documents--ibrd-ida-administration-agreement-republic-korea-totf072350</listing_relative_url>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <docty>Trust Fund Administrative Agreement</docty>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Ogawa,Akiko</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>HQBOCS</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <lang>English</lang>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Arts and Culture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Drivers of Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enablers of Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Determiners</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Drivers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Growth Enablers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>Freedom of Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shared Prosperity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Management of Public Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Finance Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Finances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Economics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Economics &amp; Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Remittances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Migration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Media</ml:concept><ml:concept>Determinants of Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Right to Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>External Audit</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inclusive Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Movement of Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>