<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>﻿Execution Version&#13;
Dated October 9, 2014&#13;
COLLABORATION ARRANGEMENT&#13;
relating to&#13;
Global In rastructure Facility Partnership Program&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿Execution Version&#13;
This Collaboration Arrangement is en ered into on October 9, 2014 between:&#13;
(1)   ENDEAVOR ENERGY HOLDINGS LLC, herein represented by its Chief Executive Officer&#13;
headquartered at 1800 West oop South, Suite 1100 B, Houston, Texas 77027, USA&#13;
("Endeavor"); and&#13;
(2)   THE WORLD BANK GROUF, comprising the INTERNATIONAL BANK FOR&#13;
RECONSTRUCTION AND DEVELOPMENT ("IBRD") and INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPIh E I7&#13;
ASSOCIATION ("IDA"), heacquartered at 1818 H Street, NW, Washington, DC 20433, USA , le&#13;
INTERNATIONAL FINANCE CORPORATION, ("IFC") headquartered at 2121 Pennsylvar i&#13;
Avenue, NW, Washington, DC 20433, USA, and the MULTILATERAL INVESTMENT&#13;
GUARANTEE AGENCY, ("MIGA"), headquartered at 1818 H Street, NW, Washington, D(  133,&#13;
USA (the "World Bank Group")&#13;
(each a "Party" and together, the "Parties").&#13;
Preamble&#13;
(A) There is broad internationa recognition, as confirmed by the G20, the OECD, Inter i it nal&#13;
Organizations (lOs), the G77, and the private sector represented by the B20 that investin : ir the&#13;
infrastructure of Emerging IVarkets and Developing Economies (EMDEs) is needed, to q: 3nd&#13;
access to basic services ano raise living standards for all, and to meet global economic r Nth&#13;
targets.&#13;
(B) Meeting this need presents a significant financing challenge. Given constraints on ci ing&#13;
sources of infrastructure finaice-particularly in the public sector-a redoubled and cooi d r ted&#13;
effort is needed to mobilize p ivate sector finance for EMDE infrastructure.&#13;
(C) There is an absence of robt st pipelines of structurally sound and bankable projects an, I th 3 is&#13;
understood to be the greates: barrier to achieving significantly more infrastructure investm:i it&#13;
(D) Governments, development finance institutions, donors, and private investors share an in en( t in&#13;
developing the market for private infrastructure finance in EMDEs: both on the demand sc , in&#13;
the numbers of structurally sound and bankable projects seeking finance, and gradual em  ice&#13;
of EMDE infrastructure as a recognized asset class; and the supply side, in the range o  ri !ate&#13;
investors that actively partic pate in financing those projects. Achieving these goals wil 1e iefit&#13;
from collective action between this range of entities-to leverage resources and know1:; a to&#13;
find  solutions  to  complex  i ifrastructure  financing  challenges  that no  single  institutio&lt;i  : &gt;uld&#13;
achieve alone.&#13;
(E) In support of these goals, thE Parties propose the establishment of a Global InfrastructurE 1 ility&#13;
Partnership Program ("GIF") The GIF will be an open global platform aiming at levera ii(- the&#13;
efforts of the wide range of i istitutions currently engaged in supporting EMDE infrastruct .E with&#13;
the participation of private infrastructure investors, coalescing around project pre rei ion,&#13;
structuring, and  risk mitigati n for individual infrastructure  investments. In this regard, :1e GIF&#13;
aims to complement existinq and proposed services and initiatives currently supporte :, the&#13;
Parties and other prospectiv! GIF partners. The GIF intends to provide resources to prepi ir iell-&#13;
structured, infrastructure prc jects, and to serve as an additional mechanism for acces :i;i the&#13;
expertise of the Parties and other GIF partners, in combination with guidance from pro :liE tive&#13;
private sector financiers into project structures. The GIF thereby aims to achieve greater I no! age&#13;
of official resources in the ft:ce of substantial EMDE infrastructure needs-in particular :- irge&#13;
and complex projects with th B potential to attract significant private capital.&#13;
(F) The Parties are now intere,ted in collaborating in developing the Global InfrastructurE :i 'ility&#13;
Partnership Program, togeth  r with other partners.&#13;
2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿Execution Version&#13;
Accordingly, the Parties have come to the following understanding:&#13;
1     Global Infrastructure Facilit I Partnership Program Framework&#13;
1.1   The GIF is intended to be based on the preliminary objectives and principles set ot t ir&#13;
Annex 1 (Preliminary GIF Foi ndational Principles). The Parties acknowledge their mutual&#13;
understanding that while the GIF Foundational Principles are an initial basis for their collat:xn on,&#13;
they are of an indicative nature and will continue to be developed amongst the Parties and Nit&#13;
other potential partners until tie GIF is formally established. The final version of these obje::'iK s&#13;
and principles will be agreed upon by the GIF Partners and be reflected in the agreement&#13;
establishing the GIF.&#13;
1.2   The Parties intend to Nork together with any additional participants who may be&#13;
collaborating on the GIF to fuither enhance their coordination, in particular by developiig tt E  IF,&#13;
with a view to formally establi:hing the program by December 2014.&#13;
2     Further Collaboration&#13;
2.1   Pursuant to the foregoing, the Parties will use reasonable endeavors to continue tc&#13;
collaborate in developing the 31F, including but not limited to:&#13;
a. Nature and scope of collaboration under the GIF, such as proposed categories of&#13;
partnership and the rmles, rights, and responsibilities associated with each categor&#13;
b. Governance arrangerients of the GIF;&#13;
c. Operational policies epplicable to the GIF's operations;&#13;
d. Scope of GIF activities and sources/uses of GIF funds, including approach to projE&#13;
selection criteria and :oordination with the Parties' existing facilities; and&#13;
e. Any other aspects of ollaboration required to finalize the design of the GIF, includ n;&#13;
sharing best practice and experience with regard to project preparation, through th wu e&#13;
of knowledge platforms for the infrastructure sector.&#13;
2.2   During the process of finaliz ng the design of the GIF, the multilateral development bank li :ed&#13;
in Annex 2 will be invited to participate as initial Technical Partners. Once the GIF d( Eic is&#13;
finalized, additional collabor3tive efforts are required to develop the operational details f:ii the&#13;
GIF, at all times complemcnting existing efforts and facilities and building upon the s, -ed&#13;
knowledge and experience of the Parties in this area. This includes determining the ia,r of&#13;
coordination between the Parties and project origination process.&#13;
3     General&#13;
3.1   This Collaboration Ar angement is not a legally binding agreement or commitment Ib) le&#13;
Parties to enter into or provido support for any specific activity or project. The Parties&#13;
acknowledge that the provisic ns of this Collaboration Arrangement represent their commoi&#13;
understanding and intentions only and that the Parties do not intend to create or impose al   I gal&#13;
obligations or liabilities on an Party.&#13;
3.2   This Collaboration Ar angement is valid and effective for a period of one year from t 'x&#13;
date thereof, unless supersec ed at an earlier date by the establishment of the GIF.&#13;
3.3   The Parties expect tl-at this document and information with respect to the collabor i1 v&#13;
activities contemplated hereir will be publicly disclosed. Such disclosure will be made in&#13;
accordance with the Parties' iespective disclosure policies. The Parties plan to consult witi : .h&#13;
3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿Execution Version&#13;
other concerning the manner and form of any acknowledgment of the other Party's suppor&#13;
regarding the activities.&#13;
3.4   Nothing in this arranc ement will constitute or be construed as a waiver, renunciatic r c&#13;
other modification of any of t&amp; e privileges, immunities and exemptions granted to any of th&#13;
Parties under their constituent documents, international conventions and any applicable la-&#13;
In witness whereof, each of the Part es has caused this Collaboration Arrangement to be executEJ i1-&#13;
two (2) counterparts of equal content 3nd form by a duly authorized representative of each Party a  he&#13;
date first set forth above.&#13;
4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿Execution Version&#13;
ENDEAVOR ENERGY HOLDINGS LLC&#13;
By:  SEAN L      IEF EXECL'TIVE OFFICER&#13;
5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿Execution Version&#13;
THE WORLD BANK GROUP, compr sing the INTERNATIONAL BANK FOR RECONSTRUCTIOI I 4HIiD&#13;
DEVELOPMENT, the INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPMENT ASSOCIATION, the INTERNATIONAL&#13;
FINANCE CORPORATION and the MULTILATERAL INVESTMENT GUARANTEE AGENCY&#13;
By   J   ONG KIM, PRESIDEN-&#13;
6&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿Execution Version&#13;
Annex I&#13;
Preliminary GIF Foundational Principles&#13;
1     Objectives&#13;
1.1   The objective of the CIF is to promote private sector investment in infrastructure pi :, ts&#13;
in emerging markets and devoloping economies (EMDEs) through robust project preparati Ir&#13;
provision of appropriate risk mitigation instruments, and thereby increasing the commercia&#13;
institutional investor engagerr ent in the EMDE infrastructure market. It is focused on&#13;
collaboration in complex publ -private partnerships and projects with potential for commer :ia&#13;
viability which require project oreparation resources, policy dialogue and eventual infrastru t.&#13;
financing solutions that no sirgle institution could achieve alone.&#13;
1.2   To this end, the GIF c ims to create a global platform to provide financial and coorc ra! on&#13;
resources in collaboration wit i the project preparation, advisory, and financing efforts of th i le&#13;
range of donor and developm ent finance institutions currently engaged in supporting EMDI&#13;
infrastructure, with the input and ideas of private infrastructure investors. GIF's engagemer t c: Ad&#13;
stretch from upstream support on project definition, preparation, and investment feasibility&#13;
assessment, through to downstream transaction preparation, financial structuring, and risk&#13;
mitigation/credit enhancement.&#13;
1.3   Over the longer term, by contributing to the stock of high quality and well-structure :&#13;
infrastructure projects, the GI can be expected to help in the development of EMDE&#13;
infrastructure as an asset cla.s attractive to a wide range of private investors seeking long :in i&#13;
assets in faster growing econ )mies, but which until now have been presented only limited&#13;
infrastructure investment opp )rtunities that meet their risk tolerance and investment profile;;&#13;
2     Operating Principles&#13;
2.1   The GIF intends to olerate according to the following core principles, to be finalizE JL On&#13;
agreement among GIF partnE rs:&#13;
(i) Leveraging the private sector-specializing in project financing modalities tl a: , ill&#13;
draw together co nparative advantages of public and private sectors;&#13;
(ii) Addressing public goods-focusing on core infrastructure; particularly thosE&#13;
infrastructure pro ects that are climate friendly or trade enabling;&#13;
(iii) Promoting sustainability and inclusiveness-ensuring projects adhere to t lt&#13;
practice standarcs for social and environmental responsibility; and&#13;
(iv) Collaborating, c Dmplementing and partnering for solutions-mobilizing tE :11 cal&#13;
and financial resources of all partner entities-World Bank Group entities, mul i: 'ral&#13;
development inst tutions, other public institutions, and private investors-in an&#13;
innovative and fl.xible way, to complement existing capacities, achieve greatE&#13;
leverage and adc ress the complex infrastructure financing challenges that are&#13;
beyond the resoL rces of any individual partner.&#13;
3     Institutional Arrangements and Governance&#13;
3.1   The GIF is expected :o involve a wide range of stakeholders who are involved in tl E&#13;
development and implementE,tion of infrastructure projects, both public and private. GIF pE rin: rs&#13;
are expected to fall into one c r more of the following categories:&#13;
7&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿Execution Version&#13;
(i) Funding Partneis-Partners that provide financial contributions to the GIF wi I&#13;
considered Fund ng Partners.&#13;
(ii) Technical Partnlrs-Partners that can and who will agree to provide specific&#13;
technical advice and support to GIF activities including execution of GIF-fLinde :&#13;
activities and/or F rovision of GIF-backed credit enhancement or liquidity suppc ri&#13;
instruments.&#13;
(iii) Advisory Partners-Private investors or entities that represent the voice of&#13;
commercial and/or institutional investment, whether pension funds, insurance&#13;
companies, sove eign wealth funds, banks or other financial institutions, as wE l1&#13;
other multilateral or bilateral agencies engaged in supporting private sector&#13;
infrastructure pro ects, to be invited into discussions related to project prepara In&#13;
optimal approaches to financial structuring, and the design and use of risk&#13;
instruments, with a view to ensure suitability of projects for commercial and/or&#13;
institutional inves:ment.&#13;
3.2   A GIF Governing Council is proposed to oversee the GIF's strategic prograrrmin&#13;
management and use of fund 3, and development of operational policies and procedures; 1:1&#13;
hold the GIF Management Ur it (see section 4.1) accountable for delivering on the facility's&#13;
objectives and principles, wit[ advice and support from the Advisory Partners. The compot cz of&#13;
the Governing Council will be agreed between IBRD and prospective partners, but is propc s  . to&#13;
comprise representatives of F unding and Technical Partners.&#13;
3.3   An Advisory Council comprised of all GIF partners, chaired by the Managing DirE c:c&#13;
and Chief Financial Officer of the World Bank Group, will be periodically convened to facilil it e&#13;
coordination of GIF activities -ind support GIF operations. This Advisory Council will serve :V;&#13;
sounding board, providing gu dance and support for GIF Management, and in particular wi h E&#13;
view to ensuring suitability of )rojects for private sector investment.&#13;
4     Management&#13;
4.1   The GIF will be admiristered by the World Bank Group, through a small, dedicatec i: :n&#13;
established for this purpose (the GIF Management Unit). The GIF Management Unit will fu -et n&#13;
as a coordinating body as prciects are identified for inclusion in the pipeline, and then mov:,&#13;
toward technical support and financing phases. The GIF Management Unit will not lead inc i\ id ial&#13;
projects.&#13;
4.2   GIF activity implemer tation teams will be led by selected staff of Technical Partnei&#13;
institutions, coordinated by th e GIF Management Unit in consultation with client governmel t;,&#13;
according to specific project r:equirements and the project origination processes. Composi i(r :f&#13;
the implementation teams mEy vary according to the need of individual projects and gover -1 n nts.&#13;
5     Activities and Projects&#13;
5.1   Project selection criteria and processes could be developed to reflect the follow irc&#13;
principles:&#13;
(i) Development Impact-projects that support the development goals of the Gll&#13;
partner institutions;&#13;
(ii) Alignment-proj  cts that are aligned with recipient/sponsor country priorities ic&#13;
strategies;&#13;
(iii) Complexity-prc jects that require multiple parties to come together to providE&#13;
structuring, arran:jing and financial support, and/or projects which require a bl r d &gt;f&#13;
financial instrumE nts; and&#13;
8&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿Execution Version&#13;
(iv) Catalytic Impaci -projects that have significant potential to achieve financial i1 lity,&#13;
leverage public ft nds, and attract private sector and/or institutional investors-  I&#13;
as through Public-Private Partnership (PPP) modalities-while still meeting&#13;
government's ser ice delivery objectives.&#13;
The GIF will focus on infrastrt cture investments that have global public good characteristic ;o ich&#13;
as climate friendly-projects that are low emitting or encourage efficiency in the provisior c f&#13;
infrastructure services; and tride enabling-projects that facilitate or enhance interconnet t wi&#13;
and trade.&#13;
5.2   The scope of suppoAt provided to a particular project will be defined flexibly, with I vi w&#13;
to complementing the resources and support already available from partner entities and ot e r&#13;
funding mechanisms. During he GIF pilot phase, this support may include the following ac 'ii  s,&#13;
corresponding to major project development stages:&#13;
(i) Project definition 3nd enabling environment - sector planning and investment&#13;
prioritization; proj ect definition, including needs analysis and pre-feasibility scri E  ig;&#13;
and legal, regulatbry, or institutional reforms;&#13;
(ii)  Project preparaticn and investment feasibility - feasibility studies, investment&#13;
appraisal, and PF P structuring;&#13;
(iii) Transaction support and financial structuring - preparing and implementing&#13;
transactions, and design of risk mitigation/credit enhancement packages; and&#13;
(iv) Financial arranging and credit enhancement - arranging and mobilizing financi '(I&#13;
packages from a *ange of sources and partners.&#13;
6     Operational Policies&#13;
Sound operational policies-i icluding in particular the management of environmental and c cl&#13;
impacts and risks, and transp 3rency in procurement-are critical to the success of infrastrt et- a&#13;
projects in supporting sustain 3ble, inclusive development; as well as for investors in those&#13;
projects to manage financial, *eputational and legal risks. In developing the appropriate&#13;
framework for GIF-supported operations, the GIF could draw upon existing arrangements 1:&#13;
external implementing entities under World Bank Partnership Programs. GIF partners will&#13;
collaborate to establish an ap roach to fiduciary, environmental and social safeguards and c :1  r&#13;
standards and policies, and dvelop, manage and oversee an accreditation process for GI&#13;
Technical Partners who are e(pected to function as implementing entities for GIF activities&#13;
9&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿Execution Version&#13;
Annex 2&#13;
Multilateral Development Banks (MDBs)&#13;
and their Respectix e Project Preparation Resources and Initiatives&#13;
During the process of finalizing the d,isign of the GIF, the following MDBs will be invited to partici:&gt;;it as&#13;
initial Technical Partners. The operational details for the GIF will at all times complement the ; is ing&#13;
efforts and facilities of these MDB., which include but are not limited to the infrastructure pn ect&#13;
preparation resources and initiatives I sted below:&#13;
a. African Development Bank (AfDB) - NEPAD Infrastructure Project Preparation ::a. lity&#13;
(NEPAD-IPPF) as wall as the project development business segment of Africa 5:) ind&#13;
various support efforts for Africa-focused PPFs;&#13;
b. Asian Development Bank (ADB) - Office of Public-Private Partnership and its pr &gt; :x ;ed&#13;
Asia Pacific Project :reparation Facility ('AP3F') as well as several dedicated I 1:i nal&#13;
PPFs;&#13;
c. European Bank foi Reconstruction and Development (EBRD) - Legal Tr ir S ion&#13;
Programme, and the oroposed EBRD Infrastructure Project Preparation Facility ('I  )&#13;
d. European Investmeit Bank (EIB) - European PPP Expertise Centre (EPEC);&#13;
e. Inter-American Development Bank (IADB) - 'InfraFund' project preparation facili y&#13;
f. Islamic Development Bank (IsDB) - Arab Financing Facility for Infrastructure TE cm cal&#13;
Assistance Facility (ikFFI TAF), co-managed with the International Finance Corl  r' ion&#13;
(IFC); and&#13;
g. World Bank Group (WBG) comprising the International Bank for Reconstruct :' ind&#13;
Development (IBRD) the International Development Association (IDA), the Interi a i nal&#13;
Finance Corporation IFC), and the Multilateral Investment Guarantee Agency (MIl'&#13;
10&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="24732663">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2014/10/24732663/official-documents--collaboration-arrangement-endeavor-energy-holdings-tf069027
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2014/10/24732663/official-documents--collaboration-arrangement-endeavor-energy-holdings-tf069027</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2014/10/24732663/official-documents--collaboration-arrangement-endeavor-energy-holdings-tf069027</new_url>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2015-06-30T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <docm_id>090224b082fa5bba</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b082fa5bba</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/CTR/2015/06/29/090224b082fa5bba/1_0/Rendered/INDEX/Official0docum0Holdings0to0TF069027.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/CTR/2015/06/29/090224b082fa5bba/1_0/Rendered/PDF/Official0docum0Holdings0to0TF069027.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2014-10-09T16:27:41Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2015-06-29T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docna>
            Official documents- Collaboration
            Arrangement with Endeavor Energy Holdings to TF069027
        </docna>
        <display_title>Official documents- Collaboration
            Arrangement with Endeavor Energy Holdings to TF069027</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/2014/10/24732663/official-documents--collaboration-arrangement-endeavor-energy-holdings-tf069027</listing_relative_url>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <docty>Trust Fund Administrative Agreement</docty>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>T. S. Ramasamy,Shirmila</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>HQBOCS</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <trustfund>TF069027-GLOBAL INFRASTRUCTURE FACILITY</trustfund>
        <lang>English</lang>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>PPP</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public-Private Partnerships</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public-Private Partnerships (PPP)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fragility, Conflict and Violence</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance &amp; Risk Mitigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pensions &amp; Retirement Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Contract Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Arrangements in Public Procurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Capacity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legal Regulatory Framework</ml:concept><ml:concept>State-Society Relations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Sustainability and Safeguards</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Emerging Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pipelines</ml:concept><ml:concept>Reparations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pensions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Safeguards</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>