<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>﻿Execution Version&#13;
Dated October 9, 2014&#13;
COLLABORATION ARRANGEMENT&#13;
relating to&#13;
Global Inirastructure Facility Partnership Program&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿Execution Version&#13;
This Collaboration Arrangement is eniered into on October 9, 2014 between:&#13;
(1)   NIGERIA SOVEREIGN INVESTMENT AUTHORITY, a body corporate established by Act :) il e&#13;
National Assembly of the Federal Republic of Nigeria with its registered address at The Cl  r&#13;
Place, 4th Floor, Plot 1386A, Tigris Crescent Maitama, Abuja, Nigeria ( "NSIA"); and&#13;
(2)   THE WORLD BANK GROUP, comprising the INTERNATIONAL BANK FOR&#13;
RECONSTRUCTION AND DEEVELOPMENT ("IBRD") and INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPIV IE 1&#13;
ASSOCIATION ("IDA"), headquartered at 1818 H Street, NW, Washington, DC 20433, US!\, le&#13;
INTERNATIONAL FINANCE CORPORATION, ("IFC") headquartered at 2121 Pennsylvar E&#13;
Avenue, NW, Washington, DC 20433, USA, and the MULTILATERAL INVESTMENT&#13;
GUARANTEE AGENCY, ("MGA"), headquartered at 1818 H Street, NW, Washington, DC :C .33,&#13;
USA (the "World Bank Group")&#13;
(each a "Party" and together, the "Parties").&#13;
Preamble&#13;
(A) There is broad international recognition, as confirmed by the G20, the OECD, Inter til nal&#13;
Organizations (IOs), the G77 and the private sector represented by the B20 that investin I ir the&#13;
infrastructure of Emerging Markets and Developing Economies (EMDEs) is needed, to :p q and&#13;
access to basic services and raise living standards for all, and to meet global economic cn: vth&#13;
targets.&#13;
(B) Meeting this need presents a significant financing challenge. Given constraints on :i ing&#13;
sources of infrastructure finance-particularly in the public sector-a redoubled and coor I n: ted&#13;
effort is needed to mobilize piivate sector finance for EMDE infrastructure.&#13;
(C) There is an absence of robu3t pipelines of structurally sound and bankable projects an (t is&#13;
understood to be the greatesi barrier to achieving significantly more infrastructure investmir t&#13;
(D) Governments, development finance institutions, donors, and private investors share an ini) e t in&#13;
developing the market for pr vate infrastructure finance in EMDEs: both on the demand :; d: , in&#13;
the numbers of structurally sound and bankable projects seeking finance, and gradual em( r;1: ice&#13;
of EMDE infrastructure as a recognized asset class; and the supply side, in the range oi F r ate&#13;
investors that actively participate in financing those projects. Achieving these goals will t= efit&#13;
from collective action between this range of entities-to leverage resources and knowl ic  to&#13;
find  solutions  to  complex  infrastructure  financing  challenges  that no  single  institutioii c  uld&#13;
achieve alone.&#13;
(E) In support of these goals, the Parties propose the establishment of a Global Infrastructure F a ility&#13;
Partnership Program ("GIF"). The GIF will be an open global platform aiming at levera( iii( the&#13;
efforts of the wide range of institutions currently engaged in supporting EMDE infrastruct, ir vith&#13;
the participation of private infrastructure investors, coalescing around project prep ae on,&#13;
structuring, and  risk mitigation for individual infrastructure investments. In this regard, he  31F&#13;
aims to complement existin(, and proposed services and initiatives currently supported 1y the&#13;
Parties and other prospective GIF partners. The GIF intends to provide resources to prepE r! , ell-&#13;
structured, infrastructure pro.ects, and to serve as an additional mechanism for acces! iii( the&#13;
expertise of the Parties and other GIF partners, in combination with guidance from pro! re: :ive&#13;
private sector financiers into )roject structures. The GIF thereby aims to achieve greater I!ei age&#13;
of official resources in the face of substantial EMDE infrastructure needs-in particular f :i ;,rge&#13;
and complex projects with the potential to attract significant private capital.&#13;
(F) The Parties are now interested in collaborating in developing the Global Infrastructure F 2 ility&#13;
Partnership Program, together with other partners.&#13;
2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿Execution Version&#13;
Accordingly, the Parties have come to the following understanding:&#13;
1     Global Infrastructure Facilily Partnership Program Framework&#13;
1.1   The GIF is intended to be based on the preliminary objectives and principles set o it i&#13;
Annex 1 (Preliminary GIF Foundational Principles). The Parties acknowledge their mutual&#13;
understanding that while the 31F Foundational Principles are an initial basis for their collat c m ion,&#13;
they are of an indicative natuie and will continue to be developed amongst the Parties and vi&#13;
other potential partners until tie GIF is formally established. The final version of these obje - i" )S&#13;
and principles will be agreed upon by the GIF Partners and be reflected in the agreement&#13;
establishing the GIF.&#13;
1.2   The Parties intend to work together with any additional participants who may be&#13;
collaborating on the GIF to fuither enhance their coordination, in particular by developing t i0 IF,&#13;
with a view to formally establi3hing the program by December 2014.&#13;
2     Further Collaboration&#13;
2.1   Pursuant to the foreg:)ing, the Parties will use reasonable endeavors to continue tiI&#13;
collaborate in developing the GIF, including but not limited to:&#13;
a. Nature and scope of collaboration under the GIF, such as proposed categories of&#13;
partnership and the rles, rights, and responsibilities associated with each categoi ,&#13;
b. Governance arrangements of the GIF;&#13;
c. Operational policies aipplicable to the GIF's operations;&#13;
d. Scope of GIF activities and sources/uses of GIF funds, including approach to projE cI&#13;
selection criteria and coordination with the Parties' existing facilities; and&#13;
e. Any other aspects of collaboration required to finalize the design of the GIF, incluc r g&#13;
sharing best practice and experience with regard to project preparation, through t1 L e&#13;
of knowledge platforms for the infrastructure sector.&#13;
2.2   During the process of finaliZing the design of the GIF, the multilateral development banl s I ted&#13;
in Annex 2 will be  invited 1: participate as initial Technical Partners. Once the GIF d: il: 1 is&#13;
finalized, additional collaboiative efforts are required to develop the operational details I:) the&#13;
GIF, at all times compleminting existing efforts and facilities and building upon the ,- red&#13;
knowledge and experience of the Parties in this area. This includes determining the Evi I of&#13;
coordination between the Pirties and project origination process.&#13;
3     General&#13;
3.1   This Collaboration Airangement is not a legally binding agreement or commitmeni ty he&#13;
Parties to enter into or provide support for any specific activity or project. The Parties&#13;
acknowledge that the provisions of this Collaboration Arrangement represent their cornmo 1&#13;
understanding and intentions only and that the Parties do not intend to create or impose aI gal&#13;
obligations or liabilities on an I Party.&#13;
3.2   This Collaboration Ai rangement is valid and effective for a period of one year fron h&#13;
date thereof, unless superseded at an earlier date by the establishment of the GIF.&#13;
3.3   The Parties expect that this document and information with respect to the collabo i)&#13;
activities contemplated herein will be publicly disclosed. Such disclosure will be made in&#13;
accordance with the Parties' respective disclosure policies. The Parties plan to consult wit e: :h&#13;
3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿Execution Version&#13;
other concerning the manner and form of any acknowledgment of the other Party's suppor&#13;
regarding the activities.&#13;
3.4   Nothing in this arrang3ment will constitute or be construed as a waiver, renunciatic n c&#13;
other modification of any of thB privileges, immunities and exemptions granted to any of thl&#13;
Parties under their constituen documents, international conventions and any applicable la)!&#13;
In witness whereof, each of the Part es has caused this Collaboration Arrangement to be execute 1 in&#13;
two (2) counterparts of equal content 3nd form by a duly authorized representative of each Party a! :I he&#13;
date first set forth above.&#13;
4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿Execution Version&#13;
NIGERIA SOVEREIGN INVESTMEN- AUTHORITY&#13;
By:  MR. UCHE ORJI, MANAGING DIRECTOR AN  :-tm&#13;
5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿Execution Version&#13;
THE WORLD BANK GROUP, comprising the INTERNATIONAL BANK FOR RECONSTRUCTIOl V D&#13;
DEVELOPMENT, the INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPMENT ASSOCIATION, the INTERNATIONAL&#13;
FINANCE CORPORATION and the IMIULTILATERAL INVESTMENT GUARANTEE AGENCY&#13;
By:     Y  G KIM, PRESIDENT&#13;
6&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿Execution Version&#13;
Annex I&#13;
Preliminary GIF Foundational Principles&#13;
1     Objectives&#13;
1.1   The objective of the GIF is to promote private sector investment in infrastructure pi :2 ts&#13;
in emerging markets and developing economies (EMDEs) through robust project preparati,r ,&#13;
provision of appropriate risk mitigation instruments, and thereby increasing the commercia z r,&#13;
institutional investor engagerr ent in the EMDE infrastructure market. It is focused on&#13;
collaboration in complex publ c-private partnerships and projects with potential for commer ::i:&#13;
viability which require project preparation resources, policy dialogue and eventual infrastru :1.j&#13;
financing solutions that no sirgle institution could achieve alone.&#13;
1.2   To this end, the GIF  tims to create a global platform to provide financial and coorc r,. on&#13;
resources in collaboration witli the project preparation, advisory, and financing efforts of th  le&#13;
range of donor and development finance institutions currently engaged in supporting EMD&#13;
infrastructure, with the input and ideas of private infrastructure investors. GIF's engagemei t c: uld&#13;
stretch from upstream support on project definition, preparation, and investment feasibility&#13;
assessment, through to dowrstream transaction preparation, financial structuring, and risk&#13;
mitigation/credit enhancemer t.&#13;
1.3   Over the longer term by contributing to the stock of high quality and well-structure I&#13;
infrastructure projects, the GI = can be expected to help in the development of EMDE&#13;
infrastructure as an asset cla;s attractive to a wide range of private investors seeking long t :&#13;
assets in faster growing economies, but which until now have been presented only limited&#13;
infrastructure investment opportunities that meet their risk tolerance and investment profile ;&#13;
2     Operating Principles&#13;
2.1   The GIF intends to operate according to the following core principles, to be finalizE: Li )on&#13;
agreement among GIF partners:&#13;
(i) Leveraging the Private sector-specializing in project financing modalities tI 2lt 'ill&#13;
draw together comparative advantages of public and private sectors;&#13;
(ii) Addressing pultlic goods-focusing on core infrastructure; particularly thosE&#13;
infrastructure projects that are climate friendly or trade enabling;&#13;
(iii) Promoting sustainability and inclusiveness-ensuring projects adhere to tc s:&#13;
practice standards for social and environmental responsibility; and&#13;
(iv) Collaborating, complementing and partnering for solutions-mobilizing t( c h cal&#13;
and financial resources of all partner entities-World Bank Group entities, mu ial )ral&#13;
development institutions, other public institutions, and private investors-in ar&#13;
innovative and flexible way, to complement existing capacities, achieve great r&#13;
leverage and address the complex infrastructure financing challenges that arE&#13;
beyond the resolirces of any individual partner.&#13;
3     Institutional Arrangements and Governance&#13;
3.1   The GIF is expected to involve a wide range of stakeholders who are involved in t -,&#13;
development and implement 3tion of infrastructure projects, both public and private. GIF p; ir:r rs&#13;
are expected to fall into one !r more of the following categories:&#13;
7&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿Execution Version&#13;
(i) Funding Partners-Partners that provide financial contributions to the GIll wil he&#13;
considered Fundi ig Partners.&#13;
(ii) Technical Partnurs-Partners that can and who will agree to provide specific&#13;
technical advice E nd support to GIF activities including execution of GIF-funde&#13;
activities and/or provision of GIF-backed credit enhancement or liquidity suppc 't&#13;
instruments.&#13;
(iii) Advisory Partnes-Private investors or entities that represent the voice of&#13;
commercial and/cr institutional investment, whether pension funds, insurance&#13;
companies, soveieign wealth funds, banks or other financial institutions, as wE 1 a:&#13;
other multilateral or bilateral agencies engaged in supporting private sector&#13;
infrastructure projects, to be invited into discussions related to project preparai on,&#13;
optimal approaches to financial structuring, and the design and use of risk&#13;
instruments, with a view to ensure suitability of projects for commercial and/or&#13;
institutional inves ment.&#13;
3.2   A GIF Governing Council is proposed to oversee the GIF's strategic programmin,&#13;
management and use of fund;, and development of operational policies and procedures; a I&#13;
hold the GIF Management Unit (see section 4.1) accountable for delivering on the facility's&#13;
objectives and principles, with advice and support from the Advisory Partners. The compoE it ci of&#13;
the Governing Council will be agreed between IBRD and prospective partners, but is propc s a: to&#13;
comprise representatives of Funding and Technical Partners.&#13;
3.3   An Advisory Counci comprised of all GIF partners, chaired by the Managing DirE::.&#13;
and Chief Financial Officer of the World Bank Group, will be periodically convened to facilitr e&#13;
coordination of GIF activities and support GIF operations. This Advisory Council will serve i!&#13;
sounding board, providing guidance and support for GIF Management, and in particular wil -&#13;
view to ensuring suitability of projects for private sector investment.&#13;
4     Management&#13;
4.1   The GIF will be admir istered by the World Bank Group, through a small, dedicatec t n&#13;
established for this purpose (Ihe GIF Management Unit). The GIF Management Unit will fu '(t n&#13;
as a coordinating body as projects are identified for inclusion in the pipeline, and then mov:!&#13;
toward technical support and inancing phases. The GIF Management Unit will not lead inc i\ i| lal&#13;
projects.&#13;
4.2   GIF activity implemertation teams will be led by selected staff of Technical Partnei&#13;
institutions, coordinated by thi GIF Management Unit in consultation with client governmel t:,&#13;
according to specific project riquirements and the project origination processes. Composi or )f&#13;
the implementation teams may vary according to the need of individual projects and goveri ni nts.&#13;
5     Activities and Projects&#13;
5.1   Project selection criteria and processes could be developed to reflect the follo\ it&#13;
principles:&#13;
(i) Development Impact-projects that support the development goals of the GIl&#13;
partner institutions;&#13;
(ii) Alignment-proj 3cts that are aligned with recipient/sponsor country priorities ii&#13;
strategies;&#13;
(iii) Complexity-projects that require multiple parties to come together to providE&#13;
structuring, arranging and financial support, and/or projects which require a blirc )f&#13;
financial instrumE nts; and&#13;
8&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿Execution Version&#13;
(iv) Catalytic Impact-projects that have significant potential to achieve financial i l: lity,&#13;
leverage public funds, and attract private sector and/or institutional investors- 1; 1&#13;
as through Public-Private Partnership (PPP) modalities-while still meeting&#13;
government's sertice delivery objectives.&#13;
The GIF will focus on infrastrUcture investments that have global public good characteristic.  ch&#13;
as climate friendly-projects that are low emitting or encourage efficiency in the provision :&#13;
infrastructure services; and trade enabling-projects that facilitate or enhance interconnet 1:i.Lil&#13;
and trade.&#13;
5.2   The scope of suppot provided to a particular project will be defined flexibly, with v w&#13;
to complementing the resources and support already available from partner entities and otl E -&#13;
funding mechanisms. During ihe GIF pilot phase, this support may include the following ac i\ iti  s,&#13;
corresponding to major project development stages:&#13;
(i) Project definition and enabling environment - sector planning and investment&#13;
prioritization; proj:ct definition, including needs analysis and pre-feasibility scre E ni ig;&#13;
and legal, regulatory, or institutional reforms;&#13;
(ii) Project preparaticn and investment feasibility - feasibility studies, investment&#13;
appraisal, and PPP structuring;&#13;
(iii) Transaction support and financial structuring - preparing and implementing&#13;
transactions, and design of risk mitigation/credit enhancement packages; and&#13;
(iv) Financial arrangir g and credit enhancement - arranging and mobilizing financi i(&#13;
packages from a -ange of sources and partners.&#13;
6     Operational Policies&#13;
Sound operational policies-iiicluding in particular the management of environmental and cci il&#13;
impacts and risks, and transp:3rency in procurement-are critical to the success of infrastrt ,:! a&#13;
projects in supporting sustainable, inclusive development; as well as for investors in those&#13;
projects to manage financial, ieputational and legal risks. In developing the appropriate&#13;
framework for GIF-supported operations, the GIF could draw upon existing arrangements I:&#13;
external implementing entities under World Bank Partnership Programs. GIF partners will&#13;
collaborate to establish an approach to fiduciary, environmental and social safeguards and c :1 ?r&#13;
standards and policies, and develop, manage and oversee an accreditation process for GI&#13;
Technical Partners who are e&lt;pected to function as implementing entities for GIF activities&#13;
9&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿Execution Version&#13;
Annex 2&#13;
Multilateral Development Banks (MDBs)&#13;
and their Respective Project Preparation Resources and Initiatives&#13;
During the process of finalizing the design of the GIF, the following MDBs will be invited to partici )it as&#13;
initial Technical Partners. The operational details for the GIF will at all times complement the : ii ing&#13;
efforts and facilities of these MDB,, which include but are not limited to the infrastructure pn: ect&#13;
preparation resources and initiatives I sted below:&#13;
a. African Developmeit Bank (AfDB) - NEPAD Infrastructure Project Preparation Ia: lity&#13;
(NEPAD-IPPF) as wall as the project development business segment of Africa 5:' ind&#13;
various support efforts for Africa-focused PPFs;&#13;
b. Asian Development Bank (ADB) - Office of Public-Private Partnership and its pr ):c ed&#13;
Asia Pacific Project Dreparation Facility ('AP3F') as well as several dedicated i a til nal&#13;
PPFs;&#13;
c. European Bank foi Reconstruction and Development (EBRD) - Legal Tr ir ion&#13;
Programme, and the roposed EBRD Infrastructure Project Preparation Facility ('I :VI);&#13;
d. European Investment Bank (EIB) - European PPP Expertise Centre (EPEC);&#13;
e. Inter-American Devolopment Bank (IADB) - 'InfraFund' project preparation facili y&#13;
f. Islamic Development Bank (IsDB) - Arab Financing Facility for Infrastructure TE c1 cal&#13;
Assistance Facility () FFI TAF), co-managed with the International Finance Corl c n ion&#13;
(IFC); and&#13;
g. World Bank Group (WBG) comprising the International Bank for Reconstruct :)i ind&#13;
Development (IBRD) the International Development Association (IDA), the Inter la t nal&#13;
Finance Corporation IFC), and the Multilateral Investment Guarantee Agency (MI :;!ki&#13;
10&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="24736228">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2014/10/24736228/official-documents--collaboration-arrangement-nigerian-sovereign-investment-authority-tf069027
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2014/10/24736228/official-documents--collaboration-arrangement-nigerian-sovereign-investment-authority-tf069027</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2014/10/24736228/official-documents--collaboration-arrangement-nigerian-sovereign-investment-authority-tf069027</new_url>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2015-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <docm_id>090224b082faa424</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b082faa424</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/CTR/2015/06/30/090224b082faa424/1_0/Rendered/INDEX/Official0docum0uthority0to0TF069027.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/CTR/2015/06/30/090224b082faa424/1_0/Rendered/PDF/Official0docum0uthority0to0TF069027.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2015-06-30T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2014-10-09T09:18:47Z</docdt>
        <docna>
            Official documents- Collaboration
            Arrangement with Nigerian Sovereign Investment Authority to TF069027
        </docna>
        <display_title>Official documents- Collaboration
            Arrangement with Nigerian Sovereign Investment Authority to TF069027</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/2014/10/24736228/official-documents--collaboration-arrangement-nigerian-sovereign-investment-authority-tf069027</listing_relative_url>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <docty>Trust Fund Administrative Agreement</docty>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>T. S. Ramasamy,Shirmila</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>HQBOCS</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <trustfund>TF069027-GLOBAL INFRASTRUCTURE FACILITY</trustfund>
        <lang>English</lang>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>PPP</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public-Private Partnerships</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public-Private Partnerships (PPP)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>PPP Structuring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public-Private Partnerships Contract Design</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public-Private Partnerships Structuring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance &amp; Risk Mitigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pensions &amp; Retirement Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Contract Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Arrangements in Public Procurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Capacity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legal Regulatory Framework</ml:concept><ml:concept>State-Society Relations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Sustainability and Safeguards</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Emerging Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>PPP Contract Design</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pipelines</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pensions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Safeguards</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>