<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>﻿Execution Version&#13;
Dated October 9, 2014L-&#13;
COLLABORATION ARRANGEMENT&#13;
relating to&#13;
Global In rastructure Facility Partnership Program&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿Execution Version&#13;
This Collaboration Arrangement is er tered into on October 9, 2014 between:&#13;
(1) WORLD PENSION COUNCIL, herein represented by its Cofounder &amp; Director-General,&#13;
headquartered at 50 Rue de _'Universite, 75007 Paris, France ("WPC"); and&#13;
(2)   THE WORLD BANK GROUP, comprising the INTERNATIONAL BANK FOR&#13;
RECONSTRUCTION AND DEVELOPMENT ("IBRD") and INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPh li1, r&#13;
ASSOCIATION ("IDA"), heat quartered at 1818 H Street, NW, Washington, DC 20433, Uc, , he&#13;
INTERNATIONAL FINANCE CORPORATION, ("IFC") headquartered at 2121 Pennsylvar in&#13;
Avenue, NW, Washington, D 20433, USA, and the MULTILATERAL INVESTMENT&#13;
GUARANTEE AGENCY, ("IVIGA"), headquartered at 1818 H Street, NW, Washington, D(: 133,&#13;
USA (the "World Bank Group")&#13;
(each a "Party" and together the "Parties").&#13;
Preamble&#13;
(A) There is broad internationa recognition, as confirmed by the G20, the OECD, Inter lut nal&#13;
Organizations (lOs), the G77, and the private sector represented by the B20 that investir: ii the&#13;
infrastructure of Emerging IV arkets and Developing Economies (EMDEs) is needed, to e :: ind&#13;
access to basic services an( raise living standards for all, and to meet global economic (r: vth&#13;
targets.&#13;
(B) Meeting this need presentE a significant financing challenge. Given constraints on :i ing&#13;
sources of infrastructure finaice-particularly in the public sector-a redoubled and cooid r ted&#13;
effort is needed to mobilize p ivate sector finance for EMDE infrastructure.&#13;
(C) There is an absence of robLst pipelines of structurally sound and bankable projects and I 3 is&#13;
understood to be the greates: barrier to achieving significantly more infrastructure investm :'i it&#13;
(D) Governments, development i nance institutions, donors, and private investors share an in ae t in&#13;
developing the market for pr vate infrastructure finance in EMDEs: both on the demand scl , in&#13;
the numbers of structurally scund and bankable projects seeking finance, and gradual em' r ;1: ice&#13;
of EMDE infrastructure as a recognized asset class; and the supply side, in the range o pr ate&#13;
investors that actively partic pate in financing those projects. Achieving these goals will bE efit&#13;
from collective action betwe -n this range of entities-to leverage resources and knowl llI   to&#13;
find  solutions  to  complex  infrastructure  financing  challenges  that no  single  institutio  c  uld&#13;
achieve alone.&#13;
(E) In support of these goals, the Parties propose the establishment of a Global Infrastructure F =s ility&#13;
Partnership Program ("GIF") The GIF will be an open global platform aiming at levera( iii the&#13;
efforts of the wide range of institutions currently engaged in supporting EMDE infrastruct rs vith&#13;
the  participation  of private  infrastructure  investors, coalescing  around  project prep :iiE on,&#13;
structuring, and  risk mitigation for individual infrastructure investments. In this regard,  a  31F&#13;
aims to complement existing and proposed services and initiatives currently supportec :y the&#13;
Parties and other prospective GIF partners. The GIF intends to provide resources to prepE rz , ell-&#13;
structured, infrastructure prciects, and to serve as an additional mechanism for acces iici the&#13;
expertise of the Parties and other GIF partners, in combination with guidance from pro! pe: tive&#13;
private sector financiers into )roject structures. The GIF thereby aims to achieve greater b iei 3ge&#13;
of official resources in the fa-e of substantial EMDE infrastructure needs-in particular f :i rge&#13;
and complex projects with the potential to attract significant private capital.&#13;
(F) The Parties are now interested in collaborating in developing the Global Infrastructure F ility&#13;
Partnership Program, togethfr with other partners.&#13;
2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿Execution Version&#13;
Accordingly, the Parties have come to the following understanding:&#13;
1     Global Infrastructure Facilily Partnership Program Framework&#13;
1.1   The GIF is intended t: be based on the preliminary objectives and principles set o 0 i&#13;
Annex 1 (Preliminary GIF Foundational Principles). The Parties acknowledge their mutual&#13;
understanding that while the 31F Foundational Principles are an initial basis for their collac ,: ion,&#13;
they are of an indicative natu e and will continue to be developed amongst the Parties and i&#13;
other potential partners until ihe GIF is formally established. The final version of these objE C:i,s&#13;
and principles will be agreed upon by the GIF Partners and be reflected in the agreement&#13;
establishing the GIF.&#13;
1.2   The Parties intend to work together with any additional participants who may be&#13;
collaborating on the GIF to futher enhance their coordination, in particular by developing t  IF,&#13;
with a view to formally establishing the program by December 2014.&#13;
2     Further Collaboration&#13;
2.1   Pursuant to the foreg:)ing, the Parties will use reasonable endeavors to continue toi&#13;
collaborate in developing the GIF, including but not limited to:&#13;
a. Nature and scope of ollaboration under the GIF, such as proposed categories of&#13;
partnership and the r les, rights, and responsibilities associated with each categol t&#13;
b. Governance arrange nents of the GIF;&#13;
c. Operational policies ipplicable to the GIF's operations;&#13;
d. Scope of GIF activitiEs and sources/uses of GIF funds, including approach to proj :I&#13;
selection criteria and coordination with the Parties' existing facilities; and&#13;
e. Any other aspects of collaboration required to finalize the design of the GIF, incluc r g&#13;
sharing best practice and experience with regard to project preparation, through tl I L e&#13;
of knowledge platforr ns for the infrastructure sector.&#13;
2.2   During the process of finali2ing the design of the GIF, the multilateral development Dani - I ted&#13;
in Annex 2 will be invited to participate as initial Technical Partners. Once the GIF d,  i is&#13;
finalized, additional collaborative efforts are required to develop the operational details i:) the&#13;
GIF, at all times complemonting existing efforts and facilities and building upon the sh red&#13;
knowledge and experience of the Parties in this area. This includes determining the ev: of&#13;
coordination between the Pzrties and project origination process.&#13;
3     General&#13;
3.1   This Collaboration Arrangement is not a legally binding agreement or commitment tl Ie&#13;
Parties to enter into or provid a support for any specific activity or project. The Parties&#13;
acknowledge that the provisions of this Collaboration Arrangement represent their commo&#13;
understanding and intentions only and that the Parties do not intend to create or impose a VI b1 gal&#13;
obligations or liabilities on an i Party.&#13;
3.2   This Collaboration Arrangement is valid and effective for a period of one year frorr I&#13;
date thereof, unless superseded at an earlier date by the establishment of the GIF.&#13;
3.3   The Parties expect tt at this document and information with respect to the collabor ri\&#13;
activities contemplated hereiii will be publicly disclosed. Such disclosure will be made in&#13;
accordance with the Parties' espective disclosure policies. The Parties plan to consult wit i :h&#13;
3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿Execution Version&#13;
other concerning the manner and form of any acknowledgment of the other Party's suppor&#13;
regarding the activities.&#13;
3.4   Nothing in this arranc ement will constitute or be construed as a waiver, renunciati( r c&#13;
other modification of any of tf e privileges, immunities and exemptions granted to any of th :&#13;
Parties under their constituer t documents, international conventions and any applicable la vs&#13;
In witness whereof, each of the Pal ies has caused this Collaboration Arrangement to be executE d i&#13;
two (2) counterparts of equal content and form by a duly authorized representative of each Party a: :) :he&#13;
date first set forth above.&#13;
4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿Execution Version&#13;
WORLD PENSION COUNCIL&#13;
By:  M. NICOLAS J. FIRZLI, COOUNDER &amp; DIRECTOR-GENERAL&#13;
5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿Execution Version&#13;
THE WORLD BANK GROUP, compr sing the INTERNATIONAL BANK FOR RECONSTRUCTIO '1e ID&#13;
DEVELOPMENT, the INTERNATIONiAL DEVELOPMENT ASSOCIATION, the INTERNATIONAL&#13;
FINANE-CORPRATION and the MULTILATERAL INVESTMENT GUARANTEE AGENCY&#13;
By:     Y  G KIM, PRESIDENT&#13;
6&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿Execution Version&#13;
Annex I&#13;
Preliriinary GIF Foundational Principles&#13;
1     Objectives&#13;
1.1   The objective of the GIF is to promote private sector investment in infrastructure p, c, :ts&#13;
in emerging markets and developing economies (EMDEs) through robust project preparat :)n,&#13;
provision of appropriate risk mitigation instruments, and thereby increasing the commercia :n I&#13;
institutional investor engagerient in the EMDE infrastructure market. It is focused on&#13;
collaboration in complex pub ic-private partnerships and projects with potential for comme c&#13;
viability which require project preparation resources, policy dialogue and eventual infrastrL:: 3&#13;
financing solutions that no sir gle institution could achieve alone.&#13;
1.2   To this end, the GIF aims to create a global platform to provide financial and coort il on&#13;
resources in collaboration with the project preparation, advisory, and financing efforts of tl -v, de&#13;
range of donor and development finance institutions currently engaged in supporting EMD-&#13;
infrastructure, with the input and ideas of private infrastructure investors. GIF's engageme -1 c uld&#13;
stretch from upstream suppo I on project definition, preparation, and investment feasibility&#13;
assessment, through to dowr stream transaction preparation, financial structuring, anc risl,&#13;
mitigation/credit enhancemer t.&#13;
1.3   Over the longer term by contributing to the stock of high quality and well-structurE J&#13;
infrastructure projects, the GIF can be expected to help in the development of EMDE&#13;
infrastructure as an asset cla 3s attractive to a wide range of private investors seeking long ta i&#13;
assets in faster growing ecor omies, but which until now have been presented only limited&#13;
infrastructure investment opportunities that meet their risk tolerance and investment profilEs&#13;
2     Operating Principles&#13;
2.1   The GIF intends to o )erate according to the following core principles, to be finaliz( c .on&#13;
agreement among GIF partn.rs:&#13;
(i) Leveraging the private sector-specializing in project financing modalities tl : ill&#13;
draw together ccmparative advantages of public and private sectors;&#13;
(ii) Addressing putlic goods-focusing on core infrastructure; particularly thos(&#13;
infrastructure prcjects that are climate friendly or trade enabling;&#13;
(iii) Promoting sustainability and inclusiveness-ensuring projects adhere tot s:&#13;
practice standards for social and environmental responsibility; and&#13;
(iv) Collaborating, complementing and partnering for solutions-mobilizing t( ch ical&#13;
and financial res &gt;urces of all partner entities-World Bank Group entities, mu tiai )ral&#13;
development ins:itutions, other public institutions, and private investors-in ar&#13;
innovative and fl 1xible way, to complement existing capacities, achieve great( r&#13;
leverage and address the complex infrastructure financing challenges that arE&#13;
beyond the resoirces of any individual partner.&#13;
3     Institutional Arrangements and Governance&#13;
3.1   The GIF is expected to involve a wide range of stakeholders who are involved in t io&#13;
development and implementition of infrastructure projects, both public and private. GIF pi r.r rs&#13;
are expected to fall into one or more of the following categories:&#13;
7&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿Execution Version&#13;
(i) Funding Partnes-Partners that provide financial contributions to the GIF wI I&#13;
considered Funding Partners.&#13;
(ii) Technical Partners-Partners that can and who will agree to provide specific&#13;
technical advice and support to GIF activities including execution of GIF-funde&#13;
activities and/or )rovision of GIF-backed credit enhancement or liquidity supp, r:&#13;
instruments.&#13;
(iii) Advisory Partners-Private investors or entities that represent the voice of&#13;
commercial and/)r institutional investment, whether pension funds, insurance&#13;
companies, sovereign wealth funds, banks or other financial institutions, as w,+ 'i&#13;
other multilateral or bilateral agencies engaged in supporting private sector&#13;
infrastructure prcjects, to be invited into discussions related to project prepare::I&#13;
optimal approaches to financial structuring, and the design and use of risk&#13;
instruments, witt a view to ensure suitability of projects for commercial ard/or&#13;
institutional inve,.tment.&#13;
3.2   A GIF Governing Council is proposed to oversee the GIF's strategic programmir g&#13;
management and use of fun( s, and development of operational policies and procedures; ;r:&#13;
hold the GIF Management U iit (see section 4.1) accountable for delivering on the facility',&#13;
objectives and principles, witi advice and support from the Advisory Partners. The compo i:i': I of&#13;
the Governing Council will be agreed between IBRD and prospective partners, but is prop :)i:e to&#13;
comprise representatives of unding and Technical Partners.&#13;
3.3   An Advisory Council comprised of all GIF partners, chaired by the Managing Dir:!(t:&#13;
and Chief Financial Officer o the World Bank Group, will be periodically convened to facili.'i::&#13;
coordination of GIF activities and support GIF operations. This Advisory Council will serve Esi&#13;
sounding board, providing gL idance and support for GIF Management, and in particular w 1:1&#13;
view to ensuring suitability of projects for private sector investment.&#13;
4     Management&#13;
4.1   The GIF will be administered by the World Bank Group, through a small, dedicate: t IM&#13;
established for this purpose (the GIF Management Unit). The GIF Management Unit will ft -:. n&#13;
as a coordinating body as projects are identified for inclusion in the pipeline, and then moN'=&#13;
toward technical support anc financing phases. The GIF Management Unit will not lead in :i,'L ual&#13;
projects.&#13;
4.2   GIF activity impleme itation teams will be led by selected staff of Technical Partner&#13;
institutions, coordinated by ttie GIF Management Unit in consultation with client governme i Z&#13;
according to specific project 'equirements and the project origination processes. Compos t :- of&#13;
the implementation teams m 3y vary according to the need of individual projects and gove rm .3nts.&#13;
5     Activities and Projects&#13;
5.1   Project selection ci iteria and processes could be developed to reflect the follo'il;&#13;
principles:&#13;
(i) Development Iripact-projects that support the development goals of the G 1:&#13;
partner institutio is;&#13;
(ii) Alignment-prc ects that are aligned with recipient/sponsor country priorities - n:&#13;
strategies;&#13;
(iii) Complexity-projects that require multiple parties to come together to provid :&#13;
structuring, arranging and financial support, and/or projects which require a b ):c. of&#13;
financial instruments; and&#13;
8&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿Execution Version&#13;
(iv) Catalytic Impact-projects that have significant potential to achieve financial v  ility,&#13;
leverage public f inds, and attract private sector and/or institutional investors- sui h&#13;
as through Publii;-Private Partnership (PPP) modalities-while still meeting&#13;
government's se vice delivery objectives.&#13;
The GIF will focus on infrastricture investments that have global public good characteristii . ich&#13;
as climate friendly-project ; that are low emitting or encourage efficiency in the provisiol :1&#13;
infrastructure services; and trade enabling-projects that facilitate or enhance interconne:: i\ y&#13;
and trade.&#13;
5.2   The scope of suppc rt provided to a particular project will be defined flexibly, with Ei )w&#13;
to complementing the resour:es and support already available from partner entities and o-e&#13;
funding mechanisms. During the GIF pilot phase, this support may include the following ac(J,il es,&#13;
corresponding to major proje-t development stages:&#13;
(i) Project definition and enabling environment - sector planning and investment&#13;
prioritization; pro ect definition, including needs analysis and pre-feasibility scr Bar ng;&#13;
and legal, regula:ory, or institutional reforms;&#13;
(ii)  Project preparati n and investment feasibility - feasibility studies, investment&#13;
appraisal, and P :'P structuring;&#13;
(iii) Transaction support and financial structuring - preparing and implementing&#13;
transactions, anc design of risk mitigation/credit enhancement packages; and&#13;
(iv) Financial arrangiig and credit enhancement - arranging and mobilizing financ ng&#13;
packages from a range of sources and partners.&#13;
6     Operational Policies&#13;
Sound operational policies- ncluding in particular the management of environmental and so: al&#13;
impacts and risks, and transparency in procurement-are critical to the success of infrastr :t. e&#13;
projects in supporting sustair able, inclusive development; as well as for investors in those&#13;
projects to manage financial, reputational and legal risks. In developing the appropriate&#13;
framework for GIF-supportec operations, the GIF could draw upon existing arrangements :c&#13;
external implementing entitie3 under World Bank Partnership Programs. GIF partners will&#13;
collaborate to establish an approach to fiduciary, environmental and social safeguards ant :dl er&#13;
standards and policies, and develop, manage and oversee an accreditation process for G 1:&#13;
Technical Partners who are expected to function as implementing entities for GIF activitie .&#13;
9&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿Execution Version&#13;
Annex 2&#13;
Multi ateral Development Banks (MDBs)&#13;
and their Respecti te Project Preparation Resources and Initiatives&#13;
During the process of finalizing the cesign of the GIF, the following MDBs will be invited to partic pa: as&#13;
initial Technical Partners. The operitional details for the GIF will at all times complement the e.:i! ting&#13;
efforts and facilities of these MDBs, which include but are not limited to the infrastructure mr ject&#13;
preparation resources and initiatives isted below:&#13;
a. African Development Bank (AfDB) - NEPAD Infrastructure Project Preparatior IZ ility&#13;
(NEPAD-IPPF) as well as the project development business segment of AfricG C and&#13;
various support effor:s for Africa-focused PPFs;&#13;
b. Asian Developmen Bank (ADB) - Office of Public-Private Partnership and its p cp: sed&#13;
Asia Pacific Project Preparation Facility ('AP3F') as well as several dedicated 1:1li &gt;nal&#13;
PPFs;&#13;
c. European Bank for Reconstruction and Development (EBRD) - Legal Ti.3-i tion&#13;
Programme, and the proposed EBRD Infrastructure Project Preparation Facility ( P:i ');&#13;
d. European Investment Bank (EIB) - European PPP Expertise Centre (EPEC);&#13;
e. Inter-American Development Bank (IADB) - 'InfraFund' project preparation facil&#13;
f. Islamic Development Bank (IsDB) - Arab Financing Facility for Infrastructure T  it cal&#13;
Assistance Facility (4FFI TAF), co-managed with the International Finance Cor) :r tion&#13;
(IFC); and&#13;
g. World Bank Grour (WBG) comprising the International Bank for Reconstruc it and&#13;
Development (IBRD , the International Development Association (IDA), the Intel l1. )nal&#13;
Finance Corporation (IFC), and the Multilateral Investment Guarantee Agency (M&#13;
10&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="24736300">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2014/10/24736300/official-documents--collaboration-arrangement-world-pension-council-tf069027
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2014/10/24736300/official-documents--collaboration-arrangement-world-pension-council-tf069027</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2014/10/24736300/official-documents--collaboration-arrangement-world-pension-council-tf069027</new_url>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2015-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <docm_id>090224b082faa46f</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b082faa46f</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/CTR/2015/06/30/090224b082faa46f/1_0/Rendered/INDEX/Official0docum00Council0to0TF069027.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/CTR/2015/06/30/090224b082faa46f/1_0/Rendered/PDF/Official0docum00Council0to0TF069027.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2014-10-09T09:22:25Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2015-06-30T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docna>
            Official documents- Collaboration
            Arrangement with World Pension Council to TF069027
        </docna>
        <display_title>Official documents- Collaboration
            Arrangement with World Pension Council to TF069027</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/2014/10/24736300/official-documents--collaboration-arrangement-world-pension-council-tf069027</listing_relative_url>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <docty>Trust Fund Administrative Agreement</docty>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>T. S. Ramasamy,Shirmila</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>HQBOCS</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <trustfund>TF069027-GLOBAL INFRASTRUCTURE FACILITY</trustfund>
        <lang>English</lang>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>PPP</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public-Private Partnerships</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public-Private Partnerships (PPP)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance &amp; Risk Mitigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sovereign Wealth Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pensions &amp; Retirement Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Contract Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Arrangements in Public Procurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Capacity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legal Regulatory Framework</ml:concept><ml:concept>State-Society Relations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Sustainability and Safeguards</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Emerging Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pipelines</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sovereign Wealth Funds</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pensions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Safeguards</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>