<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>October 2001&#13;
.,p        c. . . S&#13;
LJ\W\~.Z'UUUUU//UUUO&#13;
i,,,,~~~~~~~~~~~~~~-S                                            .-- -      0St-9BES&#13;
Africa Region&#13;
Ecological Sanitation 2 (Ecosan)&#13;
h-as made little progress in Africa&#13;
despite decades of promotion by&#13;
donors. The practical and&#13;
environmental benefits      of S&#13;
'closing the loop' (i.e. recyclingj&#13;
the nutrients in excreta) seem&#13;
remote to most poor African &#13;
households. This lack of demand-' &#13;
for Ecosan in turn makes many&#13;
sector practitioners question its&#13;
potential. There are, however, a&#13;
number of physical conditions -    e               --&#13;
including high water table and&#13;
hard rocky ground-.which can                                                                               -&#13;
increase   the   comparative                       k&#13;
advantage of many forms of&#13;
Ecosan technology. But beyond        ..                                                 -&#13;
these physical conditions there&#13;
are many factors that influence                                                    -&#13;
demand by households that have o&#13;
to be considered as well, such as&#13;
the presence of small local &#13;
operators involved in excreta&#13;
handling. This paper examines a&#13;
number of physical and non-&#13;
physical demand drivers' that         The Sanitation Ch'~allengje in Africa&#13;
may encourage households to           Inadequate sanitation remains a major cause of poor health and poverty in many African&#13;
adopt Ecosan solutions. It also       households. Sanitation coverage in Africa is lower than in any other region of the world-,&#13;
discusses practical activities        and it is declining. Recent data shows that the fraction served in Africa actually decreased&#13;
within the different segments of      over the last decade4.Poor households in fast growing urban areas are exposed to the&#13;
'the resource loop'and a number       greatest risk.&#13;
of factors, beyond the household      Governments, communities and households are yet to commit adequate financial, material&#13;
arevel, that affect the communaland human resources to sustain sanitation promotion in pace with population growth. Further&#13;
level, tha affect th  communaldeterioration of sanitary conditions will occur unless diverse solutions for improving sanitation&#13;
adoption of Ecosan and re-use         are adopted.&#13;
of excreta.                           These problems cannot be solved by the use of conventional urban sanitation technologies,&#13;
which cost far more than the urban poor can afford. One of the challenges in increasing&#13;
coverage is to identify and understand the incentives that will trigger demand by households&#13;
for improved sanitation.&#13;
All footnotes on page 4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The Ecosan Argument                   Figure 1&#13;
The organic/nutrient loop: faeces       food&#13;
Ecosan technologies are&#13;
characterized by a number of                    Safe and         PEOPLE            Faeces&#13;
attributes including those in the box                     nuPathogen&#13;
below (See box). Minimal use of                                                    A  Patcon&#13;
water and re-use of excreta nutrients       Transport                                   - composting&#13;
are positive characteristics. Limiting       Storage s                                 -dehydration&#13;
water use and increasing nutrient          Prcssn&#13;
4'Safe fertilizer&#13;
access for food production are key           Harvested                            X    Safe soil conditioner&#13;
Ecosan objectives.                               crop    :     P L                    - plant health&#13;
'~¶JPLANTS                 ater holding capacity&#13;
;=_                       | Steven Esrey &amp; lngvor Anderson: An Ecosystem Approach to the Manogement of Human WasteiRecent Developmemets&#13;
in the Ecological Sanitation (Presentation by lngvar Anderson, Roundathle Meeting on Ecoson,aroch 2001, Ndirobi, Kenya)&#13;
* On-plot&#13;
* Minimal use of water             critical challenges in every day life.  addition of ash to faeces is done&#13;
* Dehydration/aerobic composting    But these benefits could be important  properly with encouraging results. In&#13;
(with or without urine separation)  in environments where subsistence  Kisoro, public Ecosan toilets were&#13;
* May require drying/bulking       farming is significant and the practice  observed to have minimal smell and&#13;
material (ash, dry soil, lime,    of excreta re-use is culturally     near-zero flies, an improvement over&#13;
crushed sea shells etc.)          acceptable to households, individual  many public toilets based on other&#13;
farmers and communities            technologies5.&#13;
* May be above ground to facilitate&#13;
contents removal                  The Vietnamese "double-vault"       Assessing Demand Drivers&#13;
* Nutrients and sanitized excreta as  dehydrating toilet was designed and  A s    gmEcoesn&#13;
end-products                   promoted in response to the direct  f   Eo     n&#13;
agricultural use of fresh excreta by&#13;
Some promoters of Ecosan stress     most farmers. This practice was so  As shown in Figure 2, the Ecosan&#13;
urine and faeces separation for     entrenched that public health officials  loop contains three distinct segments:&#13;
nutrient re-use and soil conditioning  were hard-pressed to ensure that  * Onsite storage and treatment&#13;
as essential requirements of an     households would leave excreta       * Offsite transport, storage and&#13;
Ecoson solution. This reflects the  undisturbed long enough to achieve    treatment&#13;
global environmental "vision" of    the required dessication and         * Application for reuse&#13;
closing-the-loop (Figure 1) while   condtioning before use.              Closing the loop requires linking the&#13;
managing excreta. Unfortunately,    Experience shows that many African  different conditions, processes and&#13;
such a global vision does not always  households do not yet accept direct  activities of each segment, and&#13;
address the practical requirements of  re-use of urine and do not wish to  examining how these affect existing&#13;
its implementation. Detailed analyses  undertake excreta-based composting.  household coping strategies,&#13;
of the activities in the segments of the  However, there are a few recent  preferences, and social arrangements.&#13;
expanded loop (Figure 2) reveal the  cases (eg. Kisoro, Uganda) where   The remainder of this paper presents&#13;
critical drivers that influence     urine is diverted to soak-pits and the  practical examples of this process.&#13;
household demand for Ecosan.&#13;
One of the important lessons that     Figure 2&#13;
has emerged in sanitation promotion   Closing the loop: Segments and Main Activities&#13;
is that poor households will invest in&#13;
new latrines for reasons of dignity,            Segment 1: Excreta PraduCian, On-Site Starage and Primary Treatment&#13;
privacy, status, and convenience                              ----et            .&#13;
rather thlan for benefits of health                             Excret handling,  _&#13;
improvement alone.                                               O&amp;M of facilities &#13;
Just as improved health is not, by&#13;
itself, sufficient to create demand for   Segment 3:   uriculture,                       TSegment 2:&#13;
low cost sanitation, the benefits of   Re-Use, Nutrient  uban lancaping          Material  Recycling Station&#13;
excreta re-use may not, by             Application and  ond horticulture      Processing,   ecycling Tation,&#13;
themselves, be sufficient to trigger   Soil Conditioning         re                        Secondary Treatment&#13;
demand for Ecosan from poor                                                               and storage&#13;
households who face many more                                            \l&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Examples of Demand Drivers         been used, they demand both        Examples of Drivers in Segment 3:&#13;
Physical Drivers in Segment 1      periodic desludging and skill in   Subsistence farming and&#13;
Geo-hydrological conditions:       digging under existing structures.  alleviation of household poverty&#13;
There are examples of households   Where there is no room for pits, the  (nutrient application and soil&#13;
building raised pit latrines to    VIP option is simply not appropriate.  conditioning):&#13;
overcome flooding in areas that have  Examples of Drivers in Segment 2:  There is potential for re-use of&#13;
a high water table. In hard rocky  Small local operators:             nutrients and sanitized excreta,&#13;
areas pit digging is difficult and  The handling of stored excreta by  especially in semi-arid areas, and&#13;
expensive; if the rock is fissured,  individual householders raises   peI-urban food corridors adjacent to&#13;
there is also the risk of contaminating  concerns of both safety and cultural  large urban towns. Food sufficiency&#13;
groundwater if unlined pits are used.  acceptability. Small-scale operators  often contributes to alleviation of&#13;
In these cases, aboveground        can, however, be developed or      health-poverty.6&#13;
sanitation with offsite removal of  encouraged to provide these services  It is when all the activities of the&#13;
waste is required in any event and  in a safe and professional manner at  segments of the loop are practically&#13;
Ecosan can be an attractive option.  reasonable cost. (Such enterprises  achieved, in any given situation, that&#13;
High-Density Housing Areas:        are particularly likely to be viable in  closing-the-loop really occurs.&#13;
informal urban settlements). Small&#13;
locating pit latrines is difficult  operators can also be involved in the  Implications for Future&#13;
because  of the  digging  involvd, ,processing  and  transportation&#13;
ecause Of the digging involved.   .services required for the marketing of  Work&#13;
The ease of retrofitting Ecosan toilets,  manu re d prite oratin&#13;
above ground, into existing structures  mAnure Some private operators, in  WSP-AF will identify and study such&#13;
is an advantage.                   Accra, Ghana, provide O&amp;M services  practical examples of demand drivers&#13;
for innovative and low-cost&#13;
In a number of areas, with the twin           _                       t&#13;
problem of high water table and                                       technologies that can Improve&#13;
problemtio of huidighswater tabl an                                  services for the poor. Studies will also&#13;
congestion of buldings (for example                                   be care   u ocopr       aiu&#13;
s_             _       ~~~~~~~be carried out to compare various&#13;
performance indicators, including&#13;
costs, for various designs and other&#13;
technologies (including Ecosan).&#13;
Understanding the comparative&#13;
merits of Ecosan and other sanitation&#13;
technologies is essential if effective&#13;
- .          3E=                         sanitation coverage is to be attained.&#13;
J11,         -       i                   Other areas of WSP-AF's work will&#13;
r  3                                          ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~include:&#13;
a *                                   - ,&gt; * Country-level studies and&#13;
consultations on issues of demand&#13;
.;]|s0  - ot  1                  1g-x&lt;_   8   \     and experiences in the use of&#13;
~~~~  ~~~~~~~  I            ~~~~~~~~innovative sanitation technologies&#13;
31Y                  jg &gt; I ati; as and their impact.&#13;
V.               w                1 *Follow-up roundtable discussions/&#13;
workshops with analysts and&#13;
3. .j*-*X                      . ~subsistence farming and household&#13;
- ;,* _ *         * * *,         poverty alleviation and health&#13;
**  *! * * __      improvement.&#13;
-.~ _:s       _. _*" A           *                             Consulting and networking with&#13;
organizations and stakeholders&#13;
after installation, including removal  supporting R&amp;D in re-use and&#13;
low-income areas along the coastline  of partially stabilized material,  innovative sanitation technologies&#13;
of Accra), retrofitting of Ecosan toilets  replacing materials (e.g. mulch) in  to exchange lessons on demand&#13;
provides desired solutions for    toilet chambers and further          drivers for improved services.&#13;
households. While alternating VIP  processing and handling of the&#13;
latrines with offset pits have also  compost.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Program-Africa&#13;
Fax: (25 42) 260380&#13;
Website: www.wsp.org&#13;
-An appropriate option                                                        Direct your water supply and&#13;
An appropriate option for high water table conditions (Dor-es-Soloom, Tanzania)  sanitation-related queries to:&#13;
* Sharing and disseminating           Carrying out case studies on the roles           i    i  u   turi&#13;
knowledge to influence policies on  and effect of small-scale independent  !IIL1                    L   o&#13;
the appropriate use of innovative   providers in innovative sanitation&#13;
A GLOBAL WATER &amp; SANITATION ADVISORY SERVICE&#13;
technologies.                       technologies. &#13;
i  E-mail: whelpdesk@worldbank.org&#13;
o Documenting and disseminating     WSP-AF aims to contribute by sharing its&#13;
case studies on the impact of      experiences in sanitation promotion by&#13;
sanitation projects that have re-use  relying on its comparative advantages of&#13;
components on subsistence          field presence and ability to forge&#13;
agriculture and how they affect the  networks so that more stakeholders&#13;
poverty and health of poor         become engaged on the sanitation          Prepared by&#13;
households.                        question in Africa.                       Lukman Y. Salifu&#13;
October 2001&#13;
I This paper summarises main points of the Roundtable Discussion on Ecosan   The Water and Sanitation Prograrr&#13;
organized by WSP-Africa in March 2001 in Nairobi, Kenya                  I   an internatn    panership to&#13;
'                       ~~~~~~~~~is an international partnership to&#13;
2 Ecological Sanitation, in this paper, refers to the on-plot handling (with or  help the poor gain sustained acce!&#13;
without urine separation) of excreta with minimal use of water so that urine  to improved water supply and&#13;
nutrients and sanitized material are end products.                         sanitation services. The Program's&#13;
funding partners are the&#13;
3 Demand Drivers refer to "the physical and non-physical factors associated, with  Governments of Australia, Belgiun&#13;
a technology, which influence household (and community) choice and use of  Cana     ermany, Italy, Japan,&#13;
that technology°                                       ~~~~~~~~~~~~Canada, Germany, Italy, Japan,&#13;
that technology."                                             Luxembourg, the Netherlands,&#13;
4 Global Water Supply and Sanitation Assessment 2000 Report (2000) WHO &amp;     Norway, Sweden, Switzerland and&#13;
UNICEF: Geneva.                                                           the United Kingdom: the United&#13;
Nations Development Programme.&#13;
5 Field Notes; L. Salifu, Kisoro April 2000.                                 and the World Bank.&#13;
6 "Does Urban agriculture help prevent malnutrition? Evidence from Kampala.,&#13;
FCND Discussion Paper #45, IFPRI, Washington DC, 1998" - Maxwell D, Levin       b&#13;
C, CseteJ., Quoted in Ecological Sanitation - Closing the Loop to Urban Food  Green Design Assoiates&#13;
Security and Well-being, Stephen Esrey &amp; Ingvar Andersson ( Presentation by  Prin ed at&#13;
Ingvar Anderson, Roundtable Meeting on Ecosan, March 2001, Nairobi, Kenya)  PS Press Services Pvt. Ltd.&#13;
gdcopress@bol.net.in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="2479014">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2001/10/2479014/identifying-demand-drivers-sanitation-technologies-case-ecosan-africa
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2001/10/2479014/identifying-demand-drivers-sanitation-technologies-case-ecosan-africa</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2001/10/2479014/identifying-demand-drivers-sanitation-technologies-case-ecosan-africa</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/08/23/000094946_03081304004722/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/08/23/000094946_03081304004722/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2001-10-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2003-08-23T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Identifying demand drivers for sanitation
            technologies - the case of Ecosan in Africa
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            In identifying demand drivers for
            sanitation technologies, this note describes the case of
            Ecosan - Ecological Sanitation - which has made little
            progress in Africa despite decades of promotion by donors.
            The practical, and environmental benefits of "closing
            the loop", i.e., recycling the nutrients in excreta,
            seem remote to most poor African households. This lack of
            demand for Ecosan, in turn makes many sector practitioners
            question its potential. There are however, a number of
            physical conditions - including high water table, and hard
            rocky ground - which can increase the comparative advantage
            of many forms of Ecosan technology. But beyond these
            physical conditions, there are many factors that influence
            demand by households that need to be considered as well,
            such as the presence of small local operators involved in
            excreta handling. The note examines a number of physical,
            and non-physical "demand drivers" that may
            encourage households to adopt Ecosan solutions. It also
            discusses practical activities within the different segments
            of the "resource loop" and a number of factors,
            beyond the household level, that affect the communal
            adoption of Ecosan, and re-use of excreta.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Identifying demand drivers for sanitation
            technologies - the case of Ecosan in Africa
        </docna>
        <display_title>Identifying demand drivers for
            sanitation technologies - the case of Ecosan in Africa</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2001/10/2479014/identifying-demand-drivers-sanitation-technologies-case-ecosan-africa</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>UNDP-Water &amp; Sanitation Program</docty>
        <subtopic>Hygiene Promotion and Social Marketing,Town Water Supply and Sanitation,TF030632-DANISH CTF - FY05 (DAC PART
            COUNTRIES GNP PER CAPITA BELOW USD 2,500/AL,Health and Sanitation,Sanitation and Sewerage</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Health, Nutrition and Population</teratopic>
        <count>Africa</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Salifu, Lukman Y.</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000094946_03081304004722</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Solid waste management,Sanitation</subsc>
        <admreg>Africa,Africa</admreg>
        <colti>Water and Sanitation Program ; field note</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Health, Nutrition and Population</historic_topic>
        <sectr>Water, sanitation and flood protection</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Sanitation services; Ecological services;
            Case studies; Excreta disposal systems; Nutrient content;
            Recycling process; Physical treatment (sanitation);
            Demand-driven; Community participation
            ash,compost,composting,desludging,environmental
            benefits,excreta,Global Water
            Supply,groundwater,households,Inadequate
            sanitation,latrines,lime,local
            operators,mAnure,mulch,nutrients,performance indicators,pit
            latrines,poor health,population growth,private
            operators,public health,public
            toilets,Recycling,safety,sanitary
            conditions,sanitation,Sanitation Assessment,Sanitation
            coverage,sanitation projects,sanitation promotion,sanitation
            services,sanitation technologies,soak-pits,towns,urban
            areas,urban sanitation,use of water,waste,water supply,water use
        </keywd>
        <owner>Office of the Regional Vice Pres (AFRVP)</owner>
        <repnb>26548</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Capacities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Staffing Needs Assessments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wastewater Collection and Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crops</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Basic Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>On-site Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Marketing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fescal Sludge Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sludge Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ecosystems and Natural Habitats</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Use</ml:concept><ml:concept>Hygiene Promotion and Social Marketing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health and Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water, Sanitation and Hygiene</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sewerage</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fertilizers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Congestion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Technologies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ecosystems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>