<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>                                                                                                                                      Field Note                6&#13;
&#13;
                                             Upgraded Family&#13;
               Water and&#13;
               Sanitation&#13;
               Program                       Wells in Zimbabwe:&#13;
               An international&#13;
                                             Household-Level Water&#13;
               partnership to help&#13;
               the poor gain sustained&#13;
               access to improved&#13;
                                             Supplies for Multiple Uses&#13;
               water supply and&#13;
               sanitation services&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
           Africa Region&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Water, sanitation and hygiene are vital&#13;
components of sustainable development&#13;
and the alleviation of poverty. Across&#13;
Africa, political leaders and sector&#13;
specialists are generating new&#13;
momentum in these important areas.&#13;
This Field Note, together with the others&#13;
in the same series, constitutes a timely&#13;
contribution to that work. It is intended&#13;
principally to help politicians, leaders&#13;
and professionals in their activities. As&#13;
the Water Ambassador for Africa,&#13;
invited by the African Development           Drawing water from a UFW. Note the run-off channelling excess water to an irrigated garden.&#13;
Bank and endorsed by the African Water&#13;
Task Force and the African Ministerial       Summary&#13;
Conference on Water (AMCOW),                 Most drinking-water programmes of governments, NGOs and external support agencies concentrate on&#13;
I commend it to your attention.              public supplies, for domestic purposes only. In Zimbabwe, however, the long-established upgraded family&#13;
&#13;
                                             well (UFW) programme has two particularly interesting features. Each household invests in and manages its&#13;
&#13;
                                             own water supply without depending on the government for maintenance; the same water source is often&#13;
&#13;
                                             used for both domestic and productive purposes, which can considerably increase the incomes of poor people.&#13;
Salim Ahmed Salim                                This programme dates back many years and has grown to a large scale across the country. The&#13;
Water Ambassador for Africa                  individual wells are simple, convenient and reliable. The household-level approach avoids the problems of&#13;
&#13;
                                             ownership and decision making associated with public water provision. The wells build on traditional&#13;
&#13;
                                             practice, and serve people's multiple needs and uses for water, not just domestic drinking water. In&#13;
&#13;
                                             particular they can provide enough irrigation water for small-scale agriculture, which contributes directly to&#13;
&#13;
                                             the alleviation of poverty. Adding simple hand- or foot-pumps, which typically produce incomes eight times&#13;
&#13;
                                             greater than wells with buckets, can magnify this benefit. Thus the same water facilities can improve both&#13;
&#13;
                                             health and economic development.&#13;
&#13;
                                                 Given Zimbabwe's current economic problems, these UFWs are proving more sustainable than the&#13;
&#13;
                                             public supplies, and so are playing a vital role in enabling rural people to survive. This concept of household-&#13;
&#13;
                                             level water supply could have wide application across Africa.1&#13;
&#13;
                                             1Rain-water harvesting is another example of household-level water supply, but is not described in this Field Note.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                  government's main rural water programme, and has more&#13;
                                                                                  recently been promoted by a number of NGOs.&#13;
                                There is always&#13;
                                 something new                                    Context and description&#13;
&#13;
                                   out of Africa                                  of the upgraded&#13;
&#13;
                                           PLINY                                  family wells programme&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                  The government's main work&#13;
                                                                                  in drinking water and in irrigation&#13;
                                                                                       Over the last two decades, the government's rural water&#13;
&#13;
Background                                                                        programme has been largely based on supplying ground-&#13;
                                                                                  water, with hand-pumps being the dominant technology&#13;
                                                                                  for raising water. At least two-thirds of the rural population&#13;
                                                                                  with access to clean water obtain it from hand-pumps&#13;
     The vast majority of rural Zimbabweans live in                               fitted to boreholes and deep wells. As to sanitation,&#13;
     `communal areas', where the most common source of                            the internationally recognised ventilated improved&#13;
     water is ground-water. Many have simple family-owned                         pit latrine (known locally as the Blair latrine) is the&#13;
     hand-dug wells, while others use public wells or                             technology of choice.&#13;
boreholes. Zimbabwe's independence in 1980 coincided                                   The focus in the national programme was primarily on&#13;
with the start of the United Nations International Drinking                       improving health through providing safe water and&#13;
Water Supply and Sanitation Decade. Clean water and                               adequate sanitation for rural communities. Many boreholes&#13;
sanitation for rural communities was one of the priorities of                     made provision for cattle watering in the dry season and&#13;
the new government and Zimbabwe was able to tap                                   some provided communal washing facilities, but few were&#13;
significant international support for its efforts. An inter-                      intended to assist vegetable or crop production or other&#13;
ministerial National Action Committee for Water and                               household income-generating activities. Because the&#13;
Sanitation was established to manage a national                                   programme was only concerned with the comparatively small&#13;
programme to decentralise public rural water provision.2                          volumes of water for drinking, it did not apply the costly&#13;
    The national programme operated successfully for a                            process of careful siting needed for higher-yielding irrigation&#13;
number of years, and achieved reasonable levels of access                         boreholes. Where boreholes were found to be sufficiently&#13;
to safe water and steady progress in sanitation, most notably                     productive, vegetable gardens were encouraged, but the&#13;
with the ventilated improved pit (VIP) latrine.3 However,                         emphasis was on products for home consumption, better&#13;
the sustainability of this success has been jeopardised in                        nutrition being a further contribution to improved health&#13;
the last few years by economic decline both at the household                      status. There was little attempt within the rural water supply&#13;
and the national level. The national government's budgetary                       and sanitation programme to identify the water&#13;
allocations for maintenance of rural water infrastructure                         requirements of rural communities other than for domestic&#13;
have been cut drastically in real terms. These cuts have                          use, or to ask the people themselves about their water&#13;
been explained in the name of community-based                                     needs and uses. Productive water was the responsibility of&#13;
management; however, the requirement for communities                              other agencies and ministries, notably the Department of&#13;
to assume responsibility for maintenance comes at a time                          Agricultural and Technical Services (AGRITEX) located in the&#13;
when their resources are more stretched than ever. Ironically                     Ministry of Lands and Agriculture.&#13;
the rural water and sanitation programme, itself supposed                              AGRITEX provided formal irrigation schemes for groups&#13;
to reduce poverty in rural areas, has been threatened by                          of smallholder farmers (referred to as plotholders). The&#13;
worsening poverty.                                                                schemes typically involved building dams and providing&#13;
    As rural people have become increasingly dependent                            flood or sprinkler irrigation technologies, the latter often&#13;
on their own resources, one form of water supply stands                           involving large recurrent subsidies to pay for the pumping of&#13;
out for its sustainability: the upgraded family well (UFW).                       water. By 1999, the communal rural population was around&#13;
This concept was originally developed by the Ministry of                          5.8 million (1 million households). The number on plotholder&#13;
Health's Blair Research Laboratory as part of the                                 irrigation schemes amounted to just 2% of this total.&#13;
&#13;
2This programme is described in a separate Field Note published in 2002 by the Water and Sanitation Program-Africa Region.&#13;
3See the WSP Blue Gold Field Note: VIP Latrines in Zimbabwe, August 2002.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                               2&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
    Despite this tiny proportion of beneficiaries, the        the community as&#13;
government invested a high level of extension work and        a whole. In 1988,&#13;
direct subsidies into plotholder irrigation schemes. This     they applied the&#13;
strategy might be considered justified if these schemes had   same logic to&#13;
proved to be unambiguously viable and successful for the      water     supply.&#13;
farmers involved. Unfortunately, while some schemes have      They established&#13;
clearly been successful, the majority of plotholders have     that by lining the&#13;
not achieved significant levels of income from irrigation.    well with bricks,&#13;
                                                              raising the head&#13;
Development of the UFW programme                              works       above                       ZIMBABWE&#13;
    Government staff and others had long anticipated the      ground      level,&#13;
problems that are now evident in the national rural water     adding an apron&#13;
programme. They sought solutions that were both less          and water run-off&#13;
expensive in terms of initial investment costs and more       to remove excess&#13;
likely to be sustainable in the long term. The UFW is one     water (often to a&#13;
such solution.                                                vegetable garden or fruit trees) and using a steel windlass,&#13;
    Before 1980, very large numbers of family-owned wells     both water quality and well safety were significantly&#13;
were known to exist in rural areas, all self-built and self-  improved. The initial design of the UFW was established at&#13;
financed: later surveys showed that these traditional wells   the Blair Laboratory by combining all these simple elements.&#13;
served 30 to 40% of the rural population. But such            In the initial design, the windlass was supported on poles,&#13;
unprotected wells have been associated with outbreaks of      but brick columns later replaced these.&#13;
disease, and are prone to pollution by run-off water in           In 1988/89, the Blair Laboratory initiated demonstrations&#13;
times of rain and flood. The Ministry of Health offered small and trials in many parts of Zimbabwe through the Ministry&#13;
subsidies to help some families to make improvements such     of Health. The Ministry of Health endorsed the method in&#13;
as concrete cover slabs, and Health Assistants advised on     1990, as did the National Action Committee in 1991. By&#13;
simple protection. The traditional windlass was widely used.  the end of 1991, 2,500 units had been built, and this total&#13;
    The Ministry of Health's Blair Laboratory staff had long  had doubled within the next year. These early efforts in&#13;
observed that the key to the success of Zimbabwe's            promoting UFWs were supported by several external&#13;
sanitation programme lay in each latrine being owned and      agencies, including Swedish International Development&#13;
maintained by the individual household, rather than by        Co-operation Agency (Sida), United Nations Children's Fund&#13;
                                                                                      (UNICEF), Rotary, WaterAid, Redd&#13;
                                                                                      Barna (Save the Children­Norway)&#13;
                                                                                      and the Save the Children Fund (UK).&#13;
                                                                                          The international NGO WaterAid&#13;
                                                                                      founded a Zimbabwe country&#13;
                                                                                      programme in 1993, which became&#13;
                                                                                      the Mvuramanzi Trust. Several field&#13;
                                                                                      staff from the Blair Laboratory joined&#13;
                                                                                      the Mvuramanzi Trust. Over the&#13;
                                                                                      following nine years the Mvuramanzi&#13;
                                                                                      Trust promoted the upgrading of a&#13;
                                                                                      further 34,000 family wells, with&#13;
                                                                                      financial support from WaterAid,&#13;
                                                                                      Sida, Norwegian Agency for&#13;
                                                                                      Development            Co-operation&#13;
                                                                                      (NORAD), UNICEF, Rotary and the&#13;
                                                                                      Oak Foundation. Several other&#13;
                                                                                      NGOs, and the British Government's&#13;
                                                                                      Department       for   International&#13;
  Upgrading a family well by building brick columns to raise                          Development, also promoted UFWs&#13;
 the head works above ground level.                                                   in Zimbabwe.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                             3&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                      external support agency finance to be spread over a&#13;
  Productive water for a rural household                              much larger number of households.&#13;
&#13;
  Mr Tendai Chinamo and his family live in a communal area            Maintenance&#13;
  50 km north of Murehwa. Their farm of approximately&#13;
                                                                         The maintenance requirements of UFWs are minimal.&#13;
  2.5 hectares is all in productive use. The farm is in an area with&#13;
                                                                      Some structural repairs may be necessary from time to time,&#13;
  ahighwatertable,andhasseveralwatersources.Fordomestic&#13;
                                                                      plus periodic replacement of bearings for the windlass, which&#13;
  use, the family has a properly protected UFW. For productive&#13;
                                                                      are made from old car tyres, and of the chain and bucket&#13;
  use,theyhavetwowellsequippedwithrope-and-washerpumps&#13;
  as well as open wells, with watering via buckets.                   for drawing the water.&#13;
&#13;
      Mr Chinamo is an outgrower for a horticultural export&#13;
  company. He grows a wide range of vegetables for export to          The potential for further upgrading&#13;
  Europe. The family also produces maize, basic vegetables and           A standard UFW can be used for horticulture, watering&#13;
  fruit for home consumption and for sale both locally and in the     with the bucket and windlass. This is hard work, and&#13;
  capital city Harare. Their agricultural income, derived from        consequently most well owners can only cultivate a small&#13;
  managing water for productive use, is significant. The family is    area. Adding a simple pump, such as a rope-and-washer&#13;
  easily able to cover the maintenance costs of their domestic        pump or a treadle pump (see box on page 5), makes it&#13;
  water and productive water sources.                                 possible to water an area some eight times larger than&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    By 2002 an estimated 50,000 UFWs, serving as many&#13;
as half a million people, had been built across Zimbabwe&#13;
at no cost to the government. The household approach&#13;
changes the emphasis in rural water from public supplies&#13;
for drinking water to individual household supplies for both&#13;
domestic and productive needs, which enable families to&#13;
increase their generation of cash income. The potential of&#13;
this approach is illustrated by the description of a successful&#13;
farming family given in the box above.&#13;
    While this example shows what can be achieved,&#13;
the majority of farmers in communal areas eke out a&#13;
subsistence and depend on remittances from family&#13;
members employed in the urban areas or in other countries&#13;
in southern Africa or abroad. Addressing poverty in the&#13;
communal areas, particularly when the government is&#13;
focusing on other issues, requires strategies for individual&#13;
households to work their way out of poverty without large&#13;
capital and recurrent subsidies. Family wells provide an&#13;
opportunity for them to do so.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Analysis&#13;
&#13;
    Over a decade of experience with tens of thousands&#13;
    of UFWs has shown that they are widely accepted&#13;
    and appreciated by households. Once UFWs are&#13;
    introduced into an area, the majority of households&#13;
seek to improve their existing wells or construct new&#13;
improved wells. The households are willing to bear much&#13;
of the initial capital cost (around 80%), which both indicates         A rope-and-washer pump helps make more water&#13;
                                                                       available for productive use.&#13;
their commitment to the technology and allows public or&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                    4&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
with a bucket. Pumping is not unduly arduous with such a&#13;
pump, while the initial cost is less than US$100 (for a rope-    Treadle pumps in Africa&#13;
&#13;
and-washer pump). The materials used are all readily&#13;
available and farmers for whom the pumps provide additional      The treadle pump was invented in Bangladesh, where several&#13;
&#13;
income should be able to keep them in working condition,         variants have been developed over many years and millions&#13;
&#13;
although any such technology will inevitably have more           areinuse.IthasspreadtoanumberofcountriesinAfrica(such&#13;
&#13;
maintenance problems than a simple windlass and bucket.          as Kenya, Malawi and Zambia). There are at least three&#13;
                                                                 companies in Zimbabwe manufacturing local versions. The&#13;
    There is a trade-off between the extra economic benefits&#13;
                                                                 treadle pump in Zimbabwe is about twice the price of a rope-&#13;
of adding a pump, and the increased cost and complication.&#13;
                                                                 and-washerpump,andthelatteriscurrentlymorecommonon&#13;
The use of rope-and-washer pumps in Zimbabwe is growing&#13;
                                                                 wells used for commercial horticultural production. However,&#13;
and at this juncture the longer-run sustainability of this&#13;
                                                                 the treadle pump appears to have several advantages: it uses&#13;
technology remains to be proven. If pump-owning&#13;
                                                                 the leg muscles, which are much stronger than the arm&#13;
households do thereby increase their incomes, they will          muscles;itcandischargeunderpressure,eitherintoareservoir&#13;
have both the means and the incentive to maintain or             above the pump level for gravity feed or via a hosepipe directly&#13;
replace the pumps over time. If, on the other hand,              to the field; it is easily portable from well to well and to the&#13;
conditions change and the pumps no longer offer economic         homestead for overnight security.&#13;
benefits, they will not be maintained. However, the longevity&#13;
or otherwise of productive water technologies does not raise&#13;
the same concerns as those which apply to the sustainability&#13;
of life-supporting domestic water programmes.                  commodities, farmers with water pumped manually from&#13;
                                                               UFWs can still generate incomes comparable with their&#13;
Agricultural applications                                      counterparts in the formal irrigation schemes.&#13;
    In addition to water, however, rural people face a number     In Zimbabwe the main intermediaries supporting such&#13;
of other constraints in increasing their agricultural incomes. farmers have been private marketing companies (see box&#13;
They often have difficulty in procuring inputs such as high-   on page 6).&#13;
quality seed, fertiliser and chemicals; they may lack the         There have not been many detailed studies on the&#13;
knowledge to make the best use of such inputs; they may        returns which farmers are able to achieve from horticultural&#13;
have difficulty in marketing their produce to best advantage.  production. However, it appears that an efficient farmer&#13;
However, by concentrating on producing high-value              growing export crops can achieve an annual return of up to&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 A labour-saving treadle pump, Malawi.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                              5&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
US$600 from a 0.24-hectare plot with a well and a pump.                          deep boreholes to provide drinking water in droughts, and&#13;
The same farmer with the same well and a bucket could                            a large number of family wells for normal usage.&#13;
only cultivate a 0.03-hectare plot and achieve an annual&#13;
return of perhaps US$75. These increased income figures                          Reservations about water quality&#13;
represent a significant opportunity to generate cash income                            Concerns have also been raised about the quality of&#13;
&#13;
for rural households, in the same range as incomes from                          water from family wells. Upgrading and protecting a well&#13;
&#13;
conventional irrigation schemes.4 These figures relate to                        markedly improves water quality compared to an&#13;
&#13;
production for export, but domestic markets can also be                          unprotected well, and health benefits can be assured if the&#13;
&#13;
profitable and are easier for small farmers to access. The                       upgrading programmes are backed by effective health and&#13;
&#13;
important point is to start with market analysis and hence                       hygiene education. Furthermore, sector specialists worldwide&#13;
&#13;
decide the production needs, including water.                                    now agree that the quantity of water used is a more&#13;
                                                                                 important determinant of the health benefits of improved&#13;
&#13;
Objections                                                                       water supplies than the quality of water itself. UFWs, being&#13;
                                                                                 located adjacent to houses, result in much higher levels of&#13;
&#13;
and constraints                                                                  water use than communal boreholes. Proximity also&#13;
                                                                                 encourages the use of water for vegetable and fruit&#13;
                                                                                 production and hence improved nutrition.&#13;
&#13;
    Despite their many benefits, UFWs have not been                              Funding&#13;
completely accepted by the decision makers in the water                                Some water-sector leaders hesitated to promote UFWs&#13;
sector in Zimbabwe. There are a number of reasons for this.                      because the external funds are given to benefit individual&#13;
                                                                                 families, rather than the whole community. However, this&#13;
Geographical considerations                                                      is exactly the same situation as for latrine construction, so&#13;
    At national level, some people asserted that UFW                             there is no logic in supporting one but not the other. In&#13;
technology would only apply in parts of the country with                         fact, from the external support agency's point of view, the&#13;
high water tables and good rainfall. In practice, however,                       cost per person of supporting a family-well programme is&#13;
families have successfully upgraded wells in districts                           less than that of supporting a borehole and hand-pump&#13;
throughout the country, including notoriously dry or                             programme. This is partly because most of the cost of the&#13;
supposedly poor ground-water areas. During times of                              UFW is borne by the owner.&#13;
drought, UFWs are certainly more likely to dry up than&#13;
boreholes because they are less deep, but experience in                          Staffing&#13;
the 1991/92 and 1994/95 severe droughts showed that                                    Another constraint on the expansion of the family&#13;
boreholes frequently dry up also. People may then be forced                      wells was staffing: a government agency can install one&#13;
to resort to unprotected sources of water. One solution to                       borehole with much less work, education and time than,&#13;
this problem would be to install a small number of very                          say, twenty-five family wells.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  The work of Hortico: smallholders and big business in partnership&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  One successful smallholder scheme is run by Hortico, a company formed initially to export to Europe the horticultural produce from the&#13;
  large-scale commercial farming sector. Seeking to expand and diversify its production base, Hortico initially approached groups on&#13;
  some of AGRITEX's formal schemes, but had mixed experience with these plotholders. Not only was the water supply and hence&#13;
  continuity of production frequently disrupted, but there were disputes about grading the produce and sharing the incomes. Hortico then&#13;
  developed a system of working with individual families, which has proved very successful.&#13;
       Now working with about 3,000 households, Hortico has a network of small depots, each located within an area of about&#13;
  200 farmers. The depots feed two main packhouses, from which the produce is sent ready packed and labelled directly to supermarket&#13;
  shelves in the UK. Hortico addresses systematically all of the constraints faced by the farmers except water supply, which individual&#13;
  farmers obtain from their own household wells. It encourages farmers to produce crops which have high margins; it loans all the inputs&#13;
  (seeds, fertilisers, etc.) required for a specified production area; it trains local extension staff to assist the farmers to produce the crops;&#13;
  it provides on-the-spot grading and payment when the crops are brought to the depot. The individual productive areas vary according to&#13;
  the crop, but are small (typically 300 to 600 square metres).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
4In a recent major study of ten formal irrigation schemes [Tawonezi &amp; Mudima (2000)], half had annual average incomes per farmer of less than US$420. The best&#13;
scheme had an average income per farmer of US$4,200 per annum.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                              6&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                        of this wider objective. A UFW can serve&#13;
                                                                                        both domestic and productive needs&#13;
                                                                                        and produce high-value horticultural&#13;
                                                                                        crops. The addition of a simple water-&#13;
                                                                                        lifting device to a UFW or to an adjacent&#13;
                                                                                        well dedicated to water for productive&#13;
                                                                                        purposes, while adding to maintenance&#13;
                                                                                        requirements, greatly enlarges the area&#13;
                                                                                        which a family can comfortably water&#13;
                                                                                        and increases income-earning potential,&#13;
                                                                                        often to levels comparable with incomes&#13;
                                                                                        on conventional, formal irrigation&#13;
                                                                                        schemes. A well with a bucket enables&#13;
                                                                                        a family to survive; a well with a pump&#13;
                                                                                        helps it to overcome poverty.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                        Marketing is vital for&#13;
                                                                                        profitable commercial&#13;
 Small-scale horticulture irrigated by bucket.&#13;
                                                                                        use of UFWs&#13;
                                                                                             Household-level access to productive&#13;
Lessons for sustainability                                          water can contribute to rural poverty alleviation, if profitable&#13;
                                                                    markets can be identified. Market access should define the&#13;
and poverty reduction                                               crops to be grown and hence the inputs, technical knowledge&#13;
                                                                    and skills which need to be provided. With extension inputs&#13;
                                                                    from locally recruited extension agents, rural households&#13;
The UFW is a sustainable system                                     have shown themselves capable of growing specialised&#13;
   The UFW was originally conceived and designed by the             horticultural crops using their UFWs. There is a range of&#13;
Blair Laboratory team as a sustainable household-level water        high-value crops that could be successfully grown&#13;
supply, and its sustainability has been clearly demonstrated        and marketed from rural areas in Zimbabwe and other&#13;
over a fourteen-year period. Each household has sole                countries in Africa.&#13;
ownership and hence sole&#13;
responsibility, and can select&#13;
the technology appropriate&#13;
to its circumstances. The&#13;
Zimbabwe upgraded family&#13;
wells programme promotes&#13;
technologies (well linings, bucket&#13;
and windlass) that are cheap and&#13;
durable. In addition, each family&#13;
can    easily     upgrade      the&#13;
technology further as it wishes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The UFW helps&#13;
reduce poverty&#13;
   The provision of water and&#13;
sanitation is not just an objective&#13;
in its own right, but part of a&#13;
strategy to eliminate poverty. In&#13;
rural areas household-level&#13;
water supplies, such as UFWs,&#13;
can play a central role in respect      Typical layout for horticulture using pump irrigation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                 7&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                                                               Water and Sanitation&#13;
                                                                                                                               Program-Africa Region (WSP-AF)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                               The World Bank, Hill Park,&#13;
                                                                                                                               Upper Hill, P.O. Box 30577,&#13;
                                                                                                                               Nairobi, Kenya&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                               Phone: (254-2) 260300, 260400&#13;
                                                                                                                               Fax: (254-2) 260386&#13;
                                                                                                                               E-mail: wspaf@worldbank.org&#13;
                                                                                                                               Web site: www.wsp.org&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 An upgraded family well, covered to maintain water quality.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The UFW has international applicability&#13;
     The ideas developed in Zimbabwe have already spread to Mozambique,&#13;
where the government has recognised the benefits of household-level water&#13;
supply and has successfully implemented programmes supported by both GTZ&#13;
(German Technical Co-operation) and WaterAid. A small programme has also&#13;
started in Sierra Leone.&#13;
     There are no special conditions in Zimbabwe that suggest that the UFW&#13;
would remain unique to that country ­ on the contrary, appropriate conditions&#13;
for its use apply across large parts of the continent.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   References&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   · Poverty in Zimbabwe. Harare: Central Statistics Office, 1998.                                                              Acknowledgments&#13;
   · Manzungu, Emmanuel and Pieter van der Zaag. The Practice of Smallholder                                                    Written by: Peter Robinson&#13;
&#13;
      Irrigation: Case Studies from Zimbabwe. Harare: University of Zimbabwe                                                    Series Editor: Jon Lane&#13;
                                                                                                                                Assistant Editor: John Dawson&#13;
      Publications, 1996.&#13;
                                                                                                                                Published by: Vandana Mehra&#13;
   · Mbetu, Ramson. Rural Development: Productive Water First. Paper                                                            Photographs by: Alan Windram,&#13;
      presented at Water Pricing Workshop, Harare, 1995.                                                                        Aquamor and Jon Lane&#13;
   · Morgan, Peter and Ephraim Chimbunde. Upgrading Family Wells in                                                             Designed by: Write Media&#13;
&#13;
      Zimbabwe. Waterlines, vol. 9, no. 3, 1991.                                                                                Printed by: PS Press Services Pvt. Ltd.&#13;
&#13;
   · Morgan, Peter, Ephraim Chimbunde, Nason Mtakwa, and Anthony&#13;
      Waterkeyn. Upgraded Family Wells in Zimbabwe. Waterlines, vol. 14,                                                        August 2002&#13;
&#13;
      no. 4, 1996.&#13;
                                                                                                                                The Water and Sanitation Program is an&#13;
   · Robinson, Peter, Roy Maposa, and Ramson Mbetu. Water and Sanitation                                                        international partnership to help the&#13;
      for Poor Households ­ Reducing Costs or Increasing Incomes? Harare:                                                       poor gain sustained access to improved&#13;
      Zimconsult, 2000.                                                                                                         water supply and sanitation services.&#13;
   · Tawonezi, Dagmore and Kennedy Mudima. Socio-Economic Impact of                                                             The Program's main funding partners&#13;
      Smallholder Irrigation Development in Zimbabwe. Harare: Food &amp;                                                            are the Governments of Australia,&#13;
&#13;
      Agricultural Organisation of the United Nations, 2000.                                                                    Austria, Belgium, Canada, Denmark,&#13;
&#13;
   · Targeted Water Price Subsidies. Report on study conducted for                                                              France, Germany, Luxembourg, the&#13;
&#13;
      Water Resources Management Strategy Steering Committee. Harare:                                                           Netherlands, Norway, Sweden,&#13;
                                                                                                                                Switzerland, and the United Kingdom;&#13;
      Zimconsult, 2000.&#13;
                                                                                                                                the United Nations Development&#13;
                                                                                                                                Programme, and the World Bank.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The World Bank does not accept responsibility for the views expressed herein, which are those of the author, and should not be attributed to the World Bank or its affiliated&#13;
organisations. The designations employed and the presentation of the material are solely for the convenience of the reader anddo not imply the expression of any legal&#13;
opinion whatsoever on the part of the World Bank or its affiliates concerning the legal status of any country, territory, city, area, or its authorities, or concerning the&#13;
delimitations of its boundaries or national affiliations. Information from Water and Sanitation Program publications may be freely reproduced. Proper acknowledgment&#13;
will be appreciated.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="2494396">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2002/08/2494396/upgraded-family-wells-zimbabwe-household-level-water-supplies-multiple-uses
        </url>
        <availablein>French,Portuguese,English</availablein>
        <fullavailablein>
            <available_in lang="French" entityid="000160016_20030827173914" node_id="2494396"/>
            <available_in lang="Portuguese" entityid="000160016_20030827174159" node_id="2494396"/>
        </fullavailablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2002/08/2494396/upgraded-family-wells-zimbabwe-household-level-water-supplies-multiple-uses</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2002/08/2494396/upgraded-family-wells-zimbabwe-household-level-water-supplies-multiple-uses</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/08/27/000160016_20030827173735/Rendered/INDEX/266240PAPER0English0Blue0Gold06.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/08/27/000160016_20030827173735/Rendered/PDF/266240PAPER0English0Blue0Gold06.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2003-08-27T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2002-08-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Upgraded family wells in Zimbabwe :
            household-level water supplies for multiple uses
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Most drinking-water program of
            governments, NGOs and external support agencies concentrate
            on public supplies, for domestic purposes only. In Zimbabwe,
            however, the long-established upgraded family well (UFW)
            program has two particularly interesting features. Each
            household invests in and manages its own water supply
            without depending on the government for maintenance; the
            same water source is often used for both domestic and
            productive purposes, which can considerably increase the
            incomes of poor people. This program dates back many years
            and has grown to a large scale across the country. The
            individual wells are simple, convenient and reliable. The
            household-level approach avoids the problems of ownership
            and decision making associated with public water provision.
            The wells build on traditional practice, and serve
            people's multiple needs and uses for water, not just
            domestic drinking water. In particular they can provide
            enough irrigation water for small-scale agriculture, which
            contributes directly to the alleviation of poverty. Adding
            simple hand- or foot-pumps, which typically produce incomes
            eight times greater than wells with buckets, can magnify
            this benefit. Thus the same water facilities can improve
            both health and economic development. Given Zimbabwe's
            current economic problems, these UFWs are proving more
            sustainable than the public supplies, and so are playing a
            vital role in enabling rural people to survive. This concept
            of household level water supply could have wide application
            across Africa.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Upgraded family wells in Zimbabwe :
            household-level water supplies for multiple uses
        </docna>
        <display_title>Upgraded family wells in Zimbabwe
            : household-level water supplies for multiple uses</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2002/08/2494396/upgraded-family-wells-zimbabwe-household-level-water-supplies-multiple-uses</listing_relative_url>
        <subtopic>Town Water Supply and Sanitation,Water Supply and Systems,Water Supply and Sanitation Governance
            and Institutions,Water Conservation,Water and Industry</subtopic>
        <docty>UNDP-Water &amp; Sanitation Program</docty>
        <teratopic>Water Resources</teratopic>
        <count>Zimbabwe</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Southern Africa!$!80472</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Sub-Saharan Africa!$!80473</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000160016_20030827173735</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>Africa,Africa</admreg>
        <colti>Water and sanitation program - Africa region
            field note ; no. 6</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Water Resources</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Potable water; Drinking water standards;
            Drinking water supplies; Drinking water treatment; Drinking
            water disinfection; Irrigation systerms; Nongovernmental
            organizations; Water supply; Wells; Small scale farming;
            Hand pumps; Maintenance &amp; repair; Water quality
            management; Marketing; Commercial agriculture
            adequate sanitation,Agricultural
            applications,boreholes,clean water,commercial farming,crop
            production,dams,decision makers,decision making,deep
            wells,domestic water,drinking water,drought,excess
            water,export,farmers,gravity,hand-dug wells,hand-pumps,high
            water,households,hygiene education,initial
            investment,investment costs,Irrigation
            Development,irrigation water,latrine
            construction,linings,maintenance costs,maintenance
            requirements,open wells,pit latrine,pollution,provision of
            water,public water,public wells,pump
            irrigation,pumping,quality of water,quantity of
            water,Rain,rainfall,rural communities,rural water,rural
            water supply,safe water,sanitation,sanitation
            services,sources of water,urban areas,use of water,VIP
            Latrines,washing,Water,water allocations,water
            facilities,water harvesting,water infrastructure,Water
            partnership,Water Pricing,water quality,Water
            Resources,Water Resources Management,water source,water
            sources,water supplies,water supply,water tables,water use,wells
        </keywd>
        <owner>Water- Water and Sanit Prgrm (GWASP)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Southern Africa</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Sub-Saharan Africa</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>26624</repnb>
        <alt_title>
            Puits familiaux ameliores au Zimbabwe :
            approvisionnement en eau menageres aux usages multiples;
            Pocos familiares melhorados no Zimbabwe : abastecimento de
            agua a agregados para usos multiplos
        </alt_title>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crops</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Basic Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>On-site Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Marketing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition – Community Based Interventions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition – Raising Awareness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition – Training</ml:concept><ml:concept>Remittances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Migration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Town Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Use</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Communities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply</ml:concept><ml:concept>Diseases</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water, Sanitation and Hygiene</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Benefits</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income-Generating Activities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Movement of Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Africa</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Zimbabwe</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>