<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>                                                                                                                                           4&#13;
                                                                                                                      Field Note&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
               Water and&#13;
               Sanitation&#13;
               Program                       VIP Latrines in Zimbabwe:&#13;
               An international&#13;
                                             From Local Innovation to&#13;
               partnership to help&#13;
               the poor gain sustained&#13;
               access to improved&#13;
                                             Global Sanitation Solution&#13;
               water supply and&#13;
               sanitation services&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
           Africa Region&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Water, sanitation and hygiene are vital&#13;
components of sustainable development&#13;
and the alleviation of poverty. Across&#13;
Africa, political leaders and sector&#13;
specialists are generating new&#13;
momentum in these important areas.&#13;
This Field Note, together with the others&#13;
in the same series, constitutes a timely&#13;
contribution to that work. It is intended&#13;
principally to help politicians, leaders&#13;
and professionals in their activities. As&#13;
the Water Ambassador for Africa,&#13;
invited by the African Development           Typical Zimbabwe VIP latrine, showing spiral entrance.&#13;
&#13;
Bank and endorsed by the African Water&#13;
Task Force and the African Ministerial     Summary&#13;
Conference on Water (AMCOW),                 This Field Note describes the development of the ventilated improved pit (VIP) latrine in&#13;
I commend it to your attention.              Zimbabwe. This innovative latrine was invented at the Ministry of Health's Blair Research&#13;
                                             Laboratory in 1973, and subsequently adopted as the standard sanitation technology promoted&#13;
                                             by the Ministry of Health. For some years it was implemented at a large scale by the&#13;
                                             government's national rural water and sanitation programme, until the decline of the national&#13;
Salim Ahmed Salim                            economy. Despite that decline, however, the VIP latrine itself is still popular and is currently&#13;
Water Ambassador for Africa                  being promoted in various forms by local NGOs and others.&#13;
                                                 The VIP latrine is known and used in countries all over the world. Within Zimbabwe itself,&#13;
                                             the VIP latrine is known as the Blair latrine and is a national institution. It is still the sanitation&#13;
                                             technology of choice for most rural households. Its success demonstrates that well-supported&#13;
                                             local research can produce innovative technologies that are ideally suited to local conditions,&#13;
                                             and that home-grown technologies can generate significant political and popular support.&#13;
                                                 Its inclusion in the school curriculum has meant that an entire generation of Zimbabweans&#13;
                                             has grown up with an appreciation of the benefits of the VIP latrine. In addition, the&#13;
                                             involvement of so many government staff in the national sanitation programme, and the&#13;
                                             training that this programme provided to thousands of VIP latrine builders, have further&#13;
                                             enhanced its reputation and support.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                               its leadresearcherswasPeterMorgan,withafieldteamheaded&#13;
                                                                               by Ephraim Chimbunde. The BRL staff were encouraged to&#13;
                                 There is always                               search for effective ways to improve rural water supply and&#13;
                                                                               sanitation in Zimbabwe, and had some notable successes.&#13;
                                  something new                                There are now hundreds of thousands of Blair latrines and&#13;
&#13;
                                   out of Africa                               tens of thousands of `B' type Bush pumps and upgraded&#13;
                                                                               family wells in Zimbabwe, all of which originate from work&#13;
                                         PLINY                                 done at the BRL. All are well known within the country, and&#13;
                                                                               the VIP latrine has become famous around the world.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                               The development of&#13;
                                                                               VIP latrines in Zimbabwe&#13;
Background&#13;
                                                                               The Blair Research Laboratory's work&#13;
                                                                                    The first `Blair latrine' was built in 1973, at the Henderson&#13;
    The Republic of Zimbabwe came into existence after a                       Research Station north of Harare. This experimental latrine&#13;
    prolonged uprising against the former Government of                        used a screened ventilation pipe to control the flies and&#13;
    Rhodesia, which finally led to elections and Zimbabwe's                    odours common in previous pit latrines, and was the&#13;
    independence in 1980.                                                      forerunner of what is today known throughout the world as&#13;
    During the long period of conflict and sanctions before                    the ventilated improved pit (VIP) latrine.&#13;
that date, Zimbabwe (then Rhodesia) had few friends.                                After two years of testing and improving the design,&#13;
However, despite this isolation, the civil service continued to                the BRL released details of the Blair latrine design to the&#13;
function well, and several innovative rural technologies were                  government. At that time, the superstructure was usually&#13;
developed by government-funded researchers, and                                made from ferrocement. In Zimbabwe, rural water supply&#13;
implemented in government programmes, during this period.                      and sanitation were considered components of primary&#13;
    The Blair Research Laboratory (BRL)1 was perhaps the                       health care, thus it was the Ministry of Health (MoH) that&#13;
most remarkable of the government research units. One of                       adopted the technology and began disseminating it.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  The design of the VIP latrine                                                                                                VIP latrine&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  The VIP latrine is similar to a conventional pit latrine, but has an offset pit that&#13;
  permits the installation of a vertical ventilation pipe (or structure) beside the                                                          Fly&#13;
&#13;
  latrine superstructure.                                                                                                                   screen&#13;
                                                                                                                          Air&#13;
       ThedesignoftheVIPlatrinecausesairtoflowdownintothelatrinepitthroughthe                                           movement&#13;
&#13;
  latrine squat hole and up out of the ventilation pipe, thus removing odours from the&#13;
  latrine. Flies are always attracted by the smell from latrines, but in a VIP latrine they&#13;
                                                                                                                                             Vent&#13;
  areattractedtothetopofthevent-piperatherthantothelatrinesquathole.Therethey&#13;
                                                                                                                                             pipe&#13;
  are prevented from entering the vent-pipe by a fly screen fixed across the top of it.&#13;
       Some flies inevitably find their way into the latrine pit by other routes, and may&#13;
  breed in there. However, flies are attracted to light, and the VIP design makes use of&#13;
  this fact to get rid of them. The interior of a VIP latrine is always kept semi-dark, so that&#13;
  the flies inside the pit are drawn towards the light at the top of the vent pipe, where the&#13;
  screen traps them and they fall back into the pit or die.&#13;
       The effectiveness of this fly control was demonstrated by an experiment in                                                   Flies&#13;
&#13;
  Zimbabwe,whichcomparedthenumberoffliesfoundinanunventedpitlatrinetothat                                  SHAW&#13;
&#13;
  found in an otherwise identical VIP latrine. Over a three-month period in 1975, an&#13;
  average of 179 flies per day were caught in the unvented latrine, compared to only&#13;
  2 flies per day in the VIP latrine.  2                                                                       WEDC/ROD&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
1Named after Dr Dyson Blair, a former Secretary for Health, and an early advocate of the health benefits of low-cost and appropriate water&#13;
supply and sanitation technologies.&#13;
2Peter Morgan, 1977: see references.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                           2&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
    From the outset, the MoH was enthusiastic in its support                          They hoped that&#13;
for the Blair latrine. Initially the liberation struggle limited                      these brick VIP&#13;
promotion and uptake of the technology by rural                                       latrines would last&#13;
households, but the MoH mobilised its network of health                               a generation and&#13;
workers to promote and build Blair latrines on commercial                             thus provide a&#13;
farms and at government offices, health clinics and small                             basis for sustain-&#13;
towns around the country. As a result, between 1975 and                               able improve-&#13;
1980 tens of thousands of Blair latrines were constructed                             ments in hygiene&#13;
and many government staff became familiar with this new                               behaviour and&#13;
sanitation technology.                                                                public health. The&#13;
    After independence in 1980, the new government                                    only      obvious                            ZIMBABWE&#13;
committed itself to rural development and attracted                                   drawback of the&#13;
considerable funding from external support agencies eager                             brick VIP latrine&#13;
to assist in the reconstruction and development of                                    was its expense.&#13;
Zimbabwe. Among others, the World Bank's Technology                                   So, secondly, the&#13;
Advisory Group (the forerunner of the Water and Sanitation                            MoH decided that&#13;
Program) visited Zimbabwe to see the Blair latrine and                                its    sanitation&#13;
devised the now familiar name of VIP latrine.                                         programmes would provide a substantial direct subsidy3 to&#13;
    Despite this support and enthusiasm, the post-                                    rural households in order to make brick VIP latrines more&#13;
independence sanitation programme started slowly. The                                 affordable for them.&#13;
government was undergoing reorganisation, and new&#13;
challenges were becoming apparent. The MoH recognised                                 The VIP latrine and the&#13;
that the ferrocement VIP latrine, used so successfully in                             National Sanitation Programme&#13;
public and institutional settings prior to independence, was                              In 1985, Zimbabwe launched the Integrated Rural Water&#13;
not the best model for widespread construction under the                              Supply and Sanitation Programme (IRWSSP).4 This&#13;
highly variable conditions found in the rural areas. The BRL                          programme aimed to provide universal access to safe rural&#13;
examined alternative materials and methods of construction,                           water supply and sanitation facilities, and included the target&#13;
including low-cost mud, grass and timber models, and more                             that every rural household should have a VIP latrine by&#13;
robust brick-built latrines.                                                          2005. It was estimated that 1.4 million VIP latrines would&#13;
    MoH officials wanted the latrine programme to have                                need to be constructed to achieve this ambitious target.&#13;
long-term benefits, and they made two decisions with                                      The IRWSSP was implemented by existing line ministries,&#13;
far-reaching consequences. First, they decided to adopt the                           the major changes being that cross-linkages were&#13;
durable brick VIP latrine design as the national standard.                            encouraged between water supply, sanitation and health&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  VIP latrine designs in Zimbabwe&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  The first VIP latrines built in Zimbabwe in the mid-1970s were rectangular with wooden doors, but wood was expensive, and the doors&#13;
  wereoftenleftopen,withtheresultthatthelatrineinteriorwasnotkeptdarkandflynuisanceincreased.Consequently,thesuperstructure&#13;
  was modified into a spiral shape, which provided privacy and shade without the need for a door.&#13;
       The superstructures of these early VIP latrines were constructed in either ferrocement or wooden poles plastered with mud.&#13;
  However, with suitable wooden poles becoming scarce, and the ferrocement model proving expensive to construct in the rural areas,&#13;
  brick VIP latrines soon became the favoured option. Cheaper materials did exist, but most low-cost latrines had short lives andrequired&#13;
  frequent maintenance. In contrast, brick VIP latrines were long lasting and required little maintenance. Bricks were readily available in&#13;
  mostofthecountry,andthisdesignhadtheadditionaladvantagethatitdidnotrequireaventilationpipe,asventilationcouldbeprovided&#13;
  by a brick chimney built into the superstructure.&#13;
       The VIP latrine design continues to evolve and improve to the present day. Notable developments include the design of a fully&#13;
  recyclable VIP latrine (the brick superstructure can be taken apart and rebuilt on a new pit in only one day), and the provision of hand-&#13;
  washing facilities as part of the VIP latrine. Most recently the VIP concept has been linked to the re-use principles of Ecological Sanitation.&#13;
  Meanwhile, superstructures are now frequently built from various materials that are cheaper than bricks. The VIP concept has proven to&#13;
  be more adaptable than it seemed during the peak of the standardised national programme.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
3Typical material subsidy = five bags of cement, fly screen and reinforcing wire (approx. 30% cost of latrine).&#13;
4See the WSP-Africa Field Note The Zimbabwe Experience: Lessons from a review of 15 years of the Zimbabwe Integrated Rural Water Supply and Sanitation&#13;
Programme, May 2002.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                  3&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
 Constructing VIP latrine superstructures.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
education, and that service delivery was centrally funded                   a period of transition. Larger `integrated district projects'&#13;
and co-ordinated. In keeping with this approach, the IRWSSP                 were introduced, and the IRWSSP's central co-ordination&#13;
continued to promote the MoH brick VIP latrine design, and                  bodies began to assume more control of RWSS provision.&#13;
to provide the same material subsidy.                                       Latrine production slowed, and the MoH's engagement in&#13;
                   Initially, while the IRWSSP was being established, the   the programme began to wane.&#13;
MoH remained in control of latrine provision. There was                         Between 1991 and 1994, the Zimbabwe Government&#13;
great enthusiasm for the VIP latrine among MoH staff,                       decentralised the delivery of services to rural district councils&#13;
especially the Environmental Health Department, whose                       (RDCs). However, many of the RDCs lacked the experience&#13;
officers had all been trained in its construction, and latrine              or capacity to manage RWSS service delivery, and VIP latrine&#13;
production increased rapidly. It peaked in 1987, when nearly                production decreased to a low of around 10,000 per year&#13;
50,000 VIP latrines were constructed. There then followed                   as decentralisation was carried out.&#13;
                                                                                                                   Zimbabwe's economy&#13;
                                                                                                               was also in decline, and&#13;
                                             Annual VIP latrine production in Zimbabwe&#13;
                                                                                                               the combined effects of&#13;
                                50000                                                                          inadequate government&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                             Estimated         funds,         constraints&#13;
                                40000                                                                          associated       with    the&#13;
                                                                                             Actual&#13;
                                                                                                               unwieldy IRWSSP, and&#13;
                    otalT       30000                                                                          problems in decentralised&#13;
                                                                                                               service delivery greatly&#13;
                                                                                                               reduced the number of VIP&#13;
 2002                    Annual 20000&#13;
                                                                                                               latrines      constructed&#13;
                                                                                                               during the 1990s.&#13;
                                10000                                                                              Fortunately,         two&#13;
     Morgan,&#13;
                                                                                                               factors    had      positive&#13;
&#13;
                                   0                                                                           impacts on the progress of&#13;
            Source:                  1980         1985             1990              1995                      VIP latrine construction&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                         4&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
towards the end of the 1990s. The first was greater                           the Community Health Club approach5 pioneered by the&#13;
recognition of the importance of hygiene promotion. But                       NGO ZimAHEAD. Community Health Clubs have been so&#13;
perhaps the main factor was the increasingly significant                      successful in improving hygiene behaviour and generating&#13;
role played by NGOs, especially in introducing lower-cost                     demand for sanitation facilities that, in some areas, agencies&#13;
VIP latrine designs.                                                          managing sanitation programmes have decided that latrine&#13;
                                                                              subsidies are available to those who complete the health&#13;
Hygiene promotion                                                             education courses run by their Community Health Club.&#13;
    Health and hygiene education has been central to the&#13;
impact that the VIP latrine has made in Zimbabwe.                             VIP latrine achievements&#13;
Appropriate technologies and improved sanitation facilities                        The VIP latrine has been an enormous success.&#13;
are a good start, but they do not necessarily lead to                         More than 500,000 have been built in Zimbabwe since&#13;
improvements in the users' health. It is now recognised                       1975, and it is still the preferred sanitation technology of&#13;
that health benefits derive from improved hygiene                             most rural households. The government's decision to&#13;
behaviour, and that behavioural change requires more than                     standardise its VIP latrine design in bricks and mortar has&#13;
just the provision of appropriate and affordable facilities.                  meant that many of the original latrines are still standing,&#13;
    The MoH had been providing health education and                           and that these latrines have given lasting benefits to millions&#13;
promoting sanitation in Zimbabwe for many years, but the                      of Zimbabweans.&#13;
advent of the VIP latrine led to a significant acceleration of                     The widespread acceptance of the VIP latrine in&#13;
these efforts. The MoH trained its extension staff in hygiene                 Zimbabwe derives largely from its simple and effective&#13;
promotion and in latrine construction; distributed promotional                design and from its similarity to traditional pit latrines. The&#13;
materials in local languages; built demonstration latrines;                   VIP latrine is a familiar technology for rural users, and the&#13;
and included information on the construction and use of the                   use of locally available materials and construction skills make&#13;
VIP latrine in both primary and secondary school curricula.                   it low cost and easily replicable.&#13;
    Recently, more participatory methods of hygiene                                The utility and popularity of the VIP latrine are not in&#13;
promotion were adopted, with notable achievements from                        doubt. However, after twenty-five years of latrine building&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Block of VIP latrines at Zimbabwe school.&#13;
&#13;
5See the WSP Blue Gold Field Note: Hygiene Promotion in Burkina Faso and Zimbabwe, August 2002.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                           5&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
in Zimbabwe, only 31% of the rural population have access                        and the household provides one bag of cement and some&#13;
to adequate sanitation. This low coverage is probably                            of the other materials previously provided in the subsidy.&#13;
related to the high cost of the standard VIP design.                             This approach has managed to reduce the latrine subsidy&#13;
                                                                                 by as much as 50% and, when combined with good&#13;
Is the VIP latrine too expensive?                                                promotion, has been very successful.&#13;
    One of the criticisms of the VIP latrine has been that,&#13;
for a low-cost technology, it is relatively expensive. Points                    VIP latrines outside Zimbabwe&#13;
raised in favour of this argument include:                                           The visits to Zimbabwe in the early 1980s of external&#13;
· The standard brick VIP latrine, as adopted by the MoH and                      support agencies such as the World Bank's Technology&#13;
the IRWSSP, is beyond the price range of much of the                             Advisory Group were mentioned above. They immediately&#13;
population. A typical brick VIP latrine uses up to six bags of                   recognised that the VIP latrine would be one of the sanitation&#13;
&#13;
cement and more than fifteen hundred bricks, amounting to                        technologies most widely adopted during the International&#13;
&#13;
as much as US$80 in total (at 1998 prices). For households                       Drinking Water Supply and Sanitation Decade (1981-90).&#13;
&#13;
lucky enough to receive a subsidy, and prepared to provide                       They therefore publicised and advocated it vigorously to&#13;
&#13;
the labour themselves, their cash contribution may be reduced                    other organisations involved in water and sanitation in&#13;
&#13;
to just less than US$50. However, in a country where more                        developing countries. The VIP latrine quickly entered&#13;
&#13;
than 40% of the population has to survive on less than                           standard textbooks and educational courses.&#13;
&#13;
US$1 per day6 this represents a barely affordable expense.                            VIP latrines are now found all over the world, and the&#13;
&#13;
· The government's latrine subsidy system has proved to                          technology is commonly acknowledged as effective and&#13;
&#13;
be neither sustainable, nor capable of achieving universal                       appropriate. However, the appeal of the VIP latrine has not&#13;
&#13;
sanitation coverage. Both the size of the individual subsidies,                  been universal. For instance, the VIP latrine has been less&#13;
&#13;
and the overall cost of the subsidy programme, have been                         successful in poorer African countries, such as Mozambique&#13;
&#13;
too high. The number of VIP latrines constructed in Zimbabwe                     and Malawi, than in Zimbabwe's relatively rich neighbours&#13;
&#13;
over the last two decades may have been limited by the                           such as South Africa, Botswana and Lesotho.&#13;
&#13;
selection of the expensive brick design, and by the size of                          This is partly due to the higher subsidy that the richer&#13;
&#13;
the subsidy required to make this design affordable.                             countries are able to offer,7 although in Lesotho large&#13;
&#13;
    There are, however, counter-arguments:                                       numbers have been built with no direct subsidy.8 But there&#13;
&#13;
· Despite the high cost, there has always been a demand                          are also more complex factors at work. In Mozambique, for&#13;
&#13;
for VIP latrines in Zimbabwe. Evaluations of the IRWSSP                          example, the materials needed to construct a VIP latrine&#13;
&#13;
state that demand often outstripped supply, with households                      are generally neither cheap nor readily available, and some&#13;
&#13;
mobilised to dig latrine pits, only to discover that there                       field workers have also observed that it may be culturally&#13;
&#13;
were insufficient funds for their subsidy, or that there was a                   inappropriate to defecate in a roofed building. A different&#13;
&#13;
cement shortage. This suggests that the main constraint to                       sanitation technology of simple, low-cost slabs to upgrade&#13;
&#13;
expanding sanitation coverage was not the cost of the chosen                     traditional latrines9 has become very popular.&#13;
&#13;
technology but the subsidy system and the culture of                                 These examples suggest that the uptake of appropriate&#13;
&#13;
dependency that it fostered.                                                     technologies depends on more than just their cost, or their&#13;
&#13;
· The criticism that the VIP latrine is too expensive does not                   technical advantages. Clearly, the success of sanitation&#13;
&#13;
apply to other versions of it. The two essential features of                     technologies, such as the VIP latrine, is heavily influenced&#13;
&#13;
the VIP latrine, namely some form of screened ventilation                        by cultural differences, by local building practices, and by&#13;
&#13;
and a superstructure capable of keeping the latrine interior                     `ownership' of the technology.&#13;
&#13;
reasonably dark, are not intrinsically expensive. Recognising&#13;
this, NGOs in Zimbabwe have developed lower-cost VIP                             Lessons learned&#13;
latrine designs, without sacrificing the durability of previous&#13;
models. They are also experimenting with smaller subsidies,&#13;
arguing that linking these reduced subsidies to effective                        Sound design, good planning&#13;
hygiene promotion efforts enables their investments to                           and staff training are important&#13;
provide wider coverage and greater health benefits.                                  The design of the VIP latrine looks deceptively simple.&#13;
    For example, the Mvuramanzi Trust has promoted a                             But it is the result of thorough and careful design and&#13;
cheaper VIP latrine design and also asked households to                          development by professional researchers. It was then put&#13;
contribute more towards their latrines. This latrine design                      into practice by field workers, mainly the Ministry of Health's&#13;
requires one less bag of cement than the standard model,                         environmental health extension staff. They were trained to&#13;
&#13;
6World Development Report, 2000.&#13;
7Over 80% subsidy in South Africa; approx. 70% subsidy in Botswana.&#13;
8See the WSP Blue Gold Field Note: The National Sanitation Programme in Lesotho, August 2002.&#13;
9See the WSP Blue Gold Field Note: The National Sanitation Programme in Mozambique, August 2002.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
 VIP latrine under construction in Lesotho.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
promote the VIP latrine. This training gave their work a          They want basic, upgradeable latrines that are affordable.&#13;
strong sense of focus during the 1980s, a focus that was          The availability of several different types of latrine, with&#13;
absent after their working structure was decentralised.           systems to upgrade from low-cost models, allows&#13;
                                                                  incremental demand to develop and encourages lower-&#13;
People identify with home-grown technologies                      income households to invest in improved sanitation.&#13;
   Sanitation technologies need to suit local materials and&#13;
building practices, local economic conditions, and local          Hygiene promotion is essential&#13;
cultural practices and beliefs. In this way, many practical          Sanitation facilities rarely improve health or hygiene on&#13;
problems can be avoided, and `ownership' of the technology        their own. However, hygiene promotion can change&#13;
is more likely to develop. Technical solutions to the problem     people's hygiene behaviour and translate water and&#13;
of safe excreta disposal do not translate easily from one         sanitation investments into health benefits. In Zimbabwe,&#13;
country to another, however similar these countries may           effective health education and hygiene promotion (initially&#13;
appear: this lesson is clear even in the case of the VIP latrine, by the Ministry of Health, and more recently and notably in&#13;
which is arguably the most widespread low-cost sanitation         Community Health Clubs) have been found to improve&#13;
technology in the world.                                          hygiene behaviour, to encourage the proper use and&#13;
                                                                  maintenance of sanitation facilities, and to generate strong&#13;
Different people want different latrines                          demand for improved sanitation facilities.&#13;
   Latrine programmes need to provide a range of options.&#13;
Standard designs (such as the brick VIP latrine) are often        Sanitation subsidies&#13;
comparatively expensive because they have to function in          need to be carefully designed&#13;
a variety of conditions, and so they seldom cater for all the        Nowadays many sector professionals oppose direct&#13;
population. The most important people for whom a standard         subsidies for individual latrines, partly because these are&#13;
design may be inappropriate are the poorest households.           private expenditures as opposed to the community&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                 7&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                         expenditures           of    water&#13;
                                                                         supplies. In Zimbabwe,&#13;
                                                                         however,        direct      latrine&#13;
                                                                                                                               Water and Sanitation&#13;
                                                                         subsidies have been the&#13;
                                                                                                                               Program-Africa Region (WSP-AF)&#13;
                                                                         accepted norm for many&#13;
                                                                         years ­ both in recognition&#13;
                                                                                                                               The World Bank, Hill Park,&#13;
                                                                         that      people's          health&#13;
                                                                                                                               Upper Hill, P.O. Box 30577,&#13;
                                                                         depends on their neighbours'&#13;
                                                                                                                               Nairobi, Kenya&#13;
                                                                         sanitation and because&#13;
                                                                         subsidies can assist in&#13;
                                                                                                                               Phone: (254-2) 260300, 260400&#13;
                                                                         expanding latrine coverage&#13;
                                                                                                                               Fax: (254-2) 260386&#13;
                                                                         rapidly. However, the cost of&#13;
                                                                                                                               E-mail: wspaf@worldbank.org&#13;
                                                                         the standard Zimbabwean&#13;
                                                                                                                               Web site: www.wsp.org&#13;
                                                                         subsidy system affected&#13;
                                                                         the sustainability of the&#13;
                                                                         national programme, which&#13;
                                                                         was heavily dependent on&#13;
                                                                         finance       from        external&#13;
                                                                         support agencies. Also,&#13;
                                                                         without careful targeting,&#13;
                                                                         subsidies are often captured&#13;
                                                                         by those who can afford to&#13;
                                                                         be first in the queue or those&#13;
                                                                         who are well connected. In&#13;
                                                                         Zimbabwe, efforts are now&#13;
                                                                         focused on reducing VIP&#13;
                                                                         latrine subsidies so that&#13;
                                                                         more people benefit, and&#13;
                                                                         access to safe sanitation can&#13;
 Woman and children outside a VIP latrine.                                                                                      Acknowledgments&#13;
                                                                         increase more rapidly.                                 Written by: Andy Robinson, with&#13;
                                                                                                                                particular thanks to Peter Morgan&#13;
                                                                                                                                Series Editor: Jon Lane&#13;
&#13;
   References                                                                                                                   Assistant Editor: John Dawson&#13;
                                                                                                                                Published by: Vandana Mehra&#13;
                                                                                                                                Photographs by: Aquamor, Guy Stubbs,&#13;
   · Brandberg, B. The SanPlat System: Lowest Cost Environmental Sanitation.                                                    Ian Pearson, WEDC/Brian Skinner and&#13;
      Proceedings of 17th WEDC Conference, Nairobi, pp. 193­196.                                                                WEDC/Paul Deverill&#13;
      Loughborough: 1991.                                                                                                       Designed by: Write Media&#13;
&#13;
   · Institute of Water and Sanitation Development. Review of the Integrated                                                    Printed by: PS Press Services Pvt. Ltd.&#13;
&#13;
      Rural Water Supply and Sanitation Programme. Government of Zimbabwe,&#13;
      National Action Committee for Rural Water Supply and Sanitation.                                                          August 2002&#13;
&#13;
      Unpublished, 2001.&#13;
                                                                                                                                The Water and Sanitation Program is an&#13;
   · Morgan, P. The Pit Latrine ­ Revived. Central African Journal of Medicine,&#13;
                                                                                                                                international partnership to help the&#13;
      vol. 23, no. 1, 1977.                                                                                                     poor gain sustained access to improved&#13;
   · Morgan, P. and D. Mara. Ventilated Improved Pit Latrines: Recent                                                           water supply and sanitation services.&#13;
      Developments in Zimbabwe. TAG Technical Paper no. 3. Washington, D.C.:                                                    The Program's main funding partners&#13;
      The World Bank, 1982.                                                                                                     are the Governments of Australia,&#13;
   · Morgan, P. and D. Mara. Ventilated Improved Pit Latrines: Zimbabwean                                                       Austria, Belgium, Canada, Denmark,&#13;
      Brick Designs. Washington, D.C.: The World Bank, 1985.                                                                    France, Germany, Luxembourg, the&#13;
&#13;
   · Morgan, P. Zimbabwe's Rural Sanitation Programme. Updated version of                                                       Netherlands, Norway, Sweden,&#13;
&#13;
      1998 paper, 2002.                                                                                                         Switzerland, and the United Kingdom;&#13;
                                                                                                                                the United Nations Development&#13;
                                                                                                                                Programme, and the World Bank.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The World Bank does not accept responsibility for the views expressed herein, which are those of the author, and should not be attributed to the World Bank or its affiliated&#13;
organisations. The designations employed and the presentation of the material are solely for the convenience of the reader anddo not imply the expression of any legal&#13;
opinion whatsoever on the part of the World Bank or its affiliates concerning the legal status of any country, territory, city, area, or its authorities, or concerning the&#13;
delimitations of its boundaries or national affiliations. Information from Water and Sanitation Program publications may be freely reproduced. Proper acknowledgment&#13;
will be appreciated.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="2494296">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2002/08/2494296/vip-latrines-zimbabwe-local-innvation-global-sanitation-solution
        </url>
        <availablein>French,English</availablein>
        <fullavailablein>
            <available_in lang="French" entityid="000160016_20030827165429" node_id="2494296"/>
        </fullavailablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2002/08/2494296/vip-latrines-zimbabwe-local-innvation-global-sanitation-solution</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2002/08/2494296/vip-latrines-zimbabwe-local-innvation-global-sanitation-solution</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/08/27/000160016_20030827165057/Rendered/INDEX/266220PAPER0English0Blue0gold0no.04.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/08/27/000160016_20030827165057/Rendered/PDF/266220PAPER0English0Blue0gold0no.04.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2003-08-27T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2002-08-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            VIP latrines in Zimbabwe : from local
            innvation to global sanitation solution
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            This Field Note describes the
            development of the ventilated improved pit (VIP) latrine in
            Zimbabwe. This innovative latrine was invented at the
            Ministry of Health's Blair Research Laboratory in 1973,
            and subsequently adopted as the standard sanitation
            technology promoted by the Ministry of Health. For some
            years it was implemented at a large scale by the
            government's national rural water and sanitation
            program, until the decline of the national economy. Despite
            that decline, however, the VIP latrine itself is still
            popular and is currently being promoted in various forms by
            local NGOs and others. The VIP latrine is known and used in
            countries all over the world. Within Zimbabwe itself, the
            VIP latrine is known as the Blair latrine and is a national
            institution. It is still the sanitation technology of choice
            for most rural households. Its success demonstrates that
            well-supported local research can produce innovative
            technologies that are ideally suited to local conditions,
            and that home-grown technologies can generate significant
            political and popular support. Its inclusion in the school
            curriculum has meant that an entire generation of
            Zimbabweans has grown up with an appreciation of the
            benefits of the VIP latrine. In addition, the involvement of
            so many government staff in the national sanitation program,
            and the training that this program provided to thousands of
            VIP latrine builders, have further enhanced its reputation
            and support.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            VIP latrines in Zimbabwe : from local
            innvation to global sanitation solution
        </docna>
        <display_title>VIP latrines in Zimbabwe : from
            local innvation to global sanitation solution</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2002/08/2494296/vip-latrines-zimbabwe-local-innvation-global-sanitation-solution</listing_relative_url>
        <subtopic>Hygiene Promotion and Social Marketing,Town Water Supply and Sanitation,Urban Water Supply and Sanitation,TF030632-DANISH CTF - FY05 (DAC PART
            COUNTRIES GNP PER CAPITA BELOW USD 2,500/AL,Sanitation and Sewerage</subtopic>
        <docty>UNDP-Water &amp; Sanitation Program</docty>
        <teratopic>Water Supply and Sanitation</teratopic>
        <count>Zimbabwe</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Southern Africa!$!80472</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Sub-Saharan Africa!$!80473</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000160016_20030827165057</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>Africa,Africa</admreg>
        <colti>Water and sanitation program - Africa region
            field note ; no. 4</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Water Supply and Sanitation</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Ventilated improved pit latrines; Sanitation
            equipment; Nongovernmental organizations; Household wastes;
            Environmentally sound technology; Curriculum subjects;
            Hygiene; Health education; Promotional strategies;
            Paricipatory approaches; Staff training; Technological
            innovations; Traditional technology; Subsidies;Sanitation services
            adequate sanitation,behavioural
            change,Community Health,demand for sanitation,Drinking
            Water,Drinking Water Supply,Environmental
            Health,Environmental Sanitation,excreta,excreta disposal,fly
            control,Health and hygiene,health care,health
            education,households,hygiene,hygiene behaviour,hygiene
            education,hygiene promotion,latrine,latrine builders,latrine
            construction,latrine design,latrine
            superstructure,latrines,pit latrine,pit latrines,pits,public
            health,pumps,Rural Sanitation,rural water,rural water
            supply,safe excreta disposal,safe
            sanitation,sanitation,sanitation,sanitation
            Community,sanitation coverage,Sanitation
            Development,sanitation facilities,sanitation
            investments,Sanitation Program,sanitation
            services,sanitation technology,service
            delivery,textbooks,towns,traditional pit latrines,users,VIP
            latrines,washing,Water,water supplies,wells
        </keywd>
        <owner>Water- Water and Sanit Prgrm (GWASP)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Southern Africa</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Sub-Saharan Africa</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>26622</repnb>
        <alt_title>
            Les latrines a fosse ventilee et
            ameliorees au Zimbabwe : D'une innovation locale a une
            solution globale d'assainissement
        </alt_title>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Behavior Change Communication</ml:concept><ml:concept>Handwashing Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wastewater Collection and Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Textbooks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Basic Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>On-site Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Marketing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fescal Sludge Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sludge Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Hygiene Promotion and Social Marketing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Growth and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural &amp; Small Town Water &amp; Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water, Sanitation and Hygiene</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Hygiene Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sewerage</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning Materials</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Benefits</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Technologies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Africa</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Zimbabwe</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>