<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>May 2002&#13;
-   Water and-&#13;
5~     ~~ an *. d.l; --&#13;
:     ~~An international:...&#13;
K,.partnership to help        r-'v1     ?&#13;
qthe poor gain sustained&#13;
water,supply and         -&#13;
-~~~~~~~~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ *.               ! ' - &#13;
f_ c   Region   -  ,- 4. .-                                                         ''''&gt;-'' &#13;
-fk-f   , ~6n,                                                          d&#13;
hCommunity BaedWaeran&#13;
-anit-a-ti'on Pro gram r(COBWAS)&#13;
dpd~~~~~~-'S&#13;
uestion.-In the faceof the inabtilit&#13;
f loCalaUthorities to provideisafe -1 &#13;
da,;.      tato        ,       ;. i iu a t i 6 ri                 , iD r- I  a n{ t &#13;
ffectiveiy takecontrol of'their    i.&#13;
service                s Africa cipr  can         o          .,&#13;
ttempt.toupgradethewaStesupply a...................... -n-  .  - b             1,&#13;
1babva .capita'l city @fEth-iopiabyx -5'c s-    8t 9 x.4&#142;                       5   ..  il &#13;
ncoqur!ging lo.4ca -communities-to :-:1)                                    %~h&#13;
esign, n  iplem       I! e  action  . 1     ,    ''i' -  ....   't ,,&#13;
.ppropria-te technolog syolutios- - -'-                    ^ .        t8.&#13;
- -COBWAS isat anedrly jage&#13;
sit ar as ye aviblth             -                                SI&#13;
egre  ,of opertO'.!jnzBet_wee-%&#13;
bovrmet,      dohrgroups.,,:                .-!r                                         Q    ;&#13;
;ithint te cit ThFieldNote&#13;
-sp6rts;-6n-hekyidaofn&#13;
thopian~ eniomet   -, &#13;
-~~  -       -~~~~                          I-'P&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
of the 28 woredas (administrative&#13;
4- ^   r* tdistricts) within the city limits have been&#13;
,I. ^         :, : ;  .;given priority status, and will attract a&#13;
greater percentage of available&#13;
-'           resources during the first phase of&#13;
- tf,  &lt;            5cthe program.&#13;
In essence, the COBWAS scheme&#13;
is simple. The European Union (EU)&#13;
yw ;&lt; , j 3 ^; has provided an initial sum of money&#13;
sA         AJ -:to get the ball rolling. This 'fund' is&#13;
administered by the Bureau of Planning&#13;
&gt;~&lt;  j.'S - * &gt;q , &gt;&gt;  t;.-  ';    and Economic Development (BoPED)&#13;
of the AACA. In response to COBWAS&#13;
population bytheyear2015.         promotion and publicity, local&#13;
'The  COBWAS     approach',    communities devise plons for upgrading&#13;
developed through consultation and  water and sanitation facilities in their&#13;
COBWAS has evolved over a      discussion, emphasizes community  areas. If a community's plan is&#13;
number of years in response to ever-  management as the vehicle to achieve  considered feasible, beneficial, and&#13;
growing concerns about the poor state  scale in the city. The principles by which  sustainable, then a funding allocation&#13;
of sanitation and water supply in  it seeks to operate are outlined in a  can be made. As other communities&#13;
Addis Ababa.                      Manual of Operations, a detailed set  see the benefits of COBWAS, they will&#13;
The story starts in 1 992, when the  of guidelines to assist communities in  be encouraged to participate.&#13;
Government of Region 14 (forerunner  initiating and pursuing their own  This initiative heralds a new&#13;
of the Addis Ababa City Administration,  action plons.              pioneering approach for Ethiopia in its&#13;
AACA) published a Master Plan Study  COBWAS aims to serve the entire  commitment to ensure that projects are&#13;
which deviated from standard high-cost  city of Addis Ababa. Realistically, this  community-based. It is significant that&#13;
proposals to address the sanitation  may take many years to achieve, and  non-governmental and community-&#13;
challengeinthecitybyrecommending  will depend on factors such as the  based organizations are no longer&#13;
the provision of low-costtechnologies,  success of the initial stages of the  referred to as 'implementing agencies'&#13;
such as dry pit latrines, as the only way  program and its ability to attract  but as 'support agencies', whose role&#13;
to achieve widespread effective   significant external and domestic  is to assist and support the real prime&#13;
sanitation coverage for the urban  financial support. In the meantime, 9  movers - the communities themselves.&#13;
Water and Sanitation Problems of the- Urban Poor'-                                -&#13;
The COBWAS initiative is aimed at the urbon poor, who are particularly disadvantaged by the water supply and.&#13;
sanitation problems that afflict Addis Ababa:&#13;
* Most hciuseholds lack access to a convenient piped water supply. Water must often be carried long dist,nces&#13;
(usually by twomen and children) from communal standpipes, or bought.from vendors at hi-gh cost;&#13;
m As a consequence, water usage per capita is low, resulting in inadequate attention to hygiene.  -&#13;
* Drinking water is often contaminated, increasing the incidence of illness and disease.&#13;
* The sewerage system only serves the central part of the city. It is estimat6d'thdt -1 .5-million of Addis Ababa's 2.5&#13;
million residents use dry pit latrines.&#13;
* Solid and liquid waste disposal is inadequote.&#13;
* Many of the poor live in rented or government accommodation with little security of tenure or incentive to upgrade&#13;
their water supply and sanitation facilities.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
but they may be a considerable source&#13;
of indirect aid through administrative     Project          Project- Cycle Management&#13;
assistance and the provision of land.     Promotion            The COBWAS Project Management Cycle&#13;
- is designed to keep.stakeholders informed of&#13;
$SOm$ Leu                            ____           _      project aims and objectives, whist maintaining&#13;
Project          complete transp6rency and handig over&#13;
Although COBWAS is in its early        Appraisal         effective control of all project activities .to&#13;
stages, several lessons have alread            1            community members. There are five stoges in&#13;
been learnt. Many of these lessons            4             the cycle:&#13;
arose out of the process of compiling      Project          *  Project Promotion: The PCU encoGrages&#13;
the Manual of Operations and              Financin             the submission of project proposals through&#13;
reconciling divergent design views.                            awareness creation and promotional&#13;
The exercise provided important                             -activities.&#13;
lessons in several areas.                                     - Project Appraisal: The submissions are&#13;
.mntCniProject             assessed, taking into account a-range of&#13;
Communit,v Contributions              Implementation           .criteria, as laid out in the COBWAS Manual&#13;
Negotiations on obtaining the   -,&#13;
of Operations. Are they relevant -to the&#13;
community contribution of a minimum                            intended recipi6rits? Are-they feasible? .Can&#13;
of 10 percent of overall project costs   Evaluation            they be sustained over a long period?&#13;
has been a contentious issue. A                            -* Project Financing: Upon approval of the  ,&#13;
worrying trend is the intention of                             submission, financing agreements are&#13;
COBWAS to explore the idea of           signed between the PCU and the implementing 'ommunity: (All&#13;
'negotiated demand' for particular      agreements will include provisions for community cash and lcbor.inpits.)&#13;
projects. Potentially profit-making or  * Project Irniplementation: Projects will then be implemented, according-&#13;
self-financing services should attract  to schedules agreed and set by communities ihemselves, in collaboration&#13;
high contributions whilst publicly owned  with support agencies. The sch'edule will take into account every input&#13;
high ~ ~  ~     ~    ~   ~    fo contributions whilst pubicl  trinngned~      '&#13;
services (e.g. access roads and         from rciterials:to labor and training. -&#13;
*  Evaluation: Projects are evaluated, both during and after&#13;
-implementation. Are they working? If not, why not? What lessons are&#13;
levels of community contribution,     -'being learnt that might assist similar projects in the futur.e? '&#13;
First Come, First Served              -.                    --                    .              - -&#13;
Ratherthan waitforthe submission  Promotional Tools and             Initiatives            -&#13;
of a few meticulously prepared project  Strategies used to publicize the COBWAS message'include:- &#13;
proposals, it was decided to get the ball  * Radio and television&#13;
rolling on a 'first come, first served'  * -General guidelines and information packs         '&#13;
basis. The aim of this policy is to  - 'Leaflets, posters, and other publications -  .      -   '&#13;
achieve the greatest possible coverage  * Regular newsleters -&#13;
of community-based water supply and  * Audiovisual presentations               -                 ';&#13;
sanitation initiative overaminimu  Direct contact (community and household meetings)   -&#13;
sanitation initiatives over a minimum&#13;
period of time. It was felt that such a  * Seminars and workshops&#13;
* -Drama, theater, and cultura events&#13;
policy would also encourage a steady                                          - '&#13;
flow of external funding from additional  owned by the government. This has  accounts and the formation of groups&#13;
donors.Ariskofthisapproachwill be  implicationsforcommunityprojectsthat  are strictly governed by laws of&#13;
that if the funding does prove to be  involve, for example, the building of  associations. Both these activities are&#13;
unsustainable, the first highly    structures such as public showers. In  prerequisites forthe release of project&#13;
subsidized services will only benefit the  addition, the government owns much  funding. COBWAS will face difficulties&#13;
richer, 'more motivated communities.  of the accommodation in the city;  in this area when fully operational.&#13;
Land Tenure                        increased security of tenure would  Close collaboration with woredas and&#13;
The issue of land tenure urgently  encourage community projects    kebeles is expected to reduce and&#13;
needs to be addressed. Land is at a  Legal Issues                     smooth over some of the legal&#13;
premium in the city and is generally  In Ethiopia, the opening of bank  wranglings.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
o An improvement in the status of   Project Outputs                   the     COBWAS       Program&#13;
women as they spend less time and                                   Coordination Unit within its Bureau&#13;
energy in water transport and      The details .of individual       of Planning   and  Economic&#13;
sewagedisposal                   community plans will vary, but     Development(BoPED). The money&#13;
possible components include:       fund is administered by BoPED.&#13;
m* Secondary and tertiary access  o COBWAS is very much dependent&#13;
roads and drainage systems       on the cooperation of the AACA,&#13;
COBWAS involves the cooperation  * Low-cost sewerage schemes with   as it owns many of the dwelling units&#13;
of a wide range of partners, from large  on-site disposal facilities'  in the city, as well as, the land on&#13;
support agencies to local artisans.   Pit emptying, sludge collectionich structures such as pit ltrines&#13;
These partners, and the roles they might  and disposal, and low-cost   may besbuilt.&#13;
perform, include:                     treatment&#13;
* Solid waste collection, recycling,    0       ©&#13;
Local CommunityvGroups                and disposal&#13;
Individual community groups are  * Public, communal, and private  (©(')Ll\$&#13;
the focus of action under COBWAS.      latrines&#13;
They:                               * Communal water points            Sources of finance include:&#13;
o Identify the need for action in their  * Public showers, laundries, and  External Donors and Support&#13;
area                    .           kitchen units                Agencies&#13;
o Devise a plan                     m Education on hygiene             An initial donation has come from&#13;
o Find ways of financing the plan  Non-governmental Organizations   the EU, and more contributions are&#13;
o Negotiate with COBWAS and          Generally, support agencies and  encouraged. An important goal is to&#13;
other partners as regards the  partners leavetheactual implementation  reverse the trend of big budget, top-&#13;
implementation of the plan     of plans to local communities, but can  heavy interventions in favor of funding&#13;
o Put the plan into action        offer assistance in the following areas:  regimes that are flexible and responsive&#13;
o Funding: the Europeon Union is  to the needs and aspirations of small&#13;
Local Private Sector                 currently the only donor, but it is  community groups.&#13;
It is envisaged that local community  hoped to attract more agencies to  Implementing Communities&#13;
plans will incorporate the effective  donate money and skills.         Communities that devise plans are&#13;
participation of many local businesses,  o Offering technical advice and skills:  expected to contribute 10 percent of the&#13;
which may be involved in a number of  German Technical Cooperation  total cost of the plan.&#13;
ways:                                (GTZ) is helping to install a  Humanitarian Agencies and&#13;
a Designing systems and structures   computer database which will   Community-BasedOrganizations&#13;
according to the needs of the     provide an overview   of all      Such groups are encouraged to&#13;
community                         community-based water supply and  bring their own funds, or to contribute&#13;
o Constructing those systems         sanitation projects in the city.  in the form of materials and/or laborto&#13;
t Developing expertise in appropriate  o Providing  managerial  and  overall project funds,&#13;
technology 'tadministrative support.&#13;
o Marketing their skills to other  0 Promotionand demand stimulation  Local Businesses and OtherAgents&#13;
communities, thus ensuring the    where awareness is considered to  It is hoped that improved local&#13;
sustainability of COBWAS          be lacking.                    trade, as a result of the environmental&#13;
a                               Local government is involved at Local Government Organizations  upgrading of a neighborhood, will&#13;
1.1  ~ ~  ~   ~   ~       umberal oflvels:n                supotgurheiugrdig.Inthsnay&#13;
n § 6, ;,  2  3   ". j ).         encourage businesses to finance and&#13;
s ; Locaigovernmentisinvolvedata ~~~~~support further upgrading. In this way,&#13;
#~ ~ ~ ~~~~~~~nme of "levels: T                           COBWAS will eventuolly become self-&#13;
,N ^  .r. t_O At a local level, woredos (districts)&#13;
and kebeles (sub-districts) can use  financing - 'making sanitation pay.&#13;
their local knowledge to liaise  Government Support&#13;
V/ jq .w_  t ft,r' between community groups and  It is recognized that little direct&#13;
larger organizations.          finance for COBWAS will come from&#13;
,-,,, '*-- . .. -....j.j-,T-;i__, ' . .  '  At a citywide level, the AACA houses  local or national government sources,&#13;
l4l&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The Poor Pay More                                                 groups within the community. The&#13;
benefits may be social, environmental,&#13;
It is ironic, buttrue,thatthe poor pay more fortheirwater supplies, either  or financial; they may be direct or&#13;
directly or indirectly:                                           indirect; they may be short term or&#13;
* Water purchased from vendors or standpipe attendants ca'n be up to ten  long term.&#13;
times more-expensive than direct public service access.&#13;
* Municipal water'charges are progressive - so using a shared stondpipe  Household Benefits:&#13;
can toke a group of households into'a higher tariff brocket.    Q Increased availability of water and&#13;
* The indirect cost of poor health, and time off work due to water-related  sanitation facilities&#13;
illnesses, can account for a considerable portion of a household's budget.  Q Improvements in health and&#13;
. .                   ~~~~~~~general well-being&#13;
administered bank account.&#13;
A          Pkin               o° The community then presents its  a Financial benefits from  more&#13;
0   __                               plan to the COBWAS Program        economic water and sanitation&#13;
- -                  Coordination   Unit   (PCU)       systems, and an increase in earning&#13;
To illustrate the concept in more  which  undertokes a dialog       potential dueto improved health&#13;
detail, a typical plan might unfold in  with the community to iron out  Business Benefits:&#13;
the following manner:                any  difficulties  that might  o Payments forservices and products&#13;
o A local community within Addis     present themselves.               directly generated by the scheme&#13;
Ababa identifies a demand for the'  o When all aspects of the plan are  n Second-phase earnings from the&#13;
kind of scheme COBWAS might       agreed upon by all the agents     saleof similarservicesand products&#13;
finance. They form themselves into  involved, the community '       ' 'r- -- y  - _      -&#13;
a local action group.             signs an agreementwith the  - '&#13;
D The group devises a plan, following  fund operators, BoPED. The  A_&#13;
the procedures laid down in the   first payment goes into the                   I 1&#13;
COBWAS Manual of Operations.      community bank account. t-&#13;
The plan might involve the supply  o Thecommunitythenswings Z-            r                     =&#13;
of topped   water to rented       into action. Ideally, many  '        -....'' i"&#13;
accommodation, orthe provision of  localpeopleareinvolved  i: -                              ''&#13;
communal latrines. Innovative and  designers lay out plans,        -,r. %&#13;
creative solutions are encouraged.  consultants coordinate&#13;
o The group must display its         activities, artisans and&#13;
commitment in a detailed document,  contractors build structures .,&#13;
setting out the activities it intends to  andfitsystemsthatwillIlead  i  r&#13;
undertake, the timescale for these  to an overall improvement #.  -            ', .   '..&#13;
activities, and the role of various  in the water and sanitation facilities  to other schemes&#13;
individuals and businesses within  ofthe area.                   in Increased business as more&#13;
the community. Who will coordinate  Q Finally, other nearby communities,  customers are attracted due to the&#13;
the enterprise? Who will build the  seeing the success of the plan, will  upgrading of the neighborhood&#13;
structures? How will they be paid?  be encouraged to replicate it. Thus,  General Social and Environmental&#13;
o Theissueoffinanceisanimportant     the COBWAS initiative will     Benefits:&#13;
one: a key objective will be to   eventually spread throughout the  0 Improvement in the quality of&#13;
establish largely self-financing  entire city.                      life due to a cleaner, healthier&#13;
community   operations. The                                         environment&#13;
community group must, therefore,  ©0tW   1WG 0                   o Development of a greater sense of&#13;
detail how it will raise local money  Q mm Dn     'Ma   MM          community cohesion and pride&#13;
to add to the initial EU input.  [fneRN                             associated with the cooperative&#13;
Contributions might come from                                       noture of the scheme&#13;
sponsors, fund-raising activities, or  It is  envisaged  that  the  in Increased social awareness leading&#13;
even house-to-house collections.  implementotion of a COBWAS        to a reduction in crime and social&#13;
There must be a properly       community plan will benefit many     probJems&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Gender and Related Issues&#13;
Although COBWAS is essentially an urban upgrading program, studies&#13;
have shown that the time spent by women and children fetching and waiting     Water and Sanitation Program-&#13;
to collect water differs little from their compatriots living in small towns and  Africa Region (WSP-AF)&#13;
rural areas. Many people queue for up to four hours at communal               The World Bank, Hill Park,&#13;
water points.                                                                 Upper Hill&#13;
COBWAS guidelines, therefore, suggest that all project proposals include   PRO. Box 30577&#13;
a 'gender impact statement'. This idea is taken directly from. Oxfam Development  Nairobi, Kenya&#13;
Guidelines and seeks to ensure the active participation of women and children,  Tel: (254-2) 260300, 260400&#13;
the elderly and disabled, and similar                                         Telefax: (254-2) 260386&#13;
vulnerable groups. For example, the                                           E-mail: wspaf@worldbank.org&#13;
Field Appraisal Checklist in the Manual          -t                           Website: http://www.wsp.org&#13;
of  Operations     asks  whether                                i&#13;
communities have 'fully involved and ', f 7&#13;
listened to the concerns of women,&#13;
children and disadvantaged groups .l&#13;
within the community'. It also seeks to                                       References&#13;
confirm that 'project interventions                                            1. Manual of Operations for CO0WAS: G.R.&#13;
increase access to facilities for poor and                                    2. Campbell, April 2000&#13;
disadvantaged groups'.  ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~  ~   ~   ~   ~~~2.Environmental Sanitation in Addis Abobo,&#13;
disadvantaged groups'.                                        * jg               Field Note of the UNSDP-World B-ank Water&#13;
and Sanitation Program: Sylvia Kiingi, 1996&#13;
Decentralization of Activities        -                                        3. Demand Responsive Approaches to&#13;
Community Water Supply - Moving from&#13;
The degree of centralization of  Is-                            B:Policy to Proctice,rProceedings of Regional&#13;
COBWAS      services   proved   a   '                                             Workshop, June 23-26 1997: UNDP/World&#13;
conentousisse.Should services be                                              Bn,19&#13;
contentious issue. Su  sI b                 C  r W                             4. Addis Ababa Water Supply &amp; Sanitation&#13;
controlled almost entirely by the PCU                                             Improvement Project: Tropics Consulting&#13;
located within BoPED, or should      assessment of the technical capacity         Engineers, ENB, Knight Piesold, 1_999&#13;
services be decentralized down to    of government bureaus and their level     The Field Note was.prepared by Gary Compbell&#13;
woreda level from the outset? The latter  of interest in the program  was      and Belete Mulunch, edited by John Dawson&#13;
and reviewed by Barbara -Evons, Lukman Salifu,&#13;
wou!d be more in keeping with the    fundamental to the task. Some             and T6re Lium of the WSP-AF.&#13;
philosophy of COBWAS, but would      agencies were given advisory roles and    Gary Campbell provided photographs.&#13;
involve intense capacity building in the  some  were  given  executive         This.Field Note is an update of Environmentol&#13;
early stages. A plan for partial     responsibilities. Only time will tell if  Sanitation in Addis Ababa (reference 2 above),&#13;
which outlines initial moves towards. the&#13;
decentralization was agreed, with   these agencies and government              launching of a community-based sonitation&#13;
COBWAS      Desks being   set up     bureaus sit comfortablytogetherand        program in Addis Aboba.&#13;
immediately in a limited number of   act according to their designated roles.&#13;
selected woredos, identified by the&#13;
Master Plan Study for Addis Ababa as  _C___n_C_D_  ng _ ___M__o_ _ o           May 2002&#13;
being severely underserved and in need&#13;
of immediate attention. Initially,      COBWAS represents an exciting          The Waterand Sonitoti6n Program is an&#13;
COBWAS Desks at woreda level will    challenge for all concerned, providing    internotionol partnership to help the&#13;
a pragmatic way to address Addis          poor gain sustained access to&#13;
act as a conduit for the free flow of  Ababa's chronic environmental          improved watersupply and sanitation&#13;
information between communities and                                            services. The Program's mnain&#13;
the PCU.                             challenge. The next few years will        funding partners are the Governments&#13;
determine whether or not its              of Australia, Belgium,-Canada, Denmark,&#13;
Organization and Function            community-based approach to the           Germany, Italy, Japan, Luxembourg,&#13;
Delineating a chain of command    coordination and provision of urban       the Netherlands, Norway, Sweden,&#13;
Switzerland, and the United Kingdonn;&#13;
that fitted outside agencies into an  sanitation and small-scale water        the United Nations Development&#13;
already com plex local government    supplies proves to be an effective model  Programme, and The World Bank..&#13;
hierarchy proved time consuming. An  that can grow to scale.&#13;
Created by&#13;
Roots Advertising Services Pvt. Ltd.&#13;
E-mail: roots@del2.vsnl.net.in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="2495949">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2002/05/2495949/urban-water-supply-sanitation-community-based-approach-ethiopia
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2002/05/2495949/urban-water-supply-sanitation-community-based-approach-ethiopia</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2002/05/2495949/urban-water-supply-sanitation-community-based-approach-ethiopia</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/09/23/000094946_03082904013041/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/09/23/000094946_03082904013041/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2002-05-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2003-09-23T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Urban water supply and sanitation : a
            community-based approach in Ethiopia
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The Community-Based Water and Sanitation
            Program (COBWAS) poses a simple and interesting question. In
            the face of the inability of local authorities to provide
            safe water and sanitation services, can communities in a
            major African city effectively take control of their own
            service provision? COBWAS is an ambitious attempt to upgrade
            the water supply and sanitation services in Addis Ababa,
            capital city of Ethiopia, by encouraging local communities
            to design, and implement, action plans for their own areas.
            High priority is placed on low-cost, appropriate technology
            solutions. COBWAS is at an early stage of its development
            and although no results are as yet available, the scheme has
            already involved a high degree of cooperation between
            international agencies, local government, and other groups
            within the city. This Field Note reports on the key ideas of
            an initiative quite unique in the Ethiopian environment.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Urban water supply and sanitation : a
            community-based approach in Ethiopia
        </docna>
        <display_title>Urban water supply and sanitation
            : a community-based approach in Ethiopia</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2002/05/2495949/urban-water-supply-sanitation-community-based-approach-ethiopia</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>UNDP-Water &amp; Sanitation Program</docty>
        <subtopic>Town Water Supply and Sanitation,Urban Services to the Poor,Water Supply and Sanitation Governance
            and Institutions,Water and Industry</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Water Resources</teratopic>
        <count>Ethiopia</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>East Africa!$!80458</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Sub-Saharan Africa!$!80473</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000094946_03082904013041</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>(Historic)Sector not applicable</subsc>
        <admreg>Africa,Africa</admreg>
        <colti>Water and Sanitation Program field note</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Water Resources</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Sector not applicable</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Water supply; Sanitation; Water
            distribution; Urban areas; Rural areas; Community planning;
            Poor families; Water management; Community participation;
            Poor families; Hygiene; Drinking water supplies; Sewerage;
            Waste disposal; Households; Pit latrines; Environmental
            issues; Social issues; Partnership; Donors
            availability of water,capacity
            building,community contribution,community group,community
            groups,community members,community projects,Community
            Water,Community Water Supply,drainage systems,Drinking
            water,Economic Development,Environmental
            Sanitation,households,iron,Land Tenure,local
            communities,local community,Local Private Sector,Municipal
            water,neighborhood,piped water,pit latrines,Project
            Management,recycling,roads,sanitation coverage,sanitation
            facilities,Sanitation Problems,sewerage system,small
            towns,Solid waste,Solid waste collection,supply,Urban
            Poor,urban upgrading,Urban water,Urban water supply,waste
            disposal,water,water points,water usage
        </keywd>
        <owner>Water- Water and Sanit Prgrm (GWASP)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>East Africa</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Sub-Saharan Africa</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>26613</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wastewater Collection and Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Solid Waste Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Solid Waste Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Basic Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>On-site Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Marketing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deconcentration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delegation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Devolution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sub-National Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subnational Government and Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Very Vulnerable Groups (disability, orphans, children and youth)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Town Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply</ml:concept><ml:concept>Diseases</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water, Sanitation and Hygiene</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sewerage</ml:concept><ml:concept>Solid Waste</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Local Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Administrative Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Vulnerable Groups</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Land Tenure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Drainage</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Africa</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Ethiopia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>