<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>BUILDING PARTNERSHIPS&#13;
TO SERVE THE URBAN POOR&#13;
49~~~ 26610&#13;
Summary Proceedings -&#13;
Final Workshop of WUP Project No. 5&#13;
Abidjan, Cote d'lvoire 19-21 November, 2001&#13;
I,&#13;
_     ~~WAT'ER UTILITY PARTN-tKSHIP&#13;
FOR CAPACITY BUILDINGI A[RICA&#13;
.'                        I&#13;
,.~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ae "_ &#13;
-~~ C, 'QlIat&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
CONCLUSIONS OF THE ROUND TABLE MEETING OF CHIEF&#13;
EXECUTIVES AND POLICY MAKERS&#13;
Utility managers, policy makers and advisors, that were participating in the Abidjan workshop held a special Round Table&#13;
meeting to discuss the issues and challenges that confront them in the provision of WSS services to the poor. The Round&#13;
Table was co-chaired by Mr. Kessy Zadi of SODECI, Cote d'lvoire and Mr. Neil Macleod of Durban Metro Water Services,&#13;
South Africa.&#13;
The Round Table conclusions are summarized below beginning with the broad enabling issues followed by&#13;
recommendations on services to low-income households.&#13;
Ensuring adequate urban planning&#13;
Part of the problem in serving low-income areas is the haphazard manner in which developments in some African cities&#13;
have taken place. Governments should, therefore, place greater emphasis on planning, and define appropriate and&#13;
specific standards for low income settlements that will permit the provision of basic affordable services. Legal status,&#13;
whether permanent or temporary, should be given to informal and peri-urban settlements to enable utilities to extend&#13;
services to them.&#13;
Improving the efficiency of utilities&#13;
Utilities should strive towards greater efficiency in their operations, particularly in the area of reducing unaccounted-for-&#13;
water. Improved efficiency will allow utilities the opportunity to provide services to all customers including those in low-&#13;
income areas.&#13;
Speeding-up reform processes&#13;
A number of African governments are undertaking various reforms in the WSS sector. In most cases these have moved&#13;
slowly and expected benefits are being delayed. It is imperative that governments speed-up these reforms and ensure&#13;
that they include new policy, legal and institutional arrangements as well as incentives to enable utilities carry out their&#13;
mandate to serve the urban poor.&#13;
Training and capacity building&#13;
Manpower training should be a continuing feature of the management of utilities. African utilities should take advantage&#13;
of available opportunities for training and capacity building through both internal and external resources. Major&#13;
financing partners are ready to assist in this direction. Training and capacity-building should however not be limited to&#13;
utilities alone but also to customers and other stakeholders so that they understand the business of water and sanitation.&#13;
The problem of sanitation&#13;
Discussions on service to the poor always dwell on water supply, leaving out sanitation. However the promotion of good&#13;
health requires that serious attention is paid to sanitation. In order to create demand for sanitation services, it may&#13;
therefore be appropriate to extend subsidies for both off-site and on-site sanitation to low-income urban households.&#13;
On their part utilities should define strategic plans for providing sanitation services to the poor.&#13;
Services to low-income urban areas&#13;
The need for innovation&#13;
The technical problems associated with providing water and sanitation services to the poor are known and can be solved.&#13;
They are, therefore, not a good reason for denying water and sonitation services to low-income areas. The issue there-&#13;
fore is how utilities can develop standards and streamline their technologies so as to respond to the requirements of low-&#13;
income urban consumers. This will also require appropriate legislative and institutional support, as well as incentives&#13;
Cost recovery and subsidies&#13;
Utilities can provide sustainable services only if they can achieve some measure of cost recovery. There is convincing&#13;
evidence that the un-served poor pay relatively more per unit for the same water produced by the utility than those who&#13;
are connected. There is also clear evidence that the poor have been able and are willing to pay for WSS services&#13;
provided the necessary education and sensitization are carried out and standards are developed to suit their needs.&#13;
Serving low-income areas is therefore unlikely to compromise cost recovery. Subsidies, when availoble, should be&#13;
targeted at providing access to service connections for the urban poor.&#13;
Creating greater awareness for provision of WSS services to low-income urban areas&#13;
o  African WSS utilities should consider the establishment of dedicated units within their organizations to deal&#13;
specifically with services to low income urban communities.&#13;
o   Country level consultations among utilities and sanitation providers, policymakers and politicians should be&#13;
organized in order to create greater awareness on the provision of WSS services to the poor.&#13;
o The provision of water and sanitation services for low income areas should receive adequate treatment in country&#13;
poverty reduction strategies (PRSP) and in negotiations with development partners.&#13;
Prepared and edited by: Mukami Kariuki, Jean Doyen, Kwobena Manu, Esther Muya, Helina Tirfie and Sarah Fiset.  i WUP Nairobi, February 2002&#13;
2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
SUMMARY         PROCEEDINGS                is the product of a specific institutional and&#13;
policy context, they exhibit a number of common&#13;
characteristics:&#13;
The Challenge                              *   political goodwill translated into a coherent&#13;
The concluding workshop of WUP Project No. 5   policy - 'governments holds the key"&#13;
on water and sanitation services to the urban  .  support from a reasonably well managed&#13;
poor brought together 1 20 sector specialists in  utility with some degree of financial&#13;
Abidjan from  November 19-21, 2001. The        autonomy;&#13;
workshop drew participants from across French  .  partnerships involving communities, small&#13;
and English-speaking Africa, including chief   scale providers and municipal actors;&#13;
executives and senior staff from a number of&#13;
*  adaptation and innovation concerning service&#13;
utilities, NGOs, small scale providers, and staff  standards and the choice of options&#13;
from various development agencies including    stand        c  hicetof potions;&#13;
the EC, the AfDB and the World Bank. The work-  c   istrong communication,  promotion and&#13;
shop was opened by Mr. Patrick Achi, the       capacity building functions - outreach to&#13;
Minister for Economic Infrastructure of Cote   customers;&#13;
d'lvoire and a key note speech was delivered by  *  reliable and sustainable financial support&#13;
Mr. Kessy Zadi, the Chief Executive of SODECI.  relying to a large extent on internal cross-&#13;
Before the day was over, small scale water     subsidies.&#13;
vendors were on the podium explaining the ins&#13;
and outs of their relationships with large water  The strategic challenge for utilities  WUP No. 5 has&#13;
utilities.                                 By 2025, urbanization in Africa will have   focused on practices&#13;
progressed from about 32% today to about    demonstrated the&#13;
WUP Project No. 5 sets the focus on WSS    50%. The urban population will have grown   potential to go to&#13;
services for urban poor.                   from the current level of about 300 million to  scale in improving&#13;
WUP Project No. 5 has unfolded through three  700 mil!ion. If current trends prevail, the large  services to the urban&#13;
phases over the lost two and a half years.  majority will be living in poverty in unplanned or  poor either at city or&#13;
*  Phase 1 piloted the methodology for case  informal settlements without access to safe water  country level.&#13;
studies;                                and hygienic sanitation.&#13;
*   Phase 2 researched and documented      Utilities will be hard pressed to prevent widening&#13;
practices from nine countries leading to the  of the gap between the decreasing percentage of&#13;
June, 2000 workshop in Nairobi; and,    urban households which are connected to their&#13;
finally                                 networks and the growing number of unserved&#13;
*   Phase 3 prepared the Good Practice    left to depend on more costly and often less safe&#13;
Document and the Toolkit. Which will be  and convenient alternatives. The objective of&#13;
disseminated after this workshop        increasing the overall percentage of urban&#13;
The central objective of the WUP Project No. 5  dwellers served by a connection from the current&#13;
workshop in Abidjan is to raise awareness and  50% to 80% in 2025 would require on average&#13;
obtain the commitment of African water and  about 5 to 4 million new connections every year;&#13;
sanitation utilities to act on the challenge of  i.e. about 6,000 to 10,000 every day.&#13;
extending safe water and hygienic sanitation&#13;
services to the growing number of the poor in  Extending basic services to the urban poor, long&#13;
African cities.                            considered a peripheral objective, has to be&#13;
recognized as a strategic goal by planners and&#13;
In addition to its dissemination and validation  policy makers, and a matter of long term survival&#13;
function, the Abidicn workshop, which drew the  for utilities confronted with the prospect of&#13;
participation of 40 utility managers and senior  playing an increasingly marginal role in&#13;
policy makers, mapped the way forward and                              °&#13;
encouraged  utilities to adopt and scale up the  sprwling and dysfunionl cities (see Box 6) Extending basic&#13;
good practices documented and disseminated  Building Partnerships                      services to the urbbn&#13;
under WUP Project No. 5. The workshop also iden-  A well performing and financially sound utility is a  poor has to be&#13;
tified follow-up actions by WUP and its partners  necessary, but insufficient condition for serving the  recognized as a&#13;
(see conclusions of the Executive Roundtable) for  urban poor. While the role of utilities is central,  matter of long term&#13;
implementation under a fourth phase of the project.  they cannot, as shown  by the practices  survival for utilities&#13;
documented by WUP No. 5, succeed on their   confronted with the&#13;
Learning to move to scale                  own.                                        prospect of playing&#13;
WUP No. 5 has focused on practices that have                                           an increasingly&#13;
demonstrated the potential to go to scale in  First, the population they are meant to serve and  sprawling and&#13;
improving services to the urban poor either at  the governments that represent them need to  dysfunctional cities.&#13;
city or country level. While each "good practice"  assert their commitment to the objective of&#13;
3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
A section of participants at the Round Table meeting&#13;
extending basic services to the urban poor who  Second, they need a policy and legal frame-&#13;
should be seen as full-fledged customers and  work that (i) recognizes the broad range of local&#13;
stakeholders                                actors from communities, NGO's and the private&#13;
sector, that are engaged in water and sanitation&#13;
Box X. Parvicipants' views on services to  services, and, (ii) opens the way for partnerships&#13;
the urban poor.                            and innovation aimed at adapting the services to&#13;
the capacity and preferences of the poor.&#13;
Responses from 68 participants (70% of total)&#13;
indicate a high level of awareness and     Good policies wnil have to be complemented by&#13;
consensus on the issues in the sector. Some  implementabion strategies defining roles and&#13;
interesting results include:               responsibilities, setting frameworks and&#13;
processes for giving the poor a voice and&#13;
*  50%   of respondents did not think it  bringing in all stakeholders engaged in service&#13;
necessary for utilities to be provided with  provision. At the heart of such strategies will be&#13;
exclusive mandate within their service  tariff systems that make basic services&#13;
areasi                                 accessible and affordable to the poor while at&#13;
the same time safeguard the financial autonomy&#13;
o  55% believe that small-scale providers are  of the utility.&#13;
better placed than utilities to offer water  Eventually, good policies and sound strategies&#13;
supply services to the urban poor.     should lead to stepped up levels of Invest-&#13;
o   75%  believe that if provision of WSS i ment. The requirements even for a country like&#13;
provisionI Gate d'lvoire which stands at the high end of&#13;
service providers other than utilities were  regonal proirm w in  atte and sniaon&#13;
j  leol ad sppored, omemicr-entr kregional performance in water and sanitation&#13;
legal and supported, some micro-enter- &#13;
prises would offer sustainable low cost s services, are staggering; halving the proportion&#13;
priss wuld ffe susainble ow  ost of urban households not yet connected to the&#13;
alternatives to formal network supply.  fo  ro   oshlsntytcnetdt              h&#13;
network by 2015, would require annual outlays in&#13;
o  80% believe that WSS utilities should be  the order of magnitude of 1.5 % of the current&#13;
GDP Most countries will depend on external aid&#13;
allowed to deliver water to the poor   for a large percentage of these requirements.&#13;
through a variety of suitable arrange-&#13;
ments whether they have secure land    The conclusions from this workshop and the&#13;
practices documented by WUP Project No. 5,&#13;
°  90% believe that most African Govern-  and validated by the utilities, should inform the&#13;
ments only pay lip service to the provision  programs of donors and be' used, in particular to&#13;
of services to the urban poor and thot in  develop the water and sanitation components of&#13;
most cases, there are no clear policies or  povery reducion stregy papers (PRSP).&#13;
requirements for utilities to follow to meet&#13;
the needs of the urban poor.           Focus oon Ompiroved On-site&#13;
Sani¢3Won&#13;
Access to improved sanitation in many African&#13;
cities is limited and declining. Currently, an&#13;
estimated 80% of households in most major&#13;
4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
African urban centers rely on on-site sanitation,  Utilities as institutional anchor for pro-&#13;
primarily pit latrines, the majority of which are  poor urban sanitation program&#13;
unimproved. In densely populated informal    The scarcity of good examples within the region&#13;
settlements there is not enough space set aside  where on-site sanitation has been replicated and&#13;
for latrines. The few latrines that exist are over-  scaled up points to the importance of piloting and&#13;
used and rarely emptied. Many residents have  strategic planning to test options, match house-&#13;
no alternatives except "flying toilets" and open  hold demand to service delivery and define roles&#13;
defecation. Poor sanitation is a growing public  and responsibilities as well as resource flows.&#13;
health problem. Diarrhea and other sanitation-  Successful programs to promote improved on-&#13;
related illnesses are among the top five causes of  site sanitation and household hygiene have&#13;
morbidity and mortality. In some cities cholera  typically unfolded over several years of trials and&#13;
has become endemic.                          adaptations before gaining momentum   and&#13;
building a market for their products.&#13;
The role of utilities in the delivery of sanitation&#13;
services varies from country to country. When  In the context of weak municipal institutions, the&#13;
involved, their role is typically limited to  utilities often emerge as institutional anchors&#13;
managing traditional sewer networks serving  for household and community-based sanitation&#13;
central business districts and high income/high  programs. Their relative institutional strength,&#13;
density areas covering about 10 to 1 5 per cent of  legal standing, city-wide perspective, and ability&#13;
the households and businesses. Public financing  to mobilize financing, put them  in unique&#13;
for sanitation remains targeted to sewerage net-  position to organize and oversee the multi-&#13;
works despite the low level of access.       layered  partnerships required   for such&#13;
programs, involving communities, NGO's,&#13;
High investment requirements and high costs of  artisans, training institutions and municipal&#13;
operation for conventional sewerage systems  actors, among others.&#13;
have brought about recognition of the limitations&#13;
of traditional sewer networks and have led to  The case of Burkina, where the national utility  A well performing&#13;
initiatives to promote improved forms of     ONEA   (Office  National de   l'Eau  et de    and financially&#13;
on-site sanitation. The few   cases where    I'Assainissement) initiated and brought to scale a  sound utility is a&#13;
utilities play a lead role in on-site sanitation  program for the promotion of on-site sanitation  necessary, but insuf-&#13;
initiatives suggest that their involvement is critical  to low income households, illustrates the critical  ficient condition for&#13;
for moving to scale.                         role that utilities can play in institutionalizing the  serving the urban&#13;
program and ensuring stable financing through  poor.&#13;
a surcharge applicable to the higher blocks of&#13;
the water tariff.&#13;
The surcharge provides for communication,&#13;
training and capacity building directed at&#13;
communities, households and      artisans.&#13;
Although these functions absorb a large part of&#13;
the cost of such programs, typically more than&#13;
50 per cent, they are essential in ensuring that&#13;
the household voice is heard and that their&#13;
choice is articulated with full understanding of&#13;
their obligations and responsibilities for subse-&#13;
quent O&amp;M. Direct subsidies to households need&#13;
not cover more than the critical components, like&#13;
latrine cover plates and vent pipes, amounting to&#13;
a small proportion of the cost borne by the&#13;
households.&#13;
Way forward&#13;
*   Efforts to tackle the mounting sanitation&#13;
In the context of&#13;
problem of African cities and towns should  weak municipal&#13;
prioritize the promotion of improved on-site  institutions, the&#13;
sanitation.                               utilities often emerge&#13;
*  As their mission is centered on basic      as institutional&#13;
services and public health, utilities should be  anchor for household&#13;
pro-active  in  advocating  for  sound    and community-&#13;
sanitation policies and piloting innovative  based sanitation.&#13;
Coin vending water point "yacoli" in Abidjan     approaches to on-site sanitation.&#13;
5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
*  Utilities have a critical role to play as the  tion and the fact that, often, the majority of&#13;
institutional anchor for water supply and  the habitants are tenants. Flexibility and&#13;
sanitation services and can provide the  innovations are required to enable service deli-&#13;
continuity needed to bring such program to  very in complex socio-economic and physical&#13;
scale, provided:                        environments. The lifting of administrative&#13;
-   first, that they are reasonably efficient  requirements related to land titles and frontage&#13;
and financially sound, and          access have allowed utilities to extend services to&#13;
-   second, that their involvement is  low income groups, often without additional&#13;
supported by a clear policy expressing  risks, thereby gaining customers and revenues.&#13;
broad commitment from all stake-&#13;
holders at central and municipal levels  High risks of service delivery to unplanned settle-&#13;
ments can be overcome by partnering with&#13;
*  Utilities that are called to take up a lead role  communities for safekeeping, maintenance and&#13;
in sanitation, should work with partners to  even collection. Practices from  Durban and&#13;
define their role in relation to the whole  Manila West Zone (Maynilad Water) show that it&#13;
range of options to improve sanitation  is possible to reduce the cost of delivering water&#13;
As their mission is         services for  low  income  households  while preserving its quality. The two practices&#13;
centered on services        including on-site solutions and low-cost  were developed in order to meet household pref-&#13;
and public health,          off-site options.                      erence for in-house connections. In Manila&#13;
utilities should be                                                investment costs were brought down by laying&#13;
pro-active in           Priorities for further learning:            pipes (including flexible rubber hosing) above&#13;
asvocating for o            Study tours to Burkina Faso and other  the ground along alleys and regrouping meters&#13;
policies and pilot          documented good practices.             in batteries. In Durban the daily quantity of water&#13;
innovative  pEnabling                                              made available was matched with ability to pay&#13;
innovative     .   Enablingframeworks and    models for   byofrngadtesrvcopis;whte&#13;
approaches to               partnership between utilities and municipal  by offering groduoted service options; with the&#13;
on-site sanitation.         boie onteoehn,an            ml cl       ower cost option offering a fixed minimum&#13;
bodies on the one hand, and small scale  quantity of water by filling a 200-liter tank in the&#13;
operators and community-based organiza-  household on a daily basis.&#13;
tions on the other.&#13;
*  Funding mechanisms to ensure the stable  The targeted programs launched in Manila West&#13;
support needed to build up capacity and  Zone, and in Durban provide enhanced services&#13;
confidence, and take programs through the  at no, or minimum, additional cost to the utility.&#13;
initial trial and error phase.          Manila households participating in the so-called&#13;
*  Adaptation to African contexts of the   "Bayan Tubig" programs have on average&#13;
condominial approach (simplified sewerage)  trebled their daily consumption to about 30 I/c/d&#13;
to serve the denser settlements.        for less than half of what they were paying&#13;
before to vendors and resellers, thereby reducing&#13;
their outlays for water from 4.5% of their income&#13;
Delivery Options and                       to less than 2 per cent. In both cases, tariffs have&#13;
Standards                                  been set so that the revenues accruing to the&#13;
Opening up standards for review and revision is  utility covers only direct O&amp;M costs.&#13;
essential to improving services to low income&#13;
communities. Infrastructure and service    Both the Durban and the Manila West practices&#13;
standards designed for formal (often middle and  rely on community-based user committees to&#13;
high-income) areas, are in fact inappropriate for  ensure safekeeping, discourage unauthorized&#13;
the majority of urban dwellers who fall below the  connections and collect payments. The&#13;
poverty line and do not reside in planned settle-  community organization typically retains a&#13;
ments. Inflexible standards also contribute to the  percentage of revenues collected to cover its&#13;
O&amp;M responsibilities, to set aside a provision for&#13;
high cost of laying infrastructure In rocky, hilly or  rpisa  ela  rftmri  rvdda&#13;
waterogge   area   whee   man   infrmalrepairs as well as a profit margin provided as&#13;
wattlerlged areasoc where  many  informal  incentive for use by the community. This is also&#13;
the case in Port-au-Prince (Haiti) where water&#13;
In many countries, statutory constraints restrict committees manage tertiary reticulation systems&#13;
In mony countries, statutory constraints restrict  dsrbtn  ae rmbl  ees    h   rai&#13;
utility services to formal settlements. The extension  distributing water from bulk meters. The organi-&#13;
of utility networks into informal and peri-urban  zational capacity and savings mobilized by the&#13;
settlements is often perceived as a considerable  water users committees have typically supported&#13;
risk due to uncertain land tenure, low and often  community initiatives in related areas like sanita-&#13;
inconsistent incomes, difficulties in revenue collec-  tion, hygiene and drainage.&#13;
6&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The full realization of the health benefit from  Priorities for further learning:       The full realization&#13;
improved water services requires a sharper focus  o  Increase the level of understanding on the  of the health&#13;
on quality of water at the time of consumption.  need for, and implications of, increasing  benefits from&#13;
This, as well as user preference, led to increased  flexibility in standards and preserving service  improved water&#13;
coverage through piped household connections   quality.                                 services would&#13;
in Manila West Zone and Durban. In the latter  .  Audits of water standards to identify  require a sharper&#13;
case, public taps were in fact discontinued as the  constraints to serving the poor and to  focus on quality of&#13;
system was extended. Concern for water quality  enhance quality at the time of consumption.  water at the time of&#13;
is a strong reason for recognizing and licensing  -  Licensing arrangements for resellers and  consumption.&#13;
resellers and tanker services, i.e. to foster the  tanker services with related monitoring and&#13;
acceptance of procedures to ensure proper      enforcement systems to ensure preservation&#13;
quality in their operations.                   of water quality.&#13;
Way forward                                 Rireng2hengng )0ihreach&#13;
&#149;   Utilities, in collaboration with governments,  udo ns&#13;
should initiate a review of the legal and  "Knowing your customer" should be the starting&#13;
regulatory framework under which they   point of strategies to improve service delivery to&#13;
operate and identify constraints to their  low income communities. When utilities have&#13;
ability to deliver services to low income  attempted to reach unplanned settlements, they&#13;
communities.                            have typically prescribed standard public taps or&#13;
o   Utilities should recognize low  income  water kiosks aimed at serving a specified&#13;
communities and informal settlements as  number of users within a given distance. The&#13;
legitimate customers and should develop  proliferation of alternative services including&#13;
innovative approaches to delivering     vendors, illegal connections, etc., indicates that&#13;
services adapted to their demand.       "one-size-fits-all" approoches cannot respond to&#13;
o   Utilities should work with low  income  what is in fact a differentiated demand.&#13;
communities to lower the cost of services&#13;
and overcome security and operating     Utilities that have extended services to informal  Utilities should revise&#13;
constraints.                            settlements have acknowledged the importance  regulatory frame-&#13;
&#149;  As more flexibility is accepted, utilities should  of understanding their customers' needs and  works under which&#13;
they operate which&#13;
keep thefocus on water quality. They should  have adopted innovative strategies to do so.  restrcttheiabilily&#13;
give preference to delivery systems that  One of these strategies is to establish a 'low  to deliver services to&#13;
maintain the quality of water at the time of  income users unit' (a dedicated internal unit).  low income commu-&#13;
consumption and should work together with  The other one is to work in partnership with  nities.&#13;
water resellers, vendors and tanker services  NGOs which assist the utility with the outreach&#13;
to foster procedures that preserve water  and community rmobilization work.&#13;
quality.&#13;
The Peri-Urban Section of&#13;
S the Lusaka Water and&#13;
' acSewerage Corporation&#13;
building capacity internally&#13;
and establishing a&#13;
specialized unit dedicated to&#13;
reaching poor customers.&#13;
'An early reolization was that&#13;
in order to succeed, such a&#13;
unit had to get acceptance&#13;
WMIRMWO11     from  the whole organiza-&#13;
tion. Peri-urban  dwellers&#13;
who account for 70 % or the&#13;
population of Lusaka, had to&#13;
be  recognized  as  full- by   ihes should&#13;
Open  i I efledged customers through-'  reonlz&#13;
-out the organization.       icm      omnte&#13;
and in formal settle-&#13;
In the case of Port-au-Prince  ments as legitimate&#13;
the intermediation function  customers and adapt&#13;
was assumed initially by   their services to meet&#13;
Open drain in low income area of Abid jan                   GE,     a     nentoa        hi    ead&#13;
7&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
NGO, under an externally supported project.  tion corresponding to basic services. However, in&#13;
This NGO worked in partnership with CAMEP, the  most coses these subsidies do not reach the poor&#13;
local utility. This partnership arrangement served  who typically do not have access to the&#13;
to leverage outside funding and make good use  network because of their location, or because of&#13;
of the strong links that the NGO had with the  high up-front connection costs. Furthermore,&#13;
community and harness the specialist communi-  many poor households rely on a daily wage and&#13;
ty skills that the NGO could contribute. CAMEP  can neither save up for a connection nor&#13;
provided the necessary institutional backing and  accumulate the sums needed for monthly&#13;
gradually internalized the activities of the NGO  payments.&#13;
as capacity was built up within the utility. For this&#13;
purpose, CAMEP also found it useful to create a  Tariff and subsidy policies are central to any&#13;
dedicated unit within the utility to which GRET's  effort to extend services to the poor. They are&#13;
activities were transferred. This fulfilled GRET's  driven by diverse and sometimes conflicting&#13;
own mandate, allowing it to move into new   objectives (see Box 2).&#13;
areas, and is a good example of the evolution&#13;
and flexibility that characterizes good partner-  Box 2: Objectives of WSS tariff policy&#13;
ships.&#13;
*  Social: to ensure the right of all people to&#13;
The long-term goal, whichever interim strategy is  be able to access basic services.&#13;
chosen, should be to institutionalize the capacity  *  Financial: to allow the operator to keep&#13;
for serving low income groups throughout the     his business running, maintain assets and&#13;
utility. This is necessary to sustain its commitment  serve debt.&#13;
and fully integrate peri-urban customers in      E&#13;
planning an policy deelopment.       Economic: to take into account costs and&#13;
planning and policy development,                 benefits to the society as a whole&#13;
Way forward:                                     including the user of water resources, the&#13;
*  Working in partnership with NGOs or          impact on the public and     on the&#13;
establishing dedicated community outreach    environment.&#13;
units within the utility are complementary  *  Political: to achieve a redistribution of&#13;
Working in partner-         elements of strategies to extend services to  benefits and costs that can be accepted&#13;
ship with NGOs and         low income communities.                       and  sustained  through the political&#13;
establishing                                                             process.&#13;
dedicated commu-        *  The commitment to extending services to&#13;
nity outreach units        low   income   customers should     be&#13;
within the utility are      internalized by the entire organization and  The consensus among workshop participants&#13;
complementary              inform its mission and its culture.      was that:&#13;
elements of&#13;
strategies to extend&#13;
services to low         Priorities for further learning:            *   Social objectives are important because the&#13;
income communities.     *   Cross fertilization across utilities (study tour  poor constitute such a large proportion of&#13;
cases) to study success stories of          the customer base.&#13;
cross-sectoral partnerships and dedicated&#13;
units for low income customers.         *   Financial objectives are critical because with-&#13;
out a working utility, the poor would not get&#13;
*  Models for    community  management:        services.&#13;
partnership  arrangements  with  utility&#13;
linkages with municipal structures, sharing of  *  Politics is the least "reliable" element in the&#13;
responsibilities for O&amp;M, mobilization of   equation. If the policy depends too heavily&#13;
financial resources, contractual and        on political control, short term  conside-&#13;
incentive  frameworks, by-laws and          rations will prevail.&#13;
other legal framework, recourse and griev-&#13;
The commitment to          ance mechanisms.                         The challenge is to ensure that the institutional&#13;
extending com itmen to     ancemechanismframework under which tariffs are set and&#13;
low-income cus-         Making tariffs                              revised, ensures a balance between long-term&#13;
low-incme cus- Making    ariffsand subsidies             financial imperatives and shorter term political&#13;
tomers should be&#13;
internalized by the    work for the poor                            considerations. Hence the trend toward&#13;
entire organization     Most utilities have pricing policies based on  independent regulatory bodies.&#13;
and inform its mis-    increasing block tariffs (IBTs) which are geared to&#13;
sion and its culture.  the objectives of: (i) ensuring cost recovery for the  Subsidies needed to support pro-poor policies&#13;
utility; and, (ii) allowing poor households to  can be obtained either externally from the State&#13;
afford piped water through a subsidized "social  and municipal budgets, or can be generated&#13;
block" tariff applicable to a monthly consump-  internally by charging higher rates to customers&#13;
8&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Box 3. Pro-poor Tariffs: Guiding          connected customer has to pay a deposit     Given proper&#13;
Priniple 3Pro-poorTariffs:Guidingcorresponding to three month of basic services.      incentives, the&#13;
Principles                                This contrasts with many cases where very low  private sector holds&#13;
*  Getting the tariff level and the tariff  tariffs are combined with prohibitive and  the potential to&#13;
structure right helps all consumers,   cumbersome connection procedures.          improve services to&#13;
including the poor.                                                               the poor.&#13;
When pricing services for the poor due conside-&#13;
*  Subsidize access not consumption.      ration should be given to aspects beyond the cost&#13;
*  Subsidy delivery mechanisms should be  per cubic meter and include all the components&#13;
targeted, transparent, and triggered by  of the relationship between the customers and&#13;
household indication of demand.       the utility, in particular: the connection costs, the&#13;
*  New information is often required to   deposit requirements, the re-connection fees etc.&#13;
evaluate whether a proposed tariff or  In one instance, the length of pipes charged to&#13;
subsidy will hurt or help the poor.    new customers was reduced to a maximum of&#13;
ten meters, instead of the full length of additional&#13;
reticulation needed to reach their house.&#13;
Subsidies do not&#13;
in upper consumption brackets. Theoretical con-                                        reach the poor who&#13;
siderations favor external subsidies applied to  Way forward                           typically do not have&#13;
outputs, i.e. linked to services actually supplied  Tariff and subsidy policy needs to evolve.  access to the net-&#13;
to the target groups. However, given the dire  The establishment of appropriate regulatory  work because of&#13;
state of public finance across Africa, the practical  frameworks to balance long-term require-  because ofhigh&#13;
option is to support pro-poor polices with     ments for financial sustainability with social  up-front connection&#13;
resources from within through increasing block  and political considerations is a central  costs.&#13;
tariffs (IBTs) or consumption cross-subsidies  element of sector reform.&#13;
recognizing that they should be applied&#13;
carefully to protect the revenue bases, and, in the  *  Local authorities have a key role in the&#13;
case of industrial and institutional customers,  process. All stakeholders need to be&#13;
very sparingly.                                involved in the process of setting and&#13;
revising tariff policy including:&#13;
The application of IBTs to resellers and vendors  -  the poor whose demand and constraints&#13;
that rely on a household connection, result in     need to be understood; as well as&#13;
higher charges for their customers, pre-       -  the customers who will actually finance&#13;
dominantly poor unconnected households.           the subsidies (i.e. commerce, industry&#13;
The problem is real. Several utilities e.g. Ghana  and the relatively prosperous) so that&#13;
and Kenya, have approached the problem by         they  accept the  social objectives  important because&#13;
recognising resellers and granting them a sin-     justifying the need for cross-subsidy.  the poor constitute a&#13;
gle block tariff with service obligations and  Capacity building of all stakeholders is  large proportion of&#13;
requirements related to water quality.         needed to enable an informed debate and  the customer base.&#13;
special attention must be paid to gathering&#13;
information as a key input to this process.&#13;
(e.g. Burkina, Cote d'lvoire) illustrate examples&#13;
where programs that have had a significant     A transparent process needs to be set in&#13;
impact on services to the poor have been       place to ensure accountability of the&#13;
sustained   through    surcharges   and        utility and on the use and impact of sub-&#13;
cross-subsidies with a large degree of public  sidies, the latter usually through a special&#13;
acceptance and   minimal impact on the         financing mechanism with its own over-&#13;
financial soundness of the utility. In several  sight.&#13;
cases, the funds mobilized by utilities have been&#13;
Sanitation: In some situations, the tariff&#13;
used as counterpart funding for external grants    be used as an instrument to         Programs that have&#13;
and credits.                                   caouresed      s n  upport  tmgenerate  had a significant&#13;
resources to  support investments in    impact on services to&#13;
The "social connection" programs initiated by a  appropriate sanitation services.      the poor have been&#13;
number of the best performing utilities, including                                     sustained through&#13;
SODECI (Cote d'lvoire) and    SONES/SDE    Priorities for further learning             surcharges and&#13;
(Senegal), show the value of prioritizing access to  *  Gain a better understanding of the outcome  cross-subsidies with&#13;
a household connection. The programs use the   of tariff policies on services to the poor.  pubalc acceptance&#13;
proceeds of a surcharge on higher consumption  *  Good practice on information and consulta-  and minimal impact&#13;
brackets to subsidize low-cost connections    tion processes for tariff design.        on the financial&#13;
(through smaller diometer pipes) with simplified  *  Options and scope of institutional arrange-  soundness of the&#13;
requirements. In the case of SODECI, the newly  ments for tariff regulation.           utility.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
When pricing             *  Models of effective use of cross-subsidies for  structured to foster attention to the poor through:&#13;
services for the poor,      extension of services to low income      *   area-specific coverage torgets&#13;
due consideration           households including water supply and, also  .  built-in incentives to attend to low income&#13;
should be given to          improved sanitation.                         customers&#13;
aspects beyond the&#13;
cost per cubic meter.                                                .   licensing or franchising of SSIPs (e.g. by includ-&#13;
WSS reforms that benefit the                    ing their services in the monitored targets)&#13;
poor                                         *  removing monopoly from   legislation and&#13;
Private sector participation (PSP) is increasingly  limiting exclusivity clauses from contracts&#13;
viewed as a means of improving efficiency and  *  allowing flexible technical standards while&#13;
effectiveness of utility operations. However,   preserving quality.&#13;
proposals to involve the private sector in water&#13;
supply and sanitation services often meet   The preparation of a sound PSP contract is a&#13;
resistance as it is feared that the poor will be  lengthy and complex process requiring a well&#13;
priced out through higher tariffs and costly  thought through consultation framework, judicious&#13;
connection fees, or overlooked because they live  timing and systematic information gathering.&#13;
in hard-to-reach locations.&#13;
The selection of contract type should align with&#13;
As a rule, the prospects of private deprivation is  pro-poor objectives and incentives (see Box 4).&#13;
politically and socially much less acceptable than&#13;
long-standing public neglect. Once the respon-  The majority of utilities in Africa are still publicly&#13;
sibility for service delivery no longer rests with  managed and although the move towards PSP is&#13;
State or municipal bodies, politicians and unions  gaining momentum, public utilities will continue&#13;
become much more vocal in pressing for      to play an important role. Where the private&#13;
The establishment of     improvements.                               sector is not an option, policy and institutional&#13;
appropriate regula-                                                  reforms  are  as   important  in  ensuring&#13;
tory frameworks to       The reality is that PSP holds the potential to  improvements in service delivery to low income&#13;
balance the require-     improve services to the poor. Private operators  communities. Much can be learned from the&#13;
ments for long-term      have the skills to innovate in developing suitable  experience in PSP regarding good practice in&#13;
financial sustain-       options and different levels of service. Much  serving the poor.&#13;
ability withsocial       depends on how contracts, policies and&#13;
considerations is a      regulations are structured, how targets for  Way Forward&#13;
central element of       extending services are specified and financed,  *  The extension of services to the urban poor&#13;
sector reform.           and on Government's ability to regulate activities  should be recognized as a central objective&#13;
of private operators.                           of sector reform for cases involving PSP as&#13;
well as for those involving public sector&#13;
Designing a transaction which brings in the     agencies.&#13;
private sector provides an opportunity for&#13;
changes: technical, social and political. Bringing&#13;
in the private sector without due attention to low&#13;
income consumers can be counterproductive in&#13;
terms of access to services for low income house-&#13;
holds as the private sector operators unlike the&#13;
public operator, have to be able to disconnect&#13;
delinquent accounts.&#13;
Given proper incentives, the private sector can&#13;
achieve much of what WUP No. 5 advocates:&#13;
reducing the cost of services in particular&#13;
connections  costs; simplified  billings  and&#13;
collection; customer retention schemes, partner-&#13;
ships etc. In fact, as shown by the Manila West&#13;
concession case, and demonstrated by the social&#13;
sector is not an         connection policies in Cote d'lvoire and Senegal&#13;
option, policy and       PSP operators have willingly taken initiatives to&#13;
institutional reforms    upgrade or extend services to low income groups.&#13;
are as important in&#13;
ensuring improve-        Experience gained through ongoing PSP points&#13;
ments in service         to the need to find ways of translating pro-poor&#13;
delivery tomlow          objectives into monitorable undertakings&#13;
income communities.      embedded in PSP contracts. Contracts can be  Woman at the well... Abidjan, Cote d'lvoire&#13;
10&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Box 4. Incentives by Contract Type                             As a rule, the&#13;
prospects of private&#13;
Contract        Expansion                        Tariff and level of service           deprivation is&#13;
Management      - No incentives to develop services  - Low, apart from efficiency savings  socially much less&#13;
Affermage/      - No obligation to fund the exponsion - Operational subsidy may be needed  acceptable than&#13;
long-standing public&#13;
lease           - Incentive to increase sales    - Some responsibility for determining  neglect.&#13;
- Incentive to adopt connection fees  tariff structure may be given&#13;
to increase number of subscribers&#13;
Concession      - Responsible for funding expansion, - Affordability will increase customers&#13;
incentives to add customers.     and revenues&#13;
- Connection subsidies will foster  - Universal service obligation would&#13;
expansion, cross subsidies       encourage innovation&#13;
discouroge it&#13;
Given proper&#13;
incentives, the&#13;
*  Pro-poor objectives should be embedded in  *  Development of model clauses to include  private sector has&#13;
PSP contracts with specific targets and     pro-poor objectives in PSP transactions.  the potential to&#13;
monitoring systems that allow for inclusion                                         improve services to&#13;
of services provided through franchises and  *  Model of partnership and franchise agree-  the poor.&#13;
partnerships.                               ments with community-based organizations&#13;
and independent operators under PSP with&#13;
*  The financing of operating subsidies during ini-  the participation of PSP operators.&#13;
tial period of reform should be facilitated to&#13;
allow gradual transition to cost-recovery tariffs.  Box 5 is a ten point summary of WUP No. 5&#13;
findings.&#13;
Priorities for further learning&#13;
* Systematic analysis and documentation of&#13;
country cases and dissemination of lessons&#13;
learned and good practices.&#13;
Box 5. Ten Steps Towards Serving the&#13;
Poor&#13;
1. Policy Matters! The WUP urges govern-   6. Develop appropriate operational and&#13;
ments, municipalities, utilities and their  service standards to meet the needs of  whayoughtrexpnselatiene&#13;
partners to develop specific policies, strate-  low-income consumers.              pro-poor objectives&#13;
gies and plans for improving access to                                             into monitorable&#13;
services in low-income communities.    7. Recognize   and  support small scale     undertakings&#13;
service providers in order to reduce the  embedded in PSP&#13;
2. Support the policies with legislation and  high cost associated with the risks of   contracts have&#13;
regulations that enable utilities to deliver  carrying out informal or "illegal" activities.  emerged.&#13;
services to informal settlements.&#13;
8. Encompass all types of service providers in&#13;
3. Provide incentives to extend services to   regulations that are simple, user friendly,&#13;
informal settlements in utility contracts and  fair and appropriate.&#13;
performance plans.&#13;
9. Reform block tariffs to help - not&#13;
4. Train utility staff, allocate finances, and  hurt - the poor.&#13;
develop specific plans to improve&#13;
services for the poor either directly or in  10. Don't forget sanitation! Support on-site&#13;
partnership with small scale providers.    sanitation improvements and carry out&#13;
hygiene/environmental health education&#13;
5. Offer a wide range of service delivery     programs.&#13;
options to meet the needs of all consumers,&#13;
including the poor.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Box 6. WUP Vision for African WSS Utilities&#13;
Efficient, well-managed, accountable and responsive utilities which provide equitable, sustainable and&#13;
quality water and sanitation in their areas of operation&#13;
Sector policies and institutions providing the right incentives for utilities to:&#13;
*   Extend services to the poor through partnerships with key stakeholders&#13;
*   Foster a culture of capacity building, knowledge sharing and networking&#13;
*   Ensure a sound environment and sustainability of the water resource&#13;
The Challenge...&#13;
* 400 million urban poor by 2025 means&#13;
*   roughly 5 to 4 million new connections per year (5 to 8 inhabitants per connection)&#13;
*   6,000 to 1 0,000 connections per day on average.&#13;
Guiding Policy Principles&#13;
*   Water - focus on urban poor as customers with unique needs and demands&#13;
*   Sanitation - use water as an entry point and as a financing strategy&#13;
*   Urban - recognise unplanned or informal settlements&#13;
*   Utility - develop internal strategy and outreach capacity&#13;
*   Pricing - design around the poor, provide the necessary supports and incentives&#13;
*   Regulate - quality not price, focus on outputs not inputs&#13;
The Way Forward&#13;
&#149;   Recognize the role of utilities as leader and institutional anchor&#13;
a   Carry out institutional reforms to meet the necessary condition: i.e. an efficient and financially&#13;
sound utility&#13;
o   Draw in all stakeholders as partners under a coherent strategy&#13;
&#149;   Set clear targets, publicize commitment and build accountability&#13;
o   Foster a culture of continuous learning and exchanges within utilities, within countries and among&#13;
utilities and countries&#13;
These proceedings are also available on the web at www.wupafrica.org or www.wsp.org. For a copy, kindly contact:&#13;
Water Utility Partnership (WUP)                                                Water and Sanitation Program - Africa&#13;
05 BP 2642, Abidjan 05                                                         PO. Box 30577,&#13;
Cote d'lvoire                                        OR                        Nairobi, Kenya&#13;
Tel: +225-21-240828/241443,                                                    Tel: +254-2-260300/260303&#13;
Fax: +225-21-240063/242609                                                     Fax: +254-2-260380/6&#13;
E-mail: wup@africaonline.co.ci                                                 Email: wspaf@worldbank.org&#13;
This document is produced and distributed by the water Utilities Partnership (WUP) in colloboration with the water and Sanitation Program - Africa (WSP-AF),&#13;
which are responsible for its contents. The views and information contained herein do not necessarily reflect the views of the wuP or WSP-AF The&#13;
designations employed and the presentation of the material are solely for the convenience of the reoder and do not imply the expression of any legal&#13;
opinion whatsoever concerning the legal status of any country, territory, city, area, or of its authorities, or concerning the delimitation of its boundaries or&#13;
national affiliation.&#13;
World&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="2498956">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2001/11/2498956/building-partnerships-serve-urban-poor-summary-proceedings-final-workshop-wup-project-no-5-abidjan-cote-divoire-19-21-november-2001-building-partnerships-serve-urban-poor
        </url>
        <availablein>French,English</availablein>
        <fullavailablein>
            <available_in lang="French" entityid="000160016_20040329154830" node_id="2498956"/>
        </fullavailablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2001/11/2498956/building-partnerships-serve-urban-poor-summary-proceedings-final-workshop-wup-project-no-5-abidjan-cote-divoire-19-21-november-2001-building-partnerships-serve-urban-poor</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2001/11/2498956/building-partnerships-serve-urban-poor-summary-proceedings-final-workshop-wup-project-no-5-abidjan-cote-divoire-19-21-november-2001-building-partnerships-serve-urban-poor</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/09/23/000094946_03090304002987/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/09/23/000094946_03090304002987/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2001-11-30T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2003-09-23T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Building partnerships to serve the urban
            poor : summary proceedings - final workshop of WUP Project
            no. 5, Abidjan, Cote d'Ivoire, 19-21 November, 2001
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Utility managers, policy makers and
            advisors, that were participating in the Abidjan workshop
            held a special Round Table meeting to discuss the issues and
            challenges that confront them in the provision of WSS
            services to the poor. Some of the The Round Table
            conclusions are as follows. Part of the problem in serving
            low-income areas is the haphazard manner in which
            developments in some African cities have taken place.
            Governments should, therefore, place greater emphasis on
            planning, and define appropriate and specific standards for
            low income settlements that will permit the provision of
            basic affordable services. Legal status, whether permanent
            or temporary, should be given to informal and peri-urban
            settlements to enable utilities to extend services to them.
            Utilities should strive towards greater efficiency in their
            operations, particularly in the area of reducing
            unaccounted-for-water. Improved efficiency will allow
            utilities the opportunities to provide services to all
            customers including those in low-income areas. A number of
            African governments are undertaking various reforms in the
            WSS sector. In most cases these have moved slowly and
            expected benefits are being delayed. It is imperative that
            governments speed-up these reforms and ensure that they
            include new policy, legal and institutional arrangements as
            well as incentives to enable utilities carry out their
            mandate to serve the urban poor.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Building partnerships to serve the urban poor
        </docna>
        <display_title>Building partnerships to serve
            the urban poor : summary proceedings - final workshop of WUP
            Project  no. 5, Abidjan, Cote d'Ivoire, 19-21 November,
            2001 : Building partnerships to serve the urban poor</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2001/11/2498956/building-partnerships-serve-urban-poor-summary-proceedings-final-workshop-wup-project-no-5-abidjan-cote-divoire-19-21-november-2001-building-partnerships-serve-urban-poor</listing_relative_url>
        <subtopic>Town Water Supply and Sanitation,Urban Services to the Poor,Health Economics &amp; Finance,Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</subtopic>
        <docty>UNDP-Water &amp; Sanitation Program</docty>
        <teratopic>Health, Nutrition and Population</teratopic>
        <count>Africa</count>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000094946_03090304002987</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>(Historic)Sector not applicable</subsc>
        <admreg>Africa,Africa</admreg>
        <colti>Water and Sanitation Program,Proceedings</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Health, Nutrition and Population</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Sector not applicable</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Partnership; Urban communities; Urban
            planning; Low income households; Basic services; Water
            distribution; Policy framework; Institutional framework;
            Capacity building; Training; Stakeholders; Water;
            Sanitation; Water supply; Health issues
            access to safe water,access to
            services,Audits,basic services,capacity
            building,cities,community initiatives,community
            management,connection fees,connection policies,Cost
            recovery,counterpart funding,cross-subsidies,cubic
            meter,debt,delivery mechanisms,effective use,financial
            resources,household connection,household
            connections,income,investment costs,investment
            requirements,land tenure,legislation,Local authorities,local
            stakeholders,low income,low income areas,low income
            consumers,low income customers,low-income
            households,mortality,municipal
            institutions,municipalities,national utility,pit
            latrines,POLICY MAKERS,poverty line,Private
            operators,private sector,private sector operators,profit
            margin,provision of water,public health,public
            utilities,quality of water,quality water,quantity of
            water,regulatory framework,sanitation,sanitation
            providers,sanitation services,sanitation
            utilities,savings,service delivery,service providers,service
            standards,sewer networks,sewerage systems,small scale
            providers,surcharges,sustainable services,tariff
            policies,tariff policy,tariff regulation,tariff
            structure,towns,urban areas,urban centers,urban
            communities,urban dwellers,urban planning,urban poor,urban
            population,urban
            sanitation,urbanization,utilities,Utilities,Utility
            managers,utility operations,utility services,utility
            staff,water coverage,water quality,water resource,water
            resources,Water Services,water supply,water tariff,water
            users,water Utilities
        </keywd>
        <owner>Water- Water and Sanit Prgrm (GWASP)</owner>
        <repnb>26610</repnb>
        <alt_title>
            Partenariats pour servir les populations
            urbaines pauvres : comptu rendu sommaire - atelier final du
            projet WUP n. 5, Abidjan, Cote d'Ivoire, du 19 au 21
            Novembre, 2001
        </alt_title>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Strategy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wastewater Collection and Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Basic Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>On-site Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Marketing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Management of Public Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Finance Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Finances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Economics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Economics &amp; Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Planning and City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Strategic Planning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Planning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Planning Strategy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Planning and Design</ml:concept><ml:concept>Town Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Communities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water, Sanitation and Hygiene</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sewerage</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Adaptation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Strategic Urban Planning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>