<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>,e,r upp,UP           International Conference on Water&#13;
0,        2Supply and Sanitation for Small Towns&#13;
0* t1gf,f,                       and Multi-Village Schemes&#13;
£ | ° Addis-Ababa, Ethiopia&#13;
11-15 june 2002&#13;
Small Towns, Special Challenge&#13;
- "-&lt;1 26617&#13;
I                     iw  &#13;
~~ Wa 0 : .t A-\~~~~~~~~~~~~t &#13;
___ I Jf         I _ tf 9 '   _ "A&#13;
,2     4&#13;
U~~~~L&#13;
Water and   World Bank     Mistr of    Bank-Netherlands  World Bank&#13;
Sanitation Program         WtrRsucsWater Partnership  Institute&#13;
Ethiopia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
|Internationl Conference on Wafer Suppy and Sanitation for Small Towns and Multi-Villoge Schemes&#13;
ACRONYMS AND ABBREVIATIONS&#13;
AG      Attorney General&#13;
BNWP Bank Netherlands Water Partnership&#13;
BOO     Build Own Operate&#13;
BOT     Build Operate Transfer&#13;
CBO     Community Based Organization&#13;
CLG     Community Liaison Group - Malawi&#13;
CO      Constructor Operator&#13;
CSA     Central Statistical Authority - Ethiopia&#13;
CTB     Central Tender Board&#13;
DEM     Directorate of Operations and Maintenance&#13;
DHH     Direction d'Hydraulique Humaine - Cote d'lvoire&#13;
DRA     Demand Responsive Approach&#13;
DWD     Directorate of Water Development&#13;
EU      European Union&#13;
GNP     Gross National Product&#13;
GWC     Ghana Water Company&#13;
HIPC    Highly Indebted Poor Countries&#13;
IDA     International Development Association&#13;
IWE     Institute of Water and Environment (United Kingdom)&#13;
KfW     Kreditanstalt for Wiederaufbau (German Development Agency)&#13;
LA      Local Authority&#13;
MDG     Millennium Development Goals&#13;
MWR     Ministry of Water Resources of Ethiopia&#13;
NGO     Non Governmental Organization&#13;
NRWB North Region Water Board - Malawi&#13;
O&amp;M     Operations and Maintenance&#13;
PLC     Private Limited Company&#13;
PLC     Public Limited Company&#13;
PO      Private Operator&#13;
PPIAF   Public Private Infrastructure Advisory Facility&#13;
PPP     Public-Private Partnership&#13;
PSP     Private Sector Participation&#13;
RWSB    Regional Water Boards&#13;
RWSS    Rural Water Supply and Sanitation&#13;
SHC     State Asset Holding Company&#13;
ST      Small Town&#13;
WEDC Water, Engineering and Development Centre&#13;
WFI     Water Fund Indonesia&#13;
WSC     Water Supply Company&#13;
WSS     Water Supply and Sanitation&#13;
WTP     Willingness to Pay&#13;
12 * Small Towns Special Challenges&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Intemational Conference on Water Suppy and Sanitation for Small Towns and Multi-Village Schemes&#13;
,xr Supp/,,&#13;
o 'l&#13;
Addis Ababa, Ethiopia&#13;
11-15 June, 2002&#13;
Small Towns, Special Challenges&#13;
The Addis Ababa Conference on "Water Supply          thedevelopmentofasanitaionstrategyinsmalltowns&#13;
and Sanitation (WSS) Services for Small Towns and  *  To identify priorities for further learning, and to&#13;
Multi-Village Schemes" was the first international    use the Addis Ababa conference as a launch pad&#13;
meeting dedicated entirely to small town and multi-  for the BNWP Town WSS Initiative which will&#13;
village schemes. This Conference followed the first   provide recommendations and guidance to task&#13;
regional conferences on this topic sponsored by      managers and governments concerned with small&#13;
French Cooperation in Ouagadougou in 1 998 and       town WSS.&#13;
in Nouakchott in 2001. The Conference drew more&#13;
than 200 practitioners from all continents; about  Ethiopia moving towards a Programmatic&#13;
70% of them from Africa; and the majority with    Approach to Water Sector Development&#13;
over 1 5 years of experience in water and         Addis Ababa provided an ideal backdrop to the&#13;
sanitation. The five-day Conference was hosted by  conference. Water supply and sanitation is at the heart&#13;
the Government of Ethiopia through the Ministry   of Ethiopia's developmentagenda, including over 600&#13;
of Water Resources (MWR) and sponsored by the     small towns earmarked for improvement and extension&#13;
World Bank, the Water and Sanitation Program and  of WSS services. The sector strategy is based on&#13;
the World Bank Institute, as well as the UK       decentralization and local cost recovery for urban&#13;
Government and the Bank-Netherlands-Water-        systems. It supports the shif to a programmatic approach&#13;
Partnership (BNWP).                              to sector development.&#13;
Objectives and Expectations                       Global Overview&#13;
The goal of the Addis Conference was to provide water  The global consensus on the need to improve access to&#13;
and sanitation specialists with the unique perspective  WSS services is reflected in the Millennium Development&#13;
needed to meet the challenge of improved WSS services  Goals (MDG) which specifically call for: (a) by 2015,&#13;
for small towns.                                  reducing by half the proportion of people without&#13;
sustainable access to safe drinking water and to basic&#13;
The objectives and expectations for the conference were:  sanitation; and, (b) by 2020, to ensure that 100 million&#13;
*  To share global experience, build a community of  slum dwellers have access to improved sanitation. These&#13;
interested professionals, and start a knowledge  are daunting targets considering that 1 . billion people&#13;
network focused on small town WSS             are without access to safe drinking water and that 2.4&#13;
*  To review and enrich our understanding of the  billion do not have access to improved sanitation.&#13;
ingredients for success in small town water supply&#13;
*  To better understand the needs of small towns for  The MDG for water supply implies a 70% increase&#13;
professional support and the options to access  in annual investments from the current average&#13;
the required financial and technical expertise  level of US$15 billion to US$25 billion. Business&#13;
*  To identify tools of the trade that address    as usual will not do. Countries will have to find&#13;
professional support needs and build local capacity  new ways of mobilizing resources for the WSS&#13;
*  Tobuildknowledgeonkeyissuesandapproachesfor    sector in particular from the private sector.&#13;
Small Towns Speciol Challenges * 31&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
|International Canlerence on Water Suppy ahd Sanitation for Small Towns and Multi-Village Schemes&#13;
Equally important will be measures to tackle   As urbanization progresses, the number of&#13;
gaps in knowledge, policies and capacity. The  small towns (ST; population of 3000 to 30,000)&#13;
Addis Ababa    conference provided    an        increases. While their number rose rapidly, the&#13;
opportunity to address these issues in the      proportion of towns without improved water&#13;
context of small towns.                        supply services has doubled over the lost twenty&#13;
The Special Challenge of Small Towns           years (see Box 1).&#13;
As a rule small towns have "fallen between the&#13;
AsignificantpartofthechallengeofimprovedWSS     cracks" because they are neither an attractive&#13;
services will have to be met in small towns, which  market for urban utilities, nor are they within&#13;
account globally for about one billion people in a  the scope rf interventions designed for rural&#13;
total of roughly 1 50,000 towns and small       communities. The strong demand for piped&#13;
settlements.                                   comniis Th.togdmn                 o  ie&#13;
systems has led local authorities, communities&#13;
Sector planners, policy makers and communities  and private entrepreneurs to take initiatives to&#13;
face specic.l chplic                           develop and manage such systems, in many&#13;
face special challenges when it comes to WSS    instances outside a formal policy framework.&#13;
services for small towns. Water supply systems&#13;
for small towns can be characterized as follows:  The vast range of institutional models illustrated&#13;
*  They are sufficiently large and dense to    by the case studies reviewed by Conference&#13;
benefit from economies of scale and higher  showed the resourcefulness of local actors as&#13;
levels of services offered by piped systems;  well as their limitations and the constraints&#13;
*  The are too large and complex to be         under which they operate. ST Management&#13;
operated by communities;&#13;
operated by communities-         models fall Into two main types:&#13;
*  They are too small and dispersed to be      mdl alit w         antps&#13;
, They are too small and dispersed to be0*  Direct management by local authorities or&#13;
profitably managed by a conventional            by communities employing their own staff;&#13;
urban water utility                              ,    Nlrlt &#13;
urThey "ca'te  goiity alone", and need         often a "default" scenario; and,&#13;
*  They "can't go it alone", and need          *   Delegated management to a professional&#13;
specialized professional support in             operator either local or regional/national;&#13;
particular to train operators and to prepare   with capacity requirements and risks&#13;
and update business plans, expansion            increasing with the scope of delegation and&#13;
programs and efficiency strategies.            with the size of the systems.&#13;
Inability to access professional skills and&#13;
"Fill Between the Cracks"           precarious governance structure have been&#13;
Box 1: ST   Flil Besveen the CracKs           recurring weaknesses.&#13;
During the 90's the gap (localities without a  The great variety of approaches and the&#13;
proper water supply) increased in small       dynamism     of lao   neactin on the&#13;
towns (3,000 to 30,000 inhabitants)           dynamism of local communities, acting on their&#13;
own or in groups, points out the importance of:&#13;
(i) learning from the emerging experience; and,&#13;
__0%                                   (ii) adapting to local conditions and capacities.&#13;
80%mi     _     -Pp                     Hence the importance of gaining a bottom-up&#13;
40     %-_ wh&amp;lly                       understanding of what are the factors&#13;
20%                                     underpinning successful water supply services&#13;
0%  1     p                            for small towns.&#13;
___________________          The Ingredients for Success&#13;
1990's snapshot&#13;
. 0om ,1 _Success for water supply and sanitation&#13;
80%                                        meons good quality, affordable ond&#13;
6 ot.* IP                        sustained services for all&#13;
20%&#13;
oM.                                    The Conference reviewed and refined the findings of&#13;
research concerning key ingredients for success for&#13;
WSS services in small towns. These are summarized&#13;
below together with the outcome of the Conference&#13;
14  Small Towns Special Challenges    =_c_&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
X                              International Conference on Water Suppy and Sanitation for Small Towns and Multi-Village Scme&#13;
deliberations concerning the policies, practices and   for: (i) training their own staff (or the staff of their&#13;
tools through which they can be developed and          small scale operator) in routine functions; and, (ii)&#13;
sustained:                                             supporting non-routine functions: i.e. financial&#13;
management, business planning, tariff setting,&#13;
1) Financial and managerial autonomy                   expansion planning, efficiency improvement,&#13;
Financial and managerial autonomy is essential to      trouble shooting and communication, customer&#13;
encourage entrepreneurship and investment.             relations (Box 3).&#13;
Autonomy for ST WSS means:&#13;
*   Control of operations (staffing, connection and             Box 3: Professional Support&#13;
disconnection, billing)                                  Routine Operations   Specialist Skills&#13;
*   Own bank account, ring fencing, no transfer to      -      Meter reading     S Financial mgt training&#13;
town budget;                                             *&#13;
*   Tariffs set in light of local conditions;               * Billing            * Business planning&#13;
*   The flexibility to adapt service level to demand;    co  * Revenue collection  * Tariff setting&#13;
*   Ability to invest to adapt and develop system            * Accounting        * Customer relations&#13;
* Routine O&amp;M        * Technical training&#13;
Autonomy rests on: (i) financial viability; (ii)             . Houseconnections   * Expansion planning&#13;
stakeholders support; (iii) protection from political          S&#13;
interference through community oversight (Box 2).                                   Ergen    repaira&#13;
o                 * ~~~~~~~Emergency repair 8 ad&#13;
Box 2:How     to establish and maintain                                           fhoci dvise&#13;
autonomy                                               e~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ Efficiency improvement&#13;
autonomy&#13;
* By designing system to be financially viable        The country cases showed the range of strategies&#13;
* By building support among all stakeholders for      adopted by STs to access the expertise and the&#13;
the principles of autonomy                         professional support that they require, ranging from&#13;
* By building the professional competence of the      cost sharing to more formal aggregation whereby one&#13;
service provider                                   operator is given responsibilities for the WSS systems&#13;
By ensuring protection from political interference  of a number of towns. Aggregation strategies also&#13;
through community oversight                        allow STs to strengthen their bargaining power with&#13;
* Through user oversight and independent              suppliers and operators.&#13;
auditing                                           spiesaaoeaos&#13;
Professional support comes at a price - customers/&#13;
2) Transparency and accountability                     community must be willing to support related expenses.&#13;
Transparency and accountability are critical to gain   Sharing of professional resources between&#13;
and maintain the trust of users and investors. They    neighbouring towns results in economies of scale.&#13;
are founded on: (i) clear roles and responsibilities; (ii)  Guidelines and tools are needed for a range of&#13;
independent audit a nd monitoring; and, (iii) disclosure  functions including:&#13;
of information. They are particularly important in     *   establishing and regulating professional standards&#13;
situations where there is a monopoly in service        *   procurement and contracting of management and&#13;
provision.                                                 support services&#13;
*   business planning,&#13;
Transparency. and accountability are key to good       *   cost effective design&#13;
governance but require good information flows and      *   tariff setting and review process, billing etc.&#13;
consultation. Customers must be aware of their rights&#13;
and oversight boards need the qualification, the       The three ingredients for success outlined above deal&#13;
capacity and the tools to exert their responsibilities.  essentially with management and operational&#13;
The latter include most importantly by-laws, internal  responsibilities. They apply to the whole range of&#13;
rules, accounting systems, performance backed          management models although they are much more&#13;
contracts for operators and monitoring systems.        easily achieved and sustained in situations where the&#13;
oversight function is clearly separated from day-&#13;
3) Professional support.                               to-day management. Hence the trend for delegating&#13;
The need for outside professional support for tasks    system management to private professional operators&#13;
beyond routine functions is a defining characteristic  through contracts. Limitations include: (i) inability to&#13;
of ST WSS systems. STs need professional support       attract competent operators; (ii) lack of capacity in&#13;
Small Towns Special Challenges *_S&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
fjternatianal Conference on Wafer Suppy and Sanitatioe Far Small T_wn and mMulti-Village Schemes&#13;
drawing up and regulating the contract; and, (iii) lack&#13;
of customer confidence.                               Box 4: Supportive policies and laws&#13;
are needed for ST Water&#13;
The next two ingredients for success deal with the             Supply&#13;
enabling environment for WSS services in STs.         * To ensure stable access to and protection&#13;
of water resources&#13;
4) Competition                                        * To legitimize the role of local actors in ST&#13;
Competition keeps prices down, brings quality up,        WSS services&#13;
fosters innovations and builds capacity. STs offer a range  * To establish a framework for delegated&#13;
of opportunities for local firms. Although network-based  management and for the involvement of&#13;
water supply systems serving small towns share some      the private sector in operations and&#13;
financing&#13;
of the "natural monopoly' characteristics of urban water  * To establish cost recovery principle for&#13;
utilities, they are more amenable to competition. The    water services&#13;
large range of sizes of small towns found in most     * To define regulatory mechanisms&#13;
countries, and the extent to which they are clustered&#13;
together, creates multiple market niches attractive to&#13;
different sizes/types of operators.                 that: (i) regulation is costly and would ultimately be&#13;
supported by the users; and, (ii) in most countries, the&#13;
Competition for the market requires: (i) supportive legal  concept of independent regulation is not yet well&#13;
and regulatory environment (open entry and minimum  established and would in any case be difficult to apply&#13;
restrictions on service areas); (ii) attractive contracts in  to a lorge number of small decentralized systems.&#13;
scope, duration and size (through pooled procurement,  Whether the operator is a private or public body, simple&#13;
clustering and aggregation); and, (iii) a competitive  contracts in which responsibilities, payments terms and&#13;
procurement process.                                incentives are clearly set out, underpin regulation.&#13;
Competition in the market can be fostered by: (i)   The nexttwo ingredients for success cover services and&#13;
alternative services (tankers, vendors, private stand posts,  system development.&#13;
reselling); (ii) limited contract duration and re-bidding;&#13;
(iii) support to innovations; and, (iv) benchmarking.  6) Responding to the demand&#13;
Approaching ST WSS with the basic goal of offering&#13;
5) Legal framework and regulation                   services that customers want and are ready to pay for&#13;
As far as small towns are concerned the central purpose  is a powerful ingredient for success. At the system level&#13;
of national laws and regulations is to establish and  demand responsive approaches lead to higher cost&#13;
enforce "rules of the game" that foster fair and    recovery and internal cash generation ensuring&#13;
sustainable relationships among local actors. The   sustainability and allowing further development. At the&#13;
challenge is to translate policies into country-wide norms  country/program level demand responsiveness allows&#13;
and regulations without stifling local initiatives.  for more efficient use of public funds.&#13;
The primary focus of regulation is to reconcile the  Development projects (supported by government/&#13;
imperative of financial viability with the need to protect  external aid or NGO's) can foster demand responsive&#13;
the customers. The regulatory functions for ST WSS  approach by: (i) allowing flexibility concerning design&#13;
services should focus on process and quality standards  standards, technology choices and services levels; (ii)&#13;
and on guidelines for tariff setting and revisions  providing for informed choice by households and&#13;
(periodicity, information, consultations and recourse and  communities; and, (iii) encouraging competition.&#13;
arbitration).&#13;
7) Incentives for expansion&#13;
Effective regulation is enhanced by: (i) communityoversight;  operators of ST WSS systems are keen to develop their&#13;
(ii) sound contracts and business plans; (iii) open  distribution network thereby adding customers and sales.&#13;
communication and consultation mechanisms; and, (iii)  The issue for planners is to ensure that the proper&#13;
external auditing and benchmarking.                 requisites are in place; essentially: (i) access to adequate&#13;
water resources; (ii) stable institutional/legal framework&#13;
The build up of regulatory capacity for ST WSS should  allowing fair return on investment; and, in most&#13;
be approached with limited objectives as a response to  situations, (iii) basic production and storage facilities&#13;
specific needs. The reasons for caution relate to the fact  built (or rehabilitated) with sufficient capacity.&#13;
6   Small Towns Special Challenges&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Internotional Conference on Water Suppy and Sanitation for Small Towns and Multi-Village Schemes&#13;
Incentives and facilitating factors for system expansion  Sanitation&#13;
include:&#13;
*   Access to financing in particular for household  The problems facing sanitation and public hygiene in&#13;
connections                                     small towns reflect the general state of sanitation in most&#13;
*   Pre-financing of private connections by the    developing countries; i.e. lack of awareness and low&#13;
operator and payment in monthly installments    demand; lack of policies and institutional leadership;&#13;
*   Limited regulatory or administrative restriction on  and, no financing.&#13;
service area; certification focused on quality and&#13;
safety                                          The starting point is for communities and households to&#13;
*   Freedom of initiative with limited approval    see the need for a clean and healthy environment.&#13;
requirements focused on quality and safety     The drive to improve sanitation in small towns should&#13;
*   Access to expertise and capacity for business  address the range of environmental issues: used water&#13;
planning and management                        and excreta disposal, solid waste management and&#13;
*   Incentives for expansion built in operator's   drainage, and should rest on a clear understanding of&#13;
contract                                        the respective role and responsibilities of households&#13;
*   Output based-aid to encourage expansion into   and the community.&#13;
less profitable areas&#13;
It is when future cities are still small towns that incipient&#13;
Equity and      services to     low-income           urban communities have the best opportunities to&#13;
groups                                               establish shared expectations and land-use planning&#13;
that will set them on the right environmental path. In&#13;
Rising tides lift all boats. In most countries poverty is  order to seize these opportunities small towns need:&#13;
prevalent in small towns and villages, therefore programs  *  A Vision of a clean and healthy environment&#13;
that target small towns respond to poverty reduction  *  A Policy reflecting the attitudes needed to carry&#13;
objectives. The first concern should therefore be to ensure  the vision, e.g. ART (Avoid, Reuse, and Treat waste)&#13;
that small towns have efficient and financially viable   and, thewill to implement it through advocacy, clear&#13;
water systems. Within this framework expansion and       institutional arrangements, standards, funding&#13;
demand responsiveness will foster broader access to      mechanisms and enforcement capacity&#13;
services for low-income households in particular through  *  A Priorityto mobilize communities and households&#13;
reselling, kiosks and community taps. The key point is  to take initiatives that can make sanitation a reality&#13;
to ensure that low-income households are recognized      and evolve their own local strategy to pursue their&#13;
as legitimate customers. As they grow, towns and cities  vision of a clean and healthy city.&#13;
would eventually require programs specifically directed&#13;
at services for the poor.                             Box 5: Roles and responsibilities sanitation&#13;
systems in Small Towns&#13;
Access to services for poor households can be supported    Guiding principles: Decentralization and autonomy&#13;
by: Ii) providing an element of grant for the initial                Sanitation Solid  Drainage Hygiene&#13;
investment so that tariffs remain affordable; (ii) pre-                       Waste          Promotion&#13;
financing "social" connections; and, (iii) ensuring the  Standards/&#13;
poor have a voice as stakeholders and customers.      Guidelines     LA      LA    [A        LA&#13;
Implementation  HH/PS   LA/PS LA/PS   LA/NGO&#13;
While communities and private operators seem able to  Polic/lisation  CG      CG    CG       CG&#13;
mobilize the resource needed for expanding small town      leilatiorI CG     I      C&#13;
LA = local authority  HH = Household&#13;
distribution networks, this is often not the case for the  PS = Private Sector  CG = Central Government&#13;
lumpy capital injection needed to build or rehabilitate  NGO = non-governmental organizations&#13;
the basic facilities (borehole, pump and elevated&#13;
reservoir).&#13;
This suggests that development of optimal financing   Guiding principles:&#13;
strategies is a critical element for the preparation of  -   Focus on sanitation services from the&#13;
sector programs that seek to maximize the poverty            household's point of view,&#13;
impact of public funds (budget and external aid)         -   Achieve more effective advocacy through&#13;
allocated to the water sector.                               social marketing and health and hygiene&#13;
promotion&#13;
|Small Towns Special Challenges * 71&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Interntioncal Conference on Water SuppyandSianitftion for Small Towns and Multi-Village-Schemes  -- -  X _&#13;
- Make local authorities responsible for organizing  to pay, household demand and service levels (see&#13;
sanitation and environmental services and clarify  Box 6). The value of the BP process is that it treats&#13;
the supporting responsibilities of sector agencies  the WSS system as a whole focusing on the&#13;
(Box 5).                                      continuity of its operations. It avoids the&#13;
- Set up funding mechanisms that reflect community  shortcoming of the project driven approach&#13;
and household responsibilities and ensure at  centered on the appraisal and funding of capital&#13;
least recovery of O&amp;M.                        expenditure.&#13;
- Foster opportunities for private sector&#13;
initiatives.                                  The Contingent Valuation Methodology (CVM)&#13;
allows planners to assess the willingness to pay&#13;
Tools of the Trade                               for selected level of services; typically, stand posts,&#13;
yard taps or shared connection and individual&#13;
Tools of the trade address professional support  connections . This information is essential to support&#13;
needs, and help build the capacity of local service  community participation and enable "informed&#13;
providers. They also   play a role in the        choice" at the household level as well as for the&#13;
implementation of sector policies and in investment  co ity as a hole.kWTP suveys provids the&#13;
decisions. The tools reviewed by the Conference  community as a wkole. WTP surveys provides the&#13;
arecistioned Thel toolsgretherwe   the keyference  necessary basis for projecting sales and revenues&#13;
are outlined below together with the key points  freautn        xaso      ln    n   o  etn&#13;
arsn  rm h  eae                               for evaluating expansion plans and for setting&#13;
arising from the debate,                        tariffs. The relative high cost of WTP tolls is likely&#13;
to  to come down as they are systematically applied&#13;
The Cost Effective Design tools allow planners to and aste local   ting pression buid&#13;
test the cost recovery potential of water systems  capdacity&#13;
and provides a basis to match system components  capocity.&#13;
and service levels to town size and affordable user  The fourth tool, billing systems, is critical for&#13;
charges.  It promotes cost effective design and  sustainability and autonomy. Small towns need&#13;
resulting financial viability. One of the striking  support in setting up and managing their billing&#13;
characteristics of small town water systems is that  and collection functions. The challenge is to keep&#13;
higher investment and higher service levels (e.g.  costs down in relation to the small revenue basis&#13;
more house connections and less households served  and to overcome the constraints arising from the&#13;
through stand-posts) usually lead to lower average  lack of trained personnel, the unavailability of&#13;
costs per liter, and hence lower tariff, because the  banking services, etc. Key points: metering is&#13;
revenue increase faster than investment and O&amp;M  indispensable as well as a clear responsibility for&#13;
costs.                                           each connection.&#13;
Box 6: Business Planing                The Conference stressed the critical role of tools of&#13;
(an iterative, rolling process)        the trade to support improvements in WSS systems&#13;
and to translate general policy principles into&#13;
Assess curren  &amp; operation                    practical guidelines. Tools need to be adapted to&#13;
operations   plan    Financia  Willingness   the context of each country. The dissemination and&#13;
Project  LTechnical    o      to p           adaptation of the four tools reviewed and the&#13;
demand   I design I                          development of additional tools and guidance&#13;
Agree.financing plan       material should be given priority in the follow-up&#13;
Agree financing plan       to the Conference.&#13;
Agree performance         Management and Contracting Options&#13;
|indicators for M&amp;E -1&#13;
Direct vs. delegated management&#13;
Understanding ST water systems require clarifying:&#13;
While the cost effective design tool models a range  Who owns the facilities? Who oversees the assets&#13;
of options, the Business Planning (BP) tool focuses  and supervises operations (water authority)? And&#13;
on the operations and financial results of a specific  who operates the facilities (water services&#13;
system. The BP tool models the operations of the  providers)?&#13;
system over time and year-by-year financial flows.&#13;
The BP tool pays particular attention to the     Ohen the responsibility for ensuring that services&#13;
parameters affecting revenues; namely willingness  are provided is interpreted as the responsibility for&#13;
8   Smons Special Challenges   _                                                            j&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Intemnational Conference on Water Suppy and Sanitation for Small Towns and Multi-WI/lage S~chieme&#13;
providing the services. As a result, town water      Private Public Partnership (PPP) for ST WSS&#13;
supplies are often managed directly by a public      Services&#13;
entity (see Box 7). which hires and directly manages  The unfolding worldwide movement toward PPP in the&#13;
its own staff. It is inherently difficult under direct  WSS sector has providedagrowing body of knowledge&#13;
public management to realize the ingredients for     and lessons on which to develop an understanding of&#13;
success.                                             how to pursue PPP for small towns WSS services.&#13;
Box 7: Management Types                    The first point is that in order to succeed PPP needs some&#13;
prerequisites - most importantly: commitment from all&#13;
Direct Management   Delegated Management       stakeholders based on good communication of the&#13;
changes that will be necessary to implement PPP. The&#13;
Ownership             |wnership              choice of contract has to rest on a realistic assessment of&#13;
Oversight              Oversight             the local context against the prerequisites for success&#13;
C Operations                  ontrct         corresponding to each option ( see Box 8).&#13;
Staff                 Lprtioor                  Box 8: PPP for WS Service Mapping&#13;
Option Prerequisites&#13;
As they expand and become more complex, ST WSS             Requirement Political  CosAcovering Regulatory  Good&#13;
systems evolve from the so-called "default option" -    Option     Connitment Ter&amp;  Fromewok  Information&#13;
direct public management or informal delegation -       Service Contract  Low  Low  Low       Low&#13;
towards delegated management and contracting            Manogement&#13;
options and management models under which               Contract    Moderote  Moderate Low    Low&#13;
"professional support" is provided with increasing     LeoseAffermage  High  High   Moderate  Moderate&#13;
levels of private sector involvement in management      BOT         Moderate  High  High      High&#13;
and financing.                                          Concession  High    High    High      Hi gh&#13;
There are two types of contacts full service and&#13;
specialized services. Full service operators "offer one  The second point concerns the fact that designing a&#13;
stop shopping" where both routine and specialized    successful PSP transaction is essentially about&#13;
services are provided by the operator. In the        understandingrisks,tryingtoreducethemandmakesure&#13;
specialized service model routine operations and     thattheyareallocated in linewithcompetence, capacity&#13;
specialized services are offered separately. An      and ability to control.&#13;
example of the specialized services model is&#13;
franchising, where the fronchisor offers specialized  While the principle of private sector participation in the&#13;
services to a local operator, the franchisee for a   development and provision of WSS services is broadly&#13;
share of the revenue.                                accepted, PPP could not be considered as the exclusive&#13;
avenue for improved services. Most countries still lack&#13;
Aggregation                                          the legal framework, the regulatory capacity and the&#13;
Aggregation is critical to share cost and build a sufficient  knowledge basis to benefit fully from PPP. Nonetheless,&#13;
demand for specialized services and support. This    there is no doubt that PPP introduces opportunities for&#13;
applies also to smaller towns (2,000 to 10,000) for  entrepreneurs in the water sector, and that this builds&#13;
which costs can be reduced by directly employing their  capacity. PPP contracts set performance targets and in-&#13;
own staff through performonce agreements or by       troduce checks and balances between the oversight body&#13;
contracting a private operator from within the       and the operator. Bidding for contracts promotes com-&#13;
community.                                           petition. The overall impact is to foster productivity and&#13;
fair pricing.&#13;
Aggregation models differ by the extend to which their&#13;
association is institutionalized. Towns can:         The franchising approach as applied to WSS services,&#13;
- Form a formal association or company that contracts  would have an experienced operator, the Fronchisor,&#13;
a full service operator                           render services and transfer business know-how to a&#13;
- Join together for bidding, but sign separate contracts, or  smaller water company, the Franchisee (see Box 9). The&#13;
- Enter into separate contracts with established     Franchisor would be responsible for monitoring quality&#13;
operators in a given areas.                       of performance of its Franchisees. Although there are&#13;
Small Towns Special Challenges * 91&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Internationference on         and Sanation  Small Towns and Multi-Village Schemes  = X&#13;
just few instances where the franchising approach have  aggregation and delegation strategies with local&#13;
been implemented, in the water sector, the Conference  accountability.&#13;
considered that it had considerable potential for WSS&#13;
services for small towns.                             Governments and their development partners should&#13;
recognize that small towns and multi-village schemes&#13;
Box 9: Franchising                       represent special challenge and opportunities that&#13;
Under the franchise      necessitate development or adaptation of a supportive&#13;
'brand' Franchisees    policy, legal and regulatory frameworks as well as&#13;
Frascisor            receives business       programs. Sector policies related to small towns must be&#13;
'know-how' from                  Sco           eae      ml&#13;
,$ F  A    m            Fronchisor and         broad enough to allow a range of alternative&#13;
provides services /&#13;
products to customers  management arrangements to emerge and evolve in&#13;
Franchisor monitors    response to local demands and capacity.&#13;
service to customers&#13;
*customers pay&#13;
Fra.Chstoees forproducts       Box 10. Processes of Change&#13;
and services ond a % is&#13;
passed back to the          From default options to new approaches&#13;
fronchisor as a royolty&#13;
payment                                                   ,        I Voo&#13;
Franchising - a business methodology, based on the duplication     * publicwaterpicq *-. frionchising&#13;
of success, between two or more separate legal business entities&#13;
operating under the same brand name.                              /                     concession&#13;
ca   /                S~~~~~~~~~affermage/leasJ &#13;
In conclusion,                                                                            /&#13;
*   Larger towns could contract with a full water service&#13;
operator to provide both routine and specialized             * direct public mngt&#13;
services, whilst smaller towns would use local                  Public               Private&#13;
operators, public or private, supplemented by                              Manogement&#13;
specialist service providers.&#13;
*   Towns benefit from   competition to counter&#13;
monopolies that build capacity and improve service;  The proper focus of programs for the development of&#13;
and                                                WSS services for small towns would be to guide and&#13;
*   Towns need to join together in one way or another  support local initiatives. The learning and piloting can&#13;
(aggregate) to create viable units capable of      be supported by "retail" projects dealing with a limited&#13;
securing the necessary professional support.       number of towns, leading to a more systemic approach&#13;
based on sector-wide programs better suited to deal with&#13;
The Way Forward - a 'Change Process'                   institutional issues and financing mechanisms.&#13;
The change process is driven by the fact that, as small  Programs to support the change process for should be&#13;
towns grow and as theirWSS system expand and become    guided by the following principles:&#13;
more complex "default options" are not good enough.   - To nurture and support the initiatives of local actors&#13;
The lessons from the cases is that community management  through flexible response and support mechanisms;&#13;
has notable strengths, but is not adequate to address  - To emphasize capacity building based on tools and&#13;
long term sustainability. Beyond 5,000 inhabitants,      practices reflecting local experience;&#13;
community management needs to evolve toward more       - To foster country level learning, knowledge sharing and&#13;
institutionalized models involving water boards with a   networking among scattered actors involved in STWSS&#13;
legal basis and the capacity to enter into formal contracts.  services.&#13;
The ingredients for success provide a useful framework  Priorifies for further leaming&#13;
to assess the performance of town water supply systems  Developing and improving ST WSS service should be&#13;
and to identify their needs for professional support and  approached as a learning process at all levels:&#13;
to map options to foster efficiency and to support     communities, country and global/regional; reying on case&#13;
continued expansion.                                  studies, models, good practices, tools and guidelines&#13;
The Conference stressed the need for further knowledge&#13;
Public-private-partnerships introduce manyadvantages,  development and networking on issues related to WSS&#13;
Not least in building local business opportunities and  services far ST with special attention to sanitation and to&#13;
better career prospects. The challenge is to balance   services for low-inc gu a.n            -om mnitaie which&#13;
* SmallTwsservices for low-income groups and communifies which&#13;
riO * Smal`l ovvns Special Challenges&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- i-~        - --   I::-ftirinational Conference on Water Suppy and Sanitation for Small Towns and Multi-Village Schemes&#13;
should be a guiding pre-occupation for all knowledge   Concluding     Statement&#13;
development activities.&#13;
The Addis Conference resolved that the above findings&#13;
In order to support the development and the evolution of  and recommendations provide useful guidance to&#13;
ST WS systems, policy makers, planners as well as      recognize and address the special challenge of&#13;
operators will need to develop their understanding of:  improving WSS services for small towns and multi-&#13;
- How best to structure the contractual relationships  village systems.&#13;
between operators and small towns water board;&#13;
- How to foster aggregation and which aggregation     The Conference mandated the organizers to disseminate&#13;
models are best adapted to various situations and   its findings and recommendations to all actors engaged&#13;
categories of towns                                in the water and sanitation sectors including knowledge&#13;
- How to approach capacity building of oversight boards  organizations and development agencies as well as&#13;
and local operators; and,                          organizations focused on local authorities.&#13;
- How to nurture the emergence of specialized WSS&#13;
enterprises.                                       The Conference mandated the organizing partners to&#13;
They also need to leam more about the following specific  pursue the learning agenda outlined above and to&#13;
issues: (i) tariff setting and cross subsidies, (ii) household  organize within the next three years, i.e. by 2005,&#13;
connection policies, (iii) financing and risk mitigation, (iv)  regional or global consultations on small towns WSS&#13;
regulation, and (v) water resource management.        issues preferably in partnership with organizations&#13;
serving municipalities and local authorities. The&#13;
The Conference stressed the importance of networking   BNWP town water initiative was welcomed as an&#13;
(web-based activities, workshops, help-desk), help-desk,  opportunity for further development of the ideas&#13;
training and databases. They specifically recommended  presented during the conference and the priorities&#13;
a follow-up e-conference on ST WSS services in mid-2003.  fr furter   erning. t&#13;
Participants from West Africa resolved to form a regional  for further learning.&#13;
network during the Conference.                        The Conference mandated the organizers to express&#13;
the gratitude of all the participants to the Government&#13;
Box 1 1: WBNP Initiative for Town WSS               of Ethiopia and in particular to H.E Ato Shiferaw Jarso&#13;
The Town WSS Initiative is BNWP largest program. It   and the staff of the Ministry of Water Resources, for&#13;
searches for optimal arrangements between demand and  hosting the Conference. The Conference thanks the&#13;
supply, between revenue base and operator size. The   organizers and the supporting partners for their&#13;
program will:                                         initiative and for the good conduct of the proceedings.&#13;
1. Prepare best practice notes to facilitate sector dialogue&#13;
and improve the design and implementation of town&#13;
water and sanitation programs.&#13;
2. Identify, assess and field test professional support and&#13;
aggregation options in three to five countries in East&#13;
Asia, Central Asia, South Asia, Africa and/or Latin&#13;
America.&#13;
3. Develop practical "tools of the trade' to help&#13;
practitioners improve town water supply.&#13;
4. Disseminate results&#13;
BNWP: Bank Netherlands Water Partnership&#13;
jiansens@warldbank.org&#13;
The Bank-Netherlands Water Partnership (see Box 11)&#13;
continued support to the Small Town WSS initiative will:&#13;
- consolidate what has been learned,&#13;
-   investigate aggregation from the perspective of towns&#13;
and private operators,&#13;
-   develop practical tools of the trade that build capacity,&#13;
-   assist selected countfies that are conmitted to building&#13;
state of the art tcvn water and sanitation programs, and&#13;
-   disseminate information and support continued&#13;
consultation.&#13;
Small Towns Special Chalenges * 11|&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
,,   t1,  .   !  '  &#13;
N~  o&#13;
~~~~~h\~~~~~~   _    &#13;
V ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ 7' I- '   ''    '&#13;
ii ~ ~    ~     &lt;is ' i7'           E&#13;
lw,./ , ~ &#13;
I~~~tX-8  &gt; -//S7 _ &#13;
~~~~.: j/S,,A............ &#13;
1~. .X2117_ &#13;
W '*   w;   1- 4 a":   . .   m   8   S~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
4;nC                           t'D   't  ', &#13;
_ _ _''__ _\             '__ _ _ _  0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="2498957">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2002/06/2498957/international-conference-water-supply-sanitation-small-towns-multi-village-schemes-small-towns-special-challenge-conference-statement
        </url>
        <availablein>French,English</availablein>
        <fullavailablein>
            <available_in lang="French" entityid="000160016_20040329151842" node_id="2498957"/>
        </fullavailablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2002/06/2498957/international-conference-water-supply-sanitation-small-towns-multi-village-schemes-small-towns-special-challenge-conference-statement</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2002/06/2498957/international-conference-water-supply-sanitation-small-towns-multi-village-schemes-small-towns-special-challenge-conference-statement</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/09/23/000094946_03090304002988/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/09/23/000094946_03090304002988/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2003-09-23T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2002-06-30T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            International Conference on Water Supply
            and Sanitation for Small Towns and Multi-village Schemes -
            Small Towns, Special Challenge : Conference Statement
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            In 1999, the Bank's Rural Water
            Supply and Sanitation (WSS) Thematic Group, in collaboration
            with the Water and Sanitation Program (WSP), launched a
            global small towns initiative to study, and document
            innovative management models that provide good quality,
            affordable services that are sustainable, and can be
            expanded to meet demand. This effort led to simultaneous
            E-Conferences, sharing a wealth of information about local
            initiatives, aimed at improving water services in small
            towns. Herewith are the proceedings of the International
            Conference on Water Supply and Sanitation for Small Towns
            and Multi-village Schemes - Conference Summary V. 1 - where
            practitioners reviewed case studies, and shared experiences.
            The proceedings are structured as follows: 1) the Conference
            statement attempts to capture the broad, shared
            understanding developed through the presentations/exchanges;
            2) Volume 1 - Conference Summary - expands on the summary,
            and includes selected annexes on special sessions, and
            provides participant feedback; 3) Volume 2 - Presentations -
            includes the complete set of presentations, and will be made
            available electronically; and 4) Volume 3 - Posters - will
            be a compendium of posters, likewise to V. 2, accessible electronically.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            International Conference on Water Supply and
            Sanitation for Small Towns and Multi-village Schemes - Small
            Towns, Special Challenge : Conference Statement
        </docna>
        <display_title>International Conference on Water
            Supply and Sanitation for Small Towns and Multi-village
            Schemes - Small Towns, Special Challenge : Conference Statement</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2002/06/2498957/international-conference-water-supply-sanitation-small-towns-multi-village-schemes-small-towns-special-challenge-conference-statement</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>UNDP-Water &amp; Sanitation Program</docty>
        <subtopic>Town Water Supply and Sanitation,Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Housing &amp; Human Habitats,Water Supply and Sanitation Governance
            and Institutions,Health Economics &amp; Finance</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Health, Nutrition and Population</teratopic>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000094946_03090304002988</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Sanitation,Water supply</subsc>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Health, Nutrition and Population</historic_topic>
        <sectr>Water, sanitation and flood protection</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Water supply &amp; sanitation; Conference
            reports; Proceedings; Township &amp; village enterprises;
            Water supply systems; Service delivery; Affordable access
            services; Water tariffs; Competitiveness; Policy framework;
            Legal &amp; regulatory framework; Operations &amp;
            maintenance; Innovations; Management operations
            Access to expertise,access to safe drinking
            water,Access to services,adequate water,adequate water
            resources,Aggregation models,Asset Holding Company,capacity
            building,Central Government,cities,community
            management,community participation,connection
            policies,Contingent Valuation,contract duration,cost
            recovery,cost sharing,Customer
            relations,disclosure,economies of scale,environmental
            issues,excreta disposal,financial viability,full service
            operator,Full service operators,GNP,Gross National
            Product,guidelines for tariff setting,house
            connections,households,hygiene,hygiene
            promotion,income,inhabitants,Larger towns,local
            authorities,local capacity,local communities,local
            operator,local operators,low-income households,Meter
            reading,monopolies,municipalities,non-governmental
            organizations,policy makers,Private Operator,private
            operators,Private Public Partnership,Private
            Sector,productivity,public management,quality
            standards,regulatory capacity,regulatory
            frameworks,regulatory mechanisms,Rural Water,Rural Water
            Supply,safety,sanitation services,sanitation systems,service
            provider,service providers,settlements,small
            communities,Small Town,small town water,small town water
            supply,small town water systems,Small Towns,solid
            waste,solid waste management,tariff setting,town water
            initiative,urban communities,urban utilities,urban
            water,urbanization,villages,water authority,Water
            Board,Water Boards,Water Company,Water Development,Water
            Partnership,water resource,water resource management,Water
            Resources,Water Sector,Water Sector Development,water
            service,water services,Water Supply,Water Supply
            Company,water supply services,Water supply systems,water
            systems,water utility,Willingness to Pay,WTP
        </keywd>
        <owner>WUDWS</owner>
        <repnb>26617</repnb>
        <alt_title>
            Resume des Actes de la Conference
            Internationale sur l'Approvisionnement en Eau et
            l'Assainissement des petites villes et systems
            multi-villages : Petites Villes, Grands Defis
        </alt_title>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Science and Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Infrastructure (Water and Wastewater)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Water and Small Town Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Organisational Structures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Organizational Assessments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Basic Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>On-site Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Marketing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>HIPC</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deconcentration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delegation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Devolution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sub-National Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subnational Government and Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Checks on Executive Power</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen User Satisfaction Survey</ml:concept><ml:concept>Independent Commissions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ombudsmen</ml:concept><ml:concept>Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Parliament</ml:concept><ml:concept>Procurement Complaints Review Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supreme Audit Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Town Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Engineering</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural &amp; Small Town Water &amp; Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water, Sanitation and Hygiene</ml:concept><ml:concept>Support Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Policy Framework</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance Structures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Heavily Indebted Poor Countries (HIPC)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Administrative Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Accountability Mechanisms</ml:concept><ml:concept>Drainage</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>