<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>The Extent of Poverty in Latin America&#13;
Oscar Altimir&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 522&#13;
SWP522 5&#13;
~~LF~~LE. COPY......&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
WORLD BANK STAFF WORKING PAPERS&#13;
Number 522&#13;
The Extent of Poverty in Latin America&#13;
Oscar Altimir&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Washington, D.C., U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Copyright 0 1982&#13;
The International Bank for Reconstruction&#13;
and Development / THE WORLD BANK&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
All rights reserved&#13;
Manufactured in the United States of America&#13;
This is a working document published informally by The World Bank. To&#13;
present the results of research with the least possible delay, the typescript has&#13;
not been prepared in accordance with the procedures appropriate to formal&#13;
printed texts, and The World Bank accepts no responsibility for errors. The&#13;
publication is supplied at a token charge to defray part of the cost of&#13;
manufacture and distribution.&#13;
The views and interpretations in this document are those of the author(s) and&#13;
should not be attributed to The World Bank, to its affiliated organizations, or to&#13;
any individual acting on their behalf. Any maps used have been prepared&#13;
solely for the convenience of the readers; the denominations used and the&#13;
boundaries shown do not imply, on the part of The World Bank and its&#13;
affiliates, any judgment on the legal status of any territory or any endorsement&#13;
or acceptance of such boundaries.&#13;
The full range of The World Bank publications is described in the Catalog of&#13;
World Bank Publications; the continuing research program of the Bank is outlined&#13;
in World Bank Research Program: Abstracts of Current Studies. Both booklets are&#13;
updated annually; the most recent edition of each is available without charge&#13;
from the Publications Distribution Unit of the Bank in Washington or from the&#13;
European Office of the Bank, 66, avenue d'Iena, 75116 Paris, France.&#13;
Library of e'ongress Cataloginig i. p'ublic .tioni Dalta&#13;
Altimir, Oscar.&#13;
The extent of poverty in Latin America.&#13;
(World Bank staff working papers ; no. 522)&#13;
"March 1982."&#13;
Translation of: La dimension de la pobreza en&#13;
Ame'rica Latina.&#13;
Bibliography: p.&#13;
1. Poor--Latin America.     I. Title.    II. Series.&#13;
HC130.P6A4513    1982         339.2'2'098       82-8533&#13;
ISBN 0-8213-0012-1                              AACR2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
ABSTRACT OF THE STUDY&#13;
This work originated in a research project for the measurement&#13;
and analysis of income distribution in the Latin American countries, under-&#13;
taken jointly by the Economic Commission for Latin America and the World&#13;
Bank. The present paper presents estimates of the extent of absolute&#13;
poverty for ten Latin American countries and for the region as a whole&#13;
in the 1970s, on the basis of available household surveys and population&#13;
censuses. They are based on country-specific poverty lines representing&#13;
minimum acceptable levels of private consumption, drawn according to a&#13;
food-based method. Such poverty lines -- ranging from 150 to 250 1970&#13;
dollars of annual household consumption per capita -- express a normative&#13;
definition of the absolute dimensions of poverty, partly based on expert&#13;
appraisals and partly reflecting the actual behaviour of low income house-&#13;
holds facing the life style projected by Latin American development.&#13;
According to these estimates, 40 percent of Latin American households&#13;
were poor at the beginning of the 1970s, the incidence of poverty being&#13;
26 percent in urban areas and 60 percent in rural areas. Urban poverty&#13;
extended to more than one-third of urban households in some countries&#13;
(Brazil, Colombia, Honduras) while affecting between 20 and 30 percent in&#13;
others (Peru, Mexico, Venezuela), about 15 percent in Costa Rica and&#13;
Chile and less than 10 percent in Argentina and Uruguay. The extent of&#13;
poverty in rural areas would not be less than 20 percent in any case and&#13;
would reach more than 60 percent in some countries. The corresponding&#13;
poverty gaps were also estimated; in terms of total household income,&#13;
they may represent manageable proportions (around 2-3 percent) in the&#13;
better-off countries, but are in the 4-8 percent range in the bigger&#13;
countries of the region and reach as much as 12 percent in Peru and&#13;
17 percent in Honduras.&#13;
This work, the author of which is the Chief, Statistics and Quantitative&#13;
Analysis Division of the Economic Commission for Latin America (ECLA),&#13;
originated in a research project for the measurement and analysis of&#13;
income distribution in the Latin American countries, undertaken jointly&#13;
by the Commission and the World Bank. The opinions expressed are those&#13;
of the author alone and may not coincide with the points of view taken&#13;
by the sponsoring institutions.&#13;
Originally published as La dimensi6n de Da pobreza en America Latina,&#13;
Cuadernos de la CEPAL No. 27, Chile, 1979. Translated by D.R.J. Black,&#13;
Language Services Division, World Bank, Washington, D.C.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
TABLE OF CONTENTS&#13;
I.     INTRODUCTION&#13;
II.    THE CONCEPT OF POVERTY&#13;
A.  The poverty syndrome and how it is perceived ................... 2&#13;
B.  Theoretical significance of the concept of poverty ............. 4&#13;
C.  The normative nature of the concept of poverty ................ 10&#13;
D.  Relative poverty and absolute poverty ......................... 13&#13;
E.  Poverty and inequality ........................................ 18&#13;
III.   POVERTY AND BASIC NEEDS&#13;
A.  Material components of basic needs ............................ 23&#13;
B. Non-material basic needs                     ... 26&#13;
IV.    THE MEASUREMENT OF POVERTY&#13;
A.  Measurement of levels of living .      . ............................. 27&#13;
B.  Poverty lines .    ................................................ 33&#13;
C.  Drawing of relative poverty lines .      ............................ 37&#13;
D.  Drawing of absolute poverty lines .      ............................ 38&#13;
E.  Poverty measures .............................................. 39&#13;
V.     A METHOD OF DRAWING POVERTY LINES FOR LATIN AMERICA&#13;
A.  The method selected ............................................ 39&#13;
B. Nutritional requirements and determination of the&#13;
contents of a minimum food basket........................41&#13;
C.  Estimation of minimum food budgets ............................ 48&#13;
D. Relationship of food expenditure to other&#13;
consumption expenditure ....................................... 55&#13;
E.  Housing needs and expenditure                  ..                  61&#13;
F.  Access to public services ..................................... 66&#13;
G.  Resulting poverty lines ....................................... 70&#13;
VI.    THE DIMENSIONS OF POVERTY IN THE LATIN AMERICAN COUNTRIES&#13;
A.  The data on income distribution and consumption ............... 78&#13;
B. The incidence of poverty                     ..                   81&#13;
C.  The poverty gap ............................................... 88&#13;
D.  The relative dimension of poverty                .      .        94&#13;
ANNEXES&#13;
BIBLIOGRAPHY&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
I&#13;
INTRODUCTION&#13;
This work is an attempt to assess the magnitude of poverty in the&#13;
Latin American countries. To that end, it establishes poverty lines for the&#13;
larger countries in the region to serve as approximate indications of the&#13;
levels of purchasing power below which the basic needs of a household would be&#13;
so neglected as to place it in a situation of absolute poverty.&#13;
These poverty lines are used in conjunction with available data on&#13;
income distribution to obtain preliminary estimates of the poverty afflicting&#13;
each of the countries separately and the region as a whole. The extent of&#13;
poverty is assessed in terms both of the number of poor persons and the income&#13;
deficits involved. But the drawing of lines of absolute poverty based on&#13;
uniform criteria is also intended to provide other researchers with a means of&#13;
identifying poverty situations and so facilitate the analysis of their causes,&#13;
which can be approached through various research methods.&#13;
This initial attempt is limited to those countries in the region&#13;
best endowed with the pertinent statistics, the idea being to test the method&#13;
selected and analyze the results obtained. However, the statistical&#13;
requirements of this method of estimating absolute poverty lines suit it for&#13;
application to nearly all countries in the region, with the additional&#13;
possibility of periodic update.&#13;
This paper was originally published as La dimensiodn de la pobreza en Ame/rica&#13;
Latina, Cuadernos de la CEPAL no. 27, Chile, 1979. It was translated by D.R.J.&#13;
Black, Language Services Division, World Bank. Data used in this work were&#13;
prepared bv Mrs. Mabel Bullemore, Mr. Jorge Ducci and, in the early stages, Mr.&#13;
Pedro Tejo. The author is grateful for the suggestions and comm-ents made by&#13;
Messrs. Adolfo Gurrieri and Ruben Katzman, which enriched the discussion of the&#13;
concept of poverty.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Such an undertaking calls for the acceptance of a series of&#13;
assumptions, some of them quite forced, and the turning of a blind eye to a&#13;
number of conceptual difficulties. Only the heuristic nature of the&#13;
objectives pursued, which have no analytical aims beyond those already&#13;
indicated, justifies such an approach which, nevertheless, does not excuse&#13;
anyone who follows it from the methodical examination of those assumptions and&#13;
conceptual leaps if the results produced are to be reasonably useful to&#13;
cautious researchers.&#13;
THE CONCEPT OF POVERTY&#13;
A.   The poverty syndrome and how it is perceived&#13;
On the face of it, poverty is a situationai syndrome in which the&#13;
following are combined: underconsumption, malnutrition, precarious housing&#13;
conditions, low educational levels, bad sanitary conditions, either unstable&#13;
participation in the production system or restriction to its more primitive&#13;
strata, attitudes of discouragement and anomie, little participation in the&#13;
mechanisms of social integration and possible adherence to a particular scale&#13;
of values different to some extent from that held by the rest of the society.&#13;
The perception of poverty and its conceptualization are nevertheless&#13;
greatly influenced by the social and economic environment and the general&#13;
goals of the social project of which the prevailing anti-poverty policies form&#13;
part.&#13;
As Galbraith points out (1958), "the experience of nations with&#13;
well-being is exceedingly brief. Nearly all, throughout all history, have&#13;
been very poor. The exception ... has been the last few generations in the&#13;
comparatively small corner of the world populated by Europeans".&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 3 -&#13;
During the early stages of the developnent of capitalism, the great&#13;
mass of the working population lived in generalized poverty.    This explains&#13;
why, in both the classic and Marxist conceptualization, observations on the&#13;
poverty of the working masses are confused with reflections on wages and&#13;
employment (Smith, 1776, Book I, Chap. VIII; Marx, 1867, Book I, Chap. XXIII)&#13;
and why only the"pauperism" of the most disfavored segments of society was&#13;
regarded as a special situation, one in which the wage earned barely allowed&#13;
mere subsistence. Even after the marked improvement in the conditions of the&#13;
working population of the industrialized nations during thd 19th century, the&#13;
prevailing thought could conceive only of the possibility that the poverty of&#13;
the so-called "lower classes" might disappear gradually (Marshall, 1890)..&#13;
The economic and social development of the industrial nations over&#13;
the following decades raised living standards to the point where the existence&#13;
of huge masses of unemployed and semi-employed during the crisis of the 30s&#13;
seemed to be a paradox of "poverty amid the plenty" caused by the equilibrium&#13;
with unemployment in potentially rich economies (Keynes, 1936). After the&#13;
remarkable prosperity of the post-war period, the persistence of poor&#13;
minorities in affluent societies became more visible and shocking, giving rise&#13;
to a renewed interest in the question of poverty, regarded as a self-&#13;
perpetuating problem in rich societies (Galbraith, 1958; Harrington, 1963).&#13;
In the majority of present-day developing countries, poverty has for&#13;
centuries been the lot of the largest part of the population.    The perceptions&#13;
of poverty and underdevelopment fused in a single fatalistic diagnosis&#13;
throughout the colonial era (Myrdal, 1972). The process of decolonization&#13;
that followed the Second World War gave birth at the centers of world power to&#13;
an awareness of the iniquity of poverty and the possibilities that existed for&#13;
developing the underdeveloped nations. For two decades, the mainstream in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 4 -&#13;
this current of thought concentrated on the aggregate growth of the poor&#13;
nations and the opportunity to bridge the gap separating them from the rich&#13;
nations, the confident view being held that such growth would progressively&#13;
wash away the structures of underdevelopment, and with them poverty itself.&#13;
The rapid advance of the developing world over those two decades, without any&#13;
significant improvement in the situation of its great masses of poor, led to a&#13;
rediscovery of poverty -- a second birth of awareness that has been&#13;
preoccupied with "massive poverty", a subject now discussed in the&#13;
international fora, and with the development strategies designed to combat it&#13;
(United Nations, 1972; Chenery et al., 1974; World Bank, 1975b; Hammarskjold&#13;
Report 1975; ILO, 1977).&#13;
It is nevertheless undeniable that that preoccupation is naturally&#13;
influenced by the perception of the poverty in which the great mass of the&#13;
population -- predominantly rural -- of Asia and Africa live, although no more&#13;
than by the naked fact of its purely human dimensions.&#13;
In Latin America, given the extent of internal migrations, the&#13;
center of gravity of poverty has been moving slowly from the countryside to&#13;
the cities, so that by now urban poverty in the region is considerable and&#13;
more generalized than in rural areas.&#13;
These urban poverty situations, characteristic of the dependent&#13;
development of the post-war economy of the Latin American countries, have been&#13;
focused more specifically in the concern which emerged over a decade ago, with&#13;
"social marginalization", and in the more recent preoccupation with the&#13;
informal urban sector.&#13;
B.   Theoretical significance of the concept of poverty&#13;
An examination of the extent to which the concept of poverty has&#13;
theoretical significance may seem pedantic when juxtaposed against the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 5 -&#13;
dramatic human dimensions of the problem. It is quite clear, however, that&#13;
the ambiguity in the theory which underlies that concept becomes a fundamental&#13;
difficulty in any studies on poverty, and that justification for use of the&#13;
concept lies in an ethical and political preoccupation with this particular&#13;
and extreme facet of the problem of the uneven distribution of social goods,&#13;
and in the political will to devote special effort to its solution.&#13;
In the present state of our understanding of the poverty syndrome,&#13;
there is no theoretical framework within which poverty can be satisfactorily&#13;
explained in its entirety!/, taking into account the whole range of symptoms&#13;
that indicate its presence; we can manage no more than an explanation of each&#13;
isolated symptom as an extreme case of inequality in a particular subsystem of&#13;
the distribution of social goods.&#13;
Furthermore, although poverty and inequality of income distribution&#13;
are frequently confused, they are neither equivalent nor mutually inclusive.&#13;
They are separate problems, both conceptually and in the political sense.2!&#13;
Also, the relationship between them differs depending on whether the societies&#13;
concerned are industrialized or underdeveloped: in the latter case, poverty&#13;
situations may come to be so widespread as to make the differentiation between&#13;
them and more general social inequalities inconsequential.&#13;
The theories on income distribution in relatively developed&#13;
capitalist economies have traditionally concentrated on explaining the&#13;
1/ Attempts to identify a "culture of poverty" (Harrington, 1963; Lewis,&#13;
1966) undoubtedly take this approach, but at the price of assuming that&#13;
cultural patterns are the feature which distinguishes poverty and of&#13;
isolating the poor, as an object of analysis, from the rest of society.&#13;
2/   There are situations of broad inequality in which almost the entire&#13;
population is still above minimum consumption levels -- as there are&#13;
situations in which poverty is so general that they show a considerable&#13;
degree of comparative uniformity.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 6 -&#13;
functional distribution of income among relatively homogeneous production&#13;
factors. Such theories assume income distribution by size to depend&#13;
implicitly on the quantities each individual possesses of each of the primary&#13;
factors, whose overall share in income is spelled out, although no attempt is&#13;
made to explain the origin of inequalities in the possession of each factor.&#13;
A number of hypotheses, based on a variety of approaches, have been put&#13;
forward to explain those inequalitiesl/, although it has been impossible to&#13;
integrate them satisfactorily into a broad theory on the macro-distribution of&#13;
income. But even these hypotheses do not incorporate poverty as an analytical&#13;
category in the explicans or as a special situation of the explicandum, except&#13;
insofar as it is considered one of the extremes -- the other being richness --&#13;
in the distribution of income.&#13;
In conventional economic analysis, poverty is never more than a&#13;
problem of welfare, the result of a value judgment, for which a precise slot&#13;
cannot even be found among the propositions of the theory of welfare used in&#13;
an attempt to compare, on a scale from "better" to "worse", possible optative&#13;
economic situations.&#13;
In Marxist thought, the poverty of the workers, and particularly of&#13;
the industrial reserve army, is an essential element in the capitalist model&#13;
of accumulation: "the law which maintains the surplus population or&#13;
industrial reserve army in constant equilibrium with the volume and intensity&#13;
of accumulation ... leads to an accumulation of misery equivalent to the&#13;
accumulation of capital" (Marx, 1867, Book I, pp. 728 and 729).&#13;
Poverty as a social situation, as a problem of welfare, cannot&#13;
however be articulated with the theory of the Marxist system. Although Marx's&#13;
1/   Valid hypotheses of this type will be found in Bjerke (1970) and Cline&#13;
(1975)-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 7 -&#13;
theory of social classes and the asymmetrical distribution of powr&#13;
incorporates an explanation of social inequalities in general, it is the&#13;
exploited and not the poor who constitute a significant analytical category.&#13;
Neither considerations of welfare nor -- in particular -- possible differences&#13;
in levels of living among the exploited form part of the explanatory argument&#13;
of Marxist theory.&#13;
The poverty observable in the developing countries has required&#13;
efforts of conceptualization that go beyond the premises underlying available&#13;
theories, but attempts to meet those requirements have so far produced only&#13;
ambiguous results.&#13;
The persistence of massive poverty in the Third World despite the&#13;
growth that followed World War II has led to the recognition that it is&#13;
associated with critical shortages of physical and human capital and basic&#13;
services (Chenery et al., 1974), and also to the view that the style of&#13;
dependent development prevailing in the Third World is inconsistent with the&#13;
eradication of poverty (Hammarskjold Report, 1975). But these hypotheses are&#13;
still a long way from incorporating the concept of poverty into the theory of&#13;
underdevelopment to a significant degree. The steps that have led furthest in&#13;
that direction are perhaps the theories that endeavor to explain the most&#13;
extreme underdevelopment situations and which view poverty as a central&#13;
element in the vicious circle made up of physiological insufficient, bad&#13;
sanitary conditions, low levels of education and training, negligible capacity&#13;
to save and the set of attitudes characteristic of poverty -- factors which&#13;
are the basic obstacles to increased productivity and the growth capable of&#13;
alleviating poverty (for instance: Myrdal, 1968; Streeten, 1972).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-8-&#13;
At somewhat higher levels of development -- such as have been&#13;
achieved in Latin America -- poverty is perhaps less massive and not so&#13;
overwhelmingly rural0&#13;
Urban poverty in squatter settlements gave rise to attempts at&#13;
conceptualizing the "social marginalization" of what are considerable groups&#13;
in the Latin American population.&#13;
The initial formulations of the problem (ECLA, 1963; Rosenbluth,&#13;
1963; Utria, 1966a) were concerned with describing the poverty syndrome as&#13;
manifested among marginal population groups and therefore show a considerable&#13;
bias toward housing and ecological conditions -- a bias corrected to a large&#13;
extent as marginalization came to be understood as the very social conditions&#13;
of the inhabitants of such settlements (Quijano, 1966). However, the concept&#13;
of marginality was soon extended to analytical dimensions different from those&#13;
of poverty. One school of thought wanted to define social marginalization not&#13;
only by the lack of participation in social goods, but essentially by the lack&#13;
of active participation in decision-making and by the internal disintegration&#13;
of the marginal groups themselves (Vekemans, 1969).   Subsequently, an attempt&#13;
was made to give greater theoretical value to the concept of marginalization&#13;
by applying it to that part of the work force not absorbed by the predominent&#13;
mode of production and therefore kept on the fringes of the labor market&#13;
existing around oliogopolistic activities (Nun, 1969; Ribeiro, 1971; Quijano,&#13;
1971). Here already the subject for analysis is not poverty:&#13;
marginalization, even though conceived of as a social situation, intersects&#13;
with poverty but does not coincide with it.&#13;
Something similar occurs with the most recent attempts to&#13;
conceptualize the unemployment, underemployment and low income of considerable&#13;
segments of the urban population in developing economies in terms of an&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 9 -&#13;
"informal" sector (ILO, 1972; Bienefeld, 1975; Souza and Tokman, 1975). As&#13;
Bienefeld points out, this reformulation has done nothing of itself to confirm&#13;
this new concept as anything more than a basically descriptive term, the&#13;
analytical significance of which still remains to be established (1975,&#13;
p. 53).&#13;
In any case, these various attempts aim at the formulation of&#13;
theories of employment, and it is no easy task to incorporate poverty as a&#13;
concept of welfare into their central arguments.&#13;
The significance of the concept of poverty therefore continues to be&#13;
that it is descriptive of a social situation, so that it can only be validly&#13;
studied within the setting of some theory of the distribution of income, and&#13;
of social inequalities in general, which is regarded as applicable to the type&#13;
of society being dealt with.&#13;
The very lack of theoretical precision in the concept precludes&#13;
consideration of the poor as a social group in the strict sense, sharing&#13;
common origins, behavior and relationship with the rest of society. The&#13;
descriptive nature of the concept allows it to be used only as a rough&#13;
classificatory social category.   This explains the concern to identify within&#13;
the large group of "the poor" smaller groups that might constitute the targets&#13;
of public policy, by means of definitions which reflect the causes rather than&#13;
the symptoms of poverty and which are also homogeneous with respect to the&#13;
effect of a particular policy (Bell and Duloy, 1974).&#13;
This work limits itself to an attempted descriptive quantification&#13;
of the poverty situations observable in present-day Latin American societies,&#13;
in accordance with specific operative criteria of poverty. The "poor"&#13;
comprised in such a cut-off of the social pyramid are no more than a&#13;
statistical aggregate. Subsequent multi-variate characterization can serve to&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 10 -&#13;
identify the different human groups which would be the targets of the policies&#13;
designed to eliminate or alleviate poverty, and, it is hoped, to continue the&#13;
quest for theoretical relationships into which the concept of poverty can be&#13;
meaningfully incorporated.   Until this is accomplished, the concept is valid&#13;
as long as there is no inadvertent crossing of the frontier between the&#13;
descriptive and the explanatory and while the value judgments in which the&#13;
concept originated are kept clearly in mind.&#13;
One can indeed agree with Wolfe when he says that "to prefer the&#13;
term 'poverty' to other ways of identifying the disadvantaged group has as&#13;
background certain preconceived ideas on the nature of the problem and what&#13;
acceptable solutions would be; it also coincides with the blurring of the&#13;
subtle ideological or theoretical distinctions characteristic of the Utopias&#13;
imagined by committees" (1977, p. 1).&#13;
C.   The normative nature of the concept of poverty:    the satisfaction&#13;
of basic needs&#13;
In the final instance, the idea of poverty is based on value&#13;
judgments as to what the minimum adequate levels of welfare and the absolutely&#13;
essential basic needs are and what degree of deprivation is intolerable. Such&#13;
judgments consequently imply a reference to some norm of the basic needs and&#13;
their satisfaction which makes it possible to distinguish between those who&#13;
are poor and those who are not. The concept of poverty is essentially&#13;
normative, and its actual content varies as does the norm of basic needs or&#13;
welfare on which it depends.&#13;
Judgments on the satisfaction of basic needs are individual and&#13;
subjective. It is only through a consensus or the exercise of power by those&#13;
who share them that they are transformed into social valuations. In a&#13;
particular society, different (or even conflicting) collective valuations of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 11 -&#13;
poverty usually exist side by side: that of the governing authorities, that&#13;
of the different intellectual groups, that of the rich, that of the&#13;
disadvantaged groups themselves and that of other social groups. It is no&#13;
surprise, then, that any discussion on the problem of poverty is plagued by&#13;
differences in criteria and norms emanating from different moral and political&#13;
valuations of the existing social order and the way in which society should be&#13;
organized.&#13;
The norms on which the concept of poverty is based, the policies&#13;
selected to attack it and the assessments of their viability are embedded in&#13;
the same particular valuation. The definition of poverty adopted, whether&#13;
explicitly or otherwise, responds to the set of elements making up the value&#13;
system of those who formulate the definition.&#13;
On occasion, the norm against which poverty is defined is so shot&#13;
through with considerations on the viability of the policies designed to&#13;
attack it that the latter come to prevail in the definition, giving rise to&#13;
what Sen (1978) calls the "public policy approach" to the concept of&#13;
poverty. Without going quite so far, there is little doubt nevertheless that&#13;
the normative nature of the concept of poverty makes it particularly dependent&#13;
on the value system and the political intentions used in examining the poverty&#13;
problem. There is in fact no definition of poverty that is neutral in this&#13;
respect, and to claim that one's own definition is neutral is to fall to some&#13;
degree into "group ethnocentrism"1/.&#13;
Strategies having the satisfaction of basic needs as their primary&#13;
objective originate in a value system that is egalitarian and participatory,&#13;
1/   Accustomed to basing our reasoning on a set of axioms geared to the&#13;
principle of the ultimte harmonization of interests, economists do not&#13;
generally pay attention to this aspect of the normative indicators we&#13;
employ.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 12 -&#13;
which tends to regard as poverty any deprivation -- absolute or relative -- in&#13;
the satisfaction of a central core of human needs, whether material or&#13;
psychological and political (Hammarskjold Report, 1975; Ghai, 1977). At the&#13;
other extreme, conservative value systems tend to establish a poverty norm low&#13;
enough to minimize the pressure on total resources and on the social&#13;
transformations required to eliminate the problem.&#13;
It is conceivable -- though not necessary -- that despite these&#13;
differences in the origins of the valuation framework a broad agreement may be&#13;
reached on the poverty norm applicable in a society, without foregoing&#13;
differences in the social project and in political perspective. In some of&#13;
the more advanced societies, official poverty standards tend to reflect a&#13;
consensus of this nature.&#13;
But even when there is a fair degree of social consensus on minimum&#13;
levels of welfare, it is no easy task for the specialist in social sciences to&#13;
identify and explain that consensus. The doing so should be "...an objective&#13;
exercise. To desribe prevailing prescriptions is in fact a matter of&#13;
description, not of prescription" (Sen, 1978; p. 14). Nevertheless, the&#13;
social scientist may all too often act as an unconscious servant of&#13;
contemporary social values (Townsend, 1974; p. 24).&#13;
Furthermore, to establish the poverty norm in terms of the lack of&#13;
satisfaction of a central core of basic needs implies to some extent a more&#13;
voluntaristic attitude to the final result of the policies designed to&#13;
eliminate poverty, as far as satisfaction of individual needs is concerned.&#13;
On the other hand, to establish the norm in terms of generic welfare --&#13;
indicated solely by the income or consumption level -- implies greater&#13;
confidence in the consistency between the individual decisions that maximize&#13;
profit and the mechanisms of allocating production resources.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 13 -&#13;
Obviously, the choice of one or other type of norm is not purely&#13;
academic but closely linked to the other components of the valuation, namely&#13;
the judgment on the existing social order and the policies regarded as&#13;
acceptable. But it is also clear that whatever considerations underlie the&#13;
choice of norm and serve as basis to the valuation framework take on a&#13;
different relevance in situations of massive misery and underdevelopment or in&#13;
affluent societies.&#13;
D.   Relative poverty and absolute poverty&#13;
Poverty is relative only to the extent that the norm against which&#13;
it is defined relates to a given social context and refers to a given scale of&#13;
values associated with a particular style of living. Within a framework thus&#13;
defined, poverty has an absolute dimension as regards human dignity and&#13;
relative dimensions as regards average local levels of welfare.&#13;
It is of course clear that poverty and wealth are extremes on the&#13;
range of social inequalities, which are essentially relative. It is equally&#13;
clear that poverty is a state of deprivation -- deprivation always felt in&#13;
relation to the welfare of others. But let us agree, nevertheless, that&#13;
inequality is not necessarily poverty and that relative deprivation is not&#13;
necessarily poverty either. The concept of poverty makes a normative cut in&#13;
the more general continuum of inequality, differentiating among the diversity&#13;
of situations tht may give rise to feelings of relative deprivation and&#13;
dividing society into those who are regarded as poor and those who are not.&#13;
The concept of relative deprivaion illuminates a very important&#13;
aspect of welfare and is therefore central to the consideration of poverty.&#13;
Assessment of one's own welfare depends partly on that enjoyed by the&#13;
reference groups with which one compares oneself. The subjective perception&#13;
of this welfare, relative to that enjoyed by others, may give rise to feelings&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 14 -&#13;
of relative deprivation. It is to these feelings, and the social actions they&#13;
may originate, that the concept of relative deprivation elaborated by Merton&#13;
(1957) and Runciman (1966) refers. Townsend (1974), on the other hand,&#13;
proposes that a distinction should be drawn between feelings of deprivation&#13;
and actual conditions of deprivation, and that the concept of relative&#13;
deprivation be used in the latter sense, as an objective means of denoting&#13;
situations in which the subject possesses less of a desired attribute than&#13;
other persons. But that would require definition of the style of living&#13;
generally shared or approved of in each society and discovery of a possible&#13;
"point in the scale of the distribution of resources below which families find&#13;
it increasingly difficult (proportionate to the diminishing level of&#13;
resources) to share in the customs, activities and diets comprising that style&#13;
of living" (Townsend, 1974; p. 36). As long as the cut-off point, which&#13;
constitutes the poverty criterion, cannot be determined objectively&#13;
(Townsend's hypothesis), its specification will continue being a normative&#13;
one, the result of a collective valuation.&#13;
But even when defined normatively, poverty should refer to the&#13;
society's predominant style of living, which creates the desires and imposes&#13;
the expectations that give rise to needs. In this sense, the concept of&#13;
poverty is always relative. It is dynamic and specific to each society. Its&#13;
content varies over time, to the degree that basic needs change historically&#13;
in the same society in step with alterations in its lifestyle and with&#13;
economic development. It is specific to each society to the degree that the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 15 -&#13;
content of the concept is different -- for similar norms -- in societies where&#13;
different lifestyles predominate!/.&#13;
This contextual relativity is present whatever normative bases&#13;
underlie the definition of poverty adopted2/.   But that does not mean the&#13;
definition should necessarily be formulated in relative terms.    There is an&#13;
absolute dimension to poverty which, without going beyond the context, cannot&#13;
be defined only in terms of that context. Like Sen, we believe that "there is&#13;
an irreducible core of absolute deprivation in our idea of poverty, which&#13;
translates reports of starvation, malnutrition and visible hardship into a&#13;
diagnosis of poverty without having to ascertain first the relative picture.&#13;
The approach of relative deprivation supplements rather than competes with&#13;
this irreducible core of absolute dispossession" (Sen, 1978; p. 11). Our&#13;
perception of this irreducible core of absolute deprivation, beyond the&#13;
contextual situation of the country or community, is referenced to certain&#13;
basic elements of welfare from the lifestyle prevailing in industrial&#13;
societies, and which we believe every human being should have the right to.&#13;
The absolute norm we follow in defining this irreducible core, whatever the&#13;
particular national environment, flows from our present idea of human dignity&#13;
1/   This relativity of basic needs and of poverty may be observed even within&#13;
a single society, in the sense that relatively autonomous communities or&#13;
particular groups may take as their reference point lifestyles that&#13;
differ markedly from that prevailing in the national society. But such&#13;
differences are gradually declining in importance, given the growing&#13;
inter-relationships among communities and groups that are the result of&#13;
various economic, political, communications and welfare-service&#13;
subsystems (Townsend, 1974). At the other extreme, what is specific in&#13;
national needs is also becoming less and less marked, to the extent that&#13;
culture is universalized and the style of living predominant in the&#13;
developed countries pervades the Third World more and more.&#13;
2/   Even the supposedly universal definitions are based -- consciously or&#13;
not -- on the lifestyle to which it is thought all human beings have the&#13;
right.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 16 -&#13;
and from that universality we ascribe to basic human rights, whlich ought to be&#13;
attainable regardless of any local shortage of resources or any resignation&#13;
culturally induced down through centuries of misery and oppression. It is&#13;
beyond this irreducible core of absolute poverty that situations of relative&#13;
deprivation may be found, definable only in terms of the lifestyle predominant&#13;
in each community.&#13;
Definitions of poverty in relative terms are based on norms that&#13;
attempt to take express account of actual deprivation with respect to average&#13;
levels of needs satisfaction in the society in question -- which are thus&#13;
taken as representative of the predominant lifestyle -- and at the same time&#13;
also attempt to reflect the average availability of resources in the&#13;
society. These norms may indicate conditions of relative deprivation with&#13;
reference to each of the resources that determine the level of living&#13;
(Townsend, 1974), or they may constitute a generic criterion of poverty taken&#13;
as a fraction of the average income (Atkinson, 1975). Such relative&#13;
definitions of poverty do not prejudge the extent of the problem.&#13;
Definitions of the type "the lower x per cent of households", on the&#13;
contrary, do prejudge the extent of poverty and imply that it will be always&#13;
present, since they are not based on criteria of relative deprivation which&#13;
take account of the distance between the lower segment of the pyramid and the&#13;
average situation. More than definitions of poverty, they are approximations&#13;
of the problem and concentrate on inequality at the bottom of the income scale&#13;
(Ahluwalia, 1974).&#13;
Definitions of poverty in absolute terms, on the other hand, attempt&#13;
to pinpoint the absolute deprivation levels that may result from prevailing&#13;
inequalities, on the basis of norms as to the minimum requirements considered&#13;
adequate for the satisfaction of basic needs. Even though in formulating such&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 17 -&#13;
norms local conditions and the cultural features of the population are taken&#13;
into account, this type of definition of poverty is less tied to the levels of&#13;
living actually prevailing in the society or to the average levels of&#13;
resources it has available at a given moment, and is rooted more in universal&#13;
ideas of human dignity and basic human rights. In very dependent societies,&#13;
on the other hand, this constitutes the normative correlate of the orientation&#13;
of the style of development toward the patterns of consumption and the forms&#13;
of welfare found in industrial societies and in the local upper strata, which,&#13;
more than the average level of the traditional lifestyle in these societies,&#13;
provide the reference points for evaluating deprivation.&#13;
For want of a theoretical framework from which a definition of&#13;
poverty could be derived objectively, both absolute and relative definitions&#13;
incorporate the discretional aspects of the valuations on which they are&#13;
based. The fact that certain norms -- characteristically, those concerned&#13;
with nutrition -- underlying absolute definitions of poverty are founded on&#13;
technical reasoning does not preclude their incorporating a value element when&#13;
consideration is being given to what is adequate in the matter of nutrition,&#13;
or a by no means negligible degree of discretion in the assumptions under&#13;
which available knowledge on nutrition phenomena is applied in deriving&#13;
dietary norms (Rein, 1970). The norms used in establishing other needs than&#13;
food are even less likely to be based on scientific knowledge and therefore&#13;
have to be founded more explicitly on evaluations as to what the minima&#13;
adequate for human dignity are in each societyi/.&#13;
1/   Such evaluations are closely linked to the lifestyle viewed as desirable&#13;
for a given society. There is little doubt that changes in social values&#13;
of the magnitude observed in China -- and perhaps also in Cuba -- have a&#13;
decisive impact on the content of certain basic needs (the need for&#13;
clothing, with its "social language" function -- to take one of a number&#13;
of possible examples).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 18 -&#13;
Whether we like it or not, the use of one or other type of&#13;
definition has different political connotations. Relative definitions have&#13;
the advantage of making an unmistakable reference to the prevailing social&#13;
inequalities, while absolute definitions can make it easier to isolate the&#13;
problem of poverty, diverting attention from the broader debate on the most&#13;
adequate income distribution. These implications are clearly seen in the&#13;
industrialized societies, and are probably not unrelated to the fact that&#13;
official poverty lines in the United States have been based on absolute&#13;
definitions (Orshansky, 1965), or to the further fact that in certain Western&#13;
European countries minimum welfare benefits are also based on this type of&#13;
definition (Sawyer, 1975).&#13;
Given the circumstances of the majority of Third World countries,&#13;
the implications of both types of definition may be reversed. Relative&#13;
definitions of poverty, since they are connected with the average availability&#13;
of resources in each society, may be more influenced by views on the degree of&#13;
difficulty involved in tackling the problem in these countries than by&#13;
considerations of human rights and basic needs. On the other hand, in such&#13;
situations of underdevelopment, the absolute core of deprivation acquires a&#13;
significance stemming simply from the condition of being human; the relative&#13;
definitions of poverty can divert attention fran the requirements for&#13;
subsistence by highlighting the general limitation on the country's resources.&#13;
E.   Poverty and inequality&#13;
The fact that poverty -- however defined -- is an extreme&#13;
manifestation of economic and social inequalities has on occasion meant that&#13;
the two concepts have been employed indiscriminately, whereas, as has already&#13;
been pointed out, they are in fact different. It is plain that income&#13;
inequalities in the poorest Third World countries are usually so clearly&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 19 -&#13;
linked to generalized situations of extreme poverty that any insistence on a&#13;
distinction between the two may appear irrelevant. But it is also plain that&#13;
in many Third World societies outrageous inequalities extend beyond the&#13;
universe of poverty to affect significant medium strata of the population.&#13;
It is also indubitable that "the acceptable term 'poverty' has&#13;
become the way of discussing the more disturbing issues of inequality", and&#13;
that the "ambiguity of our use of 'poverty' is preventing the full-scale&#13;
examination of the issues of inequality" (Miller, Rein, Roby and Ross, 1967;&#13;
cit. in Sen, 1978). But, as Sen (1978) argues, the latter provides a good&#13;
reason for drawing a distinction between the two concepts.&#13;
It is clear that an absolute definition of poverty makes a normative&#13;
cut in inequality, and that both may be affected, although differently, by&#13;
economic growth. But poverty defined in relative terms also focuses solely on&#13;
the inequality between the poor and the rest of society, sidestepping the&#13;
inequalities that exist in the latter group and which can change --&#13;
significantly, on occasions -- without there being any alteration in the&#13;
situation of the poor.&#13;
Even when the concept of inequality is also given a normative&#13;
content which reflects a moral evaluation -- as an alternative to the&#13;
descriptive application of the concept of inequality to cases in which income&#13;
or wealth are simply different (Bauer and Prest, 1973; cit. in Atkinson, 1975)&#13;
-- that evaluation is probably based on ethical ideas different from and&#13;
broader than those underlying the "rights" and "needs" in which the concept of&#13;
poverty is rooted.&#13;
Nevertheless, even though the two concepts are different and&#13;
constitute different normative dimensions of the idea of justice, the&#13;
situations which both attempt to express are related causally. The causes of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 20 -&#13;
poverty lie in the same mechanisms that determine the general inequalities&#13;
prevailing in each society, while the transformations required to eradicate it&#13;
form part of the process of profound change toward a just society.&#13;
The fact that we concentrate our attention on poverty should not&#13;
become a substitute for a preoccupation with inequalities in the distribution&#13;
of welfare. The narrowest view of poverty conceals, behind the appearance of&#13;
pragmatism, a simplistic diagnosis of its causes and for that reason carries&#13;
within itself the seed of the failure of actions geared ot its definitive&#13;
eradication.&#13;
Furthermore, neither should consideration of the range of poverty&#13;
situations obscure these facts: that there exists a stratification within the&#13;
universe of poverty; that, below the minimum thresholds set for the&#13;
delimitation of poverty, inequalities of welfare -- or, in strict terms, of&#13;
deprivation -- are found among the poor; that, from the poverty threshold to&#13;
situations of greater indigence, there exists a gradation of levels of&#13;
deprivation that may have radically different consequences as far as&#13;
deterioration of the human condition is concerned.&#13;
III&#13;
POVERTY AND BASIC NEEDS&#13;
The realization that recent economic development in the Third World&#13;
has brought little benefit to the poor in those countries has given a new&#13;
slant to thinking on development. The gradual emergence of this new thought&#13;
was first seen in the strategies devised for the creation of employment (ILO,&#13;
1972) and in the transfer of the focus of development firstly to&#13;
"redistribution with growth" (Chenery et al., 1974) and then to development&#13;
centered on basic needs (Hammarskjold Report, 1975; ILO, 1976; Streeten,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 21 -&#13;
1977a), which emphasizes the satisfaction of those needs among the mass of the&#13;
poor in the shortest possible time (Ghai, 1977).&#13;
At least in the Third World, the eradication of poverty and the&#13;
satisfaction of the basic needs of the population are one and the same&#13;
thing. Both concepts are normative, and may be defined according to the same&#13;
norms.&#13;
Poverty, however, is too frequently defined on the basis of norms&#13;
that cover only situations of "critical" deprivation, or a determined&#13;
percentage of the population at the base of the income pyramid. The attack on&#13;
poverty is also too frequently conceived of from the standpoint of assistance,&#13;
implying no profound reorientation of the prevailing style of development. In&#13;
addition, anti-poverty programs almost always consist of actions designed to&#13;
increase the incomes of the poor.&#13;
When the goal is to satisfy basic needs, however, the extent to&#13;
which the whole style of development must be recast if poverty is to be&#13;
elimminated is thrown into greater relief. Furthermore, the actions involved&#13;
affect not only the incomes of the poor, but also -- and very particularly --&#13;
their access to key social services. Generally speaking, special importance&#13;
is given to channeling specific resources toward specific groups, with more&#13;
emphasis on the nature of what is provided than on income (Streeten, 1977b).&#13;
This situation is becoming responsible for the identification of use&#13;
of the concept of poverty with the more conservative policies for mitigating&#13;
it, while use of the basic needs concept is associated with the more radical&#13;
strategies for refocusing development and reorganizing the social order.&#13;
However, when it is accepted that the causes of poverty are rooted in the&#13;
functioning of the socio-economic system along with income inequalities, the&#13;
squandering of non-renewable resources and the concentration of power, the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 22 -&#13;
goal of eliminating it definitively implies the same structural&#13;
transformations as does the satisfaction of basic needs. It may also even&#13;
entail profounder transformations than those allowed for under strategies&#13;
spuriously vaunted as concentrating on "basic needs" simply because greater&#13;
importance is given to the total investment in social services.&#13;
At all events, such uses are becoming established.    In the context&#13;
of those meanings, policies for the alleviation of poverty may eventually do&#13;
no more than form part of broader programs for the satisfaction of basic&#13;
needs, the final objective of which would be the eradication of poverty, with&#13;
all the changes in the style of development that such a goal implies.&#13;
The basic needs concept is more clearly instrumental. It is linked&#13;
to the idea that, for development plans to focus eliminating situations of&#13;
deprivation, they must incorporate specific objectives aimed at satisfaction&#13;
of those needs. The concept of poverty, being aggregative, only allows&#13;
formulation of a general objective with respect to its mitigation or&#13;
eradication.&#13;
From another standpoint, the concept of poverty, since it is&#13;
descriptive of a social situation, offers more possibilities of analysis and&#13;
diagnosis. Although it only allows identification of a statistical aggregate,&#13;
the poor, it permits subsequent analysis of their social and economic&#13;
characteristics and the identification of poor groups which might be the&#13;
target of specific policy packages,as Bell and Duloy suggest (1974). The&#13;
basic needs concept, on the other hand, focuses on satisfaction levels in each&#13;
group of needs, without necessarily integrating the different characteristics&#13;
of the needy or their possible relationships with other aspects of the&#13;
functioning of the socio-economic system.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 23 -&#13;
There is nothing to prevent the concepts of poverty and basic needs&#13;
from sharing the same normative content, so long as they fit within the same&#13;
value system and are situated in the same position with regard to the&#13;
prevailing social order. This would make it possible to take advantage of the&#13;
analytical benefits in the use of the poverty concept and the instrumental&#13;
benefits belonging to the basic needs concept when formulating strategies for&#13;
the eradication of poverty and the establishment of more just societies. The&#13;
non-satisfaction of basic needs could constitute a specific and operative&#13;
element through which to define poverty.&#13;
Nevertheless, even though the basic needs concept may serve to&#13;
define poverty, it is restricted to the material dimensions of deprivation.&#13;
In its wider sense, the concept includes psychological and political as well&#13;
as material wants (Hammarskjold Report,1975). This multi-dimensional aspect&#13;
is what makes it particularly attractive for the new currents of thought on&#13;
development: the emphasis on economics has tended to blot out the ultimate&#13;
policy goal, which is not only to eradicate physical poverty but also to&#13;
provide all human beings with the opportunity to realize their potential&#13;
fully. The current demand is for development to be centered on man and his&#13;
needs. If this is done, the basic needs concept is converted into an&#13;
illuminating organizing instrument, which throws light on an entire field of&#13;
other questions (Streeten, 1977b, p. 4).&#13;
From this viewpoint, the concept of basic human needs could bring&#13;
together a more precise and wider range of norms for a juster society than&#13;
that implicit in the reduction of resource inequalities.&#13;
A.   Material components of basic needs&#13;
The basic needs that serve to define poverty. are, like poverty&#13;
itself, relative to the environment. They are specific to each country and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 24 -&#13;
dynamic. But at their center, as with the concept of poverty, there is an&#13;
absolute core of needs, the satisfaction of which is more a question of the&#13;
current idea of human dignity than of the levels of welfare and resource&#13;
availability prevailing in each country.&#13;
The concept of basic needs is not new, having provided the&#13;
foundation for much analytic work on poverty from Rowntree's time (1901) to&#13;
our own. In Western industrial societies, the extent of the needs viewed as&#13;
minimal has varied with increasing economic and social progress and the&#13;
transformation in the functions of the State. From the mere subsistence-level&#13;
provisions accepted toward the end of the last century as covering&#13;
physiological needs for the maintenance of life and ability to work, the&#13;
content of the minimum or basic needs concept has expanded to the point where&#13;
what are regarded as minima at the present day cover not only the&#13;
physiological but also the sanitary and social requirements dictated by the&#13;
idea of human dignity current in contemporary society, so that any lack of&#13;
insufficiency a household may suffer does not affect the normal physiological&#13;
development of its members, their social participation, the maintenance of&#13;
their self-respect or that of the community in which they live (Lamale, 1958;&#13;
Franklin, 1967). In the industrialized societies, this trend reflects the&#13;
changes observable in those societal values which underlie the varied&#13;
redistributive programs characteristic of the welfare State, which aim at&#13;
everything from income maintenance to subsidized public education, housing and&#13;
health programs.&#13;
The criterion of normal development and social participation against&#13;
which the industrial societies measure basic needs forms part of the common&#13;
property of mankind. But this does not mean that it would be valid simply to&#13;
transplant the same standards to the developing world.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 25 -&#13;
However, since all men are regarded as equal, it has to be&#13;
recognized that there exist here and now certain absolutely minimum levels for&#13;
satisfaction of the needs universally regarded as essential for a decent life&#13;
-- levels which it is imperative to attain. This is not to say that the&#13;
content of the basic needs concept may not be specific to each country, or&#13;
that it may not vary as social progress is achieved. But there is litle doubt&#13;
that the evolution of the basic needs concept in the industrialized societies&#13;
influences the degree of latitude at present accepted in the application of&#13;
this concept to less developed societies. The progressive universalization of&#13;
culture and in particular of consumption patterns makes the application of&#13;
universal standards to certain basic needs increasingly feasible.&#13;
The Action Program adopted by the World Conference on Employment&#13;
perhaps reflects the consensus already reached on the content of the basic&#13;
needs concept as an essential facet of development policies. The taking up of&#13;
a concept of development focused on basic needs means that the latter -- as&#13;
interpreted in the Program -- combine two elements: in the first place,&#13;
certain minimum requirements of households, usually met through private&#13;
consumption such as adequate food, lodging, clothing and some household&#13;
articles; and in the second place, such essential services -- provided for and&#13;
by the general community -- as water supply, sanitary services, public&#13;
transportation, health care, education and culture. Access to freely chosen&#13;
employment also forms part of any basic needs policy, as both a means and an&#13;
end, since it not only provides the individual with an income but allows him&#13;
an essential feeling of self-respect and dignity (ILO, 1977, p. 24).&#13;
There is likely to be fairly general agreement on a central core of&#13;
basic needs such as this, although the concept can be broadened to include&#13;
additional elements such as fuel, transportation, entertainnent or the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 26 -&#13;
supplementary private consumption expenditure required for access to public&#13;
education and health services0&#13;
The actual content of the central core of minimum basic needs should&#13;
be specific for each country. Climatic, geographical, cultural and socio-&#13;
economic differences shape such needs, although not perhaps to the point where&#13;
any substantial differentiation arises!/. It is on considering the content of&#13;
basic needs in terms of goods that greater specificity by country is reached&#13;
and that the sovereignty of the consumer and the utility functions of the&#13;
planner may come into conflict.&#13;
B.   Non-material basic needs&#13;
Even the broadest definition of the basic needs concept would be&#13;
incomplete if it were restricted to material needs. Only the exigencies of&#13;
measurement can justify concentration on those basic needs that are&#13;
material. However, the satisfaction of them as a universal imperative has&#13;
sense only in a social context characterized by effective enjoyment of the&#13;
fundamental human rights. These are at least the rights and liberties&#13;
enumerated in the United Nations Universal Declaration of Human Rights. But,&#13;
as Ghai and Alfthan (1976) point out, three other important values are also&#13;
closely related to development focused on basic needs -- equality, self-&#13;
sufficiency and participation. To the extent that basic needs are socially&#13;
determined, any acute differences in welfare levels in the particular society&#13;
weight against effective achievement of basic needs goals. National or&#13;
regional self-sufficiency in the satisfaction of basic needs is essential,&#13;
given the present international situation and the need to break away from&#13;
1/   An illustration of the extent of this differentiation is found in the&#13;
calorie targets set for each region of the world by FAO in 1970: the&#13;
difference between the highest (for North America) and the lowest (for&#13;
Asia) was no more than 23 percent (FAO, 1970, p. 491).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 27 -&#13;
inherited or imposed structures. Participation by the entire community in the&#13;
making of social decision, besides being an end in itself, is also an&#13;
essential means of securing basic needs efficiently and with the necessary&#13;
social mobilization. In the final instance, only the people themselves should&#13;
decide the extent, content and priority of their own basic needs (Ghai and&#13;
Alfthan, 1977).&#13;
IV&#13;
THE MEASUREMENT OF POVERTY&#13;
Given the difficulties inherent in defining poverty as an&#13;
interactive social situation rather than as a simple juxtaposition of wants,&#13;
it is no surprise that the operative definitions are restricted to material&#13;
deprivation or that measurements are made in terms of the inadequacy of&#13;
household resources in reaching determined levels of economic welfare -- at&#13;
the expense of other dimensions of poverty such as actual psychological&#13;
deprivation, specific cultural patterns and social or occupational&#13;
marginalization, which are not taken explicitly into account.&#13;
Since poverty is regarded as a normatively unacceptable lack of&#13;
welfare, it is necessary to resort to measurement of the levels of living that&#13;
may provide a basis for defining poverty operatively and identifying -- by&#13;
means of this normative cut-off point -- those households that are to be&#13;
regarded as poor.&#13;
A.   Measurement of levels of living&#13;
The level of living of a household is the degree to which it&#13;
satisfies its needs in accordance with its preferences. To reach this level&#13;
of utility, the household can put into practice a set of feasible decisions on&#13;
the allocation of its available resources, within the setting created by&#13;
external conditions beyond its control.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 28 -&#13;
It would be ideal if levels of living could be measured in terms of&#13;
utility or of the degree of needs satisfaction. The problem of the&#13;
interpersonal comparability of measurements of individual utility!!, however,&#13;
precludes that possibility, which would involve the objectivization -- or&#13;
perhaps only the collectivization -- of subjective judgments.&#13;
The conventional hypothesis underlying the theory of consumption is&#13;
that each household allocates its resources so as to maximize some index of&#13;
utility, a function of the amounts it acquires of each good.&#13;
This assumption can be criticized on the grounds that households are&#13;
not always efficient optimizers or that the information on which they base&#13;
their choices is incomplete or distorted. A more general criticism is that&#13;
the functioning of the economy is imperfect enough to limit access to certain&#13;
goods and services and foster the consumption of others, thus inducing choices&#13;
that lead to lower levels of living than could in fact be attained with the&#13;
same resources.&#13;
On the basis of these and other arguments2/, proposals have been&#13;
made for the measurement of levels of living by means of some combination of&#13;
indicators representing the physical inputs in the satisfiers contained in the&#13;
goods consumed (Drewnowski, 1970). The problems of comparability and&#13;
aggregation involved, however, continue to weigh against such proposals.&#13;
On the other hand, if the assumption as to consumers' optimization&#13;
of utility is accepted it becomes possible to measure levels of living in&#13;
1/   Such as those now being tested in the examination of self-evaluated&#13;
welfare (see, for instance, Andrews and Crandall, 1976), or the&#13;
estimation of individual utility functions (Van Herwaarden, Kapteyn and&#13;
Van Praag, 1976).&#13;
2/   Which are concerned more with not taking into consideration all the&#13;
resources that have an impact on the level of living.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 29 -&#13;
terms of household resources. From this standpoint, the dimension of the set&#13;
of opportunities open to the household -- represented by all the feasible&#13;
choices it has -- serves as a good conceptual point of departure, as suggested&#13;
by Carmel Ullman Chiswick (1976), for defining a measure of the level of&#13;
living of the household. Furthermore, such a conceptualization has the&#13;
advantage of highlighting the extent to which the level of living is&#13;
determined by factors beyond the immediate control of the household, and the&#13;
extent to which it is independent of the lifestyle the household actually&#13;
selects from the range of opportunities within its reach.&#13;
Part of a household's resources are the time and skills of its&#13;
members, which they can apply to remunerative activities or other tasks,&#13;
depending on the constraints imposed both by the labor market which they have&#13;
access to and by the social environment. Or they may own businesses or assets&#13;
which product income or can be sold to finance consumption expenditures and&#13;
which, in any event, give them security and social recognition. Finally, the&#13;
location of the household in relation to institutional welfare systems can&#13;
bring its members social security benefits or assistance or access to&#13;
subsidized education, health and housing systems.&#13;
It is from applying these resources and exercising these rights that&#13;
households obtain the current income and allowances -- in cash, in kind and in&#13;
free or subsidized services -- with which to ensure the satisfaction of their&#13;
needs.&#13;
The immediate utility the household as a whole obtains depends on&#13;
how much and what they decide to consume, on the effective access they have to&#13;
the markets in which the required goods are sold, on the prices they face and&#13;
on the degree of actual access to free social services.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 30 -&#13;
In addition, decisions on how much income to spend and how much to&#13;
save, as well as those on how available time should be utilized, have an&#13;
impact on both the dimension of the resources that will be available to the&#13;
household in the future and the utility it obtains immediately.&#13;
An ideal measure of levels of living should also take into account&#13;
household size and composition, intra-family distribution of goods and the&#13;
possible existence of economies of scale in the consumption of large&#13;
households.&#13;
Proposals have been put forward for composite indicators that take&#13;
into consideration in some fashion not only the purchasing power available to&#13;
a household but also the dimension of its resources and its actual access to&#13;
specific goods and services. Townsend (1970)' proposes that account be taken&#13;
not only of current money income, but also of social security benefits, assets&#13;
(including education), remunerations in kind and the value of job fringe&#13;
benefits, the value of the public social services received, production for&#13;
self-consumption and gifts in kind or help received from others. Weisbrod and&#13;
Hansen (1968) have proposed an index combining income and net worth. Morgan&#13;
and Smith (1969) combine real income indicators with an evaluation of the time&#13;
devoted to leisure. The difficulties of conceptualization and measurement&#13;
inherent in such proposals, however, make it difficult to get away from&#13;
utilizing income or consumption as the isolated indicators nearest to the&#13;
objective measurement of levels of living.&#13;
Household income may be defined in a way that covers all current&#13;
receipts, whether they originate in the production process or in transfers,&#13;
and whether they are receipts in cash, in kind or in imputed gains from goods&#13;
produced for self-consumption. It may also be defined net of taxes and other&#13;
contributions, as in the concept of disposable income employed in the national&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 31 -&#13;
accounts system recommended by the UN (1968). Although no conceptual pitfalls&#13;
exclude a definition of household income that takes account of the real value&#13;
of the free or subsidized public services to which each household may have&#13;
actual access (which is the concept of total income proposed by the UN in&#13;
1972), the incorporation of such services into the measurement of income is&#13;
conditional upon the possibilities of their being measured in each case. In&#13;
practice, measurements of current household income do not include the imputed&#13;
benefits from those services, nor do they provide any indication at all on the&#13;
degree of actual access to them.&#13;
Even when these measurement problems can be overcome and the concept&#13;
of current income made sufficiently broad, the measurement of levels of living&#13;
obtained would still be imperfect.   Firstly, because it is influenced by&#13;
household decisions on participation in the work force but does not take note&#13;
of the amount of free time resulting from them. Secondly, because it reflects&#13;
assets in accordance with their current yield and consequently does not&#13;
reflect the contribution of wealth to the level of living -- in the absence of&#13;
a perfect capital market -- in terms of security and opportunities for&#13;
expenditure. Of course, both problems tend to become irrelevant toward the&#13;
base of the social pyramid, where, on the one hand, the supposed&#13;
substitutability of income and free time is very doubtful -- as is, by&#13;
extension, the premise that the latter is in fact an important component of&#13;
the level of living -- and where, on the other hand, not many options exist&#13;
for application of the scant assets actually possessed.&#13;
Current income measures the purchasing power of the household before&#13;
the latter reaches any .decision on how much to consume and how much to save.&#13;
From this point of view, income is superior as an indicator of household level&#13;
of living to consumption, which reflects no more than present utility without&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 32 -&#13;
taking account of the degree to which savings increase the present value of&#13;
the expected levels of future consumption.&#13;
However, the measurement of current income is subject to transitory&#13;
fluctuations which affect levels of living temporarily. In a study of&#13;
poverty, it would be particularly important to examine more permanent levels&#13;
of living so as to be able to distinguish between chronic and "transient"&#13;
poverty situations. From this point of view, an acceptable measurement of&#13;
permanent income would be the preferred option. But attempts to estimate&#13;
permanent income with data from Latin America for one-year reference periods&#13;
have not been accurate enough to allow this indicator to be employed as a&#13;
measurement of levels of living (Ferber and Musgrove, 1976).&#13;
Current consumption is less subject than current income to&#13;
transitory fluctuations and could therefore give a more stable measurement of&#13;
permanent levels of consumption, even if one does not anticipate the&#13;
increments expected in those levels as a result of current savings!/.&#13;
One practical consideration gives an additional reason for employing&#13;
consumption: it tends to be estimated with greater accuracy than current&#13;
income.&#13;
The same total amount available for consumption expenditure can,&#13;
however, represent different degrees of real purchasing power for households&#13;
which have to pay different prices. Whenever such differences do exist, they&#13;
have a greater effect on low-income households, which direct a higher&#13;
1/   To the extent that the reference period for measurementx of income and&#13;
consumption can be extended, the transitory variations diminish in&#13;
importance and both measurements approach their permanent levels. In&#13;
fact, according to the permanent income hypothesis, if the reference&#13;
period used were sufficiently long expected consumption values would&#13;
approach permanent income levels so closely that both would provide the&#13;
same indication on levels of living.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 33 -&#13;
percentage of their expenditure to the satisfaction of basic needs and&#13;
therefore have only a narrow margin for maximizing their utility by&#13;
substituting goods to which different price sets apply. Such differences in&#13;
prices, and in conditions of access to goods, affect comparisons of urban and&#13;
rural levels of living particularly.&#13;
The welfare of the members of a household depends not only on its&#13;
available purchasing power but also on the number and characteristics of the&#13;
family members who endeavor to satisfy their needs through that power.&#13;
The possibility of taking household size into account, then, gives&#13;
sense to the expression of levels of living on a per capita basis, even though&#13;
this is not the sole factor determining intra-family welfare. It may also be&#13;
argued that family members of different age groups make different demands on&#13;
the household consumption budget, so that family size should be measured in&#13;
adult-equivalent unitsl/.&#13;
Allowance should also be made for the economies of scale which&#13;
benefit large households, but they are very difficult to estimate. Finally,&#13;
the assumption that all the resources of all the members of the household are&#13;
pooled to finance joint family consumption may be borne out to different&#13;
degrees, since some members may keep back part of their personal income to&#13;
finance a level of living above the average of their particular household.&#13;
B.   Poverty lines&#13;
Given the essentially normative nature of the concept of poverty, it&#13;
has to be measured as standards or levels of living, which may be formulated&#13;
in either relative or absolute terms.&#13;
1/   Since equivalencies differ depending on the expenditure category, they&#13;
also necessarily differ depending on the income or consumption level&#13;
(Howe, 1974).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 34 -&#13;
Poverty lines are those normative cut-off lines on the economic&#13;
welfare dimension of the social pyramid. They represent levels of living&#13;
below which a household or a person is regarded as poor, and therefore serve&#13;
to identify the poor. However, the utilization of arbitrary percentages of&#13;
the population at the base of the distribution pyramid to represent the poor&#13;
does not serve to express levels of living, not even in terms of the&#13;
inequality in those levels. Such utilization is therefore not a measure of&#13;
poverty itself, despite many claims to the contrary (e.g. Szal, 1977). It is&#13;
no more than a heuristic manner of referring to poverty.&#13;
The conceptual and operative problems surrounding the measurement of&#13;
poverty are consequently the same as those encountered in the measurement of&#13;
levels of living.&#13;
Poverty may be measured through the actual access to goods that&#13;
satisfy needs or through the resources disposable for the acquisition of those&#13;
goods. The first implies the direct identification of situations of&#13;
deprivation with regard to each group of needs, since it does not call for&#13;
particular assumptions on consumption behavior (Sen, 1978). However,&#13;
individual preferences are passed over in the ranking of the different needs,&#13;
and therefore also in the maximization of individual utility. On the other&#13;
hand, the measurement of poverty from the standpoint of resources does give&#13;
this flexibility but assumes that the household optimizes its welfare under&#13;
conditions of perfect information. From the point of view of measurement,&#13;
poverty too is a multi-dimensional concept, which would be applied ideally by&#13;
establishing normative standards of satisfaction or adequacy for each&#13;
representative indicator, whether of a group of needs or a type of resource,&#13;
depending on the focus chosen for measuring levels of living.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 35 -&#13;
It is possible to measure poverty in terms of a multi-variate&#13;
definition that takes account of different dimensions of welfare; however, it&#13;
is a cumbersome procedure, requiring explicit handling of the existence of&#13;
situations of "partial" poverty (i.e. with respect only to some of the&#13;
dimensions of welfare). Multi-variate defintions of this type can&#13;
nevertheless be the most appropriate for the formulation and follow-up of&#13;
development strategies oriented toward basic needs satisfaction (Ghai and&#13;
Alfthan, 1977), even if their usefulness for other purposes is limited.&#13;
More general uses call for measurements of poverty through&#13;
indicators which combine the various dimensions of welfare.&#13;
In the final instance, the aggregation of multiple level-of-living&#13;
indicators which express degrees of satisfaction of different needs in a&#13;
single composite indicator implies the adoption of assumptions on the rate of&#13;
substitution among satisfiers of those needs (Drewnowski, 1977). Something&#13;
similar occurs with the aggregation of measurements relying on indicators of&#13;
different types of resourcesi!. This partly explains the extended use of&#13;
income or total expenditure on consumption as isolated indicators of levels of&#13;
living, and the drawing of poverty lines in terms of income.&#13;
From this point of view, income may be considered as an indicator&#13;
that combines -- in a specific fashion -- different dimensions of the level of&#13;
living. From the needs standpoint, it is a combination of the different&#13;
satisfiers at market prices, assuming perfect substitutability among them.&#13;
From the resources standpoint, it is a combination of all types of resource in&#13;
accordance with their current or imputed market yields, also assuming perfect&#13;
substitutability among them.&#13;
1/   Townsend's analysis (1970) of the various aspects to be taken into&#13;
account in the definition of poverty is illuminating in this respect.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 36 -&#13;
The utilization of income in measuring poverty is founded on its&#13;
undoubted property for synthesizing -- despite the limitations pointed out so&#13;
far -- the household resource base which dictates the family level of&#13;
living. Perhaps its greatest shortcoming as a composite resource indicator is&#13;
that it does not take account -- unless a special measurement effort is made&#13;
-- of real access to free or subsidized public services.&#13;
On moving directly from resources to needs, additional constraints&#13;
appear. To take income as a composite indicator of needs satisfaction&#13;
involves major assumptions, which become particularly rarefied in poverty&#13;
situations. As Streeten (1977b) points out in this regard, consumers are not&#13;
always efficient optimizers -- especially not in the spheres of nutrition and&#13;
health; neither does the distribution of satisfiers within the household&#13;
necessarily ensure the equitable satisfaction of each family member's needs.&#13;
Further, the poor may be confronted with prices different from those paid by&#13;
other groups and with special difficulties of access to specific goods and&#13;
services.&#13;
The drawing of poverty lines in terms of income or total consumption&#13;
expenditure therefore implies the setting of norms for the minimum quantum of&#13;
resources required, whether as a function of average community welfare, if a&#13;
relative definition is adopted, or in terms of the satisfaction of a set of&#13;
basic needs, if an absolute definition is employed. In both instances, the&#13;
poverty lines synthesize a judgment as to what the minima would be below which&#13;
only unacceptable situations of deprivation would exist. They should be&#13;
interpreted as overall statistical yardsticks that serve to delimit situations&#13;
of poverty and their magnitude, since they are drawn according to heuristic&#13;
procedures which can be no more than approximate and which, in practice,&#13;
contain an irreducible degree of arbitrariness. Despite that, the size of the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 37 -&#13;
population which falls below the poverty lines is of indubitable social&#13;
significance, and the subsequent examination of its characteristics from&#13;
different data bases and through a range of analytical methods reveals the&#13;
possibiility of researching the causes of the poverty syndrome.&#13;
If poverty lines are to fulfill their discriminating function&#13;
adequately, it is obviously necessary to draw sets of lines for each country,&#13;
indicating the basic needs in households with different characteristics and&#13;
whose levels of living are not directly comparable. Such sets should at least&#13;
include the various lines produced by application of the same normative and&#13;
estimative criteria to households of different sizes in urban and rural areas.&#13;
C.   Drawing of relative poverty lines&#13;
As stated earlier, definitions of poverty in relative terms based on&#13;
income or total consumer expenditure endeavor to put into operation an idea of&#13;
welfare that is minimally adequate in relation to the average values&#13;
prevailing in the particular society.&#13;
A summary method of drawing relative poverty lines consists in&#13;
making them a fraction of average income (Atkinson, 1975) or of some other&#13;
position of income distribution (Szal, 1977).&#13;
A more sophisticated method -- and one with greater statistical&#13;
requirements -- is to draw poverty lines from Engel curves which relate&#13;
expenditure on food (or also on clothing and housing) to total income,&#13;
selecting as the poverty criterion a certain ratio which allows determinaion&#13;
of the corresponding income segments. This method, employed at one time in&#13;
the U.S. (BLS, 1960) and currently employed in Canada (Love and Oja, 1977),&#13;
requires postulation of the proportion of income devoted to basic items of&#13;
consumption, in accordance with actual patterns of expenditure, as an&#13;
indicator of relative household welfare; it also requires the making of a&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 38 -&#13;
normative choice as to what proportion of spending on basic items reflects a&#13;
minimally acceptable situation.&#13;
D.   Drawing of absolute poverty lines&#13;
The most time-honored method (Rowntree, 1901) of quantifying minimum&#13;
standards for basic needs in terms of income or consumption expenditure is&#13;
that of fixing detailed norms for the minimum quantities of provision&#13;
(calories, protein, housing, household articles, etc.) that will satisfy each&#13;
need or group of needs regarded as basic, translating them into quantities of&#13;
the specific goods required!/ and evaluating these at the prices the&#13;
households in question must pay.&#13;
Another method has been developed which takes food as the basis for&#13;
establishing absolute poverty lines. The starting point consists in&#13;
determining in detail the cost of a normative minumum diet established for&#13;
each family type. The income corresponding to the poverty line can be&#13;
estimated on the basis of a proportion of income expended on goods as shown by&#13;
Engel curves synthesizing the actual behavior of households (Orshansky, 1965),&#13;
or on the basis of the total expenditure of the marginal household which&#13;
acquires only the minima stipulated on the basic items (Kahn, 1976). Bardhan&#13;
(1970) has utilized this method for India, but applying relationships between&#13;
required expenditure on food and total actual consumption. Dandekar and Rath&#13;
(1971) employed a somewhat unusual variant of this method, by drawing poverty&#13;
lines as the level of total consumption expenditure at which a diet of the&#13;
required calorie content is actually consumed, without specifying its cost.&#13;
1/   As Pyatt and Thorbecke (1975) indicate in their useful analysis of this&#13;
problem, "the formulation of how commodities provide wants is usually&#13;
assumed to be linear"; this constitutes a dispensable restriction, which&#13;
excludes complementarity among goods.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 39 -&#13;
Finally, the legal minimum wages of a country have on occasion been&#13;
used (Fishlow, 1972) as absolute poverty lines.&#13;
E.   Poverty measures&#13;
The count of the number of households below the poverty lines is the&#13;
most widely used measure of poverty, providing an initial approximate idea of&#13;
the magnitude of the problem. This measure of the "incidence of poverty" does&#13;
not take account, however, of either the degrees to which the incomes of the&#13;
poor fall below the poverty line or the inequalities between households at&#13;
different poverty levels (Sen, 1976).&#13;
Alternatively, it is possible to measure the inadequacy of the&#13;
incomes of the poor, this being the aggregate resource gap of the poor as a&#13;
group with respect to the poverty line. This measurement -- and the&#13;
normalized version of it, the average percentage income gap -- does not take&#13;
account of the number of the poor, nor is it sensitive to changes in the&#13;
inequalities among them. In view of the limitations inherent in these&#13;
methods, Sen (1976) has axiomatically derived a poverty measure that combines&#13;
both of them and incorporates income inequalities among the poor.&#13;
Further on, these measures of poverty will be examined in detail&#13;
when they are applied in evaluating the dimensions of poverty in the Latin&#13;
American countries.&#13;
V&#13;
A METHOD OF DRAWING POVERTY LINES&#13;
FOR LATIN AMERICAN COUNTRIES&#13;
A.   The method selected&#13;
The method chosen here for drawing poverty lines depends very much&#13;
on the operational objectives set up, the degree of precision possible in&#13;
accomplishing them and the nature of the available data base.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 40 -&#13;
The view taken was that this initial, regionally focused approach to&#13;
the problems of estimating basic needs, identifying the poor and assessing the&#13;
extent of poverty in the various countries could tolerate a certain degree of&#13;
inaccuracy provided the results obtained for each country were basically&#13;
comparable and would allow an evaluation of the poverty existing in the&#13;
region. The estimation procedures were designed, however, so that the&#13;
determination of basic needs would be as specific as possible for each&#13;
country.&#13;
The poverty lines drawn were based on diet, an estimation being made&#13;
of the cost of a food basket to cover minimum nutritional needs adequately.&#13;
The lines correspond to a figure put at double that minimum food cost, on the&#13;
grounds that such a sum would cover the value, at current prices, of the goods&#13;
required to satisfy the basic needs which are usually satisfied in these&#13;
societies through private consumption expenditure. The lines therefore&#13;
represent minimum estimates of the private consumption expenditure required to&#13;
satisfy basic needs, and they imply that households are classified as poor if&#13;
their purchasing power is less than twice the cost of a nutritionally adequate&#13;
food basket.&#13;
The components of basic needs that should be satisfied through free&#13;
public services provided by existing institutuional systems are not covered in&#13;
these estimates, which allow only for the private consumption expenditure&#13;
associated directly or indirectly with access to and utilization of such&#13;
public services.&#13;
The minimum food basket in each country was based on minimum&#13;
nutritional requirements, taking account of the composition of national supply&#13;
in each food group, per-calorie prices for each food type and dietary&#13;
habits. These baskets were valued at retail prices.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 41 -&#13;
This procedure offers a number of advantages vis-a-vis the direct&#13;
use of household budget survey results. The estimated expenditure represents,&#13;
first of all, the purchasing power necessary for the satisfaction of basic&#13;
needs rather than what is actually spent by those who satisfy -- inter alia --&#13;
their minimum basic needs. In addition, it avoids the problems of&#13;
comparability affecting most surveys as a result of the possibly different&#13;
goods content of the expenditure of different households on the same&#13;
consumption item, since few surveys indicate prices and quantities. Finally,&#13;
it enables poverty lines to be drawn for any country and period even if the&#13;
results of a household budget survey are not availablle.&#13;
B.   Nutritional requirements and determination of the contents of a&#13;
minimum food basket&#13;
The contents of the minimum food basket for each country are&#13;
determined so that it satisfies minimum nutritional needs, taking account of&#13;
the real availability of each type of food in the particular country, but&#13;
offering no possibility of substituting one type of food for another without&#13;
raising the cost significantly!!.&#13;
The minimum energy and protein needs utilized by sex and age (see&#13;
Annex A) were selected according to the standards recommended by the Food and&#13;
Agriculture Organization and the World Health Organization (FAO/WHO, 1973).&#13;
The assumptions currently used in studies of this type (FAO, 1962 and 1963,&#13;
for instance) were also adopted: a moderately active population and average&#13;
weights of 65 k for adult males and 55 k for adult females; no account was&#13;
taken of the possible effect of climatic differences, given the lack of&#13;
1/   In a work (Tejo Jimenez, 1976) which supplements this present one, a&#13;
detailed listing is given of the criteria and procedures employed in&#13;
estimating the minimum food baskets utilized here.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 42 -&#13;
quantifiable data and the interdependence between climate and physical&#13;
activity (FAO/WHO, 1973).&#13;
Protein!! as well as calorie needs were used in order to ensure more&#13;
specific estimation of the minimum basket for each country. It is recognized,&#13;
nonetheless, that an adequate calorie intake almost always implies an adequate&#13;
intake of proteins and other specific nutrients2/.&#13;
This was the basis on which minimum daily per capiLa calorie and&#13;
protein requirements were established for the average composition by sex and&#13;
age of the population of each country around 1970. The results obtained,&#13;
given in Table 1, show average national energy requirements that differ, as a&#13;
maximum, by four percent (between 2,260 and 2,350 calories per day per capita)&#13;
and protein requirements that differ by less than eight percent (between 40.2&#13;
and 43,3 grams pe, day per capita). It should be remembered that on applying&#13;
these results uniformly within each country, the needs of households with a&#13;
composition older than the national average are somewhat underestimated, while&#13;
those of households with a composition younger than the average are&#13;
overestimated. Although this may be the case in principle, independently of&#13;
household size, the tendency for larger households to show a younger age&#13;
composition than the average means that the procedure utilized is likely to&#13;
overestimate their nutritional requirements to some extent.&#13;
1/   The FAO/WHO (1973) figures on protein requirements deal with high-quality&#13;
proteins (obtained from eggs or milk). It is considered that the&#13;
composition of the diet in developed countries results in average quality&#13;
of protein intake of the order of 80 percent of that of eggs or milk,&#13;
while in developing countries -- excluding extreme situations -- average&#13;
quality of protein is in the vicinity of 70 percent. The latter&#13;
assumption was applied uniformly in obtaining the figures on protein&#13;
requirements given in Annex A.&#13;
2/   See Sukhatme (1970), for example.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 43 -&#13;
TABLE 1&#13;
MINIMUM PER CAPITA FOOD-ENERGY AND PROTEIN NEEDS&#13;
Food-Energy Needs             Protein Needs&#13;
(calories per day)           (grams per day)&#13;
Argentina                            2348                        43.3&#13;
Bolivia                              2346                        41.3&#13;
Brazil                               2317                        40.2&#13;
Colombia                             2291                        40.8&#13;
Costa Rica                           2310                        41.3&#13;
Chile                                2318                        42.0&#13;
Dominican Republic                   2287                        40.6&#13;
Ecuador                              2292                        40.8&#13;
El Salvador                          2288                        40.7&#13;
Guatemala                            2306                        41.1&#13;
Haiti                                2307                        41.3&#13;
Honduras                             2287                        40.7&#13;
Mexico                               2285                        40.8&#13;
Nicaragua                            2280                        40.4&#13;
Panama                               2306                        41.4&#13;
Paraguay                             2272                        40.4&#13;
Peru                                 2304                        41.1&#13;
Uruguay                              2334                        43.3&#13;
Venezuela                            2259                        40.9&#13;
Source: Author's estimates based on FAO/WHO (1971) recommendations.&#13;
For each country, the minimum food basket that would satisfy the&#13;
nutritional needs identified was estimated on a predominantly normative or&#13;
standard basis, even when account was also taken of the relative availability&#13;
of foods and consumer habits in each case. In theory, the minimum-cost diet&#13;
could consist of the pair of foodstuffs with the lowest per-calorie price and&#13;
the lowest protein price, respectively, but this would be completely unreal.&#13;
In order to avoid this trivial conclusion, the base taken was the composition&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 44 -&#13;
of the apparent consumption of foodstuffs!', which reflects both the relative&#13;
availability of each food and national average consumption patterns.&#13;
For each country, approximately 40 staple foods were selected,&#13;
representing over 95 percent of the total apparent consumption of&#13;
foodstuffs. The apparent per capita consumption of these constitutes the&#13;
average diet. The first step in identifying the minimum standard diet was to&#13;
reconcile the caloric and protein intakes obtained from the average diet with&#13;
the minimum requirements established in each case2/. At the same time, the&#13;
role of foods with higher per-calorie and protein prices was reduced in favor&#13;
of lower priced items, in accordance with the values shown in Tables 2 and 3.&#13;
These substitutions, however, were made within the range allowed by&#13;
a set of constraints designed to reconcile commonly accepted nutritional norms&#13;
with prevailing dietary habits:&#13;
(i)    adopt either apparent consumption or actual consumption of egg&#13;
protein by the lower income strata, whichever is greater;&#13;
(ii)    complete with milk proteins up to 15 percent of protein requirements&#13;
or respect actual consumption by the lower income strata, whichever&#13;
represents the higher consumption of milk;&#13;
(iii)    meat consumption should not be less than the equivalent of five&#13;
grams per day per capita of protein or than actual consumption by&#13;
the lower income strata;&#13;
1/   As shown by the FAO Food Balance Sheets issued in 1975 for the period&#13;
1960-1975.&#13;
2/   In the majority of countries examined, apparent per capita consumption of&#13;
the foods selected led to energy intakes higher than the minima&#13;
necessary. In other countries -- Colombia, Ecuador and Honduras --&#13;
energy intakes were below the minima.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 45 -&#13;
(iv)    maintain an intake of fish protein similar to average apparent&#13;
consumption;&#13;
(v)    sugar intake should not be over the equivalent of 270 calories per&#13;
day per capita or actual consumption by the lower income strata,&#13;
whichever is greater;&#13;
(vi)    consumption of tubers should not be lower than actual consumption by&#13;
the lower income strata in the case of tubers with a per-calorie&#13;
price higher than that of cereals or legumes; the purpose of this&#13;
constraint is to give proper weight to the complementary role these&#13;
foods play in culinary habits;&#13;
(vii)    adopt the proportion of vegetables apparently consumed, and a&#13;
maximum equivalent to 50 calories per day for fruit (the incmne&#13;
elasticity of which is considerably higher than that of vegetables),&#13;
since these foods are of particular importance in the provision of&#13;
minerals and vitamins and the achievement of a balanced diet;&#13;
(viii)    adopt the same proportions for calories obtained fromn oils and fats&#13;
as shown by the figures on apparent consumption, given the degree to&#13;
which they are a culinary complement to other foods and the fact&#13;
that their per-calorie prices tend to be comparable with those of&#13;
cereals;&#13;
(ix)    cereals and legumes should not exceed 60 percent of total energy&#13;
requirements.&#13;
Adoption of the figures on actual consumption by the lower income&#13;
strata -- in accordance with the information set out in Annex C -- as minimum&#13;
substitution bounds was a means of respecting the basic features of the&#13;
dietary habits of the population and also the variety in economic&#13;
circumstances which those habits reflect and which may not be discernible in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-46 &#13;
0000000       C)4  0  00  C-, -4e     N  C-4  =   .40   e&#13;
0  'Oto-OC  ON  C  4fl~ ~~~~~                  C)N.4 Cn .4  0  ~   444 0&#13;
C              -    .4 (fl en  -          -      .~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~El a0&#13;
0&#13;
  0-&#13;
V 0 ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ o .&#13;
en...  NN,..4  4-4=  .0  -  N ~~~~~~1. 0  0 I&#13;
0  8 ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ . &#13;
10~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
~~~~~~o  .0~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~o0&#13;
-~~~~I         4    n             .4.     a      a&#13;
0  0                                -         .4             440u  J  AM.&#13;
0   W C  CN   C  C  0  0a 0'     W 44  0  Ce  to 440h &#13;
00  0                                                              0~~~A  &gt;  A0.c  :~&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-4~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ &#13;
0                -4  ~~~~4-IL  n 'DC) C4  ' -4  '&#13;
2l                                          -4U -a  4  0 I  nc &#13;
N    '~~~~0S0 c  - 04( a,   'ON  4       0r-en 0  N-&#13;
-4N           -4  .-4     -en  -&#13;
0&#13;
'o  1-4~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~o-&#13;
-4 -4  n  'n     c  rq -4I     a,  e&#13;
0                                          0~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~4 'N- &#13;
2  ~~~~~10a'C)C40 In  4  'fl, r  1 r' 1rc-1  N  ~ -I  a,  -&#13;
-4 N   m   WI  10  1-1 1-4 cj oo 0  Ln  r-  'D  " 0  .0 4&#13;
-4 04 14  cq  1~~~~~~44  &gt;&#13;
0~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
w                                          c~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~o 2&#13;
r, (a.  U) ~ ~ ~ ~ * I          .. . &#13;
E              .~~~~M nr-c  -4 CD-4,-4N.--4  -r  0  C N 0  -4)  .-&#13;
2neM                    IC                        -0      U   0U&#13;
a)-    -10'U1 440 co    0  0  n 0  10 N-N   en ( C40 C) .40a,&#13;
o                          *I II    I         .N           C-&#13;
0          I4C~ -;  N  0-: (4)  C.  400:     C -4  ~  C;.  cU&#13;
al) 2  0              (M4 . 4.Ln       a  -Z N    o       u   N&#13;
ON    0                                                        0&#13;
04-H                                                       -  0 &#13;
-4  ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~M0                    4_&#13;
2  ~~~~~,0 440- 4  o a  0r      C4-40  -, '  00  0'&#13;
H  .0  ~ ~ ~ ~  ~  ~ ~  ~ ~ ~ ~  fl 0 14  4-4 a,-0'  0 &#13;
C.)                                             -4   -44  c&#13;
2     N                                                   0   )&#13;
0  m                                       a ~ ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ .0&#13;
-4  -~~~~~~4    N- N-4        '  00        0r~4 0- &#13;
0  C)m  o  'D  ')  0  0  n 0  0        a, 0- 4-4)  4 0  .  0&#13;
ZC.)   ~~~0 -4                                           4-4  4   N1-&#13;
0&#13;
HN                                       2~~N ~C ~ C&#13;
O U                                             -~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ 4-  n ci0.&#13;
O    co&#13;
to        N4-4                 4M cq        4 "   -4l  N   4 &gt;&#13;
0 ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~   4&#13;
0-  C.)-&#13;
~~-440N-(4.4  ~ 0'  CC (4()-      0 -' -   -4  C~ &#13;
N i C :          co  *  *1    .                *    N: E- &#13;
co  0                 U)                Co~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~o-&#13;
0                                                 2  *-42~~~~~0  t&#13;
0  -4              w  co  cu  w   0)      &gt;   &gt;~~~~~~~4  N&#13;
04  Q)-4  a  - C)4,     j '.0 4N(4.4N   .-4  N   U)   2&#13;
4-                                        0'      4( C co W S44n0) -4 (V Q&#13;
a)  r- co   w  -H  0  :3  "O  ~   :j4) (V  (V  0)  m   0   0  140' :) &#13;
a~ m  w  u  p  04 (n  &gt;4  00  j  X:  90   -1 Cl~ PL4  C.,  P-4  -4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 48 -&#13;
the prices considered. Account was also taken of available nutritional&#13;
recommendations concerning specific foods in the exceptional case of countries&#13;
in which such recommendations have been issued and were applicable to present&#13;
purposes (for example, Servicio Nacional de Salud, Chile, 1974). In all&#13;
cases, care was taken not to go too far beyond apparent consumption averages,&#13;
on the grounds they are indicative 6f the actual availability of each food in&#13;
the particular country.&#13;
The composition of the standard basket within each group of foods&#13;
was estimated to reflect the composition of apaarent consumption in those&#13;
cases -- the majority -- in which it responded to the price ratios per calorie&#13;
and per protein unit. Whenever that did not occur, the nutritive contribution&#13;
of the particular food group was assigned in a higher proportion to the&#13;
cheapest food in it, up to the limit allowed by the habits of the lower income&#13;
strata, culinary substitutability and the national capacity to produce that&#13;
food.&#13;
Table 4 shows the estimated minimum food baskets.    Although the&#13;
procedures employed tend to average out situations on a national level,&#13;
application of these standard baskets to urban population groups is not too&#13;
arbitrary. They may, however, constitute unreal standards as far as some&#13;
segments of the rural population are concerned, even though, in overall terms,&#13;
national figures on domestically produced foods are confirmed to a reasonable&#13;
degree by the apparent consumption statistics which served as starting point.&#13;
C.   Estimation of minimum food budgets&#13;
It would be ideal for our purposes if the minimum food basket could&#13;
be valued at the actual prices paid by each low income group. For that, it&#13;
would be necessary to have detailed data on prices and quantities from surveys&#13;
of consumer spending. But even so, in information of that type the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-49-&#13;
0,  C  C  04  (Nr.  04  0-  -  -  I  04  4  -4  -  0&#13;
04   04  r.      14  en  -104   (N   4   44  .4  -   c&#13;
C  I C  C C  -   C' 04 10 04 C  n C'04 04 N  C 0  CC  .4 fl C  C&#13;
0.  C  04  -  InC0  C'  -14 1~&amp;#1;4 N   C -  0104  - c&#13;
0~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~1&#13;
.(I I.Iw &#13;
04  04 C  C  0-  n C  4 0 04  -  C  04  04  0-C 04  ..  to.1  0&#13;
114  0 ~ ~          A jC     4 0 m   3 , , 1: L  &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 50 -&#13;
specification of goods is usually uncertain, a fact which casts doubt on the&#13;
application of implicit prices to the standard basket. For this reason, and&#13;
because of the need to employ a method that is independent of the results of&#13;
those usually sporadic surveys, estimation of the cost of the minimum basket&#13;
was based on current retail prices gathered by national statistical systems.&#13;
In most Latin American countries, these prices are those prevailing in the&#13;
capital city or its metropolitan area; only a handful of countries gather&#13;
price information on other cities systematically!!, and in no country is&#13;
information on rural prices gathered in a systematic way.&#13;
In consequence, minimum food budgets were estimated for the capital&#13;
cities of the countries under consideration. Their subsequent adjustment to&#13;
obtain budgets that could be broadly applied firstly to the urban population&#13;
as a whole and then to the national population as a whole, is based on the&#13;
scant information available on regional price differentials.&#13;
For all foods, the prices selected were those of the lowest quality&#13;
varieties included in retail price surveys. In the case of foods for which&#13;
that source did not include prices, recourse was had to other sources or to&#13;
the prices of the nearest substitutes with similar nutrient content. Annex B&#13;
lists consumer prices in each capital city as of mid-1970, since it was these&#13;
that were used in assessing the minimum food budgets given in Table 5.&#13;
Although these results are expressed in expenditure per day per person, they&#13;
reflect average annual norms.&#13;
As any significant bias in the prices employed in calculating cost&#13;
of living indexes can affect the level of the poverty lines, a validation&#13;
exercise was carried out to ensure as far as possible that those prices were&#13;
1/   In Brazil, retail price statistics over 87 cities; in Colombia, 7; and in&#13;
Mexico, 9.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 50 -&#13;
specification of goods is usually uncertain, a fact which casts doubt on the&#13;
application of implicit prices to the standard basket. For this reason, and&#13;
because of the need to employ a method that is independent of the results of&#13;
those usually sporadic surveys, estimation of the cost of the minimum basket&#13;
was based on current retail prices gathered by national statistical systems.&#13;
In most Latin American countries, these prices are those prevailing in the&#13;
capital city or its metropolitan area; only a handful of countries gather&#13;
price information on other cities systematically!!, and in no country is&#13;
information on rural prices gathered in a systematic way.&#13;
In consequence, minimum food budgets were estimated for the capital&#13;
cities of the countries under consideration. Their subsequent adjustment to&#13;
obtain budgets that could be broadly applied firstly to the urban population&#13;
as a whole and then to the national population as a whole, is based on the&#13;
scant information available on regional price differentials.&#13;
For all foods, the prices selected were those of the lowest quality&#13;
varieties included in retail price surveys. In the case of foods for which&#13;
that source did not include prices, recourse was had to other sources or to&#13;
the prices of the nearest substitutes with similar nutrient content. Annex B&#13;
lists consumer prices in each capital city as of mid-1970, since it was these&#13;
that were used in assessing the minimum food budgets given in Table 5.&#13;
Although these results are expressed in expenditure per day per person, they&#13;
reflect average annual norms.&#13;
As any significant bias in the prices employed in calculating cost&#13;
of living indexes can affect the level of the poverty lines, a validation&#13;
exercise was carried out to ensure as far as possible that those prices were&#13;
1/   In Brazil, retail price statistics over 87 cities; in Colombia, 7; and in&#13;
Mexico, 9.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 51-&#13;
(U e  0  00  ..t  0  r-.  clj  0o   cn  OY&#13;
-           0 0   0 0 o N  0 -   0 o 0 N&#13;
N&#13;
z     00  0  0            e 0n 0  0  0  0  0 o&#13;
N    n  LI  ,.  C'  0  4  0  Os  N  0  N  X&#13;
4  4  4 c;~~ cN     &#13;
a4          C  0  ON o0  0  0 of  -4  -4   N   N  -  4&#13;
1-4   N  C'  C'4  CN   C'  0  CD   0  N  0  4  '0&#13;
a.    -4    0  0D  0  ,-1  CD  -4  0  0 O&#13;
-4    0     N  00          r-  ON Or  0 OOO  C. )  r&#13;
..             N  - o-4 &lt;4       0  -O  r4  CD  -4  -4&#13;
1;   Q   sD  '  _l  -i  ~  na1-  0 n  O C 4&#13;
0-4      0  0  0  0 0  0            C&#13;
0&#13;
z &#13;
Os          Os o .  C'  C'  N  N  f_  '0o &lt;   :  N&#13;
_           - 0 0 C O 0 o 0 0 0     0  O  0 0   i&#13;
&lt;:~~  ~~     *0  O O         I O O* &#13;
oC&#13;
44&#13;
zo ~ ~   ir  O  No  0  '0  05  N  CO 0o -o  '0 g0 ,&#13;
O ~ ~  0,      N  0  0  Ir OD  0  N d  N  0D  CS4  0&#13;
U)          2     C&gt;0 0  0 0 C0 0   0) 0 0 0&#13;
om    c&#13;
Ev~  ~   ' 0 o . 0   - 0      0 N  e      0 r o - &#13;
8~~~~' o- c-s o   s o  o - o '0     ooo&lt;           u&#13;
0:                                           -&#13;
-H  r,  ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ Q  Le)  C14  en ~ ~ -.   C&#13;
X  X   O O O    O~~~~~~~~~~-  O  O O- O O O  O O- r  @0&#13;
:4    0                                               C&#13;
.0    0  I O li O  &lt;0  m   O 4  0  N  ir  0  '  0 4  I-4&#13;
El    0&#13;
4:                                                  0.&#13;
/  C) - 0  0         0     10 0C N&#13;
in 0  0  0  0D  0  0  0  C)  0D  0  0  0  .  (4&#13;
PO                                              0&#13;
u&#13;
co~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~'&#13;
a                 U*&#13;
CD C      0  0    0 0) 0   0 0 0 0     -     i&#13;
/ :                                              i C   n &#13;
/-Z&#13;
0&#13;
.5-4~ ~~ ~ ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~P&#13;
4-4~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~4&#13;
4 -4  142                                    -&#13;
co-I                                         In &#13;
.4                              &gt;&#13;
Al                     4)~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~-&#13;
U,       in -                 0           CA i&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 52 -&#13;
the lowest available on the metropolitan marketsl/. The Joint Program on&#13;
Latin American Economic Integration (ECIEL) investigated 1968 and 1973 prices&#13;
in the member countries of the Latin American Free Trade Association, the work&#13;
for 1968 giving prices for two, and sometimes three, qualities of each food.&#13;
Re-costing of minimum food baskets at the average prices for each product&#13;
given by that Progranm2/ resulted in budgets somewhat higher than those based&#13;
on cost of living indexes for the same period. However, these are themselves&#13;
between 6 percent and 10 percent higher than the budgets obtained by re-&#13;
costing minimum baskets on the lowest ECIEL price in each case3/. To the&#13;
extent that ECIEL figures accurately reflect the spectrum of consumer food&#13;
prices in the Latin American metropolitan areas, the prices currently employed&#13;
in drawing up cost of living indexes tend to fall in the lower half of the&#13;
spectrum, and therefore are not the lowest prices available on each market.&#13;
However, their utilization in calculating standard budgets for poor groups is&#13;
appropriate, since it is not reasonble to assume that these groups always have&#13;
access to the lowest market prices or, by the same token, that they pay&#13;
premiums to obtain differentiated products to the same extent as middle-class&#13;
groups.&#13;
1/   Or, in more rigorous terms, the lowest prices that current statistical&#13;
surveys can capture.&#13;
2/   Data kindly supplied by ECIEL.&#13;
3/   Despite this, they are below the minimum food budgets obtained by&#13;
Arellano (1975) for the LAFTA countries at 1968 prices. For all&#13;
countries, he made uniform use of the diet established by the Chilean&#13;
National Health Service (1974) and applied ECIEL price data to it;&#13;
although, as indicated, the latter tend to be somewhat lower than those&#13;
applied in the present work, the basket utilized is between 10 percent&#13;
and 15 percent more expensive -- depending on the particular country --&#13;
than the baskets here estimated for each country.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 53 -&#13;
The need to have poverty lines applicable to urban households as a&#13;
whole and to all households in each country inevitably leads to rough&#13;
approximations in the assessment of the corresponding minimum food budgets,&#13;
given the scant information available on inter-regional price differentials.&#13;
The periodic retail price surveys conducted in Brazil, Colombia and&#13;
Mexico capture prices in a number of citiesl/. In Argentina, price surveys&#13;
have been carried out in certin provincial cities at the same time as the&#13;
metropolitan area survey!/. In Mexico, the Comision de Salarios Minimos&#13;
(1964) collected price data on urban and rural areas in the major states. In&#13;
a number of cases, household budget surveys provide data on food prices in&#13;
both urban and rural areas3/.   Tejo Jimenez (1976) collated these sets of&#13;
regional food price data; although no clear tendencies are discernible as&#13;
common to all countries, fresh foods and those making up the staple diet&#13;
usually cost less in non-capital cities than in metropolitan areas; foods&#13;
produced in geographically concentrated locations (winter fruit, milk&#13;
products, fish and shellfish) or which are imported tend to show higher&#13;
prices, the same being true of processed foods.&#13;
On weighting price differentials by the composition of standard&#13;
minimum baskets, the food budgets obtained for non-capital cities are somewhat&#13;
lower than those estimated for capital citie94/. In Brazil, the existence of&#13;
1/   Brazil, IBE (Yearbook); Colombia, DANE (Bulletin); Mexico, DGE&#13;
(Yearbook).&#13;
2/   Argentina, Comite Coordinador de Emenestros de Costo de Vida en el&#13;
Interior (1967a, 1967b).&#13;
3/   Honduras, DGEC (1970); Peru, Ministry of Agriculture (1975).&#13;
4/   Colombia, five percent lower; Mexico, from two percent to 8 percent&#13;
lower, depending on what data base is used; Peru, six percent lower;&#13;
Honduras, 12 percent lower. In Argentina, the budgets are similar to&#13;
those estimated for the metropolitan area.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 54 -&#13;
a multipolar urban network complicates the picture: the minimum budget&#13;
calculated on average prices taken over 87 cities is three percent higher than&#13;
that estimated for Rio de Janeiro but six percent lower than that calculated&#13;
on Sao Paolo prices.&#13;
There would therefore seem to be general justification for assuming&#13;
minimum food budgets for non-capital urban areas to be five percent lower than&#13;
those estimated for the capital city of each country.&#13;
Data on urban-rural price differentials is even more limited. In&#13;
the rural areas of the three countries for which there is data available,&#13;
fresh food prices are seen to be systematically lower than those recorded in&#13;
urban areas, and therefore even lower than those prevalent in capital&#13;
cities. Prices of processed products or those brought in from outside the&#13;
particular region are, on the contrary, consistently higher than those&#13;
recorded in non-capital cities. Costing of standard minimum baskets at rural&#13;
prices gives the following results: in Mexico, a budget 13 percent lower than&#13;
in the Federal District (and 10 percent lower than in other urban areas); in&#13;
Peru, 15 percent lower than in Lima (and nine percent lower than in other&#13;
urban areas); in Honduras, 20 percent lower than in the Central District.&#13;
At all events, these prices cover only a part of rural consumption,&#13;
since a significant percentage of needs are met from own-account production.&#13;
This percentage varies greatly from one region to another, depending on&#13;
whether subsistence or commercial agriculture predominatesl/, but the limited&#13;
1/   The Peruvian survey, for example, showed proportions of own-account&#13;
produced food that varied from 11 percent in areas where agriculture is&#13;
more commercial to between 50 percent and 75 percent in areas where&#13;
subsistence farming predominates.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 55 -&#13;
evidence availablel/ tends to indicate that the imputed prices for own-account&#13;
produced staple foods rarely differ by more than 20 percent fromn those&#13;
recorded in rural markets.&#13;
These circumstances, taken as a whole, suggest that it is reasonable&#13;
to regard the cost of standard minimum food baskets in rural areas as 25&#13;
percent below the budget estimated for the capital city of the particular&#13;
country.&#13;
Table 6 shows the minimum food budgets costed in accordance with&#13;
these criteria for the capital cities, for urban households as a whole and for&#13;
rural areas. It is doubtful, however, whether the last-mentioned standards&#13;
would be valid for specific segments of the rural population, given the&#13;
variety of situations affecting the availability and cost of the goods&#13;
concerned. For that reason, each estimated rural-area budget will be used&#13;
only as a tool in estimating the minimum food budget applicable to the&#13;
particular national population as a whole.&#13;
D.   Relationship of food expenditure to other consumption expenditure&#13;
The drawing of poverty lines based on minimum food budgets requires&#13;
that standard relationships between food expenditure and other consumption&#13;
expenditure be established. Even though this operation can in practice be&#13;
based only on the observed behavior of households, the alternative choices&#13;
offered by the corresponding Engel coefficients have different conceptual&#13;
implications.&#13;
Use of the percentages of total consumption that low income&#13;
households devote to food, although reflecting the allocation of resources by&#13;
households in extreme conditions of want, also implies an assumption that&#13;
1/   Mainly the National Food Consumption Survey, Peru (Ministry of&#13;
Agriculture, 1975).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 56 -&#13;
expenditure on food has the same income elasticity as expenditure on other&#13;
items. Actual consumption patterns, however, reveal that when their incmne&#13;
increases poor households prefer to put a higher percentage of that increase&#13;
into other items.&#13;
TABLE 6&#13;
DAILY PER CAPITA COST OF MINIMUM FOOD CONSUMPTION&#13;
ESTIMATED FOR URBAN AND RURAL AREAS, 1970&#13;
(in local currencies)&#13;
Urban&#13;
Metro-      Other&#13;
politan      Urban        Average      Rural b     National c&#13;
areas  a    areas   b     Urban  c                Averages&#13;
Argentina            1.29        1.29          1.29        0.97        1.22&#13;
Brazil               1.22        1.22          1.22        0.92        1.06&#13;
Colombia             4.42        4.20         4.26         3.32        3.87&#13;
Costa Rica           1.77        1.68         1.73         1.33        1.48&#13;
Chile                4.00        3.80         3.89         3.00        3.63&#13;
Honduras             0.52        0.49          0.50        0.39        0.42&#13;
Mexico               3.17        3.01         3.06         2.38        2.80&#13;
Peru                 9.61        9.13         9.35         7.21        8.28&#13;
Uruguay             78.06       78.06        78.06        58.55       73.32&#13;
Venezuela            1.77        1.68          1.71        1.33        1.60&#13;
aFrom Table 5.&#13;
bEstimated as per the criteria discussed in the text.&#13;
cWeighted averages for each national population.&#13;
Use of the proportions of income spent on food by all households&#13;
(Orshansky, 1965) implies a view that households which rise above the poverty&#13;
threshold consume as much on non-food items as other households.    But the&#13;
further they go beyond that threshold, households devote higher percentages of&#13;
their consumption to non-food items. Application of the relatively lower&#13;
percentages of food spending in these households to others with an income just&#13;
above the poverty threshold can lead, as Friedman indicates (1968), to&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 57 -&#13;
overestimation of both the poverty line and the magnitude of poverty. It&#13;
seems more appropriate to use the proportions spent by those households in the&#13;
group where food expenditure is somewhat higher than the minimum budget&#13;
established.&#13;
Table 7 shows food expenditure as a percentge of total private&#13;
consumption (based on available survey data) for the groups of households that&#13;
are closest to that definition and which therefore constitute the groups most&#13;
relevant for the purposes in view. Percentages are also given for all the&#13;
households covered by each survey.&#13;
Since the level of aggregation in which the data are available is&#13;
not the most desirable, interpretation of the coefficients of food expenditure&#13;
given in Table 7 should take account of the location of the group selected as&#13;
relevant and the relationship between its average expenditure on food and the&#13;
minimum food budget established in each case. For Argentina, Chile and&#13;
Venezuela, where the group observed is low-income but on average spends&#13;
considerably more on food than the minimum budget, the most pertinent group of&#13;
households for this analysis is a sub-group with an even lower income, which&#13;
probably has a higher coefficient of food expenditure than the larger group it&#13;
forms part of.&#13;
Bearing this in mind, it may be concluded that urban households&#13;
which spend somewhat more on food that the minimum budget allows will devote&#13;
-- in any Latin American country -- between 40 percent and 50 percent of their&#13;
total consumption expenditure to that item. The location of each country&#13;
within this interval reflects in considerable measure the relative degree of&#13;
development of the part of the economy being observed, which in some cases is&#13;
the more developed urban-area segment.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
_ 58 -&#13;
c            C1  .  .  .  0&#13;
4.I   co     Ltn  CO  '0  -T  CO  a'  C.  a   -  C~&#13;
-Aa)         "     m m     M 0m&#13;
2t0 .0&#13;
0)&#13;
e30&#13;
44 _W  d&#13;
COO &gt; 4-4    H a C- 0     C-- N Lf a IT&#13;
4-)  000&#13;
4   -4  . OO OH&#13;
0)  0)0  c)  Cn4  L11tn  T   CT   Lf  .-  -t  Lfn  CC&#13;
1      O4                                   OH     0 C&#13;
0)  &gt;..1-1O                           d0     0&#13;
44        to o                                 Ai &gt;i  H &#13;
0)0&#13;
tn          4i a :&gt;                              co ooo&#13;
N t       Zr -H C &#13;
44 .&gt; COM                                H -o&#13;
0      e J O&gt;X                                     0W    3)&#13;
'V    0)H .w&#13;
c 00C-4U      C- 0-      C- L0&#13;
EO                      IT ?  0 CC  0  0  - 00    c&#13;
a3 o Xc Q)                                  4     o     c&#13;
         $4 :3  0                                 &gt; nO   C&#13;
N  O   -  w0  41 tn D  H  (N  .4  tr  (N  o'  H   c--J  H  CO  4   C&#13;
'- z a    v   c0O  c                                    oQ  &#13;
  w 0 0&lt; &gt;                                m CJ 'c&#13;
Q) c   0 3)&#13;
0    0&#13;
E~~                          ~~                 4 1-r  aC  -C  S\  u  &gt;&#13;
w                         "~~~~~~~~~~-IZ  (J  co&#13;
w~ ~~~     4i 4aiw       D          D  D r x       ., ff      4 . &#13;
W 4 :3 &gt;k    I H H 0 O    I &lt; H &lt; ^        W o X&#13;
4. 4-)O)CO&#13;
W~~~~~~, -4   r                                         D     t&#13;
w   H   ,00)'   V                             I          co&#13;
C-- CY"-  &amp;J n0t 0) 2                0                       3    P&#13;
o :c4   co &gt;  C04                                   Q I          CX&#13;
Po w                 QHu) *                            .CZ &#13;
P         4-0)0.)0000                                        'V&#13;
&gt;g C)                         all 00               40    0 &#13;
c/m0                0         a'CO C0(0                  04&#13;
X4                      r- m0  ' o  o   0 .        &gt;0&#13;
&gt;-i     a r  O-  0                    tO O' 0. CO  (N  %.0  0  P4&#13;
a'     H  H  .-  CO   C-  H  H\ H&gt; O  O   C&#13;
E-4 rn  ~ ~ ~ ~ ~   ~   '.  '001.40)&#13;
u     ~a'       a' a' o~                         '0 o o &#13;
C ' H     H C                 O.H  I  0 Xf  H&#13;
ZO  Oco - e          E                     0&#13;
.    'O *.-4 &#13;
(04J'  '     0)&#13;
0 &gt;                                    Q) Q) 6    &#13;
(1              I0                   H -  u l~&#13;
caGa)))                               0 1 ( 2H  0  0&#13;
&gt;q         . :3  0 -  .0                  ' H  X&#13;
Q)      PC  co  u  u                    5-  Q) z f &#13;
cO~~~~~ JJC             .0 t &#13;
0  ~ ~ (24 (  0    4-4               OHJ-   Q)  &gt;-&#13;
0)      w  '  0      ii                          C c&#13;
0  CO          U              o P)   '  O&#13;
0 00                ujOO4   4 O&#13;
O4         co 1   b   4  O  4H `  (1  In   0)&#13;
C~1 'V  6r~  ar~ *H  o.~  NO UU r-4I0  X 3&#13;
O-4  NO OH      4.~ 'H  *d  (0  000 H      .c&#13;
h 0W O~ C- Cfl ~  ~     0     'H)O  CO    U&#13;
-1(04.4 c   4-)  o o&#13;
'V 0&#13;
Q)         H4   (Nt4 ~-H                     4i10&#13;
ID  -4 ~~~D   r-   W  O  0 0  '&#13;
4-4C)  U4-   C&#13;
Q) 4.J 4-   Q)  )  En2&#13;
"-co   I-V.  CO&#13;
CO                ~~~~~~~~~~ca  00a)  0&#13;
CO co      U)        H4     0)4 &gt;  c 00  Q)&#13;
'H   'Hco               Q)    H   0   4-i  '&#13;
4-i  HP0      -  0            Q)0.0  'H 44~  0&#13;
0O '    1 0)  'I  U         nUC 4 &#13;
b12  co  Hi  .,  C:  X  4- C&#13;
$ 4 -'  0  .0_  0  Q)  )  a) &#13;
-4      0 C-)  =  r1                     01c&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 59 -&#13;
Urban-area poverty lines have therefore been taken as corresponding&#13;
to private consumption budgets amounting to double the corresponding minimum&#13;
food budget.&#13;
Uniform application of this norm may lead to a certain degree of&#13;
underestimation of the poverty existing in the relatively more developed&#13;
countries or areas, where the propensity to consume other goods is somewhat&#13;
higher than the food coefficient at the income levels in question. There are&#13;
advantages, nonetheless, in employing a uniform standard for all the Latin&#13;
American countries in a regional evaluation such as the present one, since&#13;
that allows the method evolved to be applied even where no recent, reliable&#13;
family budget survey data exist.&#13;
The same reasoning can be used to justify uniform application of a&#13;
single food budget/total expenditure ratio to all households, without looking&#13;
at their composition and size. Even though it is important to make this&#13;
distinction in national-specific evaluations of povertyl!/ and crucial in the&#13;
implementation of anti-poverty programs, the greater accuracy the distinction&#13;
would allow in this regional evaluation is achievable for certain countries&#13;
1/   Orshansky (1965) uses different coefficients for the US:    0.27 for two-&#13;
person households and 0.33 for those with three or more members; for one-&#13;
person households, she assumes the poverty line to be 80 percent of that&#13;
drawn for a couple, on the grounds that "the lower the income, the more&#13;
difficult it would be for a single person to reduce sur-h items as housing&#13;
and household appliance costs below the minimum for a couple".&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 60 -&#13;
only and would have no relation to the degree of accuracy achieved in other&#13;
aspects of the estimations madel/.&#13;
As far as rural areas are concerned, the little information on rural&#13;
household consumer patterns2/ suggests that the groups which are relevant for&#13;
this analysis devote more than half their total expenditure to food, depending&#13;
on how self-consumption by farm households is valued. The undoubtedly greater&#13;
preponderance of food in the quantum of rural household consumption is&#13;
probably offset -- in the value of total consumption -- by the lower unit&#13;
values of the own-account produced food consumed and by the higher prices&#13;
these households pay for certain non-food goods. Even so, and in line with&#13;
the evidence referred to, the norm adopted in estimating rural-area poverty&#13;
lines is that expenditure on non-food items represents only 75 percent of the&#13;
value of the corresponding minimum food budgets. The poverty lines applicable&#13;
at the national level incorporate this criterion, appropriately weighted.&#13;
The norm underlying the drawing of poverty lines accepts that a sum&#13;
similar to the minimum food budget adequately covers the other basic needs&#13;
generally satisfied through private consumption, the grounds for this being&#13;
the assumption that households above the minimum food threshold are also above&#13;
the minimum thresholds for other basic needs. There is a risk, however, in&#13;
using this assumption without seeking some additional verification as regards&#13;
1/   Information available on this question comes from the survey conducted by&#13;
the Joint Program on Latin American Economic Integration (ECIEL)&#13;
(Musgrove, 1976) and is limited to the differences among households of&#13;
different size within the urban population as a whole and not within&#13;
specific income groups. One- and two- person households tend to spend on&#13;
food between one percent and four percent less of their total consumption&#13;
than all households taken together. Households with three to five&#13;
members have food coefficients similar to the average, while those with&#13;
six to eight members allocate between one percent and 4 percent more of&#13;
their spending to food.&#13;
2/   Coming from national surveys in Mexico and Peru and set out in Annex E.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 61 -&#13;
expenditure on housing and those costs that are complementary to access to&#13;
free public services.&#13;
E.   Housing needs and expenditure&#13;
A family's need for housing requires that it have a dwelling which&#13;
possesses the essential services, allows minimum adequate occupation density&#13;
and independence and affords sufficient shelter against the elements, in&#13;
conditions of stable tenure and at a reasonable distance from the place of&#13;
work. Poverty lines should cover the resources needed to ensure access to a&#13;
dwelling that meets these requirements in minimum fashion. However, it is no&#13;
easy task to express this need with precision or in a way which accomnmodates&#13;
the realities of each country.&#13;
In the majority of cases, the formulation of minimum housing&#13;
standards for urban households is complex and subject to considerable&#13;
variation because of differences in physical environment, in city size, in the&#13;
material available locally and in the cultural characteristics of households&#13;
(United Nations, 1977). Furthermore, it is usual to find biases originating&#13;
in the social values of those formulating the standards (Mabogunje, Misra and&#13;
Hardoy, 1976). The definition of minimum housing needs is therefore more&#13;
arguable than the establishment of minimum food needs, and the use of national&#13;
standards may lead to less realistic appraisals of the housing situation in&#13;
which large groups of families find themselves.&#13;
In addition, quite apart from the validity a set of housing norms&#13;
may have at the micro-economic level, family housing situations when taken&#13;
individually, are very much determined by the prevailing restrictions on&#13;
access to the housing market and to urban services.&#13;
High unit costs of construction, as well as the systems of financing&#13;
prevailing in the "private conventional housing" market (i.e. the type of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 62 -&#13;
dwelling demanded by the middle and upper strata of the population, which have&#13;
the main voice in this market), block access to it for large sectors of the&#13;
population. Low-cost public housing programs, with generous terms of payment,&#13;
are of very limited scope and are still inaccessible to the groups at the&#13;
bottom of the scale1/. This is reflected in the magnitude of the quantitative&#13;
deficits traditionally estimated as that proportion of the population without&#13;
a "normally adequate" or "conventional" dwelling -- in some Latin American&#13;
cities, between a third and a half of the total population (World Bank, 1975;&#13;
United Nations, 1977).&#13;
A large number of the households in this situation are found in&#13;
shantytowns and illegal squatter settlements on the outskirts of urban areas,&#13;
locations lacking in running water, local services and adequate physical&#13;
access. Amelioration of such situations is beyond the purchasing power of the&#13;
individual households affected, as the provision of services to these&#13;
settlements depends on public urban infrastructure investment programs, while&#13;
access to locations with services is denied to them by high urban land prices.&#13;
It appears that "housing poverty" could well be more widespread than&#13;
poverty defined in terms of a minimum purchasing capacity, and may also affect&#13;
large segments of the working and urban middle classes, in the sense that&#13;
their real aspirations are to the conventional type of dwelling produced by&#13;
the private market2/.&#13;
But doubts as to the true extent and actual characteristics of the&#13;
housing problem arise when an examination is made of the conventional&#13;
1/   See, for example, Utria (1966b), Altimir (1969), Tabak (1973), Rosenbluth&#13;
(1976).&#13;
2/   This factor may give rise to marked biases when the poor are identified&#13;
principally on the basis of housing indicators.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 63 -&#13;
standards used in defining housing deficits, their economic feasibility and&#13;
their technological pertinence to the realities of the particular country&#13;
(World Bank, 1975) (Mabogunje, Misra and Hardoy, 1976), and also when note is&#13;
taken that "the majority of peripheral settlements are the result of ingenious&#13;
efforts by low-income families already established in the cities to satisfy&#13;
their own needs for housing and security ..." by means of non-conventional&#13;
housing "solutions" (ECLA, 1975).&#13;
In these circumstances, the only possibility is to ask what private&#13;
expenditure is normally required to gain access to a dwelling that can be&#13;
considered minimally adequate, given the limitations imposed by the current&#13;
supply of housing, building materials and serviced urban land. However, the&#13;
reply will be valid only in the individual case. Solution of the housing&#13;
problem for all families that might consider themselves -- even on the most&#13;
realistic criteria -- to be inadequately housed would in the majority of&#13;
countries require mobilization of resources, planning efforts, enforcement of&#13;
housing standards and modification of the functioning of the private housing&#13;
market -- on a scale beyond the possibilities that exist for making stop-gap&#13;
adjustments in the prevailing system.&#13;
The heuristic procedure utilized here to ensure that the estimates&#13;
on which poverty lines are based allow reasonable coverage of the resources&#13;
needed in finding an imaginative solution, on the individual plane, to the&#13;
low-cost housing problem consists in verifying whether the annual expenditure&#13;
on housing by the groups of households examined for purposes of determining&#13;
the ratios between food and other expenditure covers the annual cost of a&#13;
relatively conventional minimum dwelling.&#13;
Computation of that annual amount, the results of which are set out&#13;
in Table 8, is based on the cost of a dwelling having 60 m2 of total area&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 64 -&#13;
(i.e. approximately 12 m2 of livable space per person) at unit construction&#13;
costs brought below the private market average by design econamies, and on the&#13;
assumption that the cost of serviced land equals 25 percent of basic structure&#13;
costi/. A third assumption is that a 25-year loan at 10 percent per annum&#13;
exists for the total purchase price -- the most favorable terms available.&#13;
Resulting total annual housing costs, expressed as monthly installments, equal&#13;
one percent of the value of the purchase price of the dwelling, which is the&#13;
usual rental percentage in many Latin American cities.&#13;
Table 8 also shows annual expenditure on housing by the households&#13;
selected as relevant for analysis of the consumption patterns applicable to&#13;
poverty thresholds. In some cases, this expenditure is higher than the&#13;
estimated annual purchase cost of a minimum dwelling, but, generally speaking,&#13;
this is due to the fact that these averages include imputed rents for owner-&#13;
occupied dwellings, a factor that tends to be overestimated in the surveys&#13;
which are the source of the data. Taking this into consideration, actual&#13;
expenditure on housing by households somewhat above the food threshold tends&#13;
to be equal to or lower than the annual purchase cost of a minimum dwelling of&#13;
the conventional type. This estimate, nonetheless, serves only as a rough&#13;
frame of reference for the extremely wide range of specific situations and&#13;
requirements. In many cases, actual family expenditure on housing corresponds&#13;
to imaginative solutions for the satisfaction of housing needs in an&#13;
unfavorable environment.&#13;
1/   For information on the grounds underlying this assumption, see World Bank&#13;
(1975a), Annex 4, and United Nations (1977), Table 14. 100 m2 lots at&#13;
prices between US$4 and US$9 per m2 are envisaged. These figures apply,&#13;
in the majority of cases, to semi-urbanized areas where only essential&#13;
services are provided.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 65 -&#13;
Cal  0)-r&#13;
,-4  I-i&#13;
0    44 W -4&#13;
to  o &#13;
U)  Oi- JJLiS &lt;       U     &lt;,_&#13;
O'                                             44id  H -  c  -  i  i  -&#13;
*, to 0 -w                           -&#13;
0                                 co&#13;
o)                    X                        4-I&#13;
ow     w                             $4         0&#13;
}o                                   0          0&#13;
0      )                             HT 0  o X Q  n  o&#13;
g~~~~~~- IT --t -4 C n Ln        ..    &#13;
cD    X      aj~~~~c                      :j          C&#13;
z                                0~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
Z                                              U) o)&#13;
z                                              r.         p H&#13;
OP~~~4               *-r-    0' C' ~o                    -&#13;
CD                                       -H P0'. C  .  i, H &#13;
c)o Ca                              4i)&#13;
0  m  "  "  m  m  --T "0         '&#13;
H o          H U)                              H    z     C&#13;
0&#13;
A: r-                                                m =  o4no &#13;
En  0                                                       co 3 &#13;
00  H 10                                               44&gt;&#13;
0)&#13;
0D      o                                           *0  0&#13;
a)~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~U                      4-X) W o&#13;
pw  r-  -H  C)   Ln   C)   C)   0   Ln   C)  5~~f  0  4~&#13;
M       w~q     CDC1 C     L  C  0)      10    H&#13;
HU)fi -  HO' %D 00 r 0'  C-n  HI  H&#13;
z                       cn CN P- -I  cn coo                  aJ&#13;
Ca O      0O&#13;
^ a^   a) g H  o  o m o      0'      H   'd&#13;
z~~~~~U CO C' CJ4 C&lt; CH O~           C'0 O )  0)  0)    U&#13;
rz~~~~~~~~H                          4-)~~~~~~~~~~~  0)  'd&#13;
n            cd                               -4  U-  e&#13;
n                                                     C: -4  a&#13;
Co  E-4d                                         o     -4   44&#13;
z C;      ~~~~~~W  w  .T                          0 S &#13;
co C)                                4J 0   0)&#13;
.                                   - e)  0  L,  0 &#13;
H  0-    0 ' C    H  0 L I         o   UW    o&#13;
-H                               -H C  H  C  C  C  )  C  b O &#13;
Cd 44                     u~~~'  Oi  'd &#13;
pq 0                              0 E4       - H&#13;
a~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ co C         ) 4 O O&#13;
en                       ~~~~~~~~~~~~~4i 0 D co w&#13;
m O  0H &#13;
V-H  4 4&#13;
0I   0  1 O )&#13;
4-4  ci) 44 &#13;
co    C d  f  la&#13;
0  ('4                  4..)~~~~~~~~~~~- U) C  0  f4 r&#13;
U0      H    c-o&#13;
0     -  0or-            - O4    H   0&#13;
~U)0        &lt;                        4-  C e A U)  H&#13;
0 -{ D   O         A &lt; v o4 0  0&#13;
000 N o _I -H                 4 &#13;
Co     - H                      H $4&#13;
SJp 0      4              - C 0 ) 4-I&#13;
&lt;4   m   u   u  P4   &gt;  co~i  4-4  ol&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 66 -&#13;
Both sets of circumstances lead to a conclusion that the poverty&#13;
lines drawn at double the minimum food budget allow reasonable coverage -- in&#13;
the countries examinedi/ -- of the resources essential for renting a minimum&#13;
dwelling, or purchasing it if adequate financing is available. In any event,&#13;
the fact that this type of financing is scarce, and that the rental market for&#13;
low-cost dwellings is limited, makes it necessary to view housing needs fron a&#13;
wider standpoint than that of poverty.&#13;
F.   Access to public services&#13;
The welfare of low-income groups depends heavily on whether or not&#13;
they have access to free or highly subsidized public services such as&#13;
education, health care and recreation!!. In practice, inequalities of access&#13;
to these services in some countries impair the distribution of welfare&#13;
obtained through private consumption and aggravate the incidence of poverty.&#13;
This suggests the need to take account of the actual access of each&#13;
household to these services when minimum private consumption budgets are being&#13;
computed, so that the dimensions of poverty can be ascertained with greater&#13;
1/   Perhaps with the exception of Brazil (see Table 8).&#13;
2/   In view of the direct impact these specific services -- which substitute&#13;
for private consumption expenditure -- have on the welfare of each&#13;
households, further imputation to households of the cost of collectively&#13;
shared "public goods" (Aaron and McGuire, 1970) proves, in the best of&#13;
circumstances, to be a problem either remote from the present analysis or&#13;
best left aside, as proposed by Meerman (1977), on the grounds that,&#13;
given their inevitability, they should be regarded as general public&#13;
services.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 67 -&#13;
precision, but, unfortunately, only very few quantitative studies are&#13;
available on this question!/.&#13;
In consequence, it cannot be said which of the households below the&#13;
poverty lines based on private consumption have effective access to free&#13;
public services and are therefore less poor than households with the same&#13;
purchasing power but no access to them. Perhaps more significant still is the&#13;
lack of knowledge on households which may show consumption expenditure above&#13;
the estimated poverty lines while being deprived of education, health and&#13;
sanitary services and therefore unable to satisfy their basic needs.&#13;
In these circumstances, it is only possible to ascertain whether&#13;
poverty-line budgets allow reasonable coverage of the complementary private&#13;
consumption expenditure households have to incur to ensure their access to&#13;
free public services, since capacity to sustain that expenditure is a&#13;
necessary -- though not sufficient -- condition for securing such access.&#13;
The surveys referred to in Table 7 show that the households selected&#13;
as relevant for analysis of the consumption patterns applicable to poverty&#13;
thresholds had direct education-related expenditure of US$4-10 and health-&#13;
related expenditure of US$30-80 per year per household in 1970. These amounts&#13;
were barely sufficient to cover complementary expenditure on school supplies&#13;
and medicines, respectively.&#13;
Beyond this verification, the only possibility is to reflect on the&#13;
reach of public social infrastructure services in each country and on the&#13;
1/   Attention is drawn to the study by Selowsky (1976) on the distribution of&#13;
public services by income groups in Colombia, which included a survey on&#13;
the actual access of households to the following: education, health&#13;
care, electric power, running water, sewerage, public lighting and trash&#13;
collection. Also notable is the study by Foxley, Aninat and Arellano&#13;
(1976) on the incidence of public expenditure; it included an examination&#13;
of the distribution of expenditure on education and health care, based on&#13;
the results of user surveys.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 68 -&#13;
probability that the poor have access to them. In itself, this question is&#13;
important in the inter-regional comparison of the results obtained, since if&#13;
that probability is less in one country than in another, the former may have&#13;
more instances of non-satisfaction of basic needs than are apparent fran the&#13;
poverty lines.&#13;
As the provision of social services in the Latin American countries&#13;
is predominantly publicl/, national differences in the reach of these services&#13;
is reflected approximately by the indicators given in Table 9.&#13;
The magnitude of each indicator can be taken as representing the&#13;
probability of access the population of the particular country has to the&#13;
various services. If the service were equitably distributed, this probability&#13;
would be the same for all social strata. However, everything points to the&#13;
fact that low-income groups experience the greatest difficulties of access to&#13;
available social services and that their probability of access is therefore&#13;
below the average. And perhaps that probability diminishes even further the&#13;
less extended a particular service is, since restricted conditions of supply&#13;
tend to favor access by the middle and higher groups in the population.&#13;
This line of reasoning is borne out by an examination of Table 9,&#13;
which shows that children from poor households in Argentina or Chile have a&#13;
seven percent probability of not attending primary school, while that&#13;
probability is over 40 percent in Ecuador and Mexico. The probabilities of&#13;
non-access to secondary schooling are over 70 percent in some countries and as&#13;
high as 85 percent in others.&#13;
Likewise, the probabilities of access to health care services are&#13;
triple (in Argentina and Uruguay) or double (in Brazil, Chile, Costa Rica and&#13;
1/   Whether provided by public agencies or, as with health care services, by&#13;
the social security system.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 69 -&#13;
a au d      - 0 C - * n   0 v s   * Cs CO&#13;
w d    b- e  L( )  OC -ST0t a O  u oO  I)  H  'D&#13;
o  &gt;  S4        %D  I:r s  t   r -   Ln   U) &#13;
39    P&#13;
0)0)&#13;
&gt;   X &#13;
En   4    0 0 -O o 0  e4 cs0 H O  -4 Cs&#13;
:3   C'4   c l  '   r.0   H  cn  LA  H  cn  .T&#13;
4.)&#13;
Cd&#13;
:3&#13;
H   cd '.. .. &#13;
.   P     CD r a 0 o  a  o   0 o   C. a&#13;
cQ  ~ '-  r-  i -  00o  a'  a'  I -  O r-.  a  co&#13;
0&#13;
CO0) C4&#13;
QenCl  -d-  0'  a   'IO  r-  Cl)  r-  -t r&#13;
Cl~~~~~~l&#13;
cn         coX &#13;
|_    =~~ W X X&#13;
co  4-C.1 &#13;
H        H H   H &#13;
0'                                                    0&#13;
C ^   X                              C)&#13;
H              4.)  '.0  a' 0 ' UM )  O  H r-  'T %0   ' 0D  a&#13;
-H   i)  %O  i- m   r-  %. o"  I)n  O   O  c   4W&#13;
Z;           oJ.                            * .   . . .  - . . . &#13;
z:           v=C                                  -H1^11^ Uc &#13;
H  ~ ~ ~ ~ c   LA  C   Cl;  Cl  H4  H  Cl  C'J  LA  C')4&#13;
o~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~c&#13;
H                                                  tJ&#13;
v)~~~$ Q) X     na      soo &#13;
0  il&#13;
-H                                      co nH&lt;nn &#13;
00  C&#13;
c     LA  Itoo It o  00  *.T 0o  t   0   00 -  &#13;
Cl  Cl  H  )  Cl   H HoC ; l  Cl&#13;
0~~S                                   0) =00SUo &#13;
'14   m4  1.&#13;
4 a) Hwri&#13;
OCo&#13;
o                                    W~~~~~~~~~~~~c&#13;
~- ~ Cc  -c .  .  A  .  " i0  Cl    a&#13;
Clcc co   C  co  Cl  -  0   C&#13;
4.1$.)$.        0         3 &#13;
co.                     00 )&#13;
*r4   r 4  V  CU  -H:   to )&#13;
0) M  04-i  -H  '0  H  U  w  ~0  0)&#13;
wf  C  o 0   is   0   ~N   .  p  a&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 70 -&#13;
Panama) those observed elsewhere (in Colombia, Mexico and Peru); confirmation&#13;
of this is seen in the differences in the probability of death between one and&#13;
four years of age. The probability that the low-income urban population will&#13;
have potable water supply is considerably less than 70 percent in almost all&#13;
countries in the region, while the probability they will have sewerage service&#13;
is barely 35 percent.&#13;
It should also be remembered that this rough attempt to summarize&#13;
the situation as regards probable access among the poor to public services&#13;
excludes any consideration of the differences in the quality of these&#13;
services, as between countries or as between poor and more affluent groups.&#13;
The appreciable differences in the probabilities of access to&#13;
education and health care among low-income population groups in the various&#13;
countries examined blur to some extent the comparability of those estimates of&#13;
the poverty dinmension obtained from private consumption poverty lines.&#13;
Probabilities of access to urban infrastructure services, on the other hand,&#13;
seem to have no significant effect on that comparability. This is not to say,&#13;
however, that, in combination with problems of access to adequate housing,&#13;
they are not typical of the housing deficit situations which affect more&#13;
households in each country than those lying below the national poverty lines.&#13;
That being so, further attention should be given to the problem of&#13;
access by the poor to each type of public service so that the present figures&#13;
on the incidence of poverty in Latin America obtained from the study of&#13;
private consumption may be qualified in some fashion.&#13;
G.   Resulting poverty lines&#13;
Table 10 shows the poverty lines estimated according to the&#13;
procedures explained. Given for each country in its own currency at 1970&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 71 -&#13;
Cd o    Ln  N    cn  o    Ln   &lt;    n   C1   C   N &#13;
O d     -t  00   14  't   CS  rb   U)   CS  CS4 %D    0&#13;
H 00 p  &lt;zr  c   c 0D     L    PI  c'S  C   C'   PI   .&#13;
-C               H    4    J    -   r   c o   cUJ  . o &#13;
.4&#13;
4Xa                 H        r- -&lt;         H    CH  '.&#13;
oa)&#13;
.-      -    0 oN o0       U%  -0  -N   %D  eN    P   0i&#13;
co    w      Cf) i     C4  It   0)  Un   14   0O  %.0  CY)~  -I&#13;
C     X X     N a ) :3  -              H   H      eN   H&#13;
94 ;&gt;                                               04 o &lt; o &#13;
Ci~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~e&#13;
o       0&#13;
*  0  bo   4q  WI   WI   .-4  0   0  CD  c  Ir'-  cn  eN  -.7&#13;
4~C!S co  .- -.7   Lfn  en   eN4  IT  00   Hq  1-4  ON&#13;
. ,n       - I  --T  Ltn %.0  .4t  0D  w-4  r  -t   -t  "a&#13;
, ~  ~   4     o C             H        H    c'S      H    c'  oo&#13;
I-I&#13;
P4            ~~~~r-4 Cd  r-4  Un  cvn '.0  0  0  0   r-   00  CN  '.0&#13;
P4            0 4)~O~  r-  It  ,-4  -T  '0   Hi   a,% LIn  0    a%  It&#13;
Z.      -        'IO  %D  -7   -1 H  HLr         -z  %O&#13;
0                                   1-4      r       -4  e      n    00&#13;
w                                   ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~C'J&#13;
a'            ~~~~~~~4J&#13;
cn&#13;
Z -4 _r&#13;
0&#13;
'-  -4CT cnr&#13;
O ~ ~ ~   ~   ~   ~   ~  I eD      a'  0    .         O   '0  H&#13;
E v) tn coo0                 C    I        0                 H o      eN   H&#13;
m  X E-4 r--HO               0    CO       a   '.O   eN  Ca'  H   '.  cs   a'&#13;
   a   o                                  "4  04   CY) -s        V) cs  n4 0&#13;
41                              H                                     L&#13;
&gt;N        ~~~~~~CO  XC &#13;
P o                z&#13;
p..&#13;
a)&#13;
CO H    eN  O    0    a%  0    0   '.0  -    %O a%     %C&#13;
o Cd   .t  a'   H   Nt  r-   cc   It   e'4  .   c    - 1&#13;
&gt;               ~~~~~0$.  a' c   H    e    c                     r N C  a  '&#13;
C) u             04 5.'a          C    H    e   -         N   '.   . &#13;
co&#13;
4J&#13;
H&#13;
Hc co       -1 0  '0  '.  0    0    0   Y) 0 0   -0  eN&#13;
la     -. a  a'0  ei  a'  e    e    C)  H4    0  cc  Ca4&#13;
14  N)  Cf) 0     eN   Nt      e1   r-  '.0o  H4&#13;
&gt;                U                               c&#13;
q   C4)  H   .0   O        0    I0   0        Cu  cl&#13;
0 )  4  ON  C1    a%  a)       00   r-   -    i0  N&#13;
00  N0   0    X4  H        en C    X     C O  C0)&#13;
CO   u   H    CO   C   C)   O   X    Q.  S &#13;
                 -4                         %D 1)t)  1 &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 72 -&#13;
prices, they signify the levels below which households are regarded as being&#13;
unable to satisfy their basic needs.&#13;
"Destitution lines" are also given, corresponding to the cost of&#13;
each country-specific minimum food basket, it being very probable that&#13;
households with total incomes below these levels suffer severe nutritional&#13;
deficitsl/.&#13;
The poverty lines are expressed in national currencies so they may&#13;
be compared unequivocally with household incomes in the particular country.&#13;
The widespread practice of expressing them in dollars leads to all the&#13;
difficulties inherent in the international comparison of prices and of the&#13;
purchasing power of different currencies.&#13;
In order to facilitate comparison of the poverty lines obtained for&#13;
the Latin American countries both among themselves and with those employed in&#13;
worldwide studies (World Bank, 1975b; ILO, 1976), conversion into dollars is&#13;
nonetheless conveinent. This has been done in Table 11 in two alternative&#13;
ways, the first of which utilizes dollar exchange rates2/.&#13;
The estimated minimum food budgets -- which we have also taken as&#13;
constituting destitution lines -- vary from US$70 to US$130 (at 1970 prices)&#13;
per capita per year, depending on the country. This relative uniformity can&#13;
be ascribed to the absolute nature of the poverty criterion utilized and to&#13;
the application of the same procedures in establishing consumption standards.&#13;
1/   All reference to "extreme", "grave" or "critical" poverty has been&#13;
avoided since these adjectives have no precise conceptual content.&#13;
2/   In order to avoid possible distortions resulting from the restricted&#13;
applicability of official exchange rates, use is made of the average&#13;
exchange rates at which each country paid for its imports.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-73-&#13;
0   0 N      N C   0'  N  '&#13;
0&gt;                             C&#13;
CO                               U&#13;
C .~~~~~O &#13;
4.4  0&#13;
mm m  04 &#13;
C'  )                            -&#13;
04C&#13;
oa,                               C:&#13;
CO  04,,0  r4  a,  I-      .6  .    0&#13;
04  0.                              U -  &#13;
.04u   c:                             -&#13;
&gt; 4  0404&#13;
0  04    -    - -4  N -   N -~   N-&#13;
C4  C   0 &gt;                          04&#13;
0~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~0&#13;
cc 0 .  04 ..                            -&#13;
o 4 C N  0   IC  CCc 0  C '0&#13;
0  U   .- ~ ~  'r    0  CCc&#13;
C-                                  '0~~~~~~~~~~1&#13;
-4 ~   ccc          0 C'  0a,&#13;
C&gt;&#13;
v       4C&#13;
W4.            o                        C:&#13;
0~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~&#13;
CC'                                  '0~~&#13;
-4  04&#13;
.0.CC   CC  NaC) N   C  N .  N&#13;
&gt;     4&#13;
04r &#13;
.2  04 c'  '0 '0 C   '   C,  CC CC 0&#13;
o0        a,&#13;
C'  04 ~ ~ ~   OC 00  0&#13;
-4  '0  04CCcl, &#13;
E-.  C  040  '0 C  n  n i  0  . CC N 0 &#13;
0  C&gt; ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~  ~  0&#13;
04 ~ ~ 04W          o &#13;
~~~  C'                           04 W 0   :&#13;
0        00~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~0&#13;
0~~~ W          .0  a  00W a&#13;
Qi   COU           w  ~ E n1 )&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 74 -&#13;
The corresponding lines of absolute poverty therefore vary between&#13;
US$1$50 and US$250 (1970 prices) of annual household consumption per person,/.&#13;
These levels are somewhat higher than those employed in the&#13;
previously mentioned global studies to obtain regional estimates of poverty.&#13;
For the most part, the differences are ascribable to the fact that the present&#13;
estimates are explicitly normative and more area-specific.&#13;
The World Bank (1975b) uses two arbitrary lines of US$50 and US$75&#13;
(1969 prices) per capita to estimate the numbers of the poor in the developing&#13;
countries. However, these lines tend essentially to reflect subsistence&#13;
conditions prevailing in the rural areas of Asia and Africa, where 80 percent&#13;
of the developing world's poor are concentrated (World Bank, 1975b, p. 79) and&#13;
include only a very modest allocation for basic non-food needsll.&#13;
ILO (1976) sets a minimum subsistence income of US$50 per capita and&#13;
a poverty line of US$100 for Asia, and on that basis estimates a "destitution"&#13;
line of US$90 per capita and a "serious poverty" line of US$180 per capita per&#13;
annum for Latin Americ,3/.&#13;
The poverty lines shown in Table 11, converted to dollars in terms&#13;
of exchange rates, represent the sum in international-trade dollars that would&#13;
be needed to purchase the staple basket within the particular country, but&#13;
they may be deceptive to the extent they suggest a lesser quantum of goods --&#13;
1/   It may be useful to know that these sums would be US$205 and US$340,&#13;
respectively, at 1975 prices.&#13;
2/   Similar estimates, from the same source, on the minimum nutritional needs&#13;
of the rural population of certain Latin American countries are&#13;
comparable in value to the minimum food budgets employed in the present&#13;
text for rural areas and which vary between US$65 and US$100 (1970) per&#13;
capita.&#13;
3/   On "the hypothesis that a typical basket of products consumed by the poor&#13;
which costs one dollar in Western Europpe may be bought for 20 cents in&#13;
Asia .... and 36 cents in Latin America".   (ILO, 1976, p. 23).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 75 -&#13;
by comparison with the industrialized economies -- than that actually&#13;
involved. For instance, they are not directly comparable with real per capita&#13;
income in the countries to which they apply when that incomne has been&#13;
calculated in dollars using purchasing power parities that match each&#13;
country's price levels with those of the US up to the point at which they&#13;
represent the same purchasing power (Gilbert and Kravis, 1954; Kravis,&#13;
Kennessey, Heston and Summers, 1975). Even less do they represent the sums&#13;
that would be required in the U.S. to pay for an"equivalent" staple basket.&#13;
In all the Latin American countries in 1970, purchasing power parities with&#13;
the U.S. were lower than the respective exchange rates (ECLA, 1977) as a&#13;
result of lower relative price levels for the goods which make up the&#13;
expenditure component in GDP. Put in other terms, the internal purchasing&#13;
power of the local currency equivalent of one dollar at the exchange rate was,&#13;
in all countries, superior to that of the dollar.&#13;
The usefulness of the second criterion employed in Table 11 is&#13;
therefore apparent, as it allows the conversion of poverty lines to dollars&#13;
through purchasing power parities of the Latin American countries employed at&#13;
the present time by ECLA (1977). According to this second criterion, the&#13;
estimated minimum food budgets would be between US$90 and US$150 per capita&#13;
and the lines of poverty between US$160 and US$300 per capita per annum.&#13;
But even this conversion criteria only takes account of general&#13;
price levels in each country and in the U.S. Private consumption price levels&#13;
in the Latin American countries may prove to be 30 percent and even 40 percent&#13;
below the U.S. level (Braithwaite, 1968; Grunwald and Salazar, 1975).&#13;
Consequently, the internal purchasing power of certain Latin American&#13;
currencies in relation to consumption goods may be over 60 percent higher than&#13;
it is internationally. Given the even lower relative levels of staple food&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 76 -&#13;
prices, the purchasing power of the same currencies in relation to this class&#13;
of goods is higher still. An approximate costing of the standard staple food&#13;
baskets at the prices paid in the U.S. for goods as nearly similar as possible&#13;
resulted in food budgets of between US$240 and US$300 (1970 prices) per capita&#13;
per annum, and over US$400 for Argentina and Uruguay1/ (V. Annex D). Although&#13;
these calculations are biased toward overestimation, owing to the inevitable&#13;
inclusion of better-quality goods that make up the basic Latin American&#13;
baskets, they do demonstrate that in Latin America the latter probably cost&#13;
well under 50 percent of what they would in the industrialized countries.&#13;
International comparison of the poverty lines estimated for the&#13;
Latin American countries may leave an impression they are too high. From the&#13;
standpoint of guaranteeing mere subsistence at the cheapest cost possible,&#13;
that may be true. But the poverty lines estimated here correspond to a&#13;
standard of basic needs satisfaction in the framework of the patterns of&#13;
consumption, expectations and technology of needs satisfaction projected by&#13;
the style of development prevailing in the Latin American societies. In terms&#13;
of the distinction drawn by Sen (1978), these lines are more "cultural" than&#13;
"physiological". The definition of dietary standards that take account of&#13;
local habits, and the estimation of standard minimum budgets based on actual&#13;
allocation of resources to each group of goods, mean that these absolute&#13;
poverty lines have been drawn with reference to the predominant style of&#13;
living.&#13;
This predominant lifestyle, to which the great majority of the&#13;
population of Latin America aspires -- in actual fact, and from a deep sense&#13;
1/   Compared to the $330 per capita minimum food budget covered by the&#13;
poverty line of $992 per capita per annum estimated in 1970 for a four-&#13;
person family by the U.S. Social Security Administration (1975).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 77 -&#13;
of conviction, which is the source of its predominance -- is not necessarily&#13;
expressed in the magnitudes associated with average welfare. It is the&#13;
lifestyle projected from the industrialized countries and which, in Latin&#13;
America, is transmitted through consumer marketing, the mass media and the&#13;
values of the leading groups.&#13;
This accounts for the considerable uniformity in the style of living&#13;
to which the mass of the population in almost any Latin American country&#13;
aspires, a uniformity that lies beyond any differences in welfare or resource&#13;
levels. As far as the procedure of measurement was concerned, this fact&#13;
facilitated the drawing of poverty lines based on specific norms for each&#13;
country but which responded to the same normative criteria. Nevertheless, it&#13;
was the poverty lines applicable to urban areas that were drawn on a specific&#13;
basis; the lines applicable to the rural population were derived from the&#13;
former, so that lines applicable on the national scale could be obtained.&#13;
Apart from the scant nature of the data available on levels of living in rural&#13;
areas, already referred to, it might be argued that rural communities do not&#13;
share the lifestyle seen in the cities of Latin America. This is undoubtedly&#13;
the case as far as average levels of living are concerned, but the extent of&#13;
rural emigration to urban areas demonstrates that the lifestyle which may be&#13;
considered predominant, and which is in evidence among affluent urban groups&#13;
and in the attractions of the urban environment, is also the point of&#13;
reference and aspiration for the majority of the rural population. In those&#13;
countries where the traditional lifestyle of the rural community continues to&#13;
exert an attraction -- though at welfare levels which are higher than the&#13;
present average -- our poverty lines will tend to overestimate the magnitude&#13;
of rural poverty to some extent.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 78 -&#13;
At all events, the poverty lines estimated here constitute a valid&#13;
tool in the present exercise, aimed at obtaining a comparative evaluation of&#13;
poverty. They may also provide the starting point for closer research in each&#13;
country, but for that purpose they would of course have to be verified through&#13;
actual field studies. Furthermore, they might be utilized in the formulation&#13;
of policy, although in that case the particular Government should review the&#13;
underlying normative criteria to ascertain whether they coincide with its own&#13;
judgments.&#13;
VI&#13;
THE EXTENT OF POVERTY IN THE LATIN AMERICAN COUNTRIES&#13;
Estimates are that 40 percent of households in Latin America live in&#13;
poverty, meaning that they cannot purchase the minimum basket of goods&#13;
required for the satisfaction of their basic needs, and that 20 percent of all&#13;
households live in destitution, meaning that they lack the means of buying&#13;
even the food that would provide them with a minimally adequate diet.&#13;
These estimates have been obtained by applying the lines of absolute&#13;
poverty and destitution to approximate distributions of households by level of&#13;
per capita consumption in the major countries of the region.&#13;
A.   The data on income distribution and consumption&#13;
The reasons why per capita household consumption provides the best&#13;
approximate measure of the level of living have already been given.&#13;
Therefore, the poverty lines estimated as per capita figures for all&#13;
households, regardless of their size, should cut off the distribution of&#13;
households by size of their per capita consumption.&#13;
Data on the distribution of income by size, collected during one or&#13;
more household surveys conducted about 1970, are available for each of the&#13;
countries considered (V. Annex E). For some countries, it was also possible&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 79 -&#13;
to obtain special tabulations on the distribution of households by levels of&#13;
per capita consumptioriL. In the remaining cases, estimates of the incidence&#13;
of poverty had to be based on available distributions by household income&#13;
level and per capita income level, and on data showing the ratio existing&#13;
between the distribution of households according to those concepts and&#13;
according to per capita consumption.&#13;
In Latin America, household income as measured through household&#13;
survey data is very often significantly underestimated, and to degrees that&#13;
differ depending on the type of income (Altimir, 1975). Such biases lead to&#13;
overestimation of poverty defined in absolute terms, and, since they differ&#13;
according to the type of income, they also affect the measurement of poverty&#13;
defined in relative terms. It is therefore necessary to adjust distributions&#13;
by income levels when they show significant bias, in an attempt to cancel out&#13;
its effects.&#13;
Given the limitations of the data available, all surveys taken&#13;
around 1970 in the countries considered were used simultaneously in estimating&#13;
the incidence of poverty, provided they were reasonably reliable; these are&#13;
the surveys listed in Annex E. A number of them cover urban areas only,&#13;
although there is at least a survey having national coverage for almost all&#13;
the countries; in these cases, estimates were made at both levels.&#13;
The poverty lines given in Table 10 were recalculated at the prices&#13;
in force during the period of reference of each survey so that they could then&#13;
be used as cut-offs on the respective distributions.&#13;
1/   These tabulations were kindly provided by the Office of the Coordinator,&#13;
ECIEL Program, from survey data obtained in Colombia, Chile, Ecuador,&#13;
Peru and Venezuela.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 80 -&#13;
Annex E indicates the percentages of households below the lines of&#13;
poverty and destitution obtained when drawing those lines across the original&#13;
distributions available from each survey, depending on whether households are&#13;
classified according to total household income, per capita household income or&#13;
per capita household consumption. As a rule, these results are affected by&#13;
biases of under-declaration and by omissions associated with the concept&#13;
utilized, and, in the majority of cases, because they are based on total&#13;
household income rather than per capita consumption.&#13;
So as to have estimates of the incidence of poverty in each country&#13;
that would be more precise and more easily compared, survey results were&#13;
adapted in successive steps. In the first instance, the distributions by size&#13;
for each income type were adjusted to the corresponding estimates from the&#13;
national accounts, in an effort to cancel out the effects of under-declaration&#13;
and omission in each survey. Further corrections were then made to reconcile&#13;
distributions by income level with the concept of disposable household income.&#13;
The proportion of households in which per capita consumption lies&#13;
below the poverty line is generally lower than the proportion of households in&#13;
which total income falls below the corresponding lines of poverty per&#13;
household'/. The regrouping of households occurring with the conversion from&#13;
per household figures to per capita figures may have some influence on this&#13;
result, although on occasions it has a slight effect in the opposite&#13;
direction. But what does deternine that result, in almost all the household&#13;
budget surveys analyzed, is that the households at the base of the pyramid&#13;
show more expenditure than income. Even allowing for the general&#13;
1/   In general, the transformation of poverty lines from per capita figures&#13;
to per household figures was effected by employing average household&#13;
sizes around the poverty threshold.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 81 -&#13;
underestimation of income in some of the surveys, between 30 and 60 percent of&#13;
households with lower incomes show consumption/income ratios considerably&#13;
greater than unityl./&#13;
It has been suggested that these results are caused by short-term&#13;
disequilibria in many consumption units due to purchase of durable goods and&#13;
receipt of transitory income (Musgrove and Howe, 1973; Prieto Duran, 1977).&#13;
But the widespread occurrence of such situations and their systematic&#13;
appearance in all the surveys weakens this explanation. Another possible&#13;
source of real dis-saving may be found in the nominally growing indebtedness&#13;
in periods of inflation. But even so, the impression lingers that consumption&#13;
is measured more accurately than income -- even after more or less general&#13;
adjustments are made to this variable -- or that income measurement does not&#13;
fully capture the accumulation of resources that low-income households manage&#13;
to obtain in order to cope with their deprivation.&#13;
These lines of reasoning and the information obtained from certain&#13;
surveys were used as the basis for transforming distributions by income level&#13;
into assumed distributions by per capita consumption, the latter being&#13;
regarded as reasonable approximations, at least for the lower half of the&#13;
pyramid.&#13;
B.   The incidence of poverty&#13;
Data from the various surveys conducted in each country served as&#13;
the basis for estimating the indexes of the incidence of poverty presented in&#13;
Table 12. These reveal the percentage of poor and destitute households in the&#13;
urban areas of each country examined and at the national level. The table&#13;
also slhows the percentages of incidence deduced residually for rural areas,&#13;
1/   V. Junac (1976) and Musgrove (1976).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 82 -&#13;
but, given the limited nature of the basic data and the procedures utilized,&#13;
these percentages should be regarded as no more than rough approximations of&#13;
the extent of rural poverty.&#13;
TABLE 12&#13;
ESTIMATES OF THE INCIDENCE OF POVERTY AROUND 1970&#13;
% of households                 % of households&#13;
below the poverty line       below the destitution line&#13;
Urban   Rural    National      Urban   Rural   National&#13;
Argentina                 5      19        8             1       1        1&#13;
Brazil                   35      73       49            15      42       25&#13;
Colombia                 38      54       45            14      23       18&#13;
Costa Rica               15      30       24             5       7        6&#13;
Chile                    12      25       17             3      11        6&#13;
Honduras                 40      75       65            15      57       45&#13;
Mexico                   20      49       34             6      18       12&#13;
Peru                     28      68       50             8      39       25&#13;
Uruguay                  10     ---      ---             4     ---      ---&#13;
Venezuela                20      36       25             6      19       10&#13;
Latin America            26      62       40            10      34       19&#13;
In certain countries (Brazil, Colombia, Honduras), over a third of&#13;
urban households were in a poverty situation, unable to cover their basic&#13;
needs. In Mexico, Peru and Venezuela, between 20 and 30 percent of urban&#13;
households were poor. In countries such as Costa Rica, Chile or Uruguay,&#13;
however, the incidence of urban poverty was between 10 and 15 percent.&#13;
Argentina showed an even lower incidence, only five percent of urban&#13;
households living in poverty.&#13;
The incidence of poverty among the population as a whole in each&#13;
country is considerably higher than in urban areas, as a consequence of the&#13;
more widespread poverty in rural areas. In countries such as Honduras, it can&#13;
be said that two thirds of the population was living in poverty around 1970.&#13;
In Brazil, Colombia and Peru, poverty affected between 45 and 50 percent of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 83 -&#13;
all households. In Mexico, over a third of the total population was poor,&#13;
while in Costa Rica and Venezuela poverty affected 25 percent of the&#13;
population. In Chile, however, approximately only one-sixth of all households&#13;
were poor, while in Uruguay the proportion was probably lower; in Argentina,&#13;
it is very likely that less than 10 percent of the population was poor.&#13;
These estimates of the incidence of poverty at the national level&#13;
incorporate an evaluation of the extent of rural poverty assessed on normative&#13;
standards more comparable with urban standards than many anthropologists&#13;
working in the region's most traditional and conservative rural communities&#13;
would think desirable. It must also be recognized that available figures on&#13;
rural incomes are less reliable than those measuring urban incomes.&#13;
Despite these shortcomings, the percentages of incidence of rural&#13;
poverty included in Table 12 and derived from the incidence estimated to exist&#13;
at the national and urban levels provide a fairly good indication of the&#13;
relative magnitude of the problem in each country. The extent of rural&#13;
poverty would certainly not be less than 20 percent in Argentina, Costa Rica,&#13;
Chile or Uruguay. In Colombia, Mexico and Venezuela, it could affect between&#13;
a third and a half of the rural population. In Brazil and Peru, over two-&#13;
thirds of rural households are probably poor. In countries like Honduras,&#13;
poverty may be so widespread in the countryside as to affect three-quarters of&#13;
the rural population.&#13;
Within the framework of these estimates on the incidence of poverty,&#13;
attempts have also been made to isolate the probable incidence of situations&#13;
of destitution or, where the purchasing power of a household is too low to&#13;
cover even the cost of minimum food needs. The figures given in Table 12 may&#13;
be taken as relatively more reliable for urban areas than for rural areas,&#13;
where such situations are more difficult to assess using an overall yardstick.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 84 -&#13;
In countries like Brazil, Colombia, Honduras and Peru, between 10&#13;
and 15 percent of urban households may have been destitute or indigent. In&#13;
the other countries, there was thought to be 5 percent destitution, the one&#13;
exception being Argentina, where levels of urban destitution were&#13;
negligible. As a general rule, between a third and a half of the urban poor&#13;
were also destitute.&#13;
Judging by the information available, and after making the&#13;
adjustments mentioned already for underestimations, omissions and changes in&#13;
concepts, the national-scale estimates obtained suggest that in Brazil,&#13;
Colombia and Peru, the number of destitute households may have amounted to and&#13;
even exceeded 20 percent of the population, so that approximately half their&#13;
poor were also destitute. In Mexico, destitution affected 12 percent of the&#13;
population and in Venezuela 10 percent, the implication in both cases being&#13;
that roughly a third of the poor were destitute. In both Costa Rica and&#13;
Chile, destitution affected slightly over five percent of all households. In&#13;
Argentina, only a very minor proportion of the poor were also destitute.&#13;
It would also seem from Table 12 that in countries like Honduras the&#13;
majority of the poor are destitute, a situation which therefore extends to&#13;
between a third and a half of the general population.&#13;
The extent of destituion in rural areas, which underlies these&#13;
estimates drawn up on the national scale, needs to be interpreted with&#13;
considerable caution. One question that arises is whether the destitution&#13;
lines can be applied uniformly to all the rural areas of a country, mainly in&#13;
view of the effect that production for self-consumption can have in enabling a&#13;
household to adapt successfully to an extreme scarcity of resources. Another&#13;
problem arises from the fact that adjustments made to the original data base,&#13;
for underestimation of both production for self-consumption and wages in kind,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 85 -&#13;
were based on general criteria that may not reflect the diversity of&#13;
situations observable among rural households with very low incomes.&#13;
But even if these caveats are respected, the estimates of rural&#13;
destitution given in Table 12 are still an indication that in some cases the&#13;
problem is of terrifying magnitude. More than half the rural population in&#13;
Honduras, and approximately 40 percent of it in Brazil and Peru, may be living&#13;
in destitution. Extreme deprivation may affect roughly 20 percent of rural&#13;
households in Colombia, Mexico and Venezuela. Only in Costa Rice and Chile&#13;
would rural destitution be as low as 10 percent, while in Argentina it is&#13;
perhaps of negligible significance.&#13;
It may be stated that the estimates of the incidence of poverty&#13;
obtained are the lowest that can result from application of the normative&#13;
standards formulated. Annex E sets out the figures that would be obtained in&#13;
the first instance if poverty lines were directly applied to the original data&#13;
generated by each survey -- as published by the entities which carried them&#13;
out -- before any adjustment for underestimation or any attempt to convert&#13;
them into the concept of per capita household consumption. In all cases,&#13;
these figures would give percentages of incidence of poverty higher than those&#13;
estimated in Table 12.&#13;
There is, moreover, a possible source of underestimation of poverty&#13;
in the adjustments based on the average ratios for each type of income and&#13;
socio-economic group, which possibly exaggerate to some extent the magnitude&#13;
of the components omitted by the poor when reporting the size of their&#13;
incomes.&#13;
Taken as a whole, the countries examined in this exercise hold 80&#13;
percent of the regional population. The results obtained for each of them&#13;
served as the basis for estimating functions of the incidence of poverty among&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 86 -&#13;
the urban population and in the population as a wholel, which were then&#13;
utilized in approximating the percentages of households afflicted by absolute&#13;
poverty and by destitution in the entire Latin American population.&#13;
According to these approximations, 40 percent of Latin American&#13;
households were poor, the incidence of poverty among urban households being 26&#13;
percent and among rural households 60 percent.&#13;
As may be seen from Table 13, these estimates are close to those put&#13;
forward by ILO (1976) for the region as a whole. On the other hand, they are&#13;
considerably higher than those used by the World Bank (1975), which result&#13;
from utilization of a single overall poverty line drawn on the basis of&#13;
conditions prevailing in Asia, and which reflects standards that prove very&#13;
low for Latin America.&#13;
It is consequently apparent that in Latin America around 1970 there&#13;
were almost 40 million urban poor, and, if one accepts that there were also 68&#13;
million rural poor, in the region as a whole 107 million persons -- 21 million&#13;
households -- were then living in poverty. Furthermore, almost half these&#13;
households were indigent, without sufficient resources to provide themselves&#13;
even with a minimum adequate diet, let alone their other basic needs.&#13;
1/   These functions, estimated for eight countries, were:&#13;
H(P)NAC  =  244,03     -    31,97     ln PIBPC    r2 = 0,744&#13;
(4,883)        (4,119)&#13;
H(P)URB  =  154,05     -    19,93     ln PIBPC    r2 = 0,661&#13;
(4,078)        (3,397)&#13;
H(I)NAC  =  182,34     -    25,52     ln PIBPC    r2 = 0,727&#13;
(4,381)       (3,948)&#13;
H(I)URB  =   67,79     -     9,15     ln PIBPC    r2 = 0,675&#13;
(4,034)       (3,506)&#13;
where:   H(P) : percentage incidence of poverty&#13;
H(I) : percentage incidence of destitution&#13;
PIBPC: GDP per capita in 1970 dollars.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 87 -&#13;
C d        I-  o~ U                    X   X&#13;
C~~~~~~L      0 U)  ol o0                     C&#13;
O J  4     r.  en  ur&#13;
14 &#13;
Cd&#13;
2-             H &#13;
4-i  4-4&#13;
rO&#13;
0&#13;
P4   co      Lfl  Lfl  H&#13;
o~~~~~c&#13;
~~~        U)&#13;
H~ ~~~      Q C V&#13;
cOH       L 1 0 3 n uP  L&#13;
1w J4     r    O- a'  LO&#13;
0 1 &#13;
H  vO      O   4                a' 0s    CO C&lt;      ~       0&#13;
-4 &gt;           0 &#13;
05 H           Cd                        H         H   H&#13;
E-4 ~~~:)  0~      L1   1   .    4    '   a&#13;
H  HO     0  _I -      r-  '.0  -        00   -0&#13;
CP   4        4           H        co   c'C&#13;
C)         co   0) L4-i  . -4&#13;
O~~~c      &lt;&#13;
E-4H&#13;
co&#13;
0&#13;
H  0   0~~p  CH     LI   .o  r-T  0   Cl4  H.&#13;
4if 444&#13;
r)  e'  u- a        ~  r&#13;
0                                             A&#13;
4-40   H~4  dLn          0   -    C)  c&#13;
&gt;        -~~~~OC  If-.  r  a'       0    r&#13;
P4       00)04  (      %CO           ('4 &#13;
)            C&#13;
4 J -&gt;i       4  O J        4  O &#13;
CDvO            C O          CiO&#13;
t-40 ~ ~~~~       taCo     G    0C       J    0 &#13;
$4 EO to             U)        $4 oo&#13;
&gt;1 H     c1 c                  1 ^ co c&#13;
: co  o  o Lr  c  cs)  o CD  4- cCV 4o &#13;
&lt; 1 "  1  c -  0 n   C4 %D     (   -  $c&#13;
'-4  '-  P.  0       C- P.  0  '  P   0&#13;
E-4  &gt;'44        ..        44 P.'44          ..&#13;
cl             co            C Df  s ne &lt;&#13;
H u)  O   0     U)  O   01   u)  O    0&#13;
U) P  V C.         0 (  .     U  01&#13;
0.H  0  0  0)  0 N  0i 0  0)1   -  0. 4-0  0&#13;
Ss &gt; 4J   a)    En &gt; 4-J  cU  H ) &gt; 4J -4  Q&#13;
%  I  0 CO-  &gt;  H   4   CO  &gt;  '- X  O.  &gt;&#13;
i-s   P.  -.4   01      0P        (a.  -,4.&#13;
(0   0    Q)  4-i 0  r0  oi     0  0&#13;
~~  p4  p  4-4  60  p4  p4  4  0   p4  P4  W-4  t&#13;
H          -4 ~~~4j4     -44-&#13;
0  0  (1) 0  C14 -4  40 w  -4 - &#13;
-H  -H  u  (L)  r-  -ri 44  u  Q)  m  .11 .11 u'-4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 88 -&#13;
C.   The poverty gap&#13;
Indexes of poverty incidence measure the percentage of the&#13;
population that is poor without indicating the extent to which the incomes of&#13;
the poor lie below the poverty line.&#13;
Assuming, with Sen (1976):&#13;
n:    the total population&#13;
z:    the income corresponding to the poverty line&#13;
q:    the number of poor persons (whose   yi ' z)&#13;
m:    the average income of the poor&#13;
m*:   the average income of the population&#13;
Yi:   the income of the individual i&#13;
ci:   the consumption by the individual i&#13;
then the measurement of the incidence of poverty is:&#13;
H = i1&#13;
n&#13;
But for each individual i,&#13;
9      z     Yi-&#13;
an equation that defines his income gap with respect to the poverty line.    The&#13;
aggregate poverty gap would then be:&#13;
T  =      9g  =   q(z - m)&#13;
i=&#13;
This measure does not show the number of poor persons, but only the&#13;
aggregate income shortfall of all the poor taken as a group, or, in other&#13;
words, the total amount of income that would bring all the poor -- whatever&#13;
their number -- up to the poverty line.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 89 -&#13;
However, as Sen (1976) points out, that measure can be easily&#13;
normalised as a percentage per capita gap which indicates the average income&#13;
shortfall of the poor as a group with respect to the poverty line:&#13;
T     z-m&#13;
qz      z&#13;
Sen (1976) has called attention to the fact that T and I are&#13;
insensitive to relative income differences among the poor, while H is&#13;
insensitive to the distance at which the poor stand below the poverty line.&#13;
It is for those reasons that he proposes an index which incorporates income&#13;
inequalities among the poorl/. As the estimates of the extent of poverty&#13;
given in this text are based on grouped data, this index may prove deceptive,&#13;
since only income differences between groups of the poor could really be taken&#13;
into consideration, within-group income differences being left to one side;&#13;
the result would be no more than a partial approximation to the weighting by&#13;
rank order required by Sen's poverty index.&#13;
1/ Sen's poverty index (1976) is:&#13;
P = H[l - (1-I) (1 - G(q/q+l))]&#13;
where G is the Gini coefficient of income distribution among the&#13;
poor. For large q , this expression becomes:&#13;
p  = i [I + (1 - I)G]&#13;
while its standardized value, when each Yi = m , is:&#13;
P = II x 1 - q/n(z-m/z) .&#13;
Sen's proposed measure of poverty uses an ordinal approach to welfare&#13;
comparisons, assigning a greater weight to the income of a poorer person,&#13;
on grounds of equity. It is this weighting by rank order than has the&#13;
effect of correcting the average deficit of the poor by the Gini&#13;
coefficient of their income distribution, weighted by the ratio between&#13;
the average income of the poor and the poverty line.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 90 -&#13;
This present study therefore restricts itself to computing the&#13;
poverty index, without considering income distribution among the poor:&#13;
P  =  H x I  =    Z -m  =   T   ;&#13;
n  z      nz&#13;
in other words, the aggregate income gap of the poor is being expressed as a&#13;
fraction of the total inccme required to maintain the entire population at the&#13;
acceptable minimum level represented by the poverty line. This index takes&#13;
into consideration both the proportion of the poor within the population (H)&#13;
and their average income gap (I).&#13;
The poverty gap T may likewise serve as a base for other&#13;
indicators. Since the poverty lines represent consumption levels, and since&#13;
Yi  = Ci , an index may be formulated to express the additional consumption&#13;
T the poor would need to raise themselves to the poverty level as a fraction&#13;
of aggregate consumption.&#13;
A more frequently used index relates the poverty gap T to the GNP&#13;
of the particular country. Perhaps it would be more appropriate to express --&#13;
as Sen (1976) points out and as Anand (1977) in fact does -- the poverty gap&#13;
sa a fraction of total household income:&#13;
M  =   T         P&#13;
nm*     m*&#13;
and also, as Fishlow (1972) does, to compute the complementary index    F&#13;
which expresses the poverty gap as a percentage of the total income of the&#13;
non-poor:&#13;
F  =&#13;
nm* - qm&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 91 -&#13;
Nevertheless, as Anand (1977) points out, these indexes are not so much&#13;
measures of poverty as indicators of the degree of effort required to&#13;
alleviate it, since they are sensitive to any change in the aggregate income&#13;
of the population above the poverty line, even though the income of the poor&#13;
might remain unchanged.&#13;
Table 14 sets out estimates of the income gap of the poor on a&#13;
national scale for each of the countries examined, in terms of the various&#13;
indicators analyzed, together with the estimated incidence of poverty (H).&#13;
TABLE 14&#13;
ESTIMATES OF VARIOUS MEASURES OF THE INCOME GAP&#13;
OF THE POOR, BY COUNTRY, AROUND 1970 a/&#13;
(percentages)&#13;
H          I           P          M          F&#13;
Argentina                    8        25.5         2.0        0.6        0.6&#13;
Brazil                      49        46.2        21.6        7.0        7.6&#13;
Colombia                    45        48.8       19.9         8.0        8.8&#13;
Costa Rica                  24        43.6         9.9        3.6        3.8&#13;
Chile                       17        43.3        6.2         2.1        2.2&#13;
Honduras                    65        50.9       30.8        17.4       20.9&#13;
Mexico                      34        39.2        12.4        4.1        4.3&#13;
Peru                        50        55.2        26.1       11.8       13.1&#13;
Venezuela                   25        37.5        7.1         2.5        2.6&#13;
a/   V. test for definition of each.&#13;
In the formulation of policies designed to attack poverty, great&#13;
caution should be exercised in interpreting the meaning of indicators deriving&#13;
from the concept of the poverty gap.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 92 -&#13;
In conceptual terms, the poverty gap reflects the proportion of the&#13;
community income that would have to be transferred directly -- without&#13;
leakages -- to the poor in order to raise them, at a given moment, to the&#13;
minimum levels of purchasing power that would enable them to satisfy their&#13;
basic private consumption needs.&#13;
It would be naive, however, to treat this measure of the poverty gap&#13;
as indicative of the actual amount that would have to be transferred in order&#13;
to eliminate poverty in each country. In the first place, to raise low&#13;
incomes permanently requires investment rather than current transfers of&#13;
incane, and in trying to obtain an approximate idea of the resources involved&#13;
capital/income ratios of at least 2 would have to be contemplated, not to&#13;
mention complementary investments in infrastructure, training and additional&#13;
financing. Secondly, allowance would have to be made for the size of the&#13;
leakages of resources to be expected in administering new redistribution&#13;
schemes through bureaucratic machinery never highly regarded for its&#13;
efficiency. In the third place, allowance would have to be made for the&#13;
diversion of resources by the beneficiaries of poverty-alleviation programs&#13;
themselves to ends not consistent with the objectives of those programs,&#13;
diversions which may well prove less effective in satisfying their basic needs&#13;
over the longer terunJ/. When general policy measures that call for indirect&#13;
action are being considered, thought would likewise have to be given to the&#13;
proportion of the resources mobilized for those measures that benefit other&#13;
1/ It may be useful to recall, in this respect, that the allocation of a part&#13;
of income to the satisfaction of needs that may be regarded as not&#13;
essential for subsistence but which are "culturally'" basic was taken into&#13;
account in the drawing of poverty lines according to the procedures&#13;
explained earlier.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 93 -&#13;
groups in the population, and which therefore cannot be accounted for as&#13;
offsetting the poverty gap.&#13;
Finally, it should be remembered that these measures of the gap take&#13;
no account of the magnitude of the penury of access to basic public services&#13;
which afflicts the poor, so that they consequently given no indication of the&#13;
size of the social resources that would have to be applied in providing such&#13;
services.&#13;
If these caveats are heeded, the estimates of the poverty gap&#13;
presented in Table 14 can, in the majority of cases, furnish a comparative&#13;
idea of the relative degree of sacrifice that would be involved in strategies&#13;
designed to alleviate poverty in various Latin American countries.&#13;
The indicator I is a measure of the depth of poverty: in almost&#13;
all the countries in question, the poor as a group have an average purchasing&#13;
power from 40 to 55 percent below the poverty line. Only in Argentina, where&#13;
the national incidence of poverty (H) is considerably less than that observed&#13;
in the other countries, is the average deficit in purchasing power as low as&#13;
25 percent.&#13;
The indicator P , which combines the incidence of poverty (H) with&#13;
its average depth (I), shows that in some countries (Brazil, Colombia,&#13;
Honduras, Peru) the aggregate income gap of the poor amounts to between 20 and&#13;
30 percent of the total income the poor as a group would need to put them&#13;
uniformly at the level of the poverty line. In others (Costa Rica, Mexico),&#13;
this indicator is in the vicinity of 10 percent, while in Argentina, Chile and&#13;
Venezuela it is significantly lower.&#13;
The poverty gap, as a proportion of total household income (M) or,&#13;
even more significantly, of the total household income of the non-poor (F),&#13;
gives an idea of the magnitude of the problem in each country, in terms of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 94 -&#13;
resources. In countries such as Honduras, income shortfall of the poor&#13;
amounts to 20 percent of the aggregate income of the non-poor, and in Peru to&#13;
13 percent. In countries with a high incidence of poverty but a better&#13;
overall situation, like Brazil or Colombia, this insufficiency represents less&#13;
than 10 percent of the income of the non-poor. Even in Mexico, and also in&#13;
Costa Rica, this indicator is around five percent. In countries with a lower&#13;
incidence of poverty, the aggregate poverty gap is still less: a little over&#13;
two percent in Chile and Venezuela, and below one percent in Argentina.&#13;
For the majority of countries in Latin America, the dimensions of&#13;
the poverty problem appear manageable, at least as regards the magnitude of&#13;
the economic resources involved and bearing in mind the considerable&#13;
additional resources that would be required in providing basic public&#13;
services.&#13;
At all events, the magnitudes of these indicators cannot be taken as&#13;
direct measures of the feasibility of implementing particular programs or&#13;
strategies designed to eliminate poverty. The poverty existing in the Latin&#13;
American countries is rooted, historically and technologically, in their&#13;
present style of development. To reorient that style so that basic needs&#13;
satisfaction became one of the community's highest priorities would involve a&#13;
significantly greater proportion of resources as well as considerably more&#13;
social conflict than such measures themselves would seem to suggest.&#13;
D.   The relative dimension of poverty&#13;
The dimensions of poverty examined up to this point have been those&#13;
associated with situations of absolute deprivation defined against norms taken&#13;
to reflect the minimum physiologically and culturally adequate levels of life&#13;
that allow for a dignified existence and for participation in the predominant&#13;
style of living.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 95 -&#13;
This exercise in evaluating the poverty problem in semi-developed&#13;
countries would not be complete, however, without a glance at the dimensions&#13;
of the problem when viewed from the standpoint of a relative definition which&#13;
assesses deprivation in terms of the average levels of needs satisfaction in&#13;
each society.&#13;
A comparison of the two types of poverty measures throws light on&#13;
such important facets of the problem in each country as: how much inequality&#13;
there is in absolute poverty; how far the norms of basic needs satisfaction&#13;
lie from average resource availability in that country; the extent to which&#13;
existing inequalities may give rise to relative deprivation that goes beyond&#13;
the absolute minima.&#13;
The same body of data on the distribuion of income and consumption&#13;
in each country has been used to draw lines of relative poverty according to&#13;
the norm suggested by Atkinson (1975), namely that relative deprivation be&#13;
defined as less than half the average per capita income of all households.&#13;
Although arbitrary, this norm has the advantage of being based on an&#13;
unambiguous notion of social justice, the unequivocal nature of which is&#13;
highlighted by the fact that the most affluent 10 percent of households&#13;
usually have an income five times the average. The results obtained are set&#13;
out in Table 15.&#13;
For the majority of countries, when poverty is defined thus it&#13;
affects a significantly higher proportion of the population than when it is&#13;
defined according to absolute norms. Even in those countries with the highest&#13;
incidence of absolute poverty, application of the relative norm raises the&#13;
number of households regarded as poor by between two and five percent. Where&#13;
the incidence of absolute povety is less severe, relative deprivation will&#13;
affect between 10 and 20 percent more households. In countries such as&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 96 -&#13;
Honduras, however, the magnitude of absolute poverty exceeds the proportion of&#13;
households that would fall below the relative norm, linked, as it is, to the&#13;
country's scarce average resources.&#13;
TABLE 15&#13;
ESTIMATES OF RELATIVE POVERTY, AROUND 1970&#13;
% of households below the a/&#13;
line of relative poverty a&#13;
Urban      National&#13;
Argentina                         27            28&#13;
Brazil                            52            54&#13;
Colombia                          43           48&#13;
Costa Rica                        34            36&#13;
Chile                             38           39&#13;
Honduras                          40            58&#13;
Mexico                            44           48&#13;
Peru                              34            48&#13;
Uruguay                           25           --&#13;
Venezuela                         37           38&#13;
Generally speaking, there are fewer disparities among the Latin&#13;
American countries when poverty is measured in relative terms than when it is&#13;
measured in absolute terms. Among countries with an approximately similar&#13;
degree of social inequality, it is in those where average resource&#13;
availability is lower that the incidence of absolute poverty is clearly more&#13;
severe.&#13;
The differences in relative poverty on the national scale shown in&#13;
Table 15 reflect differences in the degree of inequality between the lower&#13;
half of the social pyramid and the rest of it. In the countries where those&#13;
inequalities are greater, half the population live below the relative norm,&#13;
and in the remaining countries -- with the exception of Argentina, and perhaps&#13;
Uruguay -- something over a third of them do.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 97 -&#13;
In part, these differences are a result of the inequalities&#13;
prevailing within the rural sector. There is greater uniformity in the&#13;
incidence of poverty in urban areas, where it is defined with respect to&#13;
average urban income. It will be observed from Table 15 that, in almost all&#13;
countries, from 35 to 45 percent of the urban population is below the relative&#13;
norm. Only in the urban areas of Brazil can somewhat over half the population&#13;
be regarded as living in relative deprivation. At the other end of the scale,&#13;
relative poverty affects approximately a quarter of the urban population of&#13;
Argentina and Uruguay.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 98 -&#13;
Annex A&#13;
FOOD NEEDS ASSUMED&#13;
Table A-1&#13;
FOOD ENERGY NEEDS PER CAPITA FOR A_b7ODERATELY ACTIVE-/&#13;
POPULATION; ADJUSTED FOR WEIGHT-    BY AGE AND SEX&#13;
(calories per capita per day)&#13;
Children                                             Additional for&#13;
both  ~  Adolescents            Adultsprgato&#13;
both                                                pregnant or&#13;
sexes       Males   Females     Males   Females     nursing woman&#13;
Under age 1                                                           1090&#13;
1- 3       1360&#13;
4- 6       1830&#13;
7- 9       2190&#13;
10-12                   2600      2350&#13;
13-15                   2900      2480&#13;
16-19                   3070      2310&#13;
20-39                                        3000     2200&#13;
40-49                                        2850     2090&#13;
50-59                                        2700     1980&#13;
60-69                                        2400     1760&#13;
70 and over                                     2150     1540&#13;
SOURCE:   Calculated as per needs established by FAO/WHO, Technical Reports&#13;
Series No. 552, Technical Bulletin No. 52, 1971.&#13;
a/  Frame of reference:    the activities of a population are generally&#13;
classified as light, moderately. active, very active or extremely&#13;
active.&#13;
b/  Assumption:   male and female adults, 65 and 55 kg., respectively&#13;
(in developing countries).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 99 -&#13;
Table A-2&#13;
MINIMUM INTAKE OF HIGH-QUALITY PROTEIN AND PROTEIN OF 70% QUALITY&#13;
(grams per capita per day)&#13;
Age and sex                        High-quality a/         Adjusted b&#13;
protein needs-           Intake -&#13;
Children&#13;
1-3                                  16                    23&#13;
4-6                                  20                   29&#13;
7-9                                  25                   35&#13;
Adolescent males&#13;
10-12                                 30                    43&#13;
13-15                                 37                    53&#13;
16-19                                 38                    54&#13;
Adolescent females&#13;
10-12                                 29                    41&#13;
13-15                                 31                    45&#13;
16-19                                 30                    43&#13;
Adult males                             37                    53&#13;
Adult females                           29                    41&#13;
Supplement pregnant woman                5.5                   7.9&#13;
Supplement nursing mother               17                    24.3&#13;
SOURCE: Calculated as per needs established by FAO/WHO, Technical&#13;
Report Series No. 552, Technical Bulletin No. 52, 1971.&#13;
a/ Provided by milk or eggs.&#13;
b/ Assumed that the quality of the protein obtained from the diet in&#13;
the Latin American countries is about 70 percent of that obtained&#13;
from milk or eggs.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
-100-&#13;
00 cr a -4 0 0 0) C0 ( -:r C r '  - 0C 0 CD I  In~ cnC 0I  C1 c1&#13;
N&#13;
0)   en  C  -4C'J0 Or-Cir, -      04    ,-Cf 0 ~ 140ci  Iq0  )C4&#13;
:   0  CrC 0  C'J  n  z '0)  0 a , VI) 0- a,  )  a4--   ,n -4 0) i  C)  0, CrI  0&#13;
'-4         ~~~~~~4 -4  C--C  C'4CC'.-4-Z  -4 -4  &#13;
Z~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~0&#13;
a)                                                                          0).. .   r  ~ C&#13;
fx       ,c  .  NI  ~   ,  tW 0 T M  Tr  -M 1)I  .  L  4r     In        U&#13;
0                                                                                  uorCl')C.)-Cr ~ u~'-~eJ-~ &#13;
r-                                               W~0   4 'r4                               C-  0&#13;
0                                                               ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~o ,4-&#13;
a'  ~ ~ ~ :                                                                        -4      0)  En&#13;
El   $4                                                                     (U~~~~~~~~   UC  CO&#13;
0oC                                             .1                                 CC-      U   C&#13;
-4                                                             0~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~  0&#13;
-4                                                                                              -&#13;
(-C                        -.   -.     -~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~C  041 -  -4        Ca&#13;
0)  CO~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~0&#13;
C) --4                                                                                  -4&#13;
CJ~~~~                                                                                     ~ 0)   . a.&#13;
R                                                                                          U)~~&#13;
0)&#13;
o                                                                0)  C~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~1 &#13;
co                                                 al -O        o  D'               COj  r&#13;
m  0 10 "00 ~~~ -1 10 0  ~aj&#13;
z       CO     .a'a               I-~-a~                                            u   .  C &#13;
8       , I         J-C                              -4   - t4  -'-0  a  ~0A'r-CN 'C-r- I  C &#13;
(10     CO~~                                                                        co &#13;
U             -~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ &#13;
o                                                       ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~co  .. 0&#13;
U                                                                        4.4     C))  -  n00 e  0  qMLn -~m n  Tw  )m r-Qu &#13;
N  .   .   ,           ,  .  I                           u~~~~~~~~~~~~~~a  a  .  0&#13;
PO                                                          u~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~O C  C-  a&#13;
m                                                              3~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~  0)&#13;
m  C&gt; oo a, en  (D 'D o,  10 cq a, oq 00  -4 co ull CD m  m   0   10 r- r-  m  C4 0.~4 CC-  C-  C-&#13;
Ca '0 1~Ca'C                  C C C  0'0a'                          CO   4  C&#13;
0  C) 0  C  C) C) 0  IN  -4  C) 1-4  14 1-1  C-4  -1  Ul -a   4  C-C  -a  CO&#13;
CO    0   LI&#13;
CO                                                        U   -   0   -&#13;
coC                                                         CO  0)j  CO&#13;
&gt;C4           0)U0 &#13;
0              cu~~~~~~~0       a))a))Q4-.&#13;
---4-a  .0  -                                           -C   U   4 &#13;
C-C          4-.~~~~c  C)--4                     0)                              --.a)4&#13;
C)           0)j      4-'   C                                           C   a)  CO  C-&#13;
-4   0            0) r.a                            co          4-  a.  a   w&#13;
0                CO4 4  0  u   ( $-O C   0)                                &gt;)  0)  &gt;)&#13;
4)C4   0).a   o     .o    co                    a) &#13;
CO-C   0.-'0  .1  4 CO                                   0)  CO  0) 0W&#13;
0      co . w   CO   4 -CO r  J  o  -a   a  .-C                       00  0)  00&#13;
C)   4-.0)    CO    C)n          a w r. l = 0)   *4-4   w  -a    CO  C  CIC&#13;
o   H   "CC   4.C   CO    00 :   C-        U)(  c     C) C0           C       C&#13;
-4   0 0  )  COOC)    COP  _  .0 0M )   0cc ..la  -4  CO          0)   0 &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 101-&#13;
1! ~~~~r         r,0&#13;
t- r4  N  4     -. ar  N  z  CA .  . In   . 0  00-&#13;
C) In f', 01 m C), 'm -4 ri 0,~ ~ ~ ~~~~ &#13;
rl  ~ ~ ~ ~  ~   'C   0 0 :  .N 0440&#13;
00~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~.&#13;
CO- r- -O    '0C40         6&#13;
~~ .~  ~~n-r.r-J  -  NNCN m  6 ~-  - m       N).&#13;
-          a  -r- L  r l'~ r'Z,C~&#13;
I   w.   -T                   .00  c&#13;
A                             C.-.-~   C&gt;  n  C,0  1 ;  Z&#13;
0~~~~~.&#13;
; 0  40'444-                         1 *-4'40*'n  0 040&#13;
I-.  rn  co r -T00   n '  4.  4--O t-    0  0&#13;
.0                        .&#13;
.0                       .0                     0&#13;
4.4     CO~00 f- 00 I f-   Nm "   - U  1   I,  In         44,4&#13;
- o                          .-&gt;4CC  C  I  I  0 &#13;
0~~~~~~~~~~~~.                                     In       4.&#13;
CO   -  C  c-  r-  w)   4-,  M  In  C,O N c &#13;
Z      i   D--a    t1                - c;%  3r 6 ci  &#13;
400                                .0                     0.  C)ri  I&#13;
-            '0 IN4          1     0      6 66r06'-~~ . &#13;
co                              IN~~~IN&#13;
.0               -4~~~~~~~~~~t0 c&#13;
4-H   4                                                    .4   a)&#13;
U  ~~~~~~~~                  C                         004 0~~~~CZ  A  )0  0 C)C &#13;
00  14  IN                 C) r~~4-4-  444&#13;
0        0  0.0&#13;
A   In  00  T   -.T  C, I-  r4  ID0  S)  a  -.&#13;
Z         .0&#13;
0 L0     N                -NN&lt;I &#13;
C)                           N                  4'en  'n  * .4. 4  414&#13;
C).)  -       e.,N                           *a)~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~`0 I-I  4: '4&#13;
Z 0~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~.&#13;
0 L)~ ~ ~~~~.&#13;
V: C!~~           C&#13;
C.) C.)   ~ ~ ~ , V .4 m   a,ia                            4-IN&#13;
co v              r4                 'C~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~  o') .&#13;
~~~~~~~~~~CO  - ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~ ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~Oc&#13;
0                                                    0~~.  .  .   4CO'   -&#13;
'D  c~~~~~ C)  r-  (D  w  r&lt;  w0~~~~~~~~~~~C&#13;
C)                   IT ', C r- c,  4n CO4-  0'- -N       ,40  -&#13;
14'                                '1'   ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~0.0fi  4-&#13;
C  40(-I o-4  '44   C 40- 4-4- 00        . . O .r.:  I , &#13;
N  -  4-4  N-  -.~~~~~~~~  . -4&#13;
.0        ...                            COFO~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~&amp;  0.&#13;
a,~ en  44-  - - 41441 co 4N 'O-"40             :43.)0  .&#13;
oo                I~~~NN           -     00.*V&#13;
C14  rq~~~~~~~~~~~~0 '             ~   .4&#13;
444  .-4 &#13;
0                                 I&#13;
44                  '4~~~~'     44000  C&gt;-  40&#13;
I .4  44 1                     n Z4&#13;
'4  C  0    -              C~~~~~~ 0   &gt;               .4&#13;
0 ~~~~~~~~ o  - -  ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ 0 ot&#13;
.0C0        C   4  4     0           &gt;4 C ') 4&#13;
k-  v          C O  4&#13;
C4     C  &gt;) C ~  C C         .4) &gt; C  -4&#13;
40  0 v  V  CO  Cv )  C  CO  )-  .  4  v  Q. .0  CO&#13;
C) C .  0.  4-  ) C  . C  4 .   ) C  -&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 102 -&#13;
co&#13;
1-4&#13;
a)  C'im-4  N N - -4 x  4~  4  c.j&#13;
N&#13;
X   O N n ~c' Cs  C; O~ CH C~ CX &lt;&#13;
00000000  0000    0 U)&#13;
W                          (N O  Ofo' &#13;
NV  .-.4( .t  . &#13;
C O O 0'CC4-4.-4 O OO&#13;
)000 000000        0 C)   0   0&#13;
Z  ~~~  o o  o o ~~~~ o H o  o   iD~~o &#13;
v  O O O O O O O O O O  O  e~-.~2 O~&#13;
:                                 C(-   -&#13;
E. ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ .&#13;
z&#13;
M       O    0 "1 1 b1 c n C0  0  0 00  0)  0 I_0&#13;
D   tJ   N  O  O  O  OO  H  _{ _e   (N i&#13;
&gt;d   X    O o O o0O o O-O o o  o04' &#13;
x    OOCDOOOO     0    0       0&#13;
co&#13;
-4 uc o      O  " N  _   n *  aN  D *  N&#13;
(J     (V    0(N-O O-O O O O  O  ~.-O O  D&#13;
cn 04  C0       00   0.400  '0&#13;
ZC..)&#13;
Z -  co  4o                       ( N  -4&#13;
-X    000000000000     0 c  o&#13;
H &gt; ~~U&#13;
E 0  --                               a&#13;
E:~ ~ ~~~~~C C; CC CQ1 ~ &#13;
z &#13;
-  400 00 0 m 0 &lt;   m -T - 0 &lt; 0&#13;
0  0 0_  0 0 00 O  O   0 00   0 1 0 0 &#13;
co CZ   O ~ O ~ O ~  CO O O O O OOO O   00  (N&#13;
U) 9   fo                        (N  -&#13;
E. 000         0  00  00        0   0~&#13;
V)~~~~~~(&#13;
0~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~0&#13;
z&#13;
E. U)&#13;
F-4  co ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ -4V (&#13;
.lq     In -a E  D  O   In&#13;
C U&#13;
&lt;: ~                  (V Or-     NO   C S. o &#13;
-4  Lr) Cli 00  -- CN  a) CrV -Na)&#13;
0 o o o o 0o o o) o V o  oo C  Co&#13;
. ~ O(V  a)  N   N  OD ~   GJ. O-&#13;
fi N o  . OC Oa oU      CC o  ~o&#13;
po                              r)&#13;
C:&#13;
.H   C)( a)  *,   a     a ,  C)  - X  CJo&#13;
a) /  )         '' 0 C)a )   C.-0C) C  C  C,  0&#13;
D4                         -T  00 E  -4 ..&#13;
co                 a)  co ) &#13;
I   r   v   Go   aJ  U   C  @   sa  al~~~~~~~~~~~c  M&#13;
/   C   U)   ,:  t   X   _,  U  ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ D : Co&#13;
I  LS   U   a)   uo   oz   H a)  m  Q co  C &#13;
I&gt;)          H      C  U t &#13;
I        07  (U (xn V (xs (|co  .  (n  CJ  C&#13;
I   .   X  (  X  :5  H  v  u  v  sn ;  uz  tOO  X a) X&#13;
/  p.,  k 0XD  00 OC: Xs ~ % &gt; &lt; CZ  C: ? &#13;
/   G  D: @ Q W Q v H X Q +  O   C   O 4&#13;
U ~ ~~~~~- u)   cu w1&gt;XzN: XmO E   f&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Annex e&#13;
ESTIMATES OF THE INCIDENCE OF POVERTY AROUND 1970, BY COINTRY, BASED ON ORIGINAL PATA_/&#13;
OBTAINED FROM AVAILABLE HOUSEHOLD SURVEYS&#13;
(percentages of ill households covered by each survey)&#13;
Slscrlhotion by levels of:&#13;
Total                   vanita           Per cavita&#13;
Title of Survey                         E.ec.ting ageacy.L/   Coverage./   Year           household             hoosehold             ho-sebeld&#13;
tnco=e                incorue            covouryt ion&#13;
Hoo.eholds below lIne of:&#13;
Poverty  Indigence    Poverty  Indigence    Poverty   Indlve-ce&#13;
Argentina      E.coesta sabre Presoponston Fa=iliares           INDEC/ECIEL            AM           1070      l.A       0.3&#13;
Encoesta de Empleo y Deoexpleo                   INDEC                  AM           IQ7n       2.3       n.4        5.(        0.4&#13;
Brazil         Censo de Poblocion                                                      N            170     63.5       ?5.6&#13;
Pesquisa Nacional por Axostra de Doaicilios      IBGE                   N            1972     SS.9       33.6&#13;
U            1072     46.0       20.0&#13;
Coloabia      Eocoesca de Presopoestos Failiares               CEGE/ECIEL             U(4CP)      1967      30.6        5.3&#13;
AM           IQ67     22.2        4.6                             2?.R        3.g&#13;
Encoesta de Hogares                              DANF.                  N            1970     64.7'/     3o.223/&#13;
I!          1070     52.65.     25.2.c/&#13;
E-cuenta National de Hogares - Etupo 2           DANE                    1(7CP)      IQ70     26.0        6.n&#13;
Enc esta Naciosal de Hogares - Etapa 6           DANE                   N            1972     91.2d/     64.33_/    75.6'     5 7.4d&#13;
Estodio sobre la Diatribociox de los&#13;
Servicios Busboy                               CCD/Bco.Mondial        N            1974                           65.3       36.9&#13;
U            1Q74                           6n.1       32.2&#13;
Encuesta Nacioxal de Hogares - Etapa 9           DANE                   U            1975     66.4/     37,2d/&#13;
Couca Rica     Eecoe.to de Hogares par Monestreo                DGEC                   N(NA)        1067     29.,2/    11.4d/      29.7c/    12.7'&#13;
U(NA)        1067     28.2/       8.94d/    29.55!     10 47/&#13;
Sentiaa Fncuesta de Hogares por Muestreo         DGEC                   U(PA)        1971     26.4/      6.6d/     7a.2_/      0.7/&#13;
E.ccesta de Pre...poestos F-miliares             IECES                  N            1971     24.3       10.4        27.9       5.7&#13;
ti           1931                           16.2        2.0&#13;
AM           1071     14.P9       2.0&#13;
Chile          Encoesta Nacionai sobre Ingresos Fa=iliares      INE                    N            196R     29.5       Q.,&#13;
U            I%6R     16.6        4.2&#13;
AM           1960      9.9       I.&#13;
Encoesta de Fresupoestos Fa=ilJares              INE/ECIEL              AM           IQ68      8.2        1.6                               0.7       1.1&#13;
Hondoras       Encoesta de Ingresos y Gastos Fa-iliares         DEGC                   N            1967     77.4      64.0&#13;
OT           1967     52.2       18.6&#13;
AM           1967     37.0       12.7&#13;
Mexico         Estodis de InBresos y Gastos de las Fa=iliaa     FCOYFX.SA              N            1067     39.0      15.6                              0O.1t'/     s oe/&#13;
I            1967     24.0        5.7&#13;
Per.           Encuesta do Presopoestos Familiares              CISEPA/ECIEL           AM           1968     17.7       4.5                              12.4       1.q&#13;
Encuenta do Hogares                              OTEMO                  U            1970     31.8       14. 3&#13;
At           1970     23.7        7.2&#13;
Encoenta Nacianal do Conoomo de Ali.eetos        ENCA                   N            1072     60.1       30.7&#13;
1!           1972     36.7       14.R&#13;
AM           1972     19.2        2.H       20.8        6.0       17.        1.0&#13;
Urogoay        Encoesta de Preoupo.escot  Fa=iliares            U de R/ECIEL           AM           1967     13.4       4.2&#13;
Encoesta de Hogares                              DiGEC                  AM           1060     2R.2d/      8.6d/&#13;
Veoezuela      Encoesta do Presopaestos Faxiliares              BCY/ECIEL              AM           1966      5.6       0.0                               9.6        1.2&#13;
Estodio del Mercado Real de Vivienda&#13;
ax Vexe.oela                                   BNA y P                U            1970     22.3        7.8&#13;
A.M          1970     10.3        3.0&#13;
Eac.eeta de Hogares                              DGEC                   N            1971     28.R       10.5       28.0       11.7&#13;
a/   Not adjosted for axdorestimatioa or definition of income.&#13;
b/   N - entire country; U - total popalation or all orhan areao in the country; AM - oetropolit.n area of capital or cqnctrys -in m        rban nucleas;&#13;
(N)CP - (nomber of) major cities In the country; (NA) - non-agricultural popolation.&#13;
c/   Dintributino is by icooe level of head of hoonehold.&#13;
d/   Distribatiox is by level of primary household income.&#13;
e/   Shwo. distributioo by level of total household consamotion.&#13;
T.N.      BCOMEX.SA    Banco de Comercla Exterior, S.A., Mexico&#13;
BCV           Banco Central do Vemecuela&#13;
BNA y P       Banco Nacianal Agrario y Popular&#13;
CGD           Camaro de CGaercio de Daitama (Depta. do Boyaca)&#13;
CEDE          Centro de Estudios sobre Desarrollo Ecoxoilco&#13;
CISEPA        Centro de Investigaciones Sociales, EcanxmIcan, Politicas y Antropologicas&#13;
DANE          Departaexnto Adninistrattv- Nacional do Estadletica&#13;
DGEC          Direccixa-Gener-i do Estadisltia y Cena.s&#13;
ECIEL         Programa de Estudios Conjxtos sobre InteRraclox Economica Latinoaoericana&#13;
ENCA          Encoesta Nacional de Consu.= de AlieNEos&#13;
IBGE          Inatituto Brasilelro de Geografla e Estatistica&#13;
IECES         Instituto de In-estigac-i-es, Escuela de Ciencima EconrlIcaa y Sociales&#13;
INDEC         Instittao Nacioxne  do Estadiatica y Cenaos&#13;
11            Inastituto Nacional de Estadiatica&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 104 -&#13;
BIBLIOGRAPHY&#13;
Aaron, H., and M. McGuire. "Public Goods and Income Distribution",&#13;
Econometrica, vol. 38, no. 6 (November 1970).&#13;
Ahluwalia, M. "Income Inequality: Some Dimensions of the Problem". In&#13;
Hollis Chenery et al, Redistribution With Growth. Published for the&#13;
World Bank and the Institute for Development Studies, University of&#13;
Sussex. Oxford: Oxford University Press. Spanish version:&#13;
Redistribucion con crecimiento. Published for the World Bank. Madrid:&#13;
Editorial Tecnos, 1976.&#13;
Altimir, 0. "La vivienda en la Argentina. Aspectos economicos, II: El&#13;
mercado de viviendas y su financiamento", Estudios sobre la economia&#13;
argentina, no. 5 (1969). Buenos Aires: Instituto de Investigaciones&#13;
Economicas y Financieras de la Confederacion General Economica.&#13;
_  Estimaciones de la distribucion del ingreso en America Latina por&#13;
medio de encuestas de hogares y censos de poblacion: Una evaluacion de&#13;
confiabilidad. Santiago: Projecto Conjunto CEPAL/Banco Mundial sobre&#13;
Medicion y Analisis de la Distribucion del Ingreso en Paises de America&#13;
Latina, 1975.&#13;
Anand, S. "Aspects of Poverty in Malaysia", The Review of Income and Wealth,&#13;
series 23, no. 1 (1977).&#13;
Andrews, F., and R. Crandall. "The Validity of Measures of Self-Reported&#13;
Well-Being", Social Indicators Research, vol. 3 (Dordrecht, Holland,&#13;
1976), pp. 1-19.&#13;
Arellano, A.J. Hacia un canasto de consumo minimo. Documento de discussion,&#13;
ECIEL (Programa de Estudios Conjuntos sobre Integracion Economica&#13;
Latinoamericana), Estudio de Precios y Politica Economica, Facultad de&#13;
Ciencias Economicas, Departamento de Economia, Universidad de Chile,&#13;
Santiago (1975).&#13;
Argentina. Comite Coordinador de Encuestas de Costo de Vida en el Interior.&#13;
Indice de precios a nivel del consumidor (costo de vida) en la ciudad de&#13;
Cordoba, 1966-1967. Cordoba, 1967a.&#13;
Argentina. Comite Coordinador de Encuestas de Costo de Vida en el Interior.&#13;
Incide de precios a nivel del consumidor (costo de vida) en la ciudad de&#13;
Mendoza, 1966-1967, Mendoza, 1967b.&#13;
Atkinson, A.B. The Economics of Inequality, Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1975.&#13;
Bardhan, P.K. "On the Minimum Level of Living and the Rural Poor", Indian&#13;
Economic Review, vol. 5, no. 1 (1970).&#13;
Bauer, P.T., and A.R. Prest. Income Differences and Inequalities. Moorgate&#13;
and Wall Street Journal, 1973.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 105 -&#13;
Bell, C.L.G., and John H. Duloy. "Formulating a Strategy". In Redistribution&#13;
With Growth, Hollis Chenery et al. Published for the World Bank and the&#13;
Institute of Development Studies, University of Sussex.    Oxford:  Oxford&#13;
University Press. Spanish version: Redistribucion con crecimiento.&#13;
Published for the World Bank.   Madrid:  Editorial Tecnos, 1976.&#13;
Bienefed, M. "The Informal Sector and Peripheral Capitalism: The Case of&#13;
Tanzania", Human Resources Research, Institute of Development Studies&#13;
Bulletin, University of Sussex, vol. 6, no. 3 (February 1975).&#13;
Bjerke, K. "Income and Wage Distribution - Part I: A Survey of the&#13;
Literature", The Review of Income and Wealth, series 16, no. 3 (1970).&#13;
Braithwaite, S.N. "Real Income Levels in Latin America", The Review of Income&#13;
and Wealth, series 14, no. 2 (1968).&#13;
Brazil. Fundacao Instituto Brasileiro de Geografia e Estatistica. Anuario&#13;
Estatistico do Brasil. Various years.&#13;
Centro Latinoamericano de Demografia (CELADE). Boletin demografico. January&#13;
1969 and July 1975.&#13;
CEPAL. "Desarrollo humano, cambio social y crecimiento en America Latina",&#13;
Cuaderno de la CEPAL, no. 3. Santiago, 1975.&#13;
. "Series historicos del crecimiento de America Latina", Cuaderno&#13;
Estadistico, no. 3. Santiago, 1977.&#13;
Cline, W.R.  "Distribution and Development:   A Survey of the Literature",&#13;
Journal of Development Economics, vol. 1, no. 4 (1975), pp. 359-400.&#13;
Chenery, Hollis, M.S. Ahluwalia, C.L.G. Bell, J.H. Duloy, and R. Jolly.&#13;
Redistribution With Growth. Published for the World Bank and the&#13;
Institute of Development Studies, University of Sussex. Oxford: Oxford&#13;
University Press, 1974. Spanish version: Redistribucion con&#13;
crecimiento. Published for the World Bank. Madrid: Editorial Tecnos,&#13;
1976.&#13;
Chiswick, Carmel Ullman. "Income Distribution in Thailand: Measuring&#13;
Poverty". Washington, D.C.: Development Research Center, World Bank,&#13;
1976.&#13;
Colombia.  Departamento Administrativo Nacional de Estadistica.    "Indice&#13;
nacional de precos al consumidor: Empleados", Boletin mensual de&#13;
estadistica, no. 318 (January 1978), no. 322 (May 1978), no. 324 (July&#13;
1978), and various other issues.&#13;
Dandekar, V.M., and N. Rath. Poverty in India: Dimensions and Trends.&#13;
Bombay, 1971.&#13;
Drewnowski, J. "The Level of Living Index - New Version", Studies in the&#13;
Measurement of Levels of Living and Welfare, no. 2, Report No. 70.3.&#13;
Geneva: UNRISD, 1970.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 106 -&#13;
_  "Poverty:  Its Meaning and Measurement", Development and&#13;
Change, no. 8 (London, April 1977), pp. 183-208.&#13;
FAO. Third World Food Survey, Basic Study no. 11 Rome, 1963.&#13;
0 Provisional Ind'cative Plan for Agricultural Development, C 69/4. Rome,&#13;
August 1969.&#13;
* Food Balance Sheets. Rome, 1960-1975.&#13;
FAO/WHO. Energy and Protein Requirements, WHO Technical Report Series&#13;
No, 552, Report no. 52. Report of a Joint FAO/WHO Ad Hoc Expert&#13;
Committee, FAO Nutrition Meetings. Geneva, 1973.&#13;
FAO/SIECA. Perspectivas para el desarrollo y la integracion de la agricultura&#13;
en Centroamerica, Volume II, Guatemala, May 1974.&#13;
Fishlow, A. "Brazilian Size Distribution of Income", American Economic&#13;
Review, vol. 62, no. 2 (May 1972).&#13;
Foxley, A., E. Aninat, and J.P. Arellano. Who Benefits from Government&#13;
Expenditures?, WEP Working Paper No. 51, Geneva: ILO, 1976.&#13;
Franklin, N.N. "Concepto y evaluacion de los niveles minimos de vida",&#13;
Revista Internacional del Trabajo, vol. 75, no. 4 (April 1967).&#13;
Friedman, R,D, Poverty: Definition and Perspective. Washington, D.C.:&#13;
American Enterprise for Public Policy Research, 1965.&#13;
Galbraith, J,K, The Affluent Society, Houghton Mifflin Company, 1958.&#13;
Spanish version: Carlos Grau Petit, trans. La sociedad opulenta,&#13;
Barcelona: Ediciones Ariel, 1960.&#13;
Ghai, D., and T. Alfthan, On the Principles of Quantifying and Satisfying&#13;
Basic Needs. In Ghai, Kahn, Lee and Alfthan, The Basic Needs Approach to&#13;
Development: Some Issues Regarding Concepts and Methodology, Geneva:&#13;
ILO, 1977.&#13;
Gilbert, M., and I.B. Kravis. An International Comparison of National&#13;
Products and the Purchasing Power of Currencies: A Study of the United&#13;
States, the United Kingdom, France, Germany and Italy. Paris:&#13;
Organization for European Economic Cooperation, 1954.&#13;
Grunwald, J., and J. Salazar-Carillo, "Integracion economica y comparaciones&#13;
de precios y valores en la America Latina", Ensayos ECIEL, no. 2 (August&#13;
1975)e&#13;
Harrington, M. The Other America: Poverty in the United States. New York:&#13;
The MacMillan Co., 1963. Spanish version: Emma Susana Sperati, trans.&#13;
La cultura de la probreza en los Estados Unidos,   Mexico:  Fondo de&#13;
Cultura Economica, 1963.&#13;
Honduras. Direccion-General de Estadistica y Censos. Encuesta de ingresos y&#13;
gastos familiares 1967-1968, Tegucigalpa, D.C., 1970.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 107 -&#13;
Howe, H.  "Estimation of the Linear and Guarantee Expenditure Systems:    A&#13;
Cross-Section Case of Colombia", Ph.D. dissertation. Philadelphia:&#13;
University of Pennsylvania, 1974.&#13;
Hammarskjold Report.   "International Development and Cooperation", Development&#13;
Dialogue, no. 1/2, Uppsala, 1975.&#13;
International Labour Office.   Employment Incomes and Equality:   A Strategy for&#13;
Increasing Productive Employment in Kenya.   Geneva:   ILO, 1972.&#13;
. Employment, Growth and Basic Needs:    A One-World&#13;
Problem. Report of the Director-General, Tripartite World Conference on&#13;
Employment, Income Distribution and Social Progress and the International&#13;
Division of Labour. Geneva: ILO, 1976.&#13;
. Meeting Basic Needs:    Strategies for Eradicating&#13;
Mass Poverty. Geneva: ILO, 1977.&#13;
JUNAC (Junta of the Cartagena Agreement). Grupo Andino: Distribucion de&#13;
ingresos y estructura del consumo (area urbana), J/PR/68.&#13;
Kahn, A.R. Basic Needs: An Illustrative Exercise in Identification and&#13;
Quantification with reference to Bangladesh. Geneva: ILO, 1976.&#13;
Keynes, John M. The General Theory of Employment, Interest and Money.&#13;
London: MacMillan and Co., 1936.&#13;
Kravis, Irving B., Zoltan Kenessey, Alan Heston, and Robert Summers.    A System&#13;
of International Comparisons of Gross Product and Purchasing Power.&#13;
United Nations International Comparison Project, Phase I. Published for&#13;
the World Bank. Baltimore and London: Johns Hopkins University Press,&#13;
1975.&#13;
Lamale, Helen H.   "Changes in Concepts of Income Adequacy over the Last&#13;
Century", The American Economic Review, vol. 48, no. 2 (1958), pp. 291-&#13;
304.&#13;
Lewis, 0. La vida: A Puerto Rican Family in the Culture of Poverty: San&#13;
Juan and New York. New York: Random House, 1966.&#13;
Love, Roger, and Gail Oja. "Low Income in Canada", The Review of Income and&#13;
Wealth, series 23, no. 1 (1977).&#13;
Mabogunje, Akiu L., R.P. Misra, and Jorge E. Hardoy. "Aspectos ambientales de&#13;
los asentamientos humanos: Estandares y criterios en la provision de&#13;
alojamiento", Revista Interamericana de Planificacion, vol. 10, no. 39&#13;
(Mexico, 1976).&#13;
Marx, Karl. Capital, Book I. 1867. Spanish version: W. Robles, trans.&#13;
Mexico: Fondo de Cultura Economica, 1946.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 108 -&#13;
Marshall, Alfred. Principles of Economics. London: MacMillan and Co., Ltd.,&#13;
1890. Spanish version: Emilio de Figueroa, trans. Principios de&#13;
economia. Edited by M. Aguilar. Madrid, 1948.&#13;
Meerman, Jacob. The Distribution of Public Expenditure on Education and&#13;
Agriculture in Malaysia: Methodological Issues and a New Approach.&#13;
Washington, D.C.: World Bank, 1977.&#13;
Merton, R.K. Social Theory and Social Structure. Illinois: The Free Press,&#13;
1957.&#13;
Mexico. Comision Nacional de los Salarios Minimos. Memoria de los trabajos&#13;
1964. Mexico, DF, 1964.&#13;
Miller, S.M., M. Rein, P. Roby, and B. Gross. "Poverty, Inequality and&#13;
Conflict", Annals of the American Academy of Political Science, no. 373&#13;
(Philadelphia, 1967).&#13;
Musgrove, Philip, and Howard Howe. Estudio de consumo e ingreso familiar.&#13;
ECIEL (Revised edition, April 1, 1973), 1973.&#13;
Musgrove, Philip and Robert Ferber. Finding the Poor: Identifying Poverty&#13;
Households in Bogota, Medellin and Lima. ECIEL, 1976.&#13;
Myrdal, Gunnar. Asian Drama: An Inquiry into the Poverty of Nations, New&#13;
York: Twentieth Century Fund, 1968.&#13;
_  "The World Poverty Problem".   In Against the Stream:&#13;
Critical Essays in Econonics. New York: Pantheon Books, 1972.&#13;
Nun, Jose. "Superpoblacion relativa, ejercito industrial de reserva y masa&#13;
marginal", Revista Latinoamericana de Sociologia, vol. 5, no. 2 (1969),&#13;
pp. 178-236.&#13;
Orshansky, Molly. "Counting the Poor: Another Look at the Poverty Profile",&#13;
Social Security Bulletin, vol. 28 (1965), pp. 3-29.&#13;
Peru. Ministerio de Agricultura. Encuesta nacional de consumo de alimentos,&#13;
P-ENCA, nos. 11-12. Lima, Peru, 1975.&#13;
Prieto Duran, Rafael. "Gasto e ingreso familiar urbano en Colombia", Ensayos&#13;
ECIEL (Programa de Estudios Conjuntos sobre Integracion Economica&#13;
Latinoamericana), no. 4. Washington, D.C., August 1977.&#13;
Pyatt, Graham. On the Interpretation and Disaggregation of Gini&#13;
Coefficients. Washington, D.C.: Development Research Center, World&#13;
Bank, 1975.&#13;
Quijano, Anibal. Notas sobre el concepto de marginalidad social. Draft&#13;
discussion paper. CEPAL, 1966.&#13;
. Polo marginal de la economia y mano de obra maginalizada.&#13;
CEPAL, 1971.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 109 -&#13;
Rein, Martin.   Problems in the Definition and Measurement of Poverty.   In The&#13;
Concept of Poverty, edited by P. Townsend, New York: American Elsevier&#13;
Publishing Company, 1970.&#13;
Ribeiro, Darcy. "El desafio de la marginalidad", Revista Estudios&#13;
Internacionales, vol. 4, no. 16 (January-March 1971).&#13;
Rosenbluth, Guillermo.   Problemas scioeconanicos de la marginalidad y la&#13;
integracion. Escuela de Econcmia, Universidad de Chile, Santiago, 1963.&#13;
. La vivienda en America Latina: Una vision de la&#13;
probreza critica.   CEPAL/Borrador/DS 142, July 1976.&#13;
Rowntree, S. Poverty: A Study of Town Life. London: MacMillan, 1901.&#13;
Runciman, W.G. Relative Deprivation and Social Justice. Berkeley:&#13;
University of California Press, 1966.&#13;
Sawyer, Malcolm C. Poverty in Some Developed Countries. Information paper&#13;
presented to the Fourteenth General Conference of the International&#13;
Association for Research in Income and Wealth, Finland, 1975.&#13;
Selowsky, Marcelo. The Distribution of Public Services by Income Groups: A&#13;
Case Study of Colombia, Part I (Electricity, Water, Sewerage).&#13;
Preliminary version. Washington, D.C.: Development Research Center,&#13;
World Bank, 1976.&#13;
Sen, Amartya.   "Poverty:  An Ordinal Approach to Measurement", Econometrica,&#13;
vol. 44, no. 2 (March 1976).&#13;
. Three Notes on the Concept of Poverty.    Income Distribution and&#13;
Employment Programme, WEP 2-23/WP 65, Working Paper. Geneva:&#13;
International Labour Office, 1978.&#13;
Servicio Nacional de Salud (Chile). Frequencia y porciones de alimentos segun&#13;
recomendacion. Seccion Nutricion, Sub-Departamento de Fomento de Salud,&#13;
1974.&#13;
Smith, Adam. An Inquiry into the Nature and Causes of the Wealth of&#13;
Nations. Edited by Edwin Cannan from text of fifth edition (1776). New&#13;
York: Modern Library, 1904. Spanish version: Gabriel Franco, trans.&#13;
Investigacion sobre la naturaleza y causes de la rigueza de las&#13;
naciones. Mexico: Fondo de Cultura Econcmica, 1958.&#13;
Souza, Paulo R., and Victor E. Tokman. "El sector informal urbano en America&#13;
Latina".   In Sector informal:  Funcionamiento y politicas.   Santiago:&#13;
Programa Regional de Empleo para America Latina y el Caribe&#13;
(International Labour Office) (978), Chapter 2, pp. 25-38.&#13;
Streeten, Paul.  The Frontiers of Development Studies.    New York:  John Wiley&#13;
and Sons, 1972.&#13;
. Basic Needs:   An Issues Paper.   Bellaggio, Italy:&#13;
Development Research Center, World Bank, 1977a.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 110 -&#13;
_  The Distinctive Features of a Basic Needs Approach to&#13;
Development, Basic Needs Papers No. 2. Washington, D.C.: World Bank,&#13;
1977b.&#13;
Sukhatme, P.V. "Incidence of Protein Deficiency in relation to Different&#13;
Diets in India", British Journal of Nutrition, vol. 24 (1970), pp. 447-&#13;
487.&#13;
Szal, Richard J. Poverty: Measurement and Analysis. Income Distribution and&#13;
Employment Programme, WEP 2-23/WP 60, Working Paper. Geneva:&#13;
International Labour Office, 1977.&#13;
Tabak, Fanny. "Vivienda y politica de desarrollo urbano en el Brazil",&#13;
Revista Interamericana de Planificacion, vol. 7, no. 27 (September 1973),&#13;
1973.&#13;
Tejo Jimenez, Pedro. Un metodo para estimar consumos minimos de alimentos&#13;
para los paises de America Latina. CEPAL/EST/Borrador/150. Santiago:&#13;
Projecto Conjunto CEPAL/Banco Mundial sobre Medicion y Analisis de la&#13;
Distribucion del Ingreso en Paises de America Latina, 1976.&#13;
Townsend, Peter. "Measures and Explanations of Poverty in High-Income and&#13;
Low-Income Countries:  Problems of Operationalizing the Concepts of&#13;
Development, Class and Poverty". In The Concept of Poverty, edited by P.&#13;
Townsend. New York: American Elsevier Publishing Company, 1970.&#13;
o  Poverty as Relative Deprivation:  Resources and Style of&#13;
Living. In Poverty, Inequality and Class Structure, edited by Dorothy&#13;
Wedderbury. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1974.&#13;
Ul Haq, Mahbub, The Poverty Curtain: Choices for the Third World. New&#13;
York: Columbia University Press, 1976.&#13;
United Nations.  A System of National Accounts, series F, no. 2, Rev. 3.   New&#13;
York: U.N. Publication Sales No. 3.69.XVII,3, 1970.&#13;
_  A Draft System of Statistics of the Distribution of Income,&#13;
Consumption and Accumulation, E/CN.3/425. New York: U.N., February 3,&#13;
1972,&#13;
_  Committee for Development Planning.  Report on the 8th&#13;
Session, April 10-20, 1972, E/5126. New York: U.N., 1972.&#13;
. Department of Economic and Social Affairs.   World Housing&#13;
Survey 1974. New York: U.N. Publication Sales No. E.75.IV.8, 1977.&#13;
U.S. Department of Health, Education and Welfare. Social Security&#13;
Administration. Social Security Bulletin, Annual Statistical&#13;
Supplement. 1975.&#13;
U.S. Department of Labor. Bureau of Labor Statistics. "Estimating Equivalent&#13;
Incomes or Budget Costs by Family Type", Monthly Labor Review, vol. 83,&#13;
no. 11 (1960).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
- 1ll -&#13;
Utria, Ruben D. El problema de la vivienda y las condiciones del desarrollo&#13;
latinoamericano. CEPAL (preliminary mimeographed version), 1966a.&#13;
. "Los factores estructurales del desarrollo y el problema de&#13;
la vivienda en America Latina", Boletin Econanico de America Latina&#13;
(United Nations), vol. 11, no. 2 (1966b).&#13;
Van Herwaarden, F., A. Kapteyn, and B. Van Praag. "Twelve Thousand Individual&#13;
Welfare Functions: A Comparison of Six Samples in Belgium and the&#13;
Netherlands", European Economic Review, vol. 9, no. 3 (August 1977).&#13;
Vekemans, Roger. La marginalidad en America Latina: Un ensay de&#13;
conceptualizacion. Santiago: DESAL, 1969.&#13;
Weisbrod, B.A., and W.L. Hansen. "An Income/Net Worth Approach to Measuring&#13;
Economic Welfare", American Economic Review, vol. 58, no. 5 (1968), pp.&#13;
1315-19.&#13;
Wolfe, Marshall. La probreza como fenomeno social y como problema central de&#13;
la politica de desarrollo, ECLA/DRAFr/DS/133. Santiago, 1977.&#13;
World Bank. Housing. Sector Policy paper. Washington, D.C., 1975a.&#13;
_  The Assault on World Poverty:   Problems of Rural Development,&#13;
Education and Health. Baltimore and London: Johns Hopkins University&#13;
Press, 1975b.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
I HG 3881.5 .W57 W67 NO.522 C.3&#13;
ALTIMIR, OSCAR.&#13;
THE EXTENT OF POVERTY IN&#13;
LATIN AMERICA.&#13;
DATE  NAME AND EXTENSION  ROOM&#13;
X             j ~~~~NUMBER&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Headquarters:                                                                                               U&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.                                                                                           E3&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
Telephone: (202) 477-1234&#13;
Telex: WUI 64145 WORLDBANK&#13;
RCA 248423 WORLDBK&#13;
Cable address: INTB3AFRAD&#13;
WASHINGTONDC&#13;
European Office:&#13;
66, avenue d'Iena&#13;
75116 Paris, France&#13;
Telephone: 723.54.21&#13;
Telex: 842-620628&#13;
Tokyo Office:&#13;
Kokusai Building&#13;
1-1, Marunouchi 3-chome&#13;
Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo 100, Japan&#13;
Telephone: 214-5001&#13;
Telex: 781-26838&#13;
ISSN 0253-2115/ISBN 0-8213-0012-1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="2502764">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1982/03/2502764/extent-poverty-latin-america
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1982/03/2502764/extent-poverty-latin-america</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1982/03/2502764/extent-poverty-latin-america</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/09/23/000094946_03090604101619/Rendered/INDEX/multi0page.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/09/23/000094946_03090604101619/Rendered/PDF/multi0page.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2003-09-23T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1982-03-31T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            The extent of poverty in Latin America
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            This work originated in a research
            project for the measurement and analysis of income
            distribution in the Latin American countries, undertaken
            jointly by the Economic Commission for Latin America and the
            World Bank. The present paper presents estimates of the
            extent of absolute poverty for ten Latin American countries
            and for the region as a whole in the 1970s, on the basis of
            available household surveys and population censuses. They
            are based on country-specific poverty lines representing
            minimum acceptable levels of private consumption, drawn
            according to a food-based method. Such poverty lines -
            ranging from 150 to 250 dollars of annual household
            consumption per capita - express a normative definition of
            the absolute dimensions of poverty, partly based on expert
            appraisals and partly reflecting the actual behavior of low
            income households facing the life style projected by Latin
            American development. According to these estimates, 40
            percent of Latin American households were poor at the
            beginning of the 1970s, the incidence of poverty being 26
            percent in urban areas and 60 percent in rural areas. Urban
            poverty extended to more than one-third of urban households
            in some countries (Brazil, Colombia, Honduras) while
            affecting between 20 and 30 percent in others (Peru, Mexico,
            Venezuela), about 15 percent in Costa Rica and Chile and
            less than 10 percent in Argentina and Uruguay. The extent of
            poverty in rural areas would not be less than 20 percent in
            any case and would reach more than 60 percent in some
            countries. The corresponding poverty gaps were also
            estimated; in terms of total household income, they may
            represent manageable proportions (around 2-3 percent) in the
            better-off countries, but are in the 4-8 percent range in
            the bigger countries of the region and reach as much as 12
            percent in Peru and 17 percent in Honduras.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            The extent of poverty in Latin America
        </docna>
        <display_title>The extent of poverty in Latin America</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1982/03/2502764/extent-poverty-latin-america</listing_relative_url>
        <subtopic>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Services &amp; Transfers to Poor,Poverty Assessment,Health Economics &amp; Finance,Safety Nets and Transfers</subtopic>
        <docty>Staff Working Paper</docty>
        <teratopic>Poverty Reduction</teratopic>
        <count>Latin America,Caribbean</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Altimir, Oscar</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000094946_03090604101619</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>(Historic)Sector not applicable</subsc>
        <admreg>Latin America &amp; Caribbean,Latin America &amp; Caribbean</admreg>
        <colti>Staff working paper ; no. SWP 522</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Poverty Reduction</historic_topic>
        <sectr>(Historic)Sector not applicable</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications,Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <isbn>ISBN 0-8213-0012-1</isbn>
        <keywd>
            Poverty assessments; Income distribution;
            Household data; Population &amp; demography; Household
            consumption; Low income households; Urban areas; Rural
            areas; Urban poverty; Urban housing
            absolute poverty,absolute poverty
            lines,available data,average level,capitalist
            economies,developed countries,developing
            countries,ecological conditions,economic analysis,economic
            characteristics,economic development,economic
            growth,economists,employment,equilibrium,extreme
            poverty,food basket,household consumption,household
            income,household surveys,housing conditions,human
            capital,human dimensions,human rights,income
            distribution,inequality,labor market,living standards,local
            conditions,local levels,low income,nutrition,Poor,poor
            persons,population groups,poverty gap,poverty lines,Poverty
            measures,poverty policies,poverty programs,private
            consumption,productivity,public policy,public
            services,purchasing power,Quantitative Analysis,Relative
            poverty,renewable resources,research methods,rural
            areas,sanitary conditions,scientific knowledge,social
            context,social development,social group,social groups,social
            services,unemployment,urban areas,urban households,urban
            population,Urban poverty,wages,war
        </keywd>
        <owner>DEC</owner>
        <repnb>SWP522</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fragility, Conflict and Violence</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics and Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Capacities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Staffing Needs Assessments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Generic Name List</ml:concept><ml:concept>Generics</ml:concept><ml:concept>List of Generic Drugs</ml:concept><ml:concept>Off patent drugs</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutritional supplements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Vitamins</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition  Community Based Interventions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition  Raising Awareness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition  Training</ml:concept><ml:concept>Measurement and Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Assessment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Diagnostics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Impact Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Monitoring &amp; Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Monitoring and Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wage Setting</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages, Compensation and Benefits</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Lines</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Boundaries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Copyright</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Generic Drugs</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supplements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education and Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Examinations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Rights</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Measurement and Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Americas</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Caribbean</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>