<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>                                                       99613&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        WORLD BANK IDSTORY PROJECT&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                Brookings Institution&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
             Transcript of interview with&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            MUCHT ARUDIN SIREGAR&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                 November 26, 1991&#13;
                 Jakarta, Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
Interview by: John Lewis, Richard Webb, Devesh Kapur&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                           1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                      FOREWORD&#13;
&#13;
The following is a transcript of an oral interview conducted by the authors of the World&#13;
Bank' s fiftieth anniversary history: John P. Lewis, Richard Webb and Devesh Kapur,&#13;
The World Bank: Its First Half Century, Washington, DC: Brookings Institution Press,&#13;
1997. It is not a formal oral history, and it is not a systematic overview of the work of the&#13;
person interviewed. At times the authors discussed the planned publication itself and the&#13;
sources that should be consulted; at other times they talked about persons and&#13;
publications extraneous to the Banlc Some interview tapes and transcripts begin and end&#13;
abruptly. Nevertheless, the World Bank Group Archives believes that this transcript may&#13;
be of interest to researchers and makes it available for public use.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                               Muchtarudin Siregar&#13;
                           November 26, 1991 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                               2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
[Begin Tape 1, Side Ajl&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: [inaudible] money for a Joan from the World Bank [inaudible] for so many&#13;
projects, debts. In the '83 to ' 88 I was the deputy chairman for economic affairs at the&#13;
same time also in charge of the economic cooperation and all the loans from ..&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: Oh, all donors, yeah, yeah.&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Chief negotiator ..&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: I see.&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: . . from the Indonesian government. So I used to travel [inaudible] I flew&#13;
to Washington for negotiations and also [inaudible} And I was the deputy chairman; I&#13;
was responsible for six sectors: transport, {inaudible} energy, agriculture, trade and&#13;
industry [inaudible} sectors. Most of the World Bank loans go to these sectors.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: Yes, you were ...&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Including energy, PLN [[Perusahaan Listrik Negara, State Electricity&#13;
Company].&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: Yes, yes.&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: .. electric company. So if you told me that our relations with the World&#13;
Bank so close, not only here but also physically, because the World Bank used to have an&#13;
office just in our annex building across the street.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: Oh, really?&#13;
&#13;
SIRE GAR: Yeah, there was a time when under one roof, under one roof ...&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: I didn't know that.&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Yeah. It was 19--early ' 70, I think. Yeah. There was a Group Indonesia&#13;
who don't like working too much involved with [inaudible} Then finally the World Bank&#13;
moved to another office.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: Bernie [Bernard R.} Bell established this office, right?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Yeah, Bernie was. He was so close to the chairman and to the staff&#13;
[inaudible] so close to us, and always in everything including preparing the, you know&#13;
our project guidance book, the "Blue Book," what we call it, presented in the IGGI&#13;
&#13;
1&#13;
 Original transcript by the Brooking Institution World Bank history project; original insertions are in [ ].&#13;
Insertions added by the World Bank Group Archives are in italics in [].&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     Muchtarudin Siregar&#13;
                                 November 26, 1991 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                          3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
[Inter-Governmental Group for Indonesia}? He used to prepare the Blue Book together&#13;
with the World Bank staff sector by sector [inaudible} discuss it. Of course, the proposal&#13;
came from the department and BAPPENAS [Badan Perencanaan Pembangunan&#13;
Nasional, National Development Planning Board}, and then discussed together with . . .&#13;
&#13;
So when_ we start our development plan in '68 we actually carne out from a very difficult&#13;
situation, call it "Orde Lama," Old Order for New. And the situation was so desperate.&#13;
So the World Bank, ifl can say [inaudible], was not only our partner in getting the funds&#13;
for development but also our partner in, you know, trying to improve our capabilities not&#13;
only in [inaudible} cooperation and also international network of getting more donors&#13;
involved but also sometimes in the, you know, intellectual, you know, exercise with&#13;
them, to discuss all the problems because before our [inaudible} our development plans.&#13;
Well, there were several plans already after the [inaudible} never been implemented so&#13;
well prepared like when we start our [inaudible} aid. And the World Bank at that time&#13;
was and still is our partner. So the World Bank for us is not only the source of financial&#13;
assistance for loans but also partner in development. If I can say-, teaching us how to&#13;
[inaudible} This is the important thing.&#13;
&#13;
WEBB: We've heard a lot about the strength ofthe policy dialogue, the way people talk&#13;
about it, and we've met many of the people who have been involved, and this is a&#13;
dialogue that has happened very much at a high level. We are very interested to know at&#13;
the lower levels how much dialogue, teaching also occurred. You say that project&#13;
implementation improved. Is that a result of ...&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: In the planning capability, also [inaudible} I can prove it, yeah. For&#13;
instance, if you compare the government agency who received loan from the World Bank&#13;
and the government agency who never received a loan, after two or three years if you&#13;
compare, you see the difference. Those who received many loans from the World Bank,&#13;
it's like they are forced to do it in a systematic way, the correct way, the right way, not&#13;
only in the planning, project preparation, also in the implementation because there is also&#13;
someone at the World Bank who always, together with them, supervised them, remind&#13;
them how to follow the procedures correctly.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS : What would be an example?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Public works.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: Public works?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Say, public works, for instance, public works. When we started the&#13;
development plan in 1968 all was almost in the same situation. We just didn't know how&#13;
to do it. Then BAPPENAS received so many loans from the World Bank and the&#13;
government. Take, for instance, highways, the director general of highways. We are one&#13;
of the most capable directorate of [inaudible} Well, how many loans will he get?&#13;
&#13;
WEBB: Of what bank?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                               M uchtaruf[in Siregar&#13;
                           November 26, 1991 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                               4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Highways, director general of highways. I think now he's one of the most&#13;
[inaudible} And then they are also the most, the biggest budget from the {inaudible}&#13;
because, you know, every time there was a loan, there must be a counterpart to work&#13;
together and ..&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: What's an example of a ministry or area that hasn't benefited from such loans?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Ob, for instance, internal area.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: Minister of interior? And your home ministry tends to be kind of policing?&#13;
[both speaking at once]&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Home affairs, yeah.&#13;
&#13;
It's interesting in the projects, the development, I don't see it here the administration of&#13;
the World Bank [inaudible} in development. Yet you see so much difference.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: Has the Bank bad a good impact on education?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Yeah, I think so. Yes.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: Population, I guess?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Even sometimes we see that the World Bank staff sometimes goes too far.&#13;
What I mean Â·â&#128;¢too far" is sometimes in preparation, in preparing the projects, {inaudible}&#13;
and the discussion goes to, more too academic. Then we think sometimes just- if! can&#13;
say it differently, maybe we don't need that much. So it means too much time spent, too&#13;
much energy spent. And then sometimes also I will start just to borrow. Even in the&#13;
negotiations in Washington you will consider discussions, something we discussed here&#13;
with the operational people, we already do, and then we go to Washington, the same&#13;
thing raised again in the negotiations. It's all exactly the same, and then we discuss it.&#13;
&#13;
But there are some good things out of this. In the implementation we are more prepared&#13;
because the issue is already discussed many, many times. It is--1 don't want to compare&#13;
with other donors, they are-there are several donors here in Indonesia which are not so&#13;
well prepared like the World Bank. Then, in the field is this. This is the ...&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: In the field?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Yeah, always many problems because when we--in this paper preparation,&#13;
so many issues we never touched, we never discussed everything.&#13;
&#13;
WEBB: In other words with the World Bank all the prior preparation ..&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: With the World Bank everything, everything.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                 Muclztarudin Sir.egar&#13;
                            N ovember 26, 1991 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                           5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
WEBB: .. leads to less problems in the field.&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: There is a pre-evaluation mission corning, then operational mission and&#13;
several evaluation missions sometimes and discuss it with them again and again. It takes&#13;
sometimes two years when you propose one project to the negotiations, and in the two&#13;
years, as I told you, yeah, maybe it' s good, maybe not. You are in a hurry; you say, "Oh,&#13;
the World Bank just--that's too long." When you can start something, it needs [inaudible}&#13;
But on the other hand, it's like a teaching process for us, as you said, not only in a high&#13;
level, but also for the project people [inaudible}&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: A lot ofWorld Bank lending has been in a series of loans, like energy, power,&#13;
number one, two, three, four. This kind of input to the preparations must become less as&#13;
you go through a series of those. It's sort of the economies of scale. Is that right?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Yeah. Make us more easily.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: Yeah, yeah, yeah. So when you start a new line of business, a new subject, a&#13;
new subsector, then there's a pretty big investment of time that goes into it on both sides.&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Yeah.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: You worked on-are there any of these--well, you said that public works was a&#13;
good case. We heard that energy has been a ..&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Oh, energy also, energy is a good an example, energy, PLN. It's a good&#13;
example.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: Yes. We were just there talking to the ex-head of it this morning.&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: This department is not energy.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: This is not?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: No, because-railway--! don't know. The World Bank also, ifl can be very&#13;
frank ..&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: Please.&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: They are very much in the way of thinking, very much {inaudible} with the&#13;
Americans. Americans don't like railways, so ... [Laughter]&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: So they push you towards ..&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: They push you more towards highways, yeah. So every time we try to&#13;
propose railway projects, it's difficult to get the approval. On the other hand also our&#13;
&#13;
                                M uchtarudin Siregar&#13;
                            November 26, 1991 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                              6&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
departments are not too happy with those, because if you talk railways in Indonesia, also&#13;
talk also about how to make the company healthy and there are so many conditions-&#13;
what do you call it--fulfilled by the covenants and everything. Sometimes when the&#13;
department is still weak, they just not only cannot fulfill it, but they just are not happy&#13;
with that.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: I'm sorry to be so ignorant, but you have some railways now?&#13;
&#13;
SIRE GAR: Oh, yeah, we have six thousand kilometers of railways. There's only one&#13;
loan from the World Bank. That's the only one. And every time, you know, we propose&#13;
another loan, always, you know-maybe it's ideally is this the way how to do that, but if&#13;
you see the condition of our railway at times, it's just maybe not possible to follow all the&#13;
conditions of the World Bank.&#13;
&#13;
The same also with the ports, because if you talk with the ports, the harbors, not only&#13;
economic things but also politically also with how our competitiveness is, with ASEAN&#13;
[inaudibleJ&#13;
&#13;
So this department has a lot of ..&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: You look after also inter-island shipping?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Yes.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: Is that subsidized?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Of course. [inaudible]&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: Yes, I know that. I know. I know. [Laughter]&#13;
&#13;
KAPUR: Is the issue much more a question of subsidies? Is it the issue, the question of&#13;
ownership?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: No, as I remember why the World Bank is not so interested in the ocean&#13;
shipping, especially international, it's too much politics.&#13;
&#13;
KAPUR: Too much politics here?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: No, in the world. It's everything. You cannot commit the country, you&#13;
know, to follow all [inaudible] they can.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: There's just an awful lot of politics.&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: So they never fmance any. They never give any loans for shipping&#13;
internationally.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                Muchtarudin Siregar&#13;
                            November 26, 1991 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                        7&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: I'm interested about the railways. I'm a little reluctant to believe it's just&#13;
because you've got Americans at the Bank working on transportation. There must be a&#13;
mixture of people working on it.&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Yeah.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: And it must have something to do with being capital intensive.&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: No, that's the impression of people.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: Well, we heard, too, some stories about the Americans arguing one way,&#13;
Germans arguing the other way.               Â·&#13;
&#13;
KAPUR: Yesterday we heard that.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: Yeah, but . .&#13;
&#13;
KAPUR: Germans speak for railways and Americans for roads.&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: You can see here all the consultants who improve our railways mostly&#13;
Germans from Germany.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: Well, that might ~e a motivation.&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: It's why they say [inaudible} don't like railways because so many&#13;
[inaudible]&#13;
&#13;
KAPUR: Is it an issue also of ownership?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: No. This is ..&#13;
&#13;
KAPUR: Private sector?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Public.&#13;
&#13;
KAPUR : But that's not an issue?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: No, no. Not public.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: Is there any--what about urban transport? Is there a rapid transit system that&#13;
you' re pushing?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: No, under preparation.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: Under preparation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                              Muchtarudin Siregar&#13;
                          November 26, 1991 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                 8&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: The World Bank fmanced a study on that.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: I see. They provided a consultant for that?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Yeah, they proposed--the consultant proposed a light rail in Jakarta, only in&#13;
Jakarta, a combination of light rail and heavy to solve the urban transport problem in&#13;
Jakarta .&#13;
&#13;
. LEWIS: A subway?&#13;
&#13;
KAPUR: No. Light trains.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: Light train.&#13;
&#13;
KAPUR: Elevated.&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: So I can say, yeah, we are happy with the World Bank, especially when we&#13;
want to attract other donors, especially the bilateral. If World Bank is there, it's like a,&#13;
you know, it's like a status guarantee the project is well prepared and they're sure that the&#13;
implementation also will be done [inaudible] Every time we have a--what do you call it,&#13;
a co-finance?&#13;
&#13;
KAPUR: Right.&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: It {inaudible} European countries. So if we say this is a World Bank project&#13;
we need a co-finance, it's not quite difficult for us to invite other donors to participate in&#13;
the financing. Compare it, for instance, to a project we prepare under the bilateral loan,&#13;
one country prepare it and we want to invite another country to co-finance it, sometimes&#13;
much, much more difficult. But if the World Bank- it's like a, you know, a {inaudible}&#13;
good quality.&#13;
&#13;
KAPUR: Do you often find that the number of consultants in a World Bank project is&#13;
too high?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: The rate, you mean?&#13;
&#13;
KAPUR: Or just the sheer number?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Too high in terms of what?&#13;
&#13;
 WEBB: Too many consultants.&#13;
&#13;
 LEWIS: Too many consultants and also too expensive?&#13;
&#13;
 SIREGAR: Too expensive. You know, it depends on the tender because their whole&#13;
 is- no, because the World Bank always comes with the, you know- what do you call it--&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                Muchtarudin Siregar&#13;
                            November 26, 1991 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                           9&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
high standard. When we tender of course we' ll consult them and then we decide.&#13;
Compare, for instance, UNDP [United Nations Development Program] finance, we fix&#13;
the rate: it' s 3000 per [inaudible] so we cannot go beyond that. Of course, I don't want to&#13;
say the UNDP consultants were lower in quality [inaudible]; of course sometimes we can&#13;
get the second class without them, right through the World Bank project also get the best&#13;
consultant we can hire, because the fund is there, it is up to us how to use it, but the&#13;
UNDP process is now more room for us to {inaudible}&#13;
&#13;
WEBB: Does the World Bank tend to choose the best projects? Do they, in your blue&#13;
book ...&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: The best projects of what? The big projects, yes.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: Big projects.&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: And we are ready for that because normally we can get other donors to&#13;
finance it, so if the World Bank pick up a project, for instance, under two hundred million&#13;
dollars.&#13;
&#13;
WEBB: Can you push them a lot into the projects that you want them to fmance?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Oh, yes, yes, yes. It's always like that because we-what do you call it-&#13;
call it a country multi-years program, preparing three years to come and then start&#13;
discussing, identifying projects.&#13;
&#13;
WEBB: There's some flexibility on their side..&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Yeah.&#13;
&#13;
WEBB: . . in terms of what they fmance?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Oh, yes.&#13;
&#13;
WEBB: They respond to the government?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Oh, yes. Very, very responsive. So we don't have any complaints.&#13;
&#13;
WEBB: Yeah.&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Much, much better compared with some other bilateral donors. Sometimes&#13;
you just think, " Why are they going finance this?" because having us before, "Why, why&#13;
did you [inaudible]?" But the World Bank always has very good relationship so far.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: Is it sometimes able to sort of fill in the gaps? I mean, you' ve got the Germans&#13;
who want to do this, the Japanese this, and you can talk with the Bank and say, "Now ..&#13;
,&#13;
&#13;
                               Muclttarudin Siregar&#13;
                           November 26, 1991 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                         10&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: " ow you finance this one." No.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: You don't do that?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Sometimes is difficult because the average rate of return minimum 12&#13;
percent. When we talk about equity in development, yes, we face problems with the&#13;
World Bank.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: You have a problem?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: We face problems because ..&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: They want such a high return on . .&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Oh, they always stick to the 12 percent rate of return. How can we--we&#13;
make it if it's in the eastern part of Indonesia. Maybe you're not too familiar with our&#13;
philosophy of development. Equity came first, comes first. And then the second is&#13;
growth, and the third is stability. And then when we talk about equity, we mean we talk&#13;
about the poor and also the eastern part of Indonesia because Indonesia, also the&#13;
development's not yet--the western part is growing much faster, but the eastern part is&#13;
difficult. Then for the eastern part sometimes [inaudible} the World Bank. But since we&#13;
have so many projects agreeable to, still, and the World Bank wi ll give only about one&#13;
million every year, so it's still not enough.&#13;
&#13;
WEBB: But the Bank has been saying for a long time that they favor equity.&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Oh, yes. They favor equity but more to the international concept than to our&#13;
concept.&#13;
&#13;
WEBB: Not your concept. What's the difference?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: The difference is we talk about equity, yeah. If you talk about equity in the&#13;
national area, an issue like the poverty line of the urban poor, you go to the grassroots.&#13;
You can find it in the western part of Indonesia everywhere. The World Bank can easily&#13;
build roads there. But if we talk about how to build roads in Irian Jaya, Papua New&#13;
Guinea, next to Papua New Guinea, where no people live there but for the political&#13;
consideration of Indonesia we have to do it. No way you can invite World Bank.&#13;
&#13;
WEBB: They don't have much sense of regional equity.&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: I think they have, but not to our ...&#13;
&#13;
WEBB: Not in your area.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: Is it because they're still troubled about West Irian and ..&#13;
&#13;
                               Muclztarudin Siregar&#13;
                           November 26, 1991 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                          11&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: No, no.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: Not at that, no?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: I could understand because it is a bank, yeah? The World Bank is a bank,&#13;
you know. How can they political [inaudible] criteria? {inaudible] political criteria, you&#13;
know. But for us as a government if it' s necessary, just forget about the economic return&#13;
for Irian Jaya, because this we have to make a balance regionally [inaudible}&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: I'm interested in what you say about equity being the number one goal. We've&#13;
been hearing a lot about this very, very close and harmonious, really, dialogue between&#13;
the Bank and the leaders of macroeconomic policy, what I guess you call the&#13;
"technocrats."&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Technocrats, yes.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: You're too young to be one of those.&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: No, I am old enough.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: Are you one of those, too?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Oh, yeah. I am 50, 52 now.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: I'm talking about the Widjojo [Nitisastro} group.&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Yeah, I'm the second generation after Widjoj o.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: All right. Now, those folks, they also accept equity as the number one&#13;
objective?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Oh, yes. It is in the state guidelines; they have to accept it.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: I see.&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: You know it's in the constitution and then translated to the state guidelines.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: All right.&#13;
&#13;
KAPUR: Do you think that stability comes after equity?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: After growth.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: After growth. Growth comes after equity?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                               M uchtarudin Siregar&#13;
                           November 26, 1991 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                           12&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Equity, growth, and stability. Before, when we start our development, I&#13;
think it was stability and growth comes first and then equity. Now we change it. After&#13;
ten years we changed it; equity goes first.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: They changed it when, in say, 1980 or something?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: After One Repelita.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: After one presidency.&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: I believe ' 73, something like that.&#13;
&#13;
KAPUR: What's your sense of the amount of wealth or the fraction of income in&#13;
Indonesia which comes from Jakarta as opposed to other parts? Or the national income,&#13;
what fraction of it now comes from Jakarta?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: More than 50 percent.&#13;
&#13;
KAPUR: More than 50 percent, which would mean that there would be a lot of inequity.&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Oh, yeah.&#13;
&#13;
There' s a lot of inequity also in terms of population distribution. Java is only what-15&#13;
percent of the area; people live here 65 percent. Take, for instance, Irian Jaya, Papua&#13;
New Guinea, no? That' s seven times of Java in the area. Only one million people live&#13;
there. In Java 150 million, see?&#13;
&#13;
And also the natural resources. They took almost everything, you see, the army, so this is&#13;
really why, you see why I, you know, the balance ...&#13;
&#13;
KAPUR: Right now I guess it seems that the World Bank is lending more and more to&#13;
Indonesia in sort of the areas which they call human resource development, education,&#13;
population. Do you think that these, that the focus on these sectors helps Indonesia?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Helps. Oh, yes. As I said, the World Bank has been doing that for us but&#13;
still not enough for our needs, not enough. And also it's difficult for us to invite the&#13;
World Bank goes to our, you know, to our needs so far.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: Well, would you say it's generally true the World Bank has difficulty in these&#13;
areas, social sectors, of working really down at the grassroots?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: No, no. To the regions, talk about the regions in Indonesia.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: The regions. But they aren' t so-they need to somehow or another wholesale&#13;
their resources, don't they? Who then would do the work in educat!on, population, and so&#13;
on down at the village level: the government?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                Muclttarudin Siregar&#13;
                            November 26, 1991 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                             13&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Government. The World Bank also. Their reports smallest sectorals,&#13;
sectoral, say, for instance, their limit is sc4ool. If you touch also schooling there in the&#13;
poorer areas of eastern Indonesia but through the sectoral one, it's not directly to us. So&#13;
the World Bank will only touch through the education projects, through transmigration&#13;
projects, through the urban development projects. They already touch the rural people,&#13;
but this is a sectoral course. But as I said, as I told you, but if we talk, for instance, take&#13;
the area of the Moluccas where we need a lot of presence there, we want to do something&#13;
there, it's so difficult for us to [inaudible). But if we can find a sector project which is&#13;
economically feasible, of course World Bank can always do that.&#13;
&#13;
J(APUR: Do you believe like, as some people say, "Well, if that was the case, since&#13;
money is fungible, if you were, if GOI [Government of Indonesia} was going to do a&#13;
project in West Java, now that the World Bank is financing a project in West Java, that&#13;
money can instead be used by GOI in ..." So in a sense . . .&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Yeah, yeah. That is why our development budget is combined into the&#13;
loans, with the World Bank, and our own budget, our own GOI. And this is the main&#13;
sources of funds to our equity [inaudible} budgets, to tell the truth.&#13;
&#13;
WEBB: How much of it does the Bank fmance, more or less? One quarter of&#13;
development budgets?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Oh, they now reach almost 1.5 billion dollars. Our budget is something like&#13;
35.&#13;
&#13;
WEBB: Development budget?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: No, the total budget.&#13;
&#13;
WEBB: Total?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Development.&#13;
&#13;
WEBB: Total?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Total.&#13;
&#13;
WEBB: And investment?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: And investment--development is about half of it.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: About half.&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Say maybe 120 or four percent.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                 Muchtarudin Siregar&#13;
                            N ovember 26, 1991 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                      14&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
KAPUR: So that's about 12 percent of the development budget?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: They are one and a half, and the development budget is about 20 percent or&#13;
less than that.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: And are they the largest donors, the Japanese?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: No, they are almost . . .&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: About the same?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Yeah, the Japanese, yes.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: Going up rapidly.&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Even in the World Bank we have to share it with others. [Laughter}&#13;
&#13;
WEBB: You're getting a lot of investment.&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Oh, yeah, yeah. And then the Japanese, the OECF [Overseas Economic&#13;
Cooperation Fund] Joan sometimes is more flexible, so we can use it for domestic ..&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: For local costs?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: For local costs.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: Easier than the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Easier than the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
KAPUR: But the Japanese money, is that more easily used for your equity objectives?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Sometimes. Sometimes.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: When you were deputy chairman one of the things you had in your portfolio&#13;
was agriculture. What about the World Bank in agriculture?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Oh, it was quite [inaudible] especially in irrigation.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: Irrigation.&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Here also the number one was {inaudible] you know, eleven or twelve.&#13;
&#13;
WEBB: The transmigration projects have been big agricultural loans in effect.&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Yes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                              M uclttarudin Siregar&#13;
                          November 26, 1991 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                          15&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
WEBB: They were really examples of the Bank favoring development of the other&#13;
islands, weren't they, the poorer areas, even though they also helped you keep colonists?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Mrn-lunm.&#13;
&#13;
WEBB: I was interested in this comment that the Bank doesn't seem to be on the same&#13;
wavelength, flnd it difficult to accept your concept of equity which has a strong regional&#13;
context, it seems, which implies, I think--I don't know ifl' m understanding it--it implies&#13;
regional subsidies, doing things in poor areas, backward areas, which may not be&#13;
economic at the same rate and the Bank doesn't like that [inaudible]&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: So what's the ...&#13;
&#13;
WEBB: Well, I'm wondering whether the transmigration is an exception to that.&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Yeah, yeah. As I told you, World Bank equity- the involvement in equity&#13;
issues, I mean our equity program, mostly through the sectoral projects, the&#13;
transmigration, our rural development, our education, our irrigation also. But it is limited;&#13;
it is limited. They always try to fmd, they always have to justify the economical impact. I&#13;
don't know how they do it because the calculations, but always stick to that. And then if&#13;
they can make it, the project will be approved. But if you talk about poor area in one of&#13;
the islands in the eastern part oflndonesia, well, there is no transmigration, there's no&#13;
education projects we were speaking about, there is no such, there is nothing. But people&#13;
live there who want to improve their living, so how ...&#13;
&#13;
I don't know any way that we can do this, ask for this from the World Bank, not even&#13;
with other donors maybe, not only the World Bank, other bilateral donors also maybe.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: Where did the idea for transmigration come from? Was it within the&#13;
government?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: From within the government; we have a kind of planning agency.&#13;
&#13;
We call it the spontaneous, automatic, by itself.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: Spontaneous?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Spontaneous transmigration and government does ...&#13;
&#13;
KAPUR: The Bank's own review of the transmigration projects was somewhat mixed.&#13;
What was your sense of it?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: What' s that? I . . .&#13;
&#13;
KAPUR: The Bank's own review of the transmigration projects, it gave a sort of mixed&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                               Muchtarudin Siregar&#13;
                           November 26, 1991 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                            16&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
picture of the relative success, of the cost effectiveness.&#13;
&#13;
WEBB: Excuse me. Do you know the OED [Operations Evaluation Department} side&#13;
of the World Bank?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: No.&#13;
&#13;
WEBB: It's an internal auditing.&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah, I know.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: Evaluating.&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: They sent a report, also.&#13;
&#13;
WEBB: They did. They're very independent, and they often criticize the other party.&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: It's not the mistake of the World Bank only. lt's the government. All the&#13;
transmigration programs of the government are like that. So World Bank is only one of&#13;
the participants involved in this. I mean, you cannot blame World Bank.&#13;
&#13;
WEBB: Do you think it is essentially a bad idea, or it just wasn't carried out as well as it&#13;
could have been?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: It's difficult to answer because, you know, if government don't do the&#13;
transmigration, government transmigration projects, what are the ways to move people&#13;
from Java to other islands? If they do it, it's very costly. Then how to reduce the cost,&#13;
because the key is not in the government part but the multiplier effect of it--1 mean, one&#13;
government transmigrant will bring how many spontaneously? This is the big key. If the&#13;
ratio is so low, one to two is not feasible; maybe if one to 20, that will be--the costs will&#13;
be going down.&#13;
&#13;
WEBB: Has it worked like that? Has there been a big multiplier?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: No, no, maybe eight, maybe seven. I don't know how many, maybe twenty.&#13;
I don't have the figures.&#13;
&#13;
Then how to attract people to move to outer islands out of Java? So again, the regional&#13;
development. It's like, you know, they apply to see you [inaudible} make lives full and&#13;
they will try to go. It's more like that.&#13;
&#13;
This is also very much an issue also of the government bureaucracy. If you are an&#13;
investor you want to open a new business in the region. If everything is decided in&#13;
Jakarta, just your costs--you know how far is it eastern part of Indonesia? There is no&#13;
[inaudible} of the government. It's two hours' flight. You spent all your money already&#13;
just to get approval, to get a permit. You don't just go there, no labor, no-there' s&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                 Muchtarudin Siregar&#13;
                             November 26, 1991 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                        17&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
nothing. It's also very much related to the total, ifl can say, the change of the new&#13;
president, so make the region more attractive. The people will go. But transmigration is&#13;
like start to move it by themselves. I don't think this is [inaudible] Personally I don't&#13;
believe [inaudible] you know. Other government agencies support this. It's only the&#13;
transmigration doing this. But to develop the region, change the bureaucracies,&#13;
[inaudible] everything, you know, then it must be together.&#13;
&#13;
But the World Bank views the rural--they were so much impressed by this . .&#13;
&#13;
WEBB: They were?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: They were so much impressed by the government transmigration program&#13;
in {inaudible] with the belief that we followed where others have . . .&#13;
&#13;
But in reality ..&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: About when did that happen?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: I believe that was in some-when we started with transmigration projects in&#13;
West Sumatra-'79, I think. Around that time.&#13;
&#13;
L EWIS: Around there?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: But at that time, the oil boom and the government has a lot of money, and&#13;
they spent billions of rupiah, buy- what do you call it- buy the bulldozer and those&#13;
things. We had a lot of money from the oil.&#13;
&#13;
And then the World Bank--! don't know; this is my personal opinion--maybe World Bank&#13;
watch it and say, "Why am I not involved?" Maybe, I don't know. Maybe! Please don't&#13;
quote me on that! Maybe. This project done by the government, World Bank was not&#13;
involved. So, you know if you are in the World Bank, you ask the question, maybe.&#13;
Yeah! Yeah! Yeah!&#13;
&#13;
WEBB: A piece of the action.&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: But why government could do that? Because they want to? They have a lot&#13;
of money, so transmigration program was one of the programs is very much far behind&#13;
other sectors in the Bank. Government people saw it first. And at the same time the&#13;
minister of transmigration was appointed just to show how serious government has&#13;
thought that this issue was.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: And now is the perception that it's not very successful--I mean within the&#13;
government generally?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: [inaudible]&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                               Muchtarudin Siregar&#13;
                           November 26, 1991 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                          18&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: It's subsided? It's not going on at the same rate?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Ah, because there are, you know, speaking about [inaudible] activities, you&#13;
know, but still one of the big projects.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: l see.&#13;
&#13;
WEBB: We've seen often in many countries that the Bank follows a cycle like that.&#13;
They get very enthusiastic about something, then five, ten years later they are criticizing&#13;
about all of it: "That was a big mistake." Do you see many cases of that here?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Uh ... not so many. Maybe the good example would be transmigration.&#13;
&#13;
W EBB: That's the one example. Other ..&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Maybe you can find, maybe plantation [inaudible] but I don't know the&#13;
examples.&#13;
&#13;
WEBB: They've been more consistent here?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Not much. I can see only transmigration. I can see clearly, but others&#13;
{inaudible}&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: Has there been discussion here about the Bank getting into employment&#13;
programs?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: No.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: Have they done much?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Yeah, they are helping the Department of Manpower.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: Manpower?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Yeah.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: This is urban or rural employment?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Both.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: Both. They help by what, by technical assistance?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Yeah, I think. I don't remember [inaudible} It's already discussed every&#13;
time in the economic report. We have a--what do you call it--economic report that's&#13;
presented in the IGGI. It's an evaluation by the World Bank presented to the IGGI,&#13;
employment and everything like that always is covered in the topics discussed. They are&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                 Muchtarudin Siregar&#13;
                            N ovember 26, 1991 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                         19&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
very much concerned about it. Even maybe there are not so many loans, sectors, but ...&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: Well, that would certainly be local cost financing, if they were to add to it.&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Yeah, a local cost financing example is the labor-intensive projects by the&#13;
government of Indonesia.&#13;
&#13;
WEBB: Which ones?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: The labor-intensive.&#13;
&#13;
WEBB: What would they ..&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Yeah, we call it, Instruksi Presiden [Presidential Instruction} projects for&#13;
the urban and the rural areas.&#13;
&#13;
KAPUR: In the 20-odd years, 24 years, since ' 68 when the Bank has been here, there&#13;
has been a lot of changes within Indonesia. Have you had a sense of any changes in the&#13;
World Bank's approach to development?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: I did not follow. What was your ...&#13;
&#13;
KAPUR: Well, like within Indonesia itself the economy has changed and developed, in&#13;
terms of their development philosophy.&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Oh, they follow Indonesia. They are [inaudible} change since then.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: The Bank follows you, then?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Yeah. They try--they have their own, but so far we don't see any {inaudible}&#13;
concerning this idea. For instance, when we prepare our Repelita, they have also their&#13;
own assessment, but in the formal rule is very much developed. For instance, when we&#13;
start our first Repelita, they only come to us: " Stick to what we call a project loan."&#13;
Project loan means they follow everything with regard to the project which is limited to&#13;
that. "Then after 15 years, go more and more to what we call the sectoral loan." It is just&#13;
[inaudible} They see our capital is already much improved, and then--I don't know; when&#13;
was it? ' 81, ' 82? We start with a sectoral loan. I mean-yeah, it is not only when the&#13;
World Bank teach us to do [inaudible] but they always accept us to do {inaudible}&#13;
Indonesia.&#13;
&#13;
{End Tape 1}&#13;
{Begin Tape 2]&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: Usually in the Bank when somebody is like that, they get accused of being&#13;
more Indonesian than the Indonesians. But that didn't apply to Bernie for some reason.&#13;
The Bank doesn't criticize him in that regard. It's a very common complaint about people,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                               Muclrtarudin Siregar&#13;
                           November 26, 1991 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                          20&#13;
&#13;
after all, that they go native, you know. [Laughte1]&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: He has helped us a lot because he sometimes could go straight to the top.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: Yeah, he could do that.&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Not by-passing but, you know, to make us more. He has also been near the&#13;
negotiations in Washington. If a program is, you know, [inaudible}&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: Which negotiations?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Negotiations in Washington. For instance, if a program is ..&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: Oh.&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: .. is going to pot, the Indonesian delegation will always consult with Bernie&#13;
and then [inaudible} Colleagues in our negotiations have told me we always say there is&#13;
an Indonesian Mafia, Colin O' Farrell {phonetic) told me. Maybe Bernie is the Indonesian&#13;
Mafia in the World Bank. I don't know!&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: Right.&#13;
&#13;
WEBB: In most countries that I know of you find people who admire the World Bank,&#13;
but also there' s a lot of feeling of kind of some irritation and sometimes stronger, but you&#13;
don't find much of that here.&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Well, you may. Sometimes, yes. Take, for instance, right here in this office,&#13;
director general of sea transportation. You know, it' s not easy to improve the sea&#13;
transportation in a country, in a maritime country like Indonesia. So many issues,&#13;
sometimes several issues very touchy politically and also administratively and of course&#13;
maritime also. And when we had an admiral as the director general, he's already&#13;
{inaudible} not the economic, more for- I don' t know. And we had the people in, the&#13;
World Bank people, because the World Bank team came to me and said at this time,&#13;
"This is what we should do in order to improve the shipping in Indonesia." So, so many&#13;
requirements, covenants.&#13;
&#13;
WEBB: I can imagine.&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Then you know what the director general said? "You and the World Bank&#13;
are going to run this country, or what?" Then no more road map after that. Only one road&#13;
in maritime. [Laughter} It happens sometimes.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: You don't have any foreign advisors in this ministry, do you?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Not now, but in the past, yes, a lot.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                Muchtarudin Siregar&#13;
                            November 26, 1991 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                          21&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: We've been impressed by how many foreign advisors there are still here in&#13;
different ministries.&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Yeah. Mostly from bilateral.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: Mostly from bilaterals?&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: I don't know. I have some doubts on [inaudible] But Indonesian officials,&#13;
they feel comfortable with the experts. They have to do it in English now, and they make&#13;
the effort to do it. [inaudible} myself something else.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: The language is a factor [both speaking at once]&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Something like that, sometimes, you know, they' re just depending on the&#13;
consultants. The consultants are happy living in Indonesia, much better then in&#13;
Washington {inaudible} Here you can go to the beach and have five servants in your&#13;
bouse, you know. You have to be private, too, of course.&#13;
&#13;
That is why when I was in BAPPENAS I was very careful to push [inaudible} the&#13;
bilaterals donors to give more technical assistance because maybe also politically it's&#13;
easier for them to pass the parliament approval than to give credit or loan agreements.&#13;
&#13;
So you, in general I think you are {inaudible}&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: Okay.&#13;
&#13;
WEBB: That's very helpful.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: Good testimony. You give the Bank a pretty clean bill of health, I guess.&#13;
[Laughter]&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: This [inaudible] can hire {inaudible} Maybe in Indonesia that' s one of the&#13;
issues that [inaudible}&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: We trained some of them in our university, our school even. Jim [James Q.]&#13;
Harrison's got two degrees from us.&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: Yeah, maybe it's best project with the World Bank team, now. He took&#13;
reading, like in the university like the other bilateral donors.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: Yeah, I know.&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: I enjoyed it. [Laughter] Okay, sir.&#13;
&#13;
LEWIS: Thank you very much indeed.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                Muchtarudin Siregar&#13;
                           N ovember 26, 1991 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                     22&#13;
&#13;
SIREGAR: I hope I can ..&#13;
&#13;
[End Tape 2}&#13;
[End of interview}&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                           Muchtarudin Siregar&#13;
                       November 26,1991 - Verbatim&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="25074200">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2015/09/25074200/transcript-oral-history-interview-muchtarudin-siregar-held-november-26-1991
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2015/09/25074200/transcript-oral-history-interview-muchtarudin-siregar-held-november-26-1991</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2015/09/25074200/transcript-oral-history-interview-muchtarudin-siregar-held-november-26-1991</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2015-09-21T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2015-09-22T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <docm_id>090224b0830f4694</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b0830f4694</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2015/09/22/090224b0830f4694/1_0/Rendered/INDEX/Transcript0of00on0November026001991.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2015/09/22/090224b0830f4694/1_0/Rendered/PDF/Transcript0of00on0November026001991.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2015-09-22T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1991-11-26T02:42:01Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Transcript of oral history interview with
            Muchtarudin Siregar held on November 26, 1991
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            In November 1991, Muchtarudin Siregar
            interviewed on behalf of the World Bank Group Archives oral
            history program by John Lewis, Richard Webb, Devesh Kapur.
            This transcript concerns serious negotiations between
            Indonesia with the World Bank and the International Monetary
            Fund in 1968; and the World Bank’s concentration on
            infrastructure in early ‘70s.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Transcript of oral history interview with
            Muchtarudin Siregar held on November 26, 1991
        </docna>
        <display_title>Transcript of oral history
            interview with Muchtarudin Siregar held on November 26, 1991</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/1991/11/25074200/transcript-oral-history-interview-muchtarudin-siregar-held-november-26-1991</listing_relative_url>
        <topic>Monetary Policy and Growth m1326242 1076,Monetary and Financial Stability m1327169 1098,Monetary Policy m1327609 444,Monetary Analysis m1327610 1108</topic>
        <subtopic>Sustainable Land and Crop Management,Banks &amp; Banking Reform,Public Sector Corruption &amp;
            Anticorruption Measures,Transport Economics Policy &amp; Planning,Access to Finance</subtopic>
        <docty>Transcript</docty>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Transport,Public Sector Development,Rural Development</teratopic>
        <count>Indonesia</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!517191</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Asia!$!517198</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Southeast Asia!$!Southeast Asia</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>090224b0830f4694_1_0</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>East Asia and Pacific,East Asia and Pacific</admreg>
        <colti>World Bank Group Archives oral history program</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Transport,Public Sector Development,Rural Development</historic_topic>
        <topicv3>Monetary Policy and Growth m1326242 1076,Monetary and Financial Stability m1327169 1098,Monetary Policy m1327609 444,Monetary Analysis m1327610 1108</topicv3>
        <majdocty>Board Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            urban transport, employment, equity, travel,
            transportation, transit, capital, people, politics,
            financing, subway, village, interest, bank, government,
            rapid transit, industry, financial assistance, equity
            objectives, credit, trains, minister, loan, projects, public
            works, railway, highways, wealth, urban development, policy,
            new business, roads, bank lending, railways, economies of
            scale, bank loans, road, technical assistance, complaints,
            costs, investment, sources of funds, transport, agreements,
            rail, cooperation, debts, economic cooperation, complaint,
            it, lending, criteria, true, light rail, labor, loans,
            natural resources, guarantee, subsidies, finance, auditing,
            transit system
        </keywd>
        <owner>Knowledge &amp; Information Services (ITSKI)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Southeast Asia</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>99613</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sustainable Land and Crop Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Capacities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Staffing Needs Assessments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Railways Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deconcentration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delegation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Devolution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sub-National Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subnational Government and Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport in Urban Areas</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Transit</ml:concept><ml:concept>Oceans</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sustainable Land Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agricultural Growth and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Railways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports &amp; Waterways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Highways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Administrative Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Eastern Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Indonesia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>