<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>                      Document of&#13;
                    The World Bank&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                               Report No: T7602&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                 TECHNICAL    ANNEX&#13;
&#13;
              FOR A PROPOSED CREDIT&#13;
&#13;
                 IN THE AMOUNT    OF&#13;
&#13;
                  SDR 15.7 MILLION&#13;
&#13;
            (US$22 MILLION  EQUIVALENT)&#13;
&#13;
                        TO THE&#13;
&#13;
   TRANSITIONAL   ISLAMIC  STATE OF AFGHANISTAN&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                        FOR AN&#13;
&#13;
EMERGENCY   COMMUNICATIONS      DEVELOPMENT  PROJECT&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   September 5,2003&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                      CURRENCY        EQUIVALENT&#13;
             (Exchange rate Effective as of July 31,2003&#13;
&#13;
                Currency Unit                  Afghani&#13;
               AFA 1                   =-      US$O.O224&#13;
                US$l                   -       44.567 AFA&#13;
&#13;
                   GOVERNMENT            FISCAL    YEAR&#13;
                          March 21 - March 20&#13;
&#13;
               ABBREVIATIONS            AND ACRONYMS&#13;
&#13;
AACA           Afghanistan     Assistance Coordination      Authority&#13;
ARTF           Afghanistan     Reconstruction    Trust Fund&#13;
AWCC           Afghan    Wireless Communications         Company&#13;
CFAA            Country   Financial  Accountability     Assessment&#13;
CPFA            Country   Profile of Financial   Accountability&#13;
DAB            Da Afghanistan      Bank&#13;
ES              Satellite Earth Station&#13;
FMR            Financial   Monitoring     Reports&#13;
GCN            Government      Communications      Network&#13;
GSM             Global Standard for Mobile&#13;
ICT            Information    and Communication        Technologies&#13;
IDA            International    Development    Association&#13;
ITU            International    Telecommunications       Union&#13;
MIS            Management       Information   System&#13;
MOC            Ministry    of Communication&#13;
MOF            Ministry    of Finance&#13;
O&amp;M            Operation    and Maintenance&#13;
PC             Procurement      Consultant&#13;
PMS            Project Management        Specialist&#13;
PPIAF          Public Private Infrastructure     Advisory    Facility&#13;
TDF            Telecommunications        Development     Fund&#13;
TISA           Transitional    Islamic State of Afghanistan&#13;
TRAA           Telecommunications        Regulatory    Authority   of Afghanistan&#13;
TSS            Transitional    Support Strategy&#13;
               United Nations&#13;
UNDP           United Nations      Development     Program&#13;
UPU            Universal    Postal Union&#13;
USAID          United    States Agency    for International  Development&#13;
VSAT           Very Small Aperture       Terminal&#13;
WLL            Wireless Local Loop&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                         Vice President:         Praful Pate1&#13;
                       Country   Director:       Alastair  J. McKechnie&#13;
                         Sector Manager:         Pierre Guislain&#13;
  Afghanistan Reconstruction    Manager:         Philippe  Dongier&#13;
                           Team Leader:          Charles Kenny&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                       TRANSITIONAL             ISLAMIC           STATE OF AFGHANISTAN&#13;
&#13;
                EMERGENCY           COMMUNICATIONS                        DEVELOPMENT                    PROJECT&#13;
&#13;
                                               TECHNICAL               ANNEX&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                    Table of Contents&#13;
&#13;
I. Background and Recent Developments .................................................................&#13;
         A. Country Status ..........................................................................................&#13;
         B. Features of the Existing Communications System ...................................&#13;
         C. TISA Objectives ........................................................................................&#13;
&#13;
II. International Development Association (IDA) Assistance Strategy ....................&#13;
         A. The Transitional Support Strategy ............................................................&#13;
         B. Rationale for IDA Involvement in the Communications Sector.. .............&#13;
         C. Lessons Learned........................................................................................&#13;
&#13;
III. The Proposed Project ...........................................................................................      8&#13;
         A. Objectives .................................................................................................   8&#13;
         B. Project Description ....................................................................................       8&#13;
         C. Sustainability .............................................................................................  11&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
IV. Institutional Arrangements And Implementation ................................................                        12&#13;
         A . Institutional Arrangements .......................................................................           12&#13;
         B . Procurement ..............................................................................................   13&#13;
         C. Disbursement and Financial Management                       ................................................  13&#13;
         D . Environment and Social Safeguard ..........................................................                  14&#13;
         E. Monitoring and Evaluation .......................................................................             15&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Appendix I:       Project Description ............................................................................        16&#13;
Appendix II:      Procurement Arrangements ...............................................................                23&#13;
Appendix III: Financial Management,&#13;
                  Disbursement and Audit Arrangements ............................................                        28&#13;
Appendix IV: Monitoring .........................................................................................         32&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                1. BACKGROUND          AND RECENT     DEVELOPMENTS&#13;
&#13;
A. Country Status&#13;
&#13;
1       Afghanistan is one of the poorest and longest-suffering countries among the&#13;
members of the World Bank.        An estimated seven million people remain vulnerable to&#13;
hunger and very large numbers are dependent on a massive inflow               of food aid.&#13;
Afghanistan's infrastructure has been destroyed or degraded; its human resource base&#13;
severely depleted; and its social capital eroded.      State institutions are largely non-&#13;
functional, and the economy and society have become increasingly fragmented.&#13;
&#13;
2       The Afghanistan     Interim   Administration and its successor, the Transitional&#13;
Islamic State of Afghanistan (TISA) have moved quickly to restore basic government&#13;
functions and re-establish international relations.    However, expectations among the&#13;
population for a "peace dividend" are high, and if TISA does not deliver results relatively&#13;
quickly, the prospects for further progress and the peace process will dim.&#13;
&#13;
3       Despite being hampered by very limited        capacity and the difficult   security&#13;
situation in many parts of the country, the TISA has made considerable progress and has&#13;
gained widespread international recognition.      A budget has been passed by the TISA&#13;
Cabinet laying out an ambitious agendaof reconstruction, reform and growth for the next&#13;
two years.&#13;
&#13;
B. Features of the Existing Communications        Sector&#13;
&#13;
4.      Afghanistan has a barely functioning, very limited communications sector. Prior&#13;
to the recent bombing campaign, Afghanistan's telecommunications network operated&#13;
approximately 57,000 lines in five major cities (two thirds of these lines were in Kabul).&#13;
These appear to have largely survived the bombing.&#13;
&#13;
5       The Ministry    of Communications (MOC) operates a digital service mainly in&#13;
Kabul, Herat and Mazar where recent national and international satellite links have now&#13;
been established. Kabul has recently installed a 12,000 fixed line digital switch with&#13;
7,000 active lines. Herat includes a 7,500 fixed line digital system, most of which are&#13;
active and Mazar has a capacity of 4,000 lines, most of which are also active. The MOC&#13;
also operates an analogue network mainly in Kabul with an estimated 8,000 active lines&#13;
although the switch does have a capacity of 15,000 lines. Instanet is currently completing&#13;
the installation of five Very Small Aperture Terminals (VSATs) in the five main cities of&#13;
Afghanistan on behalf of the MO.           These will  give the MOC      limited backbone&#13;
transmission to connect its digital lines.&#13;
&#13;
6       Afghan Wireless Communications Company (AWCC), which is a joint venture&#13;
with the MOC, currently operatesa digital wired service in Kabul connecting some of the&#13;
Ministries   and a score of public telephone booths to its international satellite switch.&#13;
There are similar operations in Herat and Mazar with lower numbers whilst Kandahar is&#13;
estimated to have 750 active lines. AWCC has recently launched a Global Standard for&#13;
Mobile (GSM) service in Kabul with plans to offer service in the five major cities within&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                          1&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
two months. A new mobile operator is currently testing its services for full release in the&#13;
near future. The operator was selected through a process of competitive bidding earlier&#13;
this year.&#13;
&#13;
7       However, country teledensity remains on the order of two telephones per 1,000&#13;
people compared to 24 per thousand in Pakistan, 35 in Tajikistan, 68 in Uzbekistan, and&#13;
83 in Turkmenistan.      The fixed analogue, fixed digital and wireless digital networks&#13;
present in Kabul are not interconnected.&#13;
&#13;
8.      At present, the Government's abilities to coordinate its own operations are&#13;
severely limited by inadequate communications capacity between Ministries in Kabul -&#13;
in the majority of cases, inter-Ministry  communications requires either physical transfer&#13;
of information or meetings. This constraint extends to the capacity to communicate with&#13;
other actors in Kabul and internationally, with very few telephone lines and even less&#13;
Internet capacity (the majority of Ministries have no effective access to the Internet at&#13;
all).  Most Ministries also have no capacity to communicate with the provinces.           Da&#13;
Afghanistan Bank (DAB)        has limited  satellite-based connectivity with its provincial&#13;
Banks, and it is likely that the Ministry of Finance (MOF), at least in the short term, will&#13;
be able to share that capacity. Given the scale of demand and the limited nature of the&#13;
DAB network, however, the rest of the Kabul Government has effectively no access to&#13;
their regional counterparts. Furthermore, the design of the DAB network is unsuitable&#13;
for more intensive use.&#13;
&#13;
9       Postal services are also recovering from years of conflict. There is a post office in&#13;
every district, and the potential for the postal network to function as not only a delivery&#13;
vehicle for letter and parcels, but also government services, other communications&#13;
technologies and (potentially) financial services. However, at present, many post offices&#13;
are dilapidated and lack even such basic equipment as scales and franking machines.&#13;
Even the central post office      in Kabul    lacks basic mail handling and processing&#13;
equipment.&#13;
&#13;
C. TISA Objectives&#13;
&#13;
10      The overriding objective of the TISA's       national communications policy is to&#13;
achieve modernization     and rapid expansion of telecommunications            networks and&#13;
services, and to aim for universal accessto telecommunications across Afghanistan. The&#13;
TISA recognizes that in order to achieve this, it is important to create the right conditions&#13;
for open competition and private sector investment by ensuring a stable and transparent&#13;
policy, legal and regulatory environment.&#13;
&#13;
11.     Policy will also evolve toward a technologically neutral, open and convergent&#13;
status. Certain distinctions may remain for purposes of licensing and regulation, for&#13;
example for those services depending upon scarce resources and to support accessgoals.&#13;
The primary objective, however, is to lessen artificial technology and service barriers,&#13;
and to   encourage the forces of convergence and market innovation               to promote&#13;
widespread accessto a range of affordable communications services.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
12       A Telecommunications     Act is being finalized and the government is presently&#13;
working    to set up an independent Telecommunications            Regulatory  Authority   of&#13;
Afghanistan (TRAA).      Afghanistan will ensure that the TRAA is completely independent&#13;
of any operator or service provider in the ICT sector. For the coming months, with&#13;
support from the Public Private Infrastructure Advisory Facility       (PPIAF), an interim&#13;
Telecommunications      Review Board has been established in the MOC to prepare the&#13;
ground for the establishment of the TRAA by the end of 1382.&#13;
&#13;
13.      During the 5-year period covered by the existing policy,         the TISA's   clear&#13;
intention is the corporatization of the Ministry's fixed telecommunications operations.&#13;
The corporatization process (supported under the proposed project) will commence as a&#13;
priority in the last three months of 2003, with the creation of the new corporation planned&#13;
for 2004. The Ministry is planning to invite a strategic partner to manage Afghan Tel&#13;
post-corporatization.      Plans for eventual privatization    will  be augmented by an&#13;
institutional   strengthening   exercise   to   ensure    administration   procedures   and&#13;
accountability to meet all international quality and performance expectations. Although&#13;
foreign investors are invited     and encouraged to demonstrate their commitment         by&#13;
forming joint ventures with local partners, there is no minimum requirement for local&#13;
equity partners.&#13;
&#13;
14       The cellular market has two privately run national licensed operators. For long&#13;
distance and international telephony, the government has invested in some capacity with&#13;
the assistance of the Afghanistan Reconstruction Trust Fund (ARTF), but all mobile and&#13;
fixed licensees also have the right to operate long distance and international services&#13;
independently of the MOC-controlled operator. International (facilities) licenses are also&#13;
available for Internet usage - subject to separate VSAT        licensing, where appropriate&#13;
(presently only on a temporary basis).&#13;
&#13;
15       A Telecommunications     Development Fund (TDF) will be established to help&#13;
support the rapid development of universal access in areas that may be perceived as&#13;
uneconomic by the market. This Fund will be administered by the TRAA, and will be&#13;
separately identified under the Commission's operating budget. Where feasible, funds&#13;
will be employed to facilitate investment in market-oriented, sustainable operations,&#13;
which will not require further subsidy following initial start-up funding. Notwithstanding&#13;
this requirement, the Fund will be utilized to support the most beneficial investments and&#13;
services in locations most in need of communications infrastructure.       Use of the Fund&#13;
will also be coordinated with other public service projects, such as educational and health&#13;
facilities.&#13;
&#13;
16       As part of the National Development Budget and as a centerpiece of the draft&#13;
Information and Communication Technologies (ICT) Policy, the MOC has laid out as a&#13;
major priority for communications development over the next year the expansion and&#13;
improved functioning of the government's own communications system.              The MOC&#13;
expects to be the lead agency in rolling out this system as a matter of urgency, in order to&#13;
improve the ability of the TISA to govern.       The TISA recognizes the vital need for&#13;
improved     government communications      to allow more efficient     governance, greater&#13;
transparency, and greater interaction with the provinces.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         3&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
17      The TISA is keen to see the rehabilitation of the postal network both to allow the&#13;
delivery of parcels and letters, but also to expand the use of post offices as a point of&#13;
interaction between government and citizen and, potentially, a location for voice and data&#13;
communications access and financial service delivery.       The administration has already&#13;
undertaken some innovative         public-private   ventures to improve    service delivery,&#13;
including an arrangement whereby a private company provides stamps to the postal&#13;
system for no charge in return for the right to issue stamps to collectors worldwide.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  II. INTERNATIONAL           DEVELOPMENT          ASSOCIATION       (IDA) ASSISTANCE&#13;
                                          STRATEGY&#13;
&#13;
A. The Transitional     Support Strategy&#13;
&#13;
18      The Transitional Support Strategy (TSS), presented to the Executive Directors of&#13;
IDA    in March     2003, is predicated on the need for well-coordinated          efforts by&#13;
Afghanistan's development partners to realize Afghanistan's emergency reconstruction&#13;
and development priorities. The key objectives of IDA's        assistance are: (i) improving&#13;
livelihoods; (ii) fiscal strategy, institutions and management; (iii) governance and public&#13;
administration reform; and (iv) enabling private sector development. This project will in&#13;
particular support the third and fourth goals.       By allowing far more straightforward&#13;
government     communications       within    Kabul  and to    the  provinces,   government&#13;
administrative   capacity will   be significantly   enhanced.    By supporting policy    and&#13;
regulatory development for the sector as a whole, the project will enable expanded&#13;
provision of private, competitive telecommunications services.&#13;
&#13;
B. Rationale for IDA Involvement in the Communications           Sector&#13;
&#13;
19      Modern communications         systems are vital to the successful development of&#13;
Afghanistan. A dependable information system is essential for efficient management and&#13;
operation of the public and private sectors.          This includes areas such as internal&#13;
government information, citizen's services, trade, banking, and international relations.&#13;
Across the world, access to telecommunications has been linked to increased incomes,&#13;
improved delivery of services, the development of enterprises and economic growth.&#13;
&#13;
20      ICT is a sector in which the private sector can take the lead role.       Already in&#13;
Afghanistan, for example, two private operators are leading the way in rolling out access&#13;
to telecommunications.     However, there remain important roles for government oversight&#13;
and investment.      Governments must develop and enforce policies and the regulatory&#13;
environment required to promote private provision of services. Governments should play&#13;
a role in extending access beyond that which the market would provide alone, and&#13;
governments have an important part to play in ensuring that their own operations benefit&#13;
from access to and use of ICTs to improve governance and government operations. The&#13;
TISA has recognized these imperatives, and has promulgated policies that support such a&#13;
role.   The TISA has also made specific requests for donor support in the field of&#13;
communications to help it play that role.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                            4&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
21      Donors have begun to respond, including the World Bank. To date, World Bank&#13;
related support for communications in Afghanistan has been largely provided through&#13;
trust fund resources. Some support has been given through Analytical           and Advisory&#13;
Services (AAA)    to develop draft licensing documents for the MOC, as well as limited&#13;
support through the First Emergency Public Administration Project for legal assistanceto&#13;
the Ministry. The larger, trust-funded components, are discussed below:&#13;
&#13;
22      As administrator of the ARTF, IDA has appraised and is supervising a $3 million&#13;
ARTF investment operation in support of the Ministry        of Communications operational&#13;
arm (the future Afghan Tel) with three components:&#13;
&#13;
                Rehabilitation of Satellite Earth Station (ES): The rehabilitation of ES is&#13;
                required to eliminate     existing bottlenecks in transmission       capacity&#13;
                between Kabul and the outside world.       In addition, the capacity of this&#13;
                link will also be offered to other service providers to increase usage and&#13;
                thereby raise revenues for Afghan Tel. Rehabilitation of ES provides for&#13;
                replacement of the dish antenna, upgrading of power supply and other&#13;
                equipment needed to make the ES fully functional.       In order to minimize&#13;
                cost of rehabilitation, the use of the existing infrastructure such as the&#13;
                motorized antenna baseand adjacent building will be fully exploited.&#13;
&#13;
            l   Expand and improve transmission links to neighboring states: The re-&#13;
                establishment of this link will provide much neededtransmission capacity&#13;
                between Kabul and the Eastern provinces of Jalalabad, Nuristan, Kunar,&#13;
                Laghman, terminating in Peshawer (Pakistan).          These microwave links&#13;
                will   provide immediate    voice and data connectivity       for the above&#13;
                Provinces and also Peshawer as well          as national and international&#13;
                broadcasting traffic.&#13;
&#13;
            0   Billing System: In order to be able to generate and administer customer&#13;
                bills, the MOC requires an efficient billing system. Such a billing system&#13;
                together with appropriate processesand procedures shall help the MOC to&#13;
                increase the revenue generation and collection.         The project supports&#13;
                initial capacity development in this area.&#13;
&#13;
23     In addition, PPIAF resources totaling US$481,000 are being used to provide&#13;
consulting services over the course of the year June 2003 to February 2004 in order to:&#13;
&#13;
            l  Support     the   initial creation  of   minimal,     transparent   regulatory&#13;
                institutions and a regulatory unit within the Ministry, including design of&#13;
               regulatory     frameworks,     regulations,   institutional   structures   and&#13;
               procedures as well as capacity building        and support for stakeholder&#13;
               participation.&#13;
&#13;
            l  Support the creation and functioning      of the regulatory unit.   The focus&#13;
               will again be on creating a minimal unit carrying out only those functions&#13;
               necessaryto ensure a competitive environment; and&#13;
&#13;
            a   Map a process of further development of the regulatory body from a&#13;
                minimal unit within the MOC to an independent regulator with significant&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         5&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                institutional strength and capacity, outlining options for scope including&#13;
                convergence and/or multi-sectoral regulation.&#13;
&#13;
24     Other donors are also involved in the sector. Proposed and ongoing activities&#13;
indlude:&#13;
&#13;
                International   Telecommunications    Union (ITU):      The ITU has offered&#13;
                support    in  the  areas of    telecommunications       law  and  spectrum&#13;
                management and monitoring.        In cooperation with the United Nations&#13;
                Development Program (UNDP) and Universal Postal Union (UPU), the&#13;
                ITU has launched a pilot project to provide connectivity to a number of&#13;
                post offices around Kabul.&#13;
&#13;
                Government of the United States of America (US): The US government is&#13;
                providing short-term support in the form of a Chief Technical Officer&#13;
                who will assist in the resolution of engineering-related issues for the&#13;
                Ministry    of   Communications.        Through     different agencies and&#13;
                consultancies, the US Government is also supporting or has promised&#13;
                some support in the areas of utilities law, regulation and reform, short&#13;
                term assistance in corporatization       strategy and Internet policy,  and&#13;
                support for a feasibility study of a national fiber-optic backbone.&#13;
&#13;
                The Asian Development Bank (ADB)            (through an infrastructure loan&#13;
                administered by the MOF)        has provided investment support for the&#13;
                expansion of the digital switch and Wireless Local Loop (WLL) networks&#13;
                in Kabul and a number of provinces, to be operated by Afghan Tel/MOC.&#13;
&#13;
                UNDP: The UNDP has provided support in cooperation with the ITU and&#13;
                UPU (see above). It has also provided assistance in the drafting of an&#13;
                ICT policy, helped set up a Cisco Learning Academy and provided&#13;
                limited connectivity to selected ministries.&#13;
&#13;
                Iran: Iran has provided support to the MOC to rehabilitate the ICT&#13;
                Institute.&#13;
&#13;
25     Existing World Bank-managed support, in concert with support provided by other&#13;
donors, has played a role in the considerable progress that has occurred in the sector over&#13;
the past year - not least the licensing of two mobile operators, the development of a&#13;
spectrum management plan and movement towards the creation of telecommunications&#13;
laws, regulations and a regulatory body. This project will have to be closely coordinated&#13;
with these other activities through the Afghanistan Donor Consultative Group for Energy,&#13;
Mining and Telecommunications.&#13;
&#13;
26.    Nonetheless, there remains a significant        need for support to provide both&#13;
investment and technical assistance resources to the MOC.            Other donors have not&#13;
suggestedthey will provide this support, offering a strong rationale for IDA involvement:&#13;
&#13;
           0    As noted, communications capacity within          Kabul between Ministries&#13;
                remains very weak, as does capacity to communicate outside Kabul. This&#13;
                is particularly true of communications with provincial capitals. There is&#13;
                an urgent need to meet these government communications needs through&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         6&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                the development of a government communications network including an&#13;
                Intranet, as well as voice connectivity. Given that the establishment of a&#13;
                national backbone is currently only in the stage of a feasibility study, and&#13;
                with no funding for the project confirmed, rolling out this government&#13;
                communications network is a very timely stop-gap measure.&#13;
&#13;
            l   In order to foster the growth of a private-sector-led, competitive market&#13;
                for telecommunication services, a number of stepsneed to be undertaken:&#13;
                (i) the regulatory unit of the MOC, supported for its first year under&#13;
                PPIAF, needs to be further strengthened and separatedfrom the MOC to&#13;
                guarantee independence; (ii)       the MOC    requires re-engineering and&#13;
                investment to operate as a policy making body as opposed to policy&#13;
                maker-operator-regulator;     (iii)  the  nascent    Afghan     Tel   requires&#13;
                corporatization and preparation for eventual privatization.&#13;
&#13;
            0   The postal sector requires significant     investment support as well as&#13;
                corporatization to improve its ability to deliver basic postal services as a&#13;
                first step toward a potential expansion of its role into government,&#13;
                communications and financial services provision.          As initial  steps to&#13;
                ensure the long-term viability of the postal network and to maximize its&#13;
                contribution to national reconstruction, it will be necessary to define a&#13;
                sound postal sector policy and development plan.&#13;
&#13;
27      Elements of this agenda will be undertaken with the support of other donors&#13;
indluding ITU, UNDP, USAID         and the UPU in conjunction with the German postal&#13;
administration.  However, given the limited internal resources of the MOC and the TISA,&#13;
combined with the urgent need for progress, there remains a significant agenda of support&#13;
to be met by IDA and other donors.&#13;
&#13;
C. Lessons Learned&#13;
&#13;
28      Experience from post-conflict    environments suggests the great importance of&#13;
wireless communications     as the primary telecommunications         infrastructure, and the&#13;
rapidity with which competitive private wireless provision can roll out (even in poor and&#13;
war-tom environments) under the correct regulatory and policy conditions. This suggests&#13;
the   urgency    of   creating  regulatory    and    legal  institutions   that   can   foster&#13;
telecommunications rollout, particularly in the wireless segment.&#13;
&#13;
29      The limited (one year) experience of projects in post-conflict Afghanistan as well&#13;
as `longer experience in other post-conflict environments suggests the importance of&#13;
intensive project supervision to project success, as well as flexible implementation of&#13;
project components in a rapidly changing environment.         The experience of one year&#13;
suggests that capacity in line ministries to implement projects remains somewhat limited&#13;
(although the Ministry of Communications is relatively strong in this regard), and support&#13;
for training and project management capacity has been included in this project to help&#13;
ameliorate this situation.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                III. THE PROPOSED PROJECT&#13;
&#13;
A. Objective&#13;
30       The objective of the proposed Emergency Communications Development Project&#13;
is to support activities designed to improve delivery of communications services to the&#13;
Government and to the people of Afghanistan. This will be achieved by: (i) carrying out&#13;
urgent expansion of the government communications                     network      to restore critical&#13;
communications between ministries and provinces; (ii) providing urgently needed policy&#13;
advice and capacity building to the MOC to promote sustainable communications sector&#13;
performance and increased private sector participation; and (iii) improving the delivery of&#13;
postal services.      The outcomes of the Project are expected to be improvements in&#13;
communications facilities and delivery, while laying the foundations for sector reforms&#13;
and institution      building     which    would    lead to    sustainable development           of  the&#13;
communications sector. Monitoring indicators are given in Appendix IV.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
B. Project Description&#13;
&#13;
31       The credit has three components, covering: (a) Expanding and integrating the&#13;
existing Emergency Government Communications                    Network,     (b) MOC       Institutional&#13;
Capacity Building, and (c) Postal Sector Reform. Details of the project components are&#13;
provided in Appendix 1 and summarized below:&#13;
&#13;
Component 1: Emergency              Government Communications           Network      (US$M&#13;
million):&#13;
&#13;
32       The component supports: (a) the supply, installation, and commissioning of a&#13;
communications network that will integrate an existing network constructed by the World&#13;
Bank and the UNDP, as well as improve and extend coverage to Ministries and other key&#13;
Government organizations in Kabul as well as Provincial Capitals and selected other&#13;
sites, and (b) Operations and maintenance and training of Afghan Tel staff. The turnkey&#13;
service component will support the rollout of a network for government communications&#13;
utilizing tried and tested technologies in a robust configuration that can be rapidly rolled&#13;
out in the current Afghan environment.&#13;
&#13;
33       The MOC        of TISA     presently provides telecommunications             services to the&#13;
following ministries and entities:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
              l    Ministry of Communications&#13;
              l    Ministry of Reconstruction&#13;
              l    Ministry of Finance&#13;
              l    The Central Bank&#13;
              l    The Office of the President&#13;
              l    The Ministry of Higher Education*&#13;
              l    Ministry of Foreign Affairs*&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
* NB Ministries of Foreign Affairs and Higher Education - microwave link installed and ready for use.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              8&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
            l   The Afghanistan Assistance Coordination Authority (AACA)&#13;
&#13;
34      In phase one of the Government Communications Network component, the MOC&#13;
will expand the existing Government Communications Network (GCN) to include an&#13;
additional 12 ministries which are located in Kabul.    These ministries will be connected&#13;
by fiber or microwave or other suitable communication technology to a central location&#13;
and connect to a VSAT which will serve as the satellite gateway earth station of the&#13;
network. In addition to the expansion of the GCN to the 12 ministries, there will also be&#13;
a requirement to expand the network to 14 priority provincial capitals. In phase two of&#13;
the project, the remaining ministries, provincial capitals and selected other sites will be&#13;
connected.&#13;
&#13;
35      The operation and maintenance (O&amp;M) contract will run for the remaining life of&#13;
the project or until such time that both the MOC and the World Bank are satisfied that&#13;
capacity exists within the corporatized Afghan Tel to transfer operating responsibility and&#13;
ownership to Afghan Tel. This project component will also pay for sufficient training of&#13;
Afghan   Tel staff to provide them with        the capacity to operate the Government&#13;
Communications     network.    From that point onwards, the communications        network&#13;
operator will be under standard regulatory oversight and act as part of a commercial&#13;
(government owned) corporation. It is expected that, in the medium term (three years),&#13;
this company will be privatized, and operate as a standard telecommunications services&#13;
provider.&#13;
&#13;
36      The component will also cover training. MOC staff lack sufficient opportunities&#13;
to *develop the skills necessary to operate and maintain the various equipment to be&#13;
deployed in the GCN. Therefore a significant component of this project is the provision&#13;
of formal training for a team of MOC staff in order that they can develop the ability to&#13;
maintain the GCN independently and efficiently.&#13;
&#13;
37     It will be required that the bidder selected to expand the network, and provide&#13;
O&amp;M    services, also provide these training services. Penalties will be built into the&#13;
contract for failure to deliver training within the agreed timeframe without justifiable&#13;
reasons.&#13;
&#13;
Component 2: MOC Institutional      Capacity Building (US$7.44 million)&#13;
&#13;
38      The following   sub-components would provide support to (a) separate MOC's&#13;
policy, regulation, operational and ownership functions, (b) strengthen the MOC's policy&#13;
and project management capacity, (c) further establish and "bed down" independent&#13;
regulatory capacity, (d) establish the monitoring        equipment required to properly&#13;
administer the MOC's spectrum plan, and (e) establish Afghan Tel as an efficient State-&#13;
owned corporation:&#13;
&#13;
            0   Consulting services (US$2.3 million)     for MOC restructuring, Financial&#13;
                and   Management      Information   Systems    (MIS)    and  Afghan     Tel&#13;
                Corporatization to include: (i) support for management and organizational&#13;
                restructuring, and for implementation of a new organizational structure&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        9&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
               reflecting the MOC's      role as policy maker; (ii) examination of real&#13;
                staffing needs of MOC, and skills matching; (iii) MIS development; and&#13;
               (vi) corporatization of AghanTel (inter alia: creation of corporate entity&#13;
               and strategy for implementation of allocation of assets, liabilities     and&#13;
               staff; inventory of assets, liabilities  and personnel; asset and liability&#13;
               allocation; creation of Opening Financial Statements; examining options&#13;
               for labor force; and cost-basedtariff study).&#13;
&#13;
               Consulting services (US$l.3 million) to allow for the development of a&#13;
               strong, independent regulator to include, inter alia: (i) assistance for&#13;
               implementation of the transition from MOC unit to independent, stand-&#13;
               alone regulator;    (ii)  technical  standardization processes, spectrum&#13;
               management, pricing       and monitoring    quality  of   service standards,&#13;
               monitoring of compliance by operators with the law and license terms,&#13;
               disclosure/publicity   of regulatory processes, and other "as needed"&#13;
               support including potential development of a pro-competitive license for&#13;
               Afghan Tel and other service providers; (iii) development of performance&#13;
               criteria for Afghan Tel; (iv) professional development and training; and&#13;
               (v) MIS development.&#13;
&#13;
           0   Support for project management capacity including hiring of a Project&#13;
               Management Specialist to assist in the management of various financial&#13;
               and implementation arrangements during the life of the project (US$O.6&#13;
               million).&#13;
&#13;
           l   Procurement of spectrum monitoring         equipment including       (US$2.0&#13;
               million):    (i)  establishment     of   one   mobile     and    one   fixed&#13;
               spectrum/frequency monitoring kit, and associated training; and (ii) office&#13;
               equipment and vehicles including hardware and software to facilitate&#13;
               regulatory functioning.&#13;
&#13;
           0   Other elements (US$l.24 million), including but not limited to equipment&#13;
               (including  office equipment), training, technical advisory services to&#13;
               Afghan Tel, studies covering a potential universal access strategy and on&#13;
               an `as needed' basis, and other consulting services.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Component 3: Postal Sector Reform (US$O.56 million)&#13;
&#13;
39.   The following sub-components would support the separation of the MOC's policy&#13;
and operational functions in the postal sector and help develop the sector.&#13;
&#13;
           l   Consulting services to include (US$O.3 million):       (i) articulation of a&#13;
               postal sector policy and development strategy; (ii) support for the MOC&#13;
               in developing a regulatory framework and sufficient regulatory capacity&#13;
               to achieve: definition of attainable universal service levels and funding&#13;
               mechanisms, introduction and management of competition within the&#13;
               sector, management of pricing for regulated services, and an appropriate&#13;
               level of separation between the TISA/Government and the public operator&#13;
               through increased management autonomy and institutional capacity; (iii)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        10&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                support for the restructuring and reconstruction of the postal network to&#13;
                meet existing and future postal needs; including definition of a corporate&#13;
                Business Plan for the public           operator covering     subjects such as&#13;
                organization, staffing, and the potential development of new services&#13;
                including   e-services and financial services; and (iv) other consulting&#13;
                services.&#13;
&#13;
            0   Equipment including modernization of basic postal equipment/offices&#13;
                (US$O.26 million).&#13;
&#13;
40     The estimated project cost is US$22 million.        IDA will fund all project costs. The&#13;
summary break down of the proiect cost bv components is provided in the table below.&#13;
&#13;
                   Project  cost table and financing   plan (in US$ million)&#13;
                                     (100%   IDA  financed)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    A. Emergency     Government   Communications&#13;
                       Network&#13;
&#13;
                    B. MOC Institutional    Capacity Building&#13;
                            -   Consultancies  and training&#13;
                            -   Spectrum Monitoring    Equipment&#13;
                            -   Other Equipment&#13;
&#13;
                    C. Postal Sector Reform&#13;
                            -   Restructuring&#13;
                            -   Postal Equipment&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
C. Sustainability&#13;
&#13;
41.    Given the security situation and the fragile status of the economy and TISA,&#13;
sustainability is of serious concern.       Within the limited   area of sustainability issues&#13;
amenable to amelioration through project design, however, a number of steps will be&#13;
taken to enhance sustainability.&#13;
&#13;
            0   The government communications network is designed to be financially&#13;
                self sustaining over the medium term through internal charging for&#13;
                services (the MOC will charge other Ministries and government users for&#13;
                their  use    of   the   network).        The   intention   to   privatize  the&#13;
                telecommunication      provider    should enhance the likelihood        of this&#13;
                sustainability.&#13;
&#13;
            0   Technical sustainability will be enhanced through training and the ability&#13;
                to pay technicians competitive         salaries through corporatization    and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                           11&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                 private sector involvement.       Further, during the life of the project&#13;
                 (four years), the service contractor will    stay in place as operator and&#13;
                 maintainer of the network until such time that the Bank and the MOC are&#13;
                 comfortable that the network can be sustained by Afghan Tel.&#13;
&#13;
             a   Support for policy and regulatory reform is expected to have a sustained&#13;
                 impact. Given that a number of private operators are already active in the&#13;
                 telecommunications field, it appears that there is considerable likelihood&#13;
                 that private, competitive     service provision    will prove a success in&#13;
                 Afghanistan as it has worldwide, generating revenues through license fees&#13;
                 and payments significant       enough to sustain the required regulatory&#13;
                 capacity to overseethat provision.&#13;
&#13;
42       Support for postal reform and investment will have a sustainable impact if the&#13;
postal sector develops a sound sector policy          and development strategy along with&#13;
improved     capacity to operate efficiently     and generate revenues.      Improved basic&#13;
equipment, corporatization, an understanding of existing and future postal market&#13;
demand, and support for improved management are first steps in achieving improved&#13;
network performance and revenue generation. Given the relatively small investments in&#13;
this  sub-sector envisaged in the project,         and the imrnediate need for a basic&#13;
communications      infrastructure, the impact      of these investments    should also be&#13;
sustainable through delivering and collecting chargesfor improved service.&#13;
&#13;
43      The project is potentially at risk from the general security position in Afghanistan.&#13;
This particularly relates to the government communications network component, which&#13;
will involve activities in all 32 provinces.      Security issues will be taken into account&#13;
during the design and operation of the project.          However, like most of the current&#13;
reconstruction and development efforts, the long term sustainability of the project is&#13;
likely to be tied to the general security situation in the country.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
IV. INSTITUTIONAL          ARRANGEMENTS            AND PROJECT        IMPLEMENTATION&#13;
&#13;
A. Institutional   Arrangements&#13;
&#13;
44      The project would be implemented over a period of three and a half years. Project&#13;
completion date would be March 20, 2007, and the Credit closing date would be&#13;
September 30, 2007. This comparatively long time period for an emergency project is to&#13;
help ensure sustainability.      In particular, the government communications        network&#13;
component is urgently required to improve governance capacity, however, the MOC&#13;
lacks the technical and financial resources required to operate the network at the current&#13;
time.   This emergency project will allow for rapid rollout of the network, while an&#13;
extended project lifetime    will ensure network operation can be supported under the&#13;
project until such time that there is the local capacity to operate the network in a self-&#13;
sustaining manner.&#13;
&#13;
45      The Executing agency for the project would be the Ministry of Communications,&#13;
with  assistance to be provided on matters involving             financial management and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                          12&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
procurement     by the Afghanistan      Assistance Coordination    Authority  Procurement&#13;
Consultant. The MOC will be responsible for procurement of goods, works and services&#13;
estimated to cost up to US$25,000 per contract, following the provisions of the Credit&#13;
Agreement. Beyond this limit, procurement will be carried out with the assistanceof the&#13;
Procurement Consultant at the AACA, with technical inputs from the MOC.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
B. Procurement&#13;
&#13;
46      The IDA Emergency Public Administration        Project is funding the services of a&#13;
Procurement Consultant to support the AACA and various ministries.       The Procurement&#13;
Consultant will be responsible for assisting with the procurement of all goods and&#13;
consultancy services for the Emergency Communications Project. Procurement capacity&#13;
in MOC is being strengthened with suitable training.         To ensure that procurement&#13;
capacity is built up, Procurement Consultant will provide training to MOC staff, as well&#13;
as other staff as deemed necessary to ensure that they develop capacity to eventually&#13;
carryout procurement on their own. MOC will appoint a Project Management Specialist&#13;
to oversee the implementation of the proposed project.       Until funds under the project&#13;
become available Emergency Infrastructure Reconstruction Project funds will fund the&#13;
specialist. MOC will also provide an implementation plan outlining unit and personnel&#13;
responsibilities for selection and management of consultants as well as procurement and&#13;
operation of goods.&#13;
&#13;
47.     Goods and consulting services financed under the Project shall be procured in&#13;
accordance with the Bank's Procurement Guidelines and Guidelines for Selection and&#13;
Employment of Consultants, and using the Bank's standard bidding documents. Each&#13;
contract for goods estimated to be equivalent of US$300,000 or more and the first three&#13;
contracts for goods procured under international or national shopping, shall be subject to&#13;
prior review by IDA. Each contract for employment of consulting firms estimated to cost&#13;
more than US$lOO,OOOand more than US$50,000 in case of individual consultants, shall&#13;
be subject to prior review by IDA.   All other contracts will be subject to the post award&#13;
review.   Quality and Cost Based Selection (QCBS) would be the preferred method for&#13;
most of the consultancies. However, selection based on Consultants' Qualifications (CQ)&#13;
and Individual Consultants (IC) may be adopted for other consultancy services. Detailed&#13;
procurement arrangements are provided in Appendix III.&#13;
&#13;
C. Disbursement And Financial Management&#13;
&#13;
48      Since there is no Country Profile of Financial Accountability (CPFA) or Country&#13;
Financial   Accountability   Assessment (CFAA)      for Afghanistan, there is inadequate&#13;
knowledge     of  country   issues and related strengths and weaknesses.         Financial&#13;
management capacity in the country is not fully functional and appropriate mitigation&#13;
measures have been implemented through the engagement of the Financial Management&#13;
Agent.   The Financial Management Agent will be responsible for assisting the MOF to&#13;
maintain the accounts for all Government expenditures, including the proposed MOC&#13;
project, in addition to building capacity within TISA. Standard quarterly progress reports&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         13&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
will be prepared. The Project Management Specialist (PMS) in the MOC will support the&#13;
financial and implementation       arrangements of this project.     There may need to be&#13;
additional capacity in the Financial Management Agent (FMA)            to accommodate this&#13;
project due to the increasing number of projects.&#13;
&#13;
49       Funds Flow: Funds flow under the project will use the existing government&#13;
system as much as possible. As is the practice for government expenditure, all project&#13;
payments will    be routed through the Ministry      of Finance (MOF).         The Financial&#13;
Management Agent will support the MOF in executing and recording project payments.&#13;
&#13;
50       Treasury officials at the MOF will be the authorized persons to operate the USD&#13;
Special Account of the project at Da Afghanistan Bank; IDA funds will be deposited into&#13;
the Special Account.      When a project payment is required to be made, implementing&#13;
agencies (line ministries and other government departments) will           submit a standard&#13;
payment request to the MOF-Treasury.       Treasury officials, after verifying the documents&#13;
and checking the availability of funds in the Special Account and budget will, (a) for&#13;
payments in Afghanis issue a check in Afghanis for encashment at DAB, and (b) in case&#13;
of a payment in foreign currency, instruct DAB to execute the payment.&#13;
&#13;
51       All withdrawal applications to the IDA, including replenishment, reimbursement&#13;
and direct payment applications, will be prepared and submitted by the MOF.&#13;
&#13;
52       Audit Arrangements: The accounts of the Project will be audited by the Auditor&#13;
General (AG) with the support of the Audit Agent with terms of reference satisfactory to&#13;
the Association. The annual Project financial statement to the Association would include&#13;
a summary of funds received (showing funds received from all sources), and a summary&#13;
of expenditures shown under the main Project components/activities              and by main&#13;
categories of expenditures.&#13;
&#13;
53       Disbursement Method: Disbursements from the IDA Credit would be transaction-&#13;
based (replenishment, reimbursement, direct payment, and payments under Special&#13;
Commitments)      with   full documentation or against statements of expenditures as&#13;
appropriate.&#13;
&#13;
54       Use of statements of expenditures (SOEs): Disbursements will be made on the&#13;
basis of SOEs for: (a) consultants and training for contracts not exceeding US$lOO,OOO&#13;
for firms and US$50,000 for individuals; and (b) goods for contracts not exceeding&#13;
us$300,000.&#13;
&#13;
D.  Environment   And   Social Safeguard&#13;
&#13;
55       The reconstruction and investment interventions envisaged under the proposed&#13;
project are not expected to generate significant negative environmental effects.         No&#13;
activities will be supported that require involuntary land acquisition or the acquisition of&#13;
land.    Consequently, no Resettlement Action Plan will be required for the proposed&#13;
project.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         14&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
56.     Network and spectrum monitoring equipment will be housed in existing buildings&#13;
and will not involve building construction.      The government communications service&#13;
operator is expected to use VSAT and other wireless technologies to deploy services. As&#13;
a result of this choice of technology, there is no need to build accessroads, new buildings&#13;
or large power-supply installations.     Moreover, the installation of compact, modular&#13;
VSAT equipment will not adversely affect the aesthetics of rural areas. It should be&#13;
noted, however, that it is possible under an alternative configuration that in Kabul the&#13;
service provider may utilize      spurs off an existing fiber optic system to provide&#13;
connectivity to some ministries.    If that does occur, minimal ducting may be required.&#13;
The service contract will specify that such ducting will traverse only public rights of way&#13;
and involve no major construction work.&#13;
&#13;
57      Gender: The last twenty years of social upheaval has greatly affected the overall&#13;
gender situation in Afghanistan, resulting in very restrictive policies vis-a-vis women's&#13;
participation in public life, accessto education and other services as well as employment&#13;
opportunities.   During the Taliban regime, women and girls were effectively excluded&#13;
from any participation in public life. With the replacement of the Taliban regime, women&#13;
have regained the right to education, employment opportunities and services, but the&#13;
prevailing social norms are still very conservative and restrictive regarding women's&#13;
participation in the national development effort.     There are huge differences between&#13;
Kabul and the much smaller secondary cities, and the rural areas. In addition, there are&#13;
considerable regional differences with the south and southeastern areas of the country&#13;
being more restrictive and conservative than the western and northern areas. These&#13;
variations to some extent coincide with ethnic differences. To this should be added the&#13;
great difference in outlook of returning refugees (whether repatriating from the West or&#13;
from the neighboring countries) and those who remained in Afghanistan.&#13;
&#13;
58.     ICT is a major sector in which gender imbalances can be addressed, through&#13;
increased employment opportunities for women.            In addition, by allowing   for the&#13;
increased flow of information to and from Kabul and the provinces, as well as allowing&#13;
for the more efficient     operation of government in general, the project will      act to&#13;
strengthen the ability of the Authority to carry out its polices designed to decreasethe&#13;
inequality of opportunity between women and men.&#13;
&#13;
E. Monitoring     And Evaluation&#13;
&#13;
59      Monitoring    arrangements include plans for intensive supervision by IDA        to&#13;
ensurethat any implementation difficulties are dealt with promptly. At a minimum, a full&#13;
supervision mission is needed each four months, with specialists visiting Afghanistan&#13;
more frequently, if needed, during Project implementation.      A quarterly progress report&#13;
will be prepared and submitted to IDA, which consolidates all components including&#13;
progress towards meeting implementation and development objectives, as further detailed&#13;
in the Project's procurement plan and detailed monitoring indicators. Responsibility for&#13;
this reporting rests with the AACA, with each implementing agency agreeing to provide&#13;
requisite input. Appendix IV provides additional details on monitoring indicators for the&#13;
Project.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         15&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                  Appendix I&#13;
&#13;
                                PROJECT       DESCRIPTION&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Project Objectives&#13;
&#13;
1        The objective of the proposed Emergency Communications Development Project&#13;
is to support activities laid out in the Development Budget approved by the Cabinet&#13;
designed to improve delivery of communications services to the government and to the&#13;
people of Afghanistan. This will be achieved by: (i) carrying out urgent expansion of the&#13;
government communications          network to restore critical     communications    between&#13;
ministries and provinces; (ii) providing urgently needed policy advice and capacity&#13;
building to the MOC to promote sustainable communications sector performance and&#13;
increased private sector participation; and (iii) improving       the postal sector and the&#13;
delivery of postal services. The outcomes of the Project are expected to be improvements&#13;
in communications facilities and delivery, while laying the foundations for sector reforms&#13;
and institution    building   which   would     lead to sustainable development       of  the&#13;
communications sector. Monitoring indicators are given in Appendix IV.&#13;
&#13;
Project Components&#13;
&#13;
Component 1: Emergency Government Communications                 Network&#13;
&#13;
2        The component will pay for the turnkey procurement, installation, operational and&#13;
acceptance testing and maintenance of a communications network that will integrate the&#13;
existing World Bank and UNDP funded network equipment as well as improving and&#13;
extending coverage to all Ministries, the Central Bank and the Presidential Palace in&#13;
Kabul as well as Provincial Capitals. The component is envisaged to construct a network&#13;
for government communications         utilizing  tried and tested technologies in a robust&#13;
configuration that can be rapidly rolled out in the current Afghan environment.&#13;
&#13;
3.       The component will also provide funding for operating costs for both the existing&#13;
network and that to be built under the contract. The contract will run for the remaining&#13;
life of the project or until such time that both the MOC and the World Bank are satisfied&#13;
that capacity    exists within     the corporatized     Afghan   Tel  to   transfer operating&#13;
responsibility and ownership to Afghan Tel.         This project component will also pay for&#13;
sufficient training of Afghan Tel staff to provide them with the capacity to operate the&#13;
Government Communications Network.            From that point onwards, the communications&#13;
network operator will      be under standard regulatory oversight and act as par of a&#13;
commercial (government owned) corporation.           It is expected that, in the medium term&#13;
(three   years), this   company      will   be   privatized,  and   operate as a     standard&#13;
telecommunications services provider.&#13;
&#13;
4.       The emergency government communication             network will    be designed and&#13;
operated principally as a network for government communications.            After government&#13;
requirements for communications have been met at the provincial level, sparecapacity in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                           16&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
  the provincial network may be made available to operators of public telecommunications&#13;
  networks. It is noteworthy that it is currently estimated that this sparecapacity is likely to&#13;
  be limited and would not change the need to establish a normal national backbone system&#13;
  with sufficient national capacity. This would be on a non-discriminatory basis as part of&#13;
  an open and competitive regime in the international and long distance segments.&#13;
&#13;
  5       The MOC        of TISA      presently provides telecommunications             services to the&#13;
  following ministries and entities:&#13;
&#13;
                1. Ministry of Communications&#13;
                2. Ministry of Reconstruction&#13;
                3. Ministry of Finance&#13;
                4. The Central Bank&#13;
                5. The Office of the President&#13;
                6. The Ministry of Higher Education*&#13;
                7. Ministry of Foreign Affairs*&#13;
                8. The Afghanistan Assistance Coordination Authority&#13;
&#13;
  6.      In phase one of the Government Communications Network component, the MOC&#13;
B will expand the existing GCN to include an additional 12 ministries which are located in&#13;
  Kabul. These ministries will be connected by fiber or microwave radios or other suitable&#13;
  communication technology to a central location and connect to a Very Small Aperture&#13;
  Antenna which will        serve as the satellite gateway earth station of the network.                In&#13;
  addition to the expansion of the GCN to the 12 ministries, there will                        also be a&#13;
  requirement to expand the network to 14 priority provincial capitals and selected other&#13;
  sites.  In phase two of the project, the remaining ministries and provinces will be&#13;
  connected.&#13;
&#13;
  7.      The     component will        also cover training.         MOC      staff   lacked sufficient&#13;
  opportunities to develop the skills           necessary to operate and maintain the various&#13;
  equipments to be deployed in the GCN.               Therefore, a significant component of this&#13;
 project is the provision of formal training for a team of MOC staff in order that they can&#13;
  develop the ability to maintain the GCN independently and efficiently.&#13;
&#13;
  8       It will be required that the bidder selected to expand the network, and provide&#13;
  d&amp;M     services, also provide these training services.           Penalties will be built into the&#13;
  contract for failure to deliver training within the agreed timeframe without justifiable&#13;
 reasons.&#13;
&#13;
  9       A brief description of the proposed services to be provided under the project&#13;
  includes:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          l    Central hub in Kabul.         The central service centre in the MOC will require&#13;
               expansion so that it has capacity to meet the planned expansion, and further&#13;
               expansion that may occur in the future. It is proposed that the function of the&#13;
&#13;
  * NB: Ministries of Foreign Affairs and Higher Education - microwave link installed and ready for use.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                17&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                  main hub will be shifted from the AACA office where it is currently located to&#13;
                  the MOC building in Jan Khan Watt in Kabul, where a Multiplex receiver will&#13;
                  be installed. The MOC equipment will be installed in parallel with the AACA&#13;
                  system, and the central hub function will be transferred to it from AACA once&#13;
                  the equipment is installed. The AACA link will remain part of the network.&#13;
                  Minor work will be required to redirect the existing organisations to this new&#13;
                  location. This will be planned in line with the expansion to 12 new Ministries.&#13;
&#13;
           l      Ministries      in Kabul (priority I and 2). The service will offer all Ministries&#13;
                  the opportunity to link to the central network. Ministries will be able to link&#13;
                  to the existing satellite network.                        The project will provide Ministries with&#13;
                  hardware including additional computers and IT facilities so that the benefits&#13;
                  of the ICT services can be properly realised.                                     Of the total of 41 central&#13;
                  Government            organisations that receive Government                                  (operating budget)&#13;
                  funding, this proposal allows for the inclusion of around 34 (including those&#13;
                  already connected). This is based on the assumption that some Ministries&#13;
                  such as Defense and the Supreme Court will wish to install separate secure                                                 `!&#13;
                  systems.&#13;
&#13;
           l      Provinces.        The services to be provided to provinces, in particular provincial&#13;
                  capitals, include connection for the Governor's office, the Da Afghanistan&#13;
                  Bank, Mustoufiates, Customs, the local Police department, the MOC, and&#13;
                  other important Government departments.                                   Once connected, there will be&#13;
                  significant      capacity for further expansion of these services as needed.&#13;
                  Tier 1 cities, video conferencing capabilities'.A&#13;
                  Services to provinces will include email, Internet, voice connectivity and in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
              - "Tier       1". All Tier 1 provincial capitals (except Kunduz) already have 4.5 m&#13;
                  satellite dishes installed.              This project will support further rollout of services.&#13;
&#13;
              - "Tier       2".   The MOC is presently awaiting approval of the Government of&#13;
                  India for funding of satellite links and digital switching for Tier 2 cities. If&#13;
                  this approval occurs, then there will not be a requirement for satellite dishes&#13;
                  from the World Bank project. However, Tier 2 cities will require bandwidths&#13;
                  to be assigned as part of the current project, and it is also proposed that they&#13;
                  receive approximately the same level of ICT equipment as the Tier 1 cities&#13;
                  from the current project.&#13;
&#13;
              - All others (priority 2). Remaining connectivity points in provincial capitals&#13;
                  or other provincial              areas may also need, on a selective basis,                                   satellite&#13;
                  connection        (VSAT)          and bandwidth                   assignment.            The      equipment and&#13;
                  installation       needs         may       vary         depending          on       the     activities     of       other&#13;
                  telecommunications projects mentioned previously.                                    This project will need to&#13;
                  addressthese needs flexibly, and integrate this potential expansion with other&#13;
                  work occurring in the sector and potentially cover other sites.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
' The project will provide the capability for "Tier 1" cities to install relatively low-cost point-to-point videoconferencing facilities.&#13;
Individual provinces can install more expensive systemsif they require them.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                              18&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Priority One locations are the following:&#13;
&#13;
     Ministries&#13;
      1.   Ministry of Commerce                                           2.  Ministry of Interior&#13;
      3.   Ministry of Education                                          4.  Ministry of Mining and Industry&#13;
&#13;
      5.   Ministry of Agriculture                                        6.  Ministry of Information  and Culture&#13;
      7.   Central Statistics Office                                      8.  Ministry of Civil Aviation&#13;
      9.   Ministry of Public Health                                      10. Ministry of Public Works&#13;
      11. Ministry of Transport                                           12. Ministry of Energy and Power&#13;
&#13;
     Kabul hub expansion&#13;
      13. Kabul - Ministry of Communications&#13;
      "Tier 1" capitals&#13;
      14. Ball&amp; province (Mazar-e-Sharif)                                 15. Herat province (Herat)&#13;
      16. Kandahar province (Kandahar)                                    17. Kunduz province (Kunduz)&#13;
      18. Nangarhar province (Jalalabad)2&#13;
      "Tier 2" capitals&#13;
      19. Badakshan province (Faiz Abad)                                  20. Baghlan province (Baghlan)&#13;
     21. Bamiyan province (Bamiyan)                                       22. Farah province (Farah)&#13;
     23. Faryab province (Faryab)                                         24. Ghazni province (Ghazni)&#13;
     25. HiMOCand province (Lashkar Gar)                                  26. Jowzjan province (Shebergan)&#13;
     27. Paktia (Gardez)                                                  28. Parwan province (Charikar)&#13;
     29. Takhar province (Taloqan)&#13;
Priority Two locations are the following:&#13;
     Provinces&#13;
     30. Badgis province (Qaleh-y-Now)                                        Ghoor province (Chaghcharan)&#13;
      32. Kapisa province (Mahmud-e-Raqi)                                     Khost province (Khost)&#13;
     34. Konarah province (Asad Abad)                                         Laghman province (Mehtar Lam)&#13;
     36. Logar province (Baraki)                                              Nimrooz province (Zarang)&#13;
     38. Noorstan province (Nuristan)                                         Oruzgan province (Tarin Kowt)&#13;
     40. Paktika province (Sharan)                                            Samangan province (Aibak)&#13;
     42. Sar-i-PO1province (And Khoi)                                         Wardak province (Maidan Wardak)&#13;
     44. Zabul province (Qalat)&#13;
     Ministries&#13;
     45. Civil Service Commission                                             Attorney General&#13;
     47. Ministry of Food and Light Industry                                  Ministry of Labour and Social Affairs&#13;
     49. Ministry of Irrigation, Water &amp; Env't                                Ministry of Information  and Culture&#13;
     51. Ministry of Planning                                                 Ministry of Martyrs and Disabled&#13;
     53. Ministry of Religious Instruction &amp; Hajj                             Ministry of Borders&#13;
     55. Ministry of Women's' Affairs                                         Ministry of Rural Rehabilitation &amp; Devt&#13;
     57. National Olympics Committee                                          Narcotics Commission&#13;
     59. Supreme Court&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
2It is planned that Jalalabad will be linked to Kalhman and Kunur via microwave.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                           19&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Component 2: MOC Institutional          Capacity Building&#13;
&#13;
10       The following activities to strengthen the MOC's policy and project capacity will&#13;
be`supported:&#13;
    t    Support for management and organizational restructuring, including consultant&#13;
         studies and support for implementation        of a new organizational      structure&#13;
        reflecting the MOC's role as policy maker. Examination of real staffing needs of&#13;
        MOC, and skills matching.&#13;
&#13;
    l    Consultant studies covering a potential universal access strategy, design of a&#13;
        program, and institutional      development for implementation.     This consulting&#13;
        program will evaluate the success of projects to date and discuss lessons learned&#13;
        for a wider accessstrategy.&#13;
        Consultant studies on an `as needed' basis, covering areas such as convergence,&#13;
        market structure and competition.&#13;
&#13;
    l   Equipment required within the Ministry in Kabul.        Support will be provided to&#13;
        procure hardware and software, including computers and office equipment, so that&#13;
        the MOC in Kabul can better perform its functions.&#13;
&#13;
    l   Training.   This will     include inter alia the following:  technical cooperation&#13;
        arrangements with relevant policy agencies in other countries, information sharing&#13;
        and formal and informal contacts, and advice; seminars and courses offered by&#13;
        private firms, universities and associations; study tours and training for senior&#13;
        policy officials; and the organization of seminars/workshops in Afghanistan.&#13;
&#13;
    l   Support for project management capacity. Support will be provided to MOC for&#13;
        consultancy services to strengthen MOC's capacity to manage and implement the&#13;
        project.   This will    include procuring support from a Project Implementation&#13;
        Specialist to assist in the management of various implementation arrangements&#13;
        during the life of the project.&#13;
&#13;
    l   Establish and implement an improved financial management and MIS for the&#13;
        MOC.     There is a clear need for financial management and MIS to improve&#13;
        information      available  for  management, and for     provision   of transparent&#13;
        information     to MOF and Government.        This will allow greater control and&#13;
        transparency for      all  payments and improved      workflow   management and&#13;
        information reporting for staff.&#13;
&#13;
11      The following      activities will support the separation of MOC's       policy  and&#13;
operational and ownership functions and help establish Afghan Tel as an efficient State-&#13;
owned corporation. The creation of a State-owned operating company will leave MOC&#13;
free to focus on policy.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    l   Creation of corporate entity and strategy for implementation        of allocation of&#13;
        assets,liabilities and staff.&#13;
&#13;
   l    Asset/Liability    Allocation:  Afghan  Tel's  potential assets and liabilities   are&#13;
        currently reflected as government property. In order for Afghan Tel to act as an&#13;
        independent company, it will need title to its assets and to develop depreciation&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                          20&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
       and capital expenditure programs to support them. In addition to developing an&#13;
       inventory and valuation of fixed assets, this task will also include negotiation of&#13;
       land and building ownership/use between Afghan Tel and TISA.            Appropriate&#13;
       levels of debt to fund the assetsto be transferred may also need to be determined.&#13;
&#13;
   l   Creation of Opening Financial Statements: A financial audit will both identify&#13;
       Afghan Tel's opening position and create the initial financial statements that the&#13;
       corporatized Afghan Tel will be required to maintain.      The financial audit will&#13;
       also provide valuable information      about financial information   systems to be&#13;
       created for Afghan Tel.&#13;
&#13;
   l   Examining Options for Labor Force. Afghan Tel will have limited staff needs at&#13;
       its outset, given a small network.       As part of the restructuring process, an&#13;
       investigation should be made into the proposed new organizational plan and the&#13;
       real staffing needs of the new corporation along with a restructuring plan for&#13;
       staffing.&#13;
&#13;
   l   Cost-Based Tariff Study: Afghan Tel has little if any ability to charge for services&#13;
       at present. From the beginning, the company should implement a cost-basedtariff&#13;
       structure, building on a benchmarking tariff study. This study would provide: (a)&#13;
       a tariff proposal by comparing Afghan Tel to other operators in comparable&#13;
       markets that run their businessesefficiently.  This will also provide the regulatory&#13;
       unit with the required analysis to support implementation of cost-basedpricing for&#13;
       unbundled network elements.&#13;
&#13;
   l   Development of Performance Criteria for Afghan Tel to be incorporated in its&#13;
       license in order to ensure that restructuring to create Afghan Tel delivers strong&#13;
       performance.&#13;
&#13;
   l   Other potential technical advisory support for Afghan Tel.&#13;
&#13;
12     The following     activities will support the separation of MOC's policy        and&#13;
regulatory functions, and allow for the development of a strong, independent regulator:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   l   Consultant Assistance for implementation of the transition from MOC unit to&#13;
       independent, stand-alone regulator.&#13;
&#13;
   l   Consultant Assistance in the areas of technical         standardization processes,&#13;
       spectrum management, pricing and monitoring quality of service standards, and&#13;
       other `as needed' support including potential development of a pro-competitive&#13;
       license for Afghan Tel and other service providers.&#13;
&#13;
   l   Establishment of one mobile and one fixed spectrum/frequency monitoring kit,&#13;
       and associated training.    Currently there are many users of radio frequency and&#13;
       there is interference among different networks. As competition is introduced for&#13;
       mobile   radio services (such as GSM and Code Division             Multiple Access&#13;
       (CDMA),     WLL),   it is essential to manage spectrum usage and interference.&#13;
       Further, for national security reasons,the Government needsto be able to monitor&#13;
       usage of radio communications spectrum.&#13;
&#13;
   l   Professional development and training        including, inter alia the following:&#13;
       technical cooperation arrangements with        relevant policy  agencies in other&#13;
       countries, information    sharing and formal and informal     contacts, and advice;&#13;
       seminars and courses offered by private firms, universities and associations; study&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        21&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
         tours and training      for senior regulatory officials;     and the organization of&#13;
         seminars/workshops in Afghanistan.&#13;
&#13;
     l   Office equipment and vehicles including hardware and software to facilitate&#13;
         regulatory functioning.&#13;
&#13;
 Component 3: Postal Sector Support&#13;
&#13;
 13      The following     activities  will support the separation of MOC's policy         and&#13;
 operational functions in the postal sector and help establish the post office as an efficient&#13;
 State-owned corporation:&#13;
&#13;
         0   Consulting support for the MOC to create a sector policy and development&#13;
             strategy along with the necessaryregulatory framework and capacity to&#13;
             optimize the performance of the Afghan postal network and other support&#13;
             including potential support for corporatization.&#13;
&#13;
         0   Examining Options for Labor Force. The post office will have limited staff&#13;
             needsat its outset, given a small network. As part of the restructuring&#13;
             process, an investigation should be made into the proposed new&#13;
             organizational plan and the real staffing needs of the new corporation.&#13;
&#13;
         0   Development of a Business Plan. The post office will require a business plan&#13;
             to guide its initial operations and increase its ability to meet existing and&#13;
             potential demand in the postal market. This would include evaluation of the&#13;
             potential for expanding current operations to include new offering such as e-&#13;
             services and financial services.&#13;
&#13;
         0   Rehabilitation of facilities and modernization of basic postal equipment. This&#13;
             includes the replacement, refurbishment and rehabilitation of equipment&#13;
             including vehicles, scales, scooters, information systems, cancellers,&#13;
             culling/facing machines, sorting systems, private boxes, collection boxes,&#13;
             inventory and operations and maintenance.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                         Project   Costs by Expenditure Category     (%)&#13;
&#13;
   Expenditure    Category           Amount US$ million               Financing Percentage&#13;
 Goods                                        14.58                            100&#13;
1Consultant Services             I            4.38               I             100            I&#13;
 Training                                     0.31                             100&#13;
 Unallocated                                  2.73&#13;
&#13;
 Total Project Costs                          22.00&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                           22&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                            Appendix II&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                        PROCUREMENT          ARRANGEMENTS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
A. Institutional  Capacity&#13;
&#13;
 1      The project will be implemented over a period of three years. Project completion&#13;
date is March 20, 2007, and the Credit closing date is September 30, 2007.           The&#13;
executing agency for the project will be the Ministry of Communications, with assistance&#13;
to be provided on matters involving      financial management and procurement by the&#13;
Afghanistan Assistance Coordination Agency (AACA)         Procurement Consultant.    The&#13;
MOC will be responsible for procurement of goods and services estimated to cost up to&#13;
US$25,000 per contract, following the provisions of the Credit Agreement. Beyond this&#13;
limit, procurement will be carried out by the AACA procurement unit with support from&#13;
the Procurement Consultant, with technical inputs from the MOC.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
2       In view of the post-conflict environment in the country, the procurement risk is&#13;
considered high, despite the use of procurement expertise of the specialized firm&#13;
(Procurement Consultant) in the AACA.       Project supervision will include procurement&#13;
expertise in most missions over the life of the IDA credit. Threshold limits described&#13;
below have been set in consideration of these risks.    The following  arrangements will&#13;
cover the relationship between AACA and its procurement Consultant and the MOC:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
l   Where the estimated value of the Goods or Services is less than US$25,000:&#13;
&#13;
        The MOC prepares the designs, drawings, specifications, or Terms of Reference,&#13;
        which are a pre-requisite for preparation of Bid Documents or Request for&#13;
        Proposals/Quotations.&#13;
        The MOC prepares the Bid Documents, issues them, receives bids/quotations,&#13;
        evaluates them, and signs the respective contracts. This activity should be fully&#13;
        consistent with procurement arrangements described in the Credit Agreement.&#13;
        The MOC      may, if it so desires, avail itself of advisory services from the&#13;
        Procurement Consultant (PC).&#13;
        The MOC will be responsible for initial and subsequent payments under the&#13;
        respective procurements.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
l   Where the estimated value of Goods or Services is more than US$25,000:&#13;
&#13;
    a) The MOC prepares the designs, drawings, specifications or Terms of Reference&#13;
        which are a pre-requisite for preparation of Bid Documents or Request for&#13;
        Proposals and delivers these to the PC.&#13;
    b) In consultation with the MOC, the PC prepares the Bid Documents, issues them,&#13;
        receives bids/quotations, evaluates them, and delivers them to the MOC who&#13;
        signs the respective contracts.     The MOC     must participate in evaluations,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        23&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
        providing technical expertise as needed. This activity should be fully consistent&#13;
        with procurement arrangements described in the Credit Agreement.&#13;
    c) The MOC is responsible for the initial and all further payments. For the initial&#13;
        payment the PC will provide assistance,which may also be required exceptionally&#13;
        for further payments.&#13;
&#13;
B. Procurement Methods&#13;
&#13;
3       The procurement arrangements and the estimated costs for the project components&#13;
to be funded by IDA are shown in Table A. Procurement under the IDA credit would be&#13;
carried out in accordance with the "Guidelines for Procurement under IBRD Loans and&#13;
Credits"    (January 1995, revised     subsequently, last revision  January 1999) and&#13;
"Guidelines for Selection and Employment of Consultants by World Bank Borrowers"&#13;
(January 1997, revised subsequently, last revision May 2002). For the procurement of&#13;
goods, IDA shall suggest appropriate bidding documents/contract formats be used.&#13;
&#13;
4       A General Procurement Notice        for this Project was published in the UN&#13;
Development Business (UNDB) online on July 29, 2003, and paper version edition No.&#13;
612 dated August 16,2003.&#13;
&#13;
BI: Procurement of Goods (US$l6.85 million)&#13;
&#13;
5       The procurement of goods consists of the turnkey contract for the provision,&#13;
maintenance and training related to the government communications network; office&#13;
equipment for MOC and Regulatory Unit Offices; spectrum monitoring equipment and&#13;
postal equipment.     International Competitive Bidding (ICB) and National/International&#13;
Shopping (IS/NS) will be used.&#13;
&#13;
ICB (US$16.0 million):     This will be used for the government communications network  **&#13;
and spectrum monitoring equipment.&#13;
&#13;
International/National    Shopping (US$O.SS million):    This  will be used for goods&#13;
estimated to cost less than or equal to US$70,000 equivalent per contract, up to an&#13;
aggregate amount not to exceed the equivalent of US$850,000.            Under shopping&#13;
procedures, the Procurement Consultant will use simplified documents and procedures&#13;
for soliciting, receiving and evaluating competitive quotations from usually at least three&#13;
suppliers (in International Shopping from two different countries). The shopping method&#13;
to be used will be based on IDA's memorandum of June 8,2000, Guidance Procurement&#13;
Notes on handling procurement under Shopping Method.&#13;
&#13;
B2: Consulting Services and Training (US$5. I5 million).&#13;
&#13;
6       Consultancy services will be contracted following procedures in accordance with&#13;
the Bank's Procurement Guidelines mentioned above. Consultant services estimated to&#13;
cost more than US$200,000 per contract must be advertised in the national newspapers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        24&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
 and in "Development Business" before establishing the shortlist. IDA's clearance of the&#13;
 terms of reference will be mandatory irrespective of the value of the assignment.&#13;
&#13;
 Quality and cost-based selection @CBS) (US$3.9 million):                                                        It is envisaged that most of&#13;
 the consultant services will be procured through QCBS.&#13;
&#13;
 Consultant qualifications                            (CQ) and Individual                  Consultants (IC) (US$. 1.25 million):&#13;
 Training for the MOC, regulatory and postal staff, the project management specialist, and&#13;
 other consulting estimated at US$l.25M                                          will follow the CQ or IC methods. A Project&#13;
 Management Specialist will be hired as soon as possible using Emergency Infrastructure&#13;
 Reconstruction Project funds in the period until project effectiveness for this project, after&#13;
 which funds will be provided under this project. The hiring of all individual consultants&#13;
 will follow the selection of IC process in accordance with the provisions of paragraphs&#13;
 5.1 through 5.3 of the Consultant Guidelines.&#13;
&#13;
 C. Procurement Planning&#13;
&#13;
 7              The AACA                   Procurement Consultant has furnished to IDA                                       for its review a&#13;
procurement plan and will update this plan every quarter after project effectiveness. This&#13;
 procurement plan will allow monitoring of compliance with prior review requirements set&#13;
I                                                                                                            A                      . A&#13;
 out below combined with active proi ecysupervision.&#13;
                                                                *        J       A.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                     Procurement Plan&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 GOVERNMENT COMMUNICATIONS              NETWORK&#13;
 1.l Government Communications Network (GCN) and Operation a               gl   ICB           14,000,000     8/25/2003                     12/27/2004&#13;
&#13;
 Sub-Total                                                                                    14,000,000&#13;
&#13;
 IMPROVE TELECOMMUNICATION            SECTOR PERFORMANCE&#13;
 2.1 Restructuring (Moe, MIS, AfganTel Corporatization)                         QCBS          2,300,OOO      9/l 92003      l/23/2004      5/I 912006&#13;
 2.2 Regulatory Toolkit (Universal Access, Cost-Based Tariff Study,             QCBS           1,300,000   1O/20/2003       2/20/2004      4/22/2005&#13;
 2.3 Office Equipment (MoC, Regulatory)                                         NS/IS            590,000     IO/l/2003      12/g/2003      12/30/2003&#13;
 2.4 Training (MoC, Regulatory, Postal)                                                          350,000     1I /3/2003     12/5/2003      3/24/2006&#13;
 2.5 Project Management Specialist                                              Individual       600,000     8/25/2003      1o/9/2003      1O/5/2006&#13;
 2.6 Spectrum Monitoring Equipment and Facilities                               ICB           2,000,000      8/25/2003       l/6/2004      1O/l 2/2004&#13;
 2.7 Other Consultancy Services                                                 QCBS/CQ/IC       300,000     4/29/2004       9/l 12004     7/20/2005&#13;
&#13;
 Sub-Total&#13;
&#13;
 IMPROVE POSTAL SECTOR PERFORMANCE&#13;
 3.1 Restructuring (Postal Policy, Regulation &amp; Corporatization Strat      c5   QCBS            300,000       51312004      9/l 612004      3/l/2005&#13;
 3.2 Postal Equipment                                                      94   NSAS            260,000    1l/l 3/2003       1/g/2004      12/23/2005&#13;
&#13;
 Sub-Total                                                                                      560,000&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Total&#13;
                                                                                                        I&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                             25&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
D. Prior and Post Review.&#13;
&#13;
8      All goods contracts in excess of US$300,000 each, and the first three contracts for&#13;
goods, procured under international or national shopping, and consulting services&#13;
contracts above US$lOO,OOOfor firms and above US$50,000 for individual consultants,&#13;
will be subject to prior review by IDA.     All other contracts would be subject to post-&#13;
review on a random basis during supervision missions and audits.&#13;
&#13;
E. Procurement Information&#13;
&#13;
9      MOC     with the assistance of AACA        Procurement Consultant will       prepare&#13;
procurement information which will be collected and recorded as follows:&#13;
&#13;
    (a)    prompt   reporting   of   contract   award  information     for  the   respective&#13;
           components; and&#13;
    (b)    comprehensive quarterly reports prepared by AACA indicating:&#13;
       0   revised cost estimates for individual contracts and total cost;&#13;
&#13;
        l  revised timings   of procurement actions including         advertising, bidding,&#13;
           contract award and completion time for individual contracts; and&#13;
       0   compliance report by AACA within three months of the Credit signing date.&#13;
&#13;
F. Proposed Procurement Arrangements          and Frequency of Supervision&#13;
&#13;
10     The project elements, their estimated costs and proposed methods of procurement&#13;
are summarized in Table A. Thresholds are given in Table B.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        26&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                 Table A: Project Costs by Procurement Arrangements&#13;
&#13;
                                       (US$ million equivalent)&#13;
&#13;
     Expenditure                                Procurement Method (1)                                         Total&#13;
      Category                     ICB                 NCB            Others (2)             NBF                 cost&#13;
           Goods                   16.00                                   0.85                                 16.85&#13;
                                  (16.00)                                (0.85)                               (16.85)&#13;
           Services                                                        4.80                                  4.80&#13;
                                                                         (4.80)                                (4.80)&#13;
           Training                                                        0.35                                  0.35&#13;
                                                                         (0.35)                               (0.35)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            Total                  16.00                                   6.00                                22.00&#13;
                                  (16.00)                                (6.00)                               (22.00)&#13;
&#13;
           (1) Figures in parenthesis are the amounts to be financed by IDA.        All costs include contingencies&#13;
           (2) Includes  goods to be procured       through  international/national    shopping    (three quotations) and&#13;
               services (consulting services, training,  technical assistance, etc .)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          Table B: Thresholds for Procurement Methods and Prior Review&#13;
&#13;
Expenditure               Contract Value                   Procurement                       Contracts Subject to&#13;
Category                  Threshold                        Method                            Prior Review&#13;
1. Goods                  Above US$300,000                 ICB/Shopping                      US$l6 million&#13;
                          and first three&#13;
                          contracts of goods,&#13;
                          procured following&#13;
                          international /&#13;
                          national shopping&#13;
2. Services                                                                                  US$4.8 million&#13;
including Training:&#13;
a) Firms                  Above US$lOO,OOO Bank guidelines as&#13;
b) Individuals            Above US$50,000                  per para B above&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Overall Procurement Risk Assessment: High&#13;
&#13;
11      Frequency of procurement supervision missions proposed: Once every 6 months&#13;
(includes special procurement supervision for post-review/audits).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 27&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                          Appendix III&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          FINANCIAL      MANAGEMENT,         DISBURSEMENT         AND AUDIT&#13;
                                   ARRANGEMENTS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Country Issues&#13;
&#13;
1.      Since there is no Country Profile of Financial Accountability (CPFA) or Country&#13;
Financial Accountability   Assessment (CFAA)      for Afghanistan, there is inadequate&#13;
knowledge    of  country  issues and related strengths and weaknesses.          Financial&#13;
management capacity in the country is not fully functional and appropriate mitigation&#13;
measures have been suggested through the engagement of the Financial Management&#13;
                                       V        vu                                U&#13;
Agent.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Strengths and Weaknesses&#13;
&#13;
2      Strength: The Financial Management Agent, along with the TISA's commitment&#13;
to transparent and accountable financial management, are the primary strengths of the&#13;
Project financial management. The Project Management Specialist (PMS) will support&#13;
the MOC in financial and implementation arrangements of this project.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Staffing and Training&#13;
&#13;
3       The Financial Management Agent will support the MOF and the MOC to perform&#13;
the necessary financial management functions.       One of the critical functions of the&#13;
Financial Management Agent will be to provide hands-on support to MOC staff to&#13;
enhance their financial management capacity.        The PMS will support the MOC in&#13;
financial and implementation arrangements of this project.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Accounting Policies and Procedures&#13;
&#13;
4      The project will    follow   standard TISA   financial  management policies and&#13;
procedures, including using the TISA Chart of Accounts to record Project expenditures.&#13;
The use of these procedures will allow for adequate recording and reporting of Project&#13;
expenditures.&#13;
&#13;
5      Accounts    will  be consolidated centrally    in  the MOF    (by the Financial&#13;
Management Agent) for all implementing entities and consolidated Project financial&#13;
statements will be prepared for all sourcesand uses of Project funds.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        28&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
 Audit Arrangements&#13;
&#13;
 6.        The accounts of the project will be audited by the Auditor General with the&#13;
 support of the Audit Agent with terms of reference satisfactory to the Association.    The&#13;
 annual Project financial statements to the Association would include a summary of funds&#13;
 received (showing funds received from all sources), and a summary of expenditures&#13;
 shown under the main project components/activities          and by main     categories of&#13;
 expenditures. The format for the annual Project financial statements will be similar to the&#13;
 Financial Monitoring    Reports (FMRs).    The audit of the project accounts would also&#13;
 include an assessment of: (a) the adequacy of the accounting and internal control&#13;
 systems; (b) the ability to maintain adequate documentation for transactions; and (c) the&#13;
 eligibility  of incurred expenditures for Association financing.     The annual Project&#13;
 financial statements audited by the Auditor General would be submitted within 6 months&#13;
 of the close of TISA's fiscal year. The audit reports will be monitored in the Audit&#13;
 Reports Compliance System (ARCS):&#13;
&#13;
 Responsible Agency              Audit                         Auditors&#13;
 MOF                             SOE, Project Accounts and     Auditors General&#13;
                                 Special Account&#13;
&#13;
 The Auditor General will audit the accounts of all the implementing entities. However, a&#13;
 consolidated audit report (with consolidated financial statements) will be issued for the&#13;
 project.&#13;
&#13;
 Reporting and Monitoring&#13;
&#13;
 7.        Quarterly Financial Monitoring Reports will be produced showing: (i) sourcesand&#13;
 uses of funds by disbursement category and project component; (ii) physical progress;&#13;
 and (iii) status of procurement activities.  These will be submitted to the Association&#13;
 within 45 days of the end of the quarter.&#13;
&#13;
 Disbursement Arrangements&#13;
&#13;
                               Allocation of Credit Proceeds&#13;
&#13;
    Expenditure    Category         Amount US$ million           Financing Percentage&#13;
 Goods                                      14.58                          100&#13;
1Consultant Services           I            4.69              I            100              I&#13;
 Training                                   0.31                           100&#13;
 Unallocated                                2.73&#13;
&#13;
 Total Project Costs                        22.00&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         29&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
8       Financing Percentage.     Since collection of tax revenue has just begun and is&#13;
sporadic, disbursement percentages have been set at 100/o with the understanding,&#13;
however, that MOF will submit withdrawal applications on a net-of-tax basis.&#13;
&#13;
9       Disbursement Method: Disbursements from the IDA credit would be transaction-&#13;
based (replenishment, reimbursement, direct payment and payments under Special&#13;
Commitments)     with  full  documentation or against statements of expenditures as&#13;
appropriate.&#13;
&#13;
10      Use of statements of expenditures (SOEs): Disbursements will be made on the&#13;
basis of SOEs for: (a) consultants and training for contracts not exceeding US$lOO,OOO&#13;
for firms and US$SO,OOOfor individuals;       and (b) goods for contracts not exceeding&#13;
us$300,000.&#13;
&#13;
11      Special Account:    A Special Account would be opened and maintained in a bank&#13;
acceptable to the Association; and would be operated by MOF in accordance with the&#13;
Association's operational policies.    The Authorized Allocation of the Special Account&#13;
would be US$l.3     million  which represents the estimated amount of expenditures to&#13;
course through the Special Account in a 3-month period. Given the short disbursement&#13;
period and the immediate need for special account funds, the full            amount of the&#13;
Authorized   Allocation    of the Special Account      will  be available to MOF      upon&#13;
effectiveness.&#13;
&#13;
12      Minimum application size. Applications for replenishment to the Special Account&#13;
will be submitted (a) monthly, or (b) when the Special Account balance is reduced by 40&#13;
percent, whichever    comes first.     The minimum       application   size for withdrawal&#13;
applications  for  reimbursement,    direct payment,     or for   applications  for Special&#13;
Commitments is 20 percent of the Authorized Allocation of the Special Account.       In the&#13;
event that banking facilities are not fully functional at Grant effectiveness, IDA may, on&#13;
an exceptional basis, waive minimum          application   size requirements in order to&#13;
accommodate urgent needs.&#13;
&#13;
13.     Authority to withdraw Grant funds: MOF will retain the right to sign and submit&#13;
withdrawal applications to the Association.&#13;
&#13;
Supervision Plan&#13;
&#13;
14.     From a financial     management perspective, the Project will        need intensive&#13;
supervision.    The focus during the supervision will         be on the internal control&#13;
arrangements for the Project and functioning       of accounting, financial reporting and&#13;
auditing.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         30&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                  Disbursement timetable  (World Bank fiscal year)&#13;
&#13;
                                Amount        Total for period     Cumulative&#13;
                               US$ million          (4OO          disbursements&#13;
                                                                       (0OO&#13;
      FY04                         1.9                  9                  9&#13;
&#13;
      FY05                         8.2                 37                46&#13;
&#13;
      FY06                         7.0                 32                78&#13;
&#13;
      FY07                         4.9                 22               100&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Overall Financial Risk Assessment: High&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     31&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                Appendix IV&#13;
                                       MONITORING&#13;
&#13;
Component                        Monitoring      Indicators      Goals&#13;
Government                       Connectivity of ministries      Improve government&#13;
Communications Network           and provinces as laid out in    communications, reduce&#13;
                                 the project description.        implementation time for&#13;
                                 Usage levels of                 decisions taken.&#13;
                                 communications network&#13;
                                 Revenues from users&#13;
                                 meeting running costs.&#13;
Communications Ministry          Coporatization of Afghan        Increased investment in&#13;
Institutional Development        Tel                             telecommunications sector.&#13;
                                 Creation of independent         Increased rollout of&#13;
                                 regulatory body.                telecommunications&#13;
                                 MOC taking on role as           services.&#13;
                                policy-making body.              Fiscal returns to&#13;
                                                                 government.&#13;
Postal Sector Support            Installation of equipment.      Greater flow of mail.&#13;
                                 Improved management of          Increased financial&#13;
                                post office.                     sustainability of post office.&#13;
                                 Establish regulatory            Increased accessto postal&#13;
                                 framework.                      services&#13;
&#13;
                                   Performance Indicators&#13;
&#13;
Component         Monitoring     Indicators                  2003   2004      -2005&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Government        -  Number    of Ministries/Government                                     30&#13;
Communications       Departments     connected.&#13;
Network&#13;
                  -  Number    of Provinces connected                            32         32&#13;
&#13;
                  -  Total of telephone    lines under                          6550      6550&#13;
                     Government     network&#13;
&#13;
Communications    -  Establish of Afghan     Tel. As SOE&#13;
Ministry&#13;
Institutional     -  Creation  of an independent&#13;
Development          regulatory   body.&#13;
&#13;
                  -  Number    of fixed and mobile phone&#13;
                     providers.&#13;
&#13;
                  -  Number    if ISPs.&#13;
&#13;
Postal Sector     Announcement     of postal sector policy.&#13;
sumort&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                           32&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="2513113">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2003/09/2513113/afghanistan-emergency-communications-development-project
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2003/09/2513113/afghanistan-emergency-communications-development-project</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2003/09/2513113/afghanistan-emergency-communications-development-project</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/09/17/000012009_20030917101312/Rendered/INDEX/T7602.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/09/17/000012009_20030917101312/Rendered/PDF/T7602.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2003-09-05T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2003-09-17T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Gray cover</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309938</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Afghanistan - Emergency Communications
            Development Project
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The objective of the Emergency
            Communications Development Project is to support activities
            designed to improve delivery of communications services to
            the government, and to the people of Afghanistan. This will
            be achieved by: 1) carrying out urgent expansion of the
            government communications network, to restore critical
            communications between ministries, and provinces; 2)
            providing urgently needed policy advice, and capacity
            building to the Ministry of Communications (MOC) to promote
            sustainable communications sector performance, and increased
            private sector participation; and, 3) improving the postal
            sector, and the delivery of postal services. The outcomes of
            the Project are expected to be improvements in
            communications facilities, and delivery, while laying the
            foundations for sector reforms, and institution building,
            which would lead to sustainable development of the
            communications sector. While benefits include improved
            government communications capacity, sector development, and
            reform, leading to greater communications access, and
            increased private investment, there are however risks, such
            as the technical and financial sustainability of government
            network (mitigated through design), but as well, general
            security, and institutional weaknesses.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Afghanistan - Emergency Communications
            Development Project
        </docna>
        <display_title>Afghanistan - Emergency
            Communications Development Project</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/2003/09/2513113/afghanistan-emergency-communications-development-project</listing_relative_url>
        <projn>AF-Emergency Communications Development
            Project -- P083720</projn>
        <docty>Technical Annex</docty>
        <subtopic>Knowledge Economy,ICT Policy and Strategies,Broadcast and Media,Education for the Knowledge Economy,National Governance</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Education</teratopic>
        <count>Afghanistan</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Asia!$!80451</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>South Asia!$!80470</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000012009_20030917101312</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>South Asia,South Asia</admreg>
        <subsc>General information and communications sector,Telecommunications,Postal services,Information technology</subsc>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Education</historic_topic>
        <prdln>IBRD/IDA</prdln>
        <sectr>Information and communications</sectr>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Emergency projects; Transitional assistance;
            Communications infrastructure; Communications policy;
            Government ownership; Local government; Private sector
            participation; Interagency coordination; Services delivery;
            Policy formation; Capacity building; Institution building;
            Advisory services; Performance indicators; Postal services;
            Facilities refurbishment; Reform policy; Accessible
            services; Technical assistance; Financial management;
            Project design; Risks; Security measures; Capacity constraints;
            Accountability,administrative
            capacity,Authority,broadcasting,cities,Communication
            Technologies,communication technology,communications
            infrastructure,Communications Sector,communications
            systems,communications technologies,competitive
            bidding,competitive environment,components,consulting
            services,corporatization,Exchange rate,expenditure,Financial
            Management,financial resources,financial
            services,FISCAL,foreign investors,government
            departments,Government expenditures,government
            information,government services,human
            resource,ICT,Information Systems,institution
            building,Institutional Arrangements,Institutional
            Capacity,international broadcasting,Internet
            capacity,Internet policy,Intranet,joint
            ventures,Learning,legal
            institutions,liability,licensing,long distance,Management
            Information Systems,Ministries of Foreign Affairs,Ministry
            of Finance,MIS,national communications,Nations,parcels,post
            offices,postal administration,postal reform,postal
            sector,Postal Sector Reform,Postal services,Postal
            Union,private sector investment,private sector
            involvement,private sector participation,public
            administration,public administration reform,public
            service,recording,Regulatory Authority,regulatory
            body,regulatory framework,regulatory frameworks,regulatory
            oversight,regulatory reform,rehabilitation,service
            delivery,social capital,State institutions,technical
            assistance,technicians,telecommunication,telecommunication
            services,Telecommunications,Telecommunications
            Development,telecommunications
            infrastructure,telecommunications law,telecommunications
            networks,telecommunications operations,telecommunications
            services,teledensity,telephone
            lines,telephones,telephony,transparency,universal
            access,Universal Postal Union,universal service,UPU
        </keywd>
        <owner>Information &amp; Communication Tech (TWICT)</owner>
        <lndinstr>
            Emergency Recovery Loan
        </lndinstr>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>South Asia</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>T7602</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT for Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies (ICT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Capacities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Staffing Needs Assessments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Denationalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deregulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Destatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Divestiture of Ownership</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure and Networks (National; State; Local)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunication and Network Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunications</ml:concept><ml:concept>Higher Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Tertiary Education  Enhancing Access, Equity and Quality</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Servers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Switches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Administrative and Civil Service Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Management and Employment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Checks on Executive Power</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen User Satisfaction Survey</ml:concept><ml:concept>Independent Commissions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ombudsmen</ml:concept><ml:concept>Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Parliament</ml:concept><ml:concept>Procurement Complaints Review Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supreme Audit Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Connectivity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Lagging Regions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Sustainability and Safeguards</ml:concept><ml:concept>Knowledge Economy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banking Institutional Set-up</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Privatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>Satellites</ml:concept><ml:concept>Postal Sector Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunications and Broadband Access</ml:concept><ml:concept>Tertiary Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Network Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Postal Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Accountability Mechanisms</ml:concept><ml:concept>Connectivity and Lagging Regions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Safeguards</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Afghanistan</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Southern Asia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>