<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>ï»¿WAE AN S ANIATO   PRGRM REPORT&#13;
Unlocking the Potential of&#13;
Information Communications&#13;
Technology to Improve Water and&#13;
Sanitation Services&#13;
Summary of Findings and Recommendations&#13;
Mouhamed Fadel Ndaw&#13;
July 2015&#13;
!-W   AThe Water and Sanitation Program is a multi-donor partnership, part of&#13;
V    P 1the World Bank Group's Water Global Practice, supporting poor people  D&#13;
in obtaining affordable, safe, and sustainable access to water and  *&#13;
sani n program  sanitation services.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Author: Mouhamed Fadel Ndaw                                    The Water and Sanitation Program is a multi-donor partnership, part of&#13;
the World Bank Group's Water Global Practice, supporting poor people&#13;
About the Author                                               in obtaining affordable, safe, and sustainable access to water and&#13;
Mouhamed     Fadel Ndaw, a Water and            sanitation services. WSP's donors include Australia, Austria, Denmark,&#13;
Sanitation Engineer is best known for his       Finland, France, the Bill &amp; Melinda Gates Foundation, Luxembourg,&#13;
role over 15 years (1996-2011), as the          Netherlands, Norway, Sweden, Switzerland, United Kingdom, United&#13;
coordinator in Senegal of the urban water       States, and the World Bank.&#13;
sector reform and the water MDGs program&#13;
(PEPAM). He then joined the African Water       Disclaimer&#13;
Association of utilities as the coordinator of  The findings, interpretations, and conclusions expressed herein&#13;
the Water Operators Partnership-WOP Africa, a program          are entirely those of the author and should not be attributed to the&#13;
based in Johannesburg.                                         World Bank or its affiliated organizations, or to members of the Board&#13;
of Executive Directors of the World Bank or the governments they&#13;
Fadel joined WSP Africa in July 2012 as a Sr. Regional         represent. The World Bank does not guarantee the accuracy of the&#13;
Water &amp; Sanitation Specialist based in Ouagadougou             data included in this work. The boundaries, colors, denominations, and&#13;
(Burkina Faso) and is coordinating WSP Africa's work on        other information shown on any map in this work do not imply any&#13;
improving access to water supply services in rural areas       judgment on the part of the World Bank concerning the legal status of&#13;
and small towns with special focus on domestic private         any territory or the endorsement or acceptance of such boundaries.&#13;
sector participation. He recently completed a WSP study&#13;
examining the impact of the use of ICTs in the management      Copyright Statement&#13;
of water and sanitation sector in African countries.           The material in this work is subject to copyright. Since The World&#13;
Bank encourages dissemination of its knowledge, this work may be&#13;
reproduced, in whole or in part, for noncommercial purposes as long&#13;
Photo credits: The World BankWaSP                              as full attribution to the work is given.&#13;
s 2015 International Bank for Reconstruction and Development/The&#13;
World Bank&#13;
The fdg                                                                     WORLD BANKGROUP&#13;
arera                                 enieytoeoGh        uhrad hudntb           trbtdt     h&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Unlocking the Potential of&#13;
Information Communications&#13;
Technology to Improve Water and&#13;
Sanitation Services&#13;
Summary of Findings and Recommendations&#13;
Mouhamed Fadel Ndaw&#13;
July 2015&#13;
www.wsp.org&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Preface&#13;
This knowledge product is a summary of findings from the  both short- (project specific) and medium-term objectives,&#13;
Water and Sanitation Program (WSP) Study "Unlocking   understand the potential information that can be generated&#13;
the Potential of ICT Services in the Water and Sanitation  through ICTs, increase access to and use of the said&#13;
Sector". The study builds on and complements the World  information, and ensure that ICT-generated information&#13;
Bank's Africa Regional Strategy (2011) as well as the  is implemented more sustainably in support of WASH&#13;
World Bank Group's Information and Communication      objectives.&#13;
Technology (ICT) Strategy (2012). It further complements&#13;
the E-Transform Africa series, a collaboration between  The complete set of the twelve reports that make up the&#13;
the African Development Bank, the World Bank and the  findings from this knowledge product was coordinated&#13;
African Union, which captures the existing use of ICTs in  by Mouhamed Fadel Ndaw, Senior Water and Sanitation&#13;
six sectors (agriculture, climate change, education, health,  Specialist at the Water and Sanitation Program of the&#13;
financial services, government) and two cross-cutting themes  World Bank, and principal author of this Summary of&#13;
(regional trade and integration; ICT competitiveness).  Findings and Recommendations report. Contributors&#13;
include Gordon Amoako, Hosea Arito, Musa Chemisto,&#13;
WSP has spearheaded the use of ICT in many countries,  Maxim Fortin, Abdoulaye Kant6, Adama Sanogo, Lassina&#13;
particularly through its contribution to financing the  Togola, Richard Labelle, Erica Menchetti, Dorothy Kobel,&#13;
mWater pilot platform in Senegal, Mali, Niger and Benin,  Lillian Muhebwa, Fiona Ssozi, Ulrike Rivett, Lauren Intven&#13;
Akvo Flow and Fulcrum in Liberia and Sierra Leone and  from Cowater International Inc. and the University of Cape&#13;
Maji Voice in Kenya. Given the interest manifested by many  Town iCOMMS. Appreciation is extended to the following&#13;
sector stakeholders to learn from these pilot interventions, it  World Bank staff peer reviewers: Matar Fall, Lead Water&#13;
is necessary to improve the documentation on the latter and  and Sanitation Specialist, GWADR; Tim Kelly, Lead ICT&#13;
propose the practical modalities for scale-up. There is a very  Policy Specialist, GTIDR; Eija Pehu, Lead Agricultural&#13;
strong drive around the use of ICT in the WASH sector and  Specialist, GFADR; MarianaT. Felicio, Social Development&#13;
a growing interest among external partners. Engagement  Specialist, GSURR; Pierre Xavier Boulenger, Senior Water&#13;
in ICT developments requires strong collaboration with  and Sanitation Specialist, GWADR; and Andreas Rohde,&#13;
external resources and drivers of innovations. In this regard,  Senior Sanitary Engineer, GWADR.&#13;
there is a need to develop clearer partnership platforms with&#13;
iv&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Table of Contents&#13;
Executive Summary     ................................................................... Vii&#13;
A. Background and Context .. ............................................................ Vii&#13;
B. Methodology and Process  ............................................................. Vii&#13;
C. Landscape Analysis and Findings of the Study...........................................        .....Viii&#13;
A. Background and Context     ............................................................1&#13;
Al: Context of the Study.. ...........................................................1&#13;
A2: Objectives of the Study............................................................2&#13;
B. Methodology and Process     ...........................................................3&#13;
C. Landscape Analysis and Findings of the Study..................5...........             ..............5&#13;
Cl: Lessons learnt from other sectors....................................................5&#13;
C2: Aligning the role of ICT with water and sanitation goals and priorities  .................. ..........6&#13;
C3: Lessons learnt from ICT use within the WASH sector ........................................9&#13;
C4: Identification of key thematic areas for the sustainable use of ICT in WASH.......................10&#13;
Theme 1: Using ICT to strengthen monitoring and inventory of infrastructure........... ..............10&#13;
Theme 2: Sustaining ICT based planning and programming initiatives     ........     ..................14&#13;
Theme 3: ICT and operational efficiency improvements                      ....................................16&#13;
Theme 4: ICT and service delivery improvements (particularly to the poor)        ..................17&#13;
Theme 5: ICT to Strengthen the Consumer Voice.........................................19&#13;
Theme 6: ICT and governance ....................................................22&#13;
Theme 7: Financing ICTs........................................................24&#13;
Theme 8: Public-Private Partnerships                               ...................... ...................27&#13;
C5: Policy and Operation Recommendations for Service Providers  ...................................30&#13;
C6: Identification of strategic issues for at scale use of ICT .......................................31&#13;
Annex 1: Overview of ICT Tools in the WASH Sector............................................33&#13;
Annex 2: Analysis of WASH ICT Tools in Country Case Studies                        ...................................40&#13;
Annex 3: Additional Resources..........................................................50&#13;
List of Figures&#13;
Figure 1: Mobile Technology's Contribution to Latin American, Sub-Saharan Africa and Asian GDPs....................1&#13;
Figure 2: ICTs in the WASH Sector.......................................................7&#13;
List of Tables&#13;
Table 1: Financing ICTs-Uganda's National Water and Sewerage  .......................................25&#13;
Table 2: Typical Cost Benefit Streams for consideration in ICT Implementation  ........... ..............26&#13;
www.wsp.org                                                                                                V&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Acronyms and Abbreviations&#13;
ACWUA          Arab Countries Water Utilities Association&#13;
AfDB           African Development Bank&#13;
AMR            Automated Meter Reading&#13;
ASUFOR         Association des Usagers des Forages (Borehole Users' Association)&#13;
ATTI           Africa Technology &amp; Transparency Initiative&#13;
CHW            Community Health Worker&#13;
DFID           United Kingdom's Department for International Development&#13;
DGPRE          Direction de la Gestion et de la Planification des Ressources en Eau (Directorate of Water Resource&#13;
Management and Planning)&#13;
DWO            District Water Officer&#13;
EMIS           Education Management Information System&#13;
FLOW           Field Level Operations Watch&#13;
GCCN           Government Common Core Network&#13;
GDP            Gross Domestic Product&#13;
GFADR          Agricultural Global Practice&#13;
GIS            Geographic Information System&#13;
GIZ            Gesellschaft fir Internationale Zusammenarbeit (German International Cooperation Agency for&#13;
Development)&#13;
GPS            Global Positioning System&#13;
GSM            Global System for Mobile Communication&#13;
GSURR          Global Practice for Social, Urban, Rural and Resilience&#13;
GTIDR          Transport &amp; Information and Communication Technology (ICT) Global Practice&#13;
GWADR          Water Global Practice&#13;
HIV            Human Immunodeficiency Virus&#13;
ICT            Information and Communication Technology&#13;
ICT4D          ICT for Development&#13;
KCC            Korea Communications Commission&#13;
KWT            Kiamumbi Water Trust&#13;
M4W            Mobiles 4 Water&#13;
M DG           Millennium Development Goal&#13;
MHA            Minist&amp;re de l'Hydraulique et de l'Assainissement (Ministry of Water and Sanitation)&#13;
MoUD           Ministry of Urban Development&#13;
NCWSC          Nairobi City Water and Sewerage Company&#13;
N FC           Near-Field Communication&#13;
NGO            Non-Governmental Organization&#13;
NOFBI          National Optic Fibre Backbone Infrastructure&#13;
NREN           National Research Education Networks&#13;
ODF            Open Defecation Free&#13;
ONAS           Office National de l'Assainissement (National Sanitation Office)&#13;
PCMC           Pimpri Chinchwad Municipal Corporation&#13;
PEPAM          Programme eau potable et assainissement pour le mill6naire (Millennium Water and Sanitation Program)&#13;
PPP            Public-Private Partnership&#13;
RFID           Radio Frequency Identification Technology&#13;
RTI            Radar Technologies International&#13;
RWSS           Rural Water Supply System&#13;
Vi&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Unlocking the Potential of Information Communications Technology to Improve Water and Sanitation Services I Acronyms and Abbreviations&#13;
SDE             S6n6galaise Des Eaux (Senegal's Private Water Utility)&#13;
SIASAR          Sistema de Informaci6n de Agua y Saneamiento Rural (Rural Water and Sanitation Information System)&#13;
SMS             Short message service&#13;
SWM             Smart water meter&#13;
ULB             Urban Local Body&#13;
UNESCO          United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization&#13;
UNICEF          United Nations Children's Fund&#13;
USAID           United States Agency for International Development&#13;
USD             United States Dollar&#13;
WASH            Water, Sanitation and Hygiene&#13;
WASREB          Water Services Regulatory Board&#13;
WB              World Bank&#13;
WfP             Water for People&#13;
WPM             Water Point Mapping&#13;
WQR             Water Quality Reporter&#13;
WSP             Water and Sanitation Program&#13;
WSP             Water Service Provider&#13;
WSTF            Water Services Trust Fund Kenya&#13;
ZAWA            Zanzibar Water Authority&#13;
www.wsp.org                                                                                                     Vii&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Foreword&#13;
Since the first Short Message Service (SMS) text was sent  This study was carried out by the Water and Sanitation&#13;
in 1992, the proliferation of mobile technology and its  Program   (WSP) of the World Bank to fill a gap in&#13;
derivative uses has been both massive and extremely rapid.  understanding how the potential of ICT can improve water&#13;
According to a recent Groupe Speciale Mobile Association  and sanitation services globally, with a particular emphasis&#13;
(GSMA) report, in 2014, 52 percent of all global mobile  in Africa. It covers a global desk review and case studies in&#13;
money deployments took place in sub-Saharan Africa and   seven African countries (Kenya, Uganda, Tanzania, Senegal,&#13;
82 percent of Africans had access to Global System for   Benin, Niger and Liberia), complemented by experiences&#13;
Mobile (GSM) communications coverage compared to         from other regions (Latin America, North America, South&#13;
63 percent who had access to improved water supply and   Asia and East Asia) and analyzes strengths and weaknesses&#13;
32 percent to electricity. How can other sectors, in this  of existing ICT tools. It also provides evidence on how&#13;
case the water supply and sanitation services sector, make  ICT can be used to leapfrog the water and sanitation sector&#13;
best use of this increasingly ubiquitous access to mobile  towards more sustainable service delivery.&#13;
technology? And what opportunities might exist to&#13;
harness mobile technology in order to help bridge the gap  This study sought to not only document experiences&#13;
of water and sanitation services to the poor or currently  of ICT use in the WASH sector, but also analyze them&#13;
underserved populations?                                 within the framework of enabling factors and barriers in&#13;
terms of vision, process, customer/user, service delivery,&#13;
Recent experience from around the world has demonstrated  human capacity, governance and finance.&#13;
that the water and sanitation sector has not been immune&#13;
to the innovative use of Information and Communication   Mirroring the dynamic evolution of ICT solutions and&#13;
Technology (ICT) as evidenced by the many examples       applications, we hope this analysis provides an important&#13;
currently being rolled out. We may only be witnessing    entry-point to our evolving understanding of the best way&#13;
the first wave of technology innovations for water and   to harness ICT solutions for water and sanitation.&#13;
sanitation service delivery, however, and have much to learn&#13;
regarding the best way to adopt, quickly operationalize, and&#13;
continue to innovate in successive stages.&#13;
While ICT can be a key enabler for institutional&#13;
transformation to address the demand for improved water&#13;
and sanitation service, especially for hard-to-reach poor&#13;
populations in rural and urban areas, it will never be the  Glenn Pearce-Oroz&#13;
silver bullet. In order to maximize its transformational role  Principal Regional Team Leader for Africa&#13;
in the sector, ICT should be recognized as a conduit or  Water and Sanitation Program (WSP)&#13;
tool that needs to be continuously managed well in order  World Bank&#13;
to help achieve a solution. Impact and success need to be&#13;
measured not merely in terms of implementation or uptake&#13;
of the new technology, but more importantly with regards&#13;
to achieving the Water, Sanitation and Hygiene (WASH)&#13;
sector's goals and priorities.&#13;
Viii&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Executive Summary&#13;
A. BACKGROUND AND CONTEXT                                 B. METHODOLOGY AND PROCESS&#13;
Information Communications Technology (ICT) growth       In order to achieve the above objectives, the methodology&#13;
and uptake is changing the landscape of developing       and process of the study were broken down into six key&#13;
countries. Initial applications are showing how ICTs can  activities that generated input reports or analyses, as follows:&#13;
further WASH goals and priorities, including increasing      Lessons Learnt from Other Sectors: ICT has seen&#13;
access, improving   service  delivery  and  improving        phenomenal growth throughout Africa over the last&#13;
governance. There already exists a substantial knowledge     decade. Applications in the sectors of agriculture,&#13;
base on the use of ICTs for Development (ICT4D).             health, education and governance have illustrated the&#13;
However, too often the knowledge base focuses on the         benefits ICTs can provide in collecting information,&#13;
technological innovation itself, rather than how it can      streamlining information flow and improving work&#13;
be embedded into sector management and governance            processes. The first objective of the study was to take&#13;
systems. This study, therefore, aims to take stock and       stock of emerging uses of ICT across other sectors in&#13;
reflect on the findings from key ICT applications and        order to translate lessons learnt into recommendations&#13;
experiences both in other sectors as well as in the WASH     applicable to the WASH sector. This was accomplished&#13;
sector itself. By documenting and analyzing past successes,  through a desk review entitled Lessons Learnt from&#13;
failures, enablers and barriers of the key applications and  Other Sectors.&#13;
experiences, it is possible to significantly advance the areas&#13;
of policy development, guidelines, implementation, and       Experiences of ICT     Use in    the Water and&#13;
scale up of ICT in the WASH sector.                          Sanitation Sector and Country Case Studies: With&#13;
increasing support and infrastructure development,&#13;
Objectives of the Study                                      the global WASH sector is seeing heightened ICT&#13;
The specific objectives of the study were to:                interventions. In order to address two of the key&#13;
*   take stock of emerging uses of ICT across sectors,    objectives of the study: 1) Document relevant&#13;
including  agriculture, health, education  and        experiences of key ICT applications in the water&#13;
governance;                                           and sanitation sector, highlighting the strengths and&#13;
*   document the relevant experiences of key ICT          weaknesses of current initiatives, and 2) Identify&#13;
applications (both failures and good practices)       binding constraints impacting ICT adoption and&#13;
in the water and sanitation sector globally and in    scale-UP, a second desk review was conducted, Desk&#13;
selected African countries;                           Review: Experience of ICT use in the WASH Sector,&#13;
*   identify  binding  constraints impacting  ICT         and a report entitled Experience of ICT use in the&#13;
adoption and scale-up as well as the role of different  WASH Sector: Case Studies prepared, based on field&#13;
actors (private, public, development community,       visits and case studies in seven African countries.&#13;
civil society);&#13;
*   develop policy and guidelines for the at-scale use of  As part of the Desk Review: Experience of ICT use&#13;
ICTs in the water and sanitation sector, including    in the WASH Sector, a survey of ICT applications&#13;
opportunities for public/private partnership; and     was conducted (see Annex 1 for a detailed list and&#13;
*   facilitate country  peer-to-peer exchanges and        summary of the applications included) which detailed&#13;
regional learning network,                            the experiences of ICT in the WASH sector to date,&#13;
highlighting the strengths and weaknesses of different&#13;
pilot operations in Africa and other regions. As part of&#13;
Experience ofICT use in the WASH Sector: Case Studies,&#13;
www.wsp.org                                                                                                    ix&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Unlocking the Potential of Information Communications Technology to Improve Water and Sanitation Services Executive Summary&#13;
case studies were prepared based on consultations,          ICT field and can - where necessary -   be amended&#13;
interviews and focus group discussions with key water       to provide an appropriate analytical framework for the&#13;
sector stakeholders in each of the seven case study         specific needs of a study.&#13;
countries (Benin, Liberia, Niger, Senegal, Kenya,&#13;
Tanzania and Uganda), including implementers and             Guidelines and Policy Notes: Building on the work&#13;
project participants. The case studies were assessed using  done   in  previous components, Development of&#13;
an evaluation and monitoring framework, based on the         Guidelines and Policy Notes were prepared in order&#13;
two assessment frameworks described in the Analytical       to propose strategiesnh and policy recommendations&#13;
Report, and amended to the specific requirements of         to   guide  the   design  and   implementation    of&#13;
this study.                                                  appropriate and sustainable ICT    components for&#13;
WASH sector projects and to evaluate the impact&#13;
Analytical Report: The Analytical Report aligned             of these interventions. Guidelines and Policy Notes&#13;
the role of ICTs   with water and sanitation goals          included recommendations on data integration and&#13;
and   priorities by  identifying  opportunities and         mainstreaming; ICT evaluation; recommendations for&#13;
challenges, translating enabling factors of success into    policymakers and regulators; and policy and operation&#13;
assessment criteria and developing analytical pieces of     recommendations for service providers.&#13;
work on strategic issues. Lessons learnt supported the&#13;
development of analytical pieces of work on different        Online Tool: An interactive online tool was established&#13;
issues, including how   to use ICT    to strengthen         and maintained throughout the study to disseminate&#13;
planning and programming, ICT and service delivery          materials developed for the study.&#13;
improvements, ICT and operational efficiencies&#13;
improvements, financing of ICT, ICT and governance,&#13;
ICT   to strengthen the consumer voice, and ICT         C. LANDSCAPE ANALYSIS AND FINDINGS OF&#13;
and service delivery to the poor. Two frameworks            THE STUDY&#13;
for assessment were tested under this study. The first  The first desk review of the study, Lessons Learnt from&#13;
framework, the Balance Scorecard Approach', breaks       Other Sectors, translated key lessons learnt from the sectors&#13;
down the process of ICT implementation into key         of agriculture, health, education and governance into&#13;
dimensions. This framework is valuable as it supports   recommendations applicable to the WASH       sector. Key&#13;
an analysis of the various mechanisms at work during    highlights from the lessons learnt include:&#13;
the initial design and implementation stages. However,      *   Involve citizens in the design and use of the tool to&#13;
an evaluation framework should not only define the              encourage successful implementation.&#13;
success of ICT tools by the uptake or scale-up of the       *   Align ICT   interventions with the community&#13;
technology, but also by the impact that the technology          setting  and  the local resource environment;&#13;
has had on    the specific WASH     goal or target.             simple technologies that require less technical&#13;
Additionally, focus on the improved capabilities within         support and work well in resource-constrained&#13;
the user group or the beneficiaries of the tool is an           environments have a higher potential of being&#13;
important consideration. The second framework, the              successfully scaled up.&#13;
ICT Impact Chain2, therefore looked at the impact               Use ofuniversally available technology can accelerate&#13;
of the tool after implementation. The frameworks for            uptake and ICT platforms that are cost-effective,&#13;
assessment are based on tested methodologies in the             particularly in resource-constrained settings. This&#13;
strategy allows for a bigger share of the budget to be&#13;
_____________________________________________channeled directly to the service of consumers.&#13;
Kaplan, R., &amp; Norton, D. E (1992) The Balanced Scorecard-Measures That Drive  Improve communication infrastructure to allow all&#13;
Performance Harvard Business Review, P. 71-79.                     citizens to benefit and&#13;
2Gigler 2011, 'Informational Capabilities - The Missing Link for the Impact ofICT on&#13;
development", Working Paper Series No.1; E-Transform Knowledge Platform, Working  Invest in sector and ICT infrastructure with a focus&#13;
Paper, The World Bank                                               on alternative energy sources.&#13;
X&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Unlocking the Potential of Information Communications Technology to Improve Water and Sanitation Services | Executive Summary&#13;
*   Assess the performance and impact of the ICT             As part of the analytical work of the study the following&#13;
intervention, develop assessment/evaluation tools        eight key thematic areas were assessed:&#13;
to regularly monitor the impact of ICT       in the          1.  Using ICTs to strengthen monitoring and inventory&#13;
sector.                                                          of infrastructure.&#13;
*   Enable user feedback loops to periodically monitor           2.  Sustaining ICT-based planning and programming&#13;
and   evaluate, and   continually refine the ICT                 initiatives.&#13;
intervention over time.                                      3.  ICT and operational efficiency improvements.&#13;
*   Ensure technological and procedural flexibility.             4.  ICTand service delivery improvements (particularly&#13;
*   Develop comprehensive sector strategies, national                for the poor).&#13;
policies, standards and regulatory frameworks.               5.   ICT to strengthen the consumer Voice.&#13;
*   Support the development of human and institutional           6.  ICT and governance.&#13;
capacities in  terms of policy     implementation,           7.  Financing of ICTs.&#13;
provision of regulatory frameworks and managing              8.  Public-Private Partnerships.&#13;
policies.&#13;
ICTs can be a key enabler for institutional transformation&#13;
As part of the Desk Review: Experience of ICT use in the         to address the demand for improved water and sanitation&#13;
WASH Sector, a survey of ICT applications in the WASH            services for both rural and urban communities. However, in&#13;
sector was conducted. The various ICT WASH applications          order to maximize the transformational role of ICT in the&#13;
presented in the report can be summarized based on three         WASH sector, ICTs need to be perceived as merely conduits&#13;
main WASH priority areas: increasing access, improving           or contributing forces rather than as development impacts&#13;
service delivery and improving governance.                       or solutions in themselves. Impact and success need to be&#13;
measured not simply in terms of implementation or uptake&#13;
Although the global WASH sector is witnessing heightened         of the new technology but more importantly in regards to&#13;
ICT   interventions, the low   sustainability rate of ICT        achieving WASH sector goals and priorities.&#13;
interventions combined with the high frequency of failure&#13;
in scaling applications beyond the pilot phase remains a         In addition to documenting experiences on the use of ICTs&#13;
major concern. All ICT applications are driven by the desire     in the WASH sector', this study sought to examine them&#13;
to bring change to their areas of implementation. However,       through specific design and evaluation frameworks.4 The&#13;
with reliability and cost-effectiveness of the WASH sector       process facilitated the identification ofenabling factors and&#13;
still hampered by poverty, weak institutions and poor            barriers in terms of vision, process, customer/user, human&#13;
infrastructure, it must be understood that incorporating         capacity and finance. The analysis was also an opportunity&#13;
ICT solutions in the water and sanitation sector is not a        to track the progress of the said factors in the ICT Impact&#13;
'magic pill', but rather ICTs should be viewed as strategic      Chain5 as well as provide guidelines and policy notes on&#13;
research and development tools that must be used in              the inclusion of ICTs in Water and Sanitation Policy and&#13;
partnership with traditional sector approaches. The key          Planning to the sector's stakeholders.6&#13;
principles for sustainability that came out of the desk review&#13;
were summarized under the following themes: a) User-&#13;
Centered Design, Participation and Experience b) Choice&#13;
of Technology and c) Finance and Program Design.________________________&#13;
See ICTs in the WASH Sector Desk Review&#13;
See the Analytical Report for a description of the frameworks used and detailed&#13;
discussion on enabling factors and barriers&#13;
'See all seven of the Case Study Reports to see the implementation of the assessment&#13;
frameworks on the case studies&#13;
'See Development of Guidelines and Policy Notes which includes Recommendations&#13;
on Data Integration and Mainstreaming; ICT Evaluation; Recommendations for&#13;
Policy Makers and Regulators; and Policy and peration Recommendations for&#13;
Service Providers.&#13;
www.wfp.org                                                               o     p&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Unlocking the Potential of Information Communications Technology to Improve Water and Sanitation Services Executive Summary&#13;
With the desire to further support the implementation and        identified in the study three stand out as potential areas&#13;
scale-up of ICTs in the WASH sector, it is essential to move     where high-level support could be beneficial:&#13;
beyond support for specific tools or technologies and look          0    lack ofsector level policy and regulatory frameworks.&#13;
more broadly at supporting the elimination of barriers and          0    lack of sustainable financial models.&#13;
providing enabling environments. Of the common barriers             *    lack  of  monitoring     and   evaluation   of  the&#13;
implementation and impact of ICTs in the&#13;
WASH sector.&#13;
Xii&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿A        . Background and Context&#13;
Al: Context of the Study                                        As Mthuli Ncube, Chief Economist and Vice President of&#13;
Information Communications Technology (ICT) growth             the African Development Bank (AfDB), puts it: "We have&#13;
and adoption is changing the landscape of developing            seen potential and an opportunity in technology-driven&#13;
countries. The acknowledged potential that ICTs hold in         entrepreneurship across Africa especially among young&#13;
helping to boost economic growth and reduce poverty can         people. ICTs are playing a significant role in transforming&#13;
be attributed in part to how ICTs have been incorporated        African economies&#13;
into the thriving economies of Africa 78. The "Sub-&#13;
Saharan Africa Mobile Economy 2013" report by GSMA              The lack of data and information on existing water and&#13;
Intelligence shows that mobile technology contributes           sanitation assets and their current management constitute&#13;
over six percent of the GDP of Sub-Saharan Africa, higher       a barrier for the extension of the services to the poor.&#13;
than any other comparable region globally, and by 2020          Additionally, the poorest lack adequate platforms to hold&#13;
it is expected to rise to over eight percent. Evidence from     their service providers accountable and to be heard by&#13;
countries like South Africa and Kenya shows that ICTs           decision-makers. Initial applications are showing how ICTs&#13;
have played an important role in their economic growth'.        can further WASH goals and priorities, including increasing&#13;
access, improving service delivery and improving governance.&#13;
FIGURE 1: MOBILE TECHNOLOGY'S CONTRIBUTION TO LATIN AMERICAN, SUB-SAHARAN AFRICA AND ASIAN GDPS&#13;
(Source:a www.gsmamobileeconoahyafica.icorn)&#13;
APP, 2008. ICT in Africa: Boosting Economic Growth and Poverty Reduction&#13;
AFleshman, M., Essoungou, A. &amp; Gillespie, J., 2011. Investing in Africa: Digging&#13;
deep for new opportunities. Africa Renewal, (April). Available at: http://www.un.org/&#13;
africarenewal/sites/dr7.un.org.africarenewal/files/Africa-Renewal-April-20 1l-en.pdf.&#13;
dHeeks, R., 2011. ICT and Economic Growth: Evidence from Kenya. ICT4I.&#13;
Available at: http://ict4dblog.wordpress.com/201l 06/26/icr-and-economic-growth-  c hp://www.afdb.org/en/news-andp-evenrs/aicle/afdb-envisagesnhe-powerof-ic-&#13;
evidencearom-kenyac [Accessed August 16, 2014].                 fordafricas-eransformaeionle 3080/&#13;
www.wsp.org&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Unlocking the Potential of Information Communications Technology to Improve Water and Sanitation Services | Background and Context&#13;
There already exists a substantial knowledge base on the use   A2: Objectives of the Study&#13;
of ICTs for Development (ICT4D). However, too often            The specific objectives of the study were to:&#13;
the knowledge base focuses on the technological innovation         0   take stock of emerging uses of ICT across sectors&#13;
itself, rather than how it can be embedded into sector                 including  agriculture,  health,  education   and&#13;
management and governance systems. As such, this study                 governance.&#13;
aims to take stock and reflect on the findings from key ICT        *   document the relevant experiences of key ICT&#13;
applications and experiences both in other sectors, as well as         applications (both failures and good practices)&#13;
in the WASH sector itself. By documenting and analyzing in the water and sanitation sector globally and in&#13;
past successes, failures, enablers and barriers of the key             selected African countries.&#13;
applications and experiences, it is possible to significantly      0   identify  binding   constraints  impacting   ICT&#13;
advance the areas of policy development, guidelines,                   adoption and scale-up as well as the role of different&#13;
implementation, and scale-up of ICT in the WASH sector,                actors (private, public, development community,&#13;
civil society).&#13;
T   develop policy and guidelines for the at-scale use of&#13;
ICTs in the water and sanitation sector, including&#13;
opportunities for public/private partnerships.&#13;
*   facilitate  country  peer-to-peer  exchanges  and&#13;
regional learning network.&#13;
2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿B      e Methodology and Process&#13;
In order to achieve the specific objectives, as defined above,  case studies were prepared based on consultations,&#13;
the methodology and process of the study consisted of six     interviews and focus group discussions with key water&#13;
key activities::                                               sector stakeholders in each of the seven case study&#13;
*   Lessons Learnt from Other Sectors: ICT has seen            countries (Benin, Liberia, Niger, Senegal, Kenya,&#13;
phenomenal growth throughout Africa over the last          Tanzania and Uganda), including implementers and&#13;
decade. Applications in the sectors of agriculture,        project participants. The case studies were assessed using&#13;
health, education and governance have illustrated the      an evaluation and monitoring framework, based on the&#13;
benefits ICT can provide in collecting information,        two assessment frameworks described in the Analytical&#13;
streamlining information flow and improving work           Report, and amended to the specific requirements of&#13;
processes. The first objective of the study was to take   this study.&#13;
stock of emerging uses of ICT across other sectors in&#13;
order to translate lessons learnt into recommendations     Analytical Report: The Analytical Report aligned the&#13;
applicable to the WASH sector. This was accomplished       role of ICTwithwater and sanitation goals and priorities&#13;
through a desk review entitled Lessons Learntfrom Other    by identifying opportunities and challenges, translating&#13;
Sectors. Section C1 summarizes the findings from the       enabling factors of success into assessment criteria and&#13;
first desk review in tabular form, wherein the potential   developing analytical pieces of work on strategic issues.&#13;
successes, key barriers and lessons learnt from each of    Lessons learnt supported the development of analytical&#13;
the four sectors are highlighted.                          pieces of work on different issues, including how to use&#13;
ICT to strengthen planning and programming, ICT&#13;
*   Experiences of ICT Use in the Water and Sanitation         and service delivery improvements, ICT and operational&#13;
Sector and Country Case Studies: With increasing           efficiencies improvements, financing of ICT, ICT and&#13;
support and infrastructure development, the global         governance, ICT to strengthen consumer voice, and&#13;
WASH sector is seeing heightened ICT interventions. In     ICT and service delivery to the poor. Two frameworks&#13;
order to address two of the key objectives of the study: 1)  for assessment were tested as part of this study. The first&#13;
Document relevant experiences of key ICT applications      framework, the Balance Scorecard Approach", breaks&#13;
in the water and sanitation sector, highlighting the       down the process of ICT implementation into key&#13;
strengths and weaknesses of current initiatives, and 2)    dimensions. This framework is valuable as it supports&#13;
Identify binding constraints impacting ICT adoption        an analysis of the various mechanisms at work during&#13;
and scale-up, a second desk review was completed, Desk    the initial design and implementation stages. However,&#13;
Review: Experience ofICT use in the WASH Sector, and an    an evaluation framework should not only define the&#13;
Experience of ICT use in the WASH Sector: Case Studies     success of ICT tools by the uptake or scale-up of the&#13;
report was prepared based on field visits and case studies  technology, but by the impact that the technology has&#13;
in seven African countries.                                had on the specific WASH goal or target. Additionally,&#13;
focus on the improved capabilities within the user&#13;
In Desk Review: Experience of ICT use in the WASH          group or the beneficiaries of the tool is an important&#13;
Sector, a survey of ICT applications was conducted         consideration. The second framework, the ICT Impact&#13;
(see Annex 1 for a detailed list and summary of the        Chain12, therefore looked at the impact of the tool&#13;
applications included in the desk review) which&#13;
detailed the experiences of ICT in the WASH sector to  "Kaplan, R., &amp;Norton, D.P. (1992) The Balanced Scorecard-Measures That Drive&#13;
date, highlighting strengths and weaknesses of different  Performance. Harvard Business Review, R 71-79.&#13;
pilot operations in Africa and other regions. As part of  2 Gigler 2011, "Informational Capabiliies -he MissingLinkfor the Impact ofICTon&#13;
development Working Paper Series No.1; E-Transform Knowledge Platform, Working&#13;
Experience of ICT use in the WASH Sector: Case Studies  Paper, The World Bank&#13;
www.wsp.org                                                                                                       3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Unlocking the Potential of Information Communications Technology to Improve Water and Sanitation Services | Methodology and Process&#13;
after implementation. The frameworks for assessment                Online Tool: An interactive on line tool was established&#13;
are based on tested methodologies in the ICT field                 and maintained throughout the study to disseminate&#13;
and can - where necessary - be amended to provide an               materials developed as part of the study.&#13;
appropriate analytical framework for the specific needs&#13;
of a study.                                                   An effort was made to ensure knowledge building and&#13;
learning opportunities among key stakeholders, targeting&#13;
Guidelines and Policy Notes: Building on the work             in particular WASH     sector experts and ICT     innovators.&#13;
done in previous components, guidelines and policy            Prior to the commencement of the study, a workshop was&#13;
notes were prepared in order to propose strategies            held" and attended by approximately 50 participants to:&#13;
and policy recommendations to guide the design                        Enable different stakeholders to develop a common&#13;
and implementation of appropriate and sustainable                     platform for stock-taking;&#13;
ICT components for WASH          sector projects and to           *   Promote exchange on the proposed methodology,&#13;
evaluate the impact of these interventions. Guidelines                analytical framework and work plan in order to&#13;
and   Policy  Notes included     recommendations on                   achieve maximum      results of the case studies in&#13;
data integration and mainstreaming ICT evaluation,                    the seven target countries (Benin, Kenya, Liberia,&#13;
recommendations for policymakers and regulators                       Niger, Senegal, Tanzania, Uganda); and&#13;
and   policy  and   operation    recommendations for                  Provide early exposure of the WASH         ICT  tools&#13;
service providers,                                                    developed in East and West Africa.&#13;
The workshop took place in Nairobi from 7 to 8 July 2014. Nearly 50 participants&#13;
from Benin, Burkina Faso, Kenya, Liberia, Niger, Senegal, Tanzania and Uganda&#13;
attended. The key stakeholder groups were representatives of regulators, water minis-&#13;
tries, municipalities, partners and ICT4D actors present in Kenya (GIZ, SUWASA,&#13;
IRC, IBM, GSMA, WAG, iHub, University of Nairobi, Kenya CSO Network) as well&#13;
as the Consortium of Consultants: Cowater (Canada) and iComms - University of&#13;
Cape Town (South Africa).&#13;
4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿C         Landscape Analysis and Findings of the Study&#13;
Cl: Lessons Learnt from Other Sectors                  objective of the study was to take stock of emerging uses of&#13;
ICT has experienced phenomenal growth over the last    ICT across other sectors in order to translate lessons learnt&#13;
decade. Applications in the sectors of agriculture, health,  into recommendations applicable to the WASH sector.&#13;
education and governance have illustrated the benefits that  This objective was accomplished through a desk review&#13;
ICT can provide in collecting information, streamlining  entitled Lessons Learntfrom Other Sectors. The table below&#13;
information flow and improving work processes. The first  summarizes the findings from the first desk review.&#13;
Agriculture&#13;
The agriculture sector is rife with innovations and ICTs for varying tasks and purposes, including FM radio stations, mobile&#13;
phones, Radio Frequency Identification Technology (RFID), Global Positioning System (GPS), Geographic Information Systems&#13;
(GIS) and other web-based applications.&#13;
* Reduced transaction costs   * Lack of infrastructure       * Have local stakeholders facilitate the delivery of&#13;
* Increased access to           (connectivity, access to       lCT-enabled services&#13;
information and markets      technology)                  * Use the lowest cost and simplest technology&#13;
* Improved productivity and   * Lack of sector-specific lOT  * Assess performance and impact of the lCT&#13;
supply chain management      policies                        intervention&#13;
* Increased negotiating power  * Gender barriers to participation  * Develop a comprehensive sector strategy&#13;
and revenue of farmers                                     * Highlight the positive link between women's&#13;
livelihoods and lOTs&#13;
Health&#13;
The prevalence of ICT use in the health sector is substantial. There are currently 1,125 and counting rn-health deployments globally.&#13;
* Improved quality and safety of  o Limited or short-term funding  e Invest in sector and lOT infrastructure with a&#13;
treatment through the provision  * Low mobile and Internet   focus on alternative energy sources&#13;
of timely information         penetration                 e Development of national policies, standards and&#13;
* Decreased prevalence of     * Lack of sector-specific policies  regulatory frameworks&#13;
counterfeit drugs            and regulatory frameworks      Alignment of lOT interventions with the&#13;
* Expanded reach of health                                   * Shortage of skilled workers  community setting and the local resource&#13;
care to underserved and rural  o Lack of standard mechanisms  environment&#13;
communities                  and indicators to evaluate lOT  I Enable user feedback ioops to periodically&#13;
* Increased productivity and    interventions                  monitor and evaluate and to continually refine&#13;
reduced costs                                               the lOT intervention over time&#13;
a  Use of simple technologies that require less&#13;
technical support and work well in resource-&#13;
constrained environments have a higher&#13;
potential of being successfully scaled up&#13;
Te pT platforms that are cost-effective, particularly&#13;
in resource-constrained settings, allow a bigger&#13;
share of the budget to be channeled directly to&#13;
the service consumers&#13;
*  Ensure technological and procedural flexibility&#13;
www.wsp.org                                                                                               5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Unlocking the Potential of Information Communications Technology to Improve Water and Sanitation Services | Landscape Analysis and Findings of the Study&#13;
Education&#13;
Key priority areas for ICTs in the education sector include professional development for teachers, digital learning resources,&#13;
affordable technologies, Education Management Information Systems (EMIS) and National Research Education Networks&#13;
(NRENs).&#13;
* Reach underserved and under-  * Lack of financing, specifically for  * Need to incorporate ICTs into national policies&#13;
resourced communities         human resources               and strategies&#13;
* Contribute to universal access  * Poor infrastructure and  * Need to develop assessment/evaluation tools to&#13;
and quality learning and      connectivity                  regularly monitor the impact of ICT in the sector&#13;
teaching                    * Lack of gender equity       * Need to prioritize the development, review and&#13;
* Lack of policies that support  updating of local content to incentivize users&#13;
the integration of ICTs into&#13;
pedagogical practice&#13;
Governance&#13;
Advances in ICTs have created opportunities for improved participation and are being exploited to improve governance.&#13;
ICTs have strengthened partnerships between institutions such as parliaments, media and civil society organizations through&#13;
interactive platforms or fora that support information sharing and collaboration. Systems that allow citizens to report graft&#13;
or misuse of public funds have contributed to the fight against corruption and have created better mechanisms for ensuring&#13;
government accountability of public resources and transparency in the delivery of services.&#13;
* Poverty reduction with more  * Poor infrastructure        * Need to improve communication infrastructure&#13;
reliable services to the poor  * Limited access to technology  to allow all citizens to benefit and participate&#13;
* Empowerment of individuals  * Low literacy                * Use of universally available technology can&#13;
* Capacity building (skills and  * Rigid regulatory frameworks that  accelerate uptake&#13;
networks through education)  limit the ability of governance  * Setting up of community resource centers can&#13;
* Improving the quality of service  structures to respond to the  improve individual access to ICTs&#13;
delivery                      continuous and dynamic changes * Extending ICT services to local governments&#13;
* Inspiring new governance     prompted by the introduction of  can improve service delivery and support local&#13;
mechanisms                    new technologies              economic development&#13;
* Reinforcing participation                                 * Involving citizens in the design and use of the&#13;
tool is critical for successful implementation&#13;
* ICTs must be understood as merely tools&#13;
* Need to support the development of human&#13;
and institutional capacities in terms of policy&#13;
implementation, provision of regulatory&#13;
frameworks and managing policies&#13;
C2: Aligning the Role of ICT with Water and          Identify binding constraints impacting ICT adoption&#13;
Sanitation Goals and Priorities                  and scale-up, a second desk review was conducted to&#13;
With increasing support and infrastructure development,  document experience of ICT use in the WASH Sector,&#13;
the global WASH    sector is witnessing more ICT     Desk Review: Experience of ICT use in the WASH Sector,&#13;
interventions. In order to address two of the key objectives  and an Experience of ICT use in the WASH Sector: Case&#13;
of the study: 1) Document relevant experiences of key ICT  Studies report was drafted based on field visits and case&#13;
applications in the water and sanitation sector, highlighting  studies in seven African countries.&#13;
the strengths and weaknesses of current initiatives, and 2)&#13;
6&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Unlocking the Potential of Information Communications Technology to Improve Water and Sanitation Services Landscape Analysis and Findings of the Study&#13;
As part of the DeskReview: Experience oflCTuse in the WASH                (Benin, Liberia,14 Niger, Senegal, Kenya, Tanzania and&#13;
Sector, a survey of ICT       applications was conducted        (see      Uganda), including implementers and project participants,&#13;
Annex 1 for a detailed list and summary of the applications               along with supporting documentation where available. The&#13;
in the desk review) which detailed the experiences of ICT                 table in Annex 2 lists the main tools assessed as part of the&#13;
in the WASH      sector to date, highlighting the strengths and           Experience of ICT use in the WASH Sector Case Studies. The&#13;
weaknesses of different pilot operations in Africa and other              table is based on the ICT Impact Chain further discussed in&#13;
regions. As part of Experience ofICT use in the WASH Sector: the Analytical Report and summarizes various aspects of the&#13;
Case Studies, studies were prepared based on consultations,               development, implementation and application of the ICT&#13;
interviews and     focus group     discussions with     key water         tools in use in the WASH       Sector.&#13;
sector stakeholders in each of the seven case study countries&#13;
FIGURE 2: ICTs IN THE WASH SECTOR&#13;
Information and Communications Technologies in the Water, Sanitation and Hygiene (WASH) Sector&#13;
Worldwide: Including Bolivia,&#13;
Mali, Gambia, Sierra Leone,&#13;
)r                  Togo, Nigeria, Rwanda, Uganda,&#13;
Haiti: NFC RFID Safe                                                                   cSomalia, Zimbabwe, South&#13;
Water Tracking                                                                                                      Africa, SaudiArabia, Pakistan,&#13;
Afghanistan, Bangladesh, Nepal,&#13;
Senegal: mSchool,                                                                                                   Butan: Global Handwashing Day,&#13;
mSludge, Senegalaise                                                                                                SMS, M-Pesa, Text to Change&#13;
des Eau (SDE),&#13;
Supervision Cockpit                                                                                                 India: NextDrop&#13;
enya, Zambia: Smart                                                                                        J     Indonesia: Global Scaling Up&#13;
Water Systems, Smart, Rural Sanitation&#13;
HandpumpsR&#13;
South Africa, Mozambique,&#13;
enya, Nairobi: Cambodia, Vietnam: Water&#13;
M-Maji, Jisomee Mita, aQuality Reporter&#13;
Maji Voice, Maji SMS,                                                                                               SuhArc:DoDo&#13;
MaJiDataSouth Africa: DropDrop&#13;
Tanzania: MajiMatone (Raising the  Worldwide: including Dominican Republic,  Kenya, Chad, Sudan: WATEX  Senegal, Benin, Mali, Niger: mWater,&#13;
Water Pressure), Human Senor Web  El Salvador Honduras, Guatemala,      Kenya, Uganda: Field Level   Uganda: Mobiles 4 Water (M4W), NWSC: E-Water&#13;
(H2.0), mWater                    Nicaragua, Ecuador Peru, Liberia, Burkina  Operations (FLOW)       Payment and Call Centre&#13;
Tanzania, Uganda, Ghana: Taarifa  Faso, Malawi&#13;
Field Level Operations Watch (FLOW),&#13;
Water Point Mapper&#13;
(Source: Revised fom original source of Hutchings &amp;Dev, 2012)&#13;
" Liberia was not physically visited by the team as a result of the Ebola outbreak that&#13;
occurred over the study period. Instead interviews with key sector stakeholders were&#13;
done via phone and Skype.&#13;
www.wsp.org                                                                                                                                     7&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Unlocking the Potential of Information Communications Technology to Improve Water and Sanitation Services | Landscape Analysis and Findings of the Study&#13;
Initial applications are showing how    ICTs can further        02 (b): Promoting Improved Service Delivery&#13;
WASH     goals and   priorities. While the ICT     WASH         Even more vital than increasing access to WASH services&#13;
applications presented in the reports are diverse, they can     is ensuring that access is sustained. Monitoring of service&#13;
be summarized according to three main WASH         priority     provision, in terms of functionality, timely and adequate&#13;
areas: increasing access, improving service delivery and        water supply, water quality and water use management is&#13;
improving governance.                                           crucial in ensuring that coverage indicators are giving a true&#13;
picture of improved access.&#13;
C2 (a): Increasing Access to Water and Sanitation&#13;
Services                                               ICTs can offer timely and improved access to information.&#13;
Increasing access to improved water sources and sanitation      On the consumption side, ICTs can empower under-&#13;
is a key global priority recognized      as MDG     Target      served communities with better information about water&#13;
7.C: Halve, by 2015, the proportion of the population           availability, price and quality (M-Maji). Accurate water&#13;
without sustainable access to safe drinking water and basic     timing information can reduce long waits, lost workdays&#13;
sanitation.                                                     and allow individuals to effectively plan their water usage,&#13;
as is the case with Next Drop. On the supply side, improved&#13;
The first key challenge in increasing access to water and       access to information can improve water management, allow&#13;
sanitation services is the possession of accurate data on       for real time monitoring of functionality and supply (Smart&#13;
coverage and functionality. Inventorying the current levels     Handpumps), reduce repair response time (Maji Matone),&#13;
of infrastructure, creating baselines, identifying areas where  improve water quality     through   monitoring, tracking,&#13;
interventions/resources are required and demonstrating          identifying patterns in contamination and communication&#13;
progress are all dependent on data collection, monitoring,      to consumers (USAID's mWater).&#13;
presentation and analysis. Although multiple manual&#13;
and automated options exist to verify data, ICT projects,       At the utility level, ICTs can improve daily operations and&#13;
especially mobile phone applications, have the potential to     result in efficiencies: time and financial savings, decreased&#13;
improve the quality and quantity of data that is collected in   transportation, payment transactions and administrative&#13;
the long term. They can make data transfer more efficient,      costs, improved financial management, increased revenue&#13;
reduce manual data errors, and increase the frequency of        collection and improved customer management. ICTs&#13;
monitoring due to their relative cost-effectiveness.            also offer the possibility of more flexible payment models&#13;
contingent on service delivery.&#13;
Using ICTs to support mapping and monitoring of&#13;
infrastructure, such as Water Point Mapping, can facilitate     02 (c): Improved Governance in the WASH Sector&#13;
mobilization, planning and allocation of resources in the       The water sector is facing     a number of governance&#13;
WASH     sector. Depending on the interface, ICTs can           challenges where mobile services can make a difference,&#13;
also present the data visually to highlight equity issues,      especially  when  it comes to     increasing  transparency,&#13;
support allocation of resources to deliver services where       accountability and participation.15 Rogers &amp; Hall" define&#13;
they are most needed, measure performance and progress,         water and sanitation governance as the range of political,&#13;
indicate the distance to the nearest improved water source      social, economic and administrative systems that are in&#13;
and promote increased investment in the sector. ICTs can        place to develop and manage water resources, and the&#13;
also be used to identify new sources of water, as is the case   delivery of these services, at different levels of society.&#13;
with WATEX, a groundwater exploration system that uses&#13;
remote sensing technologies to locate renewable ground&#13;
water reserves in arid and semi-arid environments.               5 Hellstrom J., Jaboson M., 2014: 'You can cheat the community anymore' using&#13;
mobiles to improve water governance. In . Niang &amp; C. SHaff, eds. Proceedings of the&#13;
4p' International conftrence on M4 Mobile Communicationfor Development Dakar,&#13;
Senegal pp 48- 59&#13;
c Rogers P, Hall AW, 2003: "Effective Water Governance, available at http:/tdlc.&#13;
dlib.indiana.edudlc/bitsream/handle/ I 0535w4995TECs25207.pdsequence= 1&#13;
8&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Unlocking the Potential of Information Communications Technology to Improve Water and Sanitation Services Landscape Analysis and Findings of the Study&#13;
ICTs are becoming a dominant force in the way utility       the long-term, and also that the data collected are accessed&#13;
providers and customers communicate. ICTs can also be       and used by the audiences for which it was intended. Key&#13;
used to encourage citizens to voice their concerns and put  principles under the first themes are: build the user base&#13;
pressure on the local government to address problems with   with well-planned outreach, ensure the system is easy to use,&#13;
their water and sanitation services, increasing government  fulfil a key need (monetary incentives are not necessary) and&#13;
accountability and empowering citizens. ICTs can be used    effectively manage data and demand for data by verifying&#13;
to create a system of transparency and accountability, to   quality, implementing and promoting user access to the&#13;
promote public participation and collaboration amongst      data, shifting focus from data collection and monitoring&#13;
stakeholders in the WASH sector, to improve monitoring      to reporting and analysis and ensuring service providers!&#13;
and management of WASH projects, and reduce the cost        government agencies respond to generated reports.&#13;
of access to information and service delivery. Improving&#13;
ICT usage at the local level enhances and supports socio-   03 (b): Choice of Technology&#13;
economic   development by     empowering    community       Technical design, which refers to the appropriateness&#13;
leaders to provide timely, efficient, transparent and       of the technology platform  to meet information needs,&#13;
accountable services.                                       is the second key aspect to be taken into consideration.&#13;
The technological appropriateness and flexibility of the&#13;
C3: Lessons Learnt from         ICT use within the          ICT application should be informed by the surroundings&#13;
WASH Sector                                            (technological as well as socio-cultural, political, legal,&#13;
The global WASH sector is experiencing heightened ICT       economic, and environmental) in which it is to be utilized&#13;
interventions, but the low sustainability rate combined     along with the specific purpose of its application.&#13;
with the high frequency of failure in scaling applications&#13;
beyond the pilot phase is a matter a great concern. All ICT  Key findings to be kept in mind regarding the choice&#13;
applications are driven by the desire to bring about change  of technology include: the fact that SMS-based mobile&#13;
to their areas of implementation. However, with reliability  systems offer the potential for universal use as opposed&#13;
and cost-effectiveness of the WASH sector still hampered    to applications specifically tailored to feature phones or&#13;
by poverty, weak institutions and poor infrastructure, it   smartphones with limited penetration rates. Submission&#13;
must be understood that incorporating ICT solutions in      of data through SMS is shown to be the preferred&#13;
the water and sanitation sector is not a 'magic pill', but  method, especially when workers and customers act as&#13;
rather ICTs should be viewed as strategic research and      the data reporters; yet structured and unstructured SMS&#13;
development tools that must be used in tandem      with     applications have limitations in comparison to form-&#13;
traditional sector approaches.                              based applications, which improve data accuracy. Web-&#13;
based dashboards are the preferred method for end-user&#13;
The Desk Review: Experience ofICT use in the WASH Sector,   reporting and interfaces; web-based mapping allows for&#13;
involved conducting a survey of ICT applications in the     visualization of reports, but maps may prove more useful&#13;
WASH sector." The key principles for sustainability that    to utilities and organizations than to individual users.&#13;
came out of the desk review are summarized below.           Data formats will be dependent on user needs; and finally&#13;
dissemination of data back through the mobile phone&#13;
C3 (a): User-Centered Design, Participation and             was noted as the most accessible method for users, but it&#13;
Experience                                          restricts the way and the amount of information that can&#13;
Social design involves deciding how to recruit and engage   be sent and displayed depending on the type of receiving&#13;
users to ensure the system is scalable and sustainable in   phone. Beyond understanding the benefits and limitations&#13;
of the various data collection methods, local capacity,&#13;
SMisuraca, G., 2007. E-Governance in Africa, from theory to action: a handbook on both human and infrastructure, must also be taken into&#13;
ICTs for local governance, Trenton, NJ: Africa World Press   consideration in the design of the application.&#13;
" See Annex 2 for a detailed list and summary of the applications included in the&#13;
desk review.&#13;
www.wsp.org                                                                                                          9&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Unlocking the Potential of Information Communications Technology to Improve Water and Sanitation Services I Landscape Analysis and Findings of the Study&#13;
C3 (c): Finance and Program Design                           C4: Identification of Key Thematic Areas for&#13;
The final aspect - program design - necessitates an effective     the Sustainable Use of ICT in WASH&#13;
support structure for longevity and sustainability of       The aim of both the Desk Review and Case Studies report was to&#13;
the application. There is a need for effective design of    assess the successes achieved and the challenges faced by ICTs&#13;
the supporting program that ensures the system   can be     currently in play in the global WASH sector and highlight key&#13;
sustained and updated in response to the changing needs of  principles upon which successful sustainability and scalabiity&#13;
its users as technology evolves and improves.               models can be constructed. Key findings are presented below,&#13;
grouped under the following eight major themes:&#13;
Financial sustainability is key. Various methods of funding      1. Using ICTs to strengthen monitoring and&#13;
emerged in the survey applications. Heavy reliance on               inventory of infrastructure.&#13;
external donor agencies was the most common, while other        2. Sustaining ICT-based planning and programming&#13;
less common methods included government support, co-                initiatives.&#13;
funding by stakeholder agencies and internal funds from          3. ICT and operational efficiency improvements.&#13;
parent organizations. Initial funding and investments for       4. ICT and service delivery improvements.&#13;
applications are often time-bound and long-term funding              (particularly to the poor).&#13;
needs to be sought to determine how the system      will         5. ICT to strengthen the consumer voice.&#13;
continuously survive and evolve beyond the initial pilot         6. ICT and governance.&#13;
stage. Financial sustainability can also be supported with      7. Financing of ICTs.&#13;
strategies such as ensuring key user stakeholders invest in      8. Public-Private Partnerships.&#13;
maintaining the project (NGOs, local governments, civil&#13;
society) or leveraging technical partners to relieve some ofthe  Theme 1: Using ICT to Strengthen Monitoring and&#13;
burden of developing, acquiring, and maintaining software              Inventory of Infrastructure&#13;
or hardware. For most applications to succeed, structured   The first key challenge in increasing access to water and&#13;
collaboration  from  different stakeholders is required.    sanitation services is the possession of accurate data on&#13;
Stakeholders can include the government, community and      coverage and functionality. Inventorying current levels of&#13;
private institutions, such as service providers and telecoms  infrastructure, creating baselines, identifying areas where&#13;
to provide affordable rates for running of the applications  intervention/resources are required and demonstrating&#13;
or even cost sharing of the project for it to remain        progress all rely on data collection, monitoring, presentation&#13;
sustainable for the users. Finally, short and long-term     and analysis. While multiple manual and automated&#13;
indicators of success need to be identified and measured.   options exist to verify data, ICT   initiatives, especially&#13;
The data collected should then be used to refine system      mobile phone applications, have the potential to improve&#13;
design. The surveyed projects used a variety of metrics to  the quality and quantity of data collected in the long-&#13;
measure the effectiveness of their applications, but few were  term. They can help to make data transfer more efficient,&#13;
comprehensive enough to understand how their design and     reduce manual data errors, and increase the frequency of&#13;
implementation choices impacted success.                    monitoring due to relative cost effectiveness. Accurate data&#13;
and information management systems are a precursor for&#13;
sound management and decision-support systems.&#13;
10&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Unlocking the Potential of Information Communications Technology to Improve Water and Sanitation Services Landscape Analysis and Findings of the Study&#13;
FLOW is an open source mapping software used for data collection and monitoring of the functionality of water&#13;
access points.19 It was developed by Water for People (WfP) and in 2012 Akvo Foundation took over and continued&#13;
development of FLOW. The software runs on Android platforms (smartphone), and allows users to take GPS&#13;
coordinates, fill out text, take pictures and videos, and fill out questionnaires. This information is then translated to&#13;
Google Earth data and plotted on online maps. FLOW can be used in areas where there is no Internet connectivity.&#13;
However, when there is internet connectivity, the software automatically transmits the data to the central database&#13;
and uploads it to Google Earth.20&#13;
WfP implemented FLOW in a number of countries and thousands of water points were included in the database.21&#13;
The countries include Malawi, Rwanda, Uganda, Congo, India, Dominican Republic, Honduras, Guatemala,&#13;
Nicaragua, Ecuador, Bolivia, Peru, Liberia, Nepal, Burkina Faso and Mozambique.22&#13;
In Liberia, the use of FLOW achieved the following results:&#13;
*   Over 10,000 water points mapped in less than&#13;
6 months in 2011.&#13;
akvo                   0&#13;
*   A   national WASH      sector investment plan&#13;
(USD400 million from 2012 to 2017) identified.&#13;
Lessons    learnt  from    the  data    collection  phase                                *&#13;
included:23&#13;
*   Absence of good road infrastructure led to extra                                                  9&#13;
costs for transportation of mapping teams.&#13;
*   The lack of electricity made it necessary to                          a&#13;
purchase external battery adapters for the                    E opa&#13;
FLOW devices.&#13;
*   Absence of mobile phone network coverage&#13;
and high costs of mobile data transfer made it&#13;
necessary to use physical data collection.&#13;
Source: http.//flow.readthedocs.org/en//atest/docs/dashboard/6-maps.&#13;
htm/#navigating-the-map&#13;
Using   ICTs to    support mapping     and   monitoring   of      percent less than the paper-based survey average, and the&#13;
infrastructure can  facilitate mobilization, planning and         average time per interview question for the tablet-based&#13;
allocation of resources in the WASH sector. A recent paper24      survey was 46 percent less than the paper-based survey&#13;
compared a tablet- and paper-based survey in Africa and           average".&#13;
found that costs per completed tablet interview were "74&#13;
" https://www.engineeringforchange.org/news/2011/01/22/how_flow_can_change 2 http://www.waterforpeople.org/what-we-do/#flow&#13;
development_work.html                                             22 http://www.waterforpeople.org/what-we-do/#flow&#13;
2' Hellstrim, J., &amp; Jacobson, M. (2014). "You Cant Cheat the Community  http://akvo.og/bog/using-akvoflow-in-liberia/&#13;
Anymore'-Using Mobiles to Improve Water Governance. In of 4th International&#13;
Conference on M4D Mobile Communication for Development (pp. 48-59). Dakar,   http://www.mdpi.com/2076-0760/3/2/264&#13;
Senegal. Retrieved fromhttp://www.divaportal.org/smash/get/diva2:709233/FULL-&#13;
TEXTO2.pdf#page=51&#13;
www.wsp.org&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Unlocking the Potential of Information Communications Technology to Improve Water and Sanitation Services | Landscape Analysis and Findings of the Study&#13;
Another recent 2013 study25 analysed the use of mobile-                  experienced paper based data recorders". In their mobile-to-&#13;
to-web surveying for a survey of 12,000 households and                   web data collection in Liberia and Sierra Leone, WSP found&#13;
confirmed that it "saved time, was less costly, was at least             that eliminating post-survey transcription alone saved up to&#13;
as accurate as standard paper-based questionnaires [more                 5.7 percent of project costs and over 600 workdays, which&#13;
accurate   for GPS     coordinates], and      was preferred     by       was more than offsetting hardware and software costs.&#13;
NF   Phne  fo  Wae      PuiiainTak -               Hat&#13;
Near-Field Communication (NFC) phones with Radio-Frequency Identification (RFID) is an application that supports&#13;
the monitoring of water purification in Haiti. Programmed NFC phones are used by Haitian water technicians to&#13;
support the tracking of chlorine levels in thousands of households through RFID tags on the drinking water buckets&#13;
in homes.&#13;
The NFC tags augment an existing socio-technical system for providing clean water to households throughout Haiti.&#13;
Community Health Workers (CHWs) visit households approximately once per month and conduct a test for residual&#13;
chlorine in stored water. Prior to the NFC and SMS-based questionnaires, paper-based forms were used and it was&#13;
difficult to establish a regular electronic data entry program. As the CHWs were often in the field for long periods&#13;
of time, the data entry was delayed to the point of rendering the data irrelevant. Use of NFC phones facilitated the&#13;
real-time submission of data.&#13;
Haiti had difficulty supplying clean drinking water to more than 9.7 million inhabitants, a situation was compounded&#13;
by devastating earthquakes and a cholera outbreak in 2010, which claimed thousands of lives.26,27 The mountainous&#13;
terrain coupled with poor transportation and communications networks made it challenging to supply clean drinking&#13;
water. Without regular household visits, the population reverted to drinking unclean water, which resulted in cholera&#13;
outbreaks and other diarrhoeal infections.28&#13;
The project was a collaboration between an industrial research lab (Nokia Research Center, Palo Alto), the Public&#13;
Health School of University of Carolina Berkeley, and Deep Springs International (DSI), a non-profit organization in&#13;
Haiti.29 Through NFC and SMS-based questionnaires, technicians spend less time collecting data and more time&#13;
visiting houses, ensuring that more households have clean water.30 Over 35,000 families in Haiti were reached and&#13;
incidences of diarrhoea among users were reduced by about 50 percent.31&#13;
In post-disaster environments left with a fragile or non-existent infrastructure, NFC technology was a fast and&#13;
cost-effective way of improving water supply and maintenance.32 However, the project faced challenges linked to&#13;
sustainability and scaling up, including:&#13;
*    High costs of battery charging.&#13;
*    Inability to find additional low-end NFC phones.&#13;
*    Resource constraints.&#13;
*    Lack of a centralized accounting scheme.&#13;
25 http://goo.gl/AspdvR&#13;
26 Brown, C. (2011). NFC phones help provide clean water to Haiti earthquake victims. Retrieved September 20, 2014, from http://www.nfcworld.com/2011/03/1 1/36414/nfc-&#13;
phones-help-provide-clean-water-to-haiti-earthquake-victims/&#13;
27 Greenemeier, L. (2011). Aqua Plan: Could Cell Phones Help Aid Workers Ensure Haiti's Supply of Clean Drinking Water? Retrieved September 20, 2014, from http://www.&#13;
scientificamerican.com/article/haiti-cholera-clean-water-chlorine/&#13;
28 Ittp://www.upm.com/EN/MEDIA/All-news/Pages/Battling-cholera-with-NFC-RFID-tracked-drinking-water-in-Haiti.aspx&#13;
29 Kaye, J., Holstius, D., &amp; Seto, E. (2012). Using NFC phones to track water purification in Haiti. CHI'12, 677-689. Retrieved from http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2212839&#13;
3o Harris, J. (2010). Mobile phones are a valuable tool all over the world. Retrieved September 21, 2014, from http://conversations.nokia.com/201 1/08/10/innovative-mobile-&#13;
applications-for-healthcare/&#13;
31 http://thesmartsense.com/22574&#13;
32 http://www.nfctags.com/nfc-templates/story-detail.php?id=9&#13;
12&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Unlocking the Potential of Information Communications Technology to Improve Water and Sanitation Services Landscape Analysis and Findings of the Study&#13;
Specifically ICTs can:                                       *   Indicate the distance required to the nearest&#13;
*   Measure performance and progress.                        improved water source.&#13;
*   Identify marginalized areas and present data          *  Identify advocacy themes.&#13;
visually to highlight equity issues.                  *   Prioritize intervention areas and better target&#13;
*   Improved governance achieved through availability        available and limited resources.&#13;
of reliable data and knowledge of actual customer     *   Improve the quality and evaluation of funding&#13;
base.                                                     proposals.&#13;
*   Allow improved access to information by               *  Promote increased investment in the sector. All of&#13;
stakeholders for improved planning and decision           which can translate into more people served.&#13;
making.                                               *   Quantify actual levels of service needs.&#13;
*   Design improvement strategies.                        *  Monitor water quality.&#13;
mWater~ - Seea,Ml,Nie       *n  ei&#13;
mWater is a mobile-to-web based application for consumers and water service providers (WSPs) developed as a&#13;
response to monitoring challenges for the growing number of small-scale water schemes in rural areas and small&#13;
towns. The application aims to provide water service providers with the ability to remotely control water service&#13;
delivery and also improve the management of water usage, daily operations as well as the maintenance of the network.&#13;
As of June 2013, mWater was active in 252 water systems in Senegal, Mali, Niger and Benin.33,34&#13;
*   246,900 people served in Niger and 415,900 people served in Mali under the mWater platform, which&#13;
provides an ICT design structure in which mobile phone applications and web services are developed to&#13;
support the life cycle of water supply systems, from construction (inventory and cartography) to operation&#13;
(data collection, technical and financial management) and performance benchmarking.&#13;
*   In Benin, the use of mWater resulted in new drawings of assets and water networks for 51 rural water point&#13;
schemes.&#13;
*   In Senegal, mWater has supported the mapping of 70 percent of existing water schemes (over 28,000&#13;
water points).&#13;
" http://programme20 13.worldwaterweek.0rg/sites/defaul/files/fadelsockholm_201I3_ict and water_governance_fadel_ndaw_september_4.pdf&#13;
'"https://www.wsp.org/sites/wsp.org/files/publications/Presentation-Presenter-Daniel-Annerose.pdf&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Unlocking the Potential of Information Communications Technology to Improve Water and Sanitation Services | Landscape Analysis and Findings of the Study&#13;
Theme 2: Sustaining ICT-Based Planning and Programming Initiatives&#13;
Rua  Saiato Moniorin Syse- Idsia35&#13;
In 2009, with the support of the World Bank's Water and Sanitation Program (WSP), the Ministry of Health conducted&#13;
a pilot study to monitor rural sanitation in two districts in East Java using a mobile phone short message service&#13;
(SMS) text-monitoring (mobile monitoring) system. Information on the community's progress towards becoming&#13;
open defecation free (ODF) and changes in households' access to improved sanitation was collected and sent via&#13;
SMS and stored in a district-level database.&#13;
Based on the success of the pilot, in 2012 the mobile monitoring system was rolled out to all 119 districts and cities&#13;
in five of the country's provinces, covering approximately 36 million households and 123 million individuals. The&#13;
current rollout plan aims to reach all 500 districts in 34 provinces in the country by December 2015.&#13;
As of August 2014:&#13;
*   3,787 of the 10,559 health center sanitarians in the country had sent village sanitation data via SMS.&#13;
*   800 to 1,000 messages per month were received by the central server.&#13;
*   50,850 messages with data were collected.&#13;
*   Data for 20 provinces, including 40,470 villages and 42.9 million households, had been uploaded into the&#13;
mobile monitoring system&#13;
Summary of Progress for the Province of Central Java by Type of Access&#13;
Graftik Summar Krajuan&#13;
PROV JAWA TENGAH&#13;
6M&#13;
5M&#13;
4M&#13;
E&#13;
IM&#13;
Jamban Sehat Perrmanen  Jernbn Sehst Srni  Shring   Open Defecation&#13;
(PennianEl healttlet}  Pemrnaren (Seni-&#13;
Permanent healhylilet)&#13;
Ba:A ina E FraTrs e&#13;
Key lessons learnt:&#13;
*  A structured approached, which allows for adjustments and improvements, is needed in order for real-time&#13;
village data mobile monitoring to scale up.&#13;
*  A national harmonized approached to rural sanitation, with sector-wide objectives and monitoring framework,&#13;
is necessary for scaling up data collection.&#13;
*   It is possible to increase the use of the monitoring tool as a programming tool by establishing feedback&#13;
loops, additional data management tools and communication channels to reach target users.&#13;
*  To increase the use of the monitoring system as a management tool for programming, feedback loop, a larger&#13;
set of customized data information tools, and channels to reach specific target users could be explored.&#13;
Scaling Up Indonesias Rural Sanitation Mobile Monitoring System Nationally. Water and Sanitation Program: Learning Note, 2014.&#13;
14&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Unlocking the Potential of Information Communications Technology to Improve Water and Sanitation Services Landscape Analysis and Findings of the Study&#13;
In order to ensure reliable planning data is obtained&#13;
and used, a few   key elements should be taken into&#13;
consideration:&#13;
*   Even with ICTs offering relative cost-effectiveness,  The Government of India has invested heavily in&#13;
the costs associated with data collection remain      programs to achieve universal sanitation coverage. To&#13;
substantial. All information management initiatives   ensure investments in sanitation lead to commensurate&#13;
need to therefore be adequately planned for and       otoring syste&#13;
well resourced.&#13;
*   A participatory design stage and/or involving key    To test the viability of using mobile technology to&#13;
sector players early in the development of the        strengthen monitoring in the rural sanitation sector,&#13;
initiative can contribute to early adoption because of  a proof of concept was piloted by WSP, through a&#13;
the perceived relevance of the data to be provided. If  company involved in technology for development&#13;
key stakeholders are able to define their requirements,  Oevarn  socio-economic characr    istilt&#13;
this will facilitate meaningful use of the data and    oj    c    eo23,000   heholdsi a spn ot&#13;
confidence in planning and resource allocation.      to thre   e onths.&#13;
*   Agreeing upon selected indicators and standard&#13;
national definitions with sector players is important  This proof of concept demonstrated that:&#13;
in ensuring the use of the data, inter-operability,     *   Using smartphones can provide quick, credible&#13;
long-term funding and sustainability. For example,         information on sector outcomes in near real time,&#13;
a project-funded initiative collecting data using a         unlike that provided by conventional surveys.&#13;
different definition of coverage than the government    *   Features such as geo-tagging and photographs&#13;
would be of little use in terms of national planning.       of respondents ensure that results are more&#13;
*   Less inter-operability, ease of use and ease of data        credible and relevant.&#13;
extraction and analysis will translate into less use of  *  Presentation of data is user-friendly and maps&#13;
the data. Furthermore, data extraction will be time-        enable a viewer to grasp the status of rural&#13;
consuming and the quality and ownership of the              sanitation in a geographical unit at a glance.&#13;
data can be compromised.                                *   The process can be replicated on a large scale&#13;
*   In contrast, facilitating the use of the database           and at periodic intervals, to address the gaps in&#13;
or platform  by external actors, improving user             the monitoring of usage of sanitation facilities in&#13;
rights and allowing analysis within the database            rural areas.&#13;
or application will encourage the use of the data.&#13;
Increasing linkages increases the value of the data,&#13;
which in turn will encourage resource allocation in&#13;
the future.                                                 Project-based initiatives can also limit the integration&#13;
*   Project-based funding can result in data collection        process, due to the choice of the hosting institution,&#13;
largely being driven by the availability of funding         the limited scope of indicators, differing indicator&#13;
from  the stakeholders who require the data.                definitions or limited data collection, both spatially&#13;
Working with short-term funding can result in data          and time-wise.&#13;
quickly becoming outdated. Ideally, planning and            Data and consequently management information&#13;
programming data collection initiatives should be           systems (MIS) are decision support tools, as such,&#13;
integrated into the government's annual budget             the quality of data will have a direct correlation with&#13;
or if donor funding is required, a basket funding           any decision made. Data verification mechanisms&#13;
approach is appropriate,                                    need to be put in place to ensure reliability and&#13;
confidence in the data.&#13;
36 Kumar, C. Ajith and Singh, Upneet. You Manage whatyou Measure: Using Mobile&#13;
Phones to Strengthen Outcome Monitoring in rural Sanitation, New Delhi, India: Water&#13;
and Sanitation Program, 2012.&#13;
www.wfp.org                                                                                                        15&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Unlocking the Potential of Information Communications Technology to Improve Water and Sanitation Services I Landscape Analysis and Findings of the Study&#13;
Theme 3: ICT and Operational Efficiency               Monitoring of Service Provision: Efficiency gains as a&#13;
Improvements                                result of improved monitoring and service provision include&#13;
Urban utilities have been recording significant successes in  a shorter response time, reduction in travel distance,&#13;
the implementation of ICTs. The relatively rapid acceptance  reduction in maintenance costs, operations optimization&#13;
and adoption of these tools at the urban utility level can, in  (reduction of production costs, improved energy efficiency)&#13;
part, be attributed to the efficiency gains and cost savings  and improved quality of service.&#13;
being achieved. ICTs have recorded efficiency gains in the&#13;
following key operational areas.                     The remote control of water service delivery can improve&#13;
the management of water usage, daily operations and the&#13;
maintenance of the network. Next Drop's Live Valve Map&#13;
aDE (            D   E    S          Cockpit* -     system displays the status of water delivery in every part of&#13;
athe city. The customized dashboard helps the local utility to&#13;
s       ne    e      es             ve      te      manage staff and infrastructure. Engineers monitor progress&#13;
San dSeonexri                         t          on an internal dashboard, which provides information on&#13;
companythat manages the production                  valve activity and potential diversions due to power and&#13;
SDEf mrninajor fo iSeonequality 5ade quany ofewter,. infrastructure issues. Next Drop has helped utility companies&#13;
maintenance of the supply network, efficient billing  advleaet omng         h   vr   n   ne-upyo&#13;
and recovery, and customer relations management. In water through analysis of the collected data."8&#13;
a bid to improve customer relations and satisfaction&#13;
using  new  technologies, SDE   developed   the      Smr Wae Meer (SM) Ditrc of CoubaS&#13;
Supervision Cockpit for network interventions.       SWM    is experiencing strong growth throughout'&#13;
The cockpit was set up with the following objectives:  the industrialized world mainly in Europe and North&#13;
* To respond to customer complaints on time.       America, with annual growth projections varying&#13;
* To restore services quickly in case of           between 8 percent and 13 percent until 2016.&#13;
interruptions.&#13;
* To increase productivity and reduce water        te f   -  ork    a    tem    ipleent by&#13;
losses.&#13;
* To monitor quality of service rendered to the    2002 is a good example of the possible dividends&#13;
customers.                                      that a smart water metering intervention can yield.&#13;
Reported benefits included reductions in non-revenue&#13;
The Supervision Cockpit includes a modern            water (36 percent to 22 percent), increase in revenue&#13;
call center, a computer platform that supports       by 7 percent (through debt reduction), reduction in&#13;
geolocations using GPS/GSM, a direct consultation    meter reading costs (USD4.15 per meter to &lt;USD1),&#13;
inventory and a computerized mapping system          reduction in costs relating to the investigation of&#13;
(installed in vehicles).                             complaints (50 percent lower) and customer call&#13;
The establishment of the Supervision Cockpit has     center services (36 percent lower), 20 less field&#13;
contributed to:                                      vehicles required, and 106,000 liters of fuel saved&#13;
* An increase in network efficiency in areas       every year.39&#13;
of reduced leakages, metering and billing&#13;
improvements.                                  Billing and Payment: The most common ICTs adopted&#13;
* Improved customer relations by proving a toll   by utilities are e-payment systems offering payment&#13;
free number that is used to lodge complaints   facilitation, increased reliability in billing and payment&#13;
and request for services.                      recovery, reduced administrative and payment transaction&#13;
" Morazin, M. (2012). Measuring the Impact of NextDrops Services on Utility Compa-&#13;
ries in India (pp. 1-39). Hubli, India. Retrieved from http:/rael.berkeley.edusites/&#13;
default/files/MelissaMorazan inal APAt 5.i.2012.pdf&#13;
31 O1                                                  Hope, R., Foster, T, Krolikowski, A., &amp; Cohen, . (2011). Mobile water payments&#13;
in urban Africa: Adoption, implications, and opportunities (p. 35). UK.&#13;
16&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Unlocking the Potential of Information Communications Technology to Improve Water and Sanitation Services Landscape Analysis and Findings of the Study&#13;
costs and improved revenue collection. Further advances in  and timeliness of provision. Further, a major advantage&#13;
technology offer the potential to combine mobile banking    touted for the use of ICTs for development is the means&#13;
and smart water metering, with a secure, transparent        to reach poor, underserved communities. Mobile phones&#13;
and low-cost flow of funds and information between the      are particularly well-placed to serve the development&#13;
consumer, water service provider and delivery system.40     needs of the poorest and most vulnerable populations&#13;
because they represent a widespread and relatively low-cost&#13;
M-eawtrpet -           Kimmi Key                   communication option for rapid information transfer and&#13;
service facilitation whilst eliminating prevalent issues of&#13;
The Kiamumbi Water Trust (KWT) established an              distance and time. Mobile phones are also more affordable&#13;
M-Pesa pay bill system in December 2010, enabling          and accessible to users across socio-economic levels.4' In&#13;
550 households to settle their monthly water bills via&#13;
the mobile phone. Demand for this option arose due         Arate       nMbe    op    leitin rGe ofga G         as&#13;
to the inconvenience and costs associated with the         System  ortMobile Comunication          witM  sn     has&#13;
traditional mode of water bill payment. Due to security    arad  y vertaken  the number of  ole itsanipoe&#13;
issues, KWT could not accept cash payments on their                                                              42&#13;
premises, customers had to settle their bills at the       is twice the number of individual pipedwater connections.&#13;
nearest bank - an undertaking involving a 40-minute&#13;
round trip costing USDO.50 and the opportunity cost        i.  Potential Benefits    of lCTs    for  Low-income,&#13;
of waiting for around one hour in a bank queue. A final        Underserved Communities:&#13;
trip would then be made to deposit the bank slip at                 Increased  coverage  as a result of mapping&#13;
the KWT offices, for a receipt to be issued, and the                initiatives:&#13;
amount manually entered into a billing database. In the                o Identification of additional sources.&#13;
first month, 42 percent of customers had transitioned                  o Reliable knowledge of actual customer base&#13;
to the mobile payment channel, rising to 59 percent                       and needs based on accurate data.&#13;
by the fourth month.                                                Improved mapping and monitoring initiatives can&#13;
rapidly and accurately identify, marginalized areas&#13;
and present data visually to highlight equity issues&#13;
Challenges                                                           and prioritize intervention in these areas.&#13;
Challenges   in    maximizing    operational   efficiency            Empower under-served communities with better&#13;
improvements that have been specifically highlighted by              information:&#13;
utilities include:                                                      o On water availability, price, and quality as&#13;
*   Lack of integration between different ICT systems                  shown in the case of M-Maji.&#13;
being used in different parts of their business.                o On water timing information to reduce long&#13;
*   High development costs.                                            waits, lost workdays and allow individuals&#13;
*   Large investments needed for expansions/scale-up.                  to effectively plan their water usage, as is the&#13;
*   Poor Internet connection and low     quality of                    case with NextDrop.&#13;
telecommunications service.                                  Increased functionality, through:&#13;
*   Lack of consistent electrical supply.                           o Improving ease and efficiency in reporting&#13;
*   Heavy staff training requirements.                                 faults of water sources.&#13;
oReducing the down-time of water sources&#13;
Theme 4: ICT and Service Delivery Improvements                             that are reported as non-functional.&#13;
(Particularly to the Poor)                                    0 Providing real time information on the&#13;
ICT   applications offer improved   service delivery by                    functionality status of water sources.&#13;
simplify,ing the process and facilitating the efficiency, speed,&#13;
simpifyng he rocss ad fciltatng he eficenc, seed  41Rashid, A. T, &amp; Elder, L. (2009). Mobile Phones and Development:, 1- 16.&#13;
Retrieved from http://www.ejisdc.org/ojs2/index.php/ejisdc/artidle/viewFile/529/265&#13;
0 Hope, R., Foster, T., Krolikowski, A., &amp; Cohen, I. (2011). Mobile water payments  12 Hope, R., Foster, T, Krolikowski, A. &amp; Cohen, 1. (2011). Mobile water payments&#13;
in urban Africa: Adoption, implications, and opportunities (p. 35). UK.  in urban Afeica: Adoption, implications, and opportunities (p. 35). UK.&#13;
17&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Unlocking the Potential of Information Communications Technology to Improve Water and Sanitation Services | Landscape Analysis and Findings of the Study&#13;
o  Offering utilities/agencies insight into the                *   Increased     flexibility   and     affordability    of&#13;
issues that affect functionality      of water                  e-payment systems responds to the low and often&#13;
sources, especially in rural areas.                             unpredictable incomes of the poor;&#13;
*    Improved monitoring through measurement and                       *    Reduced costs for utilities in operating non-core&#13;
tracking of performance.                                               activities (such as revenue collection) translate&#13;
*    Improved     customer    relations   (and   customer                   into increased revenues re-invested in the core-&#13;
confidence     in   the    utility/agency)    through                  functions of the utility, for example core staff and&#13;
increased transparency, provision of information                       infrastructure development.&#13;
and response to complaints.                                       *    The ease and      decreased   costs associated    with&#13;
*    Promotion of price competitiveness (M-Maji and                         e-payment systems also encourages utilities to&#13;
M-Sludge) increases the affordability of water and                     invest in poor and traditionally underserved areas;&#13;
sanitation services;                                                   this has been the case with the Nairobi City Water&#13;
and Sewerage Company (NCWSC) and the&#13;
fisomee Mita initiative in Nairobi.&#13;
NextDrop leverages the recent proliferation of mobile phones in India to provide households with accurate and&#13;
timely information about local piped water delivery, while also enabling water utilities to access real-time information&#13;
about the status of their distribution system. NextDrop sources this information from water consumers who send&#13;
SMS notifications when water begins flowing in their area, NextDrop in turn notifies residents in the same locality&#13;
of the current delivery of water.43 The project is built on the idea of collecting and sharing data as well as engaging&#13;
communities to advocate for more equitable distribution. NextDrop's Live Valve Map system displays the status&#13;
of water delivery in every part of the city. The customized dashboard helps the local utility to manage staff and&#13;
infrastructure. Engineers monitor progress on an internal dashboard, which provides information on valve activity,&#13;
potential diversions due to power and infrastructure issues.&#13;
NextDrop was launched in July 2010, with the first pilot project recruiting over 180 families in five valve areas to&#13;
provide information and receive free updates in Hubli-Dharwad, Karnataka State, India.44 The application provided&#13;
messages to households every week about the status               An example of an SMS from NextDrop sent to a citizen4&#13;
of water supply and the reasons for non-supply. The&#13;
immediate positive development was that people living&#13;
in remote areas no longer had to spend between 20&#13;
to 40 hours per month waiting for water.45 The socio-&#13;
economic challenge of having to take a day off work&#13;
to wait for water was also reduced. NextDrop currently&#13;
serves over 75,000 citizens in the twin cities of Hubli-&#13;
Dharwad (with a population of one million46) and is&#13;
working with utility services in Bangalore to provide&#13;
water management tools to their engineers. In future, it&#13;
aims to serve all citizens in Hubli-Dharwad, and scale&#13;
up to the whole of Bangalore47.&#13;
" http://www.ischool.berkeley.edu/files/student_projects/nextdrop_final_report.pdf  6 Kumpel, E., Sridharan, A., Kote, T, Olmos, A., and Parikh, T "NextDrop: Using&#13;
" Kote, T, &amp; Olmos, A. (2011). NextDrop Final Report. Retrieved from http://www.  Human Observations to Track Water Distribution." USENIX NSDR'12, Boston,&#13;
ischool.berkeley.edu/files/student_--projects/nextdrop_final_report.pdf  MA, June 12-15, 2012. http://people.ischool.berkeley.edu/-parikh/papers/nsdl2-&#13;
5 http://www.theguardian.com/environment/terra-india/2013/aug/02/india-water-  fina]13.pdf&#13;
scarcity-simple-data-solutions                                          ' http://www.virgin.com/unite/entrepreneurship/innovation-until-the-last-drop&#13;
* http://www.nextdrop.org/&#13;
18&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Unlocking the Potential of Information Communications Technology to Improve Water and Sanitation Services Landscape Analysis and Findings of the Study&#13;
ii. Chaffenges                                                          M&#13;
*   Connectivity in most rural areas remains an issue. If&#13;
the rural communities are to be encouraged to useand&#13;
ICTs, proper infrastructure, connectivity, electricity  supported by WSR It is a platform for communication&#13;
and access to the technologies all need to be addressed.  between citizens and the Nairobi City Water and&#13;
*   While ICT offers opportunities to bridge access gaps  Sewerage Company (NCWSC), the water service&#13;
in infrastructure, if tools are not adequately designed  provider for Kenya's capital city.&#13;
for resource-constrained environments, ICT initiatives&#13;
can be plagued by the same lack of infrastructure they  The benefits that have been realized through its use&#13;
are trying to overcome.                              include: improved work flow   processes, improved&#13;
*   In the case of the NFC phones for water purification  response time to customer complaints and as a result&#13;
tracking, charging of phone batteries was identified  improved customer confidence in the utility. The tool&#13;
as the most severe obstacle for effective use. Limited  has also contributed to a clearer understanding of the&#13;
battery life and lack of electricity at home meant users  business operating environment, informing utilities and&#13;
would be required to pay a considerable fraction of  WASREB where the main focus of interventions should&#13;
their earned income to street vendors to charge their  be. Through the use of the tool, billing was identified&#13;
phones.                                              as the main challenge for NCWSC, which led to the&#13;
*   Investing in devices that use alternative energy sources,  development of a new meter reading system.&#13;
such as solar, ensures the longevity of the devices and  The following results have been noted since the&#13;
offers the possibility for extension or uptake of the  introduction of MajiVoice:50&#13;
ICT intervention in resource-poor areas.               *   MajiVoice rolled out to four public water utilities in&#13;
first year: Nairobi, Nakuru, Nanyuki and Mathira.&#13;
In the case of M4W in Uganda, the low uptake has been      *  Complaints recorded rose from approx. 400 to&#13;
caused, in part, by the community users having to meet        over 4,000 per month (Nairobi).&#13;
the cost of the SMS to notify the handpump mechanic of     *  About 94 percent of submitted complaints were&#13;
the fault. The developers are working on a new version of     resolved, up from 46 percent in initial months&#13;
the system that will allow users to send SMS to a toll-free   (Nairobi).&#13;
number. It is hoped that this will increase usage of the tool  *  The average time between the lodging  and&#13;
among the community members.                                  resolution of complaints halved.&#13;
*  Over 400 employees using the system     daily&#13;
Theme 5: ICT to Strengthen the Consumer Voice                 (Nairobi).&#13;
ICTs can be used as a tool to encourage citizens to voice     majrit reprt     that Marioe smade   te&#13;
their concerns and put pressure on the local government       to    ith and folo  upio    ic m    pits"&#13;
to address problems with their water and sanitation           (9 ercet) and fimpo      te way    n sC&#13;
services. While benefits of successfully implemented ICT      deals with complaints." (98.1 percent)&#13;
initiatives include increased governance, empowerment&#13;
of citizens and increased quality of services, the many&#13;
unsuccessful initiatives are proof that citizen engagement&#13;
is an exceptionally difficult task.&#13;
Document name: ICT Case Study - Kenya to be found on the Vula Unlocking&#13;
ICT Potential site in the 'Resources" folder&#13;
http://pdu.woldbank.org/sites/pdu2/en/aboul/PDU/EngageCihizens&#13;
www.wsp.org                                                                                                 19&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Unlocking the Potential of Information Communications Technology to Improve Water and Sanitation Services | Landscape Analysis and Findings of the Study&#13;
The experiences and lessons learnt from       different ICT        3.  Ensure that the technology is easy to use and responsive&#13;
solutions suggest nine key mechanisms in supporting the                if changes to promote participation are required.&#13;
design and implementation of ICTs aimed at strengthening                With NextDrop, during the initialpilot, olderpeople had&#13;
the consumer voice:                                                    problems using the SMS system as it required specific code&#13;
1. Ensure the system    is responsive and that applications            lines. This prompted NextDrop to adopt an Interactive&#13;
are connected to a clear mechanism of action that can              Voice Response (IVR) system.&#13;
respond to feedback and complaints.&#13;
The "most crucial and challenging element of a social         4.   Fulfilling a key need can remove the need for monetary&#13;
accountability strategy is to be able to elicit a response fom     incentives.&#13;
public officials and achieve real change"51.                       As was shown with NextDrop, the application provided&#13;
monetary incentives during the pilot phase of the project,&#13;
In the case ofMaji Voice, the team made considerable efforts       offering 5-10 rupeesfor thefirstperson to call, but the use&#13;
to achieve a near instant automatic confirmation by text           of the application was not affected even after withdrawal&#13;
message. These are meant to give customers an immediate            the monetary incentive. NextDrop reported that users were&#13;
feeling of receiving a "response" and reassurance that their       incentivized by the ability to receive information as well as&#13;
complaint is taken seriously, as wellas providing them with        the idea ofhelping the community.&#13;
the benefit of being able to track it. More importantly,&#13;
however, the MajiVoice system is tightly integrated with       5.  Partnering or integration with the media can amplify&#13;
a clear mechanism-of-action - the utility customer care            the voices of consumers.&#13;
department- that does, in the majority ofcases, successfully       MajiMatone, while ultimately unsuccessfl       did come&#13;
resolve individual complaints. Each submitted data point           up with a strategy to amplify consumers' voices andplace&#13;
(complaint) is assigned to utility employees for action.           additional pressure on the government by forwarding&#13;
Kenyan utilities are subject to binding service provision          resident-submitted SISs on non-functional water points&#13;
agreements (SPAs). The SPAs legally oblige utilities to            to the local media (radio and newspapers).&#13;
respond to complaints of particular categories in a given&#13;
time. If they fail to do so, the regulator is empowered to     6.  Ensure consumers have the same access to data as the&#13;
take enforcement action, including the withdrawal of               institutions they are trying to hold accountable.&#13;
licenses. This clear mechanism of action gives the system          Opportunities are    missed  when   users do   not have&#13;
a major advantage over social-accountability mechanisms            access to the same data in order for them  to agitate for&#13;
that collect feedback, but fail to achieve concrete action         improvements. NextDrop, M4W      MajiVoice andM-Maji&#13;
beyond the publication and discussion ofdata.                      allgive users aplatform to voice complaints and also access&#13;
service delivery data.&#13;
2. Identify     and    use   the   preferred    method     of&#13;
communication      of the consumers to ensure that             7.  Manage priorities and the quality of information.&#13;
reporting is not limited by the tool of choice.                    Information sent by citizens often has to be verfiedfor&#13;
MajiVoice recognized fom     the outset that the public            validity, for example before a technical team can be sent to&#13;
preferred calling rather than sending SMSs in regards to           address a complaint. The design of the system should allow&#13;
problems with water service delivery or lack ofinformation         for a verification process.&#13;
about water service problems fom utility providers.&#13;
8.  Co-design ICT consumer applications.&#13;
In order to create user-friendly systems that respond to&#13;
local needs, co-design approach should be adopted where&#13;
the customer is part of the ICT design team. This is&#13;
particularly important to minimize the design-reality gap.&#13;
5" World Bank Social Accountability Sourcebook http://www.worldbank.org/socialac-&#13;
countability -sourcebook/&#13;
20&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Unlocking the Potential of Information Communications Technology to Improve Water and Sanitation Services Landscape Analysis and Findings of the Study&#13;
SL Cone- Inia5&#13;
The SLB Connect project was initiated in early 2012 by the Water and Sanitation Program in consultation with the&#13;
Ministry of Urban Development (MoUD). Implementation was done in PimpriChinchwad in partnership with the&#13;
PimpriChinchwad Municipal Corporation (PCMC). There is growing recognition in India of the need to engage citizens&#13;
in setting service delivery standards and monitoring performance. The aim of the tool was to provide a model for&#13;
collecting citizens' feedback and integrate the same into the workflow of respective government agencies.&#13;
Feedback from citizens is obtained not only on satisfaction levels, but also on customer's experience of services.&#13;
The feedback from citizens is compiled in a scorecard and made available to interested stakeholders who can&#13;
measure the quality of services provided.&#13;
SLB Connect has four major components:&#13;
1. Conducting a mobile-based survey of sample households on service aspects.&#13;
2. Real-time monitoring of survey quality and timelines using an online survey management module.&#13;
3. Real-time analysis of survey results using a web-based Dashboard and data analysis tools.&#13;
4. Supporting the Urban Local Body (ULB) to design appropriate reform and response processes based on&#13;
the findings from the survey.&#13;
The implementation of SLB Connect in&#13;
PimpriChinchwad demonstrated a model&#13;
that is socially sustainable (relies on voluntary&#13;
feedback  from   citizens), institutionally&#13;
compatible (embedding  processes within                     PublicService&#13;
existing institutional structures), and financially        ValueOutcornes&#13;
viable (leveraging mobile technology for faster&#13;
and cost-effective iterations).&#13;
Going forward, SLB Connect aims to:&#13;
*  Replicate the citizen feedback exercise&#13;
across multiple cities.&#13;
*  Integrate   with    state/national&#13;
investment  programs   in  water&#13;
supply and sanitation for improved&#13;
tracking of service outcomes.A&#13;
WSP Publications: SLB Connect Flyer February 2013; SLB Connect: Citizen Feedback Survey on Service Delivery using ICTs.www.slbconnect.in&#13;
www.wsp.org                                                                                    21&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Unlocking the Potential of Information Communications Technology to Improve Water and Sanitation Services | Landscape Analysis and Findings of the Study&#13;
9. Trust must be established in order to ensure reporting:  Theme 6: ICTs and Governance&#13;
*   Trust that privacy of data and anonymity will be    Good governance and public sector management are&#13;
protected                                           necessary for development and social transformation.13&#13;
Before M4W was implemented, users had to write a&#13;
signed complaint letter outlining their grievances to  Advances in ICTs have created opportunities which&#13;
the Village Local Council official. This process never  are  being  exploited  to  improve  governance. The&#13;
protected user identity/privacy and was a complicated,  integration of ICTs into local governance gives rise to an&#13;
time-consuming procedure involving several meetings.  informed population that can effectively participate in&#13;
M4W was able to solve that through SMS reporting    governance. Access to timely and relevant information&#13;
which protected user identity and never involved any  by citizens improves interaction, builds trust, confidence&#13;
meetings.                                           and   participation. ICTs   are  registering  tremendous&#13;
*   Trust that government agencies or service providers  improvements in building capacities of people previously&#13;
will respond to reports.                            excluded from   the political process, including women,&#13;
One of the major challenges of systems for citizen  youth and minorities. Family Support Institute in Kenya,&#13;
complaints has been that governments were not able  for example, is using ICTs to increase the number of&#13;
to respond to the complaints and that the system    women voters.&#13;
became irrelevant. Low expectations of government&#13;
services, based on prior unresponsiveness, create   ICTs are strengthening partnerships between institutions&#13;
the lack of motivation among users to report issues.  such as parliaments, media and civil society organizations&#13;
It is crucial to establish the capacity to respond to  through  interactive platforms or fora for supporting&#13;
queries prior to implementing a system. Service     information sharing and collaboration. Systems that allow&#13;
providers and government agencies can gain the trust  citizens to report graft or misuse of public funds have&#13;
of their customers and constituents through timely  contributed to the fight against corruption and have created&#13;
acknowledgement and response to reports, even when  better mechanisms for ensuring government accountability&#13;
a solution is not immediately possible. Projects like  of public resources and  transparency in  delivery of&#13;
MajiVoice, NextDrop, WQR and M4W       are clear    services. The use of Frontline SMS during presidential&#13;
examples of applications where reporting is linked to  elections in Nigeria was embraced by the citizens because&#13;
responsiveness.                                     it enabled transparent elections by allowing users to report&#13;
*   Trust in the service provider.                      malpractices such as vote rigging.&#13;
It is important for the service provider to provide&#13;
feedback ifa problem has been resolved. The feedback  norde tire        upon  ucceses inthece ofuictin&#13;
can be a simple tracking number that allows citizens  govranceutre  is a need    to enefcomn       icat&#13;
to follow up or an automated response when the      inft     ructu e ao   ce    s to enef       c    ite&#13;
problem will be attended to. In the case ofNextDrop  insthe gover  c    pro   e   ingvu ofccommun&#13;
it has been reported that trust between customers and  esour    ce enters can improve&#13;
water providers has increased through provision of  extedi      an seiso local gonmc            improe&#13;
feedback and reliable information on water supply   sriedlvr        n   upr     oa    cnmcdvlpet&#13;
fT Involving citizens in the design and use of the tool is&#13;
critical for successful implementation. Finally, ICTs must&#13;
be perceived as merely tools; improvements in governance&#13;
will also need to come from a government's willingness&#13;
to develop human and institutional capacities in terms of&#13;
policy implementation, provision of regulatory frameworks&#13;
and managing policies.&#13;
" Adesida, 0., 2001. Governance in Africa:pie Role for Information and&#13;
Communication Technologies Governance in Africa: The Role for Information,&#13;
Abidjan, Cote dIvoire.&#13;
22&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Unlocking the Potential of Information Communications Technology to Improve Water and Sanitation Services Landscape Analysis and Findings of the Study&#13;
SIASAR, the Rural Water and Sanitation Information System, was designed to monitor the development and&#13;
performance of rural water supply and sanitation services in participating Latin American countries. In addition to&#13;
addressing the needs of stakeholders for updated, complete and trustworthy data, it is also helping countries identify&#13;
needs, guide sector policies, and enables the continuous knowledge exchange between platform participants. It&#13;
operates on an interactive web platform adapted for Android cell phones and tablets. It is an ICT-based information&#13;
system that collects, synthesizes and analyzes data on rural water service delivery, measuring four basic&#13;
dimensions of service provision: (i) access to services (ii) quality of services (iii) performance of service providers&#13;
and (iv) the effectiveness of technical&#13;
assistance. Data collected is verified&#13;
and automatically processed before&#13;
performance rankings are published,&#13;
"grading" each of the four dimensions&#13;
from A (very good) to D (poor). One&#13;
of the major aims of the SIASAR&#13;
initiative is to build the capacity of&#13;
local technical staff to plan, monitor&#13;
and   manage    rural WSS.      These&#13;
rankings help officials to prioritize&#13;
needs, leading to higher standards&#13;
in terms of coverage, quality and&#13;
sustainability.&#13;
Challenges                                                     ICTs are tools, not solutions&#13;
For governance to be inclusive, it must be accessible and open  The successful implementation    of ICTs relies on the&#13;
to every citizen                                               stakeholders committing themselves to good governance.&#13;
Pre-existing imbalances in access to infrastructure (urban/    Strategic policies must be in place to support the role that&#13;
rural, high/low income) can translate into lack oftransparent  ICTs can play in improving the quality of life of citizens&#13;
governance initiates further promoting inequality in access    while achieving national goals.&#13;
to public services.                                                    It is therefore essential for governments to develop&#13;
*   Governments     therefore   need    to   improve               human and institutional capacities in terms of&#13;
communication infrastructure if all citizens are to            policy implementation, provision of regulatory&#13;
benefit and participate in the governance process.             frameworks and managing policies to allow for&#13;
*   By   creating   mechanism     for  participation,              inclusive access to information by all citizens.&#13;
governments will become more transparent,&#13;
accessible, accountable and    more involved in        Rigid regulatoryframeworks&#13;
meeting the needs of the citizens.                     Rigid  regulatory   frameworks    limit  the   ability  of&#13;
o  A potential solution is for governments to set   governance structures to respond to the continuous and&#13;
up community resource centers to improve         dynamic changes prompted by the introduction of new&#13;
or enable access by individuals to ICTs in       technologies.&#13;
areas where it is limited.&#13;
SPena, Lilian et al., 2013. Briefing Notes: The SMASAR Initiative: An Information&#13;
SystemTfor more Sustainable Rural Water and Sanitation Services. Water Partnership&#13;
Program, World Bank&#13;
www.wsp.org                                                                                                               23&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Unlocking the Potential of Information Communications Technology to Improve Water and Sanitation Services | Landscape Analysis and Findings of the Study&#13;
Low literacy can hamper use                                        1.      Include ICT as an integral part of development&#13;
To deal with the issue of low literacy and inability to use                 activities. Identifying ICT adoption and use as a&#13;
the technologies, governments need to look into social issues               means to an end, rather than an end in itself&#13;
like basic literacy, poverty and how ICTs can contribute to        2.       Identify ICT   as a specific element in poverty&#13;
solving these issues.                                                       reduction strategies or national development plans.&#13;
Uganda, for example, has included an objective in&#13;
The learnings from the use of ICTs in the governance sector                 their National Development Plan        (2010-2015)&#13;
are very valuable when translated to the WASH          sector,              promoting science, technology, innovation       and&#13;
especially as the water sector is facing a number ofgovernance              ICT in order to enhance competiveness.&#13;
challenges (Hellstr6m   &amp; Jacobson, 2014)55. Aspects such          3.       Specifically  prioritize  spending  on   ICTs, for&#13;
as governance through citizen participation are particularly               instance through investment in infrastructure. As&#13;
important in order to give voices to communities regarding                  the box below   illustrates, Kenya is pursuing this&#13;
water provision, service interruptions and corruption of                    method, having     invested   approximately    Sh32&#13;
officials. ICTs are becoming a dominant force in the way                    billion (USD307 million) from      2006 to 2013,&#13;
utility providers and customers communicate, as ICTs can                   which represents 3.2 percent of the gross domestic&#13;
directly link the consumer with the service operator, avoiding              product (GDP).&#13;
the need for intermediaries. Equally, citizen participation&#13;
in  making    decisions   on   infrastructure  development,&#13;
expenditure or health warnings can be of major benefit to&#13;
improve the governance of the WASH sector. ICTs can be              Kenya has adopted CT as a major thrust and building&#13;
used to create a system of transparency and accountability,         block to development, lCT is one of the key pillars for&#13;
to promote public participation and collaboration among             development as defined in Kenya's Vision 2030, the&#13;
stakeholders in the WASH     sector, to improve monitoring          strategic roadmap towards realization of social and&#13;
and management of WASH projects, and to reduce the cost             economic development by the year 2030. National&#13;
of access to information and service delivery. Some of the          policy documents and programs supporting the use&#13;
tools and applications mentioned above could very easily be         and development of lOTs to support innovation and&#13;
transformed into applicable solutions for the improvement           improved service delivery attest to this. This is further&#13;
of governance in the WASH sector.                                   evidenced by the government spending trends and&#13;
rate of adoption of ICT use by residents and public&#13;
institutions. 1DC 2014~ 5estimates that there has been&#13;
Theme 7: Financing ICTs                                             an increase of about USD3 billion (about 3.2 percent of&#13;
ICT financing at the national scale                                 GOP) in government spending on IOT over the period&#13;
"ICTs are increasingly recognised as a vitalpart ofthe economic,    2006 to 2013. The     CT-driven development process&#13;
social and political fabric of countries and as the crucial basis   has been facilitated by the liberalization of the market&#13;
for development and poverty reduction. "56                           and development of key infrastructure including the&#13;
national optic fibre backbone infrastructure (NOFBI)&#13;
As the European Commission has indicated in its report on           and a Government Common Core Network (GCCN)&#13;
Financing ICT for Development57, there are three means of           intended to serve as a shared and secure interoperable&#13;
national support for ICT.                                           government-wide ICT architecture6o.&#13;
" HellstromaJ., Jaboson M., 2014: 'You caI cheat the community anymore' using  tDocument name: ICT Case Study - Kenya to be found on the Vula Unlocking&#13;
mobiles to improve water governance. In I.Niang &amp; C.SHaff, eds. Proceedings ofthe  ICT Potential site in the "Resources" folder&#13;
45 international conference on M41) Mobile Communicationfat Development Dakar,  t IDC 2014. Breaking barriers with technology: A  special report on the Kenyan ICT&#13;
Senegal pp 48- 5p market. An examination ofKenyas ongoing technolsspowered transformation andpush&#13;
5http://www.iicd.org/articles/EU-Financing-ICT4D-(English).pdf/   to transition to a Knowledge Socie and regional ICTpomerhouse.&#13;
53 Document name: ICT Case Study - Kenya to be found on the Vula Unlocking  . The Kenya National ICT Master Plan - Towards a Digital Kenya 2014. http:/&#13;
ICT Potential site in the "Resources" folder                       www.scrid.com/doc/21791 5368ICT-Masterplan-20 14#scri d&#13;
24&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Unlocking the Potential of Information Communications Technology to Improve Water and Sanitation Services Landscape Analysis and Findings of the Study&#13;
ICT Financing at the Application/Project Scale            Financial plans need to include both funding for project&#13;
The majority of cases examined as part of the study had   start-up costs as well as long-term financing for operation&#13;
short-term or ad hoc financial models, with applications  and maintenance of the technology. MajiVoice is now&#13;
relying  heavily   on   unsustainable  project/donor-    operated, managed and used by the NCWSC. NextDrop&#13;
based funding. MajiData in Kenya for example was          has been successful in managing its sustainability by&#13;
conceptualized in 2008 by GIZ. Since no financing was     continuously re-inventing and growing into other locations&#13;
allocated by the Government of Kenya to support the      while signing up thousands of households at small cost of&#13;
process, GIZ offered technical and financial resources as  10 rupees per month for the service. M4W  relies upon&#13;
part of its support to the Kenya water sector reform process  HPMs being incentivized by DWO and the NGOs to carry&#13;
aimed at improving governance in the water sector. The    out baseline data collection and assessment of water source.&#13;
original budget of 1.5 million euros covered 2,000 areas  While minor repairs to a water source are paid for by the&#13;
as part of the initial baseline. Beyond the initial areas,  communities from their monthly user fees collected, major&#13;
scaling up of data collection to other areas was demand-  repairs are to be done by the district water office. Agencies&#13;
driven, based on funding and data requirements from other  responsible for M-Maji and M4W manage the continuous&#13;
stakeholders61. NextDrop, on the other hand, has been     running of the system. Other systems like FLOW  were&#13;
successful in managing its sustainability by continuously re-  developed by one organization (Water for People), which&#13;
inventing and growing into other locations, while signing  then sought partnership with another organization (Akvo&#13;
up thousands of households at a small cost of 10 rupees per  Foundation) to improve and manage FLOW.&#13;
month for the service.&#13;
TABLE 1: FINANCING ICTs-UGANDANS NATIONAL WATER&#13;
Many ICTs in the WASH sector rely heavily on external&#13;
donor agencies. Many of the case study applications relied  Development  The only development costs incurred&#13;
Costswere on         personnel within the utility&#13;
upon funding from   external donors agencies including     Costs&#13;
Human    Sensor Web     (Google.org, UN-HABITAT);                       IT department had to recruit software&#13;
MajiMatone (Twaweza, DflD, Daraja Trust); NextDrop                       developers to work on the system.&#13;
(Gates Foundation, Clinton Global Initiatives, Center for  Maintenance   Maintenance of the e-water infrastructure&#13;
Information Technology Research in the Interest of Society,  Costs      is currently one of the major costs. To&#13;
Knight Foundation, GSM    Association); Water Quality                    manage   countrywide  connections, it&#13;
Reporter (European Union, Gates Foundation); MajiVoice                   costs the utility approximately UGX 1.5&#13;
(World Bank, NCWSC); M4W         (SNV, IRC/Triple-S,                     billion (USD507,000) annually. However&#13;
Gates Foundation, ATTI); mWater (USAID); mSludgein contrast the utility used to spend about&#13;
(Gates Foundation); M-Maji (Stanford University and                         billion&#13;
Umande Trust).&#13;
Umade rus).Cost to the                                    Even with the introduction of a tariff for&#13;
Few ICTs receive financial support from the government                   the rie poies        the co   st.&#13;
for the planning and implementation phase through                        Telecom operators charge a tariff of UGX&#13;
to the ongoing maintenance and operation. Huduma                         1,300 (approximately USD0.40) that is paid&#13;
and Ufahamu systems received support from the Kenya                      by the customer. The cost is deducted off&#13;
government, while others mostly received support and                     the customer's mobile money account as&#13;
co-funding from stakeholder agencies. Some ICT projects                 soon as payment is made.&#13;
used internal funds of their parent organizations to finance  Increased  With the introduction of mobile payments,&#13;
their mobile phone projects, for example FLOW, WPM         Revenue       the bill collections have increased by 15&#13;
and  M 4WF                                                     n  l  a    e   t  n    e   t   u    g   r  o percent.&#13;
s Document name: ICT Case Study - Kenya to be found on the Vula Unlocking  Document name: ICT Case Study - Uganda to be found on the Vula Unlocking&#13;
ICT Potential site in the "Resoumes" folder             ICT Potential site in the "Resources" folder&#13;
www.wsp.org                                                                                                    25&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Unlocking the Potential of Information Communications Technology to Improve Water and Sanitation Services | Landscape Analysis and Findings of the Study&#13;
Cost Effectiveness of ICT                                         Financing_of_ICT _-_M4W64&#13;
TABLE 2: TYPICAL COST BENEFIT STREAMS FOR             The M4W project was initially financed by the Africa&#13;
CONSIDERATION IN ICT IMPLEMENTATION                   Technology &amp; Transparency Initiative (ATTI) with&#13;
USD30,000. The majority of this fund was spent&#13;
* S                                                 on the development of the technology in terms of&#13;
Direct Costs       Direct Benefits                   setting up the infrastructure, paying the developers,&#13;
*  Software        *   Reduction in non-revenue      purchasing handsets and deployment (including&#13;
licenses cost      water                         training) in the first five districts. For the subsequent&#13;
*   Implementation  *  Energy and fuel savings       deployment and maintenance, the M4W consortium&#13;
cost            0  Inventory savings              contributed USD20,000. Currently, the annual running&#13;
*   Hardware costs.  *  Reduction of arrears,        costs of the system are budgeted at UGX 300 million.&#13;
*   Network            customer dues                 The major costs include replacement of the mobile&#13;
connectivity    *  Improved cash flow             phones (each mobile handset costs approximately&#13;
costs           0  Paper, communication saving    USD40), and management of the infrastructure and&#13;
*  Training costs  *   Revenue increase              the personnel to maintain the system.&#13;
*   Documentation   0 Optimization of expenses       The cost of the SMS sent to report a water point fault&#13;
development&#13;
dateversioent                                     is born by the user at approximately USDO.078 (UGX&#13;
220). Low uptake by communities has been credited in&#13;
directpart with this user associated cost and the developers&#13;
Indirect Cotsme    Idrcens proveare working on a new version of the system that will&#13;
*  Stffig tme  * Proessimprvemntsandallow users to send SMS to a toll free number.&#13;
and effort         enhancement.&#13;
required by the  *  Improved people (employee)     Summaas  of the M4W costs&#13;
establishment      management and efficiency      Item                              Cost (USD)&#13;
*   Readiness costs  *  Improved planning and&#13;
that relates to    decision-making                 Development cost (including purchase 30,000&#13;
data preparation    Reduction of outages          of phones for four districts)&#13;
*   Improved information quality   Development cost (including purchase 20,000&#13;
of phones for additional districts and&#13;
Source: Information and Communication Technology for Water Utility  maintenance: 2011 -201 4)&#13;
Management - Best practices and experience sharing among ACWU4 members.  Server hosting (outsourced)  720 (annually)&#13;
*Charging                                                      phones (by hand   pump - 5 per month&#13;
mechanics)&#13;
As noted in the Financing of ICT - M4W box, the cost   Since 2011 approximately 715 SMS were sent by water&#13;
effectiveness of ICTs is very specific to the initiative in  users from Lira and Kabarole districts to the system&#13;
question; which is why it is essential to develop a long-term  and 187 water sources (26 percent) were repaired on&#13;
financial plan during the initial stages of conception along  the basis of these messages. In looking at the initiative&#13;
with a monitoring and evaluation plan to keep track of the  in regards to usage/development costs the initiative&#13;
financial health and effectiveness of the ICT initiative. The  may not necessarily appear cost-effective. However, in&#13;
aacomparison to the traditional means of data collection,&#13;
benefits streams that can be considered, but it is important to&#13;
note that some impacts may be more difficult to translate into  In order to collect the one data set for the WATSUP&#13;
financial gains, for example, increased consumer awareness  database  update, the  Ministry  of Water and&#13;
anaeeEnvironment (Uganda) spent approximately UGX 2&#13;
ioebillion. In contrast, the M4W project was able to use&#13;
y                             the same processes and institutional structures to&#13;
mhtetp:Bwww.acwua.orgasitesadefaultfiles/nabilchemaly.pdf  collect baseline data at a cost of only UGX 600 million.&#13;
T Document name: ICT Case Study - Uganda to be found on the Vula Unlocking&#13;
ICT Potential site in the "Resources" folder&#13;
26&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Unlocking the Potential of Information Communications Technology to Improve Water and Sanitation Services Landscape Analysis and Findings of the Study&#13;
Theme 8: Public-Private Partnerships                             I   Creation of an enabling environment to attract&#13;
investors:&#13;
Fiacn   ofIT-TeCs*fUad                                          Enabling legal and regulatory&#13;
Since the 1990s ICT infrastructure has largely been                     environment.&#13;
funded by the private sector65. In Uganda, the                       0  Competition.&#13;
liberalisation of the national ICT Sector has led to                 *  Start-up costs.&#13;
increased private investment in the ICT sector in terms&#13;
of foreign direct investments (FDls) in the upstream           *   International collaborations:&#13;
ICT services, as well as local investments in end-                      Building 'backbone' infrastructure&#13;
user services. The Uganda National Development                          linking countries and regions.&#13;
Plan 2010-2015 states that between 2003 and 2008&#13;
the communications sector alone managed to raise            D   Ensuring that the communication needs of the&#13;
annual average investment from USD78 million in 2004            poorest and most marginalized are met&#13;
to USD150 million in 2007, which has consequently               *  Through innovative public-private partnerships.&#13;
resulted in a growth in revenues and an increased&#13;
contribution to GDP66                                      lo   Introducing ICT into government functions and&#13;
services:&#13;
Role of the Public Sector in Financing of ICT            The UN Task Force on Financial Mechanisms for ICT&#13;
As highlighted in a number of publications, governments  for Development emphasised throughout its report that&#13;
need to create environments which attract private sector  an enabling environment is vital. Without it investment&#13;
investors. This includes developing policy and regulations  Will not be made, or once made it will not be effective in&#13;
as well as start-up processes which are supportive to the  providing services efficiently and at the best price. Each&#13;
client and the business. Aspects such as transparency, fair  country needs to develop its own policy and strategies,&#13;
competition processes and skilled human capacity are     but global communications also require regional and&#13;
required to create an investor conducive environment, international governancen.&#13;
Donors should see themselves as strategic players who&#13;
encourage investment in high-risk and low-profit areas&#13;
through  start-up funding, financial assistance and risk&#13;
mitigation. Donors also have the opportunity to create&#13;
networks of knowledge and infrastructure across countries  mWater is a business service-oriented     platform&#13;
and   regions  in  A frica.   Aspects  s c  a  transparency, fair&#13;
The European Commission has highlighted the following key seegae m      obl  s  ts     copn     y Mnb&#13;
Donrs sf houlc seecthemselvesnasn sTregic p ers : whoaee      oiesluin           opayMnb&#13;
rlesof tepulic srin inan        t                       through a public-private partnership (PPP) funded by&#13;
At        nra         vete                             the WSP in 2008. The tool itself also supports the PPP&#13;
n   Financial assistance and risk mitigation:      frameworks that exist between the municipalities and&#13;
Low-interest loans or risk guarantees.     private sector operatorS6.&#13;
The Report of the TFFM (Task Force on Financial Mechanisms) for ICT for&#13;
Development. hepp://www.ihu.ina/wsis/etffm/final-repor.doc&#13;
 Economic and Sector Work Unlocking the potential of ICT use in the water and&#13;
htp://www.iicd.org/articles/EU-Financing-pICT4D-(English).pdf/  sanitation sector in Africa. Phase 1: Assessment of the mWar platform for the&#13;
htp://www.undp-alm.orgresources/naps-leas-developed-counries-ldcs/  monitoring of rural and small towns piped water schemes in Senegal, Mali, Benin and&#13;
uganda%E2%80%99s-naional-developmen-plan-20 1011-201415-%E2%80%93  Niger. WSP 2013&#13;
www.wsp.org                                                                                                    27&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Unlocking the Potential of Information Communications Technology to Improve Water and Sanitation Services | Landscape Analysis and Findings of the Study&#13;
Patnrsi to lin Su      -aa Afric              Public-Private Partnerships&#13;
"Africa'sThe private sector is often not incentivised to provide for&#13;
cost of communication, which is partly due toh       the needs of the poorest. Infrastructure development in&#13;
lack of 'a backbone' ICT infrastructure between&#13;
countries in Africa. The cost of providing adequate   investment which private investors avoid. Greater margins&#13;
backbone infrastructure has been estimated at          are being made in urban and affluent areas, which results&#13;
between USD500-1000 million. Initial investment        in poorer areas being marginalised. However, private&#13;
is hard to attract from the private sector or existing  enterprises can be encouraged to consider investing when&#13;
soft loan facilities. But if the initial hurdle of the cost  given incentives. Corporate responsibility projects have&#13;
of the infrastructure could be overcome, African       shown evidence of such initiative and mobile operators&#13;
telecommunications services would quickly become       are investing today substantially in socially response&#13;
profitable for private operators. Voice and data traffic  projects. To combine the socially responsive project with&#13;
is predicted to grow by 20 percent a year (Traffic    the ICT implementation requires negotiations between&#13;
grew by 19 percent in 2001, 28 percent in 2002, and    governments, NGOs and business partners. In certain&#13;
37 percent in 2003 - compared with an international   instances - as in the eHealth sector in HIV - tax incentives&#13;
average growth rate of 10-12 percent per year).&#13;
What needs to be done to put the infrastructure in    resulT i    pspuro moeoerator cribting to&#13;
place? The first requirement is strong coordinated     to be     m  pm  e      over,et      are silly&#13;
strategic leadership by African governments. If they&#13;
developed a continent-wide plan and guarantee of       aid may be required71. The following three boxes provide&#13;
enabling conditions, they would be able to mobilise    examples of Public-Private-Partnerships.&#13;
a mixture of private finance, soft loans and donor&#13;
support." European Commission69&#13;
9 http://www.iicd.org/articles/EU-Financing-bICT4D-(English).pdf/&#13;
Shttp://www.iicd.org/articles/EUn-Financing-ICT4D-p(English).pdf/&#13;
28&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Unlocking the Potential of Information Communications Technology to Improve Water and Sanitation Services Landscape Analysis and Findings of the Study&#13;
One of the most common PPP ICT4WASH initiatives to date has been the introduction of mobile water payments.&#13;
Mobile water payment platforms offer mutual benefits to water service providers, mobile network providers and&#13;
consumers and have the potential to support African utilities to escape the vicious cycle of low cost recovery and&#13;
poor operational performance71.&#13;
"Mobile money is an electronic payment system that enables money transfers to and from an electronic account that&#13;
can be accessed via an ordinary mobile phone. Each customer's account is linked to their mobile phone number&#13;
by means of an in-built SIM-card application. Physical cash withdrawals and deposits are facilitated by a network&#13;
of retail agents. While configurations vary across providers, the viability of mobile money is premised upon the&#13;
cost base associated with an agent network, which is lower and more flexible than establishing 'bricks and mortar'&#13;
bank branches. Mobile money can therefore profitably extend&#13;
the reach of financial services to those who have traditionally&#13;
been unbanked, such as low-income or remote households."&#13;
Mobile payment platforms are set up based on agreements&#13;
between water service providers and mobile network&#13;
operators. The operators typically charge a fee/tariff for each&#13;
payment. For water service providers, mobile water payments&#13;
result in a reduction of costs related to billing, increased&#13;
revenue collection and improved collection efficiencies. For&#13;
mobile network operators offering mobile water payments,&#13;
benefits include direct revenue from fees/tariffs as well as an&#13;
opportunity to build customer loyalty. For consumers, time&#13;
and cost savings are the key benefits, although Hope et al&#13;
2011, caution that these benefits may occur only for wealthier&#13;
and professional segments of the population with the relative&#13;
Source: Mobile Water Payment Innovations in Urban Africa  benefits on low-income households unclear.&#13;
71 Hope, R.A., Foster, T., Krolikowski, A. and Cohen, I. (2011) Mobile Water Payment Innovations in UrbanAfrica. December 2011, School of Geography and the Environment&#13;
and Skoll Centre for Social Entrepreneurship at Said Business School, Oxford University, UK.&#13;
www.wsp.org                                                                                                 29&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Unlocking the Potential of Information Communications Technology to Improve Water and Sanitation Services | Landscape Analysis and Findings of the Study&#13;
C5: Policy and Operation Recommendations for Service Providers&#13;
Key policy and operation recommendations for ICT  scorecard approach. Detailed discussions on each of these&#13;
use by WASH services providers are provided below,  recommendations can be found in the AnalyticalReport.&#13;
grouped under the five dimensions of the balance&#13;
Policy and Operation for Service Providers Recommendations Overview&#13;
1. Vision&#13;
- Define the vision, desired impact, evaluation methods and indicators prior to implementation&#13;
- Regularly measure short and long-term indicators of success&#13;
- Use the evaluation findings to refine the system&#13;
- Share the evaluation findings with the larger ICT4WASH community&#13;
2. Process&#13;
-   Use the lowest cost and simplest technology&#13;
-   Design for the local environment&#13;
-   Build on existing ICTs where possible&#13;
-   Invest in devices that have the capacity of using alternate energy sources&#13;
-  Allow for tools and data to create value for the tool amongst stakeholders and allow consumers to&#13;
agitate for improvements&#13;
-  Allow for offline modes to combat poor connectivity&#13;
-  Allow for transparency to combat corruption&#13;
-   Develop partnerships with:&#13;
- Local government to enhance support and ease implementation&#13;
- NGOs and CBOs to build trust and market initiatives at the community level&#13;
-4 The media to facilitate dissemination of information&#13;
-- Technical partners/private sector for technical and financial support&#13;
3. Customer&#13;
-   Develop an outreach plan (for both design and implementation stages) and ensure dedicated funding&#13;
-   Include a response mechanism to inform the customer that action is being taken by the service provider&#13;
-   Ensure responsiveness to generated reports to build trust among users, value among stakeholders and&#13;
encourage uptake&#13;
-   Include complaints management component&#13;
-   Ensure privacy of data and anonymity&#13;
-   Enable feedback loops to allow for continual refinement&#13;
-   Build a user community through system development and implementation to promote the sharing of&#13;
experiences and to create a support network&#13;
30&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Unlocking the Potential of Information Communications Technology to Improve Water and Sanitation Services Landscape Analysis and Findings of the Study&#13;
4. Human Capacity&#13;
-    Ensure the data collection step is technically accessible to the user&#13;
-    Incorporate learning tools (images, audio-visual clips) to combat low literacy levels&#13;
-    Understand the socio-cultural context at the community user level&#13;
Limit workflow management changes at the organization level&#13;
-    Promote the system as a means for furthering personal development goals and increasing job&#13;
satisfaction to promote buy-in and uptake&#13;
5. Finances&#13;
- Have a long-term financing plan in place&#13;
- Have key user-stakeholders invest in maintaining the project&#13;
- Leverage technical partners to relieve some of the burden of developing, acquiring, and maintaining&#13;
software or hardware&#13;
C6: Identification of Strategic Issues for at                    well as provide guidelines and policy notes on the inclusion&#13;
Scale use of ICT                                           of ICTs in Water and Sanitation Policy and Planning75 to&#13;
ICTs can be a key enabler for institutional transformation       the sector's stakeholders.&#13;
to address the demand for improved water and sanitation&#13;
services for both rural and urban communities. However           To further support the implementation and scale-up of&#13;
in order to maximize the transformational role of ICT in         ICTs in the WASH sector, it is important to move beyond&#13;
the WASH sector, ICTs need to be understood as conduits          support for specific tools or technologies and look more&#13;
or contributing forces rather than as development impacts        broadly at supporting the elimination of barriers and&#13;
or solutions in themselves. Impact and success need to be        providing enabling environments. Of the common barriers&#13;
measured not just in terms of implementation or uptake           identified in the study, three stand out as potential areas&#13;
of the new technology, but more importantly in regards to        where high-level support could be beneficial.&#13;
achieving WASH sector goals and priorities.&#13;
The first barrier is a need for sector-level policy and&#13;
This study sought to not only document experiences of            regulatory frameworks. In the majority of the case study&#13;
ICT use in the WASH sector72, but also analyze them using        countries, the national ICT policies/frameworks in place&#13;
design and evaluation frameworks" to identify enabling           were weak, did not specifically address the key issues&#13;
factors and barriers in terms of vision, process, customer/      associated with regulating the use of ICTs in the WASH&#13;
user, service delivery, human capacity, governance and           sector and/or did not have accompanying implementation&#13;
finance.The analysis was also an opportunity to track the        strategies. Beyond simply providing guidelines towards&#13;
progress of the said factors in the ICT Impact Chain74 as        implementation, as integration of ICTs into the WASH&#13;
sector continues, key issues such as privacy, right to data&#13;
and hacking and security threats will need to be addressed.&#13;
72 See ICTs in the WASH Sector Desk ReviewICTsintheWASHs&#13;
b See the Analytical Report for a description of the frameworks used and detailed  a See Development of Guidelines and Policy Notes which includes&#13;
discussion on enabling factors and batriers                      Recommendations on Data Integration and Mainstreaming; ICT Evaluation;&#13;
i See all seven of the Case Study Reports to see the implementation of the assessment  Recommendations fot Policy Makers and Regulators; and Policy and Operation&#13;
frameworks on the case studies                                   Recommendations for Service Providers.&#13;
www.wsp.org                                                                                                                  31&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Unlocking the Potential of Information Communications Technology to Improve Water and Sanitation Services | Landscape Analysis and Findings of the Study&#13;
There is also a need for increased sector coordination     thousands of households at a small cost of 10 rupees per&#13;
and integration of data. Poor sector coordination and      month for the service. M4W   relies upon HPMs being&#13;
information access have led to fragmented/duplicated       incentivized by DWO and NGOs to carry out baseline data&#13;
implementations, unnecessary delays and     have also      collection and assessment of water sources. While minor&#13;
affected the long-term  functionality of installed water   repairs to a water source are paid for by the communities&#13;
points. This is due in part to the multiple and varied nature  from their monthly user fees collected, major repairs are&#13;
of WASH sector stakeholders with diverse responsibilities  are handled by the district water office. Donor agencies&#13;
for different levels of government, rural/urban divides, and  responsible for M-Maji and M4W  fund the management&#13;
multiple national and international donor organizations76.  of the systems. Other systems like FLOW  were developed&#13;
Data integration   and  mainstreaming   is of utmost       by one organization (Water for People), which then sought&#13;
importance for the success and long-term sustainability    partnerships with another organization (Akvo Foundation)&#13;
of ICT initiatives and should be championed as a core      to improve and manage FLOW.&#13;
function of the WASH sector.&#13;
A third major barrier identified in the study is the&#13;
A second major barrier to the success and sustainability   common    lack of monitoring and evaluation    of the&#13;
of ICTs identified in the study is the need for sustainable  implementation and impact of ICTs in the WASH sector.&#13;
financial models. The majority of cases examined as part of  Ideally, agreement on a common framework of analysis,&#13;
the study had weak or ad hoc financial models; applications  such as those proposed in this study, by stakeholders in the&#13;
often relied on unsustainable project/donor-based funding.  WASH sector, or at minimum a common set of indicators,&#13;
Many ICTs in the WASH sector rely heavily on external      would greatly improve the understanding of the barriers&#13;
donor agencies.                                            and enabling factors of successful and sustainable initiatives&#13;
and would greatly support the rate of replication. Region-&#13;
Few ICTs receive financial support from the government     wide workshops with public and private stakeholders&#13;
for the planning and implementation phase through to       (ministries, developers, potential private partners) could be&#13;
maintenance and operations. Financial plans need to        held to adopt common indicators or frameworks of analysis&#13;
include both funding for project start-up costs as well as  and evaluation. These evaluation tools would subsequently&#13;
long-term  financing for operation and maintenance of      be developed and promoted, and staff would be trained on&#13;
the technology. MajiVoice is now operated, managed and     how to implement them. Regular meetings could be held&#13;
used by the NCWSC; NextDrop has been successful in         to track progress in the sector and share lessons with a view&#13;
managing its sustainability by continuously re-inventing   of refining the system in place.&#13;
and growing into    other locations while signing up&#13;
fo (O'MeAtly, 2011); (WaterAid, 2011).&#13;
32&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Unlocking the Potential of Information Communications Technology to Improve Water and Sanitation Services I Annex 1: Overview of Ict Tools in the Wash Sector&#13;
Annex 1: Overview of ICT Tools in the&#13;
WASH Sector&#13;
DropDrop              DropDrop  is  a  mobile application  Tools: Mobile Phones  iCOMMS, City of Cape&#13;
developed by iCOMMS team, from the  (Android)              Town.&#13;
University of Cape Town. The application&#13;
runs on Android smart phones and was  Country: South Africa&#13;
developed for users to track their water&#13;
consumption. Users need to enter the  Year: 2013&#13;
water meter readings into DropDrop on a&#13;
daily or regular basis and the application&#13;
allows them to access reports on daily  Agency: iCOMMS&#13;
water usage and estimated water bill.&#13;
Information  on  water conservation&#13;
methods, the municipal contacts and&#13;
information on the water systems is also&#13;
provided.&#13;
URL: http://www.icomms.uct.ac.za/dropdrop-icomms                                (Rein, Champanis &amp;&#13;
Rivett, 2013)&#13;
Field Level Operations  FLOW is an open source data collection  Tools: Mobile Phones  Cisco; Founder of&#13;
Watch (FLOW)          tool that allows users to create surveys (SMS), GPS mapping  Craigslist (donation of&#13;
that include text, photos, video and GPS                   20,000 Motorola phones);&#13;
Country: Uganda, Kenya  Hlo   onain&#13;
coordinates. Data about the location and                   Hilton Foundation;&#13;
functionality of water points as well as Year: 2010        WaterAid; IRC; Portland&#13;
access levels of water and sanitation at                   State (Evan Thomas):&#13;
household and public institution level is                  Suite Pilot program for&#13;
collected using Android phones.                            Mercy Corp in Indonesia.&#13;
URL: http://akvo.org/products/akvoflow/                                         (Hutchings et al, 2012)&#13;
Human Sensor Web      This project is aimed at developing  Tools: Mobile phones  UN Habitat, google.&#13;
(H2.0)                community-driven services for focused                     org, GTZ Kenya, Water&#13;
and  geo-referenced  monitoring  of                        Services Trust Fund&#13;
water supply and sanitation coverage in (Tanzania)         Kenya, WaterAid, Zantel,&#13;
Zanzibar. The community used mobile  Year: 2008-2010       Zanzibar Water Authority&#13;
phones to report if a water point was  Agency: University of  (ZAWA), Upande, Net!&#13;
dry, out-of-order, or if the water was not Twente, Twente Institute  Zanzibar Datacom Ltd.&#13;
potable.                          for Wireless and Mobile&#13;
Communications and&#13;
Initiative for Geospatial&#13;
Open Source Software&#13;
URL: http://52north.org/resources/re ferences/sensor-web/h20 and http://geonetwork.itc.nll  (Hutchings et al., 2012)&#13;
zanzibar&#13;
www.wsp.org                                                                                            33&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Unlocking the Potential of Information Communications Technology to Improve Water and Sanitation Services | Annex 1: Overview of Ict Tools in the Wash Sector&#13;
Jisomee Mita         Jisomee Mita enables water consumers to  Tools: Mobile phones, SMS  NCWSC, WSP of the&#13;
use a mobile phone to query and receive                    World Bank&#13;
current water bills at a frequency of their&#13;
convenience by sending their meter Year: 2014&#13;
reading to NCWSC and receiving instant Agency: Nairobi City Water&#13;
feedback. A customer takes the meter and Sewerage Company&#13;
readings as trained, sends the reading by  (NCWSC)&#13;
phone using SMS to NCWSC. NCWSC&#13;
then calculates the water consumed&#13;
and sends a response SMS indicating&#13;
consumption and the amount to be paid.&#13;
URL: http://nwater.jambopay.co.ke/accountcheck.php_and http://jisomeemita.blogspot.ca/search//abel/&#13;
NairobiCityWaterandSewerageCompanyNCWSC&#13;
M4W                  The M4W project aims to improve water Tools: Mobile Phones and  SNV (Uganda), Makerere&#13;
(Mobiles for Water)  and sanitation in rural parts of Uganda by  District Water Management  University, IRC/Triple-S,&#13;
enabling access to information by various Information System  Water Aid (Uganda)&#13;
stakeholders and players in the Water&#13;
and Sanitation sector. The M4W project&#13;
uses SMS messages and openXdata&#13;
application on Java-based mobile phones  Year: 2011&#13;
and web interfaces to collect information.&#13;
Once collected, the data is uploaded to&#13;
a customized District Water Management Agency: Makerere&#13;
Information System  (DWMIS) that is  University&#13;
hosted on the Internet. This data can&#13;
be accessed and viewed by all relevant&#13;
stakeholders.&#13;
URL: http://m4waterorg/&#13;
MajiData             MajiData is an online database that aims Tools: Website   GIZ, UN-Habitat, Google.&#13;
to assist the Water Service Providers                     org, the ITC Faculty of&#13;
(WSPs) and Water Services Boards  County: Kenya           Geo-Information Science&#13;
(WSBs) to prepare tailor-made water                       and  Earth Observation&#13;
supply and sanitation proposals for                       (University  of Twente)&#13;
the urban slums and low income areas Agency: Kenya's Ministry of and Upande (all part of&#13;
located within their service areas.  Water and Irrigation (MWI)  the H2.0 initiative; http://&#13;
and the Water Services  www.h20initiative.org).&#13;
Trust Fund (WSTF)       Website development was&#13;
funded by UN-Habitat,&#13;
the German Development&#13;
Bank (KfW), Google.org,&#13;
GIZ and the WSTF.&#13;
URL: http://wstf.go.ke/toolkit/Downloads/l.%20/ntroducing%20MajiData%20(brochure).pdf and http://www.majidata.go.ke/&#13;
34&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Unlocking the Potential of Information Communications Technology to Improve Water and Sanitation Services | Annex 1: Overview of Ict Tools in the Wash Sector&#13;
M-Maji                M-Maji is a mobile application to improve  Tools: Mobile phones  Stanford University,&#13;
clean water access in the slums. M-Maji                    Umande Trust&#13;
enables residents in Kibera to access Country: Kenya, Nairobi&#13;
information about water from vendors. Year: 2013&#13;
M-Maji provides water information system&#13;
that aims to empower under-served  Agency: Stanford&#13;
communities with better information  University, Umande Trust&#13;
about water availability, price, and quality.&#13;
URL: https://mmaji.wordpress.com/                                               (Hellstr6m &amp; Jacobson,&#13;
2014)&#13;
MajiMatone            MajiMatone  is  a   mobile-enabled  Tools: Mobile Phones  DFID, Twaweza, Daraja&#13;
technology tool that encouraged citizens                   and District Water&#13;
to put pressure on local government Country: Tanzania      Engineers&#13;
to address problems with their rural&#13;
water supplies. SMSs were used to get Year: 2010 - 2011&#13;
citizens involved, and the media was&#13;
used to amplify their voices and increase  Agency: Daraja&#13;
local government accountability for&#13;
water services, with a focus on repairing&#13;
broken down water points and ensuring&#13;
accountability.&#13;
URL: http://www.daraja.org/our-work/rtwp                                        (Hutchings et al., 2012)&#13;
MajiVoice            ICT   application  used  to improve  Tools: Mobile Phones  World Bank, Nairobi City&#13;
communication between citizens and  (SMS)                  Water and Sewerage&#13;
Nairobi City  Water and  Sewerage  Country: Kenya          Company&#13;
Company&#13;
Year: launched 2013&#13;
Agency: World Bank,&#13;
Nairobi City Water and&#13;
Sewerage Company&#13;
URL: http://www.majivoice.com/Introduction%20to%20MajiVoice&#13;
Mobile field assistant  NCWSC uses a mobile meter reader, Tools: Mobile phones  Nairobi City Water and&#13;
the "mobile field assistant" to perform                     Sewerage Company&#13;
meter reading functions. The mobile field&#13;
assistant uses smartphones to collect Year: 2014&#13;
information on geo-references, meter Agency: Nairobi City Water&#13;
readings and location of households.  and Sewerage Company&#13;
URL: http://www.nairobiwater.co.ke/index.html&#13;
www.wsp.org                                                                                            35&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Unlocking the Potential of Information Communications Technology to Improve Water and Sanitation Services | Annex 1: Overview of Ict Tools in the Wash Sector&#13;
M-Pesa               M-Pesa is a mobile phone-based money  Tools: Mobile phones  Safaricom&#13;
transfer and micro-financing service that&#13;
was launched in 2007 by Vodafone for Country: Kenya, Tanzania,&#13;
Safaricom, the largest mobile network  South Africa, India,&#13;
operator in Kenya. M-Pesa allows users  Afghanistan&#13;
with a national ID card or passport to  Year: 2007&#13;
deposit, withdraw, and transfer money&#13;
easily with a mobile device.       Agency: Safaricom&#13;
(Shared Value Initiative, 2012); (R Hope et al., 2011); (Rob Hope, Foster, Krolikowski, &amp; Cohen,&#13;
2011)&#13;
mSchool              mSchool is an SMS tool to report and  Tools: Mobile Phones  Manobi&#13;
monitor water and sanitation in schools.&#13;
It enables students, parents, and teachers&#13;
to monitor and report on school sanitation  Country: Senegal&#13;
facilities. Users send formatted SMSs&#13;
when school hand-pumps, toilets or&#13;
hand-washing systems are in need of Year: 2013&#13;
repair. mSchool forwards alerts to local&#13;
plumbers and contractors in charge to&#13;
quickly fix problems. All the information  Agency: Manobi&#13;
(SMSs) exchanged is mapped in real time&#13;
on mSchool and on dedicated monitoring&#13;
and evaluation dashboards for the Ministry&#13;
of Education, local governments, and civil&#13;
society to track the complaints made and&#13;
if they have been met.&#13;
URL: http://www.nytimes.com/213/4/19/technology/competition-designed-to-spread-basic-technologies.htm/?-r=1&amp; and&#13;
http://appcircus.com/apps/mschool&#13;
mWater (Manobi)       A mobile-to-web based application for Tools: Mobile Phones  Manobi&#13;
consumers and water service providers (SMS)&#13;
(WSP) to support management of water Country: Senegal, Mali,&#13;
access in both peri-urban and rural areas. Benin and Niger&#13;
Year: 2007&#13;
Agency: Manobi, WSP,&#13;
Ministry of Water Senegal&#13;
URL: http://mwater.v3.manobi.com/senegal/                                       (Smertnik, 2014)&#13;
(Hellstr6m &amp; Jacobson,&#13;
2014)&#13;
mWater (USAID)        Low-cost mobile platform tool for testing  Tools: Mobile Phones  USAID&#13;
quality of water                   (SMS)&#13;
Country: Tanzania,&#13;
Rwanda, Ethiopia&#13;
Year: Launched 2013&#13;
Agency: USAID&#13;
URL: http://www.humanipo.com/news/30l88/usaid-injects- 100000-into-mwater-startup/ and http://www.mwater co/news!&#13;
water-cooperation! and http://www.mwater. co/news/div/&#13;
36&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Unlocking the Potential of Information Communications Technology to Improve Water and Sanitation Services | Annex 1: Overview of Ict Tools in the Wash Sector&#13;
ICT~~~ Sumr                                                 tkhls&#13;
NextDrop             NextDrop is an SMS-based software Tools: Google Maps,     Gates Foundation,&#13;
product that lets citizens know when  mobile phones, SMS  University of California&#13;
they are getting water, when there                        Berkeley School,&#13;
Country: India          Bree    col&#13;
is a delay in supply, when there is                       Deshpande Foundation,&#13;
pipe damage that might affect supply and  Year: 2010      Karnataka Water Board,&#13;
when water updates are provided by a                      Hubli-Dharwad Municipal&#13;
community member.                                         Corporation (HDMC)&#13;
URL: www.nextdrop.org and http://social.yourstory.com/2013/1 1/american-dropped-college-solve-problem-water-supply-india/&#13;
and http://www.ischool.berkeley.edu/files/student_projects/nextdrop_final report.pdf&#13;
NFC RFID-Tracked     Programmed near-field communication  Tools: Mobile phones  Nokia Research Center,&#13;
Drinking Water       (NFC)   phones with radio-frequency                       Palo Alto, Public Health&#13;
identification (RFID) for use by Haitian                  School of a university&#13;
water technicians are used to track Year: 2011            (UC Berkeley), and Deep&#13;
chlorine  usage  in thousands  of Agency: Deep Springs    Springs International (DSI)&#13;
households, identified by NFC tags on  International (DSI)  Haiti.&#13;
the drinking water buckets in homes.&#13;
URL: http://www.nfcworld.com/207 1/03/l1/36414/nfc-phones-help-provide-clean-water-to-haiti- (Kaye, Holstius, &amp;Seto,&#13;
earthquake-victims/ and http://www.upm.com/EN/MEDIA/All-news/Pages/Battling-cholera-with- 2012)&#13;
NFC-RFID-tracked-drinking-water-in-Haiti.aspx&#13;
Smart Handpumps      Smart   Handpumps   are  cell-phone  Tools: Mobile phones and  Oxford University&#13;
networks based on low-cost technology  network providers&#13;
for automated monitoring of water Country: Kenya, Zambia&#13;
sources. SIM-cards are placed inside&#13;
hand pump handles to provide real-time  Year: 2011&#13;
monitoring of hand pump functionality.&#13;
It introduces the possibility of a shift to  Agency: Oxford University&#13;
fully-automated systems of management&#13;
and monitoring of water sources.&#13;
URL: http://oxwaterco.uk/#/smart-handpumps/4559322273                          (Smith  School Water&#13;
Programme, 2014)&#13;
Smart Water Metering  Smart water metering refers to a system  Tools: Cell phone networks  UK Department&#13;
that measures water consumption or                        for International&#13;
abstraction and  communicates that Country: Kenya, Zambia  Development (DfID)&#13;
information in an automated fashion for&#13;
monitoring and billing purposes. Smart Year: 2002&#13;
meters differ from conventional meters in&#13;
that they measure consumption in greater Agency: UK Department for&#13;
detail and transmit that information back  International Development&#13;
to the service provider without the need  (DflD)&#13;
for manual readings.&#13;
URL: http://r4d.dfid.gov.uk/PDF/Outputs/Water/         (R Hope et al, 2011), (Oracle, 2009)&#13;
SmartWaterSystems_FinalReport-Main%28Reduced%29_April201.&#13;
pdf&#13;
www.wsp.org                                                                                           37&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Unlocking the Potential of Information Communications Technology to Improve Water and Sanitation Services | Annex 1: Overview of Ict Tools in the Wash Sector&#13;
Taarifa               Taarifa is an open source web application  Tools: Mobile phones  Bill and Melinda Gates&#13;
that enables public officials to tag and                    Foundation, Nokia, Toilet&#13;
respond to citizen complaints about Country: Tanzania, Uganda, Hackers.&#13;
the delivery of sanitation services. The  Ghana&#13;
application focuses on how local councils  Year: 2011&#13;
could increase the quality of their public&#13;
service and become more responsive to&#13;
reported problems. It also offers citizens a&#13;
channel for engaging with local councils.&#13;
URL: www.Taarifa.org and http://appcircus.com/apps/taarifa&#13;
Text to Change        TTC is a mobile solution for social change. Tools: Mobile phones  Text to Change&#13;
The idea is based on using mobile (SMS)&#13;
phones as a driving force in effective  Country: worldwide (five&#13;
communication and positive change.&#13;
TTC enables sending and receiving text&#13;
messages plus analysis and interpretation  Year:&#13;
of the data.                       Agency: Text to Change&#13;
URL: http://www.ttcmobile.com/&#13;
Water Point Mapper    Tool used to produce maps showing  Tools: Google Earth and  WaterAid, SNV, Ingenierfa&#13;
water supply points and their status.  Microsoft Excel     Sin Fronteras - ApD,&#13;
.      Concern&#13;
Country: Malawi, Ethiopia,&#13;
Uganda, Kenya, Ghana,&#13;
Tanzania&#13;
Year: 2010&#13;
Agency: WaterAid&#13;
URL: http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Water-point mapping and_http://www.waterpointmapper.org/ and http://sustainablewash.org/&#13;
resource/tool-2&#13;
Water Quality Reporter  Water Quality Reporter (WQR) a low- Tools: Mobile phones  University of Bristol,&#13;
cost, sustainable water test that can be                   Aquaya Institute, Health&#13;
used widely in low-resource settings in  Country: South Africa,  Protection Agency,&#13;
developing countries. The application  Mozambique, Vietnam and  University of Cape Town,&#13;
was   designed  because  monitoring  Cambodia              PATH, UC Berkeley,&#13;
drinking water quality and water sources  Year: 2009        University of North&#13;
is critical to the delivery of safe drinking               Carolina, University&#13;
water and yet water quality testing in rural Agency: iCOMMS  of Southampton, and&#13;
areas is challenging due to the fact that                   University of Surrey,&#13;
labs for water quality analysis tend to be                 European Union and&#13;
concentrated in urban areas.                                Bill and Melinda Gates&#13;
Foundation&#13;
URL: www.icomms.uct.ac.za/about_aquatest                                         (Champanis &amp; Rivett,&#13;
2012)&#13;
38&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Unlocking the Potential of Information Communications Technology to Improve Water and Sanitation Services | Annex 1: Overview of Ict Tools in the Wash Sector&#13;
WATEX                   WATEX is a groundwater exploration   Tools: Satellite           RTI, UNESCO, UNICEF&#13;
package  used   to locate renewable&#13;
Country: Kenya, Chad,&#13;
ground water reserves in arid and semi- Sudan&#13;
arid environments.&#13;
Year: 2004, 2006, 2013&#13;
Agency: RTI&#13;
URL:www.rtiexploration.com/watex/ and http://eeas.europa.eu/ifs/publications/articles/book2/book%20vol2_part3-chapter471&#13;
watex%20-%20a%20new%20approach%20to%20preventing%20water%20based%20conflicts_alain%20gachet.pdf and&#13;
http:///andsat.gsfc.nasa.gov/?p=6404&#13;
www.wsp.org                                                                                                     39&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Unlocking the Potential of Information Communications Technology to Improve Water and Sanitation Services I Annex 2: Analysis of WASH ICT Tools in Country&#13;
Case Studies&#13;
Annex 2: Analysis of WASH ICT Tools&#13;
in Country Case Studies&#13;
Information Needs    * Information needs     The key driver for the tool was the need for the National Water and&#13;
(Existing information  * Communication needs  Sewerage Corporation (NWSC) to relinquish non-core services and&#13;
ecologies)           * Communication channels  focus more on its core activity of water service provision; coupled with&#13;
* Information Gaps      the need to reduce costs associated with running cash offices and bill&#13;
collections.&#13;
Access to ICTs       * Access to electricity  The areas served by the utility, urban areas and towns, have access&#13;
(ICT infrastructure)  * Access to ICT        to electricity and are covered by all the major telecom providers in&#13;
infrastructure         Uganda.&#13;
* Geographic location   All telecom providers currently support mobile money payment&#13;
platforms.&#13;
The Financial institutions that NWSC partners with are strategically&#13;
located in the urban centers and towns so customers have access to&#13;
payment points.&#13;
Basic use of ICTs    * Literacy rates        The e-water payment platform is appropriate for the customers served&#13;
(simple ICT use)     * Level of education    by the utility.&#13;
* Socio-cultural context  Since the utility serves a vast number of users country wide it uses&#13;
* Basic ICT training    English as opposed to a local language, which has not impeded usage.&#13;
Residents are either literate or semi-literate, but capable of using&#13;
technology to make payments or their banks to effect payments to the&#13;
utility without needing to be trained.&#13;
Meaningful use of the  * ICT capacity building  The closure of cash offices at NWSC forced customers to use the&#13;
ICT tool             * Local and relevant    e-water payment system.&#13;
(level of use of the tool)  content          The existing infrastructure within the financial institutions and telecom&#13;
* Technical local       providers to support mobile payments has greatly contributed to the&#13;
appropriation&#13;
T Sustainabilityclity of th paymes atf                  ome.&#13;
NWSC has set up a reconciliation unit to deal with exceptions of&#13;
erroneous payments and has also revamped its customer care center&#13;
to respond to customer queries.&#13;
The system is integrated with the billing system and customers are&#13;
able to request their bills and make payments without physically going&#13;
to the utility offices but rather using of their phones.&#13;
Enhanced information  * ICT capabilities     As a result of the convenience that mobile technology gives to&#13;
capability              Information literacy  customers, more are using the mobile phones to pay for services&#13;
(multiplier effect)                                    s Communication  instead of walking to the banks or financial institutions. This is also&#13;
capabilities           driven by the ability to query how much one owes the utility and&#13;
* Content capabilities  immediately proceed to the payment options provided.&#13;
* Local technical and social The service is not complicated and no complaints have been lodged&#13;
appropriation          by the utility in terms of the technology itself since the service was&#13;
extended to support mobile payments.&#13;
The utility has registered improvements in payments since customers&#13;
are able to pay outside office hours and on weekends.&#13;
40&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Unlocking the Potential of Information Communications Technology to Improve Water and Sanitation Services I Annex 2: Analysis of WASH ICT Tools in Country&#13;
Case Studies&#13;
Codto               Dieso                  Cas Stdy -  MW Uganda&#13;
Information Needs   * Information needs     Prior to the development of M4W, SNV (one of the implementers)&#13;
(Existing information  * Communication needs  carried out research on the poor functionality of rural water supply.&#13;
ecologies)          * Communication channels  The need identified was twofold: a lack of reliable information on rural&#13;
* Information Gaps      water sources and the need to facilitate reporting and repair of faults&#13;
in rural communities.&#13;
Access to ICTs      * Access to electricity  The typical users of the M4W initiative are based in rural communities&#13;
(ICT infrastructure)  * Access to ICT       with very limited access to electricity and unstable telecom coverage.&#13;
infrastructure        Community users and hand pump mechanics have to move to nearby&#13;
* Geographic location   towns (or trading centers) to have their phones charged at a cost.&#13;
This has resulted in loss of phone batteries as batteries are easily&#13;
swapped and the phones themselves are stolen at the charging&#13;
centers, resulting in additional expenses for the implementers.&#13;
Basic use of ICTs   9 Literacy rates        The community users are typically rural farmers, semi-literate and use&#13;
(simple ICT use)    9 Level of education    their phones for voice calls as opposed to SMS.&#13;
* Socio-cultural context  The M4W application was developed in English and yet many rural&#13;
* Basic ICT training    handpump mechanics are semi-literate. A number of them were&#13;
discontinued and replaced with those who could use the phones. In&#13;
other districts, users had to bring along people who would later re-&#13;
train them on how to use the phone and the system.&#13;
This has caused delays in submitting information to the system and&#13;
has also caused the need for more training, which the implementers&#13;
are not in a position to continue funding.&#13;
Meaningful use of the  * ICT capacity building  The M4W application has not yet been integrated with the Ministry's&#13;
ICT tool            * Local and relevant    information system to support automatic information updates. With no&#13;
(level of use of the tool)  content         linkages to any other systems, the M4W system is still operated and&#13;
* Technical local       managed by the developer (Makerere University) and stakeholders are&#13;
appropriation         given access to download reports or files that they can use to lobby&#13;
* Sustainability       for funding and for their own planning.&#13;
The ministry is not yet keen on taking over the M4W initiative and this&#13;
makes its sustainability and use in the districts very uncertain especially&#13;
when the implementation or project period for the implementers&#13;
comes to an end.&#13;
Failure to create a business model around the use of M4W especially&#13;
for the hand pump mechanics resulted in low use of the technology.&#13;
The M4W implementers are certain that if handpump mechanics start&#13;
to see the M4W phone as a tool that supports their business, since&#13;
they get paid for repairing community water sources and collecting&#13;
data, they would have optimum use for this tool and eventually make&#13;
it sustainable for themselves&#13;
www.wsp.org                                                                                          41&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Unlocking the Potential of Information Communications Technology to Improve Water and Sanitation Services I Annex 2: Analysis of WASH ICT Tools in Country&#13;
Case Studies&#13;
Enhanced information  * ICT capabilities     The M4W has been considered a successful initiative because it has&#13;
capability           * Information literacy  demonstrated that mobile-based tools can:&#13;
(multiplier effect)  * Communication         a. Work in rural settings.&#13;
capabilities&#13;
* Content capabilities  b. Offer an approach that is easier, more cost effective and offers more&#13;
* Local technical and social  reliable data then current paper-based methods and systems in use&#13;
appropriation            by the ministry.&#13;
c. Provide and update data substantially faster than it took the ministry&#13;
to compile data in the past.&#13;
However, the uptake of the tool among community members is low&#13;
mainly due to the cost of reporting a fault and poor sensitisation on&#13;
how to report faults. Part of the reason for this is that no funding had&#13;
been put aside for the sensitisation activities and the districts are&#13;
not financially able to run the M4W activities without the help of the&#13;
implementers.&#13;
Codto DSimeso                               Case- Sd  - iata Keny&#13;
Information needs    * Information needs     MajiData was conceptualized in 2008 by GIZ in response to the need&#13;
(Existing information  * Communication needs  for reliable pro-poor planning data that was identified and prioritized as&#13;
ecologies)           * Communication channels  a key undertaking during the 2007 water sector review performance.&#13;
* Information Gaps      Before MajiData, information on informal settlements/urban poor was&#13;
scarce and often unreliable.&#13;
Access to ICTs       * Access to electricity  MajiData is a web-based application that requires Internet connection.&#13;
(ICT infrastructure)  * Access to ICT        GoK has invested heavily in ICT infrastructure and connectivity which&#13;
infrastructure        facilitates its use.&#13;
* Geographic location   Statistics from KCC indicate an increase of over 18 million Internet&#13;
subscribers over the last 10 years, an indicator of the high potential of&#13;
ICT use in Kenya and for MajiData.&#13;
Basic use of ICTs    e Literacy rates        The application is currently used by WSPs, CSOs working in urban&#13;
(simple ICT use)     9 Level of education    poor settlements, WSBs and WASREB. All these already use ICTs&#13;
e Socio-cultural context  in their operations, so can easily navigate and use the tool, which is&#13;
* Basic ICT training    simple and user-friendly, especially given that the current user rights&#13;
outside WSTF are limited to viewing reports and data sets.&#13;
However, with service provision devolved to counties, their capacity to&#13;
use web-based applications needs to be established.&#13;
Currently there is no linkage or direct interoperability between&#13;
applications in use and MajiData; all users outside WSTF have to&#13;
extract data from the MajiData platform and perform any required&#13;
analysis using other tools. This is time-consuming and compromises&#13;
ownership of information provided.&#13;
42&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Unlocking the Potential of Information Communications Technology to Improve Water and Sanitation Services I Annex 2: Analysis of WASH ICT Tools in Country&#13;
Case Studies&#13;
Meaningful use of the  * ICT capacity building  MajiData provided a comprehensive database on urban poor statistics.&#13;
ICT tool             * Local and relevant    However as the initiative was project driven, no updates have been&#13;
(level of use of the tool)  content          made to the data since 2011, which raises questions in terms of its&#13;
* Technical local       continued relevance.&#13;
appropriation         Application development and deployment was done in a participatory&#13;
* Sustainability        manner. Key stakeholders were able to define their requirements. This&#13;
facilitated meaningful use of the data and confidence in the planning&#13;
and resource allocation at the time.&#13;
MajiData user rights are limited, with only WSTF having full rights to&#13;
directly manipulate data on the platform. However, users (WASREB,&#13;
CSOs as represented by KEWASNET and WSPs) are currently&#13;
manually exporting data to undertake analytical assessments as part&#13;
of their performance reporting and advocacy work.&#13;
Enhanced information  * CT capabilities      The MajiData experience has helped highlight the need for reliable&#13;
capability           * Information literacy  information - strengthening the M&amp;E systems and support the increase&#13;
(multiplier effect)  * Communication         in size and technical capacity of the WSTF IT department.&#13;
capabilities          WSTF funding is now better targeted and beneficiaries (WSPs) are&#13;
* Content capabilities  able to attract funding even outside WSTF because of the increased&#13;
* Local technical and social confidence in data provided to justify their funding proposal.&#13;
appropriation&#13;
The application enabled availability of reliable planning data and&#13;
provided the WSTF a basis for evaluation of funding proposals to&#13;
ensure equity of access as well as better targeting of available and&#13;
limited resources. WSTF has reported increased value for money and&#13;
transparency of its finance allocations.&#13;
In the future KEWASNET intends to build a knowledge management&#13;
center and anticipates using MajiData as one of its information bases.&#13;
Codto DSimeso                               Case- Sd       - tr Tazai&#13;
Information needs    * Information needs     mWater is a smartphone application that was developed to serve a&#13;
(Existing information  * Communication needs  dual function: to update the functionality status of water points and to&#13;
ecologies)           * Communication channels  monitor the water quality of the water point.&#13;
* Information Gaps      A baseline study revealed the need for water quality information to&#13;
influence the choice of safe water sources with the communities.&#13;
Access to ICTs       * Access to electricity  Access to mobile phones in Mwanza is high, which favored the&#13;
(ICT infrastructure)  * Access to ICT        development and use of the mWater app.&#13;
infrastructure        The geographical location of the project area was also an enabling&#13;
* Geographic location   factor. The project area consisted of a mix of piped water supply and&#13;
point water sources. In addition, the communities behavioral practice&#13;
of using multiple water sources, created the need for water quality&#13;
information on the point sources.&#13;
The choice of an ICT solution was borne out of the need for real-time,&#13;
low resource information.&#13;
www.wsp.org                                                                                           43&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Unlocking the Potential of Information Communications Technology to Improve Water and Sanitation Services I Annex 2: Analysis of WASH ICT Tools in Country&#13;
Case Studies&#13;
Basic use of lOTs   * Literacy rates       The application has been put to meaningful use, as evidenced by the&#13;
(simple lOT use)    * Level of education   upgrades to allow for interpretation to the local language; inspection&#13;
9 Socio-cultural context  of the water source; increase privacy of the data; enabling access form&#13;
* Basic ICT training   various platforms such as smartphones and androids and allowing for&#13;
updating of information that was collected in the absence of an Internet&#13;
connection. These upgrades were intended to enhance relevance and&#13;
uptake of the tool.&#13;
The use of the ICT was however hindered by the technical nature of&#13;
the information required. While the communities were able to use&#13;
mobile phones (and therefore the mWater app), they were not able&#13;
to carry out the water quality tests and to interpret the water quality&#13;
parameters tested.&#13;
Meaningful use of the  * ICT capacity building  The capacity of the community members to participate in the data&#13;
ICT tool            * Local and relevant   collection was low.&#13;
(level of use of the tool)  content        The technical nature of water quality testing (testing of physio-chemical&#13;
* Technical local      and biological parameters) meant that the community members were&#13;
appropriation         not equipped to perform the field tests. The project participants&#13;
* Sustainability       therefore consisted of staff of the mWater project, of MWAUWASA,&#13;
MCC, and LVBWO who were then charged with explaining the test&#13;
results to the communities.&#13;
The use of the information was impeded by a lack of remedial action on&#13;
water sources that were found to be contaminated. The communities&#13;
expected the project or the government to provide an alternative safe&#13;
source. Some communities however took remedial steps and applied&#13;
for connection to the piped water network.&#13;
Enhanced information  * ICT capabilities   There has been a multiplier effect created by the availability of&#13;
capability          * Information literacy  information collected by mWater:&#13;
(multiplier effect)  * Communication       The MCC has increased the level of inspection of water sources.&#13;
capabilities&#13;
tcapabilities         The MCC has used the water quality information collected to design&#13;
*Cntehnicaliesoa  hygiene and public health awareness programs and to implement&#13;
* Local thousehold treatment/ disinfection of drinking water.&#13;
appropriation&#13;
Communities that have polluted water sources have requested for&#13;
connection to the piped water system.&#13;
There is potential to increase the functions of the application to&#13;
enhance operational efficiency of MWAUWASA. The project is&#13;
considering expansion of the functionality of the application to include&#13;
meter reading and identification of pipe leakages.&#13;
Information needs   * Information needs    Prior to the mWater pilot almost no regular documentation was kept&#13;
(Existing information  * Communication needs  on the management of rural water supply systems in Niger.&#13;
ecologies)          * Communication channels  The implementation of mWater was based on the following needs as&#13;
* Information Gaps     defined by the Ministry of Water and Sanitation (MHA):&#13;
* Oversee the provision of water services and improve water use&#13;
management, daily operations and maintenance of the network.&#13;
* Create a billing system to support the production of clear financial&#13;
systems and encourage investment&#13;
* Map community water points.&#13;
* Collect data on consumption to better evaluate demand.&#13;
44&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Unlocking the Potential of Information Communications Technology to Improve Water and Sanitation Services I Annex 2: Analysis of WASH ICT Tools in Country&#13;
Case Studies&#13;
Access to ICTs       * Access to electricity  Prerequisites for successful ICT use, namely electricity, telecom&#13;
(ICT infrastructure)  * Access to ICT        coverage and access to ICT tools are limited in Niger, given its vast&#13;
infrastructure         area of 1,267,000 km2.&#13;
* Geographic location   In the pilot region of Tahoua, lack of electricity and purchasing power&#13;
were key challenges. The equipment used which enabled success of&#13;
the pilot phase was largely based on subsidies. It would have been&#13;
difficult for users themselves to purchase the necessary equipment for&#13;
data collection and analysis&#13;
Basic use of ICTs    * Literacy rates        The literacy rate in Niger is very low, even more so in the rural areas&#13;
(simple ICT use)     * Level of education    where 75 percent of the 17 million rural population is illiterate; this&#13;
* Socio-cultural context  required additional efforts during implementation to ensure the&#13;
* Basic ICT training    efficient operation of the tool.&#13;
Once trained users were able to use the application to transmit data&#13;
when the access conditions were met (such as network connectivity).&#13;
The poverty level of the municipalities hampers the implementation of&#13;
the tool.&#13;
The connection costs in Niger are very high and the spread of mobile&#13;
phones reaches only 39.3 percent of the population.&#13;
Despite the simplicity of the application's user interface successful&#13;
implementation and use were limited by the local conditions.&#13;
Meaningful use of the  * ICT capacity building  12 months after the introduction of mWater, enough key data on the&#13;
ICT tool             * Local and relevant    management of rural water systems was collected to allow for accurate&#13;
(level of use of the tool)  content          performance assessment of private operators managing 62 rural water&#13;
* Technical local       points. Through the provision of data mWater has also supported the&#13;
appropriation         regulatory mission of the MHA.&#13;
* Sustainability        The pilot project was deemed so successful that the ministry is&#13;
committed to extending the system to the whole country. Successful&#13;
scale-up of the pilot project will require financial and human resources&#13;
support, along with a coherent exit strategy for donor organizations to&#13;
ensure sustainability.&#13;
Enhanced information  * ICT capabilities     Given optimal operability conditions, mWater has the potential to be&#13;
capability           * Information literacy  an ideal tool for effective management of rural water supply, especially&#13;
(multiplier effect)  * Communication         in the decentralized context of Niger, where water supply management&#13;
capabilities           has been transferred to the districts/municipalities.&#13;
* Content capabilities  However, successful implementation and use of the tool is hampered&#13;
* Local technical and social by limited infrastructure, illiteracy, lack of financial resources at&#13;
appropriation          the district level and in Niamey and current dependency on donor&#13;
organizations.&#13;
Information needs    * Information needs     mSludge was designed with the vision of improving poor households'&#13;
(Existing information  * Communication needs  access to sanitation services - specifically the mechanical emptying&#13;
ecologies)           * Communication channels  of septic tanks. Due to a lack of awareness and income constraints,&#13;
* Information Gaps      only 60 percent of low-income households use desludging services.&#13;
Though the use of mobile phones and a call center, mSludge seeks&#13;
to improve market effectiveness by facilitating the rapid connection&#13;
of supply (mechanical emptying operators with vacuum desludging&#13;
trucks - VDT) and demand (households) at affordable rates.&#13;
www.wsp.org                                                                                           45&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Unlocking the Potential of Information Communications Technology to Improve Water and Sanitation Services I Annex 2: Analysis of WASH ICT Tools in Country&#13;
Case Studies&#13;
Access to ICTs       * Access to electricity  mSludge is currently operational only in urban areas, specifically&#13;
(ICT infrastructure)  * Access to ICT        Dakar, where access to electricity and telecom coverage is adequate.&#13;
infrastructure&#13;
* Geographic location&#13;
Basic use of lOTs    * Literacy rates        The numbers of auctions held and requests handled reported by&#13;
(simple IOT use)     * Level of education    the various partner organizations indicate that the tool is being&#13;
* Socio-cultural context  successfully adopted.&#13;
* Basic lOT training    The tool is enabling competition amongst the operators through online&#13;
auctions - pushing down the cost of the service and optimizing the&#13;
use of the VDT through geolocation.&#13;
Uptake of the tool by households and operators is simple as it is&#13;
based on technology already in use (voice and SMS).&#13;
Households appreciate the ease of finding a desludging service&#13;
provider via the call center, are satisfied with the customer service&#13;
and are recommending the service to their neighbors. The operators&#13;
appreciated the ease of use and implementation, appreciated the&#13;
ease of connecting with customers and are learning more in terms of&#13;
customer service (location, timing.).&#13;
Meaningful use of the  * ICT capacity building  The mapping capabilities of mSludge allow for the collection of socio-&#13;
ICT tool             * Local and relevant    economic data and the creation of a database on sanitation facilities&#13;
(level of use of the tool)  content          within the project area.&#13;
* Technical local       As mSludge breaks with the traditional professional practices of the&#13;
appropriation          desludging market, it could be seen as a threat, especially to the&#13;
T Sustainability        employment of operators unfamiliar with loTS.&#13;
Despite some reluctance on the part of the operators in regards&#13;
to the geolocation application (mFleet) - which was largely due to&#13;
monthly running costs on each truck - the president of the association&#13;
indicated a good sense of ownership.&#13;
Enhanced information  * IOT capabilities     Data on septic tank or latrine pit access is continuously collected to&#13;
capability           * Information literacy  better reflect the needs of the households. For example, household&#13;
(multiplier effect)  * Communication         accessibility by the septic trucks is often a constraint so data on&#13;
capabilities          length of connection required is collected.&#13;
* Content capabilities  The data produced by mSludge is used for more effective management&#13;
* Local technical and social of sanitation services.&#13;
appropriation&#13;
ONAS has access to the data produced by mSludge and can use it to&#13;
monitor sector performance indicators, to evaluate mSludge and the&#13;
impact the tool has on the provision of sanitation services.&#13;
Information needs    * Information needs     mWater addresses the lack of data on the management of rural water&#13;
(Existing information  * Communication needs  systems and their financial status.&#13;
ecologies)           * Communication channels  mWater allows for real-time information sharing, between users,&#13;
* Information Gaps      service providers, consumers and government to ensure better&#13;
monitoring of operations and infrastructure as well as the supply and&#13;
demand for drinking water.&#13;
The ASUFORs who are the main users are responsible for sending daily&#13;
SMS to the mWater platform for the following indicators: production&#13;
levels (volume); functionality (functional or not); and the fund account&#13;
balance (financial profitability).&#13;
46&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Unlocking the Potential of Information Communications Technology to Improve Water and Sanitation Services I Annex 2: Analysis of WASH ICT Tools in Country&#13;
Case Studies&#13;
Access to ICTs      * Access to electricity  Data collection is dependent on availability of electricity to ensure&#13;
(ICT infrastructure)  * Access to ICT       that phones are charged - charging points are accessible even in rural&#13;
infrastructure        areas.&#13;
* Geographic location   Similarly, 2G and 3G networks are accessible in most of the country.&#13;
Basic use of ICTs   * Literacy rates        Data collectors need to be trained in the operation of the tool and&#13;
(simple ICT use)    * Level of education    users of the tool need to be trained in the different methods of data&#13;
* Socio-cultural context  use and analysis.&#13;
* Basic lCT training    Users of the tool (ASUFORs and PEPAM) have the capability to use&#13;
the tool once trained especially as the application makes use of&#13;
technologies already in use (mobile phones, SMS, internet).&#13;
The application can be used on available technologies including GSM&#13;
mobile phones ("feature phones") for the recording of data by SMS or&#13;
data storage, and/or smartphones with GPS for geotagging and the&#13;
internet and online tools for submission, analysis and visualization of&#13;
the data with tools such as a dashboard. Users with smart phones can&#13;
also access the internet for analysis on the job.&#13;
Meaningful use of the  * ICT capacity building  mWater supports the collection of a large amount of data at the local&#13;
ICT tool            * Local and relevant    level with which PEPAM can improve the governance of rural water.&#13;
(level of use of the tool)  content&#13;
* Technical local&#13;
appropriation&#13;
* Sustainability&#13;
Enhanced information  * ICT capabilities    PEPAM has sufficient resources to use mWater in its current form, but&#13;
capability          * Information literacy  any changes and updates to the application requires significant inputs&#13;
(multiplier effect)  * Communication        from Manobi.&#13;
capabilities          For the ASUFORs, training and awareness sessions are conducted to&#13;
* Content capabilities  further improve ownership of the tool.&#13;
* Local technical and social&#13;
appropriation         The data collected can improve the management and monitoring of&#13;
water supply systems. In total, nearly 30,000 water points across the&#13;
country have been referenced using the mWater system and over&#13;
1,000 of these points have mWater+ advanced service.&#13;
PEPAM is using data collected by the tool to assess and monitor the&#13;
achievement of its goals in the rural sector. The WASH sector in Senegal&#13;
would benefit from setting up an integrated platform between PEPAM,&#13;
S6n6galaise de I'Eau (SDE), Office National de I'Assainissement&#13;
(ONAS), DGPRE, NGOs and other sector stakeholders to maximize&#13;
use of the data.&#13;
Codto          Dieso                   mWtr(Mb)- Beni&#13;
Information needs   * Information needs     mWater supports increased understanding and improved management&#13;
(Existing information  * Communication needs  practices, which will be essential as part of the upcoming transfer of&#13;
ecologies)          * Communication channels  close to 500 rural water supply systems to private operators.&#13;
* Information Gaps      mWater allows stakeholders and operators of rural water supply&#13;
systems to be in direct and continuous communication in order to&#13;
share the necessary information on the operation and management of&#13;
the rural water supply systems (RWSS).&#13;
www.wsp.org                                                                                          47&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Unlocking the Potential of Information Communications Technology to Improve Water and Sanitation Services I Annex 2: Analysis of WASH ICT Tools in Country&#13;
Case Studies&#13;
Access to ICTs       * Access to electricity  The ICT infrastructure is generally developed enough to support&#13;
(ICT infrastructure)  * Access to ICT       the operation of the tool. Although some rural operators did face&#13;
infrastructure        connectivity issues and had to resort to specialized solutions, such as&#13;
* Geographic location   USB modems, to access the web platform.&#13;
Basic use of ICTs    * Literacy rates        Use of mWater requires a basic level of literacy. Data collection is done&#13;
(simple ICT use)     * Level of education    using widely used feature phones while smartphones are required&#13;
* Socio-cultural context  to perform more advanced operations such as geo-referencing of&#13;
* Basic ICT training    systems.&#13;
The impact of connection costs are limited as Internet is only required&#13;
for specific tasks such as viewing back data or generating reports.&#13;
Meaningful use of the  * ICT capacity building  The implementation of mWater strengthens user capabilities, as the&#13;
ICT tool             * Local and relevant    application acts as a support system for operators in the field.&#13;
(level of use of the tool)  content          The mapping and inventory of assets create a knowledge base that&#13;
* Technical local       can be employed by WASH stakeholders.&#13;
appropriation&#13;
* Sustainability&#13;
Enhanced information  * ICT capabilities     Data analysis facilitates the monitoring and development of the water&#13;
capability           * Information literacy  sector, while dashboards available via the online platform facilitate the&#13;
(multiplier effect)  * Communication         visualization and interpretation of the data by all actors.&#13;
capabilities&#13;
* Content capabilities&#13;
* Local technical and social&#13;
appropriation&#13;
Codto               Dieso                   AkoFO     - Liberia&#13;
Information needs    * Information needs     The Government of Liberia requires basic information on water point&#13;
(Existing information  * Communication needs  infrastructure, especially in rural areas. Paper-based assessments are&#13;
ecologies)           * Communication channels  time and resource consuming; results are also a challenge to integrate&#13;
* Information Gaps      across the country and between agencies and government.&#13;
Communication channels are restricted, given the limited penetration&#13;
and high cost of mobile telephony services and electricity.&#13;
Knowledge on the extent, state and quality of WASH infrastructure&#13;
and services across the country has been very limited. This knowledge&#13;
is essential in combating and preventing disease, including Ebola&#13;
Access to ICTs       * Access to electricity  Access to electricity is not an issue in Government of Liberia county&#13;
(ICT infrastructure)  e Access to ICT        offices, but it is an issue at the local and community level.&#13;
infrastructure        Neither electricity nor internet connectivity is essential to operate the&#13;
e Geographic location   smartphones with AkvoFLOW. Offline data entry is possible. Remote&#13;
locations may require enumerators carry more spare smartphone&#13;
batteries and SD cards for data backup and storage.&#13;
48&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Unlocking the Potential of Information Communications Technology to Improve Water and Sanitation Services I Annex 2: Analysis of WASH ICT Tools in Country&#13;
Case Studies&#13;
Basic use of ICTs    * Literacy rates        Literacy and education levels of enumerators are not an issue in the&#13;
(simple ICT use)     * Level of education    use of AkvoFLOW by NGOs, Government of Liberia personnel and&#13;
* Socio-cultural context  other actors in the sector.&#13;
* Basic ICT training    These could present challenges when and if AkvoFLOW is used at the&#13;
local and community level.&#13;
Connectivity costs are high, but offline data collection mitigates this&#13;
problem. In more remote locations, smartphone batteries and SD&#13;
cards are essential.&#13;
Using AkvoFLOW has resulted in increased ease of access to baseline&#13;
and midterm information for donor and government reports. AkvoFLOW&#13;
users have expressed satisfaction with the monitoring system and are&#13;
able to use the information collected to benefit program design.&#13;
Meaningful use of the  * ICT capacity building  AkvoFLOW has been assimilated and integrated into the operations of&#13;
ICT tool             * Local and relevant   the organizations and agencies that have adopted it.&#13;
(level of use of the tool)  content          Water point mapping provided a baseline in 2011, but data is outdated&#13;
* Technical local       and needs to be reviewed Other WASH indicators need to be included&#13;
appropriation          beyond water point data, such as sanitation indicators&#13;
The Government of Liberia and stakeholders using the application&#13;
have taken ownership of the data collected and analyzed.&#13;
The cost of using AkvoFLOW is significant.&#13;
The long-term sustainability of using AkvoFLOW depends on&#13;
Government of Liberia support, which has not been forthcoming.&#13;
Sustainability still has a long way to go and it is likely that in the short&#13;
to medium term, donor support will be required to support the ongoing&#13;
and extended use of AkvoFLOW in the Government of Liberia's and&#13;
among NGOs.&#13;
Enhanced information  * ICT capabilities     The National Water Sanitation and Hygiene Promotion Committee&#13;
capability           * Information literacy  Secretariat manages the AkvoFLOW  dashboard and uses it&#13;
(multiplier effect)  * Communication         extensively. However, more technical issues require the intervention of&#13;
capabilities          Akvo specialists in the Netherlands.&#13;
* Content capabilities  Capacitation on use of AkvoFLOW is now provided by the secretariat,&#13;
* Local technical and social which has acquired the skills to train and equip Government of Liberia&#13;
appropriation         employees with AkvoFLOW and smartphones configured for its use.&#13;
Enumerators do not require much in the way of information literacy but&#13;
the diffusion of smartphones, which are not heavily used in Liberia has&#13;
encouraged greater IT literacy.&#13;
www.wsp.org                                                                                           49&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Unlocking the Potential of Information Communications Technology to Improve Water and Sanitation Services I Annex 3: Additional Resources&#13;
Annex 3: Additional Resources&#13;
Impact of ICTs on Economic Development&#13;
ACET, 2014. Growth with Depth, Accra, Washington,DC. Available at: http://africantransformation.org/wp-content/&#13;
uploads/2014/02/2014-african-transformation-report.pdf&#13;
AfDB, 2013. Connecting Africa: An Assessment ofProgress Towards the Connect Africa Summit Goals, Tunis. Available at:&#13;
www.afdb.org.&#13;
AfDB, 2014. TrackingAfrica' Growth in Figures, Tunis.&#13;
APF, 2008. ICT in Africa: Boosting Economic Growth and Poverty Reduction ICT in Africa: Boosting Economic Growth&#13;
and Poverty Redution.&#13;
Deloitte, 2012. eTransform Africa : Modernising Government through ICTs. Transformation-Ready:&#13;
The strategic application ofICTs in Africa, Available at: http://siteresources.worldbank.org/&#13;
EXTINFORMATIONANDCOMMUNICATIONANDTECHNOLOGIES/Resources/282822-1346223280837/&#13;
ModernizingGovernment_Fullreport.pdf.&#13;
Devarajan, S. &amp; Fengler, W., 2013. Africa's Economic Boom: Why the Pessimists and the Optimists are Both Right.&#13;
Council on Foreign Relations, 92(3), pp.68-81. Available at: http://www.heinonline.org/HOL/Page?handle=hein.&#13;
journals/fora92&amp;id=656&amp;collection=journals#656.&#13;
Dzidonu, C., 2010. The Role of ICTs to Achieving the MDGs in Education: An Analysis of the Case ofAfrican Countries by&#13;
Technology in Government in Africa.&#13;
Fleshman, M., Essoungou, A. &amp; Gillespie, J., 2011. Investing in Africa: Digging deep for new opportunities. Africa&#13;
Renewal, (April). Available at: http://www.un.orglafricarenewal/sites/dr7.un.org.africarenewal/files/Africa-Renewal-&#13;
April-2011-en.pdf.&#13;
Heeks, R., 2011. ICT and Economic Growth: Evidence from Kenya. ICT4D. Available at: http://ict4dblog.wordpress.&#13;
com/2011/06/26/ict-and-economic-growth-evidence-from-kenyal [Accessed August 16, 2014].&#13;
IDC 2014: Breaking barriers with technology: A special report on the Kenyan ICT market. An examination of Kenya's&#13;
ongoing technology-powered transformation and push to transition to a Knowledge Society and regional ICT&#13;
powerhouse.&#13;
McKinsey, 2013. Lions go digital: The Internet 's transformative potential in Africa, Available at: http://www.mckinsey.&#13;
com/insights/high_tech_telecoms_internet/lions_go_digital-the internets_transformative_potential in_africa.&#13;
Omwansa, T., 2009. M-PESA : Progress and Prospects, Available at: http://www.strathmore.edu/pdf/innov-gsma-&#13;
omwansa.pdf.&#13;
RSA, 2013. Millennium Development Goals: Country Report 2013, Johannesburg.&#13;
Safaricom, 2013. HI FY14 Presentation. , (November), p.35. Available at: http://www.safaricom.co.ke/images/&#13;
Downloads/Resources_Downloads/Half_Year_2013-2014_Results_Presentation.pdf.&#13;
World Bank, 2011. ICT in Agriculture: Connecting Smallholders to Knowledge, Nwtwokrs, and Institutions. Available&#13;
at: http://www.ictinagriculture.org/content/ict-agriculture-sourcebook&#13;
Yonazi, E. et al., 2014. The transformational use of information and communication technologies in Africa, Washington&#13;
DC.&#13;
50&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Unlocking the Potential of Information Communications Technology to Improve Water and Sanitation Services I Annex 3: Additional Resources&#13;
Yonazi, E. et al., 2012. The Transformational Use of Information and Communication Technologies in Africa., Washington&#13;
DC. Available at: http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2012/05/17120711/transformational-use-&#13;
information-communication-technologies-africa.&#13;
Growth of Mobile Technology in Africa&#13;
GSMA Intelligence, 2013. Sub-Saharan Africa Mobile Economy, Available at: www.gsmaintelligence.com.&#13;
Hope, R., Foster, T., Krolikowski, A., &amp; Cohen, I. (2011). Mobile water payments in urban Africa: Adoption,&#13;
implications, and opportunities (p. 35). UK.&#13;
Hutchings, M. T, Dev, A., Palaniappan, M., Srinivasan, V., Ramanathan, N., &amp; Taylor, J. (2012). mWASH: mobile&#13;
phone applications for the water, sanitation, and hygiene sector. Reportfor Nexleaf... (p. 114). Retrieved from http://&#13;
www.indiasanitationportal.org/sites/default/files/Full_Report_MWASH.pdf&#13;
Rashid, A. T., &amp; Elder, L. (2009). Mobile Phones and Development:, 1-16. Retrieved from http://www.ejisdc.org/ojs2/&#13;
index.php/ejisdc/article/viewFile/529/265&#13;
World Bank, 2012a. ICTs Delivering Home - Grown Development Solutions in Africa. Available at: http://www.&#13;
worldbank.org/en/news/feature/2012/12/1 0/ict-home-grown-development-solutions-in-africa.&#13;
ICT Regulatory Policies&#13;
AfDB, 2013. Connecting Africa: An Assessment ofProgress Towards the Connect Africa Summit Goals, Tunis. Available at:&#13;
www.afdb.org.&#13;
CAK (Kenya) 2014: Quarterly sector statistics report - fourth quarter of the financial year 2013/14 (Apr-Jun 2014)&#13;
ECA, 2007b. The African Information Society Initiative (AISI): A decade' perspective, Addis Ababa: United Nations&#13;
Economic Commission for Africa (UNECA). Available at: www.uneca.org.&#13;
Eberhard R &amp; Kapika J (2013) Peer Review of the Urban Water Sector Regulatory System in Tanzania. ESAWAS&#13;
Kimura, K., Omole, D.W. &amp; Williams, M., 2011. Yes Africa Can P. Chuhan-Pole &amp; M. Angwafo, eds., Washington,&#13;
DC: World Bank.&#13;
Ministry Of Information And Communications, Kenya: National Information &amp; Communications Technology (ICT)&#13;
Policy 2006&#13;
Ministry of Water and Environment,"Water and Environment Sector Performance Report 2014," Government of&#13;
Uganda Report, pp. 17-18, Oct., 2014.&#13;
Ministry of Water and Environment website [Online]. Available: http://www.mwe.go.ug/ . [Accessed: 11-Nov-2014].&#13;
Ministry of Water and Irrigation &amp; WSP (2014) Technical Workshop on Water Point Mapping in Tanzania: Report on&#13;
Workshop Proceedings. Dar es Salaam, Tanzania&#13;
MWAUWASA (2011) Mwanza Urban Water and Sewerage Authority Business Plan July 2011 - June 2014. Mwanza,&#13;
Tanzania&#13;
MOWI (2006) National Water Sector Development Strategy 2006 to 2015 Ministry of Water and Irrigation,&#13;
Government of Tanzania. Dar es Salaam, Tanzania&#13;
MOWI (2014) Water Sector Development Program: Roadmap for the Institutionalization and Enhancement of the&#13;
Water Point Mapping System. United National University, Water Development and Management Institute and&#13;
Ministry of Water and Irrigation, Government of Tanzania. Dar es Salaam, Tanzania.&#13;
www.wsp.org                                                                                                    51&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Unlocking the Potential of Information Communications Technology to Improve Water and Sanitation Services I Annex 3: Additional Resources&#13;
Government of Tanzania, (2002). National Water Policy. URT&#13;
WASREB 2014: Impact 2014 - A Performance Review of Kenya's Water Services Sector 2012 - 2013&#13;
Recommendations for ICTs in WASH&#13;
Champanis, M. et al., 2013. ICTs in the water sector - where do we stand?&#13;
Champanis, M., &amp; Rivett, U. (2012). Reporting water quality: a case study of a mobile phone application for&#13;
collecting data in developing countries. Technologies and Development, 105-114. Retrieved from http://dl.acm.org/&#13;
citation.cfm?id=2160688&#13;
Densmore, M., 2012. Claim Mobile: When to Fail a Technology. , pp.1840 - 1842&#13;
Dimagi, 2013. CommCare. , (MA 02129), pp.1-6. Available at: http://indigotrust.files.wordpress.com/2013/08/&#13;
commcare-overview-august-2012.pdf.&#13;
Heeks, R. (2002). Information Systems and Developing Countries: Failure, Success, and Local Improvisations. The&#13;
Information Society, 18(2), 101-112. doi:10.1080/01972240290075039&#13;
Hellstr8m, J. &amp; Jacobson, M., 2014. " You Can t Cheat the Community Anymore ' - Using Mobiles to Improve&#13;
Water Governance. In I. Niang &amp; C. Scharff, eds. Proceedings of4th International Conference on M4D Mobile&#13;
Communication for Development. Dakar, Senegal, pp. 48-59.&#13;
Hicks, N., 2013. 10 Tips for Successful ICT4D Interventions: An Interview with ICT4D Pioneer Ken Banks. 2013.&#13;
Available at: http://bestict4d.wordpress.com/2013/06/02/10-tips-for-successful-ict4d-interventions-an-interview-&#13;
with-ict4d-pioneer-ken-banks/ [Accessed September 1, 20141.&#13;
Rogers, P. &amp; Hall, A.W., 2003. Effective Water Governance., (7), pp.1-42. Available at: http://dlc.dlib.indiana.edu&#13;
dlc/bitstream/handle/10535/4995/TEC%25207.pdPsequence=1&#13;
Seebregts, C.J. et al., 2008. The OpenMRS Implementers Network. internationaljournal oftmedical informatics (2 0 0&#13;
9), (IJB-2516), p.10.&#13;
Souza, P. E De, Mackintosh, G. S., Suites, C., Town, C., Management, E., &amp; Africa, S. (2014). Lessons Learnt from&#13;
the Implementation of ICT Applications to Support the Water Sector, 1-16. Retrieved from http://greenseesaw.&#13;
files.wordpress.com/2014/05/wisa2014-081-schaub-jones-et-al-b.pdf&#13;
Watson, R.T., Kunene, K.N. &amp; Islam, M.S., 2012. Frugal information systems (IS)., pp.1-12. Available at: http://&#13;
dx.doi.org/10.1080/02681102.2012.714349.&#13;
Waugaman, A., 2014. Using Technology for Social Good: An Exploration of Best Practice in the Use of Information and&#13;
Communication Technologies (ICTs) for Development, Available at: http://solutionscenter.nethope.org/assets/&#13;
collaterals/Using_Technology_for_Social_Good_v2.pdf.&#13;
World Bank, 2012b. The Transformational Use of Information and Communication Technologies in Africa. , p.17. Available&#13;
at: http://siteresources.worldbank.org/EXTINFORMATIONANDCOMMUNICATIONANDTECHNOLOGIES/&#13;
Resources/282822-1346223280837/Summary.pdE&#13;
Methodologies and Frameworks&#13;
B-S.,Gigler, "'Informational Capabilities' - The Missing Link for the Impact of ICT on development," Working Paper&#13;
Series No.1; E-Transform Knowledge Platform, The World Bank, March, 2011.&#13;
Champanis, M., Gool, S., Rivett, U., &amp; Chigona, W (2013). ICTs in the water sector - where do we stand ? Water&#13;
Research Commission (South Africa).&#13;
52&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿www.wsp.org                                                                                                                          53&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿54&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿&#13;
ï»¿July 2015&#13;
Water and Sanitation Program&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
BP 622 Ouagadougou 01 Burkina Faso&#13;
Tel. +226 504 963 43&#13;
Cell. +226 652 576 82&#13;
E-mail: wspaf@worldbank.org&#13;
Web sites: www.worldbank.org/water&#13;
www.wsp.org&#13;
Design and Layout by Eric Lugaka&#13;
WS p                                                                  WORLD BANKGROUP&#13;
sanitation program&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="25161188">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2015/10/25161188/unlocking-potential-information-communications-technology-improve-water-sanitation-services-summary-findings-recommendations
        </url>
        <availablein>French,English</availablein>
        <fullavailablein>
            <available_in lang="French" entityid="090224b08314be65_1_0" node_id="25161188"/>
        </fullavailablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2015/10/25161188/unlocking-potential-information-communications-technology-improve-water-sanitation-services-summary-findings-recommendations</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2015/10/25161188/unlocking-potential-information-communications-technology-improve-water-sanitation-services-summary-findings-recommendations</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2015-10-15T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2015-10-16T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <docm_id>090224b08314be61</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b08314be61</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2015/10/16/090224b08314be61/1_0/Rendered/INDEX/Unlocking0the000and0recommendations.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2015/10/16/090224b08314be61/1_0/Rendered/PDF/Unlocking0the000and0recommendations.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2015-07-01T02:40:01Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2015-10-16T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Unlocking the potential of information
            communications technology to improve water and sanitation
            services : summary of findings and recommendations
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Information Communications Technology
            (ICT) growth and uptake is changing the landscape of
            developing countries. Initial applications are showing how
            ICTs can further WASH goals and priorities, including
            increasing access, improving service delivery and improving
            governance. There already exists a substantial knowledge
            base on the use of ICTs for Development (ICT4D). However,
            too often the knowledge base focuses on the technological
            innovation itself, rather than how it can be embedded into
            sector management and governance systems. This study,
            therefore, aims to take stock and reflect on the findings
            from key ICT applications and experiences both in other
            sectors as well as in the WASH sector itself. By documenting
            and analyzing past successes, failures, enablers and
            barriers of the key applications and experiences, it is
            possible to significantly advance the areas of policy
            development, guidelines, implementation, and scale up of ICT
            in the WASH sector.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Unlocking the potential of information
            communications technology to improve water and sanitation
            services : summary of findings and recommendations
        </docna>
        <display_title>Unlocking the potential of
            information communications technology to improve water and
            sanitation services : summary of findings and recommendations</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2015/07/25161188/unlocking-potential-information-communications-technology-improve-water-sanitation-services-summary-findings-recommendations</listing_relative_url>
        <topic>Water Allocation and Water Supply m1326747 1063,Surface Water Management m1327239 1220,Water m1326522 137,Sanitation and Wastewater m1327393 139,Water Allocation and Water Economics
            m1326745 427</topic>
        <docty>UNDP-Water &amp; Sanitation Program</docty>
        <subtopic>ICT Policy and Strategies,E-Business,Town Water Supply and Sanitation,Water Supply and Sanitation Governance
            and Institutions,Water Supply and Systems</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Water Supply and Sanitation,Private Sector Development,Information and Communication Technologies</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Ndaw,Mouhamed Fadel</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>090224b08314be61_1_0</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>Water and Sanitation Program : report</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Water Supply and Sanitation,Private Sector Development,Information and Communication Technologies</historic_topic>
        <topicv3>Water Allocation and Water Supply m1326747 1063,Surface Water Management m1327239 1220,Water m1326522 137,Sanitation and Wastewater m1327393 139,Water Allocation and Water Economics
            m1326745 427</topicv3>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            tax incentives, financial services, enabling
            environments, e-mail, equipment, quality of services,
            customer, communication infrastructure, communication
            technologies, access to technology, materials, interfaces,
            technology platform, workflow management, video, monitoring,
            information communications technology, copyright,
            information sharing, consultants, capacity building,
            knowledge product, price, literacy rates, management
            systems, pilot project, information systems, web interfaces,
            customer relations, computer, distribution system,
            communications, data, technical assistance, efficiency
            improvements, business partners, performance indicators,
            user group, online database, mobile network, regulatory
            system, financial institutions, connectivity, web,
            interoperability, material, data analysis, rfid, hacking,
            inventory, user rights, business service, data storage,
            transactions, auctions, pdf, information flow, regulatory
            frameworks, inspection, business plan, mobile economy,
            software, best practices, customer base, knowledge base,
            mobile device, mobile phone, gps, communications
            technologies, competitiveness, electricity, networks, user
            community, delivery system, best practice, url, end-user,
            private sector, electronic data, supply chain, radio
            frequency, queries, customer confidence, backbone, result,
            economic development, ict, technical staff, user feedback,
            business, peer-to-peer, phones, electronic payment, access
            to services, performance, e-governance, institution, sites,
            functionality, price competitiveness, financial support,
            call centre, communication, private partnerships, supply
            chain management, new technology, communications networks,
            institutional capacities, photo, hackers, communication
            technology, financial systems, information society, photos,
            payment systems, server, cash flow, financing plan, radio
            frequency identification, human capacity, data entry,
            implementations, supervision, adoption of ict, cell-phone,
            operational efficiency, private partnership, foreign direct
            investments, financial management, information technology,
            e-payment, information system, radio stations,
            implementation stages, capability, information bank, data
            transfer, web sites, financial resources, payment system,
            information, infrastructure development, decision support
            tools, privacy, web services, technological innovation,
            process information, verification, web application,
            penetration rates, reduction of costs, maintenance costs,
            enabling environment, mobile telephony, satellite, payment
            transactions, hardware, online auctions, new technologies,
            institutions, query, link, literacy rate,
            telecommunications, phone number, information gaps, cell
            phone, mobile application, backup, productivity, telephony,
            limited access, private investment, global communications,
            service provider, customer service, training systems, mobile
            communication, social development, call center, application
            development, radio, capabilities, government services,
            access to information, operational efficiencies, users,
            phone, technology, transaction, system development,
            knowledge management, reliability, customer loyalty, supply
            network, results, technology tool, operating environment,
            purchasing power, mobile services, technical issues, open
            source software, universal access, smart phones, mobile
            communications, user interface, videos, information
            communications, payment transaction, images, cell phones,
            virus, licenses, security, network, central server, id,
            human resources, radio-frequency identification, telecom,
            global positioning system, innovation, mobile phones,
            profit, technical support, tagging, business model, number
            of users, customers, interface, database, social issues,
            communications technology, technologies, information
            infrastructure, target, uses, quality of service,
            innovations, knowledge society, e development, user, service
            providers, administrative systems
        </keywd>
        <owner>Water - Water &amp; Sant. Prgrm-AFR (GWASA)</owner>
        <repnb>100297</repnb>
        <alt_title>
            Étude sur la valorisation du potentiel
            des TIC dans le secteur eau, assainissement et hygiène :
            résumé des conclusions et recommandations
        </alt_title>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT for Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies (ICT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Basic Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>On-site Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Marketing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>Freedom of Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT Policy and Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>GIS</ml:concept><ml:concept>Geographical Information Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Land Information Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Connectivity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Lagging Regions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water, Sanitation and Hygiene</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Right to Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>Local Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT Strategy, Policy and Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT Applications</ml:concept><ml:concept>Geographic Information Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Connectivity and Lagging Regions</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>