<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>ï»¿Service Delivery Assessment&#13;
May 2015&#13;
Water Supply&#13;
and Sanitation&#13;
in Indonesia&#13;
Turning Finance into&#13;
Service for the Future&#13;
WSP WORLD BANK GROUP&#13;
water an&#13;
santatonprora&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿This report is the product of extensive collaboration and information sharing between many government agencies, and&#13;
organizations in Indonesia. The core team of the Directorate of Settlements and Housings in the Development Planning&#13;
Agency (Bappenas) has been key partners with the Water and Sanitation Program in analyzing the sector. The authors ac-&#13;
knowledge the valuable contributions made by the Members of the Technical Working Group on Water and Sanitation (Pokja&#13;
AMPL): Bappenas, Ministry of Public Works, Ministry of Home Affairs, Ministry of Health, Ministry of Finance, Ministry of&#13;
Environment, Ministry of Housings, National Statistical Bureau, and the provincial technical working group of the province&#13;
of West Sumatra; by the development partners (UNICEF and ADB) and the National Water Supply Association of Indonesia&#13;
(PERPAMSI).&#13;
The Task Team Leader for the Service Delivery Assessment (SDA) in East Asia and Pacific is Susanna Smets. The follow-&#13;
ing World Bank staff and consultants have provided valuable contributions to the service delivery assessment process and&#13;
report: Martin Albrecht, Rahmi Kasri, Maraita Listyasari, Deviariandy Setiawan and Almud Weitz. The peer reviewers were&#13;
George Soraya and Fook Chuan Eng from the World Bank, Aidan Cronin from UNICEF and Julian Syah from the ADB in&#13;
Indonesia.&#13;
The SDA was carried out under the guidance of the World Bank's Water and Sanitation Program and local partners. This re-&#13;
gional work, implemented through a country-led process, draws on the experience of water and sanitation SDAs conducted in&#13;
more than 40 countries in Africa, Latin America, and South Asia.&#13;
An SDA analysis has three main components: a review of past water and sanitation access, a costing model to assess the ad-&#13;
equacy of future investments, and a scorecard that allows diagnosis of bottlenecks along the service delivery pathways. SDA's&#13;
contribution is to answer not only whether past trends and future finance are sufficient to meet sector targets for infrastructure&#13;
and hardware but also what specific issues need to be addressed to ensure that finance is effectively turned into accelerated&#13;
and sustainable water supply and sanitation service delivery.&#13;
The Water and Sanitation Program is a multi-donor partnership, part of the World Bank Group's Water Global Practice, sup-&#13;
porting poor people in obtaining affordable, safe, and sustainable access to water and sanitation services. WSP's donors&#13;
include Australia, Austria, Denmark, Finland, France, the Bill &amp; Melinda Gates Foundation, Luxembourg, Netherlands, Nor-&#13;
way, Sweden, Switzerland, United Kingdom, United States, and the World Bank.&#13;
WSP reports are published to communicate the results of WSP's work to the development community. Some sources cited&#13;
may be informal documents that are not readily available.&#13;
The findings, interpretations, and conclusions expressed herein are entirely those of the author and should not be attributed&#13;
to the World Bank or its affiliated organizations, or to members of the Board of Executive Directors of the World Bank or the&#13;
governments they represent. The World Bank does not guarantee the accuracy of the data included in this work. The bound-&#13;
aries, colors, denominations, and other information shown on any map in this work do not imply any judgment on the part&#13;
of the World Bank Group concerning the legal status of any territory or the endorsement or acceptance of such boundaries.&#13;
The material in this publication is copyrighted. Requests for permission to reproduce portions of it should be sent to world-&#13;
bankwater@worldbank.org. WSP encourages the dissemination of its work and will normally grant permission promptly. For&#13;
more information, please visit www.wsp.org.&#13;
D 2015 International Bank for Reconstruction and Development/The World Bank&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Water Supply and Sanitation&#13;
in Indonesia&#13;
Service Delivery Assessment&#13;
Turning Finance into&#13;
Services for the Future&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Strategic Overview&#13;
Indonesia has made modest progress in recent years to help  than 100 million people have to gain access to improved&#13;
people gain access to improved water and sanitation ser-  sanitation services to reach the sector targets. Urban ar-&#13;
vices. In 2011, around 55% of the population had access to  eas have had higher access rates to improved services, but&#13;
improved water supply services, and 56% of the population  similar to water supply, the absolute number of people that&#13;
had access to improved sanitation services. Compared to  need to gain access is also still high due to the high rates of&#13;
1993, this is an increase of 17 percentage points for water  urban population growth.&#13;
supply, and 31 percentage points for sanitation. Increasing&#13;
political priority for sanitation in recent years, and the result-  From an institutional point of view, Indonesia has made good&#13;
ing increase in budget allocation for the sanitation subsec-  progress in the past decade in setting up the framework for&#13;
tor, suggests that Indonesia is on the right track to scale up  a well-functioning service delivery pathway. This is reflected&#13;
access to improved sanitation services. It remains unlikely,  in the Service Delivery Assessment (SDA) scorecard, which&#13;
however, that the Millennium Development Goals for sanita-  identified a sound institutional and policy framework. Laws,&#13;
tion will be met by 2015. Similarly, the sector targets of uni-  policies and strategies regulate and guide the service deliv-&#13;
versal access by 2019 remain ambitious, and the increasing  ery and distribute general roles and responsibilities between&#13;
efforts will need to continue to achieve these targets.  line ministries and different levels of government, resulting&#13;
in improved coordination between stakeholders involved.&#13;
Despite the moderate gains in water supply and sanitation  Since decentralization in 2001, local governments have&#13;
as a whole, a closer look at the urban and rural disaggrega-  made good progress in building capacity to provide water&#13;
tion of access rates reveals wide disparities. For water sup-  supply and sanitation services in their districts and cities,&#13;
ply, most access gains were achieved in rural areas, where  and being consistent in reducing inequality by providing ac-&#13;
58% of the rural population had access to improved facili-  cess to low income communities in both rural and urban&#13;
ties in 2011, compared to only 32% in 1993. In urban areas,  areas. Budget allocation to the water supply and sanitation&#13;
almost no nominal increase in access rates can be deter-  sector has increased significantly in recent years, proving&#13;
mined in the last two decades, which is mainly attributed to  the increase in political priority to the sector.&#13;
the high urban population growth that absorbs most of the&#13;
relative gains in access rates.                  While this policy and institutional framework is in place, the&#13;
Service Delivery Assessment process also revealed that the&#13;
For sanitation, both urban and rural areas have seen quite  bottlenecks in the service delivery pathway mainly describe&#13;
an increase in access rates over the past two decades.  the lack of effectiveness with which policies and finance is&#13;
However, despite an increase of 28 percentage points to  turned into access to improved services. The gaps in the&#13;
39% access to rural sanitation services in 2011, the low  planning and budgeting building block, as well as in the out-&#13;
starting point of only 11 % in 1993 suggests that still more  put and uptake and use building blocks provide evidence&#13;
iv                                                                  Water Supply and Sanitation in Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿that Indonesia still faces challenges in turning finances into  to be very significant: The Government needs to allocate an&#13;
services in an effective way.                      additional US$3.1 billion per year for water supply, and an&#13;
additional US$1 .4 billion per year for sanitation. In absolute&#13;
The focus in the future will be to strengthen the existing  numbers, this translates into almost 24 million people per&#13;
system, improve the implementation of policies and strate-  year to gain access to water supply, and 16 million people&#13;
gies into actual outputs, improve the overall effectiveness  per year to gain access to sanitation services.&#13;
and efficiency of the systems and sustain the achieved&#13;
services through strong ownership, operation and mainte-  In summary, in order for Indonesia to achieve universal ac-&#13;
nance. Bottlenecks in the developing and sustaining pillars  cess to improved water supply and sanitation services by&#13;
suggest that high political will needs to be translated into  2019, the Government not only has to significantly raise&#13;
improved investment plans that are linked with local gov-  their financial commitments to the sector, but also find so-&#13;
ernment work plans and budgeting processes. At the same  lutions of how to best utilize the funds through the existing&#13;
time, priority has to be given to the sound and integrated  sector institutions to improve the performance and increase&#13;
planning to ensure the future availability of water resources.  access rates at scale.&#13;
Comparing the number of people who still need to gain ac-  Concretely, the agreed priority actions to tackle these chal-&#13;
cess to services to achieve the sector targets of universal  lenges, and ensure finance is effectively turned into ser-&#13;
access with the financial commitments made by the Gov-  vices, are:&#13;
ement for the near future, the SIDA costing tool calculates&#13;
the financial requirements in capital expenditures until 2019&#13;
Service Delivery Assessment                                                                      V&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Sector-wide&#13;
Recommended Priority Actions                    Who to take action&#13;
* Identify support structures for local governments to assess and improve the  POKJA AMPL (Water&#13;
quality of their strategic planning processes.                and Sanitation Technical&#13;
* Scale up development of human resources through institutionalized  Working Group),&#13;
capacity building.                                            Ministry of Public Works,&#13;
* Urge development of sound investment plans and their endorsement  Ministry of Health,&#13;
and incorporation into local government work plans for immediate  Ministry of Planning and&#13;
implementation.                                               Development (Bappenas),&#13;
* Investigate how local accountability mechanisms are functioning and  Ministry of Finance,&#13;
potential ways to improve this.                               Ministry of Home Affairs.&#13;
* Actively seek involvement of private sector cooperation in the sector.&#13;
* Engage local governments to improve their planning processes to secure&#13;
future availability of water resources.&#13;
Equity&#13;
Recommended Priority Actions                    Who to take action&#13;
* Clearly define poor households at the bottom 40% of the income  Bappenas,&#13;
distribution and design targeted support to ensure inclusive service-delivery.  Menkokesra (Coordinating&#13;
* Improve greater coordination between water supply and sanitation  Ministry for Community&#13;
programs and poverty programs to increase the effectiveness of service  Welfare),&#13;
delivery for the bottom 40% households.                       National Team for the&#13;
Acceleration of Poverty&#13;
Reduction (TNP2K).&#13;
Monitoring and evaluation&#13;
Recommended Priority Actions                    Who to take action&#13;
* Link monitoring and evaluation systems to budgeting and planning  Bappenas,&#13;
processes.                                                    Ministry of Finance,&#13;
* Strengthen the National Water Supply and Sanitation Information Services  BPS (National Statistics&#13;
System (NAWASIS) to become an integrated portal for sector-wide M&amp;E.  Agency), National and&#13;
* Improve local capacity for use of M&amp;E data for sector planning, budgeting  Local POKJAs.&#13;
and targeting implementation support.&#13;
Vi                                                               Water Supply and Sanitation in Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Rural water supply&#13;
Recommended Priority Actions                    Who to take action&#13;
* Establish a clear demarcation of roles and responsibilities within the local  Ministry of Public Works,&#13;
governments after the hand-over of assets on managing and maintaining  Bappenas,&#13;
the water supply systems.                                      Ministry of Home Affairs.&#13;
* Continue to facilitate and support community organizations in accessing&#13;
commercial finance from local banks.&#13;
* Establish comprehensive technical support structures for communities to&#13;
ensure sustainability of water and sanitation schemes.&#13;
* Improve capacity to scale up M&amp;E at local level and use it as resource for&#13;
sector planning, budgeting and implementation support.&#13;
Recommended Priority Actions                    Who to take action&#13;
*Continue to assist 'unhealthy' Local Government Water Utilities (PDAMs) Ministry of Public&#13;
to improve their overall business management condition and become and  Works, BPPSPAM&#13;
remain 'healthy'. by improving asset management, implementing cost-  (Support Agency for the&#13;
recovery tariffs, reduce non-revenue water and improving the management  Development of Drinking&#13;
of human resources.                                            Water Supply Schemes)&#13;
*Intensify assistance to PDAMs to access financial sources such as Ministry of Finance,&#13;
commercial financing or govern ment-assisted schemes.          Bappenas.&#13;
*Continue sLupportive incentive schemes such as Water Hibah to realize&#13;
financial commitments by local government into the sector.&#13;
*Identify further incentives for PDAMs to increase access into low-income&#13;
communities.&#13;
*Engage local governments into a sound planning to secure future&#13;
availability of water sources, e.g. by developing sound water safety plans.&#13;
Service Delivery Assessment                                                                 Vii&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Rural sanitation and hygiene&#13;
Recommended Priority Actions                     Who to take action&#13;
* Strengthen the capacity of the secretariat of the Community-based Total  Ministry of Health,&#13;
Sanitation Strategy (STBM) to coordinate and assist the implementation of  Bappenas.&#13;
STBM in Indonesia.&#13;
* Continue efforts to increase the number and capacity of sanitation&#13;
entrepreneurs and sanitation personnel to support STBM scaling up&#13;
nationwide.&#13;
* Improve capacity to scale up M&amp;E at local level and use it as resource for&#13;
sector planning, budgeting and implementation support.&#13;
* Ensure sufficient funding on software components to ensure leverage of&#13;
household contributions.&#13;
Urban sanitation and hygiene&#13;
Recommended Priority Actions                     Who to take action&#13;
Viii                                                               Water Supply and Sanitation in Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Contents&#13;
Strategic Overview        ......................................................................iv&#13;
Contents....................................                                                                  ...........ix&#13;
Abbreviations andAcronyms..................................................                                 .....................x&#13;
1.bIrodction  ......onm....................................................................................................1.&#13;
1 .  Introduction&#13;
2.   Sector Overview: Access Trends.........................................................3&#13;
3.   Reform Context..        ..................................................................10&#13;
4.   Institutional Framework     ...............................................................12&#13;
5.   Financing and its Implementation........................................................18&#13;
6.   Sector Monitoring and Evaluation........................................................21&#13;
7.   Subsector: Rural Water Supply.........................................................23&#13;
8.   Subsector: Urban Water Supply .........................................................26&#13;
9.   Subsector: Rural Sanitation and Hygiene....................................................29&#13;
10. Subsector: Urban Sanitation and Hygiene..................................................32&#13;
11. Conclusion         .......................................................................35&#13;
Annex 1: The Score of SIDA in Indonesia......................................................38&#13;
Annex 2: Key Inputs for the Required and Anticipated Capital Expenditures.............................. 63&#13;
Annex 3: Comparison with Alternative Estimates of Investment Requirements............................ 69&#13;
Service Delivery Assessment                                                                                                  ix&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Abbreviations and Acronyms&#13;
ADB                  Asian Development Bank&#13;
AKKOPSI              Association of Districts and Cities that Care about Sanitation&#13;
AMPL                 Water and Sanitation&#13;
Bappenas             Ministry for National Planning and Development&#13;
BPKP                 Finance and Development Controller Bureau&#13;
BPPSPAM              Support Agency for the Development of Drinking Water Supply Systems&#13;
BPS                  National Statistics Agency&#13;
CAPEX                Capital Expenditure&#13;
CBO                  Community-Based Organization&#13;
CLTS                 Community-Led Total Sanitation&#13;
CSR                  Corporate Social Responsibility&#13;
DAK                  Special Allocation Fund&#13;
DAU                  General Budget Allocation&#13;
DEWATS               Decentralized Waste Water Treatment Systems&#13;
DFAT                 Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade of Australia.&#13;
DPSP                 Domestic Private Sector Participation Project&#13;
ESI                  Economic of Sanitation Initiatives&#13;
GDP                  Gross Domestic Product&#13;
JMP                  WHO/UNICEF Joint Monitoring Programme&#13;
Menkokesra           Coordinating Ministry for Community Welfare&#13;
MDG                  Millenium Development Goal&#13;
MoE                  Ministry of Environment&#13;
MoF                  Ministry of Finance&#13;
MoH                  Ministry of Health&#13;
MoHA                 Ministry of Home Affairs&#13;
MoPH                 Ministry of People's Housing&#13;
MoPW                 Ministry of Public Works (or Pekerjaan Umum/PU)&#13;
NAWASIS              National Water and Sanitation Information Services&#13;
O&amp;M                  Operation and Maintenance&#13;
PDAM                 Local Government Water Utility&#13;
PAMSIMAS             Water and Sanitation for Low Income Communities Project 3&#13;
PERPAMSI             National Water Supply Association of Indonesia&#13;
Pokja AMPL           Water and Sanitation Technical Working Group&#13;
PPP                  Public Private Partnership&#13;
PPSP                 Sanitation Acceleration Program&#13;
Riskesdas            Indonesia Basic Health Survey&#13;
PRIJM                Local Government Mid-Term Investment Plan&#13;
RPJMN                Mid-Term Development Plan&#13;
SAIG                 Sanitation Australian Indonesian Grant&#13;
X                                                                  Water Supply and Sanitation in Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿SDA                  Service Delivery Assessment&#13;
SSK                  City Sanitation Strategy&#13;
STBM                 Community-Based Total Sanitation Strategy&#13;
SUSENAS              National Socio-Economic Survey&#13;
TNP2K                National Team for the Acceleration of Poverty Reduction&#13;
UNICEF               United Nations Children's Fund&#13;
USAID                U.S. Agency for International Development&#13;
USDP                 Urban Development Sanitation Program&#13;
WSP                  Water and Sanitation Program&#13;
WSSLIC               Water and Sanitation for Low Income Communities Project&#13;
Service Delivery Assessment                                                                  Xi&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿&#13;
ï»¿1. Introduction&#13;
Water and Sanitation Service Delivery Assessments (SDA)  late to developing the services (expenditure of funds, equity&#13;
are being carried out in eight countries in East Asia and the  in use of these funds, service output), and three functions&#13;
Pacific region under the guidance of the World Bank's Wa-  that relate to sustaining these services (facility maintenance,&#13;
ter and Sanitation Program and local partners. This regional  expansion of infrastructure, use of the service). Each building&#13;
work, implemented through a country-led process, draws  block is assessed against specific indicators and is scored&#13;
on the experience of water and sanitation SDAs conduct-  from 0 to 3 accordingly. The scorecard uses a simple color&#13;
ed in more than 40 countries in Africa, Latin America, and  code to indicate building blocks that are largely in place, act-&#13;
South Asia.'                                      ing as a driver for service delivery (score &gt;2, green); building&#13;
blocks that are a drag-on service delivery and that require at-&#13;
An SDA analysis has three main components: a review of  tention (score 1-2, yellow); and building blocks that are mad-&#13;
past water and sanitation access, a costing model to as-  equate, constituting a barrier to service delivery and a priority&#13;
sess the adequacy of future investments, and a scorecard  for reform (score&lt;1, red).&#13;
that allows diagnosis of bottlenecks along the service de-&#13;
livery pathways. SDA's contribution is to answer not only  The SDA analysis relies on an intensive, facilitated consulta-&#13;
whether past trends and future finance are sufficient to  tion process, with government ownership and self-assess-&#13;
meet sector targets for infrastructure and hardware but also  ment at its core. The SDA in Indonesia was led by the Na-&#13;
what specific issues need to be addressed to ensure that fi-  tional Water and Sanitation Technical Working Group (Pokja&#13;
nance is effectively turned into accelerated and sustainable  AMPL) under the guidance of its chair, Ministry of National&#13;
water supply and sanitation service delivery. Bottlenecks  Planning and Development (Bappenas), and with sup-&#13;
can in fact occur throughout the service delivery pathway -  port from the World Bank's Water and Sanitation Program&#13;
all the institutions, processes, and actors that translate sec-  (WSP). Data collection of relevant sector documents served&#13;
tor funding into sustainable services. Where the pathway  as the basis for the following facilitated process. Parallelly,&#13;
is well developed, sector funding should turn into services  financial data on government and donor budgets and ex-&#13;
at the estimated unit costs. Where the pathway is not well  penditures were collected and used to calculate required&#13;
developed, investment requirement may be needed to "un-  and anticipated investments through the SDA costing tool.&#13;
block" the bottlenecks in the pathways.           In a consultation workshop held in June 2013, preliminary&#13;
results of the SDA were reviewed and verified by sector&#13;
The scorecard looks at nine building blocks of the service de-  stakeholders, and areas for priority actions were identified.&#13;
livery pathway, which correspond to specific functions classi-&#13;
fied in three categories: three functions that refer to enabling  Despite the efforts of the SDA to provide an evidence-&#13;
conditions for putting services in place (policy development,  based analysis of the sector, the methodology does have&#13;
planning new undertakings, budgeting), three actions that re-  limitations. In highly decentralized countries an assess-&#13;
For example, refer to the Africa CSO synthesis report available at http://www.wsp.org/sites/wsp.org/fies/pubicat ionu/CO-Syntheianeport.pdf&#13;
Service Delivery Assessmentay&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿ment at national level will inevitably lead to generalizations  improved water and sanitation services is being circulated&#13;
of the performance at local level. This is especially true in  among senior government officials involved in the sector.&#13;
the Indonesian context, where water supply and sanitation  While a final decision is pending upon official approval of&#13;
service delivery is the responsibility of districts and cities,  the RPJMN, it is likely that targets will be set at 100% ac-&#13;
of which there are more than 500. Among local govern-  cess by 2019. It was therefore decided to use these num-&#13;
ments, performance level varies substantially between well-  bers for the calculations of investment requirements and for&#13;
performing ones and those that still have a long way to go  references made in this report.&#13;
to meet the sector targets. The SDA does not claim to be&#13;
representative of the diversity of this decentralized country,  The discussions within the structured SDA framework in-&#13;
but rather seeks to give a general impression of the sector  cluding the scorecard exercise as well as discussing sub-&#13;
performance from a national level point of view. However,  sector targets and identifying funding requirements and&#13;
interest was expressed by several Indonesian provincial  gaps informed ongoing discussion forums, technical stud-&#13;
governments to have the SDA methodology applied for an  ies and briefings to higher echelons. Ultimately, this report&#13;
analysis at the provincial level.                aims to support the Indonesian government in their assess-&#13;
ment and evaluation of the water and sanitation service de-&#13;
The Service Delivery Assessment in Indonesia has been  livery pathway, locate bottlenecks and present the agreed&#13;
aligned with the preparation process of the third five-year  priority actions to help address them.&#13;
mid-term development plan (RPJMN) 2015-19. This pro-&#13;
cess also requires adjusting the targets for water supply  The Water and Sanitation Program in collaboration with the&#13;
and sanitation coverage by the end of the RPJMN period.  Pokja AMPL and other valuable stakeholders produced this&#13;
Currently, the idea of how to achieve universal access to  SDA report.&#13;
Figure 1: Map of Indonesia&#13;
karta&#13;
'z'3&#13;
2eWater Supply and Sanitation in Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿2. Sector Overview: Access Trends&#13;
Access: Assessing Past Progress&#13;
Data from the Joint Monitoring Programme2 (JMP) suggest  improved sanitation facilities between the rural (44%) and&#13;
that Indonesia made modest gains in terms of increasing  urban (73%) population. The amount of treated wastewater&#13;
access to improved water supply and sanitation (see Figure  is also still low, with only about one percent of the urban&#13;
2.1). Access to improved water supply, which was already  population having access to sewerage systems.' Therefore,&#13;
quite high in 1990 at 70%, rose to 84% in 2011 and is ex-  continuous high efforts will be needed to achieve the tar-&#13;
pected to meet, albeit barely, the Millennium Development  gets of 100% access to improved sanitation by 2019.&#13;
Goal (MDG) target by 2015. Most of the gains are in rural&#13;
areas, where access rates increased from 61 % of the popu-  Government and JMP estimates generate similar conclu-&#13;
lation in 1990 to 76% in 2011. Access to improved facilities  sions with respect to the low access rates and wide disparity&#13;
in urban areas changed very little between 1990 (90% of the  in access rates between rural and urban areas. Government&#13;
population) and 2011 (93%). The JMP also estimates that  statistics further indicate that, if current trends continue, the&#13;
only a small proportion of the population (21%) had access  country is likely to miss government targets in 2019 by a wide&#13;
to piped facilities,                                    margin.&#13;
Government estimates of access to improved water sup-   Figure 2.1 Progress in water supply access&#13;
ply, which are based on the national socio-economic survey&#13;
(SUSENAS), use more stringent criteria and indicate lower&#13;
access rates compared to the JMP3. Trends in government&#13;
indicators suggest that, despite the relatively sharp increase&#13;
in access rates from 2009 to 2011, considerably higher ef- Tr80%&#13;
forts are needed to achieve the target of 100% access to                                                    -&#13;
improved water supply by 2019.t i0v                                                   s&#13;
0 C&#13;
As of 2011, JMP estimates indicate that only 59% of thec&#13;
Indonesian population had access to improved sanita-          20%-&#13;
tion facilities (Figure 2.2). Compared to the past two dew         -_p&#13;
cades, progress in increasing access in recent years has        1990  1995   2000  2005   2010   2015  2020&#13;
been more rapid, suggesting that the country is on the right&#13;
path towards scaling up access to sanitation services by           iMP improved estimates   0 M2DG target&#13;
2015. However, there is still a wide disparity in access to  SDA Costing toosp  JMP (21), and Bappenas&#13;
2 JMP (2013) Progress on Drinking Water and Sanitation: 2013 Update. UNICEF and WHO.&#13;
Based on the JMP .eport on Intercountry Workshop (2009), there are some major discrepancies between JMP and national data in Indonesia: differences in&#13;
data sources, methodologies, population estimates, urban/rural definitions and definitions of'adequate' and sustainable'.&#13;
The targets for water supply and sanitation are currently being considered by Bappenas for the third Medium-term Development Plan (RPJMN) 2015-1.&#13;
rSee Eales K., . Siregar, E. Febriani and . Blackett (2013) Review of Community Managed Decentralized Wastewater Treatment Systems in Indonesia, WSP,&#13;
February. Also see World Bank and AusAID (2013) Urban Sanitation teview: A Call for Accelerating Action, Draft report, May.&#13;
6 JMP (2013) Progress on Drinking Water and Sanitation: 2013 Update. UNICEF and WHO.&#13;
Service Delivery Assessment                                                                                3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Figure 2.2 Progress in sanitation access             The picture for sanitation is less optimistic. Both in urban&#13;
and rural areas there is a big gap between access to im-&#13;
proved sanitation within households in the lowest two&#13;
too%-quintiles in urban (40% and 65%) and in rural areas (36%&#13;
180%                                             and 65%), and the higher three quintiles (82% - 100% in&#13;
&gt;                                      both urban and rural areas). Moreover, there is still a huge&#13;
6 &gt;0 60%-                                           number of people practicing open defecation both in urban&#13;
0 C                                    (37%) and rural areas (43%). This provides evidence that&#13;
2 20%-&#13;
W                                      sanitation programs should re-validate and possibly recon-&#13;
&lt; m20%-                                           sider their strategy of how to target the bottom 40% of the&#13;
population.&#13;
0%&#13;
1990  1995  2000  2005  2010   2015 2020&#13;
Figure 2.3 Access to urban and rural water supply by&#13;
-0- JMP improved estimates  0 MDG target               quintile&#13;
SDA Costing tool, JMP (2013)7, and BPS                       Access to urban water supply by quintile&#13;
100            0     0      0&#13;
13           8&#13;
Equity of Access                                             23&#13;
a                                      Otherunierproved&#13;
Assessing access to improved services disaggregated by  a&#13;
0&#13;
wealth levels in Indonesia provides a more nuanced and  40*Ppdnpreis&#13;
less positive picture than national averages. For water sup-  _&#13;
ply, access to improved services is relatively equally dis-  20&#13;
tributed between the four higher wealth quintiles, while the&#13;
lowest quintile is lagging slightly behind (Figure 2.3). In ur-  Poorest  2nd  3rd  4th  Richest&#13;
ban areas, 74% of the people in the lowest quintile have&#13;
access to improved water supply, compared to 86% - 96%       Access to rural water supply by quintile&#13;
in the higher quintiles. In rural areas, the situation is more&#13;
severe, with only 57% of the people in the poorest quintile  100&#13;
having access to services, compared to 75% - 93% in the  0         23&#13;
higher quintiles.                                     _&#13;
a                                      Otherunirmproved&#13;
0 60                            4&#13;
0)                          U  Other ierproved&#13;
While progress has been made within each of the quintiles,  :&#13;
access to piped water supply is still very low for people in&#13;
the poorest urban quintile (9%) and in the lowest three rural  20&#13;
quintiles (3% - 11 %). The rest of the people with access to&#13;
improved water supply is serviced through protected wells,  0&#13;
Poourlaea hrest isnd  big 4th  Resteacsstim&#13;
rainwater or refill water.&#13;
National quintiles&#13;
JqP (2013) Progress on Drinking Water and Sanitation: 2013 Update. UNICEF and WHO.&#13;
4                                                                       Water Supply and Sanitation in Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Figure 2.3 Access to urban and rural sanitation by    Investment Requirements:&#13;
quintile                                    Testing the Sufficiency of Finance&#13;
Access to urban sanitation by quintile&#13;
In line with the current preparations of the third Mid-term&#13;
100o&#13;
100                                   Development Plan (RPJ MN) 2015-2019, the SDA costing&#13;
C&#13;
0                                                   tool estimates the investments required to meet the tar-&#13;
0  0&#13;
16                       U Open Defecation  gets of universal access to improved water and sanitation&#13;
60U&#13;
CL6                                     Unionpro-ed  services by 2019. It also facilitates a comparison of these&#13;
23mroe                                requirements with sector investments in order to provide a&#13;
40a Improved&#13;
20                                                 sense of funding situations.&#13;
20   .&#13;
The analysis derives capital expenditure (CAPEX) require-&#13;
0&#13;
Poorest  2nd  3rd   4th   Richest              ments, representing hardware costs of new facilities as well&#13;
as replacement costs of existing facilities at the end of their&#13;
Accesseconomic life cycle. Estimated CAPEX requirements are fur-&#13;
Ather disaggregated between publicly funded, donor funded&#13;
100                                                and investments contributed by households'. Key inputs in&#13;
60&#13;
:314                                             and target year access rates, (b) population projections, (c)&#13;
a o                                     OenDecome    unit costs of different facilities and (d) technology mix at the&#13;
(V                                      Unimproved&#13;
-.  21                              Impove      base year and target year. Access rates for the base year&#13;
~40                                  U  Imeproved&#13;
o                                                   (2011), which were based on the SUSENAS survey, were ob-&#13;
20                                                tained from the National Statistics Agency (BPS) and Bappe-&#13;
nas. The analysis assumes government targets of universal&#13;
0                                    access to improved water supply and sanitation by 2019. It&#13;
Poorest  2nd  3rd    4th  Richest&#13;
Poorst  2d  3d  4t  Ricestalso assumes that 6% of the urban population will have ac-&#13;
National quintiles                   cess to sewerage systems by 2019.&#13;
Investment data were collected from publicly available doc-&#13;
Reomene prort acin fo equity,                  uments and websites, and subsequently validated through&#13;
visits to the various stakeholders. The collected information&#13;
Cleary define poor households at the bottom 40% of&#13;
the income distribution and design targeted support to  was divided between recent and anticipated investments,&#13;
ensure inclusive service-delivery                  which represent the average annual budgets of govern-&#13;
Improve greater coordination between water supply  ment, development partners and users from 2009 to 2011&#13;
and sanitation programs and poverty programs to    and 2012 to 2014, respectively. Expenditures were also dis-&#13;
increase the effectiveness of service delivery for the  aggregated as follows: (a) sector - water supply or sanita-&#13;
tion, (b) location - rural or urban, (c) nature - hardware or&#13;
software, (d) year, and (e) budget versus actual.&#13;
Investments of utilities, NGOs and the private sector were excluded in the analysis because of the lack of summaty information.&#13;
Service Delivery Assessment                                                                             5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿perts. Provincial and district budgets for 2009 to 2011 were&#13;
Box 1.1 Special Allocation Fund - DAK              provided by the World Bank. Budgets for 2012 and 2013&#13;
DAK grants represent central government transfers to lo-  were extrapolated using the available data.&#13;
cal governments for specific purposes that are of interest&#13;
to the central government. Sectors, geographical locations  Funds from development partners represent the invest-&#13;
that receive these grants as well as the total grant amount&#13;
are identified in the Government Annual Work Plan and are  ments/loans coming from the Asian Development Bank&#13;
decided on a yearly basis. For water and sanitation, these  (ADB), the Australian Department for Foreign Affairs and&#13;
funds are intended for providing (a) drinking water and sani-  Trade (DFAT), the Japan International Cooperation Agency&#13;
tation for the improvement of health conditions, (b) house-&#13;
hold and communal connections for the poor, and (c) access  (JICA), the Islamic Development Bank (IDB) and the World&#13;
to safe water for remote areas difficult to reach. A condition  Bank.&#13;
of the DAK provision is that the recipient local governments&#13;
should match at least 10% of DAK funds through their own&#13;
budget. Challenges linked to the DAK include insufficiency  Figure 2.4 shows estimates of anticipated and recent ex-&#13;
of funds to meet the specific requirements and the difficulty  penditures for the water and sanitation sector of Indonesia&#13;
to track and monitor the use of the funds.         based on the methodology discussed above. It indicates&#13;
that nearly two-thirds of anticipated investments are ex-&#13;
pected to come from local governments. The large share&#13;
Information on government investments was obtained from  of local government units, which in the current analysis was&#13;
the Ministry of Finance, Ministry of Public Works and Bap-  only estimated rather than based on published documents,&#13;
penas. Central government funding captures expenditures  stresses the importance of reviewing the budgets and ac-&#13;
under the regular budget for water and sanitation and the  tual expenditures of these institutions in a recommended&#13;
Special Allocation Fund (DAK).                        follow-up activity.10&#13;
Local government funds capture their share of contribu-  A more detailed description of the sources and limitations of&#13;
tions to DAK funding from national level as well as rough  the information used in the analysis is presented in Annex 2.&#13;
estimates of expenditures for water supply and sanitation&#13;
in provincial and district budgets. Based on interviews with  Figure 2.4 Estimated investments for water and&#13;
government officials, local governments are expected to         sanitation by source of funding&#13;
contribute 10% of DAK-funded projects.                              Water and Sanitation Total&#13;
2,500&#13;
The analysis also assumes that the following shares of pro-&#13;
vincial budgets were allocated to water supply and sanita-  2,000&#13;
tion: 0.b15% for rural drinking water supply, 0.15% for urban&#13;
water supply, 0% for rural sanitation, and 0.2% for urban                                    e     ex&#13;
pectd t coe fom oca goernent. Tentlargershen&#13;
sntto.Additionally, the following shares of district and                                Ceta0ovrmn&#13;
saiaio.f loal goenetuis*hihi h                                           urn Lonalysis wasn&#13;
city budgets are allocated to water supply and sanitation:  Eocment&#13;
1 % for rural water supply, 1 % for urban water supply, 0%a&#13;
for rural sanitation, and 0.7% for urban sanitation. These&#13;
proportions were derived by examining documents from the       Anticipated expenditures Recent expenditures&#13;
World Bank9, Waspola and consultations with various ex-        a   2012-2014    (2009-2011)&#13;
World Bank (2013) Urban Sanitation Review: Indonesia Country Study, World Bank Group, Washington D.C., September.&#13;
LOne recommended follow-up activity would be a more detailed analysis of government budgeting and spending. The World Bank is currently in the process&#13;
of conducting a Water and Sanitation Public Expenditure aeview.&#13;
6                                                                        Water Supply and Sanitation in Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Table 2.1 presents the annual averages of the CAPEX re-    Table 2.1 also shows that anticipated public CAPEX are&#13;
quirements and anticipated investments that were estimat-  about US$1.6 billion per year for water supply and US$496&#13;
ed for Indonesia. It indicates that national targets will be met  million per year for sanitation. Accounting for about 0.2% of&#13;
if about 24 million people per year gain access to improved  2012 GDP, most of these funds are expected to come from&#13;
water supply, and 16 million people per year gain access   domestic sources.&#13;
to improved sanitation facilities. Relatively rapid population&#13;
growth also implies that a larger proportion of the required  Subtracting the sum of anticipated CAPEX contributions&#13;
beneficiaries are located in urban areas.                  of the public and households from CAPEX requirements&#13;
suggests deficits of ULS$2.4 billion per year for water sup-&#13;
The people that will need access to improved water supply  ply and US$1.4 billion per year for sanitation. This implies&#13;
and sanitation facilities translate to CAPEX requirements of  that projected investments for 2012 to 2014 fall far short of&#13;
US$4.7 billion per year and 2.8 billion per year, respectively.  the amounts required to meet targets, especially for water&#13;
Higher per capita costs and number of people requiring ac-  supply. The expected deficits from 2012 to 2014 suggest&#13;
cess explain the higher investment requirements for water  the need for higher expenditures from 2015 to 2019 if the&#13;
supply. The required CAPEX for urban areas is also higher  country wishes to achieve its targets for water supply and&#13;
than for rural areas mostly as a result of higher per capita  sanitation.&#13;
costs."1&#13;
Table 2.1   Coverage and Investment Figuresa&#13;
Cooerageble                      1 AnnualhCAPEX  Anticipated public CAPEX  ic  CAPXar&#13;
(bvase ear g201  requiring     requirement               2012-2014           household  surplus&#13;
(bs er  09     access     Total    Public   Domestic   External   Total     CAPEX    (deficit)&#13;
o% '000/year                                b$ million/year&#13;
Rural water supply  58%   100%     9,283      772       315       733        58       791        457       476&#13;
Urban water supply  52%   100%     14,637    3,975      2,868     747        25       771        298      -2,906&#13;
Water supply     55%      100%     23,920    4,748      3,183     1,480      83       1,563     755       -2,430&#13;
total&#13;
Rural sanitation  39%     100%     8,380      414        4         39        29        69       410        65&#13;
(on-site)&#13;
Urban sanitation  7%      10        ,8        ,4         ,3        0          8       47         49       -,7&#13;
(waste treatment)  7%     10        ,8        ,4        ,3         0          847               49        -,7&#13;
Sanitation       56%      100%     15,764    2,755      1,443     439        57       496        848      -1,411&#13;
total&#13;
Notes:                                                          GPColumns may not add up due to rounding.&#13;
Sources: SDA costing, JMP (2013)do, BPS, Bappenas.&#13;
1 There are other studies that preaent alternative estimatea of investment requirements for the water supply and anitation sector of Indonesia. The estimates&#13;
from theae studios and short comparison with the estimates preaented here are provided in Annex 3.&#13;
pJMP (2013) Progresa on Drinking Water and Sanitation: 2013 Update. UNICEF and WHO.&#13;
Service Delivery Assessment                                                                                      7&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿There is some uncertainty over the estimated deficits. Ag-    investments"' from 2009-11. While this is a good sign, an-&#13;
gregate and sector-specific deficits can be reduced by ac-    ticipated investments still fall short of investment require-&#13;
counting for expenditures of utilities and the private sector.  ments.&#13;
The implied reduction in the deficits may also be partially&#13;
or wholly offset when one considers the fact that the antici-  Annual operation and maintenance expenditures for wa-&#13;
pated household CAPEX is no more than a rough estimate       ter supply and sanitation facilities are important consider-&#13;
of the amounts that the households are expected to con-       ations. These expenditures impose pressure on the budgets&#13;
tribute. However, it is important to note that encouraging    of households in the case of private facilities like toilets. It&#13;
households to invest in improved facilities also entails costs  is also a burden on utilities in terms of the need to gener-&#13;
in terms of efforts by government and other agencies in so-   ate income for their daily operations. Table 2.2 shows that&#13;
cial outreach and demand creation.                            water supply and sanitation service provision requires an-&#13;
nual operation and maintenance funds of US$538 million&#13;
Figure 2.5 and Figure 2.6 indicate that anticipated invest-   and US$262 million, respectively. Most of these funds are&#13;
ments (excluding the contribution of households) for 2012-    expected to be used in urban areas.&#13;
14 in water supply and sanitation are higher than recent&#13;
Figure 2.5 Required vs anticipated (public) and               Figure 2.6 Required vs anticipated (public) and&#13;
assumed (household) expenditure for water                     assumed (household) expenditure for&#13;
supply                                                        sanitation&#13;
Total water supply                                              Total sanitation&#13;
Lnt  5,000                                                    St 3,000&#13;
Z)                                            V                                              Household&#13;
C 4,500D&#13;
0                                           Household                  a 2,500  m                        Efteraal&#13;
42 0                                       *  External     .2&#13;
an3,500                                                    E U                                           Domestic&#13;
* Domestic         2,000&#13;
S3,000                                                      SSewerage&#13;
1a                                             Replacecent                                                  system&#13;
E  2,500                                                      a)  1,500&#13;
2,00 uNew 2  R                                                                                              Replacement&#13;
assme                                                   1,000                                     New&#13;
C:  1,500&gt;&#13;
&lt;/ 1,000                                                      mo  500&#13;
C   500                                        H&#13;
&lt;   ,0 -                 WW,0                                                                               Etra&#13;
&lt;&#13;
Total investment  Anticipated  Recent investment              Total investment  Anticipated  Recent investment&#13;
requirement  investment 2012-2014  200.-2011                 requirement  investment 2012-2014  2009-2011&#13;
Source: SDA costing. Note: Recent investments do not eccount for the contribution of  Source: SDA costing. Note: Recent investments do not account for the contribution of&#13;
households,.                                                  households.&#13;
1) Recent investments do not include the contribution of households.&#13;
8                                                                                   Water Supply and Sanitation in Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Table 2.2 Annual operation and maintenance&#13;
requirements&#13;
Subsector                          O&amp;M&#13;
US$ million/year&#13;
Rural water supply                            64&#13;
Urban water supply                           474&#13;
Water supply total                           538&#13;
Rural sanitation                              31&#13;
Urban sanitation                             231&#13;
Sanitation total                             262&#13;
Source: SDA Costing.&#13;
Note: Columns may not add up due to rounding.&#13;
Service Delivery Assessment                                                                                                             9&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿3. Reform Context&#13;
In the decades between the 1970s and the 1990s, Indone-        experience and skills needed in their new role. As a con-&#13;
sia implemented an extensive water and sanitation devel-       sequence of this lack of skills as well as of the inadequate&#13;
opment program that resulted in remarkable achievements         availability of capital funding for investments and operation&#13;
in the sector: a tenfold increase in production capacity of    and maintenance, water supply services provided by local&#13;
piped water supply, reaching 94,000 liters per second in       water utilities (PDAMs) and community groups suffered se-&#13;
1997, a full cost-recovery and low-income focused tariff       rious degradation in the following years. In several cases,&#13;
policy and growing private sector participation in the de-     the challenges in service provision continue onwards until&#13;
livery of water supply services. However, the country ex-      today.&#13;
perienced a significant set-back in the economic and in-&#13;
stitutional landscape when the Asian financial crisis hit in    The situation in urban areas is further exacerbated by the&#13;
1997. Further, a law was passed to implement nationwide        fact that access rates to water supply services cannot catch&#13;
decentralization reforms in 2001, which handed responsi-        up with high urban population growth rates of around 4%.14&#13;
bilities from central to local city and district levels, including  Against this backdrop, the government's commitment to&#13;
the provision of water and sanitation services. Local gov-     the Millennium Development Goals (MDGs) in 2000 had a&#13;
ernments, being newly responsible for service provision fol-   considerable impact on refocusing public investments on&#13;
lowing decades of centralized structures, were lacking the     water and sanitation sector priorities.&#13;
Table 3.1   Key dates in the reform of the sector in Indonesia&#13;
Year                                                     Reform Context&#13;
1945          Independence&#13;
2001          1 January 2001 Law No. 22/1999 implemented a beginning of decentralization reforms and local autonomy period&#13;
2003          Establishment of the inter-ministerial technical water supply and sanitation working group (Pokja AMPL)&#13;
2004          Law No. 7/2004 on water resources&#13;
2005          Government Decree No 16/2005 on development of water service systems&#13;
2008          Ministry of Health Decree No 832/2008 on national community based total sanitation program&#13;
2009          Presidential Regulation No.29/2009 on Guaranty and Interest Subsidy by National Government to Accelerate Provision of Water Supply&#13;
SBappenas, "Perkembangan Kebijakan Penyediaan Air Minum", http://perkim-Bappenas.info/index.php?prm-page_-id=l&amp;prm-id=21&amp;prm2ype-d=4&amp;prm-&#13;
parentuid=20&amp;prmpdocwcatiid=4&amp;prmtiext=airofejarah.php&amp;prmaubn=Sejarah&#13;
10                                                                                     Water Supply and Sanitation in Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿As a response, the Indonesian government strengthened  SDA scorecard tool was developed to provide a snapshot&#13;
the responsibilities for the water and sanitation sector de-  of the reform progress along the service delivery pathway.&#13;
velopment within five line ministries: Bappenas, the Min-  The scorecard was designed to assist the government in&#13;
istries of Public Works, Home Affairs, Health and Finance.  consolidating information on the status of water supply and&#13;
In line with political decentralization reforms, the service  sanitation based on subsector development progress. It&#13;
provision shifted from central government to local govern-  does so by grouping the service delivery pathway into three&#13;
ments, from projects to programs, from government of-  pillars, each of which comprising of three building blocks:&#13;
ficers to communities, from infrastructure construction to  developing services (policy, planning and budget), enabling&#13;
sustainable infrastructure and behavior change, and from  services (expenditure, equity and output) and sustaining&#13;
loans to increasing financial contributions from govern-  services (maintenance, expansion, user outcome). The re-&#13;
ment, communities and the private sector. A number of  suits of the scorecard are then interpreted in the light of&#13;
supporting laws and regulations were issued to enable a  progress, past spending, future funding needs and com-&#13;
conducive environment for sector development (see Table  mitments.&#13;
3.1).&#13;
Section 4 to 6 highlight challenges across three thematic&#13;
The reform history puts the service delivery pathway into a  areas: the institutional framework, finance, and monitoring&#13;
broader historical context that allows the report to explore  and evaluation (M&amp;E). The scorecards for each subsector&#13;
the progress of different pillars of service provision. The  are presented in their entirety in sections 7 to 10.&#13;
Service Delivery Assessmentssp&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿4. Institutional Framework&#13;
Priority actions for institutional framework&#13;
* Identify support structures for local governments to assess and improve the quality of their strategic planning pro-&#13;
cesses.&#13;
* Clarify roles and responsibilities for regulation and operation of urban sanitation service provision at local govern-&#13;
ment level.&#13;
* Ensure efficient implementation of agreed commitments on water and sanitation sector development.&#13;
* Scale up development of human resources through institutionalized capacity building.&#13;
* Establish a comprehensive technical support structure for communities to ensure sustainability of water and sani-&#13;
tation schemes.&#13;
Decentralization and Coordination&#13;
With the implementation of decentralization in 2001, roles  activities. The national Pokja is headed by Bappenas and&#13;
and responsibilities for water and sanitation service deliv-  comprises representatives of 8 line ministries engaged in&#13;
ery changed. Central government including the line minis-  the sector, such as the Ministries of Home Affairs, Health,&#13;
tries responsible for water and sanitation service provision  Public Works, Finance, Environment, Education and Na-&#13;
now focuses on policy and strategy development as well  tional Bureau of Statistics. The national Pokja is also sup-&#13;
as oversight of implementation rather than direct control  ported by various projects, NGOs, donor agencies, univer-&#13;
of service delivery. At the sub-national level, districts and  sities, etc. At local level, Pokjas comprise the respective&#13;
cities carry the authority to ensure service delivery, while  local government agencies responsible for water supply&#13;
provincial governments provide technical support to their  and sanitation. When meeting on a regular basis, Pokjas&#13;
respective cities and districts. A critical challenge for the  have proved to be a very effective forum to support and&#13;
sector is for sub-national government to develop the ca-  coordinate sector development. To date, Pokjas have been&#13;
pacity to fulfil its devolved role in the planning, development  established in all provinces, and in more than 400 district&#13;
and management of services; and for effective instruments  and city governments.&#13;
to be in place to hold it accountable for doing so.&#13;
While provision of water and sanitation services since de-&#13;
Technical working groups for water and sanitation (Pokja  centralization in Indonesia has been divided up between&#13;
AMPL) have been established both at national as well as  central government for policy making and overviewing, and&#13;
sub-national levels to support the implementation of poli-  local governments for implementation, the actual responsi-&#13;
cies and strategies, and the coordination of day to day  bilities for particular subsectors lie with individual line minis-&#13;
12                                                                  Water Supply and Sanitation in Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿tries and their corresponding offices at local level. The Min-  to low-income households, providing incentives to expand&#13;
istry of Public Works is the lead agency for providing water  their networks into these areas. Another way to address&#13;
and sanitation infrastructure to urban and rural areas, while  these challenges is by accessing the government's special&#13;
the Ministry of Health is responsible for behavior change  budget allocation fund (DAK, see Box 1.1), which is granted&#13;
and setting standards for drinking water quality. Bappenas  from central government to cities and districts to reduce idle&#13;
is in charge of setting sector targets and policy develop-  capacity of water supply in urban area or to serve low-in-&#13;
ment. The Ministry of Home Affairs is responsible for capac-  come communities in urban slums and water scarce areas&#13;
ity building for local governments&#13;
Water utilities are being supervised and receive technical&#13;
Water Supply Service Provision                     support through several channels. The Ministry of Finance&#13;
monitors PDAM performance across a wide range of pa-&#13;
Drinking water supply in Indonesia is carried out through  rameters through semi-annual audits undertaken by its&#13;
different ways and organizational structures, and can be  financial and development oversight agency, the Finance&#13;
broadly divided into utility-managed and community-man-  and Development Controller Bureau (BPKP). Under the&#13;
aged systems. As part of the utility-managed systems,  Ministry of Public Works, BPPSPAM (Support Agency for&#13;
local water utilities in urban areas (PDAMs) are in charge  the Development of Drinking Water Supply Systems) com-&#13;
of providing water to households through piped systems.  piles and disseminates a statistical summary of the BPKP&#13;
Owned by the respective local governments, management  performance data. Based on criteria derived from that data,&#13;
of PDAMs - including budget and tariff approvals, as well  BPPSPAM further establishes the PDAM rating system,&#13;
as investment decisions - is usually undertaken in close co-  categorizing the utilities into healthy, less healthy or sick.&#13;
operation with other departments at local government level,  To date, around 375 PDAMs exist across the country, with&#13;
and local parliament. Typical challenges PDAMs are facing  214 of them categorized as 'healthy'.15 Setting water tariffs&#13;
include providing equity investment for their PDAMs to ex-  is under the responsibility of the district heads (Bupati) or&#13;
pand into low-income areas or accessing debt restructuring  mayors, who are guided by laws and regulations issued by&#13;
programs. The lack of revenues due to tariffs below cost-  the Ministry of Home Affairs. PERPAMSI (the National Water&#13;
recovery level is another frequent challenge PDAMs are fac-  Supply Association of Indonesia) is an association repre-&#13;
ing. Failure to increase tariffs to a cost-recovery level, how-  senting all PDAMs in Indonesia with the objective of coor-&#13;
ever, is only the symptom of deeper issues. Since laws and  dinating investment and support activities, demonstrating&#13;
regulations for appropriate, cost-recovery tariffs do exist,  best practices, promoting professional business principles&#13;
the main reason local government and PDAM management  and motivating utilities to improve human resource man-&#13;
do not implement tariff increases reflects a lack of political  agement.&#13;
will and support for a sound management of the PDAMs.&#13;
In urban areas that are not served by piped water supply,&#13;
One way to support the development of urban water supply  households tend to access groundwater through deep wells&#13;
services is through the Water Hibah program (a grant pro-  and pumps, although groundwater quality has been deterio-&#13;
gram), which the Government set up with assistance by the  rating in densely populated areas due to overuse and con-&#13;
Australian government. Through the Water Hibah, the central  tamination by domestic waste. Laws and regulations exist&#13;
government reimburses a large part of the capital investment  to regulate the overuse of groundwater, but monitoring and&#13;
costs to local governments or PDAMs for investments made  enforcement are difficult due to a limitation of resources.&#13;
15BPPSPAM conducts an assessment of PDAMs against a set of 30 indicators, including technical, financial, managerial ones, categorizing the utilities as&#13;
healthy, less healthy or sick. The target is that all 375 PDAMs are in a healthy condition by 2014.&#13;
Service Delivery Assessment                                                                     13&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Developing community-based water supply systems in ru-  Altogether, management of the water supply schemes over-&#13;
ral and peri-urban areas has been on the Government's pri-  all has become more effective in recent years. The work&#13;
ority agenda since the late 1990s. Through large programs  of institutions and large-scale programs are backed up by&#13;
such as Water and Sanitation for Low Income Communities  supportive regulations, planning processes coordination&#13;
1 and 2 (WSSLIC) and the successor Water and Sanitation  mechanisms, finance and audit mechanisms and monitor-&#13;
for Low Income Communities Project 3 (PAMSIMAS), the   ing and evaluation systems. Many recommendations from&#13;
central government is supporting the development of lo-  evaluations are being followed up if financial and human&#13;
cal community-based water and sanitation systems. The  resources allow. Performance evaluations for PDAMs are&#13;
program is aimed at attracting local government funding to  done regularly by BPPSPAM according to standards laid&#13;
set up, support, and scale up community-based systems  out in PDAM performance indicators&#13;
throughout the country. This approach is working quite suc-&#13;
cessfully in Indonesia: access rates to rural water supply  Sanitation Service Provision&#13;
services have increased from 61 % in 1990 to 76% in 2011.16&#13;
Further, community-based organizations (CBOs) managing  For urban sanitation services, institutional challenges are&#13;
water supply schemes are formally recognized by the cen-  much more severe than that for water supply systems, so&#13;
tral government as official providers of water supply sys-  several large gaps remain. Despite good overall progress&#13;
tems as stated in Government Regulation No.16/2005. It is  made in recent years in increasing access to sanitation ser-&#13;
estimated that around 13,000 CBOs exist to date.       vices, coverage of centralized wastewater systems in urban&#13;
areas in Indonesia remains very low - estimates range from&#13;
Challenges remain such as how to attract support from local  1-2% for altogether only 12 cities (Jakarta, Banjarmasin,&#13;
governments to enable CBOs expand their services since in  Denpasar, Medan, Cirebon, Bandung, Prapat, Yogyakarta,&#13;
reality, CBOs are still facing many challenges to do so: (a)  Surakarta, Balikpapan, Tangerang, Batam). According to&#13;
a lack of capacity to maintain and expand services; (b) a  a recent study, only 1 % of the sewerage is actually being&#13;
lack of access to finance that would provide much-need-  treated.18 These centralized systems are managed by local&#13;
ed capital; and (c) an unclear legal framework in relation  utilities" that are owned by local governments. They require&#13;
to the expansion of services across more than one village  heavy subsidization mainly due to low wastewater tariffs as&#13;
administration area. Commercial banks remain reluctant in  potential source of revenues and a low number of house-&#13;
granting credits to CBOs, mainly due to poor accountabil-  hold connections to the systems. Several initiatives have&#13;
ity mechanisms within the CBOs, a lack of collaterals, poor  been carried out by central government to reduce idle ca-&#13;
financial management of the CBOs or simply a lack of un-  pacity in the existing sewerage systems, which some stud-&#13;
derstanding of the local water and sanitation service mar-  ies quantify to around 50%. Some cities are also preparing&#13;
ket by the banks. Some initiatives to improve and expand  feasibility studies and detailed engineering designs to build&#13;
community-managed water schemes have been carried out  new sewerage systems. Further, the Government through&#13;
by the Ministry of Public Works with support from WSP and  the Sanitation Australian Indonesian Grant (SAIG) project&#13;
DFAT (formerly AusAID). The aim of these initiatives is to  is intensifying its effort to develop simplified centralized&#13;
build partnerships among CBOs, local governments and   sewerage systems in many cities. However, despite these&#13;
the private sector in supporting the development of rural  efforts, national targets for centralized sewerage systems&#13;
water supply in Indonesia .17                          are only 5% by 2014, which is still far from being realized.&#13;
16 In comparison, access to urban water supply services has only increased from 90% to 93% between 1990 and 2011. While pointing out successes in rural&#13;
water supply development, the report does acknowledge that the different increase in access rates between urban and rurl areas is majorly influenced by&#13;
the high urban population growth rate of around 4%.&#13;
17 Several projects such as the Multi Village Pooling Project, the Second Generation Proect and the Domestic Private Sector Participation Proect (DPSP)&#13;
have been implemented by MPW to facilitate partnerships among local governments, chOs and local banks in order to improve provision of rural water&#13;
supply services.&#13;
18 World Bank &amp; AusAID (2013): EAP Urban Sanitation aeview, Indonesia Country Study: Only 1% of sewerage and 4% of sludge is being treated, while 95%&#13;
of waste water is not disposed safely.&#13;
I These utilities are either specific waste water utilities (PDPAL, or combined with water supply utilities (PDAM) or own an own utility for this system only&#13;
(BLUD in Denpasar, Bali).&#13;
14                                                                          Water Supply and Sanitation in Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Hence, the majority of urban areas in Indonesia will con-  is treated properly.22 This is caused by several issues cor-&#13;
tinue to depend on decentralized and on-site sanitation  monly found in cities, such as low demand for pit and tank&#13;
systems in the foreseeable future.                 emptying service; lack of enforcement to ensure septage&#13;
from tanker is treated safely; and under-performance of&#13;
Decentralized wastewater treatment systems (DEWATS)  septage treatment plants. Efforts are currently ongoing un-&#13;
are one of the available options to bridge the gap between  der the leadership of the Ministry of Public Works-with&#13;
onsite sanitation and centralized sewerage systems, par-  support from USAID and WSP-to support local govern-&#13;
ticularly in dense, low-income urban areas. A growing num-  ment to improve their urban septage management systems.&#13;
ber of DEWATS have been built in Indonesia over the past  Some cities are starting to pilot regular desludging in order&#13;
years, with over 80% of them functioning well. However,  to lower the risk of groundwater and surface water pollution.&#13;
challenges within a number of DEWATS systems remain,  In response to the growing demand of desludging within&#13;
especially in relation to ineffective community management  the city, private sector operator engagement is sporadically&#13;
structures, lack of local government support, and a short-  available. But often, sludge is not disposed safely into the&#13;
age of skilled project facilitators to train residents about the  treatment plant, but illegally dumped into the environment.&#13;
long-term operation and maintenance of the systems.20&#13;
Compared to urban sanitation services, rural sanitation, on&#13;
One of the key aspects of introducing both centralized or  the other hand, has seen some remarkable progress in re-&#13;
decentralized wastewater systems to urban settings is the  cent years. Following the introduction and success of the&#13;
willingness of households to connect to the system. Pre-  Community-Led Total Sanitation (CLTS) approach in 2005,&#13;
liminary findings of a WSP study show that households can  the Government under the leadership of the Ministry of&#13;
be reluctant to conduct physical work on their premises,  Health has developed the Community-based Total Sanita-&#13;
mainly due to financial, institutional, technical and/or so-  tion Strategy (STBM), which takes the CLTS approach as&#13;
cial reasons, e.g. who whould bear the cost for installing  basis and complements it with hand washing with soap, hy-&#13;
the pipe to the house or unclear land and asset ownership.  giene and safe food and water treatment, safe wastewater&#13;
Different solutions are currently being considered, e.g. in-  management as well as solid waste management at house-&#13;
terceptors that capture gray and black water at the cor-  hold level. At the same time, the Government is actively en-&#13;
ner of the premises or from a canal. This also allows for  couraging the private sector to deliver affordable sanitation&#13;
better functioning system through sufficient inflow into the  products and services, with local sanitarians and health&#13;
treatment plants and the possibility of a gradual upgrade of  cadres taking a key role in behavior change and demand&#13;
household connections to the wastewater system.    creation. Since rolling out in 2008, STBM is now accepted&#13;
as the standard approach for sanitation across Indonesia.&#13;
Recent studies show that around 60% of the urban popula-  Responsibilities for implementation are with local health of-&#13;
tion have access to onsite sanitation facilities, which mostly  fices and their sanitarian staff to carry out the program in&#13;
consist of enforced pit-latrines or septic tanks.21 These facil-  their respective communities with strong support of local&#13;
ities do count as 'access to improved sanitation' according  government, local and international NGOs, as well as de-&#13;
to the JMP but that masks the fact that the management of  velopment partners.&#13;
septage is not functioning well - only around 4% of septage&#13;
20 WSP (2013): Review of Commun ity- Managed Decentralized Wastewater Treatment Syatems in Indonesia.&#13;
21 World Bank &amp; AusAID (2013): EAP Urban Sanitation Review, Indonesia Country Study.&#13;
22 WSP (2013): Review of Fecal Sludge Management in 12 Cities, Draft Report.&#13;
Service Delivery Assessment                                                                     15&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Hygiene Practices                                 target in medium term. Only around 9,000 sanitation per-&#13;
sonnel are currently available, though, indicating a gap of&#13;
Although hygiene programs had been introduced and im-  50%.&#13;
plemented nationally since 1970s together with the provi-&#13;
sion of latrines and the establishment of official schools  Different training institutions exist within the Ministries of&#13;
for sanitation, the outcomes of the programs have only re-  Public Works and Health, which follow standard govern-&#13;
suIted in limited success. In 2007, hand washing with soap  ment curricula aligned with existing government programs&#13;
practice was still low with only 23% of the population regu-  such as STBM. However, the amount of graduates that fi-&#13;
larly washing their hands at 'critical times'.23 The Commu-  nally support the sector development in the districts and&#13;
nity-Based Total Sanitation (STBM) strategy adopted by the  provinces - especially facilitators, project managers and&#13;
Government in 2008 also includes a hygiene component  technicians - continue to fall short of the demand through-&#13;
focusing on behavior change as basis for communities to  out the country. Since 2013, MoH connects the STBM ca-&#13;
adopt safe hygiene practices. According to the RISKESDAS  pacity building program to the ministry's human resource&#13;
survey, by 2013 the rate of people washing their hands with  development schemes through accredited training, individ-&#13;
soap at critical times has risen to around 47%.    ual government officer' performance credit mechanisms,&#13;
e-learning, and by including it into the health schools cur-&#13;
To successfully scale up hygiene promotion in Indonesia,  ricula.&#13;
the most important link necessary is a strong partnership&#13;
with the private sector. Using mass media to communicate&#13;
hygiene-related messages to a large number of people, or  Sustainability and Asset Transfer&#13;
combining sales strategies for hygiene products with the&#13;
persuasive messaging are areas where the private sector  Sustainability  of community-operated  water supply&#13;
has a comparative advantage over government. Further, the  schemes is often weakened by an unclear transfer process&#13;
collaboration with midwives to communicate hygiene be-  of assets from government programs or projects to com-&#13;
havior messages is a way to reach scale.           munities. In theory, existing laws and regulations define how&#13;
ownership of assets is handed over by national government&#13;
Human Resources Development                        and projects to local governments and communities after&#13;
the completion of an intervention to operate, maintain and&#13;
Despite the progress made in recent years, institutional  manage the systems. In reality the operational process of&#13;
challenges are to deliver at-scale services throughout the  handing over assets bears a number of challenges: For ex-&#13;
country and to provide the human resources required to do  ample, monitoring and registration of assets is required on&#13;
so. Scaling up water and sanitation service provision in or-  a voluntary basis and therefore not conducted diligently; at&#13;
der to reach sector targets will require a large number of  handover, the registry of the assets as well as their func-&#13;
skilled personnel. For the water supply sector, however, no  tionality is not clear; and subsequently, responsibilities after&#13;
aggregated data on number and status of human resources  handover are often disputed with communities or local gov-&#13;
needed or those available exist yet. The sanitation subsec-  ernments refusing to allocate budget for repairs, operation&#13;
tor, on the contrary, has estimated in a recent study24 that  and maintenance. Furthermore there is a lack of support&#13;
around 18,000 personnel are needed to meet the national  structures for communities to request assistance for the&#13;
s Hand washing at five critical times includes after defecation, after babies and children defecate, before eating and prepring tood, before breastfeeding and&#13;
after contact with animls.&#13;
2m Qipra Galang Kualita (2012): Sanitation Personnel: Capacity Development Strategy.&#13;
16                                                                    Water Supply and Sanitation in Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿proper operation and management of their newly acquired&#13;
systems. Assistance is required to help both parties monitor&#13;
and register the quantity and functionality of the assets at&#13;
the point of transfer, as well as to technical support to com-&#13;
munities on how to manage the new systems in the time&#13;
after handover. Government programs and projects are fur-&#13;
ther to engage more actively already from an early stage&#13;
with the community representatives, who will be part of the&#13;
operation and maintenance teams after transfer.&#13;
Service Delivery Assessment                                                                17&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿5. Financing and its Implementation&#13;
Priority actions for financing and its implementation&#13;
* Urge development of sound investment plans and their endorsement and incorporation into local government work&#13;
plans for immediate implementation.&#13;
* Establish a clearly defined public financing policy for urban sanitation with sources well identified.&#13;
* Actively seek involvement of private sector participation in the sector.&#13;
* Continue to develop alternative financing schemes to leverage sector investment.&#13;
Investment Planning&#13;
Investment planning in the water and sanitation sector in  While these investment planning exercises cover large parts&#13;
Indonesia is still not done systematically throughout the  of the water supply and sanitation sector, it does not cover ru-&#13;
sector and lacks coordination among key stakeholders. For  ral sanitation development. In fact, the investment roadmaps&#13;
the water supply subsector, the Ministry of Public Works  and plans are mainly focusing on infrastructure development&#13;
has developed the Water Investment Roadmap (WIRA),25  in the sector, which is why they have not yet been fully applied&#13;
which includes an assessment of issues in the water supply  to the rural sanitation sub-sector with its behavior change ap-&#13;
subsector and proposes specific investment packages and  proach that is aimed at leveraging household contributions.&#13;
programs to reach sector targets. For sanitation, Bappenas  Even though the PPSP roadmap covers both rural and urban&#13;
coordinates the Sanitation Acceleration Program (PPSP),  sanitation development nationwide, it does lack the depth&#13;
which includes an overview of investment requirements  and detail of a comprehensive investment plan.&#13;
based on the stages of the program.&#13;
In order to achieve sector targets by 2019, the raising rate of&#13;
At local government level, a mid-term investment plan (RPI-  budget allocation to the sector over recent years has to be&#13;
JM) is developed to coordinate funding from the Ministry  increased even further. It is therefore crucial to continuously&#13;
of Public Works at national level as well as from provincial  optimize the processes of how finances are turned into ac-&#13;
and local level budgets. Cities and districts participating  cess to services. For that, a sound and comprehensive in-&#13;
in PPSP have to develop city sanitation strategies (SSK),  vestment planning process is key so that available funds&#13;
which includes mid-term investment plans and is also in-  can be utilized in an efficient way. It is further important to&#13;
cluded into the RPIJM. For water supply, local water utilities  link investment planning processes at central level with the&#13;
(PDAMs) develop investment plan as part of their business  more detailed, specific investment planning processes at&#13;
plans, which is a requirement to participate at the debt re-  local level, to ensure that local sector development also&#13;
structuring program.                               contributes to national targets.&#13;
25 MoPW, World Bank (2012): Indonesia Water Investment noadmap 2011-14.&#13;
18                                                                    Water Supply and Sanitation in Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Budget Transparency                              Utilization of Budgets&#13;
Despite clear mandates and regulations, it remains difficult  It is difficult to get a real picture of the budget utilization&#13;
to get a comprehensive picture of the total budget and ex-  given the unreliability of data as described above. In fact,&#13;
penditures in the water and sanitation sector. The Indone-  the lack of compiled data reports in the water and sanitation&#13;
sian law requires a three-party consensus for budget plan-  sector continues into the auditing mechanisms. Audits are&#13;
ning, including the Ministry of Finance, Bappenas, and the  mostly done for individual ministries or projects, but do not&#13;
according line ministry. A number of criteria have been set  cover a disaggregation between rural and urban areas. Au-&#13;
up to develop the budget, such as consistency with tar-  dit reports do exist but are scattered among different agen-&#13;
geted performance indicators, accountability of users and  cies or projects. Stakeholders estimate that the rate of bud-&#13;
source of funds. The formula used to calculate the budget  get utilization is more than 75% for the sector as a whole&#13;
might be revised every year depending on national and lo-  and in some cases reaches almost 100%. In the review of&#13;
cal revenues, the share of tax allocation for the sector, the  the RPJMN 2010-2014, the ADB estimated a 75% utiliza-&#13;
population growth and technical conditions. The Ministry of  tion of the development budget for the water and sanitation&#13;
Finance releases a detailed mechanism and formula every  sector, which is why many ministries work hard to ensure a&#13;
year as guidance for developing budget allocations. For  maximum utilization of their budgets.&#13;
transparency and accountability reasons, a national gov-&#13;
ernment accounting system is implemented jointly between  Private Sector Participation&#13;
the Ministry of Finance and the line ministries. Budget and&#13;
financial audit reports are available for the public, although  Private involvement through public-private partnerships&#13;
most of those documents are not accessible online but only  (PPP) or by utilizing corporate social responsibility funds for&#13;
upon request.                                    the water sector does exist, although it's still limited. Two&#13;
presidential regulationS26 to strengthen partnerships with&#13;
There has been great improvement in recording govern-  the private sector and to provide a guarantee fund mecha-&#13;
ment budgets and auditing expenditures, including catego-  nism for viable PPP schemes have been developed and&#13;
rizing budgets and expenditures by source of funds. The  need to be intensified in its implementation to provide ac-&#13;
disaggregation of data, however, stops at the sector-level-  cess to new and large sources of investment funds for local&#13;
reports do not disaggregate the water and sanitation sector  governments. Currently, the Indonesia Water and Sanitation&#13;
further into urban and rural areas. This complicates specific  Investment Facility is under preparation. This initiative, led&#13;
accountability of sector performance to individual agencies,  by Ministry of Finance, Bappenas, and the Ministry of Pub-&#13;
especially because the water and sanitation budget is held  lic Works with support from World Bank is aimed at provid-&#13;
by several ministries involved with particular parts of the  ing financing in combination with technical assistance when&#13;
sector, and can even be spread out within several depart-  required, to help PDAMs access non-government sources&#13;
ments within one ministry. So despite the fact that the data  of funding, in case they are not 'healthy' enough to borrow&#13;
do exist in one form or another, due to a variety of different  from commercial banks.&#13;
forms and templates used by different ministries or local&#13;
government agencies, no consolidated report is available at  Another idea to leverage increased private sector funding&#13;
national level for the sector as a whole, neither at national  would be to establish a pooled Municipal Development&#13;
nor at local level.                              Fund, aimed to mobilize funds from different sources for&#13;
c Perpres 13/2010 and Perpres 78/2010.&#13;
Service Delivery Assessment                                                                   19&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿investment in infrastructure. This would then have to be  It is clear from Figure 5.1 that households and other do-&#13;
combined with a project preparation facility to support lo-  mestic stakeholderS27 are expected to be a major source of&#13;
cal governments in developing good, bankable investment  investments in both rural and urban areas. In rural sanita-&#13;
projects.                                                tion, removing anticipated household investments leads to&#13;
a deficit rather than a fully funded subsector. This raises a&#13;
Budget Adequacy                                          question of whether rural sanitation is actually fully fund-&#13;
ed. The reason is that the household anticipated expen-&#13;
Figure 5.1 shows the different sources of finance for the  ditures were modeled rather than based on documents or&#13;
four sectors. As a whole, there are deficits in the urban wa-  expressed intentions of stakeholders, which was the case&#13;
ter and sanitation sector, as can be seen in orange color in  for Government and donor agencies. In other words, there&#13;
the diagram. However the reverse seems to be the case in  is no assurance that households will actually make these&#13;
rural areas, where water supply and sanitation are projected  investments.&#13;
to be fully funded.&#13;
Figure 5.1 Overall annual and per capita investment requirements and contribution to anticipated financing by&#13;
source&#13;
Rural water supply          Urban water supply        Rural sanitation            Urban sanitation&#13;
Total      :US$772,000,000  Total      :US$3,980,000,000 Total    :US$414,000,000  Total     :US$2,340,0005000&#13;
Per capita (new): US$35     Per capita (new): US$180  Per capita (new): US$28     Per capita (new): US$184&#13;
U Domestic anticipated  U External anticipated  Household anticipated  u   Deficit&#13;
investment            investment             investment&#13;
Source: SDA costing&#13;
d Domestic stakeholders are represented in this case mostly by the national government. The basis of the Figure 3 contains limited information on local&#13;
governments and no information on utilities and the private sector.&#13;
20                                                                             Water Supply and Sanitation in Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿6. Sector Monitoring and Evaluation&#13;
Priority actions for sector monitoring and evaluation&#13;
* Link monitoring and evaluation systems to budgeting and planning processes.&#13;
* Strengthen the National Water Supply and Sanitation Information Services System (NAWASIS) to become an inte-&#13;
grated portal for sector-wide M&amp;E.&#13;
* Improve local capacity for use of M&amp;E data for sector planning, budgeting and targeting implementation support.&#13;
Most monitoring efforts in the Indonesian water and sanita-  While this is a very useful and welcomed exercise, the re-&#13;
tion sector are still being undertaken at a program or project  suits of these reviews are not sufficiently shared and agreed&#13;
level with limited coordination across the sector. Decentral-  corrective actions of respective agencies at national and&#13;
ization and the new responsibilities of local governments to  local level are not always followed through diligently. De-&#13;
provide water and sanitation services has not made this ef-  spite annual review mechanisms, development partners&#13;
fort easier. Many local governments still lack the capacity, full  and projects continue to carry out their own internal M&amp;E&#13;
understanding and incentives to regularly conduct monitor-  reviews, but do not necessarily share the findings with other&#13;
ing and utilize the data for planning purposes. In fact, many  line ministries or the Pokja. Communities also conduct M&amp;E&#13;
local governments are reaching their capacity limits with the  reviews on a voluntary basis, but there is no clear reporting&#13;
multitude of reports they already have to submit every year  requirement to share their reports with their respective dis-&#13;
for numerous programs and projects they participate in.2  trict offices. M&amp;E studies done by line ministries and part-&#13;
ners, even though available, are also not always shared or&#13;
Despite these difficulties, there has been significant improve-  published. Above all, consolidated reports based on com-&#13;
ment in sector monitoring and evaluation in recent years,  parable sets of data are not yet available, either, making it&#13;
both regarding coordination mechanisms and technical as-  difficult to find reliable data, except for project M&amp;E sys-&#13;
pects. Line ministries, local governments and other stake-  tems such as PAMSIMAS, which now operates in 220 out&#13;
holders have conducted regular monitoring and evaluation  of 440 districts in Indonesia. Similarly, other large programs&#13;
exercises, formulated follow up actions, and implemented  that fund for example water schemes, such as PNPM, have&#13;
corrective actions based on the results. The national Pokja  their own program M&amp;E system.&#13;
undertakes a coordinated regular annual review for the sec-&#13;
tor, involving several main government agencies related to  NAWASIS as a national level M&amp;E platform would facilitate&#13;
water and sanitation.                              consistent targets and indicators derived from a compre-&#13;
2l Some local governments report that they have to submit up to 27 reports annually to various donors and proects that are active in their areas.&#13;
Service Delivery Assessment                                                                     21&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿hensive results framework. So far, the RPJMN 2009-2014  in detail how this system can be incorporated into the NA-&#13;
does not differentiate between targets and indicators for ru-  WASIS umbrella.&#13;
ral and urban areas, and each ministry or sector partner has&#13;
their own specific indicators and targets for their part of the  Despite increased efforts to carry out monitoring and evalu-&#13;
sector - which are not always in line with national indicators  ation in the water and sanitation sector, the data collected&#13;
in mid-term or long-term development plans.        are not always analyzed and compiled in a systematic sec-&#13;
tor review. Furthermore, recommendations and priority ac-&#13;
The Ministry of Public Works has developed an online M&amp;E  tions, if available, are not always followed up to improve the&#13;
tool for water supply named SIMSPAM. The number, condi-  quality of services. It is therefore recommended to improve&#13;
tion, and location of water utilities are constantly kept up-  the Government's capacity to scale up M&amp;E at local level&#13;
dated. At this moment, the system covers about 6 million  and use it as resource for sector planning, budgeting and&#13;
people. MoH is also developing an online reporting system  implementation support. This should be linked to a system-&#13;
for sanitation, through SMS and web-based M&amp;E. This sys-  atic incentive structure tailored to local circumstances, that&#13;
tem currently covers 9 provinces. It is planned that it will be  combines rewards and punishments.&#13;
implemented nationally in 2014. It remains to be discussed&#13;
22                                                                    Water Supply and Sanitation in Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿7. Subsector: Rural Water Supply&#13;
Priority actions for rural water supply&#13;
* Establish a clear demarcation of roles and responsibilities within the local governments after the hand-over of as-&#13;
sets on managing and maintaining the water supply systems.&#13;
* Continue to facilitate and support community organizations in accessing commercial finance from local banks.&#13;
* Establish comprehensive technical support structure for communities to ensure sustainability of water and sanita-&#13;
tion schemes.&#13;
* Improve capacity to scale up M&amp;E at local level and use it as resource for sector planning, budgeting and imple-&#13;
mentation support.&#13;
Figure 7.1 shows access rates and targets for rural water  However, JMP and government indicators both suggest&#13;
supply. Government estimates from Bappenas, which are  modest increases in access rates over time and, if current&#13;
based on the SUSENAS survey, indicate that only about  trends continue, a strong likelihood that country targets for&#13;
58% of the rural population had access to improved wa-  2019 will not be reached.&#13;
ter supply in 2011. Progress between 1993 and 2011 has&#13;
been moderate, with about 0.7 percentage points per year  Figure 7.1 Access to rural water supply&#13;
on average. However, following years of large rural wa-  100%&#13;
ter supply projects,29 and an increase in the Government's&#13;
commitment into the sector in recent years, a more rapid  &gt; 80%&#13;
increase in access rates can be witnessed between 2009  0                             /.&#13;
Zi ,, 60%&#13;
to 2011, amounting to around 5% per year on average. If  E&#13;
this accelerated trend continues to rise, it might be pos-  40%&#13;
sible for the Government to meet the 2019 targets of uni-  U&#13;
versal access.                                                   in a    20%&#13;
0%&#13;
JMP estimates, which have a less stringent standard for   1990  1995  2000  2005  2010  2015  2020&#13;
defining improved water supply compared to the Govern-    ***** Govt.estimates(1993-2011)  Governmenttarget&#13;
ment, indicate that a much higher proportion (76%) of     -4   Govt.estimates(2009-2011)&#13;
the rural population had access to improved sanitation.  Sources: SDA costing, Bappenas, and JMP (2013)30&#13;
Three Water Supply and Sanitation for Low-Income Communities Projects have been implemented in the past two decades (WSSLIC 1 and 2, PAMSIMAS).&#13;
JoJMP (2013) Progress on Drinking Water and Sanitation: 2013 Update. UNICEF and WHO.&#13;
Service Delivery Assessment                                                                     23&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Figure 7.2 Rural water financing (required, anticipated  Figure 7.3 Rural water supply financing, anticipated&#13;
and recent investments)                               and gaps&#13;
t^ 1,400 -                                              Total      US$772,000,000&#13;
Ln                                      Ho-shold&#13;
Hoseol                                        Per capita (new): US$35&#13;
1,200 -                               External       P                          Domestic anticipated&#13;
-2                                                                                investment&#13;
E  1,000                              U m  Domestic&#13;
-C                                    M  Replacement                            U  External anticipated&#13;
-  800&#13;
New                                                                            investment&#13;
600-&#13;
Household anticipated&#13;
.:  40investment&#13;
:3  200-&#13;
C                            ,                                                    Deficit&#13;
CF&#13;
Total investment  Anticipated  Recent investment&#13;
requirement  investment 2012-2014  2009-2011&#13;
Source: SDA costing&#13;
The SUSENAS survey for 2010, as presented in the JMP,11  ment has to be treated with caution. As explained earlier,&#13;
indicates that protected wells were the most common   this has to do with household investments being modeled&#13;
(33% of the rural population) drinking water source in the  in the analysis rather than reflecting an expressed desire&#13;
rural Indonesia. Other common sources were tubewells/  of households to fund expenditures for water supply facili-&#13;
boreholes (13%) and protected springs (14%). Private ac-  ties.&#13;
cess to piped water remains low at less than 5% of the&#13;
rural population.                                     Figure 7.4 shows the scorecard results of the rural water&#13;
supply service delivery pathway. The development of the&#13;
The country needs to raise an estimated US$772 million  rural water supply subsector reflects positive scores as a&#13;
per year in order to meet its rural water supply targets for  result of a supportive policy, shared roles and responsibili-&#13;
2019 (Figure 7.2). About 57% of this amount is needed  ties among major stakeholders, good coordination among&#13;
to replace worn-out facilities over the period of analysis.  government institutions, and improving quality of scheme&#13;
Anticipated investments ($1.2 billion per year), which rep-  management and financial record keeping. At the same&#13;
resent projected annual investments from 2012-14, are  time the red scores and those on the lower end of the yel-&#13;
much higher than requirement investments. This finding  low blocks, particularly equity, output, expansion and user&#13;
is consistent with the earlier projection that the sector is  outcomes, give reason for concern: It is especially the focus&#13;
likely to meet its target. It also suggests that government  on equity, ensuring that the money is spent effectively on&#13;
and donors should continue with current efforts to fund  developing new services, as well as expanding and sustain-&#13;
the sector. While funds from government and donors seem  ing performance of existing schemes that need to function&#13;
sufficient to fund requirements, the fully funded budget re-  well in order to increase access rates especially for low-&#13;
sutting from the inclusion of household anticipated invest-  income areas.&#13;
3 JMP (2012) Estimates forithe use of Improved Drinking-tWater Sources: Indonesia, wtinfo.org.&#13;
24                                                                        Water Supply and Sanitation in Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Figure 7.4 Rural water supply scorecard&#13;
Enabling                      Developing                      Sustaining&#13;
Policy  Planning  Budget      Expenditure Equity  Output    Maintenance Expansion  Use&#13;
1.5      1.5                    1        1            1.5               1&#13;
Source: SDA scorecard&#13;
In order to improve the service delivery pathway for ac-  have been established with support from the Ministry of&#13;
cess to rural sanitation, a series of priority actions can be  Public Works. These associations are a forum for CBOs&#13;
identified. Since most systems are built through national  to engage in knowledge sharing and horizontal learning&#13;
programs or projects, problems - if there are any - most-  amongst each other. Further, the associations are used as&#13;
ly occur after the projects are finished. There is no clear  vehicle to carry out performance monitoring. Finally, the&#13;
division of roles and responsibilities within local govern-  Government is strengthening the capacity of the asso-&#13;
ments on who does what in terms of providing assistance  ciations to provide technical assistance to their member&#13;
to communities. Although a Ministry of Home Affairs De-  CB3s, and serve as a supportive link between the CBOs&#13;
cree" is being issued that aims to increase the priority of  and other potential partners, such as the private sector.&#13;
supporting CBOs as part of the expansion and improve-&#13;
ment of existing rural water supply schemes, it is not clear  Aside from the level of capacity of CBOs, the amount of&#13;
yet on how this will be implemented. The capacity of many  public funds available is not sufficient to cover the de-&#13;
CBOs to manage existing water supply schemes, on the  mand for access to services in the rural areas. However,&#13;
other hand, is still limited.                      facilitating CBOs to access finance from local banks has&#13;
proved to improve the capacity of the CBOs to improve&#13;
To address these gaps in capacity of CBOs, the challenge  and expand services. It is therefore recommended to den-&#13;
is how to reach the large number of CBOs in the country  tify well functioning, alternative financial sources as well&#13;
with only limited resources. In that regard, two approaches  as alternative financial schemes, and scale them up more&#13;
are being carried out: In the first approach, the Ministry of  widely across the country.&#13;
Public Works with support from WSP through the Domes-&#13;
tic Private Sector Participation project (DPSP) is strength-  In terms of sustaining services, the monitoring and infor-&#13;
ening the role of local governments to provide assistance  mation system developed through PAMSIMAS has been&#13;
to CBOs, in order to improve community-managed service  widely used to provide updates on the functionality of local&#13;
provision through public and private investment funds.  water systems. Moreover, this monitoring system could be&#13;
used as a tool for local governments to track their achieve-&#13;
The second approach includes CBO Associations (Asso-  ments compared with the targets stated in their individual&#13;
siasi BPSPAM), both at central and at district levels, that  development plans.&#13;
32 Ministry of Home Affairs Decree No. 23/2013 regarding the Local Government Development Plans (nrKPD).&#13;
Service Delivery Assessment                                                                     25&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿8. Subsector: Urban Water Supply&#13;
* Continue to assist 'unhealthy' PDAMs to improve their overall business management condition and become and&#13;
remain 'healthy', by improving asset management, implementing cost-recovery tariffs, reduce non-revenue water&#13;
and improving the management of human resources.&#13;
* Intensify assistance to PDAMs to access financial sources such as commercial financing or government assisted&#13;
schemes.&#13;
* Continue spporng politi c ive schemes sLiCh as Water Hibah to realize financial commitments by local government&#13;
into the sector.&#13;
* Identify further incentives for PDAMs to increase access into low-income communities.&#13;
* Engage local governments into a sound planning to secure future availability of water sources, e.g. by developing&#13;
sound water safety plans.&#13;
Figure 8.1 shows access rates and targets for urban water  100%&#13;
supply. Government estimates from Bappenas, which are  idctsta  cest   rvt   ie    ae  upis(8&#13;
based on the SUSENAS survey, indicate that only about ofteubnpulin)aasurefdikngwern&#13;
52% of the urban population had access to improved water  teubnaeso noei sqielw        hr ean&#13;
supply in 2011. Access rates have significantly improved  ahayrlac  ntbwlsbrhls(9) rtce&#13;
since 2010 due to strong political commitment to prioritize  wls(2) ote  ae 9)adwtrrfles(6)&#13;
the achievement of the MVDGs, as stated in RIPJMVN 2010- Fiue81Acstorbnwerupl&#13;
2014. However, in order to reach the more ambitious target&#13;
of universal access by 2019, more efforts than in the recent   10&#13;
past are needed.&#13;
The JMP uses less stringent standards compared to the    %&#13;
Government and estimates that 93% of the urban popula-  Et3&#13;
.0 M&#13;
tion had access to improved water supply sources in 2011.&#13;
(U M0&#13;
Despite this difference, JMP and government estimates are  2&#13;
similar in the sense that access rates have changed very&#13;
slowly over the past two decades and that 2019 targets are  0%&#13;
unlikely to be met if the current changes in access rates  1990  1995  2000  2005  2010  2015  2020&#13;
continue.                                                 -    Govt. estimates (1993-2011) a p Government target&#13;
indicates   Govt. estimates (2009-2011)&#13;
Sources: SDA costing, Bappenas. JMP (2013)34&#13;
oJMP (2012) Estimates for the use of Improved Drinking-Water Sources: Indonesia, wssinfo.org.&#13;
tJMP (2013) Progress on Drinking Water and Sanitation: 2013 Update. UNICEF and WHO.&#13;
26                                                                    Water Supply and Sanitation in Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Figure 8.2 Urban water supply financing (required,    Figure 8.3 Urban water supply financing (anticipated&#13;
anticipated and recent investments)                   and gap)&#13;
a1r 4,500 -                                             Total      US$3,980,000,000&#13;
4,000                                                Per capita (new): US$180  U Domestic anticipated&#13;
C  3,soo                                 Household                                 iVeStment&#13;
= 3,500-&#13;
E  External&#13;
E  3,000 -                                                                      0  External anticipated&#13;
-  2,500 -                               Domestic                                  investment&#13;
aJ                                     *  Replacement&#13;
E 2,500 .-neSm                                                                          n&#13;
e pl em                                     Household anticipated&#13;
0) 1,500                                               Ag&#13;
1   -investment&#13;
C&#13;
.- 1,000&#13;
Soo  00                                                                       Deficit&#13;
Total investment  Anticipated  Recent investment&#13;
requirement  investment 2012-2014  2012-2014&#13;
Source: SDA costing&#13;
The country needs to raise an estimated US$4 billion per  The service delivery pathway for urban water supply achieves&#13;
year in order to meet its targets for 2019 (Figure 8.2). More  overall higher scores than the other subsectors (Figure 8.4),&#13;
than half (66%) of these requirements are for providing  which can mainly be attributed to better policy and legal guid-&#13;
access to people who did not have facilities (new invest-  ance on well-defined responsibilities, coordination mecha-&#13;
ments) in the base period. The remaining investments are  nisms, recording and reporting, as well as organization and&#13;
required for replacing facilities at the end of their economic  management of the utilities. While there is high commitment&#13;
life (replacement investment). Recent investments, which  by the central government to provide access to water sup-&#13;
are mostly from domestic sources, are very low. Anticipated  ply in urban areas, local governments continue to face chal-&#13;
investments, which are also projected to come mostly from  lenges to increase access rates. One major gap identified by&#13;
domestic sources, are estimated to be higher than recent  stakeholders remains the Government's ability to commit an&#13;
investments. However, this only amounts to about 10% of  adequate budget necessary to reach the sector targets. This&#13;
investment requirements. Funding issues are compounded  is exacerbated by the limited resources available to PDAMs&#13;
by the findings in Section 2 that an additional US$474 mil-  to invest and expand coverage.&#13;
lion per year needs to be generated for O&amp;M expenditures.&#13;
In comparison, expansion in the sustaining pillar receives&#13;
The high deficit of almost US$3 billion per year is mainly  a medium score of 1.5, indicating autonomy and the avail-&#13;
due to the high targets for piped water supply in urban ar-  ability of business plans. This is an important basis, but - as&#13;
eas (projected to be for 90% of all households with access  can be seen at the low output block - does not automati-&#13;
to improved water supply by 2019), and the associated high  cally translate into effective results if the quality of these&#13;
unit costs for these piped systems." Considering the urban  business plans is not sufficient and not enough funds are&#13;
population growth, reaching these targets will require con-  available to implement them. Closely related to the low&#13;
siderable investments into the subsector.             score of the output building block is the medium score of&#13;
m                                                           e For more information on unit costs, see Annex 2.&#13;
Service Delivery Assessment                                                                           27&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿1.5 given to planning and budgeting within the enabling pil-  local government, CSOs and projects, as well as realizing&#13;
lar. In order to meet the target of universal access by 2019,  equity funds from local budgets, should be continuously&#13;
the effectiveness of producing outputs and expanding ser-  advocated and encouraged. Support and participation of&#13;
vices needs to be increased.                       private sector such as corporate social responsibility (CSR)&#13;
should also be strengthened.&#13;
Of specific concern is the low score of 0.75 attributed to the&#13;
maintenance building block of the sustainability pillar. Many  Water Resources Security&#13;
of the issues that prevent PDAMs from more efficiency are&#13;
compiled in this building block: non-revenue water losses  High population growth, and continuous high rate of urban-&#13;
(NRW), cost-recovery and tariff reviews. The national aver-  ization, combined with widespread water pollution and de-&#13;
age for NRW is still as high as 38% in 2012, just two per-  creasing water conservation areas are increasingly stress-&#13;
centage points below a red score in the scorecard; the ratio  ing the availability of water resources for domestic use.&#13;
between operational revenues and costs is below 0.8, in-  Linked with rising economic growth and increased prosper-&#13;
dicating insufficient collection of revenues and high losses  ity, the volume of water used is also rising. At the same&#13;
(e.g. due to NRW); and tariffs are reviewed regularly with  time, the development and implementation of technologies&#13;
regards to cost-recovery level, as required by law, but often  to reclaim water has started although its use is still limited.&#13;
no tariff adjustment is made. This underlines the important  Leaking latrines and the lack of a properly functioning fecal&#13;
point that well managed water provision through utilities is  sludge management system also contributes to pollution of&#13;
not only a technical or managerial matter, but heavily de-  water sources, which is why the synergy between sanitation&#13;
pendent on the dynamics of the political economy at local  and water has to start from the planning stage. For future&#13;
level. With a strong political leader understanding the need  security of water sources in view of the projected demo-&#13;
for sustainable service provision by the water utility, tariff re-  graphic and climate change scenarios, local governments&#13;
views and adjustments are expected to happen faster and  need to be engaged into a rigorous discussion to improve&#13;
more frequently.                                   resilience and improve their capability to adjust service pro-&#13;
vision accordingly. Continuous focus on an integrated and&#13;
In order to strengthen efforts to serve low-income com-  coordinated water safety planning process at local level is&#13;
munities, active participation of communities facilitated by  crucial for this challenge.&#13;
Figure 8.4 Urban water supply scorecard and results (0 =lowest; 3 = highest)&#13;
Enabling                      Developing                      Sustaining&#13;
Policy  Planning  Budget      Expenditure Equity  Output    Maintenance Expansion  Use&#13;
p.5               1.5            3                             07 D.5           1&#13;
28                                                                    Water Supply and Sanitation in Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿9. Subsector:&#13;
Rural Sanitation and Hygiene&#13;
Priority actions for rural sanitation and hygiene&#13;
* Strengthen the capacity of the STBM secretariat to coordinate and assist the implementation of STBM in Indone-&#13;
sia.&#13;
* Continue efforts to increase the number and capacity of sanitation entrepreneurs and sanitation personnel to sup-&#13;
port scaling up STBM nationwide.&#13;
* Improve capacity to scale up M&amp;E at local level and use it as resource for sector planning, budgeting and imple-&#13;
mentation support.&#13;
* Ensure sufficient funding on software components to ensure leverage of household contributions.&#13;
Figure 9.1 shows access rates and targets for rural sanita-  also require that the toilets be private and have access to&#13;
tion. Government estimates from BPS, which are based on  either a septic tank, a sewerage system or a pit. The JMP11&#13;
the SUSENAS survey, indicate that only about 39% of the  also estimates that more than a third (35%) of the rural pop-&#13;
rural population had access to improved sanitation in 2011.  ulation still practiced open defecation in 2011.&#13;
While the 2011 access rate is about three times higher com-&#13;
pared to 1993, the rate of increase (1.5 percentage points  Figure 9.1 Access to rural sanitation&#13;
per year) is not fast enough to meet the target of universal&#13;
access in 2019.                                     .   0&#13;
c80%&#13;
The JMP operates on less stringent standards compared  0&#13;
to the Government and estimates that 44% of the urban  ( 6&#13;
population had access to improved sanitation in 2011. De-&#13;
spite this difference, JMP and government estimates are&#13;
similar in the sense that 2019 targets are unlikely to be met   20%&#13;
it the current trends in access rates continue.&#13;
&lt; 0%&#13;
1990  1995  2000  2005  2010  2015   2020&#13;
The SUSENAS survey for 2010, as presented in the JMP,36      Govt. estimates (1993-2011)  Government target&#13;
indicates that flush-toilets/gooseneck pans are very com-  -- Govt. estimates (2009-2011)&#13;
mon in rural Indonesia (64%). However, government defini-&#13;
tions for improved facilities are much lower because these  SDA costing, BPS and JMP (2013)1&#13;
36 JMP (2012) Estimates for the use of Improved Sanitation Facilities: Indonesia, wssinfo.org.&#13;
JeMP (2013) Progress on Drinking Water and Sanitation: 2013 Update. UNICEF and WHO.&#13;
3u JMP (2013) Progress on Drinking Water and Sanitation: 2013 Update. UNICEF and WHO.&#13;
Service Delivery Assessment                                                                      29&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Figure 9.2 Rural sanitation financing (required,    Figure 9.3 Rural sanitation financing (anticipated and&#13;
anticipated and recent investments)                 gap/surplus)&#13;
Rural sanitation                       Rural sanitation&#13;
600 -                                              Total     : US$414,000,000&#13;
so                                                 Per capita (new): US$28  U Domestic anticipated&#13;
C 500                                 Household&#13;
.2                                                                              investment&#13;
External&#13;
E  400                                 Domestic                               0  External anticipated&#13;
.C&#13;
3oo -                             0  Replacement                             investment&#13;
200 -mewHousehold anticipated&#13;
investment&#13;
c  00 -                               elcmn&#13;
E- loomHoseol&#13;
o                       .                                                   Deficit&#13;
0&#13;
Total investment  Anticipated  Recent investment&#13;
requirement  investment2012-2014  2012-2014&#13;
Source: SDA costing&#13;
Indonesia needs to raise an estimated US$414 million per  Rural sanitation has received a significant increase in po-&#13;
year in order to meet its rural sanitation targets for 2019  litical priority over the past years, following the National&#13;
(Figure 9.2). About 43% of these requirements are need-  Community-Based Total Sanitation Strategy (STBM) issued&#13;
ed for replacing facilities at the end of their economic life  in 2008 and the definition of sector targets including 'open&#13;
(replacement investment). Anticipated investments are ex-  defecation free' status by 2014. Meeting these targets,&#13;
pected to meet requirements, indicating that targets for  however, remains challenging for various reasons. First, the&#13;
rural sanitation might even be reached earlier than 2019.  magnitude of the problem. With still 100 million people still&#13;
However, care must be exercized in interpreting the results  not having access to improved sanitation facilities (and 58&#13;
for two reasons. First, current trends presented earlier sug-  million people still practicing open defecation in 2011), In-&#13;
gest that the access rate in 2019 is likely to be way below  donesia will need to help 16 million people per year gain&#13;
the target. Second, the anticipated contribution of house-  access to improved sanitation facilities, current population&#13;
holds (US$410 million per year) is the primary reason for the  growth rates considered. Second, the type of approach&#13;
existence of the surplus. Recalling that such investments  used for sector development. The methodology underlying&#13;
were simply modeled rather than based on documents/  STBM is based on a community-participatory, non-subsidy&#13;
budgets suggests a significant amount of uncertainty. The  approach triggering behavior change, ultimately leveraging&#13;
surplus could very well be a deficit if households decide to  household contributions as main source of financing, and&#13;
spend less than projected here. The fact that access to im-  aiming for collective outcomes. This means a higher focus&#13;
proved sanitation in rural areas remains low suggests that a  on software compared to hardware expenditures, such as&#13;
significant amount of investment for demand creation (soft-  capacity building through training and institutionalization&#13;
ware) will also be necessary to induce households to invest  in schools or the development of real-time SMS and web-&#13;
in hardware facilities.                             based monitoring.&#13;
30                                                                      Water Supply and Sanitation in Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿In this regard, the scorecard reveals a quite realistic pic-  Promising improvements as well as large remaining gaps&#13;
ture of the current situation of the rural sanitation subsector  are both combined in the sustainability level of the program.&#13;
(Figure 9.4): The green building blocks policy and up-take  Acceptance of the approach among the community, willing-&#13;
reflect the existence of the STBM program, a sound policy  ness to bear the cost of improved sanitation services, and&#13;
framework including sector targets and clearly established  improved health and hygiene outcomes were confirmed by&#13;
roles and responsibilities, embracing a high degree of com-  an impact evaluation in 20121 The local private sector of&#13;
munity participation and equity, with a number of incentives  sanitation enterprises is seen as an important partner in de-&#13;
and focus on behavior change.                       livering services, as well as contributions through corporate&#13;
social responsibility programs, all of which are contribut-&#13;
The challenges now focus on the next step in the process,  ing towards better sector performance.40 At the same time,&#13;
the implementation of the policy at national level, and sus-  the use building block still shows a score of 0, indicating&#13;
tainability of the services created. Here, the scorecard re-  that great efforts are still required to meet the 2019 sector&#13;
suits show some bottlenecks. The planning and budgeting  targets, the effectiveness of the equity focus still needs to&#13;
building blocks, including creating investment plans, estab-  be strengthened, and the use of improved facilities is still&#13;
lishing monitoring and evaluation mechanisms, assessing  quite low.&#13;
number and capacity of human resources, as well as having&#13;
sound budget and financial planning mechanisms in place,  At central government level, a secretariat in the Ministry of&#13;
are maturing, although are still in need of development to  Health has been set up to assist the implementation of the&#13;
achieve full nation-wide implementation. A number of initia-  STBM program. This is key to scale up STBM to a nation-&#13;
tives, activities and mechanisms have been implemented in  wide level. The secretariat, however, requires continued as-&#13;
numerous provinces and now being replicated across the  sistance to build capacity and coordinate the implementa-&#13;
wide-spread rural population in Indonesia.          tion of the strategy.&#13;
Figure 9.4 Rural sanitation and hygiene scorecard and results (0 = lowest; 3  highest)&#13;
Enabling                       Developing                       Sustaining&#13;
Policy  Planning  Budget      Expenditure Equity  Output       Markets  Up-take    Use&#13;
D1.125              1             1.5       2        1           1.125&#13;
WSn (2013): TeaM Impact Evaluation, Field note.&#13;
40 According to the Association for Sanitation Entrepreneurs (APPSANI), more than 3000 private sanitation entrepreneurs exist in Indonesia to date.&#13;
Service Delivery Assessment                                                                        31&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿10. Subsector:&#13;
Urban Sanitation and Hygiene&#13;
Priority actions for urban sanitation and hygiene&#13;
Figure 10.1 shows access rates and targets for urban sani-  and Eales et al.11,13 The JMP also estimates that as of 2011,&#13;
tation. Government estimates from the BPS, which are    about 14% of the urban population still practiced open def-&#13;
based on the SUSENAS survey, indicate that about 73%    ecation.4&#13;
of the urban population had access to improved sanitation&#13;
in 2011. Access rates have improved modestly since 1993  Figure 10.1 Access to urban sanitation&#13;
and the changes do not seem large enough to meet the tar-  C 100%&#13;
get of universal access in 2019. The JMP access rates for&#13;
2011 are very close to government estimates.              -  80%&#13;
The SUSENAS survey for 2010, as presented in the JMP,41&#13;
2&#13;
indicates that flush toilets/gooseneck toilet pans are com-&#13;
mon in rural Indonesia (88%). However, government defini-&#13;
tions for improved facilities are much lower than JMP defi-  20%&#13;
nitions, because they require that the toilets be private and&#13;
&lt; 0%&#13;
have access to either a septic tank, a sewerage system or      1990   1995   2000   2005  2010   2015   2020&#13;
a pit. Access to sewerage systems and sewerage treatment           Govt. estimates (1993-2011)  Government target&#13;
in urban areas is still very low, covering only about 1 % of      Govt. estimates (2009-2011)&#13;
the urban population, according to studies by the USDP  Soucs                             a tSDAht costi&#13;
JaMP (2012) Estimates for the use of Improved Sanitation Facilities: Indonesia, w 1sinfo.org.&#13;
42 Urban Sanitation Development Program (2012) National Sanitation Demand Assessment 2012, Draft report, November.&#13;
4Eales K., R. Siregar, E. Febriani and 1. Blackett (2013) Review of Community Managed Decentralized WNastewater Treatment Systems in Indonesia, WSP,&#13;
February.&#13;
4JMP (2013) Progress on Drinking Water and Sanitation: 2013 Update. UNICEF and WHO.&#13;
32                                                                           Water Supply and Sanitation in Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Figure 10.2 Urban sanitation financing (required,        Figure 10.3 Urban sanitation financing (anticipated and&#13;
anticipated and recent investments)                      gap)&#13;
Urban sanitation&#13;
Urban sanitation&#13;
L  2,500&#13;
Household       Total       US$2,340,000,000&#13;
.C                                       0External         Per capita (new): US$184  N Domestic anticipated&#13;
.2  2,000 .M                               Etra&#13;
E                  0 Doesticinvestment&#13;
* Domestic&#13;
C&#13;
1,500 -                                 Sewerage                                  U  External&#13;
system&#13;
syte                                                                        investment&#13;
E&#13;
S 1,000 .U                               Replacement&#13;
-o  5,00  -&#13;
(V&#13;
&gt;                                New                                         Householdanipte&#13;
00so                                                                                 investment&#13;
C&#13;
0                                                                                 Deficit&#13;
Total investment  Anticipated  Recent investment&#13;
requirement investment 2012-2014  2012-2014      1&#13;
The country needs to raise an estimated US$2.3 billion per  by medium scores for planning, expenditure and equity.&#13;
year in order to meet its 2019 targets for urban sanitation  However, the performance of how services are implement-&#13;
(Figure 10.2). About 24% (US$560 million per year) of this  ed and sustained still show major weaknesses, especially&#13;
amount is for providing access to sewerage systems, with  regarding the rate of expansion and quality of treatment,&#13;
a national target of 6% of the urban population by 2019.  described through the low output score. For example, in the&#13;
Anticipated investments are less than investment require-  past, a number of urban sanitation facilities were construct-&#13;
ments, suggesting that planned expenditures for 2012-14  ed throughout the country, but as recent studies shoW,45&#13;
are not enough to meet the targets. This implies that achiev-  many of the facilities still have substantial issues regard-&#13;
ing the targets for 2019 may require substantial increases  ing the quality of their performance. Although regulations&#13;
in investments starting now. The deficits for 2012-14 might  (including norms and standards) are available, but ensuring&#13;
actually be higher than what is estimated here. The reason  high quality technical and managerial performance is one of&#13;
is that 51 % of the anticipated expenditures are projected to  the biggest challenges Indonesia faces in the urban sanita-&#13;
come from households. Funding issues are compounded      tion sector.&#13;
further by the finding in Section 2 that an additional UIS$214&#13;
million per year needs to be generated for maintenance and  Another major bottleneck is the markets building block,&#13;
operating expenditures                                   which reveals the shortcomings in fecal waste collection&#13;
and treatment (score = 0) and the lack of cost recovery of&#13;
The results of the urban sanitation scorecard (Figure 10.4)  treatment systems (score = 0). Given the large prevalence of&#13;
show that it is evident that Indonesia has developed a   pit latrines and septic tanks in urban areas, the lack of fecal&#13;
sound basis for urban sanitation service delivery: Policy and  sludge management is of particular concern. Studies have&#13;
budget building blocks receive quite high scores, followed  shown46,47 that the majority of facilities, which are com-&#13;
m Refer to Ws   (2013), Review of Community-Managed Decentralized Wastewater Treatment Systems in Indonesia, World Bank and AusAID (2013), Urban&#13;
Sanitation Review: Indonesia Country Study.&#13;
i0 Urban Sanitation Review: Indonesia Country Study. The World Bank, 2013.&#13;
 Urban Sludge Management, Wse [reference]&#13;
Service Delivery Assessment                                                                                 33&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿monly called 'septic tanks', do not actually include a prop-  Further bottlenecks in the service delivery pathway of the&#13;
erly functioning sealed tank and treatment system; in most  urban sanitation and hygiene subsector is the lack of prop-&#13;
cases, they are merely latrine facilities with an enforced  er management of decentralized wastewater treatment sys-&#13;
pit as sub-structure. Households in urban areas - many of  tems (DEWATS systems), as well as septage and wastewa-&#13;
them are tenants with unclear land ownership structures -  ter treatment plants. Tariffs collected do not cover costs for&#13;
are not aware of the potentially improperly functioning sub-  operation and maintenance, which leads to dysfunctional&#13;
structures, hence operation and maintenance is poor, pits  facilities. In particular for DEWATS systems, studies have&#13;
are leaking and often discharging directly into the ground-  shown that external monitoring and support for technical&#13;
water. As a consequence, only a few households request  and non-technical problem solving is highly necessary to&#13;
their tanks to be emptied regularly by calling either public or  keep infrastructure in a well functioning shape and ensure&#13;
private service providers for desludging. Once the sludge is  good treatment performance on the long term. Further-&#13;
collected from the households, these providers then further  more, this management issue is also related with institu-&#13;
lack a regulatory mechanism and incentives to safely dis-  tional arrangements due to the unclear distinction between&#13;
pose the fecal sludge into the septage treatment plants. As  regulator and service provider - in numerous cases at local&#13;
a result, a large portion of the collected sludge is disposed  government level, one entity resumes both roles. To tackle&#13;
unsafely directly into the environment.48 The Government is  this issue, central government has started some initiatives,&#13;
aware of the issue and with support from USAID and WSP  such as the Ministry of Public Works and the Ministry of&#13;
is currently developing a program of fecal sludge manage-  Home Affairs, with support from development partners.&#13;
ment to improve the services.&#13;
Figure 10.4 Urban sanitation and hygiene scorecard and results (0 = lowest; 3  highest)&#13;
Enabling                       Developing                       Sustaining&#13;
Policy  Planning  Budget       Expenditure Equity  Output      Markets  Up-take    Use&#13;
t1.5    2             1.5      1.5 D               flE          1        1&#13;
4s It is estimated that only 4% of septage in urban areas is being treated (Urban Sanitation Review: Indonesia Country Study, The World Bank, 2013).&#13;
34                                                                     Water Supply and Sanitation in Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿11. Conclusion&#13;
Both Government and JMP data sources indicate that In-  access in the coming years to achieve universal access by&#13;
donesia has made significant progress in the overall in-  2019; about 24 million people per year have to gain ac-&#13;
crease of access to water and sanitation services in recent  cess to water supply services and 16 million per year for&#13;
years. However, sector targets of 100% coverage by 2019,  sanitation services.&#13;
as set out in the development plans, are very ambitious,&#13;
even though they can be interpreted as a reflection of the  The financial analysis reveals that most of the money is&#13;
increased political priority the sector is receiving as result  needed for the development of urban water supply facili-&#13;
of years of strong sector development. Nonetheless, the  ties (US$4 billion per year) as well as urban sanitation fa-&#13;
strong political support to the sector needs to be continued,  cilities (US$2.3 billion per year). The reason for these high&#13;
and budget allocations need to be increased even more  costs associated with urban services is attributed to the&#13;
than they already have over the recent years to reach these  high rate of urbanization and population growth as well as&#13;
targets. At the same time a focus on reducing the overall  the higher unit costs associated with urban services.&#13;
bottlenecks in the sector through more accurate planning,&#13;
effective implementation and a focus on sustaining the ser-  The scorecard analysis shows that overall, Indonesia is&#13;
vices is required to improve the service delivery pathway  progressing reasonably well in the enabling and develop-&#13;
ing pillars of the service delivery pathway. This results from&#13;
Reaching universal access by 2019 will require a total an-  a supportive institutional environment, improved coordina-&#13;
nual investment into the sector amounting to more than  tion between line ministries, and consistency in reducing&#13;
US$4.7 billion per year for water supply and US$2.8 bil-  inequality by providing access to low income communities&#13;
lion per year for sanitation. These numbers constitute a  in both rural and urban areas. The focus in the future will be&#13;
4.5-fold and 7.5-fold increase in investment into the water  to strengthen the existing system, improve the implementa-&#13;
supply and sanitation subsector, respectively, compared  tion of policies and strategies into actual outputs, improve&#13;
to recent years, when progress was already at an all-time  the overall effectiveness and efficiency of the systems and&#13;
high level. However, the anticipated investments over the  sustain the achieved services through strong ownership,&#13;
three years between 2012 and 2014 still fall far short of  operation and maintenance. Bottlenecks in the developing&#13;
the requirements, with projected deficits of US$2.4 million  and sustaining pillars suggest that high political will needs&#13;
for water supply and US$1.4 billion for sanitation. On top  to be translated into improved investment plans that are&#13;
of this, approximately US$538 million is required for the  linked with local government work plans and budgeting&#13;
operation and maintenance of water supply services, and  processes. Considering the high investment requirements&#13;
US$244 million for sanitation. This money is necessary  to develop urban water supply services, the need for wa-&#13;
when considering the number of people that have to gain  ter utilities to generate revenues and expand access to the&#13;
Service Delivery Assessment                                                                   35&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿poor is rising as well. This includes a supportive political  0  Improve greater coordination between water and&#13;
economy environment at local government level and its in-  sanitation sector programs and poverty programs to&#13;
fluence on achieving cost-recovery tariffs. It further includes  increase the effectiveness of service delivery for the&#13;
strengthening the equity focus by developing clear sub-  poor.&#13;
sector strategies for reaching the poor, including specific  0  Improve local capacity for using M&amp;E systems to in-&#13;
incentives or subsidies for the poor.                 form sector planning, budgeting and targeting imple-&#13;
mentation support.&#13;
At the same time, priority has to be given to the sound and  0  Strengthen the National Water Supply and Sanitation&#13;
integrated planning to ensure the future availability of wa-  Information Services System (NAWASIS) to become an&#13;
ter resources. Without this, many existing weaknesses in  integrated portal for sector-wide M&amp;E.&#13;
the performance of the water supply and sanitation service&#13;
delivery will be exacerbated and investments and solutions&#13;
required will increase significantly.&#13;
The big task for Indonesia in the near future will be to find&#13;
ways to address these challenges. In addition to detailed&#13;
subsector priority actions identified in section 6 to 10, the&#13;
following sector-wide priority actions have been identified&#13;
by stakeholders:&#13;
m Identify support structures for local governments to as-&#13;
sess and improve the quality of their strategic planning&#13;
processes.&#13;
I Scale up development of human resources through in-&#13;
stitutionalized capacity building.&#13;
"   Develop sound investment plans and ensure their en-&#13;
dorsement and incorporation into local government&#13;
work plans for immediate implementation.&#13;
w   Investigate how local accountability mechanisms are&#13;
functioning and potential ways to improve this.&#13;
f  Actively seek involvement of private sector and devel-&#13;
op alternative financing mechanism.&#13;
*   Engage local governments in water management and&#13;
planning to secure future availability of water resources.&#13;
*  Cleary define poor households at the bottom 40% of&#13;
the income distribution and design targeted support to&#13;
ensure inclusive service-delivery.&#13;
36                                                                    Water Supply and Sanitation in Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Figure 11.1 Scorecard of the service delivery pathway for all four subsectors&#13;
Rural Water Supply&#13;
Enabling                            Developing                           Sustaining&#13;
Policy  Planning  Budget           Expenditure  Equity  Output        Maintenance Expansion    Use&#13;
1.5       1.5                         1         1              1.5                   1&#13;
Urban Water Supply&#13;
Enabling                            Developing                          Sustaining&#13;
Policy  Planning  Budget           Expenditure  Equity  Output        Maintenance Expansion    Use&#13;
1.5       1.5                         2                                  1.5        1&#13;
Rural Sanitation and Hygiene&#13;
Enabling                            Developing                           Sustaining&#13;
Policy  Planning  Budget           Expenditure  Equity  Output          Markets   Up-take      Use&#13;
1.125       1              1.5         2         1             1.125&#13;
Urban Sanitation and Hygiene&#13;
Enabling                            Developing                           Sustaining&#13;
Policy  Planning  Budget           Expenditure  Equity  Output          Markets   Up-take      Use&#13;
D&gt;              1.5        2               1.5       1.5     D1                                     1&#13;
Service Delivery Assessment                                                                                     37&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿&amp;,-â&#128;&#149;ã&#128;&#130;ì&#136;&#145;â&#128;&#149;--i&#13;
CO&#13;
í&#155;&#132;ï¼&#137;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿--;,ï¼»ë&#132;&#136;â&#128;&#153;&#13;
C)&#13;
dè®&#147;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿â&#128;&#153;ã&#128;&#149;ã&#128;&#149;ã&#128;&#149;å&#143;«ï¼&#154;å·&#158;&#13;
0&#13;
å&#144;&#139;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿/1/(:1ï¼&#143;ä¸&#137;&#13;
1â&#134;&#146;es&#13;
å¯¸&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿&amp;-------&amp;â&#128;&#153;ã&#128;&#140;ã&#128;&#140;â&#128;&#152;&amp;&amp;â&#128;&#156;ã&#128;&#140;ã&#131;»â&#128;&#149;-----&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;â&#128;&#149;ã&#128;&#129;â&#128;&#149;-----â&#128;&#149;ã&#128;&#140;ã&#128;&#140;ã&#128;&#140;ã&#128;&#140;â&#128;&#153;&amp;-&#13;
N&#13;
å¯¸&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿/1/-&amp;1ï¼¼ä¸&#128;ï¼&#154;ã&#128;&#141;â&#128;&#153;&#13;
ã&#129;®&#13;
å¯¸&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿&amp;ï¼&#143;ã&#128;&#141;ï¼&#143;--:ï¼&#155;ã&#128;&#129;ï¼&#154;:-ï¼&#155;ä¸&#128;&#13;
å¯¸&#13;
å¯¸&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿ï¼&#143;ã&#128;&#141;ï¼&#143;ä¸&#128;&#13;
ã&#129;®&#13;
å¯¸&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿&amp;ï¼&#143;ã&#130;¶â&#128;&#152;&amp;&amp;-&#13;
ã&#129;®&#13;
å¯¸&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿/-ï¼&#154;ã&#128;&#141;ï¼&#128;ä¸&#137;&#13;
ã&#131;&#136;&#13;
å¯¸&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿&amp;/1/-&amp;&amp;â&#128;&#153;ã&#128;&#140;ã&#128;&#140;ã&#131;»ã&#128;&#141;ï¼&#143;-1;1 -:;ï¼&#154;ã&#128;&#129;â&#128;&#149;&#13;
ã&#129;®&#13;
å¯¸&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿ï¼&#143;ã&#128;&#141;ï¼&#143;--ï¼&#154;ã&#128;&#141;ï¼&#128;â&#128;&#149;ã&#128;&#129;1/-;1&amp;&#13;
ã&#129;®&#13;
å¯¸&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿&amp;---â&#128;&#149;ì»¤ï¼&#155;]&#13;
ã&#133;&#135;&#13;
LO&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿0     CL&#13;
0&#13;
0&#13;
0&#13;
cn    cn                         co                         UD                      UD&#13;
w-&#13;
er                         m                         m                       m&#13;
C3-&#13;
wES&#13;
52                   E                                                     w&#13;
F                                                                       d W&#13;
CD&#13;
5Ã½Ã½,                                                            w&#13;
CD          m          Ã½co       Ã¥ 5 5&#13;
2 :Ã½Ã½                                                                2&#13;
W&#13;
18&gt;    -1                                                               w 15 w&#13;
CD                   LI"                 2:9&#13;
W          Ã¶ E co                 --&#13;
U                    2&#13;
r&#13;
I w-                                                               w&#13;
LE                  8 -Ã¥ 2               -5 Ã½5                                         w&#13;
r-      CO                 t5                                           w&#13;
c&#13;
c)&#13;
c)                                                                      W&#13;
wm      cm&#13;
C,&#13;
=&gt;                                           Id&#13;
CO                                                                 W&#13;
C5    w cm a m m m m                                                          w    w&#13;
c"                      m IM                                            m&#13;
2&#13;
CD&#13;
0&#13;
x&#13;
w                       w&#13;
CD&#13;
-i                                                                                     w&#13;
w&#13;
Ln&#13;
w                       w w&#13;
lcÃ½                                                        w&#13;
w&#13;
w&#13;
w&#13;
C3-                        w&#13;
M&#13;
W&#13;
w    x&#13;
w W                  E W&#13;
w w                     w       w&#13;
w    w&#13;
cl                           w cÃ½                    Id w     B            W w&#13;
C3&#13;
&amp;        ss                                                 0&#13;
W                                                  w&#13;
-s ;ES                            t-,        76 w&#13;
CD                                              20             w M w     w               W&#13;
w    - -tÃ½                   5 W        W&#13;
Ã½4      cm           E&#13;
CD   lcÃ½                    cu                                  m          C5-&#13;
2                                  _cs,&#13;
cl                                      M    ,       ,                     M&#13;
C2                                                                    -Ã½5 W&#13;
w    ct            w    w&#13;
3:&#13;
W W                  W&#13;
2       w                  W&#13;
W&#13;
w.        E 2 E&#13;
0 &lt;D&#13;
E&#13;
Id&#13;
cr&#13;
n:                      w&#13;
w-&#13;
w&#13;
Ã¤ 2     -:5&#13;
M&#13;
w&#13;
rn&#13;
Ã¤g&#13;
el-&#13;
c&gt; W&#13;
Ã¥s &lt;D  E&#13;
cn&#13;
LO&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿&amp;-/-ï¼&#140;ë»&#144;ã&#128;&#130;â&#128;&#149;&#13;
Cë&#135;&#140;&#13;
LO&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿-/-ï¼&#140;ì&#154;¥&#13;
dè®&#147;&#13;
LO&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿&amp;---â&#128;&#149;ã&#128;&#140;ã&#131;»ï¼&#155;ï¼&#155;ã&#128;&#129;â&#128;&#149;-----â&#128;&#149;ã&#128;&#140;ã&#128;&#129;ã&#128;&#129;â&#128;&#149;-----ï¼&#154;ã&#128;&#140;ï¼&#138;ã&#128;&#129;â&#128;&#149;;------ï¼&#154;ã&#128;&#129;ï¼&#155;;----ï¼&#154;ã&#128;&#129;ã&#128;&#129;â&#128;&#149;&#13;
å¯¸&#13;
ã&#129;®&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿0      CL&#13;
0&#13;
cn                           co                                                         UD                           cn&#13;
cn&#13;
w-&#13;
ca 5  w&#13;
M                                                                                          m                      CD&#13;
Cj&#13;
Cn&#13;
2 Ã½                                                                                             w                   cn&#13;
C1-&#13;
CD        Wu)                       -0&#13;
C/D p&#13;
C3-&#13;
W W&#13;
CD&#13;
Id&#13;
r&#13;
cc                                                                                                  gt                        E&#13;
Id&#13;
Ã½6              -E&#13;
W                 Id&#13;
M W                       Ã½ = -                  .&#13;
w&#13;
Cn                                                           -9                         w&#13;
C,- &lt;                                                     W  W&#13;
Id&#13;
E w&#13;
5&#13;
m                                                                                            CD- CD-             CÃ¤ V) St&#13;
Lo                                                              to&#13;
0      CD                                                              CD&#13;
E                         Ã¤ 2&#13;
-t5                                                              w&#13;
E&#13;
E&#13;
CD     5                                           c,2&#13;
. -                 -5 Ã½Ã½ Ã½t= w b&#13;
's                                             CD- w&#13;
!E -2,&#13;
2- -a Ã½        .&#13;
15 u                       2&#13;
cÃ½       . , m                  =     -5 Ã½ -0          =  CD-   W&#13;
CD-  Id                                          CD&#13;
E2           Ã½&amp;&#13;
w w           -                                  w&#13;
E                                  W W      w                         15&#13;
g        t:f&#13;
E                                                   w w w&#13;
w&#13;
cs&#13;
CD&#13;
-EU&#13;
cl                           ct                                                                 w w&#13;
E u                          W W              W W      -u&#13;
C6                           co 5     52                             !E&#13;
92                                 2                                                   -5 2      w&#13;
CD&#13;
r                                                                                  -w&#13;
CD                                                                                                                          Ã¥&#13;
-m                                                     w                    w        w t5 m-             lÃ¶&#13;
E                 w&#13;
C2                                  ct&#13;
I     f                                                                      w -w&#13;
Ã¥ w 3Ã½ Ã½9 -.s&#13;
-E w&#13;
2           2Ã½                                                     Id            Id&#13;
r &lt;D&#13;
E                                                                     Id&#13;
x&#13;
-2 t5&#13;
rn&#13;
Ã¤g&#13;
CD&#13;
Id                     Id                           Id&#13;
15-                    151&#13;
c&gt; CJ&#13;
5                                  5                                                    5&#13;
cn&#13;
=                                                                     t5                     t5&#13;
U)                           co                                 UD                      UD                           cn&#13;
LO&#13;
LO&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿&amp;---/-:lã&#128;&#130;ë&#139;&#137;&#13;
ã&#128;&#138;D&#13;
LO&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿0&#13;
0&#13;
0&#13;
CD    cn                                          co                          UD                       UD&#13;
cn&#13;
-2                                          -2&#13;
C')&#13;
w-    CD      -E&#13;
M CD                              Ã½5                                    59                                  ct&#13;
:Ã½Ã½ CO                           -E                                   M&#13;
3Ã½:   5 2     C)&#13;
C)          E E 1,Ã½ .                                     w&#13;
cli         w m -   w           -                                                  w CD&#13;
jÃ½                                     E    E5 g p -&#13;
2 C)                       Ã¤ 5                                                    0-&#13;
CD                                      w                                      M       w     E 3Ã½&#13;
w                    E co         CD       2       cÃ½                                  2        w               =W    5&#13;
c7)                      7,                                          w E     -,j E        52 m  2 P-&#13;
m w&#13;
7,- -5                                                                w&#13;
. -        ' g -2                     w                        W -W     W W&#13;
9-9 9 - 2             . w                           E&#13;
'S                                                                   X&#13;
W W          -E -        w -EO&#13;
cl         a             FE A C) 5                                                               -Ã¥Ã½ 2   Ã½-&#13;
r           s                        C) w                                      w'      E     W&#13;
cc                                                                                                        w     w&#13;
C) m                cm E                                        E 0-&#13;
C)         2Ã½    w                2                                           M&#13;
c) cm                                                                                    Ã½6 W.&#13;
LÃ¤             c)    5&#13;
gÃ¥-                                                          w 6 m&#13;
5                                                    6 Ã½     - E&#13;
w&#13;
co                          w                                        t5    m 15                w l--&#13;
cn&#13;
C5 =                                                            w                                      3:&#13;
CD    E&#13;
:E-5 m-       9 -w            CD-      w&#13;
w w                      w&#13;
F= 25  E                                      m                        W&#13;
2&#13;
Ã¥ co W                                                                             w&#13;
w                        w w&#13;
C-D      &amp; CÃ½r                                                               &lt;   w&#13;
L9                                          Lf)                         to                      to&#13;
0     CD                                           CD                         CD                       CD&#13;
x&#13;
Z,&#13;
CD                                                                             w                        w 2&#13;
w&#13;
w&#13;
w&#13;
LO&#13;
w&#13;
w w&#13;
cÃ½&#13;
m                                                            w&#13;
w A                           Id                  w&#13;
w                     sm&#13;
c3                                          C3                                                      W&#13;
C2-                         w&#13;
g     m&#13;
a                                              M                     w                                 W&#13;
w W                   Id&#13;
w&#13;
w&#13;
w w                              w&#13;
cl                                                w                  I . w       w               =     L&#13;
2 w M                       m w                   W w&#13;
w-                                                                                     w&#13;
E                                                               C3-                  ct-            0&#13;
CD             2                                                                ',5           =        = wW&#13;
W                                                      w           w&#13;
g       w                                w     W W&#13;
E 8                         E                       m     m&#13;
W      cÃ½            2&#13;
Ã½5 Ã½                        ,                                                           g&#13;
-5 t5                                                      w M     j                                w ci&#13;
C2           a       Clt5                                                                 .5                             W&#13;
fi                                                                               w            Ã¤&#13;
-2       5 f2    ff   w     -2                 w&#13;
w 2,                    -E    w&#13;
Ã¥-, w-                                                           1Ã½ , -- E w 2&#13;
0 &lt;D&#13;
E&#13;
cr&#13;
w-                                                                                               W&#13;
w&#13;
:5                                                                                              w-&#13;
w&#13;
rn&#13;
Ã¤g&#13;
el-&#13;
W&#13;
&lt;D   E                                                                       5&#13;
cn&#13;
C2&#13;
LO&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿&amp;-]!;::ï¼&#140;ì»¤ï¼&#154;-::,,-:,,,-&#13;
CO&#13;
LO&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿-/-ï¼&#140;ã&#128;&#141;ã&#128;&#141;ï¼&#140;ì&#154;¤â&#128;&#149;ã&#128;&#130;ï¼&#154;,:ï¼&#140;ã&#128;&#141;â&#128;&#153;&#13;
C)&#13;
LO&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿â&#128;&#153;â&#128;¦â&#128;¦â&#128;¦â&#128;¦ã&#128;&#129;ã&#128;&#129;â&#128;¦ï½&#155;â&#128;¦â&#128;¦ã&#128;&#129;â&#128;¦&#13;
O&#13;
å¹»&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿-a                                  cÃ½Ã¶                    -a                        -a&#13;
Q? u&#13;
C:&gt;&#13;
-a                                                         -a                        -a&#13;
2    c:&gt;&#13;
co                                     CD                   UD                       UD&#13;
t&#13;
-2                                                         -2&#13;
Ã½2&#13;
UD&#13;
cn&#13;
-a&#13;
-a m  E&#13;
-NI&#13;
x g&#13;
U&#13;
E&#13;
p&#13;
-a                             w&#13;
w 1Ã½                          t5&#13;
w w&#13;
E :E                           w                              m&#13;
w&#13;
w&#13;
t5                             w&#13;
w w I                          -&#13;
W       w&#13;
E&#13;
W       w&#13;
f5 F-                     w  L -w&#13;
F=                                                               w&#13;
c)                                                       E                   co    3:&#13;
o-&#13;
&lt;- kal a   51                                                                        o-&#13;
LO                          LO&#13;
CD                          CD&#13;
-E&#13;
w    w                    w&#13;
E&#13;
-a&#13;
W&#13;
W                                                CD-&#13;
X Id&#13;
w&#13;
w                      w&#13;
_w   JÃ½    W&#13;
. -W E&#13;
2               2 w                                            -   E&#13;
cl                      W                                   Ã½w w Ã½w w&#13;
M w W&#13;
5&#13;
CD            Ã¥ w                                           w b,2 a                   w x     E&#13;
w&#13;
cs&#13;
-EL&#13;
t75 E&#13;
w            51      W 'W&#13;
n- -us&#13;
5    '5      r            . - t -E&#13;
rn                                                                     E W     W            . m w W W&#13;
w E            w 0-    E E&#13;
-5 -2      E U                                             _w         I  w              xw      w&#13;
I w                      5&#13;
W&#13;
C6                                                              t5    -W 0-          2       2&#13;
I&#13;
M                                                           w&#13;
Ã½92     Ã¥-    m E              92                             Ã½i  -W m                         E&#13;
w                         w&#13;
M                                      -a                                  2                 w       Id&#13;
F=                                        E                -E m-              2Ã½             .5&#13;
- -s 0-1                         -a M          W    W                                                -w&#13;
2-5 -j3- -a t75 a-                        m    w E       E                                        W&#13;
a -2 w&#13;
E    w&#13;
a Cl    m a M M                          .2 SÃ½                                       E               w&#13;
W                    W         a                   -a&#13;
C2                                      w          E m w p                6                 w w     Id t5&#13;
Ã¶                                                           a      w m        w -    5 .        .&#13;
-w m       s tÃ¥                 b Ã½ -5         -n&#13;
5;              Id&#13;
GE                  m                     -W Ã½&#13;
Y w aÃ½2&#13;
E s       5 E&#13;
E,&#13;
&lt;9&#13;
er&#13;
a, m M                         a                            w&#13;
-E                        a                            10&#13;
M -.                                                        M.                       Id&#13;
&lt;&#13;
rn&#13;
(i                                 -a                          -a                        -a&#13;
x                           x                         x&#13;
(J CJ&#13;
c2 2&#13;
U)                             Cf)                         CID                       UD&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿éµ â&#128;&#149;---l&#13;
Qlã&#128;&#130;â&#128;&#149;ã&#128;&#148;â&#128;&#149;ã&#128;&#148;â&#128;&#149;ï¼&#140;ã&#128;&#130;â&#128;&#149;&#13;
å&#143;¬ã&#128;&#130;â&#128;&#149;9â&#128;&#149;è±&#144;â&#128;&#149;91æ&#130;¶l&#13;
U 91é°&#147;â&#128;&#149;å&#143;©â&#128;&#149;é°&#147;â&#128;&#149;C-&#13;
é&#155;&#153;1 91æ&#136;&#150;â&#128;&#149;å¯«â&#128;&#149;æ&#136;&#150;â&#128;&#149;å½&#142;â&#128;&#149;&#13;
äº¡å&#156;&#159;â&#128;&#149;dâ&#128;&#149;ä¹&#153;â&#128;&#149;å&#143;¤â&#128;&#149;ç©¶â&#128;&#149;&#13;
ï¼&#141;ç´°jâ&#150; ï¼&#135;râ&#150; ã&#128;&#142;jè¼ªâ&#150; rã&#128;&#141;hâ&#150; ï¼&#135;æ±&#151;å&#133;&#128;â&#150; &#13;
â&#128;¢ï¼&#141;â&#150; äº&#140;ã&#128;&#143;â&#128;&#149;äº&#140;äº&#140;â&#128;&#149;äº¡ã&#128;&#143;â&#128;&#149;UJ-&#13;
äº¡æ&#155;°Iå»&#136;äº&#140;â&#128;&#149;å&#143;£â&#128;&#149;Cã&#128;&#149;â&#128;&#149;-&#13;
ä¸&#128;é¨&#153;Jâ&#150; â&#128;&#149;-â&#128;&#149;äº&#140;äº&#140;â&#128;&#149;&#13;
ä¸&#128;â&#134;&#146;â&#150; ã&#128;&#144;äº&#140;â&#128;&#149;ã&#128;&#144;äº&#140;â&#128;&#149;è¨&#140;äº&#140;â&#128;&#149;é¨&#153;J-&#13;
Lï½&#158;å&#133;&#128;äº&#140;â&#150; Cäº¡â&#128;&#149;Cäº¡â&#128;&#149;rç&#130;ºâ&#128;&#149;,~--&#13;
ã&#128;&#142;ã&#128;&#129;é»&#156;â&#150; å&#143;£â&#150; å¿&#133;æ&#151;¥å¿&#133;â&#150; å¿&#133;æ&#151;¥å¿&#133;â&#150; å¿&#133;æ&#151;¥å¿&#133;â&#150; ï¼&#135;ï¼&#142;â&#150; ï½&#128;â&#150; &#13;
ã&#128;&#129;jâ&#150; å·&#158;ï¼&#140;â&#150; å·&#158;ldï¼&#140;â&#150; ï¼&#135;lâ&#134;&#146;ï¼&#141;å·&#158;lç·¨ï½&#158;JI&#13;
æ±&#159;äº&#140;ä¸­lå&#155;&#154;â&#128;&#149;å&#155;&#154;â&#128;&#149;æ&#130;¶â&#128;&#149;OU-&#13;
ä¹&#159;eâ&#128;&#149;æ´»â&#128;&#149;ä¿&#152;â&#128;&#149;æ¾&#128;â&#128;&#149;ä¸&#141;â&#128;&#149;&#13;
ä»&#149;äº&#140;Iä¸­â&#128;&#149;ä¸­â&#128;&#149;å&#139;¾â&#128;&#149;d-&#13;
ã&#128;&#148;0IVJ-UJ-UJ-1ã&#128;&#145;ï¼¿l&#13;
é&#135;&#140;ç&#154;&#132;â&#128;&#149;äº¡â&#128;&#149;äº¡â&#128;&#149;äº¡â&#128;&#149;ç&#156;¾ä¸&#128;l&#13;
VJIä¸­â&#128;&#149;ä¸­â&#128;&#149;ä¸­â&#128;&#149;ä¸&#138;ä¹&#139;å¼&#139;f-&#13;
-lç´°â&#128;&#152;â&#128;&#149;ç¶ºâ&#128;&#152;â&#128;&#149;çº&#143;ã&#128;&#141;â&#128;&#149;Oã&#128;&#149;ã&#128;&#148;å&#136;&#129;â&#128;&#149;&#13;
å¿&#133;läº&#140;ä¸&#141;läº&#140;ä¸&#141;läº&#140;ä¸&#141;læ±&#151;å¹³ï¼&#136;å·&#158;l&#13;
æ&#136;¶â&#150; â&#150; ä¸&#128;jâ&#150; ï¼&#141;jâ&#150; ï¼&#141;â&#150; Ljå¿&#133;ï¼&#141;ä¸&#128;â&#150; &#13;
ç¥&#144;â&#128;&#149;---ï¼¿ã&#128;&#130;â&#128;&#149;&#13;
æ&#150;&#151;å&#141;&#156;lå£«äº&#140;â&#128;&#149;,-â&#128;&#149;å&#129;&#142;â&#128;&#149;&#13;
å¯«çµ¨Iè ¶â&#128;&#149;ä¸&#138;d-â&#128;&#149;å¿&#133;U-&#13;
é&#128;&#143;â&#128;&#149;ã&#128;&#130;ã&#128;&#129;ç&#128;&#137;â&#128;&#149;ä½»â&#128;&#149;â&#128;&#149;é&#135;&#140;â&#128;&#149;&#13;
äº&#140;â&#128;&#149;ä»»ã&#128;&#130;äº¡â&#128;&#149;å&#144;&#138;â&#128;&#149;â&#128;&#149;æ&#155;°ï¼&#140;-&#13;
&amp;nlå£¯å¿&#133;å&#145;&#136;äº¡ï¼&#135;å&#133;«1 9 1 1 COAè&#153;&#159;l&#13;
ç&#150;&#139;â&#128;&#149;é&#156;&#135;è&#138;»é§&#157;â&#128;&#149;å&#143;¬â&#128;&#149;â&#128;&#149;äº&#140;å&#149;&#158;â&#128;&#149;&#13;
01å¦&#157;å½&#142;ï¼&#135;ä»&#129;â&#128;&#149;Q--hå°¸ã&#128;&#148;å&#136;&#136;â&#128;&#149;&#13;
å&#144;&#131;äº¡ä¸­Iå&#143;ªï¼&#141;ä¸&#141;â&#128;&#149;ä¸&#131;äº&#140;â&#128;&#149;â&#128;&#149;è®&#138;å&#143;&#148;lã&#128;&#129;ï½&#128;-&#13;
LUå&#141;&#156;â&#150; ä¸&#128;ï¼&#136;å¿&#133;ä¸&#141;â&#128;&#149;uã&#128;&#141;â&#128;&#149;-&amp;&amp;-&#13;
äº¡ï¼&#140;å&#148;±å&#136;&#129;â&#150; r-gäº&#140;æ±&#151;è&#144;¬â&#128;&#149;æ&#150;&#151;ï½&#128;--&amp;,&amp;,~--&#13;
ç&#149;¸å·&#158;ã&#128;&#129;ï¼&#135;ã&#128;&#129;â&#150; ï¼&#141;äº¡äº¡h-ï¼&#141;ç¶²ç¦ºç¶²é¦´â&#150; â&#150; â&#150; é¨&#153;kå·&#158;â&#150; &#13;
&amp;&amp;ï¼&#135;äº&#134;è±&#144;â&#150; ï¼&#136;jJUã&#128;&#145;å·&#158;ï½&#128;â&#128;&#149;äº&#134;é»&#145;â&#128;&#149;â&#128;&#149;ä¸&#128;å¼&#139;f-&#13;
ç&#148;&#152;ï¼&#135;lå&#143;¬ä¸&#128;å&#157;&#144;ç&#148;°â&#128;&#149;ä¸«â&#128;&#149;-1äº&#140;ã&#128;&#148;å&#136;&#129;â&#128;&#149;&#13;
å·&#146;1 PCå&#133;«1â&#128;&#149;ä¸&#128;â&#128;&#149;-O)ï¼&#136;å·&#158;â&#128;&#149;&#13;
å&#150;&#157;å&#136;&#129;â&#150; ä¸&#141;äº&#140;â&#128;&#157;~ï¼&#141;å&#139;¾jâ&#128;&#149;äº¡å¯«â&#128;&#149;â&#128;&#149;ä»&#149;ï¼&#135;ä¸&#128;â&#128;&#149;&#13;
å&#141;&#156;â&#128;&#149;å&#139;¾ä¸&#131;ç&#154;&#132;â&#128;&#149;d-â&#128;&#149;ç½&#149;æ&#150;&#151;l&#13;
äº&#140;ICå&#136;&#128;CCã&#128;&#145;l_11è&#152;&#138;hå¿&#133;è¦&#129;l&#13;
jâ&#150; é³¥â&#150; ï¼&#135;æ&#136;¶â&#134;&#146;ï¼&#141;å·&#158;â&#150; käº&#140;äº&#140;â&#150; ä¸&#128;â&#150; â&#150; däº&#140;ï¼&#141;â&#150; &#13;
äº¡ä»&#149;â&#150; å&#141;&#156;ï½&#158;ç&#155;¤ä¸­å&#139;°å¿&#133;jâ&#128;&#149;ç·¨â&#128;&#152;j&amp;-â&#128;&#149;ä¸&#128;â&#128;&#149;1--&#13;
äº¡å¿&#133;äº&#140;â&#150; äº&#140;äº&#140;ç·¨ä¹&#136;lã&#128;&#144;äº&#140;11ä¸&#128;äº&#140;æ&#150;&#151;ä¸&#141;l&#13;
æ&#150;&#151;æ&#155;°â&#150; ã&#128;&#129;å¿&#133;ï¼&#141;ã&#128;&#138;ã&#128;&#145;lä¸&#128;11ï½&#128;ä¹&#139;ï¼&#135;é¨&#153;å°¸JI&#13;
å¯¶Iç±µè&#128;&#140;äº¡ä¸&#141;â&#128;&#149;æ¯&#128;â&#128;&#149;â&#128;&#149;æ&#151;¥ï½&#158;äº&#140;å&#136;&#129;â&#128;&#149;&#13;
hâ&#150; â&#150; ä»&#149;é&#150;&#128;å&#143;«å¿&#133;äº&#140;â&#150; å½&#142;ï¼&#135;â&#150; â&#150; â&#150; ï½&#158;&amp;jã&#128;&#149;â&#150; &#13;
ã&#128;&#143;å&#143;£é&#150;&#139;â&#150; â&#128;&#152;]ï½&#128;â&#150; ï¼&#140;ã&#128;&#129;ï¼&#135;â&#134;&#146;ã&#128;&#158;ï¼&#135;ã&#128;&#149;â&#150; rã&#128;&#149;ã&#128;&#129;ï¼&#135;rï¼&#140;â&#150; â&#150; ã&#128;&#129;ï¼&#142;ï¼&#142;â&#150; jâ&#150; &#13;
ï½&#128;å¼&#152;Jâ&#150; ã&#128;&#142;ã&#128;&#142;ï¼&#135;ï¼&#140;â&#150; å°¸ï¼&#135;ä¹&#139;ç&#155;¡â&#150; â&#150; ré&#150;&#145;å·&#158;â&#150; &#13;
â&#150; â&#150; â&#150; â&#150; â&#150; æ±&#151;ä¸&#141;gäº¡äº&#140;ï¼&#136;äº&#140;r-läº¡äº&#140;é¨&#153;ï½&#128;11ã&#128;&#129;ï¼&#141;&amp;ï¼&#135;ç«ºï¼&#141;äº¡l&#13;
æ±&#151;â&#128;&#149;è¨&#136;å¤&#156;ç¹&#148;ç&#132;¡â&#128;&#149;ä»¥Jå³¶â&#128;&#149;â&#128;&#149;å&#140;&#149;b-&#13;
ï¼&#142;å&#129;½lç&#148;²è¡«æ&#155;°äº¡â&#128;&#149;å&#143;¬æ&#155;°â&#128;&#149;-nã&#128;&#129;å¼&#139;æ&#137;&#141;â&#128;&#149;&#13;
-lä»&#149;å·&#158;ç´¯gã&#128;&#149;â&#128;&#149;å¿&#133;â&#128;&#152;ã&#128;&#141;â&#128;&#149;â&#128;&#149;äº&#142;ã&#128;&#148;å&#136;&#129;â&#128;&#149;&#13;
â&#128;&#149;å&#145;&#130;é­&#154;é&#128; é¯&#138;â&#128;&#149;æ&#156;&#155;å&#140;&#149;â&#128;&#149;_â&#128;&#149;ä¸&#145;é»&#156;â&#128;&#149;&#13;
Inã&#128;&#129;ï¼&#155;æ&#137;&#141;äº&#140;ä¸&#128;â&#128;&#149;å¦&#157;å£«äº&#140;â&#128;&#149;Uã&#128;&#145;â&#128;&#149;æ­¢äº¡ä¸&#141;â&#128;&#149;&#13;
1 Chsqå¹³ä¸&#131;å&#144;&#136;lä¸&#138;å&#140;&#149;ã&#128;&#139;ã&#128;&#138;IDå¿&#133;lï¼&#136;ã&#128;&#149;å&#128;&#152;æ&#151;¥l&#13;
lã&#128;&#138;å&#143;£â&#128;&#152;äº&#140;å®&#137;å&#140;&#149;â&#128;&#149;Cjç&#156;¾â&#128;&#149;iè&#142;&#150;ã&#128;&#145;â&#128;&#149;å·¥äº&#140;é&#157;¢â&#128;&#149;&#13;
â&#150; nã&#128;&#129;â&#128;&#149;Hç&#148;°ï½&#128;å¿&#133;10ã&#128;&#149;ä¸&#128;ï¼&#135;lä¸&#128;1 QJn,l&#13;
â&#128;&#149;å·¢ç&#149;°è&#131;&#142;pâ&#128;&#149;æ¢&#129;å&#138;&#141;â&#128;&#149;å&#144;&#139;â&#128;&#149;æ¯&#128;å&#145;&#130;â&#128;&#149;&#13;
lå&#156;&#159;ä»&#149;ã&#128;&#149;å&#157;&#144;dä¹&#159;lä»&#149;å·&#158;å&#143;£ã&#128;&#149;1 OJIæ±&#151;ã&#128;&#145;ä»&#149;dl&#13;
lè¨&#152;äº¡å·&#158;å·&#158;ç&#148;²â&#128;&#149;ï¼&#135;å·&#158;æ&#150;&#151;â&#128;&#149;â&#134;&#146;ä¸&#141;â&#128;&#149;â&#150; å¼&#159;ã&#128;&#148;å·¥â&#128;&#149;&#13;
â&#128;&#149;ä¸&#128;â&#128;&#156;â&#128;&#153;ä¸&#128;ä¸&#128;å¿&#133;â&#128;&#152;å¿&#133;â&#150; å·&#158;â&#128;&#152;&amp;â&#128;&#149;ä¸&#128;ä¸&#128;â&#128;&#149;&#13;
â&#128;&#153;ã&#128;&#149;ç±&#159;ç&#148;²ç½&#159;ã&#128;&#149;ã&#128;&#149;l&#13;
ä¹&#159;ä¹&#143;1 11â&#134;&#146;IUã&#128;&#149;l&#13;
å&#144;&#132;â&#128;&#149;-â&#128;&#149;æ±&#159;â&#128;&#149;è³¢ï¼¿-&#13;
é&#159;¿â&#128;&#149;â&#128;&#149;ç´&#153;â&#128;&#149;å&#155;&#155;â&#128;&#149;å&#143;¸å&#144;&#141;â&#128;&#149;&#13;
Cã&#128;&#141;Iâ&#128;&#149;ä¸&#141;â&#128;&#149;é&#157;&#132;äº&#140;â&#128;&#149;å&#143;¬å¹³hæ³&#149;â&#128;&#149;&#13;
&amp;-â&#128;&#149;ç&#159;³â&#128;&#149;pç&#156;¾â&#128;&#149;ä¸&#141;å&#140;&#149;â&#128;&#149;&#13;
-9â&#128;&#149;é&#159;¿â&#128;&#149;å±&#134;å·¨â&#128;&#149;è·&#154;å»¿â&#128;&#149;&#13;
-&amp;-u-&amp;&amp;â&#128;&#149;ã&#128;&#141;ã&#128;&#130;â&#128;&#149;&#13;
,â&#128;&#149;å¦&#130;â&#128;&#149;â&#128;&#149;ã&#128;&#130;â&#128;&#149;,-&#13;
â&#128;&#156;äº¡â&#128;&#149;äº¡ä»»â&#128;&#149;ç¦ºâ&#128;&#149;ä¸&#141;æ&#156;&#155;â&#128;&#149;ç&#153;½äº&#140;â&#128;&#149;&#13;
Câ&#128;¢10å&#157;&#144;â&#128;&#149;ä¸&#128;å·¢â&#128;&#149;æ±°â&#128;&#149;gJ-&#13;
ä¸&#128;1 Fkâ&#128;&#149;æ&#155;°ï¼&#140;æ&#155;°â&#128;&#149;ï½&#128;â&#134;&#146;â&#128;&#149;-~-&#13;
è&#136;&#155;läº¡iè&#128;&#145;â&#128;&#149;ä¸&#128;ç&#137;&#135;äº&#140;ä¸&#141;â&#128;&#149;ï¼&#136;å&#136;&#136;â&#128;&#149;äº¡â&#128;&#149;&#13;
â&#150; Jâ&#150; ï¼&#141;è±&#144;äº¡e~lã&#128;&#142;ã&#128;&#129;r-näº&#140;è&#144;¬è¨&#136;lä¹&#136;éº¾1 res&amp;&amp;l&#13;
å&#144;&#141;â&#128;&#149;è±&#136;æ&#157;±â&#128;&#149;è&#137;²é&#155;ªé&#130;&#149;è&#151;&#157;â&#128;&#149;å&#143;&#131;â&#128;&#149;ç¥&#157;ç¿&#129;â&#128;&#149;&#13;
æ&#154;¹â&#128;&#149;ç³§æ¡&#145;â&#128;&#149;ç&#148;&#154;è ¶é&#128;&#149;è&#150;¹â&#128;&#149;æ&#131;¡â&#128;&#149;æ&#151;¦ä»»â&#128;&#149;&#13;
â&#128;&#149;ä¸&#128;â&#128;&#156;lä¸&#128;â&#128;&#153;ä¸&#128;lä¸&#128;ã&#128;&#149;å&#140;¹ã&#128;&#130;l&#13;
&amp;ï¼&#142;é­&#154;l--â&#128;&#149;å¾&#145;p-&#13;
ä¹&#142;â&#128;&#149;æ&#147;&#138;å&#143;¬â&#128;&#149;â&#128;&#149;å&#138;&#141;â&#128;&#149;äº¡â&#128;&#149;&#13;
å&#141;&#148;â&#128;&#149;è±&#144;è±&#144;â&#128;&#149;ç´&#153;â&#128;&#149;é&#129; â&#128;&#149;å&#143;¬ç&#133;®â&#128;&#149;&#13;
å¾&#145;è±&#144;è±&#144;â&#150; LUã&#128;&#138;ã&#128;&#145;â&#128;&#149;hé¦´â&#128;&#149;ç&#148;³ç&#148;²â&#128;&#149;ç£&#154;ç¶²å·&#158;ä¸&#141;ä¸&#141;â&#128;&#149;&#13;
=lé¦³é³¥lç&#159;³lä¸&#141;æ¯&#128;â&#128;&#149;ã&#128;&#130;å&#140;&#149;l&#13;
â&#128;&#149;è·&#145;æµ©â&#128;&#149;ç&#149;¶â&#128;&#149;è·&#154;å&#156;­â&#128;&#149;ç&#133;&#153;å»¿â&#128;&#149;&#13;
â&#128;&#149;è&#151;&#157;â&#128;&#156;;lä¸&#128;lä¸&#128;è®&#147;äº&#140;lä¸&#128;è&#142;&#150;l&#13;
â&#128;&#149;è&#142;&#150;å&#128;¡é¦®â&#128;&#149;äº&#140;â&#128;&#149;ä»&#149;å&#146;&#146;å·&#158;å&#157;&#144;â&#128;&#149;ä¸&#131;é&#156;&#128;P-&#13;
ï¼&#140;ã&#128;&#149;å®¶å&#145;½è&#143;¯æ&#142;&#146;ã&#128;&#149;é¾&#148;ã&#128;&#129;l&#13;
å&#143;£ã&#128;&#141;I----&#13;
å¿&#133;èª¿å&#144;&#131;è±&#144;â&#150; â&#128;&#149;&amp;n---&#13;
ä»&#129;è·&#154;Iâ&#128;&#149;ç&#154;&#132;â&#128;&#149;--&#13;
ä¸­å£«l-P---&#13;
æ±¨è³¼â&#128;&#149;â&#128;&#149;å·±â&#128;&#149;â&#128;&#149;ç&#154;&#132;â&#128;&#149;&#13;
ã&#128;&#139;å&#136;&#131;lå¦&#157;ä¸&#128;â&#128;&#149;p-&amp;â&#128;&#149;å&#143;&#159;â&#128;&#149;&#13;
å&#143;£Jç«ºeâ&#150; å£«d resâ&#128;&#149;æ±&#151;ä¸&#141;â&#128;&#149;yiâ&#128;&#149;å&#156;&#159;äº¡â&#128;&#149;&#13;
ç´°ç&#156;¾â&#128;&#149;é¨&#153;6â&#128;&#149;äº¡â&#128;&#149;å&#144;&#136;â&#128;&#149;äº&#142;â&#128;&#149;&#13;
å&#148;±å&#136;&#129;æ&#150;&#151;é¨&#153;â&#150; å&#143;&#159;æ&#150;&#151;å¿&#133;â&#128;&#149;cn-â&#128;&#149;é¦®â&#128;&#149;&#13;
ä»&#150;å·²â&#150; qï¼&#135;å&#141;&#156;ï¼&#140;lç´°äº&#140;läº&#140;äº&#140;lå&#141;&#156;ç&#149;&#153;l&#13;
å&#149;¦ã&#128;&#138;qlé&#150;&#128;ã&#128;&#129;ä»»æ&#139;±â&#128;&#149;Cjâ&#128;&#149;å¿&#133;â&#128;&#149;æ&#137;&#141;ï¼&#141;-&#13;
Cã&#128;&#130;â&#128;&#152;â&#150; Iå¯§äº&#140;äº¡æ&#151;¥â&#128;&#149;å&#143;£ã&#128;&#149;â&#128;&#149;),â&#128;&#149;ä¸&#141;ä¸&#141;â&#128;&#149;&#13;
å²&#140;ã&#128;&#130;â&#128;&#149;ç&#133;&#153;å¡&#158;â&#128;&#149;é&#143;&#150;â&#128;&#149;è¨&#128;â&#128;&#149;j-&#13;
_â&#128;&#149;ä¸&#128;lä¸&#128;lä¸&#128;lä¸&#128;l&#13;
ã&#128;&#148;è¨&#149;11----&#13;
gã&#128;&#143;å¿&#133;lä»&#129;â&#128;&#149;---&#13;
tå±&#134;ã&#128;&#138;JIã&#128;&#138;å&#136;&#129;1 1 11&#13;
é»&#157;ç&#155;®ï¼&#142;å¦&#146;â&#150; hâ&#150; äº¡å¼&#139;ä¹&#143;â&#150; â&#150; â&#150; â&#150; &#13;
lå¸¸ã&#128;&#143;å¿ læ&#136;¶â&#128;&#149;---&#13;
På&#143;£ã&#128;&#141;lè&#141;&#138;â&#128;&#149;---&#13;
å&#155;&#154;â&#128;&#149;å&#136;&#134;â&#128;&#149;B-B-B-&#13;
â&#128;&#149;å±±â&#128;&#149;&amp;-&amp;-&amp;-&#13;
é&#129;&#156;â&#128;&#149;----&#13;
å&#143;£J-â&#128;&#153;è¨&#128;ï¼&#140;â&#150; â&#128;&#149;---&#13;
ï¼&#142;è&#135;¼ä¸&#128;â&#128;&#149;ã&#128;&#130;â&#128;&#149;ã&#128;&#130;â&#128;&#149;ã&#128;&#130;â&#128;&#149;ã&#128;&#130;â&#128;&#149;&#13;
ä¹&#158;å·±â&#128;&#149;å&#145;&#136;â&#128;&#149;é&#130;&#145;â&#128;&#149;é&#145;&#146;â&#128;&#149;å&#145;&#136;â&#128;&#149;&#13;
ä¸­91ä»&#149;â&#128;&#149;å£¯â&#128;&#149;ä»&#149;â&#128;&#149;ä»&#149;â&#128;&#149;&#13;
ç&#154;&#132;é&#129;²â&#128;&#149;é»&#145;â&#128;&#149;é»&#145;â&#128;&#149;é»&#145;â&#128;&#149;é»&#145;â&#128;&#149;&#13;
ä¸­Ié&#130;¢â&#128;&#149;é&#130;¢â&#128;&#149;é&#150;&#139;â&#128;&#149;é&#150;&#139;â&#128;&#149;&#13;
ã&#128;&#130;â&#128;&#149;ç&#154;&#132;â&#128;&#149;ç&#154;&#132;â&#128;&#149;ç&#154;&#132;â&#128;&#149;ç&#154;&#132;â&#128;&#149;&#13;
å&#135;¶&#13;
O&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Annex 2:&#13;
Key Inputs for the Required and&#13;
Anticipated Capital Expenditures&#13;
This annex describes the key inputs that were used to   Demographic Variables&#13;
generate estimates of the required and anticipated capital&#13;
expenditures. It discusses the sources, adjustments and  The model requires two sets of demographic variables. The&#13;
assumptions of the following information: exchange rates,  first set captures rural and urban population estimates/pro-&#13;
demographic variables, sector-specific technologies and  jections for base year (2011) and target year (2019). This in-&#13;
spending plans.                                         formation is combined with existing and target access rates&#13;
for water and sanitation in order to calculate the number of&#13;
Exchange Rates                                          people that will be requiring access to improved facilities&#13;
during the period of analysis. The other set of information&#13;
Amounts in Indonesia rupiah (IDR) from 2009 to 2012 were  refers to the average size of households. This is used to&#13;
converted into US Dollars using annual exchange rates from  convert costs of facilities, which are generally in expressed&#13;
the World Development Indicators." Projections for 2013 fol-  on a per household basis, into per capita terms.&#13;
low the assumptions used by the Ministry of Finance, which&#13;
are in turn based on Law No. 15 on the State Budget for  Table A2.1 shows the key demographic variables used in&#13;
2013.10 The exchange rates for succeeding years were as-  the analysis. Aggregate population data for 2011 and 2019&#13;
sumed to be the same as in 2013.                        were obtained from Bappenas et al. (2005).11 Rural and&#13;
urban population data were generated using proportions&#13;
Table A2.1 Current and target access rates              and growth rates from the UN .12 The analysis assumes that&#13;
there are 3.9 members per household .53&#13;
Region   Population (millions)&#13;
Annual population growth  Access Rates&#13;
2011      2019&#13;
Table A2.2 shows the baseline (2011) and target (2019) ac-&#13;
Rural   117          112           -0.3%             cess rates for water supply and sanitation. The 2011 ac-&#13;
Urban   120          146           2,5%b             cess rates for sanitation and water supply were calculated&#13;
National  236         258         not calculated      using data from the SUSENAS by the BPS and Bappenas,&#13;
respectively.&#13;
a All values for this row were calculated as residuals. b This value represents the&#13;
projected population growth rate for 2010-2015 of the UN (2012) World Statistics&#13;
Pocketbook, Department of Economic and Social Affairs, UN, New York. c Bappenas,&#13;
BPS and United Nations Population Fund (2005) Proyeksi Penduduk Indonesia&#13;
(Indonesia Population Projection), Jakarta.&#13;
World Bank (2013) World Development Indicators, http://data.worldbank.org/indicator/PA.NUS.FCRF.&#13;
Ministry of Finance website, http://www.depkeu.go.id/Eng/?menu=engiish.&#13;
Bappenas, BPS and United Nations Population Fund (2005) Proyeksi Penducluk Indonesia (Indonesia Population Projection), Jakarta.&#13;
12 UN (2012) World Statistics Pocketbook, Department of Economic and Social Affairs, UN, New York.&#13;
13 The estimate is for 2010. Badan Pusat Statistilk [Statistics Indonesia] (2013) Perkembangan Beberapa Indikator Utama Social-Ekonomi Indonesia [Trends&#13;
of Selected Socio-Economic Indicators of Indonesia], Jakarta, May.&#13;
Service Delivery Assessment                                                                               63&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Sector-specific Technologies: Water                    Table A2.4 presents information on the expected household&#13;
distribution, costs and lifespans of key sanitation technolo-&#13;
Information on sector-specific technologies, unit costs, and  gies.&#13;
expected life are necessary for the calculation of invest-&#13;
ment requirements. Table A2.3 presents data on the var-  Improved sanitation facilities are defined by Indonesian au-&#13;
ables mentioned above for water supply.                thorities as a household that has its own latrine, gooseneck&#13;
latrine and/or pit latrine, and uses a septic tank as the final&#13;
The options included and shares for 2011 were based on  disposal facility.55&#13;
the technologies reported in SUSENAS 2010, which was&#13;
presented in JMP However, given the absence of docu-  An Urban Sanitation Development Program (USDP)56 report&#13;
ments, the distribution of water supply technologies for  identifies improved facilities as private or shared facility that&#13;
2020 was based on the informed judgment of stakeholders  has access to a gooseneck as a type of barrier and either&#13;
at the SDA validation workshop in Jakarta on June 2013.54  a septic tank, pit latrine or sewerage system as a type of&#13;
treatment .57 The 2011 distribution of facilities in Table A2.4&#13;
Unit capital costs represent expenditures for materials and  were apportioned across facilities using information from&#13;
labor used in the construction of the different facilities while  the JMP58 Given the absence of documents, the distribu-&#13;
lifespan refers to the projected number of years before a  tion of sanitation options for rural areas in 2019 was based&#13;
facility is fully replaced. For urban water supply, the infor-  on the opinions that stakeholders provided at the SDA&#13;
mation in Table A2.2 was based on the project experience  validation workshop in Jakarta on June 2013. For urban&#13;
of participants at the SDA validation workshop in Jakarta  households, the projected distribution was obtained as fol-&#13;
on June 2013. On the other hand, unit costs for rural water  lows. Information from Bappenas indicates that national&#13;
supply were based on estimates from the Domestic Private  targets for communal facilities (which represents SANIMAS&#13;
Sector Project (DPSP) and the Third Water Supply and San-  in the analysis) rise by about one percentage point per year&#13;
itation for Low Income Communities Project (PAMSIMAS).  between 2010 (1%) to 2014 (5%). If this trend continues,&#13;
then about 9% of the national population will have access&#13;
to such facilities by 2019. Confining the use of such facili-&#13;
Sector-specific Technologies: Sanitation               ties to urban areas suggests that about 16% of the urban&#13;
population in 2019 will have access to communal facilities.&#13;
Table A2.2 Current and target access rates             However, using 16% for SANIMAS facilities will be difficult&#13;
Sector            2011            2019          to employ in the analysis because it means that proportion&#13;
Rura watr spply58%          00%of the urban population with access to private facilities will&#13;
Rural water supply      58%             100%fall from 86% in 2011 to 84% in 2019. Hence, the decision&#13;
Urban water supply      52%             100%          adopted for the analysis is to assume that access to private&#13;
Rural sanitation        39%             100%          facilities in 2019 will be the same as in 2011 and that all&#13;
the remaining urban households (14%) will have access to&#13;
Urban sanitation        73%             100%          SANIMAS.&#13;
1JMP (2012) Estimates for the Use of Improved Drinking Water Sources: Indonesia. Downloaded from wss.info.org.&#13;
IMinistry of Health (2013), Main Findings of Indonesia Basic Health Survey 2013.&#13;
51 Urban Sanitation Development Program (2012) National Sanitation Demand Assessment 2012, Draft report, November.&#13;
i The USDP report identifies the following facilities as not improved: (a) public facility, (b) public/private/shared facilities that do not have access to a&#13;
gooseneck and/or septic tank/pit latrine/sewer system, (c) no toilets.&#13;
58 JMP (2012) Estimates for the Use of Improved Sanitation: Indonesia. Downloaded from wss.info.org.&#13;
64                                                                          Water Supply and Sanitation in Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Table A2.3 Selected information on sanitation technologies&#13;
Distribution of facilities Projected distibution           Unit capital cost&#13;
facilities&#13;
Option                     (base year, %)f (2020               s              (per capita at 2012 prices)  Lifespan&#13;
(in years)&#13;
Rural         Urban         Rural         Urban         Rural        Urban&#13;
Piped into dwelling/yard              9%           26%           58%           90%            40           181           30&#13;
Public tap                            5%           9%            5%            5%             4            91            30&#13;
Tubewell/Borehole                    26%           28%            5%           0%             40           160            5&#13;
Protected well                       23%           32%           25%           5%             20           64             5&#13;
Protected spring                     28%           5%            4%            0%             24            3             5&#13;
Rainwater                             9%           0%            3%            0%             40           21             4&#13;
Total                                100%          100%          100%          100%           nc            nc            nc&#13;
'As a share of the population that have access to improved facilities. b Based on informed judgments of participants in a&#13;
stakeholder workshop in Jakarta on June 2013.&#13;
Unit capital costs in urban areas, which exclude the costs         conditions, reflects the under-utilization of the Community&#13;
of sewers, and the lifespan of private and shared facilities        Sanitation Centers.&#13;
were based on the informed judgment of the participants in&#13;
the SDA validation workshop in Jakarta on June 2013. Fur-           Sewerage Systems&#13;
thermore, it is also assumed that three households share a&#13;
facility; which translates to unit costs of shared facilities that  Sewerage systems in urban areas, which are also covered&#13;
are a third of private facilities. The cost of a private facility in  in the analysis, are treated separately from  on-site treat-&#13;
rural areas ($31 per person or $120 per facility) is based on       ment facilities. The assumptions used in the analysis are&#13;
the curriculum for the STBM entrepreneur training of 2013           as follows:&#13;
of the Ministry of Health). This cost is conservative relative&#13;
to the median price of permanent pit latrines (at $44 per           *   Access: In the base period (2011), it is assumed that&#13;
person or $173 per facility at 2010 prices) found by Giltner            1 %  of the urban population had access to sewerage&#13;
and Arianto6' for rural areas in Indonesia. It is also way be-          systems. While there seems to be no solid evidence&#13;
low the costs of a toilet with septic tank ($140 per person)            on access rates, studies by the World          Bank and&#13;
used in the Economics of Sanitation Initiative (ESI).60 The             AusAID62,USDP63 and       Eales et. al.64 suggest values&#13;
per capita cost of SANIMAS facilities, which includes treat-            close to this assumption. Access to sewerage systems&#13;
ment facilities, represents investments for Community Sani-             is assumed to increase to 6%    by the target year (2019).&#13;
tation Centers. The value represents median capital costs           *   Unit costs: The analysis assumes unit costs of $372&#13;
as calculated by Eales et al. (2013) using survey data.61 The per person (at 2012 prices). This represents the lower&#13;
per capita estimates here, which are much higher than es-               end of per capita CAPEX costs (US$ 350 per person&#13;
timated per capita costs of $152 per person under optimal               at 2010 prices) estimates presented in a study by the&#13;
59 Giltner, S and 1. Arianto (2011) Rural Latrine Costs in Indonesia, UNICEF, Plan Indonesia, ADB and WSP, World Bank.&#13;
60 Winara, A., G. Hutton, Gktarinda, E. Purnomo, K. Hadiwardoyo, 1. Merdykasari, T. Nurmadi, B. Bruinsma, D. Gunawan, D. Fadliah and M. Albrecht (2011)&#13;
Economic Assessment of Sanitation Interventions in Indonesia, Water and Sanitation Program, World Bank.&#13;
1 Eales K., R. Siregar, E. Febriani and 1. Blackett (2013) Review of Community Managed Decentralized Wastewater Treatment Systems in Indonesia, WsP,&#13;
February.&#13;
62 World Bank and AusAID (2013) East Asia Urban Sanitation Flagship Study: Indonesia ountry Study, Main Report, February.&#13;
63 Urban Sanitation Development Program (2012) National Sanitation Demand Assessment 2012, Draft report, November.&#13;
Eales K., R. Siregar, E. Febriani and 1. Blackett (2013) Review of Community Managed Decentralized Wastewater Treatment Systems in Indonesia, WSP,&#13;
February.&#13;
Service Delivery Assessment                                                                                                     65&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Table A2.4 Selected information on sanitation technologies&#13;
Distribution of facilities   Projected distribution of facilities       Unit capital cost&#13;
Option              (base year, %)                     (2020, %),                   (per capita at 2012 prices)      Lifespan&#13;
(in years)&#13;
Rural         Urban            Rural              Urban           Rural            Urban&#13;
Private facility       69%            86%             80%                86%              31                55               20&#13;
Shared facility        31%            13%             20%                 0%              10                18               20&#13;
SANIMAS                 na            1%               na                14%              na               294               20&#13;
Total                  100%          100%             100%               100%              nc               nc               no&#13;
' As a share of households with access to improved facilities.&#13;
Table A2.5 Public investments (million US$, annual average)&#13;
Sector                    Central government       Local government    Development partners   Total&#13;
Anticipated (2012-2014)&#13;
Rural water supply                                254                     480                     58                    791&#13;
Urban water supply                                265                     481                     25                    771&#13;
Rural sanitation                                   37                      2                      29                     69&#13;
Urban sanitation                                   48                     352                     28                    427&#13;
Total                                             604                    1,315                   140                    2,059&#13;
Recent (2009-2014)&#13;
Rural water supply                                111                     369                    43                     524&#13;
Urban water supply                                121                     370                     19                    510&#13;
Rural sanitation                                   23                      2                      22                     47&#13;
Urban sanitation                                   32                     271                     21                    324&#13;
Total                                             287                    1,013                   105                    1,405&#13;
a Anticipated investments of the government only represent expenditures for 2012 and 2013.&#13;
66                                                                                              Water Supply and Sanitation in Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿World Bank and AusAID,66. The value used in the   a clear distinction by location (rural or urban), annual dis-&#13;
analysis is much higher than the average capital costs  bursements for multi-year projects, actual expenditures&#13;
at optimal use of simplified sewerage systems ($136  and allocations, and nature (hardware and software). In all&#13;
per person at 2012 prices) and combined systems     these cases, the approach used in the analysis was to ask&#13;
($186 per person at 2012 prices) of SANIMAS projects.  the concerned stakeholders for their best guess of how the&#13;
However, it is closer to the median costs at actual use  data might be suitably disaggregated.&#13;
of simplified sewerage systems ($228 per person at&#13;
2012 prices) and combined systems ($251 per person  Given the available information, estimates of anticipated&#13;
at 2012 prices) of SANIMAS projects.67 The costs are  (2012-2014) and recent (2009-2011) CAPEX from the gov-&#13;
also higher than the unit costs of centralized sewer-  ement and development partners are shown in Table A2.5.&#13;
age and treatment systems ($130 per person at 2012  To ensure comparability with the investment requirements,&#13;
prices) reported in the ESI.68                      estimates of anticipated and recent CAPEX are limited to&#13;
Lifespan: Sewerage systems are assumed to have a    hardware expenditures only.&#13;
lifespan of 20 years. This value was taken from the&#13;
ESI.69                                              Given the available information, estimates of anticipated&#13;
(2012-201 4) and recent (2009-2011) CAPEX which come&#13;
Spending Plans                                          from government and development partners are shown in&#13;
Table A2.4. To ensure comparability with the investment re-&#13;
Collecting information on recent and anticipated invest-  quirements, estimates of anticipated and recent CAPEX are&#13;
ments and comparing the results to CAPEX requirements  limited to hardware expenditures only.&#13;
allows the costing tool to generate estimates of financing&#13;
gaps (or surpluses). As discussed in the text, investments  The planned spending of users is computed by specify-&#13;
for water and sanitation were obtained/derived from docu-  ing the proportion of investments that the authorities are&#13;
ments and websites of various stakeholders.             expecting households to contribute. Table A2.5 shows the&#13;
proportion of investments that households are expected to&#13;
The process of the collecting and compiling the information  contribute. In the absence of an expressed policy, all the&#13;
for capital expenditures was difficult and the subject to the  proportions used for urban areas were based on the in-&#13;
following issues and limitations. First, expenditures of the  formed judgment of the stakeholders who participated in&#13;
central government for 2014 are not yet available. Hence,  the June 2013 workshop in Jakarta. Users are expected to&#13;
anticipated expenditures of the government only represent  finance 15% of piped water into dwellings. The amount rep-&#13;
the average over two years (2012 and 2013). Second, there  resents household payments for the connection pipe and&#13;
is also some uncertainty surrounding the sub-sectoral data  meter. The only exception is the contribution of households&#13;
used in the analysis. In some instances, information was  in SANIMAS projects which is the midpoint of the estimated&#13;
only available for water supply and sanitation as a whole  contribution of the community that was estimated in the lit-&#13;
but not separately. Quite often, the data also do not make  eraturee.70&#13;
World Bank and AusAID (2013) Eaat Aaia Urban Sanitation Flagahip Study: Indoneal country Study, Main Report, February.&#13;
The value uaed in the analysia, which ia at 2012 pricea, accounta tor change in the general price level and exchange rate.&#13;
Ealea K., R. Siregar, E. Febriani and 1. Blackett (2013) Review of Community Managed Decentralized Wastewater Treatment Syatems in Indoneafa, WSP,&#13;
February.&#13;
68 Winara, A., G. Hutton, Oktarinda, E. Purnomo, K. Hadiwardoyo, 1. Merdykaaari, T Nurmadi, B. Bruinama, D. Gunawan, D. Fadilah and M. Albrecht (2011)&#13;
Economic Aaaeaament of Sanitation Interventions in Indoneaia, Water and Sanitation Program, World Bank.&#13;
69 Winara, A., G. Hutton, Oktarinda, E. Purnomo, K. Hadiwardoyo, 1. Merdykaaari, T Nurmadi, B. Bruinama, D. Gunawan, D. Fadilah and M. Albrecht (2011)&#13;
Economic Aaaeaament of Sanitation Interventiona in Indoneaoa, Water and Sanitation Program, World Bank.&#13;
76 Ealea K., R. Siregar, E. Febriani and 1. Blackett (2013) Review of Community Managed Decentralized Waatewater Treatment SyAtema in Indonelia, WSP,&#13;
February.&#13;
Service Delivery Assessment                                                                               67&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Table A2.6 Share of users in capital/development&#13;
costs, %&#13;
Option                       Rural       Urban&#13;
Water Supply&#13;
Public tap                                      0%           0%&#13;
Piped into dwelling/yard                        15%         15%&#13;
Tubewell/Borehole                               99%          n.a.&#13;
Improved dug well                               99%         99%&#13;
Protected spring                                99%          n.a.&#13;
Rainwater                                       99%          n.a.&#13;
Sanitation'&#13;
Private facility-gooseneck-with treatment       99%         99%&#13;
Shared facility-gooseneck-with treatment        99%         99%&#13;
SANIMAS                                          na          3%b&#13;
a Sewerage systems in urban areas are not included in the table. Such facilities are&#13;
expected to be initially financed entirely by government/donors/utilities and not by house-&#13;
holds. b Eales K, R. Siregar E Febriani and 1. Blackett (2013) Review of Community&#13;
Managed Decentralized Wastewater Treatment Systems in Indonesia, WSR February&#13;
68                                                                                                     Water Supply and Sanitation in Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Annex 3:&#13;
Comparison with Alternative Estimates&#13;
of Investment Requirements&#13;
This annex compares the estimates and key assumptions  people per year). Second, the analysis presented by the&#13;
of the SDA costing tool with two studies in the water and  WIRA study team does not appear to include replacement&#13;
sanitation sector in Indonesia. The first study, which pres-  costs. Removing this item from the estimates of the current&#13;
ents estimated investment requirements for the water sup-  analysis reduces the investment requirement to $1.8 billion&#13;
ply sector, provides an investment roadmap for Indonesia  per year, a figure that is not very different from the values&#13;
(WIRA study team, 2012). The second study, which was  presented by the WIRA study team.&#13;
conducted by USDP (2012), examines, among others, sani-&#13;
tation investments. Table A3.1 summarizes the key informa-  The USDP (2012) calculations assume universal access to&#13;
tion from the current analysis and the two studies.  improved sanitation by 2035. It estimates costs to be in&#13;
the order of Rp472 trillion (about $2.5 billion per year) from&#13;
The WIRA study team (2012) presents an estimated invest-  2015 to 2035. Estimates in the current analysis ($2.4 billion!&#13;
ment requirement of Rp64 trillion from 2011 to 2014. The  year) seem very close to the USDP estimate but this should&#13;
study asserts that this estimate will lead to 56 million people  be viewed with care. The reason is that the USDP invest-&#13;
(41 million with access to piped systems and 15 million with  ment requirements do not appear to include expenditures&#13;
access to non-piped systems) having access to improved  for replacing worn-out facilities. Removing these replace-&#13;
water supply services by 2014. It was derived by adding up  ment costs from the current analysis leads to investments&#13;
on the costs of various activities in rural and urban areas.71  requirements ($1.9 billion per year) that are noticeably lower&#13;
than USDP estimates. The resulting difference between the&#13;
Converted into US Dollar and expressed on an annual ba-  two estimates may then be explained in part by examining&#13;
sis, the costs presented by the WIRA study team ($1.7 bil-  the technology distribution at the target year. In the current&#13;
lion per year) are much lower than the estimates presented  analysis, it is assumed that only about 3.4% of the total&#13;
in the current analysis ($4.8 billion per year). There are two  population in 2019 (or 8.8 million people) will have access&#13;
factors that might explain this. First, the target adopted in  to offsite wastewater treatment facilities by the target year.&#13;
the current analysis suggests that about 29 million people  In contrast, the USDP analysis assumes that about 32% of&#13;
a year will gain access to improved water supply facilities.  the 2035 population (95.2 million people) will have access&#13;
This is more than twice as many as the estimate of the  to medium scale decentralized wastewater treatment facili-&#13;
WIRA study team (56 million in 4 years equals 13.3 million  ties.&#13;
coTsbe 2 of the WIR                                          t report provides the detaois.&#13;
Service Delivery Assessment                                                                    69&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Table A3.1 Comparison among three studies&#13;
Item                       Current SDA analysis              WIRA Study team (2012)             USDP analysis (2012)1&#13;
Sector of interest                 Water supply and sanitation       Water supply                       Sanitation&#13;
Period of analysis                 2011-2019                         2011-2014                          2015-2035&#13;
Access to improved facilities at target  Water supply: 100%           56 million people or about 68% of the  2035:100%&#13;
year                               Sanitation: 100%                   population by end 2014&#13;
Estimated costs (as presented in study)  Water supply: $4.75bn/ year ($1.79bn/  Rp65 trillion for the entire period  Rp472 trillion for the entire period&#13;
year excluding replacement costs)&#13;
Sanitation: $2.42bn/ year ($1.86bn/&#13;
year)&#13;
Estimated cost (converted to billion US$/  Water supply: $4.75bn/ year ($1.79bn/  $1.73bn/year          $2.5bn/year&#13;
year)y                             year excluding replacement costs)&#13;
Sanitation: $2.42bn/ year ($1.86bn/&#13;
year)&#13;
a Estimates from WIRA and USDP were converted to US$ using the 2012 exchange rate of Rp93861US$. b USDP estimates are not yet&#13;
final.&#13;
70                                                                                                 Water Supply and Sanitation in Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿References&#13;
Bappenas, BPS and United Nations Population Fund (2005)  Government of Indonesia (1974), Presidential Decree No.&#13;
Proyeksi Penduduk Indonesia (Indonesia Population Projec-  5/1974 on Household Water and Latrines (SAMIJAGA) Na-&#13;
tion), Jakarta.                                  tional Program.&#13;
Bappenas, "Perkembangan Kebijakan Penyediaan Air  Government of Indonesia (1997), Ministry of Health Decree&#13;
Minum" [Development of Water Provision Policy], can  No. 173/Men.Kes/Per/VIII/1977 on Surveillance of Water&#13;
be accessed at     http://perkim-Bappenas.info/index.  Polution Related to Health Issues.&#13;
php?prm_page_id=1 &amp;prm_id=21 &amp;prm_type_id=4&amp;prm_&#13;
parent_id=20&amp;prm_doc_cat_id=4&amp;prm_text=air_sejarah.  Government of Indonesia (1999), Law No. 22/1999 on Local&#13;
php&amp;prm_1bl=Sejarah.                              Autonomy.&#13;
Badan Pusat Statistik [Statistics Indonesia], Socioeconom-  Government of Indonesia (2004), Law No. 7/2004 on Water&#13;
ic Survey 2011.                                   Resources.&#13;
Badan Pusat Statistik [Statistics Indonesia] (2013) Perkem-  Government of Indonesia (2005), Government Decree No.&#13;
bangan Beberapa Indikator Utama Social-Ekonomi Indone-  16/2005 on Water Provision Systems. Government of In-&#13;
sia fTrends of Selected Socio-Economic Indicators of Indo-  donesia (2005), Indonesia Long-Term Development Plan&#13;
nesia], Jakarta, May.                             (2005-2025).&#13;
BPPSPAM (2011), Laporan Kinerja PDAM [PDAM Perfor-  Government of Indonesia (2006), Minister of Public Works&#13;
mance Report.                                    Regulation No.20/2006 on Water System Management.&#13;
Eales K., R. Siregar, E. Febriani and I. Blackett (2013) Re-  Government of Indonesia (2007), Government Decree No.&#13;
view of Community Managed Decentralized Wastewater  38/2007 on Demarcation of Roles Between National and&#13;
Treatment Systems in Indonesia, WSP, February..   Local Government.&#13;
http://www.isf.uts.edu.au/pdfs/ISF_VietnamWASH.pdf&#13;
Government of Indonesia (2008), Minister of Public Works&#13;
Giltner, S and I. Arianto (2011) Rural Latrine Costs in Indo-  Decree No. 16/2008 on Policy and National Strategy on&#13;
nesia, UNICEF, Plan Indonesia, ADB and WSP, World Bank,  Settlements; Sewerage Water System Development.&#13;
October&#13;
Government of Indonesia (2008), Minister of Health Decree&#13;
Government of Indonesia (1962), Law No 5/1962 on Water  No.832/2008 on National Community-Based Total Sanita-&#13;
Companies (PDAM).                                tion Program.&#13;
Service Delivery Assessment                                                                    71&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Government of Indonesia (2009), Law No. 18/2009 on  Government of Indonesia (2013), Minister of Home Affairs&#13;
Waste Management.                                   Decree No. 23/2013 on Guideline on Planning, Controlling&#13;
and Evaluating Local Development Workplan. Joint Moni-&#13;
Government of Indonesia (2009), Law No. 32/2009 on the  toring Programme (2013), Progress on Drinking Water and&#13;
Protection and Management of Environment.           Sanitation: 2013 Update. UNICEF and WHO.&#13;
Government of Indonesia (2009), Presidential Regulation  Joint Monitoring Programme (2009), Report on Intercountry&#13;
No.29/2009 on Guaranty and Interest Subsidy by National  Workshop on Water Supply and Sanitation, Indonesia.&#13;
Government to Accelerate Provision of Water Supply.&#13;
Joint Monitoring Programme (2012), Estimates for the Use&#13;
Government of Indonesia (2009), Minister of Finance De-  of Improved Drinking-Water Sources, Indonesia. Report&#13;
cree No. 229/2009 on Implementation Guideline on the  available at www.wssinfo.org.&#13;
Guaranty and Interest Subsidy by National Government to&#13;
Accelerate Provision of Water Supply.               Joint Monitoring Programme (2013), Progress on Drinking&#13;
Water and Sanitation: 2013 Update. UNICEF and WHO.&#13;
Government of Indonesia (2010), Indonesia Mid-Term De-&#13;
velopment Plan (2010-2014).                         Ministry of Finance (2012), The Indonesian Budget Overview&#13;
2011: Sekilas APBN, Dinamika Penganggaran di Indonesia.&#13;
Government of Indonesia (2010), Minister of Public Works&#13;
Decree No. 12/2010 on Water System Business Manage-  Ministry of Health (2010), PHLN Dalam Disparitas Pemban-&#13;
ment.                                               gunan Kesehatan.&#13;
Government of Indonesia (2010), Minister of Health Regula-  Ministry of Health (2011), Indonesia Basic Health Survey&#13;
tion No. 736/2010 on Guideline for Water Quality Surveil-  2010.&#13;
lance.&#13;
Ministry of Health (2013), Main Findings of Indonesia Basic&#13;
Government of Indonesia (2012), Minister of Public Works  Health Survey 2013.&#13;
Regulation No. 18/20n12 on the Guidance for the Manage-&#13;
ment of Water Provision System Development.         Ministry of Public Works and World Bank (2012), Indonesian&#13;
Water Investment Roadmap (2011-2014).&#13;
Government of Indonesia (2013), Ministry of Public Works&#13;
Decree No. 131PRT/M12013 on the National Policy and  Pokja AMPL (2010), Handbook of Water and Environmental&#13;
Strategy on Development of Water Provision System.  Health Policy.&#13;
Government of Indonesia (2013), Minister of Health Regula-  Pokja AMPL (2013), Pokja AMPL Decree No. Kep.38D.&#13;
tion No. 32/2013 on the Management of Work of the Sani-  V110712013 on the Establishment of Water and Sanitation&#13;
tarians.                                            Technical Working Group.&#13;
72                                                                     Water Supply and Sanitation in Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Qipra Galang Kualita (2012), Sanitation Personnel: Capacity  WSP (2006), Pathways to Progress, Tansitioning to Coun-&#13;
Development Strategy, Report was prepared for Bappenas,  try-Led Service Delivery Pathways to Meet Africa's Water&#13;
WSP, and AusAID.                                   Supply and Sanitation Targets. Report available at http:H&#13;
www.wsp.org/sites/wsp.org/files/publications/CSO-Syn-&#13;
United Nations (2012) World Statistics Pocketbook, Depart-  thesis-Report.pdf&#13;
ment of Economic and Social Affairs, UN, New York.&#13;
WSP (2013), Review of Community-Managed Decentralized&#13;
Urban Sanitation Development Program (2012) National  Wastewater Treatment Systems in Indonesia.&#13;
Sanitation Demand Assessment 2012, Draft report, Novem-&#13;
ber.                                               WSP (2013), Review of Fecal Sludge Management in 12 Cit-&#13;
ies, Draft Report.&#13;
Utomo, Nugrono Tri (2010), Water Investment, published at&#13;
www.ampl.or.id.&#13;
Winara, A., G. Hutton, Oktarinda, E. Purnomo, K Hadi-&#13;
wardoyo, (. Merdykasari, T2 Nurmadi, B. Bruinsma, D. Gu-&#13;
nawan, D. Fadilah and M. Albrecht (2011) Economic As-&#13;
sessment of Sanitation Interventions in Indonesia, Water&#13;
and Sanitation Program, World Bank.&#13;
WIRA Study team (2012), Indonesia Water Investment&#13;
Roadmap 2011-2014, World Bank, Ministry of Public Works&#13;
and Water Partnership Program, January.&#13;
World Bank and AusAID (2013), Urban Sanitation Review:&#13;
Indonesia Country StudyR&#13;
World Bank (2013) World Development Indicators, available&#13;
at http://data.worldbank.org/indicator/PA.NUS.FCRF&#13;
Service Delivery Assessment                                                                      73&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿74                                                                     Water Supply and Sanitation in Indonesia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿&#13;
ï»¿~WSp                                      WORLD BANKGROUP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="25259965">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2015/11/25259965/water-supply-sanitation-indonesia-turning-finance-service-future
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2015/11/25259965/water-supply-sanitation-indonesia-turning-finance-service-future</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2015/11/25259965/water-supply-sanitation-indonesia-turning-finance-service-future</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2015-11-10T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2015-11-11T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <docm_id>090224b0831a63fc</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b0831a63fc</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2015/11/10/090224b0831a63fc/1_0/Rendered/INDEX/Water0supply0a0rvice0for0the0future.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2015/11/10/090224b0831a63fc/1_0/Rendered/PDF/Water0supply0a0rvice0for0the0future.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2015-11-10T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2015-05-01T04:01:02Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Water supply and sanitation in Indonesia :
            turning finance into services for the future
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Water and sanitation service delivery
            assessments (SDA) are being carried out in eight countries
            in East Asia and the Pacific region under the guidance of
            the World Bank’s water and sanitation program and local
            partners. An SDA analysis has three main components: a
            review of past water and sanitation access, a costing model
            to assess the adequacy of future investments, and a
            scorecard that allows diagnosis of bottlenecks along the
            service delivery pathways. The SDA in Indonesia has been
            aligned with the preparation process of the third five-year
            mid-term development plan (RPJMN) 2015-19. This process also
            requires adjusting the targets for water supply and
            sanitation coverage by the end of the RPJMN period. This
            report aims to support the Indonesian government in their
            assessment and evaluation of the water and sanitation
            service delivery pathway, locate bottlenecks, and present
            the agreed priority actions to help address them.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Water supply and sanitation in Indonesia :
            turning finance into services for the future
        </docna>
        <display_title>Water supply and sanitation in
            Indonesia : turning finance into services for the future</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2015/05/25259965/water-supply-sanitation-indonesia-turning-finance-services-future</listing_relative_url>
        <topic>Sanitation m1326453 2000,Water Supply and Sanitation m1327240 1199,Water, Sanitation and Hygiene m1326125 1462,Sanitation and Wastewater m1327393 139,Water Supply m1326961 138</topic>
        <projn>4E-Service Delivery Assessments For Eap -- P131116</projn>
        <subtopic>Wastewater Treatment,Water Supply and Sanitation Governance
            and Institutions,Urban Water Supply and Sanitation,Water and Industry,Town Water Supply and Sanitation</subtopic>
        <docty>UNDP-Water &amp; Sanitation Program</docty>
        <teratopic>Water Supply and Sanitation,Water Resources</teratopic>
        <count>East Asia and Pacific</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Smets,Susanna</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>090224b0831a63fc_1_0</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <theme>Other public sector governance,Rural services and infrastructure</theme>
        <subsc>Water supply,Sanitation,Wastewater Treatment and Disposal,Wastewater Collection and Transportation</subsc>
        <admreg>East Asia and Pacific,East Asia and Pacific</admreg>
        <colti>Water and Sanitation Program</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Water Supply and Sanitation,Water Resources</historic_topic>
        <prdln>Economic and Sector Work</prdln>
        <topicv3>Sanitation m1326453 2000,Water Supply and Sanitation m1327240 1199,Water, Sanitation and Hygiene m1326125 1462,Sanitation and Wastewater m1327393 139,Water Supply m1326961 138</topicv3>
        <sectr>Water, sanitation and flood protection</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            water quality, access to sewerage systems,
            national water supply, local capacity, asset ownership,
            sanitation service, waste management, waste water treatment,
            water supply service, local budgets, water sector, community
            organizations, water utility, water systems, water supply,
            availability of water, investment planning, urban water,
            surface water, maintenance of water, capacity building, safe
            water, water schemes, asset management, local partners,
            water supply services, local private sector, rural water,
            water resources, sanitation service provision, water system,
            wastewater treatment, local water utilities, cost recovery,
            performance indicators, population growth, rural water
            supply, water treatment, water treatment systems, liters per
            second, sanitation water supply, water, sustainable water,
            sewerage systems, service provider, service provision, rural
            drinking water, service delivery, sustainable services,
            toilets, pit latrines, pit latrine, investment decisions,
            water supply systems, sewerage system, waste water,
            low-income households, provision of water supply, wastewater
            system, urban sanitation, sustainable water supply,
            provision of water, performance data, utilities, wastewater
            systems, rural sanitation, solid waste, systems, central
            government, open defecation, local accountability
            mechanisms, urban areas, water tariffs, urban area,
            sanitation sector, solid waste management, local
            accountability, local water, household connections,
            sanitation development, community management, public works,
            population growth rate, sanitation strategy, water
            utilities, wells, water sources, municipal development,
            water supply facilities, sanitation water, drinking water
            supply, sanitation services, drinking water, annual budgets,
            households, access to services, urban water supply, access
            to water supply, private sector operator, waste collection,
            provincial governments, investment requirements, water
            partnership, community groups, septic tank, water service,
            sanitation coverage, sanitation service delivery,
            sustainable service provision, water conservation, water
            source, maintenance requirements, service providers,
            sanitation facilities
        </keywd>
        <owner>Water - Water &amp; Sant. Prgrm-EAP (GWASE)</owner>
        <majtheme>Public sector governance,Rural development</majtheme>
        <repnb>100891</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Capacities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Staffing Needs Assessments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation and Sewerage</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wastewater Treatment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Infrastructure (Water and Wastewater)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Water and Small Town Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wastewater Collection and Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Strategic Planning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Basic Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>On-site Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Marketing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Expenditures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Investment Plan</ml:concept><ml:concept>Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deconcentration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delegation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Devolution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sub-National Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subnational Government and Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation and Wastewater</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water, Sanitation and Hygiene</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sewerage</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Strategic Policy Planning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Local Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Investment Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Administrative Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Eastern Asia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>