<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Privatesector     P   U   B   L   I C       P  O   L  I  C   Y     F O  R       T  H   E&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The World Bank                                                                                          October 1995&#13;
&#13;
              Lessons from Power Sector Reform&#13;
Note No. 61&#13;
&#13;
              in England and Wales&#13;
&#13;
Robert Bacon   The 1990 power reforms in England and Wales          A framework for retail competition&#13;
               were designed to permit the introduction of com-     and regulation&#13;
               petition at both the retail and the wholesale level.&#13;
               Generation was both vertically separated from        The reforms sought to foster retail competition&#13;
               transmission and horizontally separated. The         by allowing an increasing number of consumers&#13;
               sector was almost completely privatized--only        to shop around for the best service. To start this,&#13;
               the nuclear capacity was left in public hands--      final consumers were divided into three classes:&#13;
               and regulation was applied both to promote            Small. Consumers with peak demand of less&#13;
               competition and to ensure that the remaining           than 1 megawatt (MW) are "franchise cus-&#13;
               monopolies did not exploit their advantage.            tomers" who must buy from their local REC.&#13;
                                                                      This limit was reduced to 100 kilowatts (kW)&#13;
               The new industry structure emerged with three          in 1994 and is scheduled to be abolished in&#13;
               generating companies: National Power (52 per-          1998. RECs have an obligation to serve this&#13;
               cent of capacity at that time) and PowerGen (33        group of consumers at regulated prices.&#13;
               percent), which were privatized, with 60 per-         Medium. Consumers with peak demand of 1&#13;
               cent of their shares sold initially, and Nuclear       to 10 MW have a "right to tariff," but they can&#13;
               Electric (15 percent), which was left under pub-       also purchase at unregulated prices from the&#13;
               lic ownership. National Power's share of capac-        "second-tier" suppliers--firms with a license&#13;
               ity gave it significant market power. The national     to sell (mainly the other RECs and the genera-&#13;
               grid company--after separation from the gener-         tors). Of the approximately 4,000 customers in&#13;
               ating companies--was transferred to joint own-         this class (30 percent of total demand), 40 per-&#13;
               ership by the twelve privatized regional               cent were using a second-tier supplier by 1993.&#13;
               distribution companies. (The grid company re-         Large. Consumers with demand exceeding&#13;
               tains control of dispatch.) Each of the twelve         10 MW have no right to tariff. Instead, they&#13;
               regional distribution companies (RECs) has two         have to negotiate their prices with the sup-&#13;
               separate functions--distribution (through low-         plier they choose.&#13;
               voltage wires or, more simply, grid to door) and&#13;
               retail supply (the sale of electricity to final cus- This market structure has a mix of regulated and&#13;
               tomers)--and these functions must be accounted       unregulated prices, but even the unregulated&#13;
               for separately. Access to the distribution opera-    prices are subject to oversight by the regulator in&#13;
               tion of the RECs is regulated so that any seller     his capacity as promoter of competition. The&#13;
               of electricity has the right to "use" the associ-    prices for supply to final consumers are controlled&#13;
               ated distribution network when selling to a fi-      by the price cap formula--RPI ­ X + Y, where&#13;
               nal customer. Until March 1995, the government       RPI is the rate of inflation, X is the estimated&#13;
               retained a "golden share" in each REC, giving it     potential productivity gain, and Y is a passthrough&#13;
               the power to block any takeover or merger.           factor made up of transmission charges, distribu-&#13;
                                                                    tion charges, electricity purchase costs, and a fossil&#13;
               Five years have now elapsed since the reforms        fuel levy that subsidizes nuclear power. The fac-&#13;
               began--and this Note discusses some of the           tors covered by passthrough account for about&#13;
               lessons starting to emerge.                          95 percent of the total costs of supply.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
               Industry and Energy Department          Vice Presidency for Finance and Private Sector Development&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Lessons from Power Sector Reform in England and Wales&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The distribution charges account for just over 20    The regulator quickly reviewed pool prices and&#13;
percent of the final price. The initial distribution concluded that the generators could raise prices&#13;
price caps ranged from RPI + 0 to RPI + 2.5 among    above marginal costs in at least two ways. First,&#13;
the RECs, implying that the prices at vesting were   they could declare some plant unavailable and&#13;
seen as inadequate to cover future costs. Trans-     thus affect the LOLP by reducing supply relative&#13;
mission charges, which account for about 4 per-      to demand. Later, after the dispatching schedule&#13;
cent of final prices, are regulated through a price  had been determined, they might even declare&#13;
cap for which X was initially set at zero.           this plant available. Because of the huge differ-&#13;
                                                     ence between the typical SMP and the VOLL, a&#13;
Wholesale markets--the power pool                    small increase in the LOLP has a large effect on&#13;
                                                     the pool price. Second, the generators could&#13;
The most innovative reform was to the pricing        manipulate the uplift factor. Because of trans-&#13;
of power sold by the generators to the RECs or       mission constraints, certain power stations were&#13;
to large final users. The generators sell all power  optimal to dispatch even when their price was&#13;
to a pool. In this power pool (operated by the       well above that of the marginal station bid in to&#13;
national grid company), generators bid to sup-       meet the demand. The generators soon learned&#13;
ply various units in half-hour slots during the      to set the bids for these stations well above costs.&#13;
next twenty-four hours. Dispatch is carried out&#13;
by choosing plants in merit order of these bids,     To prevent the withdrawal of plant that was&#13;
up to the point at which demand is satisfied.        actually available, the regulator appointed an in-&#13;
                                                     dependent assessor. The price spikes disap-&#13;
The price the generators receive has three com-      peared, but big industrial users continued to&#13;
ponents: the system marginal price (SMP), the        complain about the general level of prices. Rather&#13;
highest price bid by dispatched plants; the ca-      than refer the generators to the Monopolies Com-&#13;
pacity payment, the loss-of-load probability         mission, whose decision could have involved re-&#13;
(LOLP) times the value of lost load (VOLL) less      structuring--a decision that would have been&#13;
the SMP; and the uplift, an adjustment to cover      seen as betraying the shareholders--the regula-&#13;
the costs imposed by transmission constraints,       tor in 1994 accepted undertakings by the gen-&#13;
standby capacity, and the like. The pool attempts    erators. The generators specified that they would&#13;
to mimic an unregulated market, but in fact it       bid into the pool so that the pool price would&#13;
includes a strong degree of regulation (especially   average about 2.5 pence per kWh for the next&#13;
in the setting of the VOLL). To protect themselves   two years, and that they would dispose of an-&#13;
against the potential variability of pool prices,    other 6 gigawatts (GW) of capacity within two&#13;
generators and suppliers have entered into a se-     years. The pricing agreement amounted to a 7&#13;
ries of short-term "contracts for differences" that  percent cut in real prices over the previous year.&#13;
allow both parties to manage the risks caused by     This capping of pool prices cannot be a perma-&#13;
uncertainty about pool prices.                       nent solution for a market designed to be com-&#13;
                                                     petitive, however. The regulator probably expects&#13;
Volatile pool prices                                 that new investment will help to make the mar-&#13;
                                                     ket more competitive over time.&#13;
The new structure of the generation market im-&#13;
mediately attracted attention. Pool prices fluc-     RECs' profits and shifting structures&#13;
tuated sharply and, paradoxically, occasionally&#13;
rose during times of low demand. For example,        In the past two years, the RECs have come un-&#13;
while the yearly average was about 2 pence per       der public attack because of their continuing&#13;
kilowatt-hour (kWh), the price for three half-       high profits and the large salary increases&#13;
hour slots reached 16 pence per kWh on a sunny       (boosted by share options) for top executives&#13;
September afternoon in 1991 and spiked to 33         (table 1). (Profits in generation, though substan-&#13;
pence per kWh during December.                       tial, have not been attacked as excessive, and&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                             TABLE 1 PRETAX PROFITS AND REVENUE OF THE POWER SYSTEM&#13;
&#13;
                                                                        IN ENGLAND AND WALES, 1992/93&#13;
&#13;
                                                                        (millions of pounds)&#13;
&#13;
supply has been the least profitable part of the&#13;
                                                             Company                     Pretax profits                        Revenue&#13;
electricity business.) The RECs have been only&#13;
lightly regulated, with the result that growth in            National Power                      580                              4,348&#13;
their profits has averaged up to 30 percent a&#13;
                                                             PowerGen                            425                              3,188&#13;
year. Following the first scheduled review of&#13;
the price cap for distribution in 1994, the RECs             Nuclear Electric                    661                              1,400&#13;
&#13;
had to reduce their charges by 11 to 17 percent              GridCo                              350                              1,396&#13;
&#13;
in 1995­96, and thereafter an RPI ­ 2 price cap              RECs&#13;
was to be used until 1999­2000.                               Distribution                    1,042                               3,751&#13;
&#13;
                                                              Supply                              --a                           13,921&#13;
The rapid growth in the profits of RECs made&#13;
them attractive targets for takeover. In Decem-              a. The companies had small profits or losses.&#13;
&#13;
ber 1994, anticipating the expiration of the gov-            Source: Mark Armstrong, Simon Cowan, and John Vickers, Regulatory Reform:&#13;
&#13;
ernment's golden shares preventing takeovers,                Economic Analysis and British Experience (Cambridge, MIT Press, 1994).&#13;
&#13;
Trafalgar House bid £1.2 billion for Northern&#13;
Electric (about four times its selling price at priva- By 1995, the RECs were considering selling off&#13;
tization), or £10.81 a share. Northern Electric        the grid, suggesting that there was no great&#13;
responded by offering its shareholders a pack-         advantage in having left this vertical link at the&#13;
age worth £5.07 a share to reject the bid, pro-        time of privatization (generators are not allowed&#13;
voking more public criticism. The temperature          to own shares in it, though, to prevent anti-&#13;
rose further when, in early 1995, the govern-          competitive links). Because the market value&#13;
ment sold its remaining 40 percent of shares in        of the grid (£5 billion) appears to be consider-&#13;
the two privatized generators. On the day after        ably higher than that used at flotation (the RECs&#13;
the sale, the regulator announced that the dis-        were sold for only £8 billion), the possibility&#13;
tribution review had not been completed and            of returning to final consumers part of any prof-&#13;
that he would be considering tightening the price      its from its sale has been raised.&#13;
caps. This announcement created a political&#13;
storm, with the government being accused of            An assessment&#13;
insider dealing. And although new price caps&#13;
were soon announced that further cut real prices       The ultimate aims of the U.K. reforms were to&#13;
over the next few years, takeover activity has         remove the sector from government funding and&#13;
continued, suggesting that investors still expect      to reduce prices for consumers through the in-&#13;
a good return from what is a low-risk business.        creased efficiency of private sector operation&#13;
Clearly, the government could have held out            and the pressure of competition. Broadly speak-&#13;
for a higher price at the time of privatization.       ing, the first objective has been accomplished,&#13;
                                                       but the second objective has yet to be convinc-&#13;
The RECs have made substantial new investments         ingly achieved. Many of the difficulties in achiev-&#13;
in generation--in a "dash for gas"--despite the        ing this second objective are related to the speed&#13;
overcapacity at the time of privatization. By          with which the restructuring and privatization&#13;
1993, they had interests in 5.4 GW of plant            had to take place. The political pressures at the&#13;
(mainly combined-cycle gas turbines) under             time allowed a relatively short "window of op-&#13;
construction or in operation. Diversifying sup-        portunity," but the desire to privatize the whole&#13;
ply has given them some protection from the            system and to introduce as much competition&#13;
market power of the generators. But because            as possible demanded the creation of entirely&#13;
the price cap formula allows them to pass              new market forms for the industry. So some of&#13;
through all costs of purchasing electricity, they      the reforms are still under way. Shifting to an&#13;
have a weak incentive to seek the cheapest             open power pool with continuous bidding and&#13;
source of supply, despite their obligation (to         introducing retail competition in the second-tier&#13;
the regulator) to do so.                               market, for example, are both highly complex&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                          Lessons from Power Sector Reform in England and Wales&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                          reforms that take time to achieve, and the op-     industry by making it harder for the regulator to&#13;
                          eration of these markets is still evolving.        identify the true costs of distribution. But a gov-&#13;
                                                                             ernment cannot adopt a market-based system&#13;
                          The drop in the franchise limit to 100 kW ini-     and then expect the structure to be set in stone.&#13;
                          tially created severe accounting problems be-&#13;
                          cause many potential customers lacked the          The use of RPI ­ X price caps in the U.K. system&#13;
                          special meters required to trace their usage       has already yielded substantial experience. Price&#13;
                          through the day. Introducing retail competi-       cap regulation was chosen to avoid the lack of&#13;
                          tion in this segment of the market appears dif-    incentive to reduce costs in a cost-plus (rate-of-&#13;
                          ficult if, as in England and Wales, the regulator  return) regulation formula, and the regulatory&#13;
                          is not given the responsibility and power to       process was designed to give the companies an&#13;
                          oversee expansion of this market. Metering is      assured period between regulatory reviews in&#13;
                          expensive, and the cost may not be worth it        which to look for cost savings greater than the&#13;
                          below 75 kW. Despite the vertical integration      X factors. But the regulator has been forced to&#13;
                          between transmission and distribution and be-      intervene between scheduled reviews and to in-&#13;
                          tween distribution and supply, there is no evi-    vestigate the actual and potential returns to capi-&#13;
                          dence that distributors hindered second-tier       tal for the companies, moving the system toward&#13;
                          access to consumers in their region. This sug-     the criteria used in U.S. rate-of-return regula-&#13;
                          gests that here the regulatory threat was effec-   tion. The initial failure to set a reasonable price&#13;
                          tive--though possibly because the RECs did         cap for the distributors has proved expensive&#13;
                          not wish to draw attention to their profits.       for the consumer. Moreover, subsequent ex-&#13;
                                                                             perience with setting price caps shows how&#13;
                          As it turns out, new investment in generation      difficult it is to correctly assess the level of pro-&#13;
                          has been slow to have an effect on competi-        ductivity that can be obtained in the distribu-&#13;
                          tion, and the dominant generators still have       tion sector. Prices have fallen relative to costs,&#13;
This series is published  considerable market power. Partitioning the        but few of the efficiency gains have been&#13;
to share ideas and invite sector into smaller units and reducing the mar-    passed on to consumers. Only time will tell&#13;
discussion. It covers&#13;
                          ket share of the largest generator at the time of  whether this problem is transitory or reflects a&#13;
financial and private&#13;
sector development as     privatization would have helped create com-        basic weakness. Given the tendency toward&#13;
well as industry and      petition faster. Changing the structure of the     large profits in the system, a form of regula-&#13;
energy. The views&#13;
                          industry or the general rules of the game after    tion that provides a formula for sharing exces-&#13;
expressed are those of&#13;
the authors and are not   privatization is extremely difficult politically,  sive profits with consumers may well emerge.&#13;
intended to represent     because purchasers accept the terms of the&#13;
an official statement of&#13;
                          privatization on the basis of the status at the    The regulator has come under enormous pres-&#13;
Bank policy or strategy.&#13;
                          time of privatization. Shareholders inevitably     sure. He has been made a scapegoat for sub-&#13;
Comments are welcome.     would claim that they had been cheated.            optimal decisions made by the government at&#13;
Please call the FPD&#13;
                                                                             the time of privatization, a predicament illus-&#13;
Note line to leave a&#13;
message (202-458-1111)    A striking trend in the system is the movement     trating the need for a strong and independent&#13;
or contact Suzanne        toward reintegration. Market forces are pushing    regulatory commission. The regulatory reviews&#13;
Smith, editor, Room&#13;
                          distributors to consider merging with one an-      show the difficulty of the regulator's task. Each&#13;
G8105, The World Bank,&#13;
1818 H Street, NW,        other, to ward off threats of takeover from out-   REC assembled its own regulatory team and&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433,   side the industry by taking advantage of           produced massive documentation to support&#13;
or Internet address&#13;
                          economies of scale. Vertical reintegration is also their own assessments of the desirable price&#13;
ssmith7@worldbank.org.&#13;
                          occurring as distributors purchase their own       caps. The relatively small size of the regulator's&#13;
9Printed on recycled      generating capacity. In addition, one of the gen-  office and its broad responsibilities clearly&#13;
paper.&#13;
                          erators is bidding to acquire a REC. The take-     worked to the advantage of the companies.&#13;
                          over movement, inevitable in mature stock&#13;
                          markets when large profits are visible, will sub-  Robert Bacon, Oxford University, Oxford, England&#13;
                          stantially complicate the formal regulation of the (email: econ46@vax.ox.ac.uk)&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="2529229">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1995/10/2529229/lessons-power-sector-reform-england-wales
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <virt_coll>Knowledge Notes</virt_coll>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1995/10/2529229/lessons-power-sector-reform-england-wales</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1995/10/2529229/lessons-power-sector-reform-england-wales</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/10/01/000090341_20031001094507/Rendered/INDEX/268290VP0note0no10610bacon.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/10/01/000090341_20031001094507/Rendered/PDF/268290VP0note0no10610bacon.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>1995-10-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2003-10-01T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Lessons from power sector reform in England
            and Wales
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The 1990 power reforms in England and
            Wales were designed to permit the introduction of
            competition at both the retail and the wholesale level.
            Generation was both vertically separated from transmission
            and horizontally separated. The sector was almost completely
            privatized-only the nuclear capacity was left in public
            hands-and regulation was applied both to promote competition
            and to ensure that the remaining monopolies did not exploit
            their advantage. The new industry structure emerged with
            three generating companies: National Power (52 percent of
            capacity at that time) and PowerGen (33 percent), which were
            privatized, with 60 percent of their shares sold initially,
            and Nuclear Electric (15 percent), which was left under
            public ownership. National Power's share of capacity
            gave it significant market power. The national grid
            company-after separation from the generating companies-was
            transferred to joint ownership by the twelve privatized
            regional distribution companies. (The grid company retains
            control of dispatch.) Each of the twelve regional
            distribution companies (RECs) has two separate
            functions-distribution (through low voltage wires or, more
            simply, grid to door) and retail supply (the sale of
            electricity to final customers) -and these functions must be
            accounted for separately. Access to the distribution
            operation of the RECs is regulated so that any seller of
            electricity has the right to "use" the associated
            distribution network when selling to a final customer. Until
            March 1995, the government retained a "golden
            share" in each REC, giving it the power to block any
            takeover or merger.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Lessons from power sector reform in England
            and Wales
        </docna>
        <display_title>Lessons from power sector reform
            in England and Wales</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1995/10/2529229/lessons-power-sector-reform-england-wales</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Viewpoint</docty>
        <subtopic>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Markets and Market Access,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Access to Markets,Consumption</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Environment,International Economics and Trade,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</teratopic>
        <count>Europe</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Robert Bacon</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000090341_20031001094507</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Power</subsc>
        <admreg>Europe and Central Asia,Europe and Central Asia</admreg>
        <colti>Public policy for the private sector ; Note
            no. 61</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Environment,International Economics and Trade,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</historic_topic>
        <sectr>Energy and mining</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Power sector reform; Competition policy;
            Retail marketing; Wholesale marketing, Privatization;
            Monopolies; Nuclear energy; Ownership; Grids; Consumer
            demand; Generators; Tariff cuts
            bidding,consumers,cost savings,Economic
            Analysis,economies of scale,inflation,marginal costs,Market
            forces,market power,market structure,market
            value,monopolies,price
            caps,productivity,purchasing,retail,suppliers,takeover,total costs,users
        </keywd>
        <owner>Off of VP, FPD - WB (FPDVP)</owner>
        <repnb>26829</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics and Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Denationalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deregulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Destatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Divestiture of Ownership</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Market Access</ml:concept><ml:concept>Checks on Executive Power</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen User Satisfaction Survey</ml:concept><ml:concept>Independent Commissions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ombudsmen</ml:concept><ml:concept>Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Parliament</ml:concept><ml:concept>Procurement Complaints Review Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supreme Audit Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fuels</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Privatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inflation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Accountability Mechanisms</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Central Asia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>