<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>                                                 100933&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  Bulgaria&#13;
Judicial Performance, Caseload and Expenditure Review&#13;
                      (2008-2014)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                 November 2015&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Global Governance Practice&#13;
&#13;
Europe and Central Asia Region&#13;
&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       1&#13;
&amp;#12;                       CURRENCY EQUIVALENTS&#13;
                (Exchange Rate Effective August 31, 2015)&#13;
&#13;
                  Currency Unit = Bulgarian Leva (BGN)&#13;
                             0.57 = 1 US$&#13;
&#13;
                                 FISCAL YEAR&#13;
                           January 1 â&#128;&#147; December 31&#13;
&#13;
                    ABBREVIATIONS AND ACRONYMS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
BGN                  Bulgarian Leva&#13;
&#13;
CEPEJ                European Commission on Efficiency of Justice&#13;
&#13;
CoE                  Council of Europe&#13;
&#13;
CoM                  Council of Ministers&#13;
&#13;
CR                   Clearance Rate&#13;
&#13;
DP                   Disposition Time&#13;
&#13;
EU                   European Union&#13;
&#13;
GDP                  Gross Domestic Product&#13;
&#13;
JSA                  Judicial Systems Act&#13;
&#13;
MOF                  Ministry of Finance&#13;
&#13;
MOJ                  Ministry of Justice&#13;
&#13;
NAO                  National Audit Office&#13;
&#13;
NIS                  National Investigative Service&#13;
&#13;
PAC                  Proposal and Attestation Committee&#13;
&#13;
PEIR                 Public Expenditure and Institutional Review&#13;
&#13;
SJC                  Supreme Judicial Council&#13;
&#13;
        Vice President                      Cyril E. Muller&#13;
        Country Director                    Mamta Murthy&#13;
        Country Manager                     Antony Thomson&#13;
        Practice Manager                    Adrian Fozzard&#13;
        Primary Author                      Arun Arya&#13;
        Task Team Leader                    David Bernstein&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                      2&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                 Table of Contents&#13;
&#13;
Table of Contents...................................................................................................................................... 3&#13;
&#13;
Executive Summary................................................................................................................................... 6&#13;
&#13;
Summary of Recommendations ................................................................................................................ 9&#13;
&#13;
Preface ................................................................................................................................................... 10&#13;
&#13;
I.       Legal Framework for Administration of Justice ................................................................................ 11&#13;
&#13;
II.      Justice Sector Reform Strategy ........................................................................................................ 14&#13;
&#13;
III.         Performance of Judiciary in Terms of Case Disposition................................................................. 16&#13;
&#13;
      Table 2: Clearance Rate and Disposition Time of Bulgarian Courts between 2008 and 2014 ................ 18&#13;
&#13;
      Table 3: Comparison of Clearance Rate and Disposition Time among CoE States in 2012 ..................... 19&#13;
&#13;
IV.          Judicial Caseload in Bulgaria ........................................................................................................ 21&#13;
&#13;
      Table 5: Number of Judges and Caseloads per Type of Court in 2014................................................... 21&#13;
&#13;
      Table 6: District Courts with consistent low caseloads since 2010........................................................ 24&#13;
&#13;
      Table 7: Regional Courts with consistent low caseload between 2010 and 2014 .................................. 25&#13;
&#13;
V.       Benchmarking of Number of Judges ................................................................................................ 25&#13;
&#13;
      Table 8: Comparison of Number of Professional Judges per 100,000 ................................................... 26&#13;
&#13;
      in Bulgaria and other CoE States.......................................................................................................... 26&#13;
&#13;
      Table 9: Number of Incoming Cases between 2008 and 2014 .............................................................. 27&#13;
&#13;
      Table 10: Number of Judicial Positions in Different Courts between 2008 and 2014 ............................ 27&#13;
&#13;
      Table 11: Comparative Ratio of Courts to Population .......................................................................... 28&#13;
&#13;
      by Country .......................................................................................................................................... 28&#13;
&#13;
VI.          Investigation Magistrates ............................................................................................................ 30&#13;
&#13;
VII.         Secondment Program .................................................................................................................. 30&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                               3&#13;
&amp;#12;     Table 12: Number of Judges Seconded by Institution in 2015 .............................................................. 31&#13;
&#13;
     Table 13: Number of Cases Completed and Pending by Court Type ..................................................... 31&#13;
&#13;
     Table 14: Length of Secondment Service ............................................................................................. 32&#13;
&#13;
VIII.      Support Staff in Judiciary ............................................................................................................. 32&#13;
&#13;
     Table 15: Ratio of Support Staff to Judges ........................................................................................... 32&#13;
&#13;
     Table 16: Comparative Ratio of Staff to Judges .................................................................................... 33&#13;
&#13;
IX.        Expenditure Framework for the Judiciary Sector .......................................................................... 34&#13;
&#13;
     Table 17: Judicial Budget Request Compared to State Budget Act and Actual Expenditures ................. 35&#13;
&#13;
     (Amount in 1000 BGN) ........................................................................................................................ 35&#13;
&#13;
X.      Trends in Judiciary Budget and Expenditure .................................................................................... 35&#13;
&#13;
     Table 18: Judicial State Budget Act Funding and Institutional Expenditure ........................................... 36&#13;
&#13;
     Figure 1: Budget and Expenditure of the Judiciary (2007-2014) ........................................................... 36&#13;
&#13;
     Table 19: Annual Budget allocations to Judicial Systems: Comparison with CoE states......................... 37&#13;
&#13;
     Table 19b: Annual Budget allocation to Judicial Systems: Comparison to CoE States ........................... 37&#13;
&#13;
XI.        Funding Operations of the Judiciary............................................................................................. 38&#13;
&#13;
     Table 20: Funding Judicial Operations: Own Resources and Government Subsidy ................................ 38&#13;
&#13;
XII.       Judicial Budget and Expenditure by Administrative Classifications: .............................................. 39&#13;
&#13;
     Table 21: Composition of Judiciary Budget by Administrative Classifications ....................................... 39&#13;
&#13;
     Figure 2: Composition of 2014 Judicial Budget by Administrative Classifications .................................. 41&#13;
&#13;
     Figure 3: Budget and Expenditure by Administrative Classification ...................................................... 42&#13;
&#13;
     Table 22: Budget Execution % by Administrative Classifications........................................................... 42&#13;
&#13;
XIII.      Judicial Budget and Expenditure by Economic Classifications ....................................................... 43&#13;
&#13;
     Table 23: Composition of Judicial Budget by Economic Classification ................................................... 43&#13;
&#13;
     Figure 4: Composition of Judiciary Budget 2014 by Economic Classifications ....................................... 44&#13;
&#13;
     Table 24: Capital Budget Requests and Approvals by Parliament ......................................................... 45&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                          4&#13;
&amp;#12;   Table 25: Composition of Judicial Expenditure by Economic Classification ........................................... 45&#13;
&#13;
   Figure 5: Composition Judicial Expenditure in 2014 by Economic Classifications .................................. 46&#13;
&#13;
   Table 26: Budget Execution by Economic Classification (2008-2014).................................................... 47&#13;
&#13;
   Table 27: Budget and Expenditure for Acquisition and Renovation of Judicial Facilities ....................... 48&#13;
&#13;
Conclusions and Recommendations ........................................................................................................ 49&#13;
&#13;
ANNEX 1: Case Disposal and Workload between 2008 and 2014 ............................................................. 53&#13;
&#13;
ANNEX 2: Court-Wise Actual Workloads between 2008 and 2014 ........................................................... 60&#13;
&#13;
ANNEX 3: Benchmarking of Per Capita State Budget and % of GDP with CoE Member States .................. 83&#13;
&#13;
ANNEX 4: Benchmarking of Salaries of Judiciary with other COE Member States ..................................... 86&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                    5&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                  Executive Summary&#13;
&#13;
         The World Bank published a Public Expenditure and Institutional Review (PEIR) of the Bulgarian&#13;
justice sector entitled â&#128;&#156;Resourcing the Judiciary for Performance and Accountability: A Judici al Public&#13;
Expenditure and Institutional Reviewâ&#128;&#157; in 2008. The objective of the present study is to conduct an&#13;
assessment of the spending and institutional changes in Bulgariaâ&#128;&#153;s judiciary from 2008 onwards. The&#13;
current report examines the principal trends in resourcing Bulgariaâ&#128;&#153;s judiciary since 2008, while comparing&#13;
the expenditure and judicial performance with those of other European countries. The report provides a&#13;
set of conclusion and recommendations for improving the efficiency and effectiveness of Bulgariaâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
judiciary and the judicial budget1 process.&#13;
&#13;
         As per the latest published report on "European judicial systems â&#128;&#147; Edition 2014 (2012 data):&#13;
efficiency and quality of justiceâ&#128;&#157;, Bulgariaâ&#128;&#153;s annual budget per inhabitant for the entire judicial system was&#13;
29.5 euros, which was less than the average of 60.6 euros for the CoE states. However, when compared&#13;
with the per capita GDP, Bulgariaâ&#128;&#153;s annual budget for its judicial system was 0.54 % of the per capita GDP,&#13;
which was higher than the average of 0.33 % for the CoE states. Despite high judicial expenditure as a&#13;
percentage of per capita GDP, Bulgariaâ&#128;&#153;s judiciary has been under-funded in relation to its budget requests&#13;
and the statutory required minimum salaries for judges. Current expenditures account for 98 % of&#13;
Bulgariaâ&#128;&#153;s judicial budget, the majority of which is for salaries and other remuneration. However, current&#13;
budget levels are insufficient to pay the minimum salary for magistrates prescribed under law. The capital&#13;
budget is also not adequate to meet judicial needs as only about 10-15 % of the judiciaryâ&#128;&#153;s capital budget&#13;
requests are approved by the Parliament. There is scope for the judiciary to increase its own revenues by&#13;
reforming and raising court filing fees. The Supreme Judicial Council (SJC) has prepared a proposed revision&#13;
of the tariff and submitted it to the Council of Ministers.&#13;
&#13;
         The performance of judiciary in terms of case disposition has been quite satisfactory. The clearance&#13;
rate in Bulgarian courts has been close to 100 % in all of the past 7 years and the disposition time has been&#13;
less than 75 days for all years except 2008, both of which can be considered good performance in&#13;
comparison to other European countries.&#13;
&#13;
         At the same time, the report reveals that there is scope for Bulgariaâ&#128;&#153;s judiciary to reorganize itself&#13;
to improve its efficiency and effectiveness based on an assessment of judicial workloads. There are 2,225&#13;
approved judge positions, against which, 1,811 judges are working. The average actual caseload per judge&#13;
per month at the national level is about 30. There are several courts with caseloads well below this national&#13;
average. As a result, there is scope to redeploy surplus or underworked judges to other courts with high&#13;
caseloads. At the national level, as an initial step in a broader judicial restructuring, the SJC could consider&#13;
reducing the number of approved judge positions to the number of currently filled positions. The ratio of&#13;
judicial staff to inhabitants in Bulgaria is 2.7, which is one of the highest in Eastern European countries.&#13;
The SJC could consider reducing this ratio at the national level (thereby contributing to cost-savings) and&#13;
uniformly distributing the revised national ratio across courts (thereby improving efficiency).&#13;
&#13;
        There are presently 13 district courts where the caseload per judge is less than 10 cases per month&#13;
and 6 regional courts where the caseload is 20 or fewer cases per judge per month, both of which, are well&#13;
below the average for each type of case. It is likely that the number of judges in these courts can be&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
1&#13;
    Throughout this paper the term â&#128;&#156;judicial budgetâ&#128;&#157; will be used to refer to the budget of the Bulgarian judicial system.&#13;
&#13;
                                                             6&#13;
&amp;#12;reduced with some judges freed to be redeployed to other courts where there are higher caseloads.&#13;
Similarly, there are 147 judges working in 6 appellate courts, which have an average caseload of only 8&#13;
cases per month. The SJC could consider consolidating the 6 appellate courts into 2 or 3 appellate courts&#13;
and redeploy surplus judges elsewhere. In 4 military courts, there are 19 judges working with an average&#13;
caseload of only 2 cases per judge per month. The SJC could consider consolidating 4 military courts into a&#13;
single military court to handle the existing caseload and redeploy the surplus judges. Among the&#13;
investigation magistrates, the average annual caseload at the National Investigative Service was estimated&#13;
to be 12 cases in 2013, of which only 6 cases were completed and just 0.6 cases led to court indictments.&#13;
The Supreme Judicial Council should carefully examine the potential workload for these magistrates and&#13;
decide how many are required to do the job at hand. The surplus judges could be redeployed elsewhere.&#13;
&#13;
         It is possible that the SJC may not be able to identify suitable places for the redeployment of the&#13;
all the judges identified in a court restructuring plan. However, under Bulgarian law, judges cannot be&#13;
removed from service except by way of attrition. Hence, the government may want to consider the option&#13;
of allowing these judges to retire or be deployed elsewhere in the government as an alternative exit route&#13;
to changing the law. Retirement or deployment out of the judiciary would be expected to reduce annual&#13;
recurrent expenditure on salaries, other remuneration and related office expenses in the budget. Given&#13;
the overall costs, it is recommended that a proportion of any savings from restructuring of the sector be&#13;
used to finance increases in salaries and higher capital expenditure.&#13;
&#13;
         At present, there are about 114 judges seconded to other courts through agreements between&#13;
court presidents. There may be an appearance of favoritism when some judges are seconded to higher&#13;
courts with associated increases in wages. To address this issue, the SJC should consider terminating the&#13;
secondment program as it is currently administered (by agreement between court presidents) and assume&#13;
direct responsibility for deciding the placement of seconded judges based on an assessment of the most&#13;
efficient and effective handling of the court caseloads.&#13;
&#13;
        The judiciary has raised concerns that any economies realized in a judicial restructuring program,&#13;
through reduced costs or increased income, could result in the reduction of the governmentâ&#128;&#153;s subsidy to&#13;
the judicial budget leaving overall expenditures at their present insufficient level. The latest State Budget&#13;
Act has, for the first time, provided that if the judiciary fails to reach the budgeted levels of its own income,&#13;
the state budget subsidy would not be raised to compensate any shortfall. (However, this provision was&#13;
recently overturned by the Constitutional Court.) The SJC would like greater predictability in the resources&#13;
they receive from the government budget so that they can undertake necessary reorganization and&#13;
restructuring of the courts and judiciary with confidence that they will have access to necessary resources.&#13;
&#13;
         In light of the opportunities for restructuring the judicial system identified in this paper, it is&#13;
recommended that the SJC, MOJ and MOF reach an agreement on a medium term funding strategy for the&#13;
judiciary. Such an agreement could be based on a judicial restructuring plan that leads to a more efficient&#13;
court system with a more equitable distribution of workload (by redeploying judges, consolidating courts,&#13;
and shrinking judicial and staff positions as necessary) that can be fully funded (both current and capital&#13;
expenditures) without resort to annual debates and uncertainty over supplemental budget requests.&#13;
&#13;
        Apart from the appropriate funding level for the judiciary, there is an issue of over centralized&#13;
decision making at the SJC level. Under existing law, courts must receive prior authorization from the SJC&#13;
for every expenditure that they make from the budget. Court presidents cannot retain any funds or take&#13;
any expenditure decisions on their own. The SJC could consider proposing legal changes that will allow it&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                       7&#13;
&amp;#12;to decentralize some of its authority by allowing court presidents to retain some percentage of the fees&#13;
that their courts collect. The SJC could frame specific rules defining the object and method by which court&#13;
presidents could use those funds and hold court presidents accountable for the use of these retained funds&#13;
and for prior agreed results.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                    8&#13;
&amp;#12;                                Summary of Recommendations&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
1. Revision of court tariffs: A revision of tariff is overdue and it is recommended that the SJCâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
    proposed revised tariffs be evaluated based on its economic impact and its effects on access to&#13;
    the courts.&#13;
2. Reducing the number of approved judges: SJC could consider reducing the number of approved&#13;
    judge positions to the currently filled positions as an initial step in a broader judicial restructuring.&#13;
3. Reducing number of support staff: The ratio of staff to inhabitants 2.7, which is one of the highest&#13;
    among European countries. The SJC could consider reducing this ratio at the national level and&#13;
    uniformly distributing the revised national ratio across courts.&#13;
4. Redeployment of judges in District and Regional Courts: Bulgaria could reduce the number of&#13;
    judges from 13 district courts with caseload less than 10 cases per judge per month and from 6&#13;
    regional courts with caseloads of 20 or fewer cases per judge per month. These judges could be&#13;
    redeployed in courts with high caseloads.&#13;
5. Consolidation of Appellate Courts: The SJC could consider consolidating 6 appellate courts into 2&#13;
    or 3 appellate courts and redeploy the surplus judges elsewhere.&#13;
6. Consolidation of Military Courts: The SJC could consider consolidating 4 military courts into a&#13;
    single military court to handle the existing caseload.&#13;
7. Reducing the number of Investigation Magistrates: The number of investigation magistrates&#13;
    working at the National Investigation Service (NIS) could be reduced from the present number of&#13;
    approximately 80 based on the current workload.&#13;
8. Consider options for judges who are not redeployed: The government may consider offering a&#13;
    program to allow those judges who cannot be redeployed elsewhere in the judicial system,&#13;
    following the implementation of a judicial restructuring program, to retire from the bench or&#13;
    deploy elsewhere in the government.&#13;
9. Re-appropriation of savings: It is recommended that a portion of nay savings generated by a&#13;
    judicial restructuring plan be used for financing salary increases and higher capital expenditures.&#13;
10. Medium-term funding strategy: It is recommended that SJC, MOJ and MOF reach an agreement&#13;
    on a medium term funding strategy for the judiciary based upon a judicial restructuring plan, tied&#13;
    to the achievement of goals under the Judicial Reform Strategy that can be fully funded without&#13;
    resort to supplementary budgets.&#13;
11. Decentralization of expenditure: The SJC could consider decentralizing its budget authority by&#13;
    allowing court presidents to retain some percentage of the fees that their courts collect for the&#13;
    maintenance and development of their respective courts, and frame accountability rules defining&#13;
    the object and method by which court presidents could use those funds.&#13;
12. Reorganization of secondment program of judges: The SJC could consider terminating the&#13;
    secondment program as it is currently administered by court presidents and assume responsibility&#13;
    itself for deciding the placement of judges in order to improve the efficiency of the court systems.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                    9&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                     Preface&#13;
&#13;
The World Bank published a Public Expenditure and Institutional Review (PEIR) of the Bulgarian justice&#13;
sector entitled â&#128;&#156;Resourcing the Judiciary for Performance and Accountability: A Judicial Public Expenditure&#13;
and Institutional Reviewâ&#128;&#157; in 2008. The paper included a review of selected judicial budget, human&#13;
resources, incentives and infrastructure issues; suggested a process to strengthen management of judicial&#13;
resources; and, proposed benchmarks to track progress on performance and efficiency. The paper analyzed&#13;
the spending of the justice sector over time, including the total spending level and its distribution by&#13;
individual courts and main spending categories and analyzed the various spending drivers, including&#13;
staffing numbers and salary increases. The review also compared spending with indicators such as average&#13;
caseloads and rates of case dispositions to get an idea of the development in productivity. Finally, the&#13;
review looked at a number of institutional factors underpinning the budget process.&#13;
&#13;
The objective of the present Judicial Performance, Caseload and Expenditure Review is to update the Bankâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
2008 Report and conduct an assessment of the spending and institutional changes in Bulgariaâ&#128;&#153;s judiciary&#13;
from 2008 onwards. A World Bank mission2 travelled to Sofia in June 2015. The mission team reviewed the&#13;
procedures and process for developing and allocating the judicial budget, reviewed the institutional&#13;
framework for developing and implementing this budget, and analyzed the data on judicial expenditures;&#13;
courtsâ&#128;&#153; own revenues; and, performance of the Bulgarian courts. This report and our recommendations&#13;
are focused exclusively on Bulgariaâ&#128;&#153;s judiciary and do not address the issue of the budget or caseload of&#13;
the prosecutors.&#13;
&#13;
The team met with senior officials in the key stakeholder government agencies, which included, inter alia:&#13;
Ms. Nadejda Yordanova, Head of Cabinet, and Mr. Petko Petkov, Deputy Minister, in the Ministry of Justice;&#13;
Mr. Kiril Ananiev, Deputy Minister and Mr. Dobrin Pindjurov, Director Budget in the Ministry of Finance;&#13;
Mr. Kalin Kalpakchiev, Ms. Elka Atanasova, Mr. Mihail Kozharev and Kamen Ivanov, Members of Supreme&#13;
Judicial Council; Ms. Christina Todorova, Director of International Relations in Supreme Judicial Council;&#13;
Ms. Gorista Grancharova-Kozhareva, Vice-President of the National Audit Office; Ms. Anelia Shtereva,&#13;
Deputy Chief of Regional Court in Sofia; Head of Accounts in the Regional Court in Sofia; Mr. Vesselin&#13;
Hadjiev, Chief of Court in the Plovdiv District Court; and, Mr. Kalin Monov, Chief Accountant, Plovdiv district&#13;
Court. The mission team collected publicly available data from these institutions and gathered insights&#13;
into the functioning of judiciary from the key stakeholders.&#13;
&#13;
 The current report examines the principal trends in resourcing Bulgariaâ&#128;&#153;s judiciary since 2008, while&#13;
comparing the expenditure and performance with those of other European countries. The report makes&#13;
recommendations for improving the resourcing of Bulgariaâ&#128;&#153;s judiciary in light of the recently updated&#13;
Judicial Sector Reforms Strategy in Bulgaria. The report provides a set of conclusion and recommendations&#13;
for improving the efficiency and effectiveness of Bulgariaâ&#128;&#153;s judiciary and the judicial budget process. More&#13;
comprehensive research on the conclusions and recommendations identified in this report and more&#13;
rigorous exploration of reform paths may be necessary once planned amendments to Bulgariaâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
Constitution and Judicial System Act become reality.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
2&#13;
  The mission team was led by Mr. Arun Arya (Senior Public Sector Specialist), and included Mr. Joseph Bobek&#13;
(Consultant), Ms. Svetozara Petkova (Consultant), and Ms. Adela Delcheva (Team Assistant). Ms. Stella Ilieva (Senior&#13;
Economist) joined the team in Sofia and Mr. David Bernstein, Task Team Leader (Lead Public Sector Specialist) and&#13;
Mr. Jonas Fallov (Senior Public Sector Specialist) provided support from Washington, DC and Denmark, respectively.&#13;
&#13;
                                                        10&#13;
&amp;#12;                             I.       Legal Framework for Administration of Justice&#13;
&#13;
1.       Bulgariaâ&#128;&#153;s Constitution and Judicial Systems Act constitute the core legal framework for the&#13;
administration of justice. The Constitution provides that the judiciary shall protect the rights and legitimate&#13;
interests of all citizens, legal entities and the State; it shall be independent in the manner and performance&#13;
of its functions; all judges, jurors, prosecutors and investigating magistrates shall be subservient only to&#13;
the law; and it shall have an independent budget. The administration of justice in Bulgaria is based on three&#13;
instances. The courts are state bodies that administer justice in civil, criminal and administrative cases. The&#13;
organization and activities of the Bulgarian courts are governed by the Judicial System Act, which lays down&#13;
the structure and operating principles of the judicial bodies and governs their interaction with each other&#13;
and with the legislative and executive bodies. The territorial jurisdictions of the regional, district,&#13;
administrative, military and appeal courts coincide with the administrative division of the country. The&#13;
organization of courts in Bulgaria is presented in Box 1 below.&#13;
&#13;
                                          Box 1: Organization of Courts in Bulgaria&#13;
&#13;
Regional courts â&#128;&#147; The regional courts are the main courts for examining cases in the first instance. Their decisions are&#13;
subject to appeal before the relevant district court. There are 113 regional courts of which 27 are in the district&#13;
centers.&#13;
&#13;
District courts â&#128;&#147; The district courts act as courts of first and second instance. As courts of first instance, they examine&#13;
a precisely defined category of cases involving significant sums or substantial societal interest. When acting as a&#13;
second (appellate) instance, they re-examine decisions taken by the regional courts. There are 28 district courts,&#13;
including Sofia City Court.&#13;
&#13;
Administrative courts - The administrative courts have jurisdiction over all actions seeking the issue, amendment,&#13;
repeal or annulment of administrative acts. They act as second (appellate) instance to the regional courts in some&#13;
categories of administrative cases. There are 28 Administrative courts.&#13;
&#13;
Appellate Courts â&#128;&#147; These courts consider appeals and objections against first-instance rulings by district courts within&#13;
their territorial jurisdictions. There are 5 Appellate courts.&#13;
&#13;
The Supreme Court of Cassation â&#128;&#147; The Supreme Court of Cassation is the supreme judicial instance in criminal and&#13;
civil cases. Its jurisdiction covers the entire territory of the Republic of Bulgaria. It exercises supreme judicial review&#13;
over the proper and uniform application of laws by all courts. It has its seat in Sofia.&#13;
&#13;
The Supreme Administrative Court - This court exercises supreme judicial review over the proper and uniform&#13;
application of laws by administrative courts. It deals with complaints and objections against acts by the Council of&#13;
Ministers, Prime Minister, Deputy Prime Minister, ministers, heads of other institutions directly subordinate to the&#13;
Council of Ministers, acts of the Supreme Judicial Council, acts of the Bulgarian National Bank, acts of district&#13;
governors and other acts established by statute.&#13;
&#13;
SPECIALIZED COURTS&#13;
&#13;
Military courts - examine, as courts of first instance, criminal cases concerning offences allegedly committed in the&#13;
performance of their duties, or in connection therewith, by generals, officers, non-commissioned officers and rank-&#13;
and-file in the Bulgarian army, civilian staff at the Ministry of Defence and personnel at other ministries and agencies&#13;
within the structures reporting to the Minister of Defence, at the National Security Agency and at the National&#13;
Intelligence Service. There are 3 Military Courts.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                            11&#13;
&amp;#12;Military Court of Appeal - examines appeals and objections lodged against decisions handed down by military courts&#13;
nationwide. There is only 1 Military Court of Appeal.&#13;
&#13;
The Specialized Criminal Court - which has its seat in Sofia, is equivalent to a district court. Its jurisdiction is laid down&#13;
by law and it deals mostly with organized crime cases.&#13;
&#13;
The Specialized Criminal Court of Appeal - considers appeals and objections lodged against decisions handed down&#13;
by the Specialized Criminal Court.&#13;
&#13;
Arbitration Court at the Bulgarian Chamber of Commerce and Industry - The Arbitration Court settles civil disputes&#13;
and disputes over filling gaps in contracts or adapting contracts to new circumstances, regardless of whether one or&#13;
both parties have their registered office or domicile in the Republic of Bulgaria.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
2.       All judicial power is exercised in the name of the people and justice shall be administered by the&#13;
Supreme Court of Cassation, the Supreme Administrative Court, courts of appeal, regional courts, courts-&#13;
martial and district courts. Specialized courts can be set up by virtue of law. The Supreme Court of Cassation&#13;
exercises supreme judicial oversight as to the precise and equal application of the law by all courts. The&#13;
Supreme Administrative Court exercises supreme judicial oversight as to the precise and equal application&#13;
of the law in administrative justice.&#13;
&#13;
3.       The governance of the judiciary is entrusted to the Supreme Judicial Council (SJC), which is&#13;
responsible for recruitment, promotion, reassignment and discipline (including dismissal) of the judicial&#13;
branch officials including judges, prosecutors and investigating magistrates. It also has the responsibility of&#13;
preparing and executing the budget for the judiciary. Under the Judicial System Act, published in State&#13;
Gazette No 64/2007, the SJC is the highest administrative authority and is responsible for managing the&#13;
judiciary and ensuring its independence. It determines the composition and organization of the judiciary&#13;
and manages its affairs without interfering with the independence of the bodies concerned. It determines&#13;
the number of judicial districts and the seats of the regional, district, administrative and appeal courts on&#13;
the basis of a proposal by the Minister of Justice and â&#128;&#147; as regards military courts â&#128;&#147; in coordination with the&#13;
Minister of Defense.&#13;
&#13;
4.       The hierarchy of Bulgarian courts is presented in Figure 1 below.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                             12&#13;
&amp;#12;Figure 1: Bulgarian Court Hierarchy&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                Supreme Court of Cassation                                         Supreme Administrative Court&#13;
                                               (1) - last instance for civil and                                       (1) - last instance for&#13;
                                                        criminal cases                                                 administrative cases&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            Specialized Appellate Criminal     Military Appellate Court (1) -       Appellate Courts (5) - 2nd&#13;
             Court (1) - 2nd instance for       2nd instance for military          instance for District Courts'&#13;
               organized crime cases                   criminal cases                         cases&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                    Administrative Courts (28) -&#13;
                                                                                      District Courts (28) - 1st       1st instance for most&#13;
            Specialized Criminal Court (1) -&#13;
                                                  Military Courts (3) - 1st         instance for some civil and      administrative cases; 2nd&#13;
              1st instance for organized&#13;
                                                instance for military cases        criminal cases; 2nd -instance   instance for Regional Courts'&#13;
                      crime cases&#13;
                                                                                     for Regional Courts' cases        administrative cases&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                    Regional Courts (113) - 1st&#13;
                                                                                      instance for most civil&#13;
                                                                                    andcriminal and for some&#13;
                                                                                       administrative cases&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
5.      The structure of the prosecution office corresponds to that of the courts and the Prosecutor&#13;
General oversees the legality and provides methodological guidance to all other prosecutors. The&#13;
prosecution office has to ensure that legality is observed by leading and supervising investigations. It may&#13;
also conduct investigations.&#13;
&#13;
6.      The Chairman of the Supreme Court of Cassation, the Chairman of the Supreme Administrative&#13;
Court and the Prosecutor General are appointed and removed by the President of the Republic upon a&#13;
proposal from the SJC for a period of seven years. The Judicial Systems Act sets forth the structure and&#13;
operational principles of judicial system bodies, the interaction among them, as well as that among judicial&#13;
system bodies and the legislature and executive ones.&#13;
&#13;
7.     Amendments to the Constitution of the Republic of Bulgaria were approved at first reading on&#13;
September 23, 2015. The Constitutional amendment provides for a division of the Supreme Judicial Council&#13;
into two Chambers - a judicial chamber and a prosecutors' chamber - each responsible for the&#13;
administration of the respective professions.&#13;
&#13;
8.       Draft amendments to the JSA, prepared but not submitted to the National Assembly, contain the&#13;
following provisions: division of the SJC into two Chambers - judicial and prosecutorial; direct election of&#13;
SJC members by General Assemblies of judges and of prosecutors and investigators; increase in the self-&#13;
governance of courts through increasing the functions of the general assemblies of judges; changes to the&#13;
disciplinary proceedings in order to guarantee impartiality and independence; improvements to the&#13;
attestation of magistrates in order to ensure just and transparent career growth; providing a procedure for&#13;
SJC approval in order to indict a magistrate; development of the professional qualification of magistrates;&#13;
clear and predictable rules on secondment of magistrates - decisions should be made by the general&#13;
assemblies of courts and not - as the practice currently stands - by court chairs; increasing the&#13;
independence of individual prosecutors; improving the work of SJC's Inspectorate; and introducing E-&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                      13&#13;
&amp;#12;justice. This package of amendments would allow Bulgaria to meet the goals of its Updated Justice Sector&#13;
Reform Strategy, discussed below, and responds to European Commission assessments and&#13;
recommendations for strengthening Bulgariaâ&#128;&#153;s justice system, particularly by separating the administration&#13;
of judges and prosecutors within the SJC.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                          II.       Justice Sector Reform Strategy&#13;
&#13;
9.       The Council of Ministers adopted an Updated Strategy to continue judicial sector reforms by a&#13;
resolution dated December 17, 2014, which was subsequently approved by the National Assembly on&#13;
January 21, 2015. The overall objective of this Strategy is to build on the efforts to modernize the judiciary&#13;
and to complete its reform within the next seven years. In doing so, Bulgaria will rely upon the resources&#13;
and opportunities arising from its membership of the European Union and the Council of Europe, as well&#13;
as upon the maturing of civil society and the professional community. The Strategy aims to: achieve&#13;
effective independence of the courts and the judiciary; ensure good governance of the judicial authorities&#13;
and their highly effective functioning; unfold the potential of human resources in the judiciary and&#13;
guarantee the high motivation, competence and social responsibility of judges, prosecutors and&#13;
investigating magistrates; implement a modern and effective criminal policy through the necessary&#13;
institutional and regulatory reforms; ensure a full-fledged right to a fair trial for each citizen and effective&#13;
protection of human rights. Once fully implemented, the Updated Strategy will ensure European standards&#13;
of justice to natural and legal persons and turn the judiciary into an effective guarantor of the Rule of Law&#13;
and the strengthening of State governance and institutions in the country.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                        Box 2: Updated Strategy of Judicial Sector Reforms (December 2014)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Strategic goal         Guaranteeing the independence of the court and the other judicial authorities&#13;
        1:               through effective measures against corruption, political and economic pressure&#13;
                         and other dependences&#13;
&#13;
     Specific goal 1:    Overcoming the institutional reasons for undue influence on and through the Supreme&#13;
                         Judicial Council&#13;
&#13;
     Specific goal 2:    Judgesâ&#128;&#153; self-governance as an effective means to limit the possibilities for administrative&#13;
                         forms of influence on the independence of the court and increasing the responsibility and&#13;
                         efficiency of courtsâ&#128;&#153; administration&#13;
&#13;
     Specific goal 3:    Systematic policy for prevention of corruption in the judiciary&#13;
&#13;
     Specific goal 4:    Strengthening the ethics regulations&#13;
&#13;
  Strategic goal         The judiciaryâ&#128;&#153;s human resources: an essential asset and focus of the reform;&#13;
        2:               status of judges, prosecutors and investigating magistrates&#13;
&#13;
     Specific goal 1:    Reform of law education and internships as a guarantee of high qualification upon entry and&#13;
                         motivation of human resources of the judiciary&#13;
&#13;
     Specific goal 2:    Guaranteeing trust in competitions for magistratesâ&#128;&#153; appointment and promotion&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                14&#13;
&amp;#12;   Specific goal 3:   Sustained improvement of the quality of operation of the National Institute of Justice (NIJ)&#13;
                      and affirming its achievements&#13;
&#13;
   Specific goal 4:   Effective appraisals based on a uniform integral standard assessing in depth all aspects of&#13;
                      the work of a judge, prosecutor and investigating magistrate&#13;
&#13;
   Specific goal 5:   Introducing the fair trial principles in the disciplinary proceedings against magistrates&#13;
&#13;
   Specific goal 6:   Predictable remuneration fixing rules&#13;
&#13;
   Specific goal 7:   Reckoning with the opinions of judges, prosecutors and investigating magistrates in the&#13;
                      process of administrating the judiciary&#13;
&#13;
Strategic Goal 3: Effective administration of the judiciary&#13;
&#13;
    Specific goal 1: Knowledge-based governance: capacity for research related to the governance and&#13;
                     performance of the judicial authorities&#13;
&#13;
    Specific goal 2: Regulating magistratesâ&#128;&#153; and judicial entitiesâ&#128;&#153; caseload&#13;
&#13;
    Specific goal 3: The judiciary budget: a tool of effective governance, accountability and reform&#13;
                     ï&#130;·    Introducing programme budgeting for each entity of the judiciary institutions and&#13;
                          orienting the budget to achieving results and pegging financing to the targets, activities&#13;
                          and caseload set and an objective assessment of expenditures disaggregated by type&#13;
                          of case file and case so as to achieve adequate financing of the administration of justice&#13;
                          as an essential function of the State.&#13;
                     ï&#130;·    Defining and periodically renewing the objectives and fulfilment indicators in&#13;
                          partnership between the SJC, the Ministry of Justice, the Ministry of Finance and civil&#13;
                          society, as well as periodic renewing the assessment of expenditures disaggregated by&#13;
                          type of case.&#13;
                     ï&#130;·    Introducing effective measures to decentralise budget planning and implementation,&#13;
                          bound to requirements of increased transparency, publicity and reporting of the results&#13;
                          and attainment of targets and planning the expenditures and activities of each judicial&#13;
                          entity in line with locally planned priorities.&#13;
                     ï&#130;·    Quarterly and annual reporting of the attainment of the targets and the achievement&#13;
                          of results, periodic external assessment (â&#128;&#156;Report on the State of the Judiciaryâ&#128;&#157;).&#13;
&#13;
    Specific goal 5: e-Justice&#13;
&#13;
    Specific goal 6: Development of the separate judiciary institutions&#13;
&#13;
 Strategic goal       Modern and effective penal policy&#13;
       4:&#13;
&#13;
   Specific goal 1:   Updating penal policy&#13;
&#13;
   Specific goal 2:   Reform and development of the investigating authorities&#13;
&#13;
   Specific goal 3:   An effective prosecution service&#13;
&#13;
   Specific goal 4:   Effectiveness of the specialised prosecution office and court&#13;
&#13;
   Specific goal 5:   Expert examinations&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                              15&#13;
&amp;#12;    Specific goal 6:   Penitentiary reform&#13;
&#13;
  Strategic goal       Guarantees of the rule of law, protection of human rights, access to justice and&#13;
        5:             humanity of justice&#13;
&#13;
    Specific goal 1:   Effective judicial protection of human rights&#13;
&#13;
    Specific goal 2:   Direct petition to the Constitutional Court&#13;
&#13;
    Specific goal 3:   Overcoming the reasons for the ECHR judgments against Bulgaria and respect for&#13;
                       international human rights standards&#13;
&#13;
    Specific goal 4:   Development of the legal aid system&#13;
&#13;
    Specific goal 5:   Court fees&#13;
&#13;
                            ï&#130;·    Assessing the court fees system and analysing possible changes in it&#13;
&#13;
    Specific goal 6:   Restorative justice&#13;
&#13;
    Specific goal 7.   Juvenile justice system targeting prevention, ensuring effective protection and humane&#13;
                       remedial measures&#13;
&#13;
  Strategic goal       Building trust in the judiciary through public participation and transparency&#13;
        6:&#13;
&#13;
    Specific goal 1:   Strengthening the social responsibility of the SJC parliamentary quota&#13;
&#13;
    Specific goal 2:   Ensuring tangible public participation in the administration of justice through the institute&#13;
                       of lay judges&#13;
&#13;
    Specific goal 3:   Turning the budget procedure into a tool of transparency and public control&#13;
                           ï&#130;·    Introducing programme and results-oriented budgeting for each judicial entity.&#13;
                           ï&#130;·    Public discussions involving specialised and professional non-governmental&#13;
                                organisations of the draft judiciary budget and the budget implementation report.&#13;
                           ï&#130;·    Parliamentary debate at separate sittings of the judiciary budget and its&#13;
                                implementation report.&#13;
&#13;
    Specific goal 4:   Strengthening the transparency of the judiciary and dialogue with citizens&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                        III.        Performance of Judiciary in Terms of Case Disposition&#13;
&#13;
10.     Data on the performance of the Judiciary over the past 7 years is presented in ANNEX 1: Case&#13;
Disposal and Workload between 2008-2014, which gives the number of pending cases at the beginning of&#13;
the year, number of incoming cases, number of resolved cases, number of resolved cases within 3 months&#13;
and number of pending cases at the end of that year for each court. It also presents the estimation of&#13;
caseload per judge per month, on the basis of the number of cases heard and resolved; and on the basis&#13;
of the number of approved judge positions and the actual number of working judges. Table 1 presents the&#13;
performance of the judiciary in terms of case-disposition for 2014.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                              16&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                 Table 1: Performance of Judiciary: Case Disposition in 2014&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                       Resolved cases&#13;
&#13;
                                             Pending at the                       Received                                                                            Within 3                      Pending at&#13;
                                                                                                                 Total for&#13;
               COURTS                       beginning of the                     during the                                                                           months3                       the end of&#13;
                                                                                                                 hearing&#13;
                                                 period                             year                                                       Total                                                the period&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                              Number                  %&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      Appellate courts                                         2,374                       12,497                         14,871               12,547            11,153            89%                          2,324&#13;
&#13;
      Military courts                                                48                         498                            546                517                 480          93%                                29&#13;
&#13;
      District courts +&#13;
      Sofia City Court                                       26,510                        88,720                      115,230                 89,473            68,300            76%                        25,757&#13;
&#13;
      RC in district&#13;
      centers     +Sofia&#13;
      Regional Court                                         62,932                     280,788                        343,720             288,648            246,197              85%                        55,072&#13;
&#13;
      Regional courts                                        16,159                     109,802                        125,961             111,992            100,244              90%                        13,969&#13;
&#13;
      Administrative&#13;
      courts                                                 12,614                        42,355                         54,969               43,285            31,293            72%                        11,684&#13;
&#13;
            Total cases                                    120,637                      534,660                        655,297             546,462            457,667              84%                      108,835&#13;
              (Source: Summarized Statistical Tables on the Activity of Courts in 2014).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
11.      Table 1 demonstrates good performance in terms of â&#128;&#156;clearance rate percentageâ&#128;&#157;4 and â&#128;&#156;calculated&#13;
disposition timeâ&#128;&#157;5, both of which are internationally recognized indicators of courtsâ&#128;&#153; efficiency. A Clearance&#13;
Rate close to 100 % indicates the ability of the court or of a judicial system to resolve more or less as many&#13;
cases as the number of incoming cases within the given time period. A Clearance Rate above 100 %&#13;
indicates the ability of the system to resolve more cases than received, thus reducing any potential backlog.&#13;
Conversely, a Clearance Rate below 100 % indicates that the number of incoming cases is higher than the&#13;
number of resolved cases, thus increasing any potential backlog of cases.&#13;
&#13;
12.     The Disposition Time indicator provides further insight into how a judicial system manages its flow&#13;
of cases. Generally, a case turnover ratio and Disposition Time compares the number of resolved cases&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
3&#13;
  The assessment team was unable to clarify whether the three-month period referred to in the official court statistics is uniformly measured&#13;
across courts from the date of filing of the case or from the date of the last court hearing. However, these are official statistics published in&#13;
government websites.&#13;
&#13;
4&#13;
    í µí°¶í µí±&#153;í µí±&#146;í µí±&#142;í µí±&#159;í µí±&#142;í µí±&#155;í µí±&#144;í µí±&#146; í µí±&#133;í µí±&#142;í µí±¡í µí±&#146; (%)=(í µí±&#133;í µí±&#146;í µí± í µí±&#156;í µí±&#153;í µí±£í µí±&#146;í µí±&#145; í µí±&#144;í µí±&#142;í µí± í µí±&#146;í µí±  í µí±&#150;í µí±&#155; í µí±&#142; í µí±&#157;í µí±&#146;í µí±&#159;í µí±&#150;í µí±&#156;í µí±&#145;/í µí°¼í µí±&#155;í µí±&#144;í µí±&#156;í µí±&#154;í µí±&#150;í µí±&#155;í µí±&#148; í µí±&#144;í µí±&#142;í µí± í µí±&#146;í µí±  í µí±&#150;í µí±&#155; í µí±&#142; í µí±&#157;í µí±&#146;í µí±&#159;í µí±&#150;í µí±&#156;í µí±&#145;) Ã&#151;100&#13;
&#13;
5&#13;
    í µí°¶í µí±&#142;í µí±&#153;í µí±&#144;í µí±¢í µí±&#153;í µí±&#142;í µí±¡í µí±&#146;í µí±&#145; í µí°·í µí±&#150;í µí± í µí±&#157;í µí±&#156;í µí± í µí±&#150;í µí±¡í µí±&#150;í µí±&#156;í µí±&#155; í µí±&#135;í µí±&#150;í µí±&#154;í µí±&#146;=(í µí±&#129;í µí±¢í µí±&#154;í µí±&#143;í µí±&#146;í µí±&#159; í µí±&#156;í µí±&#147; í µí±¢í µí±&#155;í µí±&#159;í µí±&#146;í µí± í µí±&#156;í µí±&#153;í µí±£í µí±&#146;í µí±&#145; í µí±&#144;í µí±&#142;í µí± í µí±&#146;í µí±  í µí±&#142;í µí±¡ í µí±¡â&#132;&#142;í µí±&#146; í µí±&#146;í µí±&#155;í µí±&#145; í µí±&#156;í µí±&#147; í µí±&#142; í µí±&#157;í µí±&#146;í µí±&#159;í µí±&#150;í µí±&#156;í µí±&#145;/í µí±&#129;í µí±¢í µí±&#154;í µí±&#143;í µí±&#146;í µí±&#159; í µí±&#156;í µí±&#147; í µí±&#159;í µí±&#146;í µí± í µí±&#156;í µí±&#153;í µí±£í µí±&#146;í µí±&#145; í µí±&#144;í µí±&#142;í µí± í µí±&#146;í µí±  í µí±&#150;í µí±&#155; í µí±&#142; í µí±&#157;í µí±&#146;í µí±&#159;í µí±&#150;í µí±&#156;í µí±&#145;) Ã&#151;365&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                               17&#13;
&amp;#12;during the observed period and the number of unresolved cases at the end of the observed period. The&#13;
ratios measure how quickly a judicial system (or a court) turns over the received cases â&#128;&#147; that is, how long&#13;
it takes for a type of case to be resolved.&#13;
&#13;
13.          The Clearance Rate and Disposition Time in Bulgarian courts in the last 7 years has been as follows:&#13;
&#13;
             Table 2: Clearance Rate and Disposition Time of Bulgarian Courts between 2008 and 2014&#13;
                  Number of cases                                                  Number of                              Estimated&#13;
                                           Number of          Number of                                 Clearance&#13;
                   pending at the                                              Unresolved Cases                        Disposition Time&#13;
                                            Incoming           Resolved                                Rate (CR) (in&#13;
      Year        beginning of the                                             at the end of the                       (DT) (in number&#13;
                                              Cases             Cases                                       %)&#13;
                       year                                                          year                                  of days)&#13;
&#13;
     2008              110,776               446,749            456,375              108,598               102.2              86.9&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     2009               99,503               524,351            526,932              106,046               100.5              73.5&#13;
&#13;
     2010              106,037               620,326            613,672              112,691                98.9              67.0&#13;
&#13;
     2011              112,871               650,015            643,780              119,106                99.0              67.5&#13;
&#13;
     2012              119,758               624,232            620,170              123,820                99.4              72.9&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     2013              123,997               580,249            583,825              120,421               100.6              75.3&#13;
&#13;
     2014              120,637               534,660            546,462              108,835               102.2              72.7&#13;
(Source: Summarized Statistical Tables on the Activity of Courts in 2014)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
14.     The Clearance Rate for all cases in all Bulgarian courts has been close to 100 % in all of the past 7&#13;
years and the Disposition Time has been less than or just above 75 days for all the years except 2008. In&#13;
2014, the Clearance Rate was 102% and the estimated Disposition Time was 72.69 days, both of which will&#13;
be considered very good performance in comparison to other European countries.&#13;
&#13;
15.      In comparison with other member states of the Council of Europe (CoE),6 Bulgaria comes out quite&#13;
well when looking at the parameters of Clearance Rate and Disposition Time based on the latest publication&#13;
of judicial statistics from CEPEJ7 (using 2012 data):&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
6&#13;
  The Council of Europe (CoE; French: Conseil de l'Europe), founded in 1949, is a regional intergovernmental organization which promotes human&#13;
rights, democracy and the rule of law in its 47 member states, covering 820 million citizens. The organization is separate from the 28-&#13;
nation European Union.&#13;
&#13;
7&#13;
    CEPEJ - Report on "European judicial systems â&#128;&#147; Edition 2014 (2012 data): efficiency and quality of justice"&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                       18&#13;
&amp;#12;           Table 3: Comparison of Clearance Rate and Disposition Time among CoE States in 2012&#13;
&#13;
                                                        (Non-Criminal Cases)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                      Clearance Rate (%)                     Disposition Time (no. of days)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        Total of                                          Total of&#13;
                                       other than                                        other than&#13;
                                        criminal        Admin. law                        criminal    Admin. law       Other&#13;
                                         cases            cases            Other cases     cases        cases          cases&#13;
&#13;
    Bulgaria                               98.9             92.1              99.4          74            150            69&#13;
&#13;
    Average for CoE states                100.4             99.2             105.4          253           356           184&#13;
&#13;
    Median amongst member&#13;
    states of Council of Europe&#13;
    (CoE)                                 100.2            100.7             100.2          149           245            93&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                          11&#13;
                                                            40.2               67                                        08&#13;
    Minimum      amongst       CoE        65.4                                              17         (Russian&#13;
    states                              (Greece)          (Malta)          (Armenia)     (Denmark)    Federation)     (Georgia)&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                         1520&#13;
    Maximum       amongst      CoE        115.7            143.2              150           860                         989&#13;
    states                               (Turkey)         (Greece)        (Montenegro)   (Portugal)    (Greece)      (Armenia)&#13;
        Source: CEPEJ 2014 publication (2012 data).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
16.    Table 3 shows that with respect to non-criminal cases, Bulgariaâ&#128;&#153;s Clearance Rate was fairly close to&#13;
the average of CoE states. However, in terms of Disposition Time, Bulgaria was much better than the&#13;
average and median for the EU states.&#13;
&#13;
17.      Similar results are found when looking at Bulgariaâ&#128;&#153;s Clearance Rate and Disposition Time statistics&#13;
in the criminal cases.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
8&#13;
 Georgia had 0 cases at the start of the year, and had 18,437 incoming cases in 2012. It resolved 18,425 cases, leaving&#13;
only 12 pending cases at the end of the year. This makes disposition time very close to zero days as per the definition&#13;
of the term.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                     19&#13;
&amp;#12;         Table 4: Comparison of Clearance Rate and Disposition Time among CoE States in 2012&#13;
&#13;
                                                        (Criminal Cases)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              Clearance Rate (%)           Disposition Time (days)&#13;
&#13;
  Bulgaria                                              98.8                         62&#13;
&#13;
  Average for CoE states                                100.5                       146&#13;
&#13;
  Median amongst CoE states                             100.5                       120&#13;
&#13;
  Minimum amongst CoE states                       90.6 (Moldova)               43 (Estonia)&#13;
&#13;
  Maximum          amongst         CoE&#13;
  states                                           120.7 (Slovenia)             490 (Malta)&#13;
      Source: CEPEJ 2014 publication (2012 data)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
18.     Table 4 shows that in respect of criminal cases, Bulgariaâ&#128;&#153;s Clearance Rate was very close to the&#13;
average for CoE states. In respect of the Disposition Time, it was much better than the average and median&#13;
for CoE states.&#13;
&#13;
19.     Thus, on the whole, taking all kinds of cases into consideration â&#128;&#147; whether criminal or non-criminal&#13;
- Bulgariaâ&#128;&#153;s performance in terms of efficiency of courts is on par with CoE states in respect of clearance&#13;
rate and much better in respect of disposition time.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                20&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                  IV.        Judicial Caseload in Bulgaria&#13;
&#13;
20.           Table 5 presents the number of judges and caseload in each category of courts in Bulgaria.&#13;
&#13;
                              Table 5: Number of Judges and Caseloads per Type of Court in 2014&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                       Workload according&#13;
                                                                                               Workload according&#13;
                                                                                                                       to actual number of&#13;
                                                                                               to approved position&#13;
                                                                                                                          working judges&#13;
                                                                                      Actual    of judges (cases per&#13;
                                                           Actual        Number                                        (cases per judge per&#13;
                                             Number                                   numbe      judge per month)&#13;
                                                           numbe            of                                               month)&#13;
                                 Number         of                                      r of&#13;
                                                             r of       approved&#13;
           COURTS                   of      approved                                  Judges&#13;
                                                           judges        position               As per                  As per&#13;
                                  Courts    positions                                 workin               As per                  As per&#13;
                                                           workin       of judges              number                  number&#13;
                                            of judges                                  g per              number                  number&#13;
                                                               g        per court              of cases                of cases&#13;
                                                                                       court                  of                      of&#13;
                                                                                                put up                  put up&#13;
                                                                                                          resolved                resolved&#13;
                                                                                                  for                     for&#13;
                                                                                                            cases                   cases&#13;
                                                                                               hearing                 hearing&#13;
&#13;
               (1)                 (2)          (3)           (4)           (5)        (6)       (7)         (8)         (9)        (10)&#13;
&#13;
    1. Appellate courts            6            162          147            27         25        7.7         6.5         8.5         7.1&#13;
&#13;
    2. Military courts             4             25           19             6          5        1.8         1.7         2.4         2.3&#13;
&#13;
    3. District courts + Sofia&#13;
                                   29           777          620            27         21        12.4        9.6        15.5        12.0&#13;
       City Court&#13;
&#13;
    4. Regional Courts in&#13;
       district centers +          27           631          484            23         18        45.4        38.1       59.2        49.7&#13;
       Sofia Regional Court&#13;
&#13;
    5. Regional courts             86           361          315             4          4        29.0        25.9       33.4        29.7&#13;
&#13;
    6. Administrative&#13;
                                   28           269          226            10          8        17.0        13.4       20.3        16.0&#13;
       courts&#13;
&#13;
     TOTAL /AVERAGE               180          2,225        1,8119          12         10        30.2        25.2       30.2        25.2&#13;
         (Source: Summarized Statistical Tables on the Activity of Courts in 2014).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
21.     Table 5 shows that there are 180 courts broken into 6 different levels or categories with 2,225&#13;
approved judge positions, against which 1,811 judges are actually working. The average number of&#13;
approved judge positions per court is 12 and actual average number of judges working per court is 10. The&#13;
maximum number of judges working per court is 25 in Appellate Courts, which is followed by 21 in District&#13;
Courts, and 18 in Regional Courts in District Centers. The lowest number of judges working per court is 4&#13;
found in the Regional Courts located outside of district centers.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
9&#13;
    The actual number of total working judges increased to 2,030 by the end of year, i.e. December 31, 2014.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                        21&#13;
&amp;#12;22.      Whether this wide difference is justified or not will have to be examined from the perspective of&#13;
average caseload per working judge. The workload of a judge is based on the number and types of cases&#13;
s/he hears. The number of resolved cases per judge is a parameter of his/her efficiency. Column (9) shows&#13;
the caseload based on number of cases heard per working judge. According to the above information, the&#13;
overall caseload per working judge is 30.2 cases per month. However this varies from the lowest 2.4 cases&#13;
per month in Military Courts to 59.2 cases per month in the Regional Courts in District Centers, including&#13;
the Sofia Regional Court, the largest court in Bulgaria. Apart from the Military Courts, the caseload appears&#13;
to be relatively low in Appellate Courts (8.5 cases per judge per month) and District Courts (15.5 per judge&#13;
per month). Bulgariaâ&#128;&#153;s overall average caseload compares well with the average caseload per judge per&#13;
month in the neighboring countries such as Romania (39.3), France (38.1), Greece (23.0), Serbia (30.2), and&#13;
Ukraine (27.3).&#13;
&#13;
23.     From the above analysis, the following conclusions emerge:&#13;
&#13;
        1) Appellate Courts: There are 147 judges working in 6 Appellate Courts. On average, there are&#13;
           25 judges per court and they are hearing only 8.4 cases and resolving 7.1 cases per month. It&#13;
           is not clear how such a large number of Appellate Court judges can be justified in view of the&#13;
           number of cases being heard and resolved per judge. One explanation for the high number of&#13;
           judges in Appellate Courts is that lower-level judges may need to be promoted after some&#13;
           years of service and therefore, they move up to higher courts such as the Appellate Courts.&#13;
           However, the caseload in Appellate Courts does not appear to justify the present number of&#13;
           judges or the growth in these judges through promotions based on seniority alone.&#13;
&#13;
        2) Military Courts: There are 19 judges working in 4 Military Courts. The caseload per judge is&#13;
           only 2.4 cases per month. This does not justify the number of judges in the 4 courts. It seems&#13;
           likely that 1 Military Court with 2 judges could manage the existing caseload10.&#13;
&#13;
        3) District Courts: There are 623 judges working in 29 District Courts with an average of 21 judges&#13;
           per court. Their caseload is only 15.5 cases per month. This is low compared to the national&#13;
           average and even if half of these judges were redeployed to other courts, the caseload would&#13;
           not exceed the national average of 30 cases per month per judge. Considering District Courts&#13;
           have been established as per the administrative jurisdictions of the respective districts, it is&#13;
           likely more difficult to reduce their number. However, there is potential for redeploying at&#13;
           least 300 judges working in these courts to courts with higher caseloads. With regard to district&#13;
           courts, Sofia City Court deserves special attention. Even though it has 152 approved judicial&#13;
           positions (including judges and junior judges), only 119 judges were actually working at the&#13;
           court as of December 31, 2014. The caseload of these judges in 2014 was 46.6 cases per&#13;
           months, which is three times higher than the national average for district courts. It would be&#13;
           advisable to redeploy judges from other district courts to Sofia City Court to fill the available&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
10&#13;
  The MOJ informed the Bank team that it believes that Bulgaria does not need a separate military court system&#13;
because this is a remnant from a time when the country had a huge professional army. MOJ believes that general&#13;
courts could easily handle crimes committed by military personnel.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                     22&#13;
&amp;#12;            approved positions, in order to reduce caseload to levels commensurate with other courts of&#13;
            the same category.&#13;
&#13;
        4) Regional Courts in District Centers (including Sofia Regional Court): There are 484 judges&#13;
           working in 27 Regional Courts located in District Centers with an average of 18 judges per court.&#13;
           However, these courts have the highest caseload of 59.2 cases per judge per month. If a&#13;
           number of judges working in District Courts were redeployed to these Regional Courts, the&#13;
           average caseload per judge could be reduced to a more manageable level. This redeployment&#13;
           would not necessarily lead to a dislocation of judges as District Court judges could continue to&#13;
           work in the same district. Again, the biggest court in this category, Sofia Regional Court, is an&#13;
           outlier. Of the 171 approved positions for magistrates in Sofia Regional Court, 13 positions&#13;
           have not been filled yet and another 20 magistrates have been seconded to other courts. The&#13;
           actual caseload of judges in this court in 2014 was 124.4 cases per month, which is&#13;
           approximately twice the workload of judges in regional courts in district towns and almost four&#13;
           times the workload of other regional courts. In order to reduce this caseload, the Sofia Regional&#13;
           Court should be fully staffed and judges from this court should not be seconded elsewhere.&#13;
&#13;
        5) Regional Courts: There are 314 judges working in 86 Regional Courts at an average of 4 Judges&#13;
           per court. However, the caseload in these courts is 33.37 cases per judge per month, which is&#13;
           not substantially high. However, there may be scope for redeploying judges to these courts to&#13;
           reduce the caseload further.&#13;
&#13;
        6) Administrative Courts: There are 226 Judges working in 28 Administrative Courts at an average&#13;
           of 8 judges per court and the caseload is 20.26 cases per judge per month. Both the number&#13;
           of judges and their average caseload are moderate in comparison to other types of courts in&#13;
           Bulgaria. These courts do not require intervention in terms of redeployment.&#13;
&#13;
24.     It may be noted, however, that all the analysis above is based on the simple number of cases and&#13;
that we do not have data on the types or complexity of cases that each level of Bulgarian courts may hear.&#13;
The SJC is currently conducting an exercise to classify each case-group by the â&#128;&#156;complexity" involved in&#13;
resolving them. Conclusions regarding the appropriate number of judges and manageable levels of&#13;
caseload for each type of Bulgarian court could be revised after considering the outcome of the SJCâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
complexity exercise. A detailed description of the last seven years of judicial workloads by category of court&#13;
is presented in ANNEX 2: Court-Wise Actual Workload between 2008 and 2014.&#13;
&#13;
25.     It will be pertinent to note that among the District Courts, the following ones in particular have&#13;
sustained low caseloads since 2010:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                     23&#13;
&amp;#12;                             Table 6: District Courts with consistent low caseloads since 2010&#13;
&#13;
     S. No.              Name of                         Caseload in number of cases per working judge per month&#13;
&#13;
                     District Court         2014      2013        2012          2011   2010    Average for     Average for&#13;
                                                                                               2010-2014       2012-2014&#13;
&#13;
       1         Shumen                      8.3       8.9          9.0         18.1   23.7       13.6             8.7&#13;
&#13;
       2         Targovishte                 5.2       5.5          5.8         5.3    5.6         5.5             5.5&#13;
&#13;
       3         Dobrich                     7.9       9.2          9.4         8.9    9.2         8.9             8.9&#13;
&#13;
       4         Silistra                    7.9      11.5          8.0         8.4    9.3         9.0             9.2&#13;
&#13;
       5         Rousse                      9.0       9.6         10.6         10.3   10.6       10.0             9.8&#13;
&#13;
       6         Razgrad                     9.2       9.6          9.7         9.2    10.4        9.6             9.5&#13;
&#13;
       7         Pazardjik                   9.7      10.2         10.4         10.2   9.9        10.1             10.1&#13;
&#13;
       8         Montana                     6.1       6.5          6.9         7.2    6.8         6.7             6.5&#13;
&#13;
       9         Lovech                      8.8       7.9          7.6         7.9    9.0         8.2             8.1&#13;
&#13;
      10         Kurdzali                    5.6       6.1          7.0         6.7    6.5         6.4             6.2&#13;
&#13;
      11         Vratsa                      7.9       7.7          8.0         8.6    7.7         8.0             7.9&#13;
&#13;
      12         Vidin                       8.9       7.5          9.2         9.1    8.9         8.7             8.5&#13;
&#13;
      13         Sofia Region                9.4       9.0          9.9         10.8   12.2       10.3             9.4&#13;
&#13;
    Average for above 13 courts              7.9       8.4         8.6          9.3    9.9         8.9             8.3&#13;
&#13;
    Average for all District Courts         15.5      15.3         16.6         16.1   15.6       15.8             15.8&#13;
           (Source: Summarized Statistical Tables on the Activity of Courts).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
26.      Table 6 shows 13 out of total 28 District Courts where the average case load has been consistently&#13;
low since 2010. These courts have an average caseload of less than 10 cases per working judge per month,&#13;
and the caseloads have further declined in the last 3 years. The average case load of these 13 courts is&#13;
about half the average of all District Courts. These courts have, on an average, approximately 21 judges&#13;
per court. Some of those judges could be redeployed to Regional Courts located in the same district towns&#13;
or to District Courts with significantly heavier judicial caseloads such as Sofia City or other Regional Courts&#13;
with high judicial caseload like Sofia City, Varna, Pernik, and Plovdiv. Any redeployment of judges will not&#13;
be easy and may be complicated by the fact that some Districts Courts likely have judges who are senior to&#13;
those in the regional courts and therefore less willing to move â&#128;&#156;downâ&#128;&#157; to a Regional Court. Nevertheless,&#13;
in the interest of overall efficiency of judicial system, the SJC may need to identify a solution to the existing&#13;
unbalanced distribution of workload across the District Courts. One possible solution could be to protect&#13;
the salary and rank of District Court judges while redeploying them to Regional Courts.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      24&#13;
&amp;#12;27.       Amongst the Regional Courts, the following have had a consistent low caseload since 2010.&#13;
&#13;
                   Table 7: Regional Courts with consistent low caseload between 2010 and 2014&#13;
&#13;
            Name of                                Caseload in number of cases per working Judge per month&#13;
&#13;
         Regional Court&#13;
                                  2014         2013         2012           2011    2010        Average         Average&#13;
                                                                                             (2012-2014)     (2010-2014)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      1. Topolovgrad               16          19.2          20.6          21.9    22.9         18.6            20.1&#13;
&#13;
      2. Ivaylovgrad              11.4         17.8          15.3          17.6    14.9         14.8            15.4&#13;
&#13;
      3. Breznik                  23.3         19.8          14.6          15.2    13.4         19.2            17.3&#13;
&#13;
      4. Trun                     17.0         13.7          26.1          18.7    12.5         18.9            17.6&#13;
&#13;
      5. Krumovgrad               16.5         17.8          19.0          23.1    16.2         17.8            18.5&#13;
&#13;
      6. Ardino                   10.3         13.3          15.4          23.4    17.3         13.00           15.9&#13;
&#13;
      Average for 6 courts        15.8         16.9          18.5          19.9    16.2         17.1            17.5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        Average for all           33.4         36.5          38.8          43.5    40.3         36.2            38.5&#13;
        Regional Courts&#13;
       (Source: Summarized Statistical Tables on the Activity of Courts)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
28.     Table 7 above shows 6 Regional Courts which have a consistently low caseload of less than 20 cases&#13;
per judge per month. This amounts to less than one case per day for each judge. This is a low average in&#13;
comparison to other Regional Courts. The average of these 6 courts is less than half of average of all&#13;
Regional Courts in the same years. Based on this assessment (which does not account for variations in the&#13;
complexity of the cases that are heard in each court), the current number of judges working in these 6&#13;
courts may not be justified. Surplus judges could be transferred to other courts, or if the number of judges&#13;
in the concerned courts is low, these courts could be consolidated with other Regional Courts based on&#13;
geographical proximity.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         V.         Benchmarking of Number of Judges&#13;
&#13;
29.     If we compare Bulgaria with other EU states in terms of number of judges per 100,000 inhabitants,&#13;
the situation that emerges is as follows:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                     25&#13;
&amp;#12;                     Table 8: Comparison of Number of Professional Judges per 100,000&#13;
                                      in Bulgaria and other CoE States&#13;
&#13;
                                              Number of Professional Judges Per 100,000 Inhabitants     Evolution&#13;
                                                                                                      (2006-2012) in&#13;
                                                2006        2008           2010            2012             %&#13;
&#13;
     Bulgaria                                   23.7         29             29.8           30.7           29.6&#13;
&#13;
     Average for CoE States                     20.3         20.9           21              21             4.2&#13;
&#13;
     Median for CoE States                       19          16.5           17.3            21             2.4&#13;
&#13;
     Minimum for CoE States (UK-&#13;
     Northern Ireland)11                        21.3         7.0             -              3.8           -81.9&#13;
&#13;
     Maximum for CoE States (Monaco)            54.5        112.5          100.3          102.4           87.7&#13;
            Source: CEPEJ 2014 publication (2012 data)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
30.      Table 8 shows that the number of professional judges per 100,000 inhabitants in Bulgaria was 23.7&#13;
in 2006, which was close to the average of 20.3 for the CoE states. However, after 2006, there has been a&#13;
consistent increase in the number of professional judges per 100,000 inhabitants in Bulgaria and it reached&#13;
30.7 in 2012, whereas the average for CoE states increased minimally and remained at a level of 21 judges&#13;
per 100,000 inhabitants. The evolution in the number of professional judges per 100,000 inhabitants in&#13;
Bulgaria between 2006 and 2012 has been 29.6 % which is substantially higher than the average growth of&#13;
4.2 % for the COE states.&#13;
&#13;
31.     Bulgaria is experiencing a demographic crisis, with negative population growth since the 1990's&#13;
and an economic stagnation that has promoted significant emigration. Bulgaria's population is now&#13;
shrinking at an alarming rate, losing 582,000 in ten years, and 1.5 million since 1985. Bulgaria has an&#13;
estimated population of 7.11 million in 2015, which is down from the official population of 7.36 million at&#13;
the 2011 census. (There are also significant â&#128;&#156;pullâ&#128;&#157; factors that also have influenced this recent emigration.)&#13;
However, the number of professional judges increased from 2,147 to 2,225 between 2011 and 2015. The&#13;
number of professional judges per 100,000 population in 2015 is 31.3. The evolution between 2006 and&#13;
2012 has been 32.1 %. The contrast of a shrinking overall population with the increase of almost 32% in&#13;
number of judges per 100,000 inhabitants is striking.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
11&#13;
  The changes in number of judges in UK-Northern Ireland appears to be an outlier. Data for UK-Northern Ireland&#13;
needs to be qualified by the fact that data reported for 2006 and 2008 includes the number of lay judges (243) and&#13;
seems to be presented in terms of â&#128;&#156;personsâ&#128;&#157; rather than â&#128;&#156;full time equivalentsâ&#128;&#157; as reported by other COE states.&#13;
&#13;
                                                              26&#13;
&amp;#12;                             Table 9: Number of Incoming Cases between 2008 and 2014&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                  Number of Incoming Cases&#13;
             COURTS&#13;
                                                2014            2013              2012          2011     2010       2009          2008&#13;
&#13;
Appellate courts                             12,497            12,792             13025      12542       11488      10433        10634&#13;
&#13;
Military courts                                 498             1,230             1501          1407     2001       1724          1934&#13;
&#13;
District courts + Sofia City Court           88,720            92,270             97074      92439       88362      81323        78600&#13;
Regional Courts in district centers&#13;
+ Sofia Regional Court                      280,788            304,631            332322     351132     340638     285547       229926&#13;
&#13;
Regional courts                             109,802            122,770            133396     148318     138327     109284        91595&#13;
&#13;
Administrative courts                        42,355            46,556             46914      44177       39510      36040        34060&#13;
&#13;
            Total cases                     534,660            580,249        624,232       650,015     620,326    524,351      446,749&#13;
  (Source: Summarized Statistical Tables on the Activity of Courts).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
32.     Table 9 shows that there was an increase in the number of incoming cases from 2008 to 2010. But&#13;
there has been a continuous decline in the number of incoming cases since 2011. If these caseload figures&#13;
are compared to the increase in the number of professional judges per 100,000 inhabitants to 31.3 in 2015&#13;
we see that the number of judges in Bulgaria grew despite a reduction in population and a reduction in the&#13;
number of incoming cases. (Though it should be noted that the absolute number of incoming cases in 2012&#13;
and even in 2014 was still greater than in 2008 for all of Bulgariaâ&#128;&#153;s courts except the Military Courts.) This&#13;
analysis can be used to support the case for establishing a freeze on the number of approved judgesâ&#128;&#153;&#13;
positions and redeploying existing working judges based on the distribution of caseload.&#13;
&#13;
33.     Digging deeper into the judicial statistics we can assess the evolution in the number of judicial&#13;
positions from 2008 to 2014 to see in which category of courts it has increased the most:&#13;
&#13;
              Table 10: Number of Judicial Positions in Different Courts between 2008 and 2014&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                             Evolution of&#13;
                                                                                                                                Judges'&#13;
    COURTS                2008           2009           2010             2011              2012        2013       2014         Positions&#13;
                                                                                                                             (2008-2014)&#13;
                                                                                                                                  in %&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Appellate courts           135            140            141             142               158         159        162            20&#13;
&#13;
Military courts            31              30             28                 27            27          27         25            -19.3&#13;
&#13;
District courts +&#13;
                           744            752            759             751               767         768        777            4.4&#13;
Sofia City Court&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                        27&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                            Evolution of&#13;
                                                                                                               Judges'&#13;
    COURTS                2008            2009           2010             2011   2012         2013   2014     Positions&#13;
                                                                                                            (2008-2014)&#13;
                                                                                                                 in %&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Regional Courts in&#13;
district centers +&#13;
                           562              572          577              573     575         618    631       12.3&#13;
Sofia     Regional&#13;
Court&#13;
&#13;
Regional courts            390              398          394              385     381         373    361        -7.4&#13;
&#13;
Administrative&#13;
                           263              270          266              269     268         269    269        2.2&#13;
courts&#13;
&#13;
     TOTAL                2125            2162           2165             2147   2176         2214   2225       4.7&#13;
     (Source: Summarized Statistical Tables on the Activity of Courts).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
34.      Table 10 shows that the maximum proportionate increase in the number of judicial positions has&#13;
been in the Appellate Courts. This is followed by Regional Courts in District Centers. This is as expected,&#13;
since, as the judges get promoted, they likely move â&#128;&#156;upâ&#128;&#157; the court hierarchy and ultimately are posted in&#13;
Appellate Courts. In Regional Courts in district centers, there is the maximum caseload and it is expected&#13;
that the number of judges would be increased to match the increasing caseload. The increase in District&#13;
Courts has been 4.44 %, but in relation to the caseload in these courts, this may be considered high. As&#13;
suggested earlier, this growth could have been to provide promotional avenues to judges in the Regional&#13;
Courts. A reduction of 7.44 % in the number of judges in Regional Courts, is, however, not justified because&#13;
these are first instance courts with caseloads that are greater than the average. A reduction of 19.35 % in&#13;
Military Courts is to be expected due to reducing caseload.&#13;
&#13;
35.      If we compare the number of courts per 100,000 inhabitants in Bulgaria and other COE member&#13;
states, the situation emerges as follows:&#13;
&#13;
                                   Table 11: Comparative Ratio of Courts to Population&#13;
                                                       by Country&#13;
&#13;
                                 Country                     Number of Courts    Number of Courts&#13;
                                                                                   per 100,000&#13;
                                                                                   population&#13;
&#13;
                                 Serbia                              343                4.8&#13;
&#13;
                                 Bosnia and                          188                4.9&#13;
                                 Herzegovina&#13;
&#13;
                                 Bulgaria                            185                2.5&#13;
&#13;
                                 Hungary                             157                1.6&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      28&#13;
&amp;#12;                          Romania                             144                 0.7&#13;
&#13;
                          Croatia                             89                  2.0&#13;
&#13;
                          Montenegro                          22                  3.6&#13;
&#13;
                          Slovenia                            49                  2.5&#13;
&#13;
                          Albania                             45                  1.4&#13;
&#13;
                          Netherlands                         16                  0.1&#13;
&#13;
                          France                              NA                  1.0&#13;
&#13;
                          Germany                            1162                 1.9&#13;
&#13;
                          Poland                              NA                  1.5&#13;
                              Source: Efficiency of Justice (CEPEJ) June 2013).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
36.     In many European countries, planned or current reforms to the judicial map tend to reduce the&#13;
number of courts with the aim of cutting budgets or increasing efficiency by grouping courts together or&#13;
making them more specialized. This applies to Croatia and Serbia in the above list of countries. Similar&#13;
types of reduction or consolidation of courts could be justified in Bulgaria based on the declining&#13;
population, downward trend in incoming cases, growth in the number of judges and uneven distribution&#13;
of caseload among different court levels.&#13;
&#13;
37.      The caseload analysis in the sections above was conducted based on the actual number cases filed&#13;
and resolved in courts as per statistics published by the SJC. However, (as noted above in paragraph 24)&#13;
these statistics do not distinguish between the complexities of different types of cases. All cases are not&#13;
equally complex. Some cases raise a number of difficult issues, involve multiple parties or address novel&#13;
legal issues and therefore require greater effort from a judge to understand and resolve. Other cases, such&#13;
as the issuance of enforcement orders and writs of execution, can be resolved in minutes. In order to&#13;
incorporate this additional characteristic in its statistics, the SJC has developed a methodology for&#13;
measuring the complexity of cases.&#13;
&#13;
38.      Under this methodology, administrative cases have been divided into 50 groups and criminal and&#13;
civil cases have been divided into 100 groups. Judges have been asked to fill out questionnaires specifying&#13;
how many hours they typically need to devote to a case from each group. Once the information from all&#13;
these questionnaires is processed, SJC will determine a â&#128;&#156;Complexity Quotientâ&#128;&#157; for each case group, which&#13;
will form the basis of the case weighing methodology. A survey of judges across Bulgaria was started in July&#13;
2014 and concluded in March 2015. Questionnaires were completed by judges and uploaded electronically&#13;
to the central server. Processing of survey results is ongoing. The entire set of results is expected by end of&#13;
August 2015. The questionnaire cards were entered on a retrospective basis, but in the future can be&#13;
entered on real time basis. Time Control Sheets will have to be entered by judges in the electronic system.&#13;
The electronic system will enable the monitoring of complexity of cases on a real time basis. The SJC should&#13;
have the ability to track the â&#128;&#156;complexity quotientâ&#128;&#157; by court/case type and arrange the cases in ascending&#13;
or descending order of complexity. This exercise will help in assessing the caseload in different courts more&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                              29&#13;
&amp;#12;accurately by more effectively incorporating complexity into the assessment. If adopted by the SJC in 2015,&#13;
the results will be available for use in preparing budget estimates for the courts starting in 2017.&#13;
&#13;
39.     There is a risk that the judges (and possibly the SJC) will identify more time needed to handle a&#13;
particular type of case than it actually takes them to resolve the case. Thus the SJCâ&#128;&#153;s Complexity Quotient&#13;
could have an upward bias to it. This has been observed in another sector in Bulgaria where an assessment&#13;
of complexity tended to move in the direction of more rather than less complexity when measured by the&#13;
participants. At the same time the SJCâ&#128;&#153;s efforts could provide a useful benchmark against which court&#13;
workloads can be measured going forward. Such measurements could help the SJC reallocate caseload&#13;
among different courts in a more refined manner based on complexity and could be used to develop a&#13;
more fair evaluation of judges.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        VI.      Investigation Magistrates&#13;
&#13;
40.      Investigation magistrates also form part of the judiciary. More than 1,000 investigation magistrates&#13;
were appointed during 1999-2005, of which about 500 have either retired or become prosecutors. There&#13;
are still approximately 500 investigation magistrates, approximately 80 of which work at the National&#13;
Investigative Service (NIS). Many of them do not have sufficient workload, especially the ones working at&#13;
NIS. Thus, the average caseload per investigation magistrate at the National Investigative Service in 2013&#13;
was estimated to be 11.89 cases, of which 5.79 cases have been completed and just 0.56 have ended with&#13;
an opinion for bringing an indictment to court12. Unfortunately current data on investigation magistratesâ&#128;&#153;&#13;
workload was not publicly available. Anecdotal evidence suggests that workload may have dropped further&#13;
since 2013. As per Constitutional provisions, these magistrates can exit only through retirement; they&#13;
cannot be removed from service unless there is a disciplinary ground. Based on available information, the&#13;
government may consider conducting a detailed examination of the potential and actual workloads for&#13;
these magistrates in order to make a decision on the optimal number needed to handle the expected&#13;
caseload.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                          VII.     Secondment Program&#13;
&#13;
41.     Court presidents have the authority to temporarily transfer judicial assistance between the courts.&#13;
The assistance is based on an assessment of the workload in the receiving court. Both the sending and&#13;
receiving court presidents must agree on the transfer of judicial assistance. The funds to pay for the salaries&#13;
of the temporary judge are reallocated through the SJC. If the judge is temporarily assigned to a higher&#13;
level court, the salary of the judge is increased to the level of the higher level judge position. Only salary&#13;
funds are transferred to the receiving court. No provision is made for the additional travel or other&#13;
incidental costs. Once the assignment is complete, the seconded judge returns to the resident court and&#13;
the salary is reduced to the level of the original, lower resident court.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
12&#13;
  Report on the Application of the Law and the Activity of the Prosecution and the Investigative Bodies in 2013, page&#13;
125&#13;
&#13;
                                                         30&#13;
&amp;#12;                         Table 12: Number of Judges Seconded by Institution in 2015&#13;
&#13;
        Court/Institution                        Number of Judges            Number of Judges on&#13;
                                              Transferred to Another        Temporary Assignment&#13;
                                                 Court/Institution&#13;
&#13;
        Appellate Court                                   -3                         24&#13;
&#13;
        Supreme Court of Cassation                        0                          3&#13;
&#13;
        District Court                                  -36                          21&#13;
&#13;
        Sofia Regional Court                            -21                          7&#13;
&#13;
        Other Regional Courts                           -37                          24&#13;
&#13;
        Sofia City Court                                -10                          25&#13;
&#13;
        Administrative Court                              -7                         8&#13;
&#13;
        Military                                          0                          0&#13;
&#13;
        National Institute of Justice                     0                          1&#13;
&#13;
        European Commission                               0                          1&#13;
&#13;
        TOTAL                                           -114                         114&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
42.   The case disposition during 2013 and 2014 is represented below to see the impact of secondment.&#13;
&#13;
                   Table 13: Number of Cases Completed and Pending by Court Type&#13;
&#13;
                         Court Type           Cases        Pending End     Cases         Pending&#13;
                                            Completed       of period    Completed        End of&#13;
                                              2013                         2014           period&#13;
&#13;
            Appellate                          12,752           2,396       12,547          2,324&#13;
&#13;
            Military                            1,286              48          517             29&#13;
&#13;
            District                           91,226          25,456       89,473         25,757&#13;
&#13;
            Regional Courts in District       306,383          62,777      288,648         55,072&#13;
            Towns&#13;
&#13;
            Regional Courts                   123,681          16,148      111,992         13,969&#13;
&#13;
            Administrative Courts              48,496          12,596       43,285         11,684&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                     31&#13;
&amp;#12;43.      Based on Tables 12 and 13 it appears that backlogs continued to fall even in those courts that&#13;
experienced a net loss of judges due to secondments. The one exception were the District Courts which&#13;
experienced both a net loss in judges and an increase in backlog. While we cannot draw specific&#13;
conclusions from this data (for example would the backlog in the Regional Courts have fallen more if these&#13;
courts did not have a net loss in seconded judges?), we can conclude that the secondment program will&#13;
result in an increased caseload burden for the judges remaining in courts that experience a net loss of&#13;
seconded judges. For example, the Regional Court in Sofia seconded 21 judges to other courts and received&#13;
7 seconded judges, resulting in a net reduction of 14 judges which contributes to the high caseload carried&#13;
by the judges remaining in the Sofia Regional Court. The length of secondment service has been as follows:&#13;
&#13;
                                   Table 14: Length of Secondment Service&#13;
&#13;
                  Over 36 Months       Over 24 months            Over 12 Month      Under 12 Months&#13;
&#13;
                          21                    17                     24                  52&#13;
&#13;
44.     The above table indicates that some of the secondments have become de-facto permanent re-&#13;
assignments. In the category of secondments with a duration of more than 36 months, some judges have&#13;
been on assignment for more than 60 months and in one case, for more than 80 months. Based on this&#13;
data, the SJC may consider reviewing the list of seconded judges to determine those that should be placed&#13;
permanently in vacant positions in the receiving courts.&#13;
&#13;
45.       The secondment program can be used by the SJC as a valuable tool to address the workload of&#13;
judges in overburdened courts. However, the SJC should consider restructuring the secondment program&#13;
as it is currently administered â&#128;&#147; through agreement of the sending and receiving Court Presidents â&#128;&#147; for it&#13;
to make more effective use of this tool. Under a revised secondment procedure the SJC could assume&#13;
responsibility for deciding the placement of seconded judges based on a work load analysis conducted by&#13;
the SJC.&#13;
&#13;
46.     The above arrangement would eliminate both the perception of favoritism in the assignment of&#13;
some judges to higher courts (with an accompanying increase in wages) and the possibility of Court&#13;
Presidents influencing the decisions of seconded judges who would like to remain in their seconded&#13;
positions.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        VIII.    Support Staff in Judiciary&#13;
&#13;
47.     The SJC is developing a court reorganization strategy by studying court closure alternatives and the&#13;
impact those closures would have on access to justice. Following that study, the SJC plans to estimate the&#13;
number of support staff needed in relation to the workload. The present ratio of support staff to judges is&#13;
as follows:&#13;
&#13;
                                   Table 15: Ratio of Support Staff to Judges&#13;
&#13;
                                        2007         2008    2009      2010      2011   2012     2013   2014&#13;
&#13;
       Total Working Judges             1734         1757    1780      1798      1779   1785     1775   1861&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                            32&#13;
&amp;#12;       Total Working Court Clerks             4164       4270      4466      4538         4594     4700         4650   4684&#13;
&#13;
       Ratio of Clerks to Judges               2.4        2.4         2.5     2.5         2.6       2.6         2.6    2.5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
48.      The current ratio of support staff to Magistrates is 2.52. However, this ratio is not uniform across&#13;
courts. It will be useful to ensure that this ratio is equitably applied within each court. There are several&#13;
courts that do not have an adequate number of support staff, which can affect the courtâ&#128;&#153;s efficiency. It&#13;
may be possible to have a redeployment of support staff from courts with higher ratios to courts with lower&#13;
ones. It would also be helpful for the SJC to analyze if a ratio of 2.52 clerks to each judge is necessary for&#13;
the efficient delivery of judicial services. If not, and if the ratio can be reduced to 2 while maintaining the&#13;
same level of outputs and judicial services, then the number of clerks could be reduced to around 950&#13;
which could result in an annual savings of approximately 17.5 million BGN.&#13;
&#13;
                                    Table 16: Comparative Ratio of Staff to Judges&#13;
&#13;
                                                By Country and Population&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                         Country                  Population          Ratio of Staff to     Ratio of staff to&#13;
                                                                          Judges                100,000&#13;
                                                                                              Population&#13;
&#13;
                         Croatia                     4,412,137              3.7                   47.8&#13;
&#13;
                         Greece                   11,309,885                3.3                    18&#13;
&#13;
                         Bosnia      and             3,843,126              3.2                   24.4&#13;
                         Herzegovina&#13;
&#13;
                         Slovenia                    2,050,189              3.2                   49.9&#13;
&#13;
                         Hungary                     9,986,000              2.7                    29&#13;
&#13;
                         Bulgaria                    7,364,570              2.6                   29.8&#13;
&#13;
                         Romania                  21,431,298                2.1                    19&#13;
&#13;
                         Netherlands              16,655,799                2.6                   2.6&#13;
&#13;
                         France                   65,026,885                 3                     3&#13;
&#13;
                         Italy                    60,626,442                3.7                   3.7&#13;
&#13;
                         Germany                                            2.7                   66.9&#13;
                                                  80,233,100&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                         Sweden                   9,555,893                 4.6                   54.1&#13;
                           Source: European Commission for the Efficiency of Justice (CEPEJ) June 2013).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                 33&#13;
&amp;#12;49.      As can be seen, the ratio of staff to judges falls into three groups. There are three countries with&#13;
ratios of 3.7 or more, four countries with ratios between 3 and 3.2 and four countries with ratios of 2.6 or&#13;
2.7 and one country with a ratio of 2.1. Bulgaria falls in the middle with a ratio of staff to judges of 2.6.&#13;
&#13;
50.     The ratio of staff to inhabitants is the highest in the highly developed EU countries; Germany and&#13;
Sweden all have over 50 staff per 100,000 inhabitants. Serbia, Montenegro, Croatia and Slovenia (all&#13;
former Yugoslav republics, not listed) also each have well over 30 staff and judges per 100,000 inhabitants.&#13;
The rest of the Eastern European countries have ratios of staff and judges to 100,000 inhabitants ranging&#13;
from a high of 29 in Bulgaria to a low of 11.7 in Albania. The ratio of both staff and judges in all of the&#13;
Eastern European countries are very similar. The three other EU members, Italy, Netherlands and France,&#13;
have substantially less staff per 100,000 inhabitants ranging from 2.6 to 3.7&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                         IX.      Expenditure Framework for the Judiciary Sector&#13;
&#13;
51.     The Public Finance Act, 2014 assigns the responsibility for the budget formulation process and&#13;
timetable to the Ministry of Finance (MOF). The SJC follows the Budget Instructions issued by the MOF&#13;
that are applicable to all Primary Budget Holders. The SJC is the Primary Budget Holder for the judiciary.&#13;
The courts are considered Secondary Budget Holders. The instructions and budget schedules to be&#13;
completed by the courts are issued by January 31 of each year. The budget call circular requests the&#13;
Primary Budget Holders to estimate their budget requirements for two years into the future. All budget&#13;
proposals including from the Judiciary and the Parliament are approved by the Council of Ministers.&#13;
&#13;
52.      The SJC sends budget instructions to the courts requiring the courts to prepare their budget&#13;
proposals using the standard budget classification for all government bodies. The standard classification&#13;
is by economic object class of expenditures (Salaries, Social Security, Travel, Maintenance, etc.). The courts&#13;
submit their budget proposals to the SJC as email attachments. The analysts in the SJCâ&#128;&#153;s Directorate of&#13;
the Budget and Finance Sector consolidate all 185 budget proposals by court type and submit the budgets&#13;
to the Budget and Finance Committee of the SJC for review.&#13;
&#13;
53.     There are two sources of funding for the judiciary budget â&#128;&#147; Own Revenue and State Subsidy. The&#13;
courts estimate the level of court fees to be collected during the fiscal year based on the expected number&#13;
of incoming cases and their types. An estimate is also made in regard to the amount to be collected through&#13;
penalties based on cases under consideration and past trends. The estimated level of fees to be collected&#13;
during a year is linked to the tariff-rates approved by the Council of Ministers. Once the SJC approves the&#13;
Judiciary budget including estimated expenditure, Own Revenue, and State Subsidy, it is sent to the&#13;
Ministry of Justice (MOJ) for presentation to the Council of Ministers.&#13;
&#13;
54.      Article 117 of the Constitution of the Republic of Bulgaria makes the following provision in respect&#13;
of the judiciary:&#13;
&#13;
         â&#128;&#156;(1) The judiciary shall protect the rights and legitimate interests of all citizens, legal entities and&#13;
         the State.&#13;
&#13;
         (2) The judiciary shall be independent. In the performance of their functions, all judges, court&#13;
         assessors, prosecutors and investigating magistrates shall be subservient only to the law.&#13;
&#13;
         (3) The judiciary shall have an independent budgetâ&#128;&#157;.&#13;
&#13;
                                                      34&#13;
&amp;#12;55.     The Judiciary is guaranteed an independent budget to ensure its independence from the executive.&#13;
The Budget for the judiciary is, therefore, not amended by MOJ or the Council of Ministers. The Council of&#13;
Ministers consolidates budgets of all ministries, departments and agencies and forwards them to the&#13;
Parliament for approval. Table 17 below illustrates the significant reduction to the judicial budget request&#13;
as proposed by the MOF and adopted by the Parliament for inclusion in the State Budget Act.&#13;
&#13;
        Table 17: Judicial Budget Request Compared to State Budget Act and Actual Expenditures&#13;
&#13;
                                                (Amount in 1000 BGN)&#13;
                                                2010         2011          2012        2013          2014&#13;
&#13;
 Judiciary Budget Request                   540,014      483,429       493,982    507,217        543,552&#13;
&#13;
 Judiciary Budget Included in the State&#13;
 Budget Act                                 387,705      387,705       400,000    404,000        434,000&#13;
&#13;
 Actual Judiciary Expenditures              436,227      422,825       420,243    441,539        460,472&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Judiciary Budget Request Reduced in&#13;
 State Budget Act                           152,309      95,724        93,982     103,217        109,552&#13;
&#13;
 Judiciary Budget Request Above&#13;
 Actual Expenditures                        103,787      60,604        73,740     65,677         83,080&#13;
&#13;
56.     Traditionally the MOF submits an alternate budget for the judiciary to Parliament. The alternate&#13;
budget is always lower than the budget proposal from the SJC. This is typically due to the fact that the&#13;
MOF considers broader resource constraints and tries to allocate the budget rationally and equitably based&#13;
on these broader constraints. Since the parties running the executive branch are also in control of the&#13;
Parliament, the Parliament usually approves MOFâ&#128;&#153;s alternate budget proposal for the judiciary. As a result,&#13;
the annual State Budget Act has included the MOFâ&#128;&#153;s alternative budget rather than the budget proposed&#13;
by SJC.&#13;
&#13;
57.     After the State Budget Act is approved, the SJC distributes an annual allocation of funds to courts&#13;
by economic classification along with an approved employment ceiling. The court presidents have the&#13;
authority to reprogram funds among the various classes of expenditures with approval of the SJC.&#13;
&#13;
58.     The courts manage their budget within the approved funding level. All court expenditures are&#13;
transmitted to the SJC electronically for prior approval. Courts cannot incur any expense without prior&#13;
authorization from the SJC. This practice is uniformly followed across all government agencies where&#13;
secondary budget holders are required to take prior authorization for all expenditures from the primary&#13;
budget holders. Courts maintain their own accounting records and submit monthly accounting reports to&#13;
the SJC. The reports are consolidated by the SJC and are subject to certification by the Bulgarian National&#13;
Audit Office.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                 X.       Trends in Judiciary Budget and Expenditure&#13;
&#13;
59.      The trends in the Budget provision and expenditures in the Judiciary sector are presented below:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                        35&#13;
&amp;#12;                        Table 18: Judicial State Budget Act Funding and Institutional Expenditure&#13;
                                                  (Amount in 1000 BGN)&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                        Annual&#13;
                                     2007          2008          2009          2010        2011       2012         2013     2014          %&#13;
                                                                                                                                        Growth&#13;
&#13;
        Budget Act                 313,120      385,300      438,323        387,705       387,705    400,000     404,000    434,000      4.8&#13;
&#13;
        Actual Expenditures        335,070      418,610      378,622        436,227       422,825    420,243     441,539    460,472      4.7&#13;
&#13;
        Budget Execution Rate&#13;
        (%)                             107          109            86            113          109         105       109         106&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       60.      Table 18 shows that during the period 2007 â&#128;&#147; 2014, there has been a steady increase in the Budget&#13;
       for judiciary at the rate of 4.8 % per year and an increase expenditures at the rate of 4.7% per year. In&#13;
       comparison, the trends in the Total Budget and Total Expenditures during this period have been as follows:&#13;
&#13;
                                            Table 18b: Total Bulgarian State Budget and Expenditures&#13;
                                                            (Amount in Million BGN)&#13;
Year                           2007         2008          2009          2010            2011          2012          2013         2014&#13;
Total Budget&#13;
(calculated amounts)          22,099     25,371       30,362        27,940         28,172         29,844         31,978     33,087&#13;
Total Expenditures            22,103        25,323        25,667         26,755         26,867       27,828        30,418     32,482&#13;
Expenditure as % of&#13;
Budget                          100.0         99.8          84.5           95.8           95.4         93.2          95.1        98.2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       The total budget of the country has risen by 6.4 % per year and total expenditure of the country has risen&#13;
       by 5.9 % per year. The budget execution rate has been 95 % on an average over this period.&#13;
&#13;
       The Budget Execution for the judiciary is presented below:&#13;
&#13;
                                   Figure 1: Budget and Expenditure of the Judiciary (2007-2014)&#13;
&#13;
                      500,000&#13;
                      450,000&#13;
                      400,000&#13;
                      350,000&#13;
                      300,000&#13;
                      250,000                                                                                      Budget&#13;
                      200,000                                                                                      Expenditure&#13;
                      150,000&#13;
                      100,000&#13;
                       50,000&#13;
                               0&#13;
                                      2007 2008 2009 2010 2011 2012 2013 2014&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                            36&#13;
&amp;#12;61.     Figure 1 shows that Expenditure has been higher than the originally approved budget in all years&#13;
except in 2009, when the investigative function was transferred from courts to the police. The average&#13;
budget execution during this period has been 106%, which was largely covered by the supplementary&#13;
budgets passed in these years.&#13;
&#13;
62.      When we compare Bulgariaâ&#128;&#153;s budget allocation to different components of the judicial system â&#128;&#147;&#13;
Courts, Public Prosecution and Legal Aid â&#128;&#147; with the allocation in other COE states the situation emerges as&#13;
follows:&#13;
&#13;
             Table 19: Annual Budget allocations to Judicial Systems: Comparison with CoE states&#13;
&#13;
                               Annual      Budget      Annual Budget for    Annual Budget for Legal    Annual Budget for Judicial&#13;
                               allocated to Courts     Public Prosecution   Aid per inhabitant         System (Court, Prosecution&#13;
                               per     inhabitant      per     inhabitant   (2012)                     and Legal Aid) per inhabitant&#13;
                               (2012)                  (2012)                                          (2012)&#13;
&#13;
 Bulgaria                      17.1 Euros              11.5 Euros           0.80 Euros                 29.5 Euros&#13;
&#13;
 Maximum in CoE states         122.1 Euros             62.1 Euros           53.55 Euros                197.7 Euros&#13;
&#13;
                               (Switzerland)           (Switzerland)        (Norway)                   (Switzerland)&#13;
&#13;
 Minimum in CoE states         2.7 Euros               1.7 Euros            0.02 Euros                 4.7 Euros&#13;
&#13;
                               (Moldova)               (Moldova)            (Albania)                  (Moldova)&#13;
&#13;
 Average for CoE states        34.8 Euros              11.4 Euros           8.63 Euros                 60.6 Euros&#13;
      Source: CEPEJ 2014 (2012 data).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
63.      Table 19 shows that the annual budget allocation per inhabitant for Courts is 17.1 Euros in Bulgaria&#13;
against the average for CoE states of 34.8 Euros. For the entire Judicial System, comprising of Courts, Public&#13;
Prosecution and Legal Aid, the annual budget allocation per inhabitant in Bulgaria is 29.5 Euros, in&#13;
comparison to the average for CoE states of 60.6 Euros. Bulgaria thus provides a lower absolute budget&#13;
allocation (per inhabitant) for its judicial system in comparison to the average of CoE member states.&#13;
&#13;
64.        In terms of GDP per capita, the Bulgariaâ&#128;&#153;s budget allocation to the judicial sector is as follows:&#13;
&#13;
              Table 19b: Annual Budget allocation to Judicial Systems: Comparison to CoE States&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                     Annual Budget for Judicial&#13;
                                                 Annual Budget allocated to&#13;
                                                                                     System (Court, Prosecution&#13;
                                                Courts as % of GDP per capita&#13;
                                                                                    and Legal Aid as % of GDP per&#13;
                                                           (2012)&#13;
                                                                                            capita (2012)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                  Bulgaria                                     0.32                                0.54&#13;
                  Maximum in CoE states                        0.60                                0.82&#13;
                                                     (Bosnia and Herzegovina)            (Bosnia and Herzegovina)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                    37&#13;
&amp;#12;              Minimum in CoE states                       0.06                            0.132&#13;
                                                        (Norway)                        (Norway)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
              Average for CoE states                        0.21                          0.33&#13;
                    Source: CEPEJ 2014 (2012 data)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
65.     Table 19b shows that Bulgariaâ&#128;&#153;s annual budget allocation as a percentage of GDP per capita is&#13;
higher than a rich country like Norway and lower than a poor country like Bosnia and Herzegovina.&#13;
Bulgariaâ&#128;&#153;s allocation to its courts and judicial system on a GDP per capita basis is also above the COE&#13;
averages. In fact only four COE states spend more on their judicial systems relative to GDP per capita than&#13;
Bulgaria (Bosnia, Montenegro, Serbia and UK-N. Ireland). It is important to note that Bulgaria receives&#13;
large scale assistance to strengthen rule of law from EU and other international organizations. As a result,&#13;
the annual budget allocation may be higher than what it would have otherwise been.&#13;
&#13;
66.      A benchmarking of Bulgariaâ&#128;&#153;s judicial budget in comparison to other EU member states in relation&#13;
to GDP is presented in ANNEX 3: Benchmarking of Per Capita State Budget and % of GDP with COE Member&#13;
States. This benchmarking reveals that Bulgariaâ&#128;&#153;s judicial budget allocation as a percentage of GDP is&#13;
second at 0.46%; only Slovenia spends more as a percentage of its GDP on the judiciary (0.53%). The&#13;
benchmarking also shows that Bulgaria is dedicating almost 26 euros per capita for the operation of the&#13;
judiciary compared to an average of over 50 euros per capita for EU Member States. Of the newer EU&#13;
Member States, only Hungary, Poland, Slovakia and Slovenia are spending more per capita than Bulgaria.&#13;
The rest of the former Eastern European countries are spending similar amounts as Bulgaria on their&#13;
judicial system.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                    XI.          Funding Operations of the Judiciary&#13;
&#13;
67.     The breakdown of funding sources for the judicial operations in Bulgaria is as follows:&#13;
&#13;
              Table 20: Funding Judicial Operations: Own Resources and Government Subsidy&#13;
                                                     (Amount in 1000 BGN)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                           2007           2008        2009          2010      2011      2012        2013      2014&#13;
&#13;
 Funded from     Own      79,533       80,367        104,879       132,643   143,318   140,448     140,646   122,326&#13;
 Resources&#13;
&#13;
 Funded        from      262,867       334,802       317,857       292,633   279,297   256,561     275,664   337,072&#13;
 Government Subsidy&#13;
&#13;
 Total Funding Source    342,401       415,169       422,736       425,276   422,615   397,008     416,310   459,398&#13;
&#13;
 %     From      Own       23%            19%         25%           31%       34%       35%         34%       27%&#13;
 Resources&#13;
&#13;
 % From Government         77%            81%         75%           69%       66%       65%         66%       73%&#13;
 Subsidy&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                               38&#13;
&amp;#12;   68.    Table 20 shows that the judiciary is currently funding 27 % of its expenditure from its own sources,&#13;
   whereas the Government is funding 73 % through its subsidy. If we compare court fees with respect to&#13;
   expenditure on courts, the court fees cover 49 % of court expenditures.&#13;
&#13;
   69.      Currently the judiciary is experiencing a reduction in filings which in turn reduces the collection of&#13;
   filing fees. The level of filing fee collection was reduced from a high of 124,009,000 BGN in 2011 and has&#13;
   declined almost each year since to its current level of 105,578,000 BGN in 2014. This is a reduction of&#13;
   18,431,000 BGN or almost 15% over four years. It is anticipated that the amount of filing fees collected will&#13;
   continue to fall in succeeding years (matching the trend of decreasing intake of new court cases).&#13;
&#13;
   70.      The SJC is proposing a restructuring of filing fees that will increase revenue in future years. Under&#13;
   this proposal, some fees would be increased to reflect the actual work being performed by the courts. For&#13;
   example, some fees for administrative cases and privately filed criminal cases are low based on the level&#13;
   of judicial effort and could be increased.13 On the other hand, the 4% proportionate fee charged in civil&#13;
   cases based on the amount of monetary interest can become extremely high in high-value cases and may&#13;
   deter some claimants from making claims or cause them to file only partial claims. Therefore, the SJC has&#13;
   proposed introducing a ceiling to this fee.&#13;
&#13;
   71.      The SJC has submitted the revised court fee plan to the Council of Ministers, through the Deputy&#13;
   Minister of Finance, over the past few years for submission to Parliament. (The Council of Ministers is the&#13;
   only government body authorized to propose legislation to the Parliament.) The Council of Ministers has&#13;
   yet to act on the SJCâ&#128;&#153;s fee proposal. A revision of Bulgariaâ&#128;&#153;s court tariffs is overdue. The SJCâ&#128;&#153;s proposal&#13;
   should be reviewed and evaluated based on its impact on access to Bulgariaâ&#128;&#153;s courts as well as its revenue&#13;
   raising impact.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   XII.    Judicial Budget and Expenditure by Administrative Classifications:&#13;
&#13;
   72.       The composition of the budget14 by Administrative Classifications is as follows:&#13;
&#13;
                   Table 21: Composition of Judiciary Budget by Administrative Classifications&#13;
                                                   (Amount in 1000 BGN)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Administrative&#13;
                    2008         2009           2010         2011           2012          2013        2014         2015&#13;
 Classification&#13;
&#13;
Supreme&#13;
Judicial&#13;
Council            4,776         10,191        7,711         7,711         12,506        11,906      11,962        12,004&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   13&#13;
     Some judges believe raising the filing fees on some administrative and privately filed criminal cases will have the&#13;
   added benefit of leading to a reduction in frivolous filing allowing more time for judges to review other cases.&#13;
&#13;
   14&#13;
      This covers the actual budget approved by the Parliament. There were Supplementary Budgets approved&#13;
   thereafter, for which the break-down by administrative or economic classification is not available.&#13;
&#13;
                                                            39&#13;
&amp;#12;Administrative&#13;
                   2008        2009         2010         2011         2012         2013       2014         2015&#13;
 Classification&#13;
&#13;
Supreme&#13;
Court of&#13;
Cassation         13,889      15,586       13,946       13,946       13,946       13,946      14,091      14,788&#13;
&#13;
Supreme&#13;
Administrative&#13;
Court              9,829      11,136       10,152       10,152       10,152       10,152      10,270      11,331&#13;
&#13;
Prosecution       104,346     120,981      154,908      154,908      158,908     162,708     169,414     183,325&#13;
&#13;
National&#13;
Investigative&#13;
Service            8,878      10,049&#13;
&#13;
Courts&#13;
(including&#13;
administrative&#13;
courts)           200,107     221,247      195,368      195,368      198,868     199,068     221,973     244,455&#13;
&#13;
Investigative&#13;
Services          37,481      42,678&#13;
&#13;
National&#13;
Institute of&#13;
Justice            2,642       3,027        2,578        2,578        2,578       2,578       2,601       3,086&#13;
&#13;
Inspectorate&#13;
under the&#13;
Supreme&#13;
Judicial&#13;
Council            2,752       2,828        2,442        2,442        2,442       3,042       3,089       3,412&#13;
&#13;
Reserves for&#13;
urgent and&#13;
unanticipated&#13;
expenses           600         600           600         600           600         600         600         600&#13;
&#13;
Total             385,300     438,323      387,705      387,705      400,000     404,000     434,000     473,000&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   73.      Table 21 shows that there has been a modest 2.8 % per annum rise in the budget funding for the&#13;
   judiciary sector between 2008 and 2015. There was a reduction in the budget in 2010 due to the transfer&#13;
   of the investigation function to the police department. The judiciary was left with investigations of higher&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                       40&#13;
&amp;#12;order crimes against the nation15. The budget of National Investigative Services and Investigation Services&#13;
were transferred to the Prosecution in 2010.&#13;
&#13;
74.       The composition of budget by administrative classifications for the year 2014 is presented below:&#13;
&#13;
                 Figure 2: Composition of 2014 Judicial Budget by Administrative Classifications&#13;
&#13;
                                           1%      0% Budget Composition&#13;
                                          1%         3%&#13;
                                                          3%&#13;
                                                               2%                            Supreme Judicial Council (SJC)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                             Supreme Court of Cassation&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                             Supreme Administrative&#13;
                                 51%                         39%                             Court&#13;
                                                                                             Prosecution&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                             Courts&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
75.      Figure 2 shows that 51 % of the judicial budget is for the courts, 39 % for the prosecution, and 10&#13;
% for all other judicial institutions. The Supreme Court of Cassation and Supreme Administrative Court&#13;
together have an allocation of 5 % of the judicial budget. The Supreme Judicial Council and the Inspectorate&#13;
under it together have an allocation of 4 % of the judicial budget. The National Institute of Justice has an&#13;
allocation of 1 % of the judicial budget. The budget expenditure follows the same trend.&#13;
&#13;
76.      The budget execution for the different administrative classifications described in Figure 3 and Table&#13;
22 is as follows:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
15&#13;
   The investigators under the District Prosecutorsâ&#128;&#153; offices can investigate any crimes that are assigned to them by the respective district&#13;
prosecutors, however, usually the more complex crimes go to them. The investigators at the National Investigative Service investigate, according&#13;
to the Judicial System Act, cases with special factual or legal complexity, crimes committed abroad, requests for legal assistance from foreign&#13;
countries, as well as other cases specified in law.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      41&#13;
&amp;#12;             Figure 3: Budget and Expenditure by Administrative Classification&#13;
&#13;
500,000&#13;
&#13;
450,000&#13;
&#13;
400,000                                                                                                                                Inspectorate under the&#13;
                                                                                                                                       Supreme Judicial Council&#13;
350,000&#13;
                                                                                                                                       National Institute of Justice&#13;
300,000&#13;
&#13;
250,000                                                                                                                                Courts&#13;
&#13;
200,000&#13;
                                                                                                                                       Prosecution&#13;
150,000&#13;
&#13;
100,000                                                                                                                                Supreme Administrative Court&#13;
&#13;
 50,000&#13;
                                                                                                                                       Supreme Court of Cassation&#13;
         0&#13;
                                               Expenditure&#13;
                       Expenditure&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                        Expenditure&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                Expenditure&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                        Expenditure&#13;
              Budget&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     Budget&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                             Budget&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                      Budget&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                              Budget&#13;
                                                                                                                                       Supreme Judicial Council&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                2010                   2011                    2012                     2013                    2014&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
              Table 22: Budget Execution % by Administrative Classifications&#13;
                                                                      (Expenditure as % of Budget)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              2008                    2009                     2010                    2011           2012       2013           2014&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Supreme Judicial&#13;
Council&#13;
                                              157                      85                      116                     98             50           55             56&#13;
&#13;
Supreme Court of&#13;
Cassation                                     91                       80                      97                      97             97           98            101&#13;
&#13;
Supreme&#13;
Administrative Court                          101                      86                      108                     107            113         107            112&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Prosecution&#13;
                                              112                      109                     111                     108            103         107            108&#13;
&#13;
National&#13;
Investigative Service                         116                      39&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Courts&#13;
                                              109                      87                      115                     112            110         115            108&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                42&#13;
&amp;#12;                                             2008     2009      2010         2011     2012   2013   2014&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                  Investigative&#13;
                  Services                    98      32&#13;
&#13;
                  National Institute of&#13;
                  Justice                    112      89        106          104       115    133   119&#13;
&#13;
                  Inspectorate under&#13;
                  the Supreme Judicial&#13;
                  Council                     87      83        109          103       109    102   104&#13;
&#13;
                   Total Expenditures&#13;
                  as a % of the Budget       109      86        113          109       105    109   106&#13;
&#13;
 77.      Table 22 shows a budget execution by the Supreme Judicial Council that has been consistently low&#13;
 each of the last three years. The SJC has been unable to spend almost 45-50 % of its budget. The SJC should&#13;
 carefully assess its capacity to spend as it prepares future budgets. The highest budget execution by&#13;
 percentage is that of the National Institute of Justice on a consistent basis. Therefore, the Institute also&#13;
 should more accurately assess its needs during its budget preparation. The execution of the judicial budget&#13;
 exceeded the amounts in the State Budget Act for all years with the exception of budget year 2009. The&#13;
 Council of Ministers ordinances dealing with the judiciaryâ&#128;&#153;s budget for the period 2008 â&#128;&#147; 2014 were&#13;
 examined to determine if the judiciary received supplemental funds. There were a number of decrees&#13;
 approved for 2013 and 2014 and only one decree approved in the three prior years. The National Audit&#13;
 Office confirmed that the additional judicial expenditures were authorized.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                          XIII.        Judicial Budget and Expenditure by Economic Classifications&#13;
&#13;
 78.       The composition of the judicial budget by economic classifications is as follows:&#13;
&#13;
                           Table 23: Composition of Judicial Budget by Economic Classification&#13;
                                                        (Amount in 1000 BGN)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      Economic&#13;
                               2008          2009       2010          2011          2012     2013   2014   2015&#13;
    Classification&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Salaries                     213,917        281,385   263,372     263,372&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Other Remuneration            32,700        24,515     19,107      20,000&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Social Security               71,022        66,596     64,596      64,335&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Maintenance                   56,951        55,803     37,544      36,912&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Membership Fees                   10          24           36          36&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                 43&#13;
&amp;#12;     Economic&#13;
                          2008       2009      2010       2011           2012     2013      2014       2015&#13;
   Classification&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Current Expenditure      374,600    428,323   384,655    384,655      396,950    400,950   428,950   463,400&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Capital Expenditure      10,100      9,400     2,450      2,450          2,450    2,450     4,450     9,000&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Reserve                   600        600        600          600         600      600       600        600&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Total                    385,300    438,323   387,705    387,705      400,000    404,000   434,000   473,000&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 79.     From Table 23, it may be noted that the budget was classified only into current and capital&#13;
 expenditures from 2012 onwards; the breakdown of current expenditures into salaries, social security,&#13;
 other remuneration and payments and expenses for maintenance was not included in the budget. This&#13;
 gave more flexibility to the judiciary to use its current budget allocation based on its specific needs each&#13;
 year. The distribution of judicial budget into current and capital expenditures has been as follows:&#13;
&#13;
                    Figure 4: Composition of Judiciary Budget 2014 by Economic Classifications&#13;
&#13;
                                        Capital                Reserve&#13;
                                      Expenditure                0%&#13;
                                          1%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                          Current&#13;
                                                        Expenditure&#13;
                                                           99%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 80.     The Capital Budget has been significantly low. One of the reasons is that the Capital Budget&#13;
 requests submitted by the SJC are not approved in the Budget voted by the Parliament. This is described&#13;
 in Table 24.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                        44&#13;
&amp;#12;                        Table 24: Capital Budget Requests and Approvals by Parliament&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                             Budget Request              Budget Received        Budget&#13;
                                            by Judiciary (BGN            from Parliament     Received as a&#13;
                        Year                      000)                      (BGN 000)        % of Request&#13;
&#13;
                        2008               28,800                   10,100                   35.1%&#13;
&#13;
                        2009               27,109                   9,400                    34.7%&#13;
&#13;
                        2010               31,900                   2,450                    7.7%&#13;
&#13;
                        2011               25,325                   2,450                    9.7%&#13;
&#13;
                        2012               24,761                   2,450                    9.9%&#13;
&#13;
                        2013               19,918                   2,450                    12.3%&#13;
&#13;
                        2014               19,900                   4,450                    22.4%&#13;
                               (Source: Supreme Judicial Council)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
81.      The table shows that a very small proportion of the capital budget requests of the judiciary are&#13;
included in the Budget Act. This leads to lack of resources for the judiciary in regard to modernization. Since&#13;
2007 the Ministry of Justice is responsible for the capital assets of the judiciary and these funds form part&#13;
of MOJâ&#128;&#153;s budget. Since 2009 the Judicial System Act specifies that this responsibilit y extends only to&#13;
immovable capital goods such as court buildings. The change appears to not have impacted SJCâ&#128;&#153;s ability to&#13;
get more funds for movables, i.e. it continuously appears to get insufficient funds. The responsibility over&#13;
capital budget was moved to MOJ because the judiciary was not doing a very good job of managing it. The&#13;
main negative effect of separating the responsibility over movable and immovable properties has been&#13;
that currently the judiciary pays for ordinary repair and MOJ pays for capital repair. Therefore, there have&#13;
been arguments over how to characterize individual repair works, which has led to their postponement.&#13;
&#13;
82.      The expenditures are recorded as per detailed economic classifications. The composition of the&#13;
judicial expenditure by economic classification is presented below.&#13;
&#13;
                  Table 25: Composition of Judicial Expenditure by Economic Classification&#13;
                                                       (Amount in 1000 BGN)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         Economic&#13;
                               2008           2009            2010             2011         2012         2013      2014&#13;
       Classification&#13;
&#13;
    Salaries               256,498           230,348         293,025          274,472      270,374      286,250   288,252&#13;
&#13;
    Other&#13;
    Remuneration           27,413            32,109          34,471           34,513       38,187       35,616    43,833&#13;
&#13;
    Social Security        70,400            67,335          64,520           69,778       70,333       79,083    82,254&#13;
&#13;
    Maintenance            51,437            47,160          42,087           41,632       39,525       39,053    38,600&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                    45&#13;
&amp;#12;          Economic&#13;
                           2008        2009               2010     2011          2012          2013      2014&#13;
        Classification&#13;
&#13;
      Membership Fees       24          44                 37       41            40              39      42&#13;
&#13;
      Current&#13;
      Expenditure         405,772     376,996         434,140     420,436       418,459       440,041   452,981&#13;
&#13;
      Capital&#13;
      Expenditure         12,838       1,624              2,087    2,390         1,783         1,429     7,337&#13;
&#13;
      Total               418,610     378,620         436,227     422,826       420,242       441,470   460,308&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
83.    The composition of judicial expenditure by economic classifications for 2014 is broken down&#13;
below:&#13;
&#13;
               Figure 5: Composition Judicial Expenditure in 2014 by Economic Classifications&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                    Composition of Expenditure in 2014&#13;
                         Salaries                Other Renumeration         Social Security&#13;
                         Maintenance             Membership Fees            Capital Expenditure&#13;
&#13;
                                                     0%     2%&#13;
&#13;
                                                      8%&#13;
&#13;
                                               18%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                9%                63%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
84.    Figure 5 shows that nearly 90% of expenditure is used to support the judiciaryâ&#128;&#153;s human resources&#13;
(63% for salaries, 18 % for Social Security and 9 % on other remuneration). This leaves only 8 % for&#13;
Maintenance and only 2 % for Capital Expenditure. This has been the general trend over several years.&#13;
&#13;
85.       The budget execution by economic classifications over the past 7 years has been as follows:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                            46&#13;
&amp;#12;                         Table 26: Budget Execution by Economic Classification (2008-2014)&#13;
                                                (Expenditure as % of Budget)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          Economic&#13;
                             2008        2009          2010          2011        2012         2013          2014&#13;
        Classification&#13;
&#13;
     Salaries                120          82            111           104&#13;
&#13;
     Other&#13;
     Remuneration            84           131           180           173&#13;
&#13;
     Social Security         99           101           100           108&#13;
&#13;
     Maintenance             90           85            112           113&#13;
&#13;
     Membership Fees         240          183           103           114&#13;
&#13;
     Current&#13;
     Expenditure             108          88            113           109         105          110          106&#13;
&#13;
     Capital&#13;
     Expenditure             127          17            85             98         73           58           165&#13;
&#13;
          Average            109          88            113           109         105          109          106&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
86.     From Table 26, it is clear that budget execution been more than 100 % since 2010 and in six of the&#13;
past seven years. The average budget execution during 2008-2014 has been 106 %. The average budget&#13;
execution of current expenditure has been 106 % and that of capital expenditure has been 89 %. The&#13;
execution percentage for â&#128;&#156;other remunerationâ&#128;&#157; was exceptionally high during 2010 and 2011. The&#13;
breakdown of budget execution for the current budget is not available for 2012-2014 as the budget itself&#13;
did not provide this detail.&#13;
&#13;
87.    The execution of the Capital Budget in 2013 was 58 % while in 2014 it was 165 %. Both of these&#13;
were exceptional. The high capital budget execution in 2014 was due to the completion of building&#13;
construction in Sofia. Expenditure in excess of the originally approved budget is usually done with prior&#13;
approval of the Ministry of Finance, in the form of Supplementary Budgets.&#13;
&#13;
88.     The Ministry of Justice has the responsibility for managing the property of the judiciary; the funds&#13;
for construction and complete refurbishment of real estate; and for property entailed obligations, i.e.&#13;
taxes, fees, rent16. The Table 27 shows the funding approved in the State Budget Act and actual&#13;
expenditures for judicial facilities.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
16&#13;
     The funds for acquiring, using and managing â&#128;&#152;movablesâ&#128;&#153; is made available under the budget of the judiciary.&#13;
&#13;
                                                              47&#13;
&amp;#12;         Table 27: Budget and Expenditure for Acquisition and Renovation of Judicial Facilities&#13;
                                                  (Amount in BGN)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                               State Budget Act       Actual Expenditures       Expenditure %&#13;
&#13;
              2008                 28,000,000             19,614,058                  70&#13;
&#13;
              2009                 29,054,500             11,299,216                  39&#13;
&#13;
              2010                 13,200,000               8,463,789                 64&#13;
&#13;
              2011                 11,400,000             15,507,440                 136&#13;
&#13;
              2012                 11,400,000               9,965,048                 87&#13;
&#13;
              2013                 11,400,000               8,422,942                 74&#13;
&#13;
              2014                 9,814,980                2,656,245                 27&#13;
                (Source: Ministry of Justice).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
89.     The general tendency to under-execute the capital budget demonstrates the complexities involved&#13;
in new space acquisition and major renovation projects. Most of the issues, if not all, are outside the control&#13;
of the MOJ.&#13;
&#13;
90.      The SJC has a minimal capital budget of its own to be used for minor space maintenance and repair&#13;
projects. Some of these minor capital expenditure projects have resulted in disagreements with the MOJ&#13;
as to which monies should be used for the project. This is one of the reasons why the MOJ is considering&#13;
proposing that the SJC assume responsibility for all space acquisition, major renovation as well as the minor&#13;
maintenance and repair projects for which it is already responsible. The proposal for the SJC to manage&#13;
the buildings was part of the draft amendments to the Constitution of Republic of Bulgaria approved at&#13;
first reading in September 2015.&#13;
&#13;
91.       Considering that salaries are a major component of Bulgariaâ&#128;&#153;s judicial budget, a benchmarking with&#13;
other COE member states has been done as shown in ANNEX 4: Benchmarking of Salaries of Judiciary&#13;
with other CoE states. It is evident from Annex 4 that both gross wages of a Supreme Court judge and a&#13;
first instance judge in Bulgaria are lower than in most other CoE states. The only country paying a lower&#13;
wage than Bulgaria is Albania. However, the ratio of gross wages of a judge in comparison to the gross&#13;
average wage is one of the highest in Bulgaria, and is second only to Romania.&#13;
&#13;
92.    The following provisions of the Judicial Systems Act provide for a minimum salary for magistrates&#13;
and judges:&#13;
&#13;
        â&#128;&#156;Article 218 (1). The chairpersons of the Supreme Court of Cassation and of the Supreme&#13;
        Administrative Court, the Prosecutor General and the Director of the National Investigation&#13;
        Service shall have a basic monthly remuneration equal to 90 percent of the remuneration of the&#13;
        chairperson of the Constitutional Court.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                       48&#13;
&amp;#12;        (2) The basic monthly remuneration for the lowest judicial, prosecutorial or investigating&#13;
        magisterial position shall be set at the double amount of the average monthly salary of&#13;
        budget-funded employees, based on data of the National Institute of Statistics.&#13;
        (3) Remunerations for other positions at judicial system bodies shall be set by the Supreme&#13;
        Judicial Council.&#13;
        Article 219. On top of the basic monthly remuneration, judges, prosecutors and investigating&#13;
        magistrates shall be paid additional remuneration for extended work as a judge, prosecutor and&#13;
        an investigating magistrate at the amount of 2 percent for each year of service record, not to&#13;
        exceed 40 percentâ&#128;&#157;.&#13;
&#13;
93.     The salary of civil servants was enhanced in 2012, but there was no equivalent increase in the salary&#13;
of magistrates and judges. Accordingly, about 20 % of judges and magistrates are receiving less than the&#13;
salary prescribed under the above provisions of the Judicial Systems Act. This has led to hardships and&#13;
resentment among judges.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   Conclusions and Recommendations&#13;
&#13;
94.     Performance of the Judiciary: The performance of judiciary in terms of case disposition has been&#13;
quite satisfactory. The clearance rate in Bulgarian courts has been close to 100 % in all of the past 7 years&#13;
and the disposition time has been less than 75 days for all years except 2008, both of which can be&#13;
considered good performance in comparison to other European countries.&#13;
&#13;
95.      Judicial Staffing and Workloads: There are 2,225 approved judge positions, against which, 1,811&#13;
judges are working. The average actual caseload per judge per month at the national level is about 30.&#13;
There are several courts with very low caseloads. As a result, there is scope to redeploy surplus judges to&#13;
other courts with high caseloads. At the national level, however, there does not appear to be a need to&#13;
increase the total number of working Judges. As an initial step in the judicial restructuring process, the SJC&#13;
could consider reducing the number of approved judge positions to the number of currently filled positions&#13;
(1,811). Further restructuring, including possibly additional reductions in judicial positions, could then be&#13;
based on a more refined analysis of workloads and case complexity.&#13;
&#13;
96.     Support Staff Levels: The ratio of staff to inhabitants in Bulgaria is 2.7, which is one of the highest&#13;
in Eastern European countries. However, staffing is not uniform across courts. The SJC should consider&#13;
reducing the ratio at the national level (thereby contributing to cost-savings) and uniformly distributing the&#13;
revised national ratio across courts (thereby improving efficiency).&#13;
&#13;
97.     District and Regional Courts Workloads: There is scope for the judiciary to reorganize itself to&#13;
improve its efficiency and effectiveness based on an assessment of judicial workloads.17 There are presently&#13;
13 district courts where the caseload per judge is less than 10 cases per month. Similarly, there are 6&#13;
regional courts where the caseload is 20 or fewer cases per judge per month. Both of which are well below&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
17&#13;
  For this study the World Bank has only measured the number of cases per court and per judge and has not assessed&#13;
the complexity or the types of cases that are handled in different courts in Bulgaria. A deeper analysis of case&#13;
complexity could result in different conclusions.&#13;
&#13;
                                                       49&#13;
&amp;#12;the average for each type of case. It is likely that the number of judges in these courts can be reduced with&#13;
some judges freed to be redeployed to other courts where there are higher caseloads. Surplus judges in&#13;
district courts could be redeployed within regional courts located in the same district centers to avoid any&#13;
discomfort due to re-location18. In addition, regional courts with low caseloads could be consolidated with&#13;
other regional courts or they could be retained as territorial units of other, larger regional courts.&#13;
Considering that there are only about 4 judges in regional courts on average, redeployment of judges to&#13;
other courts may not be appropriate.&#13;
&#13;
98.     Appellate Courts: There are 147 judges working in 6 appellate courts (including 1 Appellate Military&#13;
Court). On average, there are 25 judges per court who each hear only 8.4 cases per month and resolve only&#13;
7.1 cases per month. It may be difficult to justify this level of appellate court staffing given the existing&#13;
caseload. The SJC should consider consolidating the 6 appellate courts into 2 or 3 appellate courts and&#13;
redeploy surplus judges elsewhere, so that the average appellate caseload per judge is around 25 cases&#13;
per month â&#128;&#147; closer to the overall average of 30 cases per judge per month for all Bulgariaâ&#128;&#153;s courts.&#13;
&#13;
99.     Military Courts: There are 19 judges working in 4 military courts. The caseload per judge is only&#13;
2.4 cases per month. It is likely difficult to justify the existing number of military judges given the caseload.&#13;
One court with 2 judges could manage the existing caseload. The SJC should consider consolidating 4&#13;
military courts into a single military court to handle the existing caseload. Surplus judges could be&#13;
redeployed elsewhere, if needed. Alternatively, the SJC, MOJ and military leadership could consider&#13;
moving all military cases into the general courts and closing the military court system as suggested by the&#13;
MOJ.&#13;
&#13;
100. Investigation Magistrates: the average caseload per Investigation Magistrate at the National&#13;
Investigative Service in 2013 was estimated to be 11.89 cases, of which 5.79 cases have been completed&#13;
and just 0.56 have ended with an opinion for bringing an indictment to court. This is very low workload and&#13;
even lower indictment rate. According to the Ministry of Justice, this caseload has declined further since&#13;
2013. The government should carefully examine the potential workload for these magistrates and decide&#13;
how many are required to do the job at hand. The surplus judges could be redeployed elsewhere.&#13;
&#13;
101. Options for Surplus Judges: In view of the analysis and conclusions in this paper, a number of&#13;
judges may be determined to be surplus because the SJC may not be able to identify suitable places for&#13;
their redeployment. However, under Bulgarian law, judges cannot be removed from service except by way&#13;
of attrition. Hence, the government may want to consider options to allow these judges to retire or&#13;
redeploy within the government as alternative exit routes to changing the law.&#13;
&#13;
102. Secondment of Judges: At present, there are about 114 judges seconded to other courts through&#13;
agreements between the court presidents. There are two major issues regarding the current&#13;
administration of the program: the appearance of favoritism in the assignment of judges to higher courts&#13;
with associated increase in wages and the possibility of court presidents influencing the decision of those&#13;
seconded judges who want to maintain their secondment assignment. To address these issues the SJC&#13;
should consider terminating the secondment program as it is currently administered by the court&#13;
presidents and assume direct responsibility itself for deciding the placement of seconded judges. The SJCâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
18&#13;
 It is acknowledged this could considered as demotion by some judges. Hence, the pay and title must be protected.&#13;
On the other hand, it may be possible for example to redeploy judges from other District Courts to Sofia City Court.&#13;
&#13;
                                                        50&#13;
&amp;#12;decisions should then be based on a careful and detailed analysis of workloads across Bulgariaâ&#128;&#153;s courts and&#13;
the circumstances under which full-time vacancies have been generated from the termination of&#13;
magistrates on any of the grounds listed in Article 165 of the Judicial Systems Act, i.e., tendering of&#13;
resignation, disciplinary termination, etc. In the event of such circumstances, secondment of magistrates&#13;
may remain the most expedient manner of swift and effective resolution of workload issues.&#13;
&#13;
103. Under-Funded Judicial Budget Request: Despite high judicial expenditures in relation to its per&#13;
capita GDP (based on comparison with EU and neighboring countries), Bulgaria has underfunded its&#13;
judiciary in relation to the SJCâ&#128;&#153;s budget request and the statutory required minimum salaries for judges.&#13;
Ninety-eight percent of Bulgariaâ&#128;&#153;s judicial budget is for current expenditure, the majority of which is for&#13;
salaries and other remuneration. However, current budget levels are insufficient to pay even the minimum&#13;
salary for magistrates prescribed under law. The capital budget is also not adequate to meet judicial needs&#13;
as only about 10-15 % of the judiciaryâ&#128;&#153;s capital budget requests are approved by the Parliament. The low&#13;
execution rate for the capital budget had been of a concern until 2013, but in 2014, the execution rate for&#13;
the Capital Budget reached 165 %.&#13;
&#13;
104. Judicial Restructuring and Cost Savings: In light of the funding uncertainty faced by the judiciary&#13;
and the opportunities for restructuring the judicial system identified in this paper, it may be possible for&#13;
the SJC, MOJ and MOF to reach agreement on a medium term funding strategy for the judiciary. Such an&#13;
agreement could be based on a judicial restructuring plan that leads to a more efficient court system with&#13;
a more equitable distribution of workload (by redeploying judges, consolidating courts, and shrinking&#13;
judicial and staff positions as necessary) that can be fully funded (both current and capital expenditures)&#13;
without resort to annual debates over supplemental budget requests. Given the overall costs, it is&#13;
recommended that a proportion of any savings from judicial restructuring be used to finance increases in&#13;
salaries and higher capital expenditure.&#13;
&#13;
105. Court Fee Structure: There is a scope for the judiciary to increase its own revenues by reforming&#13;
and raising filing fees. For a number of years, the SJC has submitted proposals to the Council of Ministers&#13;
seeking support to submit a revised court fee structure to Parliament for approval. The Council of Ministers&#13;
has not acted on the SJC proposal. A revision of the tariff is overdue and the SJC proposal should be&#13;
evaluated based on its impact on access to Bulgariaâ&#128;&#153;s courts and on the court systemsâ&#128;&#153; revenue raising&#13;
capacity. In the determination of the revised court fee structure, it would be necessary to strike a balance&#13;
between the need to boost own revenues in the judiciary budget and the right of access to justice for&#13;
citizens and legal entities.&#13;
&#13;
106. Predictability of Government Subsidy: The judiciary has raised concerns that any economies&#13;
realized through reduced costs or increased income that it is able to achieve through judicial restructuring&#13;
would result in the reduction of the governmentâ&#128;&#153;s subsidy to the judicial budget leaving overall&#13;
expenditures at their present insufficient level. These concerns have been aggravated by the latest State&#13;
Budget Act which for the first time provided that if the judiciary fails to reach the budgeted levels of its&#13;
own income, the state budget subsidy would not be raised to compensate any shortfall. It is noteworthy,&#13;
however, that in its Decision No 4/2015, the Constitutional Court declared this provision of the State&#13;
Budget Act to be contrary to the Constitution and would therefore not be implemented. The SJC would like&#13;
greater predictability in the resources they receive from the government budget so that they can undertake&#13;
necessary reorganization and restructuring of the courts and judiciary with confidence that they will have&#13;
access to sufficient resources to manage a restructured judicial system.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                    51&#13;
&amp;#12;107. Preparing Medium-Term Budget as Per Plans of Judiciary: It is recommended that SJC prepare a&#13;
medium-term Action Plan based on the Justice Sector Reform Strategy approved by the Council of&#13;
Ministers in December 2014 and approved by National Assembly in January 2015. The Action Plan could&#13;
then be used to develop the judiciaryâ&#128;&#153;s medium term financial requirements. The medium term financing&#13;
plan could incorporate the minimum salary for judges and other judicial officials as prescribed under law.&#13;
It also is recommended that the judiciaryâ&#128;&#153;s full capital budget needs in reference to their modernization&#13;
plan are included in the financing plan. The medium term financing plan could account for any funding&#13;
expected to be received from the EU or other international organizations for judicial modernization. The&#13;
judiciaryâ&#128;&#153;s spending should be aligned to the performance of its functions. A realistic medium-term budget&#13;
forecast should be based on an analysis of the spending efficiency in the system and tied to plans for the&#13;
achievement of the goals defined in the Judicial Reform Strategy. It is also recommended that the Ministry&#13;
of Justice and Ministry of Finance review this medium term financing framework and have an open&#13;
discussion with the SJC in order to reach consensus on a stable funding plan.&#13;
&#13;
108. One option that a number of Latin American countries have used to increase the predictability in&#13;
government funding to the judiciary is linking the government subsidy to the judicial budget to GDP. If all&#13;
the parties can agree on a formula for sufficient and consistent government subsidies to the judicial budget,&#13;
then this could help to build trust between the judiciary and the Government and motivate the former to&#13;
reform. However, this linkage does not appear to have any impact on judicial performance, including the&#13;
length of court processes.19 In addition, earmarks make the budget allocation process more rigid. They&#13;
undermine allocative efficiency by preventing the government from moving resources to meet changing&#13;
needs; they may reduce technical efficiency by undermining managerial incentives; and there is a risk of&#13;
such earmarks proliferating.&#13;
&#13;
109. Decentralization of Expenditure Decisions: Presently courts must receive prior authorization from&#13;
the SJC for every expenditure that they make from the budget, while every fee that a court receives is&#13;
transferred to the SJC. Court presidents cannot retain any funds or take any expenditure decisions on their&#13;
own. The SJC could consider allowing court presidents to retain some percentage of the fees that their&#13;
courts collect. Considering that some courts collect fees to a significantly lesser extent in comparison to&#13;
their maintenance requirements, SJC could use the pool of fees collected to address the needs of resource-&#13;
deficient courts. The objective of this recommendation is to empower courts to use a portion of their&#13;
collected fees for the maintenance and development of their respective courts. The SJC could match this&#13;
decentralization of authority with specific rules defining the object and method by which court presidents&#13;
could use those funds and providing procedures for holding court presidents more accountable for the use&#13;
of these retained funds. Also, a results agreement could be signed between the SJC and court presidents&#13;
at the beginning of the year and the latter made accountable for results.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
19&#13;
  OECD (2013), â&#128;&#156;What makes civil justice effective?â&#128;&#157; OECD Economics Department, Policy Notes, No. 18 June 2013,&#13;
at p.5.&#13;
&#13;
                                                      52&#13;
&amp;#12;                              ANNEX 1: Case Disposal and Workload between 2008 and 2014&#13;
&#13;
Ð&#134;. Movement of cases 2008&#13;
&#13;
                                    Pending at                                                  Completed cases              Pending&#13;
                                       the        Received                                                                    at the&#13;
                                                                    Total for                           Within 3 months&#13;
           COURTS                   beginning    during the                                                                   end of&#13;
                                                                    hearing             Total&#13;
                                      of the        year                                                                       the&#13;
                                                                                                        Number       %&#13;
                                      period                                                                                  period&#13;
&#13;
 Appellate courts                     3124         10634             13758             11554             8865       77%       2204&#13;
&#13;
 Military courts                       169          1934             2103               1978             1842       93%        125&#13;
&#13;
 District courts + Sofia CC           33503        78600            112103             84258             59026      70%       27845&#13;
&#13;
 RC in district centers +Sofia&#13;
 RC                                   53664        229926           283590             233622           175188      75%       49968&#13;
&#13;
 Regional courts (RC)                 20316        91595            111911             92525             73612      80%       19386&#13;
&#13;
 Administrative courts                7448         34060             41508             32438             21226      65%       9070&#13;
&#13;
         Total cases                 11,0776      44,6749           564,973           456,375           339,759     74%      108,598&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Ð&#134;Ð&#134;. Number of judges according to staff and workload of judges according to staff in 2008&#13;
&#13;
                                            Number of judges                        Workload according to staff TOTAL&#13;
             COURTS&#13;
                                         according to staff TOTAL           To all cases for hearing       To total completed cases&#13;
&#13;
 Appellate courts                                  135                               8.49                           7.13&#13;
&#13;
 Military courts                                   31                                5.65                           5.32&#13;
&#13;
 District courts + Sofia CC                        744                               12.56                          9.44&#13;
&#13;
 RC in district centers +Sofia RC                  562                               42.05                          34.64&#13;
&#13;
 Regional courts (RC)                              390                               23.91                          19.74&#13;
&#13;
 Administrative courts                             263                               13.15                          10.28&#13;
&#13;
              TOTAL                               2,125                              22.16                          17.90&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                53&#13;
&amp;#12;Ð&#134;. Movement of cases in 2009&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                          Completed cases&#13;
                               Pending at&#13;
                                            Received&#13;
                                  the                            Total for                     Within 3 months          Pending at the end&#13;
         COURTS                            during the&#13;
                              beginning of                       hearing                                                  of the period&#13;
                                              year                                Total&#13;
                               the period&#13;
                                                                                             Number         %&#13;
&#13;
 Appellate courts                2233             10433              12666       10953         8289         76%               1713&#13;
&#13;
 Military courts                  123              1724              1847         1766         1702         96%                81&#13;
&#13;
 District courts + Sofia CC      27816            81323           109139         85747        63085         74%               23392&#13;
&#13;
 RC in district centers&#13;
 +Sofia RC                       49920            285547          335467         281985       227080        81%               53482&#13;
&#13;
 Regional courts (RC)            19411            109284          128695         110771       92541         84%               17924&#13;
&#13;
 Administrative courts           9124             36040              45164       35710        23916         67%               9454&#13;
&#13;
        Total cases              99,503           524,351        632,978        526,932       416,613       79%              106,046&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Ð&#134;Ð&#134;. Number of judges according to staff, workload according to staff actual workload of judges for 2009&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                             Workload according to&#13;
                                                                                                                  Actual workload&#13;
                                                                 staff TOTAL&#13;
&#13;
                                     Number of&#13;
                                                                                            Men-month&#13;
           COURTS                 judges according            To all          To total                        To all        To total&#13;
                                                                                            worked out&#13;
                                   to staff TOTAL           cases for        completed                      cases for      completed&#13;
                                                             hearing           cases                         hearing         cases&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Appellate courts                         140                 7.54             6.52            1436           8.82             7.63&#13;
&#13;
 Military courts                           30                 5.13             4.91            295.83         6.24             5.97&#13;
&#13;
 District courts + Sofia CC               752                12.09             9.50            7241.8        15.07            11.84&#13;
&#13;
 RC in district centers +Sofia&#13;
                                          572&#13;
 RC                                                          48.87             41.08          5794.45        57.89            48.66&#13;
&#13;
 Regional courts (RC)                     398                26.95             23.19          3999.71        32.18            27.69&#13;
&#13;
 Administrative courts                    270                13.94             11.02          2771.93        16.29            12.88&#13;
&#13;
            TOTAL                         2,162              24.40             20.31         21539.72        29.39            24.46&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      54&#13;
&amp;#12;Ð&#134;. Movement of cases in 2010&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                        Completed cases&#13;
                               Pending&#13;
                                at the          Received                                                                 Pending at&#13;
                                                               Total for                        Within 3 months&#13;
          COURTS              beginning        during the                                                                the end of&#13;
                                                               hearing&#13;
                                of the            year                         Total                                     the period&#13;
                                period                                                       Number            %&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Appellate courts                1659            11488          13147          11286           9472           84%          1861&#13;
&#13;
 Military courts                  81             2001            2082           1951           1908           98%           131&#13;
&#13;
 District courts + Sofia CC      23433           88362          111795         88742          70866           80%          23053&#13;
&#13;
 RC in district centers&#13;
 +Sofia RC                       53481           340638         394119         334503         289668          87%          59616&#13;
&#13;
 Regional courts (RC)            17940           138327         156267         138991         124111          89%          17276&#13;
&#13;
 Administrative courts           9443            39510          48953          38199          27881           73%          10754&#13;
&#13;
        Total cases              106037          620326         726363         613672         523906          85%         112691&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Ð&#134;Ð&#134;. Number of judges according to staff, workload according to staff actual workload of judges for 2010&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                             Workload according to&#13;
                                                                                                               Actual workload&#13;
                                                                 staff TOTAL&#13;
                                     Number of                                              Men-&#13;
                                       judges                                              month&#13;
            COURTS&#13;
                                    according to              To all        To total       worked           To all       To total&#13;
                                    staff TOTAL             cases for      completed        out           cases for     completed&#13;
                                                             hearing         cases                         hearing        cases&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Appellate courts                         141                 7.77           6.67          1405.14          9.36           8.03&#13;
&#13;
 Military courts                          28                  6.20           5.81          280.50           7.42           6.96&#13;
&#13;
 District courts + Sofia CC               759                12.27           9.74          7160.95         15.61          12.39&#13;
&#13;
 RC in district centers +Sofia&#13;
                                          577&#13;
 RC                                                          56.92           48.31         6031.49         65.34          55.46&#13;
&#13;
 Regional courts (RC)                     394                33.05           29.40         3879.34         40.28          35.83&#13;
&#13;
 Administrative courts                    266                15.34           11.97         2770.29         17.67          13.79&#13;
&#13;
             TOTAL                        2165               27.96           23.62        21527.71         33.74          28.51&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                     55&#13;
&amp;#12;Ð&#134;. Movement of cases in 2011&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                              Completed cases&#13;
                                                                                                                               Pending&#13;
                                  Pending at        Received                                                                    at the&#13;
                                                                   Total for                           Within 3 months&#13;
           COURTS               the beginning      during the                                                                   end of&#13;
                                                                   hearing&#13;
                                of the period         year                          Total                                        the&#13;
                                                                                                      Number           %        period&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Appellate courts                   1820            12542          14362           12351             10966            89%        2011&#13;
&#13;
  Military courts                     131            1407           1538            1463               1425            97%         75&#13;
&#13;
  District courts + Sofia CC         23061           92439         115500           90801             71594            79%        24699&#13;
&#13;
  RC in district centers&#13;
  +Sofia RC                          59833          351132         410965           347829            297853           86%        63136&#13;
&#13;
  Regional courts (RC)               17259          148318         165577           148612            134854           91%        16965&#13;
&#13;
  Administrative courts              10767           44177          54944           42724             32178            75%        12220&#13;
&#13;
         Total cases                 112871         650015         762886           643780            548870           85%     119106&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Ð&#134;Ð&#134;. Number of judges according to staff, workload according to staff actual workload of judges for 2011&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                      Workload according to staff&#13;
                                                                                                                Actual workload&#13;
                                                               TOTAL&#13;
                                       Number of&#13;
                                                                                             Men-&#13;
                                        judges&#13;
                                                                                            month&#13;
              COURTS                   according&#13;
                                                         To all          To total           worked                            To total&#13;
                                        to staff                                                         To all cases for&#13;
                                                       cases for        completed            out                             completed&#13;
                                        TOTAL                                                               hearing&#13;
                                                        hearing           cases                                                cases&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Appellate courts                           142         8.43               7.25            1441.40            9.96            8.57&#13;
&#13;
  Military courts                             27         4.75               4.52            270.00             5.70            5.42&#13;
&#13;
  District courts + Sofia CC                 751         12.82              10.08           7197.57            16.05          12.62&#13;
&#13;
  RC in district centers +Sofia RC           573         59.77              50.59           5847.50            70.28          59.48&#13;
&#13;
  Regional courts (RC)                       385         35.84              32.17           3803.71            43.53          39.07&#13;
&#13;
  Administrative courts                      269         17.02              13.24           2800.57            19.62          15.26&#13;
&#13;
               TOTAL                        2147         29.61              24.99       21360.75               35.71           30.14&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                 56&#13;
&amp;#12;Ð&#134;. Movement of cases in 2012&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                 Completed cases&#13;
&#13;
                               Pending at the         Received       Total                                                     Pending at&#13;
                                                                                                       Within 3 months&#13;
          COURTS                beginning of         during the       for                                                      the end of&#13;
                                 the period             year        hearing             Total                                  the period&#13;
                                                                                                     Number         %&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Appellate courts                    2007             13025            15032           12675         11321        89%           2357&#13;
&#13;
  Military courts                      75              1501              1576           1472           1444        98%            104&#13;
&#13;
  District courts + Sofia CC         24948             97074        122022              96694         77009        80%           25328&#13;
&#13;
  RC in district centers&#13;
  +Sofia RC                          63481            332322        395803             331335         286026       86%           64468&#13;
&#13;
  Regional courts (RC)               16982            133396        150378             133328         119893       90%           17050&#13;
&#13;
  Administrative courts              12265             46914            59179           44666         32250        72%           14513&#13;
&#13;
         Total cases                 119,758          624,232       743,990            620,170        527,943      85%          123,820&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Ð&#134;Ð&#134;. Number of judges according to staff, workload according to staff actual workload of judges for 2012&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                       Workload according to staff&#13;
                                                                                                                      Actual workload&#13;
                                                                TOTAL&#13;
                                       Number of&#13;
                                         judges                                                   Men-month&#13;
             COURTS&#13;
                                      according to                           To total             worked out         To all      To total&#13;
                                      staff TOTAL     To all cases for&#13;
                                                                            completed                              cases for    completed&#13;
                                                         hearing&#13;
                                                                              cases                                 hearing       cases&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Appellate courts                           158           7.93                 6.69                1679.86          8.95          7.55&#13;
&#13;
  Military courts                            27            4.86                 4.54                306.00           5.15          4.81&#13;
&#13;
  District courts + Sofia CC                 767           13.26                10.51               7331.55         16.64         13.19&#13;
&#13;
  RC in district centers +Sofia RC           575           57.36                48.02               5519.27         71.71         60.03&#13;
&#13;
  Regional courts (RC)                       381           32.89                29.16               3874.94         38.81         34.41&#13;
&#13;
  Administrative courts                      268           18.40                13.89               2720.91         21.75         16.42&#13;
&#13;
              TOTAL                         2,176          28.49                23.75              21,432.53        34.71         28.94&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                   57&#13;
&amp;#12;Ð&#134;. Movement of cases in 2013&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                              Completed cases&#13;
&#13;
                                Pending at        Received                                                                     Pending at&#13;
                                                                 Total for                         Within 3 months&#13;
          COURTS              the beginning      during the                                                                    the end of&#13;
                                                                 hearing&#13;
                              of the period         year                              Total                                    the period&#13;
                                                                                                 Number             %&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Appellate courts                 2,356           12,792             15,148       12,752          11,372           89%           2,396&#13;
&#13;
 Military courts                  104              1,230              1,334          1,286        1,264            98%            48&#13;
&#13;
 District courts + Sofia CC      25,412           92,270          117,682         91,226          71,293           78%          26,456&#13;
&#13;
 RC in district centers&#13;
 +Sofia RC                       64,529           304,631         369,160        306,383         257,171           84%          62,777&#13;
&#13;
 Regional courts (RC)            17,059           122,770         139,829        123,681         110,050           89%          16,148&#13;
&#13;
 Administrative courts           14,537           46,556             61,093       48,497          35,503           73%          12,596&#13;
&#13;
        Total cases              123,997          580,249         704,246        583,825         486,653           83%          120421&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Ð&#134;Ð&#134;. Number of judges according to staff, workload according to staff actual workload of judges for 2013&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                     Workload according to staff&#13;
                                                                                                                    Actual workload&#13;
                                                              TOTAL&#13;
                                   Number of&#13;
                                     judges                                                   Men-month&#13;
            COURTS&#13;
                                  according to                             To total           worked out                        To total&#13;
                                  staff TOTAL      To all cases for                                             To all cases&#13;
                                                                          completed                                            completed&#13;
                                                      hearing                                                   for hearing&#13;
                                                                            cases                                                cases&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Appellate courts                     159               7.94                  6.68              1753.12            8.64           7.27&#13;
&#13;
 Military courts                        27              4.12                  3.97              271.50             4.91           4.74&#13;
&#13;
 District courts + Sofia CC           768               12.77                 9.90              7701.02            15.28          11.85&#13;
&#13;
 RC in district centers +Sofia&#13;
                                      618&#13;
 RC                                                     49.78                 41.31             5580.30            66.15          54.90&#13;
&#13;
 Regional courts (RC)                 373               31.24                 27.63             3833.96            36.47          32.26&#13;
&#13;
 Administrative courts                269               18.93                 15.02             2659.82            22.97          18.23&#13;
&#13;
             TOTAL                   2,214              26.51                 21.97            21,799.72           32.31          26.78&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                58&#13;
&amp;#12;Ð&#134;. Movement of cases in 2014&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                              Resolved cases&#13;
&#13;
                                 Pending at         Received                                                              Pending at&#13;
                                                                     Total for                     Within 3 months&#13;
           COURTS              the beginning       during the                                                             the end of&#13;
                                                                     hearing&#13;
                               of the period          year                           Total                                the period&#13;
                                                                                                 Number           %&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Appellate courts                 2,374            12,497           14,871         12,547        11,153         89%        2,324&#13;
&#13;
  Military courts                   48                498                546          517          480           93%          29&#13;
&#13;
  District courts + Sofia CC      26,510            88,720           115,230        89,473        68,300         76%        25,757&#13;
&#13;
  RC in district centers&#13;
  +Sofia RC                       62,932            280,788          343,720        288,648      246,197         85%        55,072&#13;
&#13;
  Regional courts (RC)            16,159            109,802          125,961        111,992      100,244         90%        13,969&#13;
&#13;
  Administrative courts           12,614            42,355           54,969         43,285        31,293         72%        11,684&#13;
&#13;
         Total cases              120,637           534,660          655,297        546,462      457,667         84%       108,835&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Ð&#134;Ð&#134;. Number of judges according to staff, workload according to staff actual workload of judges for 2014&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                            Workload according to staff&#13;
                                                                                                                Actual workload&#13;
                                                                     TOTAL&#13;
                                                                                                Men-&#13;
                                  Number of judges&#13;
                                                                                               month&#13;
            COURTS                according to staff&#13;
                                                                                  To total     worked                      To total&#13;
                                       TOTAL                To all cases for                               To all cases&#13;
                                                                                 completed      out                       completed&#13;
                                                               hearing                                     for hearing&#13;
                                                                                   cases                                    cases&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Appellate courts                          162                  7.65              6.45        1759.42         8.45         7.13&#13;
&#13;
  Military courts                           25                   1.82              1.72        229.00          2.38         2.26&#13;
&#13;
  District courts + Sofia CC                777                  12.36             9.60        7437.35         15.49        12.03&#13;
&#13;
  RC in district centers +Sofia&#13;
                                            631&#13;
  RC                                                             45.39             38.12       5806.19         59.20        49.71&#13;
&#13;
  Regional courts (RC)                      361                  29.08             25.85       3774.26         33.37        29.67&#13;
&#13;
  Administrative courts                     269                  17.03             13.41       2712.96         20.26        15.95&#13;
&#13;
             TOTAL                         2,225                24.54              20.47      21,719.18        30.17        25.16&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                59&#13;
&amp;#12;             ANNEX 2: Court-Wise Actual Workloads between 2008 and 2014&#13;
&#13;
2008: Graph on workload per approved position in District Courts with reference to (1) completed&#13;
                                   cases and (2) all cases:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              60&#13;
&amp;#12;2008: Graph on workload per approved position in Regional Courts in District Towns with reference to&#13;
                              (1) completed cases and (2) all cases:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                61&#13;
&amp;#12;2008: Graph on workload per approved position in Regional Courts with reference to (1) all and (2)&#13;
                                      completed cases:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                               62&#13;
&amp;#12;2009: Graph on (1) workload per approved position and (2) actual workload in District Courts with&#13;
                       reference to (1) completed cases and (2) all cases:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                               63&#13;
&amp;#12;2009: Graph on (1) workload per approved position and (2) actual workload in Regional Courts in&#13;
             District Towns with reference to (1) completed cases and (2) all cases:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              64&#13;
&amp;#12;2009: Graph on actual workload in Regional Courts with reference to (1) all and (2) completed cases:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                65&#13;
&amp;#12;2010: Graph on (1) workload per approved position and (2) actual workload in District Courts with&#13;
                       reference to (1) completed cases and (2) all cases:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                               66&#13;
&amp;#12;2010: Graph on (1) workload per approved position and (2) actual workload in Regional Courts in&#13;
             District Towns with reference to (1) completed cases and (2) all cases:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              67&#13;
&amp;#12;2010: Graph on actual workload in Regional Courts with reference to (1) all and (2) completed cases:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  68&#13;
&amp;#12;2011: Graph on (1) workload per approved position and (2) actual workload in District Courts with&#13;
                       reference to (1) completed cases and (2) all cases:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                               69&#13;
&amp;#12;2011: Graph on (1) workload per approved position and (2) actual workload in Regional Courts in&#13;
             District Towns with reference to (1) completed cases and (2) all cases:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              70&#13;
&amp;#12;2011: Graph on actual workload in Regional Courts with reference to (1) all and (2) completed cases:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  71&#13;
&amp;#12;2012: Graph on (1) workload per approved position and (2) actual workload in District Courts with&#13;
                       reference to (1) completed cases and (2) all cases:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                               72&#13;
&amp;#12;2012: Graph on (1) workload per approved position and (2) actual workload in Regional Courts in&#13;
             District Towns with reference to (1) completed cases and (2) all cases:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              73&#13;
&amp;#12;2012: Graph on actual workload in Regional Courts with reference to (1) all and (2) completed cases:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  74&#13;
&amp;#12;2013: Graph on actual workload in District Courts with reference to (1) completed cases and (2) all cases:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                   75&#13;
&amp;#12;2013: Graph on actual workload in Regional Courts in District Towns with reference to (1) completed&#13;
                                     cases and (2) all cases:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                76&#13;
&amp;#12;2013: Graph on actual workload in Regional Courts with reference to all cases:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     77&#13;
&amp;#12;78&#13;
&amp;#12;2014: Graph on actual workload in District Courts with reference to (1) completed cases and (2) all cases:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                   79&#13;
&amp;#12;2014: Graph on actual workload in Regional Courts in District Towns with reference to (1) completed&#13;
                                     cases and (2) all cases:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                80&#13;
&amp;#12;2014: Graph on actual workload in Regional Courts with reference to all cases:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     81&#13;
&amp;#12;82&#13;
&amp;#12;ANNEX 3: Benchmarking of Per Capita State Budget and % of GDP with CoE Member States&#13;
                                      (Amount in Euros)&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                              State Court&#13;
                                    State Budget       Per Capita State&#13;
          Country   Population                                               2014 GDP         Budget as a&#13;
                                 Allocated to Courts    Court Budget&#13;
                                                                                               % of GDP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Austria             8,387,742            NA&#13;
&#13;
Belgium             10,839,905           NA&#13;
&#13;
Bulgaria            7,364,570       191,414,387                25.99       42,011,000,000       0.46%&#13;
&#13;
Croatia             4,412,137        62,426,606                14.15       43,085,000,000       0.14%&#13;
&#13;
Cyprus               804,536         49,511,239                61.54       17,506,000,000       0.28%&#13;
&#13;
Czech republic      10,517,247      429,944,098                40.88      154,939,000,000       0.28%&#13;
&#13;
Denmark             5,560,628            NA                        -&#13;
&#13;
Estonia             1,340,194        35,932,954                26.81       19,526,000,000       0.18%&#13;
&#13;
Finland             5,375,276       286,003,350                53.21      204,015,000,000       0.14%&#13;
&#13;
France              65,026,885           NA                        -&#13;
&#13;
Germany             81,751,602           NA                        -&#13;
&#13;
Greece              11,309,885           NA                        -&#13;
&#13;
Hungary             9,986,000       361,822,453                36.23      103,303,000,000       0.35%&#13;
&#13;
Ireland             4,581,269       192,576,000                42.04      185,412,000,000       0.10%&#13;
&#13;
Italy               60,626,442     4,300,429,606               70.93      1,616,048,000,000     0.27%&#13;
&#13;
Latvia              2,229,600        52,833,365                23.70       24,058,000,000       0.22%&#13;
&#13;
Lithuania           3,244,600        80,122,945                24.69       36,288,000,000       0.22%&#13;
&#13;
Luxembourg           511,840             NA                        -&#13;
&#13;
Malta                417,617         12,829,000                30.72       7,962,000,000        0.16%&#13;
&#13;
Netherlands         16,655,799     1,606,309,000               96.44      653,476,000,000       0.25%&#13;
&#13;
Poland              38,200,000     1,677,599,570               43.92      413,133,000,000       0.41%&#13;
&#13;
Portugal            10,636,979      648,844,787                61.00      174,384,000,000       0.37%&#13;
&#13;
Romania             21,431,298      517,675,070                24.16      150,665,000,000       0.34%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              83&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                                      State Court&#13;
                                                        State Budget           Per Capita State&#13;
          Country                 Population                                                         2014 GDP         Budget as a&#13;
                                                     Allocated to Courts        Court Budget&#13;
                                                                                                                       % of GDP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Slovakia                         5,435,273             202,196,674                      37.20    75,215,000,000       0.27%&#13;
&#13;
  Slovenia                         2,050,189             197,422,295                      96.29    37,246,000,000       0.53%&#13;
&#13;
  Spain                           45,989,016                  NA                             -&#13;
&#13;
  Sweden                           9,415,570             684,576,783                      72.71   430,258,000,000       0.16%&#13;
&#13;
  United       Kingdom&#13;
  (England/Wales)                 55,200,000            1,937,810,000                     35.11&#13;
&#13;
  United          Kingdom&#13;
  (Scotland)                       5,222,100             281,896,020                      53.98&#13;
&#13;
  United         Kingdom&#13;
  (Northern Ireland)               1,799,392             126,654,000                      70.39   2,222,361,000,000&#13;
&#13;
                                 276,946,088           13,936,830,202                     50.32   6,610,891,000,000     0.21%&#13;
&#13;
  EU28 Average                  12,588,458.55          633,492,281.91                     50.32&#13;
          (Source: European Commission for the Efficiency of Justice (CEPEJ) June 2013)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Bulgaria is dedicating almost 26 euros per capita for the operation of the judiciary compared to over an&#13;
average of over 50 euros per capita for all EU Member States. Of the new Member States Hungary, Poland,&#13;
Slovakia and Slovenia are spending more per capita than Bulgaria. The rest of the former Eastern European&#13;
countries in the EU are spending similar amounts as Bulgaria on their judicial system.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                    84&#13;
&amp;#12;            Per Capita State Court Budgets and % of GDP of EU Candidate and Potential Candidates&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                      Per Capita                      Court&#13;
                                                                  State Budget          State                         State&#13;
                                                                  Allocated to          Court                       Budget as&#13;
  Country                                      Population            Courts            Budget          2014 GDP     % of GDP&#13;
&#13;
                                                        CANDIDATE COUNTRIES&#13;
&#13;
  Iceland                                       318,452            8,286,532            26.02      12,854,000,000    0.06%&#13;
&#13;
  FYR Macedonia                                2,057,284           33,282,618           16.18      8,123,000,000     0.41%&#13;
&#13;
  Montenegro                                    620,029            25,120,882           40.52      3,149,000,000     0.80%&#13;
&#13;
  Serbia                                       7,120,566          133,625,333           18.77      33,059,000,000    0.40%&#13;
&#13;
  Turkey                                       72,561,312              NA&#13;
&#13;
                                                  POTENTIAL CANDIDATE COUNTRIES&#13;
&#13;
  Albania                                      3,195,000           19,454,578               6.09   8,975,000,000     0.22%&#13;
&#13;
  Bosnia and Herzegovina                       3,843,126           89,700,564           23.34&#13;
&#13;
  Average for candidate countries              17,154,457         309,470,507           18.04      66,160,000,000    0.47%&#13;
           (Source: European Commission for the Efficiency of Justice (CEPEJ) June 2013).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Montenegro is the only candidate country that is spending more as a percent of per capita GDP than&#13;
Bulgaria on their judicial system. In contrast, Iceland is spending considerable less than Bulgaria.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                     85&#13;
&amp;#12;         ANNEX 4: Benchmarking of Salaries of Judiciary with other COE Member States&#13;
&#13;
                                                     Gross Wage of a                              Gross Wage of a&#13;
                             Gross Wages of                                   Gross Wages of&#13;
                                                   Judge Compared to                            Judge Compared to&#13;
                              a Judges at a                                   Judges at Court&#13;
             Country                               the National Gross                           the National Gross&#13;
                             Supreme Court                                        of First&#13;
                                                     Average Annual                               Average Annual&#13;
                                 (euros)                                      Instance(Euros)&#13;
                                                          Wage                                         Wage&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         Romania                  43 865                    8.2                   25 750               4.8&#13;
&#13;
         Bulgaria                 22 177                     7                    10 230               3.2&#13;
&#13;
         Croatia                  65 592                    5.2                   30 396               2.4&#13;
&#13;
         Bosnia      and          38 108                    5.1                   22 936               3.1&#13;
         Herzegovina&#13;
&#13;
         Serbia                   22 514                    4.2                   13 595               2.5&#13;
&#13;
         Hungary                  37 986                    4.1                   18 252                2&#13;
&#13;
         Albania                  14 700                    3.9                    7 350               1.9&#13;
&#13;
         Montenegro               32 202                    3.8                   24 142               2.5&#13;
&#13;
         Greece                   87 240                    3.6                   32 704               1.3&#13;
&#13;
         Slovenia                 57 909                    3.2                   28 968               1.6&#13;
              (Source: European Commission for the Efficiency of Justice (CEPEJ) June 2013)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
It is evident from Table that both gross wages of a Supreme Court judge and a first instance judge in Bulgaria&#13;
are lower than most of other EU member states. The only country paying a lower wage to its judges than&#13;
Bulgaria is Albania. However, the ratio of gross wages of a judge in comparison to the gross average wage&#13;
is one of the highest in Bulgaria and it is second only to Romania. So relative to local Bulgarian workers,&#13;
Bulgarian judges are well paid.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                  86&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="25301298">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2015/11/25301298/bulgaria-judicial-performance-caseload-expenditure-review-2008-2014
        </url>
        <availablein>Bulgarian,English</availablein>
        <fullavailablein>
            <available_in lang="Bulgarian" entityid="090224b0831ae35a_1_0" node_id="25301298"/>
        </fullavailablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2015/11/25301298/bulgaria-judicial-performance-caseload-expenditure-review-2008-2014</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2015/11/25301298/bulgaria-judicial-performance-caseload-expenditure-review-2008-2014</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2015-11-11T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2015-11-11T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <docm_id>090224b0831ae27b</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b0831ae27b</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2015/11/11/090224b0831ae27b/1_0/Rendered/INDEX/Bulgaria000jud0e0review002008020140.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2015/11/11/090224b0831ae27b/1_0/Rendered/PDF/Bulgaria000jud0e0review002008020140.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2015-11-01T14:10:05Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2015-11-11T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Bulgaria – judicial performance, caseload
            and expenditure review (2008-2014)
        </repnme>
        <docna>
            Bulgaria – judicial performance, caseload
            and expenditure review (2008-2014)
        </docna>
        <display_title>Bulgaria – judicial performance,
            caseload and expenditure review (2008-2014)</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2015/11/25301298/bulgaria-judicial-performance-caseload-expenditure-review-2008-2014</listing_relative_url>
        <projn>BG-Bulgaria Governance Reform -- P156952</projn>
        <subtopic>Legal Institutions of the Market Economy,Bankruptcy and Resolution of Financial Distress,Judicial System Reform,Gender and Law</subtopic>
        <docty>Working Paper</docty>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Law and Development,Gender,Public Sector Development</teratopic>
        <count>Bulgaria</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!517191</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>South Eastern Europe and Balkans!$!517208</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>090224b0831ae27b_1_0</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <theme>Legal institutions for a market economy,Judicial and other dispute resolution mechanisms,Other public sector governance,Decentralization</theme>
        <admreg>Europe and Central Asia,Europe and Central Asia</admreg>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Law and Development,Gender,Public Sector Development</historic_topic>
        <prdln>Technical Assistance (Non-lending)</prdln>
        <sectr>Public Administration, Law, and Justice</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            benefit, court, financing, quality of
            justice, administration of justice, criminal, judicial
            oversight, laws, guarantees, salary, appellate courts, good
            governance, asset, legal assistance, restructuring plan,
            administrative court, reorganization, regulatory reforms,
            salaries, subsidy, legal entities, crime, corruption,
            judicial districts, will, payments, court restructuring,
            budget, resignation, organization of courts, jurisdictions,
            courts, arbitration, judicial statistics, dispositions,
            penalties, judicial positions, title, judge, prosecutors,
            restructuring, judicial reform, magistrates, court hearing,
            domicile, eu, cases, judges, legislation, social security,
            research, judicial authorities, district courts, legality,
            audit office, judicial assistance, rule of law, subsidies,
            legal framework, judicial institutions, judicial power,
            judicial system, regulations, access to justice,
            jurisdiction, wages, immovable properties, insufficient
            funds, police, crimes, budgets, judicial council, claims,
            performance of judiciary, judicial services, restructuring
            process, offences, allocation of funds, agencies, property,
            legal aid, properties, accountant, court filing, assets,
            constitutional court, judicial branch, military courts,
            administrative courts, claimants, capital goods,
            enforcement, economic stagnation, justice, human rights,
            fair trial, existing law, dismissal, national bank, court
            processes, legal persons, judicial performance, judicial
            systems, legal changes, court of appeal, judiciary, criminal
            cases, judgments, disposition, judicial resources,
            restructuring program, law, justice system, investigators,
            court systems, exchange rate, institutional framework,
            judicial review, judicial staff, court statistics, judicial
            sector, juvenile justice, guarantee, equitable distribution,
            court system, judicial bodies, estate
        </keywd>
        <owner>GOV PSP - ECA (GGO15)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>South Eastern Europe and Balkans</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <majtheme>Public sector governance,Rule of law</majtheme>
        <repnb>100933</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fragility, Conflict and Violence</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Alternative Sentencing Options</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community based Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Correctional Services and Facilities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corrections</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime and Society</ml:concept><ml:concept>Defense Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Detention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enforcement Policies and Oversight Mechanism</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigative Task Force Police</ml:concept><ml:concept>Juvenile Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Law Enforcement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Offender Reintegration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Administration and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Problem solving Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Prosecution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Restorative Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Therapeutic Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Assistance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim-Offender Mediation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Expenditure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Capacities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Staffing Needs Assessments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Asset Recovery</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Efficiency of Public Expenditures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Expenditures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Financial Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Spending</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Expenditures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Investment Plan</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Anti-Corruption and Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Constitutional Courts</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ombusdam</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Corruption &amp; Anticorruption Measures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Corruption and Anticorruption Measures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Checks on Executive Power</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen User Satisfaction Survey</ml:concept><ml:concept>Independent Commissions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ombudsmen</ml:concept><ml:concept>Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Parliament</ml:concept><ml:concept>Procurement Complaints Review Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supreme Audit Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Judicial Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Justice Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legal and Judicial Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wage Setting</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages, Compensation and Benefits</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Courts</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Language</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Law and Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Legal Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Bar Aassociations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Gender and Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Geographic Access</ml:concept><ml:concept>Judicial Review of Procurement Complaints and Contract Disputes</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legal Aid</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legal Aid Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legal Clinics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legal Empowerment of the Poor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pro se representation, Barriers</ml:concept><ml:concept>ProBono Legal Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Defenders</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Defenders Offices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women and Access to Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legal Institutions of the Market Economy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Criminal Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government Expenditure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supplementary</ml:concept><ml:concept>Placement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inspectorate</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Rights</ml:concept><ml:concept>Organized Crime</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Managing Public Finances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Investment Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Anti-Corruption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Accountability Mechanisms</ml:concept><ml:concept>Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Justice</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Europe</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Bulgaria</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Central Asia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>