<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Note No. 190                                                                                               July 1999&#13;
&#13;
             Protecting Minority Shareholders in&#13;
             Closely Held Firms&#13;
&#13;
Chad Leechor   In all but a few advanced countries most publicly listed corporations are closely held, with the&#13;
&#13;
               main shareholder typically playing an active role in management. In emerging markets firms with&#13;
&#13;
               active owner-managers provide effective business solutions where business environments are&#13;
&#13;
               characterized by corruption and weak contract enforcement. But they also pose a significant risk of&#13;
&#13;
               asset expropriation for minority shareholders. To promote investor confidence and develop&#13;
&#13;
               successful securities markets, this risk must be mitigated. Some policy analysts argue that the way&#13;
&#13;
               to do this is to restrict ownership concentration. Such a step could cause serious harm. This Note&#13;
&#13;
               argues instead for mitigating risk by strengthening corporate laws to safeguard minority&#13;
&#13;
               shareholdings, ensuring that markets for corporate control work, and enforcing disclosure&#13;
&#13;
               requirements for firms and ethical standards for public officials.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
               Modern publicly traded corporations are com-         A study of the world's top twenty-seven stock&#13;
               monly perceived to have widely dispersed own-        markets finds that only 36 percent of the largest&#13;
               ership and a separation of ownership and             publicly traded firms are widely held--that is,&#13;
               control, with the control delegated to profes-       with no shareholders controlling more than 20&#13;
               sional managers. The owners of the firm rely on      percent of the votes (La Porta, Lopez-de-Silanes,&#13;
               the board of directors to supervise the managers,    and Shleifer 1999). Most of these widely held&#13;
               voting only on major strategic decisions. The key    firms are concentrated in a few advanced mar-&#13;
               issue of corporate governance in this situation is   kets, especially the United Kingdom, Japan, and&#13;
               to ensure that managers act in the best interest     the United States (figure 1). Most large publicly&#13;
               of the shareholders. The board therefore plays a     traded firms (64 percent) have a controlling&#13;
               pivotal role.                                        shareholder, which may be a family (30 percent),&#13;
                                                                    the state (19 percent), or another firm (15 per-&#13;
               In reality, in all but a few advanced markets most   cent). Among smaller companies the share of&#13;
               publicly traded firms are closely held, with the     closely held firms is higher still.&#13;
               principal shareholder typically playing a very&#13;
               active role in management. The principal share-      In most closely held firms ownership is not sep-&#13;
               holder often serves as the chief executive officer   arated from control. For more than two-thirds (69&#13;
               or chairman of the board and has the decisive vote   percent), a nominee or relative of the controlling&#13;
               in major corporate decisions. In this setting the    shareholder ranks among the top executives (La&#13;
               key issue of corporate governance is more com-       Porta, Lopez-de-Silanes, and Shleifer 1999). In&#13;
               plex: how to prevent the insiders--those who         some emerging Asian markets (such as Indo-&#13;
               own a large stake and control the firm--from         nesia, the Republic of Korea, and Malaysia) that&#13;
               expropriating the assets of minority shareholders.   share is about 80 percent (Claessens, Djankov,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
               The World Bank Group  Finance, Private Sector, and Infrastructure Network&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Protecting Minority Shareholders in Closely Held Firms&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      FIGURE 1          SHARE OF WIDELY HELD FIRMS IN THE TOP TWENTY LISTED FIRMS,&#13;
                        DECEMBER 1995&#13;
      Percent&#13;
      100&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       80&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       60&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       40&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       20&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        0&#13;
                                                        of&#13;
                                                                                              Italy       Kong&#13;
        United   Japan StatesCanada France         Rep.GermanyDenmarkSpain&#13;
                                                                                 NorwaySweden&#13;
                                                                                                 Singapore    AustriaBelgiumArgentinaMexico&#13;
        Kingdom                                                                                       Hong&#13;
                 United                Switzerland&#13;
                                             Korea,                   Netherlands&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      Source: La Porta, Lopez-de-Silanes, and Shleifer 1999.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
and Lang 1999b). Insiders use a variety of instru-                            ties as compensation for the risk (Claessens,&#13;
ments to acquire and entrench their position,                                 Djankov, and Lang 1999a). Where the risk is not&#13;
including debt, pyramid schemes, cross-holding                                adequately checked, the discount can be dra-&#13;
of shares within a business group, and corporate                              matic, ranging from 82 percent (Zingales 1994)&#13;
poison pills (Leechor forthcoming).                                           to nearly 100 percent. In advanced securities&#13;
                                                                              markets with stronger protection for outside&#13;
The risk of insider expropriation                                             investors, the discount tends to be smaller but&#13;
                                                                              still significant (6 to 20 percent). Such discounts&#13;
With ownership concentrated among a few large                                 depress the valuation of firms' securities, increas-&#13;
shareholders who also manage the firm, potential                              ing the cost of funds and weakening insiders'&#13;
investors are naturally concerned about the risk                              incentive to reduce their ownership stake.&#13;
of insider expropriation. The firm's business could&#13;
be structured to serve the insiders' interest. The                            The preponderance of closely held firms in most&#13;
compensation paid to insiders could be excessive.                             markets has important implications for the devel-&#13;
Profits could be diverted to the insiders--easily                             opment of securities markets. Outside investors&#13;
done in most markets. And business transactions                               have few attractive investment options. In addi-&#13;
may not be at arm's length: sales to related par-                             tion, with depressed securities valuation, the&#13;
ties might be underpriced, and purchases from                                 firms find it more attractive to rely on the bank-&#13;
them overpriced.                                                              ing system, where they can contain the cost of&#13;
                                                                              funds through collateral. Moreover, limited inter-&#13;
Some self-serving actions by insiders may be per-                             est in marketable securities hampers the emer-&#13;
fectly legal. For example, many jurisdictions allow                           gence of a deep and liquid market. So foreign&#13;
freeze-outs of minority shares--where the con-                                investors, often large and prepared to deal with&#13;
trolling shareholder or an acquirer "takes the com-                           the risk, may nonetheless be unable to invest.&#13;
pany private" and pays the minority shareholders&#13;
a market price that does not reflect the new value                            Targeting the risk, not ownership&#13;
arising from acquisition. Some jurisdictions allow&#13;
the controlling shareholder to issue new shares                               Despite the risk, the ownership concentration in&#13;
through private placement and thereby dilute the                              closely held firms is not necessarily a bad thing.&#13;
voting power of outside shareholders.                                         Often it is a response to a variety of business and&#13;
                                                                              corporate governance problems.&#13;
In response to the risk of insider expropriation,&#13;
outside investors refrain from investing in closely                           Ownership concentration eases the job of mon-&#13;
held firms, or demand a discount on the securi-                               itoring and directing corporate management.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
With just a few large shareholders, changing              restructure target firms. The threat of a hostile&#13;
management or strategic direction becomes                 takeover--an external source of discipline for&#13;
more manageable. And in a difficult business              management--would weaken. And corporate&#13;
environment--with a murky legal framework,                governance would suffer.&#13;
uneven ethical standards among public officials,&#13;
and inadequate transparency among business             Experience shows that the risk of insider abuse&#13;
partners--direct operational involvement of the        can be mitigated without limiting ownership&#13;
major shareholders can safeguard against losses.       concentration.&#13;
&#13;
Even in the most advanced markets concentrated         How to reduce the risk&#13;
ownership is found in many leading firms. Here&#13;
ownership concentration can be important in facil-     Mitigating the risk of insider abuse can make a&#13;
itating corporate restructuring and industry con-      difference--to the investor, the closely held firm,&#13;
solidation, which seldom occur at the initiative of    and the securities market. The prospect of more&#13;
existing management, but more often through            secure returns enhances investors' confidence.&#13;
mergers and acquisitions (Jensen 1993). In addi-       Securities markets become more viable, giving&#13;
tion, securities analysts generally regard significant insiders an incentive to build the reputation their&#13;
share ownership by corporate insiders as a sign of     firm needs to access the markets. As more equi-&#13;
commitment--an assessment that enhances the            ties are issued to the public, ownership of firms&#13;
firm's value. Some of the world's most admired         becomes more dispersed.&#13;
companies are closely held, including Microsoft&#13;
and Berkshire Hathaway (Fortune, March 1, 1999).       Several mechanisms can reduce the risk of&#13;
                                                       insider abuse.&#13;
The prevalence of closely held firms indicates&#13;
the effectiveness of ownership concentration as         Duty of loyalty&#13;
a business solution. Thus as long as the risk of&#13;
insider abuse can be controlled, outside share-        A key tool in reducing the risk is a legal pre-&#13;
holders stand to benefit. So closely held firms        sumption of the duty of loyalty owed by insiders&#13;
pose a policy challenge: the risk of insider abuse     to outside investors. Guided by this doctrine, the&#13;
must be guarded against--while preserving the          judiciary would expect corporate directors to put&#13;
many advantages of ownership concentration.            the interest of the firm, including its outside&#13;
                                                       investors, before their personal interests. For&#13;
Many policymakers and analysts have suggested          example, no insiders would be allowed to vote&#13;
that the risk should be controlled by restricting      on transactions in which they have a personal&#13;
ownership concentration in publicly held firms.        stake. The relationship between outside investors&#13;
But that would be a costly mistake:                    and corporate insiders is akin to a long-term&#13;
   The incentive of a large shareholder to provide     contract in which the insiders' obligations cannot&#13;
   intensive monitoring and early strategic re-        be precisely delineated in advance. The duty of&#13;
   direction would be lost.                            loyalty addresses this basic difficulty.&#13;
   Owners of firms in the dynamic growth phase,&#13;
   reluctant to give up a substantial ownership        This legal principle works best in an established&#13;
   stake and control, might not sell shares to the     legal system in which members of the judiciary&#13;
   public to raise funds for expansion.                are honest and competent. Developing such a&#13;
   Most critical, restrictions on ownership con-       legal system can take many years, but is nonethe-&#13;
   centration hamper the market for corporate          less well worth the effort. The duty of loyalty, as&#13;
   control. Potential deal-makers might not be         a tool for enhancing corporate governance, can&#13;
   allowed, or might find it too costly, to acquire    be strengthened by rigorous enforcement of con-&#13;
   the ownership stake necessary to control and        tracts and bankruptcy procedures. Since all&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                             Protecting Minority Shareholders in Closely Held Firms&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             business obligations represent more senior claims    ences. To comply with political directives, corpo-&#13;
                             than those of shareholders, corporate insiders face  rate insiders may make poor investment decisions&#13;
                             strong external pressures to be prudent.             or take excessive risks. Enforcing stringent ethical&#13;
                                                                                  standards and conflict-of-interest laws applicable&#13;
                             Market for corporate control                         to public officials can help. In particular, public&#13;
                                                                                  officials should be prohibited from deriving per-&#13;
                             A functioning market for corporate control also      sonal gains or giving preferential treatment to oth-&#13;
                             provides a powerful tool for mitigating the risk of  ers through the exercise of official power. But this&#13;
                             insider abuse. Dissatisfied shareholders, active     safeguard requires a strong legal tradition and&#13;
                             institutional investors, and takeover specialists    democratic restraints (such as a free press) on the&#13;
                             could all acquire an ownership stake sufficient to   use of political power.&#13;
                             remove existing insiders. But the control market&#13;
                             can be curbed by anti-takeover devices, including    Market liberalization&#13;
                             rights plans (poison pills), intercorporate cross-&#13;
                             holding of shares, restrictions on business          In some cases ownership concentration reflects&#13;
                             combination, and control share rules (Leechor        broader policy issues, such as protectionism and&#13;
                             forthcoming). The policy challenge is to review the  barriers to entry. These policy distortions could&#13;
                             impact of anti-takeover tools and devise remedies.   lead to misguided investment, market power, and&#13;
                                                                                  unusual concentration of wealth. Policy reforms&#13;
                             Transparency                                         to correct these weaknesses--antimonopoly laws&#13;
Viewpoint is an open&#13;
forum intended to                                                                 and liberalization of trade, foreign ownership,&#13;
encourage                    Another safeguard is transparency in corporate       and market entry--can foster market competition&#13;
dissemination of and&#13;
                             affairs,  often  achieved     through   disclosure   and broaden the dispersion of wealth and cor-&#13;
debate on ideas,&#13;
innovations, and best        requirements. Transparency helps investors           porate ownership.&#13;
practices for expanding      make informed decisions and deters question-&#13;
the private sector. The&#13;
                             able actions by insiders. Adequate disclosure        References&#13;
views published are&#13;
those of the authors and     requires compliance with accepted financial&#13;
should not be attributed                                                          Claessens, Stijn, Simeon Djankov, and Larry H. P. Lang. 1999a.&#13;
                             accounting standards (IASC or FASB for firms&#13;
to the World Bank or any                                                            "Expropriation of Minority Shareholders: Evidence from East Asia."&#13;
                             listed on the New York Stock Exchange) and&#13;
of its affiliated organiza-                                                         Policy Research Working Paper 2088. World Bank, Financial Sector&#13;
&#13;
tions. Nor do any of the     auditing standards, as well as the coverage of         Practice Department, Washington, D.C.&#13;
&#13;
conclusions represent                                                             ------. 1999b. "Who Controls East Asian Corporations?" Policy&#13;
                             material facts, including significant changes in&#13;
official policy of the                                                              Research Working Paper 2054. World Bank, Financial Sector&#13;
                             ultimate corporate ownership. But compliance is&#13;
World Bank or of its                                                                Practice Department, Washington, D.C.&#13;
&#13;
Executive Directors or       not always enforced.                                 Fortune. 1999. "Most Admired Companies." March 1.&#13;
&#13;
the countries they                                                                Jensen, Michael C. 1993. "The Modern Industrial Revolution, Exit, and&#13;
&#13;
represent.                                                                          the Failure of Internal Control Systems." JournalofFinance 48:831­80.&#13;
                             Transparency requires the active participation of    La Porta, Rafael, Florencio Lopez-de-Silanes, and Andrei Shleifer.&#13;
&#13;
To order additional          professional watchdogs and reputational agents,        1999. "Corporate Ownership around the World." Journal of&#13;
&#13;
copies please call                                                                  Finance 54:471­517.&#13;
                             including securities analysts, credit rating agen-&#13;
202 458 1111 or contact                                                           Leechor, Chad. Forthcoming. "Reviving the Corporate Control&#13;
                             cies, and knowledgeable financial media. Where&#13;
Suzanne Smith, editor,                                                              Market." Viewpoint. World Bank, Finance, Private Sector, and&#13;
&#13;
Room F11K 208,               these services are not available domestically,         Infrastructure Network, Washington, D.C.&#13;
&#13;
The World Bank,                                                                   Zingales, Luigi. 1994. "The Value of the Voting Right: A Study of the Milan&#13;
                             they can often be imported by liberalizing the&#13;
1818 H Street, NW,                                                                  Stock Exchange Experience." Review of Financial Studies 7:125­48.&#13;
                             financial service industry, allowing local firms to&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433,&#13;
or Internet address          be listed abroad, and permitting local asset man-&#13;
ssmith7@worldbank.org.       agers to invest in foreign securities.               Chad Leechor (cleechor@worldbank.org),&#13;
The series is also&#13;
                                                                                  Business Environment Unit, Private Sector&#13;
available on line&#13;
(www.worldbank.org/          Strong ethical standards                             Development Department&#13;
html/fpd/notes/).&#13;
&#13;
                             The integrity and professional judgment of insid-&#13;
     Printed on recycled&#13;
paper.                       ers are sometimes compromised by political influ-&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="2531240">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1999/07/2531240/protecting-minority-shareholders-closely-held-firms
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <virt_coll>Knowledge Notes</virt_coll>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/1999/07/2531240/protecting-minority-shareholders-closely-held-firms</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>1999/07/2531240/protecting-minority-shareholders-closely-held-firms</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/10/02/000090341_20031002104151/Rendered/INDEX/268420VP0no101900leechor.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/10/02/000090341_20031002104151/Rendered/PDF/268420VP0no101900leechor.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2003-10-02T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>1999-07-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Protecting minority shareholders in closely
            held firms
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            In all but a few advanced countries most
            publicly listed corporations are closely held, with the main
            shareholder typically playing an active role in management.
            In emerging markets firms with active owner-managers provide
            effective business solutions where business environments are
            characterized by corruption and weak contract enforcement.
            But they also pose a significant risk of asset expropriation
            for minority shareholders. To promote investor confidence
            and develop successful securities markets, this risk must be
            mitigated. Some policy analysts argue that the way to do
            this is to restrict ownership concentration. Such a step
            could cause serious harm. This Note argues instead for
            mitigating risk by strengthening corporate laws to safeguard
            minority shareholdings, ensuring that markets for corporate
            control work, and enforcing disclosure requirements for
            firms and ethical standards for public officials. Modern
            publicly traded corporations are commonly perceived to have
            widely dispersed ownership and a separation of ownership and
            control, with the control delegated to professional
            managers. The owners of the firm rely on the board of
            directors to supervise the managers, voting only on major
            strategic decisions. The key issue of corporate governance
            in this situation is to ensure that managers act in the best
            interest of the shareholders. The board therefore plays a
            pivotal role.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Protecting minority shareholders in closely
            held firms
        </docna>
        <display_title>Protecting minority shareholders
            in closely held firms</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/1999/07/2531240/protecting-minority-shareholders-closely-held-firms</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Viewpoint</docty>
        <subtopic>Microfinance,Small Scale Enterprise,Economic Theory &amp; Research,International Terrorism &amp; Counterterrorism,Private Participation in Infrastructure</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth,Infrastructure Economics and Finance,Industry,Conflict and Development</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Chad Leechor</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000090341_20031002104151</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>Public policy for the private sector ; Note
            no. 190</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth,Infrastructure Economics and Finance,Industry,Conflict and Development</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Shareholding structure; Business support
            services; Corporate governance; Shareholders; Expropriation;
            Market liberalization; Ethical values
            antimonopoly laws,asset
            expropriation,bankruptcy,barriers to entry,Business
            Environment,contract enforcement,control share,corporate
            control,corporate directors,corporate governance,corporate
            management,corporate ownership,corporate
            restructuring,corporations,debt,disclosure,disclosure
            requirements,expansion,Financial Sector,firms,foreign
            ownership,foreign securities,insider abuse,large
            shareholders,market entry,mergers,protectionism,shareholders,shareholdings,takeover,transparency,valuation,wealth
        </keywd>
        <owner>Off of VP, FPD - WB (FPDVP)</owner>
        <repnb>26842</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fragility, Conflict and Violence</ml:concept><ml:concept>Arts and Culture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Business Regulation for Enterprise Creation and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legal Regulation and Business Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civic Participation and Corporate Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corporate Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nationalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Enterprise Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>State Owned Enterprise Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>State-Owned Enterprise Restructuring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corporate Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enterprise Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enterprise and Commercial Law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Emerging Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Business Environments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Media</ml:concept><ml:concept>Placement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Securities Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Terrorism</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Business Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>State Owned Enterprises</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enterprise and Corporate Law</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>