<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>                                 101038&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
International Bank for Reconstruction and&#13;
               Development&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Managementâ&#128;&#153;s Discussion &amp; Analysis&#13;
                 and&#13;
Condensed Quarterly Financial Statements&#13;
         September 30, 2015&#13;
              (Unaudited)&#13;
&amp;#12;&amp;#12;INTERNATIONAL BANK              FOR    RECONSTRUCTION            AND   DEVELOPMENT&#13;
(IBRD)&#13;
&#13;
CONTENTS&#13;
SEPTEMBER 30, 2015&#13;
&#13;
MANAGEMENTâ&#128;&#153;S DISCUSSION                   AND   ANALYSIS&#13;
&#13;
I.     OVERVIEW                                                                              3&#13;
II.    FINANCIAL PERFORMANCE AND RISK MANAGEMENT                                             4&#13;
III.   SUMMARY OF FAIR VALUE RESULTS                                                        13&#13;
IV. SENIOR MANAGEMENT CHANGES                                                               15&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CONDENSED QUARTERLY FINANCIAL STATEMENTS&#13;
&#13;
CONDENSED BALANCE SHEET                                                                     16&#13;
CONDENSED STATEMENT OF INCOME                                                               18&#13;
CONDENSED STATEMENT OF COMPREHENSIVE INCOME                                                 19&#13;
CONDENSED STATEMENT OF CHANGES IN RETAINED EARNINGS                                         19&#13;
CONDENSED STATEMENT OF CASH FLOWS                                                           20&#13;
NOTES TO CONDENSED QUARTERLY FINANCIAL STATEMENTS                                           21&#13;
INDEPENDENT AUDITORSâ&#128;&#153; REVIEW REPORT                                                         49&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                IBRD MANAGEMENTâ&#128;&#153;S DISCUSSION AND ANALYSIS: SEPTEMBER 30, 2015 1&#13;
&amp;#12;Box 1: Selected Financial Data&#13;
&#13;
In millions of U.S. dollars, except ratios which are in percentages&#13;
                                                                                                                 As of and for&#13;
                                                                       As of and for the three months ended       fiscal year&#13;
                                                                        September 30,        September 30,&#13;
                                                                              2015               2014           June 30, 2015&#13;
 Lending Highlights (Section II)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Commitmentsa                                                             $ 6,369         $       9,916            $ 23,528&#13;
 Gross disbursements                                                        7,868                 5,439              19,012&#13;
 Net disbursementsb                                                         5,586                 3,332               9,999&#13;
&#13;
 Reported Basis (Section II)&#13;
&#13;
 Income Statement&#13;
&#13;
 Board of Governors-approved and other transfers                          $      -         $          -            $   (715)&#13;
 Net income (loss)                                                             745                 (417)               (786)&#13;
&#13;
 Balance Sheet&#13;
&#13;
 Total assets                                                             $355,240          $353,328               $343,225&#13;
 Net investment portfolio                                                   44,067            40,925                 45,105&#13;
 Net loans outstanding                                                     160,258           152,458                155,040&#13;
 Borrowing portfolio                                                       168,708           157,152                158,853&#13;
&#13;
 Key Management Indicators (Section II)&#13;
&#13;
 Allocable Income                                                         $     29            $    556             $    686&#13;
&#13;
 Usable Equityc                                                           $ 40,248          $ 39,915               $ 40,195&#13;
&#13;
 Equity-to-loans Ratiod                                                        24.7%               25.3%                25.1%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 a. Commitments include guarantee commitments and guarantee facilities that have been approved by the Executive Directors.&#13;
 b. Amounts include transactions with the International Finance Corporation (IFC), and loan origination fees.&#13;
 c. Excluding amounts associated with unrealized mark-to-market gains/losses on non-trading portfolios, net and related&#13;
   cumulative translation adjustments.&#13;
 d. Ratio is computed using usable equity and excludes the respective periodsâ&#128;&#153; income. (Full year June 30, 2015 amount includes&#13;
   proposed transfer to the General Reserve).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
2   IBRD MANAGEMENTâ&#128;&#153;S DISCUSSION AND ANALYSIS: SEPTEMBER 30, 2015&#13;
&amp;#12;I.    Overview&#13;
This document should be read together with the International Bank for Reconstruction and Developmentâ&#128;&#153;s (IBRD)&#13;
Financial Statements and Managementâ&#128;&#153;s Discussion and Analysis (MD&amp;A) for the fiscal year ended June 30, 2015&#13;
(FY15). IBRD undertakes no obligation to update any forward looking statements. Box 1 provides IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s selected&#13;
financial data as of, and for the three months ended, September 30, 2015 and 2014, as well as for the fiscal year&#13;
ended June 30, 2015.&#13;
Business Model&#13;
IBRD, an international organization owned by its 188 member countries, is the largest multilateral development&#13;
bank in the world and is one of the five institutions of the World Bank Group (WBG); the others are the&#13;
International Development Association (IDA), the International Finance Corporation (IFC), the Multilateral&#13;
Investment Guarantee Agency (MIGA), and the International Centre for Settlement of Investment Disputes (ICSID).&#13;
Each of these organizations is legally and financially independent, with separate assets and liabilities. IBRD is not&#13;
liable for their respective obligations. The WBGâ&#128;&#153;s two goals, to be achieved by 2030, are to end extreme poverty by&#13;
reducing the percentage of people living on less than $1.90 per day to no more than 3% globally, and to promote&#13;
shared prosperity in a sustainable manner by fostering income growth for the bottom 40% of the population in every&#13;
developing country. In October 2015, the WBG raised its poverty line figure upwards, from $1.25 to $1.90 a day, to&#13;
reflect the increase in prices worldwide based on updated purchasing-power-parity data.&#13;
IBRD provides loans, guarantees, and knowledge for development focused projects and programs to middle-income&#13;
and creditworthy lower-income member countries. Its main business activity is extending loans to its eligible&#13;
member countries. IBRD offers its borrowers long-term loans that can have a final maturity of up to 35 years.&#13;
Borrowers may customize their repayment terms to meet their debt management or project needs. Loans are offered&#13;
on both fixed and variable terms, and in multiple currencies; though borrowers have generally preferred loans in U.S&#13;
dollars and euros. IBRD also provides access to risk management tools such as derivative instruments, including&#13;
currency and interest rate swaps.&#13;
IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s loans are financed through its equity, and from money borrowed in the capital markets. IBRD is rated triple-&#13;
A by the major rating agencies and investors view its bonds as high quality securities. IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s funding strategy is&#13;
aimed at achieving the best long-term value on a sustainable basis for its borrowing members. Its ability to&#13;
intermediate the funds it raises in international capital markets to developing member countries is important in&#13;
helping it achieve its goals. IBRD issues its securities both through global offerings and bond issues tailored to the&#13;
needs of specific markets or investor types. This is done by offering bonds to investors in various currencies,&#13;
maturities, markets, and with fixed and variable terms, often opening up new markets for international investors by&#13;
offering new products or bonds in emerging-market currencies. IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s annual funding volumes vary from year to&#13;
year. This strategy has enabled IBRD to borrow at favorable market terms and pass the savings on to its borrowing&#13;
members. Funds not immediately deployed for lending are held in IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s investment portfolio to supply liquidity&#13;
for its operations.&#13;
IBRD makes extensive use of derivatives to manage its exposure to various market risks arising from the above&#13;
activities. These are used to align the interest and currency composition of its assets (loan and investment trading&#13;
portfolios) with that of its liabilities (borrowing portfolio), and to stabilize the earnings on its equity.&#13;
Management believes that these risk management strategies, taken together, effectively manage market risk in&#13;
IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s operations from an economic perspective. However, these strategies necessarily entail the extensive use of&#13;
derivatives, which introduce volatility through unrealized mark-to-market gains and losses on the reported basis&#13;
income statement (particularly given the long-term nature of some of IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s assets and liabilities). Accordingly,&#13;
Management makes decisions on income allocation without reference to unrealized mark-to-market gains and losses&#13;
in its non-trading portfolios â&#128;&#147; see Basis of Reporting â&#128;&#147; Allocable Income below.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                      IBRD MANAGEMENTâ&#128;&#153;S DISCUSSION AND ANALYSIS: SEPTEMBER 30, 2015 3&#13;
&amp;#12;Basis of Reporting&#13;
Financial Statements&#13;
IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s financial statements conform with accounting principles generally accepted in the United States of America&#13;
(U.S. GAAP), referred to in this document as the â&#128;&#156;reported basisâ&#128;&#157;. All instruments in the investment and borrowing&#13;
portfolios and all other derivatives are reported at fair value, with changes in fair value reported in the statement of&#13;
income. IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s loans are reported at amortized cost, except for loans with embedded derivatives, which are&#13;
reported at fair value. Management uses the reported net income as the basis for deriving allocable income.&#13;
Fair Value Results&#13;
In an attempt to address the asymmetry in the reported financial statements, in which not all financial instruments&#13;
are reported on the same measurement basis, IBRD reflects all financial instruments at fair value in the MD&amp;A. The&#13;
fair value of these instruments is affected by changes in such market variables as interest rates, exchange rates, and&#13;
credit risk. Management uses fair value to assess the performance of the investment-trading portfolio; to manage&#13;
certain market risks, including interest rate risk and commercial counterparty credit risk; and to monitor the results&#13;
of the Equity Management Framework (EMF).&#13;
Allocable Income&#13;
The volatility in IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s reported net income is primarily driven by the unrealized mark-to-market gains and losses&#13;
on the derivative instruments in IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s non-trading portfolios (loans, borrowings, and EMF). These derivatives are&#13;
primarily used to align the interest rate and currency bases of its assets and liabilities. In line with IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s financial&#13;
risk management policies, IBRD expects to maintain its non-trading portfolio positions. As a result, for non-trading&#13;
portfolios, allocable income only includes amounts which have been realized. For trading portfolios (investment&#13;
portfolio), allocable income includes both realized amounts, as well as unrealized mark-to-market gains and losses.&#13;
Management has consistently followed this practice of excluding unrealized mark-to-market gains and losses on its&#13;
non-trading portfolios from reported net income to arrive at allocable income, since adopting Financial Accounting&#13;
Standards Boardâ&#128;&#153;s (FASBâ&#128;&#153;s) guidance on derivatives and hedging in FY01. Accordingly, in years in which reported&#13;
net income has been positively impacted by unrealized mark-to-market gains on the non-trading portfolios, IBRD&#13;
did not take these unrealized mark-to-market gains into account in making income allocation decisions. Likewise, in&#13;
the case of unrealized mark-to-market losses on the non-trading portfolios, IBRD consistently excludes these&#13;
amounts from reported net income to arrive at allocable income.&#13;
Allocable income also reflects certain other adjustments to reported net income, namely: Board of Governors-&#13;
approved and other transfers, pension adjustments, and restricted income. All of these adjustments reflect&#13;
Managementâ&#128;&#153;s view of the most appropriate measure of a given yearâ&#128;&#153;s financial results for allocation purposes&#13;
(Table 2). See June 30, 2015, MD&amp;A for a detailed discussion on allocable income.&#13;
&#13;
II.      Financial Performance and Risk Management&#13;
As part of IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s lending, borrowing, and investment activities, IBRD is exposed to market, counterparty and&#13;
country credit risks. To manage these risks, IBRD has put in place a strong risk management framework, which&#13;
supports Management in its oversight functions. This framework is designed to enable and support IBRD in&#13;
achieving its goals in a financially sustainable manner.&#13;
In an effort to maximize IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s capacity to lend to member countries for development purposes, IBRD limits its&#13;
exposure to market and counterparty credit risks. Among the various types of market risks, interest rate risk is the&#13;
most significant risk faced by IBRD. IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s exposure to currency and liquidity risks is minimal as a result of its&#13;
risk management policies. In addition, IBRD faces two types of credit risk: country credit risk and counterparty&#13;
credit risk.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
4     IBRD MANAGEMENTâ&#128;&#153;S DISCUSSION AND ANALYSIS: SEPTEMBER 30, 2015&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                          Figure 1: Equity-to-Loans Ratio Trend (%)&#13;
Capital Adequacy&#13;
                                                                           30&#13;
IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s capital adequacy is the degree to which its capital is        28&#13;
sufficient to withstand unexpected shocks. IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s Board of           26&#13;
&#13;
Executive Directors (Board) monitors IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s capital adequacy         24&#13;
                                                                     22&#13;
within a strategic capital adequacy framework and uses the&#13;
                                                                     20&#13;
equity-to-loans ratio as a key indicator of IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s capital           18&#13;
                                                                                    Minimum Level&#13;
adequacy. The framework seeks to ensure that IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s capital          16&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                 Jun 11&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                           Jun 12&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                    Jun 13&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                 Jun 14&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                           Jun 15&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                    Sep 15&#13;
is aligned with the financial risk associated with its loan&#13;
portfolio as well as other exposures over a medium-term&#13;
capital-planning horizon. Under this framework, IBRD&#13;
evaluates its capital adequacy as measured by stress tests and an appropriate Board approved minimum level for the&#13;
long term equity-to-loans ratio, currently set at 20%.&#13;
As shown on Table 1, IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s equity-to-loans ratio decreased from 25.1% at June 30, 2015 to 24.7% at September&#13;
30, 2015, and remained above the minimum ratio of 20%. The decrease in the ratio was primarily due to the $5.6&#13;
billion increase in net positive loan disbursements. Of this amount, $2.6 billion relates to disbursements on Deferred&#13;
Drawdown Options (DDOâ&#128;&#153;s). The decline in effective and undisbursed DDOâ&#128;&#153;s, therefore did not have a net impact&#13;
on the total exposure. Under IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s currency management policy, to minimize exchange rate risk in a&#13;
multicurrency environment, IBRD matches its borrowing obligations in any one currency (after derivative activities)&#13;
with assets in the same currency. In addition, IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s policy is to minimize the exchange rate sensitivity of its&#13;
capital adequacy as measured by the equity-to-loans ratio. It implements this policy by periodically undertaking&#13;
currency conversions to align the currency composition of its equity with that of its outstanding loans, across major&#13;
currencies. As a result, the impact on IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s equity-to-loans ratio from the exchange rate movements during the&#13;
year was negligible.&#13;
Table 1: Equity-to-Loans Ratio&#13;
In millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
                                                                                                             Variance&#13;
                                                                                                               Due to&#13;
                                         Sep 30,             June 30,                                        Translation             Due to&#13;
As of                                     2015                 2015               Total                      Adjustment             Activities&#13;
Usable paid-in capital                  $ 14,348             $ 14,297           $   51                           $ 13               $    38&#13;
 Special reserve                             293                   293                -                               -                     -&#13;
 General reservea                         26,925                26,925                -                               -                     -&#13;
 Cumulative translation adjustmentb         (591)                 (593)               2                               2                     -&#13;
 Other adjustmentsc                         (727)                 (727)               -                               -                     -&#13;
Equity (usable equity)                  $ 40,248             $ 40,195           $   53                           $ 15               $    38&#13;
&#13;
 Loans exposure                         $162,133             $156,802           $ 5,331                          $(257)             $ 5,588&#13;
 Present value of guarantees               1,109                  894               215                              4                  211&#13;
 Effective but undisbursed DDOs            1,475                4,095            (2,620)                             -               (2,620)&#13;
 Relevant accumulated provisions          (1,691)              (1,592)              (99)                            (1)                 (98)&#13;
 Deferred loan income                       (426)                (418)               (8)                             -                   (8)&#13;
 Other exposures                             527                  550               (23)                             -                  (23)&#13;
Loans (total exposure)                  $163,127             $160,331           $ 2,796                          $(254)             $ 3,050&#13;
&#13;
Equity-to-Loans Ratio                       24.7%                25.1%&#13;
&#13;
a. The June 30, 2015 amount includes proposed transfers to the General Reserve.&#13;
b. Excluding cumulative translation amounts associated with the unrealized mark-to-market gains/losses on non-trading portfolios,&#13;
   net.&#13;
c. Other adjustments comprise the net underfunded status of IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s pension plans and income earned on Post-Employment Benefit&#13;
   Plan (PEBP) assets prior to FY 2011.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         IBRD MANAGEMENTâ&#128;&#153;S DISCUSSION AND ANALYSIS: SEPTEMBER 30, 2015 5&#13;
&amp;#12;As a result of the General and Selective Capital                   Figure 2: Status of FY11 GCI/SCI Subscriptions as&#13;
Increase resolutions in the fiscal year ended June 30,             of September 30, 2015&#13;
                                                                   In billions of U.S. dollars&#13;
2011 (FY11), subscribed capital is expected to increase&#13;
by $87.0 billion (including shares subscribed under the                   Subscribed Capital                     Paid-in Capital&#13;
Voice Reform for which no paid-in capital was                                    $87 Billion                       $5.1 Billion&#13;
required), of which $5.1 billion will be paid-in. The&#13;
General Capital Increase (GCI) subscription period is&#13;
for five years and ends on March 16, 2016 or March                               23.8                                1.4&#13;
16, 2017 depending upon individual membersâ&#128;&#153;                                              63.2                               3.7&#13;
extension requests. As of September 30, 2015, $63.2&#13;
billion was subscribed, resulting in additional paid-in&#13;
capital of $3.7 billion, of which $32 million was                        Subscribed      Unsubscribed          Paid-In     Remaining&#13;
received during the first three months of the fiscal year&#13;
ending June 30, 2016 (FY16).&#13;
Financial Results&#13;
The primary sources of IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s income are the equity contribution and the net interest margin on its loans funded by&#13;
borrowings. The main driver of the equity contribution is revenue from the derivatives used as part of the EMF. In&#13;
addition to the regular interest earned from the derivative instruments, this revenue, on an allocable income basis,&#13;
includes net mark-to-market gains which have been realized during the year as a result of the liquidation of&#13;
derivative positions. Additionally, equity contribution includes revenue from the proportion of loans which are&#13;
funded by equity and certain minor adjustments including those relating to discontinued loan products. IBRD also&#13;
earns revenue from other development activities, as well as the margin on its investment portfolio.&#13;
On a reported basis, IBRD had net income of $745 million for the first three months of FY16, compared with a net&#13;
loss of $417 million during the same period in FY15. The higher net income during the first three months of FY16&#13;
primarily relates to the unrealized mark-to-market gains experienced on the non-trading portfolios (See Table 4). For&#13;
the first three months of FY16, IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s allocable income was $29 million, compared with $556 million during the&#13;
same period in FY15. The higher allocable income during the first three months of FY15 was primarily due to the&#13;
$581 million of gains from the termination of certain EMF positions. In contrast, there were no terminations of&#13;
trades during the same period in FY16. The following is a discussion on the key drivers of IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s financial&#13;
performance, including a reconciliation between IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s allocable income and reported net income.&#13;
Table 2: Condensed Statement of Income&#13;
 In millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
 For the three months ended September 30,                                               2015            2014                  Variance&#13;
 Interest revenue, net of funding costs&#13;
    Interest margin                                                                     $ 217           $ 213                 $    4&#13;
    Equity contributiona                                                                  191             674                   (483)&#13;
    Investments                                                                            10              14                     (4)&#13;
 Net interest revenue                                                                   $ 418           $ 901                 $ (483)&#13;
    Provision for losses on loans and other exposures                                     (98)            (40)                   (58)&#13;
    Other income, netb                                                                    (10)              3                    (13)&#13;
    Net non-interest expensesc                                                           (318)           (322)                     4&#13;
    Unrealized mark-to-market gains/(losses) on non-trading portfolios, neta,d            753            (959)                 1,712&#13;
 Net Income (loss)                                                                      $ 745           $(417)                $1,162&#13;
 Adjustments to reconcile net gains/(loss) to allocable income:&#13;
    Pension and other adjustments                                                          37              14                      23&#13;
    Unrealized mark-to-market (gains)/losses on non-trading portfolios, neta,d           (753)            959                  (1,712)&#13;
 Allocable income                                                                       $ 29            $ 556                 $ (527)&#13;
&#13;
 a. This includes the reclassification of net realized mark-to-market gains of $581 million for the first three months ended&#13;
    September 30, 2014, associated with the termination of certain positions under the EMF, from unrealized mark-to-market&#13;
    losses on non-trading portfolios, net, to equity contribution.&#13;
 b. Amount includes guarantee fee income, loan commitment fee income and net earnings from PEBP.&#13;
 c. See Table 3.&#13;
 d. See Table 4.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
6   IBRD MANAGEMENTâ&#128;&#153;S DISCUSSION AND ANALYSIS: SEPTEMBER 30, 2015&#13;
&amp;#12;Net Interest Margin&#13;
As of September 30, 2015, IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s equity to loans ratio was 24.7%, indicating that approximately 25% of IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
net loans and other exposures is funded by equity, and the remainder funded by borrowings. For the portion of loans&#13;
funded by borrowings, the net interest margin has remained relatively stable compared with the prior year (Table 2).&#13;
Net Non-Interest Expenses&#13;
As shown on Table 3, IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s net non-interest expenses primarily comprise administrative expenses, net of revenue&#13;
from externally funded activities. These expenses have remained stable over the two year period.&#13;
Table 3: Net Non-Interest Expenses&#13;
In millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
For the three month ended September 30,                                     2015           2014         Variance&#13;
Administrative expenses&#13;
  Staff costs                                                               $202           $197            $5&#13;
  Travel                                                                      29             26              3&#13;
  Consultant and contractual services                                         66             66              -&#13;
  Pension and other post-retirement benefits                                  55             58             (3)&#13;
  Communications and technology                                               11             11              -&#13;
  Equipment and buildings                                                     32             29              3&#13;
  Other expenses                                                              10             15             (5)&#13;
  Total administrative expenses                                             $405           $402            $3&#13;
Grant Making Facilities                                                       30             33             (3)&#13;
Revenue from externally funded activities&#13;
  Reimbursable revenue â&#128;&#147; IBRD executed trust funds                           (70)           (73)              3&#13;
  Other revenue                                                              (47)           (40)             (7)&#13;
Total Net Non-Interest Expenses (Table 2)                                   $318           $322            $ (4)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Unrealized mark-to-market gains/losses on non-trading portfolios&#13;
These mainly comprise unrealized mark-to-market gains and losses on IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s loan, borrowing, and EMF&#13;
portfolios. Since IBRD expects to maintain its non-trading portfolio positions, unrealized mark-to-market gains and&#13;
losses associated with these positions, are excluded from reported net income to arrive at allocable income. As a&#13;
result, from a long-term financial sustainability perspective, income allocations are made on the basis of amounts&#13;
which have been realized.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       IBRD MANAGEMENTâ&#128;&#153;S DISCUSSION AND ANALYSIS: SEPTEMBER 30, 2015 7&#13;
&amp;#12;As shown on Table 4, for the first three months of FY16, $753 million of unrealized mark-to-market gains were&#13;
excluded from reported net income to arrive at allocable income ($959 million unrealized mark-to-market losses in&#13;
the first three months of FY15). See discussion below for more details.&#13;
Table 4: Unrealized Mark-to-Market Gains/Losses, on Non-Trading Portfolio, net&#13;
In millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
                                                                      For the three months ended September 30, 2015&#13;
                                                               Unrealized gains&#13;
                                                             (losses), excluding&#13;
                                                              realized amounts        Realized gains            Total&#13;
Borrowing portfoliob                                                 $ 513a               $ 4                 $ 517&#13;
Loan portfoliob                                                       (497)                   -                (497)&#13;
EMF                                                                    741                    -                 741&#13;
Asset-liability management portfolioc                                   (1)                   -                  (1)&#13;
Client operations portfolio                                             (3)                   -                  (3)&#13;
   Total                                                             $ 753                $ 4                 $ 757&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      For the three months ended September 30, 2014&#13;
                                                               Unrealized gains&#13;
                                                             (losses), excluding&#13;
                                                              realized amounts        Realized gains            Total&#13;
Borrowing portfoliob                                                 $(244)a                 $  6                   $(238)&#13;
Loan portfoliob                                                         11                      -                      11&#13;
EMF                                                                   (723)a                  581                    (142)&#13;
Asset-liability management portfolioc                                   (1)                     -                      (1)&#13;
Client operations portfolio                                             (2)                     -                      (2)&#13;
   Total                                                             $(959)                  $587                   $(372)&#13;
&#13;
a. Includes adjustments to reclass net realized mark-to-market gains (losses) to the related interest income and expense lines for&#13;
   allocable income purposes.&#13;
b. Includes related derivatives.&#13;
c. Included in other derivatives on the Balance Sheet.&#13;
&#13;
EMF: During the first three months of FY16, IBRD had unrealized mark-to-market gains of $741 million for the&#13;
EMF in its reported net income, primarily as a result of the decline in the U.S. interest rates.&#13;
Loan portfolio: On a reported basis, while the derivatives which convert IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s loans to variable rates are reported&#13;
at fair value, all loans are reported at amortized cost, with the exception of one loan with an embedded derivative,&#13;
which is reported at fair value. As a result, while from an economic perspective, all of IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s loans after the effect&#13;
of derivatives carry variable rates, and therefore have a low sensitivity to interest rates, this is not reflected in its&#13;
reported net income. For the first three months of FY16, the $497 million of unrealized mark-to-market losses on the&#13;
loan portfolio relate primarily to the impact of the decrease in long-term interest rates during the period on the loan&#13;
related derivatives. In order to show the effect of its risk management policies, IBRD reflects its loans at fair value&#13;
in the MD&amp;A. See Section III for more details.&#13;
Borrowing portfolio: Given that all of the derivatives and the related underlying borrowings are at fair value, there is&#13;
no asymmetry in the reported net income, and therefore, unrealized mark-to-market gains and losses on the&#13;
borrowing related derivatives are correspondingly offset by unrealized mark-to-market gains and losses on the&#13;
underlying borrowings. As a result, since IBRD does not hedge its own credit, the main component of the net&#13;
unrealized mark-to-market gains and losses relates to the impact of the change in IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s own credit. See Section III&#13;
for more details.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
8    IBRD MANAGEMENTâ&#128;&#153;S DISCUSSION AND ANALYSIS: SEPTEMBER 30, 2015&#13;
&amp;#12;Balance Sheet Analysis&#13;
IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s principal assets are its loans to member countries. These are financed by IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s equity and proceeds of&#13;
borrowings from capital markets.&#13;
&#13;
Table 5: Condensed Balance Sheet&#13;
 In millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
                                                                September 30,        June 30,&#13;
 As of                                                               2015              2015               Variance&#13;
 Investments and due from banks                                  $ 49,184           $ 50,339              $ (1,155)&#13;
 Net loans outstanding                                            160,258            155,040                 5,218&#13;
 Receivable from derivatives                                      136,489            134,325                 2,164&#13;
 Other assets                                                         9,309             3,521                5,788&#13;
  Total assets                                                   $355,240           $343,225              $12,015&#13;
 Borrowings                                                      $169,592           $160,980              $ 8,612&#13;
 Payable for derivatives                                          135,489            132,324                 3,165&#13;
 Other liabilities                                                  10,694            11,284                  (590)&#13;
 Equity                                                             39,465            38,637                   828&#13;
  Total liabilities and equity                                   $355,240           $343,225              $12,015&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Loan portfolio&#13;
As part of its lending activities, consistent with its mandate IBRD has exposure to sovereign (country) credit risk.&#13;
Country credit risk reflects potential losses arising from protracted arrears on payments from borrowers on loans and&#13;
other exposures. IBRD manages this risk by applying individual country exposure limits. These limits take into&#13;
account the creditworthiness and performance of borrowers. In addition, to ensure that the financial risks associated&#13;
with its loans and other exposures do not exceed its risk-bearing capacity, IBRD uses a strategic capital adequacy&#13;
framework as a key medium-term capital planning tool.&#13;
Portfolio Concentration Risk&#13;
Portfolio concentration risk, which arises      Figure 3: Country Exposures as of September 30, 2015&#13;
when a small group of borrowers account for     In billions of U.S. dollars&#13;
a large share of loans outstanding, is a key&#13;
                                                                       Top Ten Country Exposures&#13;
concern for IBRD. The ten countries with&#13;
                                                     Brazil                                        15.4&#13;
the highest exposures accounted for about&#13;
                                                    Mexico                                       14.6&#13;
66% of IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s total exposure.&#13;
                                                 Indonesia                                      14.4&#13;
The concentration risk is carefully managed,         China                                  12.9&#13;
in part, by applying an exposure limit for the        India                               12.5&#13;
aggregate balance of loans outstanding, the         Turkey                               12.0&#13;
present value of guarantees, the undisbursed     Colombia                       8.3&#13;
portion of Deferred Drawdown Options                Poland                     8.2&#13;
(DDOs), and other eligible exposures that        Argentina               5.9&#13;
have become effective, to a single borrowing       Ukraine              5.6&#13;
country. Under the current guidelines,&#13;
                                                            0     2    4     6      8  10     12   14   16     18&#13;
IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s exposure to a single borrowing&#13;
country is restricted to the lower of an Equitable Access Limit (EAL) and the Single Borrower Limit (SBL). The&#13;
SBL effective on September 30, 2015 was $20.0 billion for India and $19.0 billion for the other four SBL-eligible&#13;
borrowing countries (Brazil, China, Indonesia, and Mexico), lower than the EAL of $28.1 billion at September 30,&#13;
2015.&#13;
Provision on Loans and Other Exposures&#13;
IBRD records a provision to reflect the probable losses inherent in its loan portfolio and other exposures. As of&#13;
September 30, 2015, IBRD had an accumulated provision for losses on loans and other exposures of $1,657 million,&#13;
which was approximately 1% of these exposures, ($1,554 million as of June 30, 2015 - 1% of exposures). As of&#13;
September 30, 2015, only 0.3% of IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s loans were in nonaccrual status and were all related to Zimbabwe. (Refer&#13;
to Note D: Loans and Other Exposures in the Notes to the Condensed Quarterly Financial Statements).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     IBRD MANAGEMENTâ&#128;&#153;S DISCUSSION AND ANALYSIS: SEPTEMBER 30, 2015 9&#13;
&amp;#12;For the first three months of FY16, there was a charge of $98 million, reflecting an increase in net loan&#13;
disbursements and the change in the credit quality of the loan portfolio during the period. This compares with a&#13;
charge of $40 million in the same period in FY15, primarily reflecting an increase in net loan disbursements during&#13;
the period.&#13;
Lending Activities&#13;
As of September 30, 2015, IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s net loans outstanding amounted to $160.3 billion,              Figure 4: Net Loans&#13;
3% higher than June 30, 2015. The increase was mainly attributable to $5.6 billion in net       Outstanding&#13;
positive loan disbursements made in the first three months of FY16.                             In billions of U.S. dollars&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                200&#13;
In the first three months of FY16, IBRD had new loan commitments (including&#13;
guarantees) totaling $6.4 billion, 36% lower than the same period in FY15 (Table 6).            150&#13;
Commitments during the first three months of FY15 were exceptionally high due to the&#13;
                                                                                                100&#13;
transitional pricing measures that were in place during that time.&#13;
                                                                                                  50&#13;
Gross disbursements during the first three months of FY16 were $7.9 billion, 45% above&#13;
the same period in FY15 (Table 7). The higher gross disbursement level in FY16 is                  0&#13;
                                                                                                       Jun 14   Jun 15   Sep 15&#13;
primarily due to higher disbursements to the countries in the East Asia and Pacific&#13;
region.&#13;
Table 6: Commitments by Region â&#128;&#147; For the Fiscal Year-To-Date&#13;
In millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
For the three months ended                September 30, 2015                September 30, 2014&#13;
                                        Commitments      % of total       Commitments    % of total              Variance&#13;
Africa                                    $ 260               4%            $ 559              6%                $ (299)&#13;
East Asia and Pacific                        150              2              3,017            30                  (2,867)&#13;
Europe and Central Asia                    3,054             48              3,836            39                    (782)&#13;
Latin America and the Caribbean            1,405             22                715             7                     690&#13;
Middle East and North Africa               1,500             24              1,789            18                    (289)&#13;
South Asia                                      -             -                  -              -&#13;
Total                                     $6,369           100%             $9,916           100%                $(3,547)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table 7: Gross Disbursements by Region - For the Fiscal Year-To-Date&#13;
In millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
                                           September 30, 2015                September 30, 2014&#13;
For the three months ended             Disbursements       % of total    Disbursements      % of total           Variance&#13;
Africa                                    $ 507                 7%           $  57               1%                $ 450&#13;
East Asia and Pacific                      2,656               34              683              13                  1,973&#13;
Europe and Central Asia                    2,543               32            2,416              44                    127&#13;
Latin America and the Caribbean            1,411               18            1,319              24                     92&#13;
Middle East and North Africa                 418                5              837              16                   (419)&#13;
South Asia                                   333                4              127               2                    206&#13;
Total                                     $7,868              100%          $5,439             100%                $2,429&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Investment Portfolio&#13;
Funds raised through IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s borrowing activity which have not yet been deployed for lending, are held in IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
investment portfolio to ensure liquidity for its operations. IBRD restricts its liquid assets to high-quality investments&#13;
as its investment objective prioritizes principal protection over yield. Liquid assets are therefore managed&#13;
conservatively, and are primarily held for potential disruptions in IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s access to capital markets.&#13;
IBRD has operated at levels of liquidity in the range of between 140% and 175% of the prudential minimum. The&#13;
prudential minimum liquidity level has been set at $27.5 billion for FY16, and the liquid asset portfolio was at 156%&#13;
of this level as of September 30, 2015.&#13;
Commercial Counterparty Credit Risk&#13;
Commercial counterparty credit risk is managed by applying eligibility criteria, volume limits for transactions with&#13;
individual counterparties, and using mark-to-market collateral arrangements for swap transactions. The effective&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
10   IBRD MANAGEMENTâ&#128;&#153;S DISCUSSION AND ANALYSIS: SEPTEMBER 30, 2015&#13;
&amp;#12;management of this risk is vital to the success of IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s funding, investment, and asset/liability management. The&#13;
monitoring and managing of this risk is continuous, given the changing market environment.&#13;
As a result of IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s use of mark-to-market collateral arrangements for swap transactions, its residual commercial&#13;
counterparty credit risk is concentrated in the investment portfolio. IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s overall commercial counterparty credit&#13;
exposure decreased by $1.6 billion during the first three months of FY16, reflecting the impact on the investment&#13;
portfolio, of loan disbursements made during the first three months of FY16. As shown on Table 8, the credit&#13;
quality of IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s portfolio remains concentrated in the upper end of the credit spectrum, with 70% of the portfolio&#13;
rated AA or above and the remaining portfolio primarily rated A. The A rated counterparties primarily consisted of&#13;
financial institutions (limited to short-term deposits and swaps) and sovereigns. Most of the BB or lower rated&#13;
exposure relates to IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s investment in a debt security issued by the Hypo Alpe-Adria Bank as discussed below.&#13;
Table 8: Commercial Credit Exposure, Net of Collateral Held, by Counterparty Rating&#13;
In millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
                                                                   As of September 30, 2015&#13;
                                         Investments&#13;
                                                  Agencies,&#13;
                                              Commercial paper,&#13;
                                                Asset-Backed&#13;
                                                 Securities,&#13;
                                             Corporates and Time          Net Swap&#13;
Counterparty Ratinga          Sovereigns          Deposits                Exposure             Total Exposure             % of Total&#13;
AAA                            $10,402              $ 9,939                $ â&#128;&#147;                     $20,341                    45%&#13;
AA                               4,524                6,879                 139                     11,542                    25&#13;
A                               10,040                3,862                   81                    13,983                    30&#13;
BBB                                 42                   12                    *                        54                      *&#13;
BB or lower/unrated                   -                  29                    *                        29                      *&#13;
Total                          $25,008              $20,721                $220                    $45,949                   100%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      As of June 30, 2015&#13;
                                         Investments&#13;
                                                  Agencies,&#13;
                                              Commercial paper,&#13;
                                                Asset-Backed&#13;
                                                 Securities,&#13;
                                             Corporates and Time          Net Swap&#13;
Counterparty Ratinga          Sovereigns          Deposits                Exposure             Total Exposure             % of Total&#13;
AAA                            $10,451              $ 9,571                $ -                     $20,022                    42%&#13;
AA                               4,385                9,375                   78                    13,838                    29&#13;
A                                7,336                5,997                 107                     13,440                    28&#13;
BBB                                223                    8                    2                       233                      *&#13;
BB or lower/unrated                   -                  18                    5                        23                      *&#13;
Total                          $22,395              $24,969                $192                    $47,556                   100%&#13;
&#13;
a. Average rating is calculated using available ratings from the three major rating agencies; however, if ratings are not available from&#13;
   each of the three rating agencies. IBRD uses the average of the ratings available from any of such rating agencies or a single rating&#13;
   to the extent that an instrument or issuer (as applicable) is rated by only one rating agency.&#13;
* Indicates amount less than $0.5 million or percentage less than 0.5%.&#13;
&#13;
In FY07, IBRD purchased for $190 million a debt security issued by an Austrian bank, Hypo Alpe-Adria, which was&#13;
fully guaranteed by the state of Carinthia. As of September 30, 2015, this debt security had a carrying value of $25&#13;
million. The loss in the value of the security is the result of legislation passed in FY14 to cancel the underlying debt.&#13;
In July 2015, this legislation was overturned and ruled by the Austrian Constitutional Court as unconstitutional and&#13;
the guarantee was reinstated. The investment had a carrying value of $13 million as of June 30, 2015, resulting in&#13;
unrealized mark-to-market gains of $12 million during the three month period ended September 30, 2015. IBRD&#13;
will continue to monitor the value of this investment and related market developments.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                           IBRD MANAGEMENTâ&#128;&#153;S DISCUSSION AND ANALYSIS: SEPTEMBER 30, 2015 11&#13;
&amp;#12;Liquid Asset Portfolio&#13;
As of September 30, 2015, the net investment portfolio totaled $44.1 billion (Figure       Figure 5: Liquid Asset&#13;
5), with $43.0 billion representing the liquid asset portfolio (see Note C:                Portfolio&#13;
Investments to the Condensed Quarterly Financial Statements). This compares with           In billions of U.S. dollars&#13;
an investment portfolio valued at $45.1 billion as at June 30, 2015, with $44.0            50&#13;
billion representing the liquid asset portfolio. The $1.0 billion decline in the liquid    40&#13;
asset portfolio reflects the impact of loan disbursements made during the first three&#13;
                                                                                           30&#13;
months of FY16.&#13;
                                                                                           20&#13;
During the first three months of FY16, interest revenue net of funding cost, from&#13;
                                                                                           10&#13;
the investment portfolio, amounted to $10 million. This compares with $14 million&#13;
during the same period in FY15. The decrease in net interest revenue during FY16,           0&#13;
                                                                                                    Jun 14    Jun 15    Sep 15&#13;
was primarily due to higher unrealized mark-to-market losses on the portfolio,&#13;
partially offset by higher interest income.&#13;
Borrowing Portfolio&#13;
IBRD issues debt securities to both institutional and retail investors in a variety of     Figure 6: Borrowing&#13;
currencies. During the first three months of FY16, IBRD raised medium and long-            Portfolio&#13;
term debt of $14.3 billion in 15 currencies.                                               In billions of U.S. dollars&#13;
                                                                                           200&#13;
As of September 30, 2015, the borrowing portfolio totaled $168.7 billion, an&#13;
increase of $9.9 billion from June 30, 2015 (see Note E: Borrowings in the Notes to        150&#13;
&#13;
the Condensed Quarterly Financial Statements). This increase was mainly due to net&#13;
                                                                                           100&#13;
new issuances of $10.1 billion to support the increase in loan disbursements. Of the&#13;
new issuances, $5.9 billion remained unsettled as of September 30, 2015, and a              50&#13;
receivable for the proceeds was recorded under Other Assets on the Condensed&#13;
                                                                                                0&#13;
Balance Sheet.                                                                                       Jun 14    Jun 15   Sep 15&#13;
&#13;
Equity Contribution and Equity Management Framework&#13;
Under its current interest rate risk management strategy, IBRD seeks to match the interest rate sensitivity of its&#13;
assets (loan and investment trading portfolios) with those of its liabilities (borrowing portfolio) by using derivatives,&#13;
such as interest rate swaps. These derivatives effectively convert IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s financial assets and liabilities into&#13;
variable-rate instruments. This strategy helps IBRD to manage the interest margin on the proportion of loans funded&#13;
by debt, against interest rate volatility. The interest revenue on the remaining proportion of loans funded by equity,&#13;
if left unmanaged, would be highly sensitive to fluctuations in short-term interest rates. To manage this exposure,&#13;
IBRD uses an EMF, which seeks to manage the sensitivity of IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s revenue from loans funded by equity to&#13;
fluctuations in short-term interest rates. In particular, the EMF allows the flexibility of managing the duration of&#13;
IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s equity within a range of zero to five years based on market and macroeconomic conditions. It also allows&#13;
IBRD to realize some of the unrealized mark-to-market gains from the positions. As measured by duration, the&#13;
interest rate sensitivity of IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s equity remained largely unchanged at 4.4 years as of September 30, 2015, from&#13;
4.8 years as of June 30, 2015. The market value of the EMF position increased to $1.6 billion as of September 30,&#13;
2015, from $0.7 billion as of June 30, 2015. The increase was primarily as a result of net unrealized mark-to-market&#13;
gains of $741 million experienced during the first three months of FY16, due to the decline in the U.S. interest rates&#13;
(Table 4).&#13;
The main driver of equity contribution is revenue from the derivatives used as part of the EMF. In addition to the&#13;
regular interest income earned from the derivative instruments, this revenue, on an allocable income basis, includes&#13;
net mark-to-market gains which have been realized during the year as a result of the termination of derivative&#13;
positions. Additionally, equity contribution includes revenue from the proportion of loans which are funded by&#13;
equity and certain minor adjustments including those relating to discontinued loan products.&#13;
For the first three months of FY16, the equity contribution amounted to $191 million, compared with $674 million&#13;
for the same period in FY15, where IBRD had $581 million of realized gains as a result of the liquidation of certain&#13;
EMF positions during that time. There were no terminations of positions during the same period in FY16. This&#13;
decline was however partially offset by the increase in interest income earned during FY16, as a result of the&#13;
increase in the volume of EMF positions.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
12   IBRD MANAGEMENTâ&#128;&#153;S DISCUSSION AND ANALYSIS: SEPTEMBER 30, 2015&#13;
&amp;#12;III.         Summary of Fair Value Results&#13;
Fair Value Adjustments&#13;
An important element in achieving IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s financial goals is its ability to minimize the cost of borrowing from&#13;
capital markets for lending to member countries by using financial instruments, including derivatives. The fair value&#13;
of these financial instruments is affected by changes in the market environment such as interest rates, exchange rates&#13;
and credit risk. Fair value is used mainly to assess the performance of the investment trading portfolio, to monitor&#13;
the results of the EMF, and to manage certain market risks, including interest rate and commercial credit risk for&#13;
derivative counterparties.&#13;
As shown in Table 9, on a fair value basis, if interest rates increased by one basis point, IBRD would experience a&#13;
net unrealized mark-to-market loss of approximately $24 million as of September 30, 2015.&#13;
Table 9: Effect of Interest Rates and Credit on IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s Fair Value Income&#13;
 In millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
                                                                               Interest Rate Effect                     Credit Effect&#13;
                                                                              on Fair Value Incomea                 on Fair Value Incomeb&#13;
 As of September 30, 2015                                                          Sensitivityc                          Sensitivityc&#13;
 Borrowing portfolio                                                                    $ 3                                   $ 51&#13;
 Loan portfolio                                                                           (8)                                  (36)&#13;
 EMF                                                                                     (18)                                     *&#13;
 Investment portfolio                                                                     (1)                                    3&#13;
 Total (loss)/gains                                                                     $(24)                                 $ 18&#13;
&#13;
 a. After the effects of derivatives.&#13;
 b. Excludes CVA adjustment on swaps.&#13;
 c. Amount represents dollar change in fair value corresponding to a one basis-point parallel upward shift in interest rates.&#13;
 * Sensitivity is marginal.&#13;
&#13;
Figure 7 provides a further breakdown of how the use of derivatives affects the overall sensitivity of the loan and&#13;
borrowing portfolios. For example, for the borrowing portfolio, a one basis point increase in interest rates would&#13;
result in net unrealized mark-to-market gains of $51 million on the bonds. These would be significantly offset by the&#13;
$48 million of net unrealized mark-to-market losses on the related swaps, resulting in net unrealized mark-to-market&#13;
gains of $3 million for the portfolio.&#13;
Figure 7: Sensitivity to Interest Rates as of September 30, 2015&#13;
(Dollar change in fair value corresponding to a one-basis-point upward parallel shift in interest rates)&#13;
In millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
       Borrowing Portfolio                Loan Portfolio                         EMF                            Investment Portfolio&#13;
            Swaps Bonds                     Loans Swaps                       Swaps                           Instruments&#13;
                  0                              0                                         0&#13;
             -48    51                        -27 19                                                                   -0.7&#13;
                                                                              -18&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       -60 -40 -20 0 20 40 60          -60 -40 -20 0 20 40 60                                                 -20    -10      0    10      20&#13;
                                                                        -20    -10     0       10   20&#13;
&#13;
       Net Sensitivity = $3 million   Net Sensitivity = $(8) million    Net Sensitivity= $(18) million        Net Sensitivity = $(0.7) million&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
For the first three months of FY16, IBRD experienced net unrealized mark-to-market losses on a fair value basis of&#13;
$267 million on its non-trading portfolios. See Table 10 below for details.&#13;
Table 10: Summary of Fair Value Adjustments on Non-Trading Portfoliosa&#13;
In millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
For the three months ended September 30,                                                                    2015                   2014&#13;
Borrowing portfolio                                                                                      $ 516                     $(237)&#13;
Loan portfolio                                                                                            (1,524)                   (566)&#13;
EMF                                                                                                          741                    (142)&#13;
                                                                                                         $ (267)                   $(945)&#13;
&#13;
a. See Table 12 for reconciliation to the fair value comprehensive basis net income.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                          IBRD MANAGEMENTâ&#128;&#153;S DISCUSSION AND ANALYSIS: SEPTEMBER 30, 2015 13&#13;
&amp;#12;Effect of Interest and Credit&#13;
IBRD uses derivatives in its loan and borrowing portfolios to arrive at floating rate instruments, as part of its risk&#13;
management strategies. The sensitivity of these portfolios to interest rate movements, after the effect of derivatives&#13;
is therefore low, resulting in relatively small interest rate related unrealized mark-to-market gains/losses in income&#13;
(Figure 7).&#13;
For the first three months of FY16, the unrealized mark-to-market gains on the EMF position of $741 million were&#13;
primarily due to the decrease in U.S. interest rates experienced during the first three months of FY16.&#13;
For the first three months of FY16, IBRD experienced $516 million of unrealized mark-to-market gains on the&#13;
borrowing portfolio, which is comprised of $665 million mark-to-market unrealized gains due to the widening of its&#13;
credit spreads, partially offset by $232 million of mark-to-market losses due to the decline in interest rates. As&#13;
shown on Table 9, the dollar value change corresponding to a one-basis-point upward parallel shift in interest rates&#13;
on IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s own credit relative to LIBOR is about $51 million of unrealized mark-to-market gains.&#13;
In addition, IBRD experienced $1.5 billion of unrealized mark-to-market losses on the loan portfolio, which was&#13;
mainly due to the net widening of Credit Default Swaps (CDS) spreads for several of its borrowing member&#13;
countries during the same period. As shown on Table 9, the dollar value change corresponding to a one-basis-point&#13;
upward parallel shift in CDS rates on the loan portfolio is about $36 million of unrealized mark-to-market losses.&#13;
See the June 30, 2015, MD&amp;A for a detailed discussion on how the credit risk of each portfolio is managed.&#13;
Fair Value Results&#13;
As non-financial assets and liabilities are not reflected at fair value, IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s equity is not intended to reflect fair&#13;
value. Under the fair value basis, in addition to the instruments in the investment and borrowing portfolios, and all&#13;
other derivatives, loans are reported at fair value and all changes in AOCI are also included in fair value net income.&#13;
Tables 11-12 provide a reconciliation from the reported basis to the fair value basis for both the balance sheet and&#13;
income statement.&#13;
Table 11: Condensed Balance Sheet on a Fair Value Basis&#13;
In millions U.S. dollars&#13;
                                            As of September 30, 2015                              As of June 30, 2015&#13;
                                     Reported                    Fair Value           Reported                          Fair Value&#13;
                                       Basis      Adjustments        Basis               Basis       Adjustments          Basis&#13;
Due from banks                       $     887       $            $     887           $     388                         $    388&#13;
Investments                             48,297                       48,297              49,951                           49,951&#13;
Net loans outstanding                  160,258         (168)        160,090             155,040         $870             155,910&#13;
Receivable from derivatives           136,489                      136,489             134,325                           134,325&#13;
Other assets                             9,309                        9,309               3,521                            3,521&#13;
Total assets                         $355,240        $(168)       $355,072            $343,225          $870            $344,095&#13;
&#13;
Borrowings                           $169,592         $ 10a         $169,602          $160,980          $   8a          $160,988&#13;
Payable for derivatives               135,489                        135,489           132,324                           132,324&#13;
Other liabilities                      10,694                         10,694            11,284                            11,284&#13;
Total liabilities                     315,775            10          315,785           304,588              8            304,596&#13;
Paid-in capital stock                  15,224                         15,224            15,192                            15,192&#13;
Retained earnings and other equity     24,241          (178)          24,063            23,445           862              24,307&#13;
Total equity                           39,465          (178)          39,287            38,637           862              39,499&#13;
Total liabilities and equity         $355,240         $(168)        $355,072          $343,225          $870            $344,095&#13;
&#13;
a. Amount represents amortization of transition adjustment relating to the adoption of FASBâ&#128;&#153;s guidance on derivatives and hedging&#13;
   on July 1, 2000.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
14    IBRD MANAGEMENTâ&#128;&#153;S DISCUSSION AND ANALYSIS: SEPTEMBER 30, 2015&#13;
&amp;#12;Table 12: Reconciliation from Net Income to Income on a Fair Value Comprehensive Basis&#13;
In millions U.S. dollars&#13;
For the three months ended September 30,                         2015                    2014                     Variance&#13;
Net income (loss) from Table 2                                  $ 745                  $ (417)                   $1,162&#13;
Fair value adjustment on loansa                                  (1,027)                  (577)                    (450)&#13;
Changes to AOCI:&#13;
   Currency translation adjustments                                 (5)                   (443)                     438&#13;
   Others                                                           34                      52                      (18)&#13;
     Net (loss) on fair value comprehensive basis               $ (253)                $(1,385)                  $1,132&#13;
&#13;
a. Amount has been adjusted to exclude the provision for losses on loans and other exposures: $98 million charge and $40 million&#13;
   charge â&#128;&#147; three months ended September 30, 2015 and September 30, 2014, respectively.&#13;
&#13;
Table 13: Fair Value Adjustments, net&#13;
In millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
                                                                    For the three months ended September 30, 2015&#13;
                                                                                         Fair Value                 Total&#13;
                                                       Unrealized gains      Realized   Adjustment       Other      from&#13;
                                                           (losses)           gains    from Table 12 Adjustments Table 10&#13;
Borrowing portfolioc                                         $ 513a             $ 4                      $(1)b    $ 516&#13;
Loan portfolioc                                               (497)                       $(1,027)                 (1,524)&#13;
EMFd                                                           741                                                    741&#13;
Asset-liability management portfoliod                           (1)                                        1            -&#13;
Client operations portfolio                                     (3)                                        3            -&#13;
   Total                                                     $ 753              $ 4       $(1,027)       $3       $ (267)&#13;
&#13;
                                                                  For the three months ended September 30, 2014&#13;
                                                                                       Fair Value               Total&#13;
                                                       Unrealized gains    Realized   Adjustment       Other     from&#13;
                                                           (losses)         gains    from Table 12 Adjustments Table 10&#13;
Borrowing portfolioc                                         $(244)a           $ 6                            $1b          $(237)&#13;
Loan portfolioc                                                 11                            $(577)                        (566)&#13;
EMFd                                                          (723)a            581                                         (142)&#13;
Asset-liability management portfoliod                           (1)                                            1               -&#13;
Client operations portfolio                                     (2)                                            2               -&#13;
   Total                                                     $(959)            $587           $(577)          $4           $(945)&#13;
&#13;
a. Includes amounts reclassified to realized mark-to-market gains (losses).&#13;
b. Amount represents amortization of transition adjustment relating to the adoption of FASBâ&#128;&#153;s guidance on derivatives and hedging&#13;
   on July 1, 2000, included in AOCI.&#13;
c. Includes related derivatives.&#13;
d. Included in other derivatives on the condensed Balance Sheet.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
IV.        Senior Management Changes&#13;
On November 6, 2015, Bertrand Badre announced that he will be leaving as Managing Director and WBG Chief&#13;
Financial Officer at the end of March 2016.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        IBRD MANAGEMENTâ&#128;&#153;S DISCUSSION AND ANALYSIS: SEPTEMBER 30, 2015 15&#13;
&amp;#12;CONDENSED BALANCE SHEET&#13;
Expressed in millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
&#13;
                                                                             September 30, 2015   June 30, 2015&#13;
                                                                                 (Unaudited)       (Unaudited)&#13;
Assets&#13;
Due from banksâ&#128;&#148;Notes C and K&#13;
    Unrestricted cash                                                           $      833        $      311&#13;
    Restricted cash                                                                     54                77&#13;
                                                                                       887               388&#13;
    Investments-Trading (including securities transferred under repurchase&#13;
      agreements or securities lending agreements of $390 millionâ&#128;&#148;&#13;
     September 30, 2015; $844 millionâ&#128;&#148;June 30, 2015)â&#128;&#148;Note C                          45,804            47,823&#13;
Securities purchased under resale agreementsâ&#128;&#148;Note C                                   2,493             2,128&#13;
Derivative assets&#13;
     Investmentsâ&#128;&#148;Notes C, F and K                                                    24,894            22,196&#13;
     Loansâ&#128;&#148;Notes D, F and K                                                           4,122             3,902&#13;
     Client operationsâ&#128;&#148;Notes D, F, I and K                                           28,349            28,739&#13;
     Borrowingsâ&#128;&#148;Notes E, F and K                                                     77,012            78,267&#13;
     Othersâ&#128;&#148;Notes F and K                                                             2,112             1,221&#13;
                                                                                    136,489           134,325&#13;
Loans outstandingâ&#128;&#148;Notes D, I and K&#13;
     Total loans                                                                    220,787           217,223&#13;
     Less undisbursed balance                                                        58,446            60,211&#13;
       Loans outstanding (including a loan at fair value of $117 millionâ&#128;&#148;&#13;
        September 30, 2015; $125 millionâ&#128;&#148;June 30, 2015)                             162,341           157,012&#13;
     Less:&#13;
       Accumulated provision for loan losses                                          1,657             1,554&#13;
       Deferred loan income                                                            426               418&#13;
         Net loans outstanding                                                      160,258           155,040&#13;
Other assetsâ&#128;&#148;Notes C, E and I                                                         9,309             3,521&#13;
     Total assets                                                               $ 355,240         $ 343,225&#13;
Â                                      Â &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
16        IBRD CONDENSED QUARTERLY FINANCIAL STATEMENTS: SEPTEMBER 30, 2015 (UNAUDITED)&#13;
&amp;#12;Â &#13;
&#13;
                                                                       September 30, 2015    June 30, 2015&#13;
                                                                           (Unaudited)        (Unaudited)&#13;
Liabilities&#13;
Borrowingsâ&#128;&#148;Notes E and K                                                   $ 169,592         $   160,980&#13;
Securities sold under repurchase agreements, securities lent under&#13;
 securities lending agreements, and payable for cash collateral&#13;
 receivedâ&#128;&#148;Notes C and K                                                         3,015              3,575&#13;
Derivative liabilities&#13;
    Investmentsâ&#128;&#148;Notes C, F and K                                               24,401             21,279&#13;
    Loansâ&#128;&#148;Notes D, F and K                                                      5,996              5,535&#13;
    Client operationsâ&#128;&#148;Notes D, F, I and K                                      28,350             28,747&#13;
    Borrowingsâ&#128;&#148;Notes E, F and K                                                76,128             76,140&#13;
    Othersâ&#128;&#148;Notes F and K                                                          614                623&#13;
                                                                              135,489            132,324&#13;
Other liabilitiesâ&#128;&#148;Notes C, D and I                                              7,679              7,709&#13;
    Total liabilities                                                         315,775            304,588&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Equity&#13;
Capital stockâ&#128;&#148;Note B&#13;
    Authorized (2,307,600 sharesâ&#128;&#148;September 30, 2015, and&#13;
     June 30, 2015)&#13;
    Subscribed (2,100,276 sharesâ&#128;&#148;September 30, 2015, and 2,095,748&#13;
     sharesâ&#128;&#148;June 30, 2015)                                                    253,367            252,821&#13;
      Less uncalled portion of subscriptions                                  238,143            237,629&#13;
    Paid-in capital                                                            15,224             15,192&#13;
Nonnegotiable, noninterest-bearing demand obligations on account of&#13;
 subscribed capital                                                              (295)              (304)&#13;
Receivable amounts to maintain value of currency holdings                        (350)              (365)&#13;
Deferred amounts to maintain value of currency holdings                          (188)              (174)&#13;
Retained earnings (see Condensed Statement of Changes in Retained&#13;
 Earnings; Note G)                                                             28,246             27,501&#13;
Accumulated other comprehensive lossâ&#128;&#148;Note J                                    (3,172)            (3,213)&#13;
    Total equity                                                               39,465             38,637&#13;
    Total liabilities and equity                                           $ 355,240         $   343,225&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    The Notes to the Condensed Quarterly Financial Statements are an integral part of these Statements.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
              IBRD CONDENSED QUARTERLY FINANCIAL STATEMENTS: SEPTEMBER 30, 2015 (UNAUDITED)                 17&#13;
&amp;#12;CONDENSED STATEMENT OF INCOME&#13;
Expressed in millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      Three Months Ended September 30,&#13;
                                                                                 (Unaudited)&#13;
                                                                            2015                   2014&#13;
&#13;
Net interest revenue&#13;
Â  Interest revenueÂ &#13;
Â  Â  Loans, netâ&#128;&#148;Note D                                                 $       330             $      290&#13;
Â  Â  Equity management, net                                                    184                     93&#13;
Â  Â  Investments - Trading, net                                                 59                     51&#13;
Â  Â  Other, net                                                                  1                      1&#13;
Â  Interest expensesÂ &#13;
Â  Â  Borrowings, netâ&#128;&#148;Note E                                                   (126)                   (94)&#13;
Â Â       Net interest revenue, before provision for losses                     448                    341&#13;
Â  Â  Provision for losses on loans and other exposuresâ&#128;&#148;Note D                  (98)                   (40)&#13;
Â Â       Net interest revenue, after provision for losses                      350                    301&#13;
Â Â &#13;
Non-interest revenue&#13;
Â  Â Â  Revenue from externally funded activitiesâ&#128;&#148;Note I                         117                    113&#13;
Â  Â Â  Commitment chargesâ&#128;&#148;Note DÂ                                                  7                      4&#13;
Â  Â  Other, net                                                                  1                      1&#13;
Â Â         Total                                                               125                    118&#13;
Â &#13;
Non-interest expenses&#13;
Â  Administrativeâ&#128;&#148;Note IÂ                                                      (350)                  (344)&#13;
Â  Pensionâ&#128;&#148;Note HÂ                                                              (55)                   (58)&#13;
Â  Contributions to special programsÂ                                           (30)                   (33)&#13;
Â  Â Â  TotalÂ                                                                   (435)                  (435)&#13;
Â Â &#13;
Unrealized mark-to-market losses on Investments-Trading&#13;
 portfolio, netâ&#128;&#148;Notes F and K                                                 (52)                   (29)&#13;
Â Â &#13;
Unrealized mark-to-market gains (losses) on non-trading&#13;
 portfolios, netâ&#128;&#148;Notes D, E, F and K                                          757                   (372)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Net income (loss)                                                     $       745             $     (417)&#13;
Â  Â Â  Â Â                                                           Â Â     Â Â            Â Â    Â Â    Â Â             Â Â &#13;
Â Â Â Â  Â Â                                                           Â Â     Â Â            Â Â    Â Â    Â Â             Â Â &#13;
Â Â Â Â  Â Â                                                           Â Â     Â Â            Â Â    Â Â    Â Â             Â Â &#13;
Â Â Â Â  Â Â                                                           Â Â     Â Â            Â Â    Â Â    Â Â             Â Â &#13;
     The Notes to the Condensed Quarterly Financial Statements are an integral part of these Statements.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
18           IBRD CONDENSED QUARTERLY FINANCIAL STATEMENTS: SEPTEMBER 30, 2015 (UNAUDITED)&#13;
&amp;#12;CONDENSED STATEMENT OF COMPREHENSIVE INCOME&#13;
Expressed in millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                       Three Months Ended September 30,&#13;
                                                                                  (Unaudited)&#13;
                                                                        2015                       2014&#13;
&#13;
Net income (loss)                                                  $     745                  $    (417)&#13;
Other comprehensive incomeâ&#128;&#148;Note J&#13;
Â  Reclassification to net income:Â &#13;
Â  Â  Â  Derivatives and hedging transition adjustment                         -                         1&#13;
Â  Â Â  Â  Amortization of unrecognized net actuarial losses                  29                         45&#13;
Â  Â Â  Â  Amortization of unrecognized prior service costs                    6                          6&#13;
Â  Currency translation adjustmentÂ                                          6                       (438)&#13;
Â  Â Â  Total other comprehensive income (loss)                              41                       (386)&#13;
&#13;
Comprehensive income (loss)                                        $     786                  $    (803)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Â &#13;
Â &#13;
Â &#13;
Â &#13;
Â &#13;
CONDENSED STATEMENT OF CHANGES IN RETAINED EARNINGS&#13;
Expressed in millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                       Three Months Ended September 30,&#13;
Â  Â Â  Â Â                                                     Â Â                      (Unaudited)&#13;
                                                                        2015                    2014&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Retained earnings at beginning of the fiscal year                 $ 27,501                   $ 28,287&#13;
Â  Net income (loss) for the periodÂ                                     745                       (417)&#13;
Retained earnings at end of the period                            $ 28,246                   $ 27,870&#13;
Â  Â Â  Â Â                                                     Â Â       Â Â            Â Â    Â Â        Â Â            Â Â &#13;
Â Â  Â Â  Â Â                                                    Â Â       Â Â            Â Â    Â Â        Â Â            Â Â &#13;
Â Â  Â Â  Â Â                                                    Â Â       Â Â            Â Â    Â Â        Â Â            Â Â &#13;
       The Notes to the Condensed Quarterly Financial Statements are an integral part of these Statements.&#13;
Â  Â Â  Â Â                                                     Â Â       Â Â            Â Â    Â Â        Â Â            Â Â &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
              IBRD CONDENSED QUARTERLY FINANCIAL STATEMENTS: SEPTEMBER 30, 2015 (UNAUDITED)                     19&#13;
&amp;#12;CONDENSED STATEMENT OF CASH FLOWS&#13;
Expressed in millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
                                                                    Three Months Ended September 30,&#13;
                                                                               (Unaudited)&#13;
                                                                     2015                        2014&#13;
Cash flows from investing activities&#13;
  Loans&#13;
   Disbursements                                                $    (7,855)               $ (5,428)&#13;
   Principal repayments                                               2,282                   2,107&#13;
   Loan origination fees received                                         5                       3&#13;
  Net derivatives-loans                                                   1                      (1)&#13;
  Other investing activities, net                                       (27)                    (33)&#13;
           Net cash used in investing activities                     (5,594)                     (3,352)&#13;
Cash flows from financing activities&#13;
  Medium and long-term borrowings&#13;
   New issues                                                         8,927                     14,961&#13;
   Retirements                                                      (12,228)                   (11,209)&#13;
  Net short-term borrowings                                           8,032                     (2,564)&#13;
  Net derivatives-borrowings                                           (275)                      (218)&#13;
  Capital subscriptions                                                  32                        209&#13;
  Other capital transactions, net                                        19                         (3)&#13;
           Net cash provided by financing activities                  4,507                      1,176&#13;
Cash flows from operating activities&#13;
  Net income (loss)                                                    745                        (417)&#13;
  Adjustments to reconcile net income (loss) to net cash&#13;
   provided by operating activities&#13;
     Unrealized mark-to-market (gains) losses on non-trading&#13;
     xxportfolios, net                                                 (757)                       372&#13;
     Depreciation and amortization                                      170                        198&#13;
     Provision for losses on loans and other exposures                   98                         40&#13;
     Changes in:&#13;
       Investments-Trading, net                                       1,541                      1,447&#13;
       Other assets and liabilities                                    (186)                       571&#13;
             Net cash provided by operating activities                1,611                      2,211&#13;
Effect of exchange rate changes on unrestricted cash                     (2)                        (95)&#13;
Net increase (decrease) in unrestricted cash                           522                          (60)&#13;
Unrestricted cash at beginning of the fiscal year                      311                       3,606&#13;
Unrestricted cash at end of the period                          $      833                 $     3,546&#13;
Supplemental disclosure&#13;
  Increase (decrease) in ending balances resulting from&#13;
    exchange rate fluctuations&#13;
      Loans outstanding                                         $      (257)               $ (2,842)&#13;
      Investment portfolio                                                8                    (236)&#13;
      Borrowing portfolio                                                65                  (2,212)&#13;
  Capitalized loan origination fees included in total loans              13                         11&#13;
  Interest paid on borrowings                                            39                             8&#13;
Â  Â Â  Â Â  Â Â  Â Â  Â Â                                                                   Â Â         Â Â &#13;
 The Notes to the Condensed Quarterly Financial Statements are an integral part of these Statements.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
20           IBRD CONDENSED QUARTERLY FINANCIAL STATEMENTS: SEPTEMBER 30, 2015 (UNAUDITED)&#13;
&amp;#12;NOTES TO CONDENSED QUARTERLY FINANCIAL STATEMENTS&#13;
NOTE Aâ&#128;&#148;SUMMARY OF SIGNIFICANT ACCOUNTING AND RELATED POLICIES&#13;
Basis of Preparation&#13;
These unaudited condensed quarterly financial statements should be read in conjunction with the June 30, 2015,&#13;
audited financial statements and notes included therein. The condensed comparative information that has been&#13;
derived from the June 30, 2015, audited financial statements has not been audited. In the opinion of management,&#13;
the condensed quarterly financial statements reflect all adjustments necessary for a fair presentation of IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
financial position and results of operations in accordance with accounting principles generally accepted in the&#13;
United States of America (U.S. GAAP).&#13;
Management makes estimates and assumptions that affect the reported amounts of assets and liabilities and&#13;
disclosure of contingent assets and liabilities at the date of the condensed quarterly financial statements and the&#13;
reported amounts of income and expenses during the reporting periods. Due to the inherent uncertainty involved in&#13;
making those estimates, actual results could differ from those estimates. Areas in which significant estimates have&#13;
been made include, but are not limited to, the provision for losses on loans and other exposures, valuation of certain&#13;
instruments carried at fair value, and valuation of pension and other postretirement plan-related liabilities. The&#13;
results of operations for the first three months of the current fiscal year are not necessarily indicative of results that&#13;
may be expected for the full year.&#13;
Certain reclassifications of the prior yearâ&#128;&#153;s information have been made to conform with the current yearâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
presentation. In particular, the presentation for realized mark-to-market gains and losses on the Statement of Income&#13;
and the Statement of Cash Flows for the prior period was changed to better reflect the manner in which these&#13;
derivatives are economically hedging the related portfolios. For the Statement of Income, these amounts were&#13;
previously presented on a gross basis as part of Interest, net, for the Equity management and Borrowing portfolios,&#13;
with a corresponding offset in the related Unrealized mark-to-market gains and losses for the respective portfolios.&#13;
For the Statement of Cash flows, within the Cash flows from operating activities category, consistent with the gross&#13;
basis presentation on the Statement of Income, realized mark-to-market gains and losses, were previously shown as&#13;
part of Other assets and liabilities, with a corresponding offset in the Unrealized mark-to-market gains and losses on&#13;
non-trading portfolios, net. Under the new presentation, realized mark-to-market gains and losses are no longer&#13;
presented on a gross basis. As a result:&#13;
&#13;
    ï&#130;·    On the Statement of Income, for the three months ended September 30, 2014, interest revenue on Equity&#13;
         management, net, decreased by $581 million, while the related unrealized mark-to-market losses decreased&#13;
         by $581 million. Interest expenses on Borrowings, net, increased by $6 million while the related unrealized&#13;
         market-to-market losses, net decreased by $6 million. Similarly, interest revenue on Investments-Trading,&#13;
         net increased by $29 million while the related unrealized mark-to-market losses increased by $29 million.&#13;
         There was no net effect on net income (loss) due to this reclassification.&#13;
&#13;
    ï&#130;·    For the Statement of Cash Flows, for the three months ended September 30, 2014, Unrealized mark-to-&#13;
         market losses (gains) on non-trading portfolios, net decreased by $587 million, with a corresponding&#13;
         change in miscellaneous assets. There was no net effect on the Cash flows from operating activities in the&#13;
         Statement of Cash Flows.&#13;
&#13;
Accounting and Reporting Developments&#13;
In July 2010, the Dodd-Frank Wall Street Reform and Consumer Protection Act (the Act) became law. The Act&#13;
seeks to reform the U.S. financial regulatory system by introducing new regulators and extending regulation over&#13;
new markets, entities, and activities. The implementation of the Act is dependent on the development of various&#13;
rules to clarify and interpret its requirements. As the rules are being developed, IBRD continues to assess the impact&#13;
on its business. As of September 30, 2015, IBRD believes that the Act has not had any significant effect on its&#13;
business.&#13;
In August 2015, the FASB issued ASU 2015-14, Revenue from Contracts with Customers (Topic 606): Deferral of&#13;
the Effective Date. The ASU defers for one year the effective date of ASU 2014-09 Revenue from Contracts with&#13;
Customers. As a result, for IBRD, ASU 2014-09 will be effective beginning from the quarter ending September 30,&#13;
2018, with earlier application permitted as of the quarter ending September 30, 2017.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
             IBRD CONDENSED QUARTERLY FINANCIAL STATEMENTS: SEPTEMBER 30, 2015 (UNAUDITED)                              21&#13;
&amp;#12;NOTE Bâ&#128;&#148;CAPITAL STOCK&#13;
The following table provides a summary of changes in IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s authorized and subscribed shares during the three&#13;
months ended September 30, 2015 and the fiscal year ended June 30, 2015:&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                Authorized shares         Subscribed shares&#13;
As of June 30, 2014                                                                     2,307,600                1,929,711&#13;
 General and Selective Capital Increase (GCI/SCI)                                               -                  166,037&#13;
As of June 30, 2015                                                                    2,307,600                  2,095,748&#13;
 GCI/SCI                                                                                       -                      4,528&#13;
As of September 30, 2015                                                               2,307,600                  2,100,276&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The following table provides a summary of the changes in subscribed capital, uncalled portion of subscriptions and&#13;
paid-in capital during the three months ended September 30, 2015 and the fiscal year ended June 30, 2015:&#13;
In millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
                                                                                Uncalled portion of&#13;
                                                          Subscribed capital      subscriptions              Paid-in capital&#13;
As of June 30, 2014                                        $       232,791        $   (218,786)               $    14,005&#13;
 GCI/SCI                                                            20,030             (18,843)                     1,187&#13;
As of June 30, 2015                                                252,821            (237,629)                    15,192&#13;
 GCI/SCI                                                               546                (514)                        32&#13;
As of September 30, 2015                                   $       253,367        $   (238,143)               $    15,224&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The uncalled portion of subscriptions is subject to call only when required to meet the obligations incurred by IBRD&#13;
as a result of borrowings, or guaranteeing loans.Â &#13;
NOTE Câ&#128;&#148;INVESTMENTS&#13;
As of September 30, 2015, IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s investments include the liquid asset portfolio and, holdings relating to the&#13;
Advance Market Commitment for Pneumococcal Vaccines Initiative (AMC), Post Employment Benefit Plan&#13;
(PEBP), and the Post Retirement Contribution Reserve Fund (PCRF) which is used to stabilize IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
contributions to the pension plan.&#13;
The composition of IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s net investment portfolio as of September 30, 2015 and June 30, 2015 was as follows:&#13;
In millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
Â                                                           September 30, 2015                         June 30, 2015&#13;
Net investment portfolio&#13;
Â  Liquid asset portfolioÂ                                       $   42,982                             $     43,983&#13;
Â Â  PCRF holdingsÂ                                                       74                                         60&#13;
Â Â  AMC holdingsÂ                                                       142                                      156&#13;
Â Â  PEBP holdingsÂ                                                      869                                      906&#13;
TotalÂ                                                          $   44,067                             $     45,105&#13;
   Â &#13;
Investments held by IBRD are designated as trading and are carried and reported at fair value, or at face value which&#13;
approximates fair value. As of September 30, 2015, the majority of Investments is composed of government and&#13;
agency obligations, and time deposits (60% and 26%, respectively), with all the instruments classified as Level 1 or&#13;
Level 2 within the fair value hierarchy. As of September 30, 2015, U.S. Treasuries represented the largest holding of&#13;
a single counterparty, and amounted to 13.8% of the Investmentsâ&#128;&#147;Trading portfolio. Over 99% of IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
investments were rated A and above, as of September 30, 2015.&#13;
Â &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
22        IBRD CONDENSED QUARTERLY FINANCIAL STATEMENTS: SEPTEMBER 30, 2015 (UNAUDITED)&#13;
&amp;#12;A summary of IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s Investments-Trading at September 30, 2015 and June 30, 2015, is as follows:&#13;
In millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
                                                                  September 30, 2015                            June 30, 2015&#13;
&#13;
Â     Equity securitiesaÂ                                           $         495                             $           504&#13;
Â     Government and agency obligations Â                                  27,709                                      24,665&#13;
Â     Time deposits Â                                                      11,844                                      16,898&#13;
Â     Asset-backed securities (ABS) Â                                       5,633                                       5,653&#13;
Â     Alternative InvestmentsbÂ                                               123                                         103&#13;
Total                                                             $      45,804                             $        47,823&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
a. Includes $152 million of investments in commingled funds, related to PEBP holdings ($197 millionâ&#128;&#148;June 30, 2015).&#13;
b. Includes investments in hedge funds, private equity funds and real estate funds, related to PEBP holdings, at net asset value per&#13;
xxshare (NAV).&#13;
&#13;
IBRD manages its investments on a net portfolio basis. The following table summarizes IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s net portfolio&#13;
position as of September 30, 2015 and June 30, 2015:&#13;
In millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
Â  Â                                                                                September 30, 2015              June 30, 2015&#13;
 Â &#13;
Investments - Trading Â                                                               $     45,804                    $   47,823&#13;
Securities purchased under resale agreements                                                2,493                         2,128&#13;
Securities sold under repurchase agreements, securities lent                               (3,015)                       (3,575)&#13;
   under securities lending agreements, and payable for cash collateral&#13;
 Â  received&#13;
Derivative assets Â &#13;
Â Â     Currency forward contracts Â                                                            7,001                         4,388&#13;
Â Â     Currency swaps Â                                                                      17,756                        17,706&#13;
Â Â     Interest rate swaps Â                                                                    119                               91&#13;
Â Â     Swaptions, exchange traded options and futures contracts                                  18                              11&#13;
Â Â     Other a&#13;
                Â                                                                                  *                              -&#13;
Â Â     Total Â                                                                               24,894                        22,196&#13;
Derivative liabilities Â &#13;
Â Â     Currency forward contracts Â                                                           (7,042)                       (4,366)&#13;
Â Â     Currency swaps Â                                                                     (17,211)                       (16,787)&#13;
Â Â     Interest rate swaps Â                                                                    (117)                           (107)&#13;
Â Â     Swaptions, exchange traded options and futures contracts                                 (31)                            (19)&#13;
Â Â     OtheraÂ                                                                                     -                              (*)&#13;
Â Â     Total Â                                                                              (24,401)                       (21,279)&#13;
Cash held in investment portfoliobÂ                                                             704                           201&#13;
Receivable from investment securities tradedc                                                   38                            69&#13;
Payable for investment securities purchaseddÂ                                                (2,450)                       (2,458)&#13;
Net Investment Portfolio Â                                                            $     44,067                $       45,105&#13;
&#13;
a. These relate to Mortgage-backed Securities To-Be-Announced (TBA securities).&#13;
b. These amounts are included in Unrestricted cash under Due from banks on the Condensed Balance Sheet.&#13;
c. This amount is included in Other assets on the Condensed Balance Sheet.&#13;
d. This amount is included in Other liabilities on the Condensed Balance Sheet.&#13;
* Indicates amount less than $0.5 million.&#13;
&#13;
IBRD uses derivative instruments to manage currency and interest rate risks in the investment portfolio. For details&#13;
regarding these instruments, see Note Fâ&#128;&#148;Derivative Instruments.&#13;
As of September 30, 2015, there were $1,519 million of short sales included in Other liabilities on the Condensed&#13;
Balance Sheet ($1,635 millionâ&#128;&#148;June 30, 2015).&#13;
Â &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    IBRD CONDENSED QUARTERLY FINANCIAL STATEMENTS: SEPTEMBER 30, 2015 (UNAUDITED)                                     23&#13;
&amp;#12;Fair Value Disclosures&#13;
The following tables present IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s fair value hierarchy for investment assets and liabilities measured at fair value&#13;
on a recurring basis as of September 30, 2015 and June 30, 2015:&#13;
In millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
                                                                                                                                     Â &#13;
                                                                              Fair Value Measurements on a Recurring Basis&#13;
                                                                                                                            Â &#13;
                                                                                          As of September 30, 2015&#13;
                                                                Level 1               Level 2                 Level 3                    Total&#13;
Assets:&#13;
Â Â  Investments â&#128;&#147; Trading Â &#13;
Â Â  Â  Equity securities                                      $       343               $          -        $             -            $       495&#13;
                                                                                                                                                   a&#13;
&#13;
Â Â  Â  Government and agency obligations                           18,851                      8,858                      -                  27,709&#13;
Â Â  Â  Time deposits                                                3,196                      8,648                      -                  11,844&#13;
Â Â  Â  ABS                                                                  -                  5,633                      -                   5,633&#13;
Â Â  Â  Alternative investmentsb                                             -                      -                      -                        123&#13;
Â Â  Total Investments â&#128;&#147; Trading Â                                  22,390                     23,139                      -                  45,804&#13;
Â Â  Securities purchased under resale agreements                     464                      2,029                      -                   2,493&#13;
Â Â  Derivative assets-Investments Â &#13;
Â Â  Â  Currency forward contracts                                           -                  7,001                      -                   7,001&#13;
Â Â  Â  Currency swaps                                                       -                 17,756                      -                  17,756&#13;
Â Â  Â  Interest rate swaps                                                  -                    119                      -                        119&#13;
            Swaptions, exchange traded options and&#13;
Â Â  Â          futures contracts                                            -                     18                      -                         18&#13;
Â Â  Â  Otherc                                                               -                       *                     -                          *&#13;
Â Â  Total Derivative assets-Investments Â                                   -                 24,894                      -                  24,894&#13;
        Â &#13;
Total                                                       $    22,854               $     50,062        $             -            $     73,191&#13;
                 Â &#13;
Liabilities:&#13;
Â Â  Securities sold under repurchase agreementsÂ Â                                  Â                     Â                          Â Â &#13;
     and securities lent under securities lending&#13;
Â Â  Â  agreementsd                                            $       296               $         94        $             -            $           390&#13;
Â Â  Derivative liabilities-Investments Â &#13;
Â Â  Â  Currency forward contracts                                           -                  7,042                      -                   7,042&#13;
Â Â  Â  Currency swaps                                                       -                 17,211                      -                  17,211&#13;
Â Â  Â  Interest rate swaps                                                  -                    117                      -                        117&#13;
            Swaptions, exchange traded options and&#13;
Â Â  Â  futures contracts                                               14                         17                      -                         31&#13;
Â Â  Â  Otherc                                                               -                      -                      -                          -&#13;
Â Â  Total Derivative liabilities-Investments Â                         14                     24,387                      -                  24,401&#13;
Â Â  Payable for investments securities purchasedeÂ                  1,519                          -                      -                   1,519&#13;
        Â &#13;
Total                                                       $     1,829               $     24,481        $             -            $     26,310&#13;
&#13;
a. Includes $152 million of commingled funds at NAV, related to PEBP holdings and not included in the fair value hierarchy.&#13;
b. Investments at NAV related to PEBP holdings, not included in the fair value hierarchy.&#13;
c. These relate to TBA securities.&#13;
d. Excludes $2,625 million relating to payable for cash collateral received.&#13;
e. These relate to short sales of investments securities.&#13;
* Indicates amount less than $0.5 million.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
24             IBRD CONDENSED QUARTERLY FINANCIAL STATEMENTS: SEPTEMBER 30, 2015 (UNAUDITED)&#13;
&amp;#12;In millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
                                                                          Fair Value Measurements on a Recurring Basis&#13;
                                                                                       As of June 30, 2015&#13;
                                                                Level 1             Level 2             Level 3              Total&#13;
Assets:&#13;
Â Â  Investments â&#128;&#147; Trading Â                                                                                                    Â &#13;
&#13;
Â Â  Â  Equity securities                                      $       307             $          -    $             -      $        504&#13;
                                                                                                                                        a&#13;
&#13;
Â Â  Â  Government and agency obligations                           15,442                  9,223                    -              24,665&#13;
Â Â  Â  Time deposits                                                2,811                 14,087                    -              16,898&#13;
Â Â  Â  ABS                                                                  -              5,653                    -               5,653&#13;
Â Â  Â  Alternative investmentsb                                             -                    -                  -                  103&#13;
Â Â  Total Investments â&#128;&#147; Trading Â                             $    18,560             $   28,963      $             -      $       47,823&#13;
Â Â  Securities purchased under resale agreements                     541                  1,587                    -               2,128&#13;
Â Â  Derivative assets-Investments Â                                                                                            Â &#13;
&#13;
Â Â  Â  Currency forward contracts                                           -              4,388                    -               4,388&#13;
Â Â  Â  Currency swaps                                                       -             17,706                    -              17,706&#13;
Â Â  Â  Interest rate swaps                                                  -                   91                  -                   91&#13;
            Swaptions, exchange traded options and&#13;
Â Â  Â          futures contracts                                            *                   11                  -                   11&#13;
Â Â  Â  Otherc                                                               -                    -                  -                     -&#13;
Â Â  Total Derivative assets-Investments Â                                   *             22,196                    -              22,196&#13;
        Â &#13;
Total                                                       $    19,101             $   52,746      $             -      $       72,147&#13;
                 Â &#13;
Liabilities:&#13;
Â Â  Securities sold under repurchase agreements Â                                                                              Â &#13;
    and securities lent under securities lending&#13;
Â Â  Â  agreementsd                                            $       309             $      537      $             -      $           846&#13;
Â Â  Derivative liabilities-Investments Â &#13;
Â Â  Â  Currency forward contracts                                           -              4,366                    -               4,366&#13;
Â Â  Â  Currency swaps                                                       -             16,787                    -              16,787&#13;
Â Â  Â  Interest rate swaps                                                  -                107                    -                  107&#13;
            Swaptions, exchange traded options and&#13;
Â Â  Â  futures contracts                                                8                       11                  -                   19&#13;
Â Â  Â  Otherc                                                               -                    *                  -                     *&#13;
Â Â  Total Derivative liabilities-Investments Â                          8                 21,271                    -              21,279&#13;
Â Â  Payable for investments securities purchasedeÂ                  1,635                        -                  -               1,635&#13;
        Â &#13;
Total                                                       $     1,952             $   21,808      $             -      $       23,760&#13;
&#13;
a. Includes $197 million of commingled funds at NAV, related to PEBP holdings and not included in the fair value hierarchy.&#13;
b. Investments at NAV related to PEBP holdings, not included in the fair value hierarchy.&#13;
c. These relate to TBA securities.&#13;
d. Excludes $2,729 million relating to payable for cash collateral received.&#13;
e. These relate to short sales of investments securities.&#13;
* Indicates amount less than $0.5 million.&#13;
&#13;
During the three months ended Septermber 30, 2015, there were no transfers between Level 1 and Level 2. On June&#13;
30, 2015, $834 million of investments related to non-U.S. government obligations were transferred from Level 2 to&#13;
Level 1 within the fair value hierarchy. This transfer was based on the outcome of the annual review of the inputs&#13;
used to measure fair value.&#13;
Valuation Methods and Assumptions&#13;
Summarized below are the techniques applied in determining the fair values of investments.&#13;
Investment securities&#13;
Investment securities are classified based on managementâ&#128;&#153;s intention on the date of purchase, their nature, and&#13;
IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s policies governing the level and use of such investments. These securities are carried and reported at fair&#13;
value, or at face value or NAV, which approximates fair value. Where available, quoted market prices are used to&#13;
&#13;
                     IBRD CONDENSED QUARTERLY FINANCIAL STATEMENTS: SEPTEMBER 30, 2015 (UNAUDITED)                                   25&#13;
&amp;#12;determine the fair value of trading securities. Examples include most government and agency securities, mutual&#13;
funds, futures contracts, exchange-traded equity securities and ABS and TBA.&#13;
For instruments for which market quotations are not available, fair values are determined using model-based&#13;
valuation techniques, whether internally-generated or vendor-supplied, that include the standard discounted cash&#13;
flow method using market observable inputs such as yield curves, credit spreads, and constant prepayment rates.&#13;
Where applicable, unobservable inputs such as constant prepayment rates, probability of default and loss severity are&#13;
used. Unless quoted prices are available, time deposits are reported at face value which approximates fair value, as&#13;
they are short term in nature.&#13;
Securities purchased under resale agreements, Securities sold under repurchase agreements, and Securities lent&#13;
under securities lending agreements&#13;
These securities are of a short term nature and reported at face value which approximates fair value.&#13;
Commercial Credit Risk&#13;
For the purpose of risk management, IBRD is party to a variety of financial transactions, certain of which involve&#13;
elements of credit risk. Credit risk exposure represents the maximum potential loss due to possible nonperformance&#13;
by obligors and counterparties under the terms of the contracts. For all securities, IBRD limits trading to a list of&#13;
authorized dealers and counterparties. In addition, IBRD receives collateral in connection with resale agreements as&#13;
well as swap agreements. This collateral serves to mitigate IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s exposure to credit risk.&#13;
Swap Agreements: Credit risk is mitigated through the application of eligibility criteria and volume limits for&#13;
transactions with individual counterparties and through the use of mark-to-market collateral arrangements for swap&#13;
transactions. IBRD may require collateral in the form of cash or other approved liquid securities from individual&#13;
counterparties in order to mitigate its credit exposure.&#13;
IBRD has entered into master derivatives agreements which contain legally enforceable close-out netting provisions.&#13;
These agreements may further reduce the gross credit risk exposure related to the swaps. Credit risk with financial&#13;
assets subject to a master derivatives arrangement is further reduced under these agreements to the extent that&#13;
payments and receipts with the counterparty are netted at settlement. The reduction in exposure as a result of these&#13;
netting provisions can vary due to the impact of changes in market conditions on existing and new transactions. The&#13;
extent of the reduction in exposure may therefore change substantially within a short period of time following the&#13;
balance sheet date. For more information on netting and offsetting provisions see Note Fâ&#128;&#148;Derivative Instruments.&#13;
The following is a summary of the collateral received by IBRD in relation to swap transactions as of September 30,&#13;
2015 and June 30, 2015.&#13;
In millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
                                                                        September 30, 2015        June 30, 2015&#13;
Collateral received&#13;
 Cash                                                                       $   2,625              $    2,729&#13;
 Securities                                                                     1,583                   2,229&#13;
Total collateral received                                                   $   4,208              $    4,958&#13;
Collateral permitted to be repledged                                        $   4,208              $    4,958&#13;
Amount of collateral repledged                                                      -                       -&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
As of September 30, 2015, IBRD had received total cash collateral of $2,625 million ($2,729 millionâ&#128;&#148;June 30,&#13;
2015), of which $2,605 million was invested in highly liquid instruments ($2,714 millionâ&#128;&#148;June 30, 2015).&#13;
Securities Lending: IBRD may engage in securities lending and repurchases, against adequate collateral, as well as&#13;
securities borrowing and reverse repurchases (resales) of government and agency obligations, and corporate and&#13;
ABS. These transactions have been conducted under legally enforceable master netting arrangements, which allow&#13;
IBRD to reduce its gross credit exposure related to these transactions. For balance sheet presentation purposes,&#13;
IBRD presents its securities lending and repurchases, as well as resales, on a gross basis. As of September 30, 2015,&#13;
amounts which could potentially be offset as a result of legally enforceable master netting arrangements were $374&#13;
million ($822 millionâ&#128;&#148;June 30, 2015).&#13;
Securities lending and repurchase agreements expose IBRD to several risks, including counterparty risk,&#13;
reinvestment risk, and risk of a collateral gap (increase or decrease in the fair value of collateral pledged). IBRD has&#13;
procedures in place to ensure that trading activity and balances under these agreements are below predefined&#13;
counterparty and maturity limits, and to actively manage net counterparty exposure, after collateral, through daily&#13;
mark-to-market. Whenever the collateral pledged by IBRD related to its borrowings under repurchase agreements&#13;
&#13;
26        IBRD CONDENSED QUARTERLY FINANCIAL STATEMENTS: SEPTEMBER 30, 2015 (UNAUDITED)&#13;
&amp;#12;and securities lending agreements declines in value, the transaction is re-priced as appropriate by returning cash or&#13;
pledging additional collateral.&#13;
The following is a summary of the carrying amount of the securities transferred under repurchase or securities&#13;
lending agreements, and the related liabilities:&#13;
In millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
                                         September 30, 2015   June 30, 2015           Financial Statement Presentation&#13;
&#13;
Securities transferred under&#13;
                                                                                 Included under Investments-Trading on the&#13;
 repurchase or securities lending             $ 390             $ 844&#13;
                                                                                  Condensed Balance Sheet.&#13;
 agreements&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                 Included under Securities sold under&#13;
Liabilities relating to securities                                                repurchase agreements, securities lent&#13;
 transferred under repurchase or              $ 390             $ 846             under securities lending agreements, and&#13;
 securities lending agreements                                                    payable for cash collateral received,&#13;
                                                                                  on the Condensed Balance Sheet.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Transfers of securities by IBRD to counterparties are not accounted for as sales as IBRD still retails control over&#13;
these securities and therefore the accounting criteria for the treatment as a sale have not been met. Counterparties are&#13;
permitted to repledge these securities until the repurchase date.&#13;
At September 30, 2015, and June 30, 2015 there were no liabilities relating to securities transferred under repurchase&#13;
or securities lending agreements that had not settled at that date.&#13;
The following tables present the disaggregation of the gross obligation by class of collateral pledged and the&#13;
remaining contractual maturities for repurchase or securities lending agreements that are accounted for as secured&#13;
borrowings as of September 30, 2015 and June 30, 2015:&#13;
In millions of U.S. dollarsÂ &#13;
                                     Â                                              September 30, 2015&#13;
                                                                           Remaining contractual maturity of the&#13;
                                     Â                                                 agreements&#13;
                                                                    Overnight and&#13;
Â                                                                     continuous&#13;
                                                                                     Up to 30 days            Total&#13;
Repurchase or securities lending agreementsÂ &#13;
   Government and agency obligationsÂ                                    $ 296            $   78             $ 374&#13;
   Equity securitiesÂ                                                       16                 -                16&#13;
Total liabilities relating to securities transferred under&#13;
                                                                        $ 312            $   78             $ 390&#13;
 repurchase or securities lending agreements&#13;
&#13;
Â &#13;
In millions of U.S. dollarsÂ &#13;
                                     Â                                                 June 30, 2015&#13;
                                                                           Remaining contractual maturity of the&#13;
                                     Â                                                 agreements&#13;
                                                                    Overnight and&#13;
Â                                                                     continuous&#13;
                                                                                     Up to 30 days            Total&#13;
Repurchase or securities lending agreementsÂ &#13;
   Government and agency obligationsÂ                                    $ 557            $ 277              $ 834&#13;
   Equity securitiesÂ                                                       12                -                 12&#13;
Total liabilities relating to securities transferred under&#13;
                                                                        $ 569            $ 277              $ 846&#13;
 repurchase or securities lending agreements&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
In the case of resale agreements, IBRD receives collateral in the form of liquid securities and is permitted to&#13;
repledge these securities. While these transactions are legally considered to be true purchases and sales, the&#13;
securities received are not recorded on IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s Balance Sheet as IBRD has not obtained control over these securities&#13;
and therefore the accounting criteria for treatment as a sale have not been met. As of September 30, 2015, securities&#13;
purchased under resale agreements included $437 million of securities which had not settled at that date ($252&#13;
millionâ&#128;&#148;June 30, 2015). For the remaining purchases, IBRD received securities with a fair value of $2,048 million&#13;
($1,875 millionâ&#128;&#148;June 30, 2015). None of these securities had been transferred under repurchase or security lending&#13;
agreements as of that date (Nilâ&#128;&#148;June 30, 2015).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
               IBRD CONDENSED QUARTERLY FINANCIAL STATEMENTS: SEPTEMBER 30, 2015 (UNAUDITED)                             27&#13;
&amp;#12;NOTE Dâ&#128;&#148;LOANS AND OTHER EXPOSURES&#13;
IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s loans and other exposures (exposures) are generally made to, or guaranteed by, member countries of IBRD.&#13;
In addition, IBRD may also make loans to the International Finance Corporation (IFC), an affiliated organization,&#13;
without any guarantee. Other exposures include: Deferred Drawdown Options (DDOs), Irrevocable Commitments,&#13;
Exposures to member Countriesâ&#128;&#153; Derivatives, and Guarantees. IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s loans are reported at amortized cost, with the&#13;
exception of one loan which is carried and reported at fair value, because it contains an embedded derivative.&#13;
IBRD uses derivative contracts to manage the currency risk as well as the repricing risk between its loans and&#13;
borrowings. For details regarding derivatives used in the loan portfolio, see Note Fâ&#128;&#148;Derivative Instruments.&#13;
Of the total loans outstanding as of September 30, 2015, 82% were to the Latin America and the Caribbean, Europe&#13;
and Central Asia, and East Asia and Pacific regions, combined.&#13;
As of September 30, 2015, only 0.3% of IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s loans were in nonaccrual status and were all related to one&#13;
borrower. The total provision for losses on accrual and nonaccrual loans accounted for 1.0% of the total loan&#13;
portfolio. Based on IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s internal credit quality indicators, the majority of loans outstanding are in the medium&#13;
risk and high risk classes.&#13;
Credit Quality of Sovereign Exposures&#13;
Based on an evaluation of IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s exposures, management has determined that IBRD has one portfolio segment â&#128;&#147;&#13;
Sovereign Exposures. IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s loans constitute the majority of the Sovereign Exposures portfolio segment.&#13;
IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s country risk ratings are an assessment of its borrowersâ&#128;&#153; ability and willingness to repay IBRD on time and&#13;
in full. These ratings are internal credit quality indicators. Individual country risk ratings are derived on the basis of&#13;
both quantitative and qualitative analyses. The components considered in the analysis can be grouped broadly into&#13;
eight categories: political risk, external debt and liquidity, fiscal policy and public debt burden, balance of payments&#13;
risks, economic structure and growth prospects, monetary and exchange rate policy, financial sector risks, and&#13;
corporate sector debt and vulnerabilities. For the purpose of analyzing the risk characteristics of IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s exposures,&#13;
these exposures are grouped into three classes in accordance with assigned borrower risk ratings which relate to the&#13;
likelihood of loss: Low, Medium and High risk classes, as well as exposures in nonaccrual status. IBRD considers&#13;
all exposures in nonaccrual status to be impaired.&#13;
IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s borrowersâ&#128;&#153; country risk ratings are key determinants in the provision for losses. Country risk ratings are&#13;
determined in review meetings that take place several times a year. All countries are reviewed at least once a year,&#13;
or more frequently, if circumstances warrant, to determine the appropriate ratings.&#13;
IBRD considers loans to be past due when a borrower fails to make payment on any principal, interest or other&#13;
charges due to IBRD on the dates provided in the contractual loan agreement.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
28      IBRD CONDENSED QUARTERLY FINANCIAL STATEMENTS: SEPTEMBER 30, 2015 (UNAUDITED)&#13;
&amp;#12;The following tables provide an aging analysis of the loans outstanding as of September 30, 2015 and June 30, 2015:&#13;
In millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
                              Â                                          September 30, 2015&#13;
Days past due                     Up to 45   46-60   61-90     91-180     Over 180       Total Past Due       Current               Total&#13;
Risk Class&#13;
  Low                             $   -      $ -     $ -        $ -       $      -       $      -         $     21,495          $    21,495&#13;
  Medium                              *        -       -          -              -              *               83,868               83,868&#13;
  High                                1        -       -          -              -              1               56,409               56,410&#13;
Loans in accrual statusa              1         -        -         -             -              1              161,772              161,773&#13;
&#13;
Loans in nonaccrual&#13;
 statusa                              -         -        -         -          451             451                       -              451&#13;
&#13;
Loan at fair valueb                   -         -        -         -             -              -                 117                  117&#13;
&#13;
Total                             $   1      $ -     $ -        $ -       $ 451          $    452         $ 161,889             $ 162,341&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
In millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
                              Â                                                June 30, 2015&#13;
Days past due                     Up to 45   46-60   61-90     91-180     Over 180       Total Past Due        Current               Total&#13;
Risk Class&#13;
  Low                             $   -      $ -     $ -        $ -       $          -   $       -         $    20,574          $    20,574&#13;
  Medium                              -        -       -          -                  -           -              81,233               81,233&#13;
  High                                -        -       -          -                  -           -              54,628               54,628&#13;
Loans in accrual statusa              -         -        -          -                -           -             156,435              156,435&#13;
&#13;
Loans in nonaccrual&#13;
 statusa                              -         -        -          -          452            452                           -           452&#13;
&#13;
Loan at fair valueb                   -         -        -          -                -           -                 125                  125&#13;
&#13;
Total                             $   -      $ -     $ -        $ -       $ 452          $    452          $ 156,560            $ 157,012&#13;
&#13;
a. At amortized cost.&#13;
b. For the loan that is reported at fair value, and which is in accrual status, the credit risk assessment is incorporated&#13;
   in the determination of the fair value.&#13;
&#13;
Accumulated Provision for Losses on Loans and Other Exposures&#13;
Management determines the appropriate level of accumulated provisions for losses, which reflects the probable&#13;
losses inherent in IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s exposures. Probable losses comprise estimates of potential losses arising from default and&#13;
nonpayment of principal amounts due, as well as present value losses. Delays in receiving loan payments result in&#13;
present value losses to IBRD since it does not charge fees or additional interest on any overdue interest or charges.&#13;
These present value losses are equal to the difference between the present value of payments of interest and charges,&#13;
made according to the related instrumentâ&#128;&#153;s contractual terms and the present value of its expected future cash flows.&#13;
It is IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s practice not to write off its loans. All contractual obligations associated with exposures in nonaccrual&#13;
status have eventually been cleared, thereby allowing borrowers to eventually emerge from nonaccrual status. To&#13;
date, no loans have been written off.&#13;
Notwithstanding IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s historical experience, the risk of losses associated with nonpayment of principal amounts&#13;
due is included in the accumulated provision for losses on loans and other exposures.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                IBRD CONDENSED QUARTERLY FINANCIAL STATEMENTS: SEPTEMBER 30, 2015 (UNAUDITED)                                                 29&#13;
&amp;#12;Changes to the Accumulated provision for losses on loans and other exposures for the three months ended&#13;
September 30, 2015, and for the fiscal year ended June 30, 2015 are summarized below:&#13;
In millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
                                                                         September 30, 2015                       June 30, 2015&#13;
                                                                     Loans         Other Total               Loans      Other Total&#13;
Accumulated provision, beginning of the fiscal year                $ 1,554        $ 39 $ 1,593             $ 1,626     $ 41 $ 1,667&#13;
Provision - charge (release)                                            102          (4)     98                 (11)       1     (10)&#13;
Translation adjustment                                                    1            -       1                (61)      (3)    (64)&#13;
Accumulated provision, end of the period/fiscal year               $   1,657      $ 35     $   1,692       $   1,554   $ 39       $     1,593&#13;
  Composed of accumulated provision for losses on:&#13;
   Loans in accrual status                                         $   1,432                               $   1,328&#13;
   Loans in nonaccrual status                                            225                                     226&#13;
Total                                                              $   1,657                               $   1,554&#13;
Loans, end of the period/fiscal year:&#13;
  Loans at amortized cost in accrual status                        $ 161,773                               $ 156,435&#13;
  Loans at amortized cost in nonaccrual status                           451                                     452&#13;
  Loan at fair value in accrual status                                   117                                     125&#13;
Total                                                              $ 162,341                               $ 157,012&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                Reported as Follows&#13;
                                                   Condensed Balance Sheet                      Condensed Statement of Income&#13;
Accumulated Provision for Losses on:&#13;
Loans                                        Accumulated provision for loan losses         Provision for losses on loans and other&#13;
                                                                                            exposures&#13;
&#13;
Other exposures (excluding exposures to x Other liabilities                                Provision for losses on loans and other&#13;
xmember countriesâ&#128;&#153; derivatives)                                                             exposures&#13;
&#13;
Exposures to member countriesâ&#128;&#153;               Derivative liabilities â&#128;&#147; Client operations    Unrealized mark-to-market gains/losses on&#13;
 Derivatives                                                                               xnon-trading portfolios&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Overdue Amounts&#13;
At September 30, 2015, there were no principal or interest amounts on loans in accrual status, which were overdue&#13;
by more than three months. The following tables provide a summary of selected financial information related to&#13;
loans in nonaccrual status as of September 30, 2015 and June 30, 2015, and for the three months ended September&#13;
30, 2015 and September 30, 2014:&#13;
In millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
                                                                                          September 30, 2015            June 30, 2015&#13;
Recorded investment in nonaccrual loansa                                                      $   451                     $   452&#13;
Accumulated provision for loan losses on nonaccrual loans                                         225                         226&#13;
Average recorded investment in nonaccrual loans for the period/fiscal year                        452                         457&#13;
Overdue amounts of nonaccrual loans:                                                              882                         873&#13;
     Principal                                                                                       451                          452&#13;
     Interest and charges                                                                            431                          421&#13;
&#13;
a. A loan loss provision has been recorded against each of the loans in nonaccrual status.&#13;
In millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
                                                                                               Three Months Ended September 30,&#13;
                                                                                                     2015                   2014&#13;
Interest revenue not recognized as a result of loans being in nonaccrual status                  $     7                $     9&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
During the three months ended September 30, 2015 and September 30, 2014, no loans were placed in nonaccrual&#13;
status or restored to accrual status.&#13;
In addition, during the three months ended September 30, 2015, interest income of $2 million was recognized on&#13;
loans in nonaccrual status (Nilâ&#128;&#148;three months ended September 30, 2014).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
30        IBRD CONDENSED QUARTERLY FINANCIAL STATEMENTS: SEPTEMBER 30, 2015 (UNAUDITED)&#13;
&amp;#12;Information relating to the sole borrowing member with loans or guarantees in nonaccrual status at September 30,&#13;
2015, is as follows:&#13;
In millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
Â                                                       Principal       Principal, Interest and     Nonaccrual&#13;
Borrower                                              Outstanding        Charges overdue             Since&#13;
&#13;
Zimbabwe                                                $ 451               $ 882                 October 2000&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Guarantees&#13;
Guarantees of $1,670 million were outstanding at September 30, 2015 ($1,432 millionâ&#128;&#148;June 30, 2015). This&#13;
amount represents the maximum potential amount of undiscounted future payments that IBRD could be required to&#13;
make under these guarantees, and is not included in the Condensed Balance Sheet. These guarantees have original&#13;
maturities ranging between 5 and 20 years, and expire in decreasing amounts through 2029.&#13;
At September 30, 2015, liabilities related to IBRD's obligations under guarantees of $60 million ($42 millionâ&#128;&#148;June&#13;
30, 2015), have been included in Other liabilities on the Condensed Balance Sheet. These include the accumulated&#13;
provision for guarantee losses of $23 million ($17 millionâ&#128;&#148;June 30, 2015).&#13;
During the three months ended September 30, 2015 and September 30, 2014, no guarantees provided by IBRD were&#13;
called.&#13;
Waivers of Loan Charges&#13;
IBRD provides waivers on eligible loans, which include a portion of interest on loans, a portion of the commitment&#13;
charge on undisbursed balances and a portion of the front-end fee charged on all eligible loans. Waivers are&#13;
approved annually by the Executive Directors of IBRD.&#13;
The reduction in net income for the three months ended September 30, 2015 and September 30, 2014, resulting from&#13;
waivers of loan charges is summarized below:&#13;
In millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
                                                                         Three Months Ended September 30,&#13;
                                                                           2015                    2014&#13;
Interest waivers                                                          $ 22                    $ 27&#13;
Commitment charge waivers                                                     1                      1&#13;
Front-end fee waivers                                                         4                      5&#13;
Total                                                                     $ 27                    $ 33&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Segment Reporting&#13;
Based on an evaluation of IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s operations, management has determined that IBRD has only one reportable&#13;
segment since financial results are reviewed, and resource allocation decisions are made, at the entity level.&#13;
Loan income comprises interest, commitment fees, loan origination fees and prepayment premia, net of waivers. For&#13;
the three months ended September 30, 2015, one country contributed in excess of 10 percent of total loan revenue;&#13;
this amounted to $63 million.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
               IBRD CONDENSED QUARTERLY FINANCIAL STATEMENTS: SEPTEMBER 30, 2015 (UNAUDITED)                       31&#13;
&amp;#12;Information about IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s loans outstanding and associated loan revenue by geographic region, as of, and for the&#13;
three months ended September 30, 2015 and September 30, 2014, is presented in the following table:&#13;
                              Â &#13;
In millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
Â &#13;
Â                        Â                                September 30, 2015                                September 30, 2014&#13;
                                                                                                                               Â &#13;
          Â                                                                           b&#13;
Region                                         Loans Outstanding    Loan Revenue          Loans Outstanding           Loan Revenueb&#13;
Â  Africa Â                                        $    3,344           $    45               $    2,523                  $    23&#13;
Â Â  East Asia and Pacific Â                            34,277                  112                    30,526                         100&#13;
                                                                                                                                              Â &#13;
&#13;
Â Â  Europe and Central Asia Â                          43,877                  102                    43,648                         113&#13;
                                                                                                                                              Â &#13;
&#13;
Â Â  Latin America and the Caribbean Â                  54,650                  250                    52,059                         240&#13;
                                                                                                                                              Â &#13;
&#13;
Â Â  Middle East and North Africa Â                     12,379                   35                    12,341                           38&#13;
                                                                                                                                              Â &#13;
&#13;
Â Â  South Asia Â                                       13,601                   27                    13,196                           21&#13;
                                                                                                                                              Â &#13;
&#13;
Â Â  OtheraÂ                                               213                      *                        221                             *&#13;
                                                                                                                                              Â &#13;
&#13;
Â Â  Total Â                                        $ 162,341            $      571             $ 154,514                  $          535&#13;
                                                                                                                                              Â &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
a. Represents loans to IFC, an affiliated organization.&#13;
b. Does not include interest expenses, net from loan related derivatives of $234 million ($241 millionâ&#128;&#148;September 30, 2014).&#13;
                                                                                 Â &#13;
   Includes commitment charges of $7 million ($4 millionâ&#128;&#148;September 30, 2014).&#13;
                                           Â Â &#13;
* Indicates amount less than $0.5 million.&#13;
&#13;
Fair Value Disclosures&#13;
The only loan carried at fair value is classified as Level 3. This loan has an embedded derivative and its fair value is&#13;
estimated on a matrix basis against the related bond. As IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s loans are not traded, the yield which is used as a&#13;
key input to determining the fair value of this loan is not observable. The yield applied in determining the fair value&#13;
of the loan at September 30, 2015 was 6.2%. An increase (decrease) in the yield would result in a decrease&#13;
(increase) in the fair value of the loan.&#13;
The following table provides a summary of changes in the fair value of IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s Level 3 loan during the three&#13;
months ended September 30, 2015 and September 30, 2014:&#13;
In millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
Â  Â Â  Â Â                                                                                       Three Months Ended September 30,&#13;
Â  Â Â  Â Â                                                                                         2015                          2014&#13;
Beginning of the fiscal year                                                                  $ 125                         $ 141&#13;
Total realized/unrealized gains (losses) in:&#13;
Â  Â Â  Net incomeÂ                                                                                      1                               2&#13;
Â  Â Â  Other comprehensive lossÂ                                                                       (9)                            (11)&#13;
End of the period                                                                             $ 117                         $ 132&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Information on unrealized mark-to-market gains or losses, relating to IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s Level 3 loan, included in revenue, for&#13;
the three months ended September 30, 2015 and September 30, 2014 as well as where those amounts are included in&#13;
the Condensed Statement of Income, is presented in the following table:&#13;
In millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
Â  Â                                                                                       Three Months Ended September 30,&#13;
Unrealized Gains (Losses)                                                                  2015                        2014&#13;
Condensed Statement of Income location&#13;
 Unrealized mark-to-market losses on non-trading portfolios, net                          $ (3)                        $ (*)&#13;
&#13;
* Indicates amount less than $0.5 million.                                                  Â Â  Â Â            Â Â           Â Â  Â Â                      Â Â &#13;
The table below presents the fair value of all IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s loans for disclosure purposes, along with their carrying values&#13;
as of September 30, 2015 and June 30, 2015:&#13;
In millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
                                                      September 30, 2015                                    June 30, 2015&#13;
                    Â                   Â      Carrying Value         Fair Value             Carrying Value               Fair Value&#13;
Net Loans Outstanding                        $ 160,258             $ 160,090               $ 155,040                   $ 155,910&#13;
&#13;
Â &#13;
&#13;
32            IBRD CONDENSED QUARTERLY FINANCIAL STATEMENTS: SEPTEMBER 30, 2015 (UNAUDITED)&#13;
&amp;#12;Valuation Methods and Assumptions&#13;
All IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s loans are made to, or guaranteed by, countries that are members of IBRD, except for those loans made&#13;
to IFC. IBRD does not currently sell its loans.&#13;
As of September 30, 2015 and June 30, 2015, except for one loan which is reported at fair value, all other loans are&#13;
carried at amortized cost. The fair value of these loans is calculated using a discounted cash flow method. This&#13;
method incorporates Credit Default Swap spreads for each borrower. Basis adjustments are applied to market&#13;
recovery levels to reflect IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s recovery experience. IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s loans, including the one reported at fair value on a&#13;
recurring basis, are classified as Level 3, within the fair value hierarchy.&#13;
NOTE Eâ&#128;&#148;BORROWINGS&#13;
IBRD issues unsubordinated and unsecured fixed and variable rate debt in a variety of currencies. Some of these&#13;
debt instruments are callable. Variable rates may be based on, for example, exchange rates, interest rates or equity&#13;
indices.&#13;
Borrowings issued by IBRD are carried and reported at fair value. As of September 30, 2015, 99% of the&#13;
instruments in the portfolio were classified as Level 2, within the fair value hierarchy.&#13;
IBRD uses derivative contracts to manage the currency risk as well as the repricing risk between its loans and&#13;
borrowings. For details regarding the derivatives used in the borrowing portfolio, see Note Fâ&#128;&#148;Derivative&#13;
Instruments.&#13;
The following table summarizes IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s borrowing portfolio after derivatives at September 30, 2015 and June 30,&#13;
2015:&#13;
 In millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
                                                                      September 30, 2015                    June 30, 2015&#13;
 Borrowingsa                                                          $    169,592                      $      160,980&#13;
 Currency swaps, net                                                           3,402                             1,433&#13;
 Interest rate swaps, net                                                      (4,286)                           (3,560)&#13;
 Â Â                                                                    $      168,708                    $     158,853&#13;
&#13;
 a. Includes $5,872 million of unsettled borrowings, representing a non-cash financing activity, for which there is a related&#13;
 xxreceivable included in Other assets on the Condensed Balance Sheet ($225 millionâ&#128;&#148;June 30, 2015).&#13;
Interest, net for Borrowings on the Condensed Statement of Income includes $767 million of interest revenue, net&#13;
related to derivatives associated with the Borrowing portfolio ($901 millionâ&#128;&#148;three months ended September 30,&#13;
2014).&#13;
Fair Value Disclosures&#13;
IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s fair value hierarchy for borrowings measured at fair value on a recurring basis as of September 30, 2015 and&#13;
June 30, 2015 is as follows:&#13;
In millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
                                                                           September 30, 2015                June 30, 2015&#13;
Level 1                                                                        $       -                      $        -&#13;
Level 2                                                                          167,550                        158,574&#13;
Level 3                                                                            2,042                           2,406&#13;
                                                                                $ 169,592                     $ 160,980&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The following table provides a summary of changes in the fair value of IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s Level 3 borrowings during the three&#13;
months ended September 30, 2015 and September 30, 2014:&#13;
In millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
                                                                                  Three Months Ended September 30,&#13;
                                                                                  2015                            2014&#13;
Beginning of the fiscal year                                                  $    2,406                     $     3,883&#13;
Total realized/unrealized mark-to-market (gains) losses in:&#13;
  Net income                                                                        (105)                           220&#13;
  Other comprehensive income                                                          (6)                          (256)&#13;
Issuances                                                                              7                            286&#13;
Settlements                                                                         (272)                          (500)&#13;
Transfers into (out of), net                                                          12                           (150)&#13;
End of the period                                                             $    2,042                     $    3,483&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
               IBRD CONDENSED QUARTERLY FINANCIAL STATEMENTS: SEPTEMBER 30, 2015 (UNAUDITED)                                    33&#13;
&amp;#12;Information on the unrealized mark-to-market gains or losses included in the condensed Statement of Income for the&#13;
three months ended September 30, 2015 and September 30, 2014, relating to IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s Level 3 borrowings still held at&#13;
the reporting dates, as well as where those amounts are included in the Condensed Statement of Income, is presented&#13;
in the following table:Â &#13;
In millions of U.S. dollarsÂ &#13;
                                                                                  Three Months Ended September 30,&#13;
Unrealized Gains (Losses)                                                              2015                   2014&#13;
Condensed Statement of Income location&#13;
Unrealized mark-to-market gains (losses) on non-trading portfolios, net            $      75              $ (151)&#13;
&#13;
The following table provides information on the unrealized mark-to-market gains or losses included in the&#13;
condensed Statement of Income for the three months ended September 30, 2015 and September 30, 2014, relating to&#13;
IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s total borrowings held at the reporting dates, as well as where those amounts are included in the Condensed&#13;
Statement of Income:Â &#13;
In millions of U.S. dollarsÂ &#13;
                                                                                       Three Months Ended September 30,&#13;
Unrealized Gains (Losses)                                                              2015                   2014&#13;
Condensed Statement of Income location&#13;
Unrealized mark-to-market (losses) gains on non-trading portfolios , net           $ (477)                $     21&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
During the three months ended September 30, 2015, IBRD credit spreads widened. The estimated financial effects&#13;
on the fair value of the debt issued and outstanding as of September 30, 2015, were unrealized mark-to-market gains&#13;
of $665 million. During the three months ended September 30, 2014, IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s credit spreads tightened. The&#13;
estimated financial effects on the fair value of the debt issued and outstanding as of September 30, 2014, were&#13;
unrealized mark-to-market losses of $153 million.&#13;
IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s Level 3 borrowings primarily relate to structured bonds. The fair value of these bonds is estimated using&#13;
valuation models that incorporate model parameters, observable market inputs, and unobservable inputs. The&#13;
significant unobservable inputs used in the fair value measurement of structured bonds are correlations and long-&#13;
dated interest rate volatilities. Generally, the movements in correlations are considered to be independent from the&#13;
movements in long-dated interest rate volatilities.&#13;
Correlation is the statistical measurement of the relationship between two variables. For contracts where the holder&#13;
benefits from the convergence of the underlying index prices (e.g. interest rates and foreign exchange rates), an&#13;
increase in correlation generally results in an increase in the fair value of the instrument. The magnitude and&#13;
direction of the fair value adjustment will depend on whether the holder is short or long the option.&#13;
Interest rate volatility is the extent to which the level of interest rates change over time. For purchased options, an&#13;
increase in volatility will generally result in an increase in the fair value. In general, the volatility used to price the&#13;
option depends on the maturity of the underlying instrument and the option strike price. For IBRD, interest rate&#13;
volatilities are considered an unobservable input for maturities greater than ten years for certain currencies.&#13;
The following table provides a summary of the valuation technique applied in determining fair values of these Level&#13;
3 instruments and quantitative information regarding the significant unobservable inputs used.&#13;
In millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
                  Fair Value at   Fair Value&#13;
                 September 30,    at June 30,     Valuation     Unobservable      Range (average),        Range (average),&#13;
Portfolio             2015           2015        Technique         input         September 30, 2015        June 30, 2015&#13;
&#13;
                                                                 Correlations    -52% to 75% (8%)         -50% to 72% (2%)&#13;
                                                Discounted&#13;
 Borrowings          $2,042         $2,406                       Long-dated&#13;
                                                Cash Flow&#13;
                                                                 interest rate   20% to 53% (37%)        19% to 71% (36%)&#13;
                                                                  volatilities&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
34          IBRD CONDENSED QUARTERLY FINANCIAL STATEMENTS: SEPTEMBER 30, 2015 (UNAUDITED)&#13;
&amp;#12;The table below provides the details of all gross inter-level transfers for the three months ended September 30, 2015&#13;
and September 30, 2014. Transfers between Level 2 and Level 3 are due to changes in price transparency.&#13;
In millions of U.S. dollars                                                               Â Â       Â Â    Â Â           Â Â        Â Â &#13;
Â                                                   Three Months Ended                          Three Months Ended&#13;
                                                   September 30, 2015                          September 30, 2014&#13;
                                               Level 2              Level 3              Level 2Â                  Level 3&#13;
Borrowings&#13;
Transfers into (out of)                        $     9              $   (9)              $ 152                   $ (152)&#13;
Transfers (out of) into                            (21)                 21                     (2)                      2&#13;
                                               $   (12)             $   12               $ 150                   $ (150)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Presented below is the difference between the aggregate fair value and aggregate contractual principal balance of&#13;
borrowings:&#13;
In millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
                                                                               Principal Amount&#13;
                                                           Fair Value         Due Upon Maturity            Difference&#13;
September 30, 2015                                        $ 169,592              $ 168,626             $          966&#13;
June 30, 2015                                             $ 160,980              $ 160,568             $          412&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Valuation Methods and Assumptions&#13;
Techniques applied in determining the fair values of debt instruments are summarized as follows:&#13;
Discount notes and vanilla bonds&#13;
Discount notes and vanilla bonds are valued using the standard discounted cash flow method which relies on market&#13;
observable inputs such as yield curves, foreign exchange rates, basis spreads and funding spreads, where available,&#13;
quoted marked prices are used to determine the fair value of short-term notes.&#13;
Structured bonds&#13;
Structured bonds issued by IBRD have coupon or repayment terms linked to the level or the performance of interest&#13;
rates, foreign exchange rates, equity indices or commodities. The fair value of the structured bonds is derived using&#13;
the discounted cash flow method based on estimated future pay-offs determined by applicable models and&#13;
computation of embedded optionality such as caps, floors and calls. A wide range of industry standard models such&#13;
as one factor Hull-White, LIBOR Market Model and Black-Scholes are used depending on the specific structure.&#13;
These models incorporate market observable inputs, such as yield curves, foreign exchange rates, basis spreads,&#13;
funding spreads, interest rates volatilities, equity index volatilities and equity indices. Where applicable, the models&#13;
also incorporate significant unobservable inputs such as correlations and long-dated interest rate volatilities.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
               IBRD CONDENSED QUARTERLY FINANCIAL STATEMENTS: SEPTEMBER 30, 2015 (UNAUDITED)                                     35&#13;
&amp;#12;NOTE Fâ&#128;&#148;DERIVATIVE INSTRUMENTS&#13;
IBRD uses derivative instruments in its investment, loan and borrowing portfolios, and for asset/liability&#13;
management purposes (including equity management). It also offers derivatives intermediation services to clients&#13;
and concurrently enters into offsetting transactions with market counterparties.&#13;
The following table summarizes IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s use of derivatives in its various financial portfolios:&#13;
    Portfolio                            Derivative instruments used                       Purpose / Risk being managed&#13;
&#13;
    Risk management&#13;
      purposes:&#13;
                                 Currency swaps, interest rate swaps,&#13;
                                   currency forward contracts, options,            Manage currency and interest rate risks in the&#13;
      Investments&#13;
                                   swaptions and futures contracts, TBA              portfolio&#13;
                                   securities&#13;
                                                                                   Manage currency risk as well as repricing risks&#13;
      Loans                      Currency swaps, and interest rate swaps&#13;
                                                                                     between loans and borrowings&#13;
                                                                                   Manage currency risk as well as repricing risks&#13;
      Borrowings                 Currency swaps, and interest rate swaps&#13;
                                                                                     between loans and borrowings&#13;
      Other                                                                        Manage currency risk and the duration of IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
                                 Currency swaps, and interest rate swaps&#13;
        assets/liabilities                                                           equity (equity management)&#13;
&#13;
    Other purposes:&#13;
      Client operations          Currency swaps, and interest rate swaps           Assist clients in managing risks&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The following tables provide information on the fair value amounts and the location of the derivative instruments on&#13;
the Condensed Balance Sheet, as well as notional amounts and credit risk exposures of those derivative instruments&#13;
as of September 30, 2015 and June 30, 2015:&#13;
Fair value of derivative instruments on the Condensed Balance Sheet:&#13;
In millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
                                                                              Balance Sheet Location&#13;
                                                          Derivative Assets                          Derivative Liabilities&#13;
                                                September 30, 2015     June 30, 2015       September 30, 2015         June 30, 2015&#13;
Derivatives not designated as&#13;
 hedging instruments&#13;
    Swaptions, exchange traded options and&#13;
Â     futures contracts â&#128;&#147; Investment-Trading Â      $         18            $       11         $          31            $         19&#13;
    Interest rate swaps                                  8,378                  6,510                5,244                    4,450&#13;
    Currency swapsa                                   128,093                 127,804             130,214                 127,855&#13;
    Otherb                                                     *                    -                     -                       *&#13;
Total Derivatives                                 $   136,489             $ 134,325          $    135,489             $ 132,324&#13;
&#13;
a. Includes currency forward contracts and structured swaps.&#13;
b. These relate to TBA securities.&#13;
* Indicates amount less than $0.5 million.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
36           IBRD CONDENSED QUARTERLY FINANCIAL STATEMENTS: SEPTEMBER 30, 2015 (UNAUDITED)&#13;
&amp;#12;Notional amounts and credit risk exposure of the derivative instruments:&#13;
In millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
Â  Â Â  Â Â  Â                                                               September 30, 2015                June 30, 2015&#13;
Type of contract&#13;
Investments - Trading&#13;
Â  Interest rate swaps Â &#13;
Â    Â Â  Notional principal Â                                               $      9,363                   $         8,755&#13;
Â    Â Â  Credit exposure Â                                                           119                               91&#13;
Â    Currency swaps (including currency forward contracts)&#13;
Â    Â Â  Credit exposure Â                                                           797                             1,136&#13;
Â    Swaptions, exchange traded options and futures contractsa&#13;
Â    Â Â  Notional long position Â                                                  1,761                             1,313&#13;
Â    Â Â  Notional short position Â                                                 5,274                             7,224&#13;
Â    Â Â  Credit exposure Â                                                            18                               11&#13;
Â    Other derivativesbÂ &#13;
Â    Â Â  Notional long position Â                                                     28                               28&#13;
Â    Â Â  Notional short position Â                                                      -                                 -&#13;
Â    Â Â  Credit exposure Â                                                              *                                 -&#13;
Loans&#13;
Â  Interest rate swaps Â &#13;
Â  Â Â  Notional principal Â                                                       27,677                            28,118&#13;
Â  Â Â  Credit exposure Â                                                              71                              139&#13;
Â  Currency swaps Â &#13;
Â  Â Â  Credit exposure Â                                                             821                              507&#13;
Client operations&#13;
Â  Interest rate swaps Â &#13;
Â  Â Â  Notional principal Â                                                       22,488                            23,024&#13;
Â  Â Â  Credit exposure Â                                                           1,606                             1,221&#13;
Â  Currency swaps Â &#13;
Â  Â Â  Credit exposure Â                                                           1,783                             1,657&#13;
Borrowings&#13;
Â  Interest rate swaps Â &#13;
Â  Â Â  Notional principal Â                                                      188,656                           184,491&#13;
Â  Â Â  Credit exposure Â                                                           4,965                             4,325&#13;
Â  Currency swaps Â &#13;
Â  Â Â  Credit exposure Â                                                           7,777                             8,025&#13;
Other derivatives&#13;
Â  Interest rate swaps Â &#13;
Â  Â Â  Notional principal Â                                                       53,929                            45,647&#13;
Â  Â Â  Credit exposure Â                                                           1,617                              734&#13;
Â  Currency swaps Â &#13;
Â  Â  Credit exposure                                                                  -                                 -&#13;
Â                                                                                                            Â &#13;
a. Exchange traded instruments are generally subject to daily margin requirements and are deemed to have no material&#13;
   credit risk. All swaptions, options, and futures contracts are interest rate contracts.&#13;
b. These relate to TBA securities.&#13;
&#13;
IBRD is not required to post collateral under its derivative agreements as long as it maintains a AAA credit rating.&#13;
The aggregate fair value of all derivative instruments with credit-risk related contingent features that are in a liability&#13;
position on September 30, 2015 is $5,270 million ($4,230 millionâ&#128;&#148;June 30, 2015). IBRD has not posted any&#13;
collateral with these counterparties due to its AAA credit rating.&#13;
If the credit-risk related contingent features underlying these agreements were triggered to the extent that IBRD&#13;
would be required to post collateral on September 30, 2015, the amount of collateral that would need to be posted&#13;
would be $2,411 million ($1,709 millionâ&#128;&#148;June 30, 2015). Subsequent triggers of contingent features would require&#13;
posting of additional collateral, up to a maximum of $5,270 million ($4,230 millionâ&#128;&#148;June 30, 2015). In contrast,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                  IBRD CONDENSED QUARTERLY FINANCIAL STATEMENTS: SEPTEMBER 30, 2015 (UNAUDITED)                            37&#13;
&amp;#12;IBRD received collateral totaling $4,208 million as of September 30, 2015 ($4,958 millionâ&#128;&#148;June 30, 2015), in&#13;
relation to swap transactions (see Note Câ&#128;&#148;Investments).&#13;
The following table provides information on the location and amount of unrealized mark-to-market gains and losses&#13;
on the non-trading derivatives during the three months ended September 30, 2015, and September 30, 2014, and&#13;
their location on the Condensed Statement of Income:&#13;
In millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
                                                 Condensed Income Statement location         Unrealized mark-to-market gains (losses)&#13;
                                                                                                 Three Months Ended September 30,&#13;
                                                                                                       2015                  2014&#13;
Derivatives not designated as hedging&#13;
  instruments, and not held in a trading&#13;
  portfolioa&#13;
Interest rate swaps                                                                                $     981             $    (532)&#13;
Currency swaps (including currency              Unrealized mark-to-market gains (losses)&#13;
 forward contracts and structured                on non-trading portfolios, net                          256                   139&#13;
 swaps)&#13;
Total                                                                                              $    1,237            $    (393)&#13;
&#13;
a. For alternative disclosures about trading derivatives, see the following table.&#13;
&#13;
All of the instruments in IBRD's investment portfolio are held for trading purposes. Within the investment portfolio,&#13;
IBRD holds highly rated fixed income instruments, equity securities as well as derivatives.&#13;
The following table provides information on the location and amount of gains and losses on the net investment â&#128;&#147;&#13;
trading portfolio and their location on the Condensed Statement of Income during the three months ended September&#13;
30, 2015 and September 30, 2014:&#13;
                              Â &#13;
In millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
                                                                                     Unrealized mark-to-market gains (losses) on&#13;
                                            Â                                                                             a&#13;
Condensed Statement of Income Location                                                           Investments-Trading, net&#13;
Â                                                                                                                                          Â &#13;
                                                                                         Three Months Ended September 30,&#13;
Â                                                                                                                                          Â &#13;
                                                                                          2015                         2014&#13;
                      Â &#13;
Type of instrument&#13;
Â                                                                                                                                      Â &#13;
    Fixed income (including associated derivatives)                                  $    (31)                     $   (25)&#13;
Â                                                                                                                                      Â &#13;
    Equityb                                                                               (21)                          (4)&#13;
        Â &#13;
Total                                                                                $    (52)                     $   (29)&#13;
&#13;
a. Amounts associated with each type of instrument include gains and losses on both derivative instruments and non-derivative&#13;
                Â &#13;
   instruments.&#13;
b. Includes alternative investments, related to PEBP holdings.&#13;
&#13;
Offsetting assets and liabilities&#13;
IBRD enters into International Swaps and Derivatives Association, Inc. (ISDA) master netting agreements with&#13;
substantially all of its derivative counterparties. These legally enforceable master netting agreements give IBRD the&#13;
right to liquidate securities held as collateral and to offset receivables and payables with the same counterparty, in&#13;
the event of default by the counterparty.&#13;
The presentation of derivative instruments is consistent with the manner in which these instruments are settled.&#13;
Interest rate swaps are settled on a net basis, while currency swaps are settled on a gross basis.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
38            IBRD CONDENSED QUARTERLY FINANCIAL STATEMENTS: SEPTEMBER 30, 2015 (UNAUDITED)&#13;
&amp;#12;The following table summarizes information on derivative assets and liabilities (before and after netting&#13;
adjustments) that are reflected on IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s Condensed Balance Sheet as of September 30, 2015 and June 30, 2015.&#13;
Total derivative assets and liabilities are adjusted on an aggregate basis to take into consideration the effects of&#13;
legally enforceable master netting agreements. The net derivative asset positions have been further reduced by the&#13;
cash and securities collateral received.&#13;
In millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
                                                                     September 30, 2015&#13;
                                                           Located on the Condensed Balance Sheet&#13;
                                            Derivative Assets                                Derivative Liabilities&#13;
                              Gross Amounts Gross Amounts Net Amounts           Gross Amounts Gross Amounts Net Amounts&#13;
                               Recognized        Offset       Presented          Recognized         Offset          Presented&#13;
Interest rate swaps            $    24,978    $ (16,600)        $     8,378      $    17,962     $ (12,718)     $     5,244&#13;
Currency swapsa                    128,093             -            128,093          130,214              -         130,214&#13;
Otherb                                  18             -                 18               31              -              31&#13;
 Total                         $ 153,089      $ (16,600)        $   136,489      $ 148,207       $ (12,718)     $   135,489&#13;
Amounts subject to&#13;
 legally enforcable&#13;
                                                                    (130,128)                                       (130,128)&#13;
 master netting&#13;
 agreementsc&#13;
Net derivative&#13;
 positions at&#13;
                                                                       6,361                                           5,361&#13;
 counterparty level&#13;
 before collateral&#13;
Less:&#13;
 Cash collateral&#13;
  receivedd                                                            2,180&#13;
 Securities collateral&#13;
                                                                       1,344&#13;
  receivedd&#13;
Net derivative&#13;
 exposure after                                                 $      2,837&#13;
 collateral&#13;
a. Includes currency forward contracts and structured swaps.&#13;
b. These relate to swaptions, exchange traded options, futures contracts and TBA securities.&#13;
c. Not offset on the Condensed Balance Sheet.&#13;
d. Does not include excess collateral received.&#13;
In millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
                                                                        June 30, 2015&#13;
                                                           Located on the Condensed Balance Sheet&#13;
                                            Derivative Assets                                Derivative Liabilities&#13;
                              Gross Amounts Gross Amounts Net Amounts           Gross Amounts Gross Amounts Net Amounts&#13;
                               Recognized        Offset       Presented          Recognized         Offset          Presented&#13;
Interest rate swaps            $    24,968    $ (18,458)        $     6,510      $    16,938     $ (12,488)     $     4,450&#13;
Currency swapsa                    127,804             -            127,804          127,855              -         127,855&#13;
Otherb                                  11             -                 11               22            (3)              19&#13;
 Total                         $ 152,783      $ (18,458)        $   134,325      $ 144,815       $ (12,491)     $   132,324&#13;
Amounts subject to&#13;
 legally enforcable&#13;
                                                                    (128,010)                                       (128,010)&#13;
 master netting&#13;
 agreementsc&#13;
Net derivatives&#13;
 positions at&#13;
                                                                       6,315                                           4,314&#13;
 counterparty level&#13;
 before collateral&#13;
Less:&#13;
 Cash collateral&#13;
  receivedd                                                            2,284&#13;
 Securities collateral&#13;
                                                                       1,609&#13;
  receivedd&#13;
Net derivative&#13;
 exposure after                                                 $      2,422&#13;
 collateral&#13;
&#13;
a. Includes currency forward contracts and structured swaps.&#13;
b. These relate to swaptions, exchange traded options, futures contracts and TBA securities.&#13;
c. Not offset on the Condensed Balance Sheet.&#13;
d. Does not include excess collateral received.&#13;
&#13;
               IBRD CONDENSED QUARTERLY FINANCIAL STATEMENTS: SEPTEMBER 30, 2015 (UNAUDITED)                                39&#13;
&amp;#12;Fair Value Disclosures&#13;
IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s fair value hierarchy for derivative assets and liabilities measured at fair value on a recurring basis as of&#13;
September 30, 2015 and June 30, 2015 is as follows:&#13;
In millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
                                                               Fair Value Measurements on a Recurring Basis&#13;
                                                                        As of September 30, 2015&#13;
                                                 Level 1                Level 2               Level 3             Total&#13;
Derivative Assets:&#13;
 Investments&#13;
   Currency forward contracts                $             -        $    7,001           $         -          $    7,001&#13;
   Currency swaps                                          -            17,756                     -              17,756&#13;
   Interest rate swaps                                     -               119                     -                 119&#13;
   Swaptions, exchange traded options&#13;
     and futures contracts                                 -                18                     -                  18&#13;
   Othera                                                  -                  *                    -                    *&#13;
                                                           -            24,894                     -              24,894&#13;
    Loans&#13;
      Currency swaps                                       -             3,921                  130                4,051&#13;
      Interest rate swaps                                  -                71                    -                   71&#13;
                                                           -             3,992                  130                4,122&#13;
    Client operations&#13;
      Currency swaps                                       -            26,743                     -              26,743&#13;
      Interest rate swaps                                  -             1,606                     -               1,606&#13;
                                                           -            28,349                     -              28,349&#13;
    Borrowings&#13;
     Currency swaps                                        -            70,868                1,179               72,047&#13;
     Interest rate swaps                                   -             4,952                   13                4,965&#13;
                                                           -            75,820                1,192               77,012&#13;
    Other assets/liabilities&#13;
     Currency swaps                                        -              495                     -                 495&#13;
     Interest rate swaps                                   -            1,617                     -               1,617&#13;
                                                           -            2,112                     -               2,112&#13;
    Total derivative assets                  $             -        $ 135,167            $    1,322           $ 136,489&#13;
Derivative Liabilities:&#13;
 Investments&#13;
   Currency forward contracts                $             -        $    7,042           $         -          $    7,042&#13;
   Currency swaps                                          -            17,211                     -              17,211&#13;
   Interest rate swaps                                     -               117                     -                 117&#13;
   Swaptions, exchange traded options&#13;
     and futures contracts                            14                    17                     -                  31&#13;
   Othera                                              -                     -                     -                   -&#13;
                                                      14                24,387                     -              24,401&#13;
    Loans&#13;
      Currency swaps                                       -             3,129                  101                3,230&#13;
      Interest rate swaps                                  -             2,766                    -                2,766&#13;
                                                           -             5,895                  101                5,996&#13;
    Client operations&#13;
      Currency swaps                                       -            26,735                     -              26,735&#13;
      Interest rate swaps                                  -             1,615                     -               1,615&#13;
                                                           -            28,350                     -              28,350&#13;
    Borrowings&#13;
     Currency swaps                                        -            74,271                1,178               75,449&#13;
     Interest rate swaps                                   -               582                   97                  679&#13;
                                                           -            74,853                1,275               76,128&#13;
    Other assets/liabilities&#13;
     Currency swaps                                        -               547                     -                 547&#13;
     Interest rate swaps                                   -                67                     -                  67&#13;
                                                           -               614                     -                 614&#13;
Total derivative liabilities                 $        14            $ 134,099            $    1,376           $ 135,489&#13;
&#13;
a.These relate to TBA securities.&#13;
* Indicates amount less than $0.5 million.&#13;
Â                                         Â &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
40          IBRD CONDENSED QUARTERLY FINANCIAL STATEMENTS: SEPTEMBER 30, 2015 (UNAUDITED)&#13;
&amp;#12;In millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
                                                               Fair Value Measurements on a Recurring Basis&#13;
                                                                             As of June 30, 2015&#13;
                                                 Level 1                Level 2               Level 3             Total&#13;
Derivative Assets:&#13;
 Investments&#13;
   Currency forward contracts                $             -       $      4,388         $           -         $     4,388&#13;
   Currency swaps                                          -             17,706                     -              17,706&#13;
   Interest rate swaps                                     -                 91                     -                  91&#13;
   Swaptions, exchange traded options&#13;
     and futures contracts                                 -                 11                     -                  11&#13;
   Othera                                                  -                  -                     -                   -&#13;
                                                           -             22,196                     -              22,196&#13;
  Loans&#13;
    Currency swaps                                         -              3,671                   92                3,763&#13;
    Interest rate swaps                                    -                139                    -                  139&#13;
                                                           -              3,810                   92                3,902&#13;
  Client operations&#13;
    Currency swaps                                         -             27,518                     -              27,518&#13;
    Interest rate swaps                                    -              1,221                     -               1,221&#13;
                                                           -             28,739                     -              28,739&#13;
  Borrowings&#13;
   Currency swaps                                          -             72,555                1,387               73,942&#13;
   Interest rate swaps                                     -              4,258                   67                4,325&#13;
                                                           -             76,813                1,454               78,267&#13;
  Other assets/liabilities&#13;
   Currency swaps                                          -               487                     -                  487&#13;
   Interest rate swaps                                     -               734                     -                  734&#13;
                                                           -             1,221                     -                1,221&#13;
  Total derivative assets                    $             -       $   132,779          $      1,546          $   134,325&#13;
Derivative Liabilities:&#13;
 Investments&#13;
   Currency forward contracts                $             -       $      4,366         $           -         $     4,366&#13;
   Currency swaps                                          -             16,787                     -              16,787&#13;
   Interest rate swaps                                     -                107                     -                 107&#13;
   Swaptions, exchange traded options&#13;
     and futures contracts                             8                     11                     -                  19&#13;
   Othera                                              -                       *                    -                    *&#13;
                                                       8                 21,271                     -              21,279&#13;
  Loans&#13;
    Currency swaps                                         -              3,188                   77                3,265&#13;
    Interest rate swaps                                    -              2,270                    -                2,270&#13;
                                                           -              5,458                   77                5,535&#13;
  Client operations&#13;
    Currency swaps                                         -             27,515                    -               27,515&#13;
    Interest rate swaps                                    -              1,224                    8                1,232&#13;
                                                           -             28,739                    8               28,747&#13;
  Borrowings&#13;
   Currency swaps                                          -             74,021                1,354               75,375&#13;
   Interest rate swaps                                     -                690                   75                  765&#13;
                                                           -             74,711                1,429               76,140&#13;
  Other assets/liabilities&#13;
   Currency swaps                                      -                   547                     -                  547&#13;
   Interest rate swaps                                 -                    76                     -                   76&#13;
                                                       -                   623                     -                  623&#13;
   Total derivative liabilities              $         8           $   130,802          $      1,514          $   132,324&#13;
&#13;
a.These relate to TBA securities.&#13;
* Indicates amount less than $0.5 million.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
               IBRD CONDENSED QUARTERLY FINANCIAL STATEMENTS: SEPTEMBER 30, 2015 (UNAUDITED)                                 41&#13;
&amp;#12;The following tables provide a summary of changes in the fair value of IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s Level 3 derivatives, net during the&#13;
three months ended September 30, 2015 and September 30, 2014:Â &#13;
In millions of U.S. dollarsÂ                                                                              Â &#13;
Â                                           Three Months Ended September 30, 2015                     Three Months Ended September 30, 2014&#13;
                                           Currency            Interest Rate                         Currency            Interest Rate&#13;
Â                                            Swaps                 Swaps                Total          Swaps                 Swaps                          Total&#13;
Â &#13;
Beginning of the fiscal year               $       48             $ (16)          $        32        $        461           $      26                  $      487&#13;
Total realized/unrealized&#13;
 gains (losses) in:&#13;
    Net income                                     (8)              (72)                  (80)                173                 (15)                        158&#13;
    Other comprehensive income                     12                   -                  12                (235)                      -                    (235)&#13;
Issuances                                              -                -                      -                  (2)                   -                          (2)&#13;
Settlements                                        (6)                  4                  (2)                (85)                      -                         (85)&#13;
Transfers, net                                    (16)                  -                 (16)                (14)                (25)                            (39)&#13;
End of the period                          $       30             $ (84)          $       (54)       $        298           $ (14)                     $      284&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Unrealized mark-to-market gains or losses included in the Condensed Statement of Income for the three months&#13;
ended September 30, 2015 and September 30, 2014, relating to IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s Level 3 derivatives, net still held at the&#13;
reporting dates as well as where those amounts are included in the Condensed Statement of Income, are presented in&#13;
the following table:Â &#13;
In millions of U.S. dollarsÂ &#13;
                                                                                                    Three Months Ended September 30,&#13;
Unrealized Gains (Losses)                                                                                2015                                   2014&#13;
Condensed Statement of Income Location&#13;
Unrealized mark-to-market (losses) gains on non-trading portfolios, net                              $       (45)                           $    108&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The following table provides details of all inter-level transfers during the three months ended September 30, 2015&#13;
and September 30, 2014:Â &#13;
In millions of U.S. dollars Â &#13;
                                         Three Months Ended September 30, 2015                           Three Months Ended September 30, 2014&#13;
                                               Level 2                       Level 3                           Level 2                             Level 3&#13;
Derivatives, net&#13;
Transfer into (out of)                      $      -                        $      -                          $     14                            $        (14)&#13;
Transfer out of (into)                            16                            (16)                                25                                     (25)&#13;
                                            $     16                        $   (16)                          $     39                            $        (39)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Transfers between Level 2 and Level 3 are due to changes in price transparency.&#13;
The fair value of IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s Level 3 borrowings related derivatives is estimated using valuation models that&#13;
incorporate model parameters, observable market inputs and unobservable inputs. The significant unobservable&#13;
inputs used in the fair value measurement of these derivatives are correlations and long dated interest rate&#13;
volatilities. See Note Eâ&#128;&#148;Borrowings for details on these unobservable inputs.&#13;
The following table provides a summary of the valuation technique applied in determining fair values of these Level&#13;
3 instruments and quantitative information regarding the significant unobservable inputs used.Â &#13;
In millions of U.S. dollarsÂ &#13;
                    Fair Value at   Fair Value&#13;
                   September 30, at June 30,               Valuation        Unobservable            Range (average),                    Range (average),&#13;
Portfolio               2015      Â    2015Â                 Technique             input             September 30, 2015                     June 30, 2015&#13;
Currency                                                                     Correlations           -52% to 75% (8%)                    -50% to 72% (2%)&#13;
swaps,                                                     Discounted        Long-dated&#13;
                         $(54)            $32&#13;
Interest rate                                              Cash Flow         interest rate         20% to 53% (37%)                     19% to 71% (36%)&#13;
swaps                                                                         volatilities&#13;
Â                 Â Â  Â Â            Â Â  Â Â               Â Â  Â Â                                                                        Â Â  Â Â &#13;
Â &#13;
Â &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
42        IBRD CONDENSED QUARTERLY FINANCIAL STATEMENTS: SEPTEMBER 30, 2015 (UNAUDITED)&#13;
&amp;#12;Valuation Methods and Assumptions&#13;
Derivative contracts include currency forward contracts, TBAs, swaptions, exchange traded options and futures&#13;
contracts currency swaps and interest rate swaps. Currency swaps and interest rate swaps are either plain vanilla or&#13;
structured. Currency forward contracts and plain vanilla currency and interest rate swaps are valued using the&#13;
standard discounted cash flow methods using market observable inputs such as yield curves, foreign exchange rates,&#13;
basis spreads and funding spreads. For structured currency and interest rate swaps, which primarily consist of&#13;
callable swaps linked to interest rates, foreign exchange rates, and equity indices, valuation models and inputs&#13;
similar to the ones applicable to structured bonds valuation are used. Where applicable, the models also incorporate&#13;
significant unobservable inputs such as correlations and long-dated interest rate volatilities.&#13;
NOTE Gâ&#128;&#148;RETAINED EARNINGS, ALLOCATIONS AND TRANSFERS&#13;
IBRD makes net income allocation decisions on the basis of reported net income, adjusted to exclude unrealized&#13;
mark-to-market gains and losses on non-trading portfolios, net, restricted income and Board of Governors-approved&#13;
transfers, and after considering the allocation to the pension reserve.&#13;
On August 6, 2015, IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s Executive Directors approved the following allocations relating to the net income&#13;
earned in the fiscal year ended June 30, 2015, an increase in General Reserve by $36 million and a decrease in the&#13;
Pension Reserve by $55 million.&#13;
Subsequent event: On October 9, 2015, IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s Board of Governors approved an immediate transfer to IDA of&#13;
$650 million out of the net income earned in the fiscal year ended June 30, 2015. The transfer to IDA was made on&#13;
October 15, 2015.&#13;
Retained earnings comprise the following components at September 30, 2015 and June 30, 2015:&#13;
In millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
Â &#13;
 Â                                                               Â         September 30, 2015                   June 30, 2015&#13;
Special Reserve Â                                                             $    293                          $     293&#13;
General Reserve Â                                                               26,925                            26,889&#13;
Pension Reserve Â                                                                  962                              1,017&#13;
Surplus Â                                                                          326                                326&#13;
Cumulative fair value adjustmentsaÂ                                             (1,679)                              (977)&#13;
Unallocated Net Income Â                                                         1,395                                (71)&#13;
Restricted Retained Earnings Â                                                      24                                 24&#13;
Total Â                                                                        $ 28,246                            $ 27,501&#13;
&#13;
a. Unrealized mark-to-market gains or losses, net applicable to non-trading portfolios reported at fair value.Â &#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NOTE Hâ&#128;&#148;PENSION AND OTHER POSTRETIREMENT BENEFITS&#13;
IBRD, IFC and the Multilateral Investment Guarantee Agency (MIGA) participate in a defined benefit Staff&#13;
Retirement Plan (SRP), a Retired Staff Benefits Plan (RSBP) and PEBP that cover substantially all of their staff&#13;
members.&#13;
All costs, assets and liabilities associated with these pension plans are allocated between IBRD, IFC and MIGA&#13;
based upon their employeesâ&#128;&#153; respective participation in the plans. Costs allocated to IBRD are then shared between&#13;
IBRD and IDA based on an agreed cost sharing ratio. The net periodic pension cost for the SRP, RSBP and PEBP is&#13;
included in Pension expenses, in the Condensed Statement of Income.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
               IBRD CONDENSED QUARTERLY FINANCIAL STATEMENTS: SEPTEMBER 30, 2015 (UNAUDITED)                                  43&#13;
&amp;#12;The following table summarizes the benefit costs associated with the SRP, RSBP, and PEBP for IBRD and IDA for&#13;
the three months ended September 30, 2015 and September 30, 2014:&#13;
In millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
                                                                      Three Months Ended                             Three Months Ended&#13;
                                                                      September 30, 2015                             September 30, 2014&#13;
                                                                SRP      RSBP   PEBP          Total           SRP        RSBP     PEBP       Total&#13;
Benefit Cost&#13;
 Service cost                                               $     98 $ 26 $ 15            $    139        $     97       $ 28     $ 12   $     137&#13;
 Interest cost                                                   166    28  12                 206             161          30      11         202&#13;
 Expected return on plan assets                                 (233)  (35)  -                (268)           (231)        (33)      -        (264)&#13;
 Amortization of unrecognized prior service costsa                 1     4   1                   6               1           4       1           6&#13;
 Amortization of unrecognized net actuarial lossesa               19      - 10                  29              27           7      11          45&#13;
  Net periodic pension cost                                 $    51     $ 23    $ 38      $    112        $     55       $ 36     $ 35   $     126&#13;
     of which:&#13;
       IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s shareb                                        $    25     $ 11 $        19 $      55        $     25       $ 17     $ 16   $      58&#13;
       IDAâ&#128;&#153;s share                                          $    26     $ 12 $        19 $      57        $     30       $ 19     $ 19   $      68&#13;
&#13;
a. Included in Amounts reclassified into net income in Note Jâ&#128;&#148;Comprehensive Income.&#13;
b. Included in Pension expenses in the Condensed Statement of Income.&#13;
&#13;
NOTE Iâ&#128;&#148;TRANSACTIONS WITH AFFILIATED ORGANIZATIONS&#13;
IBRD transacts with affiliated organizations by providing loans, administrative and derivative intermediation&#13;
services, as well as through its pension and other postretirement benefit plans.&#13;
In addition, IBRD provides transfers to IDA out of its net income, upon approval by the Board of Governors (see&#13;
Note Gâ&#128;&#148;Retained earnings, Allocations and Transfers).&#13;
At September 30, 2015 and June 30, 2015, IBRD had the following receivables from (payables to) its affiliated&#13;
organizations:&#13;
In millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
                                                                 September 30, 2015&#13;
                                                          Derivative Transactionsa&#13;
                               Administrative                                                      Pension and Other&#13;
                  Loans          Services             Receivable             Payable             Postretirement Benefits               Total&#13;
  IDA           $    -          $ 291                 $   8,431            $   (8,694)              $      (808)                     $ (780)&#13;
  IFC              213                54                       -                     -                     (196)                          71&#13;
  MIGA               -                 5                       -                     -                       (7)                          (2)&#13;
                $   213           $   350             $    8,431           $    (8,694)               $        (1,011)               $ (711)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
In millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
                                                                      June 30, 2015&#13;
                                                          Derivative Transactionsa&#13;
                               Administrative                                                      Pension and Other&#13;
                  Loans          Services             Receivable             Payable             Postretirement Benefits               Total&#13;
  IDA           $    -          $ 364                 $   8,962            $   (8,914)              $      (831)                     $ (419)&#13;
  IFC              213                50                       -                     -                     (210)                          53&#13;
  MIGA               -                 4                       -                     -                       (8)                          (4)&#13;
                $   213           $   418             $    8,962           $    (8,914)               $        (1,049)               $ (370)&#13;
&#13;
a. For details on derivative transactions relating to swap intermediation services provided by IBRD to IDA see Note Fâ&#128;&#148;Derivative&#13;
  Instruments.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
44        IBRD CONDENSED QUARTERLY FINANCIAL STATEMENTS: SEPTEMBER 30, 2015 (UNAUDITED)&#13;
&amp;#12;The receivables from (payables to) these affiliated organizations are reported in the Condensed Balance Sheet as&#13;
follows:&#13;
Receivables / Payables related to:                                Reported as:&#13;
Loans                                                             Loans outstanding&#13;
Receivable for administrative servicesa                           Other assets&#13;
Receivables (payables) for derivative transactions                Derivative assets/liabilities â&#128;&#147; Client operations&#13;
Payable for pension and other postretirement benefits             Other liabilities&#13;
a. Includes amounts payable to IDA for its share of investments associated with PCRF. This payable is included in Other&#13;
  Liabilities on the Condensed Balance Sheet.&#13;
&#13;
Loans&#13;
IBRD has a Local Currency Loan Facility Agreement with IFC which is capped at $300 million. At September 30,&#13;
2015, the loan balance under this facility amounted to $17 million ($17 millionâ&#128;&#148;June 30, 2015) and carried a fixed&#13;
interest rate of 3.96% and maturity of 1 year. This loan is not eligible for interest waivers.&#13;
IBRD has another facility with IFC under which IFC can borrow up to $197 million. This loan is at LIBOR less 25&#13;
basis points (0.19% as of September 30, 2015) and is not eligible for interest waivers. At September 30, 2015, the&#13;
balance of this loan was $196 million ($196 millionâ&#128;&#148;June 30, 2015).&#13;
During the fiscal year ended June 30, 2015, IBRD entered into an exposure exchange agreement with MIGA under&#13;
which IBRD and MIGA exchange selected exposures, with each divesting itself of exposure in countries where their&#13;
lending capacities are limited, in return for exposure in countries where they have excess lending capacity. Under&#13;
the agreement, IBRD and MIGA have each exchanged $120 million of notional exposure as follows: MIGA&#13;
assumes IBRD's loan principal and interest exposure in exchange for IBRD's assumption of principal and interest&#13;
exposure of MIGA under its Non-Honoring of Sovereign Financial Obligation agreement. As of September 30,&#13;
2015, liabilities related to IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s obligation under this agreement amounted to $3 million ($3 millionâ&#128;&#148;June 30,&#13;
2015). These include an accumulated provision for guarantee losses of less than $1 million (less than $1 millionâ&#128;&#148;&#13;
June 30, 2015).&#13;
Administrative Services&#13;
Expenses jointly incurred by IBRD and IDA are allocated based on an agreed cost sharing ratio, and amounts are&#13;
settled quarterly. For the three months ended September 30, 2015, IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s administrative expenses are net of the&#13;
share of expenses allocated to IDA of $349 million ($374 millionâ&#128;&#148;three months ended September 30, 2014).&#13;
Other Revenue&#13;
Revenue jointly earned by IBRD and IDA is allocated based on an agreed revenue sharing ratio. Amounts are settled&#13;
quarterly. For the three months ended September 30, 2015, IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s other revenue is net of revenue allocated to IDA&#13;
of $40 million ($45 millionâ&#128;&#148;three months ended September 30, 2014).&#13;
For the three months ended September 30, 2015 and September 30, 2014, the amount of fee revenue associated with&#13;
services provided to affiliated organizations is included in Revenue from externally funded activities on the&#13;
Condensed Statement of Income, as follows:&#13;
In millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
                                                                    Three Months Ended September 30,&#13;
                                                                 2015                                  2014&#13;
Fees charged to IFC                                            $    16                                $ 12&#13;
Fees charged to MIGA                                                  1                                   1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Pension and Other Postretirement Benefits&#13;
The payable to IDA represents IDAâ&#128;&#153;s net share of prepaid costs for pension and other postretirement benefit plans&#13;
and PEBP assets. These will be realized over the life of the plan participants.&#13;
The payables to IFC and MIGA represent their respective share of PEBP assets. The PEBP assets are managed by&#13;
IBRD and are a part of the investment portfolio.&#13;
For Pension and Other Post Retirement Benefits related disclosure see Note Hâ&#128;&#148;Pension and Other Postretirement&#13;
Benefits.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
               IBRD CONDENSED QUARTERLY FINANCIAL STATEMENTS: SEPTEMBER 30, 2015 (UNAUDITED)                              45&#13;
&amp;#12;Derivative transactions&#13;
These relate to currency forward contracts entered into by IDA with IBRD acting as the intermediary with the&#13;
market.&#13;
NOTE Jâ&#128;&#148;COMPREHENSIVE INCOME&#13;
Comprehensive income consists of net income and other gains and losses affecting equity that, under U.S. GAAP,&#13;
are excluded from net income. For IBRD, Comprehensive income (loss) comprises currency translation adjustments,&#13;
the cumulative effects of a change in accounting principle related to the implementation of FASBâ&#128;&#153;s derivatives and&#13;
hedging guidance, pension-related items, and net income. These items are presented in the Condensed Statement of&#13;
Comprehensive Income.&#13;
The following tables present the changes in Accumulated Other Comprehensive Loss (AOCL) balances for the three&#13;
months ended September 30, 2015 and September 30, 2014:&#13;
In millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
                                                                   Three Months Ended September 30, 2015&#13;
                                              Balance,         Changes            Amounts&#13;
                                            beginning of     in fair value   reclassified into net   Net changes       Balance, end of&#13;
                                           the fiscal year     in AOCL             income          during the period     the period&#13;
&#13;
Cumulative Translation Adjustment           $         *      $       6           $          -       $         6         $        6&#13;
Cumulative Effect of Change in&#13;
                                                  500                 -                     -                  -               500&#13;
 Accounting Principlea&#13;
                                                                                            b&#13;
Reclassificationa                                (509)                -                 *                      *              (509)&#13;
Unrecognized Net Actuarial (Losses)&#13;
                                                (3,022)               -                29 c                  29             (2,993)&#13;
 Gains on Benefit Plans&#13;
Unrecognized Prior Service (Costs)&#13;
                                                 (182)                -                 6c                    6               (176)&#13;
 Credits on Benefit Plans&#13;
Total Accumulated Other&#13;
                                            $ (3,213)        $       6           $     35           $        41         $   (3,172)&#13;
 Comprehensive Loss&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
In millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
                                                                   Three Months Ended September 30, 2014&#13;
                                              Balance,         Changes            Amounts&#13;
                                            beginning of     in fair value   reclassified into net   Net changes       Balance, end of&#13;
                                           the fiscal year     in AOCL             income          during the period     the period&#13;
&#13;
Cumulative Translation Adjustment           $   1,017        $   (438)           $          -       $      (438)        $      579&#13;
Cumulative Effect of Change in&#13;
                                                  500                 -                     -                  -               500&#13;
 Accounting Principlea&#13;
                                                                                            b&#13;
Reclassificationa                                (511)                -                 1                     1               (510)&#13;
Unrecognized Net Actuarial (Losses)                                                         c&#13;
                                                (3,862)               -                45                    45             (3,817)&#13;
 Gains on Benefit Plans&#13;
Unrecognized Prior Service (Costs)                                                          c&#13;
                                                 (206)                -                 6                     6               (200)&#13;
 Credits on Benefit Plans&#13;
Total Accumulated Other&#13;
                                            $ (3,062)        $   (438)           $     52           $      (386)        $   (3,448)&#13;
 Comprehensive Loss&#13;
&#13;
a. The Cumulative effect of change in accounting principle and subsequent reclassification to net income relates to the&#13;
   adoption of FASBâ&#128;&#153;s guidance on derivatives and hedging on July 1, 2000.&#13;
b. Reclassified into Borrowings, net in the Condensed Statement of Income.&#13;
c. See Note Hâ&#128;&#148;Pension and Other Post Retirement Benefits.&#13;
* Indicates amount less than $0.5 million.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
46        IBRD CONDENSED QUARTERLY FINANCIAL STATEMENTS: SEPTEMBER 30, 2015 (UNAUDITED)&#13;
&amp;#12;NOTE Kâ&#128;&#148;OTHER FAIR VALUE DISCLOSURES&#13;
The table below presents IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s estimates of fair value of its financial assets and liabilities along with their&#13;
respective carrying amounts as of September 30, 2015 and June 30, 2015:&#13;
In millions of U.S. dollars&#13;
                                                           September 30, 2015                          June 30, 2015&#13;
                                                   Carrying Value           Fair Value       Carrying Value          Fair Value&#13;
Assets&#13;
Due from Banks                                     $      887           $       887         $       388          $       388&#13;
Investments&#13;
  Trading (including Securities purchased&#13;
                                                        48,297               48,297              49,951                49,951&#13;
   under resale agreements)&#13;
Net Loans Outstanding                                  160,258              160,090             155,040              155,910&#13;
Derivative Assets&#13;
Â    InvestmentsÂ                                         24,894               24,894              22,196                22,196&#13;
Â    LoansÂ                                                4,122                 4,122              3,902                 3,902&#13;
Â    Client operationsÂ                                   28,349               28,349              28,739                28,739&#13;
Â    BorrowingsÂ                                          77,012               77,012              78,267                78,267&#13;
Â    OthersÂ                                               2,112                 2,112              1,221                 1,221&#13;
Liabilities&#13;
Borrowings                                             169,592              169,602 a           160,980              160,988 a&#13;
Securities sold/lent under repurchase&#13;
 agreements/securities lending agreements                3,015                 3,015              3,575                 3,575&#13;
 and payable for cash collateral received&#13;
Derivative Liabilities&#13;
Â    InvestmentsÂ                                         24,401               24,401              21,279                21,279&#13;
Â    LoansÂ                                                5,996                 5,996              5,535                 5,535&#13;
Â    Client operationsÂ                                   28,350               28,350              28,747                28,747&#13;
Â    BorrowingsÂ                                          76,128               76,128              76,140                76,140&#13;
Â    OthersÂ                                                614                   614                 623                  623&#13;
&#13;
a.Includes $10 million ($8 millionâ&#128;&#148;June 30, 2015) relating to transition adjustment on adoption of FASB's guidance on derivatives&#13;
Â  and hedging on July 1, 2000.Â &#13;
Valuation Methods and Assumptions&#13;
As of September 30, 2015 and June 30, 2015, IBRD had no assets or liabilities measured at fair value on a non-&#13;
recurring basis.&#13;
For valuation methods and assumptions as well as additional fair value disclosures regarding Investments, Loans,&#13;
Borrowings and Derivative assets and liabilities, refer to Note Câ&#128;&#148;Investments, Note Dâ&#128;&#148;Loans, Note Eâ&#128;&#148;&#13;
Borrowings and Note Fâ&#128;&#148;Derivative Instruments, respectively.&#13;
Due from Banks: The carrying amount of unrestricted and restricted currencies is considered a reasonable estimate of&#13;
the fair value of these positions.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                  IBRD CONDENSED QUARTERLY FINANCIAL STATEMENTS: SEPTEMBER 30, 2015 (UNAUDITED)                                   47&#13;
&amp;#12;Unrealized mark-to-market Gains or Losses on Investments-Trading and Non-Trading Portfolios, Net&#13;
The following table reflects the components of the realized and unrealized gains or losses on Investments-Trading&#13;
and non-trading portfolios, net for the three months ended September 30, 2015 and September 30, 2014:Â &#13;
In millions of U.S. dollars Â &#13;
                                                           Three Months Ended                                      Three Months Ended&#13;
                                                           September 30, 2015                                      September 30, 2014&#13;
                                                               Unrealized                                               Unrealized&#13;
                                                                   gains                                                    gains&#13;
                                                                 (losses)                                                 (losses)&#13;
                                                   Realized     excluding   Unrealized                     Realized      excluding  Unrealized&#13;
                                                     gains       realized      gains                         gains        realized      gains&#13;
                                                                         a                                                        a&#13;
                                                   (losses)     amounts      (losses)                      (losses)      amounts      (losses)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Investments - Trading                             $   22            $     (74)         $     (52)         $      (34)              $   5                   $   (29)&#13;
&#13;
Non trading portfolios, net&#13;
Â  Loans, including derivativesâ&#128;&#148;Notes D and F Â              -              (497)b             (497)                  -                   11b                      11&#13;
 Equity management, net                                    -               741                741                 581             Â     (723)                   (142)&#13;
Â  Borrowings, including derivatives Â                           Â  Â  Â  Â Â            Â  Â  Â  Â Â            Â  Â  Â Â  Â Â               Â Â  Â Â  Â Â              Â Â  Â Â  Â &#13;
Â  Â â&#128;&#148;Notes E and F                                          4               513                517                   6                  (244)                   (238)&#13;
Â  Other assets/liabilities derivativesÂ                     -                (1)                (1)                      -                  (1)                   (1)&#13;
Â  Client operations derivativesÂ                            -                (3)                (3)                      -                  (2)                   (2)&#13;
&#13;
   Total                                          $        4        $      753         $      757         $       587              $   (959)               $   (372)&#13;
&#13;
a. Adjusted to exclude amounts reclassfied to realized gains (losses).&#13;
b. Includes $494 million of unrealized mark-to-market losses related to derivatives associated with loans (unrealized mark-to-market&#13;
   gains of $11 millionâ&#128;&#148;September 30, 2014).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
NOTE Lâ&#128;&#148;CONTINGENCIES&#13;
From time to time, IBRD may be named as a defendant or co-defendant in legal actions on different grounds in&#13;
various jurisdictions. IBRDâ&#128;&#153;s management does not believe the outcome of any existing legal action, as of and for&#13;
the three months ended September 30, 2015, will have a material adverse effect on IBRD's financial position, results&#13;
of operations or cash flows.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
48         IBRD CONDENSED QUARTERLY FINANCIAL STATEMENTS: SEPTEMBER 30, 2015 (UNAUDITED)&#13;
&amp;#12;INDEPENDENT AUDITORSâ&#128;&#153; REVIEW REPORT&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                      49&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="25475919">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2015/11/25475919/management’s-discussion-analysis-condensed-quarterly-financial-statements-unaudited
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2015/11/25475919/management’s-discussion-analysis-condensed-quarterly-financial-statements-unaudited</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2015/11/25475919/management’s-discussion-analysis-condensed-quarterly-financial-statements-unaudited</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2015-11-19T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2016-01-28T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <docm_id>090224b0831e8f1c</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b0831e8f1c</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2015/11/23/090224b0831e8f1c/1_0/Rendered/INDEX/Management0s0d0atements00Unaudited0.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2015/11/23/090224b0831e8f1c/1_0/Rendered/PDF/Management0s0d0atements00Unaudited0.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2015-09-30T00:36:01Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2015-11-19T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            IBRD management’s discussion and analysis
            and condensed quarterly financial statements (Unaudited)
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            This report presents the International
            Bank for Reconstruction and Development’s (IBRD) financial
            statements and management’s discussion and analysis (MD and
            A) for the fiscal year ended June 30, 2015 (FY15). It
            provides IBRD’s selected financial data as of, and for the
            three months ended, September 30, 2015 and 2014, as well as
            for the fiscal year ended June 30, 2015. IBRD provides
            loans, guarantees, and knowledge for development focused
            projects and programs to middle-income and creditworthy
            lower-income member countries. IBRD also provides access to
            risk management tools such as derivative instruments,
            including currency and interest rate swaps.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            IBRD management’s discussion and analysis
            and condensed quarterly financial statements (Unaudited)
        </docna>
        <display_title>IBRD management’s discussion and
            analysis and condensed quarterly financial statements (Unaudited)</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2015/09/25475919/ibrd-management’s-discussion-analysis-condensed-quarterly-financial-statements-unaudited</listing_relative_url>
        <topic>Bank Internal Controls m1326283 1243,Accounting and Reporting m1326101 2064,Bank Resolution and Crisis Management
            m1326972 319,Bank Regulation and Supervision m1327225 317,Banking Regulation m1326903 971</topic>
        <subtopic>Mutual Funds,Investment and Investment Climate,Bankruptcy and Resolution of Financial Distress,Emerging Markets,Debt Markets</subtopic>
        <docty>Working Paper</docty>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Private Sector Development,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>090224b0831e8f1c_1_0</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>World Bank financial statements</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Private Sector Development,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</historic_topic>
        <topicv3>Bank Internal Controls m1326283 1243,Accounting and Reporting m1326101 2064,Bank Resolution and Crisis Management
            m1326972 319,Bank Regulation and Supervision m1327225 317,Banking Regulation m1326903 971</topicv3>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            holding, borrower, interest income,
            equipment, credit default swaps, accounting, deposits,
            contractual obligations, fixed income, long-term interest,
            risk management strategies, international capital,
            valuation, securities lending agreements, interest,
            liquidity risks, option, hedge funds, debt management,
            repayments, term deposits, portfolio, fiscal policy, capital
            adequacy, loan, financial statement, creditworthiness,
            interest rate volatilities, probability of default,
            borrowers, capital stock, asset positions, mutual funds,
            liquid instruments, prepayment, debt burden, short-term
            borrowings, cash flows, instruments, market environment,
            equity capital, derivatives, currency, exchange rate
            movements, credit risk assessment, financial portfolios,
            income instruments, loan products, nonpayment, income
            growth, exchange rates, equity contribution, interest rate
            volatility, credit risks, regulatory system, financial
            institutions, debt, collateral arrangements, markets,
            settlement, variable rate, trust funds, future cash flows,
            interest rate risks, short-term deposits, transactions,
            alternative investments, interest rate swaps, equity
            indices, fair values, transparency, country risk,
            derivative, market conditions, future, market prices,
            commercial paper, equity funds, derivative contracts, risk
            exposure, financial performance, disbursements, debt
            securities, loan portfolio, shares, face value, market risk,
            securities, public debt, credit spreads, credit risk,
            holdings, currencies, variable rates, margin requirements,
            time deposits, accounting standards, asset-backed
            securities, financial risks, financial assets, currency
            risk, coupon, mark-to-market, international swaps, lending,
            lending agreements, mark-to- market, maturities, liability
            management, liabilities, arrears, long-term loans, liquid
            assets, market quotations, prepayment rates, credit risk
            exposures, development bank, cash flow, political risk,
            backed securities, investing, guarantee fee, capital
            markets, liability, liquidation, short-term interest rates,
            stock, derivative instruments, futures, market developments,
            outstanding loan, guarantees, interest rate, exchange,
            balance of payments, treasuries, issuances, liquidity,
            international capital markets, equity securities, cds,
            mortgage, financial statements, bonds, debt security,
            macroeconomic conditions, discount, investment activities,
            loan agreement, level of interest rates, reserve fund,
            reserve, international bank, liquid asset, pension,
            developing country, credit default, maturity, risk
            exposures, international finance, financial sustainability,
            bond issues, disbursement, portfolios, contracts,
            conversions, trading, credit default swap, interest rates,
            options, fee income, principal assets, risk management
            tools, price transparency, return, international
            development, futures contracts, basis point, loans, interest
            cost, portfolio investments, private equity, amount of
            collateral, finance, credit risk exposure, equity,
            transaction, investors, currency composition,
            asset-liability management, yield curves, asset value,
            valuation technique, commercial credit, value of collateral,
            access to capital, mortgage-backed securities, long-term
            interest rates, financial instruments, investment assets,
            contract, repayment, separate assets, country credit,
            amortization, fair value, reinvestment risk, balance sheet,
            default, market, credit rating, foreign exchange, principal
            repayments, market value, asset portfolio, discount notes,
            market risks, investor, equity index, security, debt
            instruments, investment, bond, investment portfolio, share,
            collateral, valuation techniques, poverty, financial
            information, credit quality, floating rate, revenue,
            reinvestment, external debt, investments, risk management,
            interest rate risk, interest waivers, swaps, financial risk,
            use of derivatives, exchange rate, instrument, outstanding
            loans, hedge, international investors, guarantee, consumer
            protection, swap, retail investors
        </keywd>
        <owner>WBG - Finance and Accounting (WFAVP)</owner>
        <repnb>101038</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT for Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies (ICT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fragility, Conflict and Violence</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation and Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shocks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Business Models</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets and Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investment and Investment Climate</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Strategic Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shared Prosperity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pensions &amp; Retirement Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Checks on Executive Power</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen User Satisfaction Survey</ml:concept><ml:concept>Independent Commissions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ombudsmen</ml:concept><ml:concept>Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Parliament</ml:concept><ml:concept>Procurement Complaints Review Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supreme Audit Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Lines</ml:concept><ml:concept>Knowledge for Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Settlement of Investment Disputes</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Volatility</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shocks and Vulnerability</ml:concept><ml:concept>Market Risks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Mutual Funds</ml:concept><ml:concept>Reconciliation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Telecommunications Organizational Design</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investment Climate</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inclusive Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pensions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Accountability Mechanisms</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>