<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>                                                                            101039&#13;
                                                                Rampur Hydropower Project&#13;
                                Land Acquisition, Resettlement and Community Development Practices&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
RAMPUR&#13;
HYDROPOWER PROJECT&#13;
Land Acquisition | Resettlement | Community Development Practices&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                1&#13;
&amp;#12;Rampur Hydropower Project&#13;
Land Acquisition, Resettlement and Community Development Practices&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Octorber 2015 (Revised)&#13;
&#13;
This document is a product of the staff of the International Bank for Reconstruction and Development/The World Bank. The&#13;
findings, interpretations, and conclusions expressed in this document are entirely those of the authors and should not be&#13;
attributed in any manner to the World Bank, or its affiliated organizations, or to members of its Board of Executive Directors&#13;
or the countries they represent.&#13;
&#13;
The World Bank does not guarantee the accuracy of the data included in this publication. The boundaries, colors,&#13;
denominations, and other information shown on any map in this work do not imply any judgment on the part of The World&#13;
Bank concerning the legal status of any territory or the endorsement or acceptance of such boundaries.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Acknowledgements&#13;
This document was prepared by a team of I.U.B. Reddy, Rohit Mittal and Kwawu Mensan Gaba. Sona Thakur provided&#13;
presentational assistance. G. Srihari (Consultant) contributed to compilation of background information and interviews with&#13;
the project affected people and other stakeholders. Sheela Bajaj and Sanjukta Roy (Consultants) provided editorial support.&#13;
Deepali Uppal provided administrative support. The work was supervised by Julia Bucknall and Maria C. Correia.&#13;
&#13;
The team is grateful to K. K. Gupta (Head of Rampur Project and General Manager, SJVN Limited), F. Badaik (DGM, R&amp;R,&#13;
SJVNL), Alka Jaiswal (Manager, R&amp;R, SJVNL), Kaushlya Devi (Senior Officer, R&amp;R, SJVNL) and management of SJVN&#13;
Limited for their substantive inputs, suggestions and support in preparation of this document.&#13;
&#13;
The team gratefully acknowledges financial support from the Austrian Partnership Trust Fund for the preparation of this document.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
2&#13;
&amp;#12;RAMPUR&#13;
HYDROPOWER PROJECT&#13;
Land Acquisition | Resettlement | Community Development Practices&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
THIS NOTE DOCUMENTS THE PRACTICES OF SJVN LIMITED FOR LAND ACQUISITION, RESETTLEMENT&#13;
AND COMMUNITY DEVELOPMENT AND BENEFITS ACCRUING TO THE PROJECT-AFFECTED FAMILIES&#13;
AND LOCAL POPULATION IN GENERAL UNDER THE RAMPUR HYDROPOWER PROJECT.&#13;
&amp;#12;Rampur Hydropower Project&#13;
Land Acquisition, Resettlement and Community Development Practices&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
2&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                      Rampur Hydropower Project&#13;
                                                                      Land Acquisition, Resettlement and Community Development Practices&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Introduction&#13;
Context                                                                  infrastructure such as offices, power house, dumping&#13;
SJVN Limited (SJVNL), a Mini ratna public sector&#13;
                                             1                           sites, and quarry and site establishments. Of this,&#13;
undertaking of the Government of India (GoI),                            50 hectares of state forest land was acquired from&#13;
implemented the World Bank funded 412 MW                                 the Government of Himachal Pradesh (GoHP) and&#13;
run-of-the-river hydro power project at Rampur in                        30 hectares of private land from 167 landowners in&#13;
Himachal Pradesh, immediately downstream of and in                       four villages of three panchayats in Kullu and Shimla&#13;
cascade operation with the 1500 MW Nathpa Jhakri                         districts.&#13;
Hydroelectric Project (NJHP). Located in Shimla&#13;
and Kullu districts, the Rampur Project involved the                     Challenges&#13;
construction of a 15.17 km, 10.5 m of diameter, head                     Situated in a remote, hilly area of Himachal Pradesh&#13;
race tunnel that delivers water to a power house                         with limited access and development, the key&#13;
with six turbine generators. The project got fully                       challenges faced by SJVNL in implementing this&#13;
commissioned in December 2014.                                           project were:&#13;
&#13;
The project-affected area covered eight panchayats.                      â&#128;¢	 Timely land acquisition, enabling commencement&#13;
SJVNL required 80 hectares of land for building project                     of civil work on schedule; and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
1&#13;
  Central Public Sector Undertaking (CPSU) companies are divided into three categories: (i) Maharatna; (ii) Navratna; (iii) Mini ratna&#13;
- Category I; and (iv) Mini ratna - Category II. SJVNL is a Mini ratna â&#128;&#147; Category I company, which entitles the company board to do&#13;
investments up to a limit of Rs. 5000 million or equal to their net worth, whichever is lower, without seeking government permission.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                         3&#13;
&amp;#12;Rampur Hydropower Project&#13;
Land Acquisition, Resettlement and Community Development Practices&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
â&#128;¢	 Sustainable resettlement, rehabilitation and                      â&#128;¢	 The innovative design and success of the&#13;
   community development program for project-                           community development program undertaken&#13;
   affected families, to provide benefits in addition to                by SJVNL, both in Nathpa-Jhakri and Rampur&#13;
   mandatory compensation.                                              Projects, also contributed to the GoHPâ&#128;&#153;s design of&#13;
                                                                        new policy provisions of Local Area Development&#13;
Lessons learnt by SJVNL during its first project                        Fund (LADF) under the State Hydropower policy&#13;
at Nathpa Jakhri were utilized to formulate better                      (2006), wherein it has been made mandatory&#13;
implementation practices regarding land acquisition,                    for all hydropower developers (more than 5 MW&#13;
resettlement and community development in the                           capacity) in the State to earmark 1.5 percent of the&#13;
Rampur Project. The overall experience of the                           project cost towards local area development during&#13;
Rampur Project demonstrates that benefit sharing                        project implementation from 2008 onwards. The&#13;
has broad and multi-layered advantages. The                             money has to be deposited with the Local Area&#13;
approach adopted by SJVNL in the Rampur Project                         Development Committee (LADC) that manages and&#13;
went beyond one-time compensation and short-term                        implements the various community development&#13;
resettlement support and in this spirit, displaced                      activities in the project-affected villages. As a result,&#13;
people and local communities were both treated                          local infrastructure development has received a&#13;
as legitimate partners and beneficiaries in the                         boost in the state with creation of LADCs for each&#13;
development process.                                                    power project with capacity exceeding 5 MW. For&#13;
                                                                        example, since 2009, LADCs have implemented 85&#13;
â&#128;¢	 SJVNL adopted proactive and innovative&#13;
   approaches to social safeguards and community&#13;
   development that included a fair compensation,&#13;
   inclusive resettlement measures, demand driven&#13;
   local infrastructure improvement, opportunities for&#13;
   employment and skill upgrading, and support to&#13;
   various welfare and cultural activities. The project&#13;
   not only supported the affected communities in&#13;
   livelihood restoration but also the larger local&#13;
   communities in local area development.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
4&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                    Rampur Hydropower Project&#13;
                                                                    Land Acquisition, Resettlement and Community Development Practices&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    infrastructure works (like constructing permanent&#13;
    paths, retaining walls, playgrounds and fencing,&#13;
    footbridges, drinking water pipelines, rooms for&#13;
    schools and community halls) in Rampur project&#13;
    area.&#13;
&#13;
â&#128;¢	 With commencement of operations, the project will&#13;
   also start making annuity payments to residents&#13;
   of the project-affected area, during the projectâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
   operational life, from revenue of sale of one percent&#13;
   of free power in accordance with the revised&#13;
   guidelines for local area development adopted by&#13;
   State Government in 2011 under their Hydropower&#13;
   Policy (2006). In addition, the project will also                       usually associated with large infrastructure projects&#13;
   provide 100 units of electricity per month to each                      due to protracted land acquisition and resettlement&#13;
   project-affected family for a period of 10 years as                     of displaced families.&#13;
   per the Hydro Policy (2008) of GoI. This is expected&#13;
   to further strengthen the ownership of the project                  	   The land acquisition and resettlement plan were&#13;
   with local communities.                                                 fully implemented by the time of closure of the&#13;
                                                                           World Bank loan in December 2014 in accordance&#13;
Outcomes                                                                   with the provisions of the framework adopted for&#13;
The key features of the approach adopted by SJVNL                          the project. The End-Term Impact Evaluation&#13;
and their results are listed as below:                                     undertaken for the Project confirmed that the&#13;
                                                                           Project affected families have an overall improved&#13;
â&#128;¢	 A more equitable approach to land acquisition:                          living standard; proportion of workers in regular&#13;
   SJVNL responded to landownersâ&#128;&#153; demand for fair                          employment, average income, earning capacity&#13;
   compensation by appointing a committee through                          and diversification of income have increased, and&#13;
   the state government to determine market value of                       housing standards have improved.&#13;
   the land they were to acquire. New parameters such&#13;
   as the nature and use of land were considered,                      â&#128;¢	 Self-relocation option: SJVNL demonstrated&#13;
   as were rates for land fixed in recent court cases                     flexibility in resettlement4 by encouraging&#13;
   and private sector transactions. As a result, the                      self-relocation for displaced families, and&#13;
   compensation rates finally paid ranged between                         offering them sites of their choice and attractive&#13;
   Rs. 5.8-6.0 million (~US$ 1,05,450-1,09,090)2                          resettlement assistance instead of project-&#13;
   per hectare and were up to 10 times higher than                        sponsored resettlement. Fifteen project-affected&#13;
   those that had been initially determined in the                        families without a house opted for a 60 sq. m&#13;
   range of Rs. 0.3-0.6 million per hectare. The                          plot with a construction grant of Rs. 0.18 million&#13;
   compensation was declared within one year of the                       (~US$ 3,270) and a temporarily leased two-&#13;
   land acquisition notification, thereby reducing the                    room accommodation or Rs. 2000 (~US$ 36) per&#13;
   time for acquisition by 1-1.5 years and the entire                     month for 18 months. Ten displaced families, who&#13;
   process was completed before commencement of                           had an alternative house, were each offered a&#13;
   civil works3. This prevented implementation delays                     construction grant of Rs. 0.18 million (~US$ 3,270)&#13;
&#13;
2&#13;
  Conversion used for 2004-14 is US$ 1=Rs. 55.&#13;
3&#13;
  Under land acquisition act, there is mechanism to appeal to the courts for enhancement of compensation, which can generally involve time&#13;
and cost. Accordingly, the people preferred to pursue with SJVNL for higher compensation.&#13;
4&#13;
  SJVNL provided options for resettlement - self-relocation, or cash grant or project constructed houses.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                         5&#13;
&amp;#12;Rampur Hydropower Project&#13;
Land Acquisition, Resettlement and Community Development Practices&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                        on long-term contracts; and (iii) rental of light&#13;
                                                                        vehicles - Till June 2015, around 60 vehicles for&#13;
                                                                        about 4,370 vehicle months have been hired by&#13;
                                                                        the project, significantly helping to supplement&#13;
                                                                        household income.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                     â&#128;¢	 Focused community welfare measures: SJVNL&#13;
                                                                        sought to spread the benefits of induced&#13;
                                                                        development beyond those directly affected, to also&#13;
                                                                        include residents of the wider project-affected area,&#13;
                                                                        thereby increasing the ownership and acceptance&#13;
                                                                        of the project among the community at large.&#13;
                                                                        To that effect, SJVNL has spent around Rs. 480&#13;
                                                                        million (~US$ 8.7 million) on improving basic&#13;
                                                                        infrastructure in the area such as approach&#13;
                                                                        roads, pathways, school buildings, playgrounds,&#13;
                                                                        street lights, water supply, sewerage, sanitation,&#13;
                                                                        community centres, etc.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                     â&#128;¢	 Continuous health services: Provision of mobile&#13;
                                                                        health vans, referral services and periodical&#13;
                                                                        medical camps helped strengthen the relationship&#13;
    to improve or construct additional rooms. The                       between SJVNL and local communities. By&#13;
    other four displaced families were offered Rs. 0.99                 December 2014, more than 58,500 people (of&#13;
    million (US$ 18,000) in cash in lieu of alternative                 which 51 percent females) had benefitted from&#13;
    houses. All displaced families were provided cash                   mobile health vans and 250 chronic patients&#13;
    assistance to cover relocation expenses.                            referred to the main hospital for timely treatment.&#13;
                                                                        The operation of mobile health unit is now&#13;
â&#128;¢	 Support for income generation schemes: SJVNL                         transferred to a professional agency called â&#128;&#156;Help&#13;
   offered income enhancement opportunities to                          age Indiaâ&#128;&#157;. In addition, more than 50 health camps&#13;
   people in the project area through initiatives such                  have benefitted over 6,200 patients (of which 24&#13;
   as: (i) reserving small contracts below Rs. 1 million                percent females) so far. Recently, the project has&#13;
   (~US$ 18,180) to be implemented by them - By                         constructed about 300 toilets for school children in&#13;
   December 2014, 119 contracts worth Rs. 338                           the school around the project.&#13;
   million (US$ 6.15 million) and 84 contracts worth&#13;
   Rs. 40.4 million (US$ 0.73 million) had been                      â&#128;¢	 Skill upgrading measures: SJVNLâ&#128;&#153;s belief that&#13;
   awarded to local people by SJVNL and the major                       backwardness and remoteness of the area&#13;
   project contractors respectively; (ii) employment                    should not deter talented, ambitious local youth&#13;
   by contractors - From the start-up of construction                   from progressing led it to implement a technical&#13;
   in 2007 until December 2014, the project has                         education program. Since the scheme was&#13;
   provided 0.71 million person days of work to the                     launched in 2006, SJVNL has sponsored 195&#13;
   local population, covering approximately                             candidates including 31 (16 percent) females to&#13;
   28 percent employment created by contractors.                        ITIs of which 174 (89 percent) have completed their&#13;
   Thus, work opportunities to the local people                         courses and 96 (55 percent) of them, including&#13;
   increased substantially. In addition, 444 local                      13 females, were employed with the contractors&#13;
   people (7 percent females) including 25 project-                     subsequently. Careful monitoring of the outcomes&#13;
   affected persons were employed by contractors                        of this initiative encouraged SJVNL to also start&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
6&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                           Rampur Hydropower Project&#13;
                                                           Land Acquisition, Resettlement and Community Development Practices&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   Improvement in the Living Standards&#13;
   An end-term impact evaluation was undertaken by the project through independent consultants in December&#13;
   2014. The objective of the evaluation to capture the effect implementation of land acquisition, resettlement&#13;
   and community development activities had on the project beneficiaries. The evaluation revealed:&#13;
   (i)	 the average income of project-affected families has increased by more than 50 percent in real terms&#13;
          over baseline incomes and is 86 percent more than the average income of the control set of population;&#13;
   (ii)	 more than 50 percent of the affected people have added additional household assets or immovable&#13;
          assets such as land or house from the compensation amounts received by them;&#13;
   (iii)	 the proportion of people working in fixed earning income jobs has increased by around 25 percent&#13;
          from the baseline;&#13;
   (iv)	 the housing conditions of the affected people have substantially improved. For example, average&#13;
          size of the house is now 70 percent bigger than the baseline average size and more than double the&#13;
          control set populationâ&#128;&#153;s size of houses;&#13;
   (v)	 female literacy increased by 7 percent to 83 percent from the baseline level of 76 percent;&#13;
   (vi)	 average spending on food items increased by about 15 percent and is 20 percent more than the&#13;
          control set of population;&#13;
   (vii)	 compensation amounts have been used productively - Around 20 percent invested compensation&#13;
          amounts for land purchase and about 60 households made investments in the form of Bank fixed&#13;
          deposits, and mutual funds; and&#13;
   (viii)	the project-affected people identified support for technical education, merit scholarships, dispensary at&#13;
          Bayal and mobile health van, to be good initiatives by SJVNL in assisting the affected people and local&#13;
          people in their efforts towards improving the access to basic amenities and health and education facilities.&#13;
&#13;
   The summary of finding of end term impact evaluation was translated and shared with the village heads of&#13;
   the affected villages.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   an apprenticeship program in January 2012 for                 SJVNL focused on communication from an early&#13;
   the youth in order to make them employable. So                stage, with close attention to consultations with&#13;
   far 57 candidates including 8 females (14 percent)            project affected communities as well as enhanced&#13;
   have successfully completed on-the-job training. In           disclosure and transparency mechanisms&#13;
   addition, 89 candidates including 26 (29 percent)             around the project and an open-door policy for&#13;
   females have received merit scholarships to pursue            affected families. Regular informal and periodic&#13;
   higher education.                                             formal consultations ensured that views of local&#13;
                                                                 people are heard and taken into account. Direct&#13;
â&#128;¢	 Gender sensitivity: SJVNL has focused on womenâ&#128;&#153;s              communication with communities enabled clear&#13;
   empowerment by introducing measures that                      dissemination of information and program delivery,&#13;
   enhance their skills and workplace exposure.                  reducing the chances of misinformation and&#13;
                                                                 helped effectively address grievances. Proactive&#13;
â&#128;¢	 Building trust through early consultation,                    strategies, such as holding training sessions for&#13;
   communication and interaction with the local                  the local communities, placed the project at the&#13;
   community: One of the reasons that helped                     forefront of communication processes, which&#13;
   Rampur Project gain acceptance from the local                 have been emulated in other projects in the&#13;
   community was the strong effort by SJVNL to build             state. The Public Information Centre (PIC) set up&#13;
   a good relationship with the affected community               at site provided a one-stop window for project-&#13;
   from very early on. Early in project preparation,             affected communities. Relations with local media&#13;
   for example, the project deployed a mobile health             were handled pro-actively which helped manage&#13;
   van to deliver health services to the community.              perceptions around the project.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                           7&#13;
&amp;#12;Rampur Hydropower Project&#13;
Land Acquisition, Resettlement and Community Development Practices&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Land Acquisition Practices&#13;
Land Acquired: Rates and Compensation                                        on prevailing land rates in 2005, classified by type&#13;
The implementation agreement for the Rampur                                  and ranged between Rs. 0.3-0.6 million6 (~US$&#13;
Hydropower Project (RHP) was signed between the                              5,450â&#128;&#147;10,900) per hectare, approximately 10 times&#13;
Government of Himachal Pradesh and SJVNL in                                  lower than the rates in the adjoining Jagathkhana&#13;
October 2004. SJVNL required 80 hectares of land for                         and Poshna panchayats compared to the project&#13;
infrastructure such as offices, power house, dumping                         affected panchayats of Bayal, Nirmand, Gadej and&#13;
area, quarry and site establishments. Of this, 50                            Dutt Nagar. In fact, the land for another hydropower&#13;
hectares of state forest land was acquired from the                          project (Parbati Hydropower Project in Kullu district)&#13;
Government and 30 hectares of private land from 167                          was acquired at rates 8-9 times higher than what&#13;
landowners in four villages5 of three panchayats in                          was initially offered in Rampur project, on account&#13;
Kullu and Shimla districts. The private land acquisition                     of use of various parameters for assessment of&#13;
was initiated in September 2005 by the stateâ&#128;&#153;s revenue                       compensation and not past transactions only,&#13;
department under the Indian Land Acquisition Act,                            despite the relative backwardness of the area. Most&#13;
1894 and completed in October 2006.                                          landowners affected by Rampur Project vehemently&#13;
                                                                             disapproved of these low rates, being aware of&#13;
Approach: Initially compensation was based on                                other such land transactions and asked SJVNL for&#13;
rates arrived as per the Land Acquisition Act, based                         higher compensation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
5&#13;
    Includes Bayal, Koyal, Averi/Gadej in Kullu district and Dutt Nagar in Shimla district.&#13;
6&#13;
    Conversion used for 2004-14 is US$ 1=Rs. 55.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
8&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                    Rampur Hydropower Project&#13;
                                                                    Land Acquisition, Resettlement and Community Development Practices&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The project is located in a hilly terrain about 130 kms&#13;
from state capital of Shimla and situated on the bank&#13;
of River Sutlej. Being a hilly and remote region and far&#13;
away from the state capital, there were limited market&#13;
registered transactions which provided limited basis&#13;
for determination of realistic land values. A District&#13;
Level Market Rates Fixing Committee was constituted&#13;
in December 2005 with the Deputy Commissioner&#13;
as Chairman and senior representatives of key&#13;
government departments including the public&#13;
works department (PWD), forests, agriculture, and&#13;
horticulture. SJVNL and the project-affected families&#13;
both chose not to be represented, thereby enabling the&#13;
committee to carry out an independent and objective                   them in July 2006. These enhanced rates became&#13;
assessment. Land valuation was based on comparison                    basis for acquisition of additional private land triggered&#13;
with prevalent market land rates in the vicinity                      during the project implementation and made this&#13;
(see Box 1) computed as an average of land rates                      subsequent land acquisition easier and faster. The&#13;
prevalent in three areas, namely Jagathkhana, Poshna                  valuation of structures was undertaken through a third&#13;
and the village where land had to be acquired.                        party, an approved valuer of the State Government,&#13;
                                                                      who used the item rate method, namely the Himachal&#13;
Outcomes: The compensation rates finally ranged                       Pradesh PWD schedule of rates and the prevailing&#13;
between Rs. 5.8-6.0 million (~US$ 1,05,450-1,09,090)                  market premium on these rates.&#13;
per hectare and were 10 times higher than previously&#13;
determined. The committee applied these enhanced                      Based on Section 9 of the Land Acquisition Act, 18947,&#13;
rates only to land acquired for the project to speed up               project-affected families were asked to express their&#13;
the land acquisition and thus avoid delays associated                 interest in the land, assets, amount, and particulars of&#13;
with land acquisition. The district administration of                 the claim and state their objections, in the presence&#13;
Kullu considered these rates reasonable and approved                  of a SJVNL representative. While the project-affected&#13;
                                                                      families had no objections to the measurement or the&#13;
                                                                      revised land rates, they raised other demands such as:&#13;
    Box 1: Parameters considered in valuation&#13;
                                                                      (i) alternative land to those rendered landless, and a&#13;
    â&#128;¢	 Recent land transactions                                       house to those rendered houseless; (ii) employment of&#13;
    â&#128;¢	 Compensation paid in other hydropower power                    one member from each family in the project as a long&#13;
       projects in the vicinity                                       term rehabilitation measure.&#13;
    â&#128;¢	 Revised compensation rates in land acquisition&#13;
       enhanced by court rulings                                      The compensation was declared in October 2006, within&#13;
    â&#128;¢	 Type of land (agricultural or non-agricultural)                one year of the notification, thereby reducing the time for&#13;
    â&#128;¢	 Average productivity per bigha                                 acquisition by 1-1.5 years and included an additional:&#13;
    â&#128;¢	 Proximity to road and market&#13;
    â&#128;¢	 Distance from village habitation                               â&#128;¢	 30 percent towards solatium8 on the market value&#13;
    â&#128;¢	 Transportation and irrigation facilities                          of land, structure, fruit and non-fruit trees; and&#13;
    â&#128;¢	 Nature and type of standing crops                              â&#128;¢	 12 percent interest for the period following the&#13;
                                                                         notification.&#13;
7&#13;
 Law in force at that time.&#13;
8&#13;
 Terminology used in land acquisition act which means additional compensation paid for compulsory acquisition of land by solacing the&#13;
affected person.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                        9&#13;
&amp;#12;Rampur Hydropower Project&#13;
Land Acquisition, Resettlement and Community Development Practices&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The compensation also varied according to the type of                  is Rs. 286 million (US$ 5.2 million), which is less&#13;
land, such as irrigated land where it was 4 times higher,              than 1 percent of the project cost at completion.&#13;
and non-irrigated lands where it was 10-20 times higher.&#13;
&#13;
The process of compensation was completed prior to                        Key Outcomes&#13;
the commencement of civil works in February 2007.&#13;
Besides facilitating compensation, the project enabled                    The proactive approach to land acquisition and&#13;
the resettlement of 15 displaced households consisting                    providing a realistic compensation led to the&#13;
of about 70 people.9 Additional lands for civil works                     following results:&#13;
required during project implementation were also&#13;
                                                                          â&#128;¢	 land acquisition process took place in a&#13;
acquired at these rates. In addition to compensation,&#13;
                                                                             smooth manner, without any major opposition&#13;
the land losers becoming landless were also provided&#13;
                                                                          â&#128;¢	 land acquisition took place well in advance&#13;
with additional support of rehabilitation grants (Box 2)                     of commencement of civil work i.e. timely&#13;
and 51 vulnerable families including 11 women headed                         commencement of civil works&#13;
families were given financial assistance for their speedy                 â&#128;¢	 additional land acquisition during project&#13;
rehabilitation in the post land acquisition period.                          construction for facilitation of additional civil&#13;
                                                                             works&#13;
The final amount of expenditure involved towards                          â&#128;¢	 support of the affected community&#13;
land acquisition and resettlement implementation&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
8&#13;
  Terminology used in land acquisition act which means additional compensation paid for compulsory acquisition of land by solacing the&#13;
affected person.&#13;
9&#13;
  In Himachal Pradesh, landless is defined as the one who is left with less than 5 bighas of land (i.e. less than 1 acre).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
10&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                          Rampur Hydropower Project&#13;
                                                                          Land Acquisition, Resettlement and Community Development Practices&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Resettlement and Rehabilitation of&#13;
Project-affected People&#13;
Approach: The Rampur Project identified 29 families                          provided rehabilitation grants to families rendered&#13;
to be displaced and requiring relocation. This                               landless10 after acquisition and counselled them on&#13;
included 19 families that were left without houses                           productive investment (see Box 2).&#13;
and 10 families that had an alternate house. SJVNLâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
approach to resettlement and rehabilitation aimed at:&#13;
                                                                                Box 2: Rehabilitation grant by size of&#13;
â&#128;¢	 Suitable relocation of displaced families;                                   landholding (in ha)&#13;
â&#128;¢	 Relocation choice for displaced families, based on&#13;
   the NJHP experience; and,                                                      before Land        after Land         Amount (Rs.)&#13;
â&#128;¢	 Rehabilitation grants for those rendered landless                              Acquisition        Acquisition&#13;
   and houseless.                                                                      &gt; 0.4          0 or 0.004            65,000&#13;
                                                                                       &lt; 0.4          0 or 0.004            55,000&#13;
Rehabilitation grants: SJVNL recognized that in a rural                                     -        &gt; 0.004 and            45,000&#13;
economy, agricultural land is a key economic asset                                                      &lt; 0.4&#13;
whose loss must be compensated. It therefore also&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
10&#13;
     Those left with less than 5 bighas (1 acre) after land was acquired for the project.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                         11&#13;
&amp;#12;Rampur Hydropower Project&#13;
Land Acquisition, Resettlement and Community Development Practices&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                     by the committee for land acquisition, benefitting&#13;
     Box 3: Self-relocation options                                  willing sellers. The Rampur Project developed the&#13;
     â&#128;¢	 Provide an independent house with plot area of               plots before handing them over to the buyers for&#13;
        60 sq. m.                                                    construction.&#13;
     â&#128;¢	 Provide construction cost of house @ Rs. 3,000&#13;
        per sq. m. i.e. Rs. 1,80,000 (US$ 3,270)                     Construction grant: SJVNL released the construction&#13;
     â&#128;¢	 A family that does not opt for a house/plot                  grants in instalments, by assessing construction&#13;
        but constructs its house at its own cost with                progress through a project committee, so that&#13;
        a plinth area of 60 sq. m or more to be paid                 displaced families actually rebuilt their houses, and&#13;
        construction cost at Rs. 3,500 per sq.m.&#13;
                                                                     did not squander the assistance amount. Besides,&#13;
                                                                     SJVNL prepared a transit plan, providing temporary&#13;
An independent study11 found that project-affected                   accommodation to houseless families for the period&#13;
families utilized the compensation money and                         between vacating their old houses and moving to new&#13;
rehabilitation grant to purchase land, orchards in the               ones, with the options of temporarily leased two-room&#13;
vicinity, and vehicles or make improvements in their                 accommodation or Rs. 2000 (~US$ 36) per month&#13;
houses.                                                              for 18 months. Ten displaced families who had an&#13;
                                                                     alternative house were each offered a construction&#13;
Flexibility in choice for relocation: SJVNL                          grant of Rs. 0.18 million (~US$ 3,270) to improve or&#13;
demonstrated flexibility, using its resettlement and                 construct additional rooms. The other 4 displaced&#13;
rehabilitation scheme to give them the choice of                     families choose to build houses individually on their&#13;
relocation, rather than push them into a pre-identified              own as they could not find suitable site of their choice.&#13;
resettlement.                                                        Hence they were offered cash in lieu of alternative&#13;
                                                                     houses. Each of these families were paid Rs. 0.99&#13;
Consultative process: 15 out of 19 project-affected                  million (US$ 18,000), the amount equivalent to the&#13;
families without a house opted for a 60 sq. m plot with              average amount spent by the project for other 15&#13;
a construction grant (see Box 3). SJVNL purchased                    displaced families towards purchase of a plot, land&#13;
0.7850 hectares of land on a â&#128;&#152;willing seller-willing                 development, creation of infrastructure and transitional&#13;
buyerâ&#128;&#153; basis at the same enhanced rates fixed                        support.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
11&#13;
  Mid-term Impact Evaluation of Resettlement Action Plan and Community Development Plan Implementation in Rampur Hydropower&#13;
Project, November 2010, SMEC India Limited and End-term Impact Evaluation of Resettlement Action Plan and Community Development&#13;
Plan Implementation in Rampur Hydropower Project.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
12&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                    Rampur Hydropower Project&#13;
                                                                    Land Acquisition, Resettlement and Community Development Practices&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
â&#128;&#156;â&#128;¦The earlier house had four rooms and a toilet, permanent but smaller. After land acquisition, SJVNL gave&#13;
us a plot for our resettlement. Actually, the plot is only 100 meters away from our earlier home. We continue&#13;
to get fodder for our cattle from the nearby forestâ&#128;¦ so no change. â&#128;¦... This is the new house that we have&#13;
constructed. It has four rooms but as you can see they are bigger than earlierâ&#128;¦ with a toilet. Water supply is&#13;
available for 24 hours. SJVNL has provided street lighting and recently set up a sewage treatment plant for the&#13;
colonyâ&#128;¦ definitely an improvement on what we had earlier. You would notice we are now constructing the first&#13;
floorâ&#128;¦ more members in the household means need for more space!â&#128;&#157;&#13;
&#13;
â&#128;&#147; Biju Ram S/o Matu Ram, Project displaced family (houseless and landless), Averi village&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                         Key Outcomes&#13;
&#13;
                                                                         The end-term impact evaluation revealed&#13;
                                                                         significant change in the overall housing situation&#13;
                                                                         of the project affected people:&#13;
&#13;
                                                                         â&#128;¢	 Now more people live in pucca (permanent)&#13;
                                                                            houses - 100 percent as compared to 95&#13;
                                                                            percent earlier;&#13;
                                                                         â&#128;¢	 More families have now have separate toilets -&#13;
                                                                            91 percent as compared to 68 percent earlier;&#13;
                                                                         â&#128;¢	 More families have separate kitchen within&#13;
Reimbursement for moving or relocation costs: SJVNL                         house - 95 percent as against 79 percent&#13;
provided about Rs. 5,000 (~US$ 91) to households to                         earlier; and&#13;
cover their moving costs from their original dwelling                    â&#128;¢	 The average size of house has increased&#13;
units to temporary accommodation and then to their                          from 578 sq.ft. to 985 sq.ft. and the average&#13;
new houses.                                                                 number of rooms has gone up from 3.7 to&#13;
                                                                            6.85 per house.&#13;
Other facilities: The resettlement colonies at Bayal and&#13;
Averi villages were provided with piped water, internal&#13;
paths, approach roads, street lighting and a sewage                   â&#128;¢	 house sizes increased by more than 400 sq. m with&#13;
treatment plant with 25,000 litres capacity to serve                     extra rooms; and&#13;
100-125 persons. An independent study12 revealed                      â&#128;¢	 additional rooms were rented out at Rs. 1,500&#13;
that in comparison with the pre-project scenario:                        (~US$ 27) per room per month to migrant&#13;
                                                                         construction workers, who are in need of housing&#13;
â&#128;¢	 more than 60 percent additional households had                        and the income earned supplemented the overall&#13;
   permanent house structures;                                           household income.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
12&#13;
     End-term Impact Evaluation of Resettlement Action Plan and Community Development Plan Implementation in Rampur Hydropower Project.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                    13&#13;
&amp;#12;Rampur Hydropower Project&#13;
Land Acquisition, Resettlement and Community Development Practices&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Income Enhancement Measures&#13;
During Project Implementation&#13;
Approach: SJVNLâ&#128;&#153;s compensation and resettlement&#13;
grants shielded project-affected families against                       Income enhancement opportunities&#13;
adverse resettlement impacts and the long construction                  offered by RHP:&#13;
phase, and the RHP offered income enhancement                           â&#128;¢	 petty contracts (below Rs. 1.0 million or&#13;
opportunities to those in the project area such as: (i)                    ~US$ 18,180)&#13;
petty contracts, (ii) employment by contractors, and (iii)              â&#128;¢	 contractors engaging local persons&#13;
rental of light vehicles.                                               â&#128;¢	 hiring of light vehicles for the project&#13;
&#13;
Petty contracts: SJVNL awarded petty contracts                       By employing local people, the contractors substantially&#13;
(below Rs. 1.0 million or ~US$ 18,180) such                          increased local work opportunities. Petty contracts&#13;
as housekeeping, gardening and masonry for                           were tendered and awarded to registered agencies&#13;
infrastructure on a preferential basis to local people               submitting the lowest bid. The duration of such&#13;
and registered contractors under three categories:                   contracts was approximately one year and, depending&#13;
                                                                     on the nature of work, these were re-tendered annually.&#13;
â&#128;¢	   project-affected families;                                      Petty contractors confirmed receiving timely payment&#13;
â&#128;¢	   residents of project-affected areas; and                        and gaining exposure for work outside the area. By&#13;
â&#128;¢	   local persons.                                                  December 2014, 119 petty contracts worth Rs. 338&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
14&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                             Rampur Hydropower Project&#13;
                                                             Land Acquisition, Resettlement and Community Development Practices&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
million (~US$ 6.15 million) had been awarded to&#13;
local people, of which Rs. 202.30 million (~US$ 3.68&#13;
million) worth works (60 percent) have been completed.&#13;
Besides, the major project contractors have awarded 84&#13;
petty contracts worth Rs. 40.4 million (US$ 0.73 million).&#13;
&#13;
Employment of local persons by contractors:&#13;
SJVNL engaged local persons on annual contracts&#13;
through various contractors, thereby increasing local&#13;
employment for clerks, supervisors and data entry&#13;
operators on pay scales ranging between Rs. 3,000&#13;
and 8,000 (~US$ 55-145) per month. In addition, 444&#13;
local people including 25 project-affected persons&#13;
were employed by contractors on long-term contracts.&#13;
With this experience and income, these entrants&#13;
have been able to pursue higher studies and other&#13;
professional interests. Although a state-of-the-art&#13;
hydropower project like the Rampur one has only&#13;
limited manpower needs, SJVNL has stipulated that&#13;
â&#128;&#156;one member of each project affected family rendered&#13;
landless will be provided employment by the project            supervisor and workman level, thus augmenting both&#13;
authority in the category of skilled/ semi-skilled/            gainful employment and household income. From the&#13;
unskilled workmen subject to fulfilling the requisite          start-up of construction in 2007 until December 2014,&#13;
criteria/ qualification and as and when any fresh              the project has provided 0.71 million person days of&#13;
recruitment is done in these categories.â&#128;&#157; Accordingly,         work to the local population, covering approximately&#13;
one vacancy for the post of pharmacist was filled by a         28 percent employment created by contractors.&#13;
female candidate from a project-affected family.&#13;
                                                               Rental of light vehicles: SJVNL also initiated a scheme&#13;
SJVNL has also mandated that all contractors and               whereby vehicles (mainly jeeps) were to be hired by&#13;
their sub-vendors provide work opportunities to local          the project on rent, which became a major source&#13;
persons, mainly semi-skilled and unskilled, at the             of supplementary income for local people. SJVNL&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
I work with the finance department of RHP and live in Kasholi village of Badi panchayat i.e. within the project-&#13;
affected area, but not directly affected. When RHP introduced this scheme of hiring of vehicles for families&#13;
residing in the project-affected area, I considered it as a good opportunity to earn more money. â&#128;¦I purchased&#13;
a Mahindra Bolero vehicle on loan and rented it out to RHP in 2011. I get Rs. 18,000 (~US$ 327) as a fixed&#13;
rate and with fuel and other expenses it is about Rs. 27,000 (~US$ 491) per month. Part of the earnings goes&#13;
towards loan repayment and driverâ&#128;&#153;s salary. Money earned has been good and enabled me to afford more.&#13;
My son is enrolled in GNIIT â&#128;&#147; computer course from an accredited institute. Also, once the loan amount is&#13;
cleared, I get the vehicle for free. If I sell it, I will get at least Rs. 1,50,000 (~US$ 2,727).&#13;
&#13;
â&#128;&#147; Mangat Ram, Vehicle owner&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                            15&#13;
&amp;#12;Rampur Hydropower Project&#13;
Land Acquisition, Resettlement and Community Development Practices&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                     their concerns directly to him. He introduced weekly&#13;
                                                                     visiting hour, so that any local people and project&#13;
                                                                     affected people can visit and discuss their concerns&#13;
                                                                     and issues directly with him. Regular informal and&#13;
                                                                     periodic formal consultations have ensured that views&#13;
                                                                     of local people are heard and taken into account.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                     In early meetings with the villagers, the project&#13;
                                                                     staff explained to them in detail the possible social&#13;
                                                                     and environmental impacts of the proposed project&#13;
                                                                     and discussed possible mitigation measures. They&#13;
                                                                     provided information on, and translated and explained&#13;
                                                                     the provisions and guidelines of various schemes&#13;
initially advertised this scheme for project-affected                governing land acquisition and rehabilitation; the&#13;
families only, but later opened it up for other residents            development of community infrastructure works;&#13;
of the project-affected area. The local population                   compensation for potential damage due to blasting on&#13;
appreciates the scheme, for most of whom farming                     houses or crops; measures to deal with dust pollution&#13;
is the main occupation and this additional avenue for                etc. They also explained the system for resolving&#13;
earning income through vehicle rental is otherwise                   grievances of affected communities, individuals and&#13;
not available as an option. They took a loan and                     their representative groups.&#13;
purchased vehicle to give it to the project on monthly&#13;
rental. The vehicle owners now expect to recover their               All the local area development schemes are finalized&#13;
investment cost and repay the loan for purchasing the                in consultation with the community and in some&#13;
vehicle. Till June 2015, approximately 4,370 vehicle                 cases, the community is directly involved in the&#13;
months were hired by the project, significantly helping              implementation also.&#13;
to supplement household income.&#13;
                                                                     The project also took initiative to publish a quarterly&#13;
Direct communication. SJVNL has focused on building                  newsletter â&#128;&#156;Rampur Urja Samacharâ&#128;&#157; covering progress&#13;
a direct relationship with the local community right                 of the project and developmental activities carried&#13;
from start of project development stage and which                    out by the project in the vicinity of the project. This&#13;
continued in the project implementation. The head                    quarterly newsletter helped to disseminate the updated&#13;
of the project has maintained an open door policy                    information to the locals through panchayat leaders&#13;
throughout the project encouraging people to bring                   and other stakeholders.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
A Public Information Center (PIC) has been operational in Bayal village since 2005 to function as a one-stop&#13;
resource center for the local villagers for information on resettlement and rehabilitation, community development,&#13;
employment opportunities, and and serves as an additional place for registering complaints and suggestions.&#13;
This PIC is also a repository of all project related documents and allows the villagers to easily access reports&#13;
such as the resettlement action plan, social impact assessment, environmental impact assessment, and&#13;
environment management plan, etc. The PIC is manned by a local officer conversant with local issues to those&#13;
who visit the PIC. Till December 2014, 6640 number of visitors had visited the PIC.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
16&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                           Rampur Hydropower Project&#13;
                                                                           Land Acquisition, Resettlement and Community Development Practices&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Community&#13;
Development Measures&#13;
Approach: The objective of the SJVNLâ&#128;&#153;s community                              Outcomes: The innovative design of the program&#13;
development program is the sustainable development                            contributed to the State Government coming out with&#13;
and socio-economic improvement of project-affected                            a policy in 2008 for the State wherein it was made&#13;
communities in the surrounding villages by:                                   mandatory for hydropower developers to earmark&#13;
                                                                              1.5 percent of the project cost towards local area&#13;
â&#128;¢	 Providing or enhancing basic infrastructure;                               development and the money has to be deposited with&#13;
â&#128;¢	 Operating mobile health vans;                                              the Local Area Development Committee (LADC) that&#13;
â&#128;¢	 Providing scholarships for the wards of affected                           manages and implements projects.&#13;
   local people;&#13;
â&#128;¢	 Sponsoring youth to Industrial Training Institutes                         The original allocation for infrastructure development in&#13;
   (ITIs)13 to acquire technical skills; and                                  case of Rampur project was Rs. 125 million (~US$ 2.3&#13;
â&#128;¢	 Providing support services to agriculture and                              million) under the sustainable community development&#13;
   horticulture.                                                              program, however following the notification of the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
13&#13;
     local training schools providing vocational instruction in a range of technical trades.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                          17&#13;
&amp;#12;Rampur Hydropower Project&#13;
Land Acquisition, Resettlement and Community Development Practices&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Stateâ&#128;&#153;s new policy in 2008, the allocation has been&#13;
raised to Rs. 307.5 million (~US$ 5.6 million). Since&#13;
2009, the LADC has sanctioned, executed and&#13;
monitored infrastructure improvement schemes under&#13;
this allocation in the affected villages, including:&#13;
&#13;
Infrastructure works: Rs. 480 million (~US$ 8.7&#13;
million) have been spent by the project on improving&#13;
infrastructure, including on two major works, namely a&#13;
new bus station (Rs.114 million or ~US$ 2.07 million)&#13;
and a senior secondary school (Rs. 20 million or ~US$&#13;
0.36 million) at Rampur. In addition, SJVNL has also&#13;
installed energized tube wells and hand pumps for&#13;
improving drinking water supply. Based on ranking&#13;
parameters (see Box 4), the funds are earmarked&#13;
for each affected village to support the provision of&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Box 4: Ranking parameter and weightage&#13;
&#13;
     Land acquired                                 20%&#13;
     Length of river stream                        40%               small infrastructure. The project proponent then has to&#13;
     Length of underground works                                     improve basic infrastructure such as approach roads,&#13;
     (like tunnel etc.)                            40%               pathways, school buildings, playgrounds, street lights,&#13;
                                                                     water supply, sewerage, sanitation, community centres&#13;
&#13;
18&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                           Rampur Hydropower Project&#13;
                                                           Land Acquisition, Resettlement and Community Development Practices&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
â&#128;&#156;..there was a Primary Health Center at Koyal villageâ&#128;¦ but we still travelled to Khaneri or Rampur. The bus fare&#13;
apart, half a day would be required in terms of time, causing discomfort to the patient. Now with the health vans&#13;
coming and holding camps and check-up of patients, we get treatment and free medicines â&#128;¦.at our doorstep!&#13;
&#13;
â&#128;&#147; Pooja of Bakhan village, Kharga Panchayat (project-affected area)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
and cremation grounds. As infrastructure work below&#13;
the threshold of one million rupees (~US$ 18,180) is&#13;
allocable for local petty contracts, those interested&#13;
could submit their bids.&#13;
&#13;
Mobile health vans and medical camps: Prior to&#13;
the project, the nearest medical facility for local&#13;
communities was at Khaneri or Rampur, approximately&#13;
8-10 km away. Inadequate transportation rendered&#13;
access difficult. Medical camps and mobile health&#13;
vans became operational in January 2005, comprising&#13;
a team of doctors, nurses and attendants that visits&#13;
villages thrice weekly for one hour per village, also&#13;
providing treatment and referral services to villages in&#13;
the neighbourhood.&#13;
&#13;
Mobile health vans and medical camps help diagnose&#13;
patients, provide medicines free of cost, medical&#13;
guidance and referrals. This has increased awareness&#13;
about basic hygiene and balanced diet in the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                          19&#13;
&amp;#12;Rampur Hydropower Project&#13;
Land Acquisition, Resettlement and Community Development Practices&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
â&#128;¦the Rampur project has supported the schools in the area in many ways. We have used the grant scheme for&#13;
purchasing science, chemistry instruments, books for the library, furniture, tables, chairs, basketball, volleyballâ&#128;¦&#13;
sports goodsâ&#128;¦and yes, we developed a basketball court. We also get grants from the state government... it&#13;
comes throughâ&#128;¦sometimes takes longer. The project gave scholarships to encourage good studentsâ&#128;¦ there&#13;
was an essay, quiz and declamation competition tooâ&#128;¦.Recently in February; the project organized a dental,&#13;
blood grouping camp â&#128;¦in our school... very useful. Actually otherwise it is very difficult for the school to organize&#13;
such a camp. The panchayat is involved as well in the functioningâ&#128;¦.the school management committee includes&#13;
a panchayat representative, parents of wards and they monitor the grant utilization, the assessment committee is&#13;
working well&#13;
&#13;
â&#128;&#147; Headmaster, Senior Secondary School, Dutt Nagar&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                     visited, together with patients checked, referrals,&#13;
                                                                     and injections administered. In early 2015, a super&#13;
                                                                     specialised health camp was organised in Gadej&#13;
                                                                     Panchayat, where about 800 persons availed this&#13;
                                                                     facility. In addition, about 50 dental camps have been&#13;
                                                                     organised to promote dental hygiene among the&#13;
                                                                     students and about 2500 students have benefited from&#13;
                                                                     these camps.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                     In 2013, as part of its corporate social responsibility,&#13;
                                                                     SJVNL has outsourced mobile health van operations&#13;
                                                                     for the NJHP and RHP to Help Age India, a specialized&#13;
                                                                     not-for-profit society which runs mobile Medicare units&#13;
                                                                     across the country. More than 10,000 persons have&#13;
                                                                     availed the services of mobile health van through Help&#13;
                                                                     Age India.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                     Scheme for infrastructure support to schools in&#13;
                                                                     project-affected areas: A key component of SJVNLâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
                                                                     strategy for social uplift is improvement and provision&#13;
                                                                     of infrastructure and aid to 49 schools - at primary,&#13;
surrounding villages. By December 2014, more than                    middle and senior secondary levels - in the project-&#13;
58,500 people had benefitted and 250 chronic patients                affected area. Each school was eligible for three&#13;
referred to the main hospital for timely treatment.                  grants:&#13;
&#13;
SJVNL took the initiative further and organized                      â&#128;¢	 Either Rs. 5,000 (~US$ 91) or Rs. 10,000 (~US$&#13;
health camps on themes such as sports, geriatric                        182) for students to carry out plantation work in the&#13;
health, dental and vision check-up, iodine deficiency,                  schoolâ&#128;&#153;s vicinity;&#13;
blood sugar, haemoglobin, thyroid and lipid profile.                 â&#128;¢	 Varying, according to the schoolâ&#128;&#153;s level,&#13;
Since 2007, more than 50 health camps have been                         between Rs. 75,000 (~US$ 1,363) and Rs.&#13;
organized, and SJVNL has kept records of places                         2,00,000 (~US$ 3,636) for student infrastructure,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
20&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                        Rampur Hydropower Project&#13;
                                                        Land Acquisition, Resettlement and Community Development Practices&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                          Additionally, school fee concession between 27-35&#13;
                                                          percent for all levels (from nursery till class XII) is&#13;
                                                          provided to children of project-affected families at&#13;
                                                          Delhi Public School in Jhakri on the same lines as the&#13;
                                                          children of SJVNL employees.&#13;
&#13;
                                                          SJVNL has developed comprehensive criteria and&#13;
                                                          procedures for the scheme: Schools must indicate&#13;
                                                          their requirements, including the number of students&#13;
                                                          enrolled before applying. A school management&#13;
                                                          committee consisting of representatives of the project,&#13;
                                                          district administration, education department and the&#13;
                                                          headmaster, monitors the functioning of the scheme,&#13;
                                                          using parameters such as utilization of the first grant,&#13;
                                                          requirements against estimates, progress of work, and&#13;
                                                          procurement of material from the second and third&#13;
                                                          grants. It finalizes the instalments to be released and&#13;
                                                          ensures compliance with stipulated terms. The head&#13;
                                                          of RHP, if satisfied with the assessment, approves the&#13;
                                                          proposed grants.&#13;
&#13;
   namely desks, chairs, library books, laboratory        SJVNLâ&#128;&#153;s contribution has been widely acknowledged,&#13;
   equipment, education aids such as blackboards          as schools in the project-affected area used the&#13;
   and whiteboards, slide projector, computers and        project grants to supplement state government funds&#13;
   peripherals, sports equipment, musical instruments     for critical infrastructure. Further, amounts between&#13;
   and additional classrooms, released after checking     Rs. 1000-4000 (~US$ 18-73) were awarded to the&#13;
   infrastructure provided by the government in order     best students in classes V, VIII, X and XII, thereby&#13;
   to avoid duplication; and                              ensuring that deserving students in the project-affected&#13;
â&#128;¢	 50 percent of the second grant for those schools       area continued studying and did not drop out due to&#13;
   who have successfully utilised the first grant.        economic reasons.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                       21&#13;
&amp;#12;Rampur Hydropower Project&#13;
Land Acquisition, Resettlement and Community Development Practices&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Support for technical education and apprenticeship                   operator, programming assistant, cutting and sewing&#13;
for youth: As the project-affected area was                          courses by:&#13;
underdeveloped, its youth had limited access to&#13;
technical education and professional exposure for                    â&#128;¢	   Providing training for one year in different trades at&#13;
employability. The cost of the education and the                          ITIs in the state;&#13;
preference to find suitable educational institution                  â&#128;¢	   Reimbursement of tuition and examination fees; and&#13;
locally (and not go away from home) and seek work                    â&#128;¢	   Monthly stipend of Rs. 700 (~US$ 13).&#13;
locally was also a deterrent. For the development of&#13;
families in the project-affected area, SJVNL designed                Candidates from project-affected families with&#13;
a scheme for class 10th pass youth to enter ITIs and                 qualifying grades had to apply to SJVNL through the&#13;
become self-reliant in trades such as electrician,                   panchayat. Since the scheme was launched in 2006,&#13;
machinist, motor mechanic and welder. Female                         SJVNL has sponsored 195 candidates including 31 (16&#13;
candidates were specially sponsored for computer                     percent) females. Of these, 174 (89 percent) including&#13;
                                                                     25 females have successfully completed their courses&#13;
                                                                     and the rest are expected to do so shortly. Of those&#13;
                                                                     who completed their courses, 96 (55 percent) were&#13;
                                                                     gainfully employed with contractors.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                     SJVNL also initiated a three-month skill upgrading&#13;
                                                                     program, through the Construction Industry&#13;
                                                                     Development Council, with a monthly stipend of Rs.&#13;
                                                                     1,500 (~US$ 27) across all its projects to enhance&#13;
                                                                     skills in the electrical and accountancy trades for&#13;
                                                                     unemployed youth to become gainfully employed or&#13;
                                                                     set up their own enterprises.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
22&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                             Rampur Hydropower Project&#13;
                                                             Land Acquisition, Resettlement and Community Development Practices&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
A merit scholarship scheme enabled students to&#13;
pursue higher education, minimized dropouts and&#13;
created a pool of candidates capable of contributing&#13;
to the project: These scholarships were given to&#13;
vocational trainees at ITIs, diploma aspirants in&#13;
engineering, pharmacy and computer skills and&#13;
degree students in engineering and medicine. So far,&#13;
89 candidates including 26 (29 percent) females have&#13;
received scholarships. For the current year (2015-16),&#13;
additional 23 students who topped classes in 8, 10&#13;
and 12th standards in the project affect villagers were&#13;
given scholarships.                                            Infrastructure under the Sustainable Community&#13;
                                                               Development Program. At the beginning of the&#13;
Support services for horticulture, agriculture and             project implementation, SJVNL developed a&#13;
veterinary skills: SJVNL organized training in                 Sustainable Community Development Program.&#13;
agriculture, horticulture and veterinary skills to provide     Under this program, local infrastructure facilities&#13;
local persons with technical knowhow for improving the         such as playgrounds, permanent paths and foot-&#13;
quality of fruits and crops, and the breed and health          bridges specified by the village communities, fencing&#13;
of cattle. About 450 people including 170 (38 percent)         and repair of small irrigation channels, regarded as&#13;
women received support through these camps.                    village lifelines, were created. The entity for which&#13;
Through community meetings, farmers were exhorted              infrastructure is created has the responsibility for&#13;
to attend eight camps supported by agriculture and             maintenance, while the panchayat monitors property&#13;
horticulture experts from the Himachal Pradesh                 renovation through ward members in duly constituted&#13;
University. Participants, including women, were                committees. The local communities consider the&#13;
provided farm implements such as pruning scissors              quality of infrastructure works executed by the RHP&#13;
and sickles, fertilizers, animal feed and high-yielding        superior to that of the state government departments.&#13;
varieties of seeds. Consequently, local communities&#13;
adopted better farm practices, tools and implements.           Corporate social responsibility (CSR): The&#13;
                                                               experiences gained over the last decade in the NJHP&#13;
Support to cultural property, fairs and festivals: SJVNL       and the RHP helped SJVNL formulate a Corporate&#13;
also helped preserve community cultural property with          Social Responsibility â&#128;&#147; Community Development&#13;
funds and technical support to fence temple structures,        (CSR-CD) policy, involving specialized agencies. It&#13;
install tiles, construct additional rooms, and develop         includes education, infrastructure and community&#13;
community welfare centres. Its participation in fairs and      development, provision of medical services, womenâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
festivals such as Kharga Mela, Mandwa, Thirshu Mela,           empowerment and creation of awareness among&#13;
Anni Mela and Boddhi Diwali Fair has created a sense           project-affected families. SJVNLâ&#128;&#153;s CSR budget is 0.5-2&#13;
of continued support for the community.                        percent of the net profit after tax and is apportioned&#13;
                                                               across all SJVNL projects, with bi-annual monitoring&#13;
Awareness camps: SJVNLâ&#128;&#153;s community outreach                    and external evaluation every five years.&#13;
has included awareness camps on HIV/AIDS and&#13;
the Right to Information (RTI) Act for migrants and            Under the CSR-CD policy, many activities have been&#13;
others labourers with construction contractors. About          undertaken in the RHP area such as construction&#13;
150 people including about 45 (30 percent) females             of DAV Senior Secondary School at Duttnagar;&#13;
participated in the RTI awareness workshops. In                construction of a rain shelter and post office at&#13;
addition, SJVNL also held two RTI camps for the                Bayal; construction of community hall in Bahwa&#13;
general population in the project area.                        and Duttnagar; construction of 303 toilets for boys&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                            23&#13;
&amp;#12;Rampur Hydropower Project&#13;
Land Acquisition, Resettlement and Community Development Practices&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
â&#128;&#156;Am from Chambu village, Bahwa panchayatâ&#128;¦ we are a small family with parents and a younger sister. My&#13;
family supported me in going out for trainingâ&#128;¦.did my training from ITI, Bilaspur 2010-11...learnt Microsoft Excel,&#13;
Dos, C++. I have joined RHP as computer operator apprentice this January. I get Rs. 6000 (~US$ 109) per&#13;
month. My previous job outside the area was on a shift basis, required 12-14 hours on an average and most of&#13;
the work was data entry in MS-Excel. Work here is better and with more variety and I will use my earnings to&#13;
study more.â&#128;&#157;&#13;
&#13;
â&#128;&#147; Bindubala, Apprentice, RHP, Batch 2012-13&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
and girls in Shimla, Lahaul and Kullu districts under                Overall Impact of the Project in&#13;
â&#128;&#156;Swachh Vidyalya Abhiyaanâ&#128;&#157;; study tours, installation                the Neighborhood&#13;
of benches, water coolers, toilets, fencing around                   The End-term impact evaluation revealed that the&#13;
temple structures, playgrounds, installation of dust                 project affected population has been exposed to&#13;
bins, sponsorship of technical education, provision of               variety of people due to influx of workers, significantly&#13;
meritorious scholarships, apprenticeships, camps on                  impacting their social, cultural and economic life. The&#13;
agriculture, horticulture and skill awareness.                       people have become greatly aware of the development&#13;
                                                                     scenario and now have a positive outlook towards&#13;
Apprentice Training: In 2012, SJVNL introduced a                     development interventions like R&amp;R activities. The&#13;
new CSR initiative, namely an apprenticeship (on-                    people now understand the importance of education&#13;
the-job) scheme. Under this scheme, technically                      for securing the future of their wards. More and&#13;
qualified youth in the project-affected area were given              more people now have commercial considerations&#13;
an opportunity to work for one year with RHP with                    in agricultural production, which in future, will help&#13;
a monthly stipend between Rs. 5,000-8,000 (~US$                      them in providing secure and sustainable livelihoods.&#13;
91 to 145). 57 candidates, including 8 (14 percent)                  The public opinion was quite favorable in respect&#13;
females have successfully completed the training.                    of facilities like provision of merit scholarships,&#13;
The candidates have been trained as electricians,                    improvement in conditions of schools, assistance to&#13;
fitters, mechanics, refrigeration mechanics, motor                   yuvak and mahila mandalas etc. The training and&#13;
mechanics, turners, welders, computer operators, etc.                awareness camps have been an effective tool for&#13;
Male apprentices at construction sites have gained                   capacity building of local people and also to make&#13;
experience and confidence and women have become                      them aware about new opportunities in income&#13;
empowered, some working as computer operators,                       generation or to improve upon the existing&#13;
using the experience gained, or saving to study further.             livelihood strategies.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
24&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                          Rampur Hydropower Project&#13;
                                                          Land Acquisition, Resettlement and Community Development Practices&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Gender Focus&#13;
Approach: SJVNL has demonstrated a strong                   and tailoring and 2 month beautician program which&#13;
willingness to empower women in the project-affected        have benefitted more than 50 women. More recently,&#13;
area. It has provided women with education, training,       the project organised additional skill imparting training&#13;
employment, health care and support at the domestic         to ladies in the area of computer and cutting /tailoring&#13;
level as follows:                                           training. In this about 50 people benefitted.&#13;
&#13;
(i) Training and employment related support:                Employment with RHP: Two out of four professional&#13;
                                                            staff (50 percent) working on community development&#13;
Sponsorship for technical education and                     and resettlement and rehabilitation aspects are&#13;
apprenticeship: SJVNL has sponsored 31 females              females and the head of the PIC is also a female.&#13;
(16 percent) in computer operating and programming          In addition, the project hired a female pharmacist&#13;
assistant, sewing and cutting trades, resulting in jobs     at Bayal dispensary under the resettlement and&#13;
for fourteen females. About 30 percent of 89 people         rehabilitation scheme.&#13;
who received scholarships were females. Similarly, 14&#13;
percent of 57 who received apprentice training were         (ii) Health care related support&#13;
females and 7 percent of 444 local people employed&#13;
by the contractors were females. In addition, the           Treatment by mobile health van (MHV) and the Bayal&#13;
project has also organized skill upgrading training         dispensary: Many female patients in the project-&#13;
programs exclusively for women in 2014 â&#128;&#147; This               affected areas have availed of treatment from both&#13;
includes a 3 month computer training, 3 month cutting       these facilities. The coverage of female patients by&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                         25&#13;
&amp;#12;Rampur Hydropower Project&#13;
Land Acquisition, Resettlement and Community Development Practices&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
â&#128;&#156;I reside in Nirmandâ&#128;¦ from a project-affected family. I have a diploma in pharmacy. Earlier I was working in&#13;
a government hospital for 1-1/2 years, later ran a drug store. I joined SJVNL under the project employment&#13;
provision for skilled project-affected families. Here I support Out Patient Department (OPD) activities, Mobile&#13;
Health Van (MHV) services, maintain a stock register, dressings for minor ailments, etc. Itâ&#128;&#153;s a pleasure to serve&#13;
my own peopleâ&#128;¦they are happy also to receive quality treatment and medicines in their village with MHV. The&#13;
job with RHP, Bayal dispensary has given me economic security as my husband has a job that is temporary.&#13;
He is teacher in a school at Kumarsein. In the drug store earlier, I was getting about Rs. 15,000 (US$ 273)&#13;
per month but now I earn Rs. 26,000 (US$ 473) per month. And as a staff member, the project has given me&#13;
accommodation in the Jhakri staff colony. My child is studying in DPS school. Things are definitely better now.â&#128;&#157;&#13;
&#13;
â&#128;&#147; Devkumari, Member of landless PAF working as pharmacist, Bayal dispensary&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
mobile health vans (51 percent) has been significantly               medical staff or government hospital. In addition, a kit&#13;
higher than those who received treatment at the                      valued at Rs. 1000 (~US$ 18), consisting of nutritional&#13;
dispensary (22 percent). About one-fourth of 6,200                   food, soaps and other items related to hygiene, was&#13;
who availed of the services of medical camps were                    provided besides counseling and guidance.&#13;
females.&#13;
                                                                     (iii) Household related support&#13;
SJVNL Silver Jubilee women and child care scheme:&#13;
In order to provide health care to women below poverty               Piped water supply and water tankers: In order&#13;
line (BPL) and their children during the ante-natal and              to improve water supply and avoid drinking water&#13;
post-natal period, the project has provided financial                shortage, SJVNL deployed water tankers to villages in&#13;
assistance of Rs. 5,000 (~US$ 91) to 25 women at                     the project-affected area. Subsequently, along with the&#13;
both pre- and post-delivery stages. It also enabled                  irrigation and public health departments, it provided&#13;
consultation at project cost in a primary health center              piped drinking water through energized tube wells&#13;
or other suitable place in coordination with the project             and also installed hand pumps. Piped water supply&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
26&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                     Rampur Hydropower Project&#13;
                                                                     Land Acquisition, Resettlement and Community Development Practices&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
is reported to be a major boon for women as it has&#13;
significantly reduced their burden of fetching water&#13;
from distant sources.&#13;
&#13;
Provision of toilet kits: To support the total sanitation&#13;
campaign, the project distributed toilet kits to 2,200&#13;
households in the project-affected area, to inculcate&#13;
the habit of cleanliness with the perceived benefits&#13;
of clean surroundings and there by bringing about&#13;
improvement in the health conditions. Women are&#13;
the main beneficiary because in absence of toilet&#13;
in their houses either they had to go to outside for&#13;
this purpose or stay till dark. The response of the&#13;
community was positive to this initiative.&#13;
&#13;
Provision of pressure cookers: To promote forest                       Camps for agriculture, horticulture and skill awareness:&#13;
conservation, SJVNL provided each project-affected                     Farm work is done mainly by women who have&#13;
family (139 families) with a five-liter pressure cooker to             attended SJVNL camps for improving skills, farm&#13;
reduce the use of fuel wood from nearby forests.                       practices and technologies.&#13;
&#13;
The key gender related information from the above described activities is summarised in Table 1 below:&#13;
Table 1: Gender disaggregated information&#13;
&#13;
 S. No. Indicator                                                                                 Male        Female           Total&#13;
    1      Number of affected landowners                                                            156             11           167&#13;
                                                                                                                (6.58)&#13;
    2      Vulnerable families assisted                                                              40           11**             51&#13;
                                                                                                               (21.57)&#13;
    3      Sponsorships for technical education                                                     164             31           195&#13;
                                                                                                              ( 15.89)&#13;
    4      Merit scholarships provided                                                               63             26             89&#13;
                                                                                                               (29.21)&#13;
    5      Number of people given apprentice training                                                49              8             57&#13;
                                                                                                               (14.00)&#13;
    6      Number of people employed by contractors                                                 413             31           444&#13;
                                                                                                                (6.98)&#13;
    7      Number of people who availed of mobile health van services                           23,431         24,636       48,067*&#13;
                                                                                                               (51.25)&#13;
    8      Number of people who attended medical camps                                           4,722           1,518         6,240&#13;
                                                                                                               (24.33)&#13;
    9      Number people who attended veterinary and horticulture camps                             276           169            445&#13;
                                                                                                               (37.98)&#13;
Note: Figures in parentheses indicate percentage share of females.&#13;
*excludes 8937 children; **Families headed by women.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                    27&#13;
&amp;#12;Rampur Hydropower Project&#13;
Land Acquisition, Resettlement and Community Development Practices&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Additional Welfare Measures to&#13;
Address Community Concerns&#13;
SJVNL also addressed other concerns that were                        Mitigation of impact on structures due to blasting:&#13;
raised by the community, namely:                                     Although SJVNL applied the latest available&#13;
                                                                     technology of underground blasting to minimize&#13;
Provision of construction grant to 10 project-affected               harmful effects on the surface; local persons&#13;
families at Bayal village: These families had lost their             expressed concerns that blasting caused cracks&#13;
structures but, since they had a second dwelling unit in             in their structures. While a study commissioned by&#13;
the affected panchayat area, they could not be certified             SJVNL concluded to the contrary, on the villagersâ&#128;&#153;&#13;
as houseless. Recognizing this as a loss that project-               insistence for monetary assistance to repair these&#13;
affected families could ill-afford, SJVNL adopted a                  cracks, SJVNL deposited Rs. 57.37 million (~US$&#13;
humanitarian approach by providing all project-affected              1.04 million) for payment as compensation to more&#13;
families with a construction grant of Rs.1,80,000                    than 5,700 families in the project-affected area, as&#13;
(~US$ 3,270) to upgrade their houses.                                recommended by a district committee.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
28&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                          Rampur Hydropower Project&#13;
                                                          Land Acquisition, Resettlement and Community Development Practices&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
â&#128;&#156;Farmers in our village (Bayal and Koyal) keep calling to inform me regarding the sprinkling of water for dust&#13;
suppression. We are in constant touch with the project engineer who immediately acts upon our intimationâ&#128;&#157;â&#128;¦&#13;
&#13;
â&#128;&#147; Pradhan, Gadej Panchayat&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Mitigation of impact on crops due to dust: Dust from        in execution by state Irrigation and Public Health (IPH)&#13;
construction reduced farm productivity and damaged          Department of the State Government.&#13;
crops which constitute the main livelihood source&#13;
in the area. To mitigate this, SJVNL deposited              Protection of cultural heritage and participation in&#13;
compensation with the district administration, to be        local fairs: SJVNL also extended assistance to the&#13;
disbursed to those affected. So far, Rs. 70.7 million       protection, preservation and encouragement of&#13;
(~US$ 1.28 million) has been deposited by SJVNL,            local culture and customs. Support to such activities&#13;
based on assessments provided by the district               from time to time helped in imbibing a sense of&#13;
administration, for release to the beneficiaries.           belongingness to the project amongst the local&#13;
                                                            persons. So far Rs 4.53 million (~US$ 0.08 million) has&#13;
However, to supplement the compensation, SJVNL              been provided by SJVNL under this initiative.&#13;
also took preventive measures with two water&#13;
tankers, carrying 5,000 liters in total, to make four       Post Commissioning Support: During the post&#13;
                                                            commissioning stage, the project affected families will&#13;
trips around the area and sprinkled 20,000 liters each&#13;
                                                            receive 100 units of electricity per month for 10 years&#13;
day, depending on the harvest and rainy season.&#13;
                                                            (in line with Hydro Policy of GoI) and the long term&#13;
Village communities monitor this initiative, informing&#13;
                                                            residents in the affected villagers will receive annuity&#13;
the panchayat Pradhan of shortfalls, which the project&#13;
                                                            payment out of revenue generated out of sale of 1&#13;
automatically rectifies. SJVNL spent around Rs. 21.2&#13;
                                                            percent free power provided to the State Government&#13;
million (~US$ 0.39 million) under this initiative.&#13;
                                                            by project entity during life of the project. The detailed&#13;
                                                            implementation arrangements for the same are being&#13;
The Project has also contributed Rs. 55.3 million           worked out by SJVNL with the State Government. Thus,&#13;
(~US$ 1 million) to state government for augmentation       there are sustainable efforts from the project entity and&#13;
of water supply scheme which caters the needs of the        the State Government to support the project affected&#13;
eight project affected panchayats. This scheme is still     and local people beyond the project implementation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
â&#128;&#156;Though these water sprinkling trucks are paid by us i.e. by the project, village communities, through the&#13;
Pradhan, monitor the daily sprinkling. Often during the farming season we get calls to operate them even late in&#13;
the evening or night and we do so...â&#128;&#157;&#13;
&#13;
â&#128;&#147; Project Engineer, RHP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                         29&#13;
&amp;#12;Rampur Hydropower Project&#13;
Land Acquisition, Resettlement and Community Development Practices&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Implementation Practices in SJVNLâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
Nathpa Jhakri Hydroelectric Project14&#13;
The Nathpa Jhakri Hydroelectric Project (NJHP) is                       innovative measures during later part of the project&#13;
the first hydropower project constructed by SJVNL                       implementation and the same are being continued&#13;
while Rampur Hydropower Project is the second                           post commissioning of the project also under the&#13;
hydropower project to be constructed by SJVNL.                          community development fund that has been set up by&#13;
NJHP is a 1500 MW run of the river project located                      SJVNL for the project area.&#13;
on River Sutlej, in Shimla district of Himachal&#13;
Pradesh. A Memorandum of Understanding for                              Special package for landless project-affected families:&#13;
execution of the project was signed between GoI                         SJVNL acquired 224 hectares of private land from 480&#13;
and Government of Himachal Pradesh in July                              families, rendering 62 families landless - landholding&#13;
1991. The World Bank had provided financing                             of less than 5 bighas (0.3760 ha) post-acquisition. The&#13;
for the construction of the project in March 1989.                      district administration found that the actual number&#13;
The project was commissioned in May 2004. To                            of landless project-affected families had increased&#13;
respond to the demands and expectations of the                          from 62 to 120, of which 61 families had already been&#13;
local people, SJVNL has implemented the following                       provided employment with the project.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
14&#13;
     SJVNL was known as Nathpa Jhakri Power Corporation (NJPC) at the time of construction of this project.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
30&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                                                       Rampur Hydropower Project&#13;
                                                                       Land Acquisition, Resettlement and Community Development Practices&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Since SJVNL was a single project organization (at                         â&#128;¢	   permanent houses replaced temporary structures&#13;
that time) with limited employment potential, this led to                      in a small yet developed colony;&#13;
litigation seeking enhancement of compensation and                        â&#128;¢	   full-fledged medical facility set up;&#13;
provision of employment. Thus, SJVNL proposed a                           â&#128;¢	   provision of electricity, including street lighting,&#13;
special assistance package for economic rehabilitation                         internal approach paths, sewerage and drainage;&#13;
of the remaining 59 landless project-affected families,                   â&#128;¢	   free piped water supply; and&#13;
which comprised a lump-sum between Rs. 0.20 million                       â&#128;¢	   resettled families own assets such as refrigerator,&#13;
(~US$ 3,63615) to Rs. 0.30 million (US$ 5,454) as an                           television, gas stove, and mobile phone.&#13;
income enhancement measure, while retaining their&#13;
entitlement for employment with the NJHP, whenever                        Community Development Activities. During the&#13;
vacancies arose. So far 55 project-affected families                      implementation of this project, SJVNL implemented&#13;
have opted for this special package and have utilized                     a number of measures for the benefit of the local&#13;
the amount for income generation.                                         communities. Some of those activities includes (i)&#13;
                                                                          running of uninterrupted mobile health van since&#13;
Resettlement colony at NJHP: For resettlement,                            January 2000, to promote health and hygiene&#13;
SJVNL offered displaced families two choices:                             awareness and provide treatment16; (ii) financial&#13;
â&#128;¢	 self-relocation with a grant to construct a house up                   support of Rs. 80 million (~US$ 1.45 million) for the&#13;
   to 45 sq. m.; or                                                       construction of 200 bed hospital in Rampur which is&#13;
â&#128;¢	 shift to a house of 45 sq. m. at the Jhakri                            now serving as an important referral hospital in the&#13;
   Resettlement Colony.                                                   region; (iii) providing merit scholarships for pursuing&#13;
                                                                          higher and professional courses; (iv) support to welfare&#13;
The project developed a resettlement colony of 25                         programs such as awareness camps to the villagers&#13;
units with two bedrooms, attached bathroom, toilet and                    in agricultural, horticultural and veterinary practices&#13;
kitchen, each unit costing approximately Rs. 0.5 million                  through local universities, grants to Mahila Mandals,&#13;
(~US$ 9,090). Twenty-three families belonging to the                      support for drinking water facilities, etc.&#13;
same village, Jhakri, continued to live close to their&#13;
original habitation and acknowledged the contribution                     Community Development Fund: Based on the&#13;
of the project in improving their overall living standards                experience gained in the implementation of small&#13;
with the following outcomes:                                              infrastructure facilities and other welfare program&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
We had about 3-5 bighas of balance land. Earlier.. we had a small temporary structure. This house in the&#13;
Resettlement Colony is much better. .yes, internal paths, street lighting, piped water supply â&#128;&#147; this was not&#13;
there. Water is free, good quality. Maintainence is not a problem. We phone if there is a need. We pay Rs. 700&#13;
(~US$ 13) for electricity; doctor, medicine is also nearby. Also males in our family are working with the project or&#13;
contractors.&#13;
&#13;
â&#128;&#147; Kamla Devi and Sarvati Devi, Residents, Jhakri Resettlement Colony&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
15&#13;
   Exchange rate used is US$ 1 = Rs. 55, while the actual figures in US$ will be higher.&#13;
16&#13;
   Given the location of project in an underdeveloped area with limited availability of good quality medical facilities, SJVNL commissioned its&#13;
first mobile health van in 2000 which: (i) visited affected villages four days a week and provided consultation and medicines; (ii) organized&#13;
medical camps at schools and villages; (iii) afforded easy access and extra diagnostic facilities and free medicines for residents; and (iv)&#13;
helped improve health status and awareness of preventive practices for common ailments.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                             31&#13;
&amp;#12;Rampur Hydropower Project&#13;
Land Acquisition, Resettlement and Community Development Practices&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
during the project implementation, SJVNL set                         Development Fund has supported: (i) infrastructure&#13;
up a Community Development Fund in 2003 to                           such as school building, playground, village paths,&#13;
make available a dedicated fund for infrastructure                   community buildings; (ii) scholarship scheme to&#13;
development in the neighbouring villages. The SJVNL                  children of project-affected families pursuing vocational&#13;
management approved the setting up of this fund in                   and professional courses and fee concession to&#13;
2003 with an annual budget of Rs. 15 million (~US$                   children of project-affected families in the project&#13;
0.27 million) per year. Out of this, Rs. 10 million                  school, namely Delhi Public School (DPS) Jhakri; (iii)&#13;
(~US$ 0.18 million) is earmarked for infrastructure                  infrastructure aids and facilities to schools; (iv) mobile&#13;
works in the affected villages and the balance Rs 5                  health vans and health camps; (v) agriculture and&#13;
million (~US$ 0.9 million) is earmarked for welfare                  horticulture camps; (vi) apprenticeship schemes for&#13;
activities such as health services, merit scholarships,              youth; (vii) water supply schemes; and (viii) sports and&#13;
sports, drinking water, etc. Since then the Community                cultural activities.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
32&#13;
&amp;#12;View of Intake (Top) and Power House (Bottom) of Rampur Hydropower Project&#13;
&amp;#12;&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="25475923">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2015/11/25475923/rampur-hydropower-project-land-acquisition-resettlement-community-development-practices
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2015/11/25475923/rampur-hydropower-project-land-acquisition-resettlement-community-development-practices</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2015/11/25475923/rampur-hydropower-project-land-acquisition-resettlement-community-development-practices</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2015-11-18T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2015-11-19T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <docm_id>090224b0831e8f1d</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b0831e8f1d</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2015/11/19/090224b0831e8f1d/1_0/Rendered/INDEX/Rampur0Hydropo0evelopment0practices.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2015/11/19/090224b0831e8f1d/1_0/Rendered/PDF/Rampur0Hydropo0evelopment0practices.pdf</pdfurl>
        <loan_no>48700</loan_no>
        <docdt>2015-10-01T00:46:04Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2015-11-19T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Rampur Hydropower Project : land
            acquisition, resettlement, and community development practices
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            SJVN Limited (SJVNL), a mini ratna1
            public sector undertaking of the Government of India (GoI),
            implemented the World Bank funded 412 megawatt (MW)
            run-of-the-river hydro power project at Rampur in Himachal
            Pradesh, immediately downstream of and in cascade operation
            with the 1500 MW Nathpa Jhakri Hydroelectric Project (NJHP).
            The project-affected area covered eight panchayats. Lessons
            learnt by SJVNL during its first project at Nathpa Jakhri
            were utilized to formulate better implementation practices
            regarding land acquisition, resettlement, and community
            development in the Rampur project. The land acquisition and
            resettlement plan were fully implemented by the time of
            closure of the World Bank loan in December 2014 in
            accordance with the provisions of the framework adopted for
            the project. The end-term impact evaluation undertaken for
            the project confirmed that the project affected families
            have an overall improved living standard, proportion of
            workers in regular employment, average income, earning
            capacity and diversification of income have increased, and
            housing standards have improved.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Rampur Hydropower Project : land
            acquisition, resettlement, and community development practices
        </docna>
        <display_title>Rampur Hydropower Project : land
            acquisition, resettlement, and community development practices</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2015/10/25475923/rampur-hydropower-project-land-acquisition-resettlement-community-development-practices</listing_relative_url>
        <count>India</count>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <sectr>Energy and mining</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            assessments, communities, loan repayment,
            land transactions, villages, workers, state government,
            resettlement, environmental impact assessment, fairs,
            shelter, participation, income, buildings, gender, repair,
            renovation, environmental impacts, reports, hygiene,
            services, occupation, sewage, health care, household,
            housing, maintenance, neighborhood, property, agricultural
            land, youth, bedrooms, health, capacity building,
            measurement, projects, project, market, ownership,
            workshops, land acquisition, cremation, contractors, roads,
            public health, street lighting, land, landowners, children,
            community development, females, public information,
            training, private land, construction industry, households,
            patients, patient, dwelling, offices, rent, contracts,
            bridges, construction, housing standards, revenue,
            facilities, village communities, nurses, building, houses,
            investments, interventions, community, strategy, pollution,
            engineer, fees, families, medicines, developers,
            enterprises, housing conditions, migrants, female, health
            services, implementation, library, districts, cleanliness,
            finance, grants, design
        </keywd>
        <lndinstr>
            Specific Investment Loan
        </lndinstr>
        <majtheme>Financial and private sector development,Environment and natural resource management</majtheme>
        <projn>IN-Rampur Hydropower Project -- P095114</projn>
        <topic>Hydropower Law and Regulation m1327325 1871,Hydroelectric Power Law and Regulation
            m1326599 1035,Hydropower Technologies m1327559 1988,Hydropower m1327326 527,Storage Hydropower m1326849 1989</topic>
        <docty>Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>Urban Housing,Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation,Urban Governance and Management,Municipal Housing and Land,Housing &amp; Human Habitats</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Communities and Human Settlements,Urban Development,Health, Nutrition and Population</teratopic>
        <authors>
            <author>Reddy,I. U. B.</author>
            <author>Mittal,Rohit</author>
            <author>Gaba,Kwawu Mensan</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>090224b0831e8f1d_1_0</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!517191</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>South Asia!$!517212</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Asia!$!517198</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <admreg>South Asia,South Asia</admreg>
        <subsc>Hydropower</subsc>
        <theme>Infrastructure services for private sector development,Climate change</theme>
        <historic_topic>Communities and Human Settlements,Urban Development,Health, Nutrition and Population</historic_topic>
        <prdln>IBRD/IDA</prdln>
        <topicv3>Hydropower Law and Regulation m1327325 1871,Hydroelectric Power Law and Regulation
            m1326599 1035,Hydropower Technologies m1327559 1988,Hydropower m1327326 527,Storage Hydropower m1326849 1989</topicv3>
        <owner>Energy GP SAR (GEE06)</owner>
        <trustfund>TF096743-Good Environment Practices in
            Hydropower Projects,TF097109-Good Environment Practices in
            Hydropower Projects</trustfund>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>South Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Asia</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>101039</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutritional supplements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Vitamins</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wastewater Collection and Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Impact Evaluations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Randomized Control Trials</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crops</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Basic Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>On-site Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Marketing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Hydro Power</ml:concept><ml:concept>Hydroelectric Power</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Housing and Land</ml:concept><ml:concept>Housing and Planning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Housing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Land</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Land Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Boundaries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Impact Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supplements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sewerage</ml:concept><ml:concept>Scholarships</ml:concept><ml:concept>Impact Assessment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forests</ml:concept><ml:concept>Youth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Apprenticeship</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Hydropower</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Land Supply and Markets</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>India</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Southern Asia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>