<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>                                                                        101098&#13;
 November 2015&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
WITHDRAWAL FROM&#13;
CORRESPONDENT&#13;
BANKING&#13;
WHERE, WHY, AND WHAT TO DO&#13;
ABOUT IT&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking; Where, Why, and What to Do About It&#13;
November 2015&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Acknowledgments&#13;
&#13;
This report was prepared by the Finance and Markets Global Practice of the World Bank Group.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Â© 2015 International Bank for Reconstruction and Development / The World Bank Group&#13;
1818 H Street NW&#13;
Washington DC 20433&#13;
Telephone: 202-473-1000&#13;
Internet: www.worldbank.org&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
This work is a product of the staff of The World Bank Group. The findings, interpretations, and&#13;
conclusions expressed in this work do not necessarily reflect the views of The World Bank Group, its&#13;
Board of Executive Directors, or the governments they represent.&#13;
&#13;
The World Bank Group does not guarantee the accuracy of the data included in this work. The&#13;
boundaries, colors, denominations, and other information shown on any map in this work do not imply&#13;
any judgment on the part of The World Bank Group concerning the legal status of any territory or the&#13;
endorsement or acceptance of such boundaries.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Rights and Permissions&#13;
The material in this work is subject to copyright. Because The World Bank Group encourages&#13;
dissemination of its knowledge, this work may be reproduced, in whole or in part, for non-commercial&#13;
purposes as long as full attribution to this work is given.&#13;
&#13;
Any queries on rights and licenses, including subsidiary rights, should be addressed to the:&#13;
Office of the Publisher, The World Bank Group, 1818 H Street NW, Washington, DC 20433, USA;&#13;
fax: 202-522-2422; e-mail: pubrights@worldbank.org.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                        Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Table of Contents&#13;
Executive Summary .................................................................................................................................. 5&#13;
I.        Introduction ....................................................................................................................................... 9&#13;
II.             Method ......................................................................................................................................... 11&#13;
III.            Participation ................................................................................................................................ 12&#13;
IV.             Substantive Findings .................................................................................................................... 13&#13;
     a.         Overall Trend in Correspondent Banking Relationships .......................................................................... 13&#13;
          I.       Banking Authorities.............................................................................................................................. 13&#13;
          II.      Large international banks ..................................................................................................................... 17&#13;
          III. Local/regional banks ............................................................................................................................ 21&#13;
     b.         Effect on Products and Services ............................................................................................................... 23&#13;
          I.       Banking authorities............................................................................................................................... 23&#13;
          II.      Large International Banks .................................................................................................................... 24&#13;
          III. Local/Regional banks ........................................................................................................................... 26&#13;
     c.         Client segments most significantly affected by the decline of foreign CBRs ........................................... 26&#13;
          I.       Banking Authorities.............................................................................................................................. 26&#13;
          II.      Local/Regional Banks .......................................................................................................................... 27&#13;
     d.         Possible causes of decline in foreign CBRs .............................................................................................. 28&#13;
          I.       Banking authorities............................................................................................................................... 29&#13;
          II.      Large international banks ..................................................................................................................... 32&#13;
          III. Local/regional banks ............................................................................................................................ 35&#13;
     e.         Finding replacements/alternative arrangements........................................................................................ 36&#13;
     f.         Diligence on the customerâ&#128;&#153;s customers (so called KYCC) and Nested Accounts .................................... 37&#13;
V.        Conclusions and Recommendations ................................................................................................. 40&#13;
     Annex 1: Method followed .............................................................................................................................. 46&#13;
     Annex 2: Participating Banking Authorities ..................................................................................................... 47&#13;
     Annex 3: Banking Authorities- Regional breakdown ....................................................................................... 48&#13;
     Annex 4: Local/ Regional Banks - Outreach/ Completed Surveys ................................................................... 51&#13;
     Annex 5: Banking Authorities - Jurisdictions of terminations/restrictions....................................................... 52&#13;
     Annex 6: Local/Regional Banks: List of Jurisdictions â&#128;&#147; Termination and restrictions of CBRs ..................... 53&#13;
     Annex 7: Banking Authorities â&#128;&#147; Causes/ Drivers of termination/restriction of foreign CBRs......................... 57&#13;
     Annex 8: Local/Regional Banks â&#128;&#147; Causes/ Drivers of termination/restriction of foreign CBRs ..................... 58&#13;
     Annex 9: Large International Banks â&#128;&#147; Products/services affected ................................................................... 59&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                            Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Annex 10: Client Segment Impact .................................................................................................................... 60&#13;
Annex 11: Recommendations included in Consultative Report Correspondent Banking published by the&#13;
CPMI................................................................................................................................................................. 62&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                      Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                                  5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                          Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
                                 Where, Why and What to Do about It&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        Executive Summary&#13;
&#13;
   1. Background&#13;
&#13;
ES.1. Correspondent banking services are essential to enabling companies and individuals to transact&#13;
internationally and make cross-border payments. Recently there have been indications that certain large&#13;
international banks have started terminating or severely limiting their correspondent banking&#13;
relationships with smaller local and regional banks from jurisdictions around the world. To find out&#13;
whether this is indeed happening, the World Bank, with support from the Financial Stability Board&#13;
(FSB) and the Committee on Payments and Market Infrastructures (CPMI), surveyed banking&#13;
authorities and banks worldwide to examine the extent of withdrawal from correspondent banking, its&#13;
drivers, and its implications for financial exclusion/inclusion. In total, 110 banking authorities, 20 large&#13;
banks, and 170 smaller local and regional banks participated in this exercise.&#13;
ES.2. This is not a comprehensive, quantitative survey that presents an exhaustive overview of the&#13;
status of correspondent banking globally in 2015. While significant â&#128;&#147; and heterogeneous â&#128;&#147; economic&#13;
effects may result from the withdrawal of CBR, a quantitative discussion of those effects was outside&#13;
the scope of this report. It addresses national and international AML/CFT policy makers, and those&#13;
involved in implementing AML/CFT in banks and remittance service providers.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   2. Findings&#13;
&#13;
ES.3. Roughly half the banking authorities surveyed and slightly more local/regional banks indicated&#13;
they were experiencing a decline in correspondent banking relationships (CBRs). For large&#13;
international banks the figures are significantly higher at 75 percent. The Caribbean seems to be the&#13;
region most severely affected.&#13;
ES.4. The products and services identified as being most affected by the withdrawal of correspondent&#13;
banking are: (check) clearing and settlement, cash management services, international wire transfers&#13;
and, for banking authorities and local/regional banks, trade finance. The ability to conduct foreign&#13;
currency denominated capital or current account transactions in US dollars (USD) has been most&#13;
significantly affected followed by Euro, pound sterling (GBP), and Canadian dollar (CAD)&#13;
denominated transactions. A large majority of respondent banking authorities indicated that money&#13;
transfer operators and other remittance companies are most affected, followed by small and medium&#13;
domestic banks and small and medium exporters. They also specified other types of clients/client&#13;
segments that have been affected, including retail customers, international business companies, and e-&#13;
gaming/gambling.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                          Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                                 6&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ES.5. Though there was some misunderstanding of the question, information from banking authorities&#13;
and large banks on the obligation to conduct due diligence on the customerâ&#128;&#153;s customer (so-called â&#128;&#156;know&#13;
your customerâ&#128;&#153;s customerâ&#128;&#157; or â&#128;&#156;KYCCâ&#128;&#157;- in this case the customer of the respondent bank) - showed&#13;
that large banks do not consider themselves to be under an explicit legal KYCC obligation, but believe&#13;
that under certain circumstances a risk based approach might require them to conduct it anyway.&#13;
Uncertainty regarding regulatory obligations or expectations leads them to err on the side of caution.&#13;
ES.6. The ability of financial institutions in affected jurisdictions to find alternative correspondent&#13;
banks varied, but the majority indicated they were able so far to find replacements. Sometimes however,&#13;
the time and cost involved in finding alternative channels are significant and the terms and conditions&#13;
were not comparable to the previous foreign CBRs, with some noting a substantial increase in pricing.&#13;
It is unclear whether the withdrawal of correspondent banking services has resulted in banks largely&#13;
finding alternatives in so-called nested accounts - but certain authorities expressed concerns about that.&#13;
ES.7. The drivers of the decline in foreign CBRs can be divided into two groups: one category of&#13;
causes that are more business related, explaining the decision to terminate a foreign CBR in purely&#13;
economic terms, and one more regulatory and risk related, explaining the decision to sever ties with&#13;
certain actors as based on the level of Money Laundering/Financing of Terrorism (ML/FT) risk of the&#13;
counterpart deemed unmanageable, concerns that one might fall foul of AML/CFT,&#13;
international/regional sanctionsâ&#128;&#148;or other legislation or regulations. The two drivers are related though,&#13;
since higher risk can result in greater cost. While local/regional banks put more of an emphasis on the&#13;
economic/business rationale for the decline, banking authorities and large banks emphasized both&#13;
regulatory AML/CFT and business-related concerns.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   3. Conclusions and recommendations&#13;
&#13;
ES.8. The concern is that while large banks might be cleaning up their books and terminating&#13;
relationships with higher risk customers, the system as a whole ends up as it were pushing that risk to&#13;
channels that are less transparent, or excluding legitimate customers, and thus actually increasing&#13;
overall risk. The extent that this might actually be taking place is unclear and was not within the scope&#13;
of the current project.&#13;
ES.9. The withdrawal from foreign CBRs is a complex and manifold phenomenon. Some of the&#13;
drivers are not susceptible to policy tweaks. A bank is completely justified not doing business because&#13;
of business rationale, compliance costs, or excessive risk. There are risks that should not be taken.&#13;
ES.10. The issue to consider is whether in other casesâ&#128;&#148;particularly where applicable rules or facts and&#13;
circumstances are unclearâ&#128;&#148;but there is in principle a business and risk-related rationale for&#13;
engagement, there is something that authorities or the banks themselves could do to encourage the&#13;
establishment of a correspondent banking relationship. It is important to emphasize that this is a joint&#13;
public-private responsibility that needs to be dealt with in partnership. Only such an approach, with&#13;
efforts by all actors, can help reverse the decline experienced in certain parts of the world. We believe&#13;
the following actions could be useful.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                          Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                                 7&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
             a. Supervisors should ensure banks follow a risk-based approach&#13;
ES.11. An unequivocal statement from national supervisors that there will not be a zero tolerance&#13;
approach for failures to detect money laundering and setting out the tenets for a reasonable risk&#13;
assessment (to the extent supervisors have not already done so) for establishing correspondent banking&#13;
relationships can provide banks with the comfort they say they are lacking at this moment. This also&#13;
implies that the standard setter and the national AML/CFT policy makers clarify the acceptable level&#13;
of risk tolerance.&#13;
            b. Supervisors and other authorities should ensure the effective implementation of&#13;
                international AML/CFT standards&#13;
ES.12. Concerns about the effective implementation of AML/CFT obligations by countries and&#13;
jurisdictions featured prominently among the reasons large banks are withdrawing from correspondent&#13;
banking relationshipsâ&#128;&#148;despite significant on-going work by many countries to improve their&#13;
AML/CFT regimes. All jurisdictions must therefore ensure that the legal and regulatory AML/CFT&#13;
framework is in place and that their financial institutions are being effectively supervised for risk-based&#13;
compliance with those obligations. The World Bank stands ready to assist them. In addition, supervisors&#13;
should coordinate to clarify regulatory expectations and facilitate international exchange of&#13;
information.&#13;
ES.13. Respondent banks seeking to establish or maintain correspondent banking relationships should&#13;
improve their AML/CFT internal controls to reduce their risk profile.&#13;
            c. Supervisors should provide clarity on the extent of obligations to conduct due&#13;
                 diligence on the customers of the respondent banks&#13;
ES.14. Along those same lines, supervisors should provide detailed guidance on the extent to which,&#13;
or the circumstances under which, banks should conduct due diligence on the customers of a respondent&#13;
bank, the so-called â&#128;&#156;know-your-customerâ&#128;&#153;s-customerâ&#128;&#157; obligation. In other words, supervisors should&#13;
set out under what conditions it is incumbent upon a correspondent bank to go beyond conducting due&#13;
diligence on the respondent bank. If the supervisor does not consider KYCC ever to apply to its&#13;
institutions, then it should say so clearly- leaving no room for misinterpretation or misunderstanding.&#13;
           d. Improve the information position of correspondent banks&#13;
ES.15. Banks should use technical tools, notably KYC utilities, to limit information challenges as an&#13;
effective means to reduce the burden of compliance with KYC procedures and consider the use of the&#13;
Legal Entity Identifier for all banks involved in correspondent banking as recommended in a CPMI&#13;
report published for consultation on October 6, 2015.&#13;
ES.16. When establishing a relationship, a correspondent should consider gathering information from&#13;
the supervisor of a prospective respondent. To assist a correspondent bank in understanding country&#13;
risk context it is recommended that countries publish their national risk assessment in order to&#13;
demonstrate their commitment to AML/CFT and to inform outsiders of the risks they face and how&#13;
they intend to address them. The World Bank has developed a capacity-building tool for conducting a&#13;
national risk assessment and stands ready to assist countries in this process.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                          Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                               8&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
           e. Correspondent banks should consider respondentâ&#128;&#153;s interests when deciding to&#13;
              terminate a foreign CBR&#13;
&#13;
ES.17. Large banks should consider placing limits or trial periods instead of terminating relationships,&#13;
or give a longer notice period. Correspondent banks should consider placing appropriate credit and&#13;
other limits/conditions on their client banks, rather than terminating the relationships. They may also&#13;
consider trial periods. Even when banks have an existing correspondent banking relationship to which&#13;
they can shift their business, banks need time to arrange for an increase in credit and the amount of&#13;
transactions and such that the existing CBR is able and willing to provide. Therefore correspondent&#13;
banks are encouraged to extend their notice period to at least three monthsâ&#128;&#148;preferably more, and could&#13;
during that period use some of the risk management tools described below.&#13;
&#13;
ES.18. Correspondent banks should be transparent on their reason for terminating a relationship. The&#13;
reasons for termination of a correspondent banking relationship are not always made clear to respondent&#13;
banks, making it hard for them to understand the underlying reasons and how to improve the situation.&#13;
If correspondent banks are more transparent about the reasons for terminating a correspondent banking&#13;
relationship, this will help smaller banks address possible concerns on AML/CFT issues if that was&#13;
among the basis for terminating the relationship.&#13;
            f. Authorities should monitor the status of correspondent banking in their&#13;
                jurisdiction&#13;
ES.19. Finally, it would improve the overall ability of governments and private actors to take action if&#13;
jurisdictions were to more systematically gather information on the status of foreign CBRs. The surveys&#13;
overall met with a positive response but not all jurisdictions responded, and among the respondents, a&#13;
not insignificant number indicated that they lacked systematic data to complete the survey. Authorities&#13;
and financial institutions that do not already do so, should consider taking a proactive approach in&#13;
communicating with one another to monitor foreign CBR related developments in their own jurisdiction&#13;
and jurisdictions of their CBR counterparts, as well as developments at the regional and global levels.&#13;
This holds especially true for smaller jurisdictions, with fewer and smaller institutions, which appear&#13;
to be most susceptible to trends in CBRs.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                          Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                                           9&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        I.    Introduction&#13;
1.      The international payment system relies heavily on foreign correspondent banking. Generally&#13;
speaking correspondent banking is about the payment services provided by one bank to another bank.&#13;
The Committee on Payment and Market Infrastructures (CPMI) refers to correspondent banking as â&#128;&#156;an&#13;
arrangement under which one bank (correspondent) holds deposits owned by other banks (respondents)&#13;
and provides payment and other services to those respondent banks.â&#128;&#157;1 More specifically, the Wolfsberg&#13;
group of banks defines correspondent banking as â&#128;&#156;the provision of a current or other liability account,&#13;
and related services, to another financial institution, including affiliates, used for the execution of third&#13;
party payments and trade finance, as well as its own cash clearing, liquidity management and short-&#13;
term borrowing or investment needs in a particular currency.â&#128;&#157;2&#13;
2.      For some time now, stories and anecdotes have been circulating in media and international&#13;
policy fora that large international banks (predominantly US/Europe/Canada based) are terminating or&#13;
severely limiting their correspondent banking relationships with smaller local/regional banks from&#13;
jurisdictions around the world. Smaller banks are particularly dependent on such relationships to be&#13;
able to offer payment and clearing services in foreign currencies (i.e. USD/EUR/GBP/CAD). This&#13;
development is considered by many to be part of an apparent â&#128;&#156;de-riskingâ&#128;&#157; trend, according to which&#13;
financial institutions are limiting their exposure to the perceived risk posed certain classes of customers&#13;
or partners.&#13;
3.      The â&#128;&#156;riskâ&#128;&#157; in â&#128;&#156;de-riskingâ&#128;&#157; is usually used in reference to the concern that the customer or partner&#13;
could pose a higher than average risk for money laundering or terrorism financing, or that processing&#13;
transactions for them might entail a breach of sanctions regulations. However, it is not always evident&#13;
that the withdrawal from correspondent banking is driven by risk-related concernsâ&#128;&#148;and therefore&#13;
whether â&#128;&#156;de-riskingâ&#128;&#157; is the most suitable term to describe it.&#13;
4.     The Financial Action Task Force (FATF), the international standard setter on anti-money&#13;
laundering, defines de-risking as: â&#128;&#156;the phenomenon of financial institutions terminating or restricting&#13;
business relationships with clients or categories of clients to avoid, rather than manage, risk (â&#128;¦). De -&#13;
risking can be the result of various drivers, such as concerns about profitability, prudential&#13;
requirements, anxiety after the global financial crisis, and reputational risk.â&#128;&#157;3&#13;
5.       In order to explore the basis for these stories and provide concrete evidence of the withdrawal&#13;
from correspondent banking services and the factors driving it, the Financial Stability Board (FSB) in&#13;
March 2015 asked the World Bank â&#128;&#156;to examine the extent of withdrawal from correspondent banking&#13;
and its implications for financial exclusion/inclusion.â&#128;&#157; This report is the result of that examination, and&#13;
attempts to provide some clarity on the extent of the withdrawal from correspondent banking services,&#13;
the services particularly affected and the possible knock-on effect for the clients of the banks whose&#13;
relationships are being terminated or restricted, and the reasons for its occurrence.&#13;
6.    As implied in the FSB request, the crucial question is also to determine whether the final&#13;
outcome of the withdrawal from correspondent banking services, leaves certain categories of legitimate&#13;
&#13;
1.   See â&#128;&#156;A glossary of terms used in payments and settlement systemsâ&#128;&#157;, p16, available at&#13;
     http://www.bis.org/cpmi/glossary_030301.pdf.&#13;
2.   See â&#128;&#156;Wolfsberg Anti-Money Laundering Principles for Correspondent Bankingâ&#128;&#157; p1 available at http://www.wolfsberg-&#13;
     principles.com/pdf/home/Wolfsberg-Correspondent-Banking-Principles-2014.pdf. Italics added for emphasis.&#13;
3.   See â&#128;&#156;FATF clarifies risk-based approach: case by case, not wholesale de-riskingâ&#128;&#157; available at http://www.fatf-&#13;
     gafi.org/publications/fatfgeneral/documents/rba-and-de-risking.html.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                               10&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
customersâ&#128;&#148;whether defined by reference to the sector in which they are active or the geographic area&#13;
where they are basedâ&#128;&#148;without access to financial services. Access to finance per se is not the only&#13;
concern. One also needs to consider the cost of maintaining access and the transparency of the financial&#13;
flows involved: e.g. if a big international bank A terminates its relationship with a small regional bank&#13;
B, but B subsequently establishes another relationship, is there a risk that the scrutiny of the funds&#13;
handled by B will be lower because the institution willing to do business with B applies lower&#13;
standardsâ&#128;&#148;or because the institution that ultimately processes payments for B is not aware that B is its&#13;
ultimate customer? This is where the problem of so-called nested accounts arises. In addition there may&#13;
be an increase in cost due to lack of competition and a concentration of providers.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                          Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                                                                    11&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       II.        Method&#13;
7.     The main data gathering for this report took place from April through October 2015. The data&#13;
and information are drawn primarily from three sources:&#13;
                 ï&#130;·      Surveys conducted under the auspices of the FSB, CPMI and the World Bank Group of&#13;
                        banking authorities; large international banks; and local/regional banks;&#13;
                 ï&#130;·      High level fora with top officials of central banks and other banking authorities and&#13;
                        representatives of large international and local/regional banks; and&#13;
                 ï&#130;·      Follow-up discussions by the project team with authorities and banks.&#13;
The timeline for the project is provided in the Figure 1. A detailed description of the method followed&#13;
is contained in Annex 1.&#13;
Figure 1: Timeline of Data Gathering (2015)&#13;
        April&#13;
       High level&#13;
      roundtable&#13;
 discussion organized&#13;
    by FSB/WB, on&#13;
 margins of the WB-                                June-October                              Sept-October Follow&#13;
      IMF Spring                                Receipt and Analysis                           up outreach to&#13;
       Meetings,                                   of completed                                authorities and&#13;
   Washington, DC                                     surveys                                       banks&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             April-June                                   July-October                                 October&#13;
                         Design and send out                           Design and send out                          High level forum&#13;
                           Authorities and                               Local/Regional                               organized by&#13;
                         Large International                              Banks survey                              FSB/IMF/WB on&#13;
                            Banks surveys                                                                          margins of WB-IMF&#13;
                                                                                                                    annual meetings,&#13;
                                                                                                                       Lima, Peru&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
8.      Special attention was paid to a regulatory issue which has become especially significant in the&#13;
international debateâ&#128;&#148;namely the topic of â&#128;&#156;knowing your customerâ&#128;&#153;s customerâ&#128;&#157; (KYCC). The extent&#13;
to which a correspondent bank is legally required to conduct due diligence on the customer of the&#13;
respondent institution and under which circumstances and to what purposeâ&#128;&#148;and the costs incurred in&#13;
having to carry out such measures, is one of the contentious issues in the debate surrounding the&#13;
withdrawal from correspondent banking.&#13;
9.      This is not a comprehensive, quantitative survey that presents an exhaustive overview of the&#13;
status of correspondent banking globally in 2015. While significant â&#128;&#147; and heterogeneous â&#128;&#147; economic&#13;
effects may result from the withdrawal of CBR, a quantitative discussion of those effects was outside&#13;
the scope of this report. Rather, it was more narrowly focused, seeking to provide some clarity in an&#13;
ongoing debate playing out in media and in policy fora, to determine whether there is indeed a decline&#13;
in CBRs and if so, to describe it, delve into the possible causes, and to determine what, if any, policy&#13;
action would be required.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                          Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                                                     12&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      III.      Participation&#13;
10.     In all, the surveys were sent to 137 banking authorities, 24 large international banks and 433&#13;
local/regional banks. One hundred and ten jurisdictions (80 percent), 20 large international banks (83&#13;
percent) and 170 local/regional banks (39 percent) responded.4 The surveys sought to obtain&#13;
information on the development of correspondent banking relationships in the period from 2012 to mid-&#13;
2015. Follow-up teleconferences and other discussions sought to gather information on more recent&#13;
developments experienced by the respondents. Not all authoritiesâ&#128;&#153; responses consisted of completed&#13;
surveys: some sent letters explaining the information was not available and some only provided banks&#13;
contacts (Table 1). Moreover, not all respondents answered all the questions. Therefore, the numbers&#13;
provided above serve only as the maximum number of responses to any given questionâ&#128;&#148;but for almost&#13;
every question the actual number of responses provided was lower. The findings reflect information&#13;
received as of November 3, 2015.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table 1: Summary of Participation&#13;
                                      Summary of Participation (as of November 3, 2015)&#13;
                                          Authorities        Large        International               Local/Regional&#13;
                                                             Banks                                    Banks&#13;
  Total - Invited to Participate              137                        24                                   433&#13;
  (#)&#13;
  Survey Completed (#)                              91                         20                               170&#13;
  Limited Participation5 (#)                        19                        N/A                               N/A&#13;
  Total Participation (#)                          110                         20                               170&#13;
 Total Participation (%)                          80%                         83%                               39%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
4.    Please note that the total number for local/regional banks surveys completed includes only those who completed and&#13;
      returned their surveys (either directly or through their authorities) to the project team. The number does not include&#13;
      the local/regional banks to whom the authorities conducted outreach directly in order to gather data for completion of&#13;
      the authority survey. Some jurisdictions specified the number of banks that they reached out to; some did not specify&#13;
      but mentioned that they had reached out to domestic banks.&#13;
5.    In addition to the 91 authorities that completed the survey, 19 authorities participated without completing the survey.&#13;
      One authority completed the survey in its capacity as a commercial entity. Sixteen additional authorities did not&#13;
      complete the survey but provided list of contacts at local/regional banks in their respective jurisdiction to be invited to&#13;
      participate in the project. Two authorities indicated that they could not complete the survey due to lack of data. They&#13;
      are being counted as participants, as some of the authorities that did complete the survey also indicated that they lacked&#13;
      data to be able to complete the survey.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                                                    13&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      IV.      Substantive Findings&#13;
11.    Given the different perspectives of each of the groups of respondents, the findings below have&#13;
not been synthesized, but are instead presented separately. While in some instances overall patterns&#13;
emerge, the differences in responses are sufficiently important to merit independent treatment.&#13;
                    a. Overall Trend in Correspondent Banking Relationships6&#13;
12.     In certain parts and regions of the world the number of foreign CBRs is declining. As will be&#13;
clear from the different groups of responses below, roughly half the banking authorities and slightly&#13;
more local/regional banks indicated a decline in CBRs. For large international banks the figures are&#13;
significantly higher at 75 percent. The differences might be explicable in that a great majority of the&#13;
large international banks were surveyed precisely because there had been mention of those institutions&#13;
having terminated, albeit to varying degrees, their foreign CBRs. For the local/regional banks there was&#13;
an indication that others had withdrawn CBRs from the jurisdiction in question â&#128;&#147; but not from the&#13;
specific institutions surveyed. It is important to note that the overall trend is not uniform for all&#13;
jurisdictions or regions. The Caribbean seems to be the region most severely affected. The United States&#13;
is most often mentioned as being home to correspondent banks that are withdrawing from foreign&#13;
CBRs.&#13;
      I.       Banking Authorities&#13;
13.     Among the 91 authorities that completed the survey, slightly more than half indicated a&#13;
significant or some degree of decline in their financial institutionsâ&#128;&#153; foreign CBRs, from the recipient&#13;
(nostro7) perspective.8 Thirty-two jurisdictions (35 percent) indicated significant declines and&#13;
seventeen (19 percent) indicated some decline.9 Thirty jurisdictions indicated no significant change,&#13;
two indicated significant increase, nine indicated â&#128;&#156;unknownâ&#128;&#157; and one did not answer the question.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
6.    Many of the respondents were selected because of indications that the jurisdiction or institution concerned may be&#13;
      facing challenges with its foreign CBR - therefore the percentages mentioned are not reflective of the different&#13;
      populations as a whole.&#13;
7.    The terms â&#128;&#156;nostroâ&#128;&#157; (ours) and â&#128;&#156;vostroâ&#128;&#157; (yours) are used to r efer to a bank holding an account with another bank to&#13;
      distinguish between the two sets of records of the same balance and set of transactions. From the perspective of the&#13;
      bank whose money is being held at another bank, a nostro is our account of our money, held by the other bank and a&#13;
      vostro is our account of other bank money, held by us. Thus this report uses the term â&#128;&#156;vostroâ&#128;&#157; to refer to the perspective&#13;
      of the provider of the correspondent banking services, while it uses â&#128;&#156;nostroâ&#128;&#157; to refer to the bank rec eiving the service.&#13;
8.    The actual number may be higher. At least three jurisdictions did not complete the survey but experienced declines in&#13;
      their foreign CBRs, according to IMF Article IV review reports and/or press releases issued by their Central Banks. In&#13;
      addition other reliable sources/experts in the field have mentioned other jurisdictions. Those jurisdictions are not&#13;
      included in this report since the results are based solely on inputs by the three categories of respondents.&#13;
9.    A category â&#128;&#156;some declineâ&#128;&#157; has been created to include jurisdictions that had checked â&#128;&#156;declined significantlyâ&#128;&#157; or â&#128;&#156;no&#13;
      significant changeâ&#128;&#157; because there was no option to check moderate decline, and for those whose surveys were&#13;
      inconsistent. Some jurisdictions indicated that they had noticed a moderate decline or a trend towards decline, but not&#13;
      a significant decline. Others indicated â&#128;&#156;no significant changeâ&#128;&#157; but noted that a number of large international banks that&#13;
      have restricted or terminated foreign CBRs with their domestic banks. Two jurisdictions also responded â&#128;&#156;no significant&#13;
      change.â&#128;&#157; but Article IV review reports by the IMF indicated that the countries had experienced some changes in their&#13;
      CBRs; they have been included in the â&#128;&#156;Some Declineâ&#128;&#157; tally.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                                                      14&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 2: Banking Authorities: Trend in Foreign CBRs â&#128;&#147; Nostro Accounts&#13;
&#13;
                    Authorities: Trend in Foreign CBRs - Nostro accounts (%)&#13;
&#13;
                                                                 2%&#13;
                                                        11%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                  35%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                           33%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                   19%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        Increased Significantly    Declined Significantly   Some Decline   No significant change   Unknown/No Response&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Regional Breakdown10&#13;
14.     Regionally, Latin America and Caribbean appears to be the region most affected by a decline&#13;
of foreign CBRs. A majority of banking authorities in the Caribbean region reported significant decline.&#13;
In total, 89 percent of jurisdictions reported experiencing significant to moderate declines in their&#13;
foreign CBRs. Of the 19 respondent authorities, 15 reported significant declines and two others noted&#13;
a trend towards decline or a moderate decline with no significant impact on the banking system overall.&#13;
Only two jurisdictions reported â&#128;&#156;no significant changeâ&#128;&#157; to their foreign CBRs. The decline appears to&#13;
be less pronounced in Latin America with one notable exception.&#13;
15.      The Europe and Central Asia region has experienced significant decline in its foreign CBRs. A&#13;
majority of respondent authorities in the region reported experiencing significant to moderate declines&#13;
in their foreign CBRs. See for further regional breakdown figure 3 below and the tables in Annex 3.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
10. Regions in this survey follow the World Bank Regional Country Classification. Please note however that some&#13;
jurisdictions surveyed in this report are not World Bank client countries and as such are not covered by the World Bank&#13;
country classification. They have been included in the regional breakdown. An additional classification â&#128;&#156;Rest of Worldâ&#128;&#157;&#13;
has been included and covers US and Canada, and European countries that are not part of Europe and Central Asia World&#13;
Bank classification (Europe-other). For more on World Bank regional designations, please see&#13;
http://www.worldbank.org/en/country.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                                                               15&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 3: Banking Authorities: Trend in Foreign CBRs- Nostro accounts: Regional breakdown (%).&#13;
                                Authorities: Trend in foreign CBRS- Nostro accounts&#13;
                                              Regional breakdown (%)&#13;
&#13;
               100&#13;
                90&#13;
                80&#13;
                70&#13;
  Percentage&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                60&#13;
                50&#13;
                40&#13;
                30&#13;
                20&#13;
                10&#13;
                 0&#13;
                       Africa         Europe &amp;       East Asia &amp;    Latin America      Middle East &amp;     South Asia     Rest of World&#13;
                                     Central Asia      Pacific      and Caribbean      North Africa&#13;
                                                                      Regions&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     Significant decline     Some decline      No significant change       Significant increase       Unknown&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Country Profiles&#13;
16.    Jurisdictions where there has been a decline include small jurisdictions with low volumes of&#13;
business/transactions, particularly in Europe and Central Asia, the Caribbean, and Africa.&#13;
17.     Small jurisdictions with significant offshore banking activities are particularly affected by the&#13;
decline of CBRs. First and foremost, the Caribbean appears to be the region the most affected by a&#13;
decline of foreign CBRs. Small countries with significant offshore banking sector in Europe and Africa&#13;
are also experiencing a significant decline in their foreign CBRs. Despite their size, some of the relevant&#13;
off-shore jurisdictions count among the top international financial centers worldwide (measured by&#13;
volume of transactions).&#13;
18.     Jurisdictions perceived as ML/FT high-risk jurisdictions or those subject to international&#13;
sanctions, and jurisdictions affected by sanctions by the US Office of Foreign Assets Control (OFAC)&#13;
in particular, are also affected.&#13;
19.     Some significant decline in foreign CBRs has been noted in major economies which are among&#13;
the top remittance recipient countries (in terms of value of remittances). In addition, eight G20 member&#13;
jurisdictions, experienced significant to moderate decline in their foreign CBRsâ&#128;&#148;four a significant&#13;
decline and four moderate decline in nostro accounts.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                                                16&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Jurisdictions of Financial Institutions Terminating/Restricting CBRs&#13;
20.      Jurisdictions most often mentioned as being home of financial institutions terminating/&#13;
restricting CBRs were, in order of times mentioned, the US, the United Kingdom (UK), the European&#13;
Union (France, Germany, Italy, Spain, the Netherlands, Belgium, Portugal and others), and Canada.&#13;
Switzerland is also significant. The US most significantly outnumbers other jurisdictions.11 Thirty-six&#13;
(84 percent) of the 43 respondent banking authorities that answered this question listed the US as the&#13;
top jurisdiction where the foreign correspondent banking relationships have been terminated or&#13;
restricted. The UK was the second jurisdiction most mentioned with 42 percent of respondents. The&#13;
European Union (EU) as jurisdiction and other (non-UK) EU countries were also among those most&#13;
mentioned. See the table in Annex 5 â&#128;&#147; for jurisdictions of terminations/restrictions.&#13;
21.      From the providerâ&#128;&#153;s perspective (vostro accounts), 11 jurisdictions indicated that their financial&#13;
institutions terminated or restricted a significant number, or significantly altered the nature of, their&#13;
foreign corresponding banking relationship. The jurisdictions are located in Africa, the Caribbean, East&#13;
Asia and Pacific, Europe and Central Asia, the Middle East, and Rest of World.12&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 4: Banking Authorities: Jurisdictions of terminations/restrictions (%)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
11.   Such feedback has to be considered in the context of the US being understood to be the largest provider of foreign&#13;
      CBRs. However, we lack of authoritative data on the overall number of CBRs and distribution among jurisdictions.&#13;
12.   However please note that while certain authorities did not respond to this question, they discussed the most prominent&#13;
      causes for reduction/restrictions in foreign CBRs by their financial Institutions.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                              Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                                             17&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
22.     The authorities also indicated jurisdictions of financial institutions with whom their banks were&#13;
terminating CBRs. The Middle East and Africa are mentioned most frequently. One of the main reasons&#13;
given is related to concerns with countries that have sanctions imposed against them. In addressing the&#13;
issue, most authorities on both the side of correspondent and respondent banks, recognized the need to&#13;
have robust AML/CFT frameworks in place, and discussed initiatives taken to enhance AML/CFT&#13;
standards within the jurisdiction â&#128;&#147; including through:&#13;
              ï&#130;·   conducting national risk assessments;&#13;
              ï&#130;·   issuing guidelines and carrying out awareness raising among stakeholders; and&#13;
              ï&#130;·   elevating the issues faced by de-risking with the international financial community&#13;
                  through direct representations with concerned standard-setting bodies in various&#13;
                  international fora.&#13;
23.     More specifically, Mexican authorities have responded to the situation by taking steps to amend&#13;
their legislation to allow domestic banks to share information in relation to clients with foreign&#13;
correspondent banks at their request. Foreign correspondent banks need to register with the Mexican&#13;
Ministry of Finance in order to gain access to this information... In addition the Mexican authorities are&#13;
developing a centralized database that will hold information in relation to all cross-border transactions&#13;
undertaken by domestic banks, which will enable the authorities to access information held on clients.13&#13;
      II.     Large international banks&#13;
24.     Three quarters of the large international banks responded that the number of vostro accounts&#13;
they held had declined in the period between end 2012 and mid-2015. One large bank indicated an&#13;
increase, two noted no change and two did not provide data. Due to the different methods used (and&#13;
data provided) by the various banks, it is difficult to provide an accurate count of foreign CBRs closed&#13;
by the banks. However, in percentage terms the declines ranged from low single digits to more than&#13;
half in the case of one bank. For the one bank that had noted an increase in its vostro accounts, this&#13;
increase was quite small in number of relationships and in low single digit in percentage terms.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
13.    Access to the database by private entities such as banks are still being worked out. Source: Teleconferences with&#13;
       Mexico central banking authorities and a domestic bank, October 2015.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                              Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                               18&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 5: Large International Banks: Vostro Accounts Trend&#13;
                    Large international banks: vostro accounts trend&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                           Increase, 1 (5%)&#13;
            Decline, 15 (75%)&#13;
&#13;
                                                                            No Change, 2 (10%)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                         No Data Provided, 2&#13;
                                                                               (10%)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                            Decline     Increase   No Change   No Data Provided&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
25.     Fourteen banks provided data on regional distribution of their vostro accounts, however two of&#13;
them only provided data for 2015 and one provided data only for end-2014. Six remaining banks did&#13;
not provide data, citing business confidentiality. Some banks also were not able to provide the data by&#13;
region as specified in the survey, further complicating the regional trends analysis. However, it is&#13;
significant that except for a very small number of cases, the banks as a whole experienced declining&#13;
trends, in varying degrees, in their foreign CBRs across Africa, East Asia and Pacific, Europe and&#13;
Central Asia, Latin America and Caribbean (although respondents noted that the trend is more apparent&#13;
in the Caribbean than in Latin America in general), and Middle East and North Africa. The regions of&#13;
South Asia and Rest of World appeared to have increased in the number of their foreign CBRs, but the&#13;
increases were quite small, usually in double digits in number of accounts increased.&#13;
26.      Eighty percent of the banks responded that they had terminated all CBRs with financial&#13;
institutions in certain jurisdictions. A slightly larger percentage of banks responded that they had&#13;
restricted the size and/or scope of CBRs in certain jurisdictions. The banks also specified the&#13;
jurisdictions (and in some cases, regions) where they had terminated or restricted their foreign CBRs.&#13;
The central banking authorities and local/regional banks in these jurisdictions formed a significant part&#13;
of the project teamâ&#128;&#153;s outreach in the second phase of data-gathering. The results of those surveys&#13;
confirm the data provided by the large international banks.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                           Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                                                                           19&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 6: Large International Banks: Termination of foreign CBRs&#13;
                        Large International Banks: Termination of foreign CBRs&#13;
                                      18                                                                90%&#13;
&#13;
                                      16                                                                80%&#13;
&#13;
                                      14                                                                70%&#13;
&#13;
                                      12                                                                60%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                              Responses (%)&#13;
   Responses (#)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                      10                                                                50%&#13;
&#13;
                                        8                                                               40%&#13;
&#13;
                                        6                                                               30%&#13;
&#13;
                                        4                                                               20%&#13;
&#13;
                                        2                                                               10%&#13;
&#13;
                                        0                                                               0%&#13;
                                                     Yes             No               Left Blank&#13;
                   Terminated all CBRs (#)           16               3                   1&#13;
                   Terminated all CBRs (%)           80%             15%                 5%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 7: Large International Banks: Restrictions on foreign CBRs&#13;
&#13;
                          Large International Banks: Restrictions on foreign CBRs&#13;
                                             18                                                               90%&#13;
&#13;
                                             16                                                               80%&#13;
&#13;
                                             14                                                               70%&#13;
&#13;
                                             12                                                               60%&#13;
                                                                                                                              Responses (%)&#13;
   Responses (#)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                             10                                                               50%&#13;
&#13;
                                               8                                                              40%&#13;
&#13;
                                               6                                                              30%&#13;
&#13;
                                               4                                                              20%&#13;
&#13;
                                               2                                                              10%&#13;
&#13;
                                               0                                                              0%&#13;
                                                           Yes             No             No Response&#13;
                   Restricted size and/or scope of&#13;
                                                           17               2                      1&#13;
                               CBRs (#)&#13;
                   Restricted size and/or scope of&#13;
                                                           85%             10%                 5%&#13;
                              CBRs (%)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                        Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                             20&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
27.    The large international banksâ&#128;&#153; withdrawals from foreign CBRs are part of wider policy changes&#13;
implemented in recent years. Seventeen of the 20 large international banks responded that their foreign&#13;
correspondent banking policy had been revised since 2012 (Figure 7). Many expressly indicated that&#13;
their CBR policies are subject to regular or periodic review, either separately or as part of review of&#13;
other policies and guidelines pertaining to conduct risk and financial crimes, for example.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 8: Large International Banks: Policy Change&#13;
&#13;
             Large International Banks: Policy Change&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
              17 (85%)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                        3 (15%)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                    Yes   No&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
28.     The banks adopted or revised their policy not just for one reason but for a combination of&#13;
factors. The most frequently cited reason for the policy change related to the banksâ&#128;&#153; broader risk&#13;
management, as part of their business strategy or the need to comply with new or revised legal&#13;
requirements. Four banks noted that policy change was undertaken in order to comply with supervisory&#13;
direction or enforcement action.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                          Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                                                              21&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 9: Large International Banks: Reasons for Policy Change&#13;
                                      Large International Banks: Reasons - Policy Change&#13;
                               16                                                                                          80%&#13;
&#13;
                               14                                                                                          70%&#13;
&#13;
                               12                                                                                          60%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                 Responses (%)&#13;
      Responses (#)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                               10                                                                                          50%&#13;
&#13;
                                8                                                                                          40%&#13;
&#13;
                                6                                                                                          30%&#13;
&#13;
                                4                                                                                          20%&#13;
&#13;
                                2                                                                                          10%&#13;
&#13;
                                0                                                                                          0%&#13;
                                                                                 To comply with&#13;
                                                                                                        To comply with&#13;
                                        In relation to                         new or revised legal&#13;
                                                         As part of business                              supervisory&#13;
                                         broader risk                             requirement&#13;
                                                              strategy                                    direction or&#13;
                                        management                                  (including&#13;
                                                                                                      enforcement action&#13;
                                                                                   regulation)&#13;
                      Responses (#)          14                  10                    10                     4&#13;
                      Responses (%)          70%                50%                   50%                    20%&#13;
                                                                          Reason&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          III.           Local/regional banks&#13;
29.     A majority (60 percent) of local/regional banks indicated a decline in foreign CBRs. As a whole,&#13;
local/regional banks experienced declining trends at various levels throughout the world.&#13;
30.    Some of the regions most affected by declining foreign CBRs included Europe and Central Asia&#13;
where over 80 percent (30 banks) indicated a moderate or significant decline in CBRs.14&#13;
31.    Latin America and the Caribbean was also highlighted as being a region significantly affected&#13;
by declining CBRs where 66 percent of the banks reported a decline. The Caribbean more specifically&#13;
was affected with 69 percent (32 banks) indicating a moderate or significant decline in CBRs. Follow-&#13;
up conversations and phone interviews with several local banks confirmed this trend in the Caribbean.&#13;
32.     Africa was also considerably affected where over 51 percent (46 banks) from a number of&#13;
jurisdictions that vary as to the size and nature of their banking sector indicated a moderate or&#13;
significant decline in CBRs15. A detailed overview is contained in Figure 10 below.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
14.             Please note that only local/regional banks form Eastern Europe provided surveys.&#13;
15.             Please note that the numbers may be somewhat skewed for the Africa Region since local/regional banks from one&#13;
                jurisdiction under targeted sanctions completed 13 surveys (out of a total of 47), which represents 28 percent of&#13;
                responses from the region. However, the authorities and large international banks surveys and other outreach support&#13;
                the local banks survey findings for the region as a whole.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                          Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                                         22&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 10: Local/Regional Banks: Trend in foreign CBRs&#13;
                           Local/ Regional Banks: Trends in foreign CBRs&#13;
                                                                         Yes, declined&#13;
                                  No change                              significantly&#13;
                                     24%                                      14%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     Yes, increased&#13;
                      moderately                                                   Yes, declined&#13;
                           15%                                                      moderately&#13;
                              Yes, increased                                            46%&#13;
                               significantly&#13;
                                    1%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 11: Local/Regional Banks: Decline in CBRs by region&#13;
                     Local/ Regional Banks: Decline in CBRs by region&#13;
                   90%      80%&#13;
                   80%                 72%        71%&#13;
                                                               66%&#13;
                   70%&#13;
      Percentage&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   60%                                                     51%&#13;
                   50%                                                                   43%&#13;
                   40%                                                                             30%&#13;
                   30%&#13;
                   20%&#13;
                   10%&#13;
                    0%&#13;
                           Europe     Europe-   South Asia     Latin      Africa    East Asia Middle East&#13;
                         Central Asia Other       (SAR)       America                Pacific    North&#13;
                            (ECA)                            Caribbean               (EAP)      Africa&#13;
                                                               (LAC)                           (MENA)&#13;
                                                              Region&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
33.     Jurisdictions most often mentioned as being home to financial institutions terminating CBRs&#13;
were, in order of times mentioned, United States (67) and UK (30). Switzerland (14), Canada (13) and&#13;
Germany (13) are also mentioned often (please see annex 12). The US most significantly outnumbers&#13;
the othersâ&#128;&#148;more than double of the UK, the second most mentioned. Such feedback has to be&#13;
considered in the context of the US being understood as the largest provider of foreign CBRs. However,&#13;
we lack of authoritative data on the overall number of CBRs or regional distribution.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                          Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                                             23&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 12: Local/Regional Banks: Jurisdictions of terminations16&#13;
                                 Local/Regional Banks: Jurisdictions of Terminations&#13;
                       80%&#13;
                              67%&#13;
                       70%&#13;
                       60%&#13;
      Percentage (%)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                       50%&#13;
                       40%&#13;
                                    30%&#13;
                       30%&#13;
                       20%                14%      13%   13%&#13;
                                                                8%      8%     8%&#13;
                       10%                                                           5%      5%       5%   4%&#13;
                       0%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                               Jurisdictions&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                 b. Effect on Products and Services&#13;
34.      The products and services identified as being most affected by the withdrawal of correspondent&#13;
banking are: check clearing, clearing and settlement, cash management services, international wire&#13;
transfers and for banking authorities and local/regional banks, also trade finance. The discrepancy on&#13;
trade finance between the responses from the large international banks and from the other categories of&#13;
respondent may be due to the fact that local/regional banks experience the effects directly in having to&#13;
tell their customers they cannot provide trade finance17.&#13;
          I.                 Banking authorities&#13;
35.     Authorities that had indicated a decline in their CBRs were asked to indicate which&#13;
products/services were affected and to what extent. The products/services most often noted as affected&#13;
significantly to moderately significantly affected are international wire transfers (80 percent of&#13;
respondents)18, with international wire transfers in USD noted most often (46 percent); clearing and&#13;
settlement (46 percent); and check clearing (39 percent); trade finance (37 percent); cash management&#13;
services - deposit accounts, payable through accounts (34 percent); investment services (32 percent),&#13;
&#13;
16  Please note that respondents were asked to provide the name of the jurisdiction(s), however several respondents put&#13;
    regions instead, such as Europe.&#13;
17. The report of the International Chamber of Commerce ('Rethinking Trade and Finance 2015 - An ICC Private Sector&#13;
    Development Perspective'), based on responses from 482 banks across 112 countries, notes that AML/KYC&#13;
    requirements are seen as the most significant impediment to trade finance with 70% of respondents reporting declining&#13;
    transactions due to AML/KYC issues. Report at http://www.iccwbo.org/Products-and-Services/Trade-&#13;
    facilitation/ICC-Global-Survey-on-Trade-Finance/.&#13;
18. Out of 41 respondents, 33 noted that international wire transfers were moderately to significantly affected (19 for&#13;
    international wire transfers in USD; 6 in euros, and 8 in other currencies).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                          Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                                           24&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
and foreign exchange services (29 percent) were also noted as having been affected to a significant or&#13;
moderately significant extent.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 13: Banking Authorities: Products/ Services affected&#13;
                               Authorities: Products/services significantly to&#13;
                                   moderately significantly affected (%)&#13;
                                                        Lending&#13;
                          Structured Finance/Foreign Investments&#13;
      Products/Services&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                      Foreign Exchange services&#13;
                                            Investment services&#13;
                                      Cash Management Services&#13;
                                                  Trade Finance&#13;
                                                 Check Clearing&#13;
                                        Clearing and Settlement&#13;
                                    International Wire Transfers&#13;
&#13;
                                                                   0   10 20 30 40 50 60 70 80 90&#13;
                                                                              Percent (%)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Currencies Affected&#13;
36.     Banking authorities mentioned the impact of the decline of CBRs on their ability to conduct&#13;
foreign currency denominated transactions in the following jurisdictions: 87 percent of respondent&#13;
authorities mentioned the United States (20 respondents), 48 percent the European Union (11&#13;
respondents), 17 percent the United Kingdom (seven respondents), 13 percent Canada (four&#13;
respondents), and 13 percent China (three respondents). Based on the jurisdictions most often listed by&#13;
respondents, the ability to conduct foreign currency denominated capital or current account transactions&#13;
in US dollar (USD) have been most significantly affected followed by Euro, pound sterling (GBP), and&#13;
Canadian dollar (CAD) and the Renminbi (RMB).&#13;
           II.                  Large International Banks&#13;
37.    Nearly all banks provide the full menu of foreign correspondent banking services to their clients,&#13;
including clearing and settlement, foreign exchange services, international wire transfers and trade&#13;
finance. The vast majority also indicated that they provide cash management, check clearing,&#13;
investment and lending services. While a large majority of the banks indicated that they had not stopped&#13;
providing any particular products/services, there have been reductions in their provisions. It is&#13;
important to bear in mind that 75 percent of the banks indicated that the number of Vostro accounts&#13;
they held had declined in the period between end 2012 and mid-2015.&#13;
38.    Sixty percent of large international banks responded that they had significantly or moderately&#13;
reduced their check clearing services, 30 percent their clearing and settlement services and 20 percent&#13;
cash management services. Please note that for clearing and settlement and international wire transfers,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                                                                           25&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
most banks provide these services in multiple currencies, but some tend to specialize in the currency of&#13;
their jurisdiction of headquarters.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 14: Large International Banks: Products/Services Affected&#13;
                                 Large International Banks: Products/Services Affected&#13;
                      14                                                                                                70%&#13;
                           12&#13;
                      12        60%                                                                                     60%&#13;
&#13;
                      10                                                                                                50%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                              Responses (%)&#13;
      Responses (#)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                      8                                                                                                 40%&#13;
                                      6&#13;
                      6                   30%                                                                           30%&#13;
                                                4&#13;
                      4                             20%   3          3                                                  20%&#13;
                                                               15%       15%      2         2&#13;
                      2                                                               10%       10%   1        1        10%&#13;
                                                                                                          5%       5%&#13;
                      0                                                                                                 0%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                              Products/Services&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
39.     For check clearing, banks noted that they do not provide check clearing services for checks not&#13;
drawn on that bankâ&#128;&#153;s accounts or the service had always been restricted to third party banks for checks&#13;
drawn on banks of its home jurisdiction. Others noted that check clearing was significantly reduced&#13;
globally for USD checks cleared out of New York or noted a significant reduction in check clearing for&#13;
the currency of the jurisdiction of their headquarters and primary clearing currency.&#13;
40.     There was little feedback as to the jurisdictions affected but a small number of banks indicated&#13;
that they were moving towards focusing on their â&#128;&#156;homeâ&#128;&#157; currencies, including decision to reduce&#13;
clearing for exotic currencies. See Annex 9 for table of large international bank responses on&#13;
products/services affected.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                           Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                                                                       26&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
              III.                      Local/Regional banks&#13;
41.     For local/regional banks, the decline in foreign CBRs of financial institutions affected its ability&#13;
to access the following top three products/ services: check clearing, clearing and settlement services&#13;
and trade finance (letters of credit).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 15: Local /Regional Banks: Products/Services Affected&#13;
                                                Local/ Regional Banks: Products/services significantly to&#13;
                                                          moderately significantly affected (#)&#13;
                                                                 Others 1 2&#13;
                                     International Wire Transfers - EUR   5    5&#13;
                                     International Wire Transfers - GBP    6 2&#13;
      Product/ Service Impacted&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                    Structured Finance      11           12&#13;
                                                                Lending     11         7&#13;
                                             Foreign Exchange Services       13                    19&#13;
                                  International Wire Transfers - Others      14                     19&#13;
                                     International Wire Transfers - USD        17                   13&#13;
                                                   Investment Services          18                       17&#13;
                                            Cash Management Services             19                       18&#13;
                                                          Trade Finance             25                              30&#13;
                                               Clearing and Settlement               28                              26&#13;
                                                         Check Clearing                  35                                24&#13;
                                                                      0          10           20           30       40          50   60   70&#13;
                                                                                                           Responses (#)&#13;
&#13;
                                                                       Significant Impact      Moderate Impact&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                             c. Client segments most significantly affected by the decline of foreign CBRs&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
              I. Banking Authorities&#13;
42.     Over 69 percent of the respondent banking authorities indicated that money transfer operators&#13;
and other remittance companies are most affected, followed by small and medium domestic banks (44&#13;
percent) and small and medium exporters (26 percent). Respondents also specified other types of&#13;
clients/client segments including retail customers, international business companies, and e-&#13;
gaming/gambling.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                         Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                                                                     27&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 16: Banking Authorities: Client Segments affected&#13;
                                                 Authorities: Client Segment Impact&#13;
                                          30                                                                      80%&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                  70%&#13;
                                          25&#13;
                                                                                                                  60%&#13;
                                          20&#13;
                                                                                                                  50%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                        Responses (%)&#13;
      Responses (#)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                          15                                                                      40%&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                  30%&#13;
                                          10&#13;
                                                                                                                  20%&#13;
                                           5&#13;
                                                                                                                  10%&#13;
&#13;
                                           0                                                                      0%&#13;
                                                   Money Transfer&#13;
                                                   Operators/Other    Small and Medium      Small and Medium&#13;
                                                     Remittance        Domestic Banks           Exporters&#13;
                                                     Companies&#13;
                      Responses (#)                      27                  17                     10&#13;
                      Responses (% of 39 total&#13;
                                                        69%                 44%                    26%&#13;
                            responses)&#13;
                                                                       Client segment&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
43.    The respondent banking authorities that reported significant impact on money transfer operators&#13;
and other remittance companies were located mostly in the Caribbean, in East Asia and Pacific, in&#13;
MENA, Africa, and Europe and Central Asia. It is interesting to note that some jurisdictions where&#13;
money transfer operators and other remittance companies are most affected are among the top&#13;
remittance recipient countries (in terms of value of remittances).19&#13;
      II. Local/Regional Banks&#13;
44.     The respondents indicated that money transfer operators (MTOs) and other remittance&#13;
companies/ service providers are significantly affected, followed by small and medium exporters.&#13;
Respondents also specified other types of clients/client segments including â&#128;&#156;casas de cambioâ&#128;&#157; (money&#13;
exchange houses), exporters, importers and PEPs. Small and medium domestic banks appear to be less&#13;
affected, but it should be highlighted that local/regional banks selected in this survey are more users&#13;
(nostro accounts) than providers (vostro accounts) of foreign CBRs. See Annex 10 Client segment&#13;
impact.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
19.             The top recipients of remittances as a share of GDP were also considered, but the response rate for those countries&#13;
                was low.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                           Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                                                                       28&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 17: Local/Regional Banks: Client Segments Affected&#13;
                                       Local/Regional Banks: Client Segment Impact&#13;
                                           90                                                                       60%&#13;
&#13;
                                           80&#13;
                                                                                                                    50%&#13;
                                           70&#13;
&#13;
                                           60                                                                       40%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                          Responses (%)&#13;
      Responses (#)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                           50&#13;
                                                                                                                    30%&#13;
                                           40&#13;
&#13;
                                           30                                                                       20%&#13;
&#13;
                                           20&#13;
                                                                                                                    10%&#13;
                                           10&#13;
&#13;
                                            0                                                                       0%&#13;
                                                    Money Transfer&#13;
                                                   Operators (MTOs)      Small and medium     Small and medium&#13;
                                                  and other remittance      exporters          domestic banks&#13;
                                                       companies&#13;
                      Responses (#)                       77                   43                    23&#13;
                      Responses (% of 143 total&#13;
                                                          55%                  31%                  16%&#13;
                            responses)&#13;
                                                                         Client Segment&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                              d. Possible causes of decline in foreign CBRs&#13;
45.    The drivers of the decline in foreign CBRs can be divided into two groups: one category of&#13;
causes that are more business related, explaining the decision to terminate a foreign CBR in purely&#13;
economic terms, and one (as mentioned in the introduction) more regulatory and risk related, explaining&#13;
the decision to sever ties with certain actors as based on the level of ML/FT risk of the counterpart&#13;
being unmanageable, and concerns that one might fall foul of AML/CFT, international/regional&#13;
sanctionsâ&#128;&#148;or other legislation or regulations.20&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
20.             To be clear: AML/CFT and sanctions regulations, though often bracketed in the same category, are different in&#13;
                application. AML/CFT will often involve subjective judgment by the institution whether a specific transaction is&#13;
                related to money laundering or terrorism financing and should be reported or frozen. For the application of sanctions&#13;
                regulations there is no such subjectivity: if a transaction benefits a person or entity or country that is subject to&#13;
                sanctions, then the financial institution has no choice but to freeze the transaction.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                           Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                                 29&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
46.     Of course, the two categories of drivers are related. The requirement to comply with a regulatory&#13;
rule might drive up the costs of establishing and/or maintaining certain relationships. As one respondent&#13;
succinctly put it: â&#128;&#156;[B]anks face high costs of complying with standards (particularly for banks who are&#13;
concerned about jurisdictional risk and â&#128;&#147; notably given some of the uncertainties around AML/CFT&#13;
requirements - consider it necessary to know their customerâ&#128;&#153;s customers), but also high costs for any&#13;
oversight/mistakes. This risk-reward ratio, of high (potential) costs and low profitability, is a key driver&#13;
behind the decline in correspondent banking services. Given the potential damage to reputation and&#13;
balance sheet from any enforcement case, firms seek to avoid any counterparties/jurisdictions where&#13;
there is uncertainty.â&#128;&#157;&#13;
47.     Indeed quite a number of respondents indicated the decline in foreign CBRs was due to drivers&#13;
in both groups. However, the AML/CFT and/or regulatory factor cannot always be expressed in&#13;
monetary termsâ&#128;&#148;and precisely therein lies at least some of the problem. Recent high profile fines for&#13;
infringements of AML/CFT provisions and uncertainty about what exactly is required, about what the&#13;
regulatory expectations are (including in terms of acceptable risk appetite), how they might evolve over&#13;
time and what the consequences would be of possibly falling foul of certain regulatory rules (as also&#13;
highlighted in the quote above), has led banks to play it safe. As one respondent put it â&#128;&#156;Weâ&#128;&#153;re supposed&#13;
to have a risk-based approach, but what we have is a fear based approachâ&#128;&#157;. That uncertainty makes it&#13;
impossible to give it a monetary valueâ&#128;&#148;and quantify the costs in terms that can be factored in and dealt&#13;
with as part of their overall risk-reward ratio assessment.&#13;
48.     While local/regional banks put more of an emphasis on the economic/business rationale for the&#13;
decline, banking authorities and large international banks emphasized both actual level of risk,&#13;
regulatory AML/CFT and business related concerns. The discrepancy is possibly due to the fact that&#13;
not all local/regional banks are fully informed about the reasons for termination of their accounts (or&#13;
only in more vague terms) as was also mentioned in follow up discussions.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      I.   Banking authorities&#13;
49.    As noted, overall, authorities that had indicated decline in their foreign CBRs point&#13;
predominantly to both categories of drivers to explain the decline in foreign CBRs in their jurisdiction.&#13;
Figure 18 summarizes the main causes/drivers.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                          Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                                                                30&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 18: Banking Authorities: Causes and Drivers&#13;
                                                      Authorities: Causes and Drivers&#13;
&#13;
                                                    Sovereign credit risk rating         7%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         Imposition of international sanctions           7%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                            Imposition of enforcement actions by the domestic&#13;
                                                                                           9%&#13;
                                         authority on respondent&#13;
&#13;
                        Impact of internationally agreed financial regulatory&#13;
                                                                                                14%&#13;
                     reforms (other than AML/CFT) (e.g. capital requirements)&#13;
&#13;
                         Concerns about, or insufficient information about,&#13;
                      respondentâ&#128;&#153;s CDD procedures (for AML/CFT or sanctions                     14%&#13;
                                             purposes)&#13;
&#13;
                                        High-risk customer base of respondent                     18%&#13;
   Causes/Drivers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                              Compliance with pre-existing legal/ supervisory /&#13;
                                                                                                  18%&#13;
                                regulatory requirement by correspondent&#13;
&#13;
                            Jurisdiction identified as having strategic AML/CFT&#13;
                                                                                                      23%&#13;
                            deficiencies by FATF (or other international body)&#13;
&#13;
                           Structural changes to correspondent (including&#13;
                        merger/acquisitions) and/or reorganization of business                          27%&#13;
                                              portfolio&#13;
&#13;
                         Inability/ cost for correspondent to undertake CDD on&#13;
                                                                                                              36%&#13;
                                          respondents' customers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                   Concerns about ML/TF risks                                         48%&#13;
&#13;
                    Changes to legal, regulatory or supervisory requirements in&#13;
                      correspondentâ&#128;&#153;s jurisdiction that have implications for                                         48%&#13;
                                         maintaining CBRs&#13;
&#13;
                                         Overall risk appetite of correspondent                                             55%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     Lack of profitability of certain foreign CBR&#13;
                                                                                                                                  64%&#13;
                                                 services/products&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                    0%   10%    20%     30%   40%   50%     60%   70%&#13;
                                                                                          Responses (% - 44 total respondents)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                             Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                                              31&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
50.     More than 18 percent of the banking authorities that responded mentioned the high-risk&#13;
customer base of their financial institutions as a cause of decline. When asked to specify the high-risk&#13;
customer base, the following categories of high-risk customers were mentioned by some of the&#13;
authorities:&#13;
             ï&#130;§    Money transfer operators/ Money exchange companies&#13;
             ï&#130;§    Private Banks&#13;
             ï&#130;§    Customers and/or beneficial owners from high risk countries&#13;
             ï&#130;§    Offshore sector/ Offshore companies serving as Special Purpose Vehicles&#13;
             ï&#130;§    Private Members Clubs (Casino Type Business)&#13;
             ï&#130;§    Politically Exposed Persons&#13;
             ï&#130;§    Cash-intensive businesses (e.g. supermarkets)&#13;
             ï&#130;§    Specialized professionals (e.g. lawyers)&#13;
             ï&#130;§    Individuals on the OFAC Specially Designated Nationals List&#13;
51.     Ninety-one percent of banking authorities respondents (40 out of 44) mentioned either lack of&#13;
profitability of foreign CBRs services or structural changes together as accounting for the decline in&#13;
foreign CBRs. Increasing costs of regulatory compliance however, notably the inability and cost to&#13;
undertake CDD and/or insufficient information about respondentâ&#128;&#153;s CDD procedures (for AML/CFT or&#13;
sanctions purposes) have been mentioned significantly by half of respondent authorities. Almost half&#13;
of the respondents also mentioned overall risk, concerns about ML/TF risks, and changes to legal or&#13;
regulatory requirements in foreign jurisdictions as causes of decline. Altogether, 73 percent of&#13;
respondent banking authorities mentioned AML/CFT concerns as one of the driver for restriction or&#13;
termination.21 The impact of other regulations such as Basel III (14 percent)22 and FACTA were also&#13;
mentioned albeit marginally.&#13;
52.     Some banking authorities noted a recent switch in the rationale provided by banks for&#13;
termination or restriction of foreign CBRs in their jurisdictions. They have shifted from core business&#13;
portfolio reorganizations to the increasing cost of regulatory compliance, particularly related to&#13;
AML/CFT. It is unclear whether in all instances the switch is realâ&#128;&#148;or whether it is only the justification&#13;
provided to the outside world.&#13;
53.      An illustrative example was recently provided by a small financial center which had indicated&#13;
a significant decline in their CBRs in the past year. After a â&#128;&#156;Notice of Findingâ&#128;&#157; by the US Financial&#13;
Intelligence Unit, FinCEN, that one of the banks in the jurisdiction was perceived as a financial&#13;
institution of primary concern for money laundering under the US Patriot Act, all of the concerned&#13;
bankâ&#128;&#153;s foreign CBRs were terminated. This decision had a broader impact on the other banks in the&#13;
jurisdiction where a significant decline in foreign CBRs was noted for all banks in the country, even&#13;
though these institutions did not have any transactional relationships with the financial institution of&#13;
primary concern for AML/CFT. Compliance lapses â&#128;&#147; actual or alleged â&#128;&#147; by even one financial&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
21.   Percentage based on the thirty-two respondent authorities out of forty-four that mentioned either â&#128;&#156;concerns about&#13;
      ML/TF risks, the inability/ cost for foreign financial institutions to undertake CDD on your financial institutions'&#13;
      customersâ&#128;&#157; and/or â&#128;&#156;concerns or insufficient information about CDD procedures (for AML/CFT or sanctions&#13;
      purposes), and/or high-risk customer baseâ&#128;&#157;.&#13;
22.   Six respondents out of 44 for â&#128;&#156;Impact of internationally agreed financial regulatory reforms (other than AML/CFT) â&#128;&#157;&#13;
      (e.g. capital requirements).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                              Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                                               32&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
institution can have a potential spillover effects for other financial institutions in the jurisdiction, in&#13;
particular in small jurisdictions.&#13;
54.     While only four jurisdictions indicated that imposition of international sanctions was a driver&#13;
in decline in foreign CBRs, this should be seen in conjunction with the responses from large&#13;
international banks which indicated that they simply cannot conduct activities with institutions in&#13;
sanction countries.23&#13;
55.    From the provider (vostro account) perspective, consisting of a smaller number of authorities&#13;
(14 respondents in total), many of the same concerns listed above are cited, be it that profit related&#13;
concerns are not so prominent. Specifically, see Table 2 for the main causes/drivers indicated.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table 2: Banking Authorities: Main causes/drivers of decline from the provider (vostro account)&#13;
perspective&#13;
                            Main causes/drivers                                    Respondents (#)&#13;
  Concerns about money laundering/ terrorism financing risks                            12&#13;
  Imposition of international sanctions                                                 12&#13;
  Jurisdictions identified as having strategic AML/CFT deficiencies by                   8&#13;
  FATF or another international body&#13;
  Foreign correspondent bankâ&#128;&#153;s lack of compliance with AML/CFT                             7&#13;
  sanctions regulations&#13;
  Overall risk appetite                                                                    6&#13;
  Lack of profitability of certain foreign CBR services/products                           5&#13;
&#13;
      II.     Large international banks&#13;
56.     For large international banks, AML/CFT and CDD/KYC related concerns topped the list of&#13;
causes/drivers for terminating and/or restricting foreign CBRs. The banksâ&#128;&#153; overall risk appetite and&#13;
lack of profitability of certain foreign CB services/products also ranked high among the reasons for&#13;
terminating and/or restricting CBRs. In follow up interviews, large banks also mentioned that they were&#13;
worried about being â&#128;&#156;the last man standingâ&#128;&#157; in a country other banks had exited because they&#13;
considered it too high risk or not worth the cost. This was leading some to exit, merely because others&#13;
were exiting, rather than being based on an individual assessment of the countryâ&#128;&#153;s risk profile.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
23.    Three authorities that completed the survey and one authority that completed the survey as a commercial entity&#13;
       indicated that imposition of international sanctions was a driver in decline in foreign CBRs.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                               Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                                                                33&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 19: Large International Banks: Causes and Drivers&#13;
                                    Large International Banks: Causes and Drivers&#13;
&#13;
                               Industry consolidation within jurisdiction              20%&#13;
&#13;
                       Compliance with pre-existing legal/ supervisory /&#13;
                                                                                         25%&#13;
                                  regulatory requirement&#13;
&#13;
                               Structural changes to financial institution&#13;
                                                                                             30%&#13;
                                 (including merger/acquisition) and/orâ&#128;¦&#13;
&#13;
                            Impact of internationally agreed financial&#13;
                                                                                             30%&#13;
                          regulatory reforms (other than AML/CFT) (e.g.â&#128;¦&#13;
&#13;
                                   The sovereign credit risk rating of the&#13;
                                                                                               35%&#13;
                                    jurisdiction(s) of respondent banks&#13;
&#13;
                           Imposition of domestic enforcement actions                              40%&#13;
&#13;
                             Changes to legal, regulatory or supervisory&#13;
                                                                                                     45%&#13;
                                           requirements&#13;
      Causes/Drivers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                         Inability/cost to undertake CDD on respondent&#13;
                                                                                                           65%&#13;
                                        bank(s)â&#128;&#153;s customers&#13;
&#13;
                                Respondent bank jurisdiction subject to&#13;
                                                                                                                 75%&#13;
                                countermeasures or identified as havingâ&#128;¦&#13;
&#13;
                          Respondent bank(s)â&#128;&#153;s high-risk customer base                                           75%&#13;
&#13;
                              Lack of profitability of certain foreign CBR&#13;
                                                                                                                  80%&#13;
                                          services/products&#13;
&#13;
                           Concerns about, or insufficient information&#13;
                                                                                                                  80%&#13;
                         about, respondent bankâ&#128;&#153;s CDD procedures (forâ&#128;¦&#13;
&#13;
                                                    Overall risk appetite                                              85%&#13;
&#13;
                          Lack of compliance with AML/CFT or sanctions&#13;
                                                                                                                       85%&#13;
                                           regulations&#13;
&#13;
                                   Imposition of international sanctions                                                90%&#13;
&#13;
                           Concerns about money laundering/terrorism&#13;
                                                                                                                             95%&#13;
                                         financing risks&#13;
&#13;
                                                                             0% 10% 20% 30% 40% 50% 60% 70% 80% 90%100%&#13;
                                                                                 Responses (% of 20 total responses)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
57.     As far as the high risk customers are concerned, 13 out of the 15 banks that selected this as a&#13;
driver noted that they considered MTOs to be an inherently high risk client group. While only five&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                                                                               34&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
banks specifically listed FATF designated jurisdictions as a basis for considering a clientâ&#128;&#153;s risk, all&#13;
banks indicated that their risk assessment of correspondent banking clients take into consideration the&#13;
ML/TF risk levels of their client banksâ&#128;&#153; jurisdiction. As noted above, concerns over the ML/TF risks&#13;
of the foreign correspondent bankâ&#128;&#153;s jurisdiction was cited b y 19 out of 20 banks and was the top&#13;
cause/driver for termination of CBRs.&#13;
58.     Only three banks mentioned having downstream correspondent banks as clients (that is to say&#13;
offering correspondent banking services to a bank that would offer those services itself on to other&#13;
banks) as high risk situation. However, it should be noted that at least one of the banks that did not&#13;
provide a list of high risk client types is in the process of closing all accounts with downstream banks.&#13;
An enforcement action against another bank also centered on the issue of nested accounts (see further&#13;
discussion below under â&#128;&#156;nested accountsâ&#128;&#157;).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 20: Large International Banks: High Risk Customers&#13;
&#13;
                                                        Large International Banks: High Risk Customers&#13;
&#13;
                                                     Transparency Intl Index of 20 or below           7%&#13;
&#13;
                                                                        Sensitive Industries          7%&#13;
&#13;
                                                                  Section 311 listed entities         7%&#13;
&#13;
                                                             Offshore Financial Institutions          7%&#13;
&#13;
                                         Links to negative news (bribery, AML, corruption)            7%&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                  Embassies           7%&#13;
      High Risk Customer Type&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                            AML Deficiency jurisdictions - FATF designated            7%&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                 Shell Banks                20%&#13;
&#13;
                                          Geographic Risks / high risk jurisdictions (ML/TF)                    27%&#13;
&#13;
                                           Downstream CBs/ Nested Financial Institutions                    20%&#13;
&#13;
                                Charities, state licensed or regulated/other charities/ NPOs                20%&#13;
&#13;
                                             PEPs / PEPs - ownership financial institution(s)                      33%&#13;
&#13;
                                Gaming / land based casinos, including unregulated casinos                         33%&#13;
&#13;
                                                                 Gaming - Online/E-gaming                              40%&#13;
&#13;
                                Other remittance providers/Cash or Third party processors                                 47%&#13;
&#13;
                                                                 Money Transfer Operators                                                         87%&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                0%   10% 20% 30% 40% 50% 60% 70% 80% 90% 100%&#13;
                                                                                                       Responses (% of 20 total responses/type)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                         Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                                                                  35&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          III.                Local/regional banks&#13;
59.     For local/regional banks, as with the other categories of respondents, economic factors feature&#13;
prominently as a reason that would explain the decline in foreign CBRs. While risk appetite is among&#13;
the factors mentioned most often, AML/CFT risks and regulatory concerns do not come up as often as&#13;
with the other categories of respondents. Since this group of respondents is the target of the withdrawal&#13;
or restriction of foreign CBRs, it is possible that the correspondent bank does not in all cases deem it&#13;
appropriate to share those concerns with the institution with which that it is severing/restricting its&#13;
relationship. See also Annex 8.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 21: Local/Regional Banks: Causes and Drivers&#13;
                                                    Local/Regional Banks: Causes and Drivers&#13;
&#13;
                        Identified as having strategic AML/CFT deficiencies by FATF             4%&#13;
                            Insufficient information about, respondent bankâ&#128;&#153;s CDD&#13;
                                                                                                 6%&#13;
                                procedures (for AML/CFT or sanction purposes)&#13;
                       Impact of internationally agreed financial regulatory reforms&#13;
                                                                                                     8%&#13;
                                           (other than AML/CFT)&#13;
                                       Imposition of domestic enforcement actions                    8%&#13;
&#13;
                                      Respondent bank(s)â&#128;&#153;s high-risk customer base                   8%&#13;
&#13;
                                               Imposition of international sanctions                 8%&#13;
                       Compliance with pre-existing legal/ supervisory / regulatory&#13;
      Causes/Drivers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                      9%&#13;
                                             requirement&#13;
                                           Industry consolidation within jurisdiction                      13%&#13;
                             The sovereign credit risk rating of the jurisdiction(s) of&#13;
                                                                                                            15%&#13;
                                                respondent banks&#13;
                           Inability/cost to undertake CDD on respondent bank(s)â&#128;&#153;s&#13;
                                                                                                            15%&#13;
                                                   customers&#13;
                        Concerns about money laundering/terrorism financing risks                                 19%&#13;
&#13;
                          Changes to legal, regulatory or supervisory requirements                                      31%&#13;
                                   Structural changes to financial institution and/or&#13;
                                                                                                                              35%&#13;
                                         reorganization of business portfolio&#13;
                                                                Overall risk appetite                                          37%&#13;
&#13;
                       Lack of profitability of certain foreign CBR services/products                                                46%&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                          0%   5% 10% 15% 20% 25% 30% 35% 40% 45% 50%&#13;
                                                        Responses (% of 130 total responses)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                                       36&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
60.     Of the one hundred and seventy respondents, eleven banks indicated their high-risk customer&#13;
base as among the causes for terminating or restricting their CBRs. As in the other categories, the most&#13;
cited high risk customer was Money Transfer Operators (MTOs).&#13;
61.     See Table 3 for a comparison of the drivers of termination/restriction of foreign CBRs for all&#13;
three different respondents â&#128;&#147; banking authorities, large international banks and local/regional banks.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table 3 Comparing drivers of termination/restriction of foreign CBRs for different respondents&#13;
         Comparing drivers of termination/restriction of foreign CBRs for different respondents&#13;
                                                             Banking            Large&#13;
                                                                                                Local/Regional&#13;
                                                            Authorities     International&#13;
                                                                                                 Banks (%)&#13;
                                                               (%)           Banks (%)&#13;
      Lack of profitability of certain foreign CBR&#13;
                                                                 64              80                   46&#13;
      services/products&#13;
      Overall risk appetite                                      55              85                   37&#13;
      Changes to legal, regulatory or supervisory&#13;
      requirements in correspondentâ&#128;&#153;s jurisdiction that          48              45                   31&#13;
      have implications for maintaining CBRs&#13;
      Structural changes to correspondent (including&#13;
      merger/acquisition) and/or reorganization of               27              30                   35&#13;
      business portfolio&#13;
      Concerns about money laundering/terrorism&#13;
                                                                 48              95                   19&#13;
      financing risks&#13;
      Sovereign credit risk rating                                7              35                   15&#13;
      Inability/cost to undertake CDD                            36              65                   15&#13;
      Industry consolidation within jurisdiction of foreign&#13;
                                                                None             20                   13&#13;
      financial institution&#13;
      Imposition of enforcement actions                           9              40                   8&#13;
      High-risk customer base                                    18              75                   8&#13;
      Imposition of international sanctions on jurisdiction&#13;
                                                                  7              90                   8&#13;
      or respondent&#13;
      Impact of internationally agreed financial&#13;
                                                                 14              30                   8&#13;
      regulatory reforms&#13;
      Compliance with pre-existing legal/ supervisory /&#13;
                                                                 18              25                   9&#13;
      regulatory requirement&#13;
      Concern about, or insufficient information about&#13;
                                                                 14              80                    6&#13;
      respondentâ&#128;&#153;s CDD procedures&#13;
      Respondentâ&#128;&#153;s         jurisdiction    subject       to&#13;
      countermeasures or identified having strategic             23              75                   4&#13;
      AML/CFT deficiencies by FATF&#13;
      *N.B. The respondents were allowed to choose&#13;
      multiple options&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                 e. Finding replacements/alternative arrangements&#13;
62.     The ability of financial institutions in affected jurisdictions to find alternative correspondent&#13;
banks varied, but the majority indicated they were able so far to find replacements. Of the 46 banking&#13;
authorities who responded to this questionâ&#128;&#148;23 authorities indicated that their financial institutions had&#13;
found replacements and 8 indicated that they had found alternative means. Thirteen banking authorities&#13;
indicated that their banks had been unable to find replacements.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                            Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                                                     37&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
63.      Authorities noted the impact of having to find replacements/ alternatives or arrangements on&#13;
their financial institutions include:&#13;
              ï&#130;§   Increased costs24 of finding replacements/alternatives.&#13;
              ï&#130;§   Time spent looking for replacements â&#128;&#147; noting that often, banks are given limited notice&#13;
                  of termination of relationships (about 30 days) to find replacements.&#13;
              ï&#130;§   Newly imposed minimum thresholds below which the account would be closed.&#13;
              ï&#130;§   Higher (often due diligence) related costs in establishing the new CBR being passed on&#13;
                  to the customer, and&#13;
              ï&#130;§   Sometimes terminating or restricting relationships with certain clients to be able to&#13;
                  maintain access. Several small banks mentioned severing ties to MTOs to maintain&#13;
                  access to their foreign CBRs.&#13;
              ï&#130;§   Several authorities noted particular difficulties with finding replacements in the US.&#13;
&#13;
64.     According to the results of the local/regional banksâ&#128;&#153; survey, the ability of financial institutions&#13;
to find replacement CBRs, or alternative means, varied across banks. A majority (54 percent) of local/&#13;
regional banks (92) responded that they were able to find replacement CBRs, or establish alternative&#13;
arrangements to meet their needs. However, there were 10 local/regional banks (6 percent) that were&#13;
unable to find replacement CBRs, or alternative means.&#13;
65.      One local bank in a small international financial center, is extremely concerned and in danger&#13;
at the time of the survey of shutting down operations. During follow-up calls with local banks, there&#13;
were several other local banks that expressed the same fears of not being able to replace CBRs or&#13;
finding alternative means, and being threatened to close down their business in the near future. The&#13;
banks most affected tend to be the smaller banks in â&#128;&#152;higher risk jurisdictionsâ&#128;&#153; or â&#128;&#152;offshore fi nancial&#13;
centersâ&#128;&#153;.&#13;
66.     In terms of level of difficulty, a large majority (62 percent) of local/regional banks (56)&#13;
responded that they easily found replacement CBRs, or alternative arrangements. However, there were&#13;
25 banks (28 percent) that mentioned that it was difficult, or somewhat difficult, to get replacement&#13;
CBRs or find alternative means, with some banks indicating that it was expensive and time consuming&#13;
to find replacement CBRs and that the terms and conditions were not comparable to the previous&#13;
foreign CBRs. Some noted a substantial increase in pricing. Maintaining relationships however, can&#13;
come at quite a steep price, with several mentioning, newly imposed minimum thresholds below which&#13;
the account would be closed, higher (often due diligence) related costs being passed on to the customer,&#13;
and sometimes terminating relationships with certain clients to be able to maintain access. One bank in&#13;
a small offshore jurisdiction, preemptively closed all its relationships with MTOs, in order not to lose&#13;
its access to USD clearing.&#13;
                   f. Diligence on the customerâ&#128;&#153;s customers (so-called KYCC) and Nested Accounts&#13;
67.     As mentioned in the introduction, the surveys also sought to obtain information from banking&#13;
authorities and large international banks on the extent to which they considered there to be an obligation&#13;
to conduct due diligence on the customerâ&#128;&#153;s customer(s) (in the policy debate surrounding the issue&#13;
&#13;
24.   There are limited options available for replacements and alternative arrangements â&#128;&#147; and these are often more costly&#13;
      options, for example, an alternative means by financial institutions in one jurisdiction is to contract cash courier/ pick-&#13;
      up services. Furthermore, the process for onboarding and establishing new CBRs is costly, including the need for&#13;
      enhanced due diligence and other processes to be undertaken by the banks.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                               Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                                                    38&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
often referred to by shorthand as â&#128;&#156;KYCCâ&#128;&#157; for â&#128;&#156;Know Your Customerâ&#128;&#153;s Customerâ&#128;&#157;)â&#128;&#148;in this case the&#13;
customer(s) of the respondent bank. Since many who responded to the question appeared not to&#13;
understand what was meant by so-called KYCC and provided only an outline of their AML/CFT&#13;
system, an overview here of the responses received is not considered useful. Probably the first issue to&#13;
clarify is what is meant by knowing your customerâ&#128;&#153;s customer(s) in the context of correspondent&#13;
banking.&#13;
68.     One of the main interests of a respondent bank in establishing a correspondent banking&#13;
relationship is that it can offer cross border services to its customersâ&#128;&#148;allowing them (the respondentâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
customers) to transact internationally. It is, in other words, really for the benefit of a third party, the&#13;
customer of the respondent, that the service is then provided. The principle of due diligence with&#13;
regards to correspondent banking is that the correspondent bank conducts due diligence and&#13;
understands the business and internal controls of the respondent bank before establishing a&#13;
correspondent banking relationshipâ&#128;&#148;and then monitors the relationship on an ongoing basis. It is the&#13;
responsibility of the respondent bank to conduct due diligence of its customers, and the correspondent&#13;
always checks the respondent bankâ&#128;&#153;s due diligence system and protocols very carefully, in order to be&#13;
able to rely on them.&#13;
69.     Typically therefore, the correspondent bank merely executes transactions ordered by a&#13;
respondent, and does not conduct any further scrutiny on the underlying transaction. Furthermore it is&#13;
not always possible to identify an underlying transactionâ&#128;&#148;specifically when individual transfers are&#13;
batched into one transfer, such as is the case for remittances for instances, when the bank does one&#13;
transfer that aggregates a whole number of smaller individual transfers. The margins in correspondent&#13;
banking are already thinâ&#128;&#148;and the extra cost of conducting due diligence on every transaction processed&#13;
for a respondent would surely make the whole business unprofitable. More fundamentally though, it&#13;
goes against the logic of the relationship to have the correspondent redo what the respondent already&#13;
did. That is their contractual relationship.&#13;
70.     Pursuant to national AML/CFT and sanctions laws however, the correspondent bank may be&#13;
under an independent obligation to apply sanctions provisions and to report suspicious transactions. 25&#13;
It will have automated systems in place that pick up possible hits against sanctions lists and apply&#13;
certain algorithms to detect suspicious transactions (where it can identify individual transactions - see&#13;
above). The question therefore is what to do when, in processing a payment for a respondent bank, one&#13;
of those systems picks up on e.g., an originator or beneficiary that is on a sanctionâ&#128;&#153;s list, or raises&#13;
ML/FT concerns. Does the correspondent revert to the respondent and ask for and check the due&#13;
diligence on the ultimate clientâ&#128;&#148;or does the correspondent rely on the respondent having conducted&#13;
the necessary due diligence as per its contractual obligation?&#13;
71.     Large international banks mentioned in follow up discussions that although conducting due&#13;
diligence on the customerâ&#128;&#153;s customer is not, in most countries, an obligation that can be found in the&#13;
&#13;
25.   To be clear: under the international standard on anti-money laundering, this would not be the case. FATF Rec 16 on&#13;
      wire transfers, lays out the roles for the different banks involved in a wire transfer: the ordering, the intermediary and&#13;
      the beneficiary financial institution. The correspondent bank would typically be the intermediary financial institution&#13;
      processing a payment on behalf of the ordering institution. The Recommendation is quite clear about the&#13;
      responsibilities of the intermediary institution: It â&#128;&#156;should ensure that all originator and beneficiary information that&#13;
      accompanies a wire transfer is retained with itâ&#128;&#157; and that it take â&#128;&#156;reasonable measures to identify cross border wire&#13;
      transfers that lack required originator or beneficiary informationâ&#128;&#157;. Under this standard there is no obli gation that the&#13;
      intermediary conduct any further scrutiny on the substance of the originator or beneficiary information.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                               Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                                    39&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
lawâ&#128;&#148;banks do conduct such due diligence as a matter of practice in those types of casesâ&#128;&#148;just to be&#13;
on the safe side. It is not clear to such banks that reliance on the respondentâ&#128;&#153;s banks systemsâ&#128;&#148;and a&#13;
showing of the checks that the correspondent has conducted on those systemsâ&#128;&#148;would be a sufficient&#13;
defense if a correspondent is found to have let a sanctioned person conduct a transaction using its&#13;
system. It would be useful if such clarity could be provided.&#13;
72.     The need felt to perform due diligence on the customer of the foreign respondent bank depended&#13;
on the risk profile of the respondent, which itself depends on various factors such as involved&#13;
jurisdictions, the type of the correspondent bank relationship as well as on the services/products that&#13;
are provided by the correspondent bank.&#13;
Nested accounts&#13;
73.      A particular variation on this topic of customerâ&#128;&#153;s customer, is the so-called nested account. A&#13;
nested account, also referred to as a â&#128;&#156;downstream correspondentâ&#128;&#157;, occurs â&#128;&#156;when a correspondent bank&#13;
client provides correspondent services to other banks, domiciled inside or outside their country, to&#13;
facilitate international products and services on behalf of the downstream correspondentâ&#128;&#153;s clients, e.g.&#13;
when a regional savings bank offers correspondent services to the local savings banks in its area.â&#128;&#157; 26 It&#13;
is as it were, a respondent bank acting as a correspondent for another bank.&#13;
74.     The more such nested accounts are inserted into the payment chain, the more tenuous (and more&#13;
opaque) becomes the link between the institution finally processing the payment and the originator of&#13;
that payment. In fact this is one of the concerns with the knock-on effect of the withdrawal from&#13;
correspondent banking. Those whose relationships are being terminated and who can no longer&#13;
establish directly relationships with large international banks may seek to establish nested relationship.&#13;
While from the original correspondent bankâ&#128;&#153;s point of view it may have increased transparency in its&#13;
own operations by severing its ties with the respondent in question, the system as a whole has become&#13;
more opaque if that respondent is allowed to establish a nested relationship.&#13;
75.     It is not clear whether in fact the withdrawal of foreign CBRs is resulting in an increase in nested&#13;
relationships, but it is certainly a concern expressed by some respondents. Three of the large&#13;
international banks specified that they considered nested/downstream correspondents to be high risk&#13;
clients, because they lose sight of the ultimate customer and the diligence conducted on that person.&#13;
While they do not consider themselves under an obligation to perform CDD on the customers of their&#13;
respondents, they are in the process of implementing restrictions on the processing of nested&#13;
transactions. They deem such steps necessary because of their inability to validate the CDD standards&#13;
being applied by the nested account holder (the client of the respondent banks) on the ultimate&#13;
customer. In other words, they consider the level of reassurance that the due diligence conducted on&#13;
the end customer is not adequate.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
26.   See â&#128;&#156;Wolfsberg Anti-Money Laundering Principles for Correspondent Bankingâ&#128;&#157; p6, available                at&#13;
      http://www.wolfsberg-principles.com/pdf/standards/Wolfsberg-Correspondent-Banking-Principles-2014.pdf&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                            Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                                40&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      V.    Conclusions and Recommendations&#13;
76.      The individual stories and anecdotes mentioned in the introduction, appear to be founded in&#13;
reality. Several large international banks are withdrawing from a significant percentage of their foreign&#13;
CBRs and there are sufficient indications from the different groups of respondents that this trend is&#13;
real. Respondentsâ&#128;&#148;particularly from smaller jurisdictionsâ&#128;&#148;but also from some larger economies,&#13;
from the Caribbean, Africa and Europe and Central Asia, and to a lesser extent East Asia and Pacific&#13;
indicate there is a decline in CBRs. From the vostro (provider) perspective, MENA countries were also&#13;
mentioned often (not all relevant MENA countries completed the survey). It is not clear whether this&#13;
development has already reached its peakâ&#128;&#148;or whether further large scale withdrawals are still to come.&#13;
77.     As a result, smaller regional banks are facing challenges offering certain services, notably USD&#13;
payment services, and their customers, particularly MTOs, are affected in their ability to access&#13;
international payment systems. While in the large majority of cases, local/regional banks appear to be&#13;
able to find alternatives and come to some arrangement, that can sometimes come at great cost: in&#13;
purely monetary terms, in terms of the customer base of the respondent bank, in terms of time and effort&#13;
spent finding replacements and in terms of the regional banks own risk having to rely on fewer foreign&#13;
CBRs. The concentration of correspondent banking relationships could become a concern. Smaller&#13;
banks in particular, are very concerned about being at the mercy of only one correspondent bank, who&#13;
can set the terms at will. Moreover, in a very small number of cases the banks do not find replacements&#13;
and they are about to go out of business. On the basis of those two considerations alone, policy action&#13;
to address the situation appears to be justified.&#13;
78.     Quite apart from that, it is not quite clear to what extent the local/regional banks whose&#13;
relationships are being withdrawn are finding second and third-tier banks to meet their needs for foreign&#13;
CBRs and the further effect on overall transparency. The concern is that while large international banks&#13;
might be cleaning up their books and terminating relationships with higher risk customers, that risk is&#13;
then moved to channels that are less transparent, and thus actually increasing overall risk. Though a&#13;
number of respondents, including banking authorities, mentioned these concerns, neither the surveys,&#13;
nor the follow up interviews were able to shed sufficient light upon the extent to which overall&#13;
transparency is decreasing.&#13;
79.     So there is a rationale for further actionâ&#128;&#148;but what intervention is useful or necessary at this&#13;
time (as it is still unclear whether the decline will continue further)? As will have become clear, the&#13;
withdrawal from foreign CBRs is a complex and manifold phenomenon that manifests itself in different&#13;
ways and for different reasons. Some of those reasons are not susceptible to policy tweaks. Banks offer&#13;
correspondent services for different reasons: many banks offer them only to support the cross selling&#13;
of other products to respondent banks or to support the needs of corporate customers for cross border&#13;
payments. If a large international bank decides to withdraw from a country and sever its foreign CBRs&#13;
because there is no other business there to support, then it is not for any outside party to try and cajole&#13;
the bank into maintaining them.&#13;
80.    And even if a bank is in principle willing to do business, but decides not to because the&#13;
compliance costs are too high or because the risk profile of the entity it is dealing with, is too high and&#13;
not manageable, there will still be individual cases in which a bank is completely justified not doing&#13;
so. There are risks that should not be taken.&#13;
81.    The issue to consider is whether in other casesâ&#128;&#148;particularly where applicable rules or facts and&#13;
circumstances are unclear, but there is in principle a business and risk related rationale for engagement,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                          Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                               41&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
there is something that authorities or the banks themselves could do to encourage the establishment of&#13;
a correspondent banking relationship. It is important to emphasize that this is a joint public-private&#13;
responsibility that needs to be dealt with in partnership. Only such an approach with efforts by all&#13;
actors, can help reverse the decline experienced in certain parts of the world.&#13;
82.     Even between the submission of information in the surveys and some of the follow up&#13;
interviews, several respondents noted that changes had taken place as far as correspondent banking in&#13;
their institution or jurisdiction was concerned. Indications as to what may happen in the near future&#13;
were mixed. Some respondents indicated the large scale withdrawal from correspondent banking was&#13;
over- others indicated that much more is yet to come. This area of the international payments system is&#13;
undergoing rapid change.&#13;
83.     Therefore, the World Bank will continue to monitor developments over the next year, and seek&#13;
to gather information from all relevant actors in this field to contribute to the international policy&#13;
discussion surrounding this topic. Where possible, it will seek to provide more insight into the further&#13;
effects on financial inclusion and economic activity resulting from the withdrawal of CBRs. Further&#13;
work could include amongst others a more detailed examination of the effects of the withdrawal of&#13;
CBR on the flows and costs of remittances and on the provision of trade finance (and possible economic&#13;
cost thereof). In addition the following actions by supervisors, authorities and banks could contribute&#13;
to improving the situation.&#13;
Supervisors should ensure banks follow a risk based approach&#13;
84.      Whether justified or not, large international banks indicate that they are uncertain what the&#13;
consequences would be if, through the provision of foreign CBR-services, they were facilitating the&#13;
movement of tainted funds, or funds linked to a sanctioned jurisdiction, person or entity. They argue&#13;
that, even when they have conducted a solid risk assessment and are dealing with the respondent&#13;
institution accordingly, they can be penalized if that respondent institution has accepted funds from a&#13;
money launderer or a sanctions evader. In that view, they need to get it right 100 percent of the time&#13;
and are on the hook for every failure.&#13;
85.     This strikes at the heart of a risk based approach. A risk based approach requires institutions to&#13;
determine the risk level of a certain customer and take proportionate action to address that risk. A&#13;
financial institution needs to have the systems in place to gather information to be able to determine&#13;
the risk, and ensure it acts accordingly to address it. Those systems evolve according to the money&#13;
laundering methods detected and cannot be foolproof. Thus, provided an institution can show it acted&#13;
reasonably in determining risk and mitigating it, failures to detect individual instances of money&#13;
laundering should not automatically trigger penalties.&#13;
86.      An unequivocal statement from national supervisors that there wonâ&#128;&#153;t be a zero tolerance&#13;
approach for failures to detect money laundering and setting out the tenets for a reasonable risk&#13;
assessment for establishing correspondent banking relationships, can provide banks with the comfort&#13;
they say they are lacking at this moment. The mere fact that a bank dealt with tainted funds is not in&#13;
itself sufficient to conclude that the bank in question â&#128;&#156;should have knownâ&#128;&#157;. This also implies that the&#13;
standard setter and the national AML/CFT policy makers clarify the acceptable level of risk tolerance.&#13;
87.    The withdrawal of CBRs is also driven by legitimate risk-based decisions by correspondent&#13;
banks, based on an individual risk assessment of their respondent banks. In such cases, making sure&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                          Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                                                42&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
that respondent banks improve their own AML/CFT internal controls and reduce their risk profile is&#13;
paramount.&#13;
88.      As noted earlier, banks may be completely justified withdrawing correspondent banking&#13;
relationships. It should not, however, be conducted in a wholesale, categorical manner that terminates&#13;
all relationships with certain categories of customer. The AML/CFT supervisor should verify this in its&#13;
supervision. While the decision to establish a relationship is ultimately a commercial decision,&#13;
wholesale de-risking is a sign that a bank is in fact not capable of conducting a proper risk assessment-&#13;
based on an individual appraisal of the situation.27 In addition it may give rise to concerns about&#13;
breaches of consumer protection or competition legislation.28&#13;
Supervisors and other authorities should ensure the effective implementation of international&#13;
AML/CFT standards&#13;
89.     Concerns about the implementation of AML/CFT obligations by countries and jurisdictions&#13;
featured prominently among the reasons large international banks are withdrawing from correspondent&#13;
banking relationships. All jurisdictions must therefore ensure that the legal and regulatory AML/CFT&#13;
framework is in place and that their financial institutions are being effectively supervised for&#13;
compliance with those obligations. For jurisdictions that believe they are unfairly being considered&#13;
high risk because of actual or perceived AML/CFT compliance lapses, it is especially important to&#13;
demonstrate to their counterpart regulators, to foreign financial institutions and to the public at large&#13;
the reforms that have been implemented or to correct misperceptions. Particularly for small&#13;
jurisdictions, compliance lapses â&#128;&#147; actual or alleged â&#128;&#147; by even one financial institution can have a&#13;
potential spillover effects for other financial institutions in the jurisdiction.&#13;
90.     For financial institutions, especially the smaller ones deemed more vulnerable to having their&#13;
relationships terminated solely on the basis of lack of sufficient business diversity and volume, effective&#13;
compliance with AML/CFT standards is essential. Internal controls systems need to be in place. Staff&#13;
from both the business lines and compliance units should be properly trained to know and be in line&#13;
with both the AML/CFT requirements of their respective jurisdictions and those of their CBR service&#13;
providersâ&#128;&#153; jurisdictions.&#13;
91.     The World Bank has a long track record providing technical assistance to countries to put in&#13;
place AML/CFT systems, to implement them effectively and to train relevant authorities, including to&#13;
conduct ML/FT national risk assessments. Countries are encouraged to avail themselves of this&#13;
assistance to improve their AML/CFT systems.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
27.   See in that sense the statement from the Reserve Bank of New Zealand: â&#128;&#156;It seems unlikely, but if banks are using&#13;
      blanket de-risking itself as a procedure to manage and mitigate those risks, then the Reserve Bank would consider that&#13;
      an inadequate means of complying with their obligations under the AML/CFT Act.â&#128;&#157;, available at&#13;
      http://www.rbnz.govt.nz/news/2015/6004856.html&#13;
28.   See in that sense the statement from the Financial Conduct Authorit y in the UK: â&#128;&#156;(â&#128;¦) we now consider during our&#13;
      AML work whether firmsâ&#128;&#153; de-risking strategies give rise to consumer protection and/or competition issues.â&#128;&#157; available&#13;
      at https://www.fca.org.uk/about/what/enforcing/money-laundering/derisking. Further, there may be other types of&#13;
      protection- e.g. non-discrimination provisions. The second European Payment Services Directive contains provisions&#13;
      that address account denials and closures of accounts of payment service providers, including money remitters. It&#13;
      requires European Member States to ensure that credit institutions provide payment service providers with non-&#13;
      discriminatory and proportionate access to payment accounts. The access must be extensive enough to allow payment&#13;
      institutions to provide payment services in an unhindered and efficient manner. Where any payment service provider&#13;
      is rejected, the credit institution must provide the competent authority with duly motivated reasons for its decision.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                              Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                                    43&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Supervisors should provide clarity on the extent of due diligence on the customerâ&#128;&#153;s customer&#13;
(KYCC obligations)&#13;
92.      Along those same lines, supervisors should provide detailed guidance on the extent to which,&#13;
or the circumstances under which, banks should conduct risk-based due diligence on the customers of&#13;
a respondent bank, the so-called â&#128;&#156;know-your-customerâ&#128;&#153;s-customerâ&#128;&#157; obligation, and what it would&#13;
entail. In other words, supervisors should set out under what conditions, if any, it is incumbent upon a&#13;
correspondent bank to go further than only conducting due diligence on the respondent bank. Given the&#13;
exceptional nature of this obligation, the supervisor should provide clear risk-based guidance on the&#13;
circumstances under which it might apply. If the supervisor does not consider it ever to apply to its&#13;
institutions, then it should say so clearly- leaving no room for misinterpretation or misunderstanding.&#13;
93.     Concern about the respondentâ&#128;&#153;s customer also underlies the high-risk customer base of the&#13;
respondent bank as a driver for withdrawing from CBRs. Large international banks rated this factor&#13;
third and nearly all of the banks that further specified classes of customers that they considered high&#13;
risk indicated that MTOs fell into this category. The current work in FATF on guidance to MTOs is&#13;
very welcome, but will only usefully contribute to this discussion if it leads to more clarity on risk&#13;
differentiation. Well regulated and supervised MTOs should not be systematically considered as high&#13;
risk. Increased communication and outreach on supervisory practices and actions, particularly in the&#13;
case of MTOs, could further contribute to more differentiated risk decision making by banks.&#13;
Improve the information position of large international/correspondent banks&#13;
Banks should use technical tools to limit information challenges and lower costs&#13;
94.    A lack of knowledge and understanding of the entity that is seeking to establish a foreign CBR&#13;
contributes to a risk averse attitude. Conducting thorough due diligence of a prospective respondent&#13;
can be expensive. The more readily accessible the relevant information, the lower those costs. The&#13;
CPMI will shortly be issuing a report on the use of enhanced technological tools to limit information&#13;
challenges and use facilities offered by third parties to have the relevant information promptly available&#13;
and at much lower cost. This report will be an important contribution to this debate and its&#13;
recommendations on the use of KYC utilities and the Legal Entity Identifier are endorsed here. 29&#13;
Increase information exchange between correspondent banks and respondent banks and supervisory&#13;
authorities&#13;
95.     A further source of information for the large international banks that are providers of&#13;
correspondent banking services are the respondent banks themselves. Banks noted that there is greater&#13;
communication among the compliance staff of provider and client banks and in a more direct manner.&#13;
In this regard, it is significant that for example, Mexico has adopted legislation which removes legal&#13;
barriers to information sharing by its domestic banks with their foreign correspondent banks. Countries&#13;
should consider how they might allow for such exchange of information without breaching data&#13;
protection and privacy rules.&#13;
96.    In addition the setting up of working groups consisting of banking authorities and major&#13;
correspondent banks in the most relevant jurisdictions where higher restrictions are being imposed was&#13;
mentioned by one respondent. Such contacts have allowed all involved to reach a common&#13;
understanding on the interpretation and implementation of regulatory requirements imposed by the&#13;
&#13;
29.   See Annex 11 for the current list of recommendations included in the consultative CPMI report.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                              Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                              44&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
foreign jurisdiction and to promote the development of best practices that foreign correspondent and&#13;
domestic respondent banks should follow to maintain CBRs.&#13;
97.     One supervisory authority suggested that correspondent banks reach out to the supervisor of a&#13;
prospective respondent bank, if there are concerns about the risk level of that bank. Given&#13;
confidentiality requirements, likely an explicit approval from the respondent bank to allow the&#13;
supervisor to provide the relevant information would be required. It would appear in the bankâ&#128;&#153;s interest&#13;
though to give its approval for that transmission of information. Correspondent banks should consider&#13;
foreign supervisors as a potential source of information on their respondent banks. In addition,&#13;
supervisors should coordinate to clarify regulatory expectations and facilitate international exchange&#13;
of information.&#13;
Banking authorities of respondent banks should provide information on the country risk profile and&#13;
how higher risks are being addressed&#13;
98.     In assessing the risk of a prospective respondent bank, correspondent banks include&#13;
consideration of the risk profile of the country in which it is based. The international standards on&#13;
money laundering and terrorism financing oblige countries to assess their risk and to take action to&#13;
mitigate the identified risks. Many countries are currently in the process of conducting such risk&#13;
assessments and drawing up their action plans. Though countries are not obliged to publish this risk&#13;
assessment, it is recommended that countries do so, both to demonstrate their commitment to&#13;
AML/CFT and to inform outsiders of the risks they face and their plans for mitigating them. Moreover,&#13;
publication of such an assessment provides an opportunity for the country to highlight how it is&#13;
implementing AML/CFT standards. Indeed a number of authorities mentioned that they intended to&#13;
use their national risk assessment as part of their policy to address the withdrawal of correspondent&#13;
banking and problems faced by their remittance companies. The World Bank has developed a capacity&#13;
building tool for conducting a national risk assessment, which has so far been delivered in 40 countries&#13;
or jurisdictions, and stands ready to assist countries in this process.&#13;
Correspondent banks should take into account respondentâ&#128;&#153;s business needs when deciding to&#13;
terminate a foreign CBR&#13;
Provide transparency on reasons for termination&#13;
99.     Several respondents from smaller banks indicated that the reasons for termination of a CBR&#13;
were not always provided, making it hard for them to understand why a relationship was being&#13;
terminated and how to improve their situation. Possibly this fact also explains why money laundering&#13;
and financial integrity related concerns featured less prominently among the reasons provided by&#13;
local/regional banks as driving de-risking than it featured among the reasons provided by large&#13;
international banks. In order to enable the smaller banks to address possible outside concerns on&#13;
AML/CFT, large international banks are encouraged to be more transparent about the reasons for&#13;
terminating a foreign CBR relationship.&#13;
Consider longer notice periods&#13;
100.    Many of the smaller respondent banks mentioned that when their relationships are terminated&#13;
they are sometimes given only 30 days after the correspondent bank announces its intention to terminate&#13;
the relationship. For those banks maintaining only a few foreign CBRs, that can make it very hard to&#13;
find alternatives. Even when banks have an existing CBR to which they can shift their business, time&#13;
is needed to arrange for increase in credit and number transactions that the existing CBR is able and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                          Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                               45&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
willing to provide. The longer notice period is of greater importance in smaller jurisdictions or where&#13;
options for alternatives are limited. Moreover, the loss of a foreign CBR without replacement can result&#13;
in only a few channels being available to a respondent bank, thus becoming dangerously dependent on&#13;
only a few or sometimes just one institution. In order to provide smaller banks with more room for&#13;
maneuver and more time to undertake a careful review of the options available to them, large&#13;
international banks are encouraged to extend their notice period to at least three months- preferably&#13;
more, and could during that period place limits as described below.&#13;
Consider placing limits instead of terminating altogether&#13;
101.    Large international banks that are the providers of foreign correspondent banking services&#13;
should consider placing appropriate credit and other limits/conditions on their client banks, rather than&#13;
terminating the relationships. Placing conditions on a relationship is considered preferable to&#13;
straightforward termination and a trial period can be a pragmatic and efficient way to deal with possible&#13;
AML/CFT related concerns.&#13;
Consider establishing relationships at the parent level&#13;
102.    In order to meet the large international banksâ&#128;&#153; requirements for business volume/size, some&#13;
banks indicated they had established the CBR at the parent level, when the correspondent was unwilling&#13;
to establish it at the subsidiary level because of the low volume. In that way they were able to&#13;
consolidate the volume of transactions from the various branches and subsidiaries in other jurisdictions&#13;
and improving the risk/reward determination. It is recommended that other banks also explore the&#13;
possibility of this solution when volumes of an individual subsidiary bank are too low to justify the&#13;
establishment of a CBR.&#13;
Authorities should monitor the status of correspondent banking in their jurisdiction&#13;
103.    Finally, though not directly addressing the drivers of de-risking, it would improve the overall&#13;
ability of governments and private actors to take action if countries were to more systematically gather&#13;
information on the status of foreign CBRs. The surveys overall met with a positive response but not all&#13;
jurisdictions responded, and among the respondents, a not insignificant number indicated that they&#13;
lacked systematic data to be able to complete the survey.&#13;
104.     Authorities and financial institutions that do not already do so, should consider taking a&#13;
proactive approach in communicating with one another to monitor foreign CBR related developments&#13;
in their own jurisdiction and jurisdictions of their CBR counterparts, as well as developments at the&#13;
regional and global levels. This holds especially true for smaller jurisdictions, with fewer and smaller&#13;
institutions which appear to be most susceptible to trends in CBRs â&#128;&#147; since they cannot always meet the&#13;
business volume/profitability requirements of the large international banks that are their correspondent&#13;
banking products/services providers. For the smaller institutions and jurisdictions, even the loss of a&#13;
small number of CBRs can have a greater impact for all concerned. Authorities should focus their&#13;
monitoring efforts on the banks with very few or only one or two CBRs, that are heavily dependent,&#13;
and at the mercy of, the correspondent banks who can set the terms almost at will. And where necessary&#13;
assist them in their efforts to establish or maintain foreign CBRs. In addition it would be useful to&#13;
monitor to what extent banks whose foreign CBRs are being terminated or restricted, are finding&#13;
alternatives with second and third tier foreign banks, or are establishing connections with other banks&#13;
to use them as their gateway for foreign CBR services in so-called nested CBRs.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                          Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                               46&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Annex 1: Method followed&#13;
1.      To initiate the fact gathering exercise, the WB and the FSB organized a roundtable meeting in&#13;
Washington DC at the margins of the WB/IMF Spring Meetings, on April 16, 2015. The objective of&#13;
this event was to discuss the size, scope and drivers of decline in correspondent banking and other&#13;
cross-border financial services and possible policy responses. Governors and other regional and&#13;
national banking authorities, as well as representatives from the Financial Action Task Force (the&#13;
standard setter on Anti-Money Laundering and Combating the Financing of Terrorism â&#128;&#147; AML/CFT)&#13;
and the World Economic Forum, the Basel Committee on Banking Supervision and the Committee on&#13;
Payments and Market Infrastructures (CPMI) participated in that event. On the basis of the observations&#13;
made at that meeting and of the media reports mentioned earlier, the WB worked with FSB and CPMI&#13;
to put together two surveys: one for banking authorities and one for large international banks. A third&#13;
survey was designed specifically for smaller local (i.e. presence in one jurisdiction) and regional banks&#13;
to try and ascertain the impact of the decline trend on these financial institutions.&#13;
2.    Beginning in June 2015 and through October 2015, the surveys were sent, on behalf of the&#13;
CPMI, the FSB and the WB, to 3 groups of respondents:&#13;
   ï&#130;·   Central banking authorities of jurisdictions, including those which were believed to be home&#13;
       to banks that are themselves terminating relationships, as well as jurisdictions home to banks&#13;
       whose relationships are being terminated by other banks (including as identified in the results&#13;
       of the large international banks survey), and/or members of the FSB Regional Consultative&#13;
       Groups. In addition to completing the survey, these authorities were also asked to identify five&#13;
       to ten banks in their jurisdiction for whom the authorities believed that the topic of a withdrawal&#13;
       from correspondent banking might be particularly relevant.&#13;
   ï&#130;·   Large international banks which were allegedly withdrawing from foreign correspondent&#13;
       banking on a significant scale (and some others who are among the top providers of&#13;
       correspondent banking services for whom the trend was unclear from public reports), and&#13;
       primarily geared towards obtaining information on their vostro accounts (that is to say, those&#13;
       providing a service to another bank), and&#13;
   ï&#130;·   Local/regional banks whose home jurisdictions were identified in the authorities and large&#13;
       international banks surveys as affected by the withdrawal of correspondent banking and whose&#13;
       contact information was provided by their banking authorities. This survey was primarily&#13;
       geared towards obtaining information on their nostro accounts (that is to say those where they&#13;
       are receiving a service from another bank). Beyond gathering information on size and drivers,&#13;
       the objective of this survey was specifically to find out information on the ability of banks to&#13;
       find alternatives when their relationships had been terminated or restricted.&#13;
&#13;
3.      Extensive outreach was conducted to clarify some of the responses received. Because the&#13;
responses to questions on possible policy actions and on finding alternative correspondent banking&#13;
relationships were not always complete, a further series of follow-up interviews by telephone was&#13;
conducted from late September to mid-October with relevant bank and country respondents.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                          Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                                                   47&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Annex 2: Participating Banking Authorities30&#13;
&#13;
                                            Jurisdictions&#13;
 Afghanistan                   Grenada / ECCB                           Paraguay&#13;
 Albania                       Guatemala                                Peru&#13;
 Andorra                       Guyana                                   Philippines&#13;
 Anguilla / ECCB[1]            Haiti                                    Russian Federation&#13;
 Antigua and Barbuda           Hong Kong SAR, China                     Saudi Arabia&#13;
 Argentina                     India                                    Seychelles&#13;
 Armenia                       Indonesia                                Singapore&#13;
 Australia                     Italy                                    South Africa&#13;
 Bahamas, The                  Jamaica                                  Spain&#13;
 Bahrain                       Japan                                    St. Kitts and Nevis / ECCB&#13;
 Bangladesh                    Jordan                                   St. Lucia / ECCB&#13;
 Barbados                      Kazakhstan                               St. Vincent and the Grenadines /&#13;
                                                                        ECCB&#13;
 Bermuda                   Kenya                                        Sudan&#13;
 Bolivia                   Korea, Republic of                           Switzerland&#13;
 Brazil                    Latvia                                       Tanzania&#13;
 British Virgin Islands    Lebanon                                      Thailand&#13;
 Bulgaria                  Liechtenstein                                Trinidad and Tobago&#13;
 Canada                    Lithuania                                    Tunisia&#13;
 Cape Verde                Macedonia, former Yugoslav                   Turkey&#13;
                           Republic of&#13;
 Cayman Islands            Maldives                                     Uganda&#13;
 Chile                     Mauritius                                    Ukraine&#13;
 China                     Mexico                                       United Kingdom&#13;
 Colombia                  Moldova                                      United States&#13;
 Comoros                   Montenegro                                   Uruguay&#13;
 Costa Rica                Montserrat / ECCB                            Vietnam&#13;
 Dominica / ECCB           Morocco                                      West Bank and Gaza&#13;
 Dominican Republic        Namibia                                      Zimbabwe&#13;
 Ecuador                   Netherlands&#13;
 Fiji                      New Zealand&#13;
 France                    Nigeria&#13;
 Georgia                   Pakistan&#13;
 Greece                    Panama&#13;
Note: [1] Eastern Caribbean Central Bank.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
30&#13;
  These jurisdictions agreed to be listed as participants to the survey. In addition one jurisdiction completed the&#13;
questionnaire as a commercial entity. By agreeing to be listed, the jurisdictions are not implying agreement or&#13;
endorsement of any of the findings or conclusions contained herein.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                               Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;  Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
  Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                                   48&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Annex 3: Banking Authorities- Regional breakdown&#13;
  Changes in the scale and breadth of their foreign correspondent banking relationships, including the&#13;
  number of nostro accounts held.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                      Outreach: Banking Authorities&#13;
  Region         Survey         Survey              No                Survey            Unable to      No&#13;
                  sent         completed        completed           completed           complete-   response&#13;
                  out             (#)             survey,              as a              lack of       (#)&#13;
                   (#)                           provided          commercial            data (#)&#13;
                                                   bank              entity (#)&#13;
                                                  contact&#13;
                                               information&#13;
                                                  only (#)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Africa           26            11              6                   1                    n/a         8&#13;
Response rate: 69%&#13;
East Asia        19            12              1                   n/a                  1           5&#13;
&amp; Pacific&#13;
&#13;
Response rate: 74%&#13;
Europe &amp;         18            13              1                   n/a                  n/a         4&#13;
Central&#13;
Asia&#13;
Response rate: 78%&#13;
Latin            35            32              1                   n/a                  n/a         2&#13;
America&#13;
and&#13;
Caribbean&#13;
Response rate: 94%&#13;
Middle           19            7               5                   n/a                  n/a         7&#13;
East &amp;&#13;
North&#13;
Africa&#13;
Response rate: 63%&#13;
South Asia       7             5               1                   n/a                  n/a         1&#13;
Response rate: 86%&#13;
Rest of           13           11              1                   n/a                  1           n/a&#13;
World&#13;
Response rate: 100%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                            Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                                     49&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   Banking Authorities- Regional breakdown: Changes in the scale and breadth of their foreign&#13;
   correspondent banking relationships, including the number of nostro accounts held.&#13;
   Region                         Significant      Some           No                  Significant   Unknown&#13;
                                  decline          decline        significant         increase&#13;
                                                                  change&#13;
   Africa&#13;
   Number of Responses&#13;
                                  5                1              5                   1             n/a&#13;
   (#)&#13;
   (Out of 12 respondents)&#13;
   Percentage (%)                 42%              8%             42%                 8%            n/a&#13;
   Europe &amp; Central Asia&#13;
   Number of Responses&#13;
                                  4                5              3                   n/a           1&#13;
   (#)&#13;
   (Out of 13 respondents)&#13;
   Percentage (%)                 31%              38%            23%                 n/a           8%&#13;
   East Asia &amp; Pacific&#13;
   Number of Responses&#13;
                                  2                3              5                   n/a           2&#13;
   (#)&#13;
   (Out of 12 respondents)&#13;
   Percentage (%)                 17%              25%            42%                 n/a           16%&#13;
   Latin America and              16               3              9                   1             3&#13;
   Caribbean&#13;
   Number of responses(#)&#13;
   (Out of 32 respondents)&#13;
   Total (%)                      50%              10%            28%                 3%            9%&#13;
   Middle East &amp; North&#13;
   Africa&#13;
   Number of Responses            1                4              2                   n/a           n/a&#13;
   (#)&#13;
   (Out of 7 respondents)&#13;
   Percentage (%)                 14%              57%            29%                 n/a           n/a&#13;
   South Asia&#13;
   Number of Responses&#13;
                                  1                2              2                   n/a           n/a&#13;
   (#)&#13;
   (Out of 5 respondents)&#13;
   Percentage (%)                 20%              40%            40%                 n/a           n/a&#13;
   Rest of World&#13;
   Number of Responses&#13;
                                  3                n/a            4                   n/a           4&#13;
   (#)&#13;
   (Out of 11 respondents)&#13;
   Percentage (%)                 28%              n/a            36%                 n/a           36%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                          Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                                   50&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   Authorities Survey: Overall trend&#13;
&#13;
          Trend in foreign CBRs                       Responses (#)                   Responses (%)&#13;
     Increased Significantly                                2                                2&#13;
     Declined Significantly                                32                               35&#13;
     Some Decline                                          17                               19&#13;
     No Significant Change                                 30                               33&#13;
     Unknown                                                9                               10&#13;
     No Response                                            1                                1&#13;
     Total                                                 91                              100&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                          Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                                  51&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Annex 4: Local/ Regional Banks - Outreach/ Completed Surveys&#13;
 Local/Regional Banks Invited (#)            433&#13;
 Local/Regional Bank Surveys Completed       170&#13;
 Jurisdictions of Local/ Regional Banks&#13;
 Completed                                   61&#13;
 Completed Survey %                         39%&#13;
&#13;
                                Jurisdiction Completed Surveys Breakdown&#13;
                                       Completed                                        Completed&#13;
       Country/Jurisdiction           Survey Bank      Country/Jurisdiction            Survey Bank&#13;
                                        Responses                                       Responses&#13;
       Albania                              2          Kenya                                5&#13;
       Andorra                              4          Kuwait                               5&#13;
       Angola                               1          Latvia                               6&#13;
       Anguilla                             1          Liechtenstein                        3&#13;
       Antigua                              1          Lithuania                            1&#13;
       Armenia                              2          Macedonia FYR                        6&#13;
       Bahamas                              2          Maldives                             4&#13;
       Bahrain                              1          Mali                                 1&#13;
       Barbados                             3          Mauritius                            2&#13;
       Belarus                              2          Mexico                               2&#13;
       Belize                               1          Montenegro                           3&#13;
       Bermuda                              3          Namibia                              6&#13;
       Bulgaria                             1          Niger                                1&#13;
       Burkina Faso                         2          Nigeria                              3&#13;
       Cambodia                             5          Panama                               1&#13;
       Cape Verde                           5          Paraguay                             1&#13;
       Cayman Islands                       3          Peru                                 4&#13;
       Cyprus                               3          Qatar                                4&#13;
       Dominican Republic                   1          Seychelles                           1&#13;
       Georgia                              5          Sri Lanka                            3&#13;
       Germany                              1          St. Lucia                            1&#13;
                                                       St. Vincent &amp;&#13;
       Greece                               4                                               1&#13;
                                                       Grenadines&#13;
       Guatemala                            1          Suriname                             6&#13;
       Guyana                               2          Thailand                             2&#13;
       Haiti                                1          Trinidad                             2&#13;
       Iraq                                 1          Uganda                               5&#13;
       Israel                               2          UK                                   3&#13;
       Ivory Coast                          1          Ukraine                              2&#13;
       Jamaica                              4          United Arab Emirates                 1&#13;
                                                       West African Regional&#13;
       Jordan                               6                                               1&#13;
                                                       Bank&#13;
                                                       Zimbabwe                             13&#13;
                                                       Totals                              170&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                           Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                                        52&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Annex 5: Banking Authorities - Jurisdictions of terminations/restrictions&#13;
&#13;
                Jurisdiction                     Responses (#)                  Responses (% of 43 total&#13;
                                                                                     respondents)&#13;
        United States31                                 36                               84%&#13;
        United Kingdom                                  18                               42%&#13;
        France                                           9                               21%&#13;
        Germany                                          8                               19%&#13;
        Canada                                           5                               12%&#13;
        Italy                                            5                               12%&#13;
        Spain                                            5                               12%&#13;
        European Union                                   4                                9%&#13;
        Switzerland                                      4                                9%&#13;
        Netherlands                                      3                                7%&#13;
        Australia                                        2                                5%&#13;
        Belgium                                          2                                5%&#13;
        China                                            2                                5%&#13;
        Ireland                                          2                                5%&#13;
        Hong Kong SAR, China                             2                                5%&#13;
        Sweden                                           2                                5%&#13;
        United Arab Emirates                             2                                5%&#13;
        Bahrain                                          1                                2%&#13;
        Guernsey                                         1                                2%&#13;
        Japan                                            1                                2%&#13;
        Luxembourg                                       1                                2%&#13;
        Portugal                                         1                                2%&#13;
        Saudi Arabia                                     1                                2%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
31&#13;
     This has to be understood in the context of the US being the largest provider of foreign CBRs.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                                   53&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Annex 6: Local/Regional Banks: List of Jurisdictions â&#128;&#147; Termination and restrictions of CBRs&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 List of Jurisdictions -&#13;
 Terminated CBRs&#13;
 Jurisdictions mentioned by&#13;
 Respondents                           Responses (#)        Responses (%)&#13;
 US32                                       66                  67%&#13;
 UK                                         30                  30%&#13;
 Switzerland                                14                  14%&#13;
 Canada                                     13                  13%&#13;
 Germany                                    13                  13%&#13;
 France                                     8                    8%&#13;
 Netherlands                                8                    8%&#13;
 South Africa                               8                    8%&#13;
 Europe                                     5                    5%&#13;
 Australia                                  5                    5%&#13;
 Europe                                     5                    5%&#13;
 Sweden                                     5                    5%&#13;
 Austria                                    4                    4%&#13;
 Belgium                                    4                    4%&#13;
 Hong Kong SAR, China                       4                    4%&#13;
 Italy                                      3                    3%&#13;
 Norway                                     3                    3%&#13;
 Russian Federation                         3                    3%&#13;
 Cyprus                                     2                    2%&#13;
 Spain                                      2                    2%&#13;
 Botswana                                   1                    1%&#13;
 Caribbean                                  1                    1%&#13;
 Denmark                                    1                    1%&#13;
 Greece                                     1                    1%&#13;
 India                                      1                    1%&#13;
 Japan                                      1                    1%&#13;
 Latvia                                     1                    1%&#13;
 Luxembourg                                 1                    1%&#13;
 Mauritius                                  1                    1%&#13;
 New Zealand                                1                    1%&#13;
 Singapore                                  1                    1%&#13;
 Turkey                                     1                    1%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
32&#13;
     This has to be understood in the context of the US being the largest provider of foreign CBRs.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                 Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                   54&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    Foreign FI Restricted Size/Scope of CBRs&#13;
                                                           Responses (#)&#13;
 No                                                             56&#13;
 Yes                                                            76&#13;
 No Response/Not Applicable                                     38&#13;
 Total Responses                                                       170&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          Local/Regional Banks: Foreign Financial Institutions&#13;
                         Restricted CBRs (%)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                         No Response/Not&#13;
                            Applicable                 No&#13;
                               22%                    33%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   Yes&#13;
                                   45%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                          Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                                   55&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
List of Jurisdictions - Restricted CBRs&#13;
&#13;
 Jurisdictions mentioned by&#13;
 Respondents                            Responses (#)&#13;
 US33                                       41&#13;
 UK                                         20&#13;
 Germany                                    15&#13;
 Switzerland                                 8&#13;
 Europe                                      7&#13;
 Canada                                      6&#13;
 France                                      6&#13;
 South Africa                                6&#13;
 China                                       4&#13;
 Spain                                       4&#13;
 Netherlands                                 3&#13;
 Austria                                     3&#13;
 Italy                                       2&#13;
 Mauritius                                   2&#13;
 Russian Federation                          2&#13;
 Australia                                   1&#13;
 Hong Kong SAR, China                        1&#13;
 Portugal                                    1&#13;
 Bahrain                                     1&#13;
 Belgium                                     1&#13;
 Scandinavia                                 1&#13;
 Poland                                      1&#13;
 Asia                                        1&#13;
 Far East                                    1&#13;
 Denmark                                     1&#13;
 Turkey                                      1&#13;
 Singapore                                   1&#13;
 Puerto Rico                                 1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
33&#13;
     This has to be understood in the context of the US being the largest provider of foreign CBRs.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                 Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                                                     56&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                Local/Regional Banks: Jurisdictions of Restrictions&#13;
                    60%&#13;
                          54%&#13;
&#13;
                    50%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    40%&#13;
   Percentage (%)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    30%&#13;
                            26%&#13;
&#13;
                                20%&#13;
                    20%&#13;
&#13;
                                  11%&#13;
                                        9% 8% 8% 8%&#13;
                    10%&#13;
                                                      5% 5% 4% 4%&#13;
                                                                    3% 3% 3%&#13;
                                                                               1% 1% 1% 1% 1% 1% 1% 1% 1% 1% 1% 1% 1%&#13;
                    0%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     Singapore&#13;
                                            USA&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         Turkey&#13;
                                     Mauritius&#13;
                                        Canada&#13;
                                         France&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                           Italy&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                      Australia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   Scandinavia&#13;
                                          China&#13;
                                          Spain&#13;
                                        Austria&#13;
                                             UK&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                  Netherlands&#13;
                                      Germany&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                            Asia&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                      Denmark&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         Poland&#13;
&#13;
                                   Puerto Rico&#13;
                                   Switzerland&#13;
                                        Europe&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                            Russian Federation&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       Belgium&#13;
&#13;
                                       Far East&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       Portugal&#13;
                                        Bahrain&#13;
                                  South Africa&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                          Hong Kong SAR, China&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                    Jurisdiction&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                           Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                                    57&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Annex 7: Banking Authorities â&#128;&#147; Causes/ Drivers of termination/restriction of foreign CBRs&#13;
                    Cause/Driver                           Responses (#)               Responses (% - 44&#13;
                                                                                       total respondents)&#13;
     Lack of profitability of certain foreign CBR                28                          64%&#13;
     services/products&#13;
     Overall risk appetite of correspondent                      24                          55%&#13;
&#13;
     Changes to legal, regulatory or supervisory                 21                          48%&#13;
     requirements in correspondentâ&#128;&#153;s jurisdiction&#13;
     that have implications for maintaining CBRs&#13;
&#13;
     Concerns about ML/TF risks                                  21                          48%&#13;
     Inability/ cost for correspondent to                        16                          36%&#13;
     undertake CDD on respondents' customers&#13;
&#13;
     Structural changes to correspondent                         12                          27%&#13;
     (including merger/acquisitions) and/or&#13;
     reorganization of business portfolio&#13;
     Jurisdiction identified as having strategic                 10                          23%&#13;
     AML/CFT deficiencies by FATF (or other&#13;
     international body)&#13;
     Compliance with pre-existing legal/                          8                          18%&#13;
     supervisory / regulatory requirement by&#13;
     correspondent&#13;
     High-risk customer base of respondent                        8                          18%&#13;
&#13;
     Concerns about, or insufficient information                  6                          14%&#13;
     about, respondentâ&#128;&#153;s CDD procedures (for&#13;
     AML/CFT or sanctions purposes)&#13;
     Impact of internationally agreed financial                   6                          14%&#13;
     regulatory reforms (other than AML/CFT)&#13;
     (e.g. capital requirements)&#13;
     Imposition of enforcement actions by the                     4                           9%&#13;
     domestic authority on respondent&#13;
&#13;
     Imposition of international sanctions                        3                           7%&#13;
&#13;
     Sovereign credit risk rating                                 3                           7%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                           Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                                   58&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Annex 8: Local/Regional Banks â&#128;&#147; Causes/ Drivers of termination/restriction of foreign&#13;
    CBRs&#13;
      Causes/Drivers of termination/restriction of foreign CBRs               Responses   Responses&#13;
      by foreign financial institutions                                          (#)         (%)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      Lack of profitability of certain foreign CBR services/products              60        46%&#13;
      Overall risk appetite                                                       48        37%&#13;
      Structural changes to foreign financial institutions                        45        35%&#13;
      Changes to legal, regulatory or supervisory requirements                    40        31%&#13;
      Concerns about ML/TF risks                                                  25        19%&#13;
      Sovereign credit risk rating                                                19        15%&#13;
      Inability/cost to undertake CDD on respondent customers                     19        15%&#13;
      Industry consolidation                                                      17        13%&#13;
      Enforcement actions by Domestic Authority                                   11         8%&#13;
      High risk customer base                                                     11         8%&#13;
&#13;
      International Sanctions                                                     10         8%&#13;
&#13;
      Impact of internationally agreed financial regulatory reforms               10         8%&#13;
&#13;
      Compliance with pre-existing legal/ supervisory / regulatory                10         8%&#13;
      requirement&#13;
      Insufficient information about respondentâ&#128;&#153;s CDD procedures                   8         6%&#13;
      Jurisdiction identified as having â&#128;&#156;Strategic AML/CFT                         5         4%&#13;
      deficienciesâ&#128;&#157; by FATF&#13;
      *N.B. The respondents were allowed to choose multiple&#13;
      options&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                              Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                                 59&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Annex 9: Large International Banks â&#128;&#147; Products/services affected&#13;
        Product/Service            Significantly Moderately            Total -            Total -&#13;
                                   reduced (#)    reduced (#)       Significantly /   Significantly /&#13;
                                                                     Moderately        Moderately&#13;
                                                                     reduced (#)       reduced (%)&#13;
 Check Clearing                         5                7                12               60%&#13;
 Clearing and Settlement                1                5                 6               30%&#13;
 Cash Management Services               2                2                 4               20%&#13;
 International Wire Transfers           1                2                 3               15%&#13;
 Investment Services                    0                3                 3               15%&#13;
 Foreign Exchange Services              0                2                 2               10%&#13;
 Lending                                0                2                 2               10%&#13;
&#13;
 Trade Finance                          1                0                 1               5%&#13;
&#13;
 Structured Finance/Foreign             0                1                 1               5%&#13;
 Investments&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                          Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                                      60&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Annex 10: Client Segment Impact&#13;
        Authorities â&#128;&#147; Client Impact&#13;
&#13;
Money Transfer Operators and Other Remittance Companies and Service providers: 39% percent of respondent&#13;
authorities noted a significant or moderately significant decline in the MTOs clients as a group. Thirty-one&#13;
percent of respondent authorities noted that there was a significant or moderately significant decline in other&#13;
remittance companies/service providers.&#13;
 Client segments most affected by the decline of foreign CBRs (39 total respondents)&#13;
 Client segment            Significant   Moderately Insignificant Not            Total -&#13;
                                             Significant    / No Impact    applicable/   Significantly/Moderately&#13;
                                                                           Unknown       affected (%)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Money Transfer                9             6              9              13            38%&#13;
 Operators (MTOs)&#13;
 Other Remittance              7             5              9              15            31%&#13;
 companies/service&#13;
 providers&#13;
 Small and medium              8             9              7              11            44%&#13;
 domestic banks&#13;
 Small and medium              4             6              8              15            26%&#13;
 exporters&#13;
 Others - Specify&#13;
    Retail Customers           1             1&#13;
    (Students, Foreign&#13;
    Workers, Businessmen&#13;
    etc.)&#13;
    International Business                   1&#13;
    Companies&#13;
    E-gaming/Casino            2&#13;
    types of business&#13;
    Defense Industry                         1&#13;
    Adult Industry                           1&#13;
    Foreign exchange           1&#13;
    services like cambio&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Local/Regional Banks and Client Impact&#13;
Please note that local banks that indicated decline in their overall CBRs as well as a small number of banks that&#13;
did not indicate overall decline responded to the question regarding impact on client segments.&#13;
The respondents indicated that money transfer operators (MTOs) and other remittance companies/service&#13;
providers are most affected; however, a not insignificant number of banks also indicated impact to their clients&#13;
who are small and medium exporters and small and medium domestic banks. Respondents also specified other&#13;
types of clients/client segments including casas de cambios (money exchange houses), importers and PEPs.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                                  61&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                        Significantly and&#13;
                                     Significant   Moderate    Insignificant/No         Moderately&#13;
 Client Segments                       Impact       Impact          Impact      Unknown Affected (%)&#13;
&#13;
 Money Transfer Operators&#13;
 (MTOs) and Other remittance&#13;
 companies                                47           30             110             17   55%&#13;
&#13;
 Small and medium exporters               26           17             66               3   31%&#13;
&#13;
 Small and medium domestic&#13;
 banks                                    11           12             72               9   16%&#13;
&#13;
 Others - Cambios Operators&#13;
 (Money Exchange Houses)                  4            0               0               0   3%&#13;
&#13;
 Others - Corporate clients&#13;
 (exporters, tour operators,&#13;
 food and drink industries)               2            0               0               0   1%&#13;
&#13;
 Others - Importers                       2            0               0               0   1%&#13;
&#13;
 Others - PEPs                            1            0               0               0   1%&#13;
&#13;
 Others - Financial Institutions&#13;
 (Investment Services, FX)                0            1               0               0   1%&#13;
&#13;
 Total Responses as per Impact            93           60             248             29&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                               Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;Withdrawal from Correspondent Banking&#13;
Where, Why, and What to Do about It                                                                            62&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Annex 11: Recommendations included in Consultative Report Correspondent Banking&#13;
  published by the CPMI34&#13;
â&#128;¢ Recommendation on the use of KYC utilities: The use of KYC utilities in general - provided that they store&#13;
at least a minimum set of up-to-date and accurate information - can be supported as an effective means to reduce&#13;
the burden of compliance with some KYC procedures for banks active in correspondent banking business.&#13;
Relevant stakeholders (eg the Wolfsberg Group) may review the templates and procedures used by the different&#13;
utilities and identify the most appropriate data fields to compile a data set that all utilities should collect as best&#13;
practice and that all banks have to be ready to provide to banks which require the information.&#13;
â&#128;¢ Recommendation on the use of the LEI in correspondent banking: In addition to the general promotion of&#13;
LEIs for legal entities, relevant stakeholders may consider specifically promoting the use of the LEI for all banks&#13;
involved in correspondent banking as a means of identification which should be provided in KYC utilities and&#13;
information-sharing arrangements. In a cross-border context, this measure is ideally to be coordinated and&#13;
applied simultaneously in a high number of jurisdictions. In addition, authorities and relevant stakeholders (eg&#13;
the Wolfsberg Group) may consider promoting BIC to LEI mapping facilities which allow for an easy mapping&#13;
of routing information available in the payment message to the relevant LEI.&#13;
â&#128;¢ Recommendation on information-sharing initiatives: The work already conducted by the authorities with&#13;
responsibility for AML/CFT (i.e. the Financial Action Task Force (FATF) and the Basel Committee on Banking&#13;
Supervision AML/CFT Expert Group (AMLEG)) is very much appreciated. It is recommended that the FATF&#13;
and AMLEG be invited to: (i) provide additional clarity on due diligence recommendations for upstream banks,&#13;
in particular to what extent banks need to know their customersâ&#128;&#153; customers (â&#128;&#156;KYCCâ&#128;&#157;); (ii) further clarify data&#13;
privacy concerns in the area of correspondent banking; and (iii) detail, to the extent possible, the type of data&#13;
that information-sharing mechanisms could store and distribute in order to be a useful source of information. In&#13;
order to facilitate compliance with FATF customer due diligence recommendations, (i) the use of information-&#13;
sharing mechanisms (if they exist in a given jurisdiction and data privacy laws allow this) for knowing your&#13;
customersâ&#128;&#153; customers could be promoted as the first source of information by default, which (ii) could be&#13;
complemented bilaterally with enhanced information should there be a need. In order to support information-&#13;
sharing in general, the respondent bank may include provisions in its contractual framework with its customers&#13;
(eg in the terms and conditions or in a supplementary agreement) which allow the bank to provide such&#13;
information on request to other banks for AML/CFT compliance purposes.&#13;
 â&#128;¢ Recommendation on payment messages: It is recommended that the relevant stakeholders determine&#13;
whether the MT 202 COV payment message is as efficient and effective as intended or whether relying only on&#13;
the MT 103 and the serial processing method would better serve the needs of clients, the industry and law&#13;
enforcement in light of the fee structure, technological changes and payment capabilities for processing&#13;
correspondent banking payments. The Wolfsberg Group seems to be the most appropriate body to review the&#13;
issue and to initiate a recommendation in this field and lead any consequential changes if required.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
34.   Available at http://www.bis.org/cpmi/publ/d136.pdf.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             Finance and Markets Global Practice, The World Bank Group&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="25481335">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2015/11/25481335/withdraw-correspondent-banking
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2015/11/25481335/withdraw-correspondent-banking</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2015/11/25481335/withdraw-correspondent-banking</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2015-11-20T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2015-11-20T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <docm_id>090224b083395501</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b0831efdad</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2015/11/24/090224b083395501/3_0/Rendered/INDEX/Withdraw0from000what0to0do0about0it.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2015/11/24/090224b083395501/3_0/Rendered/PDF/Withdraw0from000what0to0do0about0it.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2015-11-01T11:00:03Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2015-11-20T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Withdraw from correspondent banking :
            where, why, and what to do about it
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Correspondent banking services are
            essential to enabling companies and individuals to transact
            internationally and make cross-border payments. Recently
            there have been indications that certain large international
            banks have started terminating or severely limiting their
            correspondent banking relationships with smaller local and
            regional banks from jurisdictions around the world. To find
            out whether this is indeed happening, the World Bank, with
            support from the Financial Stability Board (FSB) and the
            Committee on Payments and Market Infrastructures (CPMI),
            surveyed banking authorities and banks worldwide to examine
            the extent of withdrawal from correspondent banking, its
            drivers, and its implications for financial
            exclusion/inclusion. In total, 110 banking authorities, 20
            large banks, and 170 smaller local and regional banks
            participated in this exercise. This document includes
            finding of the survey, conclusions, and recommendations.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Withdraw from correspondent banking : where,
            why, and what to do about it
        </docna>
        <display_title>Withdraw from correspondent
            banking : where, why, and what to do about it</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2015/11/25481335/withdraw-correspondent-banking</listing_relative_url>
        <topic>Banking Regulation m1326903 971,Financial Sector Development m1327681 1920,Financial Inclusion m1327456 363</topic>
        <subtopic>Financial Intermediation,Banks &amp; Banking Reform,Public Sector Corruption &amp;
            Anticorruption Measures,Access to Finance,Emerging Markets</subtopic>
        <docty>Working Paper</docty>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Private Sector Development,Public Sector Development</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>090224b083395501_3_0</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Private Sector Development,Public Sector Development</historic_topic>
        <topicv3>Banking Regulation m1326903 971,Financial Sector Development m1327681 1920,Financial Inclusion m1327456 363</topicv3>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            deposit, financial services, receipt,
            accounting, deposits, customer, small banks, payment
            service, money laundering, financing, regional banks,
            interest, access to payment, laws, industry, remittance,
            banking system, strategies, banking services, information,
            liquidity, services, discrimination, money transfer,
            international business, information sharing, reorganization,
            capacity building, pricing, fee, corruption, payments,
            central banks, credit institution, international bank,
            market infrastructures, economic activity, access to
            financial services, jurisdictions, anti-money laundering,
            savings, technical assistance, penalties, currency,
            settlement systems, financial institution, banking
            relationships, union, current account, private banks,
            foreign currencies, deposit accounts, transfers, domestic
            banks, financial institutions, payment, markets, capital
            requirements, foreign assets, legislation, wire transfer,
            finance, foreign currency, banking sector, banks,
            supervisory authorities, capital, transparency, financial
            stability, customer base, trade finance, compliance costs,
            subsidiaries, access to finance, value, bank, credit, legal
            barriers, internal controls, source of information, foreign
            banks, cash management, affiliates, offshore banking,
            balance sheet, factors, foreign exchange, regulation,
            eastern caribbean central bank, subsidiary, profitability,
            credit risk, wire transfers, trade, interests, land,
            prudential requirements, investment, risk, lack of
            knowledge, contractual obligation, business strategy,
            payment services, banking, international payment systems,
            banking relationship, central banking, legal requirements,
            students, borrowing, investments, risk management, lending,
            chamber of commerce, savings banks, correspondent banks,
            banking supervision, customers, outreach, remittances,
            account holder, governments, payment systems, reserve bank
            of new zealand, international banks, credit institutions,
            guarantee, savings bank, consumer protection, group of
            banks, consolidation
        </keywd>
        <owner>Finance &amp; Markets - GP - IBRD (GFMDR)</owner>
        <repnb>101098</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT for Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies (ICT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fragility, Conflict and Violence</ml:concept><ml:concept>Arts and Culture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation and Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Technological Change</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>AML/CFT Diagnostics</ml:concept><ml:concept>AML/CFT Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Money-Laundering/Financing of Terrorism Risk Assessments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Markets Integrity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Payment Systems and Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Payment Instruments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Payment Systems &amp; Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Securities Settlement Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Settlement Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Inclusion Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Finance and Investment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Remittances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Migration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Anti-Money Laundering</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Intermediation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Media</ml:concept><ml:concept>Boundaries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Copyright</ml:concept><ml:concept>Technology Transfer and Diffusion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banking Institutional Set-up</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Data Privacy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Terrorism</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Anti-Money Laundering and Combating the Financing of Terrorism (AML/CFT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Integrity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Payment and Market Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Payment Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Inclusion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumer Protection</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Movement of Labor</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>