<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>                               101278&#13;
&#13;
       Tajikistan   Economic Update&#13;
                    No.2 | Fall 2015&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         A moderate Slowdown&#13;
           in Economic Growth&#13;
   Coupled with a Sharp Decline&#13;
in Household Purchasing Power&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    Macroeconomics&#13;
                    &amp; Fiscal Management&#13;
                    Global Practice&#13;
&amp;#12;&amp;#12;Tajikistan:&#13;
A moderate Slowdown in Economic Growth Coupled&#13;
with a Sharp Decline in Household Purchasing Power&#13;
________________________________________________________________________________________&#13;
&#13;
Tajikistan Economic Update No. 2&#13;
&#13;
Fall 2015&#13;
&amp;#12; Government Fiscal Year:      January 1 â&#128;&#147; December 31&#13;
 Currency Equivalents:        Exchange Rate Effective as of November 16, 2015&#13;
                              Currency Unit = Tajikistan Somoni (TJS)&#13;
                              US$1 = 6.6355 TJS&#13;
 Weights and Measures:        Metric System&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Abbreviations and Acronyms&#13;
&#13;
ADB             Asian Development Bank&#13;
BT              Barki Tojik&#13;
FDI             Foreign direct investment&#13;
GBAO            Gorno-Badakhshan Autonomous Oblast&#13;
GDP             Gross domestic product&#13;
HBS             Household budget survey&#13;
LHS             Left-hand scale&#13;
LSS             Living standards survey&#13;
MoEDT           Ministry of Economic Development and Trade&#13;
MoF             Ministry of Finance&#13;
NBT             National Bank of Tajikistan&#13;
NPL             Nonperforming loan&#13;
PFM             Public financial management&#13;
PPG             Public and publicly guaranteed&#13;
PPP             Purchasing power parity&#13;
RHS             Right-hand scale&#13;
RMB             Renminbi (abbreviation for "Chinese yuan")&#13;
ROA             Return on assets&#13;
ROE             Return on equity&#13;
RRS             Regions of Republican Subordination&#13;
SOE             State-owned enterprise&#13;
TajStat         Agency of Statistics under the President of Tajikistan&#13;
TALCO           Tajik Aluminum Company&#13;
TJS             Tajikistan somoni (unit of currency)&#13;
TSA             Targeted social assistance&#13;
VAT             Value added tax&#13;
Y/Y             Year-on-year&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ii|&#13;
&amp;#12;Contents&#13;
Foreword ................................................................................................................................................................................... iv&#13;
Overview ..................................................................................................................................................................................... 1&#13;
A.   Recent Economic Developments ........................................................................................................................... 2&#13;
           Economic Growth and Domestic Demand............................................................................................... 2&#13;
           The Labor Market, Poverty and Inequality ............................................................................................. 4&#13;
B.   Economic and Structural Policies ......................................................................................................................... 6&#13;
           Fiscal Developments ........................................................................................................................................ 6&#13;
           Monetary Policy and Financial Sector Developments ........................................................................ 8&#13;
           The Balance of Payments ............................................................................................................................. 10&#13;
C.   Outlook........................................................................................................................................................................... 12&#13;
D.   Special Focus Section: Growth and Jobs in Tajikistan ................................................................................ 14&#13;
Annex 1: Economic and Social Indicators in Tajikistan, 2010â&#128;&#147;17 .................................................................... 18&#13;
&#13;
Figures&#13;
&#13;
Figure 1. Economic Growth among Tajikistanâ&#128;&#153;s Major Trading Partners ........................................................ 2&#13;
Figure 2. Output Growth by Sector................................................................................................................................... 2&#13;
Figure 3. Economic Growth and Remittances.............................................................................................................. 3&#13;
Figure 4. GDP Growth and Income Growth................................................................................................................... 3&#13;
Figure 5. Wage Employment by Economic Activity .................................................................................................. 5&#13;
Figure 6. Average Monthly Wage by Sector .................................................................................................................. 5&#13;
Figure 7. Poverty Headcount Rate by Region and Rural/Urban Aggregate .................................................... 5&#13;
Figure 8. Gini Coefficients by Region and Rural/Urban Aggregate..................................................................... 5&#13;
Figure 9. Arrears of SOEs and Barki Tojik ..................................................................................................................... 7&#13;
Figure 10. State Budget and PPG External Debt ......................................................................................................... 7&#13;
Figure 11. Sources of Inflation ........................................................................................................................................... 8&#13;
Figure 12. Broad Money And Private Credit Growth ................................................................................................ 8&#13;
Figure 13. Interest Rates ...................................................................................................................................................... 9&#13;
Figure 14. Key Financial Soundness Indicators .......................................................................................................... 9&#13;
Figure 15. Exports, Imports and the Trade Deficit .................................................................................................. 10&#13;
Figure 16. Global Aluminum and Cotton Prices ........................................................................................................ 11&#13;
Figure 17. Global Wheat and Crude Oil Prices ........................................................................................................... 11&#13;
Figure 18. Composition of Imports ................................................................................................................................ 11&#13;
Figure 19. Composition of Exports ................................................................................................................................. 11&#13;
Figure 20. Official Nominal Exchange Rates ............................................................................................................... 12&#13;
Figure 21. Net International Reserves .......................................................................................................................... 12&#13;
Figure 22. GDP Growth and Contribution to GDP Growth by Sector ............................................................... 13&#13;
Figure 23. GDP Growth and Poverty Rates ................................................................................................................. 13&#13;
Figure 24. Structural Change, 2000-14 ........................................................................................................................ 15&#13;
Figure 25. Labor Productivity by Sector ...................................................................................................................... 15&#13;
Figure 26. Shapley Decomposition of per Capita GDP and Labor Productivity ........................................... 16&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                          |iii&#13;
&amp;#12;Foreword&#13;
This edition of the Tajikistan Economic Update is part of a biannual series of reports designed to monitor&#13;
recent economic developments in Tajikistan and examine emerging issues. It presents a broad overview of&#13;
the countryâ&#128;&#153;s macroeconomic, policy and structural context, and assesses its macro-fiscal profile and growth&#13;
outlook over the short and medium term. This editionâ&#128;&#153;s authors are Marina Bakanova (Senior Country&#13;
Economist) and Ravshan Sobirzoda (Economist). Alisher Rajabov (Poverty Economist), Zarina Odinaeva&#13;
(Operations Officer), Victoria Strokova (Economist), Angela Elzir (Junior Professional Associate), David de&#13;
Padua (Research Assistant), and Dino Merotto (Lead Economist) provided valuable contributions. The&#13;
analysis also benefited from the valuable input provided by Naoko C. Kojo (Senior Economist), Christos&#13;
Kostopoulos (Lead Economist for Central Asia), John Litwack (Lead Economist) and Patricia Veevers-Carter&#13;
(Country Manager for Tajikistan).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Miria A. Pigato&#13;
Practice Manager&#13;
Macroeconomics and Fiscal Management&#13;
Global Practice&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                         |iv&#13;
&amp;#12;Overview&#13;
Tajikistanâ&#128;&#153;s economy exceeded expectations during the first six months of 2015 despite a&#13;
challenging external environment. According to official data, GDP growth slowed only moderately&#13;
from 6.7 percent in the first half of 2014 to 6.4 percent year on year (y/y) in the first half of 2015,&#13;
even as remittances from Russia fell, global demand weakened, and prices for the countryâ&#128;&#153;s key&#13;
export commodities such as aluminum and cotton dropped significantly. Domestic factors continued&#13;
to drive growth, and both the construction and industrial sectors expanded as the economyâ&#128;&#153;s focus&#13;
shifted from consumption to investment. The state budget surplus reached 1 percent of GDP, and the&#13;
external public debt to GDP ratio dropped to below 20 percent.&#13;
&#13;
The sharp decline in remittances is limiting the growth of household consumption and could&#13;
threaten the sustainability of recent gains in poverty reduction and shared prosperity.&#13;
According to the National Bank of Tajikistan (NBT), remittances dropped by 32 percent (y/y), in US&#13;
dollar terms during the first six months of 2015. Although the decline was less dramatic (about 18&#13;
percent) in Tajikistan somoni (TJS) terms, income losses were much larger than implied by GDP&#13;
statistics. Falling remittances, limited employment creation outside the public sector, and rising&#13;
prices are slowing the rate of poverty reduction. Moreover, the lack of well-targeted social programs&#13;
leaves households vulnerable to economic shocks.&#13;
&#13;
The government is shifting its policy stance to reflect the worsening external environment.&#13;
The government is maintaining its commitment to fiscal discipline by setting clear spending&#13;
priorities and postponing less urgent expenditures while protecting social outlays. However, the&#13;
delayed revision of the budget until November has both heightened the risk of arrears and created&#13;
perverse incentives for tax authorities to exert excessive pressure on businesses in order to meet&#13;
their revenue targets. Monetary policy has been accommodative during the first six months of 2015,&#13;
and rising inflation rates have prompted the NBT to defend the somoni through a combination of&#13;
interventions and administrative controls, including ceilings on the exchange rates offered by&#13;
foreign-exchange offices. This policy has depleted the countryâ&#128;&#153;s already low stock of foreign reserves,&#13;
which stood at just one month of imports in early July. The NBT has recently ceased its interventions&#13;
and is gradually allowing the unification of the official exchange rate with both the cash and market&#13;
rates. The NBT is also intensifying efforts to rebuild its reserves and improve their management.&#13;
&#13;
The countryâ&#128;&#153;s economic outlook is broadly positive, but current forecasts are subject to&#13;
significant downside risks. The recession in Russiaâ&#128;&#148;combined with slowing growth among&#13;
Tajikistanâ&#128;&#153;s other major trading partners, including China, Kazakhstan and Turkeyâ&#128;&#148;is negatively&#13;
impacting its short-term outlook. After slowing to an estimated 4.2 percent for 2015 as a whole, GDP&#13;
growth is projected to recover gradually over the medium term, though it is expected to remain&#13;
below its recent historical average. The current-account deficit is expected to improve moderately,&#13;
narrowing from about 8 percent of GDP in 2014 to 6.3 percent in 2015 and remaining at around 6&#13;
percent thereafter. The fiscal accounts (excluding externally financed public investments) are&#13;
expected to remain broadly balanced over the near term. However, external-account volatility,&#13;
dwindling foreign-exchange reserves, contingent liabilities generated by state-owned enterprises&#13;
and systemic vulnerabilities in the banking sector all pose significant downside risks to Tajikistanâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
macroeconomic outlook. While weakening GDP growth is slowing the pace of poverty reduction, the&#13;
poverty rate is still projected to fall to 27.3 percent by 2017. As external and domestic pressures&#13;
continue to mount, addressing fiscal risks and implementing reforms to boost productivity, enhance&#13;
competitiveness and strengthen social safety nets will be critical to sustain growth and support further&#13;
progress in poverty reduction.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                     |1&#13;
&amp;#12;A.        Recent Economic Developments&#13;
Economic Growth and Domestic Demand&#13;
&#13;
According to official data, economic growth remained strong in the first half of 2015 in the&#13;
face of a challenging external environment. Tajikistanâ&#128;&#153;s GDP grew by 6.4 percent (y/y) between&#13;
January and June, down slightly from 6.7 percent for the same period a year earlier. The countryâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
main trading partnersâ&#128;&#148;China, Russia, Kazakhstan and Turkeyâ&#128;&#148;have all recently experienced either&#13;
slowing growth rates or outright recessions (Figure 1). However, falling exports have been offset by&#13;
even larger declines in imports, as a steep drop in remittances has reduced household consumption.&#13;
As a result, net exports have made a positive contribution to economic growth despite worsening&#13;
external conditions. Moreover, internal dynamics continued to drive growth, and while consumption&#13;
declined, fixed investment grew by an extraordinary 41.4 percent (y/y), up from an already robust&#13;
28.4 percent a year earlier. Thirty-nine percent of total fixed-capital investment was foreign financed,&#13;
largely by Chinese investors. The public sector accounted for 37 percent of fixed-capital investment,&#13;
and the rest was comprised of private investment by domestic firms and companies with joint foreign&#13;
and domestic ownership.1&#13;
&#13;
 Figure 1. Economic Growth among Tajikistanâ&#128;&#153;s             Figure 2. Output Growth by Sector&#13;
 Major Trading Partners                                   (Percent)&#13;
 (Percentage Change)&#13;
                                                           40&#13;
     7&#13;
                                                           30&#13;
&#13;
     5                                                     20&#13;
&#13;
                                                           10&#13;
     3&#13;
&#13;
                                                            0&#13;
     1                                                            H1'2012      H1'2013      H1'2014         H1'2015&#13;
                                                           -10&#13;
          Russia   Kazakhstan     China    Turkey&#13;
     -1                                                    -20&#13;
&#13;
                   2013    2014    2015f                   -30   Industry   Agriculture   Construction       Services&#13;
     -3&#13;
&#13;
 Source: World Bank, September 23, 2015.                  Source: TajStat, World Bank staff calculations.&#13;
&#13;
Construction and industry propelled growth in the first half of 2015 (Figure 2). The&#13;
construction sectorâ&#128;&#153;s remarkable performance reflected the completion of TJS 4 billion in investment&#13;
projects, an increase of 43 percent (y/y). Infrastructure, communications, electricity production and&#13;
transmission, and residential and commercial projects were all completed during this period. Sixty&#13;
percent of these projects were investments in productive capacity. The strong growth of industrial&#13;
production, which rose by 14.2 percent (y/y), was led by the extractive industries, the electricity&#13;
sector and manufacturing, especially the construction materials. Favorable weather conditions&#13;
boosted growth in the agricultural sector, which rose from 6 percent in the first half of 2014 to 6.9&#13;
percent in the first half of 2015. However, a frost in the early spring damaged orchards in northern&#13;
&#13;
1 These are preliminary estimates from the national statistics agency (TajStat) and may be subject to further&#13;
revision.&#13;
&#13;
2|&#13;
&amp;#12;Tajikistan, causing US$90 million in losses and a 45 percent drop in fruit production according to&#13;
official estimates. After rising by 3.8 percent in the first half of 2014, services contracted by 5.3&#13;
percent in the first half of 2015 as falling remittances undermined domestic demand.2&#13;
&#13;
    Figure 3. Economic Growth and Remittances                    Figure 4. GDP Growth and Income Growth&#13;
    (% change and % of GDP)                                      (Percent)&#13;
&#13;
     7,4                                                  50,0    30%&#13;
     7,2&#13;
                                                          40,0    20%&#13;
       7&#13;
&#13;
     6,8                                                  30,0    10%&#13;
     6,6&#13;
                                                          20,0&#13;
                                                                   0%&#13;
     6,4                                                                2006200720082009201020112012201320142015&#13;
                                                          10,0&#13;
     6,2                                                         -10%&#13;
&#13;
       6                                                  0,0&#13;
           H1'2010H1'2011H1'2012H1'2013H1'2014H1'2015            -20%&#13;
                                                                                   Contribution of Remittances&#13;
                     GDP growth, % change (LHS)                                    Contribution of GDP&#13;
                                                                                   GDP growth&#13;
                     Remittance inflows, % of GDP (RHS)&#13;
                                                                                   Income growth&#13;
    Source: NBT, World Bank staff calculations.                  Source: MoEDT, World Bank staff calculations.&#13;
&#13;
The Russian recession, a weakening ruble, and tighter regulations on labor migration sharply&#13;
reduced remittance inflows in the first half of 2015. According to the NBT, the value of remittance&#13;
inflows in US dollars during the first six months of 2015 fell to US$1.2 billion, a 32 percent decline&#13;
from the same period in 2014 (Figure 3).3 Falling remittances have negatively impacted domestic&#13;
demand, causing the service sector to contract. Over 80 percent of Tajikistanâ&#128;&#153;s inbound remittances&#13;
originate in Russia and are denominated in rubles, and the dramatic plunge in remittances is mainly&#13;
due to the exchange-rate effect of the rubleâ&#128;&#153;s depreciation.4 In somoni terms remittances fell by a&#13;
more modest 17.5 percent.5 There is also evidence that tighter restrictions on immigration in the&#13;
Russian Federation since January 2015 may be affecting remittances.6 According to Russiaâ&#128;&#153;s Federal&#13;
Migration Service, as of June 2015 there were 992,170 Tajikistani migrants in the Russian Federation,&#13;
down 15 percent from the same period in the previous year. Furthermore, the number of Tajikistani&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
2 According to the 2015 National Human Development Report, â&#128;&#156;Tajikistan: Access to Resources for Human&#13;
Development,â&#128;&#157; a full 83 percent of Tajik households depend at least in part on remittance inflows. The survey&#13;
also revealed that 86.5 percent of remittances are used for immediate consumption and are not deposited in&#13;
the banking system. See:&#13;
www.tj.undp.org/content/dam/tajikistan/docs/projects/democratic_governance/UNDP_TJK_MHDT_2014_E&#13;
ng.pdf&#13;
3 Data provided by the Central Bank of Russia indicate a decline of 46 percent (y/y) during the first half of 2015.&#13;
&#13;
The disparity may be due to differences in the periodicity of ruble-dollar conversions, differences in the&#13;
analytical methodology and/or the definition of primary and secondary income, or differences in the&#13;
accounting of inflows from other countries.&#13;
4 According to the Central Bank of Russia the ruble depreciated by 42 percent against the dollar in 2014, then&#13;
&#13;
appreciated slightly by about 1.2 percent as of end-June 2015.&#13;
5Using the unofficial (or â&#128;&#156;streetâ&#128;&#157;) rate would result in an even smaller decline of no more than 10 percent.&#13;
6 World Bank. 2015. Special Topic: Labor Migration and Remittances in â&#128;&#156;Tajikistan: Slowing Growth, Rising&#13;
&#13;
Uncertainties.â&#128;&#157; Economic Update #1, Spring 2015.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                 |3&#13;
&amp;#12;labor migrants banned from re-entry reached 324,634 by August 2015, up from 270,000 in&#13;
November 2014.&#13;
&#13;
The sharp decline in remittances is slowing the growth of household income. In recent years&#13;
household income growth in Tajikistan has substantially outpaced GDP growth, but recent events&#13;
appear to have reversed this trend. Because of sharp decline in real remittances the projected drop&#13;
in purchasing power is over 10 percent in 2015, much more than suggested by the GDP numbers&#13;
(Figure 4).7 As discussed in the following section, micro-level data confirm the diverging trends of&#13;
GDP and income growth.8 Remittances comprise the countryâ&#128;&#153;s second-largest source of household&#13;
income, and households are struggling to cope with the decline in remittance values by increasing&#13;
the labor supply, both domestically and in foreign labor markets other than Russia, such as&#13;
Kazakhstan. However, this shift in labor dynamics does not appear to have fully compensated for the&#13;
income lost due to the depreciation of the ruble.&#13;
&#13;
The Labor Market, Poverty and Inequality&#13;
&#13;
There is evidence of mounting pressure in the labor market since end-2014. According to&#13;
Tajikistanâ&#128;&#153;s national statistics agency (TajStat), the unemployment rate was just 2.5 percent in June&#13;
2015, unchanged from June 2014. However, the number of unemployed workers grew by about 5&#13;
percent during the first half of 2015 despite the creation of 120,404 jobs by the Ministry of Labor,&#13;
Migration, and Employment of Population.9 Furthermore, the number of job seekers rose by 4.1&#13;
percent, while the number of vacancies dropped by 22.1 percent (y/y), resulting in the increase in&#13;
the ratio of applicants per vacancy from 6.9 in June 2014 to 9.2 in June 2015â&#128;&#148;the highest rate of the&#13;
post-crisis period. Slow rates of employment creation have pushed many job seekers into the&#13;
informal sector, which accounted for about 49 percent of total employment in 2009. In February&#13;
2015 the government adopted a new strategy to reduce informal employment, which includes&#13;
measures to strengthen monitoring of the informal sector, reform labor laws, reduce barriers to&#13;
formalization and strengthen interagency coordination.&#13;
&#13;
Agriculture offers the lowest compensation of any sector, yet it continues to dominate the&#13;
labor market, accounting for 45 percent of total employment. Employment in agriculture&#13;
declined by 3.2 percent over the last three years (Figure 5), and a combination of rising prices for&#13;
agricultural inputs, urbanization and emigration appears to be driving this trend. Repeated droughts&#13;
in the southern part of the country encouraged rural-urban migration and emigration, and the impact&#13;
of climate change has emerged as a subject of heated political debate following recent floods and&#13;
mudslides in Gorno-Badakhshan Autonomous Oblast (GBAO) and the Rasht Valley in July 2015,&#13;
which caused about US$100 million in damages.10&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
7  For the methodology of estimation of income generated by remittances see, World Bank. 2015. â&#128;&#156;Low&#13;
Commodity Prices and Weak Currenciesâ&#128;&#157;. World Bank ECA Economic Update October 2015.&#13;
8 These data were obtained from the â&#128;&#156;Listening to Tajikistanâ&#128;&#157; survey, which was conducted through biweekly&#13;
computer-assisted telephone interviews in May 2015.&#13;
9 The ministry created 15.4 percent fewer jobs than originally planned during the first half of 2015. Major&#13;
&#13;
vacancies were left unfilled in construction, industry, agriculture, transport and communication, trade and&#13;
other areas. Of all created jobs, 30.3 percent were permanent, 33.8 percent were temporary and 33.2 percent&#13;
were seasonal.&#13;
10 See also World Bank. 2014. â&#128;&#156;Tajikistan: Autonomous Adaptation to Climate Change: Economic Opportunities&#13;
&#13;
and Institutional Constraints for Farming Households.â&#128;&#157; Report #85597-TJ, May 2014.&#13;
&#13;
4|&#13;
&amp;#12; Figure 5. Wage Employment by Economic Activity                                Figure 6. Average Monthly Wage by Sector&#13;
 (Percent)                                                                     (TJS)&#13;
 100%&#13;
                   3,3                3,4             3,1&#13;
                                                      5,2               3,2    2000&#13;
                   5,7                5,7                               5,1&#13;
                   8,4                8,5             8,7               8,9&#13;
                   9,3               10,2            11,1              11,6&#13;
                                                                               1500&#13;
                   18                18,4            18,8              18,7&#13;
     50%&#13;
                                                                               1000&#13;
                   48,3                47            46,1              45,1&#13;
                                                                                500&#13;
     0%&#13;
             June'2012          June'2013       June'2014         June'2015&#13;
                                                                                  0&#13;
                     Transport, warehousing, communication&#13;
                     Trade &amp; repair services&#13;
                                                                                         June'2012        June'2013      June'2014          June'2015&#13;
                     Construction                                                                 Agriculture, Hunting and Forestry&#13;
                     Public administration and defense                                            Construction&#13;
                     Processing industry                                                          Financial intermediary&#13;
                     Health and social services                                                   Education&#13;
                     Other activities                                                             Health and Social Services&#13;
                     Education&#13;
                                                                                                  Transport, warehousing and communication&#13;
                     Agriculture, hunting and forestry&#13;
 Source: TajStat, World Bank staff calculations.                               Source: TajStat, World Bank staff calculations.&#13;
&#13;
According to official statistics11 Tajikistanâ&#128;&#153;s poverty rate fell by 4.4 percentage points over the&#13;
last two years to 32 percent, but gains varied across regions and between urban and rural&#13;
areas. The poverty rate fell most sharply in GBAO, from 50.9 to 37.3 percent, and in Regions of&#13;
Republican Subordination (RRS), from 45.9 to 37.8 percent (Figure 7). Poverty incidence is highest&#13;
in RRS, Khatlon, and GBAO and lowest in Sughd and Dushanbe. Poverty in Tajikistan is predominantly&#13;
rural, and almost four out of five poor people live in rural areas.&#13;
&#13;
 Figure 7. Poverty Headcount Rate by Region and                                 Figure 8. Gini Coefficients by Region and&#13;
 Rural/Urban Aggregate                                                          Rural/Urban Aggregate&#13;
 (Percent)                                                                      (Percent)&#13;
                                50,9                                                                                     29,4&#13;
     50,0                                                                        30   28,4&#13;
                                                                                          29      28,4 29,128,7       28,3               29 28,8 28,4&#13;
                                                45,9                                                             27,4                           27,5&#13;
                                                                                               26,2            25,8               25,9&#13;
                                         41,3                             40&#13;
                                              37,8                               25&#13;
     40,0     36,4            37,3     37,7                                                                                     22,4&#13;
                                                                       36,1&#13;
            32,0&#13;
                                                                29,3             20&#13;
     30,0&#13;
                                                     23,1 23,5 23,5&#13;
                       21,5                                                      15&#13;
                   19,9&#13;
     20,0&#13;
                                                                                 10&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     10,0&#13;
                                                                                  5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      0,0                                                                         0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     2014     2012                                                              2012      2014&#13;
&#13;
 Source: Poverty Measurement Methodology Note, TajStat,                         Source: Poverty Measurement Methodology Note,&#13;
 2015                                                                           TajStat, 2015&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
11On June 24th, 2015 TajStat launched a new official poverty series and methodological note using a new&#13;
approach in measuring poverty. The new method is based on the quarterly Household Budget Survey (HBS),&#13;
which has been consistently implemented and repeatedly improved. The national poverty line was set at TJS&#13;
158.71 per capita per month in 2014.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                 |5&#13;
&amp;#12;Income inequality is relatively low overall, but urban centers are less equal than rural areas.&#13;
The Gini coefficient12 for per capita consumption increased by 0.6 percentage points between 2012&#13;
and 2014 to reach 29.0 in 2014 (Figure 8). This is below the conventional â&#128;&#156;low inequalityâ&#128;&#157; threshold&#13;
of 30. Inequality rose in most regions, except for Sughd, with Dushanbe and GBAO seeing the largest&#13;
increases of 2.2 and 3.5 percentage points, respectively. Overall urban inequality fell slightly, while&#13;
rural inequality increased.&#13;
&#13;
RRS is by far the countryâ&#128;&#153;s most unequal district. RSS is relatively wealthy, with an average rate&#13;
of consumption per capita higher than that of Khatlon and GBAO; it also has the highest Gini&#13;
coefficient in the country (29.4), above even that of Dushanbe. Meanwhile, at 25.9 inequality is&#13;
substantially lower in GBAO than in all other districts. GBAO is Tajikistan's poorest district. It is&#13;
largely agricultural, and has few urban areas, which likely contributes to its relative equality. At the&#13;
national level inequality in Tajikistan is comparable to that of other countries in the region. Its Gini&#13;
coefficient is the same as Kazakhstan's last recorded figure in 2010, and well below that of the Kyrgyz&#13;
Republic, which was 33 in 2011.13&#13;
&#13;
The national poverty rate fell to 31.6 percent in the first quarter of 2015, but the pace of&#13;
poverty reduction has recently slowed. Moreover, welfare indicators are worsening fastest among&#13;
poor households. According to the â&#128;&#156;Listening to Tajikistanâ&#128;&#157; survey, between May and July 2015 the&#13;
average real income per capita dropped by 23 percent among households in the bottom 40 percent&#13;
and by 16 percent among households in the top 60 percent. These declines were primarily due to&#13;
lower remittance income, which was only partially offset by seasonal increases in the number of&#13;
remittance transfersâ&#128;&#148;though even these were lower in total valueâ&#128;&#148;and by rising agricultural&#13;
income during the summer months. The decline in poverty in recent years has been driven by wage&#13;
growth, particularly in the public sector, and pensions, as well as remittances. Limited employment&#13;
creation outside the public sector, falling remittances, and rising prices have slowed the rate of&#13;
poverty reduction below its 2012-2014 average.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
B.      Economic and Structural Policies&#13;
Fiscal Developments&#13;
&#13;
Despite lower revenues the state budget showed a surplus of 1 percent of GDP in the first half&#13;
of 2015. Total revenues were 3.3 percent below target due to a sharp drop in import-related&#13;
revenues such as customs duties and VAT. In response, the government reprioritized its expenditures&#13;
and deferred certain capital investments. As a result total expenditures were under-executed by 16.8&#13;
percent, largely due to the Rogun hydropower plant, which spent 15.3 percent less than originally&#13;
planned during the first half of 2015.&#13;
&#13;
Revenue performance was uneven during the first half of 2015, raising concerns that revenue&#13;
authorities may face perverse incentives to increase collections at the expense of the tax base.&#13;
As import tax and VAT revenues fell, a substantial increase in other tax and nontax revenues helped&#13;
mitigate the net effect on the budget. However, this appears to have been the result of tax authorities&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
12 The Gini coefficient is the most commonly used measure of inequality. In this case 0 represents complete&#13;
equality of consumption, while 1 indicates complete inequality of consumption.&#13;
13 World Development Indicators, 2015.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
6|&#13;
&amp;#12;increasing pressure on businesses to meet revenue targets. While this tactic may boost revenues in&#13;
the short run, over time it threatens to erode the tax base by encouraging evasion and informality.&#13;
&#13;
The government has largely protected social programs from the fiscal consolidation, and&#13;
social spending continued to represent roughly half of total expenditures. Social spending&#13;
remained at 16 percent of GDP, similar to the first half of 2014. At 2.2 percent of GDP healthcare&#13;
spending was 0.2 percentage points higher than a year earlier, yet it remains the lowest in the Europe&#13;
and Central Asia (ECA) region. The amendment of the budget has been delayed until the fall, and its&#13;
specifics have yet to be defined. Proposed amendments designed to protect social expenditures by&#13;
cutting spending in other areas, such as procurement, and by delaying capital projects that are far&#13;
from completion. A promised increase in public sector wages and pensions in September 2015 has&#13;
been postponed due to worsening economic conditions.14&#13;
&#13;
The financial performance of state-owned enterprises (SOEs) has worsened, intensifying&#13;
fiscal risks. SOEsâ&#128;&#153; net arrears on accounts payable and receivable rose sharply during the first six&#13;
months of 2015. As of July 1st, the 24 largest SOEs had TJS 3.2 billion (US$547.8 million) in arrears on&#13;
accounts receivable and TJS14.4 billion (US$2.5 billion) on accounts payable, or about 6.8 and 30.8&#13;
percent of GDP, respectively (Figure 9). The state energy company Barki Tojik accounts for the lionâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
share of these arrears, almost 64 percent of payables and 29 percent of receivables. In August 2015&#13;
the government dismissed its top management, laid-off 50 percent of its personnel and mandated&#13;
that the new management maintain strict control over financial and human resources management.&#13;
&#13;
 Figure 9. Arrears of SOEs and Barki Tojik                     Figure 10. State Budget and PPG External Debt&#13;
 (% of GDP)                                                    (% of GDP)&#13;
 30,0                                                          35,0&#13;
&#13;
 25,0                                                          30,0&#13;
&#13;
 20,0                                                          25,0&#13;
&#13;
                                                               20,0&#13;
 15,0&#13;
                                                               15,0&#13;
 10,0&#13;
                                                               10,0&#13;
     5,0&#13;
                                                                5,0&#13;
     0,0                                                        0,0&#13;
             2013             2014             H1'2015                H1'2010 H1'2011 H1'2012 H1'2013 H1'2014 H1'2015&#13;
                       Accounts payable&#13;
                       Accounts receivable                               Expenditure                Revenue and grants&#13;
                       Accounts payable, BT&#13;
                       Accounts receivable, BT                           Fiscal balance             PPG external debt&#13;
&#13;
 Source: Ministry of Finance, World Bank staff calculations.   Source: Ministry of Finance, World Bank staff calculations.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
14 In a January speech to Parliament, President Emomali Rahmon pledged to increase public sector salaries in&#13;
September 2015. Government, law enforcement and security sector salaries are slated to rise by 15 percent,&#13;
education sector salaries and pension payments by 20 percent, wages of social protection workers by 25&#13;
percent, and stipends by 30 percent. The minimum monthly wage will rise by 60 percent, from TJS 250 to TJS&#13;
400. The Ministry of Finance is considering postponing some of these increases due to the underperformance&#13;
of revenues.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                     |7&#13;
&amp;#12;The stock of external public and publicly guaranteed (PPG) debt declined to below 20 percent&#13;
of GDP. Tajikistanâ&#128;&#153;s external PPG debt declined from 21.9 percent of GDP in the middle of 2014 to&#13;
19.6 percent in July 2015 (Figure 10) due to exchange-rate effects (US$58.4 million) and principal&#13;
repayments (US$55.1 million). The Chinese Export-Import Bank is Tajikistanâ&#128;&#153;s largest creditor, and&#13;
its loans represented about 46 percent of total external public debt in the reporting period. Other&#13;
major creditors include the World Bank (15.1 percent) and the Asian Development Bank (12.7&#13;
percent). Despite low external debt levels and a declining risk of debt distress,15 the government is&#13;
continuing to pursue concessional loans exclusively due to its limited fiscal buffers, rising debt-&#13;
service obligations and low foreign reserves.&#13;
&#13;
Monetary Policy and Financial Sector Developments&#13;
&#13;
Rising food and service sector prices are causing inflation to accelerate. Average consumer&#13;
price index (CPI) inflation reached 6.3 percent in the first half of 2015, up from 5.3 percent a year&#13;
earlier (Figure 11). As food constitutes about two-thirds of the CPI basket, and over 70 percent of all&#13;
food is imported, the pass-through effect of the depreciation pushed the food prices up 8.3 percent&#13;
(y/y) in the first half of 2015. However, the potential impact of the somoniâ&#128;&#153;s depreciation was&#13;
attenuated by falling demand and rising domestic food production. During the same period the cost&#13;
of services rose by 3.4 percent, compared to 2.2 percent a year earlier, due to a 25 percent increase&#13;
in water tariffs in Dushanbe, as well as higher energy tariffs nationwide.&#13;
&#13;
The NBT implemented an accommodative monetary policy during the first six months of 2015.&#13;
Broad money and credit to the private sector grew by 12.7 percent and 25.7 percent y/y through June&#13;
2015 (Figure 12). The refinancing rate was increased in December 2014 and has since remained&#13;
unchanged (Figure 13). However, because the NBTâ&#128;&#153;s share of funding at the refinancing rate in the&#13;
banking sector is low, monetary policy has only a limited effect on inflation. There is a considerable&#13;
gap between the refinancing rate and the interbank loan rate, and the latter stood at 20.3 percent in&#13;
June 2015.&#13;
&#13;
 Figure 11. Sources of Inflation                           Figure 12. Broad Money And Private Credit&#13;
 (Percent)                                                 Growth&#13;
                                                           (% change)&#13;
 16&#13;
                                                            55&#13;
 14&#13;
 12                                                         45&#13;
 10                                                         35&#13;
     8&#13;
                                                            25&#13;
     6&#13;
                                                            15&#13;
     4&#13;
     2                                                       5&#13;
&#13;
     0                                                       -5&#13;
         H1'2010 H1'2011 H1'2012 H1'2013 H1'2014 H1'2015&#13;
               Food                      Non-food&#13;
               Services                  Headline CPI                Broad money       Credit to the private sector&#13;
&#13;
 Source: NBT, World Bank staff calculations.               Source: NBT, World Bank staff calculations.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
15A 2015 Debt Sustainability Analysis (DSA) assessed Tajikistanâ&#128;&#153;s risk of debt distress as low, an improvement&#13;
over the rating of moderate recorded in the 2013 DSA.&#13;
&#13;
8|&#13;
&amp;#12;Faced with a deteriorating macroeconomic environment the NBT loosened monetary policy&#13;
to support output growth in the real sector. Reserve requirements for credit institutions&#13;
observing prudential norms were reduced by 50 basis points in somoni and by 100 basis points in&#13;
foreign currency to 1.5 percent and 7 percent, respectively. Meanwhile, interest rates for NBT&#13;
liquidity-support were reduced by 117 basis points to 17.5 percent. These changes took effect on&#13;
October 1st, 2015.&#13;
&#13;
 Figure 13. Interest Rates                                 Figure 14. Key Financial Soundness Indicators&#13;
 (Percent)                                                 (Percent)&#13;
  30                                                  12    30,0&#13;
                                                      10&#13;
  25&#13;
                                                      8     25,0&#13;
&#13;
  20                                                  6&#13;
                                                            20,0&#13;
                                                      4&#13;
  15&#13;
                                                      2&#13;
                                                            15,0&#13;
  10                                                  0&#13;
&#13;
                                                            10,0&#13;
                                                                    2010    2011      2012   2013    2014   H1'2015&#13;
                    Interest rate on loans (LHS)&#13;
                    Interest rate on deposits (LHS)                Capital adequacy ratio      Non-performing loans&#13;
                    Refinancing rate (RHS)&#13;
 Source: NBT, World Bank staff calculations.               Source: NBT, World Bank staff calculations.&#13;
&#13;
Banking sector indicators reveal a continuing deterioration in asset quality. The reported share&#13;
of nonperforming loans (NPLs) rose from 27.2 percent in December 2014 to 29.2 in June 2015&#13;
(Figure 14). However, the real level of NPLs may be significantly higher due to the misclassification&#13;
of certain loans. The reported aggregate capital adequacy ratio for the banking system fell from 14.8&#13;
percent in December 2014 to 14.3 percent in June 2015, and banks are becoming more sensitive to&#13;
credit risks, including indirect risks from foreign-currency lending and market (exchange) risk. Many&#13;
banks also face liquidity pressures due to maturity mismatches, and some have become increasingly&#13;
dependent on the NBT for liquidity support. The financial system remains vulnerable to shocks, and&#13;
measures to support banks in distress are urgently needed.&#13;
&#13;
Despite recent reforms targeting supervisory mechanisms and the enforcement of prudential&#13;
regulations, the banking sector continues to suffer from serious structural weaknesses. The&#13;
deterioration of asset quality reflects inadequate risk-management systems, poor regulatory&#13;
enforcement, an underdeveloped NBT supervisory framework, and deficiencies in financial&#13;
infrastructure that persist despite the rapid growth of credit-reporting and secured-transaction&#13;
systems. However, directed lending has declined significantly in recent years, as banking regulators&#13;
now closely monitor lenders and penalize misallocations of credit resources. The government has&#13;
taken steps to mitigate risks in problem banks, including through state purchases of bad loans, the&#13;
reorganization of senior management and attempts to collect on NPLs.&#13;
&#13;
Financial intermediation in Tajikistan remains limited, and it plays only a marginal role in&#13;
supporting economic growth. Tajikistanâ&#128;&#153;s credit and deposit indicators are low by regional&#13;
standards. Deposits amounted to just 16.5 percent of GDP in June 2015, up from 14.2 percent at end-&#13;
2014. Credit to the private sector increased from 20.2 percent of GDP in 2014 to 23.2 percent in June&#13;
2015, though this reflects a potentially problematic trend of aggressive credit growth (32.6 percent&#13;
in 2014 and 26.5 percent in June 2015) in a financial sector marked by weak governance and a high&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                 |9&#13;
&amp;#12;NPL ratio. In the latest Doing Business in 2016 report Tajikistan ranked 109th out of 189 countries in&#13;
terms of access to credit.16 Expanding credit access, particularly for small and medium enterprises,&#13;
will require the government to enhance enforcement of regulatory norms, strengthen its credit&#13;
culture, further develop its financial infrastructure and improve risk management.&#13;
&#13;
The Balance of Payments&#13;
&#13;
The trade deficit narrowed during the first          Figure 15. Exports, Imports and the Trade Deficit&#13;
half of 2015. Merchandise exports declined           (% of GDP)&#13;
by 8 percent (y/y), whereas imports shrank by        80,0&#13;
25 percent (y/y). Excluding precious and&#13;
semiprecious metals17 the trade gap narrowed         60,0&#13;
to 36.3 percent of GDP in the first half of 2015&#13;
from 51 percent in the first half of 2014            40,0&#13;
(Figure 15). Weakening external and domestic&#13;
demand caused trade turnover to fall by 31           20,0&#13;
percent, including a particularly sharp&#13;
contraction in trade with CIS countries. The          0,0&#13;
preliminary balance of payments data suggest                H1'2010 H1'2011 H1'2012 H1'2013 H1'2014 H1'2015&#13;
that the current account deficit narrowed in                          Exports of goods without precious metals&#13;
the first half of 2015 as the drop in remittance                      Imports of goods without precious metals&#13;
                                                                      Trade deficit without precious metals&#13;
inflows was offset by an improved trade&#13;
                                                     Source: TajStat, World Bank staff calculations.&#13;
balance.&#13;
&#13;
Lower prices for major export commodities caused total exports to decline. In the first half of&#13;
2015 merchandise exports amounted to 10.4 percent of GDP, down from 13.3 percent in the first half&#13;
of 2014. Primary commodities and simple manufactures led the export sector, including precious and&#13;
semi-precious stones, cotton and textiles, and mineral products. Electricity exports rose by 9.4&#13;
percent; Afghanistan received 92 percent of Tajikistanâ&#128;&#153;s electricity exports, and the Kyrgyz Republic&#13;
received 8 percent.&#13;
&#13;
The Tajik Aluminum Company (Talco), the countryâ&#128;&#153;s largest SOE, met its semiannual output&#13;
target and plans to double production within the next two years.18 During the first six months&#13;
of 2015 Tajikistan exported 61,200 tons of aluminum, up 3.6 percent (y/y). Talco is currently&#13;
planning to produce 190,000 tons of aluminum in 2015, 52 percent more than in 2014. Over the next&#13;
two years Talco will attempt to expand its annual production capacity to 270,000 tons in anticipation&#13;
of a moderate increase in global aluminum prices (Figure 16). However, the recent decline in global&#13;
commodity prices casts doubt on previous projections.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
16 Source: http://www.doingbusiness.org/rankings&#13;
17 Most of these exports are part of an NBT program with Switzerland to convert nonmonetary gold into&#13;
monetary gold, a process known as â&#128;&#156;affinage.â&#128;&#157; When semiprecious and precious metals are included, the deficit&#13;
narrows further to 34.7 percent of GDP, down 15.4 percentage points (y/y).&#13;
18 See Talcoâ&#128;&#153;s official website: http://talco.com.tj/en.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
10|&#13;
&amp;#12; Figure 16. Global Aluminum and Cotton Prices                                        Figure 17. Global Wheat and Crude Oil Prices&#13;
                                                                          3,5&#13;
                                                                                     320,0                                                           110,0&#13;
  2400,0&#13;
                                                                                     300,0                                                           100,0&#13;
                                                                          3,0&#13;
  2200,0                                                                             280,0                                                           90,0&#13;
&#13;
                                                                          2,5        260,0                                                           80,0&#13;
  2000,0&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                     240,0                                                           70,0&#13;
  1800,0                                                                  2,0&#13;
                                                                                     220,0                                                           60,0&#13;
&#13;
  1600,0                                                                  1,5        200,0                                                           50,0&#13;
             2010 2011 2012 2013 2014 2015f2016f2017f                                        2010 2011 2012 2013 2014 2015f 2016f 2017f&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                          Wheat, US HRW ($/mt, LHS)&#13;
         Aluminum ($/mt, LHS)                 Cotton, A Index ($/kg, RHS)                                 Crude oil, average ($/bbl, RHS)&#13;
 Source: World Bank Commodity Price Data, October 20,                                Source: World Bank Commodity Price Data, October 20,&#13;
 2015.                                                                               2015.&#13;
&#13;
Softening domestic demand caused imports to decline during the first six months of 2015.&#13;
Merchandise imports contracted from 64.2 percent of GDP to 46.7 percent of GDP (y/y), driven by a&#13;
drop in fuel and food imports, as low international prices did not pass through to the domestic&#13;
market. Although both wheat and oil prices fell dramatically in recent years (Figure 17), domestic&#13;
monopolies prevented any significant price reduction for those commodities. Nevertheless, the&#13;
depreciation of the exchange rate prompted consumers to shift from imports to domestic substitutes,&#13;
especially domestic foodstuffs. Falling household consumption also reduced demand for imported&#13;
cars and other consumer goods. During the first half of 2015 Tajikistan imported only 6,700 vehicles&#13;
valued at almost US$48 million. This represents a decline of 15,100 cars, or 60 percent in dollar&#13;
terms, compared to the first six months of 2014. The overall composition of imports by sectors&#13;
remains broadly similar to previous years, with the exception of vehicle imports (Figure 18).&#13;
&#13;
 Figure 18. Composition of Imports                                                       Figure 19. Composition of Exports&#13;
 (% of total import value)                                                               (% of total export value)&#13;
 100%&#13;
  90%                                                                                    100%&#13;
  80%                                                                                     90%&#13;
  70%                                                                                     80%&#13;
  60%                                                                                     70%&#13;
  50%                                                                                     60%&#13;
  40%                                                                                     50%&#13;
  30%                                                                                     40%&#13;
  20%                                                                                     30%&#13;
  10%&#13;
                                                                                          20%&#13;
   0%&#13;
             2010        2011         2012         2013        2014      H1'2015 e&#13;
                                                                                          10%&#13;
                                                                                           0%&#13;
        Other imports&#13;
        Means for air, land, and water transport                                                   2010        2011      2012       2013      2014   H1'2015 e&#13;
        Machinery, equipment, mechanisms, and spare parts&#13;
        Base metals and their products&#13;
                                                                                                          Others&#13;
        Wood and wood products                                                                            Fruit and vegetable products&#13;
        Food, alcoholic and non-alcoholic beverages, tobacco and its substitutes                          Means for air, land, and water transport&#13;
        Grain and flour&#13;
        Electricity                                                                                       Electricity&#13;
        Petroleum products                                                                                Cotton Fiber&#13;
        Natural gas&#13;
        Alumina                                                                                           Aluminum&#13;
&#13;
 Source: TajStat, World Bank staff calculations.                                         Source: TajStat, World Bank staff calculations.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                     |11&#13;
&amp;#12;After depreciating by 11.1 percent in 2014 the somoni lost 25 percent of its value against the&#13;
US dollar during the first ten months of 2015 (Figure 20). Concerned about rising inflation, the&#13;
NBT initially defended the somoni through a combination of interventions and administrative&#13;
controls. However, this policy depleted the countryâ&#128;&#153;s already modest reserves, which stood at about&#13;
one month of import coverage in early July (Figure 21). After about two and a half months of relative&#13;
stability, and as the currencies of Tajikistanâ&#128;&#153;s major trading partners continued to depreciate against&#13;
the US dollar, the NBT allowed the somoni to adjust gradually beginning in late August. The NBT&#13;
recently ceased its interventions, allowing for a gradual unification of exchange rates at different&#13;
market segments. The NBT has also stepped up efforts to rebuild its reserves and improve their&#13;
management. In September the NBT signed a currency-swap agreement with the Peopleâ&#128;&#153;s Bank of&#13;
China for the equivalent of US$500 million in renminbi.&#13;
&#13;
 Figure 20. Official Nominal Exchange Rates                      Figure 21. Net International Reserves&#13;
                                                                 (US$ millions and months of imports)&#13;
 5,3000                                                 0,0750     600                                               1,60&#13;
                                                                                                                     1,40&#13;
 5,5000                                                 0,0850     500&#13;
                                                                                                                     1,20&#13;
 5,7000                                                            400&#13;
                                                        0,0950                                                       1,00&#13;
 5,9000                                                            300                                               0,80&#13;
                                                        0,1050&#13;
 6,1000                                                                                                              0,60&#13;
                                                                   200&#13;
                                                        0,1150                                                       0,40&#13;
 6,3000                                                            100&#13;
                                                                                                                     0,20&#13;
 6,5000                                                 0,1250&#13;
                                                                     0                                               -&#13;
 6,7000                                                 0,1350&#13;
          01 01 01 01 01 01 01 01 01 01 01&#13;
          Jan Feb Mar Apr Mei Jun Jul Agu Sep Okt Nov&#13;
          15 15 15 15 15 15 15 15 15 15 15&#13;
                                                                                  Net international reserves (LHS)&#13;
            TJS / USD (LHS)        TJS / Russian ruble (RHS)                      Import cover (RHS)&#13;
 Source: NBT, World Bank staff calculations.                     Source: NBT, World Bank staff calculations.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
C.        Outlook&#13;
The recession in Russia, combined with slowing growth among Tajikistanâ&#128;&#153;s other major&#13;
trading partners, is negatively affecting its short-term outlook. The GDP growth rate is projected&#13;
to fall from 6.7 percent in 2014 to 4.2 percent in 2015 (Figure 22).19 An estimated 30 percent drop in&#13;
remittances, in dollar terms, is impacting growth in the services sector, which accounts for over 40&#13;
percent of the economy. Meanwhile, slowing growth among Tajikistanâ&#128;&#153;s major trading partners,&#13;
including China, Kazakhstan and Turkey, will continue to depress demand for the countryâ&#128;&#153;s key&#13;
export commodities, especially cotton and aluminum. The depreciation of the somoni may mitigate&#13;
this effect by boosting exports, encouraging the substitution of domestic production for imports and&#13;
increasing the somoni value of remittances. Yet the current-account deficit is projected to improve&#13;
only moderately, narrowing from about 8 percent of GDP in 2014 to 6.3 percent in 2015. The&#13;
depreciation will push up inflation, though low international food and fuel prices may hold the&#13;
&#13;
19 This growth forecast has improved since the previous update, which projected 3.2 percent growth in 2015, due to changes&#13;
&#13;
in some key underlying assumptions, including a less severe contraction forecast for Russia (-2.7 percent compared to -3.8&#13;
percent) and more moderate decline in the dollar value of remittances (30 percent compared to 40 percent). It also takes&#13;
into account the latest statistical data from government agencies.&#13;
&#13;
12|&#13;
&amp;#12;average inflation rate to single digits in 2015. The government is committed to keeping the fiscal&#13;
deficit below 0.5 percent of GDP over the medium term, which will require restraining and&#13;
rationalizing expenditures while protecting social programs.&#13;
&#13;
 Figure 22. GDP Growth and Contribution to GDP                  Figure 23. GDP Growth and Poverty Rates&#13;
 Growth by Sector                                               (Percent)&#13;
 (Percent)&#13;
                                                                40,0&#13;
 7,5                                                                                                                 7,5&#13;
                                                                35,0&#13;
&#13;
 6,0                                                            30,0                                                 6,0&#13;
&#13;
                                                                25,0&#13;
 4,5                                                                                                                 4,5&#13;
                                                                20,0&#13;
&#13;
 3,0                                                            15,0                                                 3,0&#13;
&#13;
                                                                10,0&#13;
 1,5                                                                                                                 1,5&#13;
                                                                 5,0&#13;
 0,0                                                             0,0                                                 0,0&#13;
        2012     2013      2014     2015f    2016f      2017f          2012    2013 2014 2015f 2016f 2017f&#13;
           Agriculture        Industry             Services                   Poverty rate (TJS 158.71/month, LHS)&#13;
           Net Taxes          GDP growth                                      GDP growth (RHS)&#13;
&#13;
 Source: TajStat, World Bank staff calculations.                Source: TajStat, World Bank staff calculations.&#13;
&#13;
GDP growth is projected to recover gradually over the medium term, but this forecast is&#13;
subject to significant downside risks. Investment will drive growth, and is projected to rise to 16&#13;
percent of GDP by 2017. Despite a modest projected recovery in exports and remittances the current-&#13;
account deficit is expected to remain at about 6 percent of GDP over the medium term, due largely to&#13;
rising capital-goods imports related to investment projects. The fiscal accounts (excluding externally&#13;
financed public investment programs) are expected to remain roughly balanced over the near term.&#13;
However, external-account volatility, dwindling foreign-exchange reserves, contingent liabilities&#13;
generated by state-owned enterprises and systemic vulnerabilities in the banking sector all pose&#13;
significant downside risks to the macroeconomic outlook.&#13;
&#13;
Slowing GDP growth is expected to limit progress in poverty reduction. The poverty rate is&#13;
projected to fall to 30.7 percent in 2015 and reach 27.3 percent in 2017 (Figure 23). However, lower&#13;
remittances, a weaker labor market, and slower increases in real wages are expected to constrain the&#13;
growth of household purchasing power. The poor are likely to be negatively affected by both the&#13;
decline in remittances and higher inflation rates, though low international food and fuel prices will&#13;
help contain CPI inflation. A lack of effectively targeted social programs leaves households vulnerable&#13;
to economic shocks, underscoring the urgency of implementing the new Targeted Social Assistance&#13;
Program nationwide. This program is relatively modest in size and scope, yet it could play a pivotal&#13;
role in mitigating the impact of a worsening external environment on extremely poor households.&#13;
&#13;
As external conditions continue to deteriorate, it will become increasingly difficult to sustain&#13;
progress in poverty reduction and shared prosperity. In an environment marked by lower&#13;
commodity prices and slowing growth among Tajikistanâ&#128;&#153;s major trading partners, domestic factors&#13;
such as productivity and competitiveness, human capital formation, the development of a more&#13;
robust service sector, and the quality of the investment climate will be critical to Tajikistanâ&#128;&#153;s medium-&#13;
and long-term growth prospects. The challenge of fostering continued growth and development&#13;
despite worsening external conditions will be compounded by the weakening of key foreign labor&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                     |13&#13;
&amp;#12;markets, particularly in Russia, which will not only depress remittances, but is likely to increase the&#13;
domestic labor supply by discouraging emigration. In this context, a focus on creating high-quality&#13;
jobs should serve as a cornerstone of the countryâ&#128;&#153;s development strategy.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
D.       Special Focus Section: Growth and Jobs in Tajikistan20&#13;
Tajikistanâ&#128;&#153;s economy grew at a robust average of 7.9 percent per year during the 2000-2014&#13;
period. Growth was supported by rising export revenues and strong remittance inflows as both the&#13;
global and regional economies expanded rapidly from 2000 to 2009. However, exports of aluminum&#13;
and cotton declined rapidly in the wake of the global financial crisis, and Tajikistanâ&#128;&#153;s economy&#13;
became increasingly dependent on remittances, which peaked to over 50 percent of GDP in 2013.&#13;
&#13;
High growth rates produced remarkable achievements in poverty reduction. Over the past 10&#13;
years Tajikistan has ranked among the top 10 performers in the world in terms of poverty&#13;
reduction.21 The countryâ&#128;&#153;s poverty headcount ratio (at the national poverty line) fell from 96 percent&#13;
in 1999 to an estimated 32 percent in 2014.22 Although Tajikistan became a lower-middle-income&#13;
country in 2014, with a gross national income per capita23 of US$1,080, it remains the poorest&#13;
country in the ECA region. Moreover, less progress has been observed in nonmonetary poverty&#13;
indicators, especially access to education, utilities and other service.24&#13;
&#13;
Rapid economic growth has not translated into robust job creation. Years of strong economic&#13;
and income growth did not produce significant improvements in the availability and quality of jobs&#13;
in Tajikistan, further incentivizing emigration.25 Due in part to limited employment opportunities in&#13;
the domestic labor market, about 1 million Tajikistani citizens have left the country in search of better&#13;
jobs. While the official unemployment rate remains low, a large share of the workforce, including&#13;
one-third of men aged 20-39, has opted to leave the country, with most bound for the Russian&#13;
Federation.26 Over the past year, however, a deepening recession in Russia and the imposition of&#13;
more stringent migration policies by the Russian authorities have encouraged the return of&#13;
Tajikistani migrants, intensifying pressure on the domestic labor market.&#13;
&#13;
Tajikistanâ&#128;&#153;s dependence on remittances and limited economic diversification have left it&#13;
highly vulnerable to external shocks. Despite important gains in income growth and poverty&#13;
reduction, the countryâ&#128;&#153;s current economic model presents several important challenges to its long&#13;
term-development. This Special Focus Section analyzes the key role of employment creation in&#13;
sustaining the countryâ&#128;&#153;s recent progress in poverty reduction and supporting the development of a&#13;
more resilient growth model capable of thriving in a less favorable external environment.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
20 Victoria Strokova is the primary author of this section, with contributions provided by Angela Elzir and David de Padua&#13;
and guidance from Dino Merotto and Marina Bakanova. The analysis presented here is based on research conducted for the&#13;
forthcoming World Bank Jobs Diagnostic and Jobs Strategy for Tajikistan.&#13;
21 Azevedo, Joao Pedro, Aziz Atamanov, and Alisher Rajabov. 2014. â&#128;&#156;Poverty Reduction and Shared Prosperity in Tajikistan:&#13;
&#13;
A Diagnostic,â&#128;&#157; World Bank Working Paper Series. WPS6923.&#13;
22 Due to the change in poverty measurement methodology the 2009 and 2014 data are not fully comparable. See, World&#13;
&#13;
Bank 2014. â&#128;&#156;Tajikistan Economic Reportâ&#128;&#157; No.6, Fall.&#13;
23 World Bank Atlas Method.&#13;
24 Ibid.&#13;
25 While increases in both labor earnings and remittances drove poverty reduction between 2003 and 2009, the creation of&#13;
&#13;
new employment opportunities contributed marginally to poverty reduction See Azevedo, Atamanov and Rajabov (2014).&#13;
26 See: World Bank 2014. â&#128;&#156;The Skills Road: Skills for Employability in Tajikistan,â&#128;&#157; and World Bank (2015) â&#128;&#156;Tajikistan&#13;
&#13;
Economic Updateâ&#128;&#157; No.1. Spring.&#13;
&#13;
14|&#13;
&amp;#12;Tajikistanâ&#128;&#153;s population is relatively young, with a median age of about 25, and the domestic&#13;
labor market is ill equipped to absorb the influx of new workers. While the working-age&#13;
population grew by almost 3.2 percent per year between 2000 and 2014, domestic employment grew&#13;
by just 2.1 percent. During this period annual real GDP growth averaged 7.5 percent, implying an&#13;
average employment-to-growth elasticity of around 0.28. This is slightly lower than the average for&#13;
both developing countries in ECA (0.30) and lower-middle-income countries worldwide (0.32).27&#13;
Moreover, this elasticity decreased significantly following the global financial crisis, from 0.33 in&#13;
2000-2009 to just 0.13 in 2010-14, further slowing the already inadequate pace of job creation.&#13;
&#13;
Tajikistanâ&#128;&#153;s structural transformation has been gradual and incomplete, and the majority of&#13;
workers remain employed in agriculture. The agricultural sector employs about two-thirds of the&#13;
workforce, and this share has remained virtually unchanged since 2000 (Figure 24). Agriculture also&#13;
continues to exhibit the lowest labor productivity of any sector (Figure 25). During the same period&#13;
the share of workers employed in the more productive industrial sector decreased from 7 to 4&#13;
percent. The only subsectors that saw both increased employment and rising labor productivity were&#13;
trade, construction, transportation and communications, all of which began at very low levels.&#13;
&#13;
 Figure 24. Structural Change, 2000-14                                                       Figure 25. Labor Productivity by Sector&#13;
                                                                                             (Value added per worker, thousands of real TJS)&#13;
&#13;
                                                            1,0       Transport and           14&#13;
     Log (Sectoral Productivity/Total&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                     communication&#13;
                                                            0,8                               12&#13;
                                               Industry            Construction Trade &amp;&#13;
           Productivity), 2014&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                            0,6                 material&#13;
                                                                                              10&#13;
                                                                               productio&#13;
                                                            0,4                    n&#13;
                                                                                               8&#13;
                                                            0,2&#13;
                                                                   Other&#13;
                                                                                               6&#13;
                                                             0,0 services&#13;
                                        -4,0         -2,0        0,0        2,0        4,0     4&#13;
                                                            -0,2&#13;
                                                                             Agricultuâ&#128;¦&#13;
                                                            -0,4                               2&#13;
&#13;
                                                            -0,6                               0&#13;
                                                                                                   2000&#13;
                                                                                                          2001&#13;
                                                                                                                 2002&#13;
                                                                                                                        2003&#13;
                                                                                                                               2004&#13;
                                                                                                                                      2005&#13;
                                                                                                                                             2006&#13;
                                                                                                                                                    2007&#13;
                                                                                                                                                           2008&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                  2009&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                         2010&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                2011&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                       2012&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                              2013&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                     2014&#13;
                                                            -0,8&#13;
&#13;
                                                            -1,0                                          Agriculture                                             Industry&#13;
                                          Change in employment share, 2000-2014 (ppts)                    Construction                                            Transport and comm.&#13;
                                                                                                          Retail trade                                            Other services&#13;
 Source: TajStat and World Bank staff calculations.                                          Source: TajStat and World Bank staff calculations.&#13;
 Note: The size of the bubble represents employment&#13;
 share by sector in 2000.&#13;
&#13;
Real wage growth in the formal sector outpaced increases in labor productivity, eroding&#13;
competitiveness and hindering job creation. Labor productivity grew by about 5 percent annually&#13;
between 2000 and 2014, substantially slower than in many comparable countries.28 Real wages in&#13;
the formal sector rose by 326 percent between 2005 and 2014, while labor productivity increased&#13;
by only 61 percent.29 Rising labor earnings play an important role in poverty reduction, but further&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
27 Authorsâ&#128;&#153; calculations using the WDI data. Regional averages are for 2000-2013, as 2014 data are not yet available.&#13;
28 World Bank 2014. â&#128;&#156;The Skills Road: Skills for Employability in Tajikistan.â&#128;&#157; World Bank, Washington, DC.&#13;
29 Tajikistan Country Partnership Strategy FY 15-18 p. 7, World Bank.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                 |15&#13;
&amp;#12;increases in wages without commensurate improvements in underlying labor productivity could&#13;
undermine competitiveness and inhibit job creation.&#13;
&#13;
Services drove the growth of labor productivity, supported by more modest recent&#13;
contributions from agriculture and industry. Increases in labor productivity underpinned the&#13;
growth of GDP per capita in 2000-14, and rising value added per worker in the service sector&#13;
represented more than half of aggregate labor productivity growth (Figure 26), with transportation&#13;
and communications playing the most important role. However, industry and agriculture have&#13;
increased their share dramatically since 2010, with services contributing less than 10 percent to total&#13;
labor productivity growth since the crisis. Inter-sectoral labor mobility is low in Tajikistan, and the&#13;
reallocation of labor has made a slight negative contribution to the growth of value added per&#13;
worker.30 These trends highlight the extent to which the countryâ&#128;&#153;s current model of remittances-&#13;
driven, service-sector-led growth has ceased to provide a sound basis for its continued economic&#13;
development.&#13;
&#13;
 Figure 26. Shapley Decomposition of per Capita GDP and Labor Productivity&#13;
                                                             (a)                                                                                     (b)&#13;
                                              Growth of Value Added per Capita                                                     Productivity Change by Sector&#13;
                                       8                                                                                   8&#13;
                                                                                         % Yearly Contribution to Growth&#13;
     % Yearly Contribution to Growth&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       6                                                                                   6&#13;
&#13;
                                       4                                                                                   4&#13;
&#13;
                                       2                                                                                   2&#13;
&#13;
                                       0                                                                                   0&#13;
&#13;
                                       -2                                                                                  -2&#13;
&#13;
                                       -4                                                                                  -4&#13;
                                            2000-2014 2000-2008    2008-2010 2010-2014                                          2000-2014 2000-2008 2008-2010 2010-2014&#13;
                                             Productivity           Employment rate&#13;
                                             Participation rate     Demographic change                                      Agriculture   Industry    Services   Intersectoral Shift&#13;
&#13;
 Source: TajStat, MoEDT and World Bank staff calculations using the JobStructure tool.&#13;
&#13;
Low rates of job creation are the result of multiple interrelated factors, but an analysis of the&#13;
labor market reveals three overarching causes.31 The first is weak macroeconomic management,&#13;
which undermines the economic stability necessary to attract private investment. The second is an&#13;
inhospitable business environment marked by weak governance, erratic tax administration and&#13;
limited access to quality infrastructure, especially energy and information technology, which inhibits&#13;
diversification and erodes competitiveness. The third is a shortage of workforce skills, low&#13;
geographic and inter-sectoral labor mobility, and information asymmetries in the labor market.&#13;
These factors conspire to constrain employment and income growth and inhibit improvements in&#13;
labor productivity.&#13;
&#13;
In order to sustain progress on poverty reduction and shared prosperity in a worsening&#13;
external environment Tajikistanâ&#128;&#153;s development strategy should prioritize accelerated job&#13;
&#13;
 The only exception to this trend was during the global financial crisis in 2008-2010.&#13;
30&#13;
&#13;
 World Bank 2010. â&#128;&#156;Inclusive Growth Analysis for a Remittance-Dependent Country: The Case of Tajikistanâ&#128;&#157;. World Bank,&#13;
31&#13;
&#13;
Washington, D.C.&#13;
&#13;
16|&#13;
&amp;#12;creation. While remittances have had a highly positive impact on poverty, excessive dependence on&#13;
foreign labor markets is unsustainable and leaves Tajikistan vulnerable to external shocks. Enabling&#13;
private sector development through an improved business environment and the continued&#13;
implementation of the structural reform agenda will be critical to robust employment growth. While&#13;
an enabling environment for private investment will be vital to the creation of high-quality jobs, a&#13;
comprehensive strategy will be necessary to address specific obstacles to private-sector-led growth.&#13;
&#13;
A comprehensive employment-creation strategy should be rooted in three core objectives: (i)&#13;
supporting job growth in the private sector, (ii) building the workforce skills demanded by&#13;
employers, and (iii) facilitating accessibility to jobs among vulnerable people and&#13;
communities. These objectives reflect the unique challenges faced by Tajikistan over both the short&#13;
and medium term. The first is based on the axiom that sustainable job creation requires an efficient&#13;
and competitive private sector. Policy actions designed to advance these objectives would include&#13;
macroeconomic and structural reforms, as well as improvements in the business climate that would&#13;
enable firms to invest, expand, and hire workers.&#13;
&#13;
Employment growth in Tajikistan is constrained by both demand- and supply-side factors.&#13;
Therefore the second objective focuses on developing the workforce skills required by an&#13;
increasingly sophisticated and dynamic labor market. Policy actions in this area range from reforms&#13;
in primary and secondary education to the provision of specialized vocational training tailored to the&#13;
needs of employers.&#13;
&#13;
Finally, promoting a healthy and inclusive labor market will require resolving information&#13;
asymmetries and encouraging labor mobility. Measures to expand the availability of information&#13;
on labor demand and ease the mobility of workers across regions and sectors would leverage the&#13;
impact of improvements in human capital. In addition, strengthening social safety nets would help to&#13;
minimize the risks faced by workers as they attempt to transition to new regions and industries,&#13;
increasing the flexibility of the labor force and enabling employers to attract workers to emerging&#13;
economic sectors.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                  |17&#13;
&amp;#12;Annex 1: Economic and Social Indicators in Tajikistan, 2010â&#128;&#147;17&#13;
(Percent of GDP unless otherwise is stated)&#13;
Selected Indicators                                     2010      2011       2012       2013      2014      2015 a    2016 a     2017a&#13;
&#13;
Income and Economic Growth&#13;
  GDP growth (percent change)                             6.5       7.4        7.5        7.4        6.7       4.2        4.8       5.5&#13;
  GNI per capita, Atlas method (current USD)             730       790        890      1,000      1,080         â&#128;¦          â&#128;¦         â&#128;¦&#13;
  Gross fixed investment                                 11.9      14.3       14.1      13.0       12.8       12.8       14.5      16.0&#13;
Money and Prices&#13;
  Consumer price inflation                                6.4      12.5        5.7        5.0       6.2        8.5        7.5        7.0&#13;
  (percentage&#13;
  Average      change,&#13;
           exchange    annual&#13;
                     rate      average)&#13;
                          (TJS/USD)                      4.38      4.61       4.76       4.77      4.94         â&#128;¦          â&#128;¦          â&#128;¦&#13;
  Real effective exchange rate                           92.1      90.9       92.4       95.1     106.4         â&#128;¦          â&#128;¦          â&#128;¦&#13;
   index (2005=100)&#13;
Fiscal&#13;
  Revenue and grants                                     23.5      25.3       25.5       26.8      28.4       26.3       26.5      27.5&#13;
  Expenditure and net lending                            26.5      27.5       24.9       27.9      28.9       27.7       28.4      29.4&#13;
  Fiscal balance                                         -3.0      -2.2        0.6       -1.0      -0.5       -1.4       -1.9      -1.8&#13;
  Primary fiscal balance                                 -2.5      -1.7        1.2       -0.1       0.5        0.1       -0.9      -0.8&#13;
  Total public debt                                      36.9      36.1       32.9       29.5      22.8       20.0       18.8      18.7&#13;
External Accounts&#13;
  Export of goods &amp; services                             15.9      18.1        22        13.9      11.3        11        11.3      11.9&#13;
  Import of goods &amp; services                             60.5      66.1       70.6       64.2      58.4       48.4       46.9      48.6&#13;
  Workers' remittances, net                              39.8      46.2        44        47.6      42.7         â&#128;¦          â&#128;¦.        â&#128;¦&#13;
  Current account balance                                -6.7       -4.8       -2.6      -2.8       -7.9       -6.3      -6.0       -5.9&#13;
  Foreign direct investment&#13;
                                                           16        65        146       105        198          â&#128;¦         â&#128;¦.            â&#128;¦&#13;
  (USD million)&#13;
Population, Employment, and Poverty&#13;
  Population (millions)                                   7.6        7.8          8       8.2        8.4       8.5        8.7        8.8&#13;
  Population growth (percent change)                      2.4        2.5        2.5       2.5        2.4       1.5        1.5        1.5&#13;
  Unemployment rate (percent of&#13;
                                                          2.1        2.4        2.4       2.4        2.5         â&#128;¦          â&#128;¦            â&#128;¦&#13;
  labor force)b&#13;
  Poverty rate (Somoni 158.71/month)c                       â&#128;¦         â&#128;¦       37.4       34.3        32       30.7       29.1      27.3&#13;
  Life expectancy (years)                                  67      67.1       67.3      67.4          â&#128;¦          â&#128;¦          â&#128;¦            â&#128;¦&#13;
Notes: An ellipsis (â&#128;¦) indicates that data are not available. a - Projections. b - Registered unemployment. c - Calculations are based&#13;
on 2014 HBS with projections using neutral distribution method (2014).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   18|&#13;
&amp;#12;&amp;#12;Tajikistan&#13;
Economic Update No.2 | Fall 2015&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="25489391">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2015/12/25489391/tajikistan-moderate-slowdown-economic-growth-coupled-sharp-decline-household-purchasing-power
        </url>
        <availablein>Russian,English</availablein>
        <fullavailablein>
            <available_in lang="Russian" entityid="090224b083cb87ba_2_0" node_id="25489391"/>
        </fullavailablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2015/12/25489391/tajikistan-moderate-slowdown-economic-growth-coupled-sharp-decline-household-purchasing-power</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2015/12/25489391/tajikistan-moderate-slowdown-economic-growth-coupled-sharp-decline-household-purchasing-power</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2015-12-17T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2015-12-17T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <docm_id>090224b083cb878d</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b083528435</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2015/12/17/090224b083cb878d/2_0/Rendered/INDEX/Tajikistan000A0old0purchasing0power.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2015/12/17/090224b083cb878d/2_0/Rendered/PDF/Tajikistan000A0old0purchasing0power.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2015-11-25T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2015-11-01T23:11:01Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Revised</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309936</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Tajikistan - A moderate slowdown in
            economic growth coupled with a sharp decline in household
            purchasing power
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Tajikistan’s economy exceeded
            expectations during the first six months of 2015 despite a
            challenging external environment. According to official
            data, GDP growth slowed only moderately from 6.7 percent in
            the first half of 2014 to 6.4 percent year on year (y/y) in
            the first half of 2015, even as remittances from Russia
            fell, global demand weakened, and prices for the country’s
            key export commodities such as aluminum and cotton dropped
            significantly. Domestic factors continued to drive growth,
            and both the construction and industrial sectors expanded as
            the economy’s focus shifted from consumption to investment.
            The state budget surplus reached 1 percent of GDP, and the
            external public debt to GDP ratio dropped to below 20
            percent. The sharp decline in remittances is limiting the
            growth of household consumption and could threaten the
            sustainability of recent gains in poverty reduction and
            shared prosperity. According to the National Bank of
            Tajikistan (NBT), remittances dropped by 32 percent (y/y),
            in US dollar terms during the first six months of 2015.
            Although the decline was less dramatic (about 18 percent) in
            Tajikistan somoni (TJS) terms, income losses were much
            larger than implied by GDP statistics. Falling remittances,
            limited employment creation outside the public sector, and
            rising prices are slowing the rate of poverty reduction.
            Moreover, the lack of well-targeted social programs leaves
            households vulnerable to economic shocks.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Tajikistan - A moderate slowdown in economic
            growth coupled with a sharp decline in household purchasing power
        </docna>
        <display_title>Tajikistan - A moderate slowdown
            in economic growth coupled with a sharp decline in household
            purchasing power</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2015/11/25489391/tajikistan-moderate-slowdown-economic-growth-coupled-sharp-decline-household-purchasing-power</listing_relative_url>
        <topic>Economic Analysis of Education m1327512 2124,Economic Growth Policy m1327634 1070,Economic Growth Project Analysis m1327635 1071,Economic Growth m1326241 471</topic>
        <docty>Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>Debt Markets,Currencies and Exchange Rates,Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Access to Finance,Economic Theory &amp; Research</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Environment,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</teratopic>
        <count>Tajikistan</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Bakanova,Marina</author>
            <author>Sobirzoda,Ravshan</author>
            <author>Rajabov,Alisher</author>
            <author>Odinaeva,Zarina</author>
            <author>Strokova,Victoria</author>
            <author>Elzir,Angela</author>
            <author>De Padua,David Keith Santos</author>
            <author>Merotto,Dino Leonardo</author>
        </authors>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>South Eastern Europe and Balkans!$!517208</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!517191</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Asia!$!517198</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Central Asia!$!545134</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Commonwealth of Independent States!$!82689</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>090224b083cb878d_2_0</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>Europe and Central Asia,Europe and Central Asia</admreg>
        <colti>Tajikistan economic update no. 2</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Environment,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</historic_topic>
        <topicv3>Economic Analysis of Education m1327512 2124,Economic Growth Policy m1327634 1070,Economic Growth Project Analysis m1327635 1071,Economic Growth m1326241 471</topicv3>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            living standards, debt source, tariffs,
            contingent liabilities, monetary policy, deficit, deposit,
            basis points, npl, economic growth, equipment, accounting,
            deposits, broad money, financial management, stock,
            information technology, perverse incentives, macroeconomic
            management, interest, post-crisis period, public
            investments, expectations, interest rate, remittance,
            private credit, exchange, banking system, balance of
            payments, economic developments, consumer goods, reserve
            requirements, liquidity, labor force, developing countries,
            domestic market, repayments, debt- service, revenues,
            capital adequacy, incentives, loan, administrative controls,
            tax, real wages, reserve, creditors, inflation, pension,
            creditor, information asymmetries, safety nets, enabling
            environment, budget, central bank, maturity, economic
            activity, labor market, oil prices, maturity mismatches,
            oil, currency, loan rate, population growth, income growth,
            capital formation, income inequality, conversions, exchange
            rates, trading, labor productivity, interest rates, credit
            risks, markets, debt, private investment, household income,
            return, inflation rate, forestry, lenders, financial sector
            developments, accounts receivable, loans, direct investment,
            reserves, capital investments, gross domestic product,
            metals, financial system, commodity price, return on assets,
            finance, foreign currency, food production, public
            investment, taxes, banking sector, fiscal deficit,
            expenditure, resources, debt levels, unemployment, equity,
            transaction, macroeconomic environment, investors,
            productivity growth, consumption, human capital, wages,
            climate change, values, budget surplus, financial crisis,
            turnover, credit access, pensions, foreign direct
            investment, credit, fixed investment, purchasing power,
            demand, cpi, prudential regulations, national income,
            farming households, investment projects, contract, financial
            performance, expenditures, asset quality, current account
            deficit, market, environment, principal repayments, public
            debt, financial infrastructure, inflation rates, currencies,
            economic development, trade, land, goods, security,
            nonperforming loan, national bank, investment, human
            resources, share, investment climate, poverty, revenue,
            external debt, investments, risk management, lending,
            consumer price index, credit growth, credit culture,
            exchange rate, fiscal discipline, remittances, capital
            investment, labor markets, liabilities, commodity prices,
            arrears, credit institutions, prices, development bank,
            swap, nonperforming loans, economic conditions, human development
        </keywd>
        <owner>Macro &amp; Fiscal Mgmt - GP (GMFDR)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>South Eastern Europe and Balkans</geo_region>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Central Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Commonwealth of Independent States</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>101278</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shocks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Safety Nets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Safety Nets and Transfers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Safety Nets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monetary and Exchange Rate Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Remittances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Migration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Employment and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Improving Labor Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Labor Market Interventions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Labor Markets, Job Creation and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wage Setting</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages, Compensation and Benefits</ml:concept><ml:concept>External Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shocks and Vulnerability</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Assistance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inflation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monetary Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Movement of Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Labor Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>State Associations</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Tajikistan</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Central Asia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>