<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>                                      3&#13;
COMPETITIVE CITIES FOR JOBS AND GROWTH&#13;
                                         101713&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
COMPANION PAPER 3&#13;
&#13;
SIX CASE STUDIES&#13;
OF ECONOMICALLY&#13;
SUCCESSFUL CITIES&#13;
Z. Joe Kulenovic and Alexandra Cech&#13;
December 2015&#13;
&amp;#12;2&#13;
&amp;#12;TABLE OF&#13;
CONTENTS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Background and Acknowledgments 5&#13;
&#13;
Executive Summary 6								&#13;
City competitiveness: General or specific? 6&#13;
Strategic planning 7&#13;
Implementation framework 7&#13;
&#13;
1. Key Concepts: Framing the Analysis 8					&#13;
Identifying and selecting â&#128;&#156;competitiveâ&#128;&#157; cities 8&#13;
City typologies 8&#13;
Case study cities 9&#13;
What do these cities exemplify? 11&#13;
&#13;
2. Analysis: What Have Successful Cities Doneâ&#128;&#148;and How? 11			&#13;
&#13;
3. Strategies and Interventions 14						&#13;
Strategic planning for economic development 14&#13;
Observed interventions and the reasons for their success 16&#13;
&#13;
4. Insights for Other Cities 24							&#13;
City competitiveness: General or specific? 24&#13;
Institutional framework 25&#13;
Strategic planning 25&#13;
Interventions 26&#13;
&#13;
References 28&#13;
&#13;
Appendix&#13;
Hypothesis for Competitive Cities Case Studies 29&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                               3&#13;
&amp;#12;4&#13;
&amp;#12;BACKGROUND AND&#13;
ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
I&#13;
   nterest in studying city competitiveness has skyrocketed         The objective of this paper is to synthesize the findings of&#13;
   in the past few years, although the topic itself is far from     six individual case studies (Bucaramanga, Colombia; Coim-&#13;
   new. Mayors and city leaders have long worried about             batore, India; Kigali, Rwanda; Gaziantep, Turkey; Changsha,&#13;
the obstacles to job creation, competitiveness, and economic        China; and Tangier, Morocco) by analyzing the similarities&#13;
growth that plague their cities.                                    and dissimilarities among them and identifying common,&#13;
                                                                    cross-cutting themes. The intent is to highlight what insti-&#13;
This paper is part of a broader research initiative, the Com-       tutions and strategies successful cities have relied on to spur&#13;
petitive Cities Knowledge Base, which is managed jointly            economic development, under what conditions such success&#13;
by the Trade and Competitiveness Global Practice and the            has occurred, and what lessons of this experience might be&#13;
Social, Urban, Rural, and Resilience Global Practice of the         applicable to decision makers in other cities.&#13;
World Bank Group. Its objective is to create a knowledge base&#13;
on competitive cities, to improve the understanding of job          The individual case study reports, which appear in the ap-&#13;
creation at city level and as a foundation for a community of       pendixes, were based on primary and secondary research, in-&#13;
practice on this topic for World Bank staff, academia, donor        cluding approximately two to three weeks spent in each city&#13;
partners, and practitioners.                                        during 2014. For each case study, interviews were organized&#13;
                                                                    with national and local government officials, members of&#13;
Our attempt in this initiative has been to focus our energies       the cityâ&#128;&#153;s business community, academia, and various other&#13;
on bringing to our clients a robust body of knowledge that          stakeholder groups. The reports also incorporate World Bank&#13;
will address their questions on benchmarking their perfor-          staff feedback received at several review events in Washing-&#13;
mance, on understanding what has worked elsewhere and               ton, D.C.&#13;
what has not, and on looking at ways to organize for delivery&#13;
in different contexts.                                              This report was prepared by Z. Joe Kulenovic and Alexandra&#13;
                                                                    Cech, with input and suggestions from Drilon Gashi, Luke&#13;
Our approach has focused on using different methodologies           Jordan, Austin Kilroy, Megha Mukim, and T. Juni Zhu, as&#13;
to tackle these questions. These methodologies are based on         well as World Bank staff members in country offices where&#13;
best practices, data availability, replicability, and simplicity.   these cities are located. The joint team task leaders of the&#13;
In many cases, we leveraged new and existing data sources           Competitive Cities Knowledge Base project are Austin Kilroy&#13;
to shed new light on some unanswered questions; in others,          and Megha Mukim. Stefano Negri, Sameh Wahba, Ceci Sager,&#13;
we have conducted primary research because available data           and Somik Lall have provided overall guidance on the project&#13;
were inadequate. We looked at global and regional trends,           as senior advisers.&#13;
comparing different typologies of cities by income, sector, re-&#13;
gion, and so on. And we have buttressed these findings with         The team would like to acknowledge gratefully the European&#13;
econometric deep dives and case studies in selected countries       Commission; the African, Caribbean, and Pacific Group of&#13;
and cities. We are able to inform the ongoing debates on what       States Secretariat; and the governments of Austria, Norway,&#13;
really matters for economic outcomes in cities with analysis        and Switzerland for financing this study through the Com-&#13;
of overarching trends and associations, supplemented with           petitive Industries and Innovation Program.&#13;
rigorous analyses to identify causal relationships. We also try&#13;
to â&#128;&#156;stand on the shoulders of giantsâ&#128;&#157; where possible: that is,&#13;
we use and reference existing resources (research, analysis,&#13;
toolkits, and experts). The summary findings of the overall&#13;
research are presented in the framework report Competitive&#13;
Cities for Jobs and Growth (World Bank, 2015).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                             5&#13;
&amp;#12;EXECUTIVE SUMMARY&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
A&#13;
        lthough every city in the world is striving to create       export promotion initiatives). These cities used extensive&#13;
        jobs for its citizens and improve economic growth, no       dialogue and a solid fact base to anchor their priorities in real&#13;
        single path leads to economic success. Our in-depth         comparative advantages, thus minimizing the ever-present&#13;
study of six economically successful cities from different          risk of capture and market distortion (such as subsidies or&#13;
parts of the world (Bucaramanga, Colombia; Coimbatore,              protectionist measures) and eventually showing the enviable&#13;
India; Kigali, Rwanda; Gaziantep, Turkey; Changsha, China;          ability to let the losers go when some sectors were recognized&#13;
and Tangier, Morocco) uncovered how each of these cities has        as not globally competitive.&#13;
pursued its own path to prosperity, taking into accountâ&#128;&#148;&#13;
consciously or unconsciouslyâ&#128;&#148;its own particular competi-            Several of these successful cities had a main themeâ&#128;&#148;one&#13;
tive advantages, existing constraints, national policies, local     area where they particularly excelled and for which they&#13;
administrative scope and capacity, overall market trends, and       wanted to be recognized. For example, in Kigali, the focus&#13;
even administrative and cultural traditions. These six cities       was on improving city livability and postconflict reconstruc-&#13;
are as different from each other as they are successful. Along      tion; Coimbatore is almost synonymous with its mechanical&#13;
their path to success, they tackled very different challenges       engineering sector; and Gaziantep is all about export-driven&#13;
that in their diversity may be comparable to those encoun-          growth, especially for select products such as carpets or&#13;
tered by the majority of other cities worldwide.                    pasta. Changsha is the only high-income city in this group,&#13;
                                                                    and it has developed a world-class construction machinery&#13;
The case studies were carried out by relying on a set of            industry. Tangier now has Africaâ&#128;&#153;s largest port and provides&#13;
standardized research hypotheses, thereby ensuring the              an example of a city successfully leveraging its geography and&#13;
comparability of findings among the six cities. This executive      national government initiatives to become a player in logis-&#13;
summary is therefore presented in a format that is based on         tics, auto manufacturing, and aerospace. Finally, Bucaraman-&#13;
those hypotheses; the reportâ&#128;&#153;s main body provides more de-          ga exemplifies the transition from commoditized manufac-&#13;
tail and explores individual themes that this summary does          turing to the new knowledge-based service economy.&#13;
not address.&#13;
                                                                    The proactive efforts of all six cities emphasized the produc-&#13;
City competitiveness: General or specific?                          tion of tradable goods and services. This focus translated into&#13;
                                                                    dedicated initiatives for those sectors. Nonetheless, nontrad-&#13;
No real-world trade-off seems to exist between cities striving      ables remain the mainstay of many of these metropolitan&#13;
to have a favorable overall business climate and those target-      economies and their employment, and nontradable sectors&#13;
ing individual sectors for proactive economic development           were not ignored in identifying priority interventions to spur&#13;
initiatives. Most cities successfully did both. Regardless of       job creationâ&#128;&#148;they were just treated differently. The evolution&#13;
whether public or private sector entities led their economic        from a closed, inward-looking economy to one mostly focused&#13;
development efforts, all six cities prioritized the provision       on global markets is a gradual one.&#13;
of basic enabling infrastructure and municipal services as&#13;
necessary to attract and retain investment. Wherever prac-          These high-performing cities have nurtured not only in-&#13;
tical and within the cityâ&#128;&#153;s scope to do so, bureaucracy was         vestments but also new business starts and the growth&#13;
streamlined, issuance of permits and licenses was simpli-           of existing firms. Although the attraction of high-profile&#13;
fied and expedited, and some services were enabled online.          outside investors has garnered the most attention for these&#13;
Offering an environment conducive to business formation             cities, most jobs are actually created through the growth of&#13;
and growth was seen as crucial in all six cities and benefited      existing firms, sometimes in supplier relationships with the&#13;
all industries. At the same time, most cities did target specific   new investors. The formation of new businesses is said to be&#13;
sectors for economic development with explicit support for          supported by all six cities, yet limited evidence exists that&#13;
their growth (for example, by providing dedicated training          this third pillar has been a major component of their recent&#13;
programs, marketing efforts, targeted infrastructure, or            growth.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
6&#13;
&amp;#12;Strategic planning                                                 Implementation framework&#13;
The six case studies paid particular attention to visible in-      The level of autonomy (fiscal, institutional, and political) and&#13;
flection points in the citiesâ&#128;&#153; economic performance over time      powers enjoyed by the government or local economic develop-&#13;
and to whether they could be attributed to specific proactive      ment authority of these citiesâ&#128;&#148;the â&#128;&#156;mayorâ&#128;&#153;s wedgeâ&#128;&#157;â&#128;&#148;has been&#13;
interventions. Although establishing causality is seldom           somewhat of a factor in their ability to push through interven-&#13;
a straightforward process, examples of strong temporal             tions that improved economic outcomes, though not necessarily&#13;
correlations have been found in several instances, suggesting      a decisive one. Some cities did not have a dedicated economic&#13;
that a more activist approach to economic growth, when well        development agency or department with sufficient autonomy&#13;
executed, may be part of the explanation.                          and funding.&#13;
&#13;
Most of the case study cities used some sort of strategic          Internal management processes within city governments were&#13;
planning for economic development, even if that strategy was       very important in only a couple of case study cities (Kigali and&#13;
not always formalized in a document or developed through a         Changsha). Most cities did not rely heavily on such internal&#13;
structured process. Strategy development was often based on        structures and arrangements because their overall approach to&#13;
robust analytics to assess competitive advantages and market       economic development involved other groups of stakeholders&#13;
opportunities, as well as on a consultative process involving      (particularly private sector firms and their associations, or even&#13;
businesses and other stakeholders in identifying key econom-       broader citywide coalitions) to a much more substantial degree.&#13;
ic development issues and constraints to growth and, some-&#13;
times, in formulating a shared long-term vision for the city.      Private for-profit firms, their associations, and other stakehold-&#13;
                                                                   er groups were highly involved in implementing city economic&#13;
All of the case study cities used some form of public-private      development strategies and interventions, though not to the&#13;
dialogue, which had a visible bearing on their economic            same extent in all cities. Their involvement included but was&#13;
outcomes. Several cities assembled â&#128;&#156;growth coalitionsâ&#128;&#157; by          not limited to providing financial and in-kind resources, acting&#13;
bringing together government agencies and diverse external         as the cityâ&#128;&#153;s public champions, collaborating with educational&#13;
stakeholder groups from civil society and engaging these           institutions to train workers and design adequate programs, and&#13;
coalitions in providing input on key issues and in making          in some cases (most dramatically in Coimbatore) actually leading&#13;
suggestions for addressing those issues.                           local development efforts.&#13;
&#13;
Only limited evidence suggests that these cities used a struc-     Path dependency is not destiny: some cities inherited advantages&#13;
tured process for evaluating policy priorities and trade-offs      (such as educational institutions, strong local identities, cultures&#13;
between different public investment alternatives, such as          conducive to business, and the like), whereas others did not. Still,&#13;
cost-benefit analyses. Interventions were largely undertaken       successful cities made the most of what little they may have had&#13;
on the basis of available funding and in response to evolving      to power ahead of competitors. A common theme across all six&#13;
opportunities; they were not evaluated against the benefits        cities is that they successfully worked with what they had going&#13;
that could have accrued from alternative courses of action.        for them as a competitive advantage (for example, skilled people,&#13;
                                                                   geography, language, cultural ties, technical know-how, existing&#13;
Depending on their specific institutional frameworks for eco-      industry base, or product and market knowledge).&#13;
nomic development, not all cities had robust or sustainable&#13;
funding mechanisms in place. In general, cities where public       Successful cities seized on opportunities when they presented&#13;
sector entities had primary responsibility for these activities    themselves and created their own opportunities where none&#13;
had a somewhat higher degree of funding stability; in some         arose naturally. In general, they forged their own paths and&#13;
cities, economic development received no public funding at         pursued growth where it made sense, rather than jump on band-&#13;
all, but because of their great importance, initiatives received   wagons and follow the latest economic development fads (such&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                               7&#13;
the support of private business membership organizations.          as biotech, software, clean technology, and the like).&#13;
&amp;#12;1. Key Concepts: Framing the Analysis                               set of macroeconomic conditions and national policies did&#13;
                                                                    not offered useful lessons regarding potential strategies and&#13;
Identifying and selecting â&#128;&#156;competitiveâ&#128;&#157; cities                      effective levers that could be used at the metropolitan level to&#13;
                                                                    improve economic growth.2&#13;
What exactly is meant by competitiveness at the city level?&#13;
We define a competitive city as a city which uses resources at      City typologies&#13;
its disposal to facilitate firms and industries to grow jobs,&#13;
productivity, and incomes over time. For the purpose of these       The six economically successful cities included in the case&#13;
case studies, cities have been assumed to be competitive if         studies are quite diverse. This diversity was purposefully&#13;
they have enjoyed success in expanding metropolitan gross           sought when the case studies were selected to increase the&#13;
domestic product (GDP) and creating jobs. Emphasizing that          applicability and replicability of these citiesâ&#128;&#153; experiences for&#13;
this competitiveness is observed through a rearview mir-            the World Bankâ&#128;&#153;s varied clients across all regions and income&#13;
rorâ&#128;&#148;that is, it reflects robust past performance and cannot         levels.&#13;
predict future economic performanceâ&#128;&#148;is important. Predict-&#13;
ing future performance is not the objective of this analysis.       The six cities have different economic structures, population&#13;
                                                                    sizes, roles in their respective national economies, levels of&#13;
What constitutes success for a metropolitan economy? De-            development and income, governance and institutional struc-&#13;
pending on the specific focus, one can define a successful city     tures, competitive advantages, and cultural contexts. Each&#13;
as broadly or as narrowly as one likes.1 In this context, the       lies in a different geographic region of the world, operating&#13;
focus is very much on economic development, not broader             under different kinds of political and legal systems. In other&#13;
social indicators that are important but fall outside the im-       words, these cities are as varied as the countries and regions&#13;
mediate scope of this analysis. Cities were deemed successful       in which they are located. These six cities are thus in a very&#13;
if they outperformed their national economies as well as            real sense a microcosm of the entire world, at least as far as&#13;
outperforming other cities in that geographic region of the         its urban dimension is concerned.&#13;
world in terms of GDP and employment growth. But to pro-&#13;
duce case studies yielding useful teachable moments, these          In terms of population size, most of the case study cities are&#13;
successful cities also needed to offer examples of specific         midsize by global standards. They mostly have metropolitan&#13;
challenges that were overcome or historic opportunities that        area populations between 1 million and 2 million, except for&#13;
were seized to jump-start economic growth and job creation.         Coimbatore (2.2 million) and Changsha (6.6 million). With&#13;
Understanding how these high-performing cities were able            the sole exception of Changsha, which is substantially more&#13;
to achieve high levels of growth while others facing the same       populous than the others, the cities in this sample are large&#13;
                                                                    enough to be emerging economic hubs yet compact enough&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Map 1.1 City GDP per capita in 2012&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                   Gaziantep&#13;
                                                    Tangier        US$5,902&#13;
                                                    US$2,661                                 Changsa&#13;
                                                                                             US$15,340&#13;
                                                                                   Coimbatore&#13;
                           Bucaramanga                                             US$3,046&#13;
                           US$11,529                              Kigali&#13;
                                                                  US$1,380&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
8&#13;
&amp;#12;for most of their key decision makers (from both the public&#13;
and private sectors3) to personally know each other and inter-     Case study cities&#13;
act directly on an almost daily basis.&#13;
                                                                   Perhaps unsurprising given their locations on various con-&#13;
Except for the sole capital city in our sample (Kigali), all the   tinents, the six case study cities operate in very divergent&#13;
cities are secondary metropolitan areas. As secondary cities,      environments in the area of institutions and governance.&#13;
most of the metropolitan economies studied do not play             The sample includes cities in highly centralized countries&#13;
dominant roles in their respective national economies. Many        (Morocco, Rwanda, and Turkey); highly decentralized ones&#13;
of them are geographically remote or somewhat isolated from        (Colombia); and very large countries where some functions&#13;
the political capitals or major economic hubs of their coun-       are concentrated at a subnational level higher than the city&#13;
tries and so have had to be largely self-reliant for production    (China and India). In practice, economic development func-&#13;
and local development. All but one (Tangier) are landlocked        tions are carried out by a range of institutional actors at vari-&#13;
and so do not enjoy the transportation and logistics advan-        ous government levels (national, state or provincial, regional&#13;
tages associated with a maritime location.                         or departmental, local) or in the private sector.&#13;
&#13;
The six case study cities span a range of income levels, from      The cities studied have very different economic structures,&#13;
low to middle to high. For example, Changsha has roughly           and a range of specific industry sectors driving their growth&#13;
11 times the per capita income of Kigali. According to the         are documented in the case studies.4 Some citiesâ&#128;&#153; economies&#13;
classification used in the World Development Report 2009           are highly manufacturing intensive (Changsha, Gaziantep),&#13;
(World Bank 2009), two case study cities would roughly fall        whereas others are relatively diversified (Bucaramanga,&#13;
into the category of market towns, with GDP per capita of ap-      Coimbatore, Tangier); Kigali has a largely preindustrial&#13;
proximately US$2,500 or less; the others would be considered       economy dominated by nontradable services and some&#13;
production centers, with GDP per capita between approx-            tourism. None of the case study cities has an economy based&#13;
imately US$2,500 and US$20,000 (see map 1.1). One city,            primarily on extractive industries (natural resource wealth),&#13;
Changsha, would be on the verge of becoming a creative and         major military installations, or other nonreplicable economic&#13;
financial service center, the last and most developed category.    advantages. We avoided studying cities benefiting from path&#13;
The differences between the cities in physical infrastructure,     dependency in ways that are highly specialized and therefore&#13;
industrial structure, research and financial resources, levels     not likely to offer teachable moments for other cities around&#13;
of human capital, and nature of developmental challenges           the world. See table 1.1 for selected indicators.&#13;
faced provide a highly representative sample of the situations&#13;
World Bank clients typically encounter.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                             9&#13;
&amp;#12;Table 1.1 Selected indicators by city&#13;
&#13;
 Indicator                Bucaramanga              Changsha             Coimbatore             Gaziantep                Kigali               Tangier&#13;
 Country                      Colombia                China                  India                Turkey               Rwanda                Morocco&#13;
&#13;
 National adminis-         Decentralized     Centralized     Decentralized    Decentralized     Centralized                                Centralized&#13;
 trative system           unitary republic unitary republic federal republic unitary republic unitary republic                            unitary mon-&#13;
                                                                                                                                              archy&#13;
 Subnational ad-            Departments             Provinces          States, districts        Provinces                None             Regions, prov-&#13;
 ministrative units                                                                                                                       inces/ prefec-&#13;
                                                                                                                                              tures&#13;
 Local administra-         Bucaramanga           Changsha City          Coimbatore              Gaziantep             Unknown            Urban Commu-&#13;
 tive units                Metropolitan                                Municipal Cor-         Metropolitan                               nity of Tangier&#13;
                           Area, four mu-                                poration             Municipality,&#13;
                            nicipalities                                                      three munici-&#13;
                                                                                                 palities&#13;
 Population, 2012                 1.1                   6.6                   2.2                   1.2                   1.1                   0.83&#13;
 (millions)&#13;
 GDP, 2012                       12.8                  101.1                  6.7                   7.0                   1.5                   2.2&#13;
 (US$Â billions)&#13;
 Income status              Upper middle               High             Lower middle          Lower middle                Low             Lower middle&#13;
 Per capita GDP,                11,529                15,340                 3,046                 5,903                 1,380                 2,661&#13;
 2012 (US$)&#13;
 Per capita GDP,                  149                   256                   222                    56                   218                    89&#13;
 2012 (% of nation-&#13;
 al average)&#13;
 Absolute GDP                    14.9                  96.4                  82.1                    34                  64.6                   11.3&#13;
 growth, 2007â&#128;&#147;12&#13;
 (%)&#13;
 Average annual                   5.8                  14.5                  11.5                   6.3                   11.7                  4.9&#13;
 GDP growth,&#13;
 2002â&#128;&#147;12a (%)&#13;
 Job growth, 2007â&#128;&#147;               26.3                  38.8                   7.3                  39.0                   33.7                  4.0&#13;
 12 (%)&#13;
 Average annu-                    2.9                   6.3                   3.2                   3.6                   8.0                   2.9&#13;
 al job growth,&#13;
 2002â&#128;&#147;12 (%)&#13;
 City Gini coeffi-               0.62                  0.53                  0.52                  0.38                   0.70                  0.48&#13;
 cient&#13;
 City employment                 0.24                  0.26                  0.27                  0.25                   0.22                  0.26&#13;
 diversification&#13;
 (HHI),b 2012&#13;
 Main existing and          Food, health   Manufacturing, Business pro-     Carpets, light  Tourism, non-                                Logistics, auto,&#13;
 emerging econom-           care, apparel, heavy engineer- cess outsourc- manufacturing, traded services,                                  aerospace,&#13;
 ic sectors                footwear, edu-   ing, tradable   ing, precision apparel, agroin-  construction                                 medical sup-&#13;
                          cation, tourism,     services    manufacturing, dustry, chemi-                                                 plies, tourism,&#13;
                            construction,   especially in     machinery     cals, construc-                                                  textiles&#13;
                            business pro-    creative cul-   engineering,  tion materials,&#13;
                           cess outsourc- tural industry textiles, educa-        trade&#13;
                             ing, energy    (film and TV    tion, services&#13;
                                             production)&#13;
&#13;
a. To ensure a common deflator is used to calculate real growth for all cities and countries, we extract numbers from the Oxford Economics database. However,&#13;
for Gaziantep and Tangier, the average annual GDP growth rate and annual job growth rate are available only since 2005; therefore, the numbers reported are&#13;
an annual average for 2005â&#128;&#147;12. For Changsha, the average annual job growth number is for 2003â&#128;&#147;12.&#13;
b. HHI is the Herfindahlâ&#128;&#147;Hirschman Index, commonly used in economics and other social sciences as a measure of diversity.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
10&#13;
&amp;#12;What do these cities exemplify?                                   2. Analysis: What Have Successful&#13;
                                                                  Cities Doneâ&#128;&#148;and How?&#13;
Despite their apparent differences, these six cities have some&#13;
broad commonalities. Their circumstancesâ&#128;&#148;the sets of chal-        Operating under very different institutional and legal frame-&#13;
lenges they faced and overcomeâ&#128;&#148;can be grouped into the            works, our six case study cities have undertaken a range of&#13;
following broad categories, which are precisely what makes        successful interventions to improve economic outcomes. This&#13;
them interesting examples to study. An individual city can, of    analysis examines some of the commonalities and differenc-&#13;
course, be an example of more than one kind of phenomenon.        es among them to extract teachable moments for city-level&#13;
                                                                  decision makers around the world. Perhaps more important,&#13;
â&#128;¢	   Transformation economies. Faced with the erosion of their    we seek to understand why these cities have enjoyed success&#13;
     traditional economic structures because of changing cir-     in their initiatives where so many others have failed.&#13;
     cumstances (for example, global competition or altered&#13;
     patterns of commerce), cities such as Bucaramanga,           Our six case study cities have in place differing institutional&#13;
     Changsha, and Coimbatore have successfully reinvented        arrangements for local economic development. Interestingly,&#13;
     their metropolitan economies.                                we found in our case studies that precisely who performed&#13;
                                                                  a particular role in economic development did not matter as&#13;
â&#128;¢	   Recovery economies. Recovering from economic and demo-       long as someone did. Depending on the nature of their legal&#13;
     graphic disruptions brought about by disasters (natural      and political systems, the degree of centralization in the&#13;
     or manmade), cities such as Bucaramanga and Kigali are       country, and the relative strength of the local private sectors,&#13;
     rebuilding and reconstructing themselves.                    cities have approached the organization of economic develop-&#13;
                                                                  ment efforts in a variety of ways:&#13;
â&#128;¢	   Globalizing city economies. The majority of the case study&#13;
     cities are located in countries that are today more open     â&#128;¢	   A predominantly public model. A dedicated city economic&#13;
     to the outside world than they were a decade or two ago.          development agency or local government department&#13;
     Closer integration into global value chains, along with a         (Changsha, Kigali, Tangier) is responsible for performing&#13;
     deliberate internationalization strategy as an economic           key functions such as investment attraction, entre-&#13;
     development tool, has been observed in some of them.              preneurial assistance, or capacity building. This model&#13;
     This group includes Changsha, Coimbatore, Gaziantep,              seems to be prevalent where (a) the state traditionally&#13;
     and Tangier.                                                      has a strong role, (b) the local private sector is underde-&#13;
                                                                       veloped, or (c) both conditions exist.5&#13;
â&#128;¢	   Catch-up economies. In all of our case study cities, eco-&#13;
     nomic growth has been robust in recent years, yet indi-      â&#128;¢	   A mixed public-private model. Local government and&#13;
     cations are that in several of them at least some of that         the private sector share responsibilities for carrying&#13;
     expansion was catch-up growth; that is, they made ef-             out economic development functions (Bucaramanga,&#13;
     forts to close the gap with more developed cities in their        Gaziantep). In general, local government plays a broadly&#13;
     countries or regions. As factor prices converge within            supportive role, participates in (and perhaps initiates)&#13;
     their countries, such growth can be expected to gradual-          public-private dialogue, and is attentive to the needs of&#13;
     ly taper off. Related to this situation is the phenomenon         business. But mayors do not play a dominant role in eco-&#13;
     of spillover growth, in which economic activity branches          nomic development: they see creation of jobs, increases&#13;
     out from existing dominant economic hubs into tier 2              in production and exports, and the like as private sector&#13;
     or tier 3 cities as their countriesâ&#128;&#153; emerging centers, in         functions. This model works in circumstances where&#13;
     the process shifting economic geography within those              strong capacity and engagement exist within the local&#13;
     countries. Examples include Changsha, Coimbatore,                 private sector, often in the form of established (some-&#13;
     Gaziantep, and Tangier.                                           times family-owned) indigenous firms, whose leaders act&#13;
                                                                       as the cityâ&#128;&#153;s champions and contribute more than just&#13;
This list is by no means exhaustive: through fieldwork many&#13;
                                                                       time and financial resources to economic development.&#13;
other kinds of phenomena are observed, which have been&#13;
documented in the individual case study reports, but these&#13;
are some of the more common.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                    11&#13;
&amp;#12;â&#128;¢	   A wholly private sectorâ&#128;&#147;driven model. Local government fo-     government, industry, and academia who were able to work&#13;
     cuses mostly on providing public goods, such as enabling       together for the advancement of their city. Of course, by vir-&#13;
     trunk infrastructure and physical security, but otherwise      tue of their high political and social profiles, mayors and oth-&#13;
     does not directly intervene in investment attraction or        er senior government officials have often been able to play an&#13;
     company formation and growth (Coimbatore). Local               effective role in convening different groups of stakeholders,&#13;
     government may lack the legal scope for interventions          as well as to act as boosters and global salespersons for their&#13;
     or just not have the institutional capacity to exercise the    cities, especially on foreign trade and investment promotion&#13;
     legal prerogatives that it does have. In this model, private   missions. But the effects of mayoral actions were greatly am-&#13;
     sector leadership may in part or in whole result from the      plified in cities with a highly engaged, capable private sector.&#13;
     absence of government involvement or governmentâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
     inability to perform certain economic development              In every city studied, its national or state government had&#13;
     functions. As in the mixed model, a capable and highly         some role in economic development and enterprise support,&#13;
     engaged local private sector is essential, and it may draw     especially programs for upgrading of skills and technologies,&#13;
     on national or state-level support tools and programs.         capital access, and export facilitation. One commonality&#13;
                                                                    among practically all the case study cities has been their su-&#13;
The schematic in figure 2.1 reveals the relative roles of the       perior ability to tap into national or state-level support tools&#13;
public and private sectors in the economic development of           through encouragement and guidance by either the local&#13;
each case study city. They range from cities whose success          government (Changsha, Kigali, Tangier) or the local private&#13;
largely depended on direct central government interventions         sector (Bucaramanga, Coimbatore, Gaziantep). Although&#13;
(Tangier, Kigali) or local government ones (Changsha), to           some examples exist of local offices of national or state&#13;
success stories driven mainly by the private sector where           agencies being responsible for implementing national support&#13;
government played a supportive or supporting role (Bucara-          programs (Bucaramanga, Coimbatore, Gaziantep, Tangier),&#13;
manga, Gaziantep). This group also has a lone example where         more often local government agencies or private sector or-&#13;
typical economic development functions were largely per-            ganizations such as chambers of commerce enabled firms to&#13;
formed by private, for-profit firms or industry associations        benefit from this support.&#13;
(Coimbatore).&#13;
                                                                    However, perhaps more important than which actors (local&#13;
The role of the private sector in urban economic development        or national, public or private) had primary responsibility for&#13;
has generally been more substantial than we had originally          metropolitan economic development is the question of how&#13;
anticipated before we carried out our research for the case         effective cities and entities in them have been at carrying&#13;
studies. Most of these citiesâ&#128;&#153; success stories were not in fact     out key economic development functions. These functions&#13;
tales of visionary mayors or other senior public sector offi-       include the following sets of specific activities:&#13;
cials single-handedly transforming metropolitan economies,&#13;
but rather accounts of diverse groups of representatives from       â&#128;¢	   Analytics and promotion. These activities consist of com-&#13;
                                                                         petitiveness analysis, planning, market research, lead&#13;
                                                                         generation, branding and marketing, and firm targeting.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 2.1 Who led local economic development effort in each city?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                     National Government&#13;
&#13;
                                                     Tangier&#13;
                                            Kigali&#13;
                                                                                   Bucaramanga&#13;
                                                                              Gaziantep&#13;
                Public Sector                                                              Private Sector&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                               Changsha                                        Coimbatore&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                      Local Government&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 12&#13;
&amp;#12;â&#128;¢	   Investment facilitation. This set of activities comprises&#13;
     business recruitment; expansion and retention; incen-&#13;
     tives; site selection services (zoning and permitting,&#13;
                                                                                           Box 2.1	Changsha: Economic success without&#13;
     business facilities, other infrastructure); customized                                  a dedicated Economic Development&#13;
     workforce training; and investor aftercare.                                             Organization&#13;
â&#128;¢	   Entrepreneurial assistance. Such activities include capital                           No single institution is responsible for economic&#13;
     access programs, technology commercialization and                                     development in Changsha. Instead, the entire&#13;
     upgrading, incubators, provision of market information,                               municipal government (chiefly the mayor) is&#13;
     and export facilitation.                                                              responsible for delivering economic growth, and&#13;
                                                                                           the municipal government has a clear mandate&#13;
â&#128;¢	   Convening function. This function involves engaging                                   and funding mechanisms. The city relies less on&#13;
     stakeholders, fostering industry-academia links, devel-                               formal structures to centralize authority because&#13;
     oping partnerships and networks, and establishing or                                  authority is already centralized and prioritized&#13;
     leading growth coalitions.                                                            within the mayorâ&#128;&#153;s office. Instead, the city uses&#13;
                                                                                           temporary agencies called leading groups. These&#13;
Most of the cities studied had dedicated entities or govern-                               leading groups manage cross-departmental&#13;
ment departments responsible for local economic develop-                                   initiatives, such as investment attraction, and&#13;
ment or its individual aspects. (Changsha is an exception                                  have unambiguous authority (reporting to the&#13;
here; see box 2.1 for details.) Regardless of whether they were                            mayor or department heads, depending on the&#13;
in the public or private sector, or what their precise geograph-                           purposes of the leading groups), a clear structure,&#13;
ical remit was (municipal, metropolitan, departmental or                                   and funding (e.g. the leading group for an open&#13;
regional), these intermediaries performed a highly beneficial                              economy falls under the Bureau of Commerceâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
role in attracting outside investment, helping existing com-                               umbrella). Most important, leading groups im-&#13;
panies to scale up, and facilitating the formation of new local                            prove the organizational capacity and effective-&#13;
businesses. The institutional arrangements showed some                                     ness of economic development efforts by prevent-&#13;
diversity in the nature, number, and specific responsibilities                             ing departments from working in silos and by&#13;
of economic development organizations found in each city                                   fast-tracking prioritized initiatives.&#13;
(table 2.1).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table 2.1	           Case study citiesâ&#128;&#153; local economic development institutional arrangements&#13;
 City                 Institutions                                Type                 Functions&#13;
 Bucaramanga          Regional Competitiveness Com-               Private sector enti- Strategic planning, public-private dialogue, invest-&#13;
                      mission, Invest in Santander, and           ties with minimal    ment promotion, entrepreneurial support, and&#13;
                      other chamber of commerce units             public funding       assistance in accessing national programs&#13;
 Changsha             Local government (mayorâ&#128;&#153;s office)           Local government,    Public investment, investment promotion, and&#13;
                                                                  with steady funding  liaison with national and provincial government&#13;
                                                                                       agencies&#13;
 Coimbatore           Industry associations, chambers             Private membership Entrepreneurial assistance (technology, skills,&#13;
                      of commerce and Confederation               organizations with market analysis); investor targeting; place branding&#13;
                      of Indian Industry, and individual          no public funding    and promotion; site selection services; and man-&#13;
                      for-profit firms                                                 agement&#13;
 Gaziantep            Chambers of industry and                    Private sector enti- Establishment and governance of private Orga-&#13;
                      commerce, supportive mayor and              ties with supportive nized Industrial Zones, market analysis, global&#13;
                      provincial governor, city council           government infra-    ties, and administration of national incentives&#13;
                      as convening or deliberative body,          structure invest-&#13;
                      and Organized Industrial Zones              ments&#13;
 Kigali               Rwanda Development Board, City              National investment Investment promotion and targeting, improve-&#13;
                      of Kigali Municipal Government              promotion agencies ments to cityâ&#128;&#153;s livability, and business climate&#13;
                      (mayorâ&#128;&#153;s office), and Construction          and local govern-    improvements&#13;
                      One-Stop Shop                               ment&#13;
 Tangier              Tangier Mediterranean Special               Port authorities     Port and free trade zone construction and oper-&#13;
                      Agency, SAPT, mayorâ&#128;&#153;s office,               and investment       ation, investment promotion, incentives, entre-&#13;
                      wilaya (administrative region),             promotion agencies, preneurial assistance, skills development, and&#13;
                      Agency for Promotion and Devel-             local and regional   infrastructure upgrades&#13;
                      opment of the North, and local              governments, and&#13;
                      offices of national agencies                national agencies&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                13&#13;
Note: SAPT is the French acronym for the corporation for redevelopment of the Port of Tangier.&#13;
&amp;#12;The specific reasons that these six citiesâ&#128;&#153; economic devel-          3. Strategies and Interventions&#13;
opment organizations (EDOs)â&#128;&#148;or equivalent government&#13;
departments or private sector entities fulfilling those              As a general lesson, the cities studied did not undertake&#13;
functionsâ&#128;&#148;have been successful whereas others in similar             random interventions: they proactively targeted initiatives&#13;
circumstances have failed vary from one city to another.             to foster economic development in their metropolitan areas.&#13;
However, regardless of the specifics, some commonalities can         Their actions were based on formal or informal strategies,&#13;
be observed across these successful cities:                          in most cases developed through a structured process of&#13;
                                                                     analysis, discussion, and stakeholder consultation. Strategic&#13;
â&#128;¢	   Successful cities had a realistic understanding of their        economic development plans aimed to build on the citiesâ&#128;&#153;&#13;
     competitive advantage, whether identified through a             competitive advantages while addressing key constraints to&#13;
     formal assessment process or just constituting conven-          economic growth. Following are some highlights of how such&#13;
     tional wisdom among key local decision makers. They did         strategic plans were developed and implemented and why&#13;
     not chase the latest economic development fad but rather        these particular cities have succeeded where so many others&#13;
     focused their limited resources on where they thought           have failed.&#13;
     they stood the best chance of being successful.&#13;
&#13;
â&#128;¢	   Such cities embraced globalization as an opportuni-&#13;
                                                                     Strategic planning for economic development&#13;
     ty, rather than fearing its disruptive potential. EDOs          Just as the characteristics of each successful city differed, so&#13;
     worked with companies to help them identify export              did their strategies; no cookie-cutter recipe for success was&#13;
     opportunities, for example, and strongly emphasized             discovered through this case study research. Operating under&#13;
     helping workers adapt their skills to the demands of the        a variety of national policy frameworks and local conditions,&#13;
     global marketplace (often in collaboration with work-           these cities devised strategies appropriate to their own needs&#13;
     force agencies).                                                (and cultural context), using a variety of approaches and&#13;
â&#128;¢	   The cities had the ability to productively engage diverse       processes to do so. Likewise, responsibility for the strategic&#13;
     stakeholder groups and build growth coalitions around           planning process rested with a range of entities (in the public&#13;
     the shared interest of seeing the cityâ&#128;&#153;s economy expand         or private sector, or both).&#13;
     and create jobs.&#13;
                                                                     Many, but not all, of our case study cities used a structured&#13;
â&#128;¢	   They overcame coordination failures and successfully            process to identify their principal competitive assets, relate&#13;
     worked across silos (internal or interorganizational), an       them to external market opportunities, and use these&#13;
     attribute that was particularly important in cities where       insights as a basis to formulate an economic development&#13;
     more than one entity had responsibility for economic            strategy. Regardless of whether a government or private&#13;
     development. Different entitiesâ&#128;&#153; functions were not             sector entity carried out this process, case study research&#13;
     always clearly spelled out, so one way problems were            revealed that the majority of successful cities used some kind&#13;
     avoided was by holding key people morally responsible           of structured process to develop a long-term plan (although&#13;
     (before their fellow decision makers) for delivering on         specific processes varied). Among other elements, this&#13;
     commitments.                                                    process entailed benchmarking the city against competitor&#13;
                                                                     locations, identifying the cityâ&#128;&#153;s competitive advantages, as-&#13;
â&#128;¢	   The cities had a professional, capable staff (in either the     sessing external market opportunities, identifying potential&#13;
     public or the private sector) with knowledge of products,       investors, and identifying constraints to growth needing to&#13;
     markets, and global business trends and an understand-          be addressed. Some cities used such information to formulate&#13;
     ing of how the economic development process should              a long-term strategy for the city, whereas others had a more&#13;
     work in practice. Many EDO professionals interviewed            immediate, operational focus.&#13;
     were truly world class.&#13;
                                                                     Distinguishing between citiesâ&#128;&#153; economic development&#13;
â&#128;¢	   The cities were willing to disrupt existing ways of doing       strategies and general geospatial development plans, which&#13;
     things and try innovative approaches. When necessary,           many cities are required by law to periodically prepare, is&#13;
     they took on vested interests and prevented capture and         also important. Every city studied engaged in some kind of&#13;
     rent-seeking behavior. Most of these cities were located        medium- to longer-term urban planning for vital municipal&#13;
     in countries that have dismantled monopolies, deregu-           services and infrastructure such as roads, water and sewer&#13;
     lated various sectors, and opened up to global trade and        lines, solid waste management, public safety, and land use&#13;
     investment.                                                     planning. However, such metropolitan plans did not always&#13;
                                                                     contain a chapter on topics such as creating jobs, addressing&#13;
â&#128;¢	   The cities displayed a generally high degree of shared          constraints to company formation and growth, attracting&#13;
     commitment to their own prosperity. This commitment             outside investors, or developing tourism. And where they&#13;
     has been observed across government, academia, and              did, these plans remained very broad (with statements such&#13;
     private for-profit entities in many of the case study cities.   as â&#128;&#156;support prosperity and job growth by enhancing trans-&#13;
     It appeared to be even stronger in cities with strong           port mobility and ensuring housing affordabilityâ&#128;&#157;), without&#13;
     regional identities and cultures that likely have a higher      delving into specifics such as what kind of outside investors&#13;
     degree of social capital and trust.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 14&#13;
&amp;#12;to target, how to attract them to the city, or how to prioritize        in mind. Across the cities studied, several used noteworthy&#13;
urban planning investments with economic development                    practices in this process (see box 3.1).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Box 3.1	E xamples of techniques cities used in formulating economic development strategies&#13;
    Formally engaging stakeholders in the strategic                      Making plans flexible and adaptable&#13;
    planning process                                                     Some cities knowingly (or unknowingly) used flexible&#13;
    Some cities used structured processes for stakeholder engage-        planning, which enabled then to adapt to changing&#13;
    ment, ensuring that economic development strategies reflect-         conditions and opportunities. For example, in Chang-&#13;
    ed the collaboration and input of local residents. In Kigali,        sha, the city did not formally prioritize the construction&#13;
    participatory planning was done at every tier of government,         engineering sector, but after witnessing the growth&#13;
    thus giving citizens greater say in identifying priorities. In       and success of several local firms, adjusted policies to&#13;
    Bucaramanga, government and nongovernmental stakehold-               support and promote the competitiveness of local firms.&#13;
    ers interacted through roundtables and regional committees,          Gaziantep did not have a formal economic development&#13;
    collectively developing a regional strategy. In Gaziantep,           strategy, but through regular meetings of committees&#13;
    public-private dialogue took place through a forum (the city         and working groups within its business chambers and&#13;
    council) that brought together business leaders, academics,          consultative bodies such as the city council, plans were&#13;
    representatives from civil society groups, and government            flexibly made in response to external developments (for&#13;
    officials.                                                           example, the situation in the neighboring countries of&#13;
                                                                         Iraq and the Syrian Arab Republic).&#13;
&#13;
    Using rigorous analytics to inform strategy develop-                 Using established economic development best&#13;
    ment                                                                 practices and benchmarking tools&#13;
    From aggregating and analyzing data to conducting analyses           Many cities used formal tools and established best prac-&#13;
    identifying cross-cutting constraints, some cities demon-            tices to guide interventions. For example, Kigali adapted&#13;
    strated advanced analytical capabilities. In Bucaramanga, the        the World Bankâ&#128;&#153;s Doing Business Index to evaluate and&#13;
    chamber of commerceâ&#128;&#153;s analytical capabilities were focused           improve the business environment in the city. Bucara-&#13;
    on identifying the needs, constraints, and opportunities of          manga used Michael Porterâ&#128;&#153;s cluster theory as a guide&#13;
    local firms, thereby helping inform interventions to support         in developing strategies and interventions to support&#13;
    firms and industry clusters with the greatest development            the growth of existing and emerging industries within&#13;
    potential. In Coimbatore, a private real estate developer            the city and especially in determining how to prioritize&#13;
    (part of a larger conglomerate) identified the potential to          among them. Gaziantepâ&#128;&#153;s Silk Road Development Agency&#13;
    capture spillover growth from Indiaâ&#128;&#153;s tier 1 cities, resulting in    used world-class processes (consultative as well as ana-&#13;
    tremendous opportunities to attract investment and create            lytical) to identify industry trends and strategic priori-&#13;
    jobs in the city. And in Tangier, the Tangier Mediterranean          ties. Moroccoâ&#128;&#153;s national government used a structured&#13;
    Special Agency carries out analyses of global business trends        process to identify and support the growth of its targeted&#13;
    to identify potential investors in the city and its free trade       industry sectors, whereas Tangier successfully operation-&#13;
    zones.                                                               alized them at the local and regional level.&#13;
&#13;
    Establishing long-term, measurable goals                             Enlisting nongovernmental stakeholders in&#13;
    Some cities not only set long-term strategic priorities in           strategy development and implementation&#13;
    terms of industry sectors, but also set quantifiable targets         Most cities involved stakeholder groups in strategy de-&#13;
    such as growth in GDP and jobs. Such metrics helped track            velopment, but in some cities (Bucaramanga, Gaziantep),&#13;
    progress, reach individual milestones, and enable midterm            stakeholders also played a crucial role in implementing&#13;
    course corrections, if needed. In Bucaramanga, the Regional          economic development plans, not just formulating them.&#13;
    Competitiveness Commission (RCC) (led by the chamber of              Mobilizing their financial resources, business know-how,&#13;
    commerce) set a goal to double the cityâ&#128;&#153;s per capita GDP in 10       relationship capital, and logistical capabilities, universi-&#13;
    years. Two years in, the chamber was already on target, and          ties, chambers of commerce, industry associations, and&#13;
    activities and short-term strategies continued to be devel-          even individual firms contributed to advancing citiesâ&#128;&#153;&#13;
    oped, adapted, and implemented in accordance with this               economic development agendas. Although such activity&#13;
    longer-term goal. Similarly, Tangierâ&#128;&#153;s economic development          was not as prominent in Kigali and Changsha, Coim-&#13;
    agencies set numeric milestones for operational phases for           batore provides an example of implementation almost&#13;
    the new seaport, as well as for the old seaportâ&#128;&#153;s redevelop-         entirely carried out by nongovernmental actors.&#13;
    ment and conversion.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                         15&#13;
&amp;#12;The degree of stakeholder involvement (and especially that         Successful interventions in our six case study cities could be&#13;
of private, for-profit firms and their membership organiza-        grouped into the following broad categories:&#13;
tions) was higher than originally anticipated in the research&#13;
hypotheses. Nongovernmental stakeholders were not just             â&#128;¢	   Business climate improvements&#13;
â&#128;&#156;consultedâ&#128;&#157;; they were often also drivers of the entire process,   â&#128;¢	   Industry sector targeting&#13;
implementers or coimplementers of strategies, and some-            â&#128;¢	   Investment attraction&#13;
times vital sources of funding for city economic development       â&#128;¢	   Entrepreneurial assistance&#13;
initiatives. Successful cities have also proven quite adept at     â&#128;¢	   Export facilitation&#13;
tapping into national support tools and resources. Finally,        â&#128;¢	   Place making and branding&#13;
the role of academic institutions was important in several         â&#128;¢	   Strengthening of human capital&#13;
cities, but perhaps less than expected before the research was&#13;
carried out.                                                       Within each of those categories, we can identify interven-&#13;
                                                                   tions on the traditional levers affecting firm-level perfor-&#13;
Observed interventions and the reasons for                         mance, as summarized in the framework paper Competitive&#13;
their success                                                      Cities for Jobs and Growth (World Bank, 2015): (a) institu-&#13;
                                                                   tions and regulations, (b) infrastructure, (c) skills and inno-&#13;
The case study cities undertook various kinds of specific          vation, and (d) enterprise support and finance.&#13;
interventions to jump-start their economic growth, but none&#13;
attempted to mimic an existing successful city. No single          Examples of these interventions in our case study cities,&#13;
formula for city success has been observed, but rather a com-      along with some discussion of why they have been effective,&#13;
bination of well-thought-out responses to specific local cir-      follow.&#13;
cumstances. Although some cities demonstrated a profound&#13;
familiarity with global best practices, none mechanistically       Business climate improvements&#13;
adhered to conventional wisdom or particular approaches&#13;
                                                                   Successful cities prioritized creating and maintaining a local&#13;
just because other successful places had used them. No city&#13;
                                                                   business climate conducive to investment and job growth. Re-&#13;
blindly followed the â&#128;&#156;Singapore Model,â&#128;&#157; â&#128;&#156;Barcelona Model,â&#128;&#157;&#13;
                                                                   gardless of whether the cities also targeted specific industry&#13;
â&#128;&#156;Pittsburgh Model,â&#128;&#157; or any other economic development fad&#13;
                                                                   sectors for additional support, most of the mayors and other&#13;
or fashion. Perhaps tellingly, all of these cities stayed away&#13;
                                                                   senior local officials interviewed as part of these case studies&#13;
from economic development clichÃ©s: none claimed or aspired&#13;
                                                                   understood the importance of offering a favorable general&#13;
to be the Silicon Valley, Rotterdam, or London of its country&#13;
                                                                   businesses environment for all firmsâ&#128;&#148;often in countries&#13;
or region, although they did, in practice, often nurture the&#13;
                                                                   with a long tradition of red tape, business-stifling regula-&#13;
emergence of centers of excellence in sectors targeted for&#13;
                                                                   tions, and indifference from local officials. To the extent that&#13;
proactive economic development efforts.&#13;
                                                                   their administrative scope allowed, many of these mayors&#13;
                                                                   strove to improve the local business climate on an ongoing&#13;
                                                                   basis, often in consultation with local business leaders. Spe-&#13;
                                                                   cific measures these cities used include expedited permitting&#13;
Box 3.2	Kigali: Meeting private sector demand                      such as one-stop shops or single-window systems (see box&#13;
  for business climate reform                                      3.2), more business-friendly zoning regulations and land use&#13;
                                                                   policies, streamlined business licensing, online e-government&#13;
Businesses in Kigali once needed 125 days to                       services, greater transparency and accountability for public&#13;
receive a construction permit. Today, businesses                   agencies (including staffing decisions and public procure-&#13;
receive a construction permit within 30 days and                   ment), and special governance regimes for organized indus-&#13;
meet their approval needs in a single, stream-                     trial zones or similar jurisdictional enclaves. In cities where&#13;
lined location. The reform process began with the                  basic infrastructure such as power or waste treatment was&#13;
creation of the Kigali Investorsâ&#128;&#153; Forum, a platform                not universally available, the public sector made a concerted&#13;
designed to take stock of the private sectorâ&#128;&#153;s con-                effort to ensure that these essential services be provided as&#13;
cerns. Through the forum and a World Bank Doing                    a necessary enabler for business activity and therefore job&#13;
Business assessment, the city identified inefficien-               creation.&#13;
cies and a lack of interagency coordination in its&#13;
construction permitting regime. The city respond-                  Why were these interventions successful? Some key reasons&#13;
ed by bringing all relevant agencies under one roof                include the following:&#13;
(a one-stop shop) and implementing an electronic&#13;
platform that significantly reduced red tape. The                  â&#128;¢	   Consulting with local business. Local business leaders were&#13;
city based the project on a similar one that was                        consulted about their needs and the constraints they&#13;
successful in Nairobi and paid for the project from                     encountered in their firmsâ&#128;&#153; daily operations. In practice,&#13;
its municipal budget (with support from the In-                         mayors talked not just to a few of the largest firms or&#13;
ternational Finance Corporation and the African                         vested interests in their cities but also to industry associ-&#13;
Development Bank).                                                      ations, sector guilds, and other entities that represented&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
16&#13;
&amp;#12;     various kinds of (often smaller) businesses and that             also a motive for targeting, with cities seeking to dramati-&#13;
     proactively worked to address their membersâ&#128;&#153; concerns.           cally increase per capita income levels targeting higher-val-&#13;
                                                                      ue-addedâ&#128;&#148;and thus higher-wageâ&#128;&#148;sectors as the mainstays&#13;
â&#128;¢	   Focusing on realistic issues. Mayors and other local officials   of tomorrowâ&#128;&#153;s economy. Finally, some cities wanted to foster&#13;
     focused on things they could realistically and directly          the development of centers of excellence in particular sectors,&#13;
     affect (for example, water supply or land use), rather than      in the hope that they would become globally or regionally&#13;
     trying to address more macrolevel issues over which they         competitive (that is, specialization).7 Interestingly, although&#13;
     had less control, such as taxation, incentives, or state-        undertaken with very different (indeed, sometimes dia-&#13;
     owned enterprises.                                               metrically opposed) motives, these interventions have been&#13;
                                                                      implemented in remarkably similar ways. As discussed in the&#13;
â&#128;¢	   Creating stability. In postconflict societies (for example,      prior section on strategic planning, the process of identifying&#13;
     Colombia or Rwanda), introducing more stability and              sectors to target and prioritizing among them also varied&#13;
     predictability into the conduct of business, along with          substantially from one city to another.&#13;
     making improvements to overall public safety, has paid&#13;
     disproportionately high dividends. Companies have                The case study cities generally employed relatively conven-&#13;
     much stronger incentive to invest when they can be rea-          tional (and widely used) support mechanisms to foster the&#13;
     sonably certain that their property will not be lost.            expansion of targeted sectors. These approaches are well doc-&#13;
                                                                      umented in academic literature as well as in the World Bankâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
â&#128;¢	   Improving public transparency and accountability. This           experience with clients in many developing countries. They&#13;
     has been beneficial in all the cities studied. Cities that       include providing free or highly subsidized land or space;&#13;
     made a commitment to advertising public sector jobs or           giving sector-specific financial incentives; creating dedicat-&#13;
     procurement contracts online, for example, did not just          ed infrastructure; offering tailored workforce development&#13;
     reduce the scope for graft but also enhanced public trust        programs; providing market information and intelligence;&#13;
     and social capital, in turn leading to greater civic en-         matchmaking of suppliers and producers using technology&#13;
     gagement and efficiency in the use of municipal funds.6          development schemes, including incubation or colocation,&#13;
     Accountability mechanisms varied across the six cities           technology commercialization, and fostering of industry-ac-&#13;
     in both degree and direction (directly to citizenry or to        ademia links; convening sector alliances and similar groups;&#13;
     higher tiers of government).                                     and building a local brand as the destination for a particular&#13;
                                                                      industry (see the section on place making and marketing,&#13;
â&#128;¢	   These case studies have found no correlation between ef-&#13;
                                                                      later in this chapter).&#13;
     fective business climate improvements and whether local&#13;
     government officials were elected or appointed.                  Why were these interventions successful? Some key reasons&#13;
                                                                      follow:&#13;
Industry sector targeting&#13;
                                                                      â&#128;¢	   Successful cities targeted sectors where they already had some&#13;
Most of the cities we studied have targeted individual                     competitive advantage. None of these successful cities&#13;
industries with proactive economic development efforts. In                 attempted to build an industry cluster from scratch.&#13;
addition to general improvements to their business climates,               At least some preconditions were already in place, such&#13;
which benefited all businesses, almost all of the case study               as appropriate infrastructure; labor pools with related,&#13;
cities focused their efforts and resources on individual indus-            transferable skills; adequate research and educational&#13;
tries as drivers of economic growth and job creation. And all              facilities; or a critical mass of existing firms (or poten-&#13;
of the cities that focused their proactive efforts on specific             tial suppliers). These vital assets were identified before&#13;
industries in fact targeted more than just one sector, though              time and resources were poured into sector development&#13;
links between the sectors often existed in terms of necessary              initiatives. None of these cities jumped on economic&#13;
skills or infrastructure (for example, automotive and aero-                development fads or chased a specific industry because&#13;
space, or logistics and tourism).                                          it was fashionable or in vogue. Rather, they targeted a&#13;
                                                                           sector because analysis suggested that the city stood a&#13;
The reasons for targeting specific industries, as well as the&#13;
                                                                           realistic chance of succeeding in growing that sector (see&#13;
process by which they were selected, varied significantly from&#13;
                                                                           box 3.3).&#13;
one city to another. Some cities simply wanted more jobs to&#13;
be created for residents, so they focused on industries likely        â&#128;¢	   Successful sector development initiatives usually had effective&#13;
to yield significant employment gains, often in relatively brief           mechanisms for engaging key stakeholders and enabling their&#13;
time spans, such as tourism or construction. Others sought                 collective action. In fact, such initiatives were often driven&#13;
to strengthen their local economiesâ&#128;&#153; resilience by reducing                by coalitions of business leaders from the industries in&#13;
overreliance on a few (often cyclically vulnerable) industry               question as well as other members of the broader busi-&#13;
sectors by encouraging the emergence of new local industries               ness community (financiers, chambers of commerce);&#13;
(that is, diversification). Still others responded to current              university rectors; government officials; and prominent&#13;
market opportunities, seeking to attract firms in industries               local figures (and sometimes also high-profile foreign in-&#13;
related to existing ones, which might need many of the same                vestors). The ability to work together for sector develop-&#13;
transferable skill sets. The quality of economic growth was                ment, particularly in an industry-academia-government&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                           17&#13;
&amp;#12;                                                                             anchor investments often play a valuable role in helping&#13;
                                                                             put a city on the map of big-league international inves-&#13;
Box 3.3 Gaziantep: Tailoring industrial zones to                             tors in a way that no amount of marketing effort can.&#13;
  meet the needs of light manufacturers                                      Such high-profile investments can help make the city a&#13;
                                                                             serious contender for similar competitions in the future,&#13;
Gaziantep developed its organized industrial                                 giving it credibility with potential investors. Through&#13;
zones (OIZs) with specific sectors and firm char-                            supply chain links (in this case, the development of&#13;
acteristics in mind, with assistance ranging from                            local suppliers), such investments can also contribute to&#13;
the type of infrastructure provided to the sizes of                          dramatic improvements in industry-specific know-how,&#13;
plots. In particular, the cityâ&#128;&#153;s fourth OIZ (in 1998)                        technological capability, and export readiness, among&#13;
responded to the impressive progress shown by&#13;
                                                                             other things.&#13;
carpet-making firms, with land plots specially&#13;
configured to host those carpet-making firms&#13;
                                                                        Investment attraction&#13;
plus smaller firms producing related products and&#13;
intermediate goods for carpet makers. Though                            The majority of cities included in these case studies have been&#13;
the model for implementing OIZs is standardized                         very successful at attracting outside investment, which can&#13;
nationally, Gaziantep aimed for greater interaction                     be foreign direct investment (FDI) or investment by domes-&#13;
with target firms and greater collaboration from                        tic firms from elsewhere in the same country. In addition to&#13;
public agencies to gauge the gap between industry                       injecting capital and know-how into the local economy and&#13;
needs and public capacity. This effort may have set                     providing significant numbers of jobs, such investments can&#13;
the cityâ&#128;&#153;s OIZs apart from less successful indus-                       (depending on the industry) spur the creation of local suppli-&#13;
trial zones in Turkey and elsewhere, which often                        er networks, lead to the development of advanced skills and&#13;
adopt a nontargeted, â&#128;&#156;build it and they will comeâ&#128;&#157;                      production capabilities, and help to more closely integrate the&#13;
approach.                                                               city into global value chains. Of the six cities studied, only&#13;
                                                                        in Gaziantep was the attraction of outside investment not a&#13;
                                                                        major part of the cityâ&#128;&#153;s success story.&#13;
     trilateral relationship, has been observed to be a critical        Many of the cities studied adhered to global best practices in&#13;
     factor of success for many metropolitan clusters, particu-         investment promotion. Their EDOs or other investment pro-&#13;
     larly in higher-value-added industries.8                           motion intermediaries tracked global business trends, identi-&#13;
                                                                        fied potential investors and reached out to them, worked with&#13;
â&#128;¢	   Most cities showed a willingness to let go of local industries     national investment promotion agencies (in the case of FDI)&#13;
     that may no longer be globally competitive (for example,           to recruit them and put together attractive incentive packag-&#13;
     electronics in Changsha, footwear and apparel in Bucara-           es, provided site selection services, and assisted outside firms&#13;
     manga, and safari tourism in Kigali). This factor is partic-       in setting up operations in their communities. Some cities&#13;
     ularly relevant because those cities managed to tackle             also offered investor aftercare services, either independently&#13;
     one of the key risks of industrial targeting at national           or in collaboration with their national investment promotion&#13;
     or local level: the potential capture by industry groups,          agencies. In Coimbatore, this entire process was handled&#13;
     leading to market distortion and subsidies and eventual            by private sector entities, which collaborated with the state&#13;
     misallocation of public funds. Fact-based deliberations, a         government in specific areas such as land acquisition and&#13;
     consultative process involving all relevant counterparts,          incentive applications.&#13;
     and a manageable city scale all contributed to make this&#13;
     outcome possible.                                                  Why were these interventions successful? Some key reasons&#13;
                                                                        include the following:&#13;
â&#128;¢	   These cities have generally been highly adept at tapping into&#13;
     national support tools, such as subsidies, research and devel-     â&#128;¢	   Successful cities carried out systematic analyses of market&#13;
     opment funding, customized workforce training programs,                 trends and opportunities. They targeted firms (especially&#13;
     and export assistance. Although national programs are                   multinational corporations) whose probability of invest-&#13;
     usually available to firms throughout a country or its                  ing in the city was fairly high (see box 3.4).&#13;
     targeted regions, high capacity at local intermediaries&#13;
     (EDOs, chambers of commerce, industry associations,                â&#128;¢	   Successful cities offered investors a compelling value proposi-&#13;
     and the like) in highly successful cities translates into               tion. Such incentives included cost factors, relevant work-&#13;
     significantly higher utilization rates compared with                    force talent, access to markets, critical infrastructure,&#13;
     national averages for those countries.9                                 financial incentives, or any other combination of factors&#13;
                                                                             important to a particular firm. No evidence indicates,&#13;
â&#128;¢	   In some cities, efforts to expand a particular targeted industry        however, that any of our six cities managed to attract&#13;
     sector were greatly enhanced by the recruitment of a major              an outside investor solely or primarily motivated by the&#13;
     anchor investment, which acted as a catalyst for private sector         financial incentives that were put on the table.&#13;
     growth in the city.10 Besides the benefits usually associated&#13;
     with attracting outside investment (see the next section),&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 18&#13;
&amp;#12;â&#128;¢	   Successful cities obtained local consensus on the importance&#13;
     of attracting outside investment, resulting in flexibility and&#13;
     adaptability to investor needs. Many business locations&#13;
                                                                             Box 3.4	Coimbatore: Private-led investor&#13;
     simply say to potential investors, â&#128;&#156;This is who we are and                attraction through targeted analysis&#13;
     what we have to offer; take it or leave it.â&#128;&#157; These successful&#13;
     cities instead made an effort to understand potential                   In Coimbatore, a development firm, KGiSL Insti-&#13;
     investorsâ&#128;&#153; specific needs and accommodated those needs                  tute of Technology, worked with city officials to&#13;
     to the extent that they were able.11 Mayors, chamber                    form a pipeline of clients during the construction&#13;
     of commerce presidents, and other senior local leaders                  of a private economic zone. KGiSL staff members&#13;
     personally reached out to corporate CEOs and assured                    undertook an extensive, systematic analysis of&#13;
     them they would be welcomed to the local business com-                  market trends and players in the offshoring world&#13;
     munity. More often than not, this kind of relationship                  and, in particular, the activities of multinational&#13;
     building paid off handsomely.                                           corporations located in India. Observing that&#13;
                                                                             some companies had run out of room to grow&#13;
â&#128;¢	   Successful cities recognized that attracting outside investors          in places such as Bangalore or Chennai, KGiSL&#13;
     is only one part of the job. Making sure that investors                 pitched Coimbatore as a viable alternative, given&#13;
     have what they need to maintain and scale up their local                that its highly educated, English-speaking work-&#13;
     production means that channels of communication with                    ers were available at significantly lower cost than&#13;
     local leaders must be kept open on an ongoing basis.                    in tier 1 cities. The zone has been able to attract&#13;
     Regardless of whether a city or its country has a formal                Cognizant, Dell, and Bosch among its tenants and&#13;
     investment aftercare program, maintaining these rela-                   eventually amassed 20,000 jobs, thanks in part&#13;
     tionships is important for ensuring that investors do not               to its ability to customize facilities and services to&#13;
     leave and in fact expand local operations as the demand                 incoming firmsâ&#128;&#153; specific needs.&#13;
     for their products or services grows.12	&#13;
&#13;
Entrepreneurial assistance&#13;
&#13;
Successful cities do not just strive to attract outside invest-       â&#128;¢	   Providing land, office space, and specialized infrastructure.&#13;
ment; they also nurture the formation and scaling up of in-                Business facilities were provided either on market or&#13;
digenous enterprises. These six case studies have no examples              concessionary terms and appear to have generally been&#13;
where cities have posted exceptional economic results simply               allocated in a transparent manner across the cities stud-&#13;
by attracting external investment without significant num-                 ied. Colocation of similar firms (for example, shoemakers&#13;
bers of jobs also being created at homegrown firms.                        or craftsmen) has resulted in geographic agglomerations&#13;
                                                                           or clustering within the cities, with certain areas acquir-&#13;
To ensure that not all growth came just from attracting                    ing reputations for particular industries (motor pumps,&#13;
external investors, the majority of successful cities studied              carpets). Sometimes facilities were provided within&#13;
provided some type of entrepreneurial assistance to local                  business incubators or technology parks, particularly for&#13;
businesses.13 This assistance often included a combination                 firms in emerging sectors. Finally, the creation of orga-&#13;
of national, state or provincial (where applicable), and local             nized industrial zones or similar entities was enabled by&#13;
tools and support mechanisms. All of the cities studied had                national or state legislation, but municipal authorities&#13;
in place or at their disposal at least national-level entrepre-            often enhanced their viability and attractiveness to&#13;
neurial assistance programs. Depending on the city and                     firms by providing the necessary investment in public&#13;
the country, applications for national support programs are                infrastructure.&#13;
sometimes channeled through local entities (government&#13;
or private sector), so even if a program is national in scope,        â&#128;¢	   Upgrading technology and development. These support&#13;
responsibility for its implementation may be local.                        programs were often designed and implemented in col-&#13;
                                                                           laboration with local universities, research institutes, na-&#13;
Businesses of various sizes benefited from support programs.               tional science and technology agencies, or private sector&#13;
Contrary to popular perceptions that only small or micro                   membership organizations (such as the Southern India&#13;
firms take advantage of entrepreneurial assistance, our case               Engineering Manufacturersâ&#128;&#153; Association or Colciencias&#13;
studies have revealed that even fairly large firms (in some                in Colombia). They provided research and development&#13;
cases employing hundreds or even thousands of workers)                     grants, focused on improving industry-academia links&#13;
have used such support tools. Eligibility criteria varied wide-            and technology transfer, and sometimes provided train-&#13;
ly.                                                                        ing for upgrading staff membersâ&#128;&#153; technical skills.&#13;
&#13;
Entrepreneurial assistance was observed in multiple forms             â&#128;¢	   Offering financial assistance. Such assistance included tax&#13;
across the six cities. The main types of support tools deployed            rebates; industry-specific subsidies and incentives; cash&#13;
included the following:                                                    grants; capital access programs (that is, loans, credit&#13;
                                                                           lines, credit guarantees); and similar schemes. For many&#13;
                                                                           cities in developing countries, particularly those with&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                         19&#13;
&amp;#12;    underdeveloped capital markets, access to credit is often    â&#128;¢	   Assisting with entrepreneurial training and skills develop-&#13;
    a major obstacle to entrepreneurship and business ex-             ment. Many of the cities had programs to assist recent&#13;
    pansion. By playing an active role in addressing market           graduates in figuring out where to channel their en-&#13;
    failures of this kind, cities (often in collaboration with        trepreneurial energy. These programs used a variety of&#13;
    higher tiers of government or private sector financial            individualized tests and offered training sessions. Like-&#13;
    institutions) can enable a vital source of funding for            wise, numerous gender-specific programs were aimed at&#13;
    business activity.                                                aspiring women entrepreneurs, â&#128;&#156;economically backward&#13;
                                                                      areasâ&#128;&#157; (in India), or other targeted segments of the local&#13;
                                                                      population. In some cases, this assistance entailed quite&#13;
Box 3.5	Coimbatore: Private-led support for                           a bit of hand-holding of budding entrepreneurs and was&#13;
                                                                      often funded by national, or state or provincial govern-&#13;
  small-scale businesses&#13;
                                                                      ment agencies.&#13;
Coimbatore enjoys a highly supportive ecosystem&#13;
                                                                 â&#128;¢	   Providing market information and business intelligence. This&#13;
for entrepreneurs. The cityâ&#128;&#153;s mostly family-owned&#13;
                                                                      form of assistance is more applicable to smaller firms,&#13;
small and medium enterprises compete with each&#13;
                                                                      which usually do not have a market research depart-&#13;
other for business opportunities but also band&#13;
                                                                      ment. Such information helps them identify opportu-&#13;
together and self-organize to build capacity, ensure&#13;
                                                                      nities in the domestic or international marketplace for&#13;
common technical standards, facilitate exports,&#13;
                                                                      their products.&#13;
and lobby the government for infrastructure&#13;
upgrades, such as the recent upgrade of the cityâ&#128;&#153;s               Why were these interventions successful? Some key reasons&#13;
airport. Coimbatore District Small-Scale Indus-                  follow:&#13;
tries Association (CODISSIA) played the key role&#13;
in driving these initiatives. CODISSIA includes                  â&#128;¢	   Entrepreneurial assistance programs were generally directly&#13;
more than 4,000 small and medium enterprises. It                      relevant to addressing the constraints to company forma-&#13;
represents entrepreneurs at grievance panels and                      tion and growth encountered in the case study cities. These&#13;
advises them on taxes, licensing, and exporting.                      programs helped address very real issues, such as lack of&#13;
Other advice is provided through partnerships                         capital access, obsolete technologies, lack of management&#13;
with local technology and engineering institutions                    know-how, or insufficient information about market&#13;
and through a dedicated Small Industries Testing                      opportunities.&#13;
and Research Centre, which was launched in 1986.&#13;
CODISSIA also leads exhibitions and trade fairs for              â&#128;¢	   Seasoned industry professionals with private sector experi-&#13;
its members and has established a permanent trade                     ence in program design and implementation were involved.&#13;
fair complex for the city.                                            The programs did not rely solely on career bureaucrats or&#13;
                                                                      program managers (see box 3.5).&#13;
&#13;
                                                                 â&#128;¢	   In implementing such assistance programs, successful cities&#13;
Box 3.6	Bucaramanga: Multilateral approach to                         often display a superior ability to work across organizational&#13;
  supporting entrepreneurs                                            silos. They also are able to overcome challenges associated&#13;
                                                                      with the sometimes hierarchical relationship between&#13;
Given informality rates that exceeded the nation-                     different tiers of government14 (see box 3.6).&#13;
al average, the Regional Competitiveness Plan for&#13;
Santander (the region where Bucaramanga is located)              â&#128;¢	   Well-designed national support programs and delivery&#13;
featured formalization and entrepreneurial develop-                   structures were in place. For example, local offices were&#13;
ment as one of its three strategic pillars. Plans were                established in individual citiesâ&#128;&#148;not just a central office&#13;
developed jointly with national agencies, municipal                   in the national capital. This analysis did not attempt to&#13;
governments, and the private sector and resulted in                   systematically compare different countriesâ&#128;&#153; approaches&#13;
an overhaul of the procedures involved in register-                   to business support service delivery. However, the most&#13;
ing a business: streamlined inspections, granting of                  effective programs appear to be the ones where national&#13;
building permits, and the establishment of a Busi-                    agencies either (a) had a presence on the ground and&#13;
ness Services Center in the municipality of Flor-                     worked directly with firms or (b) relied on a close part-&#13;
idablanca. Beyond formalization, the Bucaramanga                      nership with a local entity (not necessarily a government&#13;
Chamber of Commerce seeks to boost the produc-                        one, but perhaps a chamber of commerce or industry as-&#13;
tivity of new firms by leveraging partnerships with                   sociation) to raise awareness of programsâ&#128;&#153; availability, as-&#13;
universities and established companies to transfer                    sist firms in applying for support, and monitor progress&#13;
know-how to new firms. The chamber also holds sub-                    being made as a result of participation in the programs.&#13;
sidized entrepreneurship training programs, thereby&#13;
empowering citizens to create the next generation of&#13;
local businesses.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
20&#13;
&amp;#12;Export facilitation                                                 â&#128;¢	   Trade development missions (inbound and outbound),&#13;
                                                                         international trade shows, and matchmaking&#13;
Principal actors in all of the cities studied understood that       â&#128;¢	   Financial reimbursement for part or all of the cost of at-&#13;
production of tradable goods and services was key to their               tending trade events&#13;
citiesâ&#128;&#153; long-term economic development. All the case study&#13;
                                                                    â&#128;¢	   Construction of dedicated facilities, such as trade fairs,&#13;
cities therefore prioritized the foreign market success of their&#13;
                                                                         convention centers, and other such physical facilities,&#13;
exporting firms, sometimes as a stand-alone priority and&#13;
                                                                         bringing together buyers and sellers&#13;
sometimes as part of a broader strategy of city â&#128;&#156;internation-&#13;
alizationâ&#128;&#157; as a key pillar of planning for economic develop-        â&#128;¢	   Establishment of representative offices abroad providing&#13;
ment.15                                                                  assistance to firms&#13;
                                                                    â&#128;¢	   Hosting of intermediary or â&#128;&#156;multiplierâ&#128;&#157; organizations enabling&#13;
Significant variation existed among the cities in terms of               trade, including foreign consulates, trade and investment&#13;
which entity had primary responsibility for implementing                 representative offices, cultural centers, and banks&#13;
this support to exporters, which included active, hands-on          â&#128;¢	   Collaboration with local operations of multinational corpo-&#13;
assistance as well as promotion. In most countries, there was            rations to help integrate local suppliers into their global&#13;
a dedicated national export promotion entity, which often                supply chains&#13;
worked in collaboration with local chambers of commerce,&#13;
industry associations, and EDOs. Some national export               Why were these interventions successful? Some key reasons&#13;
promotion agencies, export-import banks, or both had an             observed include the following:&#13;
extensive field presence in their countriesâ&#128;&#153; cities (for example,   â&#128;¢	 Cities belonged to countries with generally supportive nation-&#13;
ProExport Colombia, Export-Import Bank of China), whereas               al trade policies, including multiple bilateral and multilat-&#13;
others supported exporters from their head offices in the               eral free trade agreements and open markets.&#13;
national capital or main commercial center (for example,            â&#128;¢	 Cities had in-depth knowledge of products and markets and,&#13;
Maroc Export). Successful exporters in other countries (In-             in some cases, long-standing trade ties.&#13;
dia, Turkey) relied primarily on local chambers of commerce&#13;
                                                                    â&#128;¢	 Entrepreneurs could leverage personal and family connec-&#13;
and industry groups to provide export assistance. Finally, by&#13;
                                                                        tion s in other countries to boost trade.&#13;
becoming suppliers to the local operations of multinational&#13;
corporations, companies in some cities (Coimbatore, Tangi-          â&#128;¢	 A cityâ&#128;&#153;s geographic location could be capitalized on to increase&#13;
er) became integrated into global supply chains through the             foreign trade (see box 3.7).&#13;
intermediation of multinational actors.16                           â&#128;¢	 Senior officials showed sincere commitment to international-&#13;
                                                                        ization. Political support for trade matters, whether the&#13;
Mayors played a prominent role in export facilitation in                mayor serves as the salesman-in-chief for the city, or the&#13;
several of the cities studied, even though this role is not a           city builds and promotes a trade fair complex as a place&#13;
core responsibility of their office. As the public face of their        where business is done.&#13;
respective cities, they often led delegations of businesspeople&#13;
(including exporters) on trade or investment promotion mis-&#13;
sions abroad, as well as hosting inbound missions of foreign             Box 3.7	Tangier: National authority for regional&#13;
officials and companies to their cities. Therefore, the primary            export facilitation agencies&#13;
form of support mayors personally provided to their citiesâ&#128;&#153;&#13;
exporters was building international relationships by open-              Established in 2002, the Tangier Mediterranean&#13;
ing doors and generating goodwill. Sister-city agreements in             Special Agency (TMSA) represents the Moroccan&#13;
some cases also provided a framework for bilateral trade rela-           state in all interactions pertaining to the newly&#13;
tions, though the broad scope of such relationships generally            constructed Tangier-Med cargo port and industrial&#13;
tends to include culture, education, sports, and so on.                  platform. The TMSA has sweeping powers in key&#13;
                                                                         areas such as land acquisition and allocation. The&#13;
Successful cities also differed in the specific forms of support         Tangier-Med Port Authority is a TMSA subsidi-&#13;
provided to their exporting firms. The principal (though cer-            ary (the only major port in the country not run&#13;
tainly not the only) types of export facilitation programs and           by the national ports agency). The Tangier-Med&#13;
actions benefiting trade observed through these case studies             Port Authority has helped Tangier-Med transition&#13;
were the following:                                                      from focusing on the transshipment of containers&#13;
â&#128;¢	 Adoption of formal internationalization strategies as part of         through Morocco into a point of origin and destina-&#13;
     the economic development planning process                           tion for local imports and exports. Another TMSA&#13;
â&#128;¢	 Prioritization among key export markets (neighboring,                 subsidiary is the Tangier Free Zone, which offers&#13;
     regional, overseas)                                                 a range of incentives and fiscal exemptions to its&#13;
â&#128;¢	 Diversification of exports in terms of geography and prod-            500 resident companies. Its management actively&#13;
     uct mix, ideally reducing an overreliance on individual             works to increase business opportunities, using a&#13;
     country export markets or export commodities                        range of market research and investment attraction&#13;
â&#128;¢	 Provision of foreign market intelligence and identification of        approaches.&#13;
     trade opportunities&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                        21&#13;
&amp;#12;â&#128;¢	   Policy and decision makers integrated export promotion as a     and security with lower crime rates and fewer disruptions to&#13;
     vital pillar of targeted sector development strategies.         citizens and businesses; providing more and better cultural&#13;
                                                                     amenities and sports facilities; developing local tourist attrac-&#13;
Place making and city branding                                       tions (with public or private funding), such as historic sites,&#13;
                                                                     faith-based attractions, amusement parks, or resorts; and&#13;
If a physical location (metropolitan area) is thought of as a        enhancing mobility within the metropolitan area (meaning&#13;
product, this set of interventions could be summarized as            lower congestion, shorter journey times, and improved air&#13;
product development and product marketing. Improving a               quality).&#13;
cityâ&#128;&#153;s attractiveness, as well as its perceived attractiveness, is&#13;
an important competitive tool for any modern city. Adequate-         Improving a cityâ&#128;&#153;s livability to compete economically is only&#13;
ly positioning the city in the global marketplace for discre-        one part of the task; the other part is to change external per-&#13;
tionary investment, visitors, and workforce talent is therefore      ceptions of the city by improving its image as a business and&#13;
an economic development necessity.                                   tourist destination. The challenges encountered by the six&#13;
                                                                     cities differed quite a bit in this respect. Located in countries&#13;
The livability of all six case study cites has improved since        that had seen armed conflict, Bucaramanga and Kigali en-&#13;
2000, even as their populations have swelled and the pres-           deavored to inform the outside world that they are safe places&#13;
sure on municipal services has increased. Kigali and Tangier         to visit and conduct business. Overshadowed by much better&#13;
appear to have made the greatest strides in this respect, but        known business and tourism destinations in their own large&#13;
Bucaramanga, Gaziantep, and others have also made signif-            countries, Changsha, Coimbatore, and Gaziantep strove to&#13;
icant progress. Improvements to the livability of a city have        simply get on the map (see box 3.8). Tangier has been trying&#13;
been shown to play an important role in attracting investors         to shed its image of a grimy port city and transit point for&#13;
and talent alike, not to mention enhancing a cityâ&#128;&#153;s potential        illegal migrants and narcotics to that of a modern business&#13;
for tourism development. In fact, although all sectors benefit       hub and attractive Mediterranean destination.&#13;
from improvements to a cityâ&#128;&#153;s livability, the effect on tourism&#13;
is perhaps the most direct.                                          All of our case study cities have enjoyed some success in&#13;
                                                                     rebranding themselves, but this effort remains very much a&#13;
Several of these cities have made a concerted effort to              work in progress. They have often partnered with national&#13;
improve overall livability as an important element of their          tourism or investment promotion authorities to cobrand and&#13;
economic development strategies. Specific activities include         present themselves to the world, using the usual channels of&#13;
providing better municipal services (water, sewerage, solid          conventions, fairs, trade shows, and media campaigns with&#13;
waste); improving cleanliness, in particular of public spaces;       mixed results.&#13;
developing tourism infrastructure (hotels, foreign-speaking&#13;
hospitality staff, bilingual signage); clearing out and redevel-     Why were these interventions successful? Some key reasons&#13;
oping slums; increasing green surfaces and recreational areas        include the following:&#13;
(parks, swimming pools, and so on); improving public safety&#13;
                                                                     â&#128;¢	   Strong mayoral (or equivalent) commitment to improving city&#13;
                                                                          livability, in part because of more competitive local elec-&#13;
                                                                          tions (where applicable) and increased public account-&#13;
                                                                          ability&#13;
Box 3.8	Gaziantep: Chamber of Industryâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
  Trademark City branding project                                    â&#128;¢	   Favorable national developments (for example, postconflict&#13;
                                                                          reconstruction or devolution of some decision making to&#13;
Gaziantepâ&#128;&#153;s Chamber of Industry (Gaziantep Sanayi                         the local or regional level)&#13;
OdasÄ±, or GSO) launched the Trademark City initia-&#13;
tive to help catalyze Gaziantepâ&#128;&#153;s shift from being an                â&#128;¢	   Funding and technical assistance from international donors&#13;
intermediate goods producer to a producer of final                        (including multilateral) to increase energy efficiency,&#13;
products. It aimed at increasing the quality and profit                   reduce carbon emissions, halt deforestation and desicca-&#13;
rates of products, defining â&#128;&#156;Made in Gaziantepâ&#128;&#157; as a                      tion, better manage natural resources, preserve historic&#13;
trademark and a sign of high value. The GSO secre-                        sites and monuments, and promote sustainable develop-&#13;
tary general mentioned that the projectâ&#128;&#153;s goal was                        ment&#13;
to ensure â&#128;&#156;that even the simplest consumer knows&#13;
about Gaziantep, just as everyone knows about the                    â&#128;¢	   Supportive national initiatives, such as aggressive country&#13;
Great Wall of China or the Eiffel Tower.â&#128;&#157; The GSO                         tourism promotion campaigns&#13;
argued that every firm should produce at least one&#13;
branded product as a means of increasing profitabil-                 â&#128;¢	   Increased numbers of foreign visitors (including for busi-&#13;
ity while also leveraging export goods as ambassa-                        ness), providing firsthand testimonials, an effort in part&#13;
dors for the city. The project ultimately won the Best                    enabled by relaxing visa requirements and introducing&#13;
Unconventional Project Award in the 2005 World                            low-cost air travel&#13;
Chambers Competition.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 22&#13;
&amp;#12;Strengthening of human capital                                          --   Improving the livability of the city through improve-&#13;
                                                                             ments to safety, cleanliness, low costs of living,&#13;
One of the most common success factors among the cities                      and low congestion (Kigali and others; see previous&#13;
studied was their strategic focus on human capital. Practical-               section)&#13;
ly every city studied placed human capital among its top pri-&#13;
orities, necessary for the realization of short- and long-term          --   Attracting foreign universities to establish branch&#13;
goals, as well as for the growth of key industries and attract-              campuses and offer graduate-level programs to local&#13;
ing investors. Every city did not focus on raising its overall               students (Kigali, and soon possibly Tangier)&#13;
levels of human capital, but rather on developing specialized&#13;
skills and know-how, from automotive skills to medical sci-        â&#128;¢	   Improvements to the overall educational system. Some cities&#13;
ence, that would foster the growth of these industries.                 focused on improvements at the primary, secondary,&#13;
                                                                        and tertiary levels (Bucaramanga, Kigali). Although a&#13;
The six cities inherited dramatically different levels of human         longer-term strategy, initiatives were intended to develop&#13;
capital. At one extreme was Bucaramanga, which had long                 and foster the next generation of human capital.&#13;
been home to some of the countryâ&#128;&#153;s top universities and thus&#13;
inherited high levels of human capital that boosted the cityâ&#128;&#153;s     â&#128;¢	   Engagement with academia as an economic development&#13;
capacity and that of its firms. On the opposite end, Kigali had         partner. A few cities engaged their academic stakehold-&#13;
suffered years of instability and violence (culminating in the          ers as partners in formulating local economic develop-&#13;
1994 genocide), which resulted in loss of life, disruptions to          ment strategies. Representatives from universities were&#13;
education, and high levels of emigration. In between these              encouraged to collaborate, both collectively as a cluster&#13;
two extremes were cities such as Tangier and Changsha,                  and with local public and private sector actors, to help&#13;
which suffered from both domestic and international brain               shape local strategies and the prioritization of specific&#13;
drains yet maintained high-quality educational institutions             industries.&#13;
and retained skilled workers. Some of the cities (Coimbatore,&#13;
Gaziantep, Tangier) are also major destinations for the inter-     The types of initiatives favored by each city reflected its&#13;
nal migration of workers within their respective countries.        existing capacity and resources. In general, cities with fewer&#13;
                                                                   resources, such as good-quality universities, existing levels&#13;
Citiesâ&#128;&#153; approaches to developing higher and more specialized       of human capital, and specialized skills, focused on attrac-&#13;
levels of human capital varied as well. The most common            tion initiatives (Changsha, Kigali), whereas cities with more&#13;
initiatives were centered on four pillars:                         resources (Bucaramanga, Coimbatore) focused on developing&#13;
                                                                   existing skill sets and tailoring their human capital to take&#13;
â&#128;¢	   Worker training programs. Most cities promoted the devel-     advantage of market opportunities.17&#13;
     opment of specialized skill sets by&#13;
&#13;
     --   Regulating and promoting vocational schools to&#13;
          improve the quality and applicability of training&#13;
          (see box 3.9 for an overview of skills initiatives in&#13;
          Changsha)&#13;
                                                                        Box 3.9	Changsha: Increasing human capital with&#13;
     --   Designing or funding customized worker training&#13;
          programs in response to industry needs (Bucara-&#13;
                                                                          better training and talent recruitment&#13;
          manga, Changsha, Tangier)                                     Changsha stimulates competition between voca-&#13;
                                                                        tional schools by publicizing student national exam&#13;
     --   Fostering industry-academia partnerships, including&#13;
                                                                        scores and employment rates and by distributing&#13;
          links between private for-profit firms and vocational&#13;
                                                                        performance data among local firms. The city also&#13;
          schools (or universities) to improve curricula and&#13;
                                                                        offers tax credits and funding to firms for sending&#13;
          the applicability of developed skills, to address the&#13;
                                                                        participants to worker training programs and for&#13;
          needs of firms, and to boost employment rates with-&#13;
                                                                        training offices and fairs. The city also drew together&#13;
          in the city (Bucaramanga, Changsha, Coimbatore,&#13;
                                                                        civil servants from multiple municipal departments&#13;
          Gaziantep)&#13;
                                                                        to identify the talent needs of existing and emerging&#13;
â&#128;¢	   Talent attraction programs. Some cities focused on attract-        firms (a leading group); it leverages available national&#13;
     ing new talent and educational programs to the city by             programs and funding schemes for talent attraction&#13;
                                                                        and engages in recruitment efforts domestically&#13;
     --   Creating programs that attracted new talent                   and abroad. In recent years, Changsha attracted&#13;
          through diaspora networks by offering resettlement            10,000 professionals through national and munici-&#13;
          allowances and attractive positions (Changsha,                pal programs (including 102 high-level talents and&#13;
          Kigali)                                                       17 start-ups). In general, the cityâ&#128;&#153;s firms have stated&#13;
                                                                        that skilled labor has been relatively easy to find.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                    23&#13;
&amp;#12;Why were these interventions successful? Some key reasons             4. Insights for Other Cities&#13;
follow:&#13;
                                                                      Our case studies show that economically successful cities&#13;
â&#128;¢	   Talent attraction strategies combined market mechanisms          can be found in all world regions and many different kinds of&#13;
     (financial incentives, quality employment opportunities) with    countriesâ&#128;&#148;whether they are highly centralized or decentral-&#13;
     an enhanced overall quality of life. They relied on highly ef-   ized; whether the income level is high, low, or in the middle;&#13;
     fective distribution channels such as diaspora networks.         whether the city is perpetually at peace or still recovering&#13;
                                                                      from natural or manmade disasters. Successful cities can be&#13;
â&#128;¢	   Vocational training initiatives were often designed in collab-   landlocked or maritime, endowed or not with amenities and&#13;
     oration with private for-profit firms. Such collaboration        natural resources, culturally diverse or homogeneous, and&#13;
     ensured that curricula addressed the needs of business           administratively consolidated or fragmented. They can be&#13;
     and maintained a highly applied, practical focus. In Co-         highly industrialized, postindustrial service economies or&#13;
     imbatore, for example, students spent part of each school        postagrarian societies just beginning to urbanize. Successful&#13;
     day working on the shop floor, thus not just ensuring            cities can also be examples of highly inclusive growth or stud-&#13;
     they had relevant, employable skills, but also all but           ies in contrasts between the haves and have-nots. In other&#13;
     ensuring they would get a job offer on graduation.               words, they reflect our contemporary planet of city dwellers,&#13;
                                                                      in all its complexity and contradictions.&#13;
â&#128;¢	   Program funding was often linked to performance. Perfor-&#13;
     mance was assessed through periodic reviews, in which            Taken together, these six case studies clearly demonstrate&#13;
     diverse stakeholder groups were consulted.                       that no single path leads to economic success. Each of these&#13;
                                                                      cities has pursued its own path to prosperity, accountingâ&#128;&#148;&#13;
â&#128;¢	   Some countries (Colombia, Morocco) involved representatives&#13;
                                                                      consciously or unconsciouslyâ&#128;&#148;for its particular competitive&#13;
     of various stakeholder groups (business, academia, labor) in&#13;
                                                                      advantages, existing constraints, national policies, local scope&#13;
     the design of national as well as local educational training&#13;
                                                                      and capacity, overall market trends, and even administrative&#13;
     programs. The representatives of such groups worked&#13;
                                                                      and cultural traditions. These six cities are as different from&#13;
     together to assess local skills needs and develop curric-&#13;
                                                                      each other as they are successful.&#13;
     ula and delivery mechanisms relevant to those needs.18&#13;
     Industry group input, in particular, proved to be an             So what can other cities learn from these six success stories?&#13;
     essential ingredient.                                            More than any specific answers they arrived at or solutions&#13;
                                                                      they implemented, our six successful cities provide exam-&#13;
â&#128;¢	   Customized worker training programs were highly effective&#13;
                                                                      ples of how this process can work in practice, given partic-&#13;
     in several of the cities (Bucaramanga, Changsha, Tangier) be-&#13;
                                                                      ular scope conditions. The challenges these cities faced and&#13;
     cause of their high responsiveness to employer needs. If fund-&#13;
                                                                      overcame are not dissimilar to what the World Bankâ&#128;&#153;s clients&#13;
     ed by the national or local government, such programs&#13;
                                                                      encounter on a daily basis. Following are some categories of&#13;
     are a form of economic development incentive, typically&#13;
                                                                      insights that apply beyond the specifics of geography, culture,&#13;
     designed for the benefit of major employers. They bridge&#13;
                                                                      political system, or individual personalities. They are, individ-&#13;
     the gap between general and transferable skills that the&#13;
                                                                      ually as well as collectively, among the global best practices in&#13;
     local workforce may have and the specific skills needed&#13;
                                                                      urban economic development.&#13;
     by an individual employer. The best programs actively in-&#13;
     volved universities and technical schools as well as work-&#13;
     force development agencies and EDOs in their design.&#13;
                                                                      City competitiveness: General or specific?&#13;
                                                                      Cities seeking to improve their economic performance&#13;
                                                                      should consider both pursuing sector-specific initiatives and&#13;
                                                                      developing a favorable overall business climate. Practically all&#13;
                                                                      of the cities studied prioritized providing a business envi-&#13;
                                                                      ronment conducive to investment, company formation, and&#13;
                                                                      growth. Although most of them targeted specific sectors for&#13;
                                                                      proactive economic development efforts, they did not neglect&#13;
                                                                      the â&#128;&#156;bread and butterâ&#128;&#157; industriesâ&#128;&#148;including those producing&#13;
                                                                      nontradable goods and servicesâ&#128;&#148;that still account for the&#13;
                                                                      lionâ&#128;&#153;s share of employment and, in some cities, fiscal receipts.&#13;
                                                                      Evidence suggests that maintaining a welcoming, cost-com-&#13;
                                                                      petitive business environment was an important factor in&#13;
                                                                      these six citiesâ&#128;&#153; ability to retain and attract investors, includ-&#13;
                                                                      ing those in targeted sectors.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      Successful cities do not rely only on attracting outside&#13;
                                                                      investment to spur economic growth. They balance business&#13;
                                                                      recruitment with assisting the growth of existing firmsâ&#128;&#148;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 24&#13;
&amp;#12;which typically account for the lionâ&#128;&#153;s share of new jobs in          pany formation and growth, as well as impediments to the&#13;
most economiesâ&#128;&#148;as well as with helping the formation of              business climate that need to be addressed, and they provide&#13;
new businesses. Sustained long-term economic success in              valuable input into designing economic development strate-&#13;
most case study cities has been observed across all these            gies and workforce or skills formation programs. Companies&#13;
three main pillars of economic development: growth of                may also be able to contribute financial or in-kind resources&#13;
existing firms, attraction of outside investors, and creation        and leverage their relationship capital and commercial ties&#13;
of new businesses. However, the following broad trends were          for the advancement of the city. For cities that have at least&#13;
observed:                                                            a reasonably well-developed private sector, including it as an&#13;
                                                                     integral part of the economic development effort makes a lot&#13;
â&#128;¢	   Cities with more formal, well-organized municipal eco-          of sense.&#13;
     nomic development institutions (Bucaramanga, Chang-&#13;
     sha, Gaziantep) had a fairly balanced focus between the         The private sector can lead local economic development&#13;
     attraction of new outside investment and the expansion          efforts in circumstances where public sector scope or capacity&#13;
     of existing firms.                                              is limited. In some cases, the private sector is simply better&#13;
                                                                     positioned to lead on specific kinds of initiatives. For-profit&#13;
â&#128;¢	   Cities relying mainly on economic development institu-          firms are involved in economic development not just as a&#13;
     tions at the national level (Kigali) or their local represen-   form of corporate social responsibility or as a public relations&#13;
     tatives (Tangier) had a stronger focus on the attraction of     exercise, but because an economically successful city can ben-&#13;
     new firms.                                                      efit their business and enhance their bottom-line profitability&#13;
                                                                     in the longer run.&#13;
â&#128;¢	   Cities with less organized formal economic development&#13;
     institutions had a stronger focus on the needs and ex-          A city can be successful even without a dedicated economic&#13;
     pansion of existing firms (Coimbatore).                         development agency or department, and some cities stud-&#13;
                                                                     ied have multiple entities responsible for different facets of&#13;
â&#128;¢	   Most of the cities were broadly supportive of the estab-        economic development. However, coordination and strategy&#13;
     lishment of new firms. However, new business starts             development are facilitated by the existence of a single entity&#13;
     directly attributable to proactive economic development         as a focal point for a cityâ&#128;&#153;s economic development endeav-&#13;
     efforts did not account for a sizable share of economic         orsâ&#128;&#148;whether it is a department of the city government, an&#13;
     activity in any of the six cities studied.                      independent EDO, or even the local chamber of commerce or&#13;
                                                                     other entity performing this function.&#13;
Institutional framework&#13;
                                                                     More important than which entity leads a cityâ&#128;&#153;s economic&#13;
No one preferred or optimal institutional arrangement exists         development efforts are what specific functions it performs&#13;
for city-level economic development as long as somebody is in        and how effectively it does so. Here again, issues of scope&#13;
charge of it and is accountable for it. Countries have diverse       and capacity come into play. Successful cities tend to rely on&#13;
approaches to local governance, including the administra-            dedicated economic development professionals to lead these&#13;
tive scope provided to their municipalities and metropolitan         efforts.&#13;
areas for a variety of functions. Likewise, the capacity to&#13;
design and actually implement city-level economic develop-           Strategic planning&#13;
ment strategies and initiatives can lie with any institutional&#13;
actorâ&#128;&#148;public, private, national, or local.                           Cities can post exceptional economic outcomes with or with-&#13;
                                                                     out a formal economic development strategy or a structured&#13;
Metropolitan economic development should be a shared re-             planning process to develop one. However, the process of&#13;
sponsibility of local government; higher tiers of government         creating a formal strategy can be an effective tool to facilitate&#13;
(regional, provincial, state, national); and local stakeholder       coordination among different institutional actors involved in&#13;
groups, including the productive sector. In all cases studied,       economic development and may enable them to more easily&#13;
individual city economic development functions were carried          tap into national support mechanisms (for example, if a city&#13;
out by some combination of these three sets of institutional         has selected some sectors from a longer list of those targeted&#13;
actors. The specifics of which entity is best positioned to per-     for development by the national government). The six cities&#13;
form which economic development function depend on local             studied differed according to whether they had formal eco-&#13;
circumstances as well as the broader national administrative         nomic development strategies, implementation mechanisms&#13;
and legal context. A cityâ&#128;&#153;s proactive economic development           and lines of accountability, and measurement of results. But&#13;
efforts may, but do not necessarily have to, be led by the local     in all cases they showed a good degree of alignment in terms&#13;
government to be effective.                                          of broad vision and priorities.&#13;
The local private sector can be an important partner, and            Effective economic development strategies are based on&#13;
sometimes a leader, in metropolitan economic development.            sound analytics, including global industry trends, product&#13;
Homegrown firms operate in the community and have an                 and market knowledge, competitive strengths and vulner-&#13;
economic as well as social interest in its prosperity. They can      abilities, and identification of areas of opportunity and the&#13;
play a crucial role in helping to identify constraints to com-       specific actions necessary to capitalize on them. Most cities&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                       25&#13;
&amp;#12;that did have educational development strategies used a          â&#128;¢	   Business climate improvements&#13;
structured and often quite sophisticated process to assess       â&#128;¢	   Industry sector targeting&#13;
the cityâ&#128;&#153;s competitive position as well as external trends and   â&#128;¢	   Investment attraction&#13;
opportunities and then formulated a long-term strategy to        â&#128;¢	   Entrepreneurial assistance&#13;
address those opportunities.                                     â&#128;¢	   Export facilitation&#13;
                                                                 â&#128;¢	   Place making and branding&#13;
Interventions                                                    â&#128;¢	   Strengthening of human capital&#13;
Proactive interventions can significantly affect the quantity    Successful cities not only seize on opportunities when they&#13;
and quality of a cityâ&#128;&#153;s economic growth and are a valuable       present themselves but also create opportunities where none&#13;
tool for enhancing prosperity. A variety of specific interven-   are apparent. Through systematic and painstaking analyses of&#13;
tions were used in our six case study cities, generally with     market trends, successful cities can identify areas where they&#13;
fairly high success rates measured in terms of their economic    stand the best chances of achieving results. Economically suc-&#13;
influence. These interventions fall into the following broad     cessful cities forge their own paths and pursue growth where&#13;
categories:                                                      it made sense, rather than jump on bandwagons and follow&#13;
                                                                 the latest economic development fads (biotech, software,&#13;
                                                                 clean technology, and the like).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
26&#13;
&amp;#12;Notes&#13;
1	&#13;
   In various competitiveness rankings and city benchmarking exercises,                also attracted high-caliber universities, such as Carnegie Mellon Universi-&#13;
cities are usually compared across a combination of quantifiable criteria              ty, to help develop talent at home. Changsha prioritized the attraction of&#13;
(jobs, foreign direct investment, exports, business costs, and so on) and              high-level talent by seeking individuals to contribute to research, local firm&#13;
subjective criteria (livability, diversity, and so on). Sometimes, social              competitiveness, and the start-up of new firms in targeted sectors (such as&#13;
criteria such as crime rates and health outcomes are also included. In our             3D printing). Changsha successfully leveraged resources such as its low-cost&#13;
analysis, we adhere to only two sets of quantitative criteria: growth in GDP           labor pool and large consumer market (that is, market opportunities) and&#13;
and in employment, both in absolute terms and relative to the national                 made efforts to improve its levels of human capital by addressing the qual-&#13;
economies in which the cities are located. Competitive cities were consid-             ity of vocational degree programs, promoting links between programs and&#13;
ered to be those cities that outperformed their national economies in terms            the private sector, and rewarding firms that introduced training programs&#13;
of GDP and job growth over a sustained five-year period (2007â&#128;&#147;12).                     (with tax incentives if programs became government certified). Bucaraman-&#13;
                                                                                       ga promoted collaboration between local universities and private sector&#13;
2	&#13;
   These cities are in no way without their own challenges, nor are they pre-&#13;
                                                                                       firms. At the free trade zone, the city leveraged national resources and local&#13;
dicted to have sustained growth in the future. We studied these particular&#13;
                                                                                       capacity to offer firms customized training programs for their employees.&#13;
cities to understand why they had such exceptional economic growth; we&#13;
extracted transferable lessons in each case to offer suggestions for other&#13;
                                                                                       9&#13;
                                                                                         For example, within Colombia, Santander Departmentâ&#128;&#148;of which Bucara-&#13;
cities seeking similar outcomes. No city operates in a vacuum; some condi-             manga is the capitalâ&#128;&#148;has a reputation for always submitting to BogotÃ¡ on&#13;
tions and factors will be unique in every case.                                        time its applications for programmatic support or funding, usually ahead&#13;
                                                                                       of most other regions. The Bucaramanga Chamber of Commerce assists&#13;
3	&#13;
   In this report, the terms private sector, productive sector, and for-profit firms&#13;
                                                                                       its members in identifying national sources of support (for technology&#13;
are used interchangeably. They denote enterprises of any size engaged in the&#13;
                                                                                       development, training, funding, export assistance, and the like) and in sub-&#13;
production of goods or services, regardless of actual ownership or company&#13;
                                                                                       mitting timely applications. Accordingly, although these support programs&#13;
size, as well as their membership organizations, such as industry associa-&#13;
                                                                                       are theoretically available to all Colombian firms, those in Santander tend&#13;
tions or chambers of industry or commerce. Along with government and&#13;
                                                                                       to make much more extensive use of them.&#13;
academia, the private sector is one of the three key stakeholder groups with&#13;
a role in local economic development.&#13;
                                                                                       10&#13;
                                                                                         The most dramatic example of such an effort is the recruitment French&#13;
                                                                                       automaker Renault to Tangier. That investment, in turn, attracted dozens&#13;
4	&#13;
  Data on citiesâ&#128;&#153; economic structures were obtained from their respective&#13;
                                                                                       of that automakerâ&#128;&#153;s tier 1 suppliers. The ripple effect through the local econ-&#13;
national statistical sources, World Bank field research, or both. Sector defi-&#13;
                                                                                       omy was measured in the tens of thousands of jobs, most of them paying&#13;
nitions and industry classifications vary from one city to another, and reli-&#13;
                                                                                       much more than the average local wage.&#13;
able, consistent data for making statistically sound comparisons between&#13;
the cities are not available. Nonetheless, the Competitive Cities Knowledge&#13;
                                                                                       11&#13;
                                                                                         For example, successful cities built new access roads or railroads to&#13;
Base team has been able to observe general patterns among the cities and               business facilities such as factories, designed and funded customized work-&#13;
draw some broader conclusions about the similarities and dissimilarities of            force training programs, sent potential employees to â&#128;&#156;finishing schoolsâ&#128;&#157; to&#13;
their economies and how those economies have evolved over time.                        acquire job-specific skills, and even researched and catered to the idiosyn-&#13;
                                                                                       crasies of individual foreign corporate executives (such as hosting a dinner&#13;
5&#13;
 Clearly, these generalizations are very broad, but examples from individual&#13;
                                                                                       for them and making sure to serve their favorite brand of beverage).&#13;
cities are quite revealing. For instance, Rwandaâ&#128;&#153;s postconflict society does&#13;
not yet have an indigenous private sector with sufficient capacity to assume&#13;
                                                                                       12&#13;
                                                                                         In Tangier, local leaders (from the regional governorate or wilaya, EDOs,&#13;
any major role in economic developmentâ&#128;&#147;related activities. In practice,                and workforce agency) made sure that Renault had what it needed to&#13;
government (especially at the national level) drives a lot of the initiatives,         expand production locally. Renault is now in the process of doubling its&#13;
although Kigaliâ&#128;&#153;s mayor has undertaken interventions to enhance the cityâ&#128;&#153;s             annual vehicle output while gradually expanding its local supplier network&#13;
appeal as a business and tourism destination. Circumstances differ in China            and increasing vehiclesâ&#128;&#153; local content. Land adjacent to the existing plant&#13;
and Morocco, but there, too, government has driven a lot of the initiatives            has already been allocated for the next expansion phase, when in addi-&#13;
that have resulted in the creation of private sector jobs and growth.                  tion to Renault- and Dacia-branded vehicles, the Tangier plant will begin&#13;
                                                                                       producing cars under the Nissan brand, some for the Moroccan market but&#13;
6&#13;
 This process has been far from seamless, and corruption remains a serious&#13;
                                                                                       especially for export.&#13;
issue (a de facto â&#128;&#156;hidden taxâ&#128;&#157;) the world over. For example, Bucaramangaâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
former mayor is in jail for misuse of public funds, and business leaders in&#13;
                                                                                       13&#13;
                                                                                         In this context, entrepreneurial assistance means services designed to&#13;
some other cities studied have reported being approached for â&#128;&#156;voluntaryâ&#128;&#157;               facilitate the formation and growth of companies in the metropolitan area.&#13;
contributions by public officials. Still, all six cities have undeniably made          This assistance can be to long-established businesses, to recent start-ups,&#13;
tremendous strides in improving transparency and public accountability, as             and even to students and unemployed individuals who may have ideas&#13;
well as lightening the burden that the tolerance for corruption imposes on             about productive activities but lack the know-how and financial means to&#13;
local businesses.                                                                      make them happen.&#13;
7&#13;
  This report does not delve into the specialization versus diversification&#13;
                                                                                       14&#13;
                                                                                         Changsha and Tangier both displayed highly effective mechanisms for&#13;
debate often brought up in the context of local economic development.                  kicking problems upstairsâ&#128;&#148;that is, alerting decision makers at higher tiers&#13;
Given their fairly large but not yet megacity size, most of these successful           of government about issues, obstacles, and constraints. Such mechanisms&#13;
cities have relatively diversified economies with multiple growth engines;             are particularly important for cities in more centralized countries, because&#13;
none is a one-industry town. Conventional tools for assessing the degree               lower tiers of government may lack the scope and capacity to address them.&#13;
of specialization used in high-income countries of the Organisation for                Even in much more decentralized countries (for example, Colombia), central&#13;
Economic Co-operation and Development (Herfindahl-Hirschman Index,                     government assistance was sometimes sought to address specific issues.&#13;
location quotients, shift-share, and so on) were not widely applied in these           15&#13;
                                                                                          Notwithstanding this effort, however, the export intensity (measured in&#13;
cities, nor would they have been as insightful, given the substantial rates of         terms of volume of exports relative to metropolitan GDP) remains relatively&#13;
informality and general data reliability issues. By targeting a few (usual-            low for most of these case study cities. The production of nontraded goods&#13;
ly no more than a handful) individual sectors for growth, most of these                and services, consumed entirely in the local market, remains the backbone&#13;
cities have followed a strategy of diversified specialization. Whether these           of many of these metropolitan economies, though this situation is gradually&#13;
industries had higher rates of concentration than their national economies,            changing. In addition, serious data limitations exist when attempting to&#13;
for example, mattered less than the contribution they were making to local             measure subnational exports. The measurement problem is even more acute&#13;
know-how, employment, and tax receipts, as well as their potential to drive            for service exports (including tourism). For some countries, addressing&#13;
tomorrowâ&#128;&#153;s economic growth.                                                            these data gaps is a greater priority than for others, but cities have relatively&#13;
8	&#13;
   For example, Rwanda strove to attract talent from its diaspora popula-              little say.&#13;
tion, encouraging people to return and work to help rebuild the country. It&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                      27&#13;
&amp;#12; In practice, few of these models were pure because they combined ele-&#13;
                                                                                 REFERENCES&#13;
16&#13;
&#13;
ments of different approaches.&#13;
17&#13;
   For example, Rwanda strove to attract talent from its diaspora popula-&#13;
tion, encouraging people to return and work to help rebuild the country. It      World Bank. 2009. World Development Report 2009: Reshap-&#13;
also attracted high-caliber universities, such as Carnegie Mellon Universi-&#13;
ty, to help develop talent at home. Changsha prioritized the attraction of&#13;
                                                                                         ing Economic Geography. Washington, DC: World&#13;
high-level talent by seeking individuals to contribute to research, local firm           Bank.&#13;
competitiveness, and the start-up of new firms in targeted sectors (such as&#13;
3D printing). Changsha successfully leveraged resources such as its low-cost     â&#128;&#148;â&#128;&#148;â&#128;&#148;. Forthcoming. Competitive Cities for Jobs and Growth:&#13;
labor pool and large consumer market (that is, market opportunities) and              What, Who and How. Washington, DC: World Bank.&#13;
made efforts to improve its levels of human capital by addressing the qual-&#13;
ity of vocational degree programs, promoting links between programs and&#13;
the private sector, and rewarding firms that introduced training programs&#13;
(with tax incentives if programs became government certified). Bucaraman-&#13;
ga promoted collaboration between local universities and private sector&#13;
firms. At the free trade zone, the city leveraged national resources and local&#13;
capacity to offer firms customized training programs for their employees.&#13;
18&#13;
  	 For example, in Tangier stakeholders from both the public and private&#13;
sectors interact through a dedicated body called CRAM (ComitÃ© RÃ©gional&#13;
dâ&#128;&#153;AmÃ©lioration de lâ&#128;&#153;EmployabilitÃ©), which brings together the regionâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
governor (wali); the Regional Investment Comission; the local office of the&#13;
national workforce agency; professional associations (for example, the or-&#13;
ganization representing the automotive industry); and the local university.&#13;
CRAM has four specialized commissions for targeted sectors in the region&#13;
(automotive and aeronautics, offshoring, transport and logistics, and tour-&#13;
ism) that analyze the workforce studies prepared by the national workforce&#13;
agency; assess local industry training needs; develop concrete action plans;&#13;
and periodically assess, validate, or correct the plans as needed.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 28&#13;
&amp;#12;APPENDIX&#13;
&#13;
Hypotheses for Competitive Cities Case Studies&#13;
As noted in the main body of the report, the CCKB team developed and applied a set of standardized research hypoth-&#13;
eses to all six successful cities studied. The objective was to ensure the comparability of findings and to enable the&#13;
drawing of salient lessons from the findings. The hypotheses are presented below in their entirety.&#13;
&#13;
1.	 City Competitiveness: General or Specific?&#13;
&#13;
    Cities posting exceptional economic performance have made strategic bets on specific industrial&#13;
    initiatives, rather than just improving their general investment climate. By specific industrial initia-&#13;
    tives, we mean public investments that are geared to the needs of particular growth industries (e.g. industry-spe-&#13;
    cific tax and regulations; vocational skills and customized worker training programs; sector-specific infrastruc-&#13;
    ture; club goods; investment promotion; etc.). By general investment climate, we mean tax and regulations&#13;
    more broadly, basic institutions such as land and housing markets, trunk infrastructure, primary and secondary&#13;
    education, and other investments that affect industries more equally. Indeed, some high-performing cities actual-&#13;
    ly operated with a rather poor quality overall investment climate.&#13;
&#13;
    A closer look at the components of city economic outcomes reveals the following ingredients of success:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        a.	 Successful cities often have a main â&#128;&#156;themeâ&#128;&#157; â&#128;&#147; one area where they particularly excel. Such&#13;
            themes can include the presence of a flagship university, an anchor company catalyzing private-sector&#13;
            investment, excellence in research/technology commercialization, a strong entrepreneurial ecosystem, or&#13;
            exceptionally high degrees of openness to the global economy.&#13;
            A focus on developing and/or producing tradable goods and services (rather than non-trad-&#13;
            ables). Tradable goods and services are the only way that a city can grow the size of its economic pie,&#13;
            while non-tradables such as construction or retail only recirculate existing income.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        b.	 High-performing cities have nurtured not only new investments but also new business&#13;
            starts and the growth of existing firms. Cities might enjoy short-term economic success based on&#13;
            just one or two of these pillars, but sustained growth over the longer term relies on all three pillars.&#13;
&#13;
2.	 Strategic Planning&#13;
&#13;
    Inflection points in a cityâ&#128;&#153;s economic performance over time have been attributable to the specific&#13;
    actions/interventions of its policymakers and public officials. Policy interventions have been a critical&#13;
    part of changing a cityâ&#128;&#153;s development trajectory. Specific characteristics of an impactful strategic planning process&#13;
    may include&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        a.	 Analytics to inform strategy development:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                â&#128;¢	 benchmarking the cityâ&#128;&#153;s economic performance in relation to its competitors; and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                â&#128;¢	 a longitudinal analysis looking at the cityâ&#128;&#153;s own past performance&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        b.	 A structured planning process to:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                           29&#13;
&amp;#12;              â&#128;¢	 identify key economic development issues the city is facing, such as factors adversely affecting&#13;
                 company formation, growth, and attraction, with a particular emphasis on market and coordi-&#13;
                 nation failures holding firms back from achieving faster growth;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
              â&#128;¢	 identify the cityâ&#128;&#153;s main competitive strengths, such as research excellence, human capital, or&#13;
                 infrastructure facilities; and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
              â&#128;¢	 formulate a vision of progress the city as a whole can make in a certain timeframe, including&#13;
                 specific measures to address its problems and capitalize on the cityâ&#128;&#153;s competitive strengths. The&#13;
                 particular process utilized in each city will be documented.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      c.	 Assembling a â&#128;&#156;growth coalitionâ&#128;&#157; at the city level: Bringing together public sector agencies with di-&#13;
          verse external stakeholder groups from civil society, constructively engaging them in the strategic plan-&#13;
          ning process both to provide input on key economic development issues, and to come up with suggestions&#13;
          for addressing them. Stakeholders engaged in this iterative dialogue can include: relevant public sector&#13;
          departments and agencies; universities and other entities with a role in workforce development and tech-&#13;
          nology commercialization; private-sector participants elected by each sector (rather than just the â&#128;&#156;usual&#13;
          suspectsâ&#128;&#157; or largest incumbents); trade unions and organized labor; NGOs; the media; multipliers; and&#13;
          excluded or marginalized social groups (impoverished communities, castes, religious and ethnic commu-&#13;
          nities, women).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      d.	 Strategic decision-making and prioritization: A structured process for evaluating policy priorities&#13;
          and trade-offs between different public investment alternatives, including credible cost-benefit (or compa-&#13;
          rable) analyses.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      e.	 Viable funding mechanisms: Economically successful cities have in place robust mechanisms and&#13;
          instruments to finance city-level interventions, including revenue capture and public-private partnerships&#13;
          (PPPs).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      f.	 Flexibility and adaptability: The flexibility of the formal (or informal) plan to adapt to changing condi-&#13;
          tions is of greater importance than the planâ&#128;&#153;s original design. Particular attention will been devoted to the&#13;
          process by which problems, challenges, and unexpected events are resolved along the way&#13;
&#13;
3.	 Implementation Framework&#13;
&#13;
   The level of autonomy (fiscal/institutional/political) and powers enjoyed by a city government or&#13;
   local economic development authority â&#128;&#147; the â&#128;&#156;Mayorâ&#128;&#153;s Wedgeâ&#128;&#157; â&#128;&#147; is a significant factor in being able&#13;
   to push through interventions resulting in improved economic outcomes. Critical actions include:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      a.	 Having a dedicated economic development agency or department: This entity, tasked specifically&#13;
          with achieving strategic economic objectives, is most effective when it has the following:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
              â&#128;¢	 Sufficient autonomy (both financial and administrative) from public administration rules and&#13;
                 procedures;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
              â&#128;¢	 Adequate funding to meet its statutory responsibilities; and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
              â&#128;¢	 A well-defined geographical remit (municipal, metropolitan, regional, state/provincial).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
30&#13;
&amp;#12;b.	 Efficient internal management: Successful cities are marked by the following three characteristics of&#13;
    internal management:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        â&#128;¢	 Competent teams with clear role designations, reporting structures, and incentives.  &#13;
           This includes an ability to solve inter-departmental coordination failures and implementation&#13;
           problems;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        â&#128;¢	 An enabling environment that promotes operational efficiency. In particular, effective&#13;
           public management systems and structures (PFM, HRM, internal controls, IT Systems, etc.) that&#13;
           stand the test of time are essential for getting results;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        â&#128;¢	 A credible performance monitoring and evaluation function. Monitoring and evalua-&#13;
           tion, at the heart of well-functioning organizations, is an essential tool to assess implementation&#13;
           against objectives, and to continually inform visions, strategies, policies and implementation&#13;
           effectiveness, including the following kinds of behaviors and routines: setting goals; prioritization&#13;
           among goals; developing policies; evaluation and measurement of performance; and incentive&#13;
           structures.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
c.	 Private-sector and other stakeholder involvement in implementation: Depending on how devel-&#13;
    oped a countryâ&#128;&#153;s private sector is, for-profit firms (both indigenous and foreign-owned) can play a highly&#13;
    constructive role in implementing a cityâ&#128;&#153;s economic development strategy, including through the follow-&#13;
    ing:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        â&#128;¢	 Marshaling financial and in-kind resources;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        â&#128;¢	 Integrating local small and medium-sized businesses into multinationalsâ&#128;&#153; global supply chains;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        â&#128;¢	 Enlisting senior corporate leaders to act as the cityâ&#128;&#153;s public champions (as a business location) and&#13;
           utilize their relationship capital;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        â&#128;¢	 Engaging private-sector firms in workforce development, filling the talent pipeline by collaborat-&#13;
           ing with educational institutions to transfer their know-how to younger/future workers, as well as&#13;
           to retrain existing labor that may lack the necessary skills;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        â&#128;¢	 Harnessing the efforts of trade unions; and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        â&#128;¢	 Involving other stakeholder groups from the â&#128;&#156;growth coalitionâ&#128;&#157;, as applicable.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                   31&#13;
&amp;#12;Funding for the companion papers and the main report was provided by&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CIIP     Competitive Industries and Innovation Program&#13;
&#13;
Financed by                               in partnership with&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
www.theciip.org&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Find the companion papers and the main report at&#13;
www.worldbank.org/competitivecities&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="25658344">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2015/12/25658344/six-case-studies-economically-successful-cities
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2015/12/25658344/six-case-studies-economically-successful-cities</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2015/12/25658344/six-case-studies-economically-successful-cities</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2015-12-09T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2015-12-11T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <docm_id>090224b083c4204a</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b083c40620</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2015/12/09/090224b083c4204a/2_0/Rendered/INDEX/Six0case0studi0y0successful0cities0.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2015/12/09/090224b083c4204a/2_0/Rendered/PDF/Six0case0studi0y0successful0cities0.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2015-12-09T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2015-12-01T10:35:02Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Six case studies of economically successful cities
        </repnme>
        <docna>
            Six case studies of economically successful cities
        </docna>
        <display_title>Six case studies of economically
            successful cities</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2015/12/25658344/six-case-studies-economically-successful-cities</listing_relative_url>
        <subtopic>ICT Policy and Strategies,Subnational Economic Development,City Development Strategies,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Housing &amp; Human Habitats</subtopic>
        <docty>Working Paper</docty>
        <teratopic>Communities and Human Settlements,Information and Communication Technologies,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth,Urban Development</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Kulenovic,Zeljko Joe</author>
            <author>Cech,Alexandra Mc Elroy</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>090224b083c4204a_2_0</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Communities and Human Settlements,Information and Communication Technologies,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth,Urban Development</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            skills, social profiles, business
            incubators, capital markets, city officials, economic
            growth, business opportunities, production, multipliers,
            business community, waste management, chambers of commerce,
            national economies, income, data sources, gdp growth rate,
            groups, economic objectives, gdp per capita, programs,
            information, services, exports, decision makers, social
            responsibility, mayors, incentives, capacity building,
            macroeconomic conditions, industrial zones, content, models,
            training programs, planning, cities, stakeholder
            involvement, wealth, social sciences, city governments, free
            trade, economic structures, urban economic development,
            trends, e-government, plans, collaboration, knowledge,
            development, women entrepreneurs, vocational schools,
            influence, technical assistance, per capita income,
            construction permit, training, partnerships, rent,
            development strategies, industrial structure, experts,
            failures, criteria, centralization, markets, development
            agencies, research, income levels, key industries,
            dividends, social indicators, service delivery, natural
            resources, city dwellers, trade policies, taxes, land use,
            business intelligence, technology, ppps, human capital,
            vocational training, city leaders, capital, economic
            performance, science, economic outcomes, international
            trade, transparency, software, participation, training
            initiatives, political systems, value, competitiveness,
            benchmarking, credit, stakeholders, stakeholder groups,
            solid waste, historic sites, development strategy,
            comparative advantages, secondary cities, tourism promotion,
            capital cities, cultural centers, tourism, decision-making,
            decision making, solid waste management, measurement, city
            economic development, economic development strategies,
            building permits, city economies, land acquisition, policy,
            quality of life, city competitiveness, media, governance,
            social capital, taxation, economic development, tourism
            development, slums, trade, gdp, goods, theory, supply
            chains, technology transfer, growth rate, bilateral trade,
            business climate, investment, business leaders, housing
            markets, partners, monopolies, business environment,
            competitive advantage, business licensing, law, open
            markets, funding, development agency, city livability,
            economic geography, collective action, technologies,
            outcomes, cost analysis, sewerage, competitive advantages
        </keywd>
        <owner>LCREC - External Communications (LCREC)</owner>
        <repnb>101713</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>ICT</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT for Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies (ICT)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Industry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Science and Technology</ml:concept><ml:concept>Information and Communication Technologies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Transport</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Industrial Parks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports</ml:concept><ml:concept>Strategic Planning</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT Policy and Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civil Service Employment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civil Service Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Capital</ml:concept><ml:concept>Managing People</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Employment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civil Society</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Textiles</ml:concept><ml:concept>Engineering</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Industrial Zones</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ports &amp; Waterways</ml:concept><ml:concept>Strategic Policy Planning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Local Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>ICT Strategy, Policy and Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Jobs and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Competitive Cities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resources Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>