<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>                                                      101667&#13;
    TA X ES &amp; PU BLIC&#13;
SPEN DING IN IN DON ESI A&#13;
               WH o PAYs A n d WH o b e n e F iTs ?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  minisTrY oF FinAnce&#13;
  rePUblik indonesiA&#13;
&amp;#12;2                                                                                    OCTObER 2015&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The World Bank                   The World Bank                Printed in&#13;
Office Jakarta                   1818 H Street NW              November 2015&#13;
Indonesia Stock Exchange         Washington, DC 20433,&#13;
Building Tower II/12th Floor     USA&#13;
Jl. Jend. Sudirman Kav.          T (202) 458-1876&#13;
52-53                            F (202) 522-1557/1560&#13;
Jakarta 12910                    W www.worldbank.org&#13;
P (6221) 5299-3000&#13;
F (6221) 5299-3111&#13;
W www.worldbank.org/id&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Taxes and Public Spending        The World Bank does not       endorsement or acceptance&#13;
in Indonesia: Who pays and       guarantee the accuracy of     of such boundaries.&#13;
who benefits is a product of     the data included in this     For any questions regarding&#13;
the staff of the World Bank.     work. The boundaries,         this report, please contact&#13;
The findings, interpretations,   colors, denominations, and&#13;
and conclusions expressed        other information shown       Vivi Alatas&#13;
herein do not necessarily        on any map in this work do    (valatas@worldbank.org)&#13;
reflect the views of the         not imply any judgment on&#13;
Board of Executive Directors     the part of the World Bank    and Matthew Wai-Poi&#13;
of the World Bank or the         concerning the legal status   (mwaipoi@worldbank.org).&#13;
Government they represent.       of any territory or the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
TA XE S AN D PUBLIC SPE N DING IN IN DON E S IA&#13;
&amp;#12;1                                                                    OCTOBER 2015&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         Acknowledgements&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          Taxes and Public Spending in Indonesia: Who pays and       The paper is a policy-oriented summary of Jellema,&#13;
          who beneï¬&#129;ts was prepared by Indonesiaâ&#128;&#153;s Fiscal Policy      Wai-Poi and A ar (2015). For further information, please&#13;
          Agency ( Badan Kebijakan Fiskal, or BKF) at the Ministry   contact Matthew Wai-Poi (mwaipoi@worldbank.org).&#13;
          of Finance, Government of Indonesia, and the World&#13;
          Bankâ&#128;&#153;s Poverty &amp; Equity Global Practice.                   Financial support for this background paper and its&#13;
                                                                     accompanying technical working paper was provided&#13;
          The BKF team was led by Luky Alï¬&#129;rman (Director of          by the Australian Department of Foreign A airs and&#13;
          Macroeconomic Policy Center, PKEM-BKF) and included        Trade through the trust fund for the Partnership for&#13;
          Arti Dyah Woroutami (Head of Welfare and Labor Sub-        Knowledge-based Poverty Reduction. The trust fund&#13;
          division of PKEM-BKF) and Ahmad Fikri Aulia (Executive     is under the strategic oversight of Bambang Widianto,&#13;
          of Welfare and Labor Sub-division of PKEM-BKF), under      Executive Secretary of the National Team for the&#13;
          the guidance of Suahasil Nazara, Chairman of the Fiscal    Acceleration of Poverty Reduction (Tim Nasional&#13;
          Policy Agency                                              Percepatan Penanggulangan Kemiskinan, or TNP2K)&#13;
                                                                     and Rahma Iryanti of the National Development Planning&#13;
          The World Bank team included Rythia A ar (Consultant,      Agency ( Badan Perencanaan Pembangunan Nasional,&#13;
          GPVDR), Jon Jellema (Consultant, GPVDR) and Matthew        or Bappenas).&#13;
          Wai-Poi (Senior Economist, GPVDR). The team, led by&#13;
          Vivi Alatas (Lead Economist, GPVDR), provides technical&#13;
          and policy advice based on sound empirical research and The paper was edited by Peter Milne. Layout for this&#13;
          analysis to the Government of Indonesia to support its  paper was done by Bentuk Team (Andreas Pranoto,&#13;
          e orts to reduce poverty, vulnerability and inequality. Muhammad Kamal, Phoebe Wathoel, Randy Kurnia).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
TA XE S AN D PUBLIC SPE N DING IN IN DON E S IA&#13;
&amp;#12;2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        Table of&#13;
                                                    Contents&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         01    ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS&#13;
&#13;
         02    TA B L E O F C O N T E N T S&#13;
&#13;
         03    L I S T O F A C R O N Y M S , A B B R E V I AT I O N S , A N D I N D O N E S I A N T E R M S&#13;
&#13;
         04    EXECUTIVE SUMMARY&#13;
&#13;
         06    I. RISING INEQUALITY IN INDONESIA: CAUSES AND CONSEQUENCES&#13;
&#13;
         13    I I . A D D R E S S I N G I N E Q U A L I T Y: T H E R O L E O F F I S C A L P O L I C Y&#13;
&#13;
         15    I I I . W H AT T H E G O V E R N M E N T C H O O S E S T O S P E N D O N C A N A F F E C T I N E Q U A L I T Y&#13;
&#13;
         26    I V. H O W T H E G O V E R N M E N T C H O O S E S T O R A I S E M O N E Y C A N A F F E C T I N E Q U A L I T Y&#13;
&#13;
         30    V. C O N C L U S I O N&#13;
&#13;
         33    REFERENCES&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
TA XE S AN D PUBLIC SPE N DING IN IN DON E S IA&#13;
&amp;#12;3                                                                         OCTOBER 2015&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         List Of Acronyms, Abbreviations,&#13;
         And Indonesian Terms&#13;
&#13;
          TERM                   DEFINITION&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          APBN                   Anggaran Pendapatan dan Belanja Negara (Central Government Budget)&#13;
&#13;
          Bappenas               Badan Perencanaan Pembangunan Nasional (National Development Planning Agency)&#13;
&#13;
          BKF                    Badan Kebijakan Fiskal (Fiscal Policy Agency)&#13;
&#13;
          BLSM                   Bantuan Langsung Sementara Miskin (unconditional cash transfer program)&#13;
&#13;
          BPS                    Badan Pusat Statistik (Central Statistics Agency)&#13;
&#13;
          BSM                    Bantuan Siswa Miskin (Financial Assistance for Poor Students)&#13;
&#13;
          CEQ                    Commitment to Equity&#13;
&#13;
          GDP                    Gross Domestic Product&#13;
&#13;
          IDR                    Indonesian Rupiah&#13;
&#13;
          Jamkesmas              Jaminan Kesehatan Masyarakat (Public Health Insurance)&#13;
&#13;
          KIP                    Kartu Indonesia Pintar (Indonesia Smart Card)&#13;
&#13;
          MBA                    Master of Business Administration&#13;
&#13;
          PIT                    personal income tax&#13;
&#13;
          PKH                    Program Keluarga Harapan (Family Hope Program)&#13;
&#13;
          Raskin                 Subsidi Beras Bagi Masyarakat Berpendapatan Rendah&#13;
                                 (Rice Subsidies for Low Income People)&#13;
&#13;
          SD                     Sekolah Dasar (Primary School)&#13;
&#13;
          SMA                    Sekolah Menengah Atas (Senior Secondary School)&#13;
&#13;
          SMP                    Sekolah Menengah Pertama (Junior Secondary School)&#13;
&#13;
          Susenas                Survey Sosial Ekonomi Nasional (National Socio-Economic Survey)&#13;
&#13;
          TNP2K                  Tim Nasional Percepatan Penanggulangan Kemiskinan&#13;
                                 (National Team for the Acceleration of Poverty Reduction)&#13;
&#13;
          UDB                    Uniï¬&#129;ed Database&#13;
&#13;
          US$                    United States Dollar&#13;
&#13;
          VAT                    Value-added tax&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
TA XE S AN D PUBLIC SPE N DING IN IN DON E S IA&#13;
&amp;#12;4                                                 OCTObER 2015&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         Executive&#13;
        Summary&#13;
                                                  I n e qua l i t y i n I n d on e s i a i s r i s i ng r a pi dly.&#13;
                                                  During the 1997-98 Asian financial crisis, poverty rose&#13;
                                                  sharply, while the Gini measure of inequality fell, as the&#13;
                                                  richest were the hardest hit. Since then, the Gini has&#13;
                                                  increased from 30 points in 2000 to 41 points in 2014, its&#13;
                                                  highest recorded level. In 2002, the richest 10 percent&#13;
                                                  of Indonesians consumed as much as the poorest 42&#13;
                                                  percent combined; by 2014, they consumed as much&#13;
                                                  as the poorest 54 percent. Even this is likely to be&#13;
                                                  understated, as household surveys often miss the rich.&#13;
                                                  Indonesiaâ&#128;&#153;s level of inequality is now becoming high and&#13;
                                                  climbing faster than most of its East Asian neighbors.&#13;
&#13;
                                                  Mo s t I n d on e s i a n s be l i e v e t h at u r ge n t&#13;
                                                  ac t ion i s n e e de d, o t h e rw i s e 2 0 5 mi l l ion&#13;
                                                  I n d on e s i a n s a r e at r i s k of be i ng l e f t&#13;
                                                  be h i n d. Since the 1997-97 crisis, Indonesiaâ&#128;&#153;s real GDP&#13;
                                                  per capita grew at an annual average of 5.4 percent&#13;
                                                  between 2000 and 2014. This has helped to create a&#13;
                                                  stronger middle class than ever before; there are now 45&#13;
                                                  million people (the richest 18 percent of all Indonesians)&#13;
                                                  who are economically secure and enjoy a higher quality&#13;
                                                  of life. But the problem is that this segment is leaving&#13;
                                                  the other 205 million, who are much less likely to enjoy&#13;
                                                  benefits of growth, behind. The consequences of&#13;
                                                  doing nothing to address high levels of inequality can&#13;
                                                  be serious. The public shares this view; 88 percent of&#13;
                                                  Indonesians who were surveyed in 2014 believed that it&#13;
                                                  was urgent for the Government to address inequality.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
TA XE S AN D PUBLIC SPE N DING IN IN DON E S IA&#13;
&amp;#12;5           E X ECU TI V E SU M M A RY                                      OCTObER 2015&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         Fi s c a l p ol ic y i s on e of t h e k e y op t ion s            W h i l e t h e gr e at e s t im pac t on i n e qua l i t y i s&#13;
         ava i l a bl e t o g ov e r n m e n t s t o a ddr e s s            l i k e ly t o c om e t h r ough s pe n di ng c hoic e s ,&#13;
         i n e qua l i t y a n d i t h a s be e n u s e d                   how I n d on e s i a r a i s e s r e v e n u e c a n m at t e r&#13;
         s uc c e s s f u l ly b y o t h e r c ou n t r i e s .             t o o. In Indonesia, indirect taxes such as value-added&#13;
         Fiscal policy â&#128;&#147; how and where the Government spends,               tax and tobacco excise are relatively neutral and do&#13;
         and how it raises money to fund this spending â&#128;&#147; is one of          not have much impact on inequality. Revenue from&#13;
         the four main policy responses to addressing inequality 1.         personal income tax is low in Indonesia, making up only&#13;
         Some countries have successfully used fiscal policy to             10 percent of tax revenues, or around 1.9 percent of GDP.&#13;
         reduce their levels of inequality; South Africa and Brazilâ&#128;&#153;s       An increase in compliance and a broader tax base would&#13;
         Gini coefficients fell by 17.5 and 14 points, respectively.        increase revenues and also lower inequality. Global&#13;
         In contrast, Indonesiaâ&#128;&#153;s fiscal policy (based on 2012 data)        experience shows, however, that progressive taxation&#13;
         only reduced the Gini by 3 points. With growing concern            benefitting poor and vulnerable households can only&#13;
         about rising inequality levels, Indonesia should look to           help tackle inequality if it is done in a sustainable way. In&#13;
         address the problem through fiscal policy, among others.           other countries, personal incomes tax raises significantly&#13;
                                                                            more revenue and is borne to a much greater degree by&#13;
         I n d on e s i a c ou l d c ho o s e t o s pe n d i n              the rich, helping to reduce inequality directly, as well as&#13;
         di f f e r e n t way s , i n or de r t o be n e f i t t ho s e     funding pro-poor spending.&#13;
         be i ng l e f t be h i n d mor e . Education spending,&#13;
         which by law makes up 20 percent of the budget, is                 F u rt h e r r e s e a r c h i s n e e de d t o ta k e&#13;
         inequality-reducing, although not as much as in other              r e c e n t im p orta n t de v e l opm e n t s a n d&#13;
         countries. But Indonesia spends little on programs that are        mi s s i ng f i s c a l p ol ic i e s i n t o ac c ou n t.&#13;
         most effective in reducing inequality. Health spending, for        This paper uses 2012 data but a number of new and&#13;
         example, benefits the poor relative to their income than it        important developments have taken place since then.&#13;
         does the rich. However, the low level of spending means            Changes in fuel subsidy policies and an accompanying&#13;
         it has little relatively little impact on inequality. Similarly,   expansion in the scholarships program and the&#13;
         social assistance programs are the most strongly pro-poor,         distribution of temporary cash assistance took place&#13;
         but they have little impact on inequality levels due to their      during 2013-15. As a result, further research is now&#13;
         small size. While other countries have effectively used            needed to factor in these recent developments and also&#13;
         cash transfers to reduce inequality, Indonesia invests the         to bring in other key components of fiscal policy, such&#13;
         least in these programs even though they are the most              as personal income tax, that were not included in this&#13;
         cost-effective inequality reducing programs.                       research. To address this, the Fiscal Policy Agency of&#13;
                                                                            Indonesiaâ&#128;&#153;s Ministry of Finance will collaborate with the&#13;
                                                                            World Bank on follow-up analytical activities.&#13;
&#13;
        1&#13;
          A detailed exploration of the causes and consequences of inequality in Indonesia as well as recommended policy response options&#13;
        can be found in the World Bank (2015a), Indonesiaâ&#128;&#153;s Rising Divide.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
TA XE S AN D PUBLIC SPE N DING IN IN DON E S IA&#13;
&amp;#12;6                                                                                                                                        OCTOBER 2015&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     1.&#13;
                RISING&#13;
                INEQUALITY IN&#13;
                INDONESIA:&#13;
                CAUSES AND&#13;
                CONSEQUENCES&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                Inequality has been increasing with economic growth&#13;
                being primarily enjoyed by relatively few households&#13;
                I N E QUA L I T Y I N I N D ON E S I A I S R I S I NG R A PI DLY.                                                        everyone was a ected, but the richest were the hardest&#13;
                By most measures, inequality in Indonesia has reached                                                                    hit. Since then, the Gini has increased from 30 points in&#13;
                historically high levels. In 2002, the richest 10 percent of                                                             2000 to 41 points in 2014, its highest recorded level in&#13;
                Indonesians consumed as much as the poorest 42 percent                                                                   Indonesia (Figure 1). Even this high level is likely to be&#13;
                combined; by 2014, they consumed as much as the poorest                                                                  underestimated, however, because household surveys&#13;
                54 percent. A popular measure of inequality is the Gini                                                                  tend to miss out the richest households. Once relatively&#13;
                coe cient, where 0 represents complete equality and 100                                                                  moderate by international standards, Indonesiaâ&#128;&#153;s level of&#13;
                represents complete inequality. During the 1997-98 Asian                                                                 inequality is now becoming high and climbing faster than&#13;
                ï¬&#129;nancial crisis, poverty rose sharply, while the Gini fell;                                                              most of its East Asian neighbors (Figure 2).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
After a long period of stability, the Gini began rising,                                                                                                                  SOURCE BPS, Susenas and World Bank calculations&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                          NOTE Nominal consumption Gini. The national poverty&#13;
then fell with the Asian ï¬&#129;nancial crisis, before rising                                                                                                                   line was changed in 1998, and the 1996 rate calculated&#13;
&#13;
sharply since the recovery.                                                                                                                                               under both the new and old methodologies.&#13;
&#13;
Gini coefï¬&#129;cient (points) and national poverty rate (percent) 1980â&#128;&#147;2014 (ï¬&#129;g.1)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          S UHA RTO ER A                                                                                                           ASIA N               D E M O C RACY,                                              G LO B A L FINA NCI A L&#13;
                                                                                                                                   FIN A N C IA L       DE C E N TRA L IZ ATIO N A N D                               C RISIS &amp; A F T E R MAT H&#13;
                                                                                                                                   C RISIS              C O M M O D ITY B O O M&#13;
45&#13;
40&#13;
&#13;
35&#13;
&#13;
30&#13;
                                                                                                    GINI&#13;
25&#13;
&#13;
20&#13;
&#13;
    15&#13;
&#13;
10&#13;
                                              POV ERTY              OLD                                                                                                   P OVERTY              NEW&#13;
    5&#13;
&#13;
    0&#13;
         1980&#13;
&#13;
                1981&#13;
&#13;
                       1982&#13;
&#13;
                              1983&#13;
&#13;
                                     1984&#13;
&#13;
                                            1985&#13;
&#13;
                                                   1986&#13;
&#13;
                                                          1987&#13;
&#13;
                                                                 1988&#13;
&#13;
                                                                        1989&#13;
&#13;
                                                                               1990&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                      1991&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                             1992&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                    1993&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                           1994&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                  1995&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                         1996&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                1997&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                       1998&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                              1999&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                     2000&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                            2001&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                   2002&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                           2003&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                  2004&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                         2005&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                2006&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                       2007&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                              2008&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                     2009&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                            2010&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                   2011&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                          2012&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                 2013&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        2014&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
2&#13;
 This section summarizes a more detailed examination of the causes and consequences of inequality in Indonesia from World Bank (2015a),&#13;
Indonesiaâ&#128;&#153;s Rising Divide .&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
TA XE S AN D PUBLIC SPE N DING IN IN DON E S IA&#13;
&amp;#12;7            RISING INEQUALITY IN INDONESIA:                                              OCTOBER 2015&#13;
             CAUSES AND CONSEQUENCES&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The increase in the Gini in Indonesia over the past two                                        SOURCE Zhuang, et al. 2014.&#13;
                                                                                               NOTE Consumption Ginis for all countries except Malaysia, which uses&#13;
decades is one of the highest in the region.                                                   income. The periods for each country are: Indonesia 1990-2011; Malaysia&#13;
Gini coefï¬&#129;cient in East Asia 1990s &amp; 2000s (ï¬&#129;g.2)                                              1992-2009; Lao PDR 1992-2008; China 1990-2008; Vietnam 1992-2008;&#13;
                                                                                               Thailand 1990-2009; the Philippines 1991-2009; and Cambodia 1994-2008.&#13;
    90'S           00' S&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      Malaysia&#13;
         China&#13;
    Philippines&#13;
      Thailand&#13;
     Indonesia&#13;
    Cambodia&#13;
           India&#13;
           Laos&#13;
      Vietnam&#13;
&#13;
                     0                 10                         20                      30                         40                     50                        60&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
F I F T E E N Y E A R S OF S U S TA I N E D E C ON OM IC GR OW T H                 HOW E V E R , T H E E C ON OM IC A L LY S E C U R E A R E N OW&#13;
H A S R E DUC E D P OV E RT Y A N D C R E AT E D A GR OW I NG                      L E AV I NG T H E O T H E R 2 0 5 M I L L ION BE H I N D.The&#13;
C L A S S OF E C ON OM IC A L LY S E C U R E HOU S E HOL D S .                     beneï¬&#129;ts of economic growth have been enjoyed largely&#13;
After recovering from the Asian ï¬&#129;nancial crisis, Indonesiaâ&#128;&#153;s                       by this growing consumer class. Between 2003 and 2010,&#13;
real GDP per capita grew at an annual average of 5.4 percent                       consumption per person for the richest 10 percent of&#13;
between 2000 and 2014. This growth helped to pull many                             Indonesians grew at over 6 percent per year after adjusting&#13;
out of poverty; the poverty rate more than halved, from 24                         for inï¬&#130;ation, but grew at less than 2 percent per year for the&#13;
percent during the aftermath of the crisis down to 11 percent                      poorest 40 percent. This contributed both to a slowdown&#13;
by 2014. Economic growth has also helped to create a                               in the pace of poverty reduction, with the number of poor&#13;
stronger consumer class than ever before; there are now 45                         people falling by only 2 percent per year since 2002, and the&#13;
million people (the richest 18 percent of all Indonesians) who                     numbers of those vulnerable to poverty falling barely at all&#13;
are considered economically secure and enjoying a higher                           (Figure 3).&#13;
quality of life. They are the fastest growing segment of the&#13;
population, increasing at an average 10 percent per year since&#13;
2002 (Figure 3) 3.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
An economically secure â&#128;&#156;consumerâ&#128;&#157; class has                                        SOURCE Susenas and World Bank calculations. The poor are below the national&#13;
                                                                                   poverty line of around IDR 300,000 per person per month. The vulnerable have a&#13;
grown strongly at 10 percent per year since 2002,                                  greater than 10 percent chance of being poor the next year and are under 1.5 times&#13;
                                                                                   the poverty line. The consumer class is economically secure, with a less than 10&#13;
and now includes nearly one in ï¬&#129;ve Indonesians,                                    percent chance of being poor or vulnerable next year, and consume more than IDR&#13;
but reductions in poverty and vulnerability have                                   1 million per person per month. The emerging consumer class is safe from poverty&#13;
                                                                                   but not vulnerability and lie between the vulnerability and economic security lines.&#13;
been very small.                                                                   See World Bank forthcoming (a) for more details.&#13;
&#13;
Population share by class (percent) 2002-14 (ï¬&#129;g.3)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      PO O R                                   1 8 .1 %                3 3 .7%                              41. 2%                                             7%&#13;
      ANN UA L G R OW T H    2.2 %&#13;
                                       2002&#13;
      V U L N E RA BL E                        1 7.7 %            2 8 . 8%                 43 . 3 %                                                       1 0.1 %&#13;
      ANN UA L G R OW T H    0.1 %&#13;
                                       2006&#13;
                                               1 3.3%         2 6 .1 %               45. 9%                                                      14. 8%&#13;
      EM E RGIN G C ON S U ME R&#13;
      C LAS S                          2010&#13;
      ANN UA L G R OW T H 2 .4%&#13;
                                               1 1 .3% 2 6 .9 %                  44. 2%                                                          17.7%&#13;
&#13;
      C O N S U M E R C L AS S         2014&#13;
      ANN UA L G R OW T H 10 %&#13;
                                              0                          20                    40                    60                    80                       100&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
3&#13;
  For this report, households in the consumer class in Indonesia are defined as those who are economically secure from poverty and&#13;
vulnerability. See the note to the chart and the World Bankâ&#128;&#153;s forthcoming report on the middle class in Indonesia, Indonesiaâ&#128;&#153;s New Climbers&#13;
(forthcoming (a)), for more details.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
TA XE S AN D PUBLIC SPE N DING IN IN DON E S IA&#13;
&amp;#12;8        RISING INEQUALITY IN INDONESIA:                                  OCTOBER 2015&#13;
         CAUSES AND CONSEQUENCES&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         Income inequality can be unfair when                             growth for all, if poorer people are unable to properly&#13;
                                                                          invest in their childrenâ&#128;&#153;s development, if people fail to exit&#13;
         not everyone has the same initial&#13;
                                                                          poverty and vulnerability and move into the consumer&#13;
         opportunities in life                                            class, and if people fail to ï¬&#129;nd productive jobs. Recent&#13;
                                                                          research indicates that a higher Gini coe cient leads to&#13;
         INCOME INEQUALITY IS NOT ALWAYS A BAD THING; IT                  lower and less stable growth (Dabla-Norris, et al. 2015).&#13;
         CAN PROVIDE REWARDS FOR THOSE WHO WORK HARD                      Moreover, when the share of total income held by the&#13;
         AND TAKE RISKS. Hard work and innovation beneï¬&#129;t                  richest 20 percent of people increases by 5 percentage&#13;
         society by creating new goods and services that everyone         points, economic growth falls by 0.4 of a percentage&#13;
         can enjoy, as well as contributing to a larger economy. This,    point. At the same time, when the share of total income&#13;
         in turn, can provide the Government with a greater ability       held by the poorest 20 percent of people increases&#13;
         to generate revenue and provide public services to all. If       by 5 percentage points, economic growth increases&#13;
         this results in a gap between those hard workers and those       by 1.9 percentage points. Increased income shares for&#13;
         who work less hard, then some income inequality may be           the second- and third-poorest quintiles also increase&#13;
         justiï¬&#129;ed and even desirable. Many Indonesians share this         economic growth.&#13;
         view. When asked in a 2014 survey whether inequality&#13;
         is ever acceptable, 74 percent of respondents say that           H IGH I N E QUA L I T Y C A N A L S O H AV E N E G AT I V E&#13;
         â&#128;&#156;inequality is sometimes acceptableâ&#128;&#157; so long as wealth           S O C I A L R E PE R C US S ION S . When people perceive that&#13;
         acquisition is fair and meritocratic (World Bank 2015b).         there are large di erences in income and wealth, this&#13;
                                                                          can create social tension and disharmony that can, in&#13;
         IN EQUA LIT Y CA N BE U N FA IR , HOW EV ER , W HEN              turn, create conï¬&#130;ict. Indeed, districts with higher levels of&#13;
         IT IS DU E TO FACTOR S BEYON D THE CON TROL OF                   inequality than the average in Indonesia have 1.6 times&#13;
         IN DI V IDUA LS. There are many forms of inequality.             higher rates of conï¬&#130;ict than districts with lower levels of&#13;
         There are economic inequalities of income, wealth and            inequality (Peirskalla and Sachs 2015). Conï¬&#130;ict, in turn,&#13;
         consumption.4 There are also inequalities of opportunity,        can reduce economic growth through labor disruptions&#13;
         when not everyone has access to the same opportunities           and lower investment. Furthermore, if inequality is due&#13;
         in life. Factors beyond the control of an individualâ&#128;&#148;where       to rent-seeking behaviorâ&#128;&#148;people trying to capture&#13;
         you are born, how educated or wealthy your parents are,          existing resources without generating new wealth&#13;
         and what access to public services you had when you              through productive activityâ&#128;&#148;then this also has costs;&#13;
         were growing upâ&#128;&#148;can have a major inï¬&#130;uence on how your            individuals seek favorable treatment and protection of&#13;
         life turns out. Having a healthy start in life and a quality     their positions, leading to the misallocation of resources,&#13;
         education are fundamental prerequisites for getting a            corruption and nepotism, all of which have high social&#13;
         good job and earning a decent living in the future. When         and economic costs, including a loss of conï¬&#129;dence in&#13;
         economic inequality arises because of this inequality of         public institutions.&#13;
         opportunityâ&#128;&#148;that is, when not everyone has a fair start in&#13;
         lifeâ&#128;&#148;it hurts people unfairly. There are other factors outside   I N FAC T, I N D ON E S I A N S A L R E A DY T H I N K&#13;
         of an individualâ&#128;&#153;s control that can a ect incomes, standards     I N E QUA L I T Y I S T O O H IGH . People surveyed estimate,&#13;
         of living and inequality. These include government policies      on average, that the richest ï¬&#129;fth of Indonesians account&#13;
         such as food import restrictions that increase the cost of       for 38 percent of all consumption (Figure 4) (World Bank&#13;
         living most for the poor, or patterns of government taxes        2015b). Actually, inequality is even higher than they think:&#13;
         and spending that do not collect and channel su cient            national data indicate that the richest ï¬&#129;fth really enjoy&#13;
         resources to help the poor and the vulnerable, or those          49 percent of all household consumption4. On average,&#13;
         without equal access.                                            respondents indicate a preference for a more equal&#13;
                                                                          country, one in which the richest ï¬&#129;fth only account for 28&#13;
         High inequality can also lead to slower                          percent of consumption. They may not realize, however,&#13;
         growth and poverty reduction, and can                            that this ideal would make Indonesia more equal than&#13;
                                                                          almost all other countries in the world.&#13;
         create conflict&#13;
&#13;
         HIGH LEVELS OF INEQUALITY MAY SLOW ECONOMIC&#13;
         GR OW T H , W H I L E MOR E E QUA L C OU N T R I E S M AY&#13;
         GR OW FA S T E R . High inequality may reduce economic&#13;
&#13;
         4&#13;
          And the actual consumption Gini may even be higher, since many wealthy Indonesians are not captured in the survey data. The&#13;
         World Bank, Bank Indonesia and Ministry of Finance are collaborating on a project to estimate more accurately the number of&#13;
         middle and upper class Indonesians. The findings are published in a forthcoming World Bank report (forthcoming (b)).&#13;
&#13;
TA XE S AN D PUBLIC SPE N DING IN IN DON E S IA&#13;
&amp;#12;9          RISING INEQUALITY IN INDONESIA:                                             OCTOBER 2015&#13;
           CAUSES AND CONSEQUENCES&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Not only do surveyed Indonesians believe inequality                                           SOURCE World Bank (2015b) using LSI (2014) data.&#13;
&#13;
should be lower than it is now, in reality it is even&#13;
higher than they think it currently is.&#13;
Share of national consumption by each quintile: what people think it should be,&#13;
what people think it is, what it really is (percent) (ï¬&#129;g.4)&#13;
                                                                                   POOREST QUINTILE             2        3     4       RICHEST QUINTILE&#13;
&#13;
W HAT T H E Y         14         16                          19                    23                               28&#13;
THIN K I T&#13;
SHO UL D B E&#13;
&#13;
W H AT TH E Y         7    12                18                       25                            38&#13;
THIN K I T I S&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
W H AT IT             7    10           14                    20                        49&#13;
AC TUA L LY I S&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                  0         10           20             30            40          50           60             70             80             90      100&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
           Understanding why inequality is increasing in&#13;
           Indonesia through four case studies&#13;
           THERE ARE FOUR MAIN CAUSES OF INEQUALITY                                and form the new consumer class, while Siti is a member&#13;
           IN INDONESIA THAT AFFECT BOTH CURRENT AND                               of Indonesiaâ&#128;&#153;s upper class.8&#13;
           FUTURE GENER ATIONS. 5 First, inequality of opportunity&#13;
           means that not everyone develops the skills needed                      T H E P O OR H AV E L I M I T E D R E S OU R C E S , E A R N L OW&#13;
           to ï¬&#129;nd well-paying jobs. Second, with an increasing                     I NC OM E S F R OM T H E M , S AV E L I T T L E F OR T H E&#13;
           emphasis on skill in the modern economy, the wages of                   F U T U R E , A N D A R E T H E MO S T V U L N E R A BL E T O&#13;
           these high-skilled jobs are much higher than those for                  S HO C K S . Putri (Box 1) only completed primary school.&#13;
           low-skilled jobs. At the same time, those without the skills            Because of her poor education, she works part-time&#13;
           are becoming trapped into informal or low-productivity                  at a warung (roadside food stall) and receives a low&#13;
           jobs. Third, there are inequalities in ï¬&#129;nancial and physical            informal wage. She does own a small plot of land, which&#13;
           wealth that also drive di erences in income. Fourth,                    a neighbor uses to grow rice; the neighbor keeps half&#13;
           shocks can a ect inequality at any stage of the framework               of the rice, while Putriâ&#128;&#153;s household consumes the other&#13;
           by eroding a householdâ&#128;&#153;s ability to earn an income, save,               half. However, because Putri has four children, the rice&#13;
           and invest in health and education.                                     from the land is not enough, and she needs to buy extra&#13;
                                                                                   rice from the market, so recent rice price shocks have&#13;
           FOUR CASE STUDIES ILLUSTR ATE HOW DIFFERENT                             hurt her and her family. Over time, the land has seen&#13;
           INDONESIANS ARE AFFECTED.Thirty-eight percent                           small increases in value, but the lack of a formal land&#13;
           of Indonesians were poor or vulnerable (Figure 3) in                    title means that the land value is limited and it cannot&#13;
           Indonesia in 2014.6 Putriâ&#128;&#153;s case is an illustrative example of          be used as collateral to borrow to start a small business.&#13;
           the types of assets they have, the income they generate,                Putri has a small amount of savings that she keeps at&#13;
           and how shocks may a ect them.7 Similar to 44 percent                   home for hard times. As she does not earn any interest&#13;
           of Indonesians, Fitri has escaped vulnerability but is not              on the savings, inï¬&#130;ation means that the value of these&#13;
           yet economically secure; she is a member of an emerging                 savings actually falls over time, and because she dips into&#13;
           consumer class who could still fall back into vulnerability,            the savings frequently over the course of the year when&#13;
           but are starting to generate modest disposable income.                  income is low or costs are high, the savings gradually&#13;
           Dewi represents the 18 percent of Indonesians who are                   diminish unless they are topped up. Putri also has social&#13;
           now economically secure from poverty and vulnerability                  connectionsâ&#128;&#148;friends and family in the local communityâ&#128;&#148;&#13;
&#13;
           5&#13;
             These four drivers are explored at length in World Bank (2015a).&#13;
           6&#13;
             The poor are defined as those below the national poverty line of around IDR 300,000 per person per month. The vulnerable&#13;
           have a greater than 10 percent chance of being poor the next year and are under 1.5 times the poverty line. The consumer class&#13;
           is economically secure, with a less than 10 percent chance of being poor or vulnerable next year, and consume more than IDR&#13;
           1 million per person per month. The emerging consumer class is safe from poverty but not vulnerability and lie between the&#13;
           vulnerability and economic security lines. See World Bank (forthcoming (a)) for more details.&#13;
           7&#13;
             The following cases are illustrative examples only and not real case studies.&#13;
           8&#13;
             As discussed in Footnote 7, the number of wealthier Indonesians is not well understood.&#13;
&#13;
TA XE S AN D PUBLIC SPE N DING IN IN DON E S IA&#13;
&amp;#12;10        RISING INEQUALITY IN INDONESIA:                                     OCTOBER 2015&#13;
          CAUSES AND CONSEQUENCES&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
and she has relied upon these in the past to borrow money to pay her childrenâ&#128;&#153;s tuition fees. Putri has free health insurance&#13;
from the Government, but does not know what it covers and there is no community health center near her anyway. If she or one&#13;
of her children falls sick, she will either have to borrow from her family or sell her land to meet the health care costs.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     B O X .1&#13;
&#13;
     Putri is poor with limited assets and low returns&#13;
     Asset                              Intensity of Use                 Returns                           Accumulation&#13;
&#13;
     Human Capital:                     Works part-time at a warung      Receives low informal wage        None&#13;
     SD education&#13;
&#13;
     Physical Capital: Small            Neighbor uses land to            Neighbor keeps half the           Small increase in value&#13;
     area of land                       produce rice; Putri cannot       rice, Putriâ&#128;&#153;s household           of land, but marginal&#13;
                                        use it as collateral (absence    consumes the rest                 because of lack of title and&#13;
                                        of legal title)                                                    development&#13;
&#13;
     Financial Capital: Small           Unused; kept to smooth           Negative due to inï¬&#130;ation          None. Savings depleted&#13;
     savings kept at home               consumption in the case                                            and renewed throughout&#13;
                                        of a shock                                                         the year&#13;
&#13;
     Social Capital: Family and         Used to borrow money when Allows some investment in                Ongoing social activities&#13;
     friend networks in local           her childrenâ&#128;&#153;s tuition fees her childrenâ&#128;&#153;s education               reinforce networks&#13;
     community                          are due&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
T H E E M E R GI NG C ON S U M E R C L A S S I S AC C U M U L AT I NG    small business, does not comply with minimum wage laws. Fitri&#13;
MOR E E DUC AT ION A N D S OM E S AV I NG S . Fitri (Box 2) is a         has a small amount of savings that she keeps in a basic bank&#13;
member of Indonesiaâ&#128;&#153;s largest classâ&#128;&#148;the emerging consumer                account for emergencies. These savings slowly accumulate&#13;
classâ&#128;&#148;which is above the vulnerability line but is not yet               over time, as she manages to save part of her salary. Fitri does&#13;
economically secure, having more than 10 percent chance of               not have health insurance, because she is not poor enough to&#13;
being vulnerable next year. Fitri completed junior high school           receive free health insurance from the Government, and her&#13;
and used her social connections to ï¬&#129;nd a job on an assembly              informal job at a small business means that she does not make&#13;
line at a small, locally-owned factory which, because it is a            contributions to the public health insurance system either.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     BOX.2&#13;
&#13;
     Fitri is an emerging consumer with&#13;
     minor asset accumulation&#13;
      Asset                             Intensity of Use                 Returns                           Accumulation&#13;
&#13;
      Human Capital:                    Works on a small-scale factory   Receives ï¬&#129;xed salary below        None, because the factory does&#13;
      SMP education                     assembly line                    the minimum wage as non-          not o er training&#13;
                                                                         unionized&#13;
&#13;
      Physical Capital: none            None                             None                              None&#13;
&#13;
      Financial Capital: Small          Unused; kept to smooth           Small interest payment from       Salary savings&#13;
      savings, no pension fund          consumption in the case of a     basic savings account&#13;
                                        shock&#13;
&#13;
      Social Capital: Family and        Used friend network to get       Factory job gives higher income   Ongoing social activities and&#13;
      friend networks from local        factory job                      than the informal alternatives    involvement in union activities&#13;
      community, factory worker union                                                                      reinforces networks&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
TA XE S AN D PUBLIC SPE N DING IN IN DON E S IA&#13;
&amp;#12;11       RISING INEQUALITY IN INDONESIA:                                      OCTOBER 2015&#13;
         CAUSES AND CONSEQUENCES&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
T H E M I DDL E C L A S S H A S I M PR OV I NG A S S E T S , H IGH E R        accumulating and she is also eligible for retirement beneï¬&#129;ts.&#13;
I NC OM E S A N D BE T T E R S AV I NG S . Dewi is a member of                She has a network of friends and family in Jakarta, which&#13;
Indonesiaâ&#128;&#153;s middle class (Box 3). She completed high school and               helped her to get her job. Dewi and her husband have two&#13;
works as a civil servant with a good salary and beneï¬&#129;ts. She also             children, which means that they can spend a little more on&#13;
receives ongoing training and skills certiï¬&#129;cation through her work.           their education than if she had a larger family. Dewi has&#13;
She does not own any land or housing, but does have savings that              health insurance in case illness strikes, but if she were to&#13;
are invested in the bank and earn interest. Over time her savings are         lose her job she would need to dip into her savings.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     BOX.3&#13;
&#13;
     Dewi is an economically secure&#13;
     consumer with improving assets&#13;
     Asset                             Intensity of Use                   Returns                          Accumulation&#13;
&#13;
     Human Capital:                    Works as a civil servant           Receives good salary and         Ongoing training and&#13;
     SMA education                                                        beneï¬&#129;ts                          certiï¬&#129;cation&#13;
&#13;
     Physical Capital: None            None                               None                             None&#13;
&#13;
     Financial Capital: Savings;       Invested in bank                   Interest received on savings     Salary saved&#13;
     retirement beneï¬&#129;ts&#13;
&#13;
     Social Capital: Family and        Used to obtain civil               Enables good formal sector       Ongoing social and work&#13;
     friend networks in Jakarta        servant job                        wage with beneï¬&#129;ts, relative to   activities reinforces networks&#13;
                                                                          informal sector&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
R IC H E R I N D ON E S I A N S H AV E G O OD R E S OU R C E S A N D          proï¬&#129;ts back into the business to grow it, and continues&#13;
E A R N H IGH I NC OM E S F R OM T H E M . T H E Y A L S O US E T H I S       to accumulate ï¬&#129;nancial capital over time, which in turn&#13;
I NC OM E T O S AV E , W H IC H I N T U R N L E A D S T O H IGH E R           earns even more income the following year. Siti is well-&#13;
I NC OM E T OMOR R OW. Siti is a member of Indonesiaâ&#128;&#153;s upper                  connected to the business and political elites, and has&#13;
class (Box 4). She ï¬&#129;nished university and is about to enroll in an            used these connections to secure lucrative licenses and&#13;
MBA program in the US. She receives a high salary for managing                contracts for her company. Siti and her husband have&#13;
her own company, which makes a good proï¬&#129;t. She also has                       just one child, who is now attending university in Europe.&#13;
investments in mutual funds and the stock market, which have                  A combination of savings, insurance and preventative&#13;
seen strong returns in recent years. She reinvests the company                measures means that Siti is the least a ected by shocks.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     BOX.4&#13;
&#13;
     Siti is upper class with many assets and high returns&#13;
     Asset                             Intensity of Use                   Returns                          Accumulation&#13;
&#13;
     Human Capital:                    Manages her own company            Receives a high salary           Is enrolling in a US MBA&#13;
     Tertiary education&#13;
&#13;
     Physical Capital: Owns            Lives in one house and rents       Enjoys high imputed rent and     Apartments and houses are&#13;
     apartments and houses             out the others                     receives good rental income      increasing quickly in value&#13;
&#13;
     Financial Capital: savings;       Invested in ï¬&#129;nancial sector and    Interest received on savings,    Dividends and capital gains&#13;
     mutual funds; stocks; equity in   own company                        high returns from funds and      reinvested; company proï¬&#129;ts&#13;
     company                                                              stocks; proï¬&#129;ts from company      re-invested in expansion&#13;
&#13;
     Social Capital: well-connected    Uses connections to secure         Company makes high proï¬&#129;ts        Extends and reinforces elite&#13;
     to business and governing         lucrative licenses and contracts   from licenses and contracts      network through company&#13;
     elites                            for her company                                                     contracts&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
TA XE S AN D PUBLIC SPE N DING IN IN DON E S IA&#13;
&amp;#12;12       RISING INEQUALITY IN INDONESIA:                                   OCTOBER 2015&#13;
         CAUSES AND CONSEQUENCES&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                R E C E N T C H A NGE S I N T H E F OU R&#13;
                                                                                                M A I N C AUS E S OF I N E QUA L I T Y&#13;
                                                                                                A L S O M E A N I T I S I NC R E A S I NG .&#13;
                                                                                                While gaps in access to health and&#13;
                                                                                                education have closed, a quality&#13;
                                                                                                gap remains. As a result, the gaps&#13;
                                                                                                in health and education outcomes&#13;
                                                                                                have not closed as much the gaps&#13;
                                                                                                in access. Consequently, although&#13;
                                                                                                many poorer children are staying in&#13;
                                                                                                school longer, they are not receiving&#13;
                                                                                                the skills they need for better jobs&#13;
                                                                                                when they graduate. And the stakes&#13;
                                                                                                are getting higher. With the demand&#13;
                                                                                                for skilled labor increasing constantly,&#13;
                                                                                                the gap between skilled and&#13;
                                                                                                unskilled wages is also increasing,&#13;
                                                                                                which means that inequality due to&#13;
                                                                                                wage income is also on the rise. At&#13;
                                                                                                the same time, not only do a small&#13;
                                                                                                number of Indonesians hold most&#13;
                                                                                                of the ï¬&#129;nancial and physical wealth,&#13;
                                                                                                this concentration of wealth has&#13;
                                                                                                been increasing even further, also&#13;
                                                                                                contributing to higher inequality.&#13;
                                                                                                Finally, shocks are becoming more&#13;
                                                                                                prevalent, making it increasingly hard&#13;
                                                                                                for Indonesians outside of the top&#13;
                                                                                                20 percent to climb up the economic&#13;
                                                                                                ladder. For example, people are living&#13;
                                                                                                longer but obesity is also increasing,&#13;
                                                                                                so non-communicable diseases&#13;
                                                                                                such as diabetes are becoming an&#13;
                                                                                                increasingly common problem.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         Given the high level of inequality in Indonesia and public&#13;
         concern, the consequences of doing nothing could be&#13;
         serious; urgent action is needed&#13;
         GI V E N T H I S PE R C E P T ION , MO S T I N D ON E S I A N S   F OU R H IGH PR IOR I T Y AC T ION S F OR R E DUC I NG&#13;
         F E E L T H AT U R GE N T AC T ION I S N E E DE D, W H IC H I S   I N E QUA L I T Y H AV E BE E N I DE N T I F I E D ( WOR L D&#13;
         W H Y I N E QUA L I T Y H A S BE C OM E A M A JOR P U BL IC       B A N K 2 01 5 A ). These are: improving local service&#13;
         I S S U E . Inequality was a key issue in the run-up to the       delivery to provide health and education opportunities for&#13;
         Indonesian presidential election in 2014, with major              all; creating better jobs and skills training opportunities&#13;
         national and international media outlets reporting on             for the workforce; ensuring better protection from shocks;&#13;
         rising inequality and both presidential candidates making         and getting ï¬&#129;scal policy right. Thinking about ï¬&#129;scal policy&#13;
         public statements about strategies to reduce inequality.          means thinking about how and where the Government&#13;
         They have the support of the public; 47 percent of those          spends its money, and how it raises money to fund this&#13;
         surveyed say it is â&#128;&#156;very urgentâ&#128;&#157; for the Government to            spending. This last action is the focus of this paper.&#13;
         address inequality, and another 41 percent believe it is&#13;
         â&#128;&#156;quite urgentâ&#128;&#157; (World Bank 2015b).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
TA XE S AN D PUBLIC SPE N DING IN IN DON E S IA&#13;
&amp;#12;13                                                                        OCTOBER 2015&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     2.&#13;
          ADDRESSING&#13;
          INEQUALITY:&#13;
          THE ROLE OF&#13;
          FISCAL POLICY&#13;
          Fiscal policy: the choices government makes&#13;
          about how it raises money and how it spends it&#13;
          F I S C A L P OL IC Y I S T H E C OM BI N AT ION OF A           F I S C A L P OL IC Y A F F E C T S E C ON OM IC OU T C OM E S ,&#13;
          G OV E R N M E N T â&#128;&#153; S PAT T E R N S OF R A I S I NG MON E Y    I NC LU DI NG GR OW T H , JOB S A N D I N E QUA L I T Y.&#13;
          A N D S PE N DI NG I T. Economists believe that the             These two elements of ï¬&#129;scal policy can inï¬&#130;uence growth&#13;
          choices a government makes about how it raises money            and jobs. Investments in infrastructure, for example,&#13;
          and how it spends that money can inï¬&#130;uence economic              can improve the productivity of todayâ&#128;&#153;s workers, while&#13;
          outcomes, such as economic growth, household and ï¬&#129;rm            investments in health and education can improve the&#13;
          consumption, savings and investment, and the distribution       productivity of tomorrowâ&#128;&#153;s workers. Taxes and tax credits&#13;
          of income. The combination of how a government collects         provide incentives and disincentives to work, save and&#13;
          revenue and spends that revenue is called â&#128;&#152;ï¬&#129;scal policyâ&#128;&#153;.       invest in di erent ways, which can in turn a ect economic&#13;
                                                                          growth. And who pays which taxes and who receives&#13;
          F I S C A L P OL IC Y I NC LU DE S HOW A G OV E R N M E N T     which spending a ects the ï¬&#129;nal distribution of income.&#13;
          R A I S E S R E V E N U E . There are two main instruments to&#13;
          ï¬&#129;scal policy. First, a government usually uses taxes to         Fiscal policy can help address&#13;
          raise most of its revenues. How much tax to raise and from&#13;
                                                                          inequality in both the short term and&#13;
          what types of tax to use are the ï¬&#129;rst ï¬&#129;scal policy choices&#13;
          a government makes. For example, what personal income&#13;
                                                                          the long term&#13;
          tax rates does it set, and at what levels? What corporate&#13;
                                                                          F I S C A L P OL IC Y C A N H E L P R E DUC E I N E QUA L I T Y&#13;
          tax rates? How much money does it raise from property&#13;
                                                                          I N T H E L ONG T E R M . How can ï¬&#129;scal policy help to&#13;
          taxes or sales and value-added taxes? And how much&#13;
          revenue comes from tobacco and alcohol excise tax?              address inequality? It can help in two ways. First, a&#13;
                                                                          government can choose to spend money on policies and&#13;
          F I S C A L P OL IC Y A L S O I NC LU DE S HOW A&#13;
                                                                          investments that can address inequality in the long term.&#13;
                                                                          We have seen that a key driver of inequality in Indonesia is&#13;
          G OV E R N M E N T S PE N D S MON E Y. Second, a&#13;
                                                                          unequal opportunity. More spending on health and better&#13;
          government can choose to spend in di erent ways.&#13;
                                                                          spending on education could help poorer and children in&#13;
          Some money must go towards paying the salaries of&#13;
                                                                          remote regions to receive a better start in life and develop&#13;
          civil servants; how many civil servants does it want?&#13;
                                                                          the skills needed in the modern workplace. At the same&#13;
          How much should be spent on law and order, and&#13;
                                                                          time, greater investments in infrastructure would make&#13;
          defence. How much on health, education and social&#13;
                                                                          ï¬&#129;rms and workers more productive, connect ï¬&#129;rms to their&#13;
          protection? And how much should be invested in the&#13;
                                                                          markets, and reduce costs. This could lead to more skilled&#13;
          countryâ&#128;&#153;s capital stocksâ&#128;&#148;bridges, railroads, highways,&#13;
                                                                          jobs being created, which would pay better incomes to&#13;
          power plants, and water and sanitation?&#13;
                                                                          those new skilled workers who are coming out of the&#13;
                                                                          improved health and education systems.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
TA XE S AN D PUBLIC SPE N DING IN IN DON E S IA&#13;
&amp;#12;14       ADDRESSSING INEQUALITY:                                                               OCTOBER 2015&#13;
         THE ROLE OF FISCAL POLICY&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         F I S C A L P OL IC Y C A N A L S O H E L P T O R E DUC E                             other private transfers, but before they pay any taxes and&#13;
         I N E QUA L I T Y I N T H E S HORT T E R M . Unlike many                              pension contributions, and before they receive any public&#13;
         policies for reducing inequality, ï¬&#129;scal policy can also                               beneï¬&#129;ts, whether directly (such as cash transfers or tax&#13;
         have signiï¬&#129;cant short-term e ects. For example, greater                               credits), indirectly (such as by purchasing subsidized rice&#13;
         investments in health and education for todayâ&#128;&#153;s children                              or gasoline), or in-kind (such as subsidized education and&#13;
         are a vital part of reducing inequality. But these policies                           health). The second stage of income is ï¬&#129;nal income, which&#13;
         will take years to have an impact. Fiscal policy can address                          is a householdâ&#128;&#153;s market income, plus all direct, indirect&#13;
         inequality now in two ways. First, it can raise revenues                              and in-kind beneï¬&#129;ts received from a government, less all&#13;
         using taxes that are paid more by richer households. For                              taxes it has paid.&#13;
         example, in many countries, the rich pay more in personal&#13;
         income taxes. Second, it can spend in ways that beneï¬&#129;t                                A N U M BE R OF C OU N T R I E S H AV E I N T E N T ION A L LY&#13;
         the poor and vulnerable the most. For example, spending                               US E D F I S C A L P OL IC Y T O R E DUC E I N E QUA L I T Y.&#13;
         on targeted social assistance for the poor and vulnerable                             However, in Indonesia, ï¬&#129;scal policy currently has little&#13;
         can help invest in their childrenâ&#128;&#153;s health and education,                             impact on inequality. In a number of countries, often&#13;
         reducing inequality tomorrow, while also providing them                               in Latin America where inequality is the highest of any&#13;
         income support, reducing inequality today.                                            region, the choice of taxes and spending has been&#13;
                                                                                               made with a view to reducing inequality. We can see&#13;
         Fiscal policy has been used in other                                                  how inequality in a country changes when we compare&#13;
                                                                                               the distribution of market incomes (una ected by ï¬&#129;scal&#13;
         countries to significantly reduce&#13;
                                                                                               policy) and ï¬&#129;nal incomes (fully a ected by ï¬&#129;scal policy). In&#13;
         inequality, but currently in Indonesia                                                Brazil, for example, the Gini coe cient for market income&#13;
         it does not significantly change                                                      is 14 points higher than it is for ï¬&#129;nal income, indicating&#13;
         inequality                                                                            a very large reduction in inequality due to ï¬&#129;scal policy&#13;
                                                                                               (FIGURE 5). In South Africa it is even higher (17.5 points).&#13;
         T H E R E A R E T WO T I M E S AT W H IC H W E C A N&#13;
                                                                                               Reductions of 6 points or more are also seen in Costa&#13;
                                                                                               Rica, Uruguay, Mexico and Bolivia. However, in Indonesia,&#13;
         E S T I M AT E HOU S E HOL D I NC OM E S : BE F OR E T H E&#13;
                                                                                               the Gini coe cient is reduced by only 2.5 points, the&#13;
         I M PAC T OF A N Y F I S C A L P OL IC Y A N D A F T E R T H E&#13;
                                                                                               second-lowest in the 12-country study set after Ethiopia.&#13;
         I M PAC T OF A L L F I S C A L P OL IC Y. Consider two&#13;
                                                                                               The rest of this paper explores why this should be so. Who&#13;
         di erent stages of income. The ï¬&#129;rst is market income.&#13;
                                                                                               does beneï¬&#129;t from spending in Indonesia? Who is paying&#13;
         This is the income a household receives from all wages&#13;
                                                                                               which taxes, and how much?&#13;
         and salaries, all rents, interest and dividends, and all&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         The impact of ï¬&#129;scal policy on inequality is very different across the&#13;
         countries studied. For example, the Gini falls by less than 3 points&#13;
         in Indonesia, but by 14 points in Brazil and 17.5 in South Africa.&#13;
         Reduction in Gini coefï¬&#129;cient from market income to ï¬&#129;nal income. (ï¬&#129;g.5)&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                SOUTH AFRICA&#13;
                                                         EL SALVADOR&#13;
                                           GUATEMALA&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                         COSTA RICA&#13;
                              INDONESIA&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                              URUGUAY&#13;
                ETHIOPIA&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                   ARMENIA&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                 BOLIVIA&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                              MEXICO&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                      BRAZIL&#13;
                                                                       PERU&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
               -2.4          -2.5         -2.8          -3.6           -3.8       -4.6          -5.7         -8.2             -9.9      -11.5         -14      -17.5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         SOURCE Armenia (Younger et al. 2014); Bolivia (Paz et al. 2014); Brazil (Higgins and Pereira 2014); Ethiopia&#13;
         (Woldehanna et al. 2014); Mexico (Scott 2014); Peru (Jaramillo 2014); Uruguay (Bucheli et al. 2014); Lustig (2014)&#13;
         based on Costa Rica (Sauma et al. 2014), El Salvador (Beneke de Sanfeliu et al. 2014), and Guatemala (Cabrera et&#13;
         al. 2014); South Africa (Inchauste et al. 2014); and own estimates for Indonesia based on Susenas 2012.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
TA XE S AN D PUBLIC SPE N DING IN IN DON E S IA&#13;
&amp;#12;15                                                                     OCTOBER 2015&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     3.&#13;
          WHAT THE&#13;
          GOVERNMENT&#13;
          CHOOSES TO&#13;
          SPEND ON&#13;
          CAN AFFECT&#13;
          INEQUALITY&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          A government can choose to spend in different ways,&#13;
          which benefit different people. The same benefit can also&#13;
          mean different things to people on different incomes&#13;
          T H E R E A R E M A N Y PR O GR A M S A N D P OL IC I E S    decile 10, which is the richest 10 percent. Figure 6 looks&#13;
          T H AT G OV E R N M E N T S C A N S PE N D MON E Y ON .      at how much of total spending goes to each decile. These&#13;
          Governments have a number of spending choices                are example numbers only, and could represent any type&#13;
          covering a wide range of activities, including defence       of spending. In this example, the richest decile clearly&#13;
          and the military; governance and administration; building    gets far moreâ&#128;&#148;35 percent of total spendingâ&#128;&#148;than any&#13;
          infrastructure such as roads, bridges and power plants;      of the other deciles, and the poorest 7 deciles all get&#13;
          social spending such as health, education and social         less than 10 percent of spending each. If the spending&#13;
          protection; and subsidies for energy, food and inputs such   were perfectly equal, all deciles would get 10 percent; if&#13;
          as fertilizer.                                               the spending was pro-poor, the poorest deciles would&#13;
                                                                       get more than 10 percent each. Figure 7 shows exactly&#13;
          E ACH OF TH E SE CA N BEN EFIT DIFFER EN T GROU PS           the same spending, but this time, instead of showing&#13;
          OF PEOPL E IN DIFFER EN T WAYS. In particular, we are        what share of the total each decile receives, it shows the&#13;
          interested in how much of the total beneï¬&#129;ts go to richer     average beneï¬&#129;t received by households in that decile,&#13;
          and poorer households, and how much these beneï¬&#129;ts            measured as a share of their average market income.&#13;
          actually mean to these households. Figure 6 and Figure 7     That is, in this example, although poorer households do&#13;
          are examples of how we present these two ideas in this       not receive as much as richer households in dollar terms,&#13;
          paper in the Indonesian case. In both ï¬&#129;gures, we group       because their incomes are so much lower it feels as&#13;
          households into 10 equally sized groups of 10 percent of     though it is more to them: it represents a larger increase&#13;
          the population, called deciles. Decile 1 is the poorest 10   in their market incomes than it does for the richer&#13;
          percent, decile 2 the second-poorest, all the way up to      households.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
TA XE S AN D PUBLIC SPE N DING IN IN DON E S IA&#13;
&amp;#12;16        WHAT THE GOVERNMENT CHOOSE TO                                                     OCTOBER 2015&#13;
          SPEND ON CAN AFFECT INEQUALITY&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          In some cases, more of the total amount of                                        â&#128;¦but the smaller amount received by poorer&#13;
          spending might go to richer householdsâ&#128;¦                                           households might still represent a greater&#13;
          Absolute beneï¬&#129;t of spending (ï¬&#129;g.6)                                                share of their market incomes.&#13;
                                                                                            Relative beneï¬&#129;t of spending (ï¬&#129;g.7)&#13;
                                                                                   35                                                                               10&#13;
           SHARE OF TOTAL SPENDING&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                              BENEFIT RECEIVED AS %&#13;
            RECEIVED BY DECILE %&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                   30&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                               OF MARKET INCOME&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                    8&#13;
                                                                                   25&#13;
                                                                                   20                                                                               6&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                   15                                                                               4&#13;
                                                                                   10&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                    2&#13;
                                                                                   5&#13;
                                                                                   0                                                                                0&#13;
                                     1     2   3   4   5    6   7   8     9   10                                      1    2   3   4   5   6    7   8      9   10&#13;
                                         HOUSEHOLD MARKET INCOME DECILE                                                   HOUSEHOLD MARKET INCOME DECILE&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          HOW D O W E WOR K T H I S OU T ? We combine government revenue and spending data to know how much revenue&#13;
          was raised from which sources and how much was spent in di erent areas, with household survey data, to know who&#13;
          paid which taxes and how much, and who benefitted from which spending and by how much. Box 5 provides a&#13;
          summary of how we do this.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     BOX.5&#13;
     Overview of methodology and data9&#13;
     We begin with market income, which as explained, is                                price they pay is higher than the market price, and they are&#13;
     all household income from non-government sources,                                  indirectly providing revenues to the Government. The post-&#13;
     including income from working (wages and salaries),                                ï¬&#129;scal income is a householdâ&#128;&#153;s disposable income, adjusted&#13;
     income from savings and investments (rents, interest,                              for how much the household is indirectly receiving from&#13;
     dividends), transfers from other households or individuals                         and paying to the Government through its consumption.&#13;
     (such as remittances).                                                             Finally, households can consume subsidized public&#13;
                                                                                        services, such as health and education, which represent a&#13;
     From the market income, some households will pay                                   transfer to the household in-kind (in a non-cash fashion).&#13;
     personal income taxes or contributions to public pension                           However, households may also pay some fees as part of&#13;
     plans, which reduces market income down to net market                              receiving these services, which reduces the beneï¬&#129;t to&#13;
     income. Some households can receive cash transfers (such                           them. The ï¬&#129;nal income takes into account both the cost&#13;
     as from social assistance programs like Program Keluarga                           of the in-kind services received and any payments the&#13;
     Harapan, or PKH, Indonesiaâ&#128;&#153;s conditional cash transfer),                           household makes.&#13;
     which will lead to a higher disposable income, available&#13;
     for consumption10. When households consume, they can                               To work out who is paying which taxes and who is receiving&#13;
     buy goods that are subsidized by the Government, such                              which beneï¬&#129;ts, we use the National Socio-economic&#13;
     as fuel or food. This has the e ect of increasing their                            Survey (Survei Sosial Ekonomi Nasional, or Susenas). This&#13;
     e ective income, as they are not paying the full price and                         household survey includes which households receive&#13;
     are indirectly receiving government spending. At the same                          cash or near-cash transfers (PKH, BSM, Raskin), how&#13;
     time, they may be paying taxes on their consumption,                               much households spend on subsidized energy (fuel and&#13;
     through sales taxes, value-added taxes (VAT), or excise                            electricity), and how many children they have in school at&#13;
     taxes such as on tobacco and alcohol. In this case the ï¬&#129;nal                        which level, as well as the number of in-patient and out-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
9&#13;
   This policy paper summarizes Jellema, et al.(2015). This paper is part of the project â&#128;&#156;The Distributional Impact of Fiscal Policy,â&#128;&#157; a&#13;
collaboration of the World Bank and the Department of Economics at Tulane University to implement its diagnostic tool, the Commitment&#13;
to Equity (CEQ) assessment to six middle income and developing countries. Led by Nora Lustig since 2008, the CEQ project is an initiative&#13;
of the Center for Inter-American Policy and Research (CIPR) and the Department of Economics at Tulane University, the Center for Global&#13;
Development and the Inter-American Dialogue. For more details visit www.commitmentoequity.org.&#13;
10&#13;
   Only consumption is observed in the Indonesian data, which is taken to be the same as disposable income. In reality, some households,&#13;
particularly richer ones, will save a part of their income.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
TA XE S AN D PUBLIC SPE N DING IN IN DON E S IA&#13;
&amp;#12;17          WHAT THE GOVERNMENT CHOOSE TO                                      OCTOBER 2015&#13;
            SPEND ON CAN AFFECT INEQUALITY&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     BOX.5          C O N T.&#13;
     patient health visits they have made. The survey also tells           if the Government spends on average US$1,000 per&#13;
     us how much each household spent on what items, which                 primary school child, and US$3,500 per junior secondary&#13;
     allows us to calculate VAT and tobacco excise.                        child, then a household with two primary children and&#13;
                                                                           one junior secondary child receives in-kind education&#13;
     We also have tax and spending from Indonesiaâ&#128;&#153;s national               spending beneï¬&#129;ts equal to US$5,500. If each liter of fuel is&#13;
     accounts and administrative ï¬&#129;scal data. We combine                    subsidized by US$0.50, then a household that consumes&#13;
     these with the Susenas data to determine how much of                  100 liters per month receives a US$50 subsidy beneï¬&#129;t per&#13;
     each spending a household beneï¬&#129;ts from. For example,                  month, or US$600 per year.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                            Market Income&#13;
                                            Wages and salaries, income from capital, private&#13;
                                            transfers; before government taxes, social security&#13;
                                            contributions and transfers.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     Transfers (adds to income)                                           Taxes (Subtracts from income)&#13;
                                                                                                        Income taxes&#13;
                                                                                                        and pensions&#13;
                                                           NET MAKET INCOME                             contributions&#13;
                           Direct cash&#13;
                            transfers&#13;
&#13;
                                                  DISPOSABLE INCOME / CONSUMPTION&#13;
&#13;
                       Indirect subsidies&#13;
                                                                                                        Indirect taxes&#13;
&#13;
                                                          POST-FISCAL INCOME&#13;
                        Inkind transfers&#13;
                      (health, education)                                                              Co-payment and&#13;
                                                                                                          user fees&#13;
                                                              FINAL INCOME&#13;
&#13;
     SOURCE Lustig and Higgins (2013).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            When the benefit to the poor is greater than it is to the rich,&#13;
            as a proportion of their market income, inequality falls&#13;
            I T I S T H E BE N E F I T OR BU R DE N A S A PE R C E N TAGE      ratio between the two incomes remains the same. By&#13;
            OF M A R K E T I NC OM E T H AT M AT T E R S MO S T F OR           the same token, when a tax is paid, it is the tax relative&#13;
            I N E QUA L I T Y, N O T T H E A B S OLU T E A MOU N T. Most       to market income that a ects inequality. If the poor&#13;
            measures of inequality rise or fall based on changes               household pays US$1 in consumption tax and the rich&#13;
            in relative incomes. That is, if a poor household and a            household pays US$1 in consumption tax, inequality&#13;
            rich household both see their incomes increase by 10               goes up, because the poor household can a ord to pay&#13;
            percent, inequality stays equal, even though the absolute          it less (US$1 is 1 percent of their market income but only&#13;
            increase of the poorer income is smaller than that of the          0.2 percent of the rich householdâ&#128;&#153;s income). Similarly, if&#13;
            richer income. For example, if a poor household earns              the poor household pays US$20 a month in income tax&#13;
            US$100 a month and rich household US$500 a month,                  and the rich household pays US$100 a month, inequality&#13;
            then an increase of 10 percent means an extra US$10 for            stays the same, because both amounts are the same as a&#13;
            the poor households but US$50 for the rich household.              percentage of each householdâ&#128;&#153;s market income.&#13;
            Nonetheless, inequality stays the same, because the&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
TA XE S AN D PUBLIC SPE N DING IN IN DON E S IA&#13;
&amp;#12;  18                           WHAT THE GOVERNMENT CHOOSE TO                                                    OCTOBER 2015&#13;
                               SPEND ON CAN AFFECT INEQUALITY&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  S O W H E N W E L O OK AT HOW S PE N DI NG A N D TA X E S A F F E C T I N E QUA L I T Y I N I N D ON E S I A , W E A R E I N T E R E S T E D&#13;
  MO S T I N T H E DI S T R I BU T ION OF T H E BE N E F I T OR BU R DE N R E L AT I V E T O T H E M A R K E T I NC OM E . There are three&#13;
  types of relative incidence graphs; ones that slope downwards, ones that slope upwards, and ones that are ï¬&#130;at. Downward&#13;
  sloping relative graphs (Figure 8) mean that inequality is reduced in the case of spending (the poor receive more as a&#13;
  percentage of their market income than the rich) and increased in the case of a tax (the poor pay more as a percentage of their&#13;
  market income than the rich). Conversely, an upward sloping relative graph (Figure 10) means increasing inequality for spending&#13;
  or decreasing inequality for taxes. A ï¬&#130;at curve means inequality is unchanged (Figure 9).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  A downwards sloping relative                                  A ï¬&#130;at relative incidence                                             An upwards sloping relative&#13;
  incidence curve means                                         curve means inequality is                                            incidence curve means&#13;
  inequality is reduced in the case                             unchanged for both spending                                          inequality is increased in the&#13;
  of spending or increased in the                               and taxes.                                                           case of spending or decreased in&#13;
  case of a tax.                                                Relative beneï¬&#129;t of spending as a percentage                          the case of a tax.&#13;
  Relative beneï¬&#129;t of spending as a                              of market income (ï¬&#129;g.9)                                              Relative beneï¬&#129;t of spending as a percentage&#13;
  percentage of market income (ï¬&#129;g.8)                                                                                                 of market income (ï¬&#129;g.10)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                           40                                                               40                                                                    40&#13;
&#13;
                                                           35                                                               35                                                                    35&#13;
BENEFIT/BURDEN AS SHARE&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                BENEFIT/BURDEN AS SHARE&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                      BENEFIT/BURDEN AS SHARE&#13;
                                                           30                                                               30&#13;
  OF MARKET INCOME %&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                  OF MARKET INCOME %&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                        OF MARKET INCOME %&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                  30&#13;
                                                           25                                                               25                                                                    25&#13;
                                                           20                                                               20                                                                    20&#13;
                                                           15                                                               15                                                                    15&#13;
                                                           10                                                               10                                                                    10&#13;
                                                           5                                                                5                                                                     5&#13;
                                                           0                                                                0                                                                     0&#13;
                           1      3    5    7     9                                        1     3     5    7       9                                            1     3        5     7      9&#13;
&#13;
                          HOUSEHOLD MARKET INCOME DECILE                                  HOUSEHOLD MARKET INCOME DECILE                                        HOUSEHOLD MARKET INCOME DECILE&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   Where does Indonesiaâ&#128;&#153;s public spending go,                                                                   We look at social spending, contributory&#13;
   and how does it affect inequality?                                                                           pensions and energy subsidies, which&#13;
                                                                                                                make up 57.3 percent of total primary&#13;
  I N 2 01 2 , T H E L A R GE S T S PE N DI NG I T E M WA S E N E R G Y                                         spending.&#13;
  S U B S I DI E S , F OL L OW E D B Y E DUC AT ION . Thirty percent of                                         Indonesian primary spending 2012 (tab.1)&#13;
  Indonesiaâ&#128;&#153;s 2012 public spending was on social spending (Table&#13;
  1), of which the majority was for education, which by law must&#13;
  make up 20 percent of the budget. The greatest spending was                                                    APBN 2012                                               IDR          %    % Primary&#13;
                                                                                                                 (Realized)                                          trillion       GDP    spending&#13;
  on subsidies (25 percent), most of which was on fuel subsidies&#13;
  (although sweeping reforms by the new administration in 2015                                                   1. Social spending                                    400           4.9         29.9&#13;
  mean that this is now much lower). Only 5 percent was spent on&#13;
  health, and less than 3 percent was spent on social assistance                                                 2. Contributory pensions                                  63        0.8          4.7&#13;
  through cash transfers targeting poor and vulnerable households.&#13;
                                                                                                                 3. Non-social spending                                 867         10.6         65.4&#13;
&#13;
  T H I S PA PE R L O OK S AT 57 PE R C E N T OF T O TA L P U BL IC                                              a. Energy subsidies                                    304          3.7         22.7&#13;
  S PE N DI NG , C OV E R I NG S O C I A L S PE N DI NG , E N E R G Y&#13;
  S U B S I DI E S A N D C ON T R I BU T ORY PE N S ION S . Of Table 1, 57                                       b. Other subsidies                                        32        0.4          2.4&#13;
  percent of total spending is included in this study. The two largest                                           c. Other                                              540           6.6         40.3&#13;
  components studied are energy subsidies and education, which&#13;
  together make up 73 percent of total public spending on social,                                                Primary spending                                    1,339          16.2         100&#13;
  subsidies and pensions (Figure 11). For methodological reasons,&#13;
  we exclude spending on housing and urban, and other subsidies&#13;
  (mostly fertilizer and seeds), but these are relatively small.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  TA XE S AN D PUBLIC SPE N DING IN IN DON E S IA&#13;
&amp;#12;19        WHAT THE GOVERNMENT CHOOSE TO                                                                   OCTOBER 2015&#13;
          SPEND ON CAN AFFECT INEQUALITY&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Of this, a combined 73 percent goes to energy (38                                                                                                                        SOURCE Ministry of Finance&#13;
&#13;
percent) and education (35 percent).&#13;
2012 APBN (Realized) social, pension and subsidy spending by type (ï¬&#129;g.11)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                             SU B S IDIE S                                                                        SOCIAL SP ENDING&#13;
&#13;
7.8%                                  38.0%                                                        9.1%                                                                                       0.6%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            4.0%                                                                                1.9%                                  35.1%                                                   3.4%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                CONTRIBUTORY PENSIONS                                 OTHER SUBSIDIES           ENERGY SUBSIDIES                                                HOUSING &amp; URBAN&#13;
                HEALTH                                                EDUCATION                 NON CONTRIBUTORY PENSIONS                                       CASH TRANSFERS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The most spending goes on energy subsidies, which do little to&#13;
reduce inequality, although they still have significant value for&#13;
the poor and vulnerable&#13;
          E IGH T T I M E S MOR E E N E R G Y S U B S I DI E S â&#128;&#148;T H E                                     N ON E T H E L E S S , T H E S U B S I DI E S M E A N S L IGH T LY&#13;
          L A R GE S T S PE N DI NG I T E Mâ&#128;&#148; G O T O T H E R IC H E S T                                   MOR E T O T H E P O OR A N D V U L N E R A BL E A S A&#13;
          DE C I L E T H A N T O T H E P O OR E S T DE C I L E . Energy                                   S H A R E OF T H E I R I NC OM E . When we consider the&#13;
          subsidies, which make up 25 percent of all spending                                             beneï¬&#129;ts received as a proportion of their market income,&#13;
          and 38 percent of spending looked at in this paper, are                                         the distribution is much ï¬&#130;atter, with subsidies received&#13;
          enjoyed signiï¬&#129;cantly more by richer households, which                                           meaning slightly more to the poorest four deciles than the&#13;
          are more likely to have cars and motorcycles, than by                                           richer ones (Figure 13). As a consequence, subsidies have&#13;
          poorer households. Over half of the subsidies go to the                                         relatively little impact on inequality one way or another.&#13;
          top three deciles, with one-quarter alone to the richest 10                                     Given the large amount spent on them, they represent&#13;
          percent (Figure 12). The poor and vulnerableâ&#128;&#148;the poorest                                        poor value for money if they are intended to beneï¬&#129;t the&#13;
          40 percent of Indonesiansâ&#128;&#148;receive only 20 percent of all                                        poor and vulnerable the most. Still, representing around&#13;
          energy subsidy beneï¬&#129;ts.                                                                         9-10 percent of market income for most Indonesians, their&#13;
                                                                                                          removal will be felt.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          Most subsidy spending goes to                                                                   â&#128;¦but it means slightly more as a share of their&#13;
          richer householdsâ&#128;¦                                                                              income to the poor and vulnerable.&#13;
          Absolute beneï¬&#129;t of energy subsidy spending (ï¬&#129;g.12)                                              Relative beneï¬&#129;t of energy subsidy spending (ï¬&#129;g.13)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                           30                                                                                                   12&#13;
            SHARE OF TOTAL SPENDING&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                              BENEFIT RECEIVED AS %&#13;
             RECEIVED BY DECILE %&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                               OF MARKET INCOME&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                           25                                                                                                   10&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                           20                                                                                                   8&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                           15                                                                                                   6&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                           10                                                                                                   4&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                           5                                                                                                    2&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                           0                                                                                                    0&#13;
                                        1     2     3   4    5    6     7    8    9   10                                                      1   2     3   4    5   6    7    8    9    10&#13;
&#13;
                                                  HOUSEHOLD MARKET INCOME DECILE                                                                      HOUSEHOLD MARKET INCOME DECILE&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          SOURCE Susenas 2012, APBN 2012 (Realized), World Bank calculations.                             SOURCE Susenas 2012, APBN 2012 (Realized), World Bank calculations.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
TA XE S AN D PUBLIC SPE N DING IN IN DON E S IA&#13;
&amp;#12;20         WHAT THE GOVERNMENT CHOOSE TO                                                          OCTOBER 2015&#13;
           SPEND ON CAN AFFECT INEQUALITY&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Education benefits are significantly more for poorer households&#13;
as a share of income, and are significantly inequality-reducing,&#13;
although not as much as in other countries&#13;
&#13;
          R IC H E R HOUS E HOL D S R E C E I V E S I M I L A R                                   HOW E V E R , BE C AUS E OF T H E I R M UC H L OW E R&#13;
          L E V E L S OF E DUC AT ION S PE N DI NG A S P O OR E R                                 I NC OM E S , T H E BE N E F I T S A R E WORT H FA R MOR E&#13;
          HOUS E HOL D S , BU T BE C AU S E OF OU T- OF-P O C K E T                               T O P O OR E R HOUS E HOL D S , M A K I NG E DUC AT ION&#13;
          E X PE N S E S , T H E Y PAY MOR E I N T O T H E S Y S T E M .                          S PE N DI NG IN EQUA LIT Y-R EDUCING IN IN DON E SI A .&#13;
          When considered in absolute terms, richer households                                    When we&#13;
          beneï¬&#129;t slightly more from education spending than poorer                                consider the education beneï¬&#129;ts as a share of market&#13;
          households (Figure 14). Despite having fewer children who                               income, it is nearly 20 percent for the poorest decile&#13;
          are more likely to be enrolled in private schools11, their                              compared with only 2 percent for the richest decile&#13;
          children are also more likely to be enrolled at the more                                (Figure 15). A similar pattern holds after accounting&#13;
          expensive secondary and tertiary levels. However, when                                  for out-of-pocket costs. As a consequence, education&#13;
          we include out-of-pocket expenses such as school fees,                                  spending is inequality-reducing in Indonesia.&#13;
          the net beneï¬&#129;t of education spending is slightly higher for&#13;
          poorer households (Figure 14).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
           Most households receive similar education                                              â&#128;¦but relative to household income, education&#13;
           beneï¬&#129;ts, but because richer households pay                                             spending beneï¬&#129;ts poorer households much&#13;
           more out-of-pocket, poorer households                                                  more than richer ones.&#13;
           receive a much greater net beneï¬&#129;t than                                                 Relative beneï¬&#129;t of education spending and burden of&#13;
                                                                                                  out-of-pocket expenses (ï¬&#129;g.15)&#13;
           richer householdsâ&#128;¦&#13;
          Absolute beneï¬&#129;t of education spending and burden of&#13;
          out-of-pocket expenses (ï¬&#129;g.14)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                            15                                                                                 30&#13;
         SHARE OF TOTAL SPENDING&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                     BENEFIT RECEIVED AS % OF&#13;
          RECEIVED BY DECILE %&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                            10&#13;
                                                                                                         MARKET INCOME&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                               20&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                            5&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                               15&#13;
                                                                                            0&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                               10&#13;
                                                                                            -5&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                               0&#13;
                                                                                            -10&#13;
                                    1    2       3   4    5    6     7    8    9       10                                       1   2   3   4    5      6   7   8    9    10&#13;
&#13;
                                             HOUSEHOLD MARKET INCOME DECILE                                                         HOUSEHOLD MARKET INCOME DECILE&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   OUT OF POCKET EXPENSES          EDUCATION BENEFIT                                                EDUCATION BENEFIT       NET BENEFIT&#13;
&#13;
                                   NET BENEFIT&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
           SOURCE Susenas 2012, APBN 2012 (Realized), World Bank calculations.                    SOURCE Susenas 2012, APBN 2012 (Realized), World Bank calculations.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
           N ON E T H E L E S S , E DUC AT ION S PE N DI NG BE N E F I T S P O OR E R HOUS E HOL D S A N D R E DUC E S I N E QUA L I T Y&#13;
           B Y M UC H L E S S I N I N D ON E S I A T H A N I N O T H E R C OU N T R I E S . When we compare who beneï¬&#129;ts from education&#13;
           spending in Indonesia with other countries studied, poorer households, especially those in the poorest decile,&#13;
           beneï¬&#129;t much more as a percentage of their market income in other countries. This likely reï¬&#130;ects a greater focus on&#13;
           primary education spending in these countries.&#13;
&#13;
           11&#13;
                       Although private schools also receive some public subsidies, which are captured in this analysis.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
TA XE S AN D PUBLIC SPE N DING IN IN DON E S IA&#13;
&amp;#12;21                      WHAT THE GOVERNMENT CHOOSE TO                                                      OCTOBER 2015&#13;
                        SPEND ON CAN AFFECT INEQUALITY&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Education spending reduces inequality                                                                     SOURCE For Latin America see: Lustig and Pessino 2014; Paz, et al. 2014; Higgins&#13;
                                                                                                          and Pereira 2014; Scott 2014; Jaramillo 2014; Bucheli, et al. 2014; Lustig, et al.&#13;
considerably more in other countries.                                                                     2014. For Armenia and Sri Lanka, results are preliminary by Younger, et al. (2014)&#13;
                                                                                                          and Arunatilake, et al. (2014).&#13;
Relative beneï¬&#129;t of education spending (ï¬&#129;g.16)&#13;
                                                                                                                    POOREST DECILE                    SHARE OF GDP RIGHT AXIS&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                    RICHEST DECILE&#13;
                          250%                                                                                                                                                     9%&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                   8%&#13;
                          200%                                                                                                                                                     7%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                         TOTAL SPENDING AS&#13;
     OF MARKET INCOME&#13;
     BENEFIT AS SHARE&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                           SHARE OF GDP&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                   6%&#13;
                            150%&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                   5%&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                   4%&#13;
                            100%&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                   3%&#13;
&#13;
                              50%                                                                                                                                                  2%&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                   1%&#13;
                                   0%                                                                                                                                              0%&#13;
                                          ARGENTINA         BOLIVIA    BRAZIL        MEXICO        PERU            URUGUAY                ARMENIA         SRI LANKA    INDONESIA&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
More health spending goes to richer households, but it means&#13;
more to the poor. However, other countries spend more overall&#13;
and direct it more effectively to the poor&#13;
                        MO S T I N D ON E S I A N S R E C E I V E T H E S A M E N E T                     T H E R E L AT I V E H E A LT H BE N E F I T I S I N E QUA L I T Y-&#13;
                        H E A LT H BE N E F I T S I N S PE N DI NG T E R M S , BU T                       R E DUC I NG , BU T T H E L OW S PE N DI NG L E V E L S&#13;
                        T H E R IC H E S T HOU S E HOL D S PAY MOR E I N T O                              M E A N T H AT I T H A S R E L AT I V E LY L I T T L E I M PAC T.&#13;
                        T H E S Y S T E M T H A N T H E Y R E C E I V E . The share of                    The net health beneï¬&#129;ts relative to market income mean&#13;
                        total health spending increases from poorer to richer                             around four times more to the poorest decile than to the&#13;
                        households (Figure 17). However, out-of-pocket expenses                           richest decile, which actually pays a small amount into&#13;
                        also increase with income, meaning that the net beneï¬&#129;t is                         the system after out-of-pocket expenses are considered&#13;
                        relatively similar for all but the richest decile. The richest                    (Figure 18). However, even for the poorest decile, the&#13;
                        10 percent of Indonesian households, however, pay more                            value of the net health beneï¬&#129;t is less than 4 percent of&#13;
                        in expenses than they receive in beneï¬&#129;ts, so they are net                         their market income. As a consequence, while health&#13;
                        payers into the public health system.                                             spending is inequality-reducing, the low spending levels&#13;
                                                                                                          mean that it makes little real di erence.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                        Most Indonesians receive the same net health                                      Health beneï¬&#129;ts mean most to the poor, but&#13;
                        beneï¬&#129;ts, but the richest households pay more                                      even for those with the lowest income, they&#13;
                        into the system than they receive.                                                are worth less than 4 percent of their income,&#13;
                        Absolute beneï¬&#129;t of health spending and burden of                                  so matter little.&#13;
                        out-of-pocket expenses (ï¬&#129;g.17)                                                    Relative beneï¬&#129;t of health spending and burden of out-of-&#13;
                                                                                                   6      pocket expenses (ï¬&#129;g.18)&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                   4                                                                                                  4.0&#13;
                                                                                                           BENEFIT RECEIVED AS % OF&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                      3.5&#13;
                                                                                                   2&#13;
                        HEALTH SPENDING&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                      3.0&#13;
                                                                                                               MARKET INCOME&#13;
                          IDR TRILLION&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                   0                                                                                                  2.5&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                      2.0&#13;
                                                                                                   -2&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                      1.5&#13;
                                                                                                   -4                                                                                                 1.0&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                      0.5&#13;
                                                                                                   -6&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                      0&#13;
                                                                                                   -8                                                                                                 -0.5&#13;
                                          1      2     3     4    5    6    7    8      9     10                                      1   2      3    4        5   6     7    8    9    10&#13;
                                                     HOUSEHOLD MARKET INCOME DECILE                                                            HOUSEHOLD MARKET INCOME DECILE&#13;
&#13;
                                              OUT OF POCKET EXPENSES       EDUCATION BENEFIT&#13;
                                                                                                                                              HEALTH BENEFIT             NET BENEFIT&#13;
                                              NET BENEFIT&#13;
&#13;
                        SOURCE Susenas 2012, APBN 2012 (Realized), World Bank calculations.                SOURCE Susenas 2012, APBN 2012 (Realized), World Bank calculations.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
TA XE S AN D PUBLIC SPE N DING IN IN DON E S IA&#13;
&amp;#12;22                      WHAT THE GOVERNMENT CHOOSE TO                                           OCTOBER 2015&#13;
                        SPEND ON CAN AFFECT INEQUALITY&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
HE A LTH SPEN DING R EDUCES IN EQUA LIT Y MOR E IN OTHER COU NTR IES, BECAUSE IT IS MOR E PRO-POOR A N D&#13;
BECAUSE HIGHER OV ER A LL SPEN DING LEV ELS ME A N TH AT IT IS BIG ENOUGH TO H AV E A N IMPACT. Indonesia not&#13;
only spends the least on health of the countries studied12, but health spending also beneï¬&#129;ts the poor more in other countries&#13;
(Figure 19). As a consequence, health spending is more inequality-reducing in most of these other countries than it is in&#13;
Indonesia. Moreover, greater spending on health in general would beneï¬&#129;t Indonesia as a whole, with the persistently high&#13;
stunting rate and growing incidence of non-communicable diseases, as well as the poor and vulnerable, who are more likely to&#13;
use public health services than the middle class, who tend to use private health services (World Bank 2015c).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Health spending reduces inequality considerably more in                                                    SOURCE For Latin America see: Lustig and Pessino 2014; Paz, et al.&#13;
                                                                                                           2014; Higgins and Pereira 2014; Scott 2014; Jaramillo 2014; Bucheli,&#13;
other countries, because it is more pro-poor and because                                                   et al. 2014; Lustig, et al. 2014. For Armenia and Sri Lanka, results are&#13;
&#13;
higher overall spending levels mean it is big enough to                                                    preliminary by Younger, et al. (2014) and Arunatilake, et al. (2014).&#13;
&#13;
make an impact.                                                                                                POOREST DECILE               SHARE OF GDP RIGHT AXIS&#13;
&#13;
Relative beneï¬&#129;t of health spending (ï¬&#129;g.19)                                                                     RICHEST DECILE&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             140%                                                                                                                                  7%&#13;
&#13;
                             120%                                                                                                                                  6%&#13;
     INCIDENCE AS A SHARE&#13;
       OF MARKET INCOME&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                             100%                                                                                                                                  5%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                           SHARE OF GDP&#13;
                              80%                                                                                                                                  4%&#13;
&#13;
                              60%                                                                                                                                  3%&#13;
&#13;
                              40%                                                                                                                                  2%&#13;
&#13;
                              20%                                                                                                                                  1%&#13;
&#13;
                               0%                                                                                                                                  0%&#13;
                                    ARGENTINA     BOLIVIA      BRAZIL      MEXICO        PERU       URUGUAY       ARMENIA         SRI LANKA       INDONESIA&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                       Social assistance is strongly pro-poor, but has little impact on equality&#13;
                       because too little is spent in general, and on the most effective&#13;
                       programs in particular&#13;
                      SOCI A L A SSISTA NCE SPEN DING IN IN DON ESI A IS                        T H E S E C A S H T R A N S F E R S M E A N E V E N MOR E&#13;
                      E A SILY THE MOST PRO-POOR SPEN DING OF A LL ,                            T O P O OR E R HOUS E HOL D S R E L AT I V E T O T H E I R&#13;
                      W ITH N E A R LY 60 PERCENT GOING TO THE POOR A N D                       I NC OM E S , BU T T H E AV E R AGE BE N E F I T L E V E L&#13;
                      V U LN ER A BLE A N D LITTLE TO THE R ICH. Indonesia                      I S L OW A N D T H E MO S T PR O -P O OR PR O GR A M ,&#13;
                      has a number of social assistance programs targeting                      PK H , I S T H E S M A L L E S T. When considered relative to&#13;
                      the poor and vulnerable, including Jamkesmas (health                      household incomes, the targeted cash transfer programs&#13;
                      insurance for the poor, now part of the national health                   are even more pro-poor and therefore inequality-&#13;
                      insurance scheme Jaminan Kesehatan Nasional, or JKN),                     reducing (Figure 21). However, they have little impact&#13;
                      Raskin (subsidized rice for the poor)13, BSM (Bantuan Siswa               on inequality because the total spending is the lowest&#13;
                      Miskin, ï¬&#129;nancial assistance for poor students, now Kartu                  of all the spending analyzed hereâ&#128;&#148;when combined the&#13;
                      Indonesia Pintar) and PKH (Program Keluarga Harapan,                      transfers average only 4 percent of the poorest decileâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
                      a conditional cash transfer). Much of this spending does                  incomeâ&#128;&#148;and because the most pro-poor program, PKH&#13;
                      go to the poor, with the poorest four deciles receiving                   (see Figure 25 and later discussion), has the smallest&#13;
                      56 percent of all beneï¬&#129;ts, the middle three deciles 30                    budget (IDR 2 trillion compared with IDR 11.5 trillion for&#13;
                      percent, and the richest three deciles only 14 percent                    Raskin and BSM).&#13;
                      (Figure 20).14&#13;
&#13;
                     13&#13;
                            Heavily subsidized, Raskin is considered a near-cash transfer, as households pay relatively little for staple.&#13;
                     14&#13;
                            This excludes Jamkesmas, which does not provide a cash transfer (or near-cash in the case of Raskin).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
TA XE S AN D PUBLIC SPE N DING IN IN DON E S IA&#13;
&amp;#12;  23                           WHAT THE GOVERNMENT CHOOSE TO                                                        OCTOBER 2015&#13;
                               SPEND ON CAN AFFECT INEQUALITY&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 The poor and vulnerable receive the majority of                                                      â&#128;¦although the beneï¬&#129;ts are small relative to&#13;
 cash transfers, making them the most pro-poor                                                        household income and the most inequality-&#13;
 of all spendingâ&#128;¦                                                                                     reducing program (PKH) receives the least funding.&#13;
 Absolute beneï¬&#129;t of cash transfer spending (ï¬&#129;g.20)                                                    Relative beneï¬&#129;t of cash transfer spending (ï¬&#129;g.21)&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                          20                                                                                                     4&#13;
SHARE OF TOTAL SPENDING&#13;
 RECEIVED BY DECILE %&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                          15                                                                                                     3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                     BENEFIT RECEIVED AS %&#13;
                                                                                                      OF MARKET INCOME&#13;
                                                                                          10                                                                                                     2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                          5                                                                                                      1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                          0                                                                                                      0&#13;
                               1    2      3   4      5      6      7    8       9   10                                          1       2      3     4     5     6      7     8     9     10&#13;
&#13;
                                        HOUSEHOLD MARKET INCOME DECILE                                                                   HOUSEHOLD MARKET INCOME DECILE&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                  RASKIN AND BSM                PKH           ALL TRANSFERS&#13;
&#13;
 SOURCE Susenas 2012, APBN 2012 (Realized), World Bank calculations.                                  SOURCE Susenas 2012, APBN 2012 (Realized), World Bank calculations.&#13;
 NOTE Includes PKH, Raskin and BSM.                                                                   NOTE Includes PKH, Raskin and BSM.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  A S W I T H H E A LT H A N D E DUC AT ION , O T H E R C OU N T R I E S AC H I E V E FA R MOR E I N E QUA L I T Y R E DUC T ION&#13;
  T H R OUGH C A S H T R A N S F E R S T H R OUGH M UC H GR E AT E R S C A L E A N D E V E N MOR E PR O -P O OR TA R GE T I NG .&#13;
  Indonesiaâ&#128;&#153;s spending on conditional cash transfers (PKH in Indonesia), which is less than 0.1 percent of GDP, is far lower than in&#13;
  the other countries studied, and the value of the average transfer to the poor relative to their income is far less.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Conditional cash transfer spending reduces inequality                                                                              SOURCE For Latin America see: Lustig and Pessino 2014; Paz, et al.&#13;
                                                                                                                                     2014; Higgins and Pereira 2014; Scott 2014; Jaramillo 2014; Bucheli,&#13;
  signiï¬&#129;cantly in a number other countries, by reaching the                                                                          et al. 2014; Lustig, et al. 2014. For Armenia and Sri Lanka, results are&#13;
&#13;
  poor better and providing a larger beneï¬&#129;t.                                                                                         preliminary by Younger, et al. (2014) and Arunatilake, et al. (2014).&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                         POOREST DECILE               SHARE OF GDP RIGHT AXIS&#13;
  Relative beneï¬&#129;t of ï¬&#130;agship conditional cash transfer spending (ï¬&#129;g.22)&#13;
                                                                                                                                         RICHEST DECILE&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   80%                                                                                                                                                      4.0%&#13;
                                   70%                                                                                                                                                      3.5%&#13;
                                   60%                                                                                                                                                      3.0%&#13;
                 SHARE OF MARKET&#13;
                  INCIDENCE AS A&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   50%&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                       SHARE OF GDP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                            2.5%&#13;
                      INCOME&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   40%                                                                                                                                                      2.0%&#13;
                                   30%                                                                                                                                                      1.5%&#13;
                                   20%                                                                                                                                                      1.0%&#13;
&#13;
                                   10%                                                                                                                                                      0.5%&#13;
&#13;
                                   0%                                                                                                                                                       0.0%&#13;
                                          ARGENTINA       BOLIVIA       BRAZIL       MEXICO       PERU                       URUGUAY         ARMENIA       SRI LANKA         INDONESIA&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   Public spending in Indonesia                                                  N O S I NGL E T Y PE OF S PE N DI NG AC H I E V E S S IGN I F IC A N T R E DUC T ION S&#13;
                                                                                 I N I N E QUA L I T Y, BU T T H E L A R GE S T I M PAC T C OM E S F R OM E DUC AT ION&#13;
   achieves relatively little&#13;
                                                                                 S PE N DI NG . Total education spending, which is the second-largest spending&#13;
   decrease in inequality                                                        item after subsidies, reduces the Gini by 1.9 points when moving from market&#13;
   because least is spent on                                                     income to ï¬&#129;nal income. This means that it has the largest impact, but this is still&#13;
   those programs that are the                                                   relatively small (Figure 23). Taken together, direct transfers, health spending&#13;
                                                                                 and subsidies reduce the Gini by less than 1 point.&#13;
   most effective&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  TA XE S AN D PUBLIC SPE N DING IN IN DON E S IA&#13;
&amp;#12;24       WHAT THE GOVERNMENT CHOOSE TO                                        OCTOBER 2015&#13;
         SPEND ON CAN AFFECT INEQUALITY&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         W E C A N C A L C U L AT E T H E A MOU N T OF&#13;
         I N E QUA L I T Y R E DUC E D F OR E V E RY RU PI A H                Education spending reduces inequality&#13;
         S PE N T: T H I S M E A S U R E S W H IC H PR O GR A M S             the most, but no type of spending has a&#13;
         A R E T H E MO S T C O S T-E F F E C T I V E AT R E DUC I NG         signiï¬&#129;cant impactâ&#128;¦&#13;
         I N E QUA L I T Y.&#13;
                                                                              Reduction in Gini coefï¬&#129;cient between market and ï¬&#129;nal income (ï¬&#129;g.23)&#13;
         A big program might reduce inequality more than smaller&#13;
         one but spend more to do it. To know which program is&#13;
         the most cost-e ective at reducing inequality, which one                               0.0&#13;
         receives the most â&#128;&#156;bang-for-the-buckâ&#128;&#157;, we need to adjust&#13;
         for the program budget. To do this, we calculate how                                   0.5&#13;
&#13;
         much inequality is reduced, and divide it by how much is&#13;
                                                                                                1.0&#13;
         spent on the program to achieve this.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                1.5&#13;
         HOW E V E R , T H E MO S T C O S T-E F F E C T I V E&#13;
         I N E QUA L I T Y R E DUC I NG PR O GR A M S â&#128;&#148;DI R E C T&#13;
                                                                                                2.0&#13;
         T R A N S F E R S â&#128;&#148;H AV E T H E L E A S T S PE N T ON T H E M ,&#13;
         W H I L E E N E R G Y S U B S I DI E S A R E V E RY C O S T LY                         2.5&#13;
         A N D H AV E L I T T L E E F F E C T. Direct transfers, such as                               EDUCATION     DIRECT     HEALTH     ENERGY&#13;
         PKH, Raskin and BSM, are highly e ective at reducing                                                      TRANSFERS              SUBSIDIES&#13;
&#13;
         inequality for each rupiah spent. However, at 0.33&#13;
         percent of GDP, very little is spent on them. Education is&#13;
                                                                              SOURCE Susenas 2012, APBN 2012 (Realized), World Bank calculations.&#13;
         two-thirds as e ective as direct transfers and, because&#13;
         larger sums are spent on it (2.6 percent of GDP), it has&#13;
         the largest overall e ect 15. Health is only one-third as            â&#128;¦because the most cost-effective&#13;
         e ective in reducing inequality as direct transfers, and             inequality reducing programs are the&#13;
         also receives relatively little spending (0.9 percent of             smallest.&#13;
         GDP)16, so has little overall impact on inequality. Finally,         Cost-effectiveness and total beneï¬&#129;ts distributed by spending type&#13;
         while 3.7 percent of GDP is spent on energy subsidies,               (ï¬&#129;g.24)&#13;
         they reduce inequality the least in overall terms, meaning&#13;
         they have near zero cost-e ectiveness.&#13;
                                                                                              120                                                     4.0&#13;
&#13;
         E V E N W I T H I N DI R E C T T R A N S F E R S , L E A S T I S                                                                             3.5&#13;
                                                                                              100&#13;
         S PE N T ON T H E MO S T E F F E C T I V E PR O GR A M ,&#13;
                                                                                                                                                      3.0&#13;
         PK H . Every rupiah spent on PKH reduces inequality by                               80&#13;
                                                                              EFFECTIVENESS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         2.5 times more than every rupiah spent on Raskin, yet                                                                                        2.5&#13;
&#13;
         Raskinâ&#128;&#153;s budget is more than 10 times higher (Figure 25).                            60                                                            % GDP&#13;
                                                                                                                                                      2.0&#13;
         Four times more is spent on BSM than PKH, and because&#13;
                                                                                                                                                      1.5&#13;
         of bad targeting17, BSM is even less e ective than Raskin;                           40&#13;
         PKH is over eight times more e ective than Raskin at                                                                                         1.0&#13;
         reducing inequality. In education, on the other hand, the                            20&#13;
                                                                                                                                                      0.5&#13;
         most is spent on primary and junior secondary schools,&#13;
         which have the greatest inequality-reducing e ect (as                                 0                                                      0&#13;
                                                                                                      DIRECT       ALL         HEALTH     ENERGY&#13;
         poorer households tend to have more children to beneï¬&#129;t                                     TRANSFERS   EDUCATION                SUBSIDIES&#13;
         from this spending than richer households), whereas&#13;
         tertiary spending increases inequality, as very few poorer&#13;
                                                                                                        EFFECTIVENESS INDEX     SPENDING AS %GDP&#13;
         children make it to university (Figure 26).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                              SOURCE Susenas 2012, APBN 2012 (Realized), World Bank calculations.&#13;
                                                                              NOTE E ectiveness is the change in Gini from market income to ï¬&#129;nal income&#13;
                                                                              divided by the spending as a percentage of GDP.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         15&#13;
            However, the education received by students may not be perceived as being as valuable as the spending levels. If a teacher is&#13;
         absent, the incidence approach treats the spending on his/her salary as a benefit to the student, although there is none in reality.&#13;
         16&#13;
            Although this is being increased significantly in the 2016 budget.&#13;
         17&#13;
            Historically BSM was targeted by school committees and many scholarships went to non-poor children. However, since 2012,&#13;
         BSM (now KIP) has been targeted with the new Unified Database (UDB) of the poor and vulnerable, implemented by TNP2K (the&#13;
         National Team for the Acceleration of Poverty Reduction), and targeting outcomes for BSM have improved significantly.&#13;
&#13;
TA XE S AN D PUBLIC SPE N DING IN IN DON E S IA&#13;
&amp;#12;25       WHAT THE GOVERNMENT CHOOSE TO                                                    OCTOBER 2015&#13;
         SPEND ON CAN AFFECT INEQUALITY&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         Of the direct transfers, the least is spent on the                               â&#128;¦because the most cost-effective inequality-&#13;
         most cost-effective program, PKHâ&#128;¦                                                reducing programs are the smallest.&#13;
         Cost-effectiveness and total beneï¬&#129;ts distributed by spending type                Cost-effectiveness and total beneï¬&#129;ts distributed by spending type&#13;
         (ï¬&#129;g.25)                                                                          (ï¬&#129;g.26)&#13;
&#13;
                          350                                                0.3                            120                                                1.2&#13;
&#13;
                          300                                                                               100&#13;
                                                                             0.2                                                                               1.0&#13;
                          250                                                                               80&#13;
          EFFECTIVENESS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                            EFFECTIVENESS&#13;
                          200                                                0.2                                                                               0.8&#13;
                                                                                                            60&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                   %GDP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                      %GDP&#13;
                          150                                                                               40&#13;
                                                                             0.1                                                                               0.6&#13;
                          100                                                                               20&#13;
                                                                             0.1                                                                               0.4&#13;
                          50                                                                                 0&#13;
&#13;
                           0                                                 0.0                            -20                                                0.2&#13;
                                    PKH          RASKIN          BSM                                               PRIMARY     JUNIOR    SENIOR  TERTIARY&#13;
                                                                                                                             SECONDARY SECONDARY&#13;
&#13;
                                EFFECTIVENESS INDEX       SPENDING AS %GDP                                        EFFECTIVENESS INDEX    SPENDING AS %GDP&#13;
&#13;
         SOURCE Susenas 2012, APBN 2012 (Realized), World Bank calculations.              SOURCE Susenas 2012, APBN 2012 (Realized), World Bank calculations.&#13;
         NOTE E ectiveness is the change in Gini from market income to ï¬&#129;nal income        NOTE E ectiveness is the change in Gini from market income to ï¬&#129;nal income&#13;
         divided by the spending as a percentage of GDP.                                  divided by the spending as a percentage of GDP.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
TA XE S AN D PUBLIC SPE N DING IN IN DON E S IA&#13;
&amp;#12;26                                                                                              OCTOBER 2015&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 4.&#13;
         HOW THE&#13;
         GOVERNMENT&#13;
         CHOOSES TO&#13;
         RAISE MONEY&#13;
         CAN AFFECT&#13;
         INEQUALITY&#13;
         While the greatest impact on inequality is likely to come through how the&#13;
         Government chooses to spend money, how it raises money matters too&#13;
         S PE N DI NG C HOIC E S A R E MOR E L I K E LY T O R E DUC E                           from personal income taxes exceed that of cash transfers,&#13;
         I N E QUA L I T Y T H A N TA X E S . Although personal income                          and even then it is much less than that from health&#13;
         taxes help to reduce inequality in a number of countries,                              and education. The net e ect of indirect subsidies and&#13;
         a greater impact comes from direct cash transfers, and                                 indirect taxes can increase or decrease inequality, but&#13;
         from net education and health spending most of all                                     usually has relatively little combined e ect.&#13;
         (Figure 27). Only in Mexico does the inequality reduction&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         Taxes can reduce inequality, but not usually as much as spending on&#13;
         education, health and direct cash transfers.&#13;
         Change in Gini from different ï¬&#129;scal policies (ï¬&#129;g.27)&#13;
&#13;
                          3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                          0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                         -3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                         -6&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                         -9&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                        -12&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                        -15&#13;
                              ARGENTINA       BOLIVIA        BRAZIL        MEXICO          PERU         URUGUAY       ARMENIA       SRI LANKA INDONESIA&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                 DIRECT TRANSFERS                      INDIRECT SUBSIDIES AND TAXES                         NET HEALTH AND EDUCATION&#13;
&#13;
                                 PERSONAL TAX INCOME                   NET IMPACT&#13;
&#13;
         SOURCE For Latin America see: Lustig and Pessino 2014; Paz, et al. 2014; Higgins and Pereira 2014; Scott 2014; Jaramillo 2014; Bucheli, et al. 2014; Lustig, et al. 2014.&#13;
         For Armenia and Sri Lanka, results are preliminary by Younger, et al. (2014) and Arunatilake, et al. (2014).&#13;
         NOTE Only direct transfer e ect is available for Argentina. Indonesia excludes personal income tax e ect, although this is likely to be small.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
TA XE S AN D PUBLIC SPE N DING IN IN DON E S IA&#13;
&amp;#12;27          HOW THE GOVERNMENT CHOOSES TO                                             OCTOBER 2015&#13;
            RAISE MONEY CAN AFFECT INEQUALITY&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            HOW E V E R , W H I L E F I S C A L P OL IC Y A N D P U BL IC             that can be raised, and the ease of implementation,&#13;
            S PE N DI NG C A N BE U S E D T O A DDR E S S I N E QUA L I T Y,          di er. At the same time, di erent taxes and excises are&#13;
            I T M US T BE D ON E I N A S U S TA I N A BL E FA S H ION .               borne by di erent types of household. The main taxes we&#13;
            Many Latin American countries have signiï¬&#129;cantly reduced                   examine for Indonesia are value-added tax (VAT) and the&#13;
            inequality through ï¬&#129;scal policies.Progressive taxing and                  tobacco excise, which together make up nearly half of all&#13;
            spending that primarily beneï¬&#129;t the poor and vulnerable                    tax revenue (Figure 28).&#13;
            are important tools for tackling inequality. However,&#13;
            they must be used in sustainable ways. When too much&#13;
                                                                                      We look at tax revenues, which make up&#13;
            is spent on redistribution and other social spending,&#13;
                                                                                      three-quarters of all revenues.&#13;
            relative to revenues, the ï¬&#129;scal framework can become&#13;
                                                                                      2012 APBN (Realized) revenue (tab.2)&#13;
            unsustainable. In Brazil, for example, cash transfers now&#13;
            represent 4 percent of GDP. In addition, when social&#13;
            transfers are too large, it can create a disincentive to work              APBN 2012                            IDR        %              %&#13;
                                                                                       (Realized)                       trillion     GDP        Revenue&#13;
            (cash transfers are worth 70 percent of market income to&#13;
            the poorest decile in Argentina (Lustig and Pessino 2014)).                1. Tax revenues                       981       11.9          73.3&#13;
&#13;
            HOW P U BL IC R E V E N U E I S R A I S E D W I L L A L S O                2. Non-tax revenues                   352       4.3           26.3&#13;
            A F F E C T I N E QUA L I T Y. Three-quarters of Indonesiaâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
                                                                                       3. Grants                              6         0.1            0.5&#13;
            public revenues come from taxes (Table 2). Di erent taxes&#13;
            can be used to collect revenue. The amounts of revenue                     Total revenue                    1,338         16.2             100&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
VAT is the most important tax, followed by personal income tax and                                                                 SOURCE Ministry of Finance&#13;
&#13;
excises. Corporate income tax is excluded from the analysis.&#13;
2012 tax revenue by type (ï¬&#129;g.28)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                    INC O ME TAX E S                                                     INDIR ECT TAXES&#13;
&#13;
     2.8% 37.7%                                                 10%            5.1%    9.8%          34.6%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                   PROPERTY AND OTHER             CORPORATE INCOME TAX                 PERSONAL INCOME TAX&#13;
                                   IMPORT/EXPORT DUTIES           EXCISES                              VAT&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            Indirect taxes in Indonesia do not have much&#13;
            impact on inequality. Closing VAT exemptions&#13;
            on basic staples would increase revenue but also&#13;
            inequality; increases in tobacco excise would be&#13;
            more effective&#13;
            VA L U E - A D D E D T A X A N D T H E T O B A C C O E X C I S E A R E I M P O R T A N T S O U R C E S O F R E V E N U E I N&#13;
            I N D O N E S I A T H A T N E I T H E R I N C R E A S E N O R D E C R E A S E I N E Q U A L I T Y I N I N D O N E S I A . Over one-third&#13;
            of Indonesiaâ&#128;&#153;s tax revenue comes from direct taxes, mainly VAT. VAT is almost completely neutral, with richer&#13;
            households paying about the same percentage of their market income in VAT as poorer households (Figure 29).&#13;
            The tobacco excise is slightly regressive but does not signiï¬&#129;cantly a ect inequality, reducing the Gini by only 0.4&#13;
            points. Moreover, even if a tobacco tax is regressive, there is evidence that the poor save more in the long run from&#13;
            reduced health expenditures in the future, as well as being more likely to beneï¬&#129;t from a reduction in premature lives&#13;
            than the rich (Savedo and Alwang 2015).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
TA XE S AN D PUBLIC SPE N DING IN IN DON E S IA&#13;
&amp;#12;  28                                                                                     HOW THE GOVERNMENT CHOOSES TO                                  OCTOBER 2015&#13;
                                                                                         RAISE MONEY CAN AFFECT INEQUALITY&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
VAT is almost completely neutral, with poorer and richer households                                                                                                                          SOURCE Susenas 2012, APBN 2012&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                             (Realized), World Bank calculations&#13;
paying the same as a percentage of their market income. The richest&#13;
households pay less in tobacco excises than the rest of the population,&#13;
the effect on the Gini is very small.&#13;
Relative burden of VAT and tobacco excise (ï¬&#129;g.29)&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                     VAT         EXCISE TAX&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                          8&#13;
                                                                                                                     4.3          4.2                      4.2         4.1&#13;
                                                         BU R DEN AS PER C ENTAG E O F&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                          7                3.9                                  4.0                                  3.9&#13;
                                                                                                   3.2                                                                                              3.3&#13;
                                                                                          6&#13;
                                                               M AR K ET I NC OME&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                          5                                                                                                                          1.7&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                          4&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                     3.8&#13;
                                                                                          3        3.5     3.5       3.5          3.5           3.5        3.5         3.5           3.6            3.6&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                          2&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                          1&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                         0&#13;
                                                                                                    1       2         3           4             5          6           7             8               9               10&#13;
                                                                                                                                        HOUSEHOLD MA R KET INCOME&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      I N S OM E O T H E R C OU N T R I E S , I N DI R E C T TA X E S R A I S E MOR E MON E Y, BU T A R E A L S O F E LT MOR E B Y T H E P O OR .&#13;
      As Figure 30 shows, indirect taxes are either neutral or favor the poor in Mexico, Peru, Sri Lanka and Indonesia, but are borne&#13;
      heavily by the poor in Bolivia, Brazil, Uruguay and Armenia. In the more neutral countries, indirect taxes bring in less revenue&#13;
      as a share of GDP, while in the regressive countries they bring in considerably more revenue. This is likely because the greater&#13;
      revenue with increases in inequality come through fewer or no exemptions on staple items, which are consumed frequently by&#13;
      poorer households.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   In countries that raise more revenue through indirect taxes,                                                                                                     SOURCE For Latin America see: Lustig and Pessino 2014;&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                    Paz, et al. 2014; Higgins and Pereira 2014; Scott 2014;&#13;
   those taxes are borne more by poorer households. In countries                                                                                                    Jaramillo 2014, Bucheli, et al. 2014; Lustig, et al. 2014. For&#13;
&#13;
   with more neutral indirect taxes, less revenue is raised.                                                                                                        Armenia and Sri Lanka, results are preliminary by Younger, et&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                    al. (2014) and Arunatilake,et al. (2014).&#13;
   Relative burden of indirect taxes (ï¬&#129;g.30)&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                           POOREST DECILE          SHARE OF GDP RIGHT AXIS&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                           RICHEST DECILE&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                35%                                                                                                                                                        16%&#13;
IN C I DE N C E AS A SH A R E O F M A RK ET I N C O ME&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                30%                                                                                                                                                        14%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                           12%&#13;
                                                                25%&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                           10%&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                 SH A RE O F G D P&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                20%&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                           8%&#13;
                                                                  15%&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                           6%&#13;
&#13;
                                                                  10%&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                           4%&#13;
&#13;
                                                                       5%                                                                                                                                                  2%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                       0%                                                                                                                                                  0%&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                              BO L IV IA   B RAZIL    ME X IC O         PER U         URUG UAY   AR MENIA          SR I LA NKA        INDONESI A&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  TA XE S AN D PUBLIC SPE N DING IN IN DON E S IA&#13;
&amp;#12;29                                                HOW THE GOVERNMENT CHOOSES TO                  OCTOBER 2015&#13;
                                                  RAISE MONEY CAN AFFECT INEQUALITY&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Revenue from personal income tax is low in Indonesia;&#13;
increased compliance and a broader tax base would&#13;
increase revenue and lower inequality&#13;
A BR OA DE R PE R S ON A L I NC OM E TA X C A N B O T H R A I S E S IGN I F IC A N T R E V E N U E A N D R E DUC E I N E QUA L I T Y.&#13;
Personal income taxes make up only 10 percent of tax revenues in Indonesia, or around 1.9 percent of GDP. In other countries,&#13;
they raise signiï¬&#129;cantly more revenue and this is borne to a much greater degree by the rich, helping to reduce inequality&#13;
(Figure 31)18.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
A number of other countries have used personal income taxes to both raise&#13;
signiï¬&#129;cant revenue and reduce inequality, with the richest households paying&#13;
signiï¬&#129;cantly more as a percentage of their market income.&#13;
Relative burden of personal income taxes (ï¬&#129;g.31)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                12%                                                                                                           14%&#13;
     INCIDENCE AS A SHAR E OF MAR KET IN COME&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                    TOTAL DIR ECT TAXES AS S HAR E OF GDP&#13;
                                                                                                                                                              12%&#13;
                                                10%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                              10%&#13;
                                                8%&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                              8%&#13;
                                                6%&#13;
                                                                                                                                                              6%&#13;
&#13;
                                                4%&#13;
                                                                                                                                                              4%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                2%&#13;
                                                                                                                                                              2%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                0%                                                                                                            0%&#13;
                                                        BRA ZIL        ME XIC O       P ER U   URUG UAY                  A R MENIA               SR I LANKA&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
SOURCE For Latin America see: Lustig and Pessino 2014; Paz, et al. 2014; Higgins and Pereira 2014; Scott 2014; Jaramillo 2014, Bucheli, et al. 2014;&#13;
Lustig, et al. 2014. For Armenia and Sri Lanka, results are preliminary by Younger, et al. (2014) and Arunatilake,et al. (2014).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
18&#13;
   Indonesiaâ&#128;&#153;s personal income taxes were not included in this study as they are not captured in the household survey, and many of the high&#13;
income earners who would be among the few who do pay income tax are not in the survey data either.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
TA XE S AN D PUBLIC SPE N DING IN IN DON E S IA&#13;
&amp;#12;30                                                                                  OCTOBER 2015&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  5.&#13;
         CONCLUSION&#13;
         Excluding income taxes, all households are net beneficiaries of&#13;
         Indonesian taxes and spending. Poorer households enjoy net&#13;
         benefits as a greater percentage of market income, but in total they&#13;
         represent only a 25 percent increase in spending power.&#13;
         RICHER HOUSEHOLDS RECEIVE MORE GOVERNMENT SPENDING BUT PAY MORE IN TA XES AND OUT-OF-POCKET&#13;
         EXPENSES, MEANING MOST HOUSEHOLDS RECEIVE ABOUT THE SAME NET SPENDING. The poorest 10 percent&#13;
         of households receive IDR 21 trillion of total transfer, subsidy and social spending, compared with IDR 59 trillion for&#13;
         the richest 10 percent (Figure 32).However, the poorest households pay only IDR 7 trillion in indirect taxes and out-&#13;
         of-pocket health and education expenses, and the richest households pay IDR 49 trillion. The richer a household is,&#13;
         the more it receives in beneï¬&#129;ts but the more it pays in taxes and expenses. As a consequence, most households&#13;
         receive the same beneï¬&#129;ts from government spending after taxes, or around 9-11 percent of the total. Only the richest&#13;
         households receive slightly less, at 7 percent, and even then, they remain beneï¬&#129;ciaries of net spending (although&#13;
         personal income taxes have not yet been factored in).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         Most households receive the same beneï¬&#129;ts from government spending after taxes and&#13;
         expenses; richer households beneï¬&#129;t more from spending, but pay more in taxes and&#13;
         expenses than poorer households.&#13;
         Absolute beneï¬&#129;ts and burdens of taxes and spending in Indonesia (ï¬&#129;g.32)&#13;
&#13;
                                      60&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                      40&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                      20&#13;
                     ID R TR ILLION&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                      -20&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                      -40&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                      -60&#13;
                                            POOREST    2    3        4          5      6        7         8        9     RICHEST&#13;
&#13;
                                                                H OUSEH OLD MAR KET INCOME DECILE&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       OOP HEALTH           OOP EDUCATION             INDIRECT TAXES           DIRECT TRANSFERS&#13;
                                       INDIRECT SUBSIDIES   IN KIND EDUCATION         IN KIND HEALTH           NET GAIN/LOSS&#13;
&#13;
         SOURCE Susenas 2012, APBN 2012 (Realized), World Bank calculations&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         HOW E V E R , G OV E R N M E N T S PE N DI NG BE N E F I T S               earlier, subsidies beneï¬&#129;t all households to a similar&#13;
         P O OR E R HOU S E HOL D S MOR E R E L AT I V E T O T H E I R              proportion of market income, and education is not as pro-&#13;
         M A R K E T I NC OM E . N ON E T H E L E S S , T H E N E T                 poor as it is in other countries. With these representing&#13;
         BE N E F I T T O T H E P O OR E S T HOU S E HOL D S I S ON LY              the two largest spending items, and the spending that&#13;
         2 5 PE R C E N T OF T H E I R I NC OM E . Although the beneï¬&#129;t              does beneï¬&#129;t the poor the most, direct transfers, the&#13;
         of net government spending (after taxes and expenses)                      least, then total beneï¬&#129;t of net spending for the poorest 10&#13;
         is similar for all households, because poorer households                   percent of households is worth only 25 percent of their&#13;
         have such low incomes it represents much more to them                      market income. This is no doubt a welcome boost, but&#13;
         as a percentage of market income than it does for richer                   does not substantially change their welfare, and is too&#13;
         households (Figure 33). However, as we have discussed                      little to have a signiï¬&#129;cant impact on poverty or inequality.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
TA XE S AN D PUBLIC SPE N DING IN IN DON E S IA&#13;
&amp;#12;31        CONCLUSION                                                                                    OCTOBER 2015&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Net government spending represents a greater share of their market                                                               SOURCE Susenas 2012, APBN 2012 (Realized),&#13;
                                                                                                                                 World Bank calculations&#13;
income for poorer households than richer ones. However, even for&#13;
the poorest 10 percent, it boosts incomes by only one-quarter.&#13;
Relative beneï¬&#129;ts and burdens of taxes and spending in Indonesia (ï¬&#129;g.33)&#13;
&#13;
                                                40&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                30&#13;
            PER CENTAGE OF MA R K ET I NC OME&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                20&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 10&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                -10&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                -20&#13;
                                                      POOREST     2             3      4         5        6           7           8           9       RICHEST&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                     H OUSEH OLD MAR KET INCOME DECILE&#13;
&#13;
                                                           OOP HEALTH               OOP EDUCATION             INDIRECT TAXES             DIRECT TRANSFERS&#13;
                                                           INDIRECT SUBSIDIES       IN KIND EDUCATION         IN KIND HEALTH             NET GAIN/LOSS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          The taxes and spending examined so far only result&#13;
          in a small reduction in inequality in Indonesia&#13;
          THIS PAPER CONSIDERS THE IMPACT OF VARIOUS                                                    TA X E S F R OM HOUS E HOL D S A R E M A I N LY R A I S E D&#13;
          GOVERNMENT TA XES AND SPENDING ON INEQUALITY.                                                 T H R OUGH C ON S U M P T ION , R AT H E R T H A N&#13;
          On the revenue collection side, we have focused on                                            DI R E C T LY ON I NC OM E . These consumption taxes are&#13;
          VAT and excise taxes. On the expenditure side, we have                                        neutral to slightly regressive. Personal income taxes are&#13;
          analyzed the distribution of beneï¬&#129;ts from 57 percent                                          likely highly progressive but are a smaller component of&#13;
          of primary government spending with a focus on social                                         government income and are not paid by most households&#13;
          spending, including direct cash transfers and health and                                      in the survey data.&#13;
          education spending, and non-social fuel subsidy spending.&#13;
                                                                                                        T H E C OM BI N AT ION OF S O C I A L S PE N DI NG A N D&#13;
          T H E OV E R A L L R E S U LT I S T H AT I N D ON E S I Aâ&#128;&#153; S                                  E N E R G Y S U B S I DI E S R E DUC E S I N E QUA L I T Y&#13;
          2 01 2 -E R A F I S C A L P OL IC Y R E DUC E D I N E QUA L I T Y                             S L IGH T LY, A N D MO S T LY T H R OUGH I N-K I N D&#13;
          S L IGH T LY T H R OUGH A N E U T R A L I N DI R E C T TA X                                   BE N E F I T S OF E DUC AT ION . Direct transfers are&#13;
          S Y S T E M A N D S L IGH T LY PR O GR E S S I V E S O C I A L                                the most cost-e ective way of reaching the poor and&#13;
          S PE N DI NG . In other words, everyone in Indonesia                                          vulnerable and reducing inequality, but relatively little&#13;
          contributes tax revenues (through their consumption                                           is spent on them. Energy subsidies and education&#13;
          activities) while the Government uses these resources                                         spending alone account for about 80 percent of all&#13;
          (and others) to provide transfers and in-kind spending that                                   public spending examined here. Energy subsidies in&#13;
          raises incomes for the poorest individuals and households.                                    2012 were very slightly progressive and large enough in&#13;
          However, there are very few representative individuals                                        magnitude to roughly cancel out the indirect tax burdens&#13;
          who pay more in taxes than they receive in transfers,                                         created by Indonesiaâ&#128;&#153;s VAT and excise tax regimes. As a&#13;
          meaning that the ï¬&#129;scal system provides a boost to income                                      consequence, the resulting â&#128;&#156;net subsidyâ&#128;&#157; on consumption&#13;
          (on average) at all points along the income distribution.                                     activity is neutral to slightly progressive. Direct transfers&#13;
          As a result of the ï¬&#129;scal system, the Gini coe cient was                                       more e ectively target the poor than in-kind transfers&#13;
          reduced by 2.5 points, only a modest reduction.                                               or subsidies. However, they are also quite small in sizeâ&#128;&#148;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
TA XE S AN D PUBLIC SPE N DING IN IN DON E S IA&#13;
&amp;#12;32       CONCLUSION                                                     OCTOBER 2015&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         total spending on all direct transfers represents is less&#13;
         than 0.5 percent of GDPâ&#128;&#148;and either provide relatively         F U RT H E R MOR E , A N U M BE R OF K E Y F I S C A L&#13;
         small beneï¬&#129;t packages or do not have very broad               P OL IC I E S H AV E BE E N E XC LU DE D F R OM T H E&#13;
         coverage. As a result, the inequality and poverty reduction   C U R R E N T A N A LY S I S : PE R S ON A L I NC OM E TA X E S&#13;
         impacts of these transfers are limited. In-kind beneï¬&#129;ts,      A N D I N F R A S T RUC T U R E . Personal income tax (PIT)&#13;
         which are generally larger in terms of transfer size than     is missing because most (wealthier) PIT payers are not&#13;
         are direct transfer, are received only upon access, and       covered in the survey data. Moreover, the absence of&#13;
         poorer households in Indonesia have far lower rates of        these wealthier households will also distort the 2012&#13;
         secondary- and tertiary-level education access than do        results presented here. This is because these households&#13;
         rich households, which limits the progressiveness of these    are likely to pay higher VAT, as well as PIT, and potentially&#13;
         sizeable transfer programs.                                   beneï¬&#129;t more from certain types of spending (such as fuel&#13;
                                                                       subsidies) but less from others (such as education if they&#13;
         WHILE FISCAL POLICY DOES ACHIEVE A LIMITED                    are sending their children to private schools). That means&#13;
         DEGREE OF REDISTRIBUTION IN INDONESIA, IT IS                  that the richest decile of households may no longer still&#13;
         LESS THAN IS ACHIEVED IN MOST OTHER COUNTRIES                 be net recipients of ï¬&#129;scal taxes and spending. Finally,&#13;
         STUDIED, OFTEN BY A NUMBER OF TIMES. The modest               infrastructure spending has been excluded because of&#13;
         impacts of ï¬&#129;scal policy result from low direct income tax     the methodological di culties in allocating the beneï¬&#129;ts of&#13;
         collection and low social spending levels, as well as the     such spending across households.&#13;
         fact that untargeted energy subsidies and education&#13;
         expendituresâ&#128;&#148;both of which are roughly neutral in             TO ADDRESS BOTH THESE RECENT DEVELOPMENTS&#13;
         distribution and not pro-poorâ&#128;&#148;are the largest budget          AND MISSING ANALYZES, THE FISCAL POLICY&#13;
         items. Compared with the rest of the CEQ country set,         AGENCY AND WORLD BANK HAVE AGREED A JOINT&#13;
         Indonesia begins with a relatively low market income          WORK PROGR AM THAT WILL:&#13;
         Gini. But other countries with similarly low market income    1. Extend the analysis to the 2013 budget, capturing the&#13;
         Ginisâ&#128;&#148;Armenia or Ethiopiaâ&#128;&#148;do better than Indonesia in            e ects of the fuel subsidy reforms and temporary cash&#13;
         terms of inequality reduction through ï¬&#129;scal policy (while        compensation;&#13;
         spending similarly low amounts). Regardless of the ideal&#13;
                                                                       2. Extend the analysis to the 2015 budget, capturing the&#13;
         size of ï¬&#129;scal spending in Indonesia, policymakers could&#13;
                                                                          removal of fuel subsidies, temporary cash assistance&#13;
         further enhance income equality and reduce the number&#13;
                                                                          and expansion of BSM and PKH;&#13;
         of impoverished citizens by shifting ï¬&#129;scal priorities.&#13;
                                                                       3. Extend the analysis to capture both higher income&#13;
                                                                          earners and personal income taxes by building upon&#13;
         Further research is needed to bring in&#13;
                                                                          the top incomes methodology and data of Wai-Poi, et&#13;
         other key components of fiscal policy                            al. (forthcoming); and&#13;
                                                                       4. Pilot new methodological approaches to capturing the&#13;
         T H I S PA PE R U S E S 2 01 2 DATA , T H E L AT E S T           incidence of infrastructure spending.&#13;
         AVA I L A BL E DATA AT T H E T I M E . Since then, a&#13;
         number of new and important developments have taken&#13;
         place. First, ï¬&#129;xed fuel prices were increased in 2013, and&#13;
         accompanied by an expansion in the BSM scholarships&#13;
         program and the distribution of temporary cash assistance&#13;
         in the form of BLSM (Bantuan Langsung Sementara&#13;
         Miskin). At the end of 2014, fuel prices were raised again&#13;
         and a further round of BLSM issued. At the beginning&#13;
         of 2015, fuel subsidies were removed for gasoline and&#13;
         lowered for diesel, and further expansions made for BSM&#13;
         and PKH.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
TA XE S AN D PUBLIC SPE N DING IN IN DON E S IA&#13;
&amp;#12;33                                                                      OCTOBER 2015&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         References&#13;
         Arunatilake, N., Inchauste, G. and Lustig, N. 2014. Forthcoming paper (untitled).&#13;
&#13;
         Beneke de Sanfeliu, Margarita, Nora Lustig and JosÃ© AndrÃ©s Oliva. 2014. La incidencia de los impuestos y el gasto&#13;
           social sobre la pobreza y la desigualdad en El Salvador.&#13;
&#13;
         Bucheli, M., N. Lustig, M. Rossi and F. AmÃ¡bile. 2014. Social Spending, Taxes and Income Redistribution in Uruguay.&#13;
           In Lustig, Nora, Carola Pessino and John Scott. (eds.) The Redistributive Impact of Taxes and Social Spending&#13;
           in Latin America. Special Issue, Public Finance Review: 42(3).&#13;
&#13;
         Cabrera, Maynor, Nora Lustig and HilicÃ­as E. MorÃ¡n. 2014. Fiscal Policy, Inequality and the Ethnic Divide in Guatemala.&#13;
           Commitment to Equity Working Paper 20. Center for Inter-American Policy and Research and Department of&#13;
           Economics, Tulane University and Inter American Dialogue.&#13;
&#13;
         Dabla-Norris, E., K. Kochhar, N. Suphaphiphat, F. Ricka and E. Tsounta. 2015. Causes and Consequences of Income&#13;
            Inequality: a global perspective. IMF Sta Discussion Note SDN/15/13. Washington, DC: International Monetary&#13;
           Fund.&#13;
&#13;
         Higgins, S. and C. Pereira. 2014. The E ects of Brazilâ&#128;&#153;s Taxation and Social Spending on the Distribution of Household&#13;
            Income. In Lustig, Nora, Carola Pessino and John Scott, eds. The Redistributive Impact of Taxes and Social Spending&#13;
            in Latin America. Special Issue, Public Finance Review : 42(3).&#13;
&#13;
         Inchauste, Gabriela, Nora Lustig, Mashekwa Maboshe, Catriona Purï¬&#129;eld, and Ingrid Woolard. 2015 . The Distributional&#13;
            Impact of Fiscal Policy in South Africa. CEQ Working Paper No. 29, Center for Inter-American Policy and Research&#13;
            and Department of Economics, Tulane University and Inter-American Dialogue.&#13;
&#13;
         Jaramillo, Miguel. 2014. The Incidence of Social Spending and Taxes in Peru. In Lustig, Nora, Carola Pessino and John&#13;
            Scott, eds. The Redistributive Impact of Taxes and Social Spending in Latin America. Special Issue, Public Finance&#13;
            Review: 42(3).&#13;
&#13;
         Jellema, J., M. Wai-Poi and A. A ar. 2015. Fiscal Policy, Redistribution, and Inequality in Indonesia (Working Paper).&#13;
            Washington, DC: World Bank.&#13;
&#13;
         Lembaga Survei Indonesia (LSI). 2014. Inequality Perceptions Survey. Jakarta: Lembaga Survei Indonesia.&#13;
&#13;
         Lustig, Nora. 2014. Taxes, Transfers, Inequality and the Poor in the Developing World. Round 1. CEQ Working Paper No.&#13;
           23, Center for Inter-American Policy and Research and Department of Economics, Tulane University and Inter-&#13;
           American Dialogue.&#13;
&#13;
         Lustig, Nora and Sean Higgins. 2013. Commitment to Equity Assessment (CEQ): Estimating the Incidence of Social&#13;
           Spending, Subsidies and Taxes. (Handbook) . CEQ Working Paper No. 1, July 2011; revised January 2013. New&#13;
           Orleans: Tulane University.&#13;
&#13;
         Lustig, N. and C. Pessino. 2014. Social Spending and Income Redistribution in Argentina in the 2000s: The Rising Role&#13;
           of Noncontributory Pensions. Pubic Finance Review. Published online 20 Nov 2013.&#13;
&#13;
         Lustig, N., C. Pessino and J. Scott. 2013. The Impact of Taxes and Social Spending on Inequality and Poverty in&#13;
           Argentina, Bolivia, Brazil, Mexico, Peru and Uruguay: An Overview. CEQ Working Paper No. 3. Center for Inter-&#13;
           American Policy and Research and Department of Economics, Tulane University and Inter-American Dialogue.&#13;
&#13;
         Paz Arauco, V., GG. Molina, W. JimÃ©nez Pozo, W. and E. YÃ¡Ã±ez Aguilar. 2014. Explaining Low Redistributive Impact in&#13;
           Bolivia. In Lustig, Nora, Carola Pessino and John Scott, eds. The Redistributive Impact of Taxes and Social Spending&#13;
           in Latin America. Special Issue, Public Finance Review: 42(3).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
TA XE S AN D PUBLIC SPE N DING IN IN DON E S IA&#13;
&amp;#12;34                                                                     OCTOBER 2015&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         References&#13;
         Peirskalla, Jan and Audrey Sacks. 2015. Unpacking the E ect of Decentralization on Conï¬&#130;ict: Lessons from Indonesia.&#13;
            Unpublished Manuscript.&#13;
&#13;
         Sauma, Juan Diego Trejos. 2014. Social Public Spending, Taxes, Redistribution of Income, and Poverty in Costa. CEQ&#13;
           Working Paper No. 18. Center for Inter-American Policy and Research and Department of Economics, Tulane&#13;
           University and Inter-American Dialogue.&#13;
&#13;
         Savedo , William and Albert Alwang. 2015. The Single Best Health Policy in the World: Tobacco Taxes. CGD Policy&#13;
           Paper 062. Washington DC: Center for Global Development.&#13;
&#13;
         Scott, John. 2014. Redistributive Impact and E ciency of Mexicoâ&#128;&#153;s Fiscal System. In Lustig, Nora, Carola Pessino and&#13;
           John Scott, eds. The Redistributive Impact of Taxes and Social Spending in Latin America. Special Issue, Public&#13;
           Finance Review: 42(3).&#13;
&#13;
         Wai-Poi, M., Wihardja, M. and Mervisiano, M. (Forthcoming). The Problem with Taxes: Measuring Top Incomes in&#13;
           Indonesia (Working paper). Jakarta: World Bank.&#13;
&#13;
         Woldehanna, Tassew, Eyasu Tsehaye, Gabriela Inchauste, Ruth Hill and Nora Lustig. 2014. Fiscal Incidence in Ethiopia.&#13;
           In World Bank. 2014. Ethiopia Poverty Assessment. Washington DC: World Bank.&#13;
&#13;
         World Bank. 2014. Delivering Change. Indonesia Economic Quarterly, December 2014. Jakarta: World Bank.&#13;
&#13;
         World Bank. 2015a. Indonesiaâ&#128;&#153;s Rising Divide: Why inequality is rising, Why it matters and what can be done. Jakarta:&#13;
           World Bank.&#13;
&#13;
         World Bank. 2015b. A Perceived Divide: How Indonesians think about inequality and what should be done (Working&#13;
           Paper). Jakarta: World Bank.&#13;
&#13;
         World Bank. Forthcoming (a). Indonesiaâ&#128;&#153;s New Climbers: Who are the middle class and what does it mean for the&#13;
           country? Jakarta: World Bank.&#13;
&#13;
         World Bank. Forthcoming (b). Report on top incomes in Indonesia (Working Paper). Jakarta: World Bank.&#13;
&#13;
         Younger, S. and A. Khachatryan. 2014. Fiscal Incidence in Armenia. Background Paper for World Bank (forthcoming)&#13;
           Armenia Public Expenditure Review.&#13;
&#13;
         Zhuang, J., R. Kanbur and C. Rhee. 2014. Asiaâ&#128;&#153;s income inequalities. In Zhuang, J., R. Kanbur and C. Rhee, eds.&#13;
           Inequality in Asia and the Paciï¬&#129;c: Trends, Drivers, and Policy Implications. New York: Asia Development Bank and&#13;
           Routledge.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
TA XE S AN D PUBLIC SPE N DING IN IN DON E S IA&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="25651638">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2015/12/25651638/taxes-public-spending-indonesia-pays-benefits
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2015/12/25651638/taxes-public-spending-indonesia-pays-benefits</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2015/12/25651638/taxes-public-spending-indonesia-pays-benefits</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2015-12-07T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2015-12-07T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <docm_id>090224b083c31ca9</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b083c31ca9</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2015/12/28/090224b083c31ca9/1_0/Rendered/INDEX/Taxe0and00in0Indonesia0ay0benefits.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2015/12/28/090224b083c31ca9/1_0/Rendered/PDF/Taxe0and00in0Indonesia0ay0benefits.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2015-12-07T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2015-11-01T11:25:01Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Taxes and public spending in Indonesia :
            who pays and who benefits?
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Inequality in Indonesia is rising
            rapidly. During the 1997-98 Asian financial crisis, poverty
            rosesharply, while the Gini measure of inequality fell, as
            the richest were the hardest hit. Since then, the Gini has
            increased from 30 points in 2000 to 41 points in 2014, its
            highest recorded level. In 2002, the richest 10 percent of
            Indonesians consumed as much as the poorest 42 percent
            combined; by 2014, they consumed as much as the poorest 54
            percent. Even this is likely to be understated, as household
            surveys often miss the rich. Indonesia's level of
            inequality is now becoming high and climbing faster than
            most of its East Asian neighbors.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Taxes and public spending in Indonesia : who
            pays and who benefits?
        </docna>
        <display_title>Taxes and public spending in
            Indonesia : who pays and who benefits?</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2015/11/25651638/taxes-public-spending-indonesia-pays-benefits</listing_relative_url>
        <subtopic>Services &amp; Transfers to Poor,Debt Markets,Public Sector Development,Access to Finance,Economic Theory &amp; Research</subtopic>
        <docty>Working Paper</docty>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth,Poverty Reduction</teratopic>
        <count>Indonesia</count>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>090224b083c31ca9_1_0</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>Southeast Asia!$!Southeast Asia</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!517191</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Asia!$!517198</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <admreg>East Asia and Pacific,East Asia and Pacific</admreg>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth,Poverty Reduction</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            household incomes, total revenue, physical
            capital, economic growth, accounting, excise taxes, people,
            public revenues, economic security, minimum wage, disposable
            income, income, interest, tuition, government spending,
            financial assistance, real gdp, stock market, spending, gdp
            per capita, macroeconomic policy, services, inequalities,
            housing, revenues, fiscal policy, welfare, incentives,
            distribution, subsidy, mutual funds, tax, income support,
            inputs, income tax, corruption, smart card, wealth,
            corporate income tax, inflation, trends, small business,
            credits, influence, savings, union, money, rent, vulnerable
            households, scholarships, sales taxes, payment, household
            income, public finance, labor, tax revenues, dividends,
            capital stocks, public expenditure review, per, gross
            domestic product, asset accumulation, subsidies, finance,
            grants, public, education spending, infrastructure, taxes,
            savings account, health spending, expenditure, public
            subsidies, education systems, equity, income taxes,
            consumption, human capital, capital, wages, equal access,
            economic outcomes, public expenditure, student, financial
            crisis, financial capital, family, value, bank, electricity,
            health care costs, interest payment, income distribution,
            household, expenditures, property, tax rates, legal title,
            tax revenue, roads, revenue collection, economic inequality,
            insurance, taxation, government policies, small amount of
            savings, trade, gdp, tax credits, goods, land, security,
            licenses, husband, investment, households, education access,
            equality, collateral, gini coefficient, decentralization,
            revenue, students, financial support, investments, pension
            fund, fees, remittances, public spending, governments,
            financial sector, outcomes, public bank, development bank,
            benefits, inequality
        </keywd>
        <owner>EAPEC - External Communications (EAPEC)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>Southeast Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Asia</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>101667</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shocks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Safety Nets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Safety Nets and Transfers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Safety Nets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal &amp; Monetary Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Consolidation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Governance and Structural Fiscal Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Rules</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Sustainability</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macro-Fiscal Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pensions &amp; Retirement Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Efficiency of Public Expenditures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Expenditures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Financial Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Spending</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civil Service Employment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civil Service Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Capital</ml:concept><ml:concept>Managing People</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Employment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wage Setting</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages, Compensation and Benefits</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Lines</ml:concept><ml:concept>Services &amp; Transfers to Poor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Capital</ml:concept><ml:concept>Consumption</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Boundaries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Middle-class</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shocks and Vulnerability</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Insurance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Assistance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Cash Transfers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pensions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Managing Public Finances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resources Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Eastern Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Indonesia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>