<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>                              1&#13;
COMPETITIVE CITIES FOR JOBS AND GROWTH&#13;
                                         101718&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
COMPANION PAPER 1&#13;
&#13;
CITY ANALYTICS&#13;
Kenan Fikri, T. Juni Zhu&#13;
December 2015&#13;
&amp;#12;2&#13;
&amp;#12;TABLE OF&#13;
CONTENTS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Background and Acknowledgments 5&#13;
Executive Summary 6&#13;
1. Introduction 8&#13;
2. City Profile and Performance 8&#13;
What data on cities are available? 8&#13;
Exploring the Oxford Economics data 8&#13;
   Profile of the average city in the data set by region 9&#13;
   Global variation in the data set 10&#13;
Comparing city and national economic performance 12&#13;
Productivity differentials across cities and within countries 14&#13;
Private sector job creation 15&#13;
   Industrial sector job creation 16&#13;
   Tradable sector job creation 17&#13;
Foreign direct investment 18&#13;
3. Development Pathways: How Do City Economies Evolve over Time? 20&#13;
Income pathway 20&#13;
   City GDP per capita growth by region 21&#13;
   City GDP per capita growth by region, controlling for country effects 23&#13;
   City GDP per capita growth by income level 24&#13;
   City GDP per capita growth by income level, controlling for country effects 25&#13;
   City GDP per capita growth by industrial profile 26&#13;
   Income traps 26&#13;
Industry pathways 28&#13;
Size pathways 31&#13;
4. Predictors of City Competitiveness 33&#13;
Working definition of city competitiveness 33&#13;
Stocktaking of city indexes 33&#13;
How well do city indexes predict competitiveness outcomes? 34&#13;
City competitiveness correlates: Factor analysis 35&#13;
   Factor analysis: Global results on the determinants of city competitiveness 35&#13;
   Predictors of city competitiveness by region and city type 37&#13;
How does the â&#128;&#156;mayorâ&#128;&#153;s wedgeâ&#128;&#157; relate to city competitiveness? 39&#13;
   Findings from the mayorâ&#128;&#153;s wedge analysis: Scope and autonomy 41&#13;
   Findings from the mayorâ&#128;&#153;s wedge analysis: Capacity 41&#13;
   Variation in the impact of the mayorâ&#128;&#153;s wedge by region and city type 42&#13;
How does inequality relate to city competitiveness? 44&#13;
5. Attempting to Arrive at a List of the Worldâ&#128;&#153;s Most Competitive Cities 45&#13;
6. Conclusion 46&#13;
References 48&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                    3&#13;
&amp;#12;4&#13;
&amp;#12;BACKGROUND AND&#13;
ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
I&#13;
   nterest in studying city competitiveness has skyrocketed       income, sector, region, and so on. And we have buttressed&#13;
   in the past few years, although the topic itself is far from   these findings with econometric deep dives and case stud-&#13;
   new. Mayors and city leaders have long worried about           ies in selected countries and cities. We are able to inform&#13;
the obstacles to job creation, competitiveness, and economic      the ongoing debates on what really matters for economic&#13;
growth that plague their cities.                                  outcomes in cities with analysis of overarching trends and&#13;
                                                                  associations, supplemented with rigorous analyses to identify&#13;
This paper is part of a broader research initiative, the Com-     causal relationships. We also try to â&#128;&#156;stand on the shoulders of&#13;
petitive Cities Knowledge Base, which is managed jointly by       giantsâ&#128;&#157; where possible: that is, we use and reference exist-&#13;
the Trade and Competitiveness Global Practice and the Social,     ing resources (research, analysis, toolkits, and experts). The&#13;
Urban, Rural, and Resilience Global Practice of the World         summary findings of the overall research are presented in&#13;
Bank Group. Its objective is to create a knowledge base on        the framework report, Competitive Cities for Jobs and Growth&#13;
competitive cities, to improve the understanding of job cre-      (World Bank, 2015).&#13;
ation at the city level and as a foundation for a community of&#13;
practice on this topic for World Bank staff, academia, donor      The objective of this paper is to present key findings from&#13;
partners, and practitioners.                                      the quantitative analysis of the drivers of competitiveness in&#13;
                                                                  cites around the world.&#13;
Our attempt in this initiative has been to focus our energies&#13;
on bringing to our clients a robust body of knowledge that        This note was prepared by Kenan Fikri and T. Juni Zhu, with&#13;
will address their questions on benchmarking their perfor-        contributions from Anca Rusu and guidance and assistance&#13;
mance, on understanding what has worked elsewhere and             from Austin Kilroy and Megha Mukim. The joint task team&#13;
what has not, and on looking at ways to organize for delivery     leaders of the Competitive Cities Knowledge Base project&#13;
in different contexts.                                            are Austin Kilroy and Megha Mukim. Stefano Negri, Sameh&#13;
                                                                  Wahba, Ceci Sager, and Somik Lall have provided overall&#13;
Our approach has focused on using different methodologies         guidance on the project as senior advisers.&#13;
to tackle these questions. These methodologies are based on&#13;
best practices, data availability, replicability, and simplici-   The team would like to acknowledge gratefully the European&#13;
ty. In many cases, we have leveraged new and existing data        Commission; the African, Caribbean, and Pacific Group of&#13;
sources to shed new light on some unanswered questions;           States Secretariat; and the governments of Austria, Norway,&#13;
in others, we have conducted primary research because             and Switzerland for financing this study through the Com-&#13;
available data were inadequate. We looked at global and           petitive Industries and Innovation Program.&#13;
regional trends, comparing different typologies of cities by&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                         5&#13;
&amp;#12;EXECUTIVE SUMMARY&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
C                                                                   Key findings from the global quantitative analytics work&#13;
       ities today are home to 54 percent of humanity (UN-&#13;
       DESA 2015). They cover only a fraction of the worldâ&#128;&#153;s        stream are as follows:&#13;
       landmass but concentrate 80 percent of global gross do-&#13;
mestic product (GDP) (World Bank 2013).1 Since the Industri-        â&#128;¢	   The story of the worldâ&#128;&#153;s cities from 2000 to 2012 was one&#13;
al Revolution, country after country has witnessed urbaniza-             of rising prosperity. Powered by China, GDP per capita&#13;
tion lift entire generations out of poverty and into the middle          across cities in the data set grew by 4.6 percent on aver-&#13;
class. Cities combine their societiesâ&#128;&#153; resources into something          age each year. Of the 750 cities under study, 36 percent&#13;
more than the sum of their parts. For countries, cities are the          achieved annual average growth rates above 5 percent.&#13;
engines of productivity and the workhorses of development.               GDP per capita fell in 46 cities under studyâ&#128;&#148;a small&#13;
For individuals, cities mean opportunity.                                fraction of the total that includes not only the reces-&#13;
                                                                         sion-hit cities of the developed world but also struggling&#13;
Yet what makes a city thrive and its residents prosperâ&#128;&#148;in                cities in Sub-Saharan Africa and beyond, thus reminding&#13;
short, what makes a city competitiveâ&#128;&#148;remains a frustrat-                 us that development does not always proceed as linear&#13;
ingly difficult question to answer. To some extent, every city           advancement.&#13;
has its own secret sauce. But some sauces do seem to be more&#13;
potent than others, a fact that suggests certain ingredients        â&#128;¢	   The worldâ&#128;&#153;s cities remain extremely heterogeneous, and&#13;
and combinations may matter more than others in determin-                the results presented here argue emphatically against a&#13;
ing economic outcomes. This paper aims to track down some                one-size-fits-all approach to city competitiveness. The&#13;
elusive common threads by assessing the state of cities in the           most populous city in the data set had a population 144&#13;
world today and identifying factors that appear to be correlat-          times that of the smallest, and the richest city enjoyed&#13;
ed with better economic outcomes. We explore these issues                a GDP per capita level 384 times that of the poorest. Al-&#13;
globally, across all cities, as well as within regions and across        though Chinaâ&#128;&#153;s cities achieved astonishing growth rates,&#13;
different city typologies. The paper is designed to summarize            income levels and living standards fell in parts of Europe&#13;
the projectâ&#128;&#153;s findings and demonstrate how the database and              and Central Asia and of Sub-Saharan Africa.2 Even where&#13;
analytic tools can be used in other contextsâ&#128;&#148;for example, in             growth was robust, productivity, incomes, and employ-&#13;
regional deep dives.                                                     ment were not guaranteed to follow suit.&#13;
&#13;
The analysis presented here begins by benchmarking the              â&#128;¢	   Cities generate a disproportionate share of new private&#13;
economic performance of 750 cities across the globe. It as-              sector jobs. From 2006 to 2012, 750 of the worldâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
sesses not only how quickly those cities are growing but also            largest cities analyzed here created 87.7 million private&#13;
how their economies are changing, how their performance                  sector jobs, accounting for 58 percent of all new private&#13;
compares with that of peers at home and abroad, and where                sector jobs in their 129 countries over the period despite&#13;
these cities fit in their national urban systems. We draw from           collectively being home to only one-quarter of total&#13;
these findings common development pathways and then plot                 private sector employment. Beijing and Chongqing (in&#13;
individual cities along them. The explanatory portion of the             China) and Jakarta (in Indonesia) created the most pri-&#13;
analysis starts by taking stock of the existing knowledge base           vate sector jobs in sheer numeric terms, with more than&#13;
on city competitiveness with a review of secondary sourc-                2 million new jobs each.&#13;
es. It proceeds to explore the factors associated with better&#13;
competitiveness outcomes across multiple posited buckets of         â&#128;¢	   The competitiveness opportunity is huge. If each city had&#13;
determinants through a simple correlation analysis. Then we              elevated the local rate of job creation to that achieved by&#13;
use regression analysis to explore how facets of local govern-           the average city in the top quarter of performers in its&#13;
ment autonomy relate to city competitiveness. We find no                 region, 18.9 million extra jobs would have been created&#13;
holy grail for city competitiveness, but we do find many hints.          in 2012 alone.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
6&#13;
&amp;#12;â&#128;¢	   The manufacturing sector is slowing as an engine of               services sector grows to dominate the economy. These&#13;
     growth, particularly for low-income cities. The rate of           creative and financial services hubs thrive on human&#13;
     job growth in the industrial sector of the economy has            capital and innovation.&#13;
     slowed significantly for low-income countries over the&#13;
     past 12 years, prompting the question whether the            â&#128;¢	   Cities rarely change their position in a national urban&#13;
     services sector will prove to be as powerful an engine of         hierarchy except in large countries. National urban&#13;
     development.                                                      hierarchies typically exhibit remarkable stability, but&#13;
                                                                       when changes do occur they are either dramatic (for&#13;
â&#128;¢	   Strong tradable sectors characterize competitive cities.          example, New Orleans or Detroit in the United States)&#13;
     In the 10 percent of cities in which GDP per capita grew          or in fast-growing countries with large urban systems&#13;
     fastest from 2005 to 2012, tradable sector employment             (for example, China, India, or Nigeria). In five countries,&#13;
     growth outstripped non-traded sector employment                   the primary city in terms of population was displaced by&#13;
     growth by 2.5 percent on average annually. By contrast,           2012 by the city that ranked highest in 2000 in terms of&#13;
     in less competitive cities, tradable and non-tradable             GDP.&#13;
     industries grew, both at a slower rate.&#13;
                                                                  â&#128;¢	   The factors associated with positive competitiveness&#13;
â&#128;¢	   Foreign direct investment (FDI) remains highly con-               outcomes in cities vary by income level. Institutions and&#13;
     centrated in a relatively small number of elite cities.           regulations matter at all levels of income and economic&#13;
     However, in terms of FDI inflows per dollar of GDP from           structures, whereas physical infrastructure appears to&#13;
     2003 to 2012, two-thirds of the top FDI destination               boost growth at low income levels; social infrastructure&#13;
     cities could be found in Sub-Saharan Africa, South Asia,          supports productivity at middle income levels; and inno-&#13;
     and East Asia and Pacific (excluding China). Nonetheless,         vation, human capital, and financial infrastructure all&#13;
     the economic development potential of FDI should not              contribute to growth, productivity, and living standards&#13;
     be overstated. In every city, local firms still create the        in high-income cities.&#13;
     majority of jobs.&#13;
                                                                  â&#128;¢	   Competitive cities are good at mopping up inequality.&#13;
â&#128;¢	   The dominant economic sector in a city changes only               Even without significant increases in administrative&#13;
     over very long time horizons. When it does change, cities         powers, competitive citiesâ&#128;&#148;especially cities that attract&#13;
     typicallyâ&#128;&#148;but not alwaysâ&#128;&#148;follow a well-established                a large influx of migrantsâ&#128;&#148;are good at reducing inequal-&#13;
     pathway. Four of five cities saw no change in the largest         ity. Although global city-level data confirm that in-mi-&#13;
     sector of their economy from 2000 to 2012. Of those               gration contributes to intracity inequality in the short&#13;
     that did change, almost half transitioned from industry           term, we observe that inequality tends to decline over&#13;
     to high-end services. Several South Asian cities tran-            time as cities develop and new migrants are absorbed&#13;
     sitioned from high-end services to consumer services,             into the labor force.&#13;
     thus challenging the assumption of a linear development&#13;
     pathway.                                                     â&#128;¢	   Maximizing the quality and pace of economic develop-&#13;
                                                                       ment may call for a nuanced approach to devolution.&#13;
â&#128;¢	   As incomes rise and cities progress along the develop-            Regression analysis found that expanding the scope of a&#13;
     ment pathway, their functions evolve. Up to approxi-              mayorâ&#128;&#153;s administrative remit is associated with improved&#13;
     mately US$2,500 GDP per capita, cities serve primarily            competitiveness in cities, but the same is not true for&#13;
     as market towns and central points for the exchange               financial autonomy. In-depth research carried out in&#13;
     of basic services. At GDP per capita levels of about              China suggests that local government capacity is also a&#13;
     US$2,500 to US$12,000, industry dominates the econ-               determining factor.&#13;
     omy, and cities take on a new role as production centers&#13;
     and agglomerations of people, capital, and suppliers.&#13;
     As cities progress to higher income levels, the tertiary&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                           7&#13;
&amp;#12;1. Introduction                                                    2. City Profile and Performance&#13;
This technical note concluding the global quantitative analyt-     What data on cities are available?&#13;
ics portion of the Competitive Cities Knowledge Base project&#13;
at the World Bank Group begins by reviewing the available          Numerous organizations have attempted to rank cities&#13;
data on cities and analyzing the recent economic perfor-           across the world on one combination of metrics or another,&#13;
mance of cities across regions and select typologies. It then      but city-level data sets with detailed raw data on city eco-&#13;
presents the findings from correlation and regression analy-       nomic structure and performance over time and with global&#13;
ses studying the predictors of city competitiveness. Finally,      coverage are few and far between. The World Bank Group&#13;
this paper attempts to identify development pathways and           purchased a comprehensive data set for this project: the&#13;
plot cities along them to help inform advisory or technical        Global Cities Historic Database from Oxford Economics (OE).&#13;
work across World Bank Group stakeholder communities in            Euromonitor International maintains an alternative data-&#13;
the future.                                                        base called Passport: Cities that offers a comparable range of&#13;
                                                                   indicators for 126 large cities but a much more limited range&#13;
The technical, descriptive, and analytic findings discussed        (covering population and household characteristics) for more&#13;
in this paper are intended to uncover global trends, given         than 1,000 smaller cities. The Euromonitor data set extends&#13;
available data, while at the same time illustrating a city-based   back only to 2005 but does offer forecasts to 2020 on certain&#13;
approach to development analysis. The work presented here          indicators.&#13;
can be tailored or deepened in whole or in part to explore city&#13;
performance across regions or topic areas.                         The OE database used in this paper covers 750 cities (defined&#13;
                                                                   as metropolitan areas) across 140 different countries. The&#13;
                                                                   data set is not intended to be comprehensive; the cities were&#13;
                                                                   selected from the United Nations list of urban agglomer-&#13;
                                                                   ations with at least 750,000 inhabitants and then supple-&#13;
                                                                   mented with other strategic cities such as country capitals.3&#13;
                                                                   The data set contains 12 years of historical data, covering the&#13;
                                                                   period from 2000 to 2012, and includes 90 different variables&#13;
                                                                   covering demographics, output and employment (each by sec-&#13;
                                                                   tor), household income, consumer spending, and retail sales,&#13;
                                                                   among others. This analysis uses only the small number of&#13;
                                                                   indicators that deal directly with economic outcomes.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                   Findings presented here are derived from the OE database&#13;
                                                                   unless otherwise stated. Additional sources include data&#13;
                                                                   on public finances (revenues and expenditures) that were&#13;
                                                                   obtained from the International Monetary Fund and patent-&#13;
                                                                   ing data from the Global Urban Competitiveness Project. See&#13;
                                                                   tables 4.1 and 4.2 for a list of the variables and their sources&#13;
                                                                   that were used in the correlation and regression analysis.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                   Exploring the Oxford Economics data&#13;
                                                                   Even within OEâ&#128;&#153;s sample of the worldâ&#128;&#153;s 750 largest cities, the&#13;
                                                                   basic characteristics of cities vary hugely across regions, and&#13;
                                                                   before we dive into the analysis, it will be instructive to take&#13;
                                                                   stock of the heterogeneity. Table 2.1 provides a profile of the&#13;
                                                                   average city in each World Bank Group region contained in&#13;
                                                                   the data set.4 The n reports the number of cities from each&#13;
                                                                   region.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
8&#13;
&amp;#12;Table 2.1	                   Profile of the average city in each World Bank Group region&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Source: Oxford Economics Dataset&#13;
Note: GDP = gross domestic product; GVA = gross value added.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Profile of the average city in the data set by                                                      percent of employment and nearly 50 percent of gross value&#13;
region                                                                                              added (GVA)â&#128;&#148;far above the average in any other region.&#13;
                                                                                                    Consumer services and high-end services sectors were under-&#13;
In 2012, the average Organisation for Economic Co-operation                                         sized.&#13;
and Development (OECD) city in the data set was a high-in-&#13;
come city of 2.8 million inhabitants that had extremely high                                        From Europe and Central Asia, the average city in the data&#13;
levels of labor productivity by global standards that was                                           set was upper-middle income with 1.4 million people. Many&#13;
growing slightly faster than its national economy.5 From fig-                                       cities dominated their national economies, with the average&#13;
ure 2.1, we see that high-end services dominated the average                                        city generating over one-tenth of country GDP. In terms&#13;
OECD city economy, accounting for almost 40 percent of                                              of population, European and Central Asian cities were the&#13;
value added.                                                                                        slowest growing in the world. In terms of employment and&#13;
                                                                                                    GDP, they grew slightly faster than their national economies&#13;
The average East Asian and Pacific city in the data set in 2012                                     in 2012.&#13;
was an upper-middle-income city with 5.5 million peopleâ&#128;&#148;&#13;
more than in any other regionâ&#128;&#148;and labor productivity of                                             The average city of the data set in the Middle East and&#13;
US$33,000 in value added per worker per year, second behind                                         North Africa was upper-middle income with 2.0 million&#13;
OECD cities. Job growth rates in East Asian and Pacific cities                                      people. Such a city had relatively high labor productivity, at&#13;
exceeded their national averages by 1.5 percent and output                                          US$30,500 in value added per worker per year, and a relative-&#13;
growth rates by 2.1 percent. Industry and mining dominated                                          ly high population growth rate. The average city in the Middle&#13;
the economy of the average city and accounted for over 35                                           East and North Africa played a significant role in its national&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 2.1	                  Industrial profile of the average city in each region, 2012&#13;
&#13;
Share of gross value added (%)                                                                      Share of city employment (%)&#13;
                                       Share of GVA (%)                                                                         Share of city employment&#13;
                                   0    10    20     30    40     50 Sector&#13;
                                                                      60 70 share&#13;
                                                                             80 90of 100&#13;
                                                                                     average city employment                          0   10    20    30     40   50    60    70   80      90 100&#13;
           East Asia and Pacific                                                                              East Asia and Pacific&#13;
                                                           East Asia and Pacific&#13;
   Middle East and North Africa                                                                        Middle East and North Africa&#13;
                                                   Middle East and North Africa&#13;
        Europe and Central Asia                                                                            Europe and Central Asia&#13;
                                                       Europe and Central Asia&#13;
Latin America and the Caribbean                                                                    Latin America and the Caribbean&#13;
                                             Latin America and the Caribbean&#13;
                     South Asia                                                                                         South Asia&#13;
                                                                       South Asia&#13;
            Sub-Saharan Africa                                                                                  Sub-Saharan Africa&#13;
                                                                Sub-Saharan Africa&#13;
                          OECD                                                                                               OECD&#13;
                                                                             OECD&#13;
                     Industry                Agriculture           High-end services                                  Industry                 Agriculture             High-end services&#13;
                                                           Industry     Agriculture    High-end services      Consumer services           Public sector&#13;
&#13;
Source: Oxford Economics Dataset&#13;
Note: OECD = Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                        9&#13;
&amp;#12;economy, accounting for 12 percent of total GDP. It also had         Global variation in the data set&#13;
a large public sectorâ&#128;&#148;smaller only than OECD citiesâ&#128;&#148;and a&#13;
comparatively small consumer sector.                                 The cities in this global sample vary greatly, and their diver-&#13;
                                                                     sity serves as a useful reminder that this paper analyzes 750&#13;
The average Latin American and Caribbean city in the data            heterogeneous units. Cities differ across many dimensions:&#13;
set was upper-middle income with 2.3 million inhabitants             size, economic vocation, geographic location, natural en-&#13;
and a relatively young demographic profile. Consumer ser-            dowments, income level, history, planning model, political&#13;
vices employed the largest share of workers, but industry and        system, and so on. Furthermore, each city strives to solve&#13;
high-end services accounted for the largest shares of value          dramatically different issues with different starting points.&#13;
added.                                                               A city in Europe and Central Asia may be trying to manage&#13;
                                                                     deindustrialization, whereas in South Asia or Sub-Saharan&#13;
In South Asia, the average city was lower-middle income with         Africa, a city may be struggling to integrate new migrants&#13;
2.7 million inhabitants. In a region with relatively well-de-        into the job market, social fabric, or built environment. In&#13;
veloped urban systems, the typical city accounted for only           OECD countries, a city may be preoccupied with attracting&#13;
1.2 percent of its national GDP. In productivity, workers still      talent through amenities or with rekindling fading entrepre-&#13;
lagged far behind their peers in all other regions, including        neurial zeal.&#13;
Sub-Saharan Africa. Labor productivity in the average South&#13;
Asian city stood at US$6,700 in value added per worker per           Figures 2.2 and 2.3 underscore this point. The largest city in&#13;
year.                                                                the data set, Tokyo (Japan), has 144 times the population of&#13;
                                                                     the smallest, Gaborone (Botswana). Even more starkly, the&#13;
Finally, the data setâ&#128;&#153;s typical city in Sub-Saharan Africa was       richest city in the data set, Basel (Switzerland), enjoys a GDP&#13;
lower-middle income with. 2.0 million people. The region             per capita that is an astonishing 384 times higher than that&#13;
itself experienced faster population growth than any other           of the poorest city, Kinshasa (Democratic Republic of Congo).&#13;
region. The average city in Sub-Saharan Africa was adding&#13;
jobs and increasing output at a significantly faster rate than       Nor are the cities different only across static measures. The&#13;
its country, and the typical cityâ&#128;&#153;s impact on national eco-          four panels of figure 2.3 show the maximum, minimum,&#13;
nomic performance mattered more in Sub-Saharan Africa                and mean city performance across four economic indicators&#13;
than elsewhere because the typical city accounted for over 15        for the period from 2000 to 2012. While in the United Arab&#13;
percent of its countryâ&#128;&#153;s GDP.                                        Emirates, Dubaiâ&#128;&#153;s population grew by 11.3 percent per year,&#13;
                                                                     in Latvia, Rigaâ&#128;&#153;s population fell by 1.5 percent. Putting the&#13;
                                                                     competitiveness imperative in stark relief, one notes that as&#13;
Figure 2.2 Spectrum of city starting points within the               average household disposable income grew by 13.7 percent&#13;
                                                                     per year in Guigang (China), it fell by 6.0 percent per year in&#13;
   Oxford Economics data set&#13;
                                                                     Yamoussoukro (Cameroon).&#13;
&#13;
                                                                     These disparities are not entirely driven by outliers. The&#13;
    People (millions)              GDP per capita (US$, thousands)&#13;
                                                                     difference between the average city in the top and bottom 10&#13;
    40                             120                               percent globally on these metrics ranged from 5.2 percent for&#13;
                        36.7                         108.2&#13;
                                                                     population growth to 13.7 percent for GDP growth. Popula-&#13;
    35&#13;
                                   100                               tion, employment, and living standards all shrank from 2000&#13;
    30                                                               to 2012 in the bottom 10th of the worldâ&#128;&#153;s cities analyzed&#13;
                                                                     here.&#13;
                                   80&#13;
    25&#13;
&#13;
    20                             60&#13;
&#13;
    15&#13;
                                   40&#13;
    10&#13;
                                    20   mean 17.1&#13;
      5    mean 3.2&#13;
            0.2                            0.3&#13;
      0                              0&#13;
          Minimun Maximun                Minimun Maximun&#13;
&#13;
Source: Oxford Economics Dataset&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
10&#13;
&amp;#12;Figure 2.3	           Measuring the disparities in city performance observed in the data set, 2000-2012&#13;
&#13;
          PANEL A                            PANEL B                      PANEL C                     PANEL D&#13;
 Average Annual Growth,             Average Annual Growth,       Average Annual Growth,       Average Annual Growth,&#13;
       Population                            Jobs                         GDP                 Household Disp. Income&#13;
Percent                            Percent                      Percent                     Percent&#13;
25                                  25                           25                          25&#13;
&#13;
20                                  20                           20                          20&#13;
&#13;
15                                  15                           15                          15&#13;
                                                                             23%&#13;
10                                  10                           10          gap             10&#13;
              12.8%                             17%                                                mean&#13;
  5            gap                   5          gap               5   mean&#13;
                                                                                              5           20%&#13;
      mean                               mean&#13;
                                                                                                          gap&#13;
  0                                  0                            0                           0&#13;
&#13;
 -5                                 -5                           -5                           -5&#13;
&#13;
-10                                -10                          -10                         -10&#13;
      Minimun Maximun                    Minimun Maximun              Minimun Maximun              Minimun Maximun&#13;
&#13;
Source: Oxford Economics Dataset&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                           11&#13;
&amp;#12;Comparing city and national economic                                 formed their national economies and peers. These cities are&#13;
performance                                                          of particular interest because of their particular capacity to&#13;
                                                                     achieve high growth rates no matter the characteristics of&#13;
At the country level, identifying outlier cities is the first step   their national economies.&#13;
in determining what differentiates the most competitive&#13;
cities within their peer group. The city profiles from table         Figure 2.4 compares the average difference between city&#13;
2.1 show that across regions the average city outperformed           and country employment growth each year over the 12-year&#13;
its country in terms of job growth from 2011 to 2012, and            period. Several pockets of over- and underperformance stand&#13;
except for the average city in Latin America and the Carib-          out. Cities performed much better than their national econo-&#13;
bean and the Middle East and North Africa, this metric also          mies in parts of West Africa centered on Nigeria, in East Af-&#13;
held for GDP growth. Certain individual cities far outper-           rica, in coastal and inland China, in parts of Bangladesh and&#13;
                                                                     India, and in portions of Southeast Asia. Cities in Europe;&#13;
&#13;
Figure 2.4	          Annual city employment growth rates relative to national economy, 2000â&#128;&#147;12 average&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Source: Oxford Economics Dataset&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 2.5	         Annual city GDP growth rates relative to national economy, 2000â&#128;&#147;12 average&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Source: Oxford Economics Dataset&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
12&#13;
&amp;#12;                                         the Russian Federation;              Table 2.2 lists the top 10 outperformers from each region&#13;
      Cities in Latin America            much of the United                   over a shorter periodâ&#128;&#148;from 2006 to 2012. The top 10 were&#13;
      and the Caribbean and              States; and portions of              determined by summing each cityâ&#128;&#153;s average annual employ-&#13;
                                         Australia, Latin Amer-               ment and GDP growth rates above the national average over&#13;
      the Middle East and&#13;
                                         ica, the Arab Republic               the same time period. The shorter period was chosen (a) to&#13;
      North Africa were less             of Egypt, Japan, South               reduce the number of economic cycles that the measurement&#13;
      likely to outperform their         Africa, and northeast                cut across and (b) because data before 2006 are unavailable&#13;
      national economies than            China underperformed                 for some cities. Chinese cities have been excluded to let other&#13;
      peers from other regions.          their national econo-                outperformers in East Asia and Pacific rise to the top. The&#13;
                                         miesâ&#128;&#148;in some cases,                  table shows that the vast majority of cities in South Asia and&#13;
                                         significantly so.                    Sub-Saharan Africa outperform their national economies.&#13;
                                                                              This outcome stands in stark contrast to the situation in&#13;
The output map (figure 2.5) tells a largely similar story, with               the OECD, where fewer than half of cities outperform their&#13;
a few exceptions: joining the underperformers were a number                   national economies in terms of GDP. Outperformers are&#13;
of cities in the Islamic Republic of Iran, the Philippines, and               relatively rarer in Latin America and the Caribbean and the&#13;
Turkey. This time cities in northeast China far outperformed                  Middle East and North Africa.&#13;
the country, and European cities did better in terms of GDP&#13;
as well.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table 2.2 Top 10 outperformers by region, ranked by combined average annual outperformance on output and&#13;
  jobs (2006â&#128;&#147;12)&#13;
&#13;
                    East Asia &amp; the   Europe &amp;           Latin America &amp;    Middle East &amp;                                            Sub-Saharan&#13;
 Rank               Pacific           Central Asia       the Caribbean      North Africa       OECD               South Asia         Africa&#13;
                    Nay Pyi Taw,      Makhachkala,       CancÃºn, Mexico     Sharjah, United    Austin, United     Pondicherry,       Onitsha, Nigeria&#13;
 1                  Myanmar           Russian Feder-                        Arab Emirates      States             India&#13;
                                      ation&#13;
                    Kota Kinabalu,    Sofia, Bulgaria    Santa Cruz,        Algiers, Algeria   Portland Oregon,   Patna, India       Enugu, Nigeria&#13;
 2&#13;
                    Malaysia                             Bolivia                               United States&#13;
&#13;
                    Vientiane, Lao    Tbilisi, Georgia   Saltillo, Mexico   Muscat, Oman       Aberdeen, Unit-    Tiruppur, India    Abuja, Nigeria&#13;
 3&#13;
                    PDR                                                                        ed Kingdom&#13;
&#13;
                    Mandalay,         Krasnodar, Rus-    Cochabamba,        Oran, Algeria      San Jose, Cali-    Surat, India       Benin City,&#13;
 4                  Myanmar           sian Federation    Bolivia                               fornia, United                        Nigeria&#13;
                                                                                               States&#13;
                    Yangon, Myan-     Kazan, Russian     Teresina, Brazil   Marrakesh,         Houston, Texas,    Ghaziabad, India   Abeokuta,&#13;
 5&#13;
                    mar               Federation                            Morocco            United States                         Nigeria&#13;
&#13;
                    Ujung Pandang,    Bucharest,         Campo Grande,      Riyadh, Saudi      Perth, Australia   Raipur, India      Ilorin, Nigeria&#13;
 6&#13;
                    Indonesia         Romania            Brazil             Arabia&#13;
&#13;
                    Hanoi, Vietnam    Chisinau, Mol-     San Luis Potosi,   Constantine,       Edmonton,          Hyderabad, India   Ogbomosho,&#13;
 7&#13;
                                      dova               Mexico             Algeria            Canada                                Nigeria&#13;
&#13;
                    Pekan Baru,       Yerevan, Ar-       Recife, Brazil     Abu Dhabi,         Salt Lake City,    Bangalore, India   Kano, Nigeria&#13;
 8                  Indonesia         menia                                 United Arab        United States&#13;
                                                                            Emirates&#13;
                    Ho Chi Minh       Penza, Russian     Curitiba, Brazil   Meknes, Mo-        Calgary, Canada    Vijayawada,        Ibadan, Nigeria&#13;
 9&#13;
                    City, Vietnam     Federation                            rocco                                 India&#13;
&#13;
                    Ulaanbaatar,      St. Petersburg,    Chihuahua,         Mosul, Iraq        San Antonio,       Coimbatore,        Aba, Nigeria&#13;
 10                 Mongolia          Russian Feder-     Mexico                                Texas, United      India&#13;
                                      ation                                                    States&#13;
 Number of aver-&#13;
 age annual GDP     40 out of 56      51 out of 71       53 out of 94       22 out of 46       75 out of 176      78 out of 88       63 out of 69&#13;
 outperformers&#13;
 Number of aver-&#13;
 age annual jobs    40 out of 56      50 out of 71       69 out of 94       35 out of 46       93 out of 176      71 out of 88       59 out of 69&#13;
 outperformers&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                      13&#13;
Source: Oxford Economics Dataset&#13;
&amp;#12;Productivity differentials across cities and                                               average in only one city&#13;
within countries                                                                           in the databaseâ&#128;&#148;large,        In a country with a&#13;
                                                                                           inland Chongqing. Out-        relatively mature urban&#13;
Worldwide, 70 percent of cities were more productive than                                  put per worker is nearly&#13;
                                                                                                                         system, such as the United&#13;
their countries as a whole in 2012 (measured as GVA per                                    six times the national&#13;
worker). Considerable variation can be found within coun-                                  average in Jilin (Jilin)      States, city productivity&#13;
tries, however. In a country with a mature urban system,                                   and Weihai (Shandong)         runs below the national&#13;
such as the United States, city productivity runs below the                                and approaches seven          level in nearly as many&#13;
national average in nearly as many cases (23 in this data set)                             times the national            cases as it runs above.&#13;
as it runs above (27). Output per worker in San Jose (Califor-                             average in Tangshan&#13;
nia), the most productive U.S. city, is more than twice that of                            (Hebei) and Maanshan&#13;
the least productive, Buffalo (New York), at over US$210,000                               (Anhui), where it rises above US$70,000 per year.&#13;
per worker compared with US$87,500. In rapidly developing&#13;
China, by contrast, output per worker is below the national&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 2.6: City versus country productivity levels, 2012&#13;
&#13;
a. All cities vs. all countries&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                       United States&#13;
 City GVA/Worker (US$, thousands)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                    China&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              Russian Federation&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                   Country GVA/Worker (US$, thousands)&#13;
&#13;
    b. Cities with less than US$50,000 GVA per worker&#13;
       vs. countries with less than US$25,000 country GVA per worker&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                            China&#13;
 City GVA/Worker (US$, thousands)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                  Russian Federation&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                               Indonesia                          Brazil                 Mexico&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      Colombia&#13;
                                      India&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                   Country GVA/Worker (US$, thousands)&#13;
Source: Oxford Economics Dataset&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    14&#13;
&amp;#12;The OE data show that although cities are typically the             Private sector job creation&#13;
productive engines of their national economies, many&#13;
exceptions exist. Large (and typically rural-based) natural         The private sector in the OE cities created 87.7 million jobs&#13;
resource sectors change the story in some countries: cities         over the six years from 2006 to 2012 (range chosen because&#13;
such as Sharjah (United Arab Emirates) and Jeddah, Mecca,           2006 is the first year for which all 750 cities report data).&#13;
and Medina (all in Saudi Arabia) register productivity levels       These cities accounted for 58 percent of all new private sector&#13;
only slightly above half the national value. City productivity      jobs created in their 140 countries taken together, despite&#13;
can lag in countries such as Indonesia and Nigeria, where           containing only one-quarter of total private employment.&#13;
economic development is progressing rapidly nationally but&#13;
unevenly across subnational regions. And, of course, not all        In absolute terms, Beijing and Chongqing (in China) and Ja-&#13;
cities power economic development at all times; a city such         karta (in Indonesia) created the most private sector jobs over&#13;
                                          as Buffalo, which         the period, Jakarta and Beijing each with nearly 2.9 million&#13;
                                          prospered in one era      and Chongqing with 2.3 million. China was home to 10 of the&#13;
    Individual city productivity          of industrial develop-    12 cities that created more than 1 million private sector jobs&#13;
    can lag in countries such             ment, may experience      each. Outside East Asia and Pacific, Lagos, Nigeria, saw the&#13;
    as Indonesia and Nigeria,             relative decline in the   greatest private sector job creation, with 1.5 million new pri-&#13;
    where economic develop-               next. Multiple such       vate jobs in six years, followed by SÃ£o Paulo, Brazil (950,000&#13;
    ment is progressing rapidly           forces appear to be       jobs); BogotÃ¡, Colombia (816,000 jobs); Lima, Peru (807,000);&#13;
                                          at work in Russia,        Dhaka, Bangladesh (766,000); and Dar es Salaam, Tanzania&#13;
    nationally but unevenly                                         (754,000). In Europe and Central Asia, Moscow, Russia, saw&#13;
                                          where only one-fifth of&#13;
    across subnational regions.           cities, led by Moscow     the greatest absolute increase in private sector jobs (617,000&#13;
                                          and Tyumen, produce       jobs), whereas Tokyo, Japan, led OECD countries (525,000&#13;
                                          greater output per        jobs). All together and in absolute terms, the 7 percent of cit-&#13;
worker than the national economy. Russia is, in fact, home to       ies where job creation was most voluminous created as many&#13;
four of the five cities with the lowest ratio of city to national   private sector jobs as the remaining 93 percent combined. For&#13;
productivity in the worldâ&#128;&#148;Penza, Orenburg, Makhachkala,             context, these cities were home to just over one-quarterâ&#128;&#148;27&#13;
and Barnaul.                                                        percentâ&#128;&#148;of total employment in the sample in 2005.&#13;
&#13;
Panel b of figure 2.6 takes a closer look at the distribution       In percentage terms, China claimed 39 of the 50 cities with&#13;
of city productivity levels within countries where GVA              the fastest average annual rates of private sector job growth,&#13;
per worker is less than US$25,000 annually. That national           which ranged from 17.0 percent in Hefei (Anhui) to 7.5&#13;
productivity in China still trails so far behind productivity       percent in Baotou (Inner Mongolia). Other cities in the top 50&#13;
in the countryâ&#128;&#153;s large cities betrays just how much urban-          were oil-rich city-states, such as Doha (Qatar) and Abu Dhabi&#13;
ization has coincided with productivity gains. Most cities in       and Sharjah (United Arab Emirates), as well as Myanmarâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
India are also more productive than the national economy,           newly created capital, Nay Pyi Taw. Six Nigerian cities, includ-&#13;
but the distribution is far more compressed: productivity in        ing Onitsha, Enugu,&#13;
                                          highest-ranking Delhi     and Abuja, joined the&#13;
                                          is only three-and-one-    top 50, as did Dar es         Developing countries may&#13;
    That national productivity            half times productivity   Salaam, Tanzania.&#13;
                                                                                                  be threatened by a process&#13;
    in China still trails so far          in lowest-ranking Va-     Santa Cruz (Bolivia)&#13;
                                                                                                  of premature deindustri-&#13;
    behind productivity in its            ranasi. In comparison,    posted the fastest pri-&#13;
    large cities betrays just             in Indonesia, Pekan       vate sector job growth        alization whereby man-&#13;
                                          Baru is more than five    in Latin America and          ufacturingâ&#128;&#153;s share of the&#13;
    how much more urbaniza-&#13;
                                          times as productive as    the Caribbean (5.8 per-       economy begins to decline&#13;
    tion the country stands to            Yogyakarta (and seven     cent), Tbilisi (Georgia)      at much lower income levels&#13;
    undergo.                              times as productive as    the fastest in Europe&#13;
                                                                                                  than ever before.&#13;
                                          Samarinda, an outlier).   and Central Asia (5.6&#13;
                                          Brazil and Mexico ex-     percent), Pondicherry&#13;
hibit a more balanced distribution of cities above and below        (India) the fastest in&#13;
the national average. In Mexico, Monterrey stands out with          South Asia (5.0 percent), and Perth (Australia) the fastest in&#13;
US$39,800 GVA per worker, ahead of the capital, Mexico City         OECD countries (3.2 percent). All together and in relative&#13;
(US$30,800), and more than double the national average of           terms, the 16 percent of cities that grew jobs the fastest over&#13;
US$23,800. Colombia, one of the recent pastâ&#128;&#153;s development           the period created as many private sector jobs as the bottom&#13;
success stories, boasts only two cities more productive than        84 percent combined. For context, these cities were home to&#13;
the national economy as a whole (US$16,300 GVA per work-            only 14 percent of total sample employment in 2005.&#13;
er): BogotÃ¡ and Bucaramanga.&#13;
                                                                    Mainly as a result of the recession and Euro Area crisis, pri-&#13;
                                                                    vate sector employment declined across half of OECD cities&#13;
                                                                    over the period. The largest absolute declines took place in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                     15&#13;
&amp;#12;U.S. cities hit hard by the housing crisis, such as Los Angeles     Industrial sector job creation&#13;
(California), Phoenix (Arizona), and Riverside (California);&#13;
in cities of struggling Euro Area economies, such as Athens         First, a definitional note: OE groups the mining and ex-&#13;
(Greece), Dublin (Ireland), Lisbon (Portugal), and Madrid           traction, manufacturing, utilities, and construction indus-&#13;
and Barcelona (Spain); and in industrial cities such as Osaka       tries together into its â&#128;&#156;industrialâ&#128;&#157; sector aggregate, and it&#13;
(Japan), Birmingham (United Kingdom), and Chicago (United           does not break out data for any of these individual subsec-&#13;
States). In percentage terms, private sector employment fell        tors. We refer to the sector as the industrial or manufacturing&#13;
fastest in struggling Euro Area and in U.S. Sun Belt cities.        sector, keeping in mind that the measure itself is broader and&#13;
                                                                    that its composition likely varies across cities.&#13;
When their rates of private sector job growth are compared&#13;
to the national rate, Chinese cities again come out on top.         We take a special look at industry because of manufacturingâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
Attesting to the incredible pace and scale of urbanization in       historical role as a ladder for economic development. The ex-&#13;
the country, nationwide the number of private sector jobs           port-led growth model that has propelled so many countries&#13;
grew by only 0.2 percent a year from 2006 to 2012â&#128;&#148;a rate            up the income ladder is at its core a labor-intensive, manufac-&#13;
that 138 of the 150 Chinese cities in the dataset beat easily.      turing-led growth model, in which countries take advantage&#13;
Tbilisi (Georgia), Kumasi (Ghana), Pekan Baru (Indonesia),          of their low initial labor costs (the primary variable cost in&#13;
Onitsha (Nigeria), and Dar es Salaam (Tanzania) also regis-         low-end manufacturing) to attract export-oriented produc-&#13;
tered private sector job growth rates far above (5.0 percent or     tion capital. The heavily urbanized sector absorbs population&#13;
higher) their countries.                                            from the hinterlands, and this steady flow of labor from the&#13;
                                                                    countryside keeps wages low. Eventually this process slows&#13;
Boosting city competitiveness has the potential to drastical-       as urbanization rates taper off and wages begin to rise, but at&#13;
ly accelerate job creation globally. Cities perform unequally       that point companies have typically spent years learning and&#13;
within regions. For example, cities in the top quartile of          building the capacity to move to higher-value-added activi-&#13;
Sub-Saharan African cities created jobs 4.5 percentage points       ties. In this way, industrialization and urbanization unleash a&#13;
faster than did their peers in the region. In each of the other     positive development spiral.&#13;
regions, the gap between the top quarter and the rest stood at&#13;
3.0 percentage points or more in 2012. If all cities in a region    Development economist Dani Rodrik (Rodrik, D. (2015). Pre-&#13;
grew at least as fast as the average city in the top quartile,      mature Deindustrialization (No. w20935). National Bureau&#13;
however, 18.9 million extra jobsâ&#128;&#148;on top of the 13.4 million         of Economic Research), however, raises the disturbing specter&#13;
actually witnessedâ&#128;&#148;would have been created in 2012 alone.           that the export-led growth model may have run its course.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 2.7 Industrial sector rates of job growth by                 Figure 2.8 Industrial sector rates of job growth by&#13;
   city income bracket, 2001â&#128;&#147;12                                        city specialization, 2001â&#128;&#147;12&#13;
&#13;
Percent                                                             Percent&#13;
10                                                                  10&#13;
&#13;
 8                                                                   8&#13;
                           Low-income cities&#13;
 6                                                                   6        Consumer services cities&#13;
                                      Lower-middle-income cities                                         Industrial cities&#13;
 4                                                                   4&#13;
&#13;
 2                                                                   2&#13;
     Upper-middle-income&#13;
     cities&#13;
 0                                                                   0&#13;
&#13;
-2                                                                  -2&#13;
&#13;
-4                                                                  -4&#13;
                                                                                                                     High-end services cities&#13;
-6                                                                  -6&#13;
                                               High-income cities&#13;
-8                                                                  -8&#13;
&#13;
Source: Oxford Economics Dataset                                    Source: Oxford Economics Dataset&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
16&#13;
&amp;#12;Several converging trends concern him. First, manufactur-           If we compare cities by region, those in the Middle East and&#13;
ing today is more capital- and skill-intensive than it used         North Africa typically post the fastest industrial sector job&#13;
to be and is growing less labor-intensive even at lower ends        growth rates, a finding that is presumably tied to the price of&#13;
of the value chain as rote automation technologies become           oil and the natural resources component of the aggregate sec-&#13;
less expensive. Second, the rapid growth in international           tor. Cities in Sub-Saharan Africa began the study period with&#13;
logistics has segmented supply chains to an extraordinary           high growth rates averaging 5.8 percent from 2001 to 2004&#13;
degree, thereby enabling companies to separate discrete tasks       before falling toward zero in 2009 and rising back to about&#13;
across locations rather than move the entire processâ&#128;&#148;from           2.0 percent in 2012. South Asian cities have seen the sectorâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
which countries could learnâ&#128;&#148;as in previous waves of moving          job growth rate decline more or less steadily from over 5.0&#13;
manufacture offshore. High-value-added activities, mean-            percent early in the decade to 2.0 percent in 2012, while cities&#13;
while, remain in the developed world. Third, global financial       in Europe and Central Asia and especially OECD cities have&#13;
markets encourage and enable â&#128;&#156;plug in, plug outâ&#128;&#157; behavior           struggled to maintain positive growth rates throughout the&#13;
whereby companies pick up and move on to the next, cheaper,         period.&#13;
location at the slightest change in cost calculus. In such a&#13;
world, any country that begins to move up the value chain           Tradable sector job creation&#13;
will have the proverbial rug pulled out from under it as the&#13;
foreign capital supporting its industrial base departs swiftly.     Strong tradable sectors characterize competitive cities. In&#13;
Compounding the problem is Rodrikâ&#128;&#153;s fourth concern: that            the OE data, the tradable sector can broadly be defined as the&#13;
Chinaâ&#128;&#153;s unprecedented scale crowded other countries off the         industrial sector (manufacturing, mining, and construction);&#13;
development ladder just when they could have gotten ahead           the transportation and warehousing, communications, and&#13;
of these dynamics.                                                  information sectors; and the financial and business services&#13;
                                                                    sectors combined. In the 10 percent of cities in which GDP&#13;
As a consequence, goes the hypothesis, developing countries         per capita grew fastest from 2005 to 2012, tradable sector&#13;
may be threatened by a process of premature deindustrializa-        employment growth outstripped non-traded sector employ-&#13;
tion whereby manufacturingâ&#128;&#153;s share of the economy begins            ment growth by 2.5 percent on average annually: 6.2 percent&#13;
to decline at much lower income levels than ever before.            growth compared with 3.7 percent growth. By contrast, in&#13;
Whether traded services will be able to generate the surplus,       the remaining 90 percent of cities, tradable and non-tradable&#13;
productivity gains, and investment capital needed to drive          industries grew at effectively the same rate: respectively 2.4&#13;
the economic growth as manufacturing historically has done          percent and 2.3 percent on average annually. Thus, robust&#13;
remains to be seen.                                                 tradable sector growth characterizes competitive cities and&#13;
                                                                    appears to be a prerequisite for rapid growth in the economy&#13;
The data presented in figure 2.7 lend tentative support to          as a whole.&#13;
the deindustrialization hypothesis. At the beginning of the&#13;
2000s, cities in low-income countries registered average            Faster growth in the traded sector goes hand in hand with&#13;
industrial sector job growth rates of 6.5 percent per year          growth in the non-traded sector. The 10 percent of cities in&#13;
(recall, however, that the sector encompasses manufactur-           which traded sector employment grew fastest from 2005 to&#13;
ing plus construction, mining, and natural resources). After        2012 average 9.8 percent annual job growth in the sector,&#13;
tumbling severely from 2005 to 2007 before climbing back,           6.6 percent outside the sector (that is, the non-traded sector),&#13;
the sectorâ&#128;&#153;s growth rate in low-income cities appears to have       and 8.1 percent economy-wide. By contrast, the bottom 90&#13;
converged with that of lower-middle-income and upper-mid-           percent of cities average 2.0 percent annual job growth in&#13;
dle-income cities at just above 2.0 percent annually. If such       each sector respectively and citywide. Low- and middle-in-&#13;
low job growth rates persist, the sector will indeed have lost      come cities hoping to use exports to move up the value chain&#13;
its traditional role as a sponge for excess labor, an engine of     and develop their economies are not the only places where&#13;
productivity, and a ladder of development.                          tradable sector growth differentiates competitive cities from&#13;
                                                                    their peers. Vibrancy in the traded sector appears to benefit&#13;
The data also show that, globally, industrial job growth rates      higher-income cities too: in cities with a GDP per capita above&#13;
have held up slightly better in cities where manufacturing          US$20,000, annual job growth averaged only 0.9 percent.&#13;
is the dominant sector, averaging 3.9 percent from 2001             However, the 10 percent of cities experiencing the fastest job&#13;
to 2003 and 2.9 percent from 2010 to 2012 (figure 2.8). In          growth in the traded sector achieved, on average, 5.7 percent&#13;
comparison, industrial sector job growth rates are low in           annual growth in the traded sector and 5.3 percent growth&#13;
cities dominated by high-end services, suggesting that the          economy-wide. That is more than a fivefold increase in annual&#13;
two sectors may have competing needs and accordingly that           growth rates in what are typically mature economies.&#13;
a natural sorting of activities occurs into cities specialized in&#13;
one sector or the other. Primary cities narrowly outperform&#13;
secondary cities globally for industrial sector job growth, but&#13;
the two growth rates tend to move together.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                      17&#13;
&amp;#12;Foreign direct investment                                           FDI is spreading to more cities, but it remains highly con-&#13;
                                                                    centrated. In 2003, the top 10 percent of city destinations&#13;
Foreign direct investment is frequently thought to both             captured 71 percent of all FDI projects, 77 percent of all FDI&#13;
signal and reinforce city competitiveness. Multinationals can       jobs, and 78 percent of all FDI expenditures. By 2012, those&#13;
typically select from a world of locations for their operations     numbers had fallen to 67 percent, 67 percent, and 70 percent,&#13;
and, therefore, tend to locate in cities that offer the right mix   respectively. By comparison, the top 10 percent of cities con-&#13;
of quality inputs, knowledge assets, infrastructure, supply         centrated only 56 percent of GDP.&#13;
chains, and market access they need to thriveâ&#128;&#148;in short,&#13;
competitive cities. At the same time, because of their pre-         In absolute terms, the top destinations for FDI over the&#13;
sumptive superior technology, management know-how, mar-             period were the expected global centers of business, finance,&#13;
keting prowess, and other proprietary assets, multinationals        or production; trade entrepÃ´ts; and locales that have made&#13;
are thought to offer special promise for locales wishing to         FDI a pivotal part of their development model. Table 2.3 lists&#13;
upgrade their local economies and accelerate development.           the top 10 destinations for FDI in terms of cumulative capital&#13;
However, the evidence is mixed on the extent to which pro-          expenditure from 2003 to 2012.&#13;
ductivity spillovers and technology transfer truly materialize&#13;
from FDI and when.6 Nevertheless, because cities are eager          Controlling for GDP yields a very different list of places where&#13;
to attract FDI and are learning how to better integrate it into     FDI factors most significantly in the local economy. Dividing&#13;
their local economies, we examine its geography here.               the total amount of FDI received over the 10-year period by&#13;
                                                                    GDP in the average year reveals citiesâ&#128;&#148;some expected, some&#13;
To examine FDI performance at the city level, we were able          unexpectedâ&#128;&#148;that punch well above their weight in terms&#13;
to obtain data for 673 of our 750 cities from fDi Markets, a        of FDI attraction. Table 2.4 lists the top 10 locales on this&#13;
proprietary database maintained by the Financial Times that         measure. Abuja (Nigeria) ranks first, drawing in more than&#13;
aggregates data from press releases and other sources about         a US$1 billion less FDI than its larger compatriot, Lagos,&#13;
announced green field investments. The database neither             but over a much smaller denominator. Factory Asia features&#13;
claims to achieve universal coverage nor tracks the fate of         prominently; cities from East Asia and Pacific populate nearly&#13;
investments over time to revise its estimates. Sometimes an         half the table. Tangier (Morocco) likely combines strong local&#13;
announcement contains too little information for a project to       fundamentals with relative stability and proximity to the&#13;
be assigned to a city. In other cases, fDi Markets must impute      large European market to rise to the top of the list. Among&#13;
investment details using proprietary methods. Its cities may        the better-known case studies in globalization, only Indian&#13;
not always coincide with the boundaries of our OE cities            cities, such as Hyderabad and Bangalore, and Vietnamese&#13;
either. For these reasons, the database is best regarded as a       cities, such as Da Nang, Hanoi, and Hai Phong register here.&#13;
good-quality but not comprehensive record of FDI announce-&#13;
ments.                                                              FDI has its largest influence in market towns and production&#13;
                                                                    centers. East Asia and Pacific, South Asia, and Sub-Saharan&#13;
The three metrics contained in the databaseâ&#128;&#148;number of               Africa each contain 15 cities (or 22 percent of cities) in the&#13;
projects, associated capital expenditure, and associated            top 10 percent of all cities on this measure (figure 2.9, panel&#13;
jobsâ&#128;&#148;are flow variables based on new announcements each             a). In contrast, the OECD is home to only one city with such&#13;
year. The data are therefore lumpy, subject to volatility, and      an FDI-oriented economy, WrocÅ&#130;aw (Poland). Services hubs in&#13;
highly cyclical. For that reason, much of the following analy-      general constituted only 6 percent of the top echelon of per-&#13;
sis looks at city FDI performance aggregated over the entire        formers; production centers, conversely, constituted nearly&#13;
period for which data were available (2003â&#128;&#147;12), because             half (figure 2.9, panel b). Even on this measure, however, FDI&#13;
city competitiveness should transcend economic cycles. The          remains concentrated: the average city in the top 10 percent&#13;
downside of this approach is that the world looked very             on this measure received over 11 times more FDI per dollar of&#13;
different in 2012 than it did in 2003â&#128;&#148;the dramatic fall of          GDP than the average city in the bottom 90 percent.&#13;
Cairo (Egypt) from the investor interest league tables being&#13;
a case in pointâ&#128;&#148;and the method accordingly sacrifices some          The economic development potential of FDI should not be&#13;
recency.                                                            overstated, however. In fact, in the average city that received&#13;
                                                                    any FDI at all in 2012, foreign investors created only 1,400&#13;
                                                                    jobs directly. That represented 0.1 percent of the average cityâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
                                                                    employment base, or only a small fraction of the 2.0 percent&#13;
                                                                    net job growth that occurred on average in these cities. The&#13;
                                                                    truth remains that the majority of jobs, in every city, are still&#13;
                                                                    created by local, incumbent firms.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
18&#13;
&amp;#12;Table 2.3 Top 10 cities for FDI capital expenditures (cumulative 2003â&#128;&#147;12)&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                       FDI jobs,      FDI projects,      FDI capital expenditures,&#13;
 Rank     City         Country          Region                   Typology              2003â&#128;&#147;12         2003â&#128;&#147;12           2003â&#128;&#147;12 (US$, millions)&#13;
 1        Shanghai     China            East Asia and Pacific    Production center      469,901                2,992                        157,653&#13;
 2        Singapore Singapore           East Asia and Pacific    Services hub           251,785                2,614                        125,467&#13;
&#13;
 3        Beijing      China            East Asia and Pacific    Production center      221,664                1,510                         76,084&#13;
                                        Organisation for Eco-&#13;
                       United&#13;
 4        London                        nomic Cooperation        Services hub           100,789                2,346                         72,827&#13;
                       Kingdom&#13;
                                        and Development&#13;
                       United Arab      Middle East and&#13;
 5        Dubai                                                  Services hub           167,227                1,988                         63,614&#13;
                       Emirates         North Africa&#13;
          Hong&#13;
 6        Kong         China            East Asia and Pacific    Services hub           104,261                1,666                         48,391&#13;
          SAR&#13;
                       Egypt, Arab      Middle East and&#13;
 7        Cairo                                                  Production center       52,054                 210                          40,268&#13;
                       Rep.             North Africa&#13;
          Guang-&#13;
 8                     China            East Asia and Pacific    Production center      127,854                 528                          38,534&#13;
          zhou&#13;
 9        Bangalore India               South Asia               Production center      254,815                1,075                         38,315&#13;
          Suzhou,&#13;
 10                    China            East Asia and Pacific    Services hub           150,716                 520                          34,933&#13;
          Jiangsu&#13;
&#13;
Source: fDi Markets, Financial Times&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table 2.4	            Top 10 cities for FDI inflows controlling for GDP (cumulative FDI 2003â&#128;&#147;12)&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                         FDI    FDI capital expen-   FDI capital expen-&#13;
                                                                                      FDI jobs      projects     ditures 2003â&#128;&#147;12      ditures / average&#13;
 Rank     City          Country        Region                   Typology             2003â&#128;&#147;12       2003â&#128;&#147;12         (US$, millions)           GDP (US$)&#13;
 1        Abuja         Nigeria        Sub-Saharan Africa       Market town           12,744             16                 4,393                    8.21&#13;
&#13;
 2        Da Nang       Vietnam        East Asia and Pacific    Market town           22,328             49                 3,901                    4.09&#13;
&#13;
 3        Ujung         Indonesia      East Asia and Pacific    Market town             3,532             8                 7,249                    3.76&#13;
          Pandang&#13;
 4        Phnom         Cambodia       East Asia and Pacific    Market town           15,065             96                 4,820                    3.29&#13;
          Penh&#13;
 5        Tangier       Morocco        Middle East and          Production center      27,219            61                 5,694                    2.92&#13;
                                       North Africa&#13;
 6        Hyder-        India          South Asia               Market town          136,323            431               21,428                     2.46&#13;
          abad&#13;
 7        Bangalore     India          South Asia               Production center    254,815          1,075               38,315                     2.37&#13;
&#13;
 8        Vientiane     Lao PDR        East Asia and Pacific    Market town             3,277            29                 1,621                    2.32&#13;
&#13;
 9        Hanoi         Vietnam        East Asia and Pacific    Market town           83,940           346                18,442                     2.02&#13;
&#13;
 10       Hai Phong Vietnam            East Asia and Pacific    Market town           31,874             57                 4,279                    1.95&#13;
&#13;
Source: fDi Markets, Financial Times&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                        19&#13;
&amp;#12;Figure 2.9 Distribution of the top 10 percent of cities in terms of FDI, controlled for GDP&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
By region                                                                           By city economic structure&#13;
                                                                          %                                                                       %&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Source: fDi Markets, Financial Times&#13;
Note: See the discussion under industry pathways in section 3 of this paper for an explanation of this typology.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
3. Development Pathways: How Do                                                     Income brackets may be&#13;
City Economies Evolve over Time?                                                    useful for grouping cities          The 46 cities in which&#13;
                                                                                    according to their stage of         GDP per capita fell&#13;
This work stream hypothesizes development pathways fol-                             development, as is common-&#13;
                                                                                    ly done for countries, but&#13;
                                                                                                                        over the period provide&#13;
lowed by cities and tests whether groupings of cities based on&#13;
                                                                                    such brackets are static in         a cautionary reminder&#13;
characteristics such as population size, region of the world,&#13;
stage of development, or industry specialization could be use-                      nature, and the spectrum it-        that development is&#13;
ful in diagnosing opportunities and constraints. Three path-                        self is discontinuous: a US$1       neither guaranteed&#13;
ways based on the following characteristics were used: (a) city                     increase in GDP per capita          nor a process of steady&#13;
income level, hypothesizing that economic development is                            could result in a cityâ&#128;&#153;s reclas-    advancement.&#13;
a linear process through which cities move from low to high                         sification to a higher state&#13;
income; (b) industry specialization, hypothesizing that cities,                     of development. For this&#13;
as they develop, would first industrialize and then grow to                         reason, our analysis focuses&#13;
specialize in high-end service industries; and (c) primacy or                       on the idea of development trajectories, classifying cities into&#13;
population size within a national context, hypothesizing that                       groups on the basis of their annual average GDP per capita&#13;
a cityâ&#128;&#153;s position within its national urban system should, all                      growth rates over the 12-year period in the OE data set. The&#13;
else equal, remain stable as both develop.                                          characteristics of cities growing at roughly similar ratesâ&#128;&#148;&#13;
                                                                                    that is, on roughly similar trajectoriesâ&#128;&#148;can then be studied&#13;
Income pathway                                                                      for similarities or differences.&#13;
&#13;
 The most important development pathway for cities is                               To conduct this analysis, we divided the 750 cities in the OE&#13;
arguably the progression from low-income to lower-middle,                           data set into five groups according to the rates of GDP per&#13;
upper-middle, and finally high-income status. This pathway                          capita growth registered over the period. At the top was a&#13;
is important because GDP per capita is still the most widely                        group of 135 cities that achieved GDP per capita growth rates&#13;
accepted indicator of welfare and human development avail-                          above 10.0 percent on average each yearâ&#128;&#148;astonishing rates&#13;
able.                                                                               of economic development. Below them was another group of&#13;
                                                                                    133 cities that were on a slightly less rapid but still impressive&#13;
The income pathway itself needs very little description: if we                      trajectory, with annual average GDP per capita growth rates&#13;
assume that cities strive to achieve ever higher levels of GDP                      between 5.0 and 10.0 percent. In the middle was a cohort of&#13;
per capita for their residentsâ&#128;&#148;again, a proxy for citizen wel-                      229 cities that achieved steady average annual advances in&#13;
fare and prosperityâ&#128;&#148;then the relevant pathway is a simple                           GDP per capita of between 2.0 and 5.0 percent. Below that&#13;
linear progression from a lower-income status to a higher-in-                       was a group of 207 cities that registered only modest but still&#13;
come status.                                                                        positive improvements in GDP per capita with growth rates&#13;
                                                                                    below 2.0 percent. Finally, GDP per capita fell in 46 cities in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
20&#13;
&amp;#12;     the sample set over the period. These cities, which had a nega-            and three Peruvian citiesâ&#128;&#148;Arequipa, Lima, and Trujilloâ&#128;&#148;&#13;
     tive annual average growth rate, provide a cautionary remind-              represented Latin America and the Caribbean. Cities from all&#13;
     er that city developmentâ&#128;&#148;at least as measured by output per                across Europe and Central Asia landed in this group: Yerevan&#13;
     workerâ&#128;&#148;is not always unidirectional.                                       (Armenia), Sofia (Bulgaria), Riga (Latvia), Chisinau (Mol-&#13;
                                                                                dova), St. Petersburg and Vladivostok (Russia), Dushanbe&#13;
     The following subsections examine the cities in each group by              (Tajikistan), Tashkent (Uzbekistan). No OECD cities passed&#13;
     region, income level in 2000, and industrial profile in 2000.              the 5.0 percent threshold, however.&#13;
&#13;
     City GDP per capita growth by region                                       In the middle group of citiesâ&#128;&#148;those achieving 2.0 to 5.0 per-&#13;
                                                                                cent GDP per capita growth on average annuallyâ&#128;&#148;we find the&#13;
     Powered almost exclusively by Chinaâ&#128;&#153;s rise, nearly all cities              first OECD cities, a large contingent from Latin America and&#13;
     that achieved greater than 10 percent annual average GDP                   the Caribbean, and shrinking numbers from the fast-devel-&#13;
     per capita growth from 2000 to 2012 could be found in East                 oping regions of East Asia and Pacific and South Asia. In gen-&#13;
     Asia and Pacific (figure 3.1). The lone city from outside the re-          eral, however, representation in this group was fairly broad&#13;
     gion was Baku (Azerbaijan), where GDP per capita increased                 based across regions and countries. The OECD cities encom-&#13;
     by 10.6 percent annually.                                                  passed a broad mix: resource-intensive Perth (Australia) and&#13;
                                                                                Aberdeen (United Kingdom); high-tech Portland Oregon and&#13;
     Indian cities constituted the largest national bloc in the                 San Jose (both in the United States); and Brisbane (Australia)&#13;
     second-fastest group of developers. Several East Asian and                 and Quebec (Canada) in the most developed countries. The&#13;
     Pacific cities outside China joined this group as well, includ-            Republic of Koreaâ&#128;&#153;s cities, Polandâ&#128;&#153;s cities, and other strongly&#13;
     ing Vientiane (Lao Peopleâ&#128;&#153;s Democratic Republic); Ulaan-                   performing cities in Eastern Europe, such as Prague (Czech&#13;
     baatar (Mongolia); and multiple cities in Indonesia, Malaysia,             Republic), Talinn (Estonia), and Bratislava (Slovak Republic),&#13;
     and Vietnam. Nigerian cities dominated the contingent from                 completed the group. Several Russian cities and most Turkish&#13;
     Sub-Saharan Africa but were joined by Huambo and Luanda                    cities rank in this middle group and are joined by Tirana (Al-&#13;
     (Angola), Nâ&#128;&#153;Djamena (Chad), and Addis Ababa (Ethiopia)â&#128;&#148;                    bania), Sarajevo (Bosnia and Herzegovina), Zagreb (Croatia),&#13;
     three of the latter being national capitals. Marrakesh and                 and Belgrade (Serbia) in the Balkans; Astana (Kazakhstan)&#13;
     Meknes (Morocco) both made it into this group from the                     and Bishkek (Kyrgyz Republic) in Central Asia; and Dniprop-&#13;
     Middle East and North Africa, and Panama City (Panama)                     etrovsk, Kharkov, and Odessa (all in Ukraine). Wealthy Hong&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 3.1	            Annual average GDP per capita growth rates by region for 750 cities, 2000â&#128;&#147;12&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Source: Oxford Economics Dataset&#13;
Note: If data were not available for 2000, the first available year was used.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                 21&#13;
&amp;#12;Kong SAR, China, and Singapore joined peers from across           joined too. More troubling were the 12 cities from Sub-Saha-&#13;
East Asia and Pacific.                                            ran Africa in which development retrogressed on this mea-&#13;
                                                                  sure. These struggling cities included YaoundÃ© (Cameroon),&#13;
The OECD contingent balloons in the bracket from 0.0 to 2.0       Bangui (Central African Republic), Abidjan (CÃ´te dâ&#128;&#153;Ivoire),&#13;
percent annual average growth. Laggards from other regions        Bamako (Mali), Niamey (Niger), Port Harcourt (Nigeria), and&#13;
without the luxury of already high levels of GDP per capita       LomÃ© (Togo). In the Middle East and North Africa, Aden and&#13;
include Samarinda (Indonesia) and Kuching (Malaysia) from         Sanaa (both in the Republic of Yemen) were accompaniedâ&#128;&#148;&#13;
East Asia and Pacific, Srinagar (India) and Kathmandu (Ne-        probably through a quirk of the dataâ&#128;&#148;by oil-rich United&#13;
pal) from South Asia, and Skopje (former Yugoslav Republic        Arab Emirates cities Abu Dhabi, Dubai, and Sharjah as well as&#13;
of Macedonia) and several Ukrainian cities from Europe            Kuwait City (Kuwait), where the shortcomings of our GDP-&#13;
and Central Asia. Politically and economically struggling         based measure become apparent. Unsurprisingly Port-au-&#13;
Egypt populates most of the contingent from the Middle            Prince (Haiti)â&#128;&#148;still reeling from the earthquake and a larger&#13;
East and North Africa, alongside Mosul (Iraq), Casablanca         institutional breakdownâ&#128;&#148;landed here, too. SÃ£o JosÃ© dos&#13;
(Morocco), and Sfax (Tunisia) as well as three Iranian cities.    Campos in Brazil and Tampico and Tijuana from Mexico also&#13;
Several cities of Sub-Saharan Africa remained mired here          registered negative GDP per capita growth over the period.&#13;
with near-stagnant development rates, including Cotonou&#13;
(Benin), Brazzaville (Republic of Congo), Banjul (The Gambia),    A few interesting patterns emerge to summarize. Nearly&#13;
Conakry (Guineau), Nairobi (Kenya), Dakar (Senegal), and          every East Asian and Pacific city managed to post annual&#13;
Harare (Zimbabwe). South Africaâ&#128;&#153;s cities joined them. The         average GDP per capita growth rates over 2.0 percentâ&#128;&#148;in&#13;
second-largest contingent in this group comes from Latin          most cases well over. Nearly all cities of South Asia and of&#13;
America and the Caribbean, where many Brazilian and Mex-          Europe and Central Asia, for their part, fell between 2.0 and&#13;
ican cities eked out growth alongside numerous other cities       10.0 percent annual average growth. Cities of Sub-Saharan&#13;
spread throughout the region.                                     Africa appeared up and down the ranks of the distributionâ&#128;&#148;&#13;
                                                                  too many too low, given their relatively low starting levels of&#13;
At the bottom of the distribution are 46 cities in which GDP      development. Cities of Latin America and the Caribbean and&#13;
per capita actually fell over the 12-year period studied. The     of the Middle East and North Africa found company in each&#13;
bulk of these cities could be found in the OECD and were          other in most brackets, whereas OECD citiesâ&#128;&#148;in large part&#13;
badly hit by the 2009 financial crisis in Greece, Italy, Portu-   because of high starting levels of GDP per capitaâ&#128;&#148;populated&#13;
gal, Spain, and the United States. The Hague (Netherlands)        the lower half of the distribution.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
22&#13;
&amp;#12;City GDP per capita growth by region, controlling                         The cities of the Middle East and North Africa appeared&#13;
for country effects                                                       remarkably less vibrant by contrast. GDP per capita grew&#13;
                                                                          more slowly than it did at the national level in 70 percent&#13;
Disentangling city GDP per capita growth from country GDP                 of the regionâ&#128;&#153;s citiesâ&#128;&#148;an illuminating finding in a socially&#13;
per capita growth enables us to identify the outlier cities               unstable region. Marrakesh stands apart with an annual&#13;
whose rapid development trajectory stands apart against                   average GDP per capita growth 3.0 percentage points above&#13;
backdrops of national economic growth or stagnation.                      that of Morocco. It is followed by Abu Dhabi and Sharjah in&#13;
                                                                          the United Arab Emirates and then Constantine in Algeria.&#13;
As figure 3.2 shows, in East Asia and Pacific, nearly 90 per-             In Latin America and the Caribbean, the OECD group, and&#13;
cent of cities experienced faster GDP per capita growth than              South Asia, GDP per capita increased slower than it did na-&#13;
their national economies. Moreover, in almost half of East                tionally in a majority of cities. In South Asia, the Indian cities&#13;
Asian and Pacific cities GDP per capita rose annually above               of Surat and Varanasi both achieved GDP per capita growth&#13;
national rates by more than 2.0 percentage points on aver-                rates more than 2.0 percentage points higher than that of&#13;
ageâ&#128;&#148;a remarkable testament to the wealth-generating power                 India itself.&#13;
of cities. Elsewhere in the world, only in Europe and Central&#13;
Asia did a majority of cities similarly outpace their national&#13;
economies on this measure. In Sub-Saharan Africa, as many&#13;
cities outpaced their national economies in terms of GDP per&#13;
capita growth as fell behind.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 3.2 Share of cities over-performing or underperforming their national economies in terms of average&#13;
   annual GDP per capita growth, by region, 2000â&#128;&#147;12&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
               Overperforming by &gt; 2%     Overperforming by &lt; 2%   Underperforming by &gt; -2%   Underperforming by &lt; -2%&#13;
&#13;
                                          0	10	20	30	40	50	60	70	80	90	100                                                   Percent&#13;
&#13;
                East Asia and Pacific&#13;
            Europe and Central Asia&#13;
                  Sub-Saharan Africa&#13;
 Latin America and the Caribbean&#13;
                                   OECD&#13;
                            South Asia&#13;
      Middle East and North Africa&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Source: Oxford Economics Dataset&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                             23&#13;
&amp;#12;  City GDP per capita growth by income level                                    industrialization begins. More clearly, though, the finding&#13;
                                                                                stands as a reminder that Chinaâ&#128;&#148;home to nearly every city&#13;
  As alluded to in the previous section and throughout this                     posting GDP per capita growth over 10.0 percentâ&#128;&#148;contains&#13;
  technical note, a cityâ&#128;&#153;s starting point goes a long way in                    cities at all stages of development.&#13;
  explaining its economic performance vis-Ã -vis other cities&#13;
  globally. The poorer a city is, the higher its potential growth               Low-income cities do account for the largest share of cities in&#13;
  rate tends to be; the richer a city is, the lower its potential               the second-fastest growth group, with Indian and Nigerian&#13;
  growth rate will be. Figure 3.3 supports that rule broadly but                cities well represented. Three high-income cities posted very&#13;
  shows that exceptions do exist.                                               high average annual growth rates as well: Macao SAR (China),&#13;
                                                                                Almaty (Kazakhstan), and Perm (Russia).&#13;
  For this exercise, cities were slotted into income brackets&#13;
  on the basis of their GDP per capita in 2000. The income                      This finding suggests the existence of a global convergence or&#13;
  brackets were defined by the same cutoffs that the World                      catch-up story at the city level. In fact, the speed of city con-&#13;
  Bank Groupâ&#128;&#153;s official country classification scheme uses;                     vergence is faster than that of country convergence. This sug-&#13;
  these cutoffs are based on gross national income (GNI) per                    gests that cities lead economic growth and poverty reduction,&#13;
  capita. Although GDP and GNI are clearly different measures,                  a finding that is consistent with regional growth literature&#13;
  no equivalent classification scheme could be found for GDP                    (see Gennaioli and others 2014). A five-year lagged regression&#13;
  per capita, and applying the GNI cutoffs to GDP has produced                  model controlling for fixed effects is used to calculate city&#13;
  intuitive, reasonable, and nonarbitrary results. For the sake                 economic convergence rate. A conditional convergence rate&#13;
  of simplicity, income brackets as defined in 2012 were used to                of 1.4 percent to 9.0 percent per year is observed for the 750&#13;
  classify cities in 2000.                                                      largest cities in the world from 2000 to 2012. In other words,&#13;
                                                                                cities with a lower per capita GDP are catching up at a rate of&#13;
  A first striking finding is that more than two-thirds of the                  1.4 to 9.0 percent per year.7 The unconditional convergence&#13;
  fastest-growing cities were lower-middle-income cities rather                 rate is also calculated at an interval of 1.9 to 4.5 percent per&#13;
  than low-income cities. This outcome may be because the                       year.&#13;
  process of development benefits from momentum, and cities&#13;
  very quickly graduate into lower-middle-income status once&#13;
&#13;
Figure 3.3: Annual average GDP per capita growth rates by starting income level for 750 cities (2000â&#128;&#147;12)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Source: Oxford Economics Dataset&#13;
Note: If data were not available for 2000, the first available year was used.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   24&#13;
&amp;#12; For the group of cities where GDP per capita grew between                      cutoffs over the period, falling from lower-middle-income to&#13;
 2.0 and 5.0 percent on average annually between 2000 and                       low-income status. A comparatively large number of low-&#13;
 2012, cities at all starting income levels could be found,                     er-middle-income cities were among these negative growers,&#13;
 which means an annual per capita GDP growth rate of 2.0 to                     too. In general, though, high-income cities dominated the&#13;
 5.0 percent is commonly observed among a variety of cities,                    ranks of those struggling to maintain standards of living.&#13;
 from low income to high income (figure 3.3).&#13;
                                                                                City GDP per capita growth by income level,&#13;
 Among the 207 cities that eked by with slow but still positive                 controlling for country effects&#13;
 GDP per capita growth were only three low-income cities:&#13;
 Cotonou (Benin), Banjul (The Gambia), and Srinagar (India).                    Lower-middle-income cities are most likely to have expe-&#13;
 More than two-thirds of the cities falling into this group                     rienced faster GDP per capita growth than their countries.&#13;
 were high-income cities, attesting to the challenge of main-                   Figure 3.4 shows city GDP per capita growth outperformed&#13;
 taining high per capita growth rates at high starting levels                   national GDP per capita growth in 70 percent of the cities&#13;
 of income. Of course, the 2009 financial crisis that struck                    that were lower-middle income in 2000. China accounted for&#13;
 high-income cities (generally the same as OECD cities, as                      almost three-fifths of those cities. Outperforming the rate of&#13;
 mentioned previously) would also have contributed to these                     national development appears to be harder in high-income&#13;
 low growth rates.                                                              cities: only 2 percent did so by more than 2 percentage points&#13;
                                                                                per year, and it is the only income grouping in which fewer&#13;
 Evidence of the so-called poverty trap could be found in the                   than half outperformed national rates at all. By the same to-&#13;
 three citiesâ&#128;&#148;Bangui (Central African Republic), Bamako                         ken, high-income cities were less likely to lag far behind their&#13;
 (Mali), and Niamey (Niger)â&#128;&#148;that experienced negative GDP                       national economies in terms of GDP per capita growth, sug-&#13;
 per capita growth rates and were already low-income cities in                  gesting a stable, if slow and inertial, trajectory. Upper-mid-&#13;
 2000. LomÃ© (Togo), too, had the inglorious distinction of be-                  dle-income cities, for their part, were most susceptible to&#13;
 ing the only city to regress to an earlier stage of development                severe underperformance (GDP per capita growth rates more&#13;
 according to this measure and the World Bank Groupâ&#128;&#153;s official                  than 2 percentage points below the national rates).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 3.4 Share of cities by income bracket overperforming or underperforming their national economies in&#13;
   terms of average annual GDP per capita growth, 2000â&#128;&#147;12&#13;
&#13;
             Overperforming by &gt; 2% Overperforming by &lt; 2% Underperforming by &gt; -2% Underperforming by &lt; -2%&#13;
                                                  0	10	20	30	40	50	60	70	80	90	100                                               Percent&#13;
&#13;
                            High Income&#13;
              Upper Middle Income&#13;
              Lower Middle Income&#13;
                             Low Income&#13;
&#13;
Source: Oxford Economics Dataset&#13;
Note: If data were not available for 2000, the first available year was used.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                  25&#13;
&amp;#12;City GDP per capita growth by industrial profile                                The high-income OECD cities that populate the lower rungs&#13;
                                                                                of the distribution also tend to specialize in high-end ser-&#13;
Finally, we categorized cities by annual average GDP per cap-                   vices, which figure 3.5 makes clear. Causal interpretations of&#13;
ita growth rates according to the industrial profileâ&#128;&#148;the larg-                  this connection must be limited, however: a specialization in&#13;
est sector in terms of share of GVA. In general, an orientation                 a certain sector does not cause a cityâ&#128;&#153;s GDP per capita growth&#13;
toward industrial pursuits (which encompasses manufactur-                       rate to be what it is. Instead, sector specialization is more&#13;
ing, energy, mining, and construction) was associated with                      likely to be associated with the level of development rather&#13;
faster GDP per capita growth rates, whereas cities with lower                   than to be a driver of economic performance. As subsequent&#13;
GDP per capita growth rates were more likely to have econo-                     sections of this paper discuss, another key development&#13;
mies oriented toward high-end services. By contrast, cities in                  pathway for cities is that from basic services to industry and,&#13;
which consumer (or basic) services were the dominant sector                     finally, to high-end services. Later sections expound on this&#13;
tended to fall into the second- and third-fastest groups of                     idea in greater detail.&#13;
growersâ&#128;&#148;in part because of their tendency to be low- and&#13;
lower-middle-income cities.                                                     Income traps&#13;
Thanks to the dominance of manufacturing and construc-                          Income pathways can also be depicted by plotting citiesâ&#128;&#153;&#13;
tion in Chinaâ&#128;&#153;s economy, 95 percent of cities registering                       growth rates by their initial level of development (or GDP&#13;
10.0 percent or higher GDP per capita growth were indus-                        per capita). Figure 3.6 does this, plotting all cities by average&#13;
trial cities. That number fell to 58 percent in the 5.0 to 10.0                 GDP growth from 2002 to 2012 against GDP per capita at&#13;
percent growth bracket. Cities with large consumer services                     the start of the decade, in 2002. The graph shows that growth&#13;
sectors accounted for the second-largest contingent in this                     rates tend to decline as income levels rise in an economy.&#13;
bracket. We posit that these citiesâ&#128;&#153; growth may not be driven                   This slowdown takes place for a variety of reasons, including&#13;
by this specialization, however, but rather that many cities                    the fact that richer societies at later development stages tend&#13;
in the early stages of industrialization begin the process with                 to have fewer underused resources to marshal because the&#13;
a dominant low-end services sector serving an increasingly                      formal sector already dominates, the urbanization process is&#13;
urbanized population. Some of these fast-growing cities                         far along, and population levels stabilize. In addition, more&#13;
specializing in high-end services are Beijing (China); Addis                    developed societies tend to operate at the technological fron-&#13;
Ababa (Ethiopia); Bangalore Hyderabad, and Mumbai (India);                      tier and therefore have less capacity for growth that takes&#13;
Riga (Latvia); Vilnius (Lithuania); and Panama City (Pana-                      advantage of technologies developed elsewhere to accelerate&#13;
ma).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 3.5	            Annual average GDP per capita growth rates by industrial profile for 750 cities, 2000â&#128;&#147;12&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Source: Oxford Economics Dataset&#13;
Note: If data were not available for 2000, the first available year was used.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
26&#13;
&amp;#12;the development process. In other words, easy efficiencies         (Madagascar), and&#13;
have mostly been exploited in wealthier cities, and growth         Niamey (Niger), among        A city may find itself in the&#13;
rates regress to the rate of technological change.                 others, may be mired&#13;
                                                                                                so-called middle-income&#13;
                                                                   in a poverty trap. The&#13;
Maintaining growth rates high enough to keep the economy           post-middle-income           trap if its economy exhausts&#13;
moving forward and up the income ladder is a priorityâ&#128;&#148;and          trap could be defined        the easy dividends of inte-&#13;
worryâ&#128;&#148;for many cities and countries. The frequently men-           flexibly, and here we        grating additional factors&#13;
tioned middle-income trap refers to the symptom of growth          posit that it begins just    into the production process&#13;
that slows before an economy becomes truly wealthy. Such           after US$12,000 GDP          more efficiently and fails to&#13;
a slowdown may occur when an economy exhausts the easy             per capita and extends&#13;
dividends of integrating additional factors into the produc-                                    cultivate a technology-driv-&#13;
                                                                   past US$20,000. By&#13;
tion process more efficiently and fails to cultivate a technolo-   these criteria, Porto        en engine for the economy.&#13;
gy-driven engine for the economy.                                  Alegre and Rio de Ja-&#13;
                                                                   neiro (Brazil), Thessa-&#13;
In figure 3.6, cities potentially afflicted by such a middle-in-   loniki (Greece), and Szczecin (Poland), to name a few, may all&#13;
come trap are the ones with low average annual growth              find themselves in the post-middle-income trap, struggling to&#13;
rates over the decadeâ&#128;&#148;possibly below 4.0 percent but more          rekindle growth that prematurely petered out.&#13;
stringently below 2.0 percentâ&#128;&#148;and landing between approx-&#13;
imately US$5,000 and US$12,000 in GDP per capita. By this          At the same time, a number of upper-middle-income and&#13;
definition, several Brazilian, Egyptian, and South African         high-income cities in East Asia and Pacific, Europe and Cen-&#13;
cities may be stuck in the middle-income trap as well as San       tral Asia, and Latin America and the Caribbean enjoyed an-&#13;
Salvador (El Salvador), Kingston (Jamaica), AsunciÃ³n (Para-        nual average GDP growth of more than 5.0 percent over the&#13;
guay), and Caracas (RepÃºblica Bolivariana de Venezuela).           decade. These starsâ&#128;&#148;42 in totalâ&#128;&#148;include several Chinese&#13;
                                                                   cities as well as Mendoza (Argentina), Panama City (Panama),&#13;
Cities may also find themselves in poverty traps, growing          and Arequipa and Lima (Peru) in Latin America and Caribbe-&#13;
very slowly even at extremely low levels of GDP per capita,        an and Baku (Azerbaijan), Sofia (Bulgaria), Almaty (Kazakh-&#13;
and post-middle-income traps, where city growth rates plum-        stan), and Bucharest (Romania) in Europe and Central Asia.&#13;
met before they approach the OECD average. By that defini-&#13;
tion, YaoundÃ© (Cameroon), Bangui (Central African Republic),&#13;
Abidjan (CÃ´te dâ&#128;&#153;Ivoire), Port-au-Prince (Haiti), Antananarivo&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 3.6	         Average GDP growth rates by GDP per capita in 2002, 2002â&#128;&#147;12&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Source: Oxford Economics Dataset&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                   27&#13;
&amp;#12;Industry pathways                                                                   cities specialize in&#13;
                                                                                    a mix of basic and        At early stages of development,&#13;
Globally and measured broadly, the industrial composition of                        some higher-level&#13;
                                                                                                              a relatively large share of city&#13;
city economies remained relatively stable over the 12-year pe-                      services. Once&#13;
riod, suggesting that significant changes to the distribution                       industrialization         value added in the consumer&#13;
of economic activity across sectors in cities typically occurs                      takes hold, cities        services sector is more a symp-&#13;
over longer time horizons. Excluding China, where the in-                           take on a new             tom of the underdevelopment&#13;
dustrial sector dominates, the same sector accounted for the                        role as aggrega-          of industry than it is the sign of&#13;
largest share of GVA in 2012 as it did in 2000 in 80 percent                        tors of inputs            a thriving consumer economy.&#13;
of the cities in the data set. Of those cities that did change,                     and generators of&#13;
                                                                                                              Large consumer services sectors&#13;
just below half underwent a transition from specializing in                         economies of scale&#13;
industry to specializing in high-end services. Sixteen mostly                       and agglomeration         may also appear when the pro-&#13;
South Asian cities transitioned directly from basic consum-                         forces. Eventually,       cess of urbanization precedes&#13;
er services into high-end services, bypassing the process of                        as development            that of industrialization.&#13;
industrialization for the time being (see figure 3.7). These                        continues, econ-&#13;
cities could be considered sector leapfroggers, although their                      omies transition&#13;
continued progression up the economic development ladder                            into higher-level services functions while the consumer&#13;
without a strong industrial base may not be guaranteed.                             services sector falls into an equilibrium size to support more&#13;
                                                                                    dominant traded sectors. Accordingly, the size of the consum-&#13;
Note: Blue blocks represent all cities with industry as the                         er sector appears to be a function of the size of other sectors&#13;
largest sector in 2012, gray blocks are those where high-end                        at all stages of development. At early stages of development, a&#13;
services are the largest sector, and red blocks represent cities                    relatively large share of city value added in the consumer ser-&#13;
with consumer services as the largest sector.                                       vices sector is more a symptom of the underdevelopment of&#13;
Theory would suggest that cities embark on a slightly differ-                       industry than it is the sign of a thriving consumer economy.&#13;
ent development process than do countries. Cities tend to by-                       Large consumer services sectors may also appear when the&#13;
pass the earliest agrarian stages of development because they                       process of urbanization precedes that of industrialization.&#13;
are, by nature, marketplaces for the exchange of goods and&#13;
services. Accordingly, at the earliest stages of development,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 3.7 City sector pathways from 2000 to 2012&#13;
In contrast to income growth path, stability in aggregate-level sector composition&#13;
in cities appears to hold over the medium-long (12 year) period studied&#13;
&#13;
                          2000                                                                                    2012&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                          118&#13;
                    Industry                                                                                      Industry&#13;
                   165 cities                                                                              4      129 cities&#13;
                                                                                                           7&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                          10&#13;
    Consumer services                                                                                             Consumer services&#13;
                                                                                                          32&#13;
             52 cities                                                                                            49 cities&#13;
                                                                                                           7&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                          37&#13;
       High-end services                                                                                  16&#13;
                                                                                                                  High-end services&#13;
               185 cities                                                                                         224 cities&#13;
                                                                                                         171&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Sample set excludes cities from Argentina, China, Malaysia, Morocco, Peru, Russia, Serbia, South&#13;
Africa, Turkey, United Arab Emirates, Ukraine, United States, Venezuela because of data availability.&#13;
&#13;
Source: Oxford Economics Dataset&#13;
Note: Line width is only indicative.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
28&#13;
&amp;#12;As figures 3.8 and 3.9 show, industrialization appears to take    category as productive centers. Finally, once GDP per capita&#13;
off very quickly at the lowest levels of development, where it    surpasses the US$20,000 level, high-end services take over&#13;
remains a dominant force, on average, well into upper-mid-        as the largest sector of the economy and presumptive driver&#13;
dle-income status. At the city level, industryâ&#128;&#153;s share of GVA     of growth and wealth creation. In these hubs of creative&#13;
appears to peak around US$11,000 GDP per capita. The tran-        services, innovation-stimulating Jacobian externalities likely&#13;
sition from industry to high-end services then takes place        increase in importance.&#13;
gradually as countries grow richer.&#13;
                                                                  As an aside, the pronounced differences between figures&#13;
Figure 3.8 also implies that, structurally speaking, economic     3.8 and 3.9 (the latter incorporates Chinaâ&#128;&#153;s 150 cities in the&#13;
development is a progression toward high-end servicesâ&#128;&#148;            sample) may lend further support to Rodrikâ&#128;&#153;s proposition&#13;
even if industry may be developmentâ&#128;&#153;s engine. (The figure         that the historical pathway to prosperity via industrializa-&#13;
sorts cities according to ascending GDP per capita and places     tion is closing for low-income cities today. This closure may&#13;
them into bands of 12 cities. It then stacks each bandâ&#128;&#153;s          be in part because of changes to the labor intensity of the&#13;
column according to the average size of each sector of the        manufacturing sector worldwide but also because of the&#13;
economy, producing the picture shown.)                            sheer scale of Chinaâ&#128;&#153;s manufacturing enterprise. However,&#13;
                                                                  we have no historical period with which to compare the&#13;
On the basis of figure 3.9, we posit that cities can general-     data in figure 3.9, and we cannot assess whether crowding&#13;
ly be classified into three different categories according to     out is taking place without knowing whether the amount&#13;
their stage of development. Until GDP per capita reaches          of industrial activity the world economy can support at any&#13;
approximately US$2,500 per year, cities fundamentally             given time is finite. One could therefore arrive at two very&#13;
serve as market towns in the classic sense; they are centers      different conclusions on the basis of these figures. One poten-&#13;
of exchange for people trading their wares on a small scale       tial conclusion is that the graph including China reflects the&#13;
and from a surrounding hinterland. At this stage, consumer        global steady stateâ&#128;&#148;one in which Chinese cities are winning&#13;
services dominate the economy. Then, as GDP per capita rises      the biggest pieces of the global industrial pie. The other&#13;
to about US$20,000 per year, industryâ&#128;&#153;s share of the econo-       possible conclusion is that China is an anomalyâ&#128;&#148;indeed, it&#13;
my also begins to rise and remains dominant. At this stage,       is worth recalling that construction, in addition to mining, is&#13;
cities serve as industrial agglomerations and benefit from        included in the â&#128;&#156;industrialâ&#128;&#157; aggregate, a sector that has seen&#13;
traditional Marshallian externalities.8 We label cities in this   very large booms in Chinaâ&#128;&#148;and its cities buck the normal&#13;
                                                                  trend observed in figure 3.8. The truth, of course, may also lie&#13;
                                                                  somewhere in between.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                   29&#13;
&amp;#12;       Figure 3.8	                                             The changing distribution of GVA across sectors as GDP per capita rises, 2012, excluding China&#13;
                                                Percent                      $2,000         $5,000                  $12,000             $40,000&#13;
                                                100&#13;
&#13;
                                                  90&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                            High-end services&#13;
                                                  80&#13;
Sector share of total gobal value added (%)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  70&#13;
&#13;
                                                  60&#13;
                                                                                                                                                            Public services&#13;
                                                  50&#13;
&#13;
                                                  40&#13;
                                                                                                                                                            Consumer services&#13;
                                                  30&#13;
                                                                                                                                                            Agriculture&#13;
                                                  20&#13;
                                                                                                                                                            Industry and mining&#13;
                                                  10&#13;
&#13;
                                                   0&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      Band of 12 cities ordered from lowest to highest GDP per capita&#13;
                                              Source: Oxford Economics Dataset&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       Figure 3.9	                                             The changing distribution of GVA across sectors as GDP per capita rises, 2012, including China&#13;
                                                Percent               $2,000                    $5,000                      $12,000               $40,000&#13;
                                                100&#13;
&#13;
                                                  90&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                            High-end services&#13;
                                                  80&#13;
Sector share of total gobal value added (%)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  70&#13;
&#13;
                                                  60&#13;
                                                                                                                                                            Public services&#13;
                                                  50&#13;
&#13;
                                                  40&#13;
                                                                                                                                                            Consumer services&#13;
                                                  30&#13;
                                                                                                                                                            Agriculture&#13;
                                                  20&#13;
                                                                                                                                                            Industry and mining&#13;
                                                  10&#13;
&#13;
                                                   0&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      Band of 12 cities ordered from lowest to highest GDP per capita&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     30&#13;
       Source: Oxford Economics Dataset&#13;
&amp;#12;Size pathways                                                       Figure 3.10 Cities increasing and decreasing their&#13;
                                                                       shares of national population worldwide, 2000â&#128;&#147;12&#13;
Stability reigns at the top of national urban hierarchies (see&#13;
figure 3.10). Over the 12-year period studied, no city was          Point change in city share&#13;
deposed from the top spot in its national hierarchy in terms        of national population (%)&#13;
of GDP, although five cities that were prime in terms of GDP           12 -&#13;
rose to become prime in terms of population as well, dis-&#13;
placing originally larger but less productive cities. In Bolivia,       8-&#13;
La Pazâ&#128;&#153;s population fell behind that of Santa Cruz, just as&#13;
Lilongweâ&#128;&#153;s population overtook that of Blantyre in Malawi.&#13;
In the OECD, Milan advanced past Naples to become Italyâ&#128;&#153;s               4-                       Increasing share of&#13;
most populous city, and Amsterdam displaced Rotterdam                                              country population&#13;
atop the Dutch urban hierarchy. Vietnamâ&#128;&#153;s Ho Chi Minh City              0-&#13;
surpassed Hanoi in East Asia and Pacific.&#13;
&#13;
Within large countries with multiple large cities, substan-                                                                 Decreasing share of&#13;
                                                                       -4 -&#13;
                                                                                                                            country population&#13;
tial changes in position were rare but not unheard of. In the&#13;
United States, cities such as Detroit and New Orleans fell five&#13;
                                                                       -8 -&#13;
places in population rank just as Austin climbed five plac-&#13;
es and Las Vegas and Orlando climbed six places. In terms           Source: Oxford Economics Dataset&#13;
of GDP, Portland, Charlotte, North Carolina; and Austin,&#13;
Texas all moved significantly up in the rankings. In Nigeria,&#13;
Onitsha rose eight places in terms of population. Of 72 major&#13;
cities in India, 17 substantially (defined as a movement of at      Figure 3.11 Cities increasing and decreasing their&#13;
least five places in either direction) changed their position          shares of national output worldwide, 2000â&#128;&#147;12&#13;
in the national hierarchy in terms of population, and 25 did&#13;
in terms of GDP. In China, fully one-third of 150 large cities      Point change in city share of national&#13;
rose or fell significantly in the population rankings. In terms     gross domestic product (%)&#13;
of GDP, nearly 60 percent did.                                         12 -&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The same general distribution holds for changes in city share&#13;
                                                                        8-&#13;
of national GDP (see figure 3.11). Of the 553 cities for which&#13;
data were available, 74 percent saw their share of national&#13;
GDP increase over the period, 20 percent saw their share                4-                               Increasing share of&#13;
decrease, and 6 percent saw their share remain unchanged.                                                  country population&#13;
More turbulence was found in the distribution of national&#13;
                                                                        0-&#13;
output among cities than in population. Only 55 percent&#13;
of cities saw their share of national output remain stable,&#13;
defined as changing less than 0.2 percentage points in either          -4 -&#13;
direction, compared with 71 percent in terms of population.                                                                        Decreasing share of&#13;
                                                                                                                                   country population&#13;
                                                                       -8 -&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                    Source: Oxford Economics Dataset&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                   31&#13;
&amp;#12;The share of national population increased in nearly 80 per-                     Regionally, nearly every&#13;
cent of cities in rapidly urbanizing Sub-Saharan Africa from                     city in East Asia and Pacific,        Whereas all city&#13;
2000 to 2012. By contrast, in more stable Europe and Central                     Europe and Central Asia, and          boats rise together in&#13;
Asia, only 50 percent of cities garnered a larger share of their                 Sub-Saharan Africa increased&#13;
                                                                                                                       urbanizing countries,&#13;
countryâ&#128;&#153;s population by 2012 (figure 3.12). Dynamic East                         its share of national GDP&#13;
Asia and Pacific, for its part, saw significant jockeying among                  from 2000 to 2012. By con-            industry specializa-&#13;
cities, with as many rising in population share as falling or                    trast, in the Middle East and         tions appear to drive&#13;
remaining the same. South Asia stands out for a large cohort                     North Africa and the OECD,            a cityâ&#128;&#153;s climb or fall in&#13;
of cities that neither increased nor decreased their share of                    as many cities saw their share        hierarchies of devel-&#13;
country population over 12 years and for the smallest cohort                     of national output decline as         oped countries.&#13;
of cities ceding ground. Here a change is any increase or de-                    saw it increase. This differen-&#13;
crease in country population share of 0.01 percentage points                     tial suggests that the relevant&#13;
or greater.                                                                      growth drivers may operate at the national level in the for-&#13;
                                                                                 mer group of countries undergoing increasing urbanization&#13;
                                                                                 broadly, but then operate at the city or particular industry&#13;
                                                                                 level in countries with more established urban hierarchies,&#13;
                                                                                 thus leading to shifts in a cityâ&#128;&#153;s share of output as cities rise&#13;
                                                                                 and fall with the fate of their base industries.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 3.12 Direction of change in cityâ&#128;&#153;s gain in national population and output as urbanization occurs,&#13;
   by region&#13;
&#13;
Direction of change in city share of                                       Direction of change in city share of&#13;
national population                                                        national gross domestic product&#13;
                                    Share of cities in region (%)                                            Share of cities in region (%)   Urbanization&#13;
                                0 10 20 30 40 50 60 70 80 90 100                                         0 10 20 30 40 50 60 70 80 90 100      rate (%)&#13;
         Sub-Saharan Africa                                                       Sub-Saharan Africa                                            37.2&#13;
                  South Asia                                                               South Asia                                           31.2&#13;
Middle East and North Africa                                             Middle East and North Africa                                           61.5&#13;
Latin America and Caribbean                                              Latin America and Caribbean                                            81.3&#13;
                       OECD                                                                     OECD                                            81.0&#13;
     Europe and Central Asia                                                  Europe and Central Asia                                           65.5&#13;
        East Asia and Pacific                                                    East Asia and Pacific                                          49.7&#13;
                                          Direction of Change in City Share of National GDP&#13;
Source: Oxford Economics Dataset                                Rising       Unchanged       Falling&#13;
&#13;
                                Europe and Central Asia&#13;
                                    Sub-Saharan Africa&#13;
                                   East Asia and Pacific&#13;
                                             South Asia&#13;
                           Latin America and Caribbean&#13;
                           Middle East and North Africa&#13;
                                                  OECD&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 32&#13;
&amp;#12; 4. Predictors of City Competitiveness                                    Stocktaking of city indexes&#13;
                                                                          A critical value added of this paper is to take stock of and&#13;
 Working definition of city competitiveness                               assess how the various city competitiveness indexes on the&#13;
 City competitiveness has been defined for the purposes of this           market can be most useful for policy. The team therefore&#13;
 project as follows: a competitive city is a city that successfully       inventoried popular indexes covering themes ranging from&#13;
 facilitates its firms and industries to create jobs, raise produc-       competitiveness to livability, sustainability, and infrastruc-&#13;
 tivity, and increase the incomes of citizens over time.                  ture. These indexes vary significantly in terms of methodolo-&#13;
                                                                          gy and coverage. Several adopt opaque â&#128;&#156;black boxâ&#128;&#157; approaches&#13;
 The analytics team operationalized city competitiveness with             to ranking cities that do not render them fit for statistical&#13;
 concrete and measurable economic outcomes. Although many                 analysis, whereas others show a clear bias toward only a few&#13;
 different indicators have merit, and each captures a different           regions of the world, typically OECD countries. In total, more&#13;
 facet of competitiveness, we have adopted four on the basis of           than 20 different indexes were evaluated according to the&#13;
 generalizability and availability:                                       robustness of their methodologies as well as their coverage,&#13;
                                                                          and six were chosen for folding into the final data set (see&#13;
 â&#128;¢	   Annual output growth                                                table 4.1).&#13;
 â&#128;¢	   Annual employment growth&#13;
 â&#128;¢	   Labor productivity (GVA per worker)                                 Other data sets used at various points in this analysis include&#13;
 â&#128;¢	   Household disposable income                                         the World Bank Groupâ&#128;&#153;s Doing Business Indicators (DBI), the&#13;
                                                                          Chinese Academy of Social Scienceâ&#128;&#153;s Global Urban Competi-&#13;
 These outcomes allow us to explore a cityâ&#128;&#153;s ability to add               tiveness Report for patent data, and the International Mone-&#13;
 value, grow jobs, raise productivity, and increase residentsâ&#128;&#153; in-        tary Fundâ&#128;&#153;s Government Finance Statistics Yearbook (GFSY).&#13;
 comesâ&#128;&#148;preoccupations of city leaders across the worldâ&#128;&#148;and&#13;
 the factors that are associated with such an ability.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table 4.1 Popular City Indexes Evaluated for Methodological Robustness and Coverage&#13;
&#13;
Evaluated and included in global correlation analysis                 Evaluated and not included in global correlation analysis&#13;
&#13;
AT Kearney Global Cities Index (2008, 2010, 2012) (65 cities)         2thinknow Consulting: Innovation Cities Index&#13;
Economist Intelligence Unit City Competitiveness Hotspots&#13;
                                                                      BusinessWeek â&#128;&#153;s Americaâ&#128;&#153;s Best Cities&#13;
(2012) (116 cities)&#13;
                                                                      Cisco Broadband Quality Index&#13;
Economist Intelligence Unit Liveability Index (2012) (68&#13;
cities)                                                               fDi Intelligence: Cities of the Future&#13;
Global Financial Centers Index (2006â&#128;&#147;12) (62 cities)                  Forbes Best Places for Business and Careers&#13;
Mercer Quality of Life Index (2010, 2012) (46 cities)                 IDB Emerging and Sustainable Cities Initiative&#13;
UN-Habitat City Prosperity Index (2012) (70 cities)                   Mercer Infrastructure Index&#13;
                                                                      Milken Instituteâ&#128;&#153;s Best-Performing Cities&#13;
                                                                      Monocle Quality of Life Survey&#13;
                                                                      NUMBEO Cost of Living and Quality of Life Indexes&#13;
                                                                      PWC Cities of Opportunity&#13;
                                                                      Siemens Green City Index&#13;
                                                                      Urban Sustainability Index&#13;
                                                                      World Knowledge Competitiveness Index&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                            33&#13;
&amp;#12;How well do city indexes predict competitiveness                               tions closer to the center are more strongly negative, just as&#13;
outcomes?                                                                      correlations toward the outside of the chart are more strongly&#13;
                                                                               positive.) The negative correlations should in many cases be&#13;
Ultimately the team chose six indexes to test for their pre-                   expected: they imply slower rates of growth at higher rank-&#13;
dictive power. The selection was based on transparency, data                   ings. If rankings are associatedâ&#128;&#148;as is likelyâ&#128;&#148;with stage of&#13;
accessibility, coverage, and popular use. To assess whether                    development, then relatively slow growth rates in developed&#13;
an index was a strong predictor of city competitiveness, we                    cities make for an inverse relationship. The Global Financial&#13;
ran a straightforward pair wise correlation analysis between                   Centers Index, for its part, positively predicted every compet-&#13;
the indexâ&#128;&#153;s 2012 rankings and the four primary performance                     itiveness outcome in 2012.&#13;
outcomes in 2012.&#13;
                                                                               In general, no city competitiveness index can claim a univer-&#13;
Globally, the indexes proved to be far better predictors of                    sal ability to predict the economic performance of the worldâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
the level of city development than predictors of short-term                    cities, especially in the short term. A gap in the market seems&#13;
economic performance (see figure 4.1). The Economist                           to exist for indexes to capture citiesâ&#128;&#153; growth potential.&#13;
Intelligence Unit (EIU) Hotspots and Liveability surveys,&#13;
AT Kearneyâ&#128;&#153;s Global Cities survey, and the UN-Habitat City                     Some indexes perform better in samples narrowed by either&#13;
Prosperity Index are all highly correlated with both city labor                region or city typology. The EIU Competitiveness Index, for&#13;
productivity and household disposable incomeâ&#128;&#148;two com-                          example, predicts outcomes better in East Asian and Pacific&#13;
petitiveness outcomes that vary with overall level of develop-                 and OECD cities than it does in Latin American and Carib-&#13;
ment but remain quite stable from year to year. Performance                    bean or South Asian cities and better in high-income cities&#13;
on these same indexes was actually negatively correlated                       than in low-income ones. The AT Kearney Global Cities Index&#13;
with GDP and employment growth from 2011 to 2012â&#128;&#148;                              performs better with primary cities, and the Mercer Quality&#13;
more strongly so for GDP than for employment. (Negative                        of Life Index does better for secondary cities.&#13;
correlations can be found at the center of the radar; correla-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 4.1 Correlations among city index rankings and city performance outcomes, 2012&#13;
                                                                 Correlation&#13;
                                        -0.60    -0.40   -0.20      0.00       0.20   0.40     0.60    0.80&#13;
                                                                                                                  Labor productivity&#13;
                                                                                                              Labor Productivity&#13;
 EIU City Hot Spots                                                                                           Disposable Income per Capita&#13;
                                                                                                                  Disposable income per capita&#13;
                                                                                                              Employment Growth&#13;
                                                                                                              GDP Growth&#13;
 UN-Habitat City Prosperity Index                                                                                 Job growth&#13;
                                                                                                                  GDP growth&#13;
 EIU Liveability Index&#13;
&#13;
 A.T. Kearney Global Cities Index&#13;
&#13;
 Global Financial Centers Index&#13;
&#13;
 Mercer Quality of Life Index&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Source: Oxford Economics Dataset and Various Indices&#13;
Note: EIU = Economist Intelligence Unit.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
34&#13;
&amp;#12;City competitiveness correlates: Factor analysis                                 Factor analysis: Global results on the&#13;
                                                                                 determinants of city competitiveness&#13;
Indexes are by nature composite measures of multiple factors.&#13;
As a result, the information they provide is of only limited                     Each determinant can be represented by multiple indicators&#13;
use to policy makers, who tend to see the world through                          or subcomponents of indexes. We used factor analysis meth-&#13;
discrete issues, subject matters, and areas of expertise.                        odology to consolidate multiple related variables into a single&#13;
Accordingly, we conducted a second correlation analysis to                       statistical entity. We then ran pair wise correlation analysis&#13;
assess the relationship that particular subcomponents of                         across factors and outcomes to ascertain how the relationship&#13;
indexes, as well as additional variables from the World Bankâ&#128;&#153;s                   among determinants and outcomes varies by the cityâ&#128;&#153;s stage&#13;
DBI database (with data for 2005 through 2012), have with                        of development. The stage of development is defined accord-&#13;
city competitiveness outcomes. These subcomponents and                           ing to the typology on the basis of stage of industrialization&#13;
measures were bucketed into six conceptual determinants of                       (discussed under industry pathways in section 3 of this&#13;
city competitiveness: institutions and regulations, physical                     paper) that classifies cities according to their GDP per capita&#13;
infrastructure, social infrastructure, human capital, innova-                    levels as market towns, production centers, or creative and&#13;
tion, and enterprise support and finance (see table 4.2).9                       financial services hubs. Figure 4.2 summarizes the observed&#13;
                                                                                 relationships. Only statistically significant associations at&#13;
We use the term determinant cautiously. Determinants are                         the 10 percent level are shown. The analysis incorporates&#13;
meant to capture the variables we expect to be associated                        observations spanning several years because the historical&#13;
with positive economic outcomes and city competitiveness.                        coverage of each data set used varies. We decided to retain&#13;
However, any relationships identified here are by no means                       the full sample to incorporate the largest possible number of&#13;
deterministic. They are associations and correlations and                        observations.&#13;
should be interpreted only as such.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table 4.2	           Determinants and proxies of city competitiveness&#13;
&#13;
Institutions and regulations                                                     Skills and innovation&#13;
Ease of Doing Business Index (Doing Business Indicators)                         Human capital&#13;
                                                                                 Education Index (EIU Livability)&#13;
                                                                                 Human Capital (EIU Competitive Cities)&#13;
                                                                                 Innovation&#13;
                                                                                 Number of Patents by City (Global Urban Competitiveness Report)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Infrastructure and land                                                          Enterprise support and fnance&#13;
Physical infrastructure                                                          Financial Maturity Index (EIU Competitive Cities)&#13;
Physical Capital (EIU Competitive Cities)                                        Private Credit Bureau Coverage (Doing Business Indicators)&#13;
Infrastructure Index (UN-Habitat City Prosperity Index)&#13;
Cost of Electricity (Doing Business Indicators)&#13;
Social infrastructure&#13;
Social and Cultural Capital (EIU Competitive Cities)&#13;
Healthcare Index (EIU Livability)&#13;
Quality of Life Index (UN-Habitat City Prosperity Index)&#13;
&#13;
Source: Competitive cities for jobs and growth: what, who, and how, 2015, The World Bank.&#13;
Note: EIU = Economist Intelligence Unit.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                 35&#13;
&amp;#12;We find that the correlates of city competitiveness vary de-                         â&#128;¢	      Innovation is associated with labor productivity at higher&#13;
pending on income level and industrial structure as follows:                                 income levels and economic structures.&#13;
&#13;
â&#128;¢	    Institutions and regulations matter at most levels of in-                      â&#128;¢	      Human capital is positively associated with household&#13;
      come and economic structures.                                                          disposable income, labor productivity, and job growth,&#13;
                                                                                             but only after cities reach high-income status dominated&#13;
â&#128;¢	    Physical infrastructure is positively associated with job                              by high-end services sectors.&#13;
      growth in market towns and labor productivity in pro-&#13;
      duction centers.                                                               Our results lead to an intriguing hypothesis, coherent with&#13;
                                                                                     findings in existing literature (Moretti 2004; Samad, Loza-&#13;
â&#128;¢	    Social infrastructure appears to be important for income                       no-Gracia, and Panman 2012; Shapiro 2006; World Bank&#13;
      growth and labor productivity only in relatively well-de-                      2009; World Bank and DRC 2014): cities can use a sequence&#13;
      veloped cities.                                                                of interventions. The building blocks of competitivenessâ&#128;&#148;&#13;
                                                                                     institutions and social and basic physical infrastructure at&#13;
â&#128;¢	    Financial infrastructure appears to be important for                           lower incomes, then innovation capacityâ&#128;&#148;apparently can&#13;
      labor productivity and employment growth in relative-                          be sequenced in priority to build the human capital base&#13;
      ly well-developed cities. (We did not find data sets or                        required to compete, grow, and prosper as a high-income city.&#13;
      indexes that cover the provision of enterprise support                         In prioritizing these interventions, policy makers should&#13;
      programs and, thus, could not include this factor in our                       keep in mind the main industrial structure of the city and its&#13;
      global analysis.)                                                              competitive advantages.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 4.2 Statistically significant correlations among factors of determinants and competitiveness outcomes&#13;
   by city type&#13;
                                                         Market Towns                         Market Towns                Creative Financial Centers&#13;
                                                  (&lt;US$2,500 GDP per capita)        (US$2,500â&#128;&#147;20,000 GDP per capita)        (&gt;US$20,000 GDP per capita)&#13;
                                                 Disp.    Labor    GDP      Emp.     Disp.      Labor    GDP      Emp.     Disp.   Labor    GDP      Emp.&#13;
                                                income    prod.   growth   growth   income      prod.   growth   growth   income   prod.   growth   growth&#13;
Institutions and regulation&#13;
Ease of doing business index (DB)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Physical Infrastructure&#13;
Physical infrastructure (EIU); infrastructure&#13;
index (UN); cost of electricity (DB)&#13;
Social infrastructure&#13;
Social and cultural capital (EIU);&#13;
healthcare (EIUL); quality of life (UN)&#13;
Financial infrastructure&#13;
Private credit bureau coverage (DB);&#13;
financial maturity (EIU)&#13;
Human capital&#13;
Human capital (EIU); education (EIUL)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Innovation&#13;
Number of patents (GUC)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                     Positive statistically significant correlation at the 10 percent level&#13;
                                                     Negative statistically significant correlation at the 10 percent level&#13;
&#13;
Source: Oxford Economics Dataset and Various Indices&#13;
Note: DB = Doing Business Indicators; EIU = Economist Intelligence Unit City Competitiveness Hotspots; EIUL = Economist Intelligence Unit Liveability Index;&#13;
GUC = Global Urban Competitiveness Report; UN = UN-Habitat City Prosperity Index; Disp income - Disposable income; Labor prod = Labor productivity;&#13;
GDP = gross domestic product; Emp. growth = employment growth.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 36&#13;
&amp;#12;Breaking the factors down into their component parts, as                         omies. Both measures of human capital are associated with&#13;
figure 4.3 does, enables us to isolate in even greater detail                    job growth and productivity in services hubs, as are mature&#13;
the determinants that appear to influence competitiveness                        financial markets. Together, these findings suggest that basic&#13;
outcomes.                                                                        (physical) and more advanced (human and financial) forms&#13;
                                                                                 of capital may become increasingly complementary as cities&#13;
Labor productivity appears to benefit most directly from                         develop. Social infrastructure, for its part, appears to be high-&#13;
improvements on various determinants, especially in pro-                         ly correlated to living standards and development levels but&#13;
duction centers and services hubs. Productivity and income                       exhibits no significant connection to growth rates.&#13;
levels in market towns are correlated with lower costs of&#13;
electricity and more developed financial markets. In produc-                     Predictors of city competitiveness by region and&#13;
tion centers, electricity costs, physical capital, and human                     city type&#13;
capital are all positively associated with output growth rates,&#13;
whereas productivity appears to benefit from improvements                        We also carried out pair wise correlation analyses between&#13;
on a number of different fronts.                                                 the indexes and competitiveness outcomes by region and&#13;
                                                                                 types of cities.&#13;
Physical infrastructure and human capital may become&#13;
increasingly complementary as income levels rise. Lower                          Generally across regions and types, the finding holds that&#13;
electricity costs are associated with higher job growth, out-                    city indexes are good at predicting a cityâ&#128;&#153;s overall level of&#13;
put growth, and productivity levels even in higher-income                        development but are less useful at explaining differences in&#13;
services hubs, underscoring the continued saliency of the                        performance among cities at the same stage of development.&#13;
basic microeconomics of production even in services econ-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 4.3 Statistically significant correlations among determinants and competitiveness outcomes by city type&#13;
&#13;
                                                   Market Towns                          Market Towns                 Creative Financial Centers&#13;
                                             (&lt;US$2,500 GDP per capita)         (US$2,500â&#128;&#147;20,000 GDP per capita)         (&gt;US$20,000 GDP per capita)&#13;
                                           Disp.    Labor     GDP       Emp.     Disp.    Labor      GDP      Emp.     Disp.     Labor     GDP       Emp.&#13;
                                          income    prod.    growth    growth   income    prod.     growth   growth   income     prod.    growth    growth&#13;
 Institutions and regulation&#13;
 Ease of doing business index (DB)&#13;
&#13;
 Physical Infrastructure&#13;
 Physical infrastructure (EIU)&#13;
 Infrastructure index (UN)&#13;
 Cost of electricity (DB)&#13;
&#13;
 Social infrastructure&#13;
 Social and cultural capital (EIU)&#13;
 Healthcare (EIUL)&#13;
 Quality of life (UN)&#13;
&#13;
 Financial infrastructure&#13;
 Private credit bureau coverage (DB)&#13;
 Financial maturity (EIU)&#13;
&#13;
 Human capital&#13;
 Human capital (EIU)&#13;
 Education (EIUL)&#13;
&#13;
 Innovation&#13;
 Number of patents (GUC)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                             Positive statistically significant correlation at the 10 percent level&#13;
                                             Negative statistically significant correlation at the 10 percent level&#13;
&#13;
Source: Oxford Economics Dataset and Various Indices&#13;
Note: DBI = Doing Business Indicators; EIU = Economist Intelligence Unit City Competitiveness Hotspots; EIUL = Economist Intelligence Unit Liveability In-&#13;
dex; GUC = Global Urban Competitiveness Report; UN = UN-Habitat City Prosperity Index; Disp income - Disposable income; Labor prod = Labor productivity;&#13;
GDP = gross domestic product; Emp. growth = employment growth.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                          37&#13;
&amp;#12;Accordingly, factors are consistently better at predicting labor   Figures 4.4, 4.5, and 4.6 illustrate these perspectives with&#13;
productivity and disposable income levels than they are at         actual data. Figure 4.4 explores the relationship between&#13;
predicting the shorter-term changes in output or employ-           the EIUâ&#128;&#153;s financial maturity measure and competitiveness&#13;
ment. With smaller sample sizes, even fewer correlation            outcomes across World Bank Group regions. One can see that&#13;
coefficients are statistically significant. Those caveats aside,   the measure is positively correlated with labor productivity&#13;
correlation analysis by city type constitutes a sound starting     and disposable income per capita across all regions and with&#13;
point for attempting to explain the variation in competitive-      GDP growth in the Middle East and North Africa and Europe&#13;
ness outcomes across cities.                                       and Central Asia.&#13;
&#13;
One can conduct the narrower correlation analysis from one         Figure 4.5 takes only East Asian and Pacific cities into&#13;
of three different perspectives: that of a region, that of a       account to show that across a set of indicators representing&#13;
determinant, or that of a factor. For example, one can try to      each determinant, institutional strength and social infra-&#13;
uncover what factor is most strongly correlated with compet-       structure are positively associated with job growth in the&#13;
itiveness outcomes in groups of different cities. Alternatively,   region. Observed relationships with GDP growth, in contrast,&#13;
one could approach the analysis by asking where and for            are all counterintuitively negativeâ&#128;&#148;hence suggesting that&#13;
which outcome a particular determinant seems to matter. Or         the indicator may actually be assessing something that is in-&#13;
finally, a productivity scholar, for example, may wish to know     versely related to the factors driving growth in this particular&#13;
how the relationship between a set of determinants and labor       context. Once again, associations with labor productivity and&#13;
productivity differs across regions.                               disposable income levels are stronger and more positive.&#13;
&#13;
Figure 4.4 Example correlation analysis output between financial maturity and competitiveness outcomes, by&#13;
   region&#13;
          Europe and Central Asia&#13;
&#13;
     Middle East and North Africa                                                                 Disposable income per capita&#13;
                                                                                                  Labor productivity&#13;
               Sub-Saharan Africa&#13;
                                                                                                  Job growth&#13;
                  East Asia Pacific                                                               GDP growth&#13;
&#13;
                             OECD&#13;
&#13;
                        South Asia&#13;
&#13;
 Latin America and the Caribbean&#13;
Source: Oxford Economics Dataset and Economist Intelligence Unit&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 4.5 Example correlation analysis output between competitiveness determinants and outcomes for East&#13;
   Asian and Pacific cities&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                       Institutions&#13;
&#13;
            Physical infrastructure&#13;
&#13;
                    Human capital                                                                 Disposable income per capita&#13;
                                                                                                  Labor productivity&#13;
                    Agglomeration&#13;
                                                                                                  Job growth&#13;
           Financial infrastructure                                                               GDP growth&#13;
&#13;
              Social infrastructure&#13;
&#13;
                      Environment&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
38&#13;
Source: Oxford Economics Dataset and Various Indices&#13;
&amp;#12;Figure 4.6 displays correlations between the full range of         How does the â&#128;&#156;mayorâ&#128;&#153;s wedgeâ&#128;&#157; relate to city&#13;
competitiveness determinants and labor productivity by re-         competitiveness?&#13;
gion. The example clearly shows that institutional strength is&#13;
more highly correlated with labor productivity levels in cities    Of particular interest is the idea of the â&#128;&#156;mayorâ&#128;&#153;s wedgeâ&#128;&#157;â&#128;&#148;that&#13;
of Sub-Saharan Africa (and less highly correlated in cities of     is, the capacity, scope, and autonomy for relevant policy mak-&#13;
Europe and Central Asia) than in cities of any other region,       ing at the city levelâ&#128;&#148;and its relationship with city competi-&#13;
just as social infrastructure is most strongly associated with     tiveness outcomes: GDP and job growth, disposable incomes,&#13;
higher labor productivity in cities of South Asia and least        and labor productivity.&#13;
strongly associated in cities of Europe and Central Asia. In&#13;
cities of Europe and Central Asia, physical infrastructure and     We explore the mayorâ&#128;&#153;s wedge relationship with city competi-&#13;
financial infrastructure are most closely associated with higher   tiveness using an econometric model. We obtained data from&#13;
levels of labor productivity. A chart such as this example could   the International Monetary Fundâ&#128;&#153;s GFSY database, which&#13;
help scholars from different regions identify pertinent and        provides information on spending at all levels of government&#13;
promising issues for their competitiveness inquiries.              in countries outside Asia. Coverage of this data set expand-&#13;
                                                                   ed with each year, beginning with 100 cities in the sample&#13;
Because these are only correlations, and correlations reveal       in 2000 and ending with 286 by 2012. OE data on social&#13;
associations but offer little insight into explanatory factors,    infrastructure and agglomeration, which had full coverage,&#13;
later stages of this project may conduct a more comprehen-         were also used to introduce a series of explanatory variables&#13;
sive multivariate regression analysis to complement this base.     covering additional competitiveness determinants.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                   We performed a multivariate regression analysis to test the&#13;
                                                                   ability of two components of the wedgeâ&#128;&#148;scope and financial&#13;
                                                                   autonomyâ&#128;&#148;to explain competitiveness outcomes. The ordi-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 4.6 Example correlation analysis output between labor productivity levels and competitiveness&#13;
   determinants, by region&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Physical infrastructure&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Financial infrastructure&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Human capital&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Social infrastructure&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Institutions&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Agglomeration&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Environment&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Source: Oxford Economics Dataset and Various Indices&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                   39&#13;
&amp;#12; nary least squares model controlled for city and year fixed                         interpreted as follows: a 1 percentage point increase in the&#13;
 effects to render a more robust result and reads as follows:                        local share of total government spending (a proxy we used&#13;
                                                                                     for measuring the scope of a mayorâ&#128;&#153;s administrative remit)&#13;
 (4.1)	     City Competitiveness Outcomesct=Î±c+Î²t+                                   is associated with a commensurate 0.132 percentage point&#13;
 	          Î´Mayorâ&#128;&#153; sWedgect+xct+ Îµct,                                               increase in job growth and a 0.179 percent decrease in house-&#13;
                                                                                     hold disposable income. When financial autonomy is used&#13;
 Where Î±c and Î²t are city and year fixed effects, respectively,                      as a proxy for a mayorâ&#128;&#153;s administrative remit, the regression&#13;
 and xct denotes the determinants of city competitiveness                            results show that a 1 percentage point increase in the share&#13;
 introduced as controls. The dependent variable measures                             of a cityâ&#128;&#153;s revenues raised locally is associated with a 0.174&#13;
 competitiveness outcomes for a given city (denoted by the                           percentage point decrease in GDP growth, a 0.115 percent de-&#13;
 subscript c) at a given point in time (denoted by the subscript                     crease in labor productivity, and a 0.263 percent decrease in&#13;
 t). Similarly, the explanatory variable also varies by a given                      household disposable income. Explanations of these regres-&#13;
 city and year. The numerical coefficients are shown in table                        sion results are presented in the following section.&#13;
 4.3 and depicted visually in figure 4.7. The results should be&#13;
&#13;
 Table 4.3	            Regression results from mayorâ&#128;&#153;s wedge model&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                Labor                Disposable&#13;
  City competitiveness outcomes                            GDP growth               Job growth            productivity                  income&#13;
  Mayorâ&#128;&#153;s wedge: scope                                          0.000335              0.00132***               â&#136;&#146;0.000337                â&#136;&#146;0.00179*&#13;
&#13;
                                                              (0.000827)              (0.000405)              (0.000643)                 (0.00101)&#13;
                                                              â&#136;&#146;0.00174**              â&#136;&#146;0.000629                â&#136;&#146;0.00115*              â&#136;&#146;0.00263**&#13;
  Mayorâ&#128;&#153;s wedge: financial autonomy                           (0.000809)              (0.000406)              (0.000656)                 (0.00113)&#13;
  Constant                                                        10.10***                6.425***                3.521***                3.431***&#13;
                                                                   (0.322)                 (0.217)                  (0.202)                 (0.397)&#13;
  Observations                                                       1,897                   1,897                   1,897                    1,841&#13;
  R-squared                                                          0.998                   0.998                   0.997                    0.992&#13;
  Year fixed effects                                                    Yes                     Yes                     Yes                      Yes&#13;
  City fixed effects                                                    Yes                     Yes                     Yes                      Yes&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Source: authorsâ&#128;&#153; own analysis; dataset used is authors combining oxford economics dataset and various indices&#13;
 Note: We also include a number of controls, such as physical infrastructure provisions: number of nurses, doctors, and teachers as well city Gini index to cap-&#13;
 ture the level of inequality. However, because they were not the focus of this regression exercise, we highlight only the mayorâ&#128;&#153;s wedge results here.&#13;
 Significance level: * = 10 percent, ** = 5 percent, *** = 1 percent.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 4.7	           Size, direction, and significance of mayorâ&#128;&#153;s wedge coefficients from global regression analysis&#13;
&#13;
  Scope&#13;
                                 *&#13;
                                                                                                          Disposable income per capita&#13;
                                                                              *                           Labor productivity&#13;
                                                                                                          Job growth&#13;
                                                                                                          GDP growth&#13;
  Autonomy&#13;
                       *                                                                               * Statistically significant correlation at the 10% level&#13;
                                         *&#13;
&#13;
                                  *&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                       Correlation coefficient (% change)&#13;
Source: authorsâ&#128;&#153; own analysis; dataset used is authors combining oxford economics dataset and various indices&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  40&#13;
Significance level: * = 10 percent.&#13;
&amp;#12;Findings from the mayorâ&#128;&#153;s wedge analysis: Scope                   sectors bloated with cronies may actually be associated with&#13;
and autonomy                                                      improved economic outcomes. Complicating matters further,&#13;
                                                                  proxies of public sector capacity such as public sector output&#13;
The analysis found that delegating more public functions to       per worker were negatively associated with outcomes globally.&#13;
mayorsâ&#128;&#148;that is, expanding the scope of a mayorâ&#128;&#153;s adminis-&#13;
trative remit, proxied by the local share of total government     To try to get around these global issues, we explored the per-&#13;
spendingâ&#128;&#148;is positively associated with higher levels of           formance of proxies for capacity in two institutional contexts:&#13;
employment in cities but negatively associated with income.       China and the European Union. In China, we took advantage&#13;
Financial autonomyâ&#128;&#148;the share of local government revenues         of a recent policy change that upgraded particular counties&#13;
raised locally and not transferred by the central govern-         to city status in an effort to better understand the economic&#13;
mentâ&#128;&#148;is negatively associated with all competitiveness out-       effect of an enlarged administrative remit. We found that&#13;
comes except job growth. This finding suggests that, globally,    expanded scope alone was not sufficient for improving firm-&#13;
cities perform better with stable revenue streams from the        and city-level economic outcomes. Instead, only high-capacity&#13;
central government.                                               citiesâ&#128;&#148;defined here as those with (a) a larger share of public&#13;
                                                                  employees paid through public finance out of the total pop-&#13;
Findings from the mayorâ&#128;&#153;s wedge analysis:                         ulation (proxying for adequate and institutionalized human&#13;
                                                                  capital in the public sector) and (b) higher tax extraction&#13;
Capacity&#13;
                                                                  capability, as defined by local tax revenues normalized by&#13;
Another important aspect of the efficacy of local govern-         local GDPâ&#128;&#148;appear to succeed in translating an expanded&#13;
ments is their ability to design and implement sound policies     remit into improved competitiveness outcomes (see Zhu and&#13;
in the spaces that fall within their remitâ&#128;&#148;in short, their        Mukim 2015). The other exercise took advantage of public&#13;
capacity. Unfortunately, attempts to directly measure local       employee productivity data from the European Union to find&#13;
government capacityâ&#128;&#148;the ability of a government to execute        that cities with larger administrative scopes and high levels&#13;
and implement policy efficiently and capablyâ&#128;&#148;accurately and       of public sector productivity perform better on measures of&#13;
systematically across countries met methodological road-          job growth. Using the size of the public sector as a proxy for&#13;
blocks. The size of the public sector, a proxy for inputs, was    capacity, however, reveals a negative association with GDP,&#13;
strongly positively correlated with outcomes but is fraught       jobs, and income growth. This finding stands in contrast to&#13;
with complications ranging from issues of endogeneity to          the China finding.&#13;
perverse conclusions, such as the implication that large public&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                               41&#13;
&amp;#12;Variation in the effect of the mayorâ&#128;&#153;s wedge by                                  The positive association between mayorâ&#128;&#153;s scope and job&#13;
region and city type                                                             growth observed at the global level extends only to OECD&#13;
                                                                                 cities (with statistical significance) at the regional level,&#13;
We then ran the regression by region and city typology and                       where it is also positively and significantly correlated with&#13;
found that the nature and effect of the mayorâ&#128;&#153;s wedge appears                    GDP growth.&#13;
to vary significantly across regions (see figure 4.8). The may-&#13;
orâ&#128;&#153;s wedge appears to have better explanatory power in OECD                      Sub-Saharan African and European and Central Asian cities&#13;
and Middle Eastern and North African cities than it does in                      drive the negative relationship observed between autonomy&#13;
Latin American and Caribbean or Sub-Saharan African cities,                      and job growth globally. GDP growth in the Middle East and&#13;
where we found few statistically significant relationships.                      North Africa and job growth in cities of the Middle East and&#13;
                                                                                 North Africa and the OECD, in contrast, appear to benefit&#13;
                                                                                 from local government autonomy.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 4.8: Size, direction, and significance of mayorâ&#128;&#153;s wedge coefficients from regional regression analysis&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                Gross Domestic Product                                                Autonomy                         Jobs&#13;
                                                                                      Scope&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   Middle East and North Africa                                         *                                     OECD&#13;
                                                                                                                                             *&#13;
                            OECD                            *                       Middle East and North Africa                                 *&#13;
                                                                *&#13;
   Latin America and Caribbean                                                     Latin America and Caribbean&#13;
&#13;
             Sub-Saharan Africa                                                          Europe and Central Asia                   *&#13;
                                                                                                                                        *&#13;
        Europe and Central Asia                                                               Sub-Saharan Africa         *&#13;
&#13;
                                    Correlation coefficient (% change)                                                 Correlation coefficient (% change)&#13;
&#13;
                                                            * Statistically significant correlation at the 10% level&#13;
&#13;
Source: Authorsâ&#128;&#153; own analysis; dataset used is authors combining Oxford Economics dataset and various indices&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
42&#13;
&amp;#12;Cutting the data by city primacy and size instead of by region                    GDP and job growth in industrial cities. We expect industrial&#13;
reveals a different set of findings (figure 4.9). The scope of                    cities to vary more in their economic specialization than cit-&#13;
a mayorâ&#128;&#153;s remit is positively associated with job growth at                       ies oriented to either consumer or high-end services sectors,&#13;
all city sizes, but the relationship is stronger in small and                     given what we know about the economics of agglomeration.&#13;
secondary cities than it is in large or primary ones. Fiscal                      The logic is that local leaders may therefore be better attuned&#13;
autonomy is negatively associated with job growth and GDP                         to the particular needs of their specialized regional econo-&#13;
growth in small and secondary cities but shows little relation-                   mies.&#13;
ship in large or primary ones.10&#13;
&#13;
Together these findings suggestâ&#128;&#148;perhaps intuitivelyâ&#128;&#148;that                              These findings suggest that small and secondary cit-&#13;
small and secondary cities benefit from direction by the cen-&#13;
                                                                                      ies benefit from direction by the central government&#13;
tral government but remain competent stewards of financial&#13;
inflows, better allocating resources in their administrative                          but remain competent stewards of financial inflows,&#13;
areas according to local needs and particularities. Potentially                       better allocating resources in their administrative&#13;
underscoring this point is the last cut of the mayorâ&#128;&#153;s wedge                          areas according to local needs and particularities.&#13;
analysis, which although not depicted here, finds that scope&#13;
is strongly and significantly positively associated with job&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 4.9 Size, direction, and significance of mayorâ&#128;&#153;s wedge coefficients from city size regression analysis&#13;
&#13;
                Gross Domestic Product                                                 Autonomy                           Jobs&#13;
                                                                                       Scope&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        Primary                                                                          Primary                                                 *&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                         *                                                                                                                           *&#13;
    Secondary                                                                         Secondary&#13;
                                                                                                                   *&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                             *&#13;
          Large                                                                             Large&#13;
                                                               *&#13;
&#13;
                             *                                                                                                                   *&#13;
          Small                                                                            Small&#13;
                                                                                                                    *&#13;
                          Correlation coefficient (% change)                                                     Correlation coefficient (% change)&#13;
&#13;
                                                      * Statistically significant correlation at the 10% level&#13;
&#13;
Source: Authorsâ&#128;&#153; own analysis; dataset used is authors combining Oxford Economics dataset and various indices&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                             43&#13;
&amp;#12;        How does inequality relate to city                                where Î±c and Î²t are city and year fixed effects, respectively,&#13;
        competitiveness?                                                  and Ineg_migrate is an identity variable taking the value 1 if the&#13;
                                                                          city experiences a negative net migration. The dependent&#13;
        Even without significant increases in administrative powers,      variable Gini index measures city inequality for a given city&#13;
        competitive cities are good at reducing inequalityâ&#128;&#148;especial-      (denoted by the subscript c) at a given point in time (denoted&#13;
        ly cities that attract a huge influx of migrants. Descriptive     by the subscript t).&#13;
        results across 750 cities spanning 12 years suggest that rapid&#13;
        city-GDP growth at early stages of incomes is associated with     The regression results show that cities with negative migra-&#13;
        larger reductions in inequalityâ&#128;&#148;with momentum slowing at          tion rates tend to be more equal (table 4.4). In other words,&#13;
        the US$20,000 per capita level and then reversing when cities     cities that see an influx of migrants tend to perform worse on&#13;
        reach income levels of US$50,000 to US$60,000 per capita.         inequality indicators. This result may be a natural by-product&#13;
                                                                          of the process of urbanization, as low-income migrants move&#13;
        We performed a nonlinear multivariate regression analysis         to growing cities in search of job opportunities. Under such&#13;
        controlling for year and city fixed effects to test the robust-   circumstances, we would expect to observe a high inequality&#13;
        ness of the observation that richer and more competitive          ratio. As the income level of a city increases, however, the&#13;
        cities tend to see a decrease in inequality:11                    inequality level of a city also seems to drop, bringing shared&#13;
                                                                          prosperity to city residents. In the dynamic sense and over&#13;
        (4.2) 	         City Gini Indexct=Î±c+Î²t+Î´City_GDP_PCct+           time, then, economic development reduces or â&#128;&#156;mops upâ&#128;&#157; a&#13;
        	               Î¸City_GDP_PCct2+Ineg_migrate+Îµct,                 cityâ&#128;&#153;s initial inequality.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        Figure 4.10 Inequality by income in 750 OE cities                 Table 4.4 Regression results of city inequality versus&#13;
                                                                            city income level&#13;
                                  City        Fitted values&#13;
                  0.8&#13;
                                                                           City inequality level                            City Gini index&#13;
                                                                           City GDP per capita                                      â&#136;&#146;0.000683***&#13;
                  0.6                                                                                                                  (0.000183)&#13;
Citi Gini Index&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                           City GDP per capita^2                                        â&#136;&#146;9.72e-07&#13;
                                                                                                                                        (1.53e-06)&#13;
                  0.4                                                      City with negative immigration                              â&#136;&#146;0.00142**&#13;
                                                                                                                                       (0.000637)&#13;
                                                                           Constant                                                        0.470***&#13;
                  0.2&#13;
                                                                                                                                         (0.00205)&#13;
                               City GDP per capita (US$, thousands)        Observations                                                        8,504&#13;
                                                                           R-squared                                                           0.967&#13;
        Source: Oxford Economics Dataset&#13;
                                                                           Year fixed effects                                                    Yes&#13;
                                                                           City fixed effects                                                    Yes&#13;
&#13;
                                                                          Source: authorsâ&#128;&#153; own analysis; dataset used is oxford econ dataset&#13;
                                                                          Significance level: ** = 5 percent, *** = 1 percent.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
             44&#13;
&amp;#12;5. Attempting to Arrive at a List of the                                     duced the counterintuitive finding that many cities that did&#13;
Worldâ&#128;&#153;s Most Competitive Cities                                              not meet the competitiveness criteriaâ&#128;&#148;which were defined&#13;
                                                                             at the country levelâ&#128;&#148;still performed very strongly by global&#13;
An attempt to arrive at a short list of the most competitive                 standards. The phenomenon stems from the fact that even&#13;
cities provided a cautionary lesson about the challenges                     relatively rapid growth in cities of Europe and Central Asia,&#13;
inherent in comparing a world of cities even after attempting                Latin America and the Caribbean, or the OECD pales in com-&#13;
to control for national contexts.                                            parison with the growth rates achieved by even below-aver-&#13;
                                                                             age performers in the worldâ&#128;&#153;s other regions. Even within East&#13;
We settled on three criteria to operationalize city competi-                 Asia and Pacific, the disparities across countries were stark.&#13;
tiveness. To be considered one of the worldâ&#128;&#153;s most competi-&#13;
tive cities, a city had to outperform its country (because even              A future analysis might attempt to define city outperfor-&#13;
in a globalizing world, a city cannot be taken outside of its                mance at the regional level and then determine the worldâ&#128;&#153;s&#13;
country context) on private sector job growth, productivity                  most competitive cities on a region-by-region basis. However,&#13;
growth, and household disposable income growth. Growth                       city competitiveness just may remain difficult to quantify, to&#13;
had to be positive, meaning that a city could not be deemed                  generalize across regions of the world, and to demarcate with&#13;
competitive simply by contracting more slowly than its coun-                 a clear threshold. After all, none of the other popular city&#13;
try. Growth rates were measured in annualized terms from                     competitiveness indexes analyzed in section 3 was found to&#13;
2000 to 2012.12                                                              have robust global predictive power either.&#13;
&#13;
In the end, 130 of 750 cities outperformed their countries on                As a result, we decided to quantify city competitiveness on&#13;
all three aspects of competitiveness (figure 5.1). The analy-                a metric-by-metric basis. Throughout this paper and the&#13;
sis yielded a list that was on its face intuitive and included               accompanying framework paper, we have adopted a simple&#13;
several cities from the World Bank Group Competitive Cities                  and straightforward approach to comparing the performance&#13;
Knowledge Base projectâ&#128;&#153;s case study: Bucaramanga (Colom-                     of competitive cities to their peers: we compare the top 10&#13;
bia), Coimbatore (India), and Gaziantep (Turkey).                            percent of performers on any given metric to the remainder,&#13;
                                                                             or at times the top quarter. This methodology allows competi-&#13;
However, given the diversity of their country and regional                   tiveness to be determined dynamically and depending on the&#13;
contexts, the most competitive cities did not look particularly              indicator in questionâ&#128;&#148;thereby accounting for the reality that&#13;
competitive at the global level. Comparing the performance                   competitiveness has many different dimensions, and rarely&#13;
of the 130 most competitive cities as defined with the re-                   does one city outshine the rest.&#13;
maining set of cities on economic outcomes of interest pro-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 5.1 The 130 cities that outperformed their countries on all three indicators of city competitiveness&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                   Not labeled in Europe&#13;
                                                                                                   and Central Asia&#13;
                                                                                                   Dnipropetrovosk, Kharkiv,&#13;
                                                                                                   Krasnodor, Voronezh&#13;
                                       Not labeled in OECD&#13;
                                       Budapest, Copenhage,&#13;
                                       Honolulu&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                               Not labeled in East Asia&#13;
                                                                                                                               and Pacific&#13;
                                                                                                                               Anshan, Dezhou, Jining,&#13;
                                                                                                                               Liaocheng, Tianjin, Xianyang,&#13;
                                                                                                                               Xianxiang, Yulin&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                    Not labeled in&#13;
                                                    Sub-Saharan Africa&#13;
    Not labeled in Latin America                    Abeokuta, Benin City,                   Not labeled in South Asia&#13;
    and the Caribbean                               Enugu, Ibadan, Kaduna,                  Ahmedabad, Amravati,&#13;
    Queretaro, San Luis Postoi                      Lagos, Maiduguri, Oyo,                  Aurangabad, Coimbatore,&#13;
                                                    Zaria                                   Guntur, Hyderabad, Kozhikode,&#13;
                                                                                            Thiruvananthapuram, Tiruchi-&#13;
                                                                                            rappalli, Tiruppur, Warangal&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Source: Oxford Economics Dataset&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                               45&#13;
&amp;#12;6. Conclusion                                                     of their quality and ability to predict successful economic&#13;
                                                                  outcomes. Correlation analyses that explore the relationship&#13;
This technical overview of global quantitative analytics          between determinants of competitiveness, such as institu-&#13;
attempts to build a knowledge base on city economic per-          tions, physical infrastructure, social infrastructure, human&#13;
formance and city competitiveness. Compared with similar          capital, and innovation, helped peel the onion further. Initial&#13;
efforts, this technical exercise stands out in terms of its       findings led to an intriguing hypothesis for further testing:&#13;
geographic coverage (750 of the largest cities across 140 coun-   that cities must square away a succession of building blocks&#13;
tries); its breadth and depth of topics (urban inequality, job    of competitivenessâ&#128;&#148;institutions and social and physical in-&#13;
creation through tradable sectors and FDIs, key factors that      frastructure at lower incomes, then innovation capacityâ&#128;&#148;to&#13;
drive city competitiveness outcomes, and so on); and, impor-      build the human capital base required to compete, grow, and&#13;
tantly, its identification of global and regional trends perti-   prosper as a high-income city. More robust techniques such&#13;
nent to economic development in cities (city development          as fixed-effects regressions were then used to understand&#13;
pathways, mechanisms linking governance and outcomes,             associations and generate findings regarding the mechanisms&#13;
and the like).                                                    that drive competitiveness. For instance, one of the import-&#13;
                                                                  ant findings is that a&#13;
Beginning with the basics, the very first stage of the analyt-    larger mayorâ&#128;&#153;s wedge, in&#13;
ics exercise involves benchmarking a global sample of 750         particular the scope of          Cities must square away&#13;
cities by comparing their performance with each other, with       the mayorâ&#128;&#153;s administra-          a succession of building&#13;
regional and national averages, and over time. Interesting        tive remit, generally has        blocks of competitive-&#13;
global trends and findings start to emerge. First, cities gen-    a positive relationship          ness â&#128;&#148; institutions&#13;
erate a disproportionately large share of new private sector      with city competitive-&#13;
jobs. In fact, job creation in cities is linked to the broader    ness outcomes. However,&#13;
                                                                                                   and social and physical&#13;
urban inequality debate: cities that observe a large influx of    this effect is usually           infrastructure at lower&#13;
migrants looking for jobs tend to see their inequality indi-      conditional on capacity:         incomes, then innovation&#13;
cators rise sharply initially, but the evidence presented in      the local governmentâ&#128;&#153;s           capacity â&#128;&#148; in order to&#13;
this paper posits that as cities develop, inequality drops as     capacity determines              build the human capital&#13;
migrants are assimilated into the local labor force. Second,      whether mayors can ef-           base required to compete,&#13;
the global data support a particular development pathway for      fectively harness and use&#13;
cities: from market towns to production centers to creative       their new powers to bring&#13;
                                                                                                   grow and prosper as a&#13;
and financial services hubs. At the same time, these path-        growth and prosperity to         high income city.&#13;
ways are not etched in stone: for instance, the manufactur-       their cities.	&#13;
ing sector is slowing as an engine of growth and structural&#13;
change, especially for low-income African cities. Third, in       We find no holy grail of city competitiveness. This analysis&#13;
terms of absolute volume, after normalizing using city GDP,       has left us, and probably others, wanting. We did not set out&#13;
two-thirds of the most attractive investment destinations are     to, nor did we expect to, uncover singular truths about city&#13;
in Sub-Saharan Africa, South Asia, and East Asia and Pacific      competitiveness. That being said, detailed and comprehensive&#13;
excluding China. And finally, the tradable sector turns out to    data sets focusing on particular regions should produce in-&#13;
be important for cities not just because it creates more and      sights specific to the cases at hand. This work points to global&#13;
better jobs, but also because it creates a multiplier for jobs    trends on topics such as the existence of income traps or of&#13;
created in the non-tradable sectors. In cities with lackluster    earlier deindustrialization, but these trends require further&#13;
tradable sectors, the non-tradable sectors also lose momen-       exploration to substantiate. Nonetheless, all of the research&#13;
tum.                                                              underlines the importance of understanding global trends&#13;
                                                                  and basing conclusions about them on reliable data. It also&#13;
The next stage of the technical exercise included an ex-          illustrates the value of city-based analyses, both broad based&#13;
tensive literature review, followed by a survey of existing       and customizable, depending on the client and the question&#13;
and frequently used city indexes along with an assessment         at hand.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
46&#13;
&amp;#12;Notes&#13;
1	&#13;
   The World Bankâ&#128;&#153;s 2009 World Development Report (World Bank 2009,                8&#13;
                                                                                     Marshallian externalities refer to benefits that firms derive simply by&#13;
105) cites sources indicating that 50 percent of world GDP is produced on          locating near other firms engaged in similar activitiesâ&#128;&#148;knowledge spill-&#13;
just 1.5 percent of the worldâ&#128;&#153;s land and that 90 percent of world GDP is           overs, labor market pooling, and specialized suppliersâ&#128;&#148;as observed by&#13;
produced on just 16 percent of land; however, the land area estimate for all       Alfred Marshall in Principles of Economics (1890). Jacobian externalities,&#13;
of the worldâ&#128;&#153;s cities is unknown.                                                  in contrast, refer to the benefits that firms derive from locating near firms&#13;
 Throughout this study, regions are classified according to the standard&#13;
2	                                                                                 engaged in unrelated activitiesâ&#128;&#148;chance encounters, differing perspectives,&#13;
World Bank practice.                                                               pollination across industries, and serendipitous innovationâ&#128;&#148;as observed&#13;
                                                                                   by Jane Jacobs in The Economy of Cities (1969).&#13;
3	&#13;
  For more on city selection and other methodological questions relating to&#13;
the data set generally, see OE (2014).&#13;
                                                                                   9&#13;
                                                                                    For a comprehensive review of literature on the drivers of growth in cities&#13;
                                                                                   in terms of city size, density, and per capita income, see Duranton and Puga&#13;
4	&#13;
  These descriptive statistics do not pretend to summarize the average             (2014). For a detailed analysis on the drivers of growth in Colombian cities,&#13;
characteristics of cities in each region; they merely summarize the 750 cit-       see Duranton (2015).&#13;
ies contained in this specific data set. This section is designed to contextual-&#13;
ize the subsequent analysis of this data set.&#13;
                                                                                   10&#13;
                                                                                     According to the literature, fiscal decentralization (that is, local govern-&#13;
                                                                                   ments having more fiscal autonomy) has a mixed effect across countries.&#13;
5&#13;
 OECD cities are representative cities located in developed countries that         This result is probably because fiscal decentralization has to be coupled&#13;
are OECD members.                                                                  with political and administrative decentralization when being evaluated,&#13;
6&#13;
 For a thorough review of the ambiguities of the literature, see GÃ¶rg and          because a systematic approach that takes into account the design of fiscal&#13;
Greenaway (2003).                                                                  decentralization is more relevant than the fiscal dimension alone. See Mar-&#13;
7&#13;
 The model is similar to the one used in Barro (2015). The conditional con-        tinez-Vazquez, Lago-PeÃ±as, and Sacchi (2015).&#13;
vergence rate of 1.4 percent is from a model without fixed effects, whereas        11&#13;
                                                                                     A robust test taking the log of city GDP per capita to account for extremely&#13;
9.0 percent is from a model with fixed effects (plus additional controls such      values was performed, and similar results were obtained.&#13;
as education, FDI, and provision of other public services). Positive and sig-      12&#13;
                                                                                     For some cities, data did not become available until later in the period. In&#13;
nificant unconditional convergence rates are obtained as well, at an interval      such cases, city performance was assessed over the shorter time span.&#13;
of 1.9 percent (without fixed effects) and 4.5 percent (with fixed effects). See&#13;
Barro (2015) for comparison for this convergence exercise.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                47&#13;
&amp;#12;REFERENCES&#13;
Barro, Robert J. 2015. â&#128;&#156;Convergence and Modernisation.â&#128;&#157; Economic      OE (Oxford Economics). 2014. â&#128;&#156;Global Cities 2030 Historical Data:&#13;
   Journal 125 (585): 911â&#128;&#147;42.                                           Methodology Note.â&#128;&#157; Oxford, U.K.&#13;
Duranton, Gilles. 2015. Determinants of city growth in Colombia.      Samad, Taimur, Nancy Lozano-Gracia, and Alexandra Panman, eds.&#13;
  Mimeographed, Wharton School, University of Pennsylvania.             2012. Colombia Urbanization Review: Amplifying the Gains from the&#13;
                                                                        Urban Transition. Washington, DC: World Bank.&#13;
Duranton, Gilles, and Diego Puga. 2014. â&#128;&#156;The Growth of Cities.â&#128;&#157; In&#13;
  Handbook of Economic Growth, vol. 2B, edited by Philippe Aghion     Shapiro, Jesse M. 2006. â&#128;&#156;Smart Cities: Quality of Life, Productivity,&#13;
  and Steven Durlauf, 781â&#128;&#147;853. Amsterdam: Elsevier.                      and the Growth Effects of Human Capital.â&#128;&#157; Review of Economics&#13;
                                                                         and Statistics 88 (2): 324â&#128;&#147;35&#13;
Gennaioli, Nicola, Rafael La Porta, Florencio Lopez De Silanes, and&#13;
  Andrei Shleifer. 2014. â&#128;&#156;Growth in Regions.â&#128;&#157; Journal of Economic     UN DESA (United Nations Department of Economic and Social&#13;
  Growth 19 (3): 259â&#128;&#147;309.                                               Affairs), Population Division. 2015. World Urbanization Prospects:&#13;
                                                                        The 2014 Revision. New York: United Nations.&#13;
GÃ¶rg, Holger, and David Greenaway. 2003. â&#128;&#156;Much Ado about Noth-&#13;
  ing? Do Domestic Firms Really Benefit from FDI?â&#128;&#157; IZA Discus-        World Bank. 2009. World Development Report 2009: Reshaping Eco-&#13;
  sion Paper 944, Institute for the Study of Labor, Bonn, Germany.      nomic Geography. Washington, DC: World Bank.&#13;
Jacobs, Jane. 1969. The Economy of Cities. New York: Random House.    â&#128;&#148;â&#128;&#148;â&#128;&#148;. 2013. Planning, Connecting, and Financing Citiesâ&#128;&#148;Now:&#13;
                                                                       Priorities for City Leaders. Washington, DC: World Bank.&#13;
Marshall, Alfred. 1890. Principles of Economics. London: Macmillan.&#13;
                                                                      World Bank Group. 2015. Competitive Cities for Jobs and Growth:&#13;
Martinez-Vazquez, Jorge, Santiago Lago-PeÃ±as, and Agnese Sacchi.&#13;
                                                                        What, Who and How. Washington, DC: World Bank.&#13;
  2015. â&#128;&#156;The Impact of Fiscal Decentralization: A Survey.â&#128;&#157; GEN&#13;
  Working Paper A2015-5, Governance and Economics Research            World Bank and DRC (Development Research Center of the State&#13;
  Network, Universidade de Vigo, Vigo, Spain.                           Council, the Peopleâ&#128;&#153;s Republic of China). 2014. Urban China:&#13;
                                                                        Toward Efficient, Inclusive, and Sustainable Urbanization. Washing-&#13;
Moretti, Enrico. 2004. â&#128;&#156;Human Capital Externalities in Cities.â&#128;&#157;&#13;
                                                                        ton, DC: World Bank.&#13;
  In Handbook of Regional and Urban Economics, vol. 4, edited by&#13;
  J. Vernon Henderson and Jacques-FranÃ§ois Thisse, 2243â&#128;&#147;91.           Zhu, T. Juni, and Megha Mukim. 2015. â&#128;&#156;Empowering Cities: Good&#13;
  Amsterdam: Elsevier.                                                  for Growth? Evidence from China.â&#128;&#157; Policy Research Working&#13;
                                                                        Paper 7193, World Bank Group, Washington, DC.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
48&#13;
&amp;#12;49&#13;
&amp;#12;Funding for the companion papers and the main report was provided by&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CIIP     Competitive Industries and Innovation Program&#13;
&#13;
Financed by                               in partnership with&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
www.theciip.org&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Find the companion papers and the main report at&#13;
www.worldbank.org/competitivecities&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="25658521">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2015/12/25658521/city-analytics
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2015/12/25658521/city-analytics</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2015/12/25658521/city-analytics</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2015-12-08T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2015-12-09T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <docm_id>090224b083c42092</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b083c41130</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2015/12/09/090224b083c42092/2_0/Rendered/INDEX/City0analytics.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2015/12/09/090224b083c42092/2_0/Rendered/PDF/City0analytics.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2015-12-09T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2015-12-01T00:15:04Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            City analytics
        </repnme>
        <docna>
            City analytics
        </docna>
        <display_title>City analytics</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2015/12/25658521/city-analytics</listing_relative_url>
        <subtopic>Public Sector Management and Reform,Health Systems Development &amp; Reform,City Development Strategies,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Subnational Economic Development</subtopic>
        <docty>Working Paper</docty>
        <teratopic>Health, Nutrition and Population,Public Sector Development,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth,Urban Development</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Fikri,Kenan Tansel</author>
            <author>Zhu,Tingting Juni</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>090224b083c42092_2_0</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Health, Nutrition and Population,Public Sector Development,Macroeconomics and Economic Growth,Urban Development</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            capitals, living standards, forecasts,
            national output, city size, urbanization, production, sal,
            city, urban services, coefficients, national economy,
            structural change, disposable income, national economies,
            income, administrative decentralization, gdp per capita,
            differentials, exports, revenues, economic structure,
            employment in cities, mayors, welfare, gross value,
            distribution, variables, correlation coefficient, tax,
            inputs, cities, towns, wealth, economic structures, trends,
            subnational, development, correlation analyses, influence,
            city residents, per capita income, metropolitan areas,
            industrial structure, productivity, city development,
            externalities, industrialization, criteria, business
            services, urban transition, markets, revenue streams, mayor,
            public finance, city sizes, city performance, income levels,
            capital expenditure, tax revenues, dividends, urban
            competitiveness, total employment, economic specialization,
            natural resources, averaging, gross domestic product, wealth
            creation, economic research, infrastructure, expenditure,
            human capital, value added, city leaders, economic
            performance, capital, wages, economic outcomes,
            transparency, financial crisis, utilities, value,
            competitiveness, benchmarking, policy makers, credit, large
            cities, patents, secondary cities, central government,
            national income, agriculture, economy, expenditures,
            economic development potential, measurement, city economies,
            urban development, economics, town, quality of life, market
            towns, city competitiveness, regression analysis,
            governance, economic development, city productivity, trade,
            fiscal autonomy, gdp, goods, theory, subnational regions,
            correlation analysis, economies of scale, technology
            transfer, growth rate, investment, city profiles, poverty,
            decentralization, revenue, capital expenditures, community,
            urban economics, industrial sector, economics research,
            social infrastructure, public employees, industrial” sector,
            outcomes, ease of doing business, urbanization process,
            fiscal decentralization, growth potential, competitive advantages
        </keywd>
        <owner>LCREC - External Communications (LCREC)</owner>
        <repnb>101718</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Expenditures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Investment Plan</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civil Service Employment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civil Service Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Capital</ml:concept><ml:concept>Managing People</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Employment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>GVCs</ml:concept><ml:concept>Production Sharing Networks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Value Chains</ml:concept><ml:concept>Foreign Direct Investment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wage Setting</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages, Compensation and Benefits</ml:concept><ml:concept>Foreign Direct Investments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Linkages</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Patents</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Jobs and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Competitive Cities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Investment Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resources Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Global Value Chains</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investment Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages</ml:concept><ml:concept>FDI Spillovers</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>