<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>﻿OFFICIAL    0&#13;
DOCUMENTS&#13;
ADMINISTRATION AGREEMENT&#13;
among&#13;
MINISTRY OF FINANCE OF THE PEOPLE'S REPUBLIC OF CHINA&#13;
and&#13;
INTERNATIONAL BANK FOR RECONSTRUCTION AND DEVELOPMENT&#13;
INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPMENT ASSOCIATION&#13;
INTERNATIONAL FINANCE CORPORATION&#13;
concerning the&#13;
CHINA-WORLD BANK GROUP PARTNERSHIP FACILITY&#13;
SINGLE-DONOR TRUST FUNDS&#13;
July/6, 2015&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿Administration Agreement among the Ministry of Finance of the People's Republic of China and the&#13;
International Bank for Reconstruction and Development, the International Development Association, and&#13;
the International Finance Corporation concerning the China- World Bank Group Partnership Facility&#13;
Single-Donor Trust Funds (TF Nos. 072447 &amp; 072456)&#13;
1.    The International Bank for Reconstruction and Development (IBRD), the International Development&#13;
Association (IDA) (IBRD and IDA collectively referred to as the "Bank") and the International Finance&#13;
Corporation (IFC) (the Bank and IFC collectively referred to as the "Participating WBG Organizations" and&#13;
each a "Participating WBG Organization") acknowledge that the Ministry of Finance of the People's Republic&#13;
of China (the "Donor", and together with the Participating WBG Organizations, the "Parties" and each a&#13;
"Party") agrees to provide the sum of fifty million United States Dollars (USD50,000,000) (the "Contribution")&#13;
for the China-World Bank Group Partnership Facility Single-Donor Trust Funds (the "Trust Funds") in&#13;
accordance with the terms of this Administration Agreement.&#13;
2.     The Contribution shall be used to finance activities under four windows, assigned under specific trust&#13;
fund numbers, as set forth below and in the "China-World Bank Group Partnership Facility Trust Funds&#13;
Description" attached hereto as Annex 1, all in accordance with the terms of this Administration Agreement,&#13;
including the "Standard Provisions" attached hereto as Annex 2 and "Governance" attached hereto as Annex 3.&#13;
Trust Fund No. 072447 (China-World Bank Group Partnership Facility Trust Fund):&#13;
Window 1: Investment Projects and Operations&#13;
Window 2: Knowledge Development and South-South Learning&#13;
Window 3: Human Resource Cooperation&#13;
Trust Fund No. 072456 (China-World Bank Group Partnership Facility Pre-Paid Trust Fund):&#13;
Window 4: Financing for Global and Regional Programs&#13;
The Donor and the Participating WBG Organizations agree that the Contribution will initially be allocated to&#13;
TF No. 072456 for Window 4 and subsequently, upon written confirmation by the Donor, an allocation or&#13;
allocations will be made from TF No. 072456 for Window 4 to TF No. 072447 for Windows 1, 2 and 3 or to&#13;
other trust funds or other funding mechanisms for other selected global and regional programs.&#13;
3.     The Donor shall deposit the Contribution in accordance with the following schedule and in the&#13;
currency specified in Section 1 above ("Contribution Currency") into such bank account designated by the&#13;
Bank (each amount deposited hereinafter referred to as an "Installment") upon submission of a payment request&#13;
by the Bank:&#13;
(A)    By October 31, 2015 - ten million United States Dollars (USD10,000,000)&#13;
(B)    By October 31, 2016 - twenty million United States Dollars (USD20,000,000)&#13;
(C)    By October 31, 2017 - twenty million United States Dollars (USD20,000,000)&#13;
4.     When making any deposit, the Donor shall instruct its bank to include in its deposit details information&#13;
(remittance advice) field of its SWIFT deposit message, information indicating: the amount deposited, that the&#13;
deposit is made by the Donor for TF No. 072456 (the China-World Bank Group Partnership Facility Pre-Paid&#13;
Trust Fund), and the date of the deposit (the "Deposit Instructions"). In addition, the Donor shall provide a&#13;
copy of the Deposit Instructions to the Bank's Accounting Trust Funds Division by e-mail sent to&#13;
tfremitadvice@worldbank.org or by fax sent to +1 (202) 614-1315.&#13;
5.     Except with respect to the Deposit Instructions, any notice, request or other communication to be given&#13;
or made under this Administration Agreement shall be in writing and delivered by mail, fax or e-mail to the&#13;
1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿Administration Agreement among the Ministry of Finance of the People's Republic of China and the&#13;
International Bank for Reconstruction and Development, the International Development Association, and&#13;
the International Finance Corporation concerning the China-World Bank Group Partnership Facility&#13;
Single-Donor Trust Funds (TF Nos. 072447 &amp; 072456)&#13;
1.     The International Bank for Reconstruction and Development (IBRD), the International Development&#13;
Association (IDA) (IBRD and IDA collectively referred to as the "Bank") and the International Finance&#13;
Corporation (IFC) (the Bank and IFC collectively referred to as the "Participating WBG Organizations" and&#13;
each a "Participating WBG Organization") acknowledge that the Ministry of Finance of the People's Republic&#13;
of China (the "Donor", and together with the Participating WBG Organizations, the "Parties" and each a&#13;
"Party") agrees to provide the sum of fifty million United States Dollars (USD50,000,000) (the "Contribution")&#13;
for the China-World Bank Group Partnership Facility Single-Donor Trust Funds (the "Trust Funds") in&#13;
accordance with the terms of this Administration Agreement.&#13;
2.     The Contribution shall be used to finance activities under four windows, assigned under specific trust&#13;
fund numbers, as set forth below and in the "China-World Bank Group Partnership Facility Trust Funds&#13;
Description" attached hereto as Annex 1, all in accordance with the terms of this Administration Agreement,&#13;
including the "Standard Provisions" attached hereto as Annex 2 and "Governance" attached hereto as Annex 3.&#13;
Trust Fund No. 072447 (China-World Bank Group Partnership Facility Trust Fund):&#13;
Window 1: Investment Projects and Operations&#13;
Window 2: Knowledge Development and South-South Learning&#13;
Window 3: Human Resource Cooperation&#13;
Trust Fund No. 072456 (China-World Bank Group Partnership Facility Pre-Paid Trust Fund):&#13;
Window 4: Financing for Global and Regional Programs&#13;
The Donor and the Participating WBG Organizations agree that the Contribution will initially be allocated to&#13;
TF No. 072456 for Window 4 and subsequently, upon written confirmation by the Donor, an allocation or&#13;
allocations will be made from TF No. 072456 for Window 4 to TF No. 072447 for Windows 1, 2 and 3 or to&#13;
other trust funds or other funding mechanisms for other selected global and regional programs.&#13;
3.     The Donor shall deposit the Contribution in accordance with the following schedule and in the&#13;
currency specified in Section 1 above ("Contribution Currency") into such bank account designated by the&#13;
Bank (each amount deposited hereinafter referred to as an "Installment") upon submission of a payment request&#13;
by the Bank:&#13;
(A)    By October 31, 2015 - ten million United States Dollars (USD10,000,000)&#13;
(B)    By October 31, 2016 - twenty million United States Dollars (USD20,000,000)&#13;
(C)    By October 31, 2017 - twenty million United States Dollars (USD20,000,000)&#13;
4.     When making any deposit, the Donor shall instruct its bank to include in its deposit details information&#13;
(remittance advice) field of its SWIFT deposit message, information indicating: the amount deposited, that the&#13;
deposit is made by the Donor for TF No. 072456 (the China-World Bank Group Partnership Facility Pre-Paid&#13;
Trust Fund), and the date of the deposit (the "Deposit Instructions"). In addition, the Donor shall provide a&#13;
copy of the Deposit Instructions to the Bank's Accounting Trust Funds Division by e-mail sent to&#13;
tfremitadvice@worldbank.org or by fax sent to +1 (202) 614-1315.&#13;
5.     Except with respect to the Deposit Instructions, any notice, request or other communication to be given&#13;
or made under this Administration Agreement shall be in writing and delivered by mail, fax or e-mail to the&#13;
1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿respective Party's address specified below or at such other address as such Party notifies in writing to the other&#13;
Party from time to time:&#13;
For the Bank:&#13;
Jaehyang So&#13;
Director&#13;
Trust Funds and Partnerships&#13;
Development Finance&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
1818 H Street, NW&#13;
Washington, DC 20433&#13;
U.S.A.&#13;
Tel: +1 202 473 7654&#13;
Fax: +1 202 522 2447&#13;
For IFC:&#13;
Anita Bhatia&#13;
Director&#13;
World Bank Group, Development Partner Relations&#13;
International Finance Corporation&#13;
2121 Pennsylvania Avenue NW&#13;
Washington, DC 20433&#13;
U.S.A.&#13;
Fax: +1 202 974 4344&#13;
For the Donor:&#13;
YANG Yingming&#13;
Deputy Director General&#13;
International Economic and Financial Cooperation Department&#13;
Ministry of Finance&#13;
Sanlihe&#13;
Beijing 100820&#13;
People's Republic of China&#13;
Fax: +86 10 6855 2074&#13;
6.    In the event any amounts are to be returned to the Donor under this Administration Agreement, the&#13;
Bank shall transfer such amounts to the Donor, unless otherwise agreed with the Bank.&#13;
7.     All annexes hereto constitute an integral part of this Administration Agreement, whose terms taken&#13;
together shall constitute the entire agreement and understanding between the Donor and the Participating WBG&#13;
Organizations. Unless otherwise specified in an annex hereto, this Administration Agreement may be amended&#13;
only by written amendment between the Bank and the Donor.&#13;
[remainder of page intentionally left blank]&#13;
2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿8.     Each of the undersigned represents, by confirming its agreement below, that it is authorized to enter&#13;
into this Administration Agreement and act in accordance with these terms and conditions. The Participating&#13;
WBG Organizations and the Donor are requested to sign and date this Administration Agreement, and upon&#13;
possession by the Participating WBG Organizations of this fully signed Administration Agreement, this&#13;
Administration Agreement shall become effective as of the date of the last signature.&#13;
INTERNATIONAL BANK FOR RECONSTRUCTION AND DEVELOPMENT&#13;
INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPMENT ASSOCIATION&#13;
INTERNATIONAL FINANCE CORPORATION&#13;
B :&#13;
T m&#13;
Pr *e&#13;
Date.&#13;
MINISTRY OF FINANCE OF THE PEOPLE'S REPUBLIC OF CHINA&#13;
By:&#13;
LOU Jiwei&#13;
Minister&#13;
Date:&#13;
3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿ANNEX 1&#13;
China-World Bank Group Partnership Facility Trust Funds Description&#13;
This Annex shall be applicable to and form an integral part of the Administration Agreement for the Trust&#13;
Funds between the Participating WBG Organizations and the Donor.&#13;
1.     Objectives&#13;
The objective of the Trust Funds is to assist developing member countries of the Participating WBG&#13;
Organizations achieve inclusive and sustainable development. The China-World Bank Group Partnership&#13;
Facility seeks to enhance cooperation between the Donor and the WBG and leverage different pools of&#13;
resources, both financial and knowledge-based, to support demand-driven activities.&#13;
2.     Activities&#13;
The activities (which may be described as "components" of activities) to be financed by the Trust Funds are:&#13;
2.1    Window 1: Investment Projects and Operations&#13;
(a)    Bank-executed activities, for which the Bank has implementation responsibility:&#13;
Appraisal of investment projects or public-private partnerships (PPPs) in infrastructure sectors&#13;
aligned with the country partnership frameworks for the Bank's member countries and the&#13;
Bank's regional, sector, and thematic strategies, and supervision to ensure the sound&#13;
management of the Recipient-executed activities specified in sub-paragraph (c) below.&#13;
(b)    IFC-executed activities, for which IFC has implementation responsibility:&#13;
Preparation of investment operations or PPPs in infrastructure sectors and IFC's regional,&#13;
sector, and thematic strategies.&#13;
(c)    Recipient-executed activities, for which one or more Recipients (as defined in Annex 2) have&#13;
implementation responsibility:&#13;
Preparation and implementation of investment projects or PPPs in infrastructure sectors&#13;
aligned with the country partnership frameworks for the Bank's member countries and the&#13;
Bank's regional, sector, and thematic strategies, including such projects co-financed by IBRD&#13;
loans and IDA credits and grants.&#13;
2.2    Window 2: Knowledge Development and South-South Learning&#13;
(a)    Bank-executed activities, for which the Bank has implementation responsibility:&#13;
Generation, dissemination, and sharing of development knowledge at the country, regional&#13;
and global levels, including the organization and carrying out of a program of south-south&#13;
knowledge exchange and dissemination activities around key development topics in which&#13;
China and other Bank client countries have significant development experience.&#13;
4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿(b)    IFC-executed activities, for which IFC has implementation responsibility:&#13;
Generation, dissemination, and sharing of development knowledge at the country, regional&#13;
and global levels, including the organization and carrying out of a program of south-south&#13;
knowledge exchange and dissemination activities around key development topics in which&#13;
China and other IFC client countries have significant development experience.&#13;
(c)    Recipient-executed activities, for which one or more Recipients have implementation&#13;
responsibility:&#13;
Generation, dissemination, and sharing of development knowledge at the country, regional&#13;
and global levels.&#13;
2.3    Window 3: Human Resource Cooperation&#13;
(a)    Bank-executed activities, for which the Bank has implementation responsibility:&#13;
Financing of human resource cooperation, provision of training, and organization of learning&#13;
workshops on selected development topics, including financing of officials of the Donor in&#13;
the Bank and financing of Bank staff on External Service with Pay in relevant institutions of&#13;
the Donor.&#13;
(b)    IFC-executed activities, for which IFC has implementation responsibility:&#13;
Financing of human resource cooperation, provision of training, and organization of learning&#13;
workshops on selected development topics, including financing of officials of the Donor&#13;
engaged as consultants in IFC and financing of IFC staff on External Service with Pay in&#13;
relevant institutions of the Donor.&#13;
2.4    Window 4: Financing for Global and Regional Programs&#13;
Support to various innovative development activities through the provision of financing to selected&#13;
global and regional programs managed by the Bank or IFC, including support to the Global&#13;
Infrastructure Facility and to a possible future program providing "transfers out" of funds to&#13;
international organizations to finance officials of the Donor engaged by such international&#13;
organizations.&#13;
3.     Eli2ible Expenditures&#13;
3.1    Window 1: Investment Projects and Operations&#13;
Window 2: Knowledge Development and South-South Learning&#13;
Window 3: Human Resource Cooperation&#13;
(a)    For Bank-executed activities and IFC-executed activities, the Trust Fund funds may be used&#13;
to finance:&#13;
(i)    Associated Overheads&#13;
(ii)   Consultant Fees Individuals with Indirect Costs and Firms&#13;
(iii)  Contractual Services&#13;
5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿(iv)   Equipment and Office Premises Lease Cost&#13;
(v)    Equipment Purchased&#13;
(vi)   Extended Term Consultants with Indirect Costs&#13;
(vii)  Media, Workshops, Conference and Meeting&#13;
(viii)  Staff Costs with Indirect Costs&#13;
(ix)   Temporary Support Staff Costs with Indirect Costs&#13;
(x)    Travel Expenses&#13;
(b)    Any equipment purchased under sub-paragraph (a)(v) above shall be transferred to Recipient-&#13;
government authorities upon closure of the Trust Fund or earlier when no longer required to&#13;
support Trust Fund operations, management or administration; provided such transfer is at no&#13;
cost to the Bank or IFC and is on an "as-is, where-is" basis without warranty or guarantee&#13;
from the Bank or IFC. If such disposal method is not feasible, the Bank or IFC shall seek&#13;
another means of disposal in conformity with Bank or IFC policies and procedures, as the case&#13;
may be, including potentially donation to organizations that have a charitable or non-profit&#13;
status.&#13;
(c)    For Recipient-executed activities, the Trust Fund funds may be used to finance eligible&#13;
expenditures in accordance with the Bank's applicable policies and procedures.&#13;
3.2    Window 4: Financing for Global and Regional Programs&#13;
The separate agreement(s) the Donor has entered, or shall have entered, into for any global or regional&#13;
program, including for support to the Global Infrastructure Facility, will set out the Eligible&#13;
Expenditures under such program or activity.&#13;
4.     Taxes&#13;
4.1    The foregoing activities and categories of expenditures may include the financing of taxes in&#13;
accordance with the Bank's or IFC's applicable policies and procedures.&#13;
6&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿ANNEX 2&#13;
Standard Provisions&#13;
This Annex shall be applicable to and form an integral part of the Administration Agreement for the China-&#13;
World Bank Group Partnership Facility between the Participating WBG Organizations and the Donor.&#13;
A.     Standard Provisions Applicable to All Windows of the Trust Funds&#13;
1.     Administration of the Contribution&#13;
1.1    The Contribution shall be administered in the Trust Funds by the Bank on behalf of the Donor and&#13;
used by the Participating WBG Organizations to implement or supervise, as the case may be, activities in&#13;
accordance with the terms of this Administration Agreement. Each Participating WBG Organization shall be&#13;
responsible only for performing those functions specifically set forth in this Administration Agreement and&#13;
shall not be subject to any other duties or responsibilities to the Donor, including, without limitation, any duties&#13;
or obligations that might otherwise apply to a fiduciary or trustee under general principles of trust or fiduciary&#13;
law. Nothing in this Administration Agreement shall be considered a waiver of any privileges or immunities&#13;
of the Participating WBG Organizations under their respective Articles of Agreement or any applicable law,&#13;
all of which are expressly reserved.&#13;
2.     Management of the Contribution&#13;
2.1    The currency in which the funds in the Trust Funds shall be held is United States Dollars (the "Holding&#13;
Currency").&#13;
2.2    The Donor agrees to deposit its Contribution in the Contribution Currency stated in this Administration&#13;
Agreement. In the case of deposits received in a Contribution Currency other than the Holding Currency,&#13;
promptly upon the receipt of such amounts and the accompanying Deposit Instructions, the Bank shall convert&#13;
such amounts into the Holding Currency at the exchange rate obtained by the Bank on the date of the&#13;
conversion. Where deposits prove to be insufficient to complete activities as a result of exchange rate&#13;
fluctuations, neither the Participating WBG Organizations nor the Donor shall bear any responsibility for&#13;
providing any additional financing.&#13;
2.3    The funds deposited in or allocated to the Trust Funds may be freely exchanged by the Participating&#13;
WBG Organizations into other currencies as may facilitate their disbursement at the exchange rate obtained by&#13;
the Participating WBG Organizations on the date of the conversion.&#13;
2.4    The Bank shall invest and reinvest the funds deposited in or allocated to the Trust Funds pending their&#13;
disbursement in accordance with the Bank's applicable policies and procedures for the investment of trust&#13;
funds administered by the Bank. The Bank shall transfer all income from such investment to the Donor's&#13;
applicable donor balance account with the Bank.&#13;
2.5    The Contribution will fund activities undertaken by IFC that have a potential to generate fees from&#13;
clients in the future. The client fees paid to IFC, to the extent they result from the activities funded by the&#13;
Contribution, will be set aside and used by IFC for the same purposes as the Contribution. Upon termination&#13;
of the Administration Agreement, any unused portion of such client fees may then be used by IFC in&#13;
accordance with its sole discretion.&#13;
7&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿3.     Cancellation; Refund&#13;
3.1    The Donor may cancel all or part, and the Bank may cancel all or part, upon three (3) months' prior&#13;
written notice, of the Contribution (paid and not yet paid) that are not committed pursuant to any agreements&#13;
entered into between any of the Participating WBG Organizations and any consultants and/or other third parties&#13;
for the purposes of this Administration Agreement, including any Grant Agreements, prior to the receipt of&#13;
such notice. In the event of a cancellation, the Bank shall return to the Donor any such uncommitted balance&#13;
of the Trust Funds in the Holding Currency as specified in this Administration Agreement; unless otherwise&#13;
agreed between the Bank and the Donor.&#13;
4.     Disclosure; Dispute Resolution&#13;
4.1    The Bank shall disclose this Administration Agreement and related information on these Trust Funds&#13;
in accordance with the Bank's Policy on Access to Information. By entering into this Administration&#13;
Agreement, the Donor consents to such disclosure of this Administration Agreement and such related&#13;
information.&#13;
4.2    (a)    The Donor acknowledges that IFC's Access to Information Policy (the "AIP") will apply with&#13;
respect to disclosure of all documentation, data and other information that IFC receives from the Donor relating&#13;
to this Administration Agreement and the Trust Funds or from third parties in connection with performing the&#13;
activities financed by the Trust Funds. The AlP is available on IFC's web site at www.ifc.org/disclosure.&#13;
Under the AIP, IFC makes available to the public certain information about IFC's activities. Examples of such&#13;
information include, with respect to IFC's advisory services activities, good practices or lessons learned reports&#13;
that aim to enhance the development impact of IFC's initiatives, and limited project-specific information, such&#13;
as brief project descriptions, expected development impacts and actual results. Pursuant to the AIP, IFC does&#13;
not disclose to the public financial, business, proprietary or other non-public information provided to IFC by&#13;
its clients or third parties without the consent of such clients or third parties.&#13;
(b)    By entering into this Administration Agreement, the Donor consents, as permitted under the&#13;
AIP, to disclosure by IFC of this Administration Agreement and related information on the Trust Funds.&#13;
(c)    With respect to any client or third party information that IFC, either directly or through the&#13;
Bank, communicates to the Donor, in accordance with IFC's reporting obligations under this Administration&#13;
Agreement, the Donor hereby agrees to keep confidential any information identified in writing by IFC as&#13;
confidential in accordance with the principles of the AIP. The Donor will also ensure that any access to such&#13;
confidential information granted to its officers, directors, employees, attorneys, independent auditors, rating&#13;
agencies, contractors, and consultants will be only on a need-to-know basis and provided that such persons are&#13;
subject to a similar or equivalent confidentiality obligation. The Donor and IFC agree that should the Donor&#13;
wish to publicly disclose any information shared by IFC, either directly or through the Bank, with such Donor&#13;
under this Administration Agreement, such Donor shall first ask IFC whether all or part of such relevant&#13;
information is disclosable under the AIP and then disclose only such information as IFC confirms may be&#13;
disclosed under the AIP.&#13;
4.3    The Donor and the Participating WBG Organizations shall use their best efforts to amicably settle any&#13;
dispute, controversy, or claim arising out of or relating to this Administration Agreement.&#13;
8&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿B.     Standard Provisions Applicable to Trust Fund No. 072447 for Windows 1, 2 and 3&#13;
1.     Administration&#13;
1.1    The portion of the Contribution allocated to TF No. 072447 shall be administered or used in accordance&#13;
with the Participating WBG Organizations' applicable policies and procedures, as the same may be amended&#13;
from time to time, including their procurement, financial management, disbursement and safeguard policies,&#13;
their framework to prevent and combat fraud and corruption and their screening procedures to prevent the use&#13;
of Participating WBG Organizations resources to finance terrorist activity, in line with the Participating WBG&#13;
Organizations' obligations to give effect to the relevant decisions of the Security Council taken under Chapter&#13;
VII of the of Charter of the United Nations. The Donor acknowledges that this provision does not create any&#13;
obligations of the Participating WBG Organizations under the anti-terrorist financing and asset control laws,&#13;
regulations, rules and executive orders of an individual member country that may apply to a Donor.&#13;
2.     Management&#13;
2.1    The funds allocated to TF No. 072447 shall be accounted for as a single trust fund by the Bank and&#13;
shall be kept separate and apart from the funds of the Bank. The funds allocated to TF No. 072447 may be&#13;
commingled with other trust fund assets maintained by the Bank. The Bank, in its capacity as trustee, has legal&#13;
title to the funds allocated to TF No. 072447.&#13;
3.     Trust Fund Fees and Costs&#13;
3.1    The Bank shall deduct and retain for its own account, as a deduction from each allocation to TF No.&#13;
072447, an amount equal to two percent (2%) per allocation as an administrative fee for TF No. 072447.&#13;
3.2    In addition, costs incurred by the Bank for other expenses, such as for program management and Trust&#13;
Fund administration, that are: (i) not covered by the percentage deduction specified above as an administrative&#13;
fee; and (ii) not included under Annex I of this Administration Agreement in accordance with the Bank's&#13;
applicable policies and procedures shall be charged to TF No. 072447 on an actual basis up to a maximum of&#13;
three percent (3%) of the total allocations to TF No. 072447.&#13;
3.3    The Donor acknowledges and agrees that the percentage deductions for fees in this Trust Fund Fees&#13;
and Costs section are estimated on the basis of the anticipated allocations to TF No. 072447. If the actual&#13;
allocations to TF No. 072447 significantly differ from what was originally anticipated at the time of signature&#13;
of this Administration Agreement, or if other circumstances affecting Trust Fund fees or costs change, the&#13;
Bank reserves the right to request a change to the terms of this Trust Fund Fees and Costs section, which would&#13;
be effectuated by an amendment made to this Administration Agreement which would thereafter be applicable&#13;
to all new allocations to TF No. 072447.&#13;
4.     Accounting and Financial Reporting&#13;
4.1    The Bank shall maintain separate records and ledger accounts in respect of the funds allocated to TF&#13;
No. 072447 and disbursements made therefrom.&#13;
4.2    The Bank shall furnish to the Donor current financial information relating to receipts, disbursements&#13;
and fund balance in the Holding Currency with respect to the allocations to TF No. 072447 via the World&#13;
Bank's Trust Funds Donor Center secure website. Within six (6) months after all commitments and liabilities&#13;
under TF No. 072447 have been satisfied and TF No. 072447 has been closed, the final financial information&#13;
relating to receipts, disbursements and fund balance in the Holding Currency with respect to the allocations to&#13;
9&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿TF No. 072447 shall be made available to the Donor via the World Bank's Trust Funds Donor Center secure&#13;
website.&#13;
4.3    The Bank shall provide to the Donor via the World Bank's Trust Fund Donor Center secure website,&#13;
within six (6) months following the end of each Bank fiscal year, an annual single audit report, comprising (i)&#13;
a management assertion together with an attestation from the Bank's external auditors concerning the adequacy&#13;
of internal control over cash-based financial reporting for all cash-based trust funds as a whole; and (ii) a&#13;
combined financial statement for all cash-based trust funds together with the Bank's external auditor's opinion&#13;
thereon. The cost of the single audit shall be bome by the Bank.&#13;
4.4    If a Donor wishes to request, on an exceptional basis, a financial statement audit by the Bank's external&#13;
auditors of TF No. 072447, the Donor and the Bank shall first consult as to whether such an external audit is&#13;
necessary. The Bank and the Donor shall agree on the appropriate scope and terms of reference of such audit.&#13;
Following agreement on the scope and terms of reference, the Bank shall arrange for such external audit. The&#13;
costs of any such audit, including the internal costs of the Bank with respect to such audit, shall be borne by&#13;
the Donor.&#13;
4.5    The Bank shall make available to the Donor copies of all financial statements and auditors' reports&#13;
received by the Bank from Recipients pursuant to any Grant Agreements (as defined below) in accordance&#13;
with the Bank's Access to Information Policy.&#13;
5.     Progress Reporting&#13;
5.1    The Bank shall provide the Donor with annual reports prepared by the Participating WBG&#13;
Organizations on the progress of activities implemented or supervised by such Participating WBG&#13;
Organization that are financed by the Contribution allocated to TF No. 072447. Within six (6) months of the&#13;
End Disbursement Date (as defined below), the Bank shall furnish to the Donor a final report prepared by the&#13;
relevant Participating WBG Organizations on the activities financed by TF No. 072447.&#13;
5.2    The Donor may review or evaluate activities financed by TF No. 072447 at any time up to six (6)&#13;
months following the End Disbursement Date. The Donor and the relevant Participating WBG Organizations&#13;
shall agree on the scope and conduct of such review or evaluation, and the relevant Participating WBG&#13;
Organizations shall provide all relevant information within the limits of the Participating WBG Organizations'&#13;
applicable policies and procedures. All associated costs, including any costs incurred by the relevant&#13;
Participating WBG Organizations, shall be borne by the Donor. It is understood that any such review or&#13;
evaluation will not constitute a financial, compliance or other audit of TF No. 072447.&#13;
6.     Disbursement&#13;
6.1   It is expected that the funds allocated to TF No. 072447 will be fully disbursed by the Bank by&#13;
December 31, 2020 (the "End Disbursement Date"). The Bank shall only disburse funds allocated to TF No.&#13;
072447 for the purposes of this Administration Agreement (other than returns to the Donor) after such date to&#13;
the extent such date is changed in accordance with an amendment made to this Administration Agreement.&#13;
Following the End Disbursement Date, the Bank shall return any remaining balance of TF No. 072447 to the&#13;
Donor in the Holding Currency.&#13;
7.     Grants to Recipients&#13;
7.1    The Bank shall, as administrator of TF No. 072447 on behalf of the Donor, enter into one or more&#13;
grant agreements (the "Grant Agreements") with recipients (the "Recipients") consistent with the purposes of&#13;
10&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿this Administration Agreement and on the terms and conditions set forth in the Grant Agreements. Grant&#13;
Agreements may be entered into up to the maximum amount of the allocation to TF No. 072447 that the Donor&#13;
has agreed to make available under this Administration Agreement.&#13;
7.2    The Bank shall be responsible for the supervision of the activities financed under any Grant&#13;
Agreements. Subject to the consent of any relevant Recipients, representatives of the Donor may be invited&#13;
by the Bank to participate in Bank supervision missions related to TF No. 072447.&#13;
7.3    The Bank shall promptly inform the Donor of any significant modification to the terms of any Grant&#13;
Agreements and of any contractual remedies that are exercised by the Bank under any Grant Agreements. To&#13;
the extent practicable, the Bank shall afford the Donor the opportunity to exchange views before effecting any&#13;
such modification or exercising any such remedy.&#13;
C.     Standard Provisions Applicable to Trust Fund No. 072456 for Window 4&#13;
1.     Management&#13;
1.1    The funds deposited in TF No. 072456 shall be accounted for as a single trust fund by the Bank and&#13;
shall be kept separate and apart from the funds of the Bank. The funds deposited in TF No. 072456 may be&#13;
commingled with other trust fund assets maintained by the Bank. The Bank, in its capacity as trustee, has legal&#13;
title to the funds deposited in TF No. 072456.&#13;
1.2    Subject to the availability of funds held in TF No. 072456 as determined by the Bank, the Bank shall&#13;
make commitments and transfer such funds for any purpose approved and in the amount allocated by the Donor&#13;
in accordance with the terms of this Administration Agreement.&#13;
1.3    The funds deposited in TF No. 072456 shall not be subject to any fee or charge under this&#13;
Administration Agreement provided, however, that funds transferred from TF No. 072456 to other global or&#13;
regional programs, including TF No. 072456, administered by the Bank or IFC shall be subject to the cost&#13;
recovery arrangements under such global or regional program.&#13;
2.     Accounting and Financial Reporting&#13;
2.1    The Bank shall maintain separate records and ledger accounts in respect of the funds deposited in TF&#13;
No. 072456 and disbursements made therefrom.&#13;
2.2    The Bank shall furnish to the Donor current financial information relating to receipts, disbursements&#13;
and fund balance in the Holding Currency with respect to the funds deposited in TF No. 072456 via the World&#13;
Bank's Trust Funds Donor Center secure website. Within six (6) months after all commitments and liabilities&#13;
under TF No. 072456 have been satisfied and TF No. 072456 has been closed, the final financial information&#13;
relating to receipts, disbursements and fund balance in the Holding Currency with respect to the funds&#13;
deposited in TF No. 072456 shall be made available to the Donor via the World Bank's Trust Funds Donor&#13;
Center secure website.&#13;
2.3    The Bank shall provide to the Donor via the World Bank's Trust Fund Donor Center secure website,&#13;
within six (6) months following the end of each Bank fiscal year, an annual single audit report, comprising (i)&#13;
a management assertion together with an attestation from the Bank's external auditors concerning the adequacy&#13;
of internal control over cash-based financial reporting for all cash-based trust funds as a whole; and (ii) a&#13;
combined financial statement for all cash-based trust funds together with the Bank's external auditor's opinion&#13;
thereon. The cost of the single audit shall be borne by the Bank.&#13;
11&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿2.4    If a Donor wishes to request, on an exceptional basis, a financial statement audit by the Bank's external&#13;
auditors of TF No. 072456, the Donor and the Bank shall first consult as to whether such an external audit is&#13;
necessary. The Bank and the Donor shall agree on the appropriate scope and terms of reference of such audit.&#13;
Following agreement on the scope and terms of reference, the Bank shall arrange for such external audit. The&#13;
costs of any such audit, including the internal costs of the Bank with respect to such audit, shall be bome by&#13;
the requesting Donor.&#13;
3.     Transfers&#13;
3.1    It is expected that the funds deposited in TF No. 072456 will be fully transferred by June 30, 2020 (the&#13;
"End Transfer Date"). The Bank shall only transfer TF No. 072456 funds for the purposes of this&#13;
Administration Agreement after such date with the written approval of the Donor. Following the End Transfer&#13;
Date, the Bank shall return any remaining balance of TF No. 072456 to the Donor in the Holding Currency.&#13;
12&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿ANNEX 3&#13;
Governance&#13;
This Annex shall be applicable to and form an integral part of the Administration Agreement for the China-&#13;
World Bank Group Partnership Facility (the "Facility") between the Participating WBG Organizations and the&#13;
Donor&#13;
1.     Steering Committee&#13;
1.1    The Participating WBG Organizations and the Donor will convene a Steering Committee composed&#13;
of representatives of the Donor from the Ministry of Finance and representatives of the Participating WBG&#13;
Organizations, which at the time of execution of the Administration Agreement is expected to be staff&#13;
designated by the Development Finance Vice Presidency (DFi), the East Asia and Pacific Vice Presidency&#13;
(EAP), the Global Practices Chief Economist (GPSCE), IFC's Client Services Vice Presidency (GCSVP-IFC),&#13;
or any other Vice Presidency of the relevant Participating WBG Organization as such Participating WBG&#13;
Organization may determine from time to time.&#13;
1.2    The Steering Committee will meet semi-annually to: (a) review the strategic directions of the Facility;&#13;
(b) agree on the funding allocations for each Window of the Facility; (c) review implementation progress and&#13;
progress towards achieving the expected results; and (d) provide general oversight over the Facility. Decisions&#13;
by the Steering Committee shall be made by consensus. Other staff of the Participating WBG Organizations&#13;
may be invited to participate in the meetings of the Steering Committee to provide technical and other advice&#13;
but will not participate in the Steering Committee's decision-making process.&#13;
2.     Operations Committee&#13;
2.1    The Participating WBG Organizations shall establish an Operations Committee, composed of&#13;
Director-level staff from DFi, EAP, GPSCE, GCSVP-IFC, or any other Vice Presidency of the relevant&#13;
Participating WBG Organization as such Participating WBG Organization may determine from time to time,&#13;
responsible, among other things, for: (a) reviewing proposals for financing under Window I of the Facility;&#13;
(b) reviewing project concept notes and full proposals for financing under Window 2 of the Facility; (c)&#13;
soliciting Donor preferences as to whether the Donor will fund certain positions in the Bank and IFC or&#13;
activities, training and workshops under Window 3 of the Facility; and (d) determining funding allocations to&#13;
approved proposals within the overall allocations approved by the Steering Committee for Windows 1, 2 and&#13;
3.&#13;
3.     Secretariat&#13;
3.1    The Participating WBG Organizations shall establish a Secretariat for the Facility in DFi, responsible,&#13;
among other things, for: (a) organizing and coordinating the meetings and consultations of the Steering&#13;
Committee; (b) managing the process for calling for and screening proposals as set out in the Operations&#13;
Manual (as defined below); (c) monitoring the implementation of the Facility and the progress towards&#13;
achieving the expected results; (d) preparing the annual reports on implementation progress and achievement&#13;
of results based on reports submitted by the relevant Participating WBG Organization; and (d) performing&#13;
other tasks assigned by the Steering Committee.&#13;
13&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿4.     Operations Manual&#13;
4.1    The Secretariat shall prepare and submit for the review and approval by the Steering Committee an&#13;
operations manual (the "Operations Manual") for the Facility which shall set out, among other things: (a) the&#13;
program criteria for activities to be financed under Windows 1, 2 and 3 of the Facility; (b) the process and&#13;
timelines for and other aspects related to the call for and review of proposals for financing under Windows 1&#13;
and 2 of the Facility; (c) the processes for the review and final selection of candidates and the review and final&#13;
approval of activities under Window 3 of the Facility; and (d) the Results Framework for the Facility.&#13;
4.2    In the event of any inconsistency between the Operations Manual and the provisions of this&#13;
Administration Agreement, the latter shall prevail.&#13;
5.     Funding Proposals&#13;
5.1    Except as otherwise agreed between the Donor and the Participating WBG Organizations, the process&#13;
for the review and selection of proposals for funding shall be as follows:&#13;
(a)    Window 1&#13;
On a rolling basis, the Operations Committee will receive and review project proposals for&#13;
funding under Window 1 to finance or co-finance investment projects, preparation of&#13;
investment operations, or PPPs. The Operations Committee will submit, through the Bank&#13;
and IFC contacts referred to in paragraph 5 of this Administration Agreement, project&#13;
proposals deemed eligible for funding under Window 1 to the Donor for the latter's review&#13;
and approval on a non-objection basis. Each proposal shall have detailed information on the&#13;
action plan, including a budget categorized by expenditures. Unless the Donor indicates&#13;
otherwise, the grant proposal(s) will be deemed approved for funding after four (4) weeks&#13;
from the date of submission of the grant proposal(s) to the Donor.&#13;
(b)    Window 2&#13;
On a rolling basis, the Operations Committee will receive and review project proposals for&#13;
funding under Window 2. On a quarterly basis, the Operations Committee will submit,&#13;
through the Bank and IFC contacts referred to in paragraph 5 of this Administration&#13;
Agreement, brief concept notes of project proposals deemed eligible for financing under&#13;
Window 2 to the Donor for the latter's review and endorsement on a non-objection basis.&#13;
Unless the Donor indicates otherwise, the project concept note(s) will be deemed endorsed&#13;
after four (4) weeks from the date of submission of the project concept note(s) to the Donor.&#13;
After approval of the project concept note, the Operations Committee will receive and review&#13;
the full project proposal and submit the same to the Donor for final approval. Each proposal&#13;
shall have detailed information on the action plan, including a budget categorized by&#13;
expenditures. Unless the Donor indicates otherwise, the full project proposal will be deemed&#13;
endorsed for funding after four (4) weeks from the date of submission of the full project&#13;
proposal to the Donor.&#13;
(c)    Window 3&#13;
(i)    On a yearly basis, the Operations Committee, through the Bank and IFC contacts, will&#13;
solicit Donor preferences as to whether the Donor will fund positions in certain Global&#13;
Practices/Cross-Cutting Solutions Areas or regions of the Bank or IFC, or will fund&#13;
14&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿activities, training or workshops under Window 3. The Donor may notify any changes&#13;
to its above preferences to the Bank and IFC contacts at any time; provided that no&#13;
such change will affect positions and activities previously approved by the Donor.&#13;
(ii)   The Operations Committee shall notify the Donor in writing of positions for the Donor&#13;
to consider. Such notification shall include the relevant Terms of Reference, based&#13;
solely on business needs, along with the applicable entry salary and market reference&#13;
point of the salary structure for the relevant grade level, for Donor review.&#13;
(iii)  The Donor shall notify the Bank and IFC contacts within a specified time period of&#13;
its approval for funding the position.&#13;
(iv)   If the Donor expresses interest in funding a position, the Donor will provide a list of&#13;
potential candidates for the position to the Bank and IFC contacts.&#13;
(v)    The processes for the review and final selection of candidates and review and final&#13;
approval of activities under Window 3 shall be set forth in the Operations Manual.&#13;
(d)    Window 4&#13;
The Donor will advise the WBG Participating Organizations on the global or regional&#13;
programs or activities that the Donor and specific units within the WBG Participating&#13;
Organizations have agreed to support under Window 4. Upon the signing by the Donor of a&#13;
separate agreement concerning a global or regional program or activity, the Bank will transfer&#13;
funds to the respective account of such global or regional program or activity in accordance&#13;
with such agreement.&#13;
15&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="25747987">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2015/07/25747987/official-documents--administration-agreement-ministry-finance-peoples-republic-china-tf072447-ref-china--world-bank-group-partnership-facility-single-donor-trust-funds
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2015/07/25747987/official-documents--administration-agreement-ministry-finance-peoples-republic-china-tf072447-ref-china--world-bank-group-partnership-facility-single-donor-trust-funds</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2015/07/25747987/official-documents--administration-agreement-ministry-finance-peoples-republic-china-tf072447-ref-china--world-bank-group-partnership-facility-single-donor-trust-funds</new_url>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2016-01-17T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <docm_id>090224b08401d79a</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b08401d79a</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/CTR/2016/01/07/090224b08401d79a/1_0/Rendered/INDEX/Official0Docum0le0Donor0Trust0Funds.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/CTR/2016/01/07/090224b08401d79a/1_0/Rendered/PDF/Official0Docum0le0Donor0Trust0Funds.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2015-07-16T10:08:29Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2016-01-07T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docna>
            Official Documents- Administration Agreement
            with the Ministry of Finance of the People's Republic
            of China for TF072447 Ref. China--World Bank Group
            Partnership Facility Single-Donor Trust Funds
        </docna>
        <display_title>Official Documents-
            Administration Agreement with the Ministry of Finance of the
            People's Republic of China for TF072447 Ref.
            China--World Bank Group Partnership Facility Single-Donor
            Trust Funds</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/2015/07/25747987/official-documents--administration-agreement-ministry-finance-peoples-republic-china-tf072447-ref-china--world-bank-group-partnership-facility-single-donor-trust-funds</listing_relative_url>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <docty>Trust Fund Administrative Agreement</docty>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Pascual Iv,Jose Ramon R.</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>HQBOCS</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <trustfund>TF072447-China - World Bank Group
            Partnership Facility</trustfund>
        <lang>English</lang>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Arts and Culture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Capacities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Staffing Needs Assessments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>Freedom of Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>Bank Supervision</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Leasing law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Remittances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Migration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Checks on Executive Power</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen User Satisfaction Survey</ml:concept><ml:concept>Independent Commissions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ombudsmen</ml:concept><ml:concept>Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Parliament</ml:concept><ml:concept>Procurement Complaints Review Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supreme Audit Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enforcement of Judgements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Informal Dispute Resolution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Media</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Right to Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>External Audit</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Bank Regulation and Supervision</ml:concept><ml:concept>Leasing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Movement of Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Accountability Mechanisms</ml:concept><ml:concept>Dispute Resolution</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>