<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>                                                                                                                                               Domestic Private Sector Participation:&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                  102617&#13;
                                                                                                                                               INDIA&#13;
SITUATION ASSESSMENT (RURAL SANITATION)                                                                                                        OVERVIEW&#13;
                                                                                                                                               Infrastructure for water and sanitation services exists in India but                            QUICK FACTS&#13;
 Policy and Regulatory Environment                                                                            RATING: Low Improved&#13;
                                                                                                                                               there is little emphasis on service delivery. Resistance to cost                                Population                                     (2001)          1.028 B&#13;
 l    The GoI and some states have adopted effective policies and programs to promote sanitation and hygiene, and provide incentives to        recovery, particularly in water supply has resulted in poor quality of                          Gross national income/capita                   (2006)          US$820&#13;
      achieve total sanitation and collective behavior change. On-site sanitation (latrines) is typically a household-level responsibility.    water and sanitation services in the country, with least access and&#13;
                                                                                                                                               coverage for the urban and rural poor.                                                          Urbanization                               (1990-2005)           2.5%&#13;
 l    While there are no specific policies on the promotion of PSP in the rural sanitation sector, there are many formal or informal private&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                               People living in cities with                   (2001)&#13;
      providers (NGOs, CBOs, others) that supply rural sanitation goods and services directly to households and villages.                      In urban areas, piped water supply and sanitation are&#13;
                                                                                                                                               predominantly provided by urban local bodies (municipalities) in                                    &gt; 1million inhabitants                                       35%&#13;
 l    With rising population density in India, many villages now require drainage, wastewater, and solid waste management facilities.&#13;
                                                                                                                                               charge of operations and maintenance (O&amp;M). Some larger cities                                  People living in poverty                       (2001)           320 M&#13;
      Construction of these systems is subsidized by the government, but often without adequate management arrangements that would&#13;
                                                                                                                                               have created municipal water and sanitation utilities. Notably, in                              Access to water&#13;
      ensure sustainability.&#13;
                                                                                                                                               cities, the private sector is active in providing household-level&#13;
 l    It should also be noted that while the sanitation and hygiene promotion programs are being scaled up, they are not uniform across        storage, pumping, and filtration systems to augment intermittent                                    Urban                                      (2007)            86%&#13;
      all states.                                                                                                                              and poor quality of the public water supply.                                                        Rural                                      (2004)            83%&#13;
                                                                                                                                               In rural areas, there are about 100,000 water supply systems and, in                            Access to sanitation&#13;
 Market and Business Infrastructure                                                                           RATING: Low Improved             some states, responsibility for service provision is being transferred                              Urban                                      (2007)            59%&#13;
                                                                                                                                               from state water boards and district governments to Panchayati Raj                                  Rural                                      (2008)            51%&#13;
 l    The community-led total sanitation approach has increased demand for on-site sanitation products by small-scale providers.&#13;
                                                                                                                                               institutions at block or village level. In some rural areas, including&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                               Data Sources: The World Bank; World Development Indicators (2007);&#13;
 l    There is competition in the market, due to the presence of a variety of players both in the formal and informal sectors. Most of the     bulk supply to multi-village schemes, there are examples of very                                Wikipedia.org; Census 2001; GoI; DDWS; WHO/UNICEF; JMP (2006).&#13;
      producers of sanitary wares and material are in the formal sector, while service providers are in the informal sector.                   basic service agreements or operations contracts.&#13;
 l    Capital availability for the formal producers is adequate and available, but constrained for the informal sector producers and service   On the sanitation side, while DPSP is promoted by the National Government, little attention is given to cost recovery and business plan&#13;
      delivery systems.                                                                                                                        sustainability and there are lack of incentives and enforcement for households and industries to connect to sewage systems.&#13;
                                                                                                                                               WSP-SA has helped prepare the groundwork for private sector participation (PSP) in water supply and sanitation in India by advocating for&#13;
 Domestic Provider Performance (Optional)                                                                     RATING: High Improved            performance benchmarking, institutional reform and accountability, and promoting access to market financing for service providers. It is&#13;
                                                                                                                                               also helping develop guidelines for the Government of India (GoI) on engagement with the private sector and documenting models of PSP&#13;
 l    Due to competition, the quality of services and products offered is generally of adequate standards.                                     engagement within the country and internationally.&#13;
 l    Most informal sector players have poor management, business and technical skills. For e.g., masons who provide construction services&#13;
      are unskilled in terms of technology or business skills.&#13;
                                                                                                                                               TYPES OF PROVIDERS&#13;
 l    Availability of capital is also a major hindrance for the informal sector players.&#13;
                                                                                                                                               Snap shot: Extent of Provider Involvement&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                           Public       International          Local             Usersâ&#128;&#153;          Others             Dominant&#13;
KEY OPPORTUNITIES IN RURAL SANITATION                                                                                                                                                                                                      Private             Private         Associations                         Provider&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                                                                               1              2                   3                4                 5&#13;
 Opportunities for enhancing DPSP activity in the next three years (2009-2012)                                                                    Urban water supply                                                          x                x                  x                                                    1&#13;
                                                                                                                                                  Rural water supply                                                          x                                   x                x                                   1&#13;
 1 Developing the formal supply market for sanitation produce through information on real demand from rural households and support for&#13;
   meeting those demand.&#13;
                                                                                                                                                  Small towns water supply                                                    x                                   x                                                    1&#13;
                                                                                                                                                  Urban Sanitation and Hygiene&#13;
 2 Building the capacity of informal sanitation producer with enhanced access to credit, capacity building for technical and management             Sewerage, wastewater and sludge treatment                                 x                x                  x                                                    1&#13;
   skills will strengthen the market. Capacity building of informal service providers will help consolidate/deepen the market and promote           Desludging                                                                x                                   x                                                    3&#13;
   better services.                                                                                                                                 Solid Waste Management                                                    x                x                  x                x                                   1&#13;
 3 Advocacy for improved policy and program for lagging states.                                                                                     Hygiene promotion                                                         x                x                  x                x                                   4&#13;
 4 Support development of low cost, appropriate and modern technology for drainage/wastewater and solid waste management facilities               Rural Sanitation and Hygiene&#13;
   for larger villages and small towns.                                                                                                             Sewerage, wastewater and sludge treatment                                 x                                                                      x                 1&#13;
                                                                                                                                                    Desludging                                                                x                                   x                x                                   3&#13;
                                                                                                                                                    Household sanitation product manufacturing&#13;
                                                                                                                                                    and distribution                                                                                              x                x                                   3&#13;
                                                                                                                                                    Hygiene promotion                                                         x                x                  x                x                 x                 1&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                               Notes:&#13;
                                                                                                                                               Sewerage, wastewater and sludge treatment in rural areas is done by local governments at the village level (Gram Panchayats).&#13;
&amp;#12;SITUATION ASSESSMENT (URBAN WATER SUPPLY)                                                                                                             SITUATION ASSESSMENT (URBAN SANITATION)&#13;
&#13;
 Policy and Regulatory Environment                                                                                   RATING: Low Improved              Policy and Regulatory Environment                                                                              RATING: Low Improved&#13;
 l    PSP is encouraged by GoI in the urban water supply sector to encourage cost efficiency and service improvement. The reform agenda under          l    The draft national urban policy on sanitation specifically advocates partnerships between public sector, CBOs, and private operators for&#13;
      GoI flagship program Jawaharlal Nehru National Urban Renewal Mission (JNNURM) also encourages PSP in urban water supply sector.&#13;
                                                                                                                                                            improvements in service delivery. PSP is explicitly promoted in GoIâ&#128;&#153;s policy for urban sanitation and solid waste management at&#13;
 l    Currently, no regulatory framework exists for the sector that would make providers accountable for their performance. This results in                 national, state, and city levels. This is further supported by recent schemes such as the JNNURM which also encourages active PSP .&#13;
      disincentives to private participation and risks to the contractual/business transactions between public and private groups.&#13;
 l    Moreover, there is low public and political acceptance of PSP approaches at state and local levels which serves as a barrier to entry.           l    Although DPSP is promoted, little attention is given to cost recovery and business plan sustainability. The focus is on creating&#13;
                                                                                                                                                            infrastructure and not on service delivery. And there is a lack of incentives and enforcement for households and industries to connect to&#13;
 Market and Business Infrastructure                                                                                  RATING: Low Improved                   already-built sewerage systems.&#13;
 l    Small domestic operators are active in a few cases in operating water treatment plants and small piped water systems or tanker services.         l    Regulatory systems typically address only environmental outcomes, but not tariffs, performance, and issues of transparency in&#13;
 l    Management contracts and build-operate-transfer (BOT) contracts are also being used in small selected cities for managing water                       contracting. Moreover, environmental regulations tend to be process oriented (vs. outcome) and, to that extent, influence the&#13;
      utility systems.                                                                                                                                      structuring of projects and choice of technologies.&#13;
 l    Few operators are well-established businesses with access to business development services and market financing, most are informal               l    In general, fragmented roles and responsibilities, uncertainties related to political risk and revenue stream sometimes hinder the&#13;
      operators working on the margins.                                                                                                                      participation of the private sector.&#13;
 Domestic Provider Performance (Optional)                                                                            RATING: Challenged&#13;
                                                                                                                                                       Market and Business Infrastructure                                                                             RATING: High Improved&#13;
 l    Domestic providers have limited experience in handling water supply systems at city-wide scale.&#13;
 l    Most private sector providers operate without the benefit of a proper framework for accountability and regulation.                               l    A number of sewage pumping stations and a few sewage treatment facilities are operated and maintained by the domestic private sector.&#13;
KEY OPPORTUNITIES IN URBAN WATER SUPPLY                                                                                                                l    A small number of sewage treatment facilities have also been implemented by the domestic private sector on BOT contract.&#13;
&#13;
 Opportunities for enhancing DPSP activity in the next three years (2009-2012)                                                                         l    There are also a number of partnerships with the domestic private sector in solid waste collection and transportation and in some cases,&#13;
                                                                                                                                                            small solid waste treatment plants.&#13;
 1 Capacity enhancement of local governments to design and manage successful contractual arrangements.&#13;
 2 Strengthening financial capacity of local governments and service providers to access market-based financing for water projects.                    l    CBOs, resident welfare associations and small contractors are active in several towns in providing solid waste management and on-site&#13;
 3 Developing a regulatory framework and rational pricing strategies for water services and empowering local governments to take                            sanitation services.&#13;
   decisions on water tariffs.                                                                                                                         l    Limited revenue generation potential of projects (weak financial condition of the local bodies and weak cost recovery) results in few&#13;
 4 Supporting effective communications and consultations to build understanding of challenges and options in the sector and options to                      bankable projects.&#13;
   improve service delivery, including DPSP  .&#13;
&#13;
SITUATION ASSESSMENT (RURAL WATER SUPPLY)                                                                                                              Domestic Provider Performance (Optional)                                                                       RATING: High Improved&#13;
&#13;
 Policy and Regulatory Environment                                                                                   RATING: Low Improved              l    Urban local bodies and utilities are generally satisfied with the level of service provided by domestic private providers and CBOs. They&#13;
                                                                                                                                                            are seen to be more cost efficient than their public counterparts. Quality of service delivery, however, remains variable â&#128;&#147; largely on&#13;
 l    The GoI is the main financier and consequently, implementer, provider and regulator at all levels. But the focus falls on infrastructure              account of weak monitoring systems and contractual terms. Also, these operators, working at the neighborhood level, are often not&#13;
       provision, not service delivery. Resistance to cost-recovery pricing leads to low cost recovery.&#13;
                                                                                                                                                            connected to a well-functioning city-wide sanitation system.&#13;
 l    There is no prescription against private sector provision nor is it encouraged in the rural water sector. There are numerous examples of&#13;
       water providers in the private domain which include community-based organizations (CBOs), non-government organizations (NGOs),                  l    Large service providers have the ability and capacity to access financing and business services, but there is a need for best-practice in&#13;
       private foundations, religious institutions, etc., financed by non-government agencies.                                                              project design and bidding, adequate regulation, and the potential for cost recovery.&#13;
 l    In general, service contracts have not been well-structured, and there is limited accountability for service delivery.                           l    While adequate expertise exists, and is being developed for operating solid waste collection and transportation systems, capacity gaps&#13;
 l    As yet, there is no formal policy and regulatory framework for private sector provision.                                                              exist on design and operation of treatment and disposal facilities.&#13;
&#13;
 Market and Business Infrastructure                                                                                  RATING: Low Improved&#13;
 l    There is an emerging market and business infrastructure, which is illustrated by the increasing interest of large commercial businesses&#13;
                                                                                                                                                      KEY OPPORTUNITIES IN URBAN SANITATION&#13;
      in rural water supply, such as GE, Wipro Technologies, etc.&#13;
 l    Supply chains for point source systems (hand pumps and spare parts) are well-developed. Indian manufacturers are global suppliers of&#13;
                                                                                                                                                       Opportunities for enhancing DPSP activity in the next three years (2009-2012)&#13;
      these products.&#13;
 l    Due to serious water quality issues, there is a market to provide small quantities of potable water and household disinfection systems/          1 Upgrading the capacity of local governments to design and manage successful contractual arrangements with small and large&#13;
      filters that private providers are moving into.&#13;
                                                                                                                                                         operators. Decision support for local bodies to maximize opportunities for outsourcing to CBOs and small operators, within a cohesive&#13;
 l    However, there are limited opportunities for smaller domestic providers with no access to financing.                                               operational framework.&#13;
 Domestic Provider Performance (Optional)                                                                            RATING: Not rated                 2 Facilitating a shift in focus from infrastructure creation toward achieving improved service delivery.&#13;
&#13;
 l    Without proper contracts and monitoring, it is difficult to gauge the level of performance of private sector providers in rural water supply.    3 Supporting effective communications and consultations to build consensus and understanding of sector reforms and options to improve&#13;
                                                                                                                                                         service delivery, including DPSP.&#13;
KEY OPPORTUNITIES IN RURAL WATER SUPPLY&#13;
                                                                                                                                                       4 Developing and disseminating cost recovery strategies and models and business plans for sustainable investments in urban sanitation&#13;
 Opportunities for enhancing DPSP activity in the next three years (2009-2012)                                                                           and solid waste management systems to attract domestic private operators.&#13;
&#13;
 1 Introduction of contractual frameworks that allow entry of domestic operators under simple service agreements that can evolve toward&#13;
   more complex performance- and output-based contracts.&#13;
 2 Supporting decentralization of responsibility of rural water supply systems to local governments and advocate for building capacity in&#13;
   local governments to contract out service provision.&#13;
 3 Developing models for effective contracting of large rural water systems in areas offering natural economies of scale or high consumer&#13;
   demand, such as multi-village schemes bulk supply or full service provision (bulk and distribution) and water quality treatment.&#13;
 4 Providing analytical evidence to demonstrate economic and social benefits of moving household-based water quality solutions to&#13;
   community-wide water supply systems.&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="25785284">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2016/01/25785284/domestic-private-sector-participation-india
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2016/01/25785284/domestic-private-sector-participation-india</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2016/01/25785284/domestic-private-sector-participation-india</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2016-01-15T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2016-01-19T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <docm_id>090224b08407d72a</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b08407d72a</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2016/01/15/090224b08407d72a/1_0/Rendered/INDEX/Domestic0priva0articipation000India.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2016/01/15/090224b08407d72a/1_0/Rendered/PDF/Domestic0priva0articipation000India.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2016-01-01T05:51:02Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2016-01-15T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Domestic private sector participation : India
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            In urban areas, piped water supply and
            sanitation are predominantly provided by urban local bodies
            (municipalities) in charge of operations and maintenance (O
            and M). In rural areas, there are about 100,000 water supply
            systems and, in some states, responsibility for service
            provision is being transferred from state water boards and
            district governments to Panchayati Raj institutions at block
            or village level. On the sanitation side, while domestic
            private sector participation (DPSP) is promoted by the
            national government, little attention is given to cost
            recovery and business plan sustainability and there are lack
            of incentives and enforcement for households and industries
            to connect to sewage systems. Water and sanitation program -
            South Asia (WSP-SA) has helped prepare the groundwork for
            PSP in water supply and sanitation in India by advocating
            for performance benchmarking, institutional reform and
            accountability, and promoting access to market financing for
            service providers. It is also helping develop guidelines for
            the Government of India (GoI) on engagement with the private
            sector and documenting models of PSP engagement within the
            country and internationally.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Domestic private sector participation : India
        </docna>
        <display_title>Domestic private sector
            participation : India</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2016/01/25785284/domestic-private-sector-participation-india</listing_relative_url>
        <topic>Water m1326522 137,$$Water~~m1326522~~137</topic>
        <subtopic>Sanitation and Sewerage,Wastewater Treatment,Urban Water Supply and Sanitation,Town Water Supply and Sanitation,Water Supply and Sanitation Governance
            and Institutions</subtopic>
        <docty>UNDP-Water &amp; Sanitation Program</docty>
        <teratopic>Water Supply and Sanitation</teratopic>
        <count>India</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>South Asia!$!517212</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!517191</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Asia!$!517198</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>090224b08407d72a_1_0</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>South Asia,South Asia</admreg>
        <colti>Water and sanitation program</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Water Supply and Sanitation</historic_topic>
        <topicv3>Water m1326522 137,$$Water~~m1326522~~137</topicv3>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            sanitation, water supply systems, water
            quality, waste, tariffs, wastewater, users, revenue
            generation, regulatory framework, water services, sludge,
            urbanization, urban sanitation, waste management, service
            improvement, access to water, utilities, household
            sanitation, rural sanitation, pumps, regulatory environment,
            water sector, solid waste, water systems, systems, hygiene
            promotion, hygiene, water supply, sewage, urban areas, water
            tariffs, urban water, solid waste collection, sanitation
            sector, private participation, solid waste management,
            capacity building, public water supply, regulatory systems,
            water treatment plants, towns, water boards, disinfection,
            sanitation utilities, pumping stations, rural water, small
            towns water supply, small towns, treatment facilities,
            sanitation market, filters, quality of service delivery,
            municipalities, service agreements, sludge treatment, sewage
            treatment, urban local, responsibility for service
            provision, sanitation services, water projects, private
            operators, desludging, service contracts, sewage treatment
            facilities, households, urban water supply, cost recovery,
            waste collection, filtration, rural water supply, water
            treatment, spare parts, water, water providers, latrines,
            sanitation system, bulk supply, sewerage systems, drainage,
            access to sanitation, public water, service provision,
            potable water, sewage systems, service delivery, utility,
            municipal water, quality of service, hand pumps, sewerage,
            service providers
        </keywd>
        <owner>Water- Water and Sanit Prgrm (GWASP)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>South Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Asia</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>102617</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Markets and Market Access</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation and Sewerage</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wastewater Treatment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Infrastructure (Water and Wastewater)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Water and Small Town Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Handwashing Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wastewater Collection and Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Solid Waste Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Solid Waste Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Basic Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>On-site Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Marketing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Contract Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Arrangements in Public Procurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Capacity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legal Regulatory Framework</ml:concept><ml:concept>State-Society Relations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation and Wastewater</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water, Sanitation and Hygiene</ml:concept><ml:concept>Hygiene Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sewerage</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Solid Waste</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Local Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Municipality</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Drainage</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>India</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Southern Asia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>