<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>ï»¿SHT&#13;
OFFICIAL                )-S&#13;
DOCUMENTSTo5&#13;
CONTRACT No DCI-ASIE/2015/369067&#13;
Administration Agreement between the European Commission and the International Bankfor&#13;
Reconstruction and Development and the International Development Association concerning the&#13;
Afghanistan Reconstruction Trust Fund (No. TF050576)&#13;
This Administration Agreement is concluded under Indirect Management in the context of the Framework&#13;
Agreement, co-signed on July 30, 2014 and August 15, 2014 (the "2014 Framework Agreement" or&#13;
"Framework Agreement"), between the World Bank Group and the European Commission which sets the&#13;
general conditions for this Administration Agreement. The Framework Agreement shall be applicable and&#13;
form an integral part of this Administration Agreement for the Trust Fund.&#13;
1.1   The International Bank for Reconstruction and Development and the International Development&#13;
Association (collectively, the "Bank") acknowledge that the European Commission (the "Donor", and&#13;
together with the Bank, the "Parties" and each a "Party") agrees to provide the sum of seventeen million&#13;
five hundred thousand Euros (E17,500,000) (the "Contribution") for the Afghanistan Reconstruction Trust&#13;
Fund (No.TF050576) (the "Trust Fund") in accordance with the terms of this Administration Agreement.&#13;
Other donors are also expected to contribute to the Trust Fund on the terms and conditions specified in the&#13;
Annexes to this Administration Agreement.&#13;
1.2.  The estimated total budget of the Trust Fund is eight billion nine hundred ninety four million one&#13;
hundred eighty thousand United States Dollars (US$8,994,180,000). The indicative budget set out in&#13;
Annex 4 shall be used for monitoring purpose only and shall not be binding.&#13;
2.1.   The Contribution shall be used exclusively for the purposes set out in Annex 1 which includes a&#13;
description of project and shall finance the activities set forth in the "Standard Terms and Conditions&#13;
Governing Contributions to the Afghanistan Reconstruction Trust Fund" attached hereto as Annex 2, and&#13;
shall be administered by the Bank on behalf of the Donor in accordance with the terms of this&#13;
Administration Agreement, including the Annex 2.&#13;
2.2.   Expected results of the Trust Fund and corresponding indicators (including baselines, result goals&#13;
and sources of data) are set out in Annex 3.&#13;
2.3.   The Implementation period shall start on the date following that on which the last of the two&#13;
parties signs.&#13;
3.     The Donor shall deposit the Contribution in accordance with the following schedule and in the&#13;
currency specified in Section 1 above ("Contribution Currency") into such bank account designated by&#13;
the Bank (each amount deposited hereinafter referred to as an "Installment") upon submission of a&#13;
payment request by the Bank:&#13;
(A)    Promptly following countersignature:  610,500,000&#13;
(B)    E7,000,000 subject to the disbursement of 70% of the preceding installment.&#13;
The period for payment of further installments shall be 90 days.&#13;
The period for payment of the balance shall be 90 days.&#13;
4.     When making any deposit, the Donor shall instruct its bank to include in its deposit details&#13;
information (remittance advice) field of its SWIFT deposit message, information indicating: the amount&#13;
deposited, that the deposit is made by the Donor for TF No.050576 (the Afghanistan Reconstruction Trust&#13;
-1-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Fund), the Commission internal reference number and the date of the Administration Agreement, the&#13;
name of the project for which the funds are intended, the name of the Commission department responsible&#13;
for the Trust Fund and the date of the deposit (the "Deposit Instructions"). In addition, the Donor shall&#13;
provide a copy of the Deposit Instructions to the Bank's Accounting Trust Funds Division by e-mail sent&#13;
to tfremitadvice@worldbank.org or by fax sent to +1 (202) 614-1315.&#13;
5.     Except with respect to the Deposit Instructions, any notice, request or other communication to be&#13;
given or made under this Administration Agreement shall be in writing and delivered by mail, fax or e-&#13;
mail to the respective Party's address specified below or at such other address as such Party notifies in&#13;
writing to the other Party from time to time:&#13;
For the Bank (the "Bank Contact"):&#13;
Country Director, Afghanistan&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
Kabul, Afghanistan&#13;
Tel: 00 93 706 337 883&#13;
For the Donor (the "Donor Contact"):&#13;
Head of Cooperation&#13;
European Union Delegation to Afghanistan&#13;
Charahi Sedarat, Shar-e-Naw&#13;
Kabul, Afghanistan&#13;
Tel: 00 93 202 200 459&#13;
E-mail: delegation-afghanistan-hod@eeas.europa.eu&#13;
6.    In the event any amounts are to be returned to the Donor under this Administration Agreement,&#13;
the Bank shall transfer such amounts to the Donor unless otherwise agreed with the Bank.&#13;
7.1.   The Interpretative Addendum and all Annexes hereto, as well as the Framework Agreement&#13;
between the World Bank Group and the European Commission, constitute the entire agreement and&#13;
understanding between the Donor and the Bank. In the event of any inconsistency, the Framework&#13;
Agreement prevails over the Administration Agreement and the Administration Agreement (including its&#13;
Interpretative Addendum) prevails over its Annexes. Unless otherwise specified in an annex hereto, this&#13;
Administration Agreement may be amended only by written amendment between the Bank and the&#13;
Donor; provided, however, that any annexes to this Administration Agreement may be amended only by&#13;
written amendment of all donors contributing to the Trust Fund.&#13;
7.2.   Annex 2 of this Administration Agreement, reflecting non-substantive differences with the&#13;
analogous Annex in the model Administration Agreement attached to the 2014 Framework&#13;
Agreement, applies to all donors to this Trust Fund because the Trust Fund is a joint multi-donor&#13;
initiative. Nevertheless, this Administration Agreement is concluded in the context of the 2014&#13;
Framework Agreement and, if paragraph 9.5 (ii) below applies, or for purposes of paragraph 9.5 (iii)&#13;
below when applicable, this Administration Agreement shall be interpreted in a manner consistent with&#13;
the terms of the 2014 Framework Agreement, in particular sections 4.2, 4.3 and 7.1 of the Annex 2 to&#13;
Attachment I to the 2014 Framework Agreement.&#13;
7.3    Notwithstanding paragraph 12 of Annex 2 to this Administration Agreement, the End&#13;
Disbursement date for purposes of the Contribution is April 12, 2019.&#13;
-2-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿8.    Individual procurement and grant contracts under this Administration Agreement shall be signed&#13;
by the World Bank Group entity no later than thirty-nine (39) months from the date of this Administration&#13;
Agreement.&#13;
9.1.   The following derogations from the Framework Agreement shall apply in cases of crisis,&#13;
emergency and post-emergency situations:&#13;
9.2.   Article 2.6 of the 2014 Framework Agreement specifies that, "in duly justified cases of crisis and&#13;
emergency and post-recovery situations," derogations from the terms of the 2014 Framework Agreement&#13;
may be made. Given that this Administration Agreement aims at supporting activities for the benefit of&#13;
Afghanistan, and given that Afghanistan, in the opinion of the Parties, represents such a case where such&#13;
derogations are justified, the Parties hereby agree to derogate from the 2014 Framework Agreement for&#13;
the reasons and in the manner as follow:&#13;
9.3.   Through its Article 14.1.4, the 2014 Framework Agreement sets forth a notional approach for&#13;
determining compliance with cost eligibility requirements in the case of a multi-donor trust fund (MDTF),&#13;
such as this TF050576.&#13;
9.4.   However, said Article 14.1.4's application of the notional approach solely to cost eligibility&#13;
requirements does not expressly cover the situation where the European Commission contributes to a&#13;
commingled account amounts governed by the terms of the Framework Agreement, co-signed on March&#13;
20, 2009 between the European Commission and the International Bank for Reconstruction and&#13;
Development, the International Development Association, and the International Finance Corporation (the&#13;
"2009 Framework Agreement"), and amounts governed by the terms of the 2014 Framework Agreement.&#13;
Consequently, the Parties hereby derogate from said Article's provisions by explicitly expanding them to&#13;
cover situations where successive European Commission contributions are governed by the 2009&#13;
Framework Agreement or the 2014 Framework Agreement.&#13;
9.5.   Consequently, pursuant to the notional approach, any use by the World Bank Group of amounts&#13;
contributed by the European Commission shall be deemed compliant with the terms of either the 2009&#13;
Framework Agreement or the 2014 Framework Agreements as follows:&#13;
(i)    if an activity was fully funded by resources from this TF050576 before any EC contributions&#13;
under this Administration Agreement are received by the Bank, then such activity falls under the terms of&#13;
the 2009 Framework Agreement;&#13;
(ii)  if an activity begins to be funded by resources from this TF050576 after an amount equivalent to&#13;
all contributions covered by prior Administration Agreements entered into by the European Commission&#13;
with regard to this TF050576 has been disbursed by the Bank, and the relevant Grant Agreement for such&#13;
activity was signed after the date of this Administration Agreement, then such activity falls under the&#13;
terms of the 2014 Framework Agreement.&#13;
(iii)  if an activity begins to be funded by resources from this TF050576 before an amount equivalent&#13;
to all contributions covered by prior Administration Agreements entered into by the European&#13;
Commission with regard to this TF050576 has been disbursed by the Bank, and the relevant Grant&#13;
Agreement for such activity was signed after the date of this Administration Agreement, then such&#13;
activity falls under the terms of either one of those Framework Agreements.&#13;
-3-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿10.     The measures taken to identify the EU as a source of financing shall be in accordance with&#13;
Attachment 4 of the Framework Agreement.&#13;
11.     Each of the Parties represents, by confirming its agreement below, that it is authorized to enter&#13;
into this Administration Agreement and act in accordance with these terms and conditions. The Parties are&#13;
requested to sign and date this Administration Agreement, and upon possession by the Bank of this fully&#13;
signed Administration Agreement, this Administration Agreement shall become effective as of the date of&#13;
the last signature&#13;
INTERNATIONAL BANK FOR RECONSTRUCTION AND DEVELOPMENT&#13;
INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPMENT ASSOCIATION&#13;
By:         Lsa0                          x'    -     S 0&#13;
Name:&#13;
Title:&#13;
Date:&#13;
EUROPEAN COMMISSION&#13;
B y :  -                       I      .&#13;
HEA   O   COOPERATION&#13;
Name:.&#13;
7   F HANISTAN&#13;
Title:              1j&#13;
Date:&#13;
-4-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Interpretative Addendum&#13;
For purposes of interpreting Art. 14.1.4 of the 2014 Framework Agreement (and not as a derogation from&#13;
such Article), the "notional approach" referred to therein shall apply in the following manner in cases of&#13;
both Direct and Indirect Management modalities:&#13;
a)  This Trust Fund is a "Multi Donor Trust Fund" or "MDTF," defined as follows in Article 1(v) of&#13;
the 2014 Framework Agreement: "a trust fund that may receive contributions from more than&#13;
one donor, whose funds are pooled under a single set of agreed terms and such funds are not&#13;
earmarked by individual donors for specific categories of expenditures, also known as 'joint co-&#13;
financing' by the Commission." Consequently, the contributions from the Commission, as well&#13;
as from other donors ("Other Contributions"), form an account of commingled funds (the "MDTF&#13;
Pool") within which no one particular donor's contribution can be traced.&#13;
b) In administering the MDTF Pool, the Bank applies terms that are the same for all contributions to&#13;
the MDTF, in addition to terms, derived from the 2014 Framework Agreement, that apply solely to&#13;
the Commission Contribution ("Commission Terms"). Examples of Commission Terms include&#13;
(i) that costs are incurred within a specified time period (2014 Framework Agreement Arts.&#13;
14.1.1(c) and 14.2.1(b)), (ii) that costs are verifiable through supporting documents retained for&#13;
7-years after the applicable End Disbursement Date (2014 Framework Agreement Arts. 14.1.1(e),&#13;
14.2.1(d) and 17.4), or (iii) that the Trust Fund pay for indirect costs only at levels not exceeding&#13;
those accepted by the Commission pursuant to 2014 Framework Agreement Art. 13.4.&#13;
c) The notional approach allows the Commission to participate in MDTFs where not all expenditures&#13;
would be eligible for the Commission (see point b immediately above) without earmarking its&#13;
contribution to specific items or on the basis of geographical criteria. It allows so by verifying that&#13;
there is enough expenditure in the MDTF eligible in accordance with the Commission Terms to&#13;
justify the Commission contribution.&#13;
d) Consequently, if, in carrying out verifications or audits of the Trust Fund under 2014 Framework&#13;
Agreement Art. 17.2, a sampling by a European Union competent body finds ineligible&#13;
expenditures because of non-compliance solely with Commission Terms, no refunds need be made&#13;
by the Bank or any Recipients, nor shall adjustments be made under 2014 Framework Agreement&#13;
Art. 15.3.1, nor shall any offsets be applied under 2014 Framework Agreement Art. 16.5 or&#13;
otherwise, as long as sufficient Other Contributions to cover the amount of such expenditures were&#13;
made to the MDTF Pool before the End Disbursement Date. Such refunds, adjustments or offsets&#13;
may only be applied (i) if, and to the extent, the ineligible expenditures are in excess of Other&#13;
Contributions and (ii) if the Bank does not provide documentation to justify that an amount equal&#13;
to such ineligible expenditures is covered by the Other Contributions.&#13;
The provisions of this paragraph shall be applied in conjunction and are consistent with Art. 17 of, and&#13;
Attachment 3 to, the 2014 Framework Agreement, and are also consistent with the terms of Art. 42.2 of&#13;
the Rules of Application (Commission Delegated Regulation (EU) No 1268/2012 of 29 October 2012).&#13;
-5-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿ANNEX 1&#13;
Description of Project and Non-Binding Preferred Operations&#13;
I.     Project Description&#13;
The Contribution shall be used exclusively for the following purposes:&#13;
The objective of the Trust Fund is to provide a vehicle for Donors to pool resources and coordinate their&#13;
support to the programme of the Islamic Republic of Afghanistan for the reconstruction of Afghanistan.&#13;
Without prejudice to the provisions of paragraph 7(a) of Annex 2 to this Administration Agreement, the&#13;
Bank acknowledges the Donor's expression of preference that the contribution shall be used for the&#13;
purpose of co-financing the System Enhancement for Health Action in Transition Project under the&#13;
Health Sector of the Trust Fund. The Bank will use its discretion to ensure that the Contribution supports&#13;
the said operations under the Trust Fund.&#13;
II.    Non-Binding Preferred Operations&#13;
The Contribution aims to support the System     Enhancement for Health Action in&#13;
Transition Project (SEHAT or the Project). The objectives of the Project are to expand the scope, quality&#13;
and coverage of health services provided to the population, particularly to the poor, in the Project areas,&#13;
and to enhance the stewardship functions of the Ministry of Public Health ("MOPH").&#13;
The Project consists of the following parts:&#13;
Part 1: Basic Package of Health Services and the Essential Package of Hospital Services&#13;
(a)   Delivery of a Basic Package of Health Services ("BPHS") and an Essential Package of Hospital&#13;
Services ("EPHS") in selected provinces through the engagement of NGOs under Performance-&#13;
based Service Contracts.&#13;
(b)    Delivery of BPHS and EPHS in selected provinces and in the urban area of Kabul through direct&#13;
service delivery by the MOPH.&#13;
(c)    Carrying out a program of activities designed to improve access to, and quality of the BPHS and&#13;
EPHS, such program to include enhancing access of marginalized or at risk populations to BPHS&#13;
and HIV/AIDS prevention and harm reduction services.&#13;
(d)    Implementation of results-based financing schemes aimed at gauging the effectiveness of supply-&#13;
side innovations, including: (i) provision of performance-based payments to health care&#13;
providers; (ii) testing innovations in the hospital sector aimed at strengthening performance; and&#13;
(iii) carrying out an impact evaluation to assess and document the effects of the schemes and&#13;
mainstream the schemes, through the engagement of NGOs under performance agreements.&#13;
(e)    Increase access to nutrition services regarding curative measures and prevention of&#13;
malnutrition via (i) the establishment under SEHAT of an innovation award mechanism to&#13;
contract improved nutrition services; (ii) building capacity of those same NGOs in providing&#13;
nutrition related services by training of various categories of health workers; (iii) raising&#13;
awareness of community on prevention of malnutrition.&#13;
-6-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Part 2: MOPH Stewardship Capacity and System Development&#13;
Carrying out a program of activities designed to strengthen the capacity of MOPH in its stewardship&#13;
functions, such program to include:&#13;
(a)    Strengthening Sub-national Government (provincial health departments) by supporting&#13;
strengthening sub-national planning and budgeting; strengthening operations and maintenance;&#13;
and building Provincial Health Directorates' capacity to undertake their enhanced functions as&#13;
envisaged in the sub-national governance policy and the provincial budgeting initiative&#13;
(b)    Strengthening the Healthcare Financing Directorate through support for the MOH to undertake&#13;
analytical work, including the development and testing of appropriate financing models for the&#13;
sector.&#13;
(c)    Developing Regulatory Systems and Capacities for Ensuring Quality Pharmaceuticals by&#13;
supporting will the establishment and operationalization of a regulatory mechanism and quality&#13;
assurance system for the pharmaceutical sub-sector.&#13;
(d)    Working with the Private Sector through carrying out analytical work to understand and build&#13;
knowledge about the potential role for better engagement of the private sector in the provision of&#13;
health services.&#13;
(e)  Enhancing Capacity for Improved Hospital Performance by supporting the design of a hospital&#13;
provider payment mechanism that will enhance accountability of the autonomous hospitals and&#13;
the piloting of this new mechanism in two hospitals in Kabul.&#13;
(f) Strengthening Human Resources for Health by supporting strengthening the human resources&#13;
capacities within the MOH regular civil services staff; strengthening linkages with Capacity&#13;
Building for Results (CBR) program proposal; and focusing on ensuring availability of female&#13;
health workers.&#13;
(g)   Governance and Social Accountability through support for streamlining and simplification of the&#13;
MOH internal procedures/processes; introducing a beneficiary feedback mechanism to enhance&#13;
social accountability in the health sector; and strengthening transparency of the system and&#13;
communication capacity at MOH to pro-actively reach out to the general public.&#13;
(h)    Strengthening Health Information System (HIS) and Use of Information Technology through&#13;
support for key activities such as mainstreaming HIS activities and capacity development at&#13;
central and provincial levels along with improving data utilization at different levels of the health&#13;
sector.&#13;
(i)    Strengthening Health Promotion and Behavioural Change by strengthening the capacity of the&#13;
Health Promotion Unit to implement behaviour change campaigns targeting specific behaviours&#13;
to reduce malnutrition, promoting breastfeeding and appropriate complementary feeding for the&#13;
children under two years, enhanced skilled and institutional deliveries, hygiene promotion and&#13;
hand washing, compliance with anti-TB drugs, etc.&#13;
(j)    Improving Fiduciary Systems through support to the MOPH in upgrading the financial&#13;
management (FM) and procurement system to a web-based system; simplifying payment&#13;
-7-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿procedures; strengthening capacity building of finance and internal audit staff of the MOH;&#13;
accreditation of the procurement department of the MOH; piloting e-GP (electronic Government&#13;
Procurement); and strengthening of procurement capacity at PHDs.&#13;
(k)   Mainstreaming Gender into Afghanistan's Health System by supporting gender mainstreaming at&#13;
the policy level; integrating gender at the service delivery level; building the capacity and&#13;
increasing awareness among target groups on gender based violence (GBV), and gender and&#13;
health at the community level; and strengthening the implementation of a human-rights based&#13;
approach in the health sector.&#13;
Part 3: Proiect Management&#13;
Carrying out a program of activities designed to strengthen the capacity of MOPH's central and&#13;
provincial health offices for Project management, procurement, monitoring and evaluation, health&#13;
care financing, public relations and selected management functions, enhancing the&#13;
communication capacity of MOPH among its provincial, regional and central offices, and&#13;
rehabilitation of MOPH offices.&#13;
-8-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿ANNEX 2&#13;
Standard Terms and Conditions Governing Contributions to the&#13;
Afghanistan Reconstruction Trust Fund&#13;
This Annex shall be applicable to and form an integral part of all administration agreements for the Trust&#13;
Fund (collectively, the "Administration Agreements" and each an "Administration Agreement") between&#13;
the Bank and any entities that provide any funds to the Trust Fund (collectively, the "Donors").&#13;
1.     General&#13;
The following terms and conditions will govern all agreements entered into between the Bank and&#13;
donor countries or agencies (individually referred to herein as the "Donors"; each a "Donor") that provide&#13;
grants to the Bank as contributions to the Trust Fund (the "Grant Funds").&#13;
2.     Objective of the Trust Fund&#13;
The objective of the Trust Fund is to provide a vehicle for Donors to pool resources and&#13;
coordinate their support to the programme of the Government of the Islamic Republic of Afghanistan for&#13;
the reconstruction of Afghanistan.&#13;
3.     Definitions&#13;
Unless the context otherwise requires, the several terms defined in the Letter Agreement and in&#13;
paragraph I above have the respective meanings therein set forth, and the following additional terms have&#13;
the following meanings:&#13;
(a)    "Administration" means the Administration of the Islamic Republic of Afghanistan or&#13;
any successor thereto;&#13;
(b)    "Category" means any of the categories of expenditures set forth in the table in paragraph&#13;
4 of this Annex.&#13;
(c)    "Capital Expenditures" means expenditures on account of goods, including, without&#13;
limitation, office furniture and equipment, as set forth in the Administration's budget, the&#13;
eligibility for financing of which will have been approved by the Management&#13;
Committee;&#13;
(d)    "Financing Strategy" means a three year rolling framework for planning the use of Grant&#13;
Funds, agreed annually by the Steering Committee on the basis of a recommendation&#13;
from the Strategy Working Group;&#13;
(e)    "Incentive Program" means a performance based program that allocates a certain portion&#13;
of recurrent cost financing based on the Administration's meeting of reform benchmarks,&#13;
set and reviewed by the Incentive Program Working Group;&#13;
(f)    "Incentive Program  Working Group" means the technical advisory body whose&#13;
responsibilities are described in paragraph 5(b)(ii) of this Annex, and whose membership&#13;
consists of representatives of (i) the Bank; (ii) the Ministry of Finance, and (iii)&#13;
-9-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿representatives of no more than six Donors to be reviewed on an annual basis by the&#13;
Steering Committee;&#13;
(g)    "Investment and Program Activity" means activities, the purpose of which will be to&#13;
meet a recognized development objective and which is part of an investment or sector&#13;
program of the Administration that will have been approved by the Management&#13;
Committee. Such activities will include, without limitation, activities in agriculture,&#13;
infrastructure, micro-finance and the social sectors, as well as reintegration of combatants&#13;
into society and programs to facilitate the return of private business to Afghanistan,&#13;
together with pre-feasibility and other studies related thereto. The expression "Investment&#13;
and Program Activity" includes a Law and Order Project (as this expression is hereinafter&#13;
defined);&#13;
(h)    "Law and Order Project" means an Investment Project, the purpose of which, in whole or&#13;
in part, will be the carrying out, in connection with the civil branch of the police force of&#13;
the Government of the Islamic Republic of Afghanistan, of one or more of the following&#13;
activities: (i) payment of salaries and benefits; (ii) provision of uniforms; (iii) provision&#13;
of nonmilitary or non-paramilitary vehicles; (iv) provision of computer and two way&#13;
communications equipment; (v) provision of fuel; and (vi) payment of operating and&#13;
maintenance costs associated with said vehicles and computer and communications&#13;
equipment;&#13;
(i)    "Management Committee" means the committee whose responsibilities are described in&#13;
paragraph 5(a)(ii) of this Annex, and whose membership will consist of representatives of&#13;
the Asian Development Bank, the Islamic Development Bank, the Ministry of Finance,&#13;
the United Nations Development Programme and the Bank;&#13;
(j)    "Ministry of Finance" means the Administration's Ministry of Finance or any successor&#13;
thereto;&#13;
(k)    "Monitoring Agent" means an independent firm to be engaged by the Bank in accordance&#13;
with the provisions of paragraph 6(a) of this Annex.&#13;
(1)    "Recurrent Expenditures" means those recurrent expenditures set forth in the&#13;
Administration's budget, whose eligibility for financing hereunder will have been&#13;
determined by the Management Committee, relating to wages, benefits and other&#13;
payments for civil servants, pension payments, debt service obligations, including the&#13;
payment of interest, fees and other charges, and operation and maintenance costs, but&#13;
excluding military and paramilitary expenditures and police-related expenditures, other&#13;
than the activities contemplated under paragraph 3(h);&#13;
(m)    "Steering Committee" means the committee whose responsibilities are described in&#13;
paragraph 5(a)(iii) of this Annex, and whose membership (to be reviewed on an annual&#13;
basis) consists of representatives of: (i) the Bank; (ii) each Donor; (iii) the Ministry of&#13;
Finance; and which may be attended by the other members of the Management&#13;
Committee as observers;&#13;
(n)    "Strategy Working Group" means the technical advisory body whose responsibilities are&#13;
described in paragraph 5(b) (i) of this Annex, and whose membership (to be reviewed on&#13;
an annual basis) consists of representatives of: (i) the Bank; (ii) the Ministry of Finance;&#13;
-10-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿(iii) Donors whose contributions to the Trust Fund equals or exceeds ten million United&#13;
States Dollars (US$10,000,000) per annum and that have adequate technical expertise at&#13;
the local level; (iv) Donors whose contributions to the Trust Fund are less than ten&#13;
million United States Dollars (US$10,000,000) per annum and that have adequate&#13;
technical expertise at the local level, will share a membership that will rotate semi-&#13;
annually pursuant to a rotation schedule to be agreed amongst said Donors; and (v) any&#13;
such sector Ministries of the Administration as the Strategy Working Group may decide&#13;
to invite to its meetings on an ad hoc basis;&#13;
(o)    "Sub-grant" means a grant made or proposed to be made by the Bank using Trust Funds&#13;
allocated to Category (3), herewith to any public or private entity to carry out an&#13;
Investment and Program Activity;&#13;
(p)    "Sub-grant Recipient" means a public or private entity to which the Bank proposes to&#13;
make, or has made, a Sub-grant;&#13;
(q)    "Sub-grant Agreement" means an agreement entered into, or proposed to be entered into,&#13;
between the Bank and a Sub-grant Recipient; and&#13;
(r)    "Research and Analysis Program" or the acronym "RAP" mean activities, the purpose of&#13;
which will be to strengthen analysis and research and inform ARTF's strategic focus and&#13;
work, through in-depth studies, impact evaluations, and other analytical work that will&#13;
have been approved by the Management Committee. Such activities will include, without&#13;
limitation, pre-feasibility and other studies, and analytical work.&#13;
4.     Categories of Expenditure&#13;
4.1    For Bank-executed activities, the Trust Fund funds may be used to finance:&#13;
*    Associated overheads&#13;
*    Staff costs with indirect costs&#13;
*    Extended term consultants with indirect costs&#13;
*    Short term consultants with indirect costs&#13;
*    Consultant fees for firms&#13;
*    Contractual services&#13;
*    Temporary support staff costs with indirect costs&#13;
*    Field assignment benefits&#13;
*    Travel expenses&#13;
*    Equipment and office premises lease costs&#13;
*    Media, workshops, conferences and meetings costs&#13;
- 11 -&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿4.2    For Recipient-executed activities, the Trust Fund funds may be used to finance, together with the&#13;
percentage of expenditures to be financed:&#13;
Percentage of&#13;
Expenditures&#13;
Category                                              to be Financed&#13;
(1)    Recurrent and Capital Expenditures                    100%&#13;
(2)    Expert services and training                          100%&#13;
(3)    Sub-grants for Investment Projects                    100%&#13;
5.     Governance Structure of the Trust Fund&#13;
(a)    The Trust Fund will have the following three-tier governance structure:&#13;
(i)    The Bank will be the administrator of the Trust Fund. In this capacity, the Bank will&#13;
establish and maintain appropriate records and accounts to identify the contributions to&#13;
the Trust Fund, the commitments to be financed out of the Grant Funds and the receipt&#13;
and disbursement of the Grant Funds. The Bank will also be responsible to supervise the&#13;
performance of the Monitoring Agent(s) subject to the proviso set forth at the end of&#13;
paragraph 8(a) of this Annex.&#13;
(ii)   The Management Committee will be responsible, inter alia, for resource allocation&#13;
decisions with respect to the Trust Fund, including RAP activities. In allocating Grant&#13;
Funds, the Management Committee will be guided by the Financing Strategy. The&#13;
Management Committee will be chaired by the Bank as administrator and, on a monthly&#13;
basis, meet in Kabul, Afghanistan, or in such other location as the Management&#13;
Committee may decide from time to time, or by teleconference and, will following such&#13;
meeting, report in writing to each Donor on operations and activities financed by&#13;
disbursements made by the Trust Fund and decisions taken by the Management&#13;
Committee. The Management Committee will, on a quarterly basis, prepare and submit to&#13;
the Steering Committee a report which will describe in detail the operations of the Trust&#13;
Fund, including the receipt and use of donor contributions to the Trust Fund and the&#13;
activities financed therefrom, together with minutes of the monthly meetings of the&#13;
Management Committee. The Management Committee will act collectively and, to the&#13;
extent practicable, make decisions by consensus.&#13;
(iii)  The Steering Committee will be responsible for overseeing and supervising the&#13;
performance of the Management Committee. The Steering Committee will, on a quarterly&#13;
basis, meet in Kabul, Afghanistan, or in such place as the Committee may decide, to&#13;
review progress in the implementation of activities financed under the Trust Fund, and&#13;
approve the Financing Strategy to provide guidance to the Management Committee on&#13;
Grant Fund allocation. At the start of each solar year and on the basis of a proposal from&#13;
the Strategy Working Group, the Steering Committee will (A) review and assess how&#13;
well funding decisions on individual projects, recurrent cost support and the Incentive&#13;
program met the existing Financing Strategy, and (B) revise the Financing Strategy as&#13;
needed to guide Grant Fund allocations for the upcoming annual period.&#13;
- 12 -&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿(b)    The following technical advisory bodies will report to the Steering Committee:&#13;
(i)    The Strategy Working Group, which will meet from time to time in Kabul, Afghanistan,&#13;
under the chairmanship of the Bank, to: (A) make recommendations to the Steering&#13;
Committee on the Financing Strategy at the start of each solar year; (B) inform the annual&#13;
review (by the Steering Committee) of the implementation of the Financing Strategy, and&#13;
highlight issues that arose in the course of implementation; (C) hold ad-hoc review&#13;
meetings as needed to discuss particular issues or bottlenecks; (D) ensure that the&#13;
Financing Strategy is coordinated with the Ministry of Finance Fiscal Policy unit (and&#13;
therefore the Medium Term Fiscal Framework) as well as with the Ministry of Finance&#13;
Budget Department; and (E) support the development of a results matrix for the&#13;
Financing Strategy; and&#13;
(ii)   The Incentive Program Working Group, which will meet from time to time in Kabul,&#13;
Afghanistan, under the chairmanship of the Bank, to discuss policy benchmarks with the&#13;
Administration and report thereon to the Steering Committee as part of the Incentive&#13;
Program Framework.&#13;
6.     Implementation of Activities under the Trust Fund&#13;
(a)    The Administration will be responsible for implementing the activities to be financed&#13;
under Categories (1) and (2). Implementation of the activities to be financed under Category (3) is&#13;
governed by the provisions of paragraph 9 of this Annex. The Bank will engage one or more Monitoring&#13;
Agents to monitor expenditures related to the activities financed under Categories (1), (2) and (3). Each&#13;
Monitoring Agent will be selected and retained by the Bank on the basis of terms of reference/scope of&#13;
work agreed by the Management Committee and the Bank. The responsibilities of each Monitoring Agent&#13;
will include monitoring the procurement of goods, services and other items, screening and recommending&#13;
withdrawal applications for the Bank's approval and payment, monitoring all expenditures financed by&#13;
the Grant Funds and pre-screening the financial management capacity of potential Sub-grant Recipients&#13;
so as to ensure that Grant Funds are disbursed only for the purposes specified in paragraph 4 of this&#13;
Annex and according to applicable Bank procedures.&#13;
(b)    Monitoring Agents will report to the Bank. Subject to the approval of the Management&#13;
Committee, the Bank will have the authority to change the terms of reference/scope of work of each&#13;
Monitoring Agent and, where justified, to replace each Monitoring Agent with another firm or agency.&#13;
The Bank will give advance notice to the Administration, the Management Committee and the Donors of&#13;
changes to the terms of reference/scope of work of each Monitoring Agent. The Bank will perform ex-&#13;
post evaluations of the activities undertaken by the Monitoring Agents, and will, upon completion of the&#13;
activities financed under the Trust Fund, arrange for an independent review of the performance of the&#13;
Monitoring Agents and report its findings to the Donors.&#13;
(c)    The Grant Funds may be used by the Bank to: (i) pay the reasonable fees, travel and other&#13;
reimbursable costs of Monitoring Agents; and (ii) pay the cost of goods, services and other items of&#13;
expenditure in furtherance of the Trust Fund activities, all in accordance with the provisions of the Grant,&#13;
including this Annex.&#13;
(d)    The selection and recruitment of Monitoring Agents by the Bank, and the procurement&#13;
and financing of expenditures for goods and services to be carried out by the Administration, in&#13;
connection with goods and services financed under Categories (1) and (2), and by each Monitoring Agent,&#13;
- 13 -&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿will take place on an untied basis, in accordance with the Bank's "Guidelines for Procurement under&#13;
IBRD Loans and IDA Credits" and the "Guidelines for the Use of Consultants by World Bank Borrowers&#13;
and by the World Bank as Executing Agency".&#13;
7.     The Bank's Use of Grant Funds and Administrative Cost Recovery&#13;
(a)    The Grant Funds will be accounted for as part of a single Trust Fund which will be kept&#13;
separate and apart from other funds of the Bank. Donor contributions to the Trust Fund may not be&#13;
earmarked for one or more specific Categories and will instead be allocated among all Categories in&#13;
accordance with the decisions of the Management Committee. A Donor may state a preference that its&#13;
contribution be used to finance one or more Categories, or certain activities in a given sector, with the&#13;
understanding that neither the Management Committee nor the Bank will be in a position to guarantee&#13;
that total spending with respect to any given Category or sector will match or exceed the level of the&#13;
contribution in connection with which a preference will have been stated. Undesignated contributions will&#13;
be allocated among Categories in accordance with the decisions of the Management Committee. No&#13;
contribution to the Trust Fund will be accepted unless it equals or exceeds two hundred thousand United&#13;
States dollars (US$200,000).&#13;
(b)    The Bank may invest the Grant Funds pending their disbursement in any instrument in&#13;
which the Bank is authorized to invest its own funds. The investment income earned on the Grant Funds&#13;
pending disbursement will be added to the account to be used for purposes of the Trust Fund.&#13;
(c)    In order to assist in the defrayment of its administrative costs, the Bank may upon receipt&#13;
of the Grant Funds, deduct from the T-Account and transfer to itself:&#13;
(i)    as of January 1, 2016, an amount equivalent to three percent (3.0%) of the amount of the&#13;
Grant Funds (other than for ad hoc payments);&#13;
(ii)   as of January 1, 2017, an amount equivalent to four percent (4.0%) of the amount of the&#13;
Grant Funds (other than for ad hoc payments); and&#13;
(iii)  an amount equal to two percent (2%) of the amount of the Grant Funds allocated to the&#13;
Recurrent and Capital Expenditures Category for the purposes of ad hoc payments.&#13;
The Bank may also deduct from the T-Account and transfer to itself the actual costs of the Bank's&#13;
contract with the Monitoring Agent(s), as well as the cost of the independent review of the Monitoring&#13;
Agent(s)'s performance referred to under paragraph 6(b) of this Annex.&#13;
8.     Fiduciary Responsibilities of the Bank&#13;
(a)    The Bank will be responsible only for performing those functions specifically set forth in&#13;
this Letter Agreement, including this Annex, and will not be subject to any other duties or responsibilities&#13;
to Donors, including, without limitation, any duties or obligations that might otherwise apply to a&#13;
fiduciary or trustee under general principles of trust or fiduciary law. Nothing in this Letter Agreement&#13;
will be considered a waiver of any privileges or immunities of the Bank under its Articles of Agreement&#13;
or any applicable law, all of which are expressly reserved. The Bank will have no responsibility to Donors&#13;
with respect to the performance of the Monitoring Agent(s) and will have no obligation to reimburse the&#13;
Trust Fund or provide any compensation to any Donor if the Grant Funds are not disbursed for the&#13;
purposes specified in this Annex as a result of actions of the Monitoring Agent(s).&#13;
- 14 -&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿(b)    Unless otherwise provided in this Letter Agreement, the Bank will apply its normal&#13;
financial management procedures to the Trust Fund. Such procedures applicable to the operation of the&#13;
Trust Fund will be communicated to the Donors without delay.&#13;
(c)    Unless otherwise provided in this Letter Agreement, the Bank will apply to the Trust&#13;
Fund its framework to prevent and combat fraud and corruption and its screening procedures to prevent&#13;
the use of Bank resources to finance terrorist activity, in line with the Bank's obligations to give effect to&#13;
the relevant decisions of the Security Council, taken under Chapter VII of the Charter of the United&#13;
Nations. The Donor acknowledges that this provision does not create any obligations of the Bank under&#13;
the anti-terrorist financing and asset control laws, regulations, rules and executive orders of an individual&#13;
member country that may apply to the Donor, nor will it be deemed a waiver, express or implied, of any&#13;
of the privileges and immunities of the Bank.&#13;
9.     Terms and Conditions Governing Sub-Grants Under Cate2ory (3)&#13;
In the event that the Bank deems it necessary execute a sub-grant to carry out an Investment and&#13;
Program Activity eligible for financing under Category (3), the following provisions will apply:&#13;
(a)    The Bank will conclude a Sub-grant Agreement with each "Sub-grant Recipient".&#13;
(b)    Except as provided in paragraph (c) below, responsibility for the accounting and&#13;
administration of Grant Funds made available by the Bank to Sub-grant Recipients will be decided upon&#13;
on a case-by-case basis by the Management Committee, considering, inter alia, the recommendations&#13;
made by the Monitoring Agent(s). Accordingly, the Management Committee will review proposals to&#13;
carry out activities eligible for financing under Category (3) and award Sub-grants in connection with&#13;
proposals deemed by the Management Committee to be suitable for financing and consistent with the&#13;
Financing Strategy. Proposals for financing under Category (3) will be submitted for approval to the&#13;
Administration which, when approved, will forward them to the Management Committee for&#13;
consideration. Only proposals vetted by the Administration in the manner described in this sub-paragraph&#13;
will be considered by the Management Committee. A proposal submitted to the Management Committee,&#13;
through the Administration, will include an appraisal of the Investment and Program Activity sought to be&#13;
financed. For those proposals that do not include an appraisal of the Investment Project sought to be&#13;
financed, the Bank will carry out the appraisal of the Investment Project. The representative of a member&#13;
organization of the Management Committee will recuse him or herself from deliberations over the&#13;
suitability of proposal(s) submitted or co-financed by the organization that he or she represents.&#13;
(c)    Notwithstanding the provisions of sub-paragraph (b) of this paragraph 9, proposals to&#13;
carry out a Law and Order Project may only be made and carried out by the United Nations Development&#13;
Programme. The latter will be the sole organization authorized to carry out Law and Order Projects&#13;
financed hereunder. Sub-grants to finance Law and Order Projects will be made in accordance with terms&#13;
and conditions acceptable to the Bank including, without limitation, those set forth in sub-paragraphs (a),&#13;
(d), (e), (f) and (g) of this paragraph 9 whose provisions shall apply, mutatis mutandis, to any Sub-grant&#13;
made or to be made by the Bank to the United Nations Development Programme for purposes of carrying&#13;
out a Law and Order Project. UNDP, the Bank and the Management Committee will agree on detailed&#13;
procedures including procurement, disbursements and audits for processing Law and Order Projects.&#13;
(d)    Sub-grants will be used to finance expenditures for goods, works and services, as the case&#13;
may be, in accordance with the Bank's "Guidelines for Procurement under IBRD Loans and IDA Credits"&#13;
and the "Guidelines for the Use of Consultants by World Bank Borrowers and by the World Bank as&#13;
Executing Agency", as in effect at the date of the relevant Sub-grant agreement (hereinafter collectively&#13;
- 15-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿referred to as the "Bank's Guidelines"). Any departure from the Bank's Guidelines will have to be&#13;
preapproved by the Bank.&#13;
(e)    The fiduciary arrangements for an Investment and Program Activity to be financed under&#13;
Category (3) will be carried out in accordance with the guidelines and procedures specified in paragraph&#13;
8(b) including but not limited to an environmental and social screening and assessment framework&#13;
approved by the Bank. Any departure from the guidelines contained in said framework will have to be&#13;
pre-approved by the Bank.&#13;
(f)    As required under regular Bank lending operations, a Sub-grant Agreement will obligate&#13;
a Sub-grant Recipient, among other things, to maintain an appropriate and adequate financial&#13;
management system, including records and accounts, and prepare financial statements adequate to&#13;
separately reflect the operations, resources and expenditures related to the Investment and Program&#13;
Activity financed under the Sub-grant. Within ninety (90) days of each June 30 and December 31, the&#13;
Sub-grant Recipient will prepare unaudited financial statements with respect to such Sub-grant and&#13;
forward a copy to the Bank. All financial statements appropriate to the size and purpose of the Sub-grant,&#13;
as indicated in the Sub-grant agreement will be expressed in the currency in which the Sub-grant is made,&#13;
as indicated in the Sub-grant Agreement, and will show the allocation of such funds among the activities&#13;
financed by the Sub-grant. In addition, the Sub-grant Recipient will: (i) have the above-mentioned&#13;
records, accounts and financial statements audited, in accordance with auditing standards acceptable to&#13;
the Bank, by independent auditors acceptable to the Bank; (ii) furnish to the Bank, as soon as available,&#13;
but in any case not later than six (6) months after the end of each calendar year: (A) certified copies of the&#13;
financial statements referred to above for such year as so audited, and (B) an opinion on such statements,&#13;
records and accounts and report of such audit, by said auditors, of such scope and in such detail as the&#13;
Bank will have reasonably requested; and (iii) furnish to the Bank such other information concerning said&#13;
records and accounts, and the audit thereof, as the Bank will from time to time reasonably request. In such&#13;
cases where the Sub-grant is &lt; US$100,000 the Bank has the discretion to specify in the Sub-grant&#13;
agreement that attestation from the Monitoring Agent will be sufficient to comply with the audit&#13;
procedures above.&#13;
(g)    The Bank will report quarterly to the Donors on the status of Grant Funds made available&#13;
to a Sub-grant Recipient under a Sub-grant Agreement. In addition, at a Donor's request, the Bank will&#13;
also make available, in accordance with its Policy on Access to Information, audited and unaudited&#13;
financial statements of Sub-grant Recipients furnished under paragraph (f) above.&#13;
10.    Accountin2 and Financial Reporting Responsibilities of the Bank&#13;
(a)    The Bank will maintain separate records and ledger accounts in respect of the aggregate&#13;
Grant Funds for the agreed activities and disbursements made therefrom to the Monitoring Agent(s).&#13;
Within one hundred eighty (180) days of the completion of the activities financed by the Grant Funds, the&#13;
Bank will prepare unaudited financial statements in United States dollars with respect to the Grant Funds&#13;
and forward a copy to each Donor. The Bank will provide the Donors annually with a management&#13;
assertion together with an attestation from the Bank's external auditors on the satisfactory performance of&#13;
the procedures and controls used by the Bank in administering the Grant Funds.&#13;
(b)    If a Donor wishes to request, on an exceptional basis, a financial statement audit by the&#13;
Bank's external auditors of the Trust Fund, the Donor and the Bank shall first consult as to whether such&#13;
an external audit is necessary. The Bank and the Donor shall agree on the appropriate scope and terms of&#13;
reference of such audit. Following agreement on the scope and terms of reference, the Bank shall arrange&#13;
- 16 -&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿for such external audit. The costs of any such audit, including the internal costs of the Bank with respect&#13;
to such audit, shall be paid by the requesting Donor.&#13;
11.    Progress Reporting Responsibilities of the Bank&#13;
(a)    The Bank will maintain close consultation and coordination with the Donors. The Bank&#13;
will provide each Donor with quarterly reports on its quarterly expost evaluation of the activities&#13;
undertaken by the Monitoring Agent(s) including disbursements made out of the Grant Funds. Within (6)&#13;
six months of the completion of the activities, or of full disbursement of the Grant Funds, whichever&#13;
comes later, the Bank will provide a final progress report to each Donor, together with a copy of the&#13;
independent review of the performance of the Monitoring Agent(s). Upon request by any Donor, the Bank&#13;
will send to such Donor the draft and final reports received by the Bank from each Monitoring Agent on&#13;
the activities financed by the Grant Funds.&#13;
(b)    Any Donor may review or evaluate activities financed by the Trust Fund. The Donor and&#13;
the Bank shall agree on the scope and conduct of such review or evaluation and the Bank shall provide all&#13;
relevant information within the limits of its policies and procedures. All associated costs shall be borne by&#13;
the Donor. It is understood that any such review or evaluation will not constitute a financial, compliance&#13;
or other audit of the Trust Fund and will be separate from any independent evaluation of the Trust Fund to&#13;
be arranged by the Bank.&#13;
12.    Termination&#13;
Unless otherwise agreed by the Donors and the Bank, the Trust Fund arrangement provided for&#13;
under the Letter Agreement and this Annex will expire on December 31, 2025. If at any time, either party&#13;
determines that the purposes of the Letter Agreement and this Annex can no longer be effectively or&#13;
appropriately carried out, this Letter Agreement may be terminated at the initiative of either party by&#13;
giving the other party thirty (30) days prior notice to this affect. Upon termination, unless otherwise&#13;
agreed by the Donors and the Bank: (i) any agreement entered into among the Bank, the Monitoring&#13;
Agent(s), and/or other third parties will not be affected by the termination, and the Bank will be entitled to&#13;
continue permitting withdrawals of Grant Funds in respect of such agreements as if this arrangement had&#13;
not been so terminated; and (ii) any remaining Grant Funds will be returned to the Donors on a pro-rata&#13;
basis, and the Bank's functions pursuant hereto will be considered terminated. Within six (6) months&#13;
following such termination, the Bank will furnish to the Donors an unaudited financial statement with&#13;
respect to the aggregate amount contributed by all Donors.&#13;
13.    Legal Documentation&#13;
For purposes of channeling Grant Funds to their intended beneficiaries in accordance with the&#13;
terms and conditions of the Letter Agreement and this Annex, the Bank will enter into a grant agreement&#13;
with the Administration concerning Trust Funds allocated to Categories (1) and (2). Grant Funds&#13;
allocated to Category (3) will be governed by separate sub-grant agreements to be entered into between&#13;
the Bank, on the one part, and sub-grant Recipients, on the other part, with each such agreement relating&#13;
to one or more Investment and Program Activity. Without prejudice to the foregoing, Grant Funds&#13;
allocated to Category (3) for the specific purpose of financing Law and Order Projects will be governed&#13;
by one or more grant agreements, as the case may be, to be entered into between the Bank, on the one&#13;
part, and the United Nations Development Programme, on the other part.&#13;
- 17-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿ANNEX 3&#13;
Expected results of the Trust Fund&#13;
Please refer to the Afghanistan Reconstruction Trust Fund Results Matrix dated July 2015. The results&#13;
matrix is indicative and is subject to change without the need for further amendment to this&#13;
Administration Agreement. The results martix is for monitoring and evaluation purposes only and&#13;
progress against it shall not be taken into account to determine the final amount of the Contribution to the&#13;
Trust Fund by the European Commission.&#13;
-18-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿ANNEX 4&#13;
INDICATIVE BUDGET'&#13;
The indicative total budget for the Trust Fund may be updated from time to time, including upon the&#13;
Bank's receipt of additional contributions from the European Commission and/or other donors to the&#13;
Trust Fund pursuant to their respective Administration Agreements/amendments. The updated indicative&#13;
budget will be deemed to have been agreed by both Parties without the need to further amend the&#13;
indicative total budget amount in this Annex and in paragraph 1.2 of this Administration Agreement.&#13;
1 Excel sheet with the indicative budget to be included.&#13;
-19-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿Table 5 - Actual and Expected Dxnor Co                          dodns&#13;
Paid-In. Committed, Pledged (US$ Million)&#13;
November 21, 2015&#13;
FY 1381- FY 138- FY 1381- FY 181-&#13;
SY 1381 SY 1382 SY 1383 SY 1384 SY 1385 SY 138, SY 1387 SY 1388 SY 1389 SY 1390 FY 1391 FY 1392 FY 1393               FY 1394&#13;
Donor       Total   Total  Total   Total   Total   Ttal   Total  Total   Total   Total   Tot~    Total  Total   Total  Signed  Un.~lgned  Total %of Total                  Total %ofTotal&#13;
Pad-In  Paid-in  Pald-in  Pad4n  Paid4n Pa Pan   P~ ai PaPdan P~  Pad4n  Pald4n  Padn  Pald-4n Pal~n Pledges P~    FY 1394  FY 1394                   Paidn&#13;
Australia          0,00   263     6.27    765     5.84   2.09   31.44   14.99   28.49   89.47   6.03   6236    7488  13.29    0.00     0.00   13.29  1.3%     345,44   3.8%     345.44  4,2%&#13;
Bahrain            000    050     000     0 00    000    000      000    0       .00   O. 00 0.00   .00   0.00   00   0.00    0.00     0,00    0.00  0.0%       0.50   0 0%       050   00%&#13;
Belgium            000    000     000    00     000    0.00    2.61    2,72    000     2.71   0.00    260     250    0.00    0.00     0.00    0.00  0.0%      13,13   01%       1313   02%&#13;
Brazil             0,00   0 00    000     00    0.00    0.00    000     0.20    0.00   0.00    000     000     00    0,00    0,00     000     0.00  0.0%       0.20   0.0%      020    0 0,&#13;
Canada            12.00  50 09    549    7234    5886  21346    2207    3422    3835    49 24  2608    11 84   1867   74,33    0.00    13.52   87.85  8.3%     700.58   78%      687 06  8 3%&#13;
Czech Reputllc     000    0 00    000     000     000    000     000     000     0.00    0.00   000     000     000    086     000      079     1.65  0.2%       1.65   0 0:      086   0 0,&#13;
Denmark            500    5 00    3 16    392    434     843    2086    10.25    203    1028    11 38  1070     650   1270     9.16     000    21.88  2.1%     12372    1 4%     114 56  1 4%&#13;
EC/EU             1587   5272    4760    5877   5272    7362    11.31   14 19   2552    944    34,79   3955    76.19  12.29    0.00   169.28  181.57  17.1%    693.85   7 7%,    52' 57  6,3%&#13;
Estonia           000     0 00    000     000    000     0.00    0.00    0.00    0.00    0.29   0.00    1 26    062    0.54    0.00     0.00    0.54  0.1%       2.72   0 0%      2 72   0 0%&#13;
Finland            279    245     595     000     242    540     791     8.86    782     9.90  11.10   1330    1235    9.98    0.00     0,00    9.98  0.9%     10024    1 i%     100 24  1 2%&#13;
France            000     0 00    000     0.00   0.00    0.00    5 13    5.72    5.56   0.00    5.17    5.52    000    0.00    0.00     0.00    0.00  0.0%      27.09   0.3%      2709   0 3%&#13;
Germany           1007   11 44   1594     1 23   2047   55.99   74.00   50.85   64.52   78.40  78.16   5501    7526    0.00    0.00    7476    74.76  7.0%     666.11   7.4%     591.35  7 1,&#13;
India             020     0 20    0,00    0.40   0.20    0.20    0.19    0.20    0.20   0.00    0.00    0.00    000    000     0.01     000     0.01  0.0%       1.80   0.0%       1 79  0.0%&#13;
Iran. Islamic Rep  000    0 99    000     0 00   0,00    000     0.00    0.00    0.00   0.00    0.00    0.00    000    0.00    0.00     0.00    0.00  0.0%       0.99   0.0%      099    00%&#13;
Ireland            1 00   1.70    1.81    061     1.28   1.46    1,58    2.78    2.54   1.37    0.00    0.00    0.00   0.00    0.00     0.00    0.00  0.0%      16.12   0.2%     1612    0 2%&#13;
Italy             1700    0 00    654     0.00   9.22    8.80   34.07    4.10    3.89  10.70    389     360    1769    6.14    2.55     0.00    8.69  0.8%     128.20   1 4%     12565   1 5%&#13;
Japan              500    0 00    000     0.00    0.00   0.00    0.00    0.00    000    20.00  138.00  11000   7000   60.14    0.00     000    60.14  5.7%     &amp;03.14   4 5Â¾     403 14  49%&#13;
Korea. Republic    200    2 00    200     000    000     000     000     000     000    000     0.00   1000     000    0.00    0.00     0.00    0.00  0.0%      16 00   0 2%     16 00   0 2,&#13;
Kuwait             500    500     500     000    000     000     000     0,00    000    000     000     c co    000    0.00    0.00     0.00    0.00  0.0%      15.00   0 2%      15 00  0.2%&#13;
Luxembourg         100    000     000     0.61    156    107     1.14    1.14    111    0.97    0.00    067     048    0.30    0.00     000     0.30  0.0%      10.04   01%      10.04   01%&#13;
Nethertands       3367   41 15   4641    2966    5081   3976    39,46   41.90   3266   3257    3248    2378    2491   16.81    0.00     0.00   16.81  1.6%     486.03   5 41    486 i3  59%&#13;
New Zealand       000     000     000     000    063     000     000     0.00    000    0.00    0 00    000     000    0.00    0.00     0.00    0.00  0.0%       063    0 0x     063    0 0%&#13;
Norway            682    29.63    9.91   2254    2322   3098    31 47   3836    4780   4857    5511    51 24   3913   27.79    2.00     0.00   29.80  2.8%     464.59   5 2X     Ã©62 58  5 6%&#13;
Poland             000    0.00    0.00    0,00   029     027     117     1.20    100     140    1.26    059     000    0.61    0.25     000     0.86  0.1%       804    0.11       779   01,&#13;
Portugal          000     046     073     000    000     0.00    000     0.00    000    0.00    0.00    0.00    0.00   0.00    0.00     0.00   0.00   0.0%       1 18   0 0        1 18  003%&#13;
Russian Federat    000    000     000     0.00   0.00    0.00    2.00    2.00    000    0.00    0.00    000     0,00   0.00    0.00     0.00    0.00  0.0%       400    0.0%      400    00%&#13;
Saudi Arabia     1000     500     500     000    500     000     000     0.00    000    0.00    000     0 00    000    0.00    0.00     0.00   0.00   0.0%      25.00  0.3%      25 00   0 3%&#13;
Spain             000     0 00    000     000    0.00   22.04    0.00   35.22   27.59   664     000     000     0 00   0.00    0.00     0 00    0.00  0.0%      91 50   1.0%      91 50  1 1%&#13;
Sweden             3 10   5 98   2590    1284   1468    20 18   18.35   2535    3264   28.59   31 49   3998    32 12   0.00    2,30    32,21   34.51  3.3%     325.72   36%      291 21  3 53,&#13;
Switzerland       0,67    00,0    000     000    000     000     000     0      0.00   0.00    000     000     0.00   0.00    3.94     3.94   7.87   0.7%       8.54  0 1%       067    00%&#13;
Turkey            0.50    0 00    0 00    0.00   000     0.00    000     000     0 00   000     000     000     000    0.00    0.00     0.00   0.00   0.0%       0.50   0 0       050   0 0%&#13;
UNDP              0 00    241     000     000    000     0.00    000     0.00    000    000     000     000     3,00   0.00    0.00     0.00   0.00   0.0%       241    0 0%      241    0 0%&#13;
United Kingdom    1508   47 10  10306   131 47  12849  151 05  16254    99.05   2372  132.96  136.02  13041   132 86 103.39   29.02     000   13241  125%    152622   170%     *497 20  180%&#13;
United States     38 00  2000    8959    6200    7390    000   15950   264.00  265.00  400.00  371.24  218 59  443.47  28.00  100.00  250.00  378.00  35.6%   2783,29  30.9%    2433 29  29 3%&#13;
TOTA.         | 18477   286.46  380.37  404.05  453.92  634.80  626.82  657.29  610.44  933.51, 942.20  791.00 1027.64 367.18  149.23  54450 1060.91  100.0%  8994.18  100.0%   8300.45  100:0%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="25783013">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2015/12/25783013/official-documents--administration-agreement-european-commission-contribution-tf050576-contract-no-dci-asie2015369067
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2015/12/25783013/official-documents--administration-agreement-european-commission-contribution-tf050576-contract-no-dci-asie2015369067</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2015/12/25783013/official-documents--administration-agreement-european-commission-contribution-tf050576-contract-no-dci-asie2015369067</new_url>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2016-01-24T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <docm_id>090224b08407838f</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b08407838f</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/SAR/2016/01/14/090224b08407838f/1_0/Rendered/INDEX/Official0Docum0ribution0to0TF050576.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/SAR/2016/01/14/090224b08407838f/1_0/Rendered/PDF/Official0Docum0ribution0to0TF050576.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2016-01-14T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2015-12-27T16:25:39Z</docdt>
        <docna>
            Official Documents- Administration Agreement
            with the European Commission for Contribution to TF050576
            (Contract No. DCI-ASIE/2015/369067)
        </docna>
        <display_title>Official Documents-
            Administration Agreement with the European Commission for
            Contribution to TF050576  (Contract No. DCI-ASIE/2015/369067)</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/2015/12/25783013/official-documents--administration-agreement-european-commission-contribution-tf050576-contract-no-dci-asie2015369067</listing_relative_url>
        <projn>AF-Afghanistan Reconstruction Trust Fund -- P078069</projn>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <docty>Trust Fund Administrative Agreement</docty>
        <count>Afghanistan</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Pavluk,Jonathan David</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>HQBOCS</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <owner>Afghanistan Anchor Unit (SACAA)</owner>
        <trustfund>TF050576-Afghanistan Reconstruction
            Trust Fund</trustfund>
        <lang>English</lang>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fragility, Conflict and Violence</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Capacities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Staffing Needs Assessments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Basket of Health Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Medical Supplies, Drugs</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pharmaceutical Industry</ml:concept><ml:concept>AIDS HIV</ml:concept><ml:concept>HIV AIDS</ml:concept><ml:concept>HIV/AIDS</ml:concept><ml:concept>Impact Evaluations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Randomized Control Trials</ml:concept><ml:concept>Organisational Structures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Organizational Assessments</ml:concept><ml:concept>HRH</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Workers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition – Community Based Interventions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition – Raising Awareness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition – Training</ml:concept><ml:concept>Electronic Medical Records</ml:concept><ml:concept>HMIS</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Information Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Expenditures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Investment Plan</ml:concept><ml:concept>Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deconcentration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delegation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Devolution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sub-National Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subnational Government and Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Participation, Empowerment and Accountability</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Accountability and Demand for Good Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>GBSV</ml:concept><ml:concept>GBV</ml:concept><ml:concept>Gender-based Violence</ml:concept><ml:concept>Gender-based and Sexual Violence</ml:concept><ml:concept>Remittances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Migration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demand for Good Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Open Government, Accountability and Transparency</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Accountability</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Impact Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Basic Package of Health Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pharmaceuticals</ml:concept><ml:concept>HIV and AIDS</ml:concept><ml:concept>Impact Assessment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance Structures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resources for Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Management Information Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Investment Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Administrative Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Youth and Gender-Based Violence</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Movement of Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Open Government and Transparency</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Afghanistan</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>