<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>                                                                                         102634&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
              Affordable Housing Finance Learning Product&#13;
                                         Concept Note&#13;
                                       December 15, 2015&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Background and Context&#13;
With this learning product on housing finance the Independent Evaluation Group (IEG) intends&#13;
to generate new knowledge, insights, and lessons about the factors contributing to the success&#13;
and failure in the International Bank for Reconstruction and Development and the International&#13;
Finance Corporationâ&#128;&#153;s (IFC) housing finance interventions. IEG will review interventions in&#13;
the form of loans for the World Bank or investments and advisory services for IFC. World&#13;
Bank technical assistance/knowledge products and interventions on housing finance matters&#13;
will be considered when provided in the context of lending operations. In other words, stand-&#13;
alone World Bank technical assistance interventions will not be a focus of this study, as such&#13;
operations are not currently subject to IEGâ&#128;&#153;s project-level evaluations.&#13;
&#13;
CONTEXT AND ISSUES&#13;
&#13;
Access to adequate housing is considered of such critical importance for peopleâ&#128;&#153;s well-being&#13;
and health that is part of the United Nations Universal Declaration of Human Rights.&#13;
Furthermore, it has been in the Global Policy agenda for several years, with one of the&#13;
Millennium Development Goal targets (7D) seeking to improve the lives of 100 million slum&#13;
dwellers by 2020.1 The 2015 Sustainable Development Goals (#11) establish a target of&#13;
ensuring â&#128;&#156;access for all to adequate, safe, and affordable housingâ&#128;&#157; by 2030.&#13;
&#13;
At present, hundreds of millions of people live in inadequate conditions, and the demand for&#13;
housing solutions will continue to grow as urbanization and population growth continue. The&#13;
U.N.-Habitat has estimated that if nothing is done, the number of people living in slums around&#13;
the world will rise from around 860 million in 2012 to 900 million by 2020.2 Asia and Africa&#13;
will face special challenges, because urbanization in those regions is proceeding rapidly.&#13;
&#13;
At the country level, authorities and the private sector have to provide adequate housing to new&#13;
households and also tackle existing backlogs. For example, in Mexico an estimated 500,000&#13;
&#13;
1&#13;
 In 2001, it was estimated that almost one-third of the urban population of the world lived in slums.&#13;
This estimation was exceeded well ahead of the 2020 deadline.&#13;
2&#13;
  A recent report from the McKinsey Global Institute (2014) estimates a housing affordability gap&#13;
affecting 330 million households, with 200 million households in the developing world living in&#13;
slums. The gap is expected to reach 440 million households by 2025.&#13;
&amp;#12;new households are formed every year. This helps drive the demand for housing along with&#13;
the existing housing shortfall of more than 9 million units, the majority of which is rural areas.&#13;
In Kenya, it is estimated that an annual housing gap of 156,000 homes drives the growth of&#13;
slums and self-construction of poor quality traditional housing (World Bank 2011).&#13;
&#13;
Creating sustainable and effective housing finance requires, among other things, the&#13;
mobilization of longer-term sources of fundingâ&#128;&#148;a task that is much harder in volatile&#13;
macroeconomic contextsâ&#128;&#148;understanding and effectively managing risks, sound oversight and&#13;
policy frameworks, and overcoming other shortcomings (for example, lack of properly&#13;
functioning land and property registries, collateral regimes, credit information systems, and&#13;
poor legal protection of creditor rights). When properly structured, such solutions would not&#13;
only support access to housing to underserved sectors but would also buttress the development&#13;
of financial systems, including capital markets (for example, by offering sound long-term&#13;
investment vehicles to institutional investors). Going forward, these solutions will have to&#13;
contend with tightened bank funding and prudential liquidity requirements phased in the&#13;
aftermath of the global crisis. Such requirements tend to limit banksâ&#128;&#153; capacity to carry on their&#13;
balance sheets housing finance portfolios, which makes the development of stable and&#13;
sustainable nonbank sources of longer-term funding even more critical than before.&#13;
&#13;
Such efforts may require a wider set of reforms to help develop an institutional investor base&#13;
(for example, pension funds and life insurance companies) with a longer-term investment&#13;
horizon. To bridge the gap until such reforms start to mobilize significant amounts of long-&#13;
term funding, institutions like IFC may be able to help kick start private markets and develop&#13;
the specialized know-how of financial intermediaries and support for infrastructure by making&#13;
long-term funding (equities, loans, guarantees) available and transferring expertise and best&#13;
practices.&#13;
&#13;
Governmentsâ&#128;&#153; interventions in the housing and housing finance market take multiple forms&#13;
around the world, both in developing economies and advanced countries. These interventions&#13;
are underpinned by different rationales, ranging from having a market development role to&#13;
increasing the affordability of housing to lower-income segments. They include the use of&#13;
government-sponsored enterprises; purchasing mortgages and mortgage-backed securities.&#13;
providing guarantees and state-owned housing (development) banks in the direct and indirect&#13;
provision of housing credit; organizing secondary markets; providing for the tax deductibility&#13;
of mortgage interest (and in some cases capital gains); providing guarantees to lenders on&#13;
mortgage defaults and mortgage insurance while stipulating underwriting standards; and&#13;
providing subsidies to both borrowers (for example, up-front and interest) and developers.3&#13;
However, given all the competing funding priorities that governments have, it is quite likely&#13;
that the private sector will have to play a bigger role in closing the funding gap and increasing&#13;
the supply and diversity of housing solutions for middle- and lower-income countries.4&#13;
&#13;
3&#13;
 Hoek-Smit (2008) provides a framework for the analysis of market segmentation and frictions that&#13;
keep housing finance underdeveloped and guidance for the design of subsidies.&#13;
4&#13;
  McKinsey (2014) estimates that some $16 trillion investment (including for land purchase) would&#13;
be required to build new units and replace substandard housing by 2025. Governments are expected&#13;
to provide between $1 trillion and $3 trillion.&#13;
&#13;
                                                 2&#13;
&amp;#12;In its housing finance operations, the World Bank has provided advice to member countries on&#13;
a range of policy issues in both low- and middle-income countries. In its engagement with&#13;
emerging markets, besides providing long-term funding, IFC is currently focusing on housing&#13;
microfinance and Islamic housing finance, green mortgages, women in housing finance, and&#13;
risk management.5&#13;
&#13;
RATIONALE FOR THE WORLD BANK GROUPâ&#128;&#153;S INTERVENTION&#13;
&#13;
The World Bank Group seeks to support countries and financial intermediaries in the&#13;
development of sustainable, efficient, secure, and market-based housing finance systems; of&#13;
public policies on housing; and of legal, regulatory, and oversight frameworks so that&#13;
un(der)served segments of the population in particular have the possibility of accessing&#13;
adequate housing services through the acquisition or the rental of houses. Having access to&#13;
such services supports households in their development endeavors, including income&#13;
generation efforts, thus contributing to poverty alleviation and shared prosperity.&#13;
&#13;
Housing finance projects interventions focus in five strategic areas:&#13;
      ï&#130;·    Building housing finance markets&#13;
      ï&#130;·    Funding housing finance&#13;
      ï&#130;·    Expanding housing finance for the poor&#13;
      ï&#130;·    Supplying affordable housing&#13;
      ï&#130;·    Housing finance crisis response.&#13;
&#13;
The overall goal is to build a sustainable and efficient housing finance system that can address&#13;
the needs of households at different income levels. The specific intervention depends on the&#13;
specific needs and state of development of the clientâ&#128;&#153;s housing finance system.&#13;
&#13;
IFCâ&#128;&#153;s strategic focus to housing finance have been evolving placing in 20046 a growing&#13;
emphasis in housing finance with particular focus in high-growth frontier and middle-income&#13;
countries. In 20107, IFC pulled back in countries where its interventions rely on demonstration&#13;
effect and due to the mortgage crises such effects are unlikely to be achieved. In 20128, housing&#13;
finance became a priority again with strong focus on improving financial inclusion housing&#13;
finance companies. IFCâ&#128;&#153;s current priorities are to implement housing solutions across the value&#13;
chain including primary lending for mortgages and housing microfinance, increased&#13;
construction of affordable housing, energy efficiency and urban housing and Risk management&#13;
capabilities and responsible finance. IFCâ&#128;&#153;s approach combines investment services (equity,&#13;
&#13;
5&#13;
  For example, IFC worked with Indiaâ&#128;&#153;s Housing Finance Corp. to launch a joint venture. IFC made&#13;
an equity investment and advised the venture on responsible lending and risk management practices.&#13;
Since 2011, the venture has made 2,500 loans, setting up 15 branches in Uttar Pradesh and 5 other&#13;
low-income states.&#13;
6&#13;
    IFC strategic priorities 2004.&#13;
7&#13;
    IFC strategic priorities 2010.&#13;
8&#13;
    IFC Road Map 2012â&#128;&#147;14.&#13;
&amp;#12;loans, guarantees) with expertise drawing from its global presence in helping bring in best&#13;
practices while tailoring specific solutions to individual client needs. Reportedly, it is the&#13;
number one international investor in housing, reaching 94 clients in 46 countries,9&#13;
&#13;
There are country cases where clear opportunities for positive synergies in the housing finance&#13;
interventions of the World Bank Group are present, and if realized they could lead to more&#13;
effective interventions. But there are also instances where Bank Group interventions may not&#13;
be aligned. For example, when the Bank is helping a state-owned second-tier financial&#13;
intermediary develop the capacity to manage risks and then design funding products for low-&#13;
income/informal sector households, it would be beneficial if IFC could (in parallel) be advising&#13;
private sector intermediaries on how to soundly lend to that market segment. Such a&#13;
coordinated and properly sequenced set of interventions by different parts of the World Bank&#13;
Group would likely increase the chances for having a deeper impact by helping kick start&#13;
market segments that otherwise would likely take much longer to develop.&#13;
&#13;
Purpose, Objectives, and Audience&#13;
With this learning product IEG will distill lessons from World Bank Group interventions aimed&#13;
at helping countries develop sustainable and inclusive housing finance systems. This review&#13;
will look at why interventions were undertaken, how they were undertaken, and the results. It&#13;
seeks to provide answers to a series of questions:&#13;
&#13;
    ï&#130;·   Nature of Engagement -- What has the Bank Group done to support housing finance&#13;
        and how has it evolved over time? What are the main activities, and who are the main&#13;
        clients?&#13;
    ï&#130;·   Relevance -- Is the Bank Group targeting the right countries? Were critical&#13;
        constraints identified (for example, legal, regulatory, informational, funding, product&#13;
        design, public policyâ&#128;&#148;urban, subsidies, and so forth) as barriers/impediments to the&#13;
        development of housing finance that evaluated projects sought to address? Is there&#13;
        evidence in the project documents identifying segments of the population that are&#13;
        excluded from (underserved by) housing finance markets? Are Bank Group&#13;
        interventions (at least in part) motivated by the identification of such gaps in access?&#13;
           Information to address this question is expected from the portfolio review and&#13;
        from mapping Bank Group country support to the stage of development of the&#13;
        housing finance market and from evaluations of Bank Group projects.&#13;
    ï&#130;·   Effectiveness â&#128;&#147; Has the World Bank Group support to housing finance achieved its&#13;
        intended objectives? Has support through Bank Group-combined interventions led to&#13;
        more successful interventions? What are the factors of success or failure contributing&#13;
        to the success and failure of IFC interventions?&#13;
            Information to address this question is expected to be available in Project Activity&#13;
        Documents; Implementation Completion and Results Reports; Project Performance&#13;
        Assessment Reports; Expanded Project Supervision Reports; Project Completion&#13;
&#13;
9&#13;
 As of June 2013, it had investments in 169 housing finance projects totaling $1.2 billion and was&#13;
implementing 19 advisory programs across 6 regions.&#13;
&#13;
                                                  4&#13;
&amp;#12;       Reports; official supervisory, regulatory, and housing authoritiesâ&#128;&#153; websites; and&#13;
       IEGâ&#128;&#153;s portfolio review and structured interviews.&#13;
&#13;
   ï&#130;·   Lessons for Future Operations â&#128;&#147; What are the lessons from experiences in improving&#13;
       access for excluded/underserved segments of populations? What are the lessons from&#13;
       developing market-based sources and instruments of long-term housing finance? Are&#13;
       interventions conducive to capital development? Are the interventions that are&#13;
       channeled through financial intermediaries helping developed housing finance&#13;
       systems? Are there lessons on innovative approaches that helped develop housing&#13;
       finance systems?&#13;
&#13;
AUDIENCE&#13;
The main audience for this note will be World Bank staff and management in the Global&#13;
Practices of (i) Finance and Markets, (ii) Social, Urban, Agriculture, and Resilience, and (iii)&#13;
Macroeconomic and Fiscal Management, as well as IFC management and staff (investment&#13;
and advisory) who work on or take the lead in projects with housing finance components.&#13;
&#13;
Report Scope&#13;
In addition to conducting a qualitative assessment and contextual review of the evolution of&#13;
the program, IEG seeks to synthesize findings from Bank Group housing finance projects that&#13;
it evaluated between FY05 and FY15. The portfolio analysis suggests that 55 projects fit this&#13;
criteria (see table 1).&#13;
&#13;
A preliminary review of the IBRD portfolio for FY05â&#128;&#147;15 shows that some 40 operations (of&#13;
which 13 are currently active) have housing finance and related components, with $3 billion&#13;
in commitments primarily delivered through both adjustment and investment loans. There&#13;
were 55 analytical and advisory activities products delivered during FY05â&#128;&#147;15 in 29 countries,&#13;
comprising 32 that were nonlending technical assistance and 23 that were economic and sector&#13;
work. Based on the Bank Group reorganization, most of the World Bank projects of housing&#13;
finance are in two global practices; Finance and Market and Social, Urban, Rural and&#13;
Resilience.&#13;
&#13;
IFCâ&#128;&#153;s support to housing finance consists of IFC investments and IFC advisory projects&#13;
ranging from improved construction materials and technologies to supporting residential&#13;
developers and providing access to finance to end user finance mortgages through local&#13;
lenders. Between FY05 and FY15, IFCâ&#128;&#153;s housing finance investments consisted of 97&#13;
projects in 40 countries and a committed amount of $3 billion; 31 percent were supported&#13;
through primary mortgage institutions, 32 percent through commercial banking, 9 percent&#13;
through secondary mortgage institutions, and 28 percent through residential developers. This&#13;
represents only about 2 percent of total finance and insurance commitments. The majority of&#13;
the projects (37 percent) continue to be in Latin America and the Caribbean, though there are&#13;
also efforts in South Asia and Sub-Saharan African countries. IFC Advisory support to housing&#13;
finance is mainly through (i) capacity building for financial institutions aiming to improve&#13;
underwriting and origination standards, risk management, operational efficiency and&#13;
monitoring and outreach and market understanding, and (ii) improving the enabling&#13;
environment by creating or strengthening credit bureaus, valuation standards, and land reform.&#13;
&amp;#12;Between FY05 and FY15, IFC approved 69 advisory projects in 36 countries totaling $13.8&#13;
million.&#13;
&#13;
Table 1: Housing Finance Portfolio of Projects Approved FY01â&#128;&#147;15&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
EVIDENCE&#13;
&#13;
The evidence for this learning product will be generated by the following mixed methods:&#13;
&#13;
   ï&#130;·   Analysis of the data (ratings and rational) extracted from IEGâ&#128;&#153;s evaluation databases,&#13;
       to find correlations as appropriate.&#13;
   ï&#130;·   Qualitative review of evaluative evidence, including Implementation Completion and&#13;
       Results Report Reviews, Project Performance Assessment Reports, Expanded Project&#13;
       Supervision Reviews, and Project Completion Reports, through a distillation of&#13;
       findings from evaluative evidence on housing finance. The product will be based on&#13;
       the review a subset of World Bank and IFC projects. There are five selection criteria:&#13;
       region, institution, project type, size, and rating. All regions should be covered in the&#13;
       review. The review will include evaluated (rated) projects that reflect both Bank and&#13;
       IFC interventions. The project types include commercial banking (assisting&#13;
       commercial banks to start or expand housing finance), primary market institution&#13;
       creation and expansion, secondary mortgage market institutions (liquidity facility and&#13;
       securitization entity), construction and real estate market development, microfinance,&#13;
       and small business advisory and mortgage services.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                               6&#13;
&amp;#12;   ï&#130;·   A portfolio review of the World Bank Groupâ&#128;&#153;s lending operation with housing finance&#13;
       components and of IFCâ&#128;&#153;s interventions on housing finance (both investments and&#13;
       advisory), covering their evolution over time and their main areas of focus.&#13;
&#13;
Quality Assurance&#13;
Peer reviewers for the project are Kristin Hallberg (specialist in evaluation and private sector&#13;
and financial sector development) and Douglas B. Diamond (expert on housing finance,&#13;
specializing in housing issues in developing nations).&#13;
&#13;
Resources&#13;
This learning product is subject to the protocol laid out in IEGâ&#128;&#153;s Process Framework for&#13;
learning products. The timeline for this evaluation is thus:&#13;
&#13;
   ï&#130;·   Review of the Concept Note: December 22, 2015&#13;
   ï&#130;·   Drafting of the learning evaluation reportâ&#128;&#148;December 2015 â&#128;&#147; February 2016&#13;
   ï&#130;·   One Stop and peer review of the draft learning evaluation reportâ&#128;&#148;February 29, 2016&#13;
   ï&#130;·   Circulation to DGE, World Bank Group â&#128;&#148;March 10, 2016&#13;
   ï&#130;·   Final report to CODE â&#128;&#148; March 30, 2016&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The team will be led by Maria Elena Pinglo (IEGSP) and includes Mariano Cortes (formerly&#13;
IEGPS) and Michael Lea, a housing finance expert who will provide advice and undertake the&#13;
analysis of the IBRD/IFC interventions and contribute to the drafting of the report; a junior&#13;
staff/consultant will undertake the portfolio analysis of World Bank Group housing finance&#13;
operations.&#13;
&amp;#12;References&#13;
Hoek-Smit, Maria C. 2008. â&#128;&#156;Subsidizing Housing Finance for the Poor.â&#128;&#157; Wharton School, University of&#13;
       Pennsylvania, Philadelphia.&#13;
McKinsey Global Institute. 2014. â&#128;&#156;A Blueprint for Addressing the Global Affordable Housing Challenge.â&#128;&#157;&#13;
       Available at http://www.mckinsey.com/mgi.&#13;
World Bank. 2011. â&#128;&#156;Developing Kenyaâ&#128;&#153;s Mortgage Market.â&#128;&#157; Report No. 63391 -KE, World Bank, Washington,&#13;
       DC.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                     8&#13;
&amp;#12;</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="25798708">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2016/01/25798708/affordable-housing-finance-learning-product-concept-note
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2016/01/25798708/affordable-housing-finance-learning-product-concept-note</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2016/01/25798708/affordable-housing-finance-learning-product-concept-note</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2016-01-18T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2016-01-19T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <docm_id>090224b0840b1bcc</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b0840b1bcc</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/T_MNA/2016/01/18/090224b0840b1bcc/1_0/Rendered/INDEX/Affordable0hou0oduct000concept0note.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/T_MNA/2016/01/18/090224b0840b1bcc/1_0/Rendered/PDF/Affordable0hou0oduct000concept0note.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2015-12-15T05:10:03Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2016-01-19T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Affordable housing finance learning product
            : concept note
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            With this learning product on housing
            finance the Independent Evaluation Group (IEG) intends to
            generate new knowledge, insights, and lessons about the
            factors contributing to the success and failure in the
            International Bank for Reconstruction and Development and
            the International Finance Corporation’s (IFC) housing
            finance interventions. IEG will review interventions in the
            form of loans for the World Bank or investments and advisory
            services for IFC. World Bank technical assistance and
            knowledge products and interventions on housing finance
            matters will be considered when provided in the context of
            lending operations. In other words, stand-alone World Bank
            technical assistance interventions will not be a focus of
            this study, as such operations are not currently subject to
            IEG’s project-level evaluations.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Affordable housing finance learning product
            : concept note
        </docna>
        <display_title>Affordable housing finance
            learning product : concept note</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2015/12/25798708/affordable-housing-finance-learning-product-concept-note</listing_relative_url>
        <subtopic>Banks &amp; Banking Reform,Debt Markets,Access to Finance,Non Bank Financial Institutions,Housing &amp; Human Habitats</subtopic>
        <docty>Working Paper</docty>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Communities and Human Settlements</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Pinglo,Maria Elena</author>
            <author>Cortes,Mariano</author>
            <author>Lea,Michael J.</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>090224b0840b1bcc_1_0</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development,Communities and Human Settlements</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            advisory services, capital markets, land
            reform, urbanization, people, affordable housing finance,
            defaults, valuation, interest, institutional investors, life
            insurance, guarantees, finance companies, liquidity,
            services, housing, portfolio, mortgage, health,
            reorganization, capacity building, investment loans,
            projects, project, borrowers, tax, long-term investment,
            investor base, information systems, international bank,
            pension, creditor, instruments, enabling environment,
            assurance, small business, international finance, public
            policy, institutional investor, mortgages, technical
            assistance, housing finance, market development, capital
            gains, primary market, securitization, credit bureaus,
            portfolios, financial institutions, criteria, markets,
            business advisory, creditor rights, lenders, income levels,
            life insurance companies, loans, enterprises, commercial
            banking, equities, pension funds, subsidies, real estate,
            finance, long-term funding, infrastructure, banks, emerging
            markets, equity, investors, market segmentation,
            affordability, capital, policies, mortgage interest, housing
            affordability, future, public policies, access to finance,
            value, bank, secondary markets, credit, mortgage-backed
            securities, slum, peer review, credit information, property,
            investment vehicles, mortgage insurance, habitat, collateral
            regimes, market, long- term funding, equity investment,
            underwriting standards, securities, affordable housing,
            portfolio analysis, insurance, microfinance, human rights,
            slums, investor, land, investment, secondary mortgage
            market, risk, financial intermediaries, legal protection,
            commercial banks, credit information systems, international
            investor, households, balance sheets, collateral, poverty,
            underwriting, financial intermediary, investments, risk
            management, lending, valuation standards, interventions,
            insurance companies, women, outreach, local lenders,
            financial systems, governments, urban housing, urban
            population, mortgage market, financial sector development,
            backed securities, investment horizon
        </keywd>
        <owner>IEG Sustainable Development (IEGSD)</owner>
        <repnb>102634</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fragility, Conflict and Violence</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banks and Banking Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Banks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Retail Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets and Capital Flows</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance &amp; Risk Mitigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Inclusion Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shared Prosperity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy Conservation &amp; Efficiency</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy Conservation and Efficiency</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pensions &amp; Retirement Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance for Housing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Mortgages</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Checks on Executive Power</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen User Satisfaction Survey</ml:concept><ml:concept>Independent Commissions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ombudsmen</ml:concept><ml:concept>Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Parliament</ml:concept><ml:concept>Procurement Complaints Review Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supreme Audit Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Housing and Land</ml:concept><ml:concept>Housing and Planning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Housing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Land</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Land Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banks &amp; Banking Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Emerging Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commercial Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Policy Framework</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Housing Finance for the Poor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Intermediaries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Rights</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Markets</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Inclusion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Microfinance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inclusive Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy Efficiency</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pensions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Housing Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Accountability Mechanisms</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Land Supply and Markets</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>