<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>ï»¿The World Bank                                 1818 H Street N.W.      (202) 473-1000&#13;
INTERNATIONAL BANK FOR RECONSTRUCTION AND DEVELOPMENT  Washington, D.C. 20433  Cable Address: INTBAFRAD&#13;
INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPMENT ASSOCIATION         U.S.A.                  Cable Address: INDEVAS&#13;
OFFICIAL&#13;
DOCUMENTS&#13;
6c. /          , 2015&#13;
Ms. Diane Jacovella&#13;
Assistant Deputy Minister&#13;
Global Issues and Development Branch&#13;
Department of Foreign Affairs, Trade and Development&#13;
125 Sussex Drive&#13;
Ottawa, Ontario KI A 0G2&#13;
Canada&#13;
Administration Arrangement between the Government of Canada, as&#13;
represented by Minister for International Development, acting through the&#13;
Department of Foreign Affairs, Trade and Development and the International&#13;
Bank for Reconstruction and Development and the International Development&#13;
Association concerning the Multi-Donor Trust Fund for the Global Financing&#13;
Facility (GFF) in Support of Every Woman Every Child (TF No. TFO70955)&#13;
Dear Ms. Jacovella:&#13;
1.    We are pleased to acknowledge on behalf of the International Bank for Reconstruction&#13;
and Development ("IBRD") and the International Development Association ("IDA")&#13;
(collectively, the "Bank") that the Government of Canada, as represented by Minister for&#13;
International Development, acting through the Department of Foreign Affairs, Trade and&#13;
Development (the "Donor", and together with the Bank, the "Participants" and each a&#13;
"Participant") has decided to provide the sum of two hundred million Canadian Dollars&#13;
(CAD 200,000,000) (the "Contribution") for the Multi-Donor Trust Fund for the Global&#13;
Financing Facility (GFF) in Support of Every Woman Every Child (TF No. TF070955) (the&#13;
"Trust Fund") in accordance with the terms of this Administration Arrangement. Other donors&#13;
are also expected to contribute to the Trust Fund on the terms and conditions specified in the&#13;
Annexes to this Administration Arrangement.&#13;
2.     The Contribution will be used to finance the activities set forth in the "Multi-Donor Trust&#13;
Fund for the Global Financing Facility (GFF) in Support of Every Woman Every Child&#13;
Description" attached hereto as Annex 1, and will be administered by the Bank on behalf of the&#13;
Donor in accordance with the terms of this Administration Arrangement, including the "Standard&#13;
Provisions" attached hereto as Annex 2 and the provisions on "Framework for Cooperation"&#13;
attached hereto as Annex 3.&#13;
3.     The Donor will deposit the Contribution in accordance with the following schedule and&#13;
in the currency specified in Section I above ("Contribution Currency") into such bank account&#13;
designated by the Bank (each amount deposited hereinafter referred to as an "Installment") upon&#13;
submission of a payment request by the Bank:&#13;
(A) Promptly following countersignature of this Administration Arrangement: forty&#13;
million Canadian Dollars (CAD 40,000,000):&#13;
(From the Donor's fiscal year 2015/16);&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿-2-&#13;
(B)  By March 31, 2017, forty million Canadian Dollars (CAD 40,000,000):&#13;
(From the Donor's fiscal year 2016/17);&#13;
(C) By March 31, 2018, forty million Canadian Dollars (CAD 40,000,000):&#13;
(From the Donor's fiscal year 2017/18);&#13;
(D) By March 31, 2019, forty million Canadian Dollars (CAD 40,000,000):&#13;
(From the Donor's fiscal year 2018/19); and&#13;
(E)  By March 31, 2020, forty million Canadian Dollars (CAD 40,000,000):&#13;
(From the Donor's Fiscal year 2019/20).&#13;
4.     When making any deposit, the Donor will instruct its bank to include in its deposit details&#13;
information (remittance advice) field of its SWIFT deposit message, information indicating: the&#13;
amount deposited, that the deposit is made by the Donor for TF070955 (the Multi-Donor Trust&#13;
Fund for the Global Financing Facility (GFF) in Support of Every Woman Every Child), and the&#13;
date of the deposit (the "Deposit Instructions"). In addition, the Donor will provide a copy of the&#13;
Deposit Instructions to the Bank's Accounting Trust Funds Division by e-mail sent to&#13;
tfremitadvice@worldbank.org or by fax sent to +1 (202) 614-13 15.&#13;
5.    Immediately upon receipt of the Contribution funds, the Bank will convert such funds&#13;
into the Holding Currency at the exchange rate obtained by the Bank on the date of the conversion.&#13;
Where deposits prove to be insufficient to complete activities as a result of exchange rate&#13;
fluctuations, neither the Bank nor the Donor will bear any responsibility for providing any&#13;
additional financing.&#13;
6.     Except with respect to the Deposit Instructions, any notice, request or other&#13;
communication to be given or made under this Administration Arrangement will be in writing&#13;
and delivered by mail, fax or e-mail to the respective Participant's address specified below or at&#13;
such other address as such Participant notifies in writing to the other Participant from time to&#13;
time:&#13;
For the Bank (the "Bank Contact"):&#13;
Ms. Monique Vledder&#13;
Program Manager GFF&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
1818 H Street, NW&#13;
Washington, DC 20433 U.S.A.&#13;
Tel: 1 202 473 1000&#13;
Fax: 1 202 522 3234&#13;
Email: GFF@worldbank.org&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿-3-&#13;
For the Donor (the "Donor Contact"):&#13;
Ms. Amy Baker&#13;
Director General&#13;
Health and Nutrition Bureau&#13;
Global Issues and Development Branch&#13;
Department of Foreign Affairs, Trade and Development&#13;
200 Promenade du Portage&#13;
Gatineau, Quebec, KIA 0G4&#13;
Tel: 343-203-6241&#13;
Fax: 1 613 947 8405&#13;
E-mail: amy.baker@intemational.gc.ca&#13;
7.    In the event any amounts are to be returned to the Donor under this Administration&#13;
Arrangement, the Bank will transfer such amounts to the Donor's Balance Account, unless&#13;
otherwise agreed with the Bank.&#13;
8.     All annexes hereto constitute an integral part of this Administration Arrangement, whose&#13;
terms taken together will constitute the entire agreement and understanding between the Donor&#13;
and the Bank. Unless otherwise specified in an annex hereto, this Administration Arrangement&#13;
may be amended only by written amendment between the Bank and the Donor; provided,&#13;
however, that any annexes to this Administration Arrangement may be amended only by written&#13;
amendment of all donors contributing to the Trust Fund.&#13;
9.     No member of the House of Commons of Canada will be admitted to any share or part of&#13;
this Administration Arrangement or to any benefit arising therefrom.&#13;
10.    No current or former public office holder or public servant of the Government of Canada&#13;
who is not in compliance with the Conflict of Interest and Post-Employment Code for Public&#13;
Office Holders or the Values and Ethics Code for the Public Service will derive a direct benefit&#13;
from this Administration Arrangement.&#13;
I.    Any transfer into the Trust Fund to be made under this Administration Arrangement is&#13;
subject to there being an appropriation by the Parliament of Canada for the fiscal year in which&#13;
such transfer is to be made. If Donor's appropriation is changed by the Parliament of Canada, the&#13;
Donor may reduce the Contribution, or terminate this Administration Arrangement.&#13;
12.    No offer, gift or payment, consideration or benefit of any kind, which constitutes an&#13;
illegal or corrupt practice, has or will be made to anyone, either directly or indirectly, as an&#13;
inducement or reward for the award or execution of this Administration Arrangement. Any such&#13;
practice will be grounds for terminating this Administration Arrangement or taking any other&#13;
corrective action as required.&#13;
13.   It is understood that this Administration Arrangement, including any annexes, is not an&#13;
international treaty. It is an administrative arrangement between the Bank and the Donor. All&#13;
references made in the Annexes to and: (i) "shall" and "Administration Agreement or&#13;
Administration Agreements", will have the same meaning as the term "will" and "Administration&#13;
Arrangement" herein; and (ii) "Parties", will have the same meaning as the term "Participants"&#13;
herein.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿-4-&#13;
14.    Where appropriate, the Bank: (i) will acknowledge the Donor's funding of the Trust Fund&#13;
in its publications, speeches, press release or other similar matters produced in connection with&#13;
the Trust Fund, all subject to its applicable policies and procedures; and (ii). will supply the Donor&#13;
with a copy of any such written or electronic material.&#13;
15.    The Donors and the Bank will use their best efforts to amicably settle any dispute,&#13;
controversy, or claim arising out of or relating to the Administration Arrangement.&#13;
16.    Each of the undersigned represents, by confirming its acceptance below, that it is&#13;
authorized to enter into this Administration Arrangement and act in accordance with its&#13;
provisions. The Bank and the Donor are each requested to sign and date this Administration&#13;
Arrangement, and upon possession by the Bank of this fully signed Administration Arrangement,&#13;
this Administration Arrangement will become carried out as of the date of the last signature.&#13;
Sincerely,&#13;
INTERNATIONAL BANK FOR RECONSTRUCTION AND DEVELOPMENT&#13;
INTERNATIONAL       EE    OPMENT ASSOCIATION&#13;
Timothy Grant Evans&#13;
Senior Director&#13;
HNP Global Practice&#13;
CONFIRMED AND AGREED:&#13;
GOVERNMENT OF CANADA, AS REPRESENTED BY MINISTER FOR&#13;
INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPMENT, ACTING THROUGH THE&#13;
DEPARTMENT OF FOREIGN AFFAIRS, TRADE AND DEVELOPMENT&#13;
By: I      cL                             DateTD&amp; c( &#13;
iane Jacovel&#13;
Assistant Deputy Minister&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿-5-&#13;
ANNEX I&#13;
Description of Activities and Expenditures under the Multi-Donor Trust Fund for&#13;
the Global Financing Facility (GFF) in Support of Every Woman Every Child&#13;
1.     Overview&#13;
This Trust Fund's goal is to contribute to the global efforts to end preventable maternal, newborn,&#13;
child and adolescent deaths, and improve the health and quality of life of women, adolescents&#13;
and children through mobilizing and channeling additional international aid and domestic&#13;
resources required to scale up and sustain efficient and equitable delivery of quality reproductive,&#13;
maternal, newborn, child and adolescent health (RMNCAH) services.&#13;
2.     Program Description&#13;
The Program to be funded by this Trust Fund is expected to cover a period of time up until 2022&#13;
and will support smart, scaled and sustainable financing mechanisms designed to achieve and&#13;
measure RMNCAH results.&#13;
The Trust Fund overall objective is to support results-focused financing for achieving RMNCAH&#13;
results, including the systems - particularly civil registration and vital statistics - needed to&#13;
monitor progress and measure results. The Trust Fund will finance activities to ensure access to&#13;
basic health services using a variety of mechanisms, including results-based financing (RBF).&#13;
Such mechanisms may include performance-based payments for health service delivery,&#13;
capitation payments and other forms of cash transfers to beneficiaries to facilitate their access to&#13;
such services, etc. Their use will be determined on a case by case basis in accordance with the&#13;
particular design of the project and the capacity of the Recipient countries. To that end,&#13;
Recipients of grants may need to develop "unit costs" associated with the packages of health&#13;
services to be provided, in order to facilitate disbursements.&#13;
Each country will develop an "Investment Case" and a health financing strategy to support the&#13;
achievement of the RMNCAH goals. The Investment Case will include activities to improve&#13;
RMNCAH, using a variety of mechanisms, including RBF, as well as building the necessary&#13;
multi-sectoral civil registration and vital statistics (CRVS) systems to record and track essential&#13;
data. A special emphasis will be given to countries to develop longer-term financial strategies&#13;
to increase the sustainability of RMNCAH financing and the Global Public Goods knowledge.&#13;
The specific aims of the Trust Fund are:&#13;
(i)   to support financing of comprehensive country RMNCAH investment plans;&#13;
(ii)  to support countries in the transition toward sustainable domestic financing for&#13;
RMNCAH;&#13;
(iii)  to finance the strengthening of civil registration and vital statistics systems;&#13;
(iv)   to contribute to a better-coordinated and streamlined RMNCAH financing&#13;
architecture;&#13;
(v)    to support design, implementation and evaluation of GFF mechanisms;&#13;
(vi)   to develop and disseminate the evidence base for implementing successful GFF&#13;
mechanisms;&#13;
(vii)  to build country institutional capacity to scale-up and sustain the GFF&#13;
mechanisms, within the national health strategy and system; and&#13;
(viii) to attract additional funding to the health sector;&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿-6-&#13;
3.     Activities to be Financed&#13;
Activities to be financed are set out below. Allocation levels included below are indicative only,&#13;
and are subject to change as the overall Program progresses.&#13;
Activity 1:  GFF Preparation&#13;
Activity 1 (a): RMNCAH Investment Case Grants (Bank and Recipient)&#13;
Up to $500,000 will be made available for the preparation of the GFF Investment Case and&#13;
feasibility studies, which will, inter alia, outline the desired health outcomes, the target&#13;
RMNCAH outputs, the most cost-effective health interventions to achieve these outputs, and&#13;
support rigorous analysis of data and robust resource mapping, as well as inclusive stakeholder&#13;
consultations to identify and prioritize the interventions that set a country on a course to achieving&#13;
its long-term RMNCAH targets.&#13;
Activity 1 (b): GFF Seed Grants (Bank and Recipient)&#13;
Seed funds between US$50,000 to US$200,000 may be provided to Recipients or Bank teams to&#13;
commission studies, hire consultants, and support other activities to assess the value and&#13;
feasibility of GFF mechanisms for a country.&#13;
Activity 2:  Design of GFF Projects or Project Components (Recipient)&#13;
Preparation funds up to US$500,000 will be provided to Recipients to design and implement&#13;
a GFF project or project component in accordance with standard Bank fiduciary and&#13;
safeguard requirements. These funds may be used by Recipients to commission studies, hire&#13;
consultants, and support other costs associated with the design of the GFF project or project&#13;
component.&#13;
Activity 3:  Preparation and Appraisal of GFF Projects or Project Components&#13;
(Bank)&#13;
Funds up to US$350,000 will be provided to Bank teams to support preparation and appraisal&#13;
of a GFF project or project component, ensuring linkages and integration of the Bank-&#13;
financed project or project component with the Investment Case. Project appraisal is a stage&#13;
in the project cycle which follows completion of project preparation, the final process by&#13;
which the Bank determines the suitability of a project for Bank financing. It provides a&#13;
comprehensive review of all aspects of the project, lays the foundation for its implementation&#13;
after it has been approved for Bank financing, and for evaluation when completed.&#13;
Activity 4:  Implementation&#13;
Activity 4 (a): Implementation of Bank GFF Projects or Project Components&#13;
(Recipient)&#13;
Overall responsibility for implementation lies with the Recipient country.&#13;
Grants will be made available to Recipients for implementation. Grant Agreements will be&#13;
signed between the Bank and the Recipients to reflect the funding amount and conditions of&#13;
funds release based on the specific design of the project or project component. It is expected&#13;
that Recipient countries will require significant support (e.g., technical assistance) to design&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿-7-&#13;
and strengthen systems to achieve improved results and implement the GFF projects or&#13;
project components. A key issue is the independent validation of data related to incentives.&#13;
Such data should be based on population surveys or other methods that independently verify&#13;
services and results, particularly civil registration and vital statistics (CRVS) systems.&#13;
Development Policy Financing (DPFs) (Recipient)&#13;
Grants to support Recipient country reforms through non-earmarked general budget&#13;
financing (known in the Bank as development policy financing (DPF) will also be financed&#13;
by this Trust Fund under this Activity 4. These Grants will be subject to the Recipient's own&#13;
implementation processes and systems.&#13;
The DPF should be supportive of programs of policy and institutional actions in the health&#13;
sector which create an enabling environment to move from a system of health delivery that&#13;
finances inputs to a system that finances and carefully monitors results in health outputs.&#13;
DPFs are governed by the Bank's Operational Policy/Bank Procedure (OP/BP 8.60) and their&#13;
use is determined by the respective Country Partnership Framework.&#13;
Progress in program implementation and its outcomes are monitored by the Recipient country&#13;
and the Bank throughout the implementation phase to obtain data to evaluate and measure the&#13;
ultimate effectiveness of the operation in terms of results.&#13;
Activity 4b:  Implementation  of Recipient-executed  GFF  Projects or Project&#13;
Components (Recipient)&#13;
Stand-alone grants will be made to different Recipients (member countries, NGOs, Regional&#13;
Banks, etc.) for implementation of GFF projects or project components. NGOs can be grant&#13;
Recipients with the consent of the Recipient Government. Grant Agreements will be&#13;
prepared between the Bank and these Recipients to reflect the funding amount and conditions&#13;
of funds release based on the specific design of the GFF project or project component.&#13;
Similar validation of data related to incentives, as described in Activity 4a, will be required.&#13;
The Bank will have an operational role for these Grants, including appraisal and supervision&#13;
of funded activities. The Grants' execution will be subject to Bank's policies, rules, and&#13;
procedures.&#13;
Activity 5:  Supervision of Bank and Recipient-executed GFF Projects and Project&#13;
Components (Bank)&#13;
Bank teams will supervise the GFF project or project component following standard Bank&#13;
procedures. Supervision should, as much as possible, be carried out in close collaboration&#13;
with partners, and aligned with national health sector reviews where possible.&#13;
Activity 6:  Monitoring and Documentation of Bank and Recipient-executed GFF&#13;
Projects and Project Components (Bank)&#13;
Bank teams will monitor experiences in designing and implementing the GFF project or project&#13;
component as well as the Bank operational experience in preparing and appraising the GFF&#13;
project or project component. Such monitoring aims to identify operational and other issues,&#13;
which can be addressed by corrective actions. In addition, monitoring can contribute to the&#13;
learning of lessons on why GFF projects or project components may or may not achieve their&#13;
objectives.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿-8-&#13;
Activity 7:  Knowledge and Learning (Bank)&#13;
Activity 7 (a): Evaluation of Bank and GFF Recipient-executed Projects and Project&#13;
Components&#13;
The Bank will evaluate the results of the GFF projects or project components financed by this&#13;
Trust Fund. The evaluations will be designed to answer the question of whether the GFF project&#13;
or project component was associated with or led to the achievement of results in each project site.&#13;
Activity 7 (b): Strengthening the Knowledge Base&#13;
The Bank will allocate on competitive basis grants for operational research and evaluation which&#13;
will be aimed at assessing the impact of RMNCAH and health financing interventions.&#13;
Activity 7 (c): Development of Global Public Goods&#13;
The Bank will develop and deploy Global Public Goods (GPGs) in order to accelerate the&#13;
affordability and accessibility of RMNCAH services.&#13;
Activity 8:  Dissemination and Knowledge Sharing (Bank)&#13;
GFF experiences and lessons learned will be shared through the GFF website supported by the&#13;
Trust Fund, and through meetings, country dialogue, workshops, and case studies.&#13;
Activity 9:  Trust Fund Management and Administration (Bank)&#13;
A team of Bank staff and reporting to Bank management, headed by a designated Program&#13;
Manager, will support the management and administration of the Trust Fund. The Trust Fund&#13;
will finance activities of the Bank team related to the organization of the Annual Consultation&#13;
meetings and any other additional coordination with Donors and partners, oversight of the&#13;
overall Program, coordination with country-specific Task Team Leaders, development and&#13;
consolidation of annual and semi-annual reports to Donors, etc.&#13;
Other Activities:   Buy-downs and Buy-ups (Recipient)&#13;
The possibility of using instruments such as buy-downs and buy-ups will also be considered.&#13;
Buy-downs involve the provision by Donors of committed funding to 'buy-down', or pay for&#13;
all, or part of a Bank loan/credit on behalf of the government, once results are achieved. Buy-&#13;
ups support IDA countries that receive grant financing, whereby additional Donor financing&#13;
is provided based on results. Trust Fund Donors will receive from the Bank a proposal&#13;
covering the rationale for buy-downs and buy-ups, and other approaches that can leverage&#13;
additional resources and incentivize performance for the national health sector. No more&#13;
than two-fifths of new contributions to the Trust Fund (post November 2009) may be used&#13;
for buy-downs and buy-ups.&#13;
4.     Categories of Expenditure&#13;
For Bank-executed activities: Contribution funds will be used to finance the following&#13;
categories of expenditure: Staff Costs (salaries, benefits, and indirects), Extended Term&#13;
Consultants, Consultants Fees, Contractual Services, Travel Expenses, Media and&#13;
Workshops/Conferences/Meetings, Associated Overheads, and Temporary Staff Costs.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿-9-&#13;
For Recipient-executed activities: at the Bank's discretion, funds may be allocated for&#13;
the purpose of financing either:&#13;
(i)    Standard Grants with specific activities and allowable expenses pre-&#13;
determined, in which case, Contribution funds may be used to finance Services,&#13;
Goods, Works and Incremental Operating Costs; or&#13;
(ii)   Recipient country reforms through non-earmarked general budget financing, in&#13;
which case, Contribution funds may be used for any general budgetary needs.&#13;
For purposes of this Agreement:&#13;
"Incremental Operating Costs" means incremental expenses incurred on account of&#13;
project implementation and management, including the operation and maintenance of&#13;
vehicles, office supplies, communication charges, insurance costs, office administration&#13;
costs, banking charges, utility charges, rental charges, domestic/international travel and&#13;
per diem allowance.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿-10-&#13;
ANNEX 2&#13;
Standard Provisions Applicable to the Multi-Donor Trust Fund for the Global&#13;
Financing Facility (GFF) in Support of Every Woman Every Child&#13;
The following provisions (hereinafter referred to as the "Standard Provisions") shall be&#13;
applicable to and form an integral part of all agreements entered into between the&#13;
International Bank for Reconstruction and Development ("IBRD") and the International&#13;
Development Association ("IDA") (collectively, the "Bank") and donor countries and/or&#13;
organizations (hereinafter referred to as the "Donors") that provide grants (referred to as the&#13;
"Contributions") to be administered by the Bank for the Multi-Donor Trust Fund for the Global&#13;
Financing Facility (GFF) in Support of Every Woman Every Child (the "Program").&#13;
1.     Administration of the Contributions&#13;
1.1.  The Bank shall be responsible only for performing those functions specifically set forth&#13;
in this Agreement and shall not be subject to any other duties or responsibilities to the Donors,&#13;
including, without limitation, any duties or obligations that might otherwise apply to a fiduciary&#13;
or trustee under general principles of trust or fiduciary law. Nothing in this Agreement shall be&#13;
considered a waiver of any privileges or immunities of the IBRD and IDA under their Articles&#13;
of Agreement or any applicable law, all of which are expressly reserved.&#13;
1.2.  The Contribution shall be administered in accordance with the Bank's applicable&#13;
policies and procedures, as the same may be amended from time to time, including its&#13;
framework to prevent and combat fraud and corruption and its screening procedures to prevent&#13;
the use of Bank resources to finance terrorist activity, in line with the Bank's obligations to&#13;
give effect to the relevant decisions of the Security Council, taken under Chapter VII of the of&#13;
Charter of the United Nations. The Donor acknowledges that this provision does not create any&#13;
obligations of the Bank under the anti-terrorist financing and asset control laws, regulations,&#13;
rules and executive orders of an individual member country that may apply to the Donor, nor&#13;
shall it be deemed a waiver, express or implied, of any of the privileges and immunities of the&#13;
Bank.&#13;
2.     Commingling, Exchange and Investment of the Contributions&#13;
2.1.   The Contributions shall be accounted for as a single trust fund and shall be kept separate&#13;
and apart from the funds of the Bank. The Contributions may be commingled with other trust&#13;
fund assets maintained by the Bank.&#13;
2.2.   The Contributions may be freely exchanged by the Bank into other currencies as may&#13;
facilitate their disbursement.&#13;
2.3.   The Bank shall invest and reinvest the Contributions pending their disbursement in&#13;
accordance with the Bank's policies and procedures for the investment of trust funds administered&#13;
by the Bank.  The Bank shall credit all income from such investment to the Trust Fund&#13;
established under this Agreement to be used for the same purposes as the Contributions.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿-11-&#13;
3.     Administrative Cost Recovery&#13;
3.1    In order to assist in the defrayment of the costs of administration and other expenses&#13;
incurred by the Bank under this Agreement the Bank may, following deposit of the&#13;
Contributions, deduct from such funds and retain for the Bank's own account an amount equal&#13;
to 0.83% of the Contributions. In addition, the Bank shall charge actual administration costs&#13;
up to a maximum of 0.17% of the Contributions.&#13;
4.     Grants to Recipients&#13;
4.1.   The Bank shall, as administrator of the Trust Fund on behalf of the Donors, enter into&#13;
grant agreements (the "Grant Agreements") with eligible recipients (the "Recipients") consistent&#13;
with the purposes of this Agreement and on the terms and conditions set forth in the Grant&#13;
Agreements. Grant Agreements shall be entered into up to the maximum amount of the&#13;
Contributions that all Donors have agreed to make available under the Administration&#13;
Agreements/Arrangements between the Bank and the Donors. Upon request by a Donor, the&#13;
Bank shall furnish a copy of the Grant Agreements to the Donors.&#13;
4.2.   The Bank shall be solely responsible for the supervision of activities financed under the&#13;
Grant Agreements. Subject to the consent of the Recipients, representatives of the Donors may&#13;
be invited by the Bank to participate in Bank supervision missions related to the Trust Fund.&#13;
4.3.   The Bank shall promptly inform the Donors of any significant modification to the terms&#13;
of any Grant Agreements and of any contractual remedies that are exercised by the Bank under&#13;
any Grant Agreements. To the extent practicable, the Bank shall afford the Donors the&#13;
opportunity to exchange views before effecting any such modification or exercising any such&#13;
remedy.&#13;
5.     Procurement&#13;
5.1.   For Recipient-executed activities, the Grant Agreements shall provide that the&#13;
Contributions shall be used by the Recipients to finance expenditures for goods and services, as&#13;
the case may be, in accordance with the Bank's Guidelines on "Procurement under IBRD Loans&#13;
and IDA Credits" and the Bank's Guidelines on the "Selection and Employment of Consultants&#13;
by World Bank Borrowers," as in effect at the date of entry into the respective Grant Agreements.&#13;
5.2.   For Bank-executed activities, the employment and supervision of any consultants and&#13;
the procurement of any goods financed by the Contributions shall be the responsibility of the&#13;
Bank and shall be carried out in accordance with its applicable policies and procedures.&#13;
5.3.   Donors shall not be responsible for the activities of any person or third party engaged by&#13;
the Bank as a result of this Administration Agreement, nor shall donors be liable for any costs&#13;
incurred by the Bank in terminating the engagement of any such person.&#13;
6.     Accounting and Financial Reporting&#13;
6.1.   The Bank shall maintain separate records and ledger accounts in respect of the&#13;
Contributions deposited in the trust fund account and disbursements made therefrom.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿-12-&#13;
6.2.   The Bank shall furnish to the Donors current financial information relating to receipts,&#13;
disbursements and fund balance in United States dollars with respect to the Contributions via the&#13;
World Bank's Trust Funds Donor Center secure website. Within six (6) months after all&#13;
commitments and liabilities under the Trust Fund have been satisfied and the Trust Fund has&#13;
been closed, the final financial information relating to receipts, disbursements and fund balance&#13;
in United States dollars with respect to the Contributions shall be made available to the Donors&#13;
via the World Bank's Trust Funds Donor Center secure website.&#13;
6.3.   The Bank shall provide to the Donors, within six (6) months following the end of each&#13;
Bank fiscal year, an annual single audit report, comprising (1) a management assertion together&#13;
with an attestation from the Bank's external auditors concerning the adequacy of internal control&#13;
over cash-based financial reporting for all cash-based trust funds as a whole; and (2) a combined&#13;
financial statement for all cash-based trust funds together with the Bank's external auditor's&#13;
opinion thereon. The cost of the single audit shall be borne by the Bank.&#13;
6.4.   If a Donor wishes to request, on an exceptional basis, a financial statement audit by the&#13;
Bank's external auditors of the trust fund established under this Agreement, the Donor and the&#13;
Bank shall first consult as to whether such an external audit is necessary. The Bank and the Donor&#13;
shall agree on the most appropriate scope and terms of reference of such audit. Following&#13;
agreement on the scope and terms of reference, the Bank shall arrange for such external audit.&#13;
The costs of any such audit, including the internal costs of the Bank with respect to such audit,&#13;
shall be paid by the Donor.&#13;
6.5.   The Bank shall also provide the Donors with copies of all financial statements and&#13;
auditors' reports received by the Bank from the Recipients pursuant to the Grant Agreements.&#13;
7.     Progress Reporting&#13;
7.1.   The Bank shall provide the Donors with annual progress reports by September 15th of&#13;
each calendar year. The progress reports shall be provided with reference to the results&#13;
framework agreed by the Bank and the Donors, as such results framework may be reviewed by&#13;
the Parties from time to time. Within six (6) months after the End Disbursement Date (as defined&#13;
below), the Bank shall provide to the Donors with a final progress report for the Trust Fund.&#13;
7.2.   Any Donor may review or evaluate activities financed by the Trust Fund. The Donor and&#13;
the Bank shall agree on the scope and conduct of such review or evaluation, and the Bank shall&#13;
provide all relevant information within the limits of its policies and procedures. All associated&#13;
costs shall be borne by the Donor. It is understood that any such review or evaluation shall not&#13;
constitute a financial, compliance or other audit of the Trust Fund.&#13;
8.     Disbursement Deadline; Cancellation; Refund&#13;
8.1.   It is expected that the Contributions shall be fully disbursed by the Bank in accordance&#13;
with the provisions of this Agreement by June 30, 2022. The Bank shall only disburse&#13;
Contributions for the purposes of this Agreement after such date with the written approval of the&#13;
Donors.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿-13-&#13;
8.2.   Any Donor or the Bank may, upon three (3) months' prior written notice, cancel all or&#13;
part of the Donor's pro rata share of any remaining balance of the Contribution funds that is not&#13;
committed pursuant to any agreements entered into between the Bank and any consultants and/or&#13;
other third parties for the purposes of this Agreement prior to the receipt of such notice, including&#13;
the Grant Agreements.&#13;
8.3.   Following the final disbursement date specified in paragraph 8.1, the Bank shall return&#13;
any remaining balance of the Contributions to the relevant Donor Balance Account on a pro rata&#13;
basis based on the Donors' paid Contributions. In the event of a cancellation the Bank shall&#13;
promptly return to the relevant Donor Balance Account the Donor's pro rata share of&#13;
uncommitted Contributions in accordance with paragraph 8.2.&#13;
9.     Disclosure&#13;
The Bank may disclose this Agreement and information on this Trust Fund in&#13;
accordance with the Bank's policy on disclosure of information, in effect at the time of such&#13;
disclosure. By entering into this Agreement, Donors consent to disclosure of this Agreement&#13;
and information on this Trust Fund."&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿-14-&#13;
ANNEX 3&#13;
Framework for Cooperation for the Multi-Donor Trust Fund for&#13;
the Global Financing Facility (GFF) in Support of Every Woman Every Child&#13;
1.     Country and Project Selection&#13;
Criteria set out in the Business Plan of the GFF endorsed by the Bank and the Trust Fund Donors&#13;
will be used to identify countries to be supported through the Trust Fund. After countries have&#13;
been identified in consultation with Donors, the Bank will work with countries and other eligible&#13;
recipients to design GFF projects or project components and make the final decisions in the&#13;
allocation of funds.&#13;
2.     Project Preparation, Appraisal and Supervision&#13;
The Donors will rely upon the Bank's rules and procedures for project preparation, appraisal and&#13;
supervision.&#13;
2.1.   Sr. Director, World Bank Health Nutrition and Population Global Practice&#13;
(HNP GP): the oversight of the Program will be the responsibility of the Sr. Director of HNP&#13;
GP.&#13;
2.2.   Trust Fund Program Management: day-to-day management of the overall Trust Fund&#13;
will be the responsibility of the GFF Program Manager, who will lead the GFF Secretariat located&#13;
in Washington, DC, at the Bank's headquarters. The Secretariat is comprised of staff employed&#13;
by the Bank and secondments from participating organizations. The Secretariat operates under&#13;
Bank's management and applicable Bank's policies and procedures and is also accountable to&#13;
the GFF Trust Fund Committee and the GFF Investors Group.&#13;
2.3.   GFF Project or Project Component -- Task Team Leader: each of the GFF&#13;
projects or project components will be managed by a TTL, who will be responsible for&#13;
appraisal and supervision of the respective GFF project or project component, as described&#13;
in paragraph 3.3 of the Annex 1.&#13;
2.4.   Recipients: the Recipients will be responsible for designing and implementing the&#13;
GFF project or project component. Support from the Trust Fund for GFF projects or project&#13;
components will be reviewed and, where possible, incorporated into the Medium Term&#13;
Expenditure Framework to help ensure sustainability. As in all Bank projects, the Recipients&#13;
will be expected to coordinate the effort with all relevant development actors.&#13;
3.     Coordination with Donors&#13;
3.1.   Annual Consultation Meeting: representatives from the Donors, organized as the&#13;
Trust Fund Committee, and the Bank will meet at least once a year after submission of the&#13;
annual report. The role of the Trust Fund Committee is to ensure that the GFF Trust Fund&#13;
mobilizes and uses its resources in a way that optimally supports the mission of the GFF. The&#13;
Trust Fund Committee will be composed of all original and subsequent contributing Donors to&#13;
the Trust Fund.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
ï»¿-15-&#13;
3.2    Key subjects to be discussed during the annual consultations include key achievements&#13;
throughout the year, identification of any issues, and proposed mitigation, which may affect&#13;
program effectiveness; a qualitative assessment of progress against the indicators at the country&#13;
level set forth in the GFF results framework and referred to in paragraph 7.1 of Annex 2 to this&#13;
Agreement and based on available information generated by the GFF projects or project&#13;
components (e.g., verification mechanisms, impact evaluations) and in particular:&#13;
* Assessment of the Trust Fund performance and budget execution.&#13;
* Strategic directions for the Trust Fund and the proposed annual work plan.&#13;
* Preliminary annual allocations for the Trust Fund.&#13;
* Review and assessment of criteria used to identify countries for support under the Trust&#13;
Fund.&#13;
3.3    The results of the meeting will be recorded in Agreed Minutes. The Agreed Minutes will&#13;
be drafted by the Bank and sent to all Donors for their approval/comments within two weeks&#13;
after the meeting. The Donors will inform the Bank of their approval/comments within seven&#13;
days of receipt of the draft, after which the final draft will be provided by the Bank for record&#13;
keeping.&#13;
3.4    Additional consultation meetings may be requested by the Bank and/or a/the Donor(s).&#13;
3.5    GFF Investors Group: a GFF Investors Group brings together key investors in the&#13;
global RMNCAH agenda with the purpose to mobilize institutional support and expertise at the&#13;
global level in order to optimally support efficient collective action at the country level. The&#13;
Investors Group will meet at least once a year and will also provide a platform for continuous&#13;
dialogue to increase transparency, mutual learning and accountability amongst the institutions&#13;
with significant investments in RMNCAH, including the Bank and the Donors of the GFF Trust&#13;
Fund.&#13;
4.     Independent External Evaluation of the Trust Fund: Implementing appropriate&#13;
systems to review project operations and progress against the objectives of the Trust Fund&#13;
will be important. The Donors will finance and carry out independent external evaluations&#13;
of the Trust Fund, to take place in 2016 with a final evaluation in 2022. The evaluations will&#13;
be undertaken by the Donors in accordance with section 7.2 of Annex 2 of this Agreement&#13;
and based on Terms of Reference developed by the Donors at least one year prior, and agreed&#13;
with the Bank.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="25801634">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2015/12/25801634/official-documents--administration-arrangement-government-canada-contribution-tf0709055
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2015/12/25801634/official-documents--administration-arrangement-government-canada-contribution-tf0709055</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2015/12/25801634/official-documents--administration-arrangement-government-canada-contribution-tf0709055</new_url>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2016-01-29T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <docm_id>090224b0840c345d</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b0840c345d</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/HDN/2016/01/19/090224b0840c345d/1_0/Rendered/INDEX/Official0Docum0ibution0to0TF0709055.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/HDN/2016/01/19/090224b0840c345d/1_0/Rendered/PDF/Official0Docum0ibution0to0TF0709055.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2015-12-14T10:05:34Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2016-01-19T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docna>
            Official Documents- Administration
            Arrangement with the Government of Canada for Contribution
            to TF0709055
        </docna>
        <display_title>Official Documents-
            Administration Arrangement with the Government of Canada for
            Contribution to TF0709055</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/2015/12/25801634/official-documents--administration-arrangement-government-canada-contribution-tf0709055</listing_relative_url>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <docty>Trust Fund Administrative Agreement</docty>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Pardinas Ocana,Claudia M.</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>HQBOCS</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <owner>Health, Nutrition &amp; Popultn Team (HDNHE)</owner>
        <trustfund>TF070955-Multi-Donor Trust Fund for the
            Global Financing Facility (GFF) in Suppo</trustfund>
        <lang>English</lang>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Arts and Culture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Contracting Mechanism</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pay for Performance (P4P)</ml:concept><ml:concept>RBF</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capitation Payments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Youth Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Impact Evaluations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Randomized Control Trials</ml:concept><ml:concept>Bank Supervision</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance &amp; Risk Mitigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition – Community Based Interventions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition – Raising Awareness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition – Training</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Remittances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Migration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Contract Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Arrangements in Public Procurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Capacity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legal Regulatory Framework</ml:concept><ml:concept>State-Society Relations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Checks on Executive Power</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen User Satisfaction Survey</ml:concept><ml:concept>Independent Commissions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ombudsmen</ml:concept><ml:concept>Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Parliament</ml:concept><ml:concept>Procurement Complaints Review Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supreme Audit Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Foreign Direct Investments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Linkages</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Media</ml:concept><ml:concept>Treaties</ml:concept><ml:concept>Privileges and Immunities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Disclosure of Information</ml:concept><ml:concept>Results-Based Financing for Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capitation in Health Care</ml:concept><ml:concept>Adolescent Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Cash Transfers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Policy Financing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Impact Assessment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>External Audit</ml:concept><ml:concept>Bank Regulation and Supervision</ml:concept><ml:concept>Insurance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nutrition</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Movement of Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Accountability Mechanisms</ml:concept><ml:concept>FDI Spillovers</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>