<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>﻿OFFICIAL                 '&#13;
DOCUMENTS&#13;
Administration Agreement between the European Commission and the International Bank for&#13;
Reconstruction and Development and the International Development Association concerning the&#13;
Liberia Integrated Public Financial Management Reform Single-Donor Trust Fund (No. TFO72467)&#13;
This Administration Agreement is concluded under Indirect Management in the context of the Framework&#13;
Agreement between the World Bank Group and the European Commission which sets the general&#13;
conditions for this Administration Agreement. The Framework Agreement shall be applicable and form an&#13;
integral part of this Administration Agreement for the Trust Fund.&#13;
1.    The International Bank for Reconstruction and Development and the International Development&#13;
Association (collectively, the "Bank") acknowledges that the European Commission (the "Donor", and&#13;
together with the Bank, the "Parties" and each a "Party") agrees to provide the sum of two million six&#13;
hundred ninety thousand Euros (EUR 2,690,000) (the "Contribution") for the Liberia Integrated Public&#13;
Financial Management Reform Single-Donor Trust Fund, No. TF072467 (the "Trust Fund") in accordance&#13;
with the terms of this Administration Agreement.&#13;
The estimated total budget of the Trust Fund is two million six hundred ninety thousand Euros. The&#13;
indicative budget set out in Annex 5 shall be used for monitoring purpose only and shall not be binding.&#13;
2.     The Contribution shall be used to finance the activities set forth in the "Liberia Integrated Public&#13;
Financial Management Reform Single-Donor Trust Fund Description" attached hereto as Annex 1, and&#13;
shall be administered by the Bank on behalf of the Donor in accordance with the terms of this&#13;
Administration Agreement, including the "Standard Provisions" attached hereto as Annex 2 and&#13;
"Governance" attached hereto as Annex 3.&#13;
Expected results of the Trust Fund and corresponding indicators (including baselines, result goals and&#13;
sources of data) are set out in Annex 4.&#13;
The Implementation period shall start on the date following that on which the last of the two parties signs.&#13;
3.     The Donor shall deposit the Contribution in accordance with the following schedule and in the&#13;
currency specified in Section I above ("Contribution Currency") into such bank account designated by the&#13;
Bank (each amount deposited hereinafter referred to as an "Instalment") upon submission of a payment&#13;
request by the Bank:&#13;
(A)   Promptly following countersignature - Euro 2,421,000&#13;
(B)    Euro 269,000 subject to the disbursement of 70% of the preceding instalment.&#13;
The payment period of the balance shall be 60 days.&#13;
4.     When making any deposit, the Donor shall instruct its bank to include in its deposit details&#13;
information (remittance advice) field of its SWIFT deposit message, information indicating: the amount&#13;
deposited, that the deposit is made by the Donor for TF072467 Liberia Integrated Public Financial&#13;
Management Reform Single-Donor Trust Fund, the Commission internal reference number and the date of&#13;
the Administration Agreement, the name of the project for which the funds are intended, the name of the&#13;
Commission department responsible for the Trust Fund and the date of the deposit (the "Deposit&#13;
Instructions"). In addition, the Donor shall provide a copy of the Deposit Instructions to the Bank's&#13;
-1 -&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿Accounting Trust Funds Division by e-mail sent to tfremitadvice@worldbank.org or by fax sent to +1 (202)&#13;
614-1315.&#13;
5.     Except with respect to the Deposit Instructions, any notice, request or other communication to be&#13;
given or made under this Administration Agreement shall be in writing and delivered by mail, fax or e-mail&#13;
to the respective Party's address specified below or at such other address as such Party notifies in writing&#13;
to the other Party from time to time:&#13;
For the Bank (the "Bank Contact"):&#13;
Ismaila B. Ceesay&#13;
Lead Financial Management Specialist&#13;
GGDOR&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
102 Yakubu Gowon Way&#13;
Asokoro, Abuja&#13;
Nigeria&#13;
Tel: +234 7035 830 640-4&#13;
Fax: +234&#13;
E-mail: iceesay@worldbank.org&#13;
For the Donor (the "Donor Contact"):&#13;
Tiina Intelmann&#13;
Ambassador/Head of Delegation&#13;
EU Delegation to Liberia&#13;
100 UN Drive, Mamba Point&#13;
Tel: +231 777757824/ +231 777757826&#13;
Fax: +231 777001062&#13;
E-mail: delegation-liberia@eeas.europa.eu&#13;
6.    In the event any amounts are to be returned to the Donor under this Administration Agreement, the&#13;
Bank shall transfer such amounts to the Donor unless otherwise agreed with the Bank.&#13;
7.     All annexes hereto and the Framework Agreement between the World Bank Group and the&#13;
European Commission constitute an integral part of this Administration Agreement, whose terms taken&#13;
together shall constitute the entire agreement and understanding between the Donor and the Bank. In the&#13;
event of any inconsistency, the Framework Agreement prevails over the Administration Agreement and the&#13;
Administration Agreement prevails over its Annexes. Unless otherwise specified in an annex hereto, this&#13;
Administration Agreement may be amended only by written amendment between the Bank and the Donor.&#13;
8.    Individual procurement and grant contracts under this Administration Agreement shall be signed&#13;
by the Bank no later than fifteen (15) months from the date of this Administration Agreement.&#13;
9.     The following derogations from the Framework Agreement shall apply in cases of crisis,&#13;
emergency and post-emergency situations: Non-Applicable&#13;
10.   The measures taken to identify the EU as a source of financing shall be in accordance with&#13;
Attachment 4 of the Framework Agreement.&#13;
-2-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿11.    Each of the Parties represents, by confirming its agreement below, that it is authorized to enter into&#13;
this Administration Agreement and act in accordance with these terms and conditions. The Parties are&#13;
requested to sign and date this Administration Agreement, and upon possession by the Bank of this fully&#13;
signed Administration Agreement, this Administration Agreement shall become effective as of the date of&#13;
the last signature.&#13;
INTERNATIONAL BANK FOR RECONSTRUCTION AND DEVELOPMENT&#13;
INTERNAT AL DEVELO ENT ASSOCIATION&#13;
By:&#13;
Inguna Dob ja&#13;
Country Manager for Liberia&#13;
Date:&#13;
EUROPEAN COMMISSION&#13;
By:&#13;
Name:&#13;
Title:&#13;
Date:       __&#13;
-3-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿ANNEX 1&#13;
Liberia Integrated Public Financial Management Reform Single Donor Trust Fund Description&#13;
This Annex shall be applicable to and form an integral part of the Administration Agreement for the Trust&#13;
Fund between the Bank and the Donor.&#13;
1.     Objectives&#13;
The objectives of the Trust Fund are: improved budget coverage, fiscal policy management, financial&#13;
control, and oversight of government finances of Liberia. Through strengthened institutional capacity for&#13;
the delivery of effective PFM and oversight, the government will be able to expand and deepen the scope&#13;
reforms in support of reduced corruption and improve service delivery, particularly to vulnerable groups,&#13;
thereby reducing poverty.&#13;
2.     Activities&#13;
The activities (which may be described as "components" of activities) to be financed by the Trust Fund&#13;
are:&#13;
2.1    Bank-executed activities, for which the Bank has implementation responsibility:&#13;
Providing enhanced implementation support to and oversight for the Integrated Public Financial&#13;
Management Reform Project (as described in Sub-section 2.2 of this Annex), and program management&#13;
and administration.&#13;
2.2       Recipient-executed activities, for which one or more Recipients (as defined in Annex 2) have&#13;
implementation responsibility:&#13;
Component 1: Enhancing Budget Planning Systems, Coverage and Credibility&#13;
Establishment of effective systems and procedures for aggregated fiscal policy, management budget&#13;
formulation and process and improved central and local government management, through:&#13;
(a)    Macro-Fiscal Framework. Provision of training to relevant staff of the Ministry of Finance and&#13;
Development Planning (MoFDP) in macroeconomic modelling, financial programming and revenue&#13;
forecasting and provision of software and hardware for MFAU offices to strengthen the performance of&#13;
MFAU's functions.&#13;
(b)    Fiscal Reporting and Fiscal Policy Review. Carrying out of: (i) a complete mapping of all chart of&#13;
accounts (COA) elements in producing FORs; (ii) a pilot program for the reconciliation of fiscal and&#13;
monetary accounts within the FORs to progressively include IFMIS data, incorporate FOR data in mid-&#13;
term reviews and to publish the FORs once data adequacy is established; (iii) a plan to establish financial&#13;
management and accounting standards for SOEs and allow regular reporting on SOE financial performance&#13;
and potential risks to the Recipient's fiscal position, including, inter alia, capacity building and training for&#13;
SOE staff to enhance performance of their functions and the preparation of financial reporting guidelines.&#13;
(c)    Enhanced Budget Frameworks. Establishment of an orderly, realistic budget process that includes&#13;
all central government M&amp;As and counties, through: (i) the development and delivery of training materials&#13;
and workshops to enhance the M&amp;As' performance functions at central and local level; (ii) provision of&#13;
-4-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿training on planning, capital project selection, and budgeting to MoFDP and M&amp;A relevant staff; (iii) the&#13;
implementation of a road-map for MTBF roll-out; (iv) pilot the preparation of FSEs by M&amp;As and the&#13;
MoFDP; and (v) carrying out of public consultations and hearings as a formal feature of the budget&#13;
preparation process.&#13;
Component 2: Strengthening PFM Legal Framework, Budget Execution, Accounting Reporting&#13;
Strengthening of the Recipient's legal public financial management framework to enhance delivery and&#13;
quality of budget information and allow more informed government decision making, through:&#13;
(a)    Review of PFM Legal Framework. Carrying out of a legal review and drafting of proposed&#13;
revisions to key legal instruments governing public financial management, including revisions to the&#13;
Recipient's Public Financial Management Act of 2009, to provide greater consistency with international&#13;
best practices and on improved legal framework for management and control of public finances.&#13;
(b)   IFMIS Roll-out to M&amp;As. Implementation of the roll-out of the IFMIS to the Recipient's ministries&#13;
and agencies, through: (i) implementation of software with interlinked budget preparation, execution and&#13;
fiscal reporting modules; (ii) minor office renovations; (iii) completion of the implementation of the payroll&#13;
module of said software; and (iv) establishment of e-transcript utilities to interface with county-level&#13;
systems.&#13;
(c)    Strengthening Financial Standards - Accounting and Reporting. (i) Development of guidelines to&#13;
produce IPSAS compliant consolidated financial statements: (ii) provision of training to CAGD staff on&#13;
accounting and reporting; (iii) development and design of specifications to automatically produce IPSAS&#13;
compliant reports; and (iv) carrying out of a review of the current accounting and financial processes and&#13;
provision of recommendations to improve identified areas to bring these processes in line with best&#13;
practices.&#13;
(d)    Treasury and Cash Management. Improvement of efficiency and effectiveness of the Recipient's&#13;
cash and debt management, through: (i) the preparation of a plan to establish the TSA; (ii) implementation&#13;
of banking arrangements and payments processes for TSA sub-accounts; (iii) drafting of principles for&#13;
donor project bank accounts to be incorporated under TSA; and (iv) establishment of a cash flow forecasting&#13;
and cash management mechanism.&#13;
(e)   Aid Management. Improvement of the predictability and coordination of aid flows and increase in&#13;
the transparency and accountability of aid management, through: (i) the implementation of a web-based&#13;
repository of aid data and aid funded programs in the aid management platform; (ii) carrying out of training&#13;
of AMU staff in aid management and coordination, monitoring and evaluation, and grant negotiation; (iii)&#13;
provision of hardware, software and equipment; and (iv) carrying out of minor office renovations.&#13;
(f)    Debt Management. Improvement of efficiency and effectiveness of debt management, through: (i)&#13;
provision of training on debt management systems to debt management staff; (ii) acquisition of periodic&#13;
CS-DRMS upgrades; and (iii) implementation of a domestic debt management module as an addition to&#13;
CS-DRMS.&#13;
(g)    Establishment of County Treasuries. Establishment of basic financial management and fiduciary&#13;
control at county level, through: (i) carrying out of minor renovations of existing county accounting offices;&#13;
(ii) setting up of a treasury framework, including design and provision of simplified book-keeping and&#13;
accounting tools; (iii) acquisition of basic furniture for county treasury offices; and (iv) provision of training&#13;
to county treasury officers on basic county treasury accounting and reporting.&#13;
-5-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿(h)    Donor Project Financial Management/Use of Country Systems. Increase the use of country&#13;
financial management systems and 'aid on accounting' and 'aid on reporting', through: (i) design of&#13;
budgeting, accounting, and reporting tools within IFMIS; (ii) provision of training of PFMU staff and staff&#13;
in the CAGD accounting services unit on the implementation of donor-funded project accounting; and (iii)&#13;
piloting of the transition from stand-alone financial arrangements for donor-funded projects to integrated&#13;
financial management arrangements.&#13;
Component 3: Enhancing Transparency and Accountability&#13;
Improvement of the Recipient's public financial management transparency and accountability, through:&#13;
(a)    Strengthening Public Procurement. Improve the public procurement oversight through&#13;
strengthening the institutional capacity of the PPCC to deliver on its mandate, through: (i) strengthening&#13;
the institutional capacity of the PPCC to enhance performance of its functions; (ii) training to PPCC staff&#13;
and outreach to ministries and local government officials to improve monitoring and compliance with&#13;
procurement guidelines; (iii) carrying out of south-to-south knowledge exchange activities; (iv) supporting&#13;
the interface with IFMIS procurement model and the online publication of PPCC review reports.&#13;
(b)   Internal Audits and Controls. Improvement of the internal control environment of M&amp;As to ensure&#13;
sufficient and timely services, through: (i) the establishment of the Recipient's internal audit governance&#13;
board and secretariat; (ii) provision of software, hardware and equipment to the governance board; (iii)&#13;
carrying out of training to internal auditors across M&amp;As; (iv) preparation and implementation of internal&#13;
audit manuals; (v) the development and implementation of a risk-based audit methodology; and (vi)&#13;
provision of training on specialized audit, licensing and certifications to internal auditors.&#13;
(c)    External Audit. Strengthening of the oversight role of GAC and improvement of financial&#13;
compliance, through: (i) carrying out of training to GAC staff on procurement audit, information system&#13;
audit, revenue audit, public and environmental audit, oil and gas audit; (ii) carrying out of training and&#13;
certification for GAC staff on modern audit practices; and (iii) strengthening GAC's capacity and carrying&#13;
out of minor office renovations.&#13;
(d)    Legislative Oversight. Enhancement of the capacity of LBO to apply appropriate standards of&#13;
public financial accountability to the executive branch, through: (i) provision of training on budget analysis&#13;
to LBO staff; (ii) implementation of outreach programs for PAC and the Ways and Means Committee&#13;
through south-south study tours; and (iii) provision of training to the Recipient's legislators.&#13;
(e)    Targeted capacity building in PFM processes and systems at the Ministry of Justice, Liberia&#13;
National Police, Bureau for Naturalization and Immigration, and the Judiciary.&#13;
(f)    Strengthening the demand side accountability under the IPFMRP's Non-State Actor's component&#13;
(g)    Civil Society and Social Accountability. Strengthening the capacity of NSAs as critical watchdogs&#13;
in ensuring transparency and accountability in the use of public finances, through: (i) the preparation and&#13;
dissemination of information materials on public spending at national and local levels; (ii) support the&#13;
administration of Sub-grants by NSAs under this Part D, including the recruitment of a Sub-grants&#13;
Evaluation Agent; (iii) development of a grant-making program for eligible NSAs and provision of such&#13;
Sub-grants to eligible NSAs to support demand-driven activities related to transparency and accountability&#13;
in the use of public resources for (a) analysis and monitoring of the national and local government budgets&#13;
at various stages of the budget preparation, approval and execution cycle; and (b) support for advocacy&#13;
-6-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿activities and dissemination of information on all aspects of public financial management at the national&#13;
and local government levels; and (iii) media training for journalists on covering government budget and&#13;
spending matters and related issues.&#13;
Component 4: Program Governance and Project Management&#13;
Providing a robust project and program management function that caters to the needs of integrated&#13;
coordination and monitoring of the implementation of the program, serve as the enabling component for&#13;
delivery of PFM human resource capacity, and assure the appropriate sequencing of interventions across&#13;
the various reform fronts. Activities to include:&#13;
(a)    Project Coordination. Strengthening the institutional capacity of the PFM RCU and PFMU in&#13;
order to fulfil their fiduciary duties under the Project, and liaise with the CSA, PFM Training Program and&#13;
the PPCC.&#13;
(b)    Institutional and Capacity Building. Strengthening of the institutional basis for public financial&#13;
management reforms and build national capacity for enabling new entrants into the civil service, through:&#13;
(i) provision of stipends to eligible students under the EGIRP Criteria in the public financial management&#13;
and procurement courses; (ii) review of the procurement and public financial management education&#13;
curriculum; (iii) provision of compensation to professional lecturers and other academic staff in public&#13;
financial management and procurement courses; (iv) development of a career path for public financial&#13;
management and procurement staff; (v) further implementation of the employee biometrics; and (vi)&#13;
carrying out public financial management training and knowledge sharing to key staff of M&amp;As.&#13;
(c)    Monitoring &amp; Evaluation. Strengthening the institutional capacity of the M&amp;E Unit in order to&#13;
carry out annual self-assessments of the Recipient's public expenditures financial accountability.&#13;
(d)    Fiduciary Strengthening. Strengthening the institutional capacity of the PFM RCU in order to&#13;
fulfil its fiduciary responsibilities under the Project, and provide technical support to M&amp;As.&#13;
DEFINITIONS: For purposes of the foregoing description, the following terms have the following&#13;
meanings:&#13;
"AMU"           Means Aide Management Unit&#13;
"AWPB"          Means Annual Work Program and Project Budget&#13;
"CAGD"          Means Recipient's Comptroller &amp; Accountant General's Department&#13;
"COA"           Means Chart of Accounts&#13;
"CS-DRMS"       Means Commonwealth Secretariat's Debt Recording and Management System&#13;
"CSA"           Means Recipient's Civil Service Agency&#13;
"EGIRP"         Means Economic Governance &amp; Institutional Reform Project&#13;
"FOR"           Means Fiscal Operations Reports&#13;
"FSE"           Means Forward Spending Estimates&#13;
"GAC"           Means Recipient's General Auditing Commission&#13;
"IFMIS"         Means Integrated Financial Management Information Systems&#13;
-7-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿"IPFMRP"        Means Integrated Public Financial Management Reform Project&#13;
"IPSAS"         Means International Public Sector Accounting Standards&#13;
"LBO"           Means Recipient's Legislative Budget Office&#13;
"M&amp;A"           Means Ministries and Agencies&#13;
"M&amp;E"9          Means Monitoring and Evaluation&#13;
"MFAU"          Means Macro-Fiscal Analysis Unit&#13;
"MoF"           Means Recipient's Ministry of Finance&#13;
"MoPEA"         Means Recipient's Ministry of Planning &amp; Economic Affairs&#13;
"MTBF"          Means Medium Term Budget Framework&#13;
"NSA"           Means Non-State Actors&#13;
"Operating      Means the reasonable costs of incremental expenditures incurred by the Recipient in&#13;
Costs"          relation to the implementation of the Project, which expenditures would not have&#13;
been incurred absent the Project, including, inter alia: maintenance of vehicles and&#13;
equipment, fuel, office supplies, utilities, consumables, bank charges, advertising&#13;
expenses, travel, per diems, accommodation, salaries of selected support staff, and&#13;
salaries of consultants but excluding salaries of officials of the Recipient's civil&#13;
service&#13;
"PAC"           Means Recipient's Public Accounts Committee&#13;
"PEFA"          Means Public Expenditure and Financial Accountability Assessment&#13;
"PFM"           Means Public Financial Management&#13;
"PFMU"          Means Project Financial Management Unit&#13;
"PPCC"          Means Recipient's Public Procurement and Concession Commission&#13;
"PSC"           Means Project Steering Committee&#13;
"PTC"           Means PFM Technical Committee&#13;
"RCU"           Means Reform Coordination Unit&#13;
"SOE"           Means Statement of Expenditure&#13;
"Stipends"      Means the reasonable stipend of approximately one hundred Dollars (US$100) per&#13;
eligible student under the EGIRP Criteria, and/or any other amount agreed from time&#13;
to time by the Recipient with the Association, to be paid on a monthly basis to&#13;
students attending the PFM Training Program, in order to partially cover the living&#13;
expenses&#13;
"Sub-grant"     Means a grant made or proposed to be made by the Recipient to an NSA out of the&#13;
proceeds facilitated under the LIPFMRP MDTF for the purpose of financing the&#13;
reasonable costs of goods or services required by the said NSA for the carrying out&#13;
of a Sub-project.&#13;
"TSA"           Means Treasury Single Account&#13;
-8-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿3.     Eligible Expenditures&#13;
3.1    For Bank-executed activities, the Trust Fund funds may be used to finance:&#13;
(a) Staff costs - No Indirect Costs&#13;
(b) Extended Term Consultants - No Indirect Costs&#13;
(c) Field Benefits&#13;
(d) Consultant fees for individuals - No Indirect Costs&#13;
(e) Consultant fees for firms&#13;
(f) Temporary staff costs - No Indirect Costs&#13;
(g) Contractual services&#13;
(h) Media, workshops&#13;
(i) Travel costs&#13;
3.2    For Recipient-executed activities, the Trust Fund may be used to finance all expense types as are&#13;
permitted under relevant Bank Policies for all the components/activities listed in Section 2.2 of this&#13;
Annex.&#13;
4.     Taxes&#13;
4.1    The foregoing activities and categories of expenditures may include the financing of taxes in&#13;
accordance with the Bank's applicable policies and procedures.&#13;
-9-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿ANNEX 2&#13;
Standard Provisions&#13;
This Annex shall be applicable to and form an integral part of the Administration Agreement for the Trust&#13;
Fund between the Bank and the Donor, it being understood that any plural references in the annexes to&#13;
Donors, Administration Agreements, Contributions and pro rata shares shall be read as singular references&#13;
to the Donor, its Administration Agreement, its Contributions thereunder and the remaining uncommitted&#13;
balance of the Trust Fund, respectively.&#13;
1.     Administration of the Contributions&#13;
1.1   The Bank shall be responsible only for performing those functions specifically set forth in this&#13;
Administration Agreement and shall not be subject to any other duties or responsibilities to the Donors,&#13;
including, without limitation, any duties or obligations that might otherwise apply to a fiduciary or trustee&#13;
under general principles of trust or fiduciary law. Nothing in this Administration Agreement shall be&#13;
considered a waiver of any privileges or immunities of the Bank under its Articles of Agreement or any&#13;
applicable law, all of which are expressly reserved.&#13;
1.2    Each Donor's Contribution (collectively, the "Contributions") shall be administered in accordance&#13;
with the Bank's applicable policies and procedures, as the same may be amended from time to time,&#13;
including its procurement, financial management, disbursement and safeguard policies, its framework to&#13;
prevent and combat fraud and corruption and its screening procedures to prevent the use of Bank resources&#13;
to finance terrorist activity, in line with the Bank's obligations to give effect to the relevant decisions of the&#13;
Security Council taken under Chapter VII of the of Charter of the United Nations. The Donors acknowledge&#13;
that this provision does not create any obligations of the Bank under the anti-terrorist financing and asset&#13;
control laws, regulations, rules and executive orders of an individual member country that may apply to a&#13;
Donor.&#13;
2.     Management of the Contributions&#13;
2.1    The funds deposited in the Trust Fund shall be accounted for as a single trust fund and shall be kept&#13;
separate and apart from the funds of the Bank. The funds deposited in the Trust Fund may be commingled&#13;
with other trust fund assets maintained by the Bank. The Bank, in its capacity as trustee, has legal title to&#13;
the funds deposited in the Trust Fund.&#13;
2.2    The currency in which the funds in the Trust Fund shall be held is United States Dollar (the&#13;
"Holding Currency").&#13;
2.3    Donors agree to deposit their Contributions in the Contribution Currency stated in their respective&#13;
Administration Agreements. In the case of deposits received in a Contribution Currency other than the&#13;
Holding Currency, promptly upon the receipt of such amounts and the accompanying Deposit Instructions,&#13;
the Bank shall convert such amounts into the Holding Currency at the exchange rate obtained by the Bank&#13;
on the date of the conversion. Where deposits prove to be insufficient to complete activities as a result of&#13;
exchange rate fluctuations, neither the Bank nor the Donor shall bear any responsibility for providing any&#13;
additional financing.&#13;
2.4    The funds deposited in the Trust Fund may be freely exchanged by the Bank into other currencies&#13;
as may facilitate their disbursement at the exchange rate obtained by the Bank on the date of the conversion.&#13;
- 10 -&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿2.5    The Bank shall invest and reinvest the funds deposited in the Trust Fund pending their disbursement&#13;
in accordance with the Bank's applicable policies and procedures for the investment of trust funds&#13;
administered by the Bank. The Bank shall transfer all income from such investment to the Donor's&#13;
applicable donor balance account with the Bank.&#13;
3.     Trust Fund Fees and Costs&#13;
3.1    The Bank shall deduct and retain for its own account, as a deduction from each Instalment, an&#13;
amount equal to five point five percent (5.5%) per Instalment as an administrative fee for the Trust Fund.&#13;
3.3    Each Donor acknowledges and agrees that the percentage deductions for fees in this Trust Fund&#13;
Fees and Costs section are estimated on the basis of anticipated Contributions. If actual Contributions&#13;
significantly differ from what was originally anticipated at the time of signature of the first Administration&#13;
Agreement, or if other circumstances affecting Trust Fund fees or costs change, the Bank reserves the right&#13;
to request a change to the terms of this Trust Fund Fees and Costs section, which would be effectuated by&#13;
amendments made to the Administration Agreements of all Donors and which would thereafter be&#13;
applicable to all new Contributions that are provided either as amendments to supplement existing&#13;
Administration Agreements or from new Donors under new Administration Agreements.&#13;
4.     Accountine and Financial Reportine&#13;
4.1    The Bank shall maintain separate records and ledger accounts in respect of the funds deposited in&#13;
the Trust Fund and disbursements made therefrom.&#13;
4.2    The Bank shall furnish to the Donors current financial information relating to receipts,&#13;
disbursements and fund balance in the Holding Currency with respect to the Contributions via the World&#13;
Bank's Trust Funds Donor Center secure website. Within six (6) months after all commitments and&#13;
liabilities under the Trust Fund have been satisfied and the Trust Fund has been closed, the final financial&#13;
information relating to receipts, disbursements and fund balance in the Holding Currency with respect to&#13;
the Contributions shall be made available to the Donors via the World Bank's Trust Funds Donor Center&#13;
secure website.&#13;
4.3    The Bank shall provide to the Donors via the World Bank's Trust Fund Donor Center secure&#13;
website, within six (6) months following the end of each Bank fiscal year, an annual single audit report,&#13;
comprising (i) a management assertion together with an attestation from the Bank's external auditors&#13;
concerning the adequacy of internal control over cash-based financial reporting for all cash-based trust&#13;
funds as a whole; and (ii) a combined financial statement for all cash-based trust funds together with the&#13;
Bank's external auditor's opinion thereon. The cost of the single audit shall be borne by the Bank.&#13;
4.4   If a Donor wishes to request, on an exceptional basis, a financial statement audit by the Bank's&#13;
external auditors of the Trust Fund, the Donor and the Bank shall first consult as to whether such an external&#13;
audit is necessary. The Bank and the Donor shall agree on the appropriate scope and terms of reference of&#13;
such audit. Following agreement on the scope and terms of reference, the Bank shall arrange for such&#13;
external audit. The costs of any such audit, including the internal costs of the Bank with respect to such&#13;
audit, shall be borne by the requesting Donor.&#13;
- 11 -&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿5.     Progress Reporting&#13;
5.1    The Bank shall provide the Donors with annual reports on the progress of activities financed by the&#13;
Contributions. Within six (6) months of the End Disbursement Date (as defined below), the Bank shall&#13;
furnish to the Donors a final report on the activities financed by the Trust Fund.&#13;
5.2    Any Donor may review or evaluate activities financed by the Trust Fund at any time up to six (6)&#13;
months following the End Disbursement Date. The Donor and the Bank shall agree on the scope and&#13;
conduct of such review or evaluation, and the Bank shall provide all relevant information within the limits&#13;
of the Bank's applicable policies and procedures. All associated costs, including any costs incurred by the&#13;
Bank, shall be borne by the Donor. It is understood that any such review or evaluation will not constitute&#13;
a financial, compliance or other audit of the Trust Fund.&#13;
6.     Disbursement; Cancellation; Refund&#13;
6.1   It is expected that the funds deposited in the Trust Fund will be fully disbursed by the Bank by June&#13;
30, 2017 (the "End Disbursement Date"). The Bank shall only disburse funds deposited in the Trust Fund&#13;
for the purposes of this Administration Agreement (other than returns to Donors) after such date to the&#13;
extent such date is changed in accordance with amendments made to the Administration Agreements of all&#13;
the Donors. Following the End Disbursement Date, the Bank shall return any remaining balance of the&#13;
Trust Fund to each Donor in the Holding Currency in the manner specified in its respective Administration&#13;
Agreement on a pro rata basis with regard to the total funds deposited in the Trust Fund by such Donor&#13;
relative to the total funds deposited in the Trust Fund by all Donors, all calculated as Holding Currency&#13;
amounts.&#13;
6.2    Any Donor may cancel all or part of such Donor's pro rata share, and the Bank may cancel all or&#13;
any Donors' pro rata shares, upon three (3) months' prior written notice, of any Contributions (paid and&#13;
not yet paid) that are not committed pursuant to any agreements entered into between the Bank and any&#13;
consultants and/or other third parties for the purposes of this Administration Agreement, including any&#13;
Grant Agreements, prior to the receipt of such notice. In the event of a cancellation, the Bank shall return&#13;
to the Donor its pro rata share in the Holding Currency specified in the Administration Agreement; unless&#13;
otherwise agreed between the Bank and each such Donor.&#13;
7.     Disclosure; Dispute Resolution&#13;
7.1    The Bank shall disclose the Administration Agreements and related information on this Trust Fund&#13;
in accordance with the Bank's Policy on Access to Information. By entering into Administration&#13;
Agreements, the Donors consent to such disclosure of their respective Administration Agreements and such&#13;
related information.&#13;
7.2    The Donors and the Bank shall use their best efforts to amicably settle any dispute, controversy, or&#13;
claim arising out of or relating to the Administration Agreements.&#13;
8.     Grants to Recipients&#13;
8.1    The Bank shall, as administrator of the Trust Fund on behalf of the Donors, enter into one or more&#13;
grant agreements (the "Grant Agreements") with recipients (the "Recipients") consistent with the purposes&#13;
of this Administration Agreement and on the terms and conditions set forth in the Grant Agreements. Grant&#13;
Agreements may be entered into up to the maximum amount of the Contributions that all Donors have&#13;
agreed to make available under the Administration Agreements between the Bank and the Donors.&#13;
- 12 -&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿8.2    The Bank shall be responsible for the supervision of the activities financed under any Grant&#13;
Agreements. Subject to the consent of any relevant Recipients, representatives of the Donors may be invited&#13;
by the Bank to participate in Bank supervision missions related to the Trust Fund.&#13;
8.3    The Bank shall promptly inform the Donors of any significant modification to the terms of any&#13;
Grant Agreements and of any contractual remedies that are exercised by the Bank under any Grant&#13;
Agreements. To the extent practicable, the Bank shall afford the Donors the opportunity to exchange views&#13;
before effecting any such modification or exercising any such remedy.&#13;
- 13 -&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿ANNEX 3&#13;
Governance&#13;
This Annex shall be applicable to and form an integral part of the Administration Agreement between the&#13;
Bank and the Donor. Further details are provided in the PFM Operations Manual of the Government of&#13;
Liberia that Development Partners have subscribed to.&#13;
PFM Steering Committee: The PFM Steering Committee (SC) shall be the main structure responsible for&#13;
oversight over the overall PFM reform program. It will provide policy coordination and will be the forum&#13;
for resolving strategic issues impeding program implementation. The SC shall also be the forum for policy&#13;
dialogue with Development Partners on the PFM program. Moreover, the SC will be responsible for&#13;
approving the Annual Work Program and Project Budget (AWPB). It shall meet on a quarterly basis. The&#13;
SC shall have the following membership: Minister of Finance (Chair), Minister for Planning and Economic&#13;
Affairs, Minister of State, Minister of Justice, Director General, Civil Service Agency, Auditor General,&#13;
Executive Director of the PPCC, Chair of the PFM Project Steering Committee (PSC) and the Head of the&#13;
RCU (Secretariat).&#13;
PFM Technical Committee: A PFM Technical Committee (PTC) shall be established under the project. The&#13;
PTC shall be a forum for all Component Chiefs to monitor and coordinate implementation of program&#13;
activities. Component Leads shall be selected by the respective beneficiary departments or agencies for&#13;
each of the five components of the project. The PTC shall meet monthly. Its membership shall be as follows:&#13;
Deputy Minister of Finance (Administration), Chair; all Component Chiefs and alternate leads; Leads of&#13;
cross-cutting activities; IFMIS and Capacity building; and Head of the RCU (secretary).&#13;
Coordination with Development Partners: A joint Government Donor Steering Committee will meet twice&#13;
annually to review the progress of implementation of PFM reforms, in general, in Liberia, as well as those&#13;
supported under the Project. Core reform activities financed under the IPFMRP shall be 'reviewed during&#13;
these meetings. A regular consultation process between the European Commission and the World Bank&#13;
Group on implementation progress shall be put in place. In addition, joint donor partner implementation&#13;
support missions will be carried out semi-annually to review implementation progress against key&#13;
milestones and provide technical support to implementing partners.&#13;
- 14 -&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿ANNEX 4&#13;
Expected      Indicators    Baselines  Result goals        Sources  of Assumptions&#13;
Results                                                    data&#13;
(logic   of&#13;
intervention)&#13;
Impact        PEFA PI-7     D+         B                   PEFA    Sel- The extent of&#13;
asessment    goverement&#13;
unreported&#13;
operations&#13;
will      be&#13;
improved&#13;
Outcome(s)                  Low        Improved            Annual       The   annual&#13;
converge of reportage/coverage of outturn   outturn&#13;
government government          reports      reports will be&#13;
operations  operations                      published on&#13;
timely basis.&#13;
Output(s)                              Number          of&#13;
government&#13;
unreported operations&#13;
improved&#13;
Impact        PEFA PI-12    D+         B                   PEFA    Sel- Multi-year&#13;
asessment    perspective in&#13;
fiscal&#13;
planning,&#13;
expenditure&#13;
policy and&#13;
budgeting will&#13;
be put in&#13;
place&#13;
Outcome(s)                  Absence of Improved     fiscal Annual       The   annual&#13;
multi-year  planning, expenditure outturn   outturn&#13;
perspective  policy and budgeting  reports  reports will be&#13;
in   fiscal                                 published on&#13;
planning,                                   timely basis.&#13;
expenditure&#13;
policy and&#13;
budgeting&#13;
Output(s)                              Multi-year&#13;
perspective in fiscal&#13;
planning,&#13;
expenditure policy&#13;
and budgeting&#13;
- 15 -&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿Impact        PEFA PI-18     D+          B                   PEFA   Self- Effectiveness&#13;
assessment    of    payroll&#13;
controls will&#13;
be improved&#13;
Outcome(s)                  Ineffective  Improved            Annual       The    annual&#13;
payroll     effectiveness of    outturn       outturn&#13;
controls are payroll controls   reports       reports will be&#13;
in place                                      published on&#13;
timely basis.&#13;
Output(s)                                Effective payroll&#13;
controls&#13;
Impact        PEFA PI-20     C+          B                   PEFA    Self- Effectiveness&#13;
assessment    of   internal&#13;
controls  for&#13;
non-salary&#13;
expenditure&#13;
will      be&#13;
improved&#13;
Outcome(s)                  Ineffective  Improved            Annual       The    annual&#13;
payroll     effectiveness of    outturn       outturn&#13;
controls for internal controls for  reports   reports will be&#13;
internal                                      published on&#13;
non-salary  nslrtimely basis.&#13;
expenditur  expenditure&#13;
Output(s)                               Effective internal&#13;
controls for non-&#13;
salary expenditure&#13;
Impact        PEFA PI-25     D           C+                  PEFA    Self- Quality  and&#13;
assessments   timeliness of&#13;
annual&#13;
financial&#13;
statements&#13;
will      be&#13;
improved&#13;
Outcome(s)                   Low        Improved quality and  Annual      The    annual&#13;
quality and timeliness of annual  outturn     outturn&#13;
delays  in financial statements  reports      reports will be&#13;
preparation                                   published on&#13;
of  annual                                    timely basis.&#13;
financial&#13;
statements&#13;
Output(s)                               Timely and reliable&#13;
annual financial&#13;
statements&#13;
- 16 -&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿Impact        PEFA PI-26     D           C+                  PEFA   Self- Scope, nature&#13;
assessments   and follow-up&#13;
of   external&#13;
audit will be&#13;
improved&#13;
Outcome(s)                   Limited     Improved scope,     Annual       The    annual&#13;
scope,      nature and follow-up  outturn     outturn&#13;
nature and  of external audit   reports       reports will be&#13;
follow-up                                     published on&#13;
of external                                   timely basis.&#13;
audit&#13;
Output(s)                               Expanded scope,&#13;
nature and regular&#13;
follow-up on external&#13;
audit&#13;
Impact        PEFA PI-28     D           C+                  PEFA    Self- Legislative&#13;
assessments   scrutiny  of&#13;
external audit&#13;
reports will be&#13;
improved&#13;
Outcome(s)                   Weak        Strengthened        Annual       The    annual&#13;
legislative  legislative scrutiny of outturn  outturn&#13;
scrutiny of external audit reports  reports   reports will be&#13;
external                                      published on&#13;
audit                                         timely basis.&#13;
reports&#13;
Output(s)                                Legislative scrutiny&#13;
of external audit&#13;
reports&#13;
- 17 -&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
﻿ANNEX 5&#13;
Indicative Budget Table&#13;
EU&#13;
ACTIVITIES                                      CONTRIBUTION&#13;
(IN EUR)&#13;
Recipient Executed Activities                                                           2,416,163.13&#13;
Component 1: Enhancing Budget Planning Systems, Coverage and Credibility                 181,455.27&#13;
Component 2: Strengthening PFM Legal Framework, Budget Execution, Accounting and Reporting  1,415,351.12&#13;
Component 3: Enhancing Transparency and Accountability                                   637,815.28&#13;
Component 4: Program Governance and Project Management                                   181,541.46&#13;
Bank Executed Activities                                                                  87,739.07&#13;
Enhanced Implementation Support of Client-Executed Project Activities                     87,739.07&#13;
Program Management and Administration                                                     38,148.25&#13;
Fee Percentage (5.50%)                                                                   147,949.56&#13;
TOTAL                                                                                   2,690,000.00&#13;
- 18-&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="25839134">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2015/12/25839134/official-documents--administration-agreement-european-commission-contribution-tf072467
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2015/12/25839134/official-documents--administration-agreement-european-commission-contribution-tf072467</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2015/12/25839134/official-documents--administration-agreement-european-commission-contribution-tf072467</new_url>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2016-02-07T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <docm_id>090224b08410d754</docm_id>
        <chronical_docm_id>090224b08410d754</chronical_docm_id>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/AFR/2016/01/28/090224b08410d754/1_0/Rendered/INDEX/Official0Docum0ribution0to0TF072467.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/AFR/2016/01/28/090224b08410d754/1_0/Rendered/PDF/Official0Docum0ribution0to0TF072467.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2016-01-28T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2015-12-17T14:12:34Z</docdt>
        <docna>
            Official Documents- Administration Agreement
            with the European Commission for Contribution to TF072467
        </docna>
        <display_title>Official Documents-
            Administration Agreement with the European Commission for
            Contribution to TF072467</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/2015/12/25839134/official-documents--administration-agreement-european-commission-contribution-tf072467</listing_relative_url>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <docty>Trust Fund Administrative Agreement</docty>
        <count>Liberia</count>
        <authors>
            <author>Sperling,Alexandra C.</author>
            <author>Alexandra Mendes,Sobrinho</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>HQBOCS</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <trustfund>TF072467-Liberia Integrated Public
            Financial Management Reform Single Donor Trus</trustfund>
        <lang>English</lang>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fragility, Conflict and Violence</ml:concept><ml:concept>Arts and Culture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Expenditure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Capacities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resource Management Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Staffing Needs Assessments</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Internal Financial Control (PIFC)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal &amp; Monetary Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Consolidation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Governance and Structural Fiscal Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Rules</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Sustainability</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macro-Fiscal Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Strategic Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Management of Public Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Finance Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Finances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Economics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Economics &amp; Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Efficiency of Public Expenditures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Expenditures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Financial Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Spending</ml:concept><ml:concept>Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deconcentration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delegation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Devolution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sub-National Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subnational Government and Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Very Vulnerable Groups (disability, orphans, children and youth)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Remittances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Migration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Contract Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Arrangements in Public Procurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Capacity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legal Regulatory Framework</ml:concept><ml:concept>State-Society Relations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Checks on Executive Power</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen User Satisfaction Survey</ml:concept><ml:concept>Independent Commissions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ombudsmen</ml:concept><ml:concept>Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Parliament</ml:concept><ml:concept>Procurement Complaints Review Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supreme Audit Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Media</ml:concept><ml:concept>Treasury</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government Expenditure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Budget Preparation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Budget Preparation </ml:concept><ml:concept>Internal Audit</ml:concept><ml:concept>Accounting and Reporting</ml:concept><ml:concept>External Audit</ml:concept><ml:concept>Local Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Reconciliation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Finance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Managing Public Finances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Administrative Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Vulnerable Groups</ml:concept><ml:concept>Temporary Movement of Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Accountability Mechanisms</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Africa</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Liberia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>