<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>264                                                                                                    privatesector     P U B L I C          P O L I C Y       F O R       T H E&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   NUMBER&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         NOTE&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
             2003&#13;
                                                                                                            Private Health&#13;
                 JUNE&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                               Tonia Marek, Chiaki          Policy and Regulatory Options for Private Participation&#13;
                                                                               Yamamoto, and Jeff Ruster&#13;
                                                                                                            Many developing countries face a critical gap between the demand for&#13;
                                                                               Tonia Marek (tmarek@&#13;
                                                                                                            health care services and their supply. Public resources often fall short&#13;
                                                                               worldbank.org) is a senior&#13;
&#13;
                                                                               public health specialist at  of what is needed to provide universal health care, and the typical&#13;
                                                                               the World Bank. Chiaki       incentive structure in the public sector may not always be conducive to&#13;
                                                                               Yamamoto (cyamamoto@&#13;
&#13;
                                                                               worldbank.org) is a private  expanding access, improving the quality of care, and ensuring efficient&#13;
                     NETWORK&#13;
                                                                               sector development           use of limited funding and expertise. This Note defines options for&#13;
                                                                               specialist, and Jeff Ruster&#13;
                                                                                                            mobilizing private resources to achieve public health objectives.&#13;
                                                                               (jruster@worldbank.org) a&#13;
&#13;
                                                                               lead private finance&#13;
&#13;
                                                                               specialist, in the World&#13;
                                                                                                            The range of options                                     Management--coordinating services and&#13;
                            INFRASTRUCTURE                                     Bank's Private&#13;
                                                                                                            A government seeking to encourage private par-           administering the operation of clinics or hos-&#13;
                                                                               Participation in Public&#13;
                                                                                                            ticipation in health care provision can choose           pitals, responsibilities that may or may not&#13;
                                          AND                                  Services Group.&#13;
                                                                                                            among six basic policy and regulatory options            include the authority to make employment&#13;
                                                                                                            that vary widely in the risks and responsibilities       decisions.&#13;
                                             SECTOR                                                         borne by the private (for-profit or nonprofit)           Asset maintenance--maintaining public facil-&#13;
                                                                                                            entity. At one end of the spectrum the private sec-      ities such as hospital buildings.&#13;
                                                                                                            tor takes on limited responsibilities while the          Construction and rehabilitation--investing&#13;
                                                   PRIVATE                                                  public sector remains the primary provider of            in constructing and rehabilitating facilities&#13;
                                                                                                            health care services (table 1). At the other, the        (excluding the purchase of equipment&#13;
                                                                                                            government establishes a policy environment in           needed to provide services).&#13;
                                                                                                            which qualified private entities may freely enter        Asset ownership.&#13;
                                                          GROUP                                                                                                   &#13;
                                                                                                            and exit the health care market. In this option&#13;
                                                                                                            private providers assume the full risks and           Service contracts&#13;
&#13;
                                                               BANK                                         responsibilities associated with service provision,   Under a service contract a government pays a pri-&#13;
                                                                                                            and the public sector limits its role to regulation.  vate entity to perform specific tasks. For example,&#13;
                                                                                                               The responsibilities that make up compre-          a public hospital might contract a private entity&#13;
                                                                                                            hensive health care provision can be divided          to provide routine procedures (laboratory ser-&#13;
                                                                   WORLD                                    into five main categories:                            vices) or specialized services (radiology) within&#13;
                                                                                                               Service delivery--providing specific services      the hospital, to complement its own operations.&#13;
                                                                        THE                                    relating to health care.                           Or a government might contract out functions&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
P R I V A T E H E A L T H P O L I C Y A N D R E G U L A T O R Y O P T I O N S F O R P R I V A T E P A R T I C I P A T I O N&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                            Table     Risks and responsibilities transferred to the private sector under different options&#13;
&#13;
                                           1                                                       Management contract&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                        Service    "Contract              "Contract                                         Free&#13;
&#13;
                                                      Responsibility                    contract   in"                    out"        Lease      Concessiona   Divestitureb entry&#13;
                                                      Service delivery&#13;
                                                      Management&#13;
                                                          Nonlabor supplies&#13;
                                                          Labor&#13;
2                                                     Asset maintenance&#13;
                                                      Construction and&#13;
                                                          rehabilitation&#13;
                                                      Asset ownership&#13;
                                                      Demand risk                                                                     Sometimes  Usually       Usually      Always&#13;
                                                      Access to private&#13;
                                                          finance                                                                     Sometimes  Always        Always       Always&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                   a. Including build-operate-transfer contracts.&#13;
                                                   b. Including build-own-operate contracts.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                           such as basic preventive care or a health educa-                                     Management contracts&#13;
                                           tion campaign to private organizations operating                                     Under a management contract a government&#13;
                                           outside public facilities.                                                           pays a private entity to manage public health care&#13;
                                              One example is the service contracts used in                                      facilities and provide a range of services. The&#13;
                                           the Dominican Republic to reach communities.                                         management authority transferred to the private&#13;
                                           In 1999 three provincial health directorates                                         sector varies from one contract to another and&#13;
                                           signed contracts with nongovernmental organi-                                        may include procurement of labor, supplies,&#13;
                                           zations (NGOs) to distribute contraceptives,                                         medicine, and equipment. Because medical pro-&#13;
                                           launch an education campaign on family plan-                                         fessionals are a key asset in health care provision,&#13;
                                           ning, and train health agents in reproductive                                        this Note distinguishes management contracts&#13;
                                           health. Most doctors were not trained for such                                       under which the public sector makes employ-&#13;
                                           community work, and contracting this function                                        ment decisions--the "contract in" model--from&#13;
                                           to NGOs proved to be an effective solution. A                                        those under which the private contractor makes&#13;
                                           private firm funded by the U.S. Agency for                                           these decisions--the "contract out" model. The&#13;
                                           International Development supervised the con-                                        contract-out model transfers the risks associated&#13;
                                           tracts on behalf of the government.                                                  with inputs, including labor, to the private sec-&#13;
                                              Because a service contract assigns responsi-                                      tor. Cambodia has experimented with both mod-&#13;
                                           bility for isolated tasks, it transfers little risk to                               els in district hospitals (box 1).&#13;
                                           the private entity. The government remains                                              Management contracts may be a good way to&#13;
                                           responsible for coordinating the tasks involved                                      gain access to the technical expertise and man-&#13;
                                           in providing comprehensive health care, main-                                        agerial efficiency of the private sector. But&#13;
                                           taining publicly owned assets, and making nec-                                       because commercial risks are still borne by the&#13;
                                           essary capital investments.                                                          government, they may create little incentive to&#13;
                                              Service contracts may be a good option for                                        reduce costs and improve the quality of services.&#13;
                                           introducing a private entity's comparative&#13;
                                           advantage            (highly            specialized        technology,               Leases&#13;
                                           access to rural communities) in a specific task.                                     Under a lease arrangement a private entity typi-&#13;
                                           But because responsibility for coordination still                                    cally pays the government a fee to use health care&#13;
                                           falls to the government, this option is unlikely to                                  facilities and takes on the responsibility for man-&#13;
                                           improve performance much if overall manage-                                          aging and operating them. In return the private&#13;
                                           ment is weak.                                                                        entity receives the right to the revenues from the&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                      Concessions and build-operate-transfer&#13;
       "Contracting in" and "contracting&#13;
       out" to improve the performance of                             Under concession arrangements a private entity&#13;
 Box   district hospitals in Cambodia                                 pays the government a fee to operate and&#13;
1                                                                     maintain health care facilities and also takes on&#13;
        In 1999 the government of Cambodia started testing&#13;
                                                                      responsibility for capital investment. Under build-&#13;
        contracting-in and contracting-out models in several dis-&#13;
        trict hospitals, transferring to private entities the         operate-transfer (BOT) arrangements, a variation&#13;
&#13;
        responsibility for providing a minimum package of pri-        of the concession, the capital investment takes the&#13;
&#13;
        mary health care services. The private providers,             form of constructing new facilities. A private firm&#13;
&#13;
        selected through competitive bidding based on technical       builds the facilities, provides services, and then&#13;
                                                                                                                                 3&#13;
        and financial proposals, are paid per person covered          transfers ownership to the government at the end&#13;
        and according to their bidding price.                         of a specified term (box 2). Build-lease-transfer&#13;
            A preliminary review after two and a half years of        and rehabilitate-operate-transfer schemes are also&#13;
        operation shows that the delivery of service improved in      variations of the concession.&#13;
        both contract-in and contract-out hospitals. While a&#13;
                                                                          Concessions and BOT contracts, which typi-&#13;
        composite measure based on such indicators as immu-&#13;
                                                                      cally last longer than other types of arrange-&#13;
        nization coverage and family planning knowledge among&#13;
                                                                      ments, provide greater incentives for efficiency&#13;
        the population rose by 100 percent in districts with pub-&#13;
                                                                      by transferring to the private sector full respon-&#13;
        lic hospitals, the measure increased by 180 percent in&#13;
        contract-in districts and by 320 percent in contract-out      sibility for operation and investment. They also&#13;
&#13;
        districts. Moreover, out-of-pocket health spending by         offer a good way to tap the private sector's abil-&#13;
&#13;
        patients fell by 70 percent in contract-out districts, with   ity to access private finance and raise funding for&#13;
&#13;
        the greatest impact in the poorest half of the sample.        new construction and investment.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Source: Loevinsohn 2000; Bhushan, Keller, and Schwartz 2002;     Divestitures and build-own-operate&#13;
     Fronczack 2002.&#13;
                                                                      In a divestiture a publicly owned health care facil-&#13;
                                                                      ityissoldtoaprivateentity,andownershipistrans-&#13;
operation. Since the government no longer pro-                        ferred indefinitely. Under a build-own-operate&#13;
vides the service in the leased space, the private                    (BOO) contract, a variation of the divestiture, the&#13;
entity bears all the commercial risks (such as low                    private entity also takes responsibility for con-&#13;
demand for services or a change in service fees).                     structing new facilities at its own expense. Thus&#13;
   The government of Romania opted for lease                          divestitures and BOO contracts transfer commer-&#13;
arrangements for the provision of radiology and                       cial risks entirely to the private entity and take full&#13;
laboratory services in a major public hospital,                       advantage of its access to private finance.&#13;
completing a successful tender in 2002. The&#13;
transactions have led to several benefits: lower                      Free entry&#13;
costs for providing these services to public                          When qualified private providers are allowed to&#13;
patients, high-quality services, full transfer of                     freely enter and exit the health care market&#13;
financial and demand risk from the public hos-                        without establishing a contractual relationship&#13;
pital to the private providers, and private fund-                     with the government, the private providers bear&#13;
ing for new equipment.                                                all risks and responsibilities associated with&#13;
   Lease arrangements give the private provider                       health care provision. But the absence of con-&#13;
strong incentives to operate efficiently, because                     tractual relationships does not necessarily mean&#13;
the provider's profitability depends on how                           a lack of government oversight. A government&#13;
much it can reduce costs while still meeting the                      may use other regulatory instruments--such as&#13;
quality standards specified in the contract. But                      licensing, certification, and accreditation--to&#13;
coordination between the operating program                            protect the public interest by ensuring safety&#13;
and the investment program can be cumber-                             and a minimum quality of care. In addition to&#13;
some. Thus a lease may be a good option for                           legal requirements, a government might use&#13;
public health facilities that need to improve                         financial and other incentives (taxes, subsidies,&#13;
operating efficiency, but not for those that need                     training opportunities) to influence the behav-&#13;
new investment.                                                       ior of private providers--such as their choices of&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
P R I V A T E H E A L T H P O L I C Y A N D R E G U L A T O R Y O P T I O N S F O R P R I V A T E P A R T I C I P A T I O N&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         Using a build-operate-transfer                                          Subsidies may alter the degree of risk and&#13;
         contract to build a district hospital                               responsibility transferred to the private sector.&#13;
  Box    in rural South Africa&#13;
                                                                             Because health care is both a merit good (a&#13;
2                                                                            good that consumers may undervalue and&#13;
         The government of South Africa awarded a 10-year&#13;
         build-operate-transfer (BOT) contract (renewable for                therefore consume in smaller amounts than                              viewpoint&#13;
         another 10 years) to a private company through direct               considered socially optimal) and a public good,&#13;
&#13;
         negotiation. The contractor is responsible for employing            governments and donors often provide capital&#13;
&#13;
         all administrative and nursing staff, while the govern-             investment and training to private providers.&#13;
                                                                                                                                                    is an open forum to&#13;
         ment provides medical staff. The private contractor is              Social franchising, in which the government&#13;
                                                                                                                                                    encourage dissemination of&#13;
         paid a fixed per diem per patient. But the contract                 may construct facilities and provide training, is&#13;
                                                                                                                                                    public policy innovations for&#13;
         includes a minimum occupancy clause that shifts sub-                a type of BOO arrangement that deviates from&#13;
                                                                                                                                                    private sector­led and&#13;
         stantial demand risk to the government.                             the typical risk sharing profile of such schemes.&#13;
                                                                                                                                                    market-based solutions for&#13;
                                                                                 To maximize the benefits of private partici-&#13;
                                                                                                                                                    development. The views&#13;
       Source: Broomberg, Mills, and Masobe 1997.&#13;
                                                                             pation, a government therefore needs to deter-&#13;
                                                                                                                                                    published are those of the&#13;
                                                                             mine which option is best suited for achieving its                     authors and should not be&#13;
clinic locations and target patients--to achieve                             policy objectives--and then choose the most                            attributed to the World&#13;
public health goals.                                                         appropriate contracting and payment mecha-                             Bank or any other affiliated&#13;
   In a policy environment allowing free entry,                              nisms and the best regulatory framework for                            organizations. Nor do any of&#13;
&#13;
private providers develop their own organiza-                                monitoring and enforcing the arrangements.                             the conclusions represent&#13;
&#13;
tional structures and operational models to                                                                                                         official policy of the World&#13;
&#13;
achieve the best results. One emerging opera-                                                                                                       Bank or of its Executive&#13;
&#13;
tional model is franchising, in which a private                                                                                                     Directors or the countries&#13;
&#13;
firm (franchiser) licenses other private busi-                               References                                                             they represent.&#13;
&#13;
nesses (franchisees) to operate under its trade                                  Bhushan, Indu, Sheryl Keller, and Brad Schwartz.&#13;
&#13;
name (see Ruster, Yamamoto, and Rogo 2003).                                  2002. "Achieving the Twin Objectives of Efficiency and                 To order additional copies&#13;
&#13;
                                                                             Equity: Contracting Health Services in Cambodia." ERD                  contact Suzanne Smith,&#13;
&#13;
Variation in risk sharing                                                    Policy Brief 6. Asian Development Bank, Manila.                        managing editor,&#13;
&#13;
Each of the six options transfers a different                                                                                                       Room I9-009,&#13;
                                                                                 Broomberg, Jonathan, Anne Mills, and Patrick&#13;
&#13;
degree of risk and responsibility to the private                                                                                                    The World Bank,&#13;
                                                                             Masobe. 1997. "To Purchase or to Provide? The Relative&#13;
                                                                                                                                                    1818 H Street, NW,&#13;
provider. In practice, however, the risks trans-                             Efficiency of Contracting Out versus Direct Public&#13;
                                                                                                                                                    Washington, DC 20433.&#13;
ferred by an option--and therefore the incen-                                Provision of Hospital Services in South Africa." In Sara&#13;
&#13;
tives created--can vary significantly, depending                             Bennett, Barbara McPake, and Anne Mills, eds., Private&#13;
                                                                                                                                                    Telephone:&#13;
on the contract design, selection process, pay-                              Health Providers in Developing Countries: Serving the Public&#13;
                                                                                                                                                    001 202 458 7281&#13;
ment mechanism, and availability of subsidies.                               Interest? London: Zed Books.&#13;
                                                                                                                                                    Fax:&#13;
   The method used to select contractors affects                                 Fronczack, Nancy. 2002. Informal presentation on&#13;
                                                                                                                                                    001 202 522 3480&#13;
the efficiency gains that can be expected from                               impact of contracting. World Bank, Washington, D.C.,&#13;
                                                                                                                                                    Email:&#13;
private participation. Competitive bidding gen-                              September.&#13;
                                                                                                                                                    ssmith7@worldbank.org&#13;
erally creates stronger pressure for providing                                   Loevinsohn, Benjamin. 2000. "Contracting for the&#13;
&#13;
services at lower cost (see box 1).                                          Delivery of Primary Health Care in Cambodia: Design and&#13;
                                                                                                                                                    Copyedited and produced by&#13;
   Schemes that link payment of the private                                  InitialExperienceofaLargePilotTest."WorldBankInstitute                 Communications&#13;
provider directly to its performance also give                               Flagship      Program           Online        Journal.  [http://www.   Development Inc.&#13;
stronger incentives for efficiency. For example,                             worldbank.org/wbi/healthflagship/journal/index.htm].&#13;
&#13;
a management contract will create strong incen-                                  Ruster, Jeff, Chiaki Yamamoto, and Khama Rogo. 2003.               Printed on recycled paper&#13;
&#13;
tives for a private entity to reduce costs and                               "Franchising in Health: Emerging Models, Experiences, and&#13;
&#13;
improve quality if the contract offers a bonus                               Challenges." Viewpoint 263. World Bank, Private Sector and&#13;
&#13;
payment based on services provided. In con-                                  Infrastructure Network, Washington, D.C.&#13;
&#13;
trast, such incentives may be weaker under con-&#13;
cession or BOT schemes if the government&#13;
agrees to make minimum payments regardless&#13;
of the level of service provision (see box 2).&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                               T h i s N o t e i s a v a i l a b l e o n l i n e :&#13;
                                                                                         h t t p : / / r r u . w o r l d b a n k . o r g / V i e w p o i n t / i n d e x . a s p&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="2615787">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2003/06/2615787/private-health
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <virt_coll>Knowledge Notes</virt_coll>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2003/06/2615787/private-health</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2003/06/2615787/private-health</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/10/16/000090341_20031016113749/Rendered/INDEX/268120PAPER0VP0Note0no10264.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/10/16/000090341_20031016113749/Rendered/PDF/268120PAPER0VP0Note0no10264.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2003-10-16T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2003-06-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Private health
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            Many developing countries face a
            critical gap between the demand for health care services and
            their supply. Public resources often fall short of what is
            needed to provide universal health care, and the typical
            incentive structure in the public sector may not always be
            conducive to expanding access, improving the quality of
            care, and ensuring efficient use of limited funding and
            expertise. This Note defines options for mobilizing private
            resources to achieve public health objectives. A government
            seeking to encourage private participation in health care
            provision can choose among six basic policy and regulatory
            options that vary widely in the risks and responsibilities
            borne by the private (for-profit or nonprofit) entity. At
            one end of the spectrum the private sector takes on limited
            responsibilities while the public sector remains the primary
            provider of health care services. At the other, the
            government establishes a policy environment in which
            qualified private entities may freely enter and exit the
            health care market. In this option private providers assume
            the full risks and responsibilities associated with service
            provision, and the public sector limits its role to regulation.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Private health
        </docna>
        <display_title>Private health</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2003/06/2615787/private-health</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>Viewpoint</docty>
        <subtopic>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation,Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Housing &amp; Human Habitats,Health Systems Development &amp; Reform,Health Economics &amp; Finance</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Environment,Health, Nutrition and Population,Communities and Human Settlements</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000090341_20031016113749</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Health</subsc>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>Public policy for the private sector ; Note
            no. 264</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Environment,Health, Nutrition and Population,Communities and Human Settlements</historic_topic>
        <sectr>Health and other social services</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Private health care; Policy framework;
            Public sector; Private entities; Service delivery; Hospital
            management; Building maintenance; Building construction;
            Building renovation; Equipment acquisition planning;
            Ownership structure
            aging,certification,clinics,communities,comparative
            advantage,contraceptives,districts,doctors,employment,family
            planning,health care,health care provision,health care
            services,health facilities,Health Providers,Health
            Services,hospital buildings,Hospital
            Services,hospitals,nursing,occupancy,patients,policy
            environment,Primary Health Care,private sector,public
            health,public sector,quality
            standards,radiology,rehabilitation,risk sharing,rural
            communities,safety,Service delivery
        </keywd>
        <owner>Off of VP, FPD - WB (FPDVP)</owner>
        <repnb>26812</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Preventive Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Primary and Secondary Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Birth Spacing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Alternative Service Delivery</ml:concept><ml:concept>Contracting out</ml:concept><ml:concept>Business Process Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen Mapping</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Chains</ml:concept><ml:concept>Service Fees</ml:concept><ml:concept>Service Standards</ml:concept><ml:concept>Leasing law</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Longevity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Arms Length Agencies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Contracting Out</ml:concept><ml:concept>Service Delivery Arrangements</ml:concept><ml:concept>Service Standards, Service Fees</ml:concept><ml:concept>Checks on Executive Power</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen User Satisfaction Survey</ml:concept><ml:concept>Independent Commissions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ombudsmen</ml:concept><ml:concept>Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Parliament</ml:concept><ml:concept>Procurement Complaints Review Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supreme Audit Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Communities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Preventive Care</ml:concept><ml:concept>Family Planning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Contraceptives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subsidies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Outsourcing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Adminstrative Simplification</ml:concept><ml:concept>Adminstrative Simplification </ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Leasing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Health</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Aging</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Service Delivery</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Accountability Mechanisms</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>