<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>                                    Selling Sanitation&#13;
                                       in Vietnam&#13;
           An International&#13;
           partnership to help&#13;
           the poor gain sustained       What Works?&#13;
           access to improved&#13;
           water supply and&#13;
           sanitation services&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Water and Sanitation Program&#13;
&#13;
  East Asia and the Pacific&#13;
&#13;
        (WSP-EAP)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      January 2002&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                   ACKNOWLEDGMENTS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
This report is based on site reports and community data records prepared by researchers from ADCOM.&#13;
&#13;
Hoa Thi Hoang and Nguyen Cong Tranh supervised the work in Vietnam. Technical assistance for the&#13;
&#13;
methodology, training and documentation was provided from WSP-EAP's regional office.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Peer reviewers: Barbara Evans, Richard Pollard and Peter Kolsky, provided valuable comments and questions&#13;
&#13;
for further consideration.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Field team in Vietnam: Hoa Thi Hoang, Phung Xuan Bihn, Le Thi Thia, Bui Van Kiem, Nguyen Chau Loan,&#13;
&#13;
Le Xuan Thuy, Nguyen Tranh Phuc.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Selling Sanitation in Vietnam&#13;
&#13;
What Works?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Contents&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Preface . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Introduction . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .    5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
1. What influenced the demand for household latrines? . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .                               8&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
2. Demand, Coverage, Access : How it worked for the poor . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .                                   11&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
3. What benefits matter most to users? . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 17&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
4.  Is sanitation coverage linked to hygiene awareness? . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 22&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
5.  How long does it take to change behavior?. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 25&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
6.  What interventions were effective in changing behavior? . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 27&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
7.  What helps ensure sustained sanitation services?. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 29&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Learning and Recommendations . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 31&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Annex A - Participatory Tools used for investigation . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 34&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                                        1&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Preface&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Why country-specific studies on selling sanitation?         another kind of knowledge, i.e. what does make sanitation&#13;
&#13;
                                                            interventions work, in country and culture-specific settings?&#13;
&#13;
   It is widely acknowledged that by the end of the second  Examples of successful sanitation interventions are not&#13;
&#13;
millennium considerable progress has been made in the       abundantly available, though. Deliberately seeking out&#13;
&#13;
water supply situation in the developing world, but little  communities within a country where sanitation programs&#13;
&#13;
or no progress has been made in terms of sanitation         have had better than average outcomes and studying the&#13;
&#13;
improvements for much of the world's population.            factors associated with such outcomes can offer possible&#13;
&#13;
Consequently, despite heavy investments in clean water      country-specific insights to guide policy and strategy&#13;
&#13;
supply since the 1980s worldwide, gains in terms of         development, and identify ways to start translating policies&#13;
&#13;
community health and quality of life have been far lower    into practice. This is the rationale underlying the present&#13;
&#13;
than expected.                                              investigation in Vietnam.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   During the end of the 1990s several East Asian           Why participatory assessment studies?&#13;
&#13;
countries undertook nationally-led policy and strategy&#13;
&#13;
formulation efforts in the water and sanitation sector.         How policy-related research is to be conducted is a&#13;
&#13;
Country governments engaged in sanitation sector policy     second issue.&#13;
&#13;
development have drawn upon lessons amassed from&#13;
&#13;
global experience about why past sanitation interventions       Policy development is no longer seen as the exclusive&#13;
&#13;
have had so little impact. However, policy development is   precinct of few national top bureaucrats and international&#13;
&#13;
more than a matter of simply avoiding failed strategies of  consultants. With increasing recognition of the roles and&#13;
&#13;
the past. Communities being complex bio-cultural systems    influences of a range of stakeholders in the development&#13;
&#13;
and sanitation improvement being essentially a matter of    process, policy development is becoming more&#13;
&#13;
improving community hygiene behavior, sanitation            participatory. The Water and Sanitation Program ­ East&#13;
&#13;
promotion policies need to be crafted with reference to     Asia and Pacific (WSP-EAP) is privileged to assist the process&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
2&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
of sector policy development, improvement and                   government personnel, NGOs, donor agencies and private&#13;
&#13;
implementation in Cambodia, Laos, Indonesia, the                sector agencies engaged in the sector. Studies like the&#13;
&#13;
Philippines and Vietnam. The values guiding this work           present one bring into the process the voices of a hitherto&#13;
&#13;
are: optimal stakeholder participation, informed choice         excluded principal stakeholder group ­ the intended users&#13;
&#13;
by all concerned, national leadership and ownership of          of services, the poor men and women from rural&#13;
&#13;
the process and learning generated, national capacity           communities in different parts of the country. Through such&#13;
&#13;
development, bottom-up and horizontal knowledge                 studies their voices can reach national debates, raise&#13;
&#13;
sharing . The present study, executed and analyzed by a         questions about existing policies and suggest alternatives&#13;
&#13;
team of Vietnamese stakeholders and assisted technically        which may not otherwise have been contemplated.&#13;
&#13;
by WSP-EAP1, is a tool designed to promote these values.&#13;
&#13;
Similar studies have been carried out with country teams           For ultimate impact on the country's people, who&#13;
&#13;
and communities in Indonesia and Cambodia.                      learns what lessons from what local situations and&#13;
&#13;
                                                                exchanges is of greater importance than whether the&#13;
&#13;
   The findings of these studies are discussed and debated      learning generated adds unique new insights to the global&#13;
&#13;
at national stakeholder workshops where conclusions and         store of sector knowledge. This report documents the&#13;
&#13;
recommendations for policies and strategies emerge from         learning gained by sector stakeholders in Vietnam.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
1  Water and Sanitation Program ­ East Asia and the Pacific.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                         3&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Introduction&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                              early sanitation interventions did not last, because of&#13;
&#13;
                                                                              economic difficulties, the lack of required skills and&#13;
&#13;
                                                                              materials in the countryside, the war and the resulting&#13;
&#13;
                                                                              disruption of community life.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                    By the early 1990s, the Vietnamese economy began&#13;
&#13;
                                                                              to prosper. Village development boards started to forcefully&#13;
&#13;
                                                                              promote sanitation programs in an environment where&#13;
&#13;
                                                                              project assistance became more widely available. However,&#13;
&#13;
                                                                              the use of toilets and more particularly changes in hygiene&#13;
&#13;
    In the 1960s, agricultural cooperatives initiated                         behavior have tended to proceed slowly. The 1999 National&#13;
&#13;
promotional        campaigns           aimed        at   improving            Rural Water Supply and Sanitation Strategy (NRWSS) states:&#13;
&#13;
environmental sanitation in the northern countryside of                       "about 50 per cent of households have some form of latrine&#13;
&#13;
Vietnam. Campaigns such as the "Clean House ­ Fertile                         (the remaining 50% use a neighbor's latrine, or more&#13;
&#13;
Field" and "Building Three Sanitary Works: Water Wells,                       commonly practice open defecation. Most latrines are&#13;
&#13;
Bathrooms and Toilets" encouraged rural households to                         unhygienic, consisting mainly of single vault latrines (with&#13;
&#13;
increase agricultural production and improve sanitary                         the excreta removed regularly for use as fertilizer) or simple&#13;
&#13;
practices in rural areas. Initially, the Government                           pit latrines. About 20% of households have hygienic&#13;
&#13;
encouraged people to build double-vault composting                            sanitation"2 . The NRWSS further provides explanations for&#13;
&#13;
(DVC) latrines, which were both sanitary and a source of                      what are considered `hygienic' latrines based on practices&#13;
&#13;
night-soil for the agricultural cooperatives. However, the                    prevalent in Vietnam (see Box 2 in Chapter 2).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
2 National Rural Water Supply and Sanitation Strategy (NRWSS), Volume 1. The Socialist Republic of Vietnam. March 1999.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
4&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
    The NRWSS targets that 50 per cent of the country's                                 The quantitative data emerging from this study are&#13;
&#13;
households should have coverage with "hygienic"                                    from a small, purposive5 sample and therefore not&#13;
&#13;
sanitation facilities and 80 per cent with "domestic                               intended to be used for quantitative generalizations. They&#13;
&#13;
quality"3 water supply by 2005. This should facilitate                             are to be used for identifying patterns of demand, supply,&#13;
&#13;
widespread adoption of good personal hygiene behaviors.                            behaviors and situations associated with successful&#13;
&#13;
These figures are targeted to grow to universal coverage                           sanitation interventions, so that the underlying rationales&#13;
&#13;
with "clean water supply"4, "hygienic sanitation facilities"                       may be better understood and issues for policy and strategy&#13;
&#13;
and universal adoption of good hygiene behaviors by                                debates identified.&#13;
&#13;
2020.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                   Sample and Methods&#13;
&#13;
    How can sanitation habits that have been deeply rooted&#13;
&#13;
in people's ways of life be changed? What interventions                                 During November-December 2000, field research&#13;
&#13;
and time frames are needed to effect changes in sanitation                         teams went out to four communes in the provinces of&#13;
&#13;
behaviors? What relationships exist between sanitation                             Ninh Binh, Thanh Hoa and Thai Nguyen in northern&#13;
&#13;
behaviors and hygiene awareness? What factors motivate                             Vietnam. A total of 12 communities were selected where&#13;
&#13;
or discourage people from investing in their own sanitary                          there had been interventions from community sanitation&#13;
&#13;
latrines? What is needed to ensure the sustainability of                           projects, and which had achieved uncharacteristically high&#13;
&#13;
improved sanitation services?                                                      sanitation coverage rates as compared to the national&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                   average. The field study used additional criteria for&#13;
&#13;
    To find the answers to such questions, the WSP-EAP                             diversification of the sample to understand the influence&#13;
&#13;
consulted men and women in 12 communities in three                                 of geographical locations (mountains, plains and coastal&#13;
&#13;
provinces of Vietnam, which had unusually high sanitation                          areas) on hygiene behavior patterns.&#13;
&#13;
coverage rates as compared to the national average. These&#13;
&#13;
communities, labeled by local governments as "sanitation                                In each community, the study team used a combination&#13;
&#13;
success stories" typically had coverage rates (with any kind                       of techniques to find out why these communities were more&#13;
&#13;
of latrines) at 80 to 100 per cent of households in the                            successful than others in increasing sanitation coverage.&#13;
&#13;
communities, compared to a national average for                                    The field team used a specific sequence of open-ended&#13;
&#13;
sanitation of only about 50 per cent, at the time of the                           investigation tools including community focus groups,&#13;
&#13;
study. It was hoped that investigating how they achieved                           observation, in-depth interviews, and activities drawn from&#13;
&#13;
the present situation would provide insights about what it                         the repertoires of Methodology for Participatory Assessments&#13;
&#13;
takes to scale up successful sanitation programs in Vietnam.                       (MPA), Participatory Rural Appraisal (PRA) and Participatory&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
3   Water that is adequate for domestic use, but requires further treatment before it can be used for drinking.&#13;
4   Water that meets the national drinking water quality standards (in the process of being defined) and is considered safe to drink without further treatment.&#13;
5   A sample of respondents, groups or communities chosen based on the purpose to be served by the informants. A purposive or judgment sample is a&#13;
    nonprobability one, selected not by chance but based on the researcher's judgment in order to reflect the things the researcher is interested in studying.&#13;
    Qualitative research on special populations (e.g. first-time mothers of Asian-American origin in USA, practitioners of herbal medicine in China , East&#13;
    European communities that experienced religious and ethnic violence over the last 5 years, communities that have unusually high sanitation coverage rates,&#13;
    in a particular country) rely on purposive sampling.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                              5&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Hygiene and Sanitation Transformation (PHAST)                      documented evidence is available about why some&#13;
&#13;
methodologies (see Annex A for details). The field study           sanitation interventions succeed.&#13;
&#13;
team also worked with local government personnel,&#13;
&#13;
including heads of hamlets, Women's Union staff, health            A Vietnam-specific exploration of what works is the&#13;
&#13;
department staff, and rural population planning staff that         aim. What works or has worked in another country&#13;
&#13;
accompanied some of the teams as observers.                        may not apply to Vietnam as sanitation is a behavioral&#13;
&#13;
                                                                   issue embedded in local culture and practices.&#13;
&#13;
    In each community the researchers met with key&#13;
&#13;
individuals and groups of men and women at times and               For identifying the range of possibly diverse and not&#13;
&#13;
places of their convenience, over a period of 3-5 days.            fully predictable factors associated with "successful&#13;
&#13;
Groups varied in size between 10 and 30 people for                 sanitation" in Vietnam it is more efficient and cost-&#13;
&#13;
different assessment activities. The assessment process thus       effective to study known high coverage cases (in the&#13;
&#13;
involved an average number of 150-180 people per                   absence of other indicators for success), instead of&#13;
&#13;
community. Since the populations of the communities                studying a sample representing good, bad and&#13;
&#13;
visited ranged between 63 and 202 households, this                 average cases in the country.&#13;
&#13;
meant that the process covered approximately 50 per cent&#13;
&#13;
of the adult populations of the communities. Poverty               Ninh Thang is a densely populated commune typical&#13;
&#13;
targeting methods were employed to ensure that the             of the northern plains. The majority of its population are&#13;
&#13;
groups met represented both the poor and the non-poor          agricultural peasants. Some also do carpentry, lace-&#13;
&#13;
categories of households. For topics considered sensitive      making and construction work. Quang Thai is a coastal&#13;
&#13;
to gender issues, assessment was done in gender-               commune with little cultivable land. Over half the&#13;
&#13;
segregated groups.                                             population is engaged in fishing, the rest being peasants&#13;
&#13;
                                                               and handicraft producers. It is getting increasingly difficult&#13;
&#13;
    The decision to explore patterns associated with "success  to survive only on fishing. Many handicraft workers have&#13;
&#13;
stories" rather than use classic comparative studies of        lost their jobs since the collapse of the Soviet Union and&#13;
&#13;
successful and unsuccessful examples was based on three        the Eastern European Treaty by 1990. There is a strong&#13;
&#13;
considerations :                                               out migration trend from Quang Thai in search of&#13;
&#13;
                                                               alternative livelihoods. Two communes in the Phu Luong&#13;
&#13;
    Substantial global research evidence already exists        district are in the mountains, where agriculture, livestock&#13;
&#13;
    about why sanitation programs fail, but little             rearing and forestry are the principal livelihoods.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
6&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Participating Communities&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The following 12 communities were included.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table 1: Communities participating in the assessment&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Community                      No. of Households            Last Project          Geographical&#13;
&#13;
                                in the Community            Intervention              Zone&#13;
&#13;
 Province of Ninh Binh&#13;
&#13;
 Commune of Ninh Thang :&#13;
&#13;
 Hamlet 1                               63             UNICEF, in 1985 and 1998      Plains&#13;
&#13;
 Hamlet 2                               105            UNICEF, in 1985 and 1998      Plains&#13;
&#13;
 Hamlet 4                               111            UNICEF, in 1985 and 1998      Plains&#13;
&#13;
 Hamlet 5                               108            UNICEF, in 1985 and 1998      Plains&#13;
&#13;
 Hamlet 8                               83             UNICEF, in 1985 and 1998      Plains&#13;
&#13;
 Province of Thanh Hoa&#13;
&#13;
 Commune of Quang Thai:&#13;
&#13;
 Hamlet 3                               153               UNICEF, 1997-98            Coast&#13;
&#13;
 Hamlet 6                               166               UNICEF, 1997-98            Coast&#13;
&#13;
 Hamlet 7                               202               UNICEF, 1997-98            Coast&#13;
&#13;
 Hamlet 9                               117               UNICEF, 1997-98            Coast&#13;
&#13;
 Hamlet 10                              167               UNICEF, 1997-98            Coast&#13;
&#13;
 Province of Thai Nguyen&#13;
&#13;
 Hamlet 11, Ban Cai in Yen&#13;
&#13;
 Trach commune                          68                  CIDSE, 1996             Mountains&#13;
&#13;
 Hamlet 12, Xom Ha in Yen&#13;
&#13;
 Do commune                             60                  CIDSE, 1996             Mountains&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                7&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
1.        What influenced the demand&#13;
          for household latrines?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Discussions with mixed-gender focus groups of 25 ­        activities in Vietnam. In all the communes participating in&#13;
&#13;
30 villagers were used to explore people's perceptions        this assessment, local governments have been involved in&#13;
&#13;
about what factors influenced household demand. All           numerous interventions aimed at improving hygiene&#13;
&#13;
household latrines in the villages had been financed          awareness and sanitation coverage. Such interventions&#13;
&#13;
partially or fully by the household owners. After the social  included:&#13;
&#13;
mapping exercise had identified all the households owning&#13;
                                                                  Mass education campaigns to improve hygiene&#13;
latrines, the questions used to initiate group discussions&#13;
                                                                  awareness and practices in the community, including&#13;
were: "Why did people in this commune acquire household&#13;
                                                                  the organization of "Commune Cleaning Day".&#13;
latrines?" and "Why did the others (the non-owners) not&#13;
                                                                  (Hygiene education and community mobilization&#13;
do so?" In the ensuing discussions, factors that had helped&#13;
                                                                  through IEC activities are considered very important in&#13;
or hindered community demand for household latrines&#13;
                                                                  Vietnam for the creation of demand for sanitation&#13;
were identified. Some were planned interventions, some&#13;
                                                                  facilities. The NRWSS states this strongly. Local&#13;
related to the overall country situation and some others&#13;
                                                                  authorities everywhere in the study areas also made&#13;
were found to be connected with local livelihoods.&#13;
                                                                  this observation).&#13;
&#13;
                                                                  The collection of excreta, and solid waste for site&#13;
What promoted demand for household latrines&#13;
                                                                  treatment by encouraging the construction of family&#13;
&#13;
                                                                  latrines and public dump sites. This was done by:&#13;
    In the 12 communities the factors that were most&#13;
                                                                  -   setting construction targets as key goal for the village&#13;
commonly perceived to have helped increase the demand&#13;
                                                                      to achieve&#13;
for latrines were: (i) the role of the local government&#13;
                                                                  -   getting families and community organizations to&#13;
authorities, and (ii) an increase in community awareness&#13;
                                                                      commit to construction targets, and&#13;
of sanitation as an improved way of life. Table 2 lists the&#13;
                                                                  -   stringent monitoring of the construction against&#13;
factors identified by 12 community focus groups in&#13;
                                                                      commitments made.&#13;
decreasing order of mention.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                  Health staff and local government personnel setting&#13;
&#13;
    Local government leadership: Villagers explained that         good examples themselves by building and&#13;
&#13;
local governments play an important role in community             maintaining sanitary latrines in their own homes.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
8&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
   Improvement of sanitation awareness: In all the 12                              factor may promote or inhibit demand depending on&#13;
&#13;
communities focus groups emphasized that economic                                  the technology and design of latrines being promoted.&#13;
&#13;
prosperity contributed significantly to increased awareness.&#13;
                                                                                   Economic prosperity: Living conditions have improved&#13;
As economic growth accelerated, rural people gained&#13;
                                                                                   since the Doi Moi (economic liberalization) policy&#13;
greater contact with the outside world which brought in&#13;
                                                                                   reforms were introduced, which has resulted in an&#13;
new ideas about sanitation standards and behavior.&#13;
                                                                                   increased demand for basic services and better&#13;
Beyond the simple purpose of collecting excreta, latrines&#13;
                                                                                   housing, including latrines.&#13;
are increasingly recognized as a means to improve&#13;
&#13;
cleanliness and comfort in daily life.                                             Increasing population pressure on land, which has&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                   reduced the availability of sites for open defecation.&#13;
   Other motivating factors that were felt to have increased&#13;
                                                                                   Reputation with neighbors and guests: The desire to&#13;
the demand for household latrines were :&#13;
                                                                                   be considered modern, save face with guests, and get&#13;
   Project assistance: Project assistance helped a number                          respect from neighbors can also be an important factor&#13;
   of families in constructing pour-flush latrines by                              that can influence the decision to build a latrine.&#13;
   providing toilet pans, steel bars and cement. In some&#13;
                                                                                   Availability of building materials and construction skills:&#13;
   areas, as in Phu Luong, projects also provided&#13;
                                                                                   In 5 out of the 12 communities, the availability of&#13;
   financial assistance such as credit schemes to help&#13;
                                                                                   building materials and local masons was reported to&#13;
   poorer households build their own latrines.&#13;
                                                                                   have helped fuel an increasing demand for latrines&#13;
   The use of human waste as a supply of night soil. In                            after project assistance had ceased. This has not&#13;
   many areas night soil is still used as fertilizer-making                        happened in all the communities.&#13;
   latrines necessary for its collection and storage. This&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table 2: Factors influencing demand for household latrines&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   Factors that positively influenced demand for household                                                   Frequency of identification&#13;
   latrines, according to community focus groups                                                           of the factor in 12 focus groups&#13;
                                                                                                                    in 12 communities&#13;
&#13;
   Promotional and monitoring role of the local governmental and&#13;
        medical authorities                                                                                                      12&#13;
&#13;
   Improvement in people's sanitation awareness                                                                                  12&#13;
&#13;
   Project assistance (materials support in all communities, financial&#13;
        support in 2 out of 12 communities)*                                                                                      9&#13;
&#13;
   Latrine design suited to the practice of using human waste as fertilizer&#13;
        (refers to double and single vault latrines)                                                                              9&#13;
&#13;
   Rising expectations for more comfortable and convenient living conditions                                                      8&#13;
&#13;
   Increased population and limited land availability making it difficult to&#13;
        find places for outdoor defecation                                                                                        7&#13;
&#13;
   Reputation with neighbors and guests                                                                                           7&#13;
&#13;
   Availability of building material and builders in the community                                                                5&#13;
&#13;
*  In Ninh Thang commune: 1 cement pan, steel bars and a bag of cement to interested households + 1 free sample toilet built by the project per community.&#13;
   In Quang Thai commune: 7-8 cement pans per community. In Phu Luong district: 1 ceramic pan, 150,000 VND in cash and technical guidance to each&#13;
   interested household.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                        9&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
What inhibited the demand for household latrines?                   where only one type of latrine design was promoted. In&#13;
&#13;
                                                                    the mountainous communes it was observed that many&#13;
&#13;
    A number of factors that were identified by the                 households that had built pour-flush latrines with project&#13;
&#13;
community focus groups to have worked against the                   assistance later modified the design to facilitate easy access&#13;
&#13;
emergence of a demand for household latrines are listed             to excreta, usually compromising the quality of the original&#13;
&#13;
in Table 3, in decreasing order of importance.                      design.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Lack of financial resources: In 9 of the 12                         Preference for traditional practices of defecation&#13;
&#13;
communities, lack of resources was mentioned as a major             outdoors: This factor was stated to have hindered demand&#13;
&#13;
factor that hindered households from having their own               in 4 of the 12 communities. Interestingly, all these&#13;
&#13;
latrine. Poor households reported being unable to save              communities are located on sea beaches. The sand dunes&#13;
&#13;
or access sufficient cash resources to pay the costs of             on the beach serve as highly preferred defecation sites.&#13;
&#13;
latrines. During 1999-2000 a pour-flush latrine cost VND            There is even a local saying in these communities which&#13;
&#13;
500,000 ­ 2,000,000 to build. A double-vault latrine                reflects their preference, i.e. : "First the dunes, second the&#13;
&#13;
was VND 300,000 ­ 700,000. The current minimum daily                fields." It is worth noting that the beach communities were&#13;
&#13;
wage rate for unskilled labor is VND 10,000 ­ 15,000                also the ones with little cultivable land and over half the&#13;
&#13;
per day in different provinces (14,000 Vietnamese Dong              population dependent on fishing. Thus agriculture was&#13;
&#13;
= US$1 in 2001).                                                    not a major livelihood there and subsequently demand&#13;
&#13;
                                                                    for night soil was low.&#13;
&#13;
    Latrine design and technology that interfered with&#13;
&#13;
local practices: Latrine designs were often too rigid.&#13;
                                                                        Box 1&#13;
Programs urged people in the plains, coastal areas and&#13;
&#13;
mountainous regions to build pour-flush latrines ­ while                On a visit to a fishing family in Thanh Hoa, the&#13;
&#13;
local practices of fertilizing crop fields still require a regular      host, when asked why he did not build a latrine,&#13;
&#13;
supply of night soil and many communities still lack access             answered that even if he did so, everyone would&#13;
to a regular water supply close to home, especially in the&#13;
                                                                        use it except him. He preferred to defecate on the&#13;
dry season. In 9 of the 12 communities, lack of regular&#13;
&#13;
access to night soil due to latrine design was identified an            beach because it was more spacious and convenient&#13;
&#13;
important factor that dampened people's desire to construct             and he "was not interested in using a latrine".&#13;
&#13;
and use pour-flush latrines, especially in those communities&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table 3: Factors inhibiting demand for household latrines&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Inhibiting factors                                                                               Frequency of&#13;
                                                                                              identification of the factor&#13;
                                                                                                 in 12 focus groups in&#13;
                                                                                                    12 communities&#13;
&#13;
    Economic constraints                                                                                    9&#13;
&#13;
    Design does not facilitate access to night soil                                                         9&#13;
&#13;
    Continuing preference for outdoor defecation (beach, dunes, fields)                                     4&#13;
&#13;
    Lack of awareness/promotion of alternative latrine designs                                              3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
10&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
2.        Demand, Coverage, Access:&#13;
          How it worked for the poor&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                          All communes were selected because of their success&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                     in increasing sanitation coverage to levels well above the&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                     estimated national average of 50 per cent6. To verify the&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                     coverage figures and people's access to latrines, Social&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                     mapping was used in each community. In this study a&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                     household is considered to have "coverage" when at least&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                     one latrine physically present in the household. A&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                     household has "access" to sanitation when members of&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                     the household' are able to use a latrine regularly, either&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                     through owning one or by sharing someone else's latrine.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                          The resulting access situation is illustrated in Figure 1,&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                     for households classified in three welfare categories as&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                     RICH of Better-off, AVERAGE or Middle-income and POOR.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                     These categories do not represent standard definitions of&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                     well-being and may vary between communities. People&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                     used locally relevant criteria to define them. The validity of&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                     the definitions lies in the fact that only local residents of a&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                     community can know who are really the poor and why7.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
6 The NRWSS offers only an estimate of cover. No national statistics on coverage or access and no definition of the terms are cited.&#13;
7 Although the criteria varied from one community to another, typically "Rich" households were defined as those whose income ensures that daily expenditure&#13;
  is easily met and there is enough leftover for substantial saving annually. They can thus construct durable dwellings such as two-story houses with kitchen,&#13;
  bathroom, wells and pour-flush toilets. Household assets include color TV, motorbike and other funiture. Middle-income households typically tend to have&#13;
  sufficient income for daily expenditure, but their annual savings are not substantial. They have access to smaller durable dwellings with bathroom, kitchen and&#13;
  well. Households assets include black and white TV and motorbike. Poor households generally have incomes, with no possibility to save money. They have&#13;
  no furniture, television or means of transportation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                                                              11&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Figure 1: Households having Access to Latrines&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figures for the middle-income group are used for sorting   Coverage is not synonymous to access&#13;
&#13;
communities on the graph below, since it constituted the&#13;
&#13;
biggest sub-group in the sample of households.                 After all latrines owned by individual households&#13;
&#13;
                                                           had been marked on the map prepared by community&#13;
&#13;
   As Figure 1 shows, access to latrines was very high     members, they were asked to place pieces of string&#13;
&#13;
in Ninh Thang (plains) and Phu Luong (hills) for all       around latrines that were regularly shared by more than&#13;
&#13;
household categories, whereas great variations in access   one household, encircling all households together with&#13;
&#13;
characterized the coastal Quang Thai communities.          the latrine they shared. All such encircled households&#13;
&#13;
There were large variations in poverty within the          were then counted to arrive at access figures.&#13;
&#13;
communities, which seems to be also reflected in their&#13;
&#13;
sanitation access rates (Figure 1). Welfare differentials      Overall in the 12 communities, 87 per cent of the&#13;
&#13;
were largest in coastal Quang Thai where 20 to 40 per      rich households owned a toilet, compared to 71 per&#13;
&#13;
cent were classified as poor. In Ninh Thang and Phu        cent of middle-income households and only 45 per cent&#13;
&#13;
Luong poverty seemed less widespread and the bulk of       of poor households. A comparison of access rates in&#13;
&#13;
the population fell in the middle-income category. Low     Figure 1 with the coverage (ownership) of household&#13;
&#13;
access rates in Quang Thai as compared to elsewhere        latrines in Figure 2 reveals the pattern of sharing latrine&#13;
&#13;
could also be related to these communities being located   usage among households, since access rates are&#13;
&#13;
on beaches where sand dunes provide traditionally          consistently higher than ownership. Coverage monitoring&#13;
&#13;
preferred defecation sites.                                tends to routinely miss this fact.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
12&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Figure 2: Households Owning Latrines&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  BOX 2&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  "Hygienic latrines are those that protect both users and other members of the public from infection from the feces in&#13;
   Hygienic latrines&#13;
  the latrine. The degree of protection provided is a combination of the basic type of latrine, its cleanliness and how&#13;
  the waste is reused. The term can only be applied to individual systems and not to types of technology (such as DVC&#13;
  latrine) since the hygiene of a particular latrine depends on the use/operation as much as on the technology".&#13;
&#13;
  "Unhygienic systems, which are to be actively discouraged by Information, Education and Communication (IEC) are:&#13;
  Traditional pit latrines (a hole in the ground covered with logs), Over-water latrines (latrine placed directly over a&#13;
  surface water source where the water is used for other purposes) and Single vault latrines (a sealed vault where waste&#13;
  is stored and regularly removed)".&#13;
&#13;
  "Simple systems, which are not promoted by the Strategy and will not attract grants or loans are: Improved pit latrines&#13;
  (pit latrines with some form of cement or ceramic flooring".&#13;
&#13;
  "Improved systems (high household service level) are Sulabh latrines (pour flush latrines with offset composting pits),&#13;
  Double vault composting (DVC) latrines (two sealed vaults usually at least partly above ground level. One vault is in&#13;
  operation while the other is full of composting waste); Improved fishpond latrines (a sanitation system located on a&#13;
  household fishpond, where the water is not used for other purposes and is not connected to other surface water&#13;
  sources);&#13;
&#13;
  "Septic tanks (sealed tanks) where solids settle and are partially treated. The partially treated liquid waste overflows&#13;
  and either soaks away into the ground, or more commonly in Vietnam, is used as fertilizer".&#13;
&#13;
  "Piped sewerage (underground network of gravity sewers, may be combined with surface or grey water drainage) is&#13;
  not considered appropriate for rural areas at the present time".&#13;
&#13;
                                        -- Annex D- Technologies. National Rural Water Supply and Sanitation Strategy,&#13;
                                                                                The Socialist Republic of Vietnam, 1999&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                         13&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
    Sharing of latrines seems to be inversely related to       coastal Quang Thai (hamlets 3, 6, 7, 9, 10) although&#13;
&#13;
coverage but is also influenced by social status, and local    coverage is lowest, the rich do not share latrines while&#13;
&#13;
livelihoods. It is most common in the plains of Ninh Thang     only 4-5 per cent of the other groups do.&#13;
&#13;
(hamlets 1,2,4,5,8), where household ownership of latrines&#13;
&#13;
is between 65 and 90 per cent, and the mainly agricultural     What kind of access have the poor gained?&#13;
&#13;
population depends on the latrines for a regular supply&#13;
&#13;
of night soil. As many as 38 per cent of the poor                  In comparison to estimated national averages, the&#13;
&#13;
households in Ninh Thang share latrines with neighbors,        coverage and access rates of household latrines in these&#13;
&#13;
compared to 18 per cent of the middle-income group             communities can be considered impressive. However, for&#13;
&#13;
and only 8 per cent of the rich.                               community health impact concerns, it is important to also&#13;
&#13;
                                                               examine how hygienically the facilities are used and&#13;
&#13;
    Latrines are rarely shared in the mountainous Phu          maintained. In view of the practices and conditions&#13;
&#13;
Luong hamlets (Xom Ha and Ban cai), where household            prevalent in rural Vietnam, the National Rural Water Supply&#13;
&#13;
ownership of latrines is already nearly 100 per cent. In       and Sanitation Strategy (NRWSS) stresses the promotion&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Figure 3 : Access to different types of households sanitation facilities for "Rich", "Middle-income" and "Poor"&#13;
&#13;
                 households in the 12 communities&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   POOR HOUSEHOLDS                                            MIDDLE-INCOME HOUSEHOLDS&#13;
                      (22% of sample)                                                  (59% of sample)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    RICH HOUSEHOLDS&#13;
                        (19% of sample)&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                     Pour-flush toilet&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                     Double vault compositing toilet&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                     Single vault toilet&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                     Open pit dug hole&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                     Sharing neighbors' toilet&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                     Practising open defacation&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
14&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
of sanitation facilities that are less open to the possibility   a quarter of the middle-income group and only 4 per&#13;
&#13;
of unhygienic usage. It provides the following definitions       cent of the poor households did so. 42 per cent of the&#13;
&#13;
to clarify the task.                                             poor households still practice open air defecation. Their&#13;
&#13;
                                                                 access to latrines mostly means using lower level facilities&#13;
&#13;
    It is recognized that facilities in themselves are not       like open pit dug holes and single vault latrines. Although&#13;
&#13;
"hygienic" or "unhygienic" and it is the way they are used       12 per cent of the poor share the use of neighbors' latrines,&#13;
&#13;
and maintained that makes them so. The NRWSS argues              it is likely that their neighbors, also poor, own only systems&#13;
&#13;
that popular practices related to the reuse of human excreta     classified as "unhygienic" or "simple" systems by the&#13;
&#13;
in Vietnam make it relevant to thus categorize types of          NRWSS. The middle income group, which constituted&#13;
&#13;
latrines for strategy and policy purposes. The study looked      nearly 60 per cent of the sample households, also uses&#13;
&#13;
into the actual use of all types of latrines found in the        predominantly these very systems.&#13;
&#13;
sample communities and did actually find very high risk&#13;
&#13;
unhygienic practices associated with the use of pit latrines,         Examination of access to latrine types by communities&#13;
&#13;
both single and double vault latrines and also pour-flush        shows that the access of the poor to improved systems like&#13;
&#13;
latrines (see section 4 in this report: Is sanitation coverage   pour flush or double vault composting facilities was&#13;
&#13;
linked to hygiene awareness?). Figure 3 shows the access         appreciably high only in 2 out of 12 communities (Figure&#13;
&#13;
to different types of latrines, by socioeconomic categories.     4). These were both in Phu Luong, where financial help&#13;
&#13;
                                                                 had been made available from the sanitation project in&#13;
&#13;
    Over the past decade sanitation projects in all the          the form of a credit scheme. No other hamlets in the study&#13;
&#13;
communities tried to promote the use of pour-flush latrines,     had financial assistance schemes. The CIDSE project&#13;
&#13;
which seems to have mainly benefited the better-off              provided each Phu Luong hamlet a fund of VND&#13;
&#13;
households. In the study areas 46 per cent of the rich           12,000,000, if the community could raise VND 3,000,000&#13;
&#13;
households and 18 per cent of the middle income                  from its own resources. The total amount is managed by&#13;
&#13;
households have them, but only 3 per cent of the poor            the development committee of the hamlet. Households&#13;
&#13;
do.                                                              may borrow funds to build latrines or other economic&#13;
&#13;
                                                                 activities, at 1.5% per month interest. Very poor households&#13;
&#13;
    Ownership of, and access to "improved systems" such          may be further assisted with payment for their labor&#13;
&#13;
as pour flush and DVC latrines is evidently related to           contributions to other community members. Repayments&#13;
&#13;
socioeconomic status. A little more than half of the rich        are scheduled so that people can pay after harvest or by&#13;
&#13;
households in the sample had access to them. Less than           selling offspring of livestock.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    The experience from 12 communities suggests that a significant increase in the access of poor households to&#13;
&#13;
improved sanitation facilities may require special forms of financial assistance tailored to local livelihoods and targeted&#13;
&#13;
to the really poor within communities by the community's own institutions. It raises the question whether sanitation&#13;
&#13;
projects should therefore routinely explore and test alternatives for targeting the poorest households within communities.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                             15&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
  Figure 4 : Percentage of Ownership of different types of latrines by rich, middle-income and poor households&#13;
&#13;
             in the 12 communities&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
16&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
3. What benefits matter most to users?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                 Benefits from the use of household latrines were&#13;
&#13;
                                                             identified in discussions held separately with groups of&#13;
&#13;
                                                             men and women in the 12 communities. They were first&#13;
&#13;
                                                             asked whether they had experienced any changes in their&#13;
&#13;
                                                             lives after starting to use latrines. The ensuing discussion&#13;
&#13;
                                                             helped identify what those changes (benefits) were. An&#13;
&#13;
                                                             MPA tool (Ladder 1 ­ see Annex A) was then used to help&#13;
&#13;
                                                             them assess the extent to which their expectations of each&#13;
&#13;
                                                             benefit was being satisfied, as well as their perceptions of&#13;
&#13;
                                                             the value of each benefit compared to the costs incurred&#13;
&#13;
                                                             in constructing and using latrines. Group conclusions and&#13;
&#13;
                                                             scores from the 12 communities are summarized in Figure&#13;
&#13;
                                                             5 and Table 4.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Figure 5: Frequency of mention of types of benefits in 24 focus groups of men and women&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                       17&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
    In general, women and men identified a similar set of                                 Cleanliness was an almost equally valued benefit,&#13;
&#13;
benefits, but differed in the extent to which they perceived                         stated by both men and women in all 12 communities.&#13;
&#13;
the value of some of those benefits to them. Women valued                            They said that having latrines means a cleaner environment&#13;
&#13;
more than men the benefits of convenience and cleanliness                            overall. Homes with latrines do not have excreta lying&#13;
&#13;
of the home. Men valued more the economic benefits of                                around and do not smell bad. A household without a&#13;
&#13;
night soil availability and avoidance of conflict with                               latrine can be a source of unpleasant smells, which can&#13;
&#13;
neighbors (Table 4).                                                                 lead to conflicts with neighbors. Peace with neighbors was&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                     a benefit perceived more often by men. On the other hand,&#13;
&#13;
    Groups in all communities agreed that the most                                   the esthetic benefits of a clean, smell-free home&#13;
&#13;
important advantages of having a household latrine are:                              environment appealed more to women than men, who&#13;
&#13;
a) its positive impact on health and related cost-savings                            gave it a higher value for cost score. Convenience was&#13;
&#13;
and b) clean, smell-free homes. They said that using                                 ranked as the second most important benefit. It is more&#13;
&#13;
latrines had helped prevent intestinal worms and diarrhea                            convenient to have indoor latrines that one may use at&#13;
&#13;
and made it possible to avoid epidemics. This saved large                            any time of the day or night, avoiding the need to walk to&#13;
&#13;
sums of money that the family would otherwise have                                   a defecation site away from the home, and hence saving&#13;
&#13;
incurred on medical costs.                                                           time, energy and effort. It also protects against inclement&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
  Box 3&#13;
   "By using manufactured, modern drugs human diseases may be treated quickly, but these drugs treat only the&#13;
  symptoms. Traditional medicines are more effective because they attack the root causes of diseases. When we use&#13;
  human excreta to fertilize tobacco or rice crops, it works more like traditional medicine. You can see that the plants&#13;
  look greener and have more flavor, than if we use chemical fertilizers".&#13;
                                                                                                            - men's group in Quang Thai commune&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table 4: Perceived benefits of household latrines in the 12 communities&#13;
&#13;
  Perceived benefits of having one's own                                                             Total scores* from 12 communities&#13;
  household latrine                                                                           Men's scores                           Women's scores&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                        Benefit            Value for             Benefit           Value for&#13;
                                                                                         score             cost score             score            cost score&#13;
&#13;
  Overall health protection (prevention from intestinal&#13;
  worms, epidemics, drinking water pollution, medical                                     115                 116                  116                 120&#13;
  service cost saving)&#13;
&#13;
  Cleanliness (clean houses, roads, fields; avoidance of                                  108                 103                  114                 117&#13;
  unpleasant smalls and flies)&#13;
&#13;
  Convenience (including privacy)                                                           67                  65                  81                  91&#13;
&#13;
  Night soil (freely available, fertilizer cost saving)                                     35                  42                  45                  37&#13;
&#13;
  Avoidance of conflicts with neighbors                                                     20                  22                  12                  10&#13;
&#13;
  Safety (from illnesses, weather, accidents)                                               10                  10                    7                    6&#13;
&#13;
  Time saving                                                                                6                    8                           N/A&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
*   In a group assessment session, the maximum possible Benefit score is 10. A benefit that was given the maximum score possible by men's or women's groups&#13;
    in all 12 communities would get a Total Benefit score of 120. A high Total Benefit Score means that the benefit is perceived by more community groups and&#13;
    that their expectations regarding the benefit are being met to a high extent. The same rule applies to Value for Cost scores. When the Benefit score and Value&#13;
    for cost score are equal in any community, or in the total, it means that the perceived benefit is considered fully worth the cost. A higher Value for Cost score&#13;
    implies that the perceived value of the benefit exceeds costs incurred for it, and vice versa. "N/A" means "not mentioned".&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
18&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
weather - especially important for children and the elderly    and could be better utilized in marketing strategies.&#13;
&#13;
at night. Women's groups everywhere included privacy&#13;
&#13;
and security benefits while discussing "convenience". They         Similar findings have been reported from many&#13;
&#13;
cited many examples of the problems they used to               countries. It is beginning to be recognized internationally&#13;
&#13;
encounter related to lack of privacy and insecurity before     that sanitation programs require less educational and&#13;
&#13;
they got their latrines. This explained women's higher value   more promotional approaches and that sanitation&#13;
&#13;
for cost score for `convenience'.                              interventions are more successful when they first try to&#13;
&#13;
                                                               find out what motivating forces work for local populations&#13;
&#13;
    The fourth major benefit perceived by the groups was       in bringing about behavioral change. Such&#13;
&#13;
the supply of night soil from latrines. People equated the     understanding however is not yet widespread in&#13;
&#13;
need of plants for night soil to people's need for medicines.  institutions that plan and implement sanitation projects.&#13;
&#13;
In most discussion groups the value of human excreta for       Country-specific studies such as this one can be used to&#13;
&#13;
agriculture was strongly emphasized. Quang Thai                gather indigenous evidence that can raise questions&#13;
&#13;
peasants even claimed that night soil markedly improved        about conventional approaches which are exclusively&#13;
&#13;
the flavor of tobacco crops.                                   `health education-based'.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    A comparison of Tables 2 and 4 shows that the forces       Cost-Benefit Perceptions&#13;
&#13;
that motivated people to acquire a latrine were not always&#13;
&#13;
similar to the benefits they perceived to be deriving from         Projects that were active in each of the communities&#13;
&#13;
them after they owned and used them for some time.             did require a substantial contribution of the households&#13;
&#13;
Despite the fact that in Vietnam latrines had been             themselves. In Ninh Thang, project assistance was limited&#13;
&#13;
promoted primarily as a health-improving facility, health      to the provision of hygiene awareness programs, a&#13;
&#13;
protection and cleanliness were not mentioned as initial       number of packages consisting of a cement pan, steel&#13;
&#13;
motivators of demand to get a latrine. They were, however,     pipe and a bag of cement and the construction of one&#13;
&#13;
perceived as major benefits once a household did get           demonstration latrine per community. In Quang Thai, a&#13;
&#13;
one and used it for some time. Possibly, messages about        small number of toilet pans were distributed within the&#13;
&#13;
latrines improving health are only believed when such          community, which only benefited a small percentage of&#13;
&#13;
benefits are personally experienced. On the other hand,        households, whereas in Phu Luong each household was&#13;
&#13;
convenience, access to night soil, and to a lesser extent,     provided with a toilet pan and cash assistance of VND&#13;
&#13;
prestige with neighbors were identified by groups both as      150,000 (US$11), when the average price of a household&#13;
&#13;
important motivators to get a latrine, as well as valued       latrine in Phu Luong at the time was US$20. Timeline&#13;
&#13;
benefits once people had acquired and started using their      explorations with community groups in all the 12 cases&#13;
&#13;
latrines. The implication for marketing latrines is that one   revealed that coverage with "improved systems" was very&#13;
&#13;
needs to find out and take advantage of whatever motivates     low until the early 1990s. Before that people mostly used&#13;
&#13;
a community to acquire their own facilities.                   traditional pit latrines, defecated in piggeries or practiced&#13;
&#13;
                                                               open defecation. The minority that were better off had&#13;
&#13;
    The findings suggest that sanitation promotion could       DVC latrines.&#13;
&#13;
be made more effective by not focusing promotion&#13;
&#13;
exclusively on health benefits which only become evident           As explained earlier, the study used an MPA tool to&#13;
&#13;
to users after a period of use. Other motivating factors       measure how worthwhile latrine owners thought their&#13;
&#13;
such as convenience, availability of night soil and social     investment had been for them. Women gave somewhat&#13;
&#13;
prestige or reputation with neighbors and guests may have      higher value for cost scores to their latrines, indicating&#13;
&#13;
greater appeal for first time buyers of latrines in Vietnam,   that they thought the facility was more worth its cost than&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                         19&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
the men did. The overall results showed that both men                           Xom Ha. Dissatisfaction with pour-flush latrines in some&#13;
&#13;
and women perceived the benefits from the use of sanitary                       communities was also due to poor quality of the latrine&#13;
&#13;
latrines to have exceeded the cash and labor costs incurred                     design resulting in blocked and therefore stinking toilets,&#13;
&#13;
in constructing them. In their experience, the cost of                          and due to the construction materials used. Many women&#13;
&#13;
building a household latrines works out to be lower than                        complained about the difficulty to keep cement pans of the&#13;
&#13;
the medical expenses incurred by an average family in 1-                        toilet clean, specially in Xom Ha commune of Phu Luong&#13;
&#13;
2 years, for treating illnesses resulting from lack of latrines                 where pour-flush was the only design promoted but water&#13;
&#13;
and improper sanitation. They think it has been a good                          supply close to homes was not simultaneously assured.&#13;
&#13;
investment (Table 4).&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                     People were only about 50% satisfied with their single&#13;
&#13;
    While men and women reported discussing the matter                          and double vault latrines, which were common in the&#13;
&#13;
together before deciding to acquire a household latrine,                        plains. Although they were not as convenient and smell-&#13;
&#13;
in accordance with Vietnamese family tradition, the                             free as pour-flush latrines, they were still indoors, and&#13;
&#13;
husband in most cases was the final decision-maker.                             they could be used to collect night soil.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
User satisfaction                                                                    Dug pits also provide night soil, but they were described&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                as dirty, smelly and unsafe especially for children and the&#13;
&#13;
    Visual rating scales drawn on the ground were used                          elderly. Users' satisfaction with this type of latrine is very&#13;
&#13;
with groups of users of various types of latrines to assess                     low. People use them because they cannot yet afford to&#13;
&#13;
their satisfaction with the facility (See Annex A for details).                 build other types of latrines. Their only advantage is that&#13;
&#13;
There was some debate and moving about of ratings on                            they provide ready access to excreta for fertilizing crop&#13;
&#13;
the scale until consensus was reached in groups of men                          fields.&#13;
&#13;
and women in each community.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                     It is worth noting how frequently satisfaction ratings&#13;
&#13;
    User satisfaction with household latrines varied with                       for vault and pit latrines were explained with reference to&#13;
&#13;
gender of the raters and types of latrines being rated8.                        the availability of excreta from the latrines for use as&#13;
&#13;
Figure 6 shows how the ratings were distributed in the 12                       fertilizer. The practice seems both widespread and&#13;
&#13;
communities.                                                                    embedded in local livelihoods. The NRWSS recommends&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                a national ban on the practice, which may be impossible&#13;
&#13;
    Most users of pour-flush latrines were close to fully                       to put into effect in the absence of cheaply available&#13;
&#13;
satisfied (75 - 100% satisfaction). Women were more satisfied                   alternative solutions for fertilizing crops. Even if such&#13;
&#13;
than men. Pour-flush latrines are considered modern, smell-                     solutions may be available, deeply ingrained popular&#13;
&#13;
free and provide a feeling of cleanliness, provided water is                    beliefs about the value of night soil for agriculture will&#13;
&#13;
available close by for flushing. If water is not readily                        have to be addressed in a convincing manner. The findings&#13;
&#13;
available, the pour-flush latrine quickly falls from favor                      also raise the question whether such a practice can really&#13;
&#13;
because: a) it gets as dirty and smelly as traditional pit                      be completely eradicated and whether the most realistic&#13;
&#13;
designs and b) it prevents regular access to excreta for use                    solution would be simply to aim hygiene promotion at&#13;
&#13;
as fertilizer. Due to both these reasons, users often                           more hygienic handling of the excreta by the population&#13;
&#13;
responded by converting them to dry pit latrines, as in                         that depends on it.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
8 User satisfaction was measured using an MPA tool, the 0-100% visual rating scale, with men and women's groups separately. Their choices of ratings on the&#13;
  scale were further probed to understand their reasons for high or low scores.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
20&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
21&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
4.       Is sanitation coverage linked&#13;
         to hygiene awareness?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   As most latrines were acquired for reasons other than           In Phu Luong hamlets very little animal dung was&#13;
&#13;
health protection, high coverage levels do not necessarily         observed on village paths and streets which was not&#13;
&#13;
imply high levels of hygiene awareness and hygienic                the case in other communities. Reportedly, interventions&#13;
&#13;
practices. Hygiene practices were studied using                    by the CIDSE project had managed to convince the&#13;
&#13;
environmental hygiene transect walks across the                    ethnic minority population in Phu Luong to move&#13;
&#13;
communities, observation of households and 10 randomly             domestic animals away from their living quarters and&#13;
&#13;
selected household latrines in different parts of each             keep them in pens.&#13;
&#13;
hamlet, with the help of standard observation checklists.&#13;
                                                                   Indoor household environments were generally free&#13;
Hygiene awareness was explored through participatory&#13;
                                                                   of human excreta everywhere.&#13;
diagramming methods from PHAST.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                 Some high risk unhygienic practices&#13;
Some positive trends to build upon&#13;
                                                                   In the communities along the seacoast, many people&#13;
   Family latrine use was common. Random observation&#13;
                                                                   still continue to defecate outdoors.&#13;
   of 10 latrines per community showed that they were&#13;
&#13;
   used regularly. However, only the pour-flush type               Night soil is not handled safely in case of the majority&#13;
&#13;
   latrines were kept relatively clean, with no excreta visible    of vault and pit latrines. Even in the case of DVC&#13;
&#13;
   on floors or walls around the pan.                              latrines, the vaults are often not kept separate and&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   Half of the pour-flush latrines were equipped with water&#13;
&#13;
   tanks for flushing. In villages that had no water supply&#13;
&#13;
   close to home, household waste water or water from&#13;
&#13;
   nearby ponds was being used for flushing. Dry latrine&#13;
&#13;
   users used paper to clean themselves and buckets for&#13;
&#13;
   used toilet paper were present in about half the&#13;
&#13;
   observed latrines. Domestic waste was deposited in&#13;
&#13;
   holes in gardens or public dumpsites before being&#13;
&#13;
   periodically treated.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
22&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
   vault contents are taken out as and when needed for        that there was a substantial gap between what people&#13;
&#13;
   agriculture, without allowing them to compost              know and what they actually do (Table 5).&#13;
&#13;
   adequately. Women are exposed to frequent contact&#13;
                                                                 Women tended to have marginally higher awareness&#13;
   with excreta as they generally have to undertake the&#13;
                                                                 of hygienic practices than men.&#13;
   task of removing night soil from latrines and carrying&#13;
&#13;
   it to crop fields, sometimes without the help of any          All the groups of men and women correctly identified&#13;
&#13;
   implements. In discussion groups women complained             the three main fecal-oral transmission routes, i.e.,&#13;
&#13;
   that the task makes them feel quite sick, but they feel       through water, hands and foods.&#13;
&#13;
   obliged to do it as it benefits the crops.                    In every community, both men and women identified&#13;
&#13;
   The widespread use of unsanitary latrines and                 defecating in toilets instead of in the open as a&#13;
&#13;
   modification of latrine systems to unsafe designs             preventive hygiene practice.&#13;
&#13;
   continues in all communities because there is frequent        Keeping food covered for protection from flies and&#13;
   demand for human excreta in agriculture. This leads           boiling water for drinking were also identified&#13;
   to opening up of septic tanks and leaching pits of            everywhere as good hygiene practices.&#13;
   pour flush latrines and vault and pit latrines being&#13;
                                                                 Cleaning hands with soap was identified as an effective&#13;
   maintained in a state that allows easy access to contents&#13;
                                                                 way to block the transmission route of fecal&#13;
   at any time. Covers are removed from pit and vault&#13;
                                                                 contamination by only slightly over half the&#13;
   latrines, separation walls between vaults are&#13;
                                                                 communities. Women mentioned it more often as a&#13;
   demolished, night soil contaminates floors during&#13;
                                                                 good hygiene practice than men did. However, both&#13;
   removal and the latrines stay dirty and smelly all the&#13;
                                                                 men and women thought it was necessary mainly after&#13;
   time. Nevertheless, many households still consider such&#13;
                                                                 working in the fields. There was very low awareness&#13;
   latrines to be sanitary.&#13;
                                                                 all round of the critical times for hand washing such&#13;
   Hand washing after defecation is not a common                 as before eating or feeding babies, after defecating&#13;
   practice, even with just water. In none of the                and after cleaning up a child's feces.&#13;
   communities visited, were people washing their hands&#13;
                                                                 Women in most communities were aware of the need&#13;
   with water and soap after defecation. In none of the&#13;
                                                                 to dispose of babies' feces into latrines. Men were&#13;
   latrines observed did the study team find the presence&#13;
                                                                 largely unaware.&#13;
   of soap besides water tanks or wells. The water in&#13;
&#13;
   toilet tanks was reportedly used only for flushing.           The inconsistencies between awareness and practice&#13;
&#13;
                                                              are worth noting. While all men and women considered&#13;
   In some areas people use highly hazardous anal&#13;
                                                              defecating in latrines necessary to prevent diseases, many&#13;
   cleaning practices. In the mountainous communes the&#13;
                                                              households still practice open-air defecation. In all&#13;
   researchers observed sticks or pieces of cloth hung&#13;
                                                              communities visited, people normally did not clean their&#13;
   inside the latrine which were said to be used like toilet&#13;
                                                              hands with soap, even though hand washing with water&#13;
   paper, but not discarded after single use and&#13;
                                                              and soap was identified by half the men's groups and&#13;
   repeatedly used by different family members.&#13;
                                                              two thirds of the women's discussions groups as proper&#13;
&#13;
                                                              hygiene behavior, and all groups knew about hands being&#13;
Hygiene awareness&#13;
                                                              one principal means of carrying fecal contamination to&#13;
&#13;
   The study team used a pictorial tool to assess people's    the mouth.&#13;
&#13;
awareness of the transmission routes of fecal&#13;
                                                                 People seem to have selectively adopted good hygiene&#13;
contamination, and ways to block transmission. Results&#13;
                                                              behaviors depending on whether it is convenient to do&#13;
from 24 discussion groups in 12 communities showed&#13;
                                                              so. Although the government's hygiene education&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                     23&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
campaigns seem to have spread awareness of good and                            An analysis such as above for data from 15 ­ 20&#13;
&#13;
bad hygiene behaviors, they have not yet succeeded in                     communities representative of a district or commune can&#13;
&#13;
getting good hygiene behaviors internalized by people. It                 identify and prioritize 1-2 key hygiene behaviors to promote&#13;
&#13;
is possible that what is promoted may not be relevant                     locally for optimal health impact. Low-cost locally&#13;
&#13;
according to local beliefs or not actually practicable under              developed IEC materials based on such an analysis could&#13;
&#13;
local circumstances.                                                      target key behaviors more effectively than nationally&#13;
&#13;
                                                                          produced standard hygiene education materials. For&#13;
    For instance, students are taught about sanitation but&#13;
                                                                          example, if the data above came from a sample&#13;
schools are not provided with sufficient latrines. School&#13;
                                                                          representative of a district, an appropriate behavior-&#13;
latrines observed were generally dirty and without water&#13;
                                                                          changing intervention for that district would be one that:&#13;
or soap for children to clean their hands after defecation.&#13;
                                                                          a) focused on improving the effectiveness of hand washing&#13;
Children are thus not able to put their health and hygiene&#13;
                                                                          by all family members, i.e. with soap, after defecation,&#13;
education lessons into practice. Experience in some&#13;
                                                                          after cleaning up babies and before eating or feeding,&#13;
countries has shown that children who learn good hygiene&#13;
                                                                          and b) linked hand washing promotional efforts to making&#13;
behaviors and can practice them at school often motivate&#13;
                                                                          soap and sufficient water more accessible to families and&#13;
other family members to adopt those behaviors8.&#13;
                                                                          schools.&#13;
    While PHAST participatory diagramming methods are&#13;
                                                                               The policy recommendation implied is that capacities&#13;
now being used in many countries for community-level&#13;
                                                                          for participatory hygiene behavior analysis and planning&#13;
planning of behavior-change interventions with community&#13;
                                                                          for improvement need to be made available in agencies&#13;
groups, the study experience suggests that it might be&#13;
                                                                          promoting sanitation or managing IEC interventions at&#13;
possible to raise the level of analysis to clusters of&#13;
                                                                          the community level.&#13;
communities for planning area-specific IEC interventions&#13;
&#13;
and monitoring behavior change, as explained below.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Table 5: Hygiene awareness assessed in the 12 communities&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                               Frequency of                      Frequency of&#13;
&#13;
    Awareness of :                                                                        identification in 12               identification in 12&#13;
                                                                                             group sessions                     group sessions&#13;
                                                                                                   with men                       with women&#13;
&#13;
  The 3 main fecal-oral transmission routes: water, hands and food                                      12                              12&#13;
&#13;
  Defecating in latrines as a good preventive practice                                                  12                              12&#13;
&#13;
  Covering foods with dish-covers as a good preventive practice                                         12                              12&#13;
&#13;
  Drinking boiled water as a good preventive practice                                                   12                              12&#13;
&#13;
  Need to clean hands after agricultural work                                                           6                               10&#13;
&#13;
  Need to dispose of babies' excreta into latrine                                                       5                               10&#13;
&#13;
  Need to wash hands with soap                                                                          6                                8&#13;
&#13;
  Need to wash hands before eating                                                                      5                                6&#13;
&#13;
  Need to wash hands after cleaning up babies' feces                                                    2                                2&#13;
&#13;
  Need to clean hands before feeding babies                                                             0                                0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
8 Kapadia-Kundu,Nandita and Dyalchand, Ashok. The Bal Sevak Program in India ; Mwasha,S.Eben. The HESAWA School Health and Sanitation Package,&#13;
  Tanzania; in Sanitation Promotion , WHO 1998; Mukherjee,Nilanjana and Josodipoero,Ratna. "Is it selling toilets? No, a lifestyle", Water and Sanitation&#13;
  Program ­ East Asia, 2000.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
24&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
5.         How long does it take to change&#13;
           behavior?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Timeline explorations with community groups show            to forcefully promote sanitation programs in an&#13;
&#13;
an uneven pattern of the progress of sanitation                 environment where project assistance became increasingly&#13;
&#13;
interventions. The time frames needed to change behavior        more available.&#13;
&#13;
can vary greatly depending on how behavior change&#13;
&#13;
options are chosen and promoted. The following examples             These projects offered technical assistance, construction&#13;
&#13;
illustrate why sanitation coverage can increase quickly in      materials and in some cases even cash assistance. In many&#13;
&#13;
some communities and stagnate in others. However, unless        of these projects, pour-flush toilets were the only design&#13;
&#13;
coverage was near universal in a community and people's         promoted, which had the following types of influence on&#13;
&#13;
actual latrine use rates were verified, it would be inaccurate  community behavior and demand for latrines:&#13;
&#13;
to infer that its sanitation behavior has changed.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                    Although interventions had been going on since the&#13;
&#13;
    In some of the 12 communities the first latrines were           1960s, most of the expansion happened since the&#13;
&#13;
built in the early 1960s usually by health department staff         1990s, particularly in communities where the&#13;
&#13;
to set a good example for the community to pursue. During           promotion of pour-flush toilets coincided with&#13;
&#13;
the 1960s, agricultural cooperatives initiated promotional          improvements in the access to water supply.&#13;
&#13;
campaigns aimed at improving environmental sanitation&#13;
&#13;
in the northern countryside. Double vault composting                In areas away from water sources or without sufficient&#13;
&#13;
latrines were the type promoted. But community groups               water, pour-flush toilets were not easy to use and&#13;
&#13;
as well as local government authorities met during the              therefore not popular.&#13;
&#13;
study reported that sanitation interventions did not really&#13;
&#13;
take off and spread until the early 1990s.                          In Ninh Thang people said they wanted to wait for clean&#13;
&#13;
                                                                    water service before building latrines. The ceramic latrine&#13;
&#13;
    By the early 1990s, the Vietnamese economy began                pans tended to quickly get stained and discolored when&#13;
&#13;
to prosper. Village development boards reportedly began             water from ponds or wells was used for flushing toilets.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                            25&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
    Ninh Thang was the only commune that experienced              available in several forms which targeted local obstacles&#13;
&#13;
    two project interventions. The first sanitation intervention  to demand. The project constructed demonstration latrines&#13;
&#13;
    was in 1985, when on a pilot basis, some households           to train local people in construction, promoted a hygienic&#13;
&#13;
    received a toilet pan, iron and cement to construct a         way of life, made available latrine parts as well as financial&#13;
&#13;
    pour-flush latrines. The program built some model             assistance as credit schemes for households needing to&#13;
&#13;
    latrines and expected that the community will replicate       borrow cash.&#13;
&#13;
    them. However, few of these latrines were considered&#13;
&#13;
    as good models by the population, because the toilet              Yet, as will be seen in the next section, fast growth of&#13;
&#13;
    pan was of poor quality and difficult to keep clean           the demand for latrines has not necessarily resulted in&#13;
&#13;
    and the latrine design made it difficult to extract night     sustainable investments being made, or sustained changes&#13;
&#13;
    soil for agriculture.                                         in sanitation behavior.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    The cost of pour-flush toilets was seen as a major&#13;
&#13;
    impediment for many, especially poorer households,&#13;
&#13;
    to acquire one.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    People abandoned the use of toilets that did not meet&#13;
&#13;
    their expectations, or modified them to suit their needs,&#13;
&#13;
    by cutting off water-seals and opening up septic tanks&#13;
&#13;
    to extract human excreta for fertilizer.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Of the 12 communities sanitation coverage increased&#13;
&#13;
fastest in the 2 in Phu Luong district. Latrines were&#13;
&#13;
introduced only in 1993 and by 2000 sanitary toilet&#13;
&#13;
coverage had increased to 97 per cent. The community&#13;
&#13;
feels that this was possible because project assistance was&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
26&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
6.        What interventions were effective&#13;
          in changing behavior?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Health education efforts were undertaken in all the        wells and animal pens, by ensuring people's&#13;
&#13;
communities to improve people's hygiene awareness.             contributions to common funds for improving the local&#13;
&#13;
However, community focus group discussions and                 environment, and by organizing commune cleaning&#13;
&#13;
interviews with local government personnel brought up          days in which the whole community participates. The&#13;
&#13;
evidence that health education alone did not really change     agreed targets are monitored by local governments or&#13;
&#13;
behavior. Whether people changed their hygiene and             Village Development Boards, and the results for each&#13;
&#13;
sanitation practices seemed to be a function of how far        commune are made public.&#13;
&#13;
intervention strategies leveraged local influencers and how&#13;
&#13;
far they supported local livelihoods. Sustained behavioral     Village Development Boards in Ninh Binh province&#13;
&#13;
changes however, were those that stemmed from the users'       were found to be regularly inspecting households&#13;
&#13;
own decisions to change rather than due to external            toilets. Those who do not use their toilets or leave&#13;
&#13;
pressure to change, as illustrated below. The following        them dirty have their names announced over the&#13;
&#13;
points emerged from community group discussions and            commune radio system. As a result, all households&#13;
&#13;
interviews with community leaders.                             regularly use and do not change the original design&#13;
&#13;
                                                               of the toilets, as long as monitoring by the Boards&#13;
&#13;
Use of local "influencers"                                     continues.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Peer pressure and collective community responsibility      Villagers who have had some external exposure were&#13;
&#13;
    has proved an important influencer of community            said to have contributed to changes in local sanitation&#13;
&#13;
    behavior for acquiring sanitation facilities. Local        practices. Those who had gone out of the community&#13;
&#13;
    government authorities have been very active in            seeking work had learned about these conveniences&#13;
&#13;
    mobilizing rural communities to commit to targets for      in urban areas and brought supplies back to build&#13;
&#13;
    improved sanitation practices. This was done by getting    toilets for their own families and neighbors. Many&#13;
&#13;
    households to formally agree to build toilets, water       pour-flush toilets in Ninh Thang and Quang Thai were&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                    27&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
   reportedly built this way before any project intervention.    using the feces for several years because the pits first&#13;
&#13;
   The research teams observed several fully user-financed       have to fill up, then sealed off and left for pit contents&#13;
&#13;
   latrines which were all functioning and well­                 to be oxidized to manure. When a project uses a&#13;
&#13;
   maintained.                                                   supply-driven rather than a demand-responsive&#13;
&#13;
                                                                 approach, people often comply with instructions to&#13;
&#13;
Links with local livelihoods                                     build these toilets, but then tend to change them into&#13;
&#13;
                                                                 dry pit latrines or open up the septic tanks to access&#13;
&#13;
   When communities dependent on agricultural practices          the pit contents regularly. Both modifications reduce&#13;
&#13;
   using fresh human excreta are persuaded to accept             the hygienic advantages of pour-flush latrines. In Xom&#13;
&#13;
   pour-flush latrine designs, they do not sustain the           Ha, for instance, already 30 per cent of the households&#13;
&#13;
   facilities as intended. Such designs prevent them from        that built pour-flush latrines 2 years ago have&#13;
&#13;
                                                                 converted them into dry pit latrines. Similar dilemmas&#13;
&#13;
                                                                 were reported by communities in Indonesia and&#13;
&#13;
                                                                 Cambodia where local populations have traditionally&#13;
&#13;
                                                                 used human excreta for breeding pigs and fish farming&#13;
&#13;
                                                                 in ponds.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                 In Phu Luong, hands-on construction training was&#13;
&#13;
                                                                 reported to have helped to increase the supply of&#13;
&#13;
                                                                 building materials and skills for sanitation in the&#13;
&#13;
                                                                 community, which has resulted in faster growth of&#13;
&#13;
                                                                 latrine construction. In Bai Can, for instance, in four&#13;
&#13;
                                                                 years time, access to toilets has grown from 0 to 100&#13;
&#13;
                                                                 per cent. People in Xom Ha reported that since some&#13;
&#13;
                                                                 community members learned to make concrete from&#13;
&#13;
                                                                 local raw materials, households are able to build more&#13;
&#13;
                                                                 latrines cheaply, without depending on external&#13;
&#13;
                                                                 supplies and skills.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
28&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
7.       What helps sustain sanitation services?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   Experiences from this study suggest that the failure to      flush latrines while people still needed night soil&#13;
&#13;
consult with user communities in making planning                regularly for cultivation and lacked water supply close&#13;
&#13;
decisions represents a high risk to achieving sustained         to homes for flushing toilets. In many cases, people&#13;
&#13;
sanitation services. Projects need to find out and address      did build pour-flush latrines promoted in their village,&#13;
&#13;
local consumer preferences, market potential and                but after some time they either discarded the toilet or&#13;
&#13;
constraints, and access to skills, materials and/or capital.    modified it into dry pit latrines to continue the collection&#13;
&#13;
The latter is especially important for reaching the poorer      of night soil. In Xom Ha, not a single household has&#13;
&#13;
consumers. Without the right marketing strategy, project        built a pour-flush latrines since the completion of the&#13;
&#13;
investments can be largely wasted. Some examples from           project in 1999. More telling though is that almost&#13;
&#13;
the study follow.                                               one third of the pour-flush latrines that were built with&#13;
&#13;
                                                                project assistance have already been turned into dry&#13;
&#13;
   Local authorities and project staff in 7 out of the 12       latrines within 2 years of construction. During the&#13;
&#13;
   communities aggressively promoted the use of pour-           participatory assessments, people mentioned that if&#13;
&#13;
                                                                they were asked to select the latrine design at the&#13;
&#13;
                                                                beginning, they would have opted for double-vault&#13;
&#13;
                                                                latrines instead of pour-flush latrines. The project&#13;
&#13;
                                                                promoted the pour-flush type because it was considered&#13;
&#13;
                                                                (by the project) as the most "hygienic" design.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                A similar experience was observed in Quang Thai,&#13;
&#13;
                                                                where few pour-flush latrines are actually being used.&#13;
&#13;
                                                                Of those in use, it was noted that one compartment of&#13;
&#13;
                                                                septic tanks often is left open so that sludge can be&#13;
&#13;
                                                                collected for irrigating vegetable gardens.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                          29&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
  In Ninh Thang, a first project intervention in 1985              not, the negative experiences of early adapters will&#13;
&#13;
  provided households with a number of cement pans                 ensure that the future demand for sanitation services&#13;
&#13;
  for building flush latrines which revealed many defects.         is reduced significantly, if not completely decimated.&#13;
&#13;
  Within short periods of use the water seal pipes (goose-&#13;
&#13;
  neck bend) got blocked, the pans became sticky with              A more positive example is the experience of Ban Cai&#13;
&#13;
  excreta and were difficult to clean. They absorbed urine         and Xom Ha, where project assistance helped to build&#13;
&#13;
  and developed a bad smell. Most of these latrines are            reliable capacity to construct latrines within the&#13;
&#13;
  no longer used. When the study team visited some                 community. The development of this capacity to supply&#13;
&#13;
  households, they saw a number of pans thrown in the              materials and skills for sanitation saw faster growth of&#13;
&#13;
  corners of gardens. The result was that no other                 latrine users than in any of the other 10 communities&#13;
&#13;
  households in Ninh Thang followed the example of                 within a very short time span of 2-3 years. People were&#13;
&#13;
  their neighbors who had first built latrines, and                satisfied with the quality and design of the locally built&#13;
&#13;
  experienced these problems. As with the introduction             latrines. Experience in Indonesia showed a similar&#13;
&#13;
  of any new product or service, sanitation projects               trend, because in contrast to project approaches&#13;
&#13;
  should ensure that the experience of the early adopters          prescribing a single type of latrine, locally trained&#13;
&#13;
  is positive ­ by paying sufficient attention to the technical    masons were responsive to demands from customers&#13;
&#13;
  quality and social suitability of the service provided. If       for latrine types and designs.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
30&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Learning and Recommendations&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   Demand-responsive approaches are essential for                 Agriculture-dependent communities might insist on&#13;
&#13;
sustained sanitation.                                             designs that allow access to excreta for fertilizer while&#13;
&#13;
                                                                  coastal fishing communities may have no such&#13;
&#13;
   Sanitation interventions are often seen only as public         preference.&#13;
&#13;
health measures. But as the study shows, health concerns&#13;
&#13;
are not an initial motivator for households to stimulate          In their sanitation promotion strategies agencies take&#13;
&#13;
the demand for sanitation. Hence, there is a disparity            advantage of the desire for upgrading service levels&#13;
&#13;
between the type of service and the marketing approach            so that households that are currently unable to afford&#13;
&#13;
that is followed. If sanitation services are to be demanded,      the higher service level can do so over time. Offering&#13;
&#13;
used and sustained, it seems important that:                      a range of progressively improved options that can be&#13;
&#13;
                                                                  upgraded when possible, at a range of prices, may&#13;
&#13;
   All households in the community can make informed              help to stimulate demand over larger segments of the&#13;
&#13;
   choices ­ regarding the technology, design of facilities,      community, including the poor. The findings from User&#13;
&#13;
   possible short and long-term benefits, cost and the            satisfaction ratings and the Timeline (waiting until water&#13;
&#13;
   modes of payment ­ so they can select the most suitable        supply connection is affordable) support this&#13;
&#13;
   and affordable sanitation option for themselves.               recommendation.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   Agencies avoid the promotion of single-product based       Sanitation promotion strategies should start by&#13;
&#13;
   sanitation services. Such an approach does not offer       identifying the factors that influence the demand for&#13;
&#13;
   choices appropriate for all segments of the community,     sanitation&#13;
&#13;
   nor does it fit variations in local lifestyles. The study&#13;
&#13;
   shows that the promotion of a single option like the           Just as for any other product or service, market research&#13;
&#13;
   relatively most expensive pour-flush latrine has mainly    is essential to understand what intervention strategies will&#13;
&#13;
   benefited the richer households in the community.          be most successful to ensure that sanitation services are&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                         31&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
sustained. The demand for sanitation is driven by                     Apart from promotional strategies, sustained sanitation&#13;
&#13;
numerous factors that vary between communities.                   services also seem to be linked to developing self-sustaining&#13;
&#13;
Identifying essential factors that must be present to ensure      sanitation markets i.e. demand generation along with&#13;
&#13;
that demand can arise is a first step. Some essential             growing local supply capacity to feed the demand.&#13;
&#13;
facilitating factors include the availability of land and water.  Findings from the 12 communities on access, ownership,&#13;
&#13;
It does not take research to show that introduction of pour-      user satisfaction, variations in project approaches to&#13;
&#13;
flush latrines where there is no nearby water source is a         community capacity building and time frames for coverage&#13;
&#13;
wasted investment. The type of latrine offered to a               acceleration suggest that sanitation marketing strategies&#13;
&#13;
household has first to be compatible with its physical,           need include the developing of a) a series of technically&#13;
&#13;
economic and social reality. Promotional strategies can           feasible options at a range of costs; b) upgradability of&#13;
&#13;
further utilize situation-specific motivating factors, such as    technically feasible options to suit local consumer&#13;
&#13;
higher potential demand in areas away from the sea or             preferences; c) a range of financing arrangements enabling&#13;
&#13;
rivers (traditionally preferred defecation sites), the desire     the poor to get access to a sanitation facility; and d) local&#13;
&#13;
for convenience and privacy, the interest to store night          capacity that will supply skills and materials needed for&#13;
&#13;
soil, or reasons of social prestige.                              existing and future local markets.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                  Demand for sanitation facilities does not automatically&#13;
&#13;
                                                                  result in hygiene behavior change.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      The construction of latrines may not take much time&#13;
&#13;
                                                                  as the experience in Can Bai shows. Yet, the construction&#13;
&#13;
                                                                  of latrines does not necessarily translate into improved&#13;
&#13;
                                                                  hygiene behavior. Changing behaviors like outdoor&#13;
&#13;
                                                                  defecation toward consistent use of sanitary latrines can&#13;
&#13;
                                                                  take a long time, as the value of the new behavior may&#13;
&#13;
                                                                  not be immediately obvious to most people who have&#13;
&#13;
                                                                  never used latrines.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                      Project interventions, especially health education to&#13;
&#13;
                                                                  improve public sanitation perceptions, have obtained some&#13;
&#13;
                                                                  results. However, improved hygiene awareness does not&#13;
&#13;
                                                                  simultaneously translate into a change in sanitation&#13;
&#13;
                                                                  behavior. Giving up long-standing habits such as outdoor&#13;
&#13;
                                                                  defecation, not cleaning hands with water and soap after&#13;
&#13;
                                                                  defecation, and keeping domestic animals underneath&#13;
&#13;
                                                                  the home are only changed when people can evaluate&#13;
&#13;
                                                                  the costs and benefits of the change required. Until&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
32&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
perceived benefits equal or exceed perceived costs, behavior   new latrine. Do they use it hygienically? Are they willing&#13;
&#13;
change is unlikely .                                           to repair and upgrade it? Do people build more latrines&#13;
&#13;
                                                               on their own initiative after a project concludes?&#13;
&#13;
   It is also important to recognize that the "costs" of&#13;
&#13;
behavior change are not just monetary. Costs have to be&#13;
&#13;
counted in terms of all kinds of resources (money, effort,     Projects that aim to provide sustained sanitation&#13;
&#13;
time, implications for social relationships and on other       services should plan their interventions for longer time&#13;
&#13;
resources etc.). A significant example is the present dilemma  frames&#13;
&#13;
that the households face of losing access to their supply&#13;
&#13;
of night soil when they build a sanitary pour-flush latrine,       Sanitation interventions are usually provided in&#13;
&#13;
which has often been the only option they have been            combination with water supply projects, for which the usual&#13;
&#13;
offered for sanitation improvement. Sanitation projects        time frame is 4 to 5 years. Although latrines can be&#13;
&#13;
need to invest resources and attention into getting their      constructed in this timeframe, it is important to recognize&#13;
&#13;
"menu of options" right for their client populations, so       that much more time may be needed to ensure that the&#13;
&#13;
that "costs" perceived by potential customers are minimized    sanitation services created are also sustained. Sanitation&#13;
&#13;
while "benefits" perceived by them are maximized.              interventions can only help to improve community health&#13;
&#13;
                                                               when hygiene behavior changes are made and sustained.&#13;
&#13;
Success of sanitation projects cannot be measured only         Managing behavior change requires a definite process,&#13;
&#13;
by coverage rates                                              which was not discernible in the 12 communities studied.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   As the experience in the 12 communities shows,                  Sanitation projects need to first invest time and&#13;
&#13;
coverage rates only tell part of the story. In all these       resources in gaining an understanding of the current&#13;
&#13;
communities, sanitation coverage may be high, but these        community practices, preferences and the rationale&#13;
&#13;
sanitation coverage data do not reveal the differentials in    underlying them. This understanding should form the&#13;
&#13;
coverage within the community, with the poor having much       basis for developing an appropriate marketing campaign&#13;
&#13;
less coverage than their better-off neighbors. It also does    that can generate local demand for sanitation facilities&#13;
&#13;
not take into account the difference between and within        and local desire for improvements in current hygiene&#13;
&#13;
communities in terms of actual use of sanitary facilities.     behavior patterns. When demand begins to emerge,&#13;
&#13;
                                                               projects should be able to offer and effectively explain&#13;
&#13;
   As the benefits of sanitation are often measured in         possible options and costs to potential consumers and&#13;
&#13;
terms of community health impacts, the performance of          also simultaneously develop local capacities that can&#13;
&#13;
sanitation interventions should not only measure the           respond to the emerging and future demand for sanitation.&#13;
&#13;
ownership to sanitary facilities, but also the access to and   For all these reasons, time frames of 7-8 years are&#13;
&#13;
use of the facilities, and the changes in hygiene behavior.    recommended for demand-driven sanitation and hygiene&#13;
&#13;
Indicators should also measure whether people use the          interventions in Vietnam.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                       33&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Annex A&#13;
&#13;
                                   Participatory Tools used for investigation&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      The following participatory tools supplemented open-ended focus group discussions. They did not necessitate literacy skills. Where&#13;
illiteracy was a problem, symbols and visuals replaced writing. Locally available drawing and marking materials in the communities&#13;
were used optimally.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Well Being Classification (MPA tool)­ Discussion is initiated with a group of local community members about how they&#13;
    differentiate between households in their community. Names for different categories and criteria begin to emerge in the&#13;
    discussion. The facilitator guides discussion toward upper, lower and middle socio-economic categories, using the local terms&#13;
    emerging from the discussion. People are then asked to draw pictures of a typical person from each category and list the criteria&#13;
    characterizing each category. They are then asked to distribute a pre-counted pile of 100 seeds representing the total population&#13;
    of their community among the three categories, showing their approximation of the proportion of households falling in each&#13;
    category.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Social Mapping (PRA tool): A group of 8-10 community members are requested to draw a map of their community on the&#13;
    ground/large sheets of paper, showing natural or artificial boundaries, major landmarks, water sources, public water supply and&#13;
    sanitation facilities, paths and streets and houses. They are requested to mark each house with a color code to show its well being&#13;
    category according to criteria developed earlier, and mark the homes which have each different type of latrine. The completed&#13;
    map is used for assessing latrine coverage and access (who uses which facility), in discussion with a larger community gathering of&#13;
    about 30-40 people. The map is used for deciding the route for the environmental transect, selection of latrines to observe in&#13;
    different parts of the hamlet, and also used as a reference with other tools like Timeline.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Process History Timeline (PRA tool): A group of community members, most of whom are above 50 years old, are asked to identify&#13;
    when they had first seen or heard about latrines. A discussion is facilitated to help them trace events linked to their sanitation&#13;
    experience in the community since then, to the present day. As discussion proceeds, a co-facilitator visually documents it along a&#13;
    Timeline, writing on lengths of chart paper sheets the years/other time milestones mentioned and adding brief remarks about&#13;
    events associated with them. A completed Timeline is used together with the Social Map earlier prepared, to further probe why&#13;
    things proceeded the way they did and what led to the present situation. Can be done separately for men and women.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Ladder 1 (Cost ­ benefit perceptions, MPA tool): Groups of users of latrines (men and women separately) are asked&#13;
    whether using latrines has made any difference to their lives. Out of the ensuing discussion the benefits they perceive from&#13;
    latrines are identified. They are then asked to score each benefit on a scale of 0-10, according to the extent to which their&#13;
    expectation of it is being met (the Benefit perceived score). Seeds/stones are used to show the score for each benefit. They are&#13;
    then asked to think about the costs incurred in getting and using the latrine and re-score each benefit using a different type of&#13;
    seeds/tones on a scale of 0-10, to reflect the extent to which the value of the benefit justifies the cost, according to them (value&#13;
    for cost score). The results are verified by facilitators in discussion with the group and reasons for the scores given are explored.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Contamination Routes and Blocks (PHAST tool): Separate groups of men and women are presented with an assortment of 25&#13;
    line drawings showing human feces, a human mouth and various possible routes by which feces may reach the mouth, e.g. hand,&#13;
    food, water in natural sources/storage containers/ drinking utensil/flies, people eating using hands, working in fields etc. A&#13;
    number of unrelated pictures are also included. The groups are asked to arrange the pictures to show how feces could be carried&#13;
    to the mouth. Then they are presented with pictures of various types of hygiene practices which may block the routes of such&#13;
    transmission and asked to select which blocks may be used where in their transmission diagram to prevent feces from entering the&#13;
    mouth. The resulting diagram reveals existing hygiene awareness of the group, and may be used to further plan behavior change&#13;
    strategies for their communities (which was not an objective of the present investigation).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    Environmental transect walk (PRA tool adapted by MPA): The Social Map was.3 used to identify areas that were relevant to&#13;
    observe in terms of the community sanitation situation and areas which had concentrations of poor, middle income and better off&#13;
    households. A route was then charted on the map so that the latrines chosen for observation and the neighborhoods observed&#13;
    would be properly representative of the hamlet's environmental hygiene status.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
34&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                    Observation Checklists&#13;
&#13;
                                        Observation checklist for Environmental Hygiene Transect&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                            Transect Points in community&#13;
&#13;
(Record numbers as appropriate)                                                      1    2     3    4       5    6    7  8&#13;
&#13;
Is there evidence of fecal contamination at particular sites?&#13;
&#13;
1) Along roads                            4) Around paddy fields&#13;
2) Along foot paths                       5) Outside house&#13;
3) Near clean water sources               6) Inside house&#13;
&#13;
Where are latrines installed?&#13;
&#13;
1) Inside home yard (why?)&#13;
2) Outside home yard (why?)&#13;
&#13;
Where are infants' feces disposed of?&#13;
&#13;
1) In the yard or field                   4) Into river, ditch or drain&#13;
2) Into latrine                           5) Anywhere&#13;
3) In garbage hole&#13;
&#13;
At what frequency per week are latrines cleaned?&#13;
&#13;
1) Each day                               4) do not know/not regularly&#13;
2) 2-3 times a week                           cleaned&#13;
3) once a week&#13;
&#13;
What is the distance between hand-washing facilities to latrines?&#13;
&#13;
1) Hand washing facility stands beside latrine&#13;
2) Within short walking distance of latrine&#13;
3) Inside the house&#13;
&#13;
How is garbage disposed of?&#13;
&#13;
1) In a hole in the home yard             4) Into ravine (in hilly area)&#13;
2) Burned                                 5) Others&#13;
3) Thrown into the river/ditch&#13;
&#13;
Disposal of liquid household waste :&#13;
&#13;
1) Thrown out of window/door&#13;
2) Flows into open ditch/drain&#13;
3) Thrown into drains flowing into fish pond&#13;
4) Others (explain....................................... )&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Access of animals to the kitchen :&#13;
&#13;
1) Cats and dogs&#13;
2) Chickens, goats or other livestock&#13;
3) Rats&#13;
4) Pigs&#13;
5) Flies, roaches, lizards&#13;
6) Others&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Do households have a stable/cattle pen?&#13;
&#13;
1) No&#13;
2) Yes, adjoining the house/kitchen&#13;
3) Yes, separate from the house&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Fly prevention measures in the homes&#13;
&#13;
1) Garbage in yard covered&#13;
2) Cooked food kept covered&#13;
3) Fly screen on window/door&#13;
4) Others (describe......................................)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                           35&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
           Observation checklist for Use &amp; Maintenance of Household Latrines&#13;
&#13;
 Score                                                              Transect points&#13;
&#13;
 (0=negative, 1=positive)                                   1 2  3 4    5    6     7 8  9 10&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 1. Latrines functioning (usable)&#13;
&#13;
 2. Latrines currently in use for defecation&#13;
&#13;
 3. Pit built according to safety criteria (to be agreed&#13;
    during training)&#13;
&#13;
 4. Closet construction according to technically sound&#13;
    criteria (3-4 tech. criteria ­ to be agreed during&#13;
    training)&#13;
&#13;
 5. Septic tank/pit placed over 7 m's distance and&#13;
    downstream from water source&#13;
&#13;
 6. External structure provides privacy to user&#13;
    (walls, door, woven bamboo/shutter)&#13;
&#13;
 7. Lid present over pit OR water present in water seal.&#13;
&#13;
 8. No feces visible on floor, walls or latrine surface&#13;
&#13;
 9. Water and soap/substitute available near facility&#13;
    (examine those for evidence of hand washing activity)&#13;
&#13;
 10. No human feces in yard/at garbage pile&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   TOTAL SCORE&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
36&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                            Water and Sanitation Program&#13;
                                                                            East Asia and the Pacific&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                            Jakarta Stock Exchange Building&#13;
                                                                            Tower 2, 13th floor&#13;
                                                                            Jl. Jend. Sudirman Kav. 52-53, SCBD&#13;
                                                                            Jakarta 12190, Indonesia&#13;
                                                                            Phone: (62-21) 5299-3003&#13;
                                                                            Fax: (62-21) 5299-3004&#13;
                                                                            Website: http://www.wsp.org&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
The Water and Sanitation Program is an international partnership to help&#13;
the poor gain sustained access to improved water supply and sanitation&#13;
services. The program's funding partners are the Governments of&#13;
Australia, Belgium, Canada, Denmark, Germany, Italy, Japan, Luxemburg,&#13;
the Netherlands, Norway, Sweden, Switzerland, and the United Kingdom;&#13;
the United Nations Development Programme and the World Bank&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="2617502">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2002/01/2617502/selling-sanitation-vietnam-works
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2002/01/2617502/selling-sanitation-vietnam-works</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2002/01/2617502/selling-sanitation-vietnam-works</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/10/16/000090341_20031016140039/Rendered/INDEX/270010Selling0sanitation.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/10/16/000090341_20031016140039/Rendered/PDF/270010Selling0sanitation.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2003-10-16T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2002-01-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Selling sanitation in Vietnam : what works?
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            By the early 1990s, the Vietnamese
            economy began to prosper. Village development boards started
            to forcefully promote sanitation programs in an environment
            where project assistance became more widely available.
            However, the use of toilets and more particularly changes in
            hygiene behavior have tended to proceed slowly. The 1999
            National Rural Water Supply and Sanitation Strategy (NRWSS)
            states: "about 50 per cent of households have some form
            of latrine (the remaining 50% use a neighbor's latrine,
            or more commonly practice open defecation. Most latrines are
            unhygienic, consisting mainly of single vault latrines (with
            the excreta removed regularly for use as fertilizer) or
            simple pit latrines. About 20% of households have hygienic
            sanitation". The NRWSS further provides explanations
            for what are considered 'hygienic' latrines based
            on practices prevalent in Vietnam.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Selling sanitation in Vietnam : what works?
        </docna>
        <display_title>Selling sanitation in Vietnam :
            what works?</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2002/01/2617502/selling-sanitation-vietnam-works</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>UNDP-Water &amp; Sanitation Program</docty>
        <subtopic>Hygiene Promotion and Social Marketing,Town Water Supply and Sanitation,Urban Water Supply and Sanitation,TF030632-DANISH CTF - FY05 (DAC PART
            COUNTRIES GNP PER CAPITA BELOW USD 2,500/AL,Sanitation and Sewerage</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Water Supply and Sanitation</teratopic>
        <count>Vietnam</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Asia!$!80451</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Southeast Asia!$!80471</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000090341_20031016140039</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>General water, sanitation and flood
            protection sector</subsc>
        <admreg>East Asia and Pacific,East Asia and Pacific</admreg>
        <colti>Water and Sanitation Program</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Water Supply and Sanitation</historic_topic>
        <sectr>Water, sanitation and flood protection</sectr>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Sanitation; Agricultural cooperatives;
            Environmental sanitation; Water wells; Rural households;
            Agricultural production; Rural areas; Latrines; Sanitation
            programs; Hygiene behavior
            access to latrines,clean water,clean water
            supply,cleanliness,community health,community
            sanitation,composting,composting facilities,demand for
            sanitation,drainage,drinking water,drinking water
            quality,environmental sanitation,feces,flush toilet,flush
            toilets,furniture,grey water,household
            latrines,households,human excreta,human
            waste,hygiene,hygiene behavior,hygiene behaviors,Hygiene
            education,latrine,Latrine design,latrines,night
            soil,personal hygiene,pit latrines,pits,Rural Water,Rural
            Water Supply,sanitary latrines,sanitation,sanitation
            access,sanitation awareness,sanitation coverage,sanitation
            facilities,sanitation improvement,sanitation
            interventions,Sanitation Program,sanitation
            programs,sanitation sector,sanitation services,sanitation
            standards,Sanitation Strategy,Septic
            tanks,sewerage,sewers,solid waste,surface water,Traditional
            pit latrines,use of toilets,users,water latrines,water
            source,water sources,water supply situation,Wells
        </keywd>
        <owner>Water- Water and Sanit Prgrm (GWASP)</owner>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Asia</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Southeast Asia</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>27001</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Alternative Sentencing Options</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community based Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Correctional Services and Facilities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corrections</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime and Society</ml:concept><ml:concept>Defense Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Detention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enforcement Policies and Oversight Mechanism</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigative Task Force Police</ml:concept><ml:concept>Juvenile Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Law Enforcement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Offender Reintegration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Administration and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Problem solving Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Prosecution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Restorative Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Therapeutic Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Assistance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim-Offender Mediation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Rural Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wastewater Collection and Transportation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crop Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crops</ml:concept><ml:concept>Livestock</ml:concept><ml:concept>Livestock and Animal Husbandry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Access to Basic Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>On-site Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Marketing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation Promotion</ml:concept><ml:concept>Asset Recovery</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Hygiene Promotion and Social Marketing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rural &amp; Small Town Water &amp; Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Criminal Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply and Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Quality Standards</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water Supply</ml:concept><ml:concept>Diseases</ml:concept><ml:concept>Water, Sanitation and Hygiene</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sewerage</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fertilizers</ml:concept><ml:concept>Animal Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Women</ml:concept><ml:concept>Mountains</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sanitation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Local Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Savings</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Eastern Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Viet Nam</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>