<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>                            The WorldBank&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                   ReportNo: T7611BO&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                          TECHNICAL ANNEX&#13;
&#13;
                                 FORA&#13;
&#13;
                         DEVELOPMENTCREDIT&#13;
&#13;
                   INTHEAMOUNT OFSDR 9.8 MILLION&#13;
&#13;
                     (US$14.0 MILLIONEQUIVALENT)&#13;
&#13;
    FORTHE PROPOSEDEMERGENCYECONOMICRECOVERYPROJECT&#13;
&#13;
                                 TO THE&#13;
&#13;
                         REPUBLICOFBOLIVIA&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                              December 8,2003&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Bolivia-Ecuador-Peru-Venezuela Country Management Unit&#13;
LatinAmerica and the Caribbean Region&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                             CURRENCYEQUIVALENTS&#13;
                       (Exchange Rate Effective as of 12/05/2003)&#13;
                                US$l.OO = Bolivianos 8.00&#13;
                              Currency Unit =Bolivianos (Bs)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     SYSTEMOFWEIGHTSAND MEASURES&#13;
                                         Metric System&#13;
&#13;
                                     FISCAL YEAR&#13;
&#13;
                                   January 1-December 31&#13;
&#13;
                        ABBREVIATIONS AND ACRONYMS&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
CAF         Corporaci6n Andina de Fomento---Andean Development Corporation&#13;
CAS         Country Assistance Strategy&#13;
CFAA         Country Financial and Accounting Assessment&#13;
EERC        EmergencyEconomic Recovery Credit&#13;
EERP         Emergency Economic Recovery Project&#13;
ERC          Emergency Recovery Credit&#13;
FONDESIF     Sistema Financier0 y de Apoyo a1Sector Productivo&#13;
GDP          Gross Domestic Product&#13;
IBRD         International Bank for Reconstruction and Development&#13;
IDA          International Development Association&#13;
IDB          Inter-American Development Bank&#13;
IFI          International Financial Institutions&#13;
IMF          International Monetary Fund&#13;
L A C        Latin America and the Caribbean&#13;
M A G        Ministry of Agriculture and Livestock&#13;
MOP          Memorandum of the President&#13;
MOH          Ministry o f Health&#13;
OED          Operations Evaluation Department&#13;
PCC          Project Coordination Committee&#13;
PER          Public Expenditure Review&#13;
PRGF         Poverty Reduction and Growth Facility&#13;
PRSC         Poverty Reduction Strategy Credit&#13;
PRSP         Poverty Reduction Strategy Papers&#13;
PSIA         Support Poverty and Social Impact Analysis&#13;
SAC          Social Adjustment Credit&#13;
SDR           Special Drawing Rights&#13;
SNC          RoadNational Service&#13;
YPFB          Yacimientos Petroliferos Fiscales Bolivianos&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
          Vice President:                     David de Ferranti&#13;
          Country Director:                   Marcel0 M.Giugale&#13;
          Sector Director:                    Ernest0 May&#13;
          LeadEconomist:                      Vicente Fretes Cibils&#13;
          Task Team Leader:                   Marco Scuriatti&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                           REPUBLIC OFBOLIVIA&#13;
         PROPOSEDEMERGENCY ECONOMICRECOVERYPROJECT&#13;
&#13;
                                                  Table Of Contents&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
A    Background     ............................................................................................................        1&#13;
B    SocialandEconomicDevelopment                            ......................................................................     2&#13;
C                                                                                                                                       6&#13;
D    Rationalefor EmergencyEconomicRecovery Project                                               ..................................... 9&#13;
E    ProjectDescription&#13;
                      . .        ..............................................................................................         10&#13;
F    Institutional Arrangements                ................................................................................         11&#13;
G&#13;
....&#13;
...  Bank's Assistance Strategy               ...................................................................................&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     ProjectBenefits andRisks                ..................................................................................         12&#13;
&#13;
     Table 1  ...................................................................................................................       2&#13;
     Table 2  ...................................................................................................................       3&#13;
     Table 3  ...................................................................................................................        6&#13;
     Table 4  ...................................................................................................................        8&#13;
&#13;
     Figure 1 ..................................................................................................................         4&#13;
     Figure 2 ..................................................................................................................         5&#13;
&#13;
     SCHEDULE A          .....................................................................................................          14&#13;
     SCHEDULEB           .....................................................................................................&#13;
                         .....................................................................................................          15&#13;
     SCHEDULE C                                                                                                                         16&#13;
     SCHEDULED           .....................................................................................................          17&#13;
     SCHEDULEE           .....................................................................................................          18&#13;
     SCHEDULEF           .....................................................................................................          20&#13;
&#13;
     IBRDMap31131&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                   A.      Background&#13;
&#13;
1.    Bolivia is a resource rich country, yet it remains among the most unequal countries in&#13;
the most unequal region in the world. Throughout its history the proceeds of its vast natural&#13;
resources, such as silver and tin, were never equitably distributed, especially among its&#13;
indigenous population.&#13;
&#13;
2.    In present day Bolivia, growing tensions are apparent among regions, classes, and&#13;
indigenoushon-indigenousgroups.         Groups that had been previously excluded are now&#13;
finding their voice, expressing frustration over past governments and their perceived&#13;
ineffectiveness to resolve problems and deliver promises. Tensions have intensified over the&#13;
last decade when stagnant growth, high unemployment and persistent inequality led to&#13;
increasingpublic discontent.&#13;
&#13;
3.    This discontent translated itself into an escalating trend of social unrest - with serious,&#13;
and often violent, conflicts inApril 2000, September/October2000, and January 2002. Then&#13;
again, in February 2003, when the Government tried to address the fiscal deficit through tax&#13;
increases, street protests and violence led the authorities to back down from their reform&#13;
proposals. Finally, in October 2003, yet another crisis arose when resentment toward a&#13;
Government backed natural gas export project led to more violent street protests, calling for a&#13;
stop to the project out of fear from the indigenous population that the proceeds of the&#13;
country's richnatural resourceswould not be equitably distributed.&#13;
&#13;
4.    The Government of former President Sanchez de Lozada acted with force, and in the&#13;
ensuing suppression 76 deaths and hundreds of injured were reported (all of indigenous&#13;
Aymara and Mestizo descent). This in turn led the then Vice-president Carlos Mesa to&#13;
dissociate himself from the President over the action, and soon after the coalition partners&#13;
also withdrew their support, forcing the President to resign.           Congress accepted the&#13;
resignation of President Lozada, and in accordance with the Bolivian Constitution, Vice-&#13;
PresidentMesa was sworn in as President. The new President then proceeded to appoint a&#13;
professional cabinet, selecting ministers outside of the traditional parties and laying out a&#13;
clear and manageableset of key political andeconomic priorities.&#13;
&#13;
5.     Inassuming office President Mesaput inmotionathree-steppolitical agenda. First,he&#13;
has proposed to modify the Hydrocarbons Law, with the aim of raising the effective tax&#13;
contribution of the oil and gas companies currently operating in Bolivia. Once this Law is&#13;
enacted, the President believes chances for a successful outcome of a Gas Project&#13;
Referendum, his second priority, will be high. This referendum could take place in the&#13;
 second quarter of 2004. The third priority on the President's agenda i s to call for a&#13;
Constitutional Assembly. While the assembly was initially proposed as a way to codify the&#13;
rights of indigenous peoples, it will by definition have unlimited powers -it could, for&#13;
 instance, give Bolivia a new federalist charter, establish mechanisms for revenue sharing&#13;
 across regions (notably, gas revenues), or call fresh elections.&#13;
&#13;
 6.    Bolivia's Constitution allows President Mesa to complete the original presidential term&#13;
 of Mr. Sanchez de Lozada, which will end August 2007. However, having called for a&#13;
 Constitutional Assembly, it is also possible that the Assembly could call for new general&#13;
 elections. The Constitutional Assembly will not be able to convene before some 14 months,&#13;
&#13;
                                              1&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
   as its members are yet to be elected and its operating rules agreed upon. This gives President&#13;
   Mesa a minimumeffective mandateof at least one and ahalf years.&#13;
&#13;
   7.     Inline with histhree top politicalpriorities, PresidentMesa announcedthree economic&#13;
   priorities for his administration: first, to uphold macroeconomic and fiscal discipline, the&#13;
   Government will continue to operate within the existing Stand-byAgreement with the IMF,&#13;
   buttressedby heightened attempts to collect more taxes; second, to make a series of small&#13;
   andinexpensive, but visible andhighly participatory micro interventions infavor of the poor,&#13;
   especially those living inthe areas most affected by the October events (El Alto and La Paz);&#13;
   and third, to re-launch the institutional reform agenda of fighting corruption, judicial reform,&#13;
   and the de-politicization of the civil service.&#13;
&#13;
   8.     Today, Bolivia is stable, but it is an uncertain and fragile stability.        The new&#13;
   administration of Mesa has inherited the same socioeconomic scenario that eventually led to&#13;
   the resignation of President Sanchez de Lozada. One of the casualties of the recent&#13;
   disturbances has been the shortening of what is considered the medium-term.               Some&#13;
   opposition groups have given President Mesa a limited time to resolve problems before&#13;
   launching another round of social conflict. The challenge for the Mesa government will be to&#13;
   keep social peace, convince the general public (and those threatening more social conflict)&#13;
   that the actions that the government i s implementing are substantive, even if they may not&#13;
   match exactly the opposition's original demands. Meetingthis challenge will be critical for&#13;
   the Mesa administration to carry out their agenda.&#13;
&#13;
                            B.     Social and Economic Developments&#13;
&#13;
   9.      On the socioeconomic side, over the last decade, three features stand out that helped&#13;
    fuel the general discontent present among large portions of the population-   lack of progress&#13;
    inpoverty reduction andhighinequality, the vulnerabilityof the economy to external shocks,&#13;
    and the precarious fiscal situation. Poverty reduction has been slow when reasonablerates of&#13;
    growth occurred (from 1990 to 1997). When growth rates declined (1998-2002), poverty&#13;
    increased (see Table 1).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
             Table 1. Poverty RatesModeratePoverty&#13;
                                   inBolivia, 1993-2002, (PercentagesofthePopulation)&#13;
                                                                         ExtremePoverty&#13;
                                                      Foster-&#13;
                       Headcountindex                 Greer-&#13;
                       of Poverty       Poverty Gap Thorbeckez      H           PG          FGT2&#13;
Bolivia        1993    52.04               22.15       12.48      23.66         8.40         4.52&#13;
               1997    63.59               33.73       22.73       36.47       18.93        12.51&#13;
               2000    66.38               40.16       29.8 1     45.16        26.32        19.53&#13;
               2002    65.15               36.65       25.95      41.34        22.3 1       16.00&#13;
Capital Cities 1997    50.69               20.99       11.53       21.33        7.46         3.77&#13;
               2000    52.03               23.66       14.02       25.69        9.80         5.44&#13;
               2002    51.01               22.05       12.56       23.94        8.77         4.72&#13;
Urban          1997    54.47               23.83       13.66       23.83        9.16         4.79&#13;
               2000    54.47               25.60       15.49       27.93       10.97         6.19&#13;
               2002    53.94               23.82       13.77       25.71        9.42         5.13&#13;
Rural          1997    78.01               49.40       37.07       58.96       34.39        24.73&#13;
               2000    87.02               65.39       54.62       75.01       52.92        42.65&#13;
               2002    83.41               57.56       45.80       66.80       43.31        33.70&#13;
Source: UDAPE,basedon householdsurveys, EM(1989-95); ENE(1996-97) and h4ECOVI(1999-2002).&#13;
&#13;
                                                  2&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
    10. Poverty outcomes have also been uneven-with                       significant differences across divisions&#13;
    of ruralhrban, highland/lowland and indigenoushonindigenous groups. The lack of&#13;
    significant progress in poverty reduction, the low level of private domestic investment (less&#13;
    than 1 percent of GDP in 2002), the stagnation of exports over the last twenty years&#13;
    (although the composition has changed) and continued high levels of informality have&#13;
    together to increasing questioning of the ability of the "economic model" to deliver the&#13;
    goods.&#13;
&#13;
    11. Bolivia's current fiscal problems are, inpart, a result of high growth rates experienced&#13;
    in the 1990s, led by an expansion of service sectors and exports. Ina pattern typical of&#13;
    positive shocks, there followed a bank credit boom, a shift in relative prices favoring the&#13;
    nontradable sector and increases in tax revenue with attendant increases in government&#13;
    expenditure. International reserves climbed and the primary fiscal balance before pensions&#13;
    reached 2.5 percent of GDP. At the end of 1997, there were expectations of sustained high&#13;
    growth for the entire LatinAmerican region, including Bolivia.&#13;
&#13;
     12. The positive shocks of the early and mid-1990s were followed by negative shocks in&#13;
    the late 1990s. As a result of the international capital market crisis of the late 1990s, there&#13;
    was a sudden drop in external financing leading to a reduction in growth in the entire Latin&#13;
    American region. Bolivia sufferedalong with other countries.&#13;
&#13;
     13.    Slower growth in trading partners led to slower growth in Bolivia as a result of lower&#13;
    demand for Bolivian goods and lower levels of remittances, principally from Bolivian&#13;
    workers in Argentina. The Brazilian and Argentine devaluations dramatically affected&#13;
    Bolivia's competitiveness. On the domestic side, a 70 percent drop in coca production&#13;
    between 1998 and 2002, while an important advance as a whole for the country, did reduce&#13;
    incomes. These shocks were only partly compensated for by the exploitation of new gas&#13;
    reserves. The net result of these shocks put considerable strain on the corporate and banking&#13;
     sectors. As the slowdown ingrowth occurred, the government and privatebank's response to&#13;
     strengthen the financial sector led to a credit crunch.' The overall lending portfolio shrank&#13;
     (as the banks adjusted to the less promising investment climate) and the share of non-&#13;
     performingloans increased.&#13;
&#13;
     14. These shocks and the resulting slowdown in growth led to drops in per capita income&#13;
     (see Table 2), increasesinpoverty and pressureon the fiscal balance.&#13;
&#13;
      Table 2. GDP GrowthRatesper CapitainBolivia,LAC andworld, 1961-2002 (inpercent)&#13;
                                     1961-70         1971-80            1981-90          1991-99       2000-2002~&#13;
     Bolivia                           0.35             1.67             -1.95             1.53             -0.20&#13;
     Andean Region"                     1.51           2.09              -1.18             0.77             0.06&#13;
     LAC**                             2.71             3.44             -0.74             2.05             -0.21&#13;
     World***                          4.15             2.68              2.29             1.72              0.99&#13;
     Note: *Simple average, own calculations **Weighted average, n= 26.           *** Weighted   average, n= 109&#13;
     Source:Based onLoayza, Fajnzylber and Calderon, 2002 and WDI. 2000-02 preliminary estimates.&#13;
&#13;
'  During 1995-2000 the Government passed several important new regulations, aimed at strengthening banks and enhancing&#13;
supervision. The most salient of them included new capital rules, as a result of which bank capital more than doubled during&#13;
1995-2000, from US$235million to US$495 million. The impact of these regulationsinterms of credit availability was stronger&#13;
after the shock of the late 1990s when banks stoppedborrowing abroad and the economy started to decelerated, leading both to&#13;
scarce bank liquidity.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                            3&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
15. In addition, the fall inper capita income was not uniform (see Figure 1). The drop was&#13;
greatest among the lowest income deciles inthe rural areas and inall but the wealthiest decile&#13;
in the urban areas. The recent declines inper capita income inurban areas has helped fuel&#13;
the increasing social unrest.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Figure 1. Change in Household Income per capita by Income Decile and Area, 1999-2002&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                4.0%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                 2.0%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                 0.0%&#13;
&#13;
                 .2,0%&#13;
&#13;
                 4 0 %&#13;
&#13;
                 .6,0%&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                -12 0%                                                                        1&#13;
                      1     2     3            4         5          6        7    8    9    1 0&#13;
&#13;
                                   D e c i l e s o f per capita i n c o m e&#13;
&#13;
16.    Throughout this past decade the impatience with the rate of poverty reduction was&#13;
exacerbated by unresolved issues related to land reform, social exclusion and inequality.&#13;
There i s a strong risk, accented by recent protests, that Bolivia could fall into a downward&#13;
social spiral if fiscal adjustment is made too quickly.                    As the February 2003 events&#13;
mentioned in Section A have made clear, the volatile socioeconomic situation impedes the&#13;
Government from tackling serious cutbacks in its transfer of resources to the social sectors&#13;
out of fear of renewed discontent and violence, The current fiscal problems are thus also&#13;
exacerbated by increasing costs of reforms, particularly inpensions (see Figure 2). In some&#13;
cases, there were political decisions that affected the way in which reforms were&#13;
implemented. In other cases, with hindsight, some of the reforms were either premature or&#13;
relied on assumptions that the relatively high growth rates of the mid-1990s would continue&#13;
inorder to cover future costs.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                     4&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                         Figure 2. Fiscal Balance and Tax Revenue&#13;
&#13;
       10%                                                                    - 20%&#13;
        8%                                                                    - 19%&#13;
        6%                                                                    -  18%&#13;
  %                                                                           - 17% %&#13;
  of    4%&#13;
  G     2%                                                                       16% Gof&#13;
                                                                              -&#13;
   DP 0%                                                                         15% DP&#13;
        -2%                                                                      14%&#13;
        -4%                                                                      13%&#13;
        -6%                                                                      12%&#13;
        -8%                                                                      11%&#13;
      -10%   '                                                                '  10%&#13;
              1995     1996     1997      1998     1999      2000   2001 2002&#13;
                     mOverallfiscalbalance(LHS)&#13;
                           Fiscaldeficit due to pension reform (LHS)&#13;
                      -0-Taxrevenues(RHS)&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
17.   One of the key challenges facing the new government will be to manage this fiscal&#13;
deficit. To date, the deficit for 2003 i s expectedto reach 7.5 percent of GDP, that is to say, 1&#13;
percentage point higher than the pre-October IMF projected figure. The increase in this&#13;
year's overall fiscal deficit is due to the result of both unexpected lower tax collections and&#13;
higher expenditures, (0.4 and 0.5 percentage point of GDP, respectively). These unexpected&#13;
changes were largely in part the result of the February and October events which slowed&#13;
down the economy, hence tax collections were lower than programmed; and led the&#13;
government to compensate sectors of the economy directed affected by the events, e.g., the&#13;
families of the protest victims and military forces. Inaddition, the drop inexternal financing&#13;
(amounting to 0.1 percentage points of the overall deficit in terms GDP) had largely to do&#13;
with failure of the government to produce a Poverty Reduction Strategy Paper (PRSP)&#13;
consulted with civil society before the end of calendar 2003, which in turn led to postpone&#13;
the World Bank US$30m planned Poverty Reduction Strategy Credit (PRSC) and the IMF's&#13;
(Poverty Reduction and Growth Facility (PRGF). The end result of the higher than expected&#13;
deficit has been the generation of a US$94 million financing gap, which i s presently beyond&#13;
the financial capacity of the Government ( see Table 3).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 5&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                               Table 3. Bolivia: Treasury FinancingNeeds, 2003&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                  (inmillions of USdollars)&#13;
                                                            Expected                 Expencted&#13;
                                                       before October2003        after October 2003  Diff.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Current revenues                                                     1703.0             1681.4   -21.7&#13;
     Current expenditure of GeneralGovernment                             1526.6             1558.0    31.4&#13;
     Official grants                                                      222.5                216.0   -6.5&#13;
     Capitalrevenues                                                        0.0                  0.0    0.0&#13;
     Capital expenditure                                                  560.0                578.5   18.4&#13;
     Pensionrelated net expenditure                                       375.9                377.9   -2.0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Overall deficit                                                      537.0                617.0   80.0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Net domestic financing                                                85.3                 160.3  75.0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
     Net external financing                                               451.7                390.5  -61.2&#13;
      Disbursements                                                       745.9                707.2  -38.7&#13;
          Nonconcessionaldisbursements                                     386.1               408.7   22.6&#13;
          Concessionaldisbursements                                        359.8               298.5  -61.3&#13;
            Of which: programfinancing                                     171.0                141.0 -30.0&#13;
            WB                                                             168.8                136.1 -32.7&#13;
            Other                                                          191.0                162.4 -28.6&#13;
      Amortization I /                                                    -294.2              -316.7  -22.5&#13;
           Concessional                                                    -43.6                -43.6    0.0&#13;
           Nonconcessional                                                -316.1               -338.6 -22.5&#13;
           HIF'C relief                                                     65.5                 65.5    0.0&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                             0.0                 66.2  66.2&#13;
                                                                             0.0                 94.0   94.0&#13;
                                                                             0.0                 27.8   27.8&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      'l'rcw,ur&gt;Gap Financing                                                                    94.0   94.0&#13;
              World Bank                                                                         44.0   44.0&#13;
                 Emergency RecoveryCredit                                        14.0&#13;
                 InstitutionalReform Loan                                        20.0&#13;
                 Social Safety Network                                           10.0&#13;
              IDB EnhancedCompetitive Loan                                                       50.0   50.0&#13;
     1/ Includes debt relief fromflow rescheduling and CAF subscription. Before HIPC debt relief.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                       C.     Bank's Assistance Strategy&#13;
&#13;
18.        The IDA emergency package, of which the proposedEERP for SDRs 9.8 million ($14&#13;
million) is an integral component, is being prepared in conjunction with the upcoming CAS,&#13;
currently scheduled for Board discussion in January 2004. This CAS will cover the two year&#13;
period, FYO4-FYO5.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                6&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
19.      The main objectives of the upcoming CAS are to help strengthen governance,&#13;
accelerateefforts to reduce inequality and exclusion, support macro-economic stability and limit,&#13;
if possible, reverse the impact of the crisis on the poor. At this decisive moment in Bolivia's&#13;
history, there are substantial uncertainties and risks of proceeding with significant financial&#13;
support to Bolivia, but such support also holds the promise of recovery and renewing stability,&#13;
and without it the risks would be far greater. The upcoming CAS envisages four main&#13;
instrumentsinresponseto the current crisis:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                 i. TheimmediateIDAemergencyassistancepackageincludes,inadditionto&#13;
                       the proposed $14 million Development Credit for the EERP: a) The&#13;
                       proposed release in December 2003 of the pending second tranche of $10&#13;
                       million of the existing Social Safety Net SAC (the tranche release document&#13;
                       i s scheduled to be distributed to the Board shortly, for its no objection).&#13;
                       This operation, which was presented to the Board in June 2003, was&#13;
                       conceived as a mechanism to protect priority social expenditures after the&#13;
                       February crisis, an objective whose importance and urgency have only&#13;
                       increased; and key tranche conditions have been met; and, b) the&#13;
                        acceleration of an existing operation in the portfolio, the Bolivia&#13;
                       Institutional Reform project, with $20 million envisaged to be directed&#13;
                       towards funding of wages and salaries of civil servant hired through&#13;
                       competitive andtransparent mechanismsinpilot agencies.*&#13;
                 ..&#13;
                 11.   Reassigning funds from ongoing IDA operations ($5.6 million) to support&#13;
                        small but visible social investment projects in the La Paz and El Alto&#13;
                       municipalities;&#13;
                ...&#13;
                111.   New lending; and,&#13;
&#13;
                iv.    Rapid-response technical assistance in critical areas for the new&#13;
                        administration, notably, the drafting of the Hydrocarbon Law, consultations&#13;
                        on banking, public expenditure review (PER), and anti-corruption (CFAA).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 Currently, the Superintendenciade Servicio Civil (an independentagency) has incorporated to the Civil Service&#13;
2,474 public employees following the rules of the Civil Service Statute. Only 350 of them are being financed by the&#13;
project.&#13;
&#13;
                                                         7&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
20. Table 4 below lays out the finer details of this short-term strategy.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                      Table4. Short-termCAS programfor Bolivia&#13;
&#13;
      To accelerateefforts to reduce inequality and exclusionthe Bank will use a combination of&#13;
      existing projects in its portfolio and new projects to help reduce inequality and exclusion. In&#13;
       the existing portfolio, the projects that are most closely associatedwith these objectives are:&#13;
&#13;
       0   Indigenous People's Development Project (US$4.3 Mleft to disburse)&#13;
       0   Participatory Rural Investment Project (US$39.7 Mleft to disburse)&#13;
       0   Social Safety Net Structural Adjustment Credit (US$10 Mleft to disburse)&#13;
       0   Second Health ReformProgram(directed to reduce disparities inhealth outcomes by&#13;
           income, region and ethnicity US$30.2 Mleft to disburse);&#13;
       0   Education Quality and Equity Strengthening Project (allows for customized approaches&#13;
           depending on needs of the communities, US$10.2Mleft to disburse)&#13;
       0   National LandAdministration Project (US$3.9 Mleft to disburse)&#13;
&#13;
       The new projects inthe upcoming 2-year CAS directedto the objectives of reducing&#13;
       inequality and exclusion are:&#13;
&#13;
       0   Social Sector Programmatic Credit (will be designed to accelerateprogress towards&#13;
           MDGs,US$20M)&#13;
       0   Spatial economic developmentkommunity-drivendevelopment (will be designed to&#13;
           address problems of poor ingenerating income, US$21M)&#13;
       0   LandReform(US$15 M)&#13;
&#13;
       The projects and activities directedtowards achieving macro-stability are:&#13;
&#13;
           A banking, financial and corporate restructuringloanof US$30 million (US$15 MIDA&#13;
           and US$15 MIBRD)inJanuary, 2004 with the CAS;&#13;
           Eithera secondphase of banking, financial and corporate sector loan inFY 05 or support&#13;
           for fiscal adjustment measures.&#13;
           Work with all donors on meeting projected fiscal deficit gap for 2004. Try to impress on&#13;
            all donors the need to take corrective action to ensure the financial sustainability of past&#13;
            reforms. This may involve discussion on how to finance transition costs associated with&#13;
            the pension reform;&#13;
            Facilitate exchanges between Bolivia and Guatemala so that Bolivia could benefit from&#13;
            Guatemala's experience in enacting a fiscal pact that helped to secure broad-based&#13;
            support for measures to managefiscal deficit problems;&#13;
            Reduce temporarily counterpart financing requirements inWB projects to zero;&#13;
            Discuss results of Public Expenditure Review with government to see how high impacl&#13;
            expenditures can be prioritized and lower impact expenditures be cut; and&#13;
            Support Poverty and Social Impact Analysis (PSIA) to help government calculate ex ante&#13;
            the likely effects of possible changesto try to restore macroeconomic stability.&#13;
&#13;
        On Governance, the plannedPER and CFAA will provide a good basis to consider projects&#13;
        on governance for the secondphaseof the Mesa administration (after the Constitutional&#13;
        Assembly), where the Bank, through a new CAS, would propose a package of financial&#13;
        assistance to address issueson corruption and financial sustainability.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                   8&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
21.       Donor Support. Overall support from the international financial institutions (IFI) has&#13;
been positive, expressing strong support for the present administration in implementing its short&#13;
term political and socioeconomic agenda.                 In addition to the IDA emergency package, on&#13;
December 17, IDB is presenting to its Board a proposal to increase the tranche amount from $15&#13;
to $65 million of a Competition Loan. A $50 million emergency loan, under the terms of the&#13;
latter, is embodied in this tranche. IMF on the other hand, if the on-going review of Stand-By&#13;
Arrangement (SBA) is approved, will disburse the remaining SDR 42.87 million, although this&#13;
will be to build up reserves and will take place before the SBA expires on April 1, 2004.&#13;
Bilateral donors, including the Netherlands, Denmark and USAID, are providing a total amount&#13;
of approximately $15.5 million in grants for balance of payments support. The Corporacion&#13;
Andina de Foment0 (CAF) i s approving approximately $55 million devoted to finance social&#13;
infrastructure projects, technical assistance, andbalance of payments support.&#13;
&#13;
               D.        Rationale for Emergency Economic Recovery Project&#13;
&#13;
22.       In Bolivia there exists at present a clear momentum for greater political and economic&#13;
influence from a growing social indigenous movement. Evenbefore the latest round of conflicts,&#13;
it became apparent that pressuring the government through demonstrations in the streets-&#13;
whether violent or otherwise-was             a winning political strategy. The recent resignation of Mr.&#13;
Lozada confirmed this.&#13;
&#13;
23.       The proposed EERP, in conjunction with two other components of the IDA emergency&#13;
package describedinSection C, has the objective of providing support to the poor and vulnerable&#13;
by making available external funds for critical foreign goods (whether or not directly imported&#13;
by the Government), including medicines, agricultural machinery (tractors), and diesel&#13;
oil/ga~oline.~     As such, it is an integral part of the Bank's short-term strategy under the upcoming&#13;
CAS and i s needed to supportBolivia's recovery program set forth inSection A above.&#13;
&#13;
24.       The proposed credit is structured as an emergency recovery operation in recognition of&#13;
the crisis nature of the long-standing socioeconomic tensions that have led to frequent episodes&#13;
of civil unrest over the last 2 years, escalatedinFebruary 2003, and culminated this past October&#13;
with the resignation of President Sanchez de Lozada. IDA funds are sought at this time because&#13;
Bolivia's fiscal and external balances are insufficient to cover critical needs inthe short term. It&#13;
i s now critical that the Mesa administration not disrupt its domestic public service financial&#13;
obligations, but continue past reforms and programs aimed at addressing many of the unmet&#13;
demands that persist in the country.               Failure to do so could further unrest and a possible&#13;
undemocratic, and uncontrollable, solution to the current problems facing Bolivia. The Bank's&#13;
capacity to assist Bolivia would then be much impaired and many of the positive development&#13;
outcomes achievedover the past two decades (e.g., inthe social sectors) could be lost.&#13;
&#13;
 25.       Inproposing the EERP operation for Board approval, management recognizes that OP&#13;
 8.50 on emergency recovery assistance does not strictly apply to the Bolivia situation in&#13;
 question. This is because the OP defines an emergency as an extraordinary event of limited&#13;
 duration (typically a natural disaster, war or civil disturbance) that seriously disrupts the&#13;
 borrowers economy. Consequently, the OP excludes from the definition a situation more akin to&#13;
&#13;
  Tractors were exclusively imported to attend the demands from the Campesinos after a series of street protests&#13;
 earlier this year; there exists a Supreme Decree authorizing the purchase of such machinery.&#13;
&#13;
                                                           9&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
one where long-standing socioeconomic tensions generate sporadic instances of civil unrest. In&#13;
such cases, the OP indicates that adjustment lending could be justified instead of emergency&#13;
recovery lending.&#13;
&#13;
26.    Nevertheless, managementbelieves that Bolivia i s a candidate for support under OP 8.50&#13;
even if the event coincident with the latest flare-up of the Bolivian crisis (the anti-tax increase&#13;
disturbances of February 2003) does not formally constitute an emergency for policy purposes.&#13;
Regardless of labels, the fact remains that Boliviansociety, and particularly its poorest sectors, i s&#13;
negatively affected by the situation and that the Government needs financial support to mitigate&#13;
the impact and initiate a recovery, The Association, through this proposed credit, can assist in&#13;
that effort by financing critical goods needed to promote capital investment and to maintain&#13;
economic activity threatened by a backlog of deferred expenditures that must be overcome in&#13;
order for recovery and growth to be possible and for a reduction inthe possibility of further civil&#13;
unrest. Adjustment lending could provide quick disbursement to this end, however, absent new&#13;
conditionality not already associated with other planned operations, the adjustment vehicle&#13;
would be difficult to use. Hence, management is requesting a waiver to OP 8.50 definition of&#13;
emergency as part of the proposed Board approval of this operation. To the extent some of the&#13;
required goods are technically not imported by the Government (i.e., to the extent they are&#13;
obtained from local importers by the Government in what is a purely domestic post-import&#13;
transaction, paid either inlocal or foreign currency), managementalso requests a waiver from the&#13;
OP 8.50 requirement that the fast-disbursing component of an emergency recovery operation&#13;
focus solely on financing a positive list of imports. Otherwise the Government may not be in a&#13;
position to document a sufficient number of its own expenditures against which to disburse all&#13;
the credit proceeds.&#13;
&#13;
                                  E.      Project Description&#13;
&#13;
27.     The proceeds of the proposed SDR 9.8 million (US$14 million) credit would provide&#13;
quick disbursing financing against a list of goods, which cannot be providedthrough the existing&#13;
Bank portfolio or by additional donor financing.&#13;
&#13;
28.     The proposed Credit would be on hardened IDA terms - 10 years grace and 20 years&#13;
maturity - as Bolivia is over the IDA income threshold.&#13;
&#13;
29.     Critical goods for reconstruction, economic recovery and mitigation of the social crisis&#13;
which this credit would finance are listed in Schedule A of this Technical Annex. A summary&#13;
of the proposed procurement i s shown in Schedule B and financial management and&#13;
disbursement arrangements are detailed in Section F below. Consistent with the emergency&#13;
nature of the proposed support, these arrangements have been simplified and streamlined to the&#13;
extent feasible, while seeking to ensure that overall concerns about due diligence, transparency,&#13;
and avoiding misuseof funds are addressed.&#13;
&#13;
30.     Lessons learned. Indesigning this Emergency Project, the team drew from experience of&#13;
other emergency operations. The team reviewed the Nicaragua Hurricane Emergency Project&#13;
(December 14, 1998), the Third Economic Assistance Grant to the United Nations Interim&#13;
Administration in Kosovo (March 2001), the Eritrea Emergency Recovery Credit (October 23,&#13;
2000), the Tonga Cyclone Emergency Recovery and Management Project (May 7, 2002), the&#13;
Madagascar Emergency Economic Recovery Credit (November 14, 2002) and the OED-review&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 10&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
of the Haiti Emergency Recovery Credit (Review: May 1997: Credit: May 1995). Drawing from&#13;
these sources, the following key lessonshavebeen incorporatedinthe design of this credit:&#13;
&#13;
      (i)  Early engagement is critical. While there are risks associated with emergency&#13;
           operations, potential rewards are also higher.&#13;
      (ii)Emergency     post-conflict assistance should have a simple streamlined design. Inthe&#13;
           aftermath of a crisis, liquidity needs to be injected rapidly to mitigate the social and&#13;
           economic impact of the crisis. Complicated implementation arrangements would&#13;
           overburden an already weak administration and slow-down the transfer of resources.&#13;
           Hence this EERP contains only a quick-disbursing component&#13;
      (iii)Emergency operations should complement other Bank and donor post-crisis&#13;
           assistance. Emergency operations are typically part of a broader assistance package.&#13;
           Reform conditionality i s left to follow-on operations.        This EERP effectively&#13;
           complements the upcoming CAS, which takes into account more complex investment&#13;
           needs after the crisis.&#13;
&#13;
31.    Monitoring and Evaluation. The Government and IDA have agreed that verification of&#13;
the financing provided by the overall IDA assistance package on whether it has arrived at the&#13;
intended beneficiarieskovered the identified goods will be monitored closely. Given that the&#13;
proposed emergency package covers many sectors, monitoring of the upcoming CAS and the&#13;
package will be closely linked to the monitoring of key poverty and social development&#13;
indicators presently beingdesignedfor the CAS.&#13;
&#13;
32.    Environmental Impact. The implementation of this EERP is not expected to have&#13;
negative environmental impacts. It has been given a Category "C" rating, cleared by the&#13;
LCESE-QualityAssurance Team.&#13;
&#13;
                            F.       Institutional Arrangements&#13;
&#13;
33.    Project Implementation. The Government established a Project Coordination Committee&#13;
(PCC) chaired by the Minister of Finance and comprising representatives of all implementing&#13;
agencies involved in the procurement of goods and commodities required during the crisis&#13;
period.&#13;
&#13;
34.     For management of the emergency the implementing agencies involved in procurement&#13;
of goods are: Yacimientos Petroliferos Fiscales Bolivianos (YPFB), the public sector company&#13;
responsible for production andbulk commercialization of oil and hydrocarbon products and for&#13;
purchasing of diesel oil from private sector importers; the Ministry of Agriculture, and Livestock&#13;
and Rural Development (MAG), and Fondo de Desarrollo del Sistema Financier0 y de Apoyo a&#13;
Sector Productivo (FONDESIF) for purchases of agriculture machinery; and the Ministry of&#13;
Health (MOH) for purchases of medicines.           The PCC is responsible for overall project&#13;
coordination and achievement of project objectives.&#13;
&#13;
35.     The Ministry of Finance will be incharge of monitoring andtracking the useof the credit&#13;
proceedsthrough the Vice-ministry of Treasury andPublic Credit.&#13;
&#13;
 36.    Retroactive Financing. The proposed credit will reimburse retroactively 100 percent of&#13;
the expenditures incurred to purchase the items identified in Schedule B of this report, in&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                 11&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
accordance with OP 8.50 and under the provision stated in OP 12. 10 paragraph 3 which allows&#13;
the Regional Vice Presidency to approve this increase inretroactive financing eligibility. Given&#13;
the current crisidemergency situation in Bolivia and the resulting urgency of providing the&#13;
financing for critical goods Bank regional management has agreed to provide 100percent of the&#13;
IDA credit to be eligible for retroactive financing for those items on the positive list from&#13;
February 13,2003.&#13;
&#13;
37.      Procurement Issues. Procurement arrangements for purchases of goods and commodities&#13;
have been set on the basis of a pre-identified positive list of imports to be financed under the&#13;
proposed ERC. Imported items agreed for retroactive financing will be diesel oil; medicines and&#13;
agriculture machinery (tractors). Eligible imported goods as medicines shall be procured with&#13;
the use of international competitive bidding procedures; commodities such as diesel oil through&#13;
established international commodity markets or international commercial practices, acceptable to&#13;
IDA; while agriculture machinery (tractors) through direct purchase.              A summary of&#13;
procurement arrangements for goods and commodities i s provided inSchedule B of this report.&#13;
&#13;
38.      Disbursement and Financial Management Issues. The proposed EERP will be disbursed&#13;
as a one-time transaction event from the Bank treated as a reimbursement to the Government&#13;
against a positive list of goods defined in Schedule A. In accordance with the positive list in&#13;
Schedule A, once the credit becomes effective, withdrawal application(s) are to be prepared by&#13;
the Government and submitted to IDA for reimbursement following standard disbursement&#13;
procedures and with the appropriate supporting documentation under investment lending. In&#13;
addition to the supporting documentation for each expenditure claimed, a Summary Statement&#13;
prepared by the implementing entity on the use o f funds showing the type of expenditure as well&#13;
as the cumulative amounts for each type of expenditure shouldbe provided with each withdrawal&#13;
application(s). Reimbursement for foreign expenditures would be made at 100% in the foreign&#13;
currency paid by the Government for those goods imported directly or which had been imported&#13;
by third parties explicitly acting as agents on behalf of the Government. Other goods imported&#13;
by third parties and which have been supplied to the Government in the country through local&#13;
procedures and paid by the Government in local currency (Bolivianos) would be reimbursed in&#13;
such local currency at 85%.&#13;
&#13;
39.      Upon the Association's request, the Borrower shall have the proceeds of the credit&#13;
audited in accordance with appropriate auditing standards, applied by independent auditors&#13;
acceptable to the Association. Such an audit will be submitted to the Bank as soon as available,&#13;
but in any case not later than four months after the date of the Association's request for such an&#13;
audit.&#13;
&#13;
                              G.     ProjectBenefits and Risks&#13;
&#13;
40.      Benefits. The project aims to provide financing of critical goods to help address Bolivia's&#13;
immediate crisis needs. Inaddition, the financing would be part o f a package of external support&#13;
to help close Bolivia's financing requirements and thereby support political and macroeconomic&#13;
 stabilization.  By increasing short-term flexibility, the project would also indirectly help the&#13;
 Government in moving forward and implementing its short and medium term political and&#13;
 economic priorities. This credit would constitute a critical component o f the Bank's medium&#13;
 term strategy for Bolivia, which will be discussed at the Board on January 15, 2004.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  12&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
41.     Project Risks. It i s not clear whether ensuring the continued provision of public services&#13;
would help fully mitigate the precarious political and macro environment that continues to&#13;
persist.&#13;
&#13;
42.     First, while the general population seems willing to support the President's efforts, there&#13;
are still radical elements among the union-indigenous movement that would like the political&#13;
system changed. Second, while independence from political parties and the President's cabinet&#13;
of technicians have been an asset in front of the public, the President will need to work with&#13;
those parties in Congress to see through his various legislative initiatives. Third, while the&#13;
President and his team appear committed and professional, they will have to rely on a civil&#13;
service that posses little capacity to implement their policies given its past history o f political&#13;
patronage. Fourth, the gas referendum may prove difficult to arrange or it may simply turn out a&#13;
negative response to the gas export question. Finally, there i s no way to predict the outcome of&#13;
the Constitutional Assembly or the extent of its actions.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                  13&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                    SCHEDULEA&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                BOLIVIA&#13;
&#13;
             EMERGENCYCREDIT RECOVERYPROJECT&#13;
&#13;
                          Positive List of Goods&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Medicines&#13;
&#13;
Agriculture Equipment and Machinery&#13;
&#13;
Diesel Oil&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     14&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                SCHEDULEB&#13;
&#13;
                                         BOLIVIA&#13;
&#13;
          POLITICAL AND SOCIALEMERGENCYRECOVERINGPROJECT&#13;
&#13;
                Summary of ProcurementandDisbursementArrangements&#13;
&#13;
A.     ProcurementArrangements&#13;
&#13;
        PROCUREMENTCATEGORY                     PROCUREMENTMETHOD&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   Medicines                                    Through international competitive bidding&#13;
                                                procedures provided under Paras. 2.63-2.64&#13;
                                                of IDA'SProcurement Guidelines&#13;
   Agricultural Equipment (Tractors)            Through direct purchase inaccordance&#13;
                                                with the provisions of par. 3.7 of IDA'S&#13;
                                                Procurement Guidelines&#13;
&#13;
   Commodities (diesel oil; gasoline)           Through establishedinternational&#13;
                                                commodity markets or international&#13;
                                                commercial practices, acceptableto IDA,&#13;
                                                as definedinParagraph2.65 of IDA'S&#13;
                                                Procurement Guidelines&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
B.      DisbursementsArrangements&#13;
&#13;
                                   Amount of the&#13;
                                  Credit Allocated               % of&#13;
                                   (Expressedin             Expenditures&#13;
       Category                   SDREquivalent)           to beFinanced&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
(1)   Goods                          9,800,000             100% of foreign&#13;
                                                          expenditures; 85     percent of local&#13;
expenditures.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                              15&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                                 SCHEDULEC&#13;
&#13;
                                                      CAS Annex 82 -Bolivia&#13;
        Selected Indicators*of Bank PortfolioPerformanceand Management&#13;
                                                     As Of Date 12/04/2003&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Indicator                                                              2001                   2002 2003 2004&#13;
PortfolioAssessment&#13;
Number of Projects Under Implementationa                                  17                     18   17   17&#13;
Average ImplementationPeriod(years)                                       3.0                    3.8 4.3  4.7&#13;
Percentof Problem Projects by Number          a,c                        23.5                    5.6 17.6 17.6&#13;
Percentof Problem Projects by Amount          a,                         35.0                    9.0 18.7 18.7&#13;
Percentof Projectsat Risk by Numbera,d                                   23.5                  11.1  17.6 17.6&#13;
Percentof Projectsat Risk by Amount         a,d                          35.0                    9.7 18.7 18.7&#13;
Disbursement Ratio (%)     e                                             14.5                  23.8  18.2 8.7&#13;
PortfolioManagement&#13;
CPPR duringthe year (yesho)                                              Yes                   Yes   Yes  Yes&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Memorandum Item                                      Since FY 80              Last FiveFYs&#13;
Proj Eva1by OED by Number                                                 55                       7&#13;
Proj Eva1by OED by Amt (US$ millions)                                1,293.1                 225.5&#13;
% of OED Projects Rated U or HU by Number                                25.5                    0.0&#13;
% of OED Projects Rated U or HU by Amt                                   18.0                    0.0&#13;
&#13;
a. As shown in the Annual Report on PortfolioPerformance(exceptfor current FY).&#13;
b. Average age of projectsin the Bank's country portfolio.&#13;
c. Percentof projects rated U or HU on developmentobjectives(DO) and/or implementationprogress(IP).&#13;
d. As defined under the Portfolio ImprovementProgram.&#13;
e. Ratioof disbursementsduring the year to the undisbursedbalance of the Bank's portfolioat the&#13;
   beginning of the year: Investmentprojectsonly.&#13;
* All indicatorsare for projectsactive in the Portfolio, with the exception of DisbursementRatio,&#13;
  which includesall active projects as well as projectswhich exited during the fiscal year,&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                            16&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
s    N -     2&#13;
r    O::     N&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
            m m&#13;
           - 7&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                                                                        SCHEDULEE&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Technical notes&#13;
                                         Bolivia at a glance                                                                           8/20/03&#13;
&#13;
                                                                          Lath     Lower-&#13;
POVERTY and SOCIAL                                                      Amerlca   middle-&#13;
                                                                Bolivia aCarib.   Income       DeveloDmentdiamond'&#13;
2002&#13;
Population,mid-year(millions)                                      8.7     527      2,411                       Life expectancy&#13;
GNi per capita(Atlasmethod, US$)                                  900    3,280      1,390&#13;
GNI (Atlasmethod, US$billions)                                     7.8   1,727      3,352                              T&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Averaae annual growth, 1996-02&#13;
Population(%)                                                      2.3      1.5        1.o&#13;
Laborforce (%)                                                     2.7     2.2         1.2     GNI                                    Gross&#13;
                                                                                               per                                  primary&#13;
Most recent estimate (latestvear avaliable, 1996-02)                                           capita                              nroilment&#13;
Poverty(% ofpopulationbelownafionalpovemline)                       63&#13;
Urbanpopulation (% of totalpopulation)                              63       76        49&#13;
Life expectancyat birth(years)                                      64       71        69                              I&#13;
Infantmortality(per 1,000livebirths)                                58       27        30&#13;
Childmalnutrition PO of children under5)                              8       9        11               Access to improvedwater source&#13;
Access to an improvedwater sou&amp; (% ofpopulation)                    83       86        81&#13;
Illiteracy(% ofpopulationage 154                                    13       11        13&#13;
Grass primawenrollment (% of school-agepopulation)                 116     130        111                     Bolivia&#13;
    Male                                                           117     131        111                     Lower-middle-incomegroup&#13;
    Female                                                         115     128        110&#13;
&#13;
KEYECONOMIC RATIOSand LONG-TERMTRENDS&#13;
                                                   1982          1992     2001       2002&#13;
                                                                                               Economicratios.&#13;
GDP (US$ billions)                                  3.0            5.6      8.0        7.7&#13;
Grass domesticinvestmenVGDP                         15.6          16.7    13.0&#13;
Exportsof qoods andservicesJGDP                     29.1         20.0     18.3                                       Trade&#13;
&#13;
Grass domesticsavingsIGDP                           15.3           7.7      6.8                                        -&#13;
Grass nationalsavingdGDP                            9.3            8.6      9.1&#13;
Currentaccount baiancelGDP                          -5.8          -9.5     -3.7&#13;
interestpawnents1GDP                                6.4             1.9     2.1        1.3     Domestic                           Investment&#13;
TotaldeWGDP                                       111.6          75.0     58.7       59.1      savings&#13;
&#13;
Totaldebt servicelexports                           59.1         34.6     30.8       31.O&#13;
Presentvalue of deWGDP                                                    25.0                                         I&#13;
&#13;
Presentvalue of deWexwrts                                                 112.9&#13;
                                                                                                                   Indebtedness&#13;
                                       1982-92  1992-02          2001     2002    2002-06&#13;
(average annualgrolufh)&#13;
GDP                                        1.5       3.5                                             x _ u **-Bolivia&#13;
                                                                  -1.o&#13;
                                                                    1.2     2.5        3.7&#13;
GDP per capna                             -0.6       1.1                    0.4        1.7                    Lower-middle-incomeorom&#13;
Exportsof qoods andservices                5.3       3.8            4.9&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
STRUCTURE of the ECONOMY&#13;
                                                   1982          1992     2001       2002&#13;
(%ofGDPJ&#13;
Agriculture                                                       16.0     15.7&#13;
Industw                                                           33.6    28.6&#13;
    Manufacturing                                                 19.1     15.3&#13;
Services                                               ........   50.4     55.8&#13;
Privateconsumption                                  72.9          79.4     78.4&#13;
Generalgovemmentconsumption                         11.8          12.9     14.8&#13;
lmwrts of goods and services                        29.4          29.1     24.5&#13;
&#13;
                                                 1982-92 1992-02          2001       2002&#13;
(average annualqrolufh)                                                                        Growlh of exports and imports (Oh)&#13;
&#13;
Agriculture                                            ........     2.8      1.1               30T&#13;
&#13;
Industw                                                             3.6      0.5               20&#13;
    Manufacturing                                                   3.6      1.1               10&#13;
Services                                                            4.2      1.6               0&#13;
 Privateconsumption                                  2.4            3.6      1.o              -10                                           2&#13;
Generalqovemmentconsumption                         -2.5            3.4      3.2              -20&#13;
Gross domestic investment                            7.1            5.3   -23.9&#13;
 lmwrts of goods and services                        9.4            4.5    -7.4&#13;
&#13;
 Note:2002 data are preliminaryestimates.&#13;
This table was producedfromthe Development Economicscentraldatabase.&#13;
 * The diamondsshowfour key indicatorsin the COUntW(in bold) comparedwith its income-groupaverage. If data are missing, the diamondwill&#13;
     be incomplete.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                18&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                                                              Bolivia&#13;
&#13;
PRICES and GOVERNMENT FINANCE&#13;
                                                1982     1992       2001   2002&#13;
Domesticprice5                                                                       Inflation(Oh)&#13;
&#13;
    change)                                                                        Il5                                               ` I&#13;
Consumerprices                                           10.5         0.9    0.5&#13;
Implicit GDP deflator                           159.4    13.2         0.7    2.0&#13;
&#13;
Governmentfinance&#13;
("A of GDP, includescurrentgrants)&#13;
Current revenue                                          23.8        25.2  26.1               97       98    99         M    01&#13;
Current budget balance                                    5.6         0.8   -0.4   1           -?-GDP       deflator -0-W&#13;
Overallsurplusldeficit                                    -4.4       -6.7   -7.5&#13;
&#13;
TRADE&#13;
                                                1982     1992       2001   2002&#13;
(US$ millions)                                                                     I Export and Importlevels (US$ mill.)               h&#13;
                                                                                   /L_l&#13;
Total exports (fob)                                       636       1,285  1,192&#13;
  Hydrocarbons-gas                                        134        302&#13;
  Soya                                                     57        275&#13;
  Manufactures                                            116         178&#13;
Total imports(ciR                                       1,090       1,724  1,743&#13;
  Food                                                    196        435&#13;
  Fuel and energy                                         456         891                                                              I&#13;
  Capital goods                                           439         398   491&#13;
&#13;
Exportpriceindex (1995=100)                               102         85     87             96       97  98     99      00   01&#13;
&#13;
Importprice index (1995=100)                               92         99     100                W Exqorts         HImports          O2&#13;
Terms of trade (1995=100)                                 111         86     87&#13;
&#13;
BALANCEof PAYMENTS&#13;
                                                1982     1992       2001   2002     j&#13;
(US$millions)                                                                        Currentaccountbalanceto GDP (%)&#13;
&#13;
Exportsof goods andservices                      904      613       1,521  1,433&#13;
Importsof goods andservices                      681    1,277       1,996  2,012&#13;
Resourcebalance                                  223     -464        -476  -579&#13;
&#13;
Net Income                                      -465     -190        -210  -202&#13;
Netcurrenttransfers                               45      248         393   421&#13;
Currentaccount balance                          -174     -534        -293&#13;
&#13;
Financingitems (net)                             100      554         264&#13;
Changesin net reserves                            73      -20         29     163&#13;
Memo:&#13;
Reservesincludinggold (US$millions)              216      410       1,116    858&#13;
Conversionrate (DEC./ocaVUS$)                1.20E-4       3.9        6.6    7.2&#13;
&#13;
EXTERNAL DEBT and RESOURCE FLOWS&#13;
                                                1982     1992       2001   2002&#13;
(US5millions)                                                                         Compositionof 2002 debt (US$ mill.)&#13;
Total debt outstanding anddisbursed             3,329   4,235       4,676  4,535&#13;
   IBRD                                          212      146           0      0&#13;
   IDA                                            90      464       1,146  1,321                            G: 38&#13;
&#13;
Total debt sewice                                544      288         544    475&#13;
   IBRD                                           24       35           0      0&#13;
   IDA                                              1        5          2     15&#13;
Compositionof net resourceflows&#13;
   Officialgrants                                 43      264         352&#13;
   Official creditors                             139     272         229    229&#13;
   Privatecreditors                               46        -8        -24    -75&#13;
   Foreigndirect investment                       61       93         662&#13;
   Portfolioequity                                  0        0          0&#13;
World Bankprogram&#13;
   Commkments                                       0     118         106     77&#13;
   Disbursements                                  30                                                                       E. Bilateral&#13;
                                                           55         102             A IBRD&#13;
                                                                             104      B IDA&#13;
                                                                                       --           D Other multilateral&#13;
                                                                                                      .&#13;
   Principal repayments                             9                                                                      F .Private&#13;
                                                           23           1      7      C . IMF                              G -Short-term&#13;
   Netflows                                       21       32         101     96&#13;
    Interestpayments                               16      17           1      7&#13;
   Nettransfers                                     5      15         100     89&#13;
&#13;
 Note:This tablewas producedfromthe Development Economicscentraldatabase.                                                        8120103&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                         19&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
      SCHEDULEF&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                 3&#13;
                 3&#13;
                 3&#13;
                 0&#13;
                 0&#13;
                 3&#13;
                 0&#13;
                 3&#13;
                 3&#13;
                 a&#13;
                 0&#13;
                 0&#13;
                  D&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
20&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
MAP SECTION&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="2818569">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2003/12/2818569/bolivia-emergency-economic-recovery-project
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2003/12/2818569/bolivia-emergency-economic-recovery-project</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2003/12/2818569/bolivia-emergency-economic-recovery-project</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/12/12/000012009_20031212112231/Rendered/INDEX/T76110BO.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/12/12/000012009_20031212112231/Rendered/PDF/T76110BO.pdf</pdfurl>
        <docdt>2003-12-08T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <datestored>2003-12-12T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Gray cover</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309938</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Bolivia - Emergency Economic Recovery Project
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            In line with the upcoming Country
            Assistance Strategy (CAS) objectives - strengthen
            governance, accelerate efforts to reduce inequality and
            exclusion, support macroeconomic stability - this Emergency
            Economic Recovery Project, structured as an emergency
            recovery operation in recognition of the crisis nature of
            the long-standing socioeconomic tensions that have led to
            frequent episodes of civil unrest, will provide support to
            the poor and vulnerable, by making available external funds
            for critical foreign goods (whether or not directly imported
            by the Government), including medicines, agricultural
            machinery (tractors), and diesel oil/gasoline. Quick
            disbursing financing will be provided for critical goods for
            reconstruction, economic recovery and mitigation of the
            social crisis, and for financial management, consistent with
            the emergency nature of this operation, these arrangements
            have been simplified and streamlined to the extent feasible.
            However, risks remain, above all, the presence of radical
            elements among the union-indigenous movement opposed to the
            current political environment, and, the unsure political
            power to ensure new legislation. In addition, civil service
            capacity constraints may undermine implementation of new
            policies, and, the gas referendum may prove difficult to implement.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Bolivia - Emergency Economic Recovery Project
        </docna>
        <display_title>Bolivia - Emergency Economic
            Recovery Project</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/2003/12/2818569/bolivia-emergency-economic-recovery-project</listing_relative_url>
        <projn>BO-Emergency Economic Recovery Credit -- P087661</projn>
        <docty>Technical Annex</docty>
        <subtopic>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation,Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Economic Theory &amp; Research,Poverty Assessment,National Governance</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Poverty Reduction</teratopic>
        <count>Bolivia</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>America!$!80450</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>South America!$!80469</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000012009_20031212112231</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>Latin America &amp; Caribbean,Latin America &amp; Caribbean</admreg>
        <subsc>General finance sector,General public administration sector</subsc>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Poverty Reduction</historic_topic>
        <prdln>IBRD/IDA</prdln>
        <sectr>Finance,Public Administration, Law, and Justice</sectr>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Emergency assistance; Economic recovery;
            Governance approach; Inequity; Macroeconomic stabilization;
            Economic crisis; Socioeconomic constraints; Social unrest;
            Poverty reduction; Goods; Medicines; Agricultural machinery;
            Gasoline pricing; Oil consumption; Tractors; Risk
            assessment; Political constraints; Law enforcement;
            Vulnerable groups; Capacity constraints; Policy
            implementation; Referendums;
            Agriculture,anti-corruption,balance of
            payments,Capital Cities,civil society,competitive
            bidding,competitiveness,conditionality,Constitution,corruption,Currency
            Unit,debt,debt relief,Decree,economic activity,economic
            impact,economic priorities,economic stability,environmental
            impacts,Exchange
            Rate,expenditures,exploitation,exports,external
            shocks,families,financial assistance,financial
            capacity,Financial Institutions,financial
            management,financial sector,financial support,financial
            sustainability,FISCAL,fiscal deficit,fiscal problems,fiscal
            situation,GDP,general elections,Gross Domestic Product,high
            unemployment,Household Income,imports,income,Institutional
            Arrangements,institutional reform,investment
            climate,judicial reform,land reform,liquidity,local
            currency,macroeconomic stability,macroeconomic
            stabilization,medicines,ministers,Ministry of
            Finance,Nations,natural resources,oil,per capita
            income,political parties,Poverty Gap,Poverty
            Reduction,Poverty Reduction Strategy,Presidency,private
            sector,Public Expenditure,Public Expenditure Review,public
            sector,public service,public
            services,Referendum,representatives,rural areas,short
            term,social conflict,social development,social
            exclusion,social expenditures,Social Impact Analysis,social
            infrastructure,Social Safety,Social Safety Net,Social
            Sector,social sectors,Structural Adjustment,Task Team
            Leader,tax collections,tax revenue,technical
            assistance,transparency,urban areas,victims,violence,wages,workers
        </keywd>
        <owner>Economic Policy Sector (LCSPE)</owner>
        <lndinstr>
            Emergency Recovery Loan
        </lndinstr>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>America</geo_region>
            <geo_region>South America</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>T7611</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development &amp; Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Mining</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>City Development Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture and Food Security</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Energy and Extractives</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Urban Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Adjustment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Strategy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Prices</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodity Rich Countries</ml:concept><ml:concept>Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Expenditure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shocks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Livestock</ml:concept><ml:concept>Livestock and Animal Husbandry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pensions &amp; Retirement Systems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Efficiency of Public Expenditures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Expenditures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Financial Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Spending</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indigenous Communities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Contract Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Arrangements in Public Procurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Capacity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legal Regulatory Framework</ml:concept><ml:concept>State-Society Relations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Conflict</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Resilience</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ethnic Minorities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indigenous Peoples</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nationalities &amp; Ethnic Groups</ml:concept><ml:concept>Religious Minorities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fuels</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Fiscal Adjustment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Agriculture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Commodities and Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government Expenditure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Revenue Sharing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Balance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shocks and Vulnerability</ml:concept><ml:concept>Animal Production</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Relief</ml:concept><ml:concept>Pensions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Social Impact Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Managing Public Finances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Cities and Conflict</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ethnic, Religious and other Minorities</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Americas</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Bolivia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Caribbean</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>