<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>                                                     - 2 -&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   Bulgaria: Environment and Privatization Support Adjustment Loan (EPSAL) -Loan 4538 BUL&#13;
&#13;
                                        Release of the Third Tranche&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
 I.      Background&#13;
         1.      The socialist system left Bulgaria with serious environmental problems and a relatively&#13;
         weak and ineffective institutional and regulatory system. Unsustainable industrial management&#13;
         practices of the state owned enterprises resulted in "hot spots" where people have been exposed&#13;
         to unacceptably high levels of pollution, and the accumulation of hazardous substances, which&#13;
         contaminated drinking water resources and threatened ecosystems with irreversible damage. The&#13;
         Government of Bulgaria (GOB) embarked on a structural reform program, which also aimed to&#13;
         address the environmental consequences of past environmental mismanagement. During the past&#13;
         several years, GOB made significant progress in dealing with specific sources of pollution and&#13;
         building institutional capacity to address environmental priorities. A new Environmental&#13;
         Protection Act (EPA) adopted in 2002, has fully aligned national environmental legislation with&#13;
         EU environmental management principles and legal requirements.&#13;
&#13;
 11.     Recent MacroeconomicDevelopments andProgressAgainst Tranche Release Criteria&#13;
         2.      Bulgaria's macroeconomic outlook remains favorable in 2003 due to growth&#13;
         improvements driven by structural reforms. Economic growth has been sustained at 4-5 percent&#13;
        per year. Macroeconomic stability has been maintained ,inflation is low' and public debt to&#13;
        GDP has been reduced below Maastrischt threshold of 60 percent. The Government posted a&#13;
        fiscal surplus of 0.3 percent of GDP and over performance of 1percent of GDP with respect to&#13;
        program. Unemployment has declined from 18.1percent in 2000 to 12.9as at October 2003. Per&#13;
        capita income has increased $1,220 in 1997to $1,790 in 2003. Household incomes rose in real&#13;
        terms by 18.8 in 2002 after having declined in two consecutive years. Poverty rate has decreased&#13;
        from 36 percent in 1997to 12.8in 2001. EU Commission has assessed Bulgaria's economy as a&#13;
        functioning market economy. Bulgaria closed 26 out of 30 chapters for EU Accession, including&#13;
        Chapter 22 on environment.&#13;
&#13;
        3.      Privatization of the commercial and banking sectors is largely completed.The private&#13;
        sector as a share of GDP has increased from 53 to 64 percent in 2002. The privatization of the&#13;
        energy distribution companies is on track. The Government is moving forward the private&#13;
        participation in the district heating and water companies.Bank adjustment lending includes&#13;
        Programmatic Adjustment Loans (PALS),the first one approved by the Board in February 2003,&#13;
        which supports the Government's reforms aiming at: (a) completion of privatization and&#13;
        restructuring in energy and infrastructure; (b) improving the environment for private sector led&#13;
        growth; (c) deepening the financial sector; (d) reducing poverty and improving human capital,&#13;
        and better delivery of social services; and (e) support public administration reform and anti-&#13;
        corruption programs. The PAL program is on track with the second PAL being prepared for&#13;
        appraisal /negotiations.&#13;
&#13;
        4.      To achieve the objectives of its economic program, the Bulgarian Government is fully&#13;
        committed to maintain sound and flexible macroeconomic policies centered on the Currency&#13;
        Board Arrangement and implement an ambitious reform agenda. In particular, the authorities&#13;
        have reduced the fiscal deficit to below one percent of GDP and aim to eliminate the deficit&#13;
        by 2005, conduct fiscal policy flexibly in the face of shocks, and maintain a high level of fiscal&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
' Twelve-month inflation at end October 2003 was 3.1%.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
       reserve assets. A strict incomes policy for the state enterprise sector is enforced and measures&#13;
       aimed at facilitating the adjustment of labor markets are being implemented. The structural and&#13;
       institutional reforms, which constitute the third pillar of the policy strategy, are focused on&#13;
       creating a market economy that is competitive and can flexibly adjust to shocks.&#13;
&#13;
       5.        The IMF has been leading in supporting Bulgaria's medium-term program in maintaining&#13;
       macroeconomic stability. Building on the achievements of the three-year Extended Fund Facility&#13;
       (EFF) arrangement with Bulgaria, in February 2002 the IMF Board approved a two-year Stand-&#13;
       By Arrangement (SBA) with Bulgaria, which focuses on medium-term fiscal challenges and&#13;
       structural reforms with significant macroeconomic, typically fiscal, implications.&#13;
&#13;
       6.        Despite the challenges Bulgaria continues to maintain macroeconomic stability in the&#13;
       context of the Currency Board Arrangement (CBA), by sustaining structural reforms and&#13;
       establishing business environment conducive to growth, together with improved governance,&#13;
       deeper financial system, and investments in human capital and physical infrastructure. According&#13;
       to IMF's Third Assessment Bulgaria has the right mix of macroeconomic policies to continue to&#13;
       enjoy robust macroeconomic growth and macroeconomic stability2, Therefore, the requirements&#13;
       for maintaining satisfactory macroeconomic performance for the release of tranche three are fully&#13;
       met.&#13;
&#13;
111.   Government'sPerformanceand Commitmentto theLoan&#13;
&#13;
       7.        Overall the progress made by the Government on the EPSAL implementation was&#13;
       satisfactory. Although there were some delays in meeting the remaining loan conditions by July&#13;
       30 ,2003 for disbursement of tranche three, the Government demonstrated consistent and sound&#13;
       efforts to overcome the delays in the ongoing remediation programs, eliminate formal obstacles,&#13;
       and accelerate implementation in good partnership with participating enterprises.The&#13;
       commitment of the Government to address historical pollution beyond project targets is&#13;
       noteworthy. Indeed, the Government is expanding the EPSAL model to additional eight&#13;
       industrial enterprises (KCM Plovdiv, Provadsol Provadia Elatzite, MedGorupso Madan, OCK&#13;
       Kuradjali, Gorupso Luki ,Osogovo Mine, Pirel Gotze Delchev) and is using the EPSAL process&#13;
       to work towards harmonization with EU environmental acquis. Furthermore, the institutional&#13;
       responsibilities and procedures for addressing environmental liabilities has been formalized in the&#13;
       Government Decree No. 78 from April 2003. The EPSAL has raised significant interest from&#13;
       industries not included in the pilot of integrated environmental permits. The Government has&#13;
       approved a plan for issuance of 225 IPPC by 2005, by applying the EPSAL permit model for&#13;
       industries to which the provisions of EU IPPC Directive apply.&#13;
&#13;
IV. StatusofEPSALSpecificTargets&#13;
       8.       Progress toward meeting the specific targets for tranche three release, other than the one&#13;
      requiring maintenance of satisfactory macroeconomic condition, is briefly described below.&#13;
&#13;
           (1)            Pilot integruted environmentalpermits issued according to theEU Council&#13;
                Directive 96/61 on Integrated Pollution Prevention and Control (IPPC) to at least 80%&#13;
                of large enterprises in the metallurgical and chemical sectorsfrom the agreed list3 (each&#13;
                with at least 1,000 employees) and thereafter ensured compliance with the terms ofpilot&#13;
                permits. Integrated pilot permits, substantially according to IPPC Directive have been&#13;
                completed for the following enterprises: Solvei Sodi-Devnja, OCK-Kurdjali, KCM&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
IMF Country Report No. 03/206, July 2003, Bulgaria: Third Review under the Stand by Arrangement&#13;
&#13;
The agreed list of enterprises from metallurgical and chemical sectors include twenty-one enterprises.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                          - 4 -&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      Plovdiv, UMICOR-Pirdop, Chimcho-Vraza, Sviloza Svistov,Agropolychim-Devnja,&#13;
      Sofarma Sofia, StomanaIndustry Pernik, Promet Burgas, Neochim Dimitrovgrad,&#13;
      Orgachim Russe, Biovet Peshetera, Polimeri Devnja, Balkanpharma Razgrad,&#13;
      Balkanpharma Dupnitza, Sofia Med Sofia, Radomir Metali Radomir, Nova Plama&#13;
      Pleven. Permits were issued for 19 out of 21 enterprises, which is nearly 90 percent of the&#13;
      agreed list. The new EPA, adopted in 2002 establishes solid foundation for&#13;
      implementation and monitoring of enterprises' environmental performance, which goes&#13;
      beyond EPSAL terms. Environmental Inspectorates of MOEW will monitor compliance&#13;
      on the basis of integrated permits. These actionsfully satisfy the requirements for tranche&#13;
      disbursement.&#13;
&#13;
(ii)           Satisfactory progress made in implementation of Framework Remediationplans&#13;
      ( F W ) and Complianceplans (CP) in theprivatized enterprises consideredfor thefirst&#13;
     and second tranches (Assarel Medet, Kremikovtzi AD, Neftochim-Likoil, Neochim,&#13;
     Agroplychim, and Sofarma). Implementation is progressing satisfactory despite some&#13;
      delays fiom original schedule. Four enterprises (Assarel -Medet, Neochim, Sofarma,&#13;
     Agropolychim-Devnja) have made significant progress in implementing substantial part&#13;
     of remediation and compliance plans. For the purpose of tranche three release this&#13;
     progress satisfies the loan condition. Recently Kremikovtzi AD reports progress on&#13;
     agreed measures with the Government for accelerating implementation of remediation&#13;
     plan. Similarly,Neftochim-Luckoil is in the process of finalizing the arrangements for&#13;
     signing of the contract for processing of oil sludge. All enterprises report substantial&#13;
     private investments in improved technologies and monitoring. For instance Neftochim-&#13;
     Luckoil has invested nearly US$50 million in environmental upgrading of the refinery.&#13;
     The Government has put in place all institutional and financial arrangements to sustain&#13;
     and monitor implementation of remaining remediation activities and compliance plans&#13;
     after the loan closing date. A revised Regulation on the State Liability for Environmental&#13;
     Damage has been adopted and gazetted, which includes provisions for institutional&#13;
     responsibilities, financing and monitoring of remediation programs. The 2004 State&#13;
     budget includes provisions for financing of remediation plans. Government commitment&#13;
     and steps undertaken for establishing and maintaining institutional and financial&#13;
     arrangements for completion of remediation plans and extending the EPSAL instrument&#13;
     over eight new enterprises signify substantial achievement of policy development&#13;
     objectives of the loan. Although Kremikovtzi and Neftochim-Luckoil remediation plans&#13;
     lag behind in the overall progress made up to date in the other four enterprises provides a&#13;
     satisfactory basis to assume that remediation and compliance efforts will be sustained and&#13;
     completed in a satisfactory manner. These actions substantially satisfy this condition.&#13;
&#13;
(iii)ExecutionThe Government has exercised its rights andfulJilled its obligations under the&#13;
                Agreements concluded with buyers of enterprises in such a manner toprotect&#13;
     the interest of the bank and Borrower and to achieve thepurposes of theprogram, and&#13;
     except as the bank otherwise agreed, the Borrower has not suspended or terminated&#13;
     Execution Agreement concluded in connection with sale of any of the enterprises,&#13;
     abrogated or waived any such Execution Agreements or anyprovisions thereoJ The&#13;
     Government oversees and coordinates the implementation of remediation plans based on&#13;
     the terms and conditions of Execution Agreements signed with the six enterprises. The&#13;
     Execution Agreements are legally binding and annexed to the Sales Purchase&#13;
     Agreements, which engages the Post- Privatization Agency in monitoring of enterprise's&#13;
     performance including investment commitments for environmental compliance. Funds&#13;
     for remediation programs are provided annually from the state budget to ensure&#13;
     uninterrupted implementation of agreed remediation measures. Procurement of services&#13;
     and goods follows the Bulgarian Public Procurement Law. In a few remediation items,&#13;
     IMEC has approved minor changes based on engineering designs andjustified by the&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                     - 5 -&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   selected remediation technology. These actionsfully satisfy the requirement for tranche&#13;
                   disbursement.&#13;
&#13;
              (iv) oversee Inter-agency coordinating body with membership satisfactory to the Bank to&#13;
                           implementation of the EPSAL maintained. An inter-governmental oversight and&#13;
                   coordinating body representing key stakeholder ministries is fully functional and&#13;
                   supported by a standing Inter-Ministerial Expert Council (IMEC) at all times.&#13;
                  Furthermore the IMEC has been institutionalized pursuant to the provisions of GOB&#13;
                  Decree No 78, from April 3,2003. These actionsfully satisfy the requirement for tranche&#13;
                   disbursement.&#13;
&#13;
              (VI          Measures satisfactory to the Bank have been taken to mitigate any adverse social&#13;
                  impact of the EPSP identijied during EIApublic consultation process or during EIA&#13;
                  monitoring activities. There has been no indication of adverse social or environmental&#13;
                  impact or concerns related to remediation projects during the Environmental Impact&#13;
                  Assessment (EIA) public consultations or project implementation. Hence, there is no&#13;
                  need for mitigation measures by the Government as stipulated in Schedule 3, Section I1&#13;
                  (5). Therefore, tranche conditions related to these actions are consideredfully met.&#13;
&#13;
              (vi&gt;FrameworkPayments were madefrom the Remediation Accountfor activities under the&#13;
                               Remediation Plans above an aggregate amount acceptable to the Bank. Up&#13;
                  to date the Ministry of Finance reports aggregate disbursements for remediation measures&#13;
                  under the six signed Execution Agreements of total of BGN 215,148,000 which is 68.3&#13;
                  % of the total amount of tranche one and two. The Ministry of Finance informed that by&#13;
                  end of 2003 additional payment will be made which will allow to reach an aggregate of&#13;
                  70%. These actionsfully satisfy the requirement for tranche disbursement.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
V. Conclusion and Recommendation&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
         9.       In view of the overall performance and progress with implementation of the program&#13;
         supportedby the Loan, and in compliancewith the specific conditions of release as describedin the&#13;
         Loan Agreement, the Bank has informed the Borrower of the availability of the third tranche in the&#13;
         equivalentof EUR 19,810,000.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
P:BULGARIAIRUREWEWENV-REM.SUP\SSPN\03-IFinal Memo Tranche Release (maria'scomments).doc&#13;
Irene Bomani&#13;
                                           6-18&#13;
December 19,20034:04 PM&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="2826679">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2003/12/2826679/bulgaria-environment-privatization-support-adjustment-loan-project-epsal-release-third-tranche
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2003/12/2826679/bulgaria-environment-privatization-support-adjustment-loan-project-epsal-release-third-tranche</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2003/12/2826679/bulgaria-environment-privatization-support-adjustment-loan-project-epsal-release-third-tranche</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/12/23/000112742_20031223103022/Rendered/INDEX/27544.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2003/12/23/000112742_20031223103022/Rendered/PDF/27544.pdf</pdfurl>
        <loan_no>4538</loan_no>
        <datestored>2003-12-23T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2003-12-17T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Bulgaria - Environment and Privatization
            Support Adjustment Loan Project (EPSAL) : release of the
            third tranche
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The progress made by the Government of
            Bulgaria on the Environment and Privatization Support
            Adjustment Loan (EPSAL) EPSAL implementation was
            satisfactory. Although there were delays in meeting the
            remaining loan conditions by July 30 ,2003 for disbursement
            of tranche three, the Government demonstrated consistent and
            sound efforts to overcome the delays in the ongoing
            remediation programs, eliminate formal obstacles, and
            accelerate implementation in good partnership with
            participating enterprises.  Progress toward meeting the
            specific targets for tranche three release include: issuance
            of and compliance with pilot integrated environmental
            permits; satisfactory progress made in implementation of
            framework remediation plans and compliance plans; fulfilled
            its obligations under the Execution Agreements concluded
            with buyers of enterprises; maintained inter-agency
            coordinating body with membership satisfactory to the Bank
            to oversee implementation of the EPSAL; mitigation measures
            taken as identified during EIA public consultation process
            or EIA monitoring activities; and payments were made from
            the remediation account for activities under the framework
            remediation plans above an aggregate amount acceptable to
            the Bank
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Bulgaria - Environment and Privatization
            Support Adjustment Loan Project (EPSAL) : release of the
            third tranche
        </docna>
        <display_title>Bulgaria - Environment and
            Privatization Support Adjustment Loan Project (EPSAL) :
            release of the third tranche</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/2003/12/2826679/bulgaria-environment-privatization-support-adjustment-loan-project-epsal-release-third-tranche</listing_relative_url>
        <projn>BG-Environmental &amp; Privatization Support
            Adjustment Loan -- P057927</projn>
        <docty>Tranche Release Document</docty>
        <subtopic>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Banks &amp; Banking Reform,Municipal Financial Management,Economic Adjustment and Lending,National Governance</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Finance and Financial Sector Development</teratopic>
        <count>Bulgaria</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Eastern Europe!$!107233</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Europe!$!80461</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000112742_20031223103022</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <subsc>Central government administration,Other social services,Other industry,Mining and other extractive,General water, sanitation and flood
            protection sector</subsc>
        <admreg>Europe and Central Asia,Europe and Central Asia</admreg>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Finance and Financial Sector Development</historic_topic>
        <prdln>IBRD/IDA</prdln>
        <sectr>Public Administration, Law, and Justice,Health and other social services,Industry and trade,Energy and mining,Water, sanitation and flood protection</sectr>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Tranche releases; Progress reports;
            Privatization projects; Remediation; Environmental permits;
            Adjustment Loans,anti-
            corruption,Borrower,commitment,commitments,disbursement,disbursements,drinking
            water,Economic growth,environmental management,environmental
            performance,environmental problems,Environmental
            Protection,Execution,Extended Fund Facility,financial
            sector,financial system,fiscal,fiscal deficit,fiscal
            policy,Government Decree,human
            capital,income,inflation,institutional
            capacity,institutional reforms,labor markets,legal
            requirements,legislation,Loan,Loan Agreement,Macroeconomic
            stability,Ministry of
            Finance,oil,pollution,Privatization,Privatization
            Agency,public administration,public administration
            reform,public debt,Public Procurement,regulatory
            system,reserve assets,social services,State budget,state enterprise,tranche,Unemployment
        </keywd>
        <owner>Sustainable Devmt Sector Unit (ECSSD)</owner>
        <lndinstr>
            Structural Adjustment Loan
        </lndinstr>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Eastern Europe</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Europe</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <trustfund>TF037732-BULGARIA - ENV. REMED. AND
            PRIV. SUP.,TF039731-BULGARIA - ENVIRONMENT AND
            PRIVATIZATION SUPPORT LOAN</trustfund>
        <repnb>27544</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Industry</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics and Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation and Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Structural Measures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Structural Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shocks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Denationalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deregulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Destatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Divestiture of Ownership</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ecosystems and Natural Habitats</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corporate Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Nationalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Enterprise Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>State Owned Enterprise Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>State-Owned Enterprise Restructuring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Administrative and Civil Service Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Management and Employment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civil Service Employment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civil Service Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Capital</ml:concept><ml:concept>Managing People</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Employment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Accountability (GPA)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Incentives for Good Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>National Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Contract Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Arrangements in Public Procurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Capacity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legal Regulatory Framework</ml:concept><ml:concept>State-Society Relations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Income</ml:concept><ml:concept>Industrial Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Structural Policy and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Shocks and Vulnerability</ml:concept><ml:concept>Privatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inflation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ecosystems</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>State Owned Enterprises</ml:concept><ml:concept>Human Resources Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Negotiation</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Asia</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Europe</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Bulgaria</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>Central Asia</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>