<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>Parliaments and the&#13;
PRSP Process&#13;
&#13;
                                                          Papers&#13;
K. Scott Hubli and Alicia P. Mandaville&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                orking&#13;
                                                                      W&#13;
&#13;
                                                                       WBI&#13;
&#13;
Series on Contemporary Issues in Parliamentary Development&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Parliaments and the PRSP Process&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      K. Scott Hubli, Alicia P. Mandaville&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
               World Bank Institute&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Copyright  2004&#13;
The International Bank for Reconstruction&#13;
and Development /The World Bank&#13;
1818 H Street, N.W.&#13;
Washington, D.C. 20433, U.S.A.&#13;
&#13;
The World Bank enjoys copyright under protocol 2 of the Universal Copyright Convention. This&#13;
material may nonetheless be copied for research, educational or scholarly purposes only in the mem-&#13;
ber countries of The World Bank. Material in this series is subject to revision. The findings, interpre-&#13;
tations, and conclusions expressed in this document are entirely those of the author(s) and should not&#13;
be attributed in any manner to the World Bank, to its affiliated organizations, or the members of its&#13;
Board of Executive Directors or the countries they represent.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Parliaments and the PRSP Process&#13;
K. S. Hubli and A. P. Mandaville&#13;
2004. 21 pages. Stock No. 37231&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                           Contents&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Summary       1&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
1. Rationale for Integration of Parliaments into PRSP Process          2&#13;
   1.1 Parliamentary Involvement Reinforces Core Principles of PRSP    2&#13;
   1.2 Linking PRSP Activities with Existing Parliamentary Capacities   3&#13;
   1.3 Overview of Entry Points for Parliamentary Involvement in the PRSP    4&#13;
   Figure 1. Parliamentary Engagement in the PRSP Cycle     5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
2. Parliaments and Poverty Diagnosis: Understanding the Non-quantitative&#13;
  Aspects of Poverty       6&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
3. Parliaments and PRSP Development: Poverty Policy Formulation               7&#13;
   3.1 Balancing Comprehensive PRSP Priorities       8&#13;
   3.2 Contribution to Sector-Specific Policy Formulation   9&#13;
   3.3 Parliamentary Review of the Draft PRSP Document       10&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
4. Recognizing a Role for Parliaments in PRSP Implementation: Budget Allocation,&#13;
  Legislation, and Public Education         11&#13;
   4.1 Budget Allocations     11&#13;
   Figure 2. Parliamentary Involvement in Budget and PRSP Cycles     11&#13;
   4.2 Legislation    12&#13;
   Table 1. Ensuring Legislative Compatibility with PRSP Priorities  12&#13;
   4.3 Educating the Public About PRSP Processes, Programs, and Impact    13&#13;
   Table 2. Legislative Outreach to Educate the Public on PRSP Programs  14&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
5. Aligning Parliamentary Oversight Mechanisms with PRSP Monitoring&#13;
  and Evaluation        14&#13;
   5.1 Committee Hearings on the Impact of PRSP Initiatives     15&#13;
   5.2 Legislative Review of Annual PRSP Progress Reports      16&#13;
   5.3 Integrating Parliamentarians on Parliamentary Committees into Monitoring and&#13;
       Evaluation Groups     16&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
6. Consolidating the Impact of Parliamentary Involvement in the PRSP Process         17&#13;
   Table 3. Supporting Global or Regional Parliamentary Network Activity  17&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                iii&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                       Summary&#13;
&#13;
The PRSP process is continually evolving as countries and their development partners learn from&#13;
early experience. In the January 2002 Comprehensive Review of the PRSP Process, a number of&#13;
donors and democracy organizations indicated concern with the relatively weak involvement of&#13;
existing democratic and representative institutions in PRSP formulation, implementation, and&#13;
evaluation.1 Previously, legislative involvement had occurred mostly informally through&#13;
participation of individual legislators acting in their individual capacities as political leaders: thus,&#13;
knowledge of the PRSP process by legislators and legislative staff remained generally weak.&#13;
However, as implementation of a country's PRSP often requires the legislature to approve national&#13;
budgets and pass legislation, lack of parliamentary awareness in PRSP formulation can lead to&#13;
problems in PRSP implementation over time.&#13;
&#13;
This annex is designed to assist those involved in poverty reduction strategies with identifying and&#13;
implementing activities and programs that will integrate existing democratic institutions, namely the&#13;
national assembly or parliament, into poverty reduction efforts, thus strengthening the impact and&#13;
sustainability of each country's PRSP. As such, it is intended to be a tool for Bank and Fund staff,&#13;
national PRSP commission members, members or staff of parliament, or other actors seeking to unite&#13;
a country's economic and democratic transitions. Through analysis, checklists, and activity options,&#13;
the annex highlights specific mechanisms by which parliaments can strengthen the PRSP process and&#13;
reinforce its positive outcomes, including through greater involvement in poverty diagnosis, policy&#13;
development, PRSP implementation, and evaluation/monitoring. For ease of use, it has been&#13;
organized in keeping with the PRSP cycle. Consequently, sections two, three, four, and five address&#13;
opportunities for legislative involvement in poverty diagnosis, policy formulation, implementation,&#13;
and monitoring and evaluation, respectively.&#13;
&#13;
It is worth noting that while numerous mechanisms for parliamentary involvement are detailed in the&#13;
following pages, the specific activity level relevant to a particular national parliament must be&#13;
determined by its own characteristics and capacitates. Rather than detail an explicit plan for&#13;
enhancing parliamentary engagement with the PRSP, this annex intends to provide a menu of&#13;
options, from among which appropriate activities may be selected.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
1As noted in the Main Findings Document of the Comprehensive Review of the Poverty Reduction Strategy&#13;
Paper (PRSP) Approach a number of development partners (notably the Utstein group of bilateral donors) have expressed&#13;
concern over the fact that, "the role of parliaments in the preparation, approval, and monitoring of country strategies has&#13;
generally been limited and is a concern that has been expressed." (Main Findings document; prepared by the staffs of the&#13;
World Bank and the IMF, approved by Gobind Nankani and Masood Ahmed, March 2002).&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                               1&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
2   K.S. Hubli and A. P. Mandaville&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
      1. Rationale for Integration of Parliaments into PRSP Process&#13;
&#13;
State institutions have a key role to play in the growth or stagnation of any national economy. In&#13;
recent years, global studies examining the possible correlation between specific political institutions&#13;
and fiscal outcomes, financial market regulation, and trade regulation have demonstrated that&#13;
countries with adequate institutional checks and balances are more likely to enforce national&#13;
financial regulations and policies.2 In this light, the role of the legislature as an institutional check on&#13;
executive branch policy decisions and PRSP implementation takes on added importance. Greater&#13;
parliamentary involvement in the PRSP process helps to ensure that a country's poverty strategy is&#13;
generated, implemented, and evaluated through national institutions with adequate political&#13;
legitimacy to ensure ownership and sustainability. This section explores the benefits, as well as&#13;
challenges, of greater parliamentary involvement in the PRSP process. It moves on to discuss entry&#13;
points for strengthening parliament's role with respect to the PRSP.&#13;
&#13;
1.1 Parliamentary Involvement Reinforces Core Principles of PRSP&#13;
&#13;
An examination of the core principles underlying the PRSP demonstrates how effective&#13;
legislativinvolvement reinforces the potential for efficient, sustainable economic development.3&#13;
Although limited parliamentary capacity in most PRSP countries limits legislatures in their ability to&#13;
make significant initial contributions to the PRSP process, incremental efforts to involve the&#13;
legislature can gradually strengthen the practices needed to actualize core PRSP principles.&#13;
&#13;
  Participatory, country driven and owned: Under most constitutions, legislatures are the most&#13;
   representative element of a country's national government. Although in many cases this&#13;
   representative potential has been latent or underutilized due to political conditions or lack of&#13;
   resources, parliaments remain a mechanism for channeling citizen's input into national poverty&#13;
   reduction policies and ensuring cooperation from a variety of political actors. Depending on&#13;
   popular perceptions of the parliament and MP credibility, the representative responsibilities of&#13;
   parliament, as assigned by each country's constitution, may provide a greater level of ownership&#13;
   and legitimacy than other participatory methods.&#13;
&#13;
  Results-oriented: The PRSP process is grounded in the idea that the creation of a strategy for&#13;
   poverty reduction will establish realistic targets and clear objectives to pursue in implementation.&#13;
   Once the strategy has been solidified however, enabling legislation or legal reform may be&#13;
   required before executive officials can pursue implementation. In countries where legislatures&#13;
   have significant budgetary role, the national assembly has even greater potential to affect a&#13;
   country's adherence to established poverty reduction strategies through its allocation of resources&#13;
   to implementing ministries.&#13;
&#13;
  Comprehensive: Considering the geographic spread, political composition, and sector-specific&#13;
   committee structure of national parliaments, legislatures (and legislative structures) offer a&#13;
&#13;
2The World Bank, World Development Report 2002, Building Institutions for Markets, Washington DC, September 2001.&#13;
   p104&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
3Clarification of terminology: While acknowledging the differing role of the legislative branch in presidential&#13;
   and parliamentary systems, for purposes of linguistic variety, this document uses the terms "parliament"&#13;
   and "legislature" interchangeably. It is important to note however, that the constitutionally mandated role of&#13;
   a national legislative assembly varies from country to country, and has great impact on the nature of that&#13;
   branch's involvement in the PRSP process.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                  Parliaments and the PRSP Process   3&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   potential space in which to debate a nationally comprehensive view of poverty and impacts of&#13;
   poverty reduction initiatives. Even if parliamentary debate is motivated by geographic- or&#13;
   constituency-specific interests, the airing of such views can contribute to a more comprehensive&#13;
   national poverty reduction strategy.&#13;
&#13;
  Prioritized for feasible implementation: Prioritization of poverty reduction objectives may be the&#13;
   most politically charged element of the PRSP. While economic factors and rational decision-&#13;
   making can logically prioritize policy actions in favor of certain regions or sectors, such decisions&#13;
   have significant impact on popular support for the political parties or individuals in executive&#13;
   offices. Parliaments, which typically include a range of political actors and are vested with&#13;
   constitutional authority to serve as a check on the decisions of the executive, may serve to&#13;
   balance the ruling party's political interests in PRSP formulation. Engaging the parliament in the&#13;
   PRSP prioritization process acknowledges the political impact of economic decisions, which may&#13;
   result in more effective implementation.&#13;
&#13;
  Partnership-orientation: Effective partnership between IFIs, other development partners, and PRSP&#13;
   countries depends, in part, on the transparency of the PRSP process. Through such standard legis-&#13;
   lative activities as committee hearings and reports, national assemblies may facilitate donor coor-&#13;
   dination by contributing to the transparency of the PRSP development, financing, and implemen-&#13;
   tation process.&#13;
&#13;
  Based on medium- and long-term perspectives: Despite MPs' tendency to focus on short-term per-&#13;
   spectives, building non-partisan support for poverty reduction strategies among present and future&#13;
   national leaders can engender greater continuity in the medium- and long-term. Because the&#13;
   PRSP process takes place within a political environment, broad support for the PRSP by Mem-&#13;
   bers of parliament (MPs) from both governing and opposition parties is important in ensuring that&#13;
   the PRSP's success will not be derailed by changes in the political environment. In most PRSP&#13;
   countries, national parliaments include representatives of all major political factions, and there-&#13;
   fore provide an ideal forum for multi-partisan inclusion.&#13;
&#13;
1.2 Linking PRSP Activities with Existing Contexts and Capacities&#13;
&#13;
When assessing the possible opportunities for legislative involvement in the PRSP process, it is criti-&#13;
cal to consider the specific context in which the parliament operates and to be realistic regarding&#13;
technical and professional capacities. Legislative authority to introduce legislation, amend budgets or&#13;
bills proposed by the executive, or even reject tabled legislation varies with a country's constitutional&#13;
structure and tradition of political party discipline or control. Further, political and economic condi-&#13;
tions mean that national legislatures in many PRSP countries lack the institutional capacities needed&#13;
for effective engagement. In countries where dramatic political or economic changes have recently&#13;
occurred (e.g., military coup, civil war or unrest, hyper inflation, death or removal of a dictator, un-&#13;
precedented political opening or reform, etc), basic legislative activity is a challenge for nascent or&#13;
evolving institutions and the people inside them. Lack of fundamental infrastructure (offices and&#13;
office equipment, reference materials, staff, consistent utilities), restricted access to data or&#13;
inaccurate information, scarcity of leadership experience by legislative bodies, illiteracy levels, and&#13;
limited knowledge of sitting MPs all inhibit a parliament's ability to play an active role in the PRSP&#13;
process. The extent and nature of parliamentary integration into the PRSP process must take these&#13;
factors into account, lest PRSP requirements become an unmanageable demand on legislative&#13;
resources.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
4    K.S. Hubli and A. P. Mandaville&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
While capacity constraints limit the legislature's contribution&#13;
to the PRSP process, targeted technical support and                  Assessment Checklist for Country-Specific&#13;
incremental integration of standard legislative practices into           Parliamentary Involvement in PRSP&#13;
the PRSP process not only deepens country ownership of                What are the constitutional responsibilities&#13;
poverty reduction strategies, but also enhances the                   of this particular parliament?&#13;
parliament's eventual capacity to fulfill oversight and               Is there a coalition government or a single&#13;
representative functions. For example:                                party executive with a parliamentary&#13;
                                                                      majority?&#13;
  Minimal capacity: Even where nascent legislatures have              Can governing and opposition parties&#13;
    little internal capacity to analyze the policies contained in     collaborate on issue specific initiatives or&#13;
    the PRSP, the legislature can still serve as a forum to build     is the relationship too combative?&#13;
    parliamentary and public awareness of the PRSP. Support           What historic events or attitudes might&#13;
    for formal briefings of legislators on the PRSP can improve       preclude citizen or executive trust in&#13;
    the transparency of the PRSP, while at the same time              parliament? What relationship does&#13;
    increasing the awareness and capacity of legislators to           parliament have with national media?&#13;
    contribute to the policy debate.                                  Civic groups?&#13;
                                                                      What is the level and locus of corruption?&#13;
  Limited staff resources: Where committee systems have               What is the status of parliamentary&#13;
    defined roles and assigned support staff but those staff lack     capacity and/or resources? Do members&#13;
    the technical skills necessary to support meaningful              or staff have access to computers and the&#13;
    committee work, committees can use experts drawn from             Internet?&#13;
    civil society and the donor community to provide the              How are parliamentary staff allocated&#13;
    legislature with needed technical advice. In addition to          among committees, caucuses, and&#13;
    providing immediate technical support, this strategy can be       individual members?&#13;
    an entry point for building staff capacity.                       Is there staff to support committee&#13;
                                                                      hearings and briefings?&#13;
Limited member experience: Where limited member                       How often does the legislature meet?&#13;
experience is a capacity constraint, committee briefing               What portion of the year do members&#13;
sessions that introduce such tools as spending ceilings or            spend in the capital? What portion in their&#13;
floors, notification, or reporting requirements can equip a           constituencies? Do members of&#13;
committee with the tools needed to examine pending                    parliament have office space in the&#13;
legislative activity and legislation against established PRSP         capital?&#13;
priorities over multi-year implementation.                           What is parliament's role in budget&#13;
                                                                      processes?&#13;
                                                                      How does the committee system function,&#13;
                                                                      particularly regarding economic&#13;
                                                                      legislation or policy?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
1.3 Overview of Entry Points for Parliamentary Involvement&#13;
&#13;
With the understanding that parliamentary involvement can reinforce the core principles of the&#13;
PRSP, much work has been done to identify the conceptual role that parliaments can play in PRSP&#13;
processes. These potential points of involvement for parliaments in the PRSP process will vary from&#13;
country to country and across the four components of the PRSP cycle: 1. Poverty diagnosis, 2. PRSP&#13;
development, 3. Implementation of PRSP, and 4. Monitoring of PRSP implementation and&#13;
evaluation of PRSP priorities.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                                            Parliaments and the PRSP Process                 5&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                   Figure 1: Possible Mechanisms for Parliamentary Engagement in the PRSP Cycle&#13;
&#13;
 POV ERTY DIAG NOSIS AND RE ASS ES SM ENT                                                                     P OVE RTY P OLICY FOR MULA TION&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                          Determ ine current                                E stablish                              National&#13;
                          poverty reduction                                  sectoral                              stakeholder&#13;
                                priorities                              working groups                            conferences&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                             Parliamen tary&#13;
    Review current                                                                                              review&#13;
       strategy                                                        Com mittees and                         of P RSP                       Finalize&#13;
                                                                        P RSP working                          process                        PRS P&#13;
                                         Constituency                  groups integrated&#13;
                                       outreach to solicit&#13;
                                         input/feedback&#13;
                                          from citizens&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                                    Parliamentary&#13;
                                                                                                                 debate / resolution&#13;
                                                                                                               on content of PRS P&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
       A nnual                                                                                                                           Subm it PRS P to&#13;
        P RSP                     Legislative review                                                                                       International&#13;
      progress                   of PRSP progress&#13;
                                        reports                                                                                              Financial&#13;
        report                                                                                                                              Institutions&#13;
                                                                      PARL IAM EN T&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                                                       Constituent outreach&#13;
                                                                                                           activities to&#13;
                          Public Accounts                                                                 educate public&#13;
                           Committee&#13;
                              review                                 Constituency&#13;
                                                                   feedback identifies&#13;
                                                                   projects for review&#13;
       Review                                     Sector specific                           Debate of PRSP                                  B uild public&#13;
        budg et                                  public hearings                            priorites as part                              awareness of&#13;
      expenditure                                                                           of budget cycle                               government plan&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                     Review                                      Adopt budget and&#13;
                                                     specific                                      pass legislation&#13;
                                                    programs                                    to implement PRS P&#13;
  PRS P&#13;
  MONITORING AN D E VALUATION                                                                                                 P RSP IMP LE MENTATION&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Note: Multiple actors are already involved in each stage of the PRSP process - civil society, IFIs, local government,&#13;
the ministry of Finance, Sector-specific Ministries, even the academic community each have specific roles to play. In&#13;
an effort to highlight just a few of the points at which a national legislature might strengthen the PRSP through their&#13;
own activity, this diagram has been highly simplified. Though the basic order of the PRSP process has been&#13;
preserved, the actions of other players has been omitted.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    However, if the participatory elements of the PRSP are to become an enduring part of any country's&#13;
    policy process, engagement of existing governing institutions (such as the legislature) is eventually&#13;
    necessary at all stages.4&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
    4 See Review of the Poverty Reduction Strategy (PRSP) Approach: Early Experiences with Interim PRSPs and Full PRSPs,&#13;
        section on participatory processes; prepared by the staffs of the World Bank and the IMF, approved by Gobind Nankani&#13;
        and Masood Ahmed, March 2002. The European Commission and Utstein group of bilateral donors were particularly&#13;
        concerned that greater integration of parliaments was necessary for "real and effective" country ownership.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
6   K.S. Hubli and A. P. Mandaville&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                          2. Parliaments and Poverty Diagnosis&#13;
            Understanding the Non-quantitative Aspects of Poverty&#13;
&#13;
Poverty diagnosis is the first step in any country's&#13;
development of a full PRSP; before determining                    Ghana and Nigeria: Parliamentarians&#13;
the most appropriate strategies to reduce national                         Seeking Diverse Input&#13;
poverty levels, efforts must be made to understand       Though at different points in their respective PRSP&#13;
which factors create or reinforce conditions of          processes, in 2002, parliamentarians in Ghana and&#13;
poverty. To understand how parliamentary in-             Nigeria identified new activities to ensure that the&#13;
volvement could improve the accuracy of a coun-          PRSP process included varied geographic and&#13;
try's poverty diagnosis exercises, one must view         demographic groups.&#13;
legislative involvement in light of a multi-             In Ghana, MPs' on parliamentary committees&#13;
dimensional definition of poverty. For purposes of       concerned with the PRSP have been involved in a&#13;
PRSPs, a person living in poverty lacks: opportu-        number of efforts to ensure the process garners broad&#13;
nity (due to low consumption or income); capabil-        participation. Not only were civil society-parliament&#13;
ity (due to poor health or education levels); secu-      workshops undertaken in the poorer northern part of&#13;
rity (due to exposure to economic shock); and em-        Ghana to assess how to make the PRSP process more&#13;
powerment (due to inhibited access to power).5           responsive to local communities there, but MPs also&#13;
The representative responsibilities of national as-      explored how gender concerns could be reflected&#13;
semblies mean that, particularly in nations where        better by participating in workshops on gender&#13;
local or regional governments have limited author-       budgeting.&#13;
ity (or are currently undergoing decentralization        In Nigeria, a workshop originally intended to explore&#13;
processes), MPs have a role to play in the empow-        methods to promote legislative-executive communi-&#13;
erment of citizens and citizen groups. In these in-      cation on the PRSP led MPs to launch a deeper dis-&#13;
stances, parliamentarians may provide the only           cussion of how diverse geographic input might be&#13;
political representation for large numbers of citi-      included in the participatory process. As a result,&#13;
zens from specific geographic or demographic             MPs proposed to collaborate with state level authori-&#13;
constituencies; thus, an accurate diagnosis of the       ties to solicit input from each of the six geopolitical&#13;
roots of poverty in a country could include parlia-      divisions.&#13;
mentary input regarding poverty's non-&#13;
quantitative aspects.&#13;
&#13;
In PRSP countries at varying levels of political development, parliamentarians already gather&#13;
information relevant to poverty diagnosis. Although limited staff, resources, capacity, and political&#13;
space all inhibit MPs' interaction with citizens and citizen groups, deputies can be a logical conduit&#13;
for gathering demographic data from sector specific NGOs, or more basic information on popular&#13;
perceptions of poverty, through constituency relations, collaboration with local NGO's, or even&#13;
meetings with local groups or individuals. While MP access to accurate statistical information may&#13;
be limited, in part because PRSP country parliaments are unlikely to have sufficient staff resources&#13;
to devote to gathering or reviewing demographic data, deputies are well positioned to communicate&#13;
the perceptions of citizens and citizen groups in their home districts. In many places, MPs' direct&#13;
contact with constituents or personal experience in their electoral district provides them with a more&#13;
accurate sense of how poverty is felt in specific regions and among specific demographics. In&#13;
countries where the capacity of civic organizations is severely limited due to economic or historic&#13;
constraints, MPs may also serve as a conduit through which to ascertain specific geographic or&#13;
demographic perceptions of poverty outside of the capital city. Furthermore, technical assistance to&#13;
enhance the representative capacity of legislators provides an excellent entry point for gradual insti-&#13;
5Poverty as defined by Overview Chapter 1.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                 Parliaments and the PRSP Process     7&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
tative capacity of legislators provides an excellent entry point for gradual institutionalization of the&#13;
PRSP.&#13;
&#13;
Where legislatures use committee hearings or&#13;
other public forums to include NGOs in                       Constituency Outreach That May Reveal&#13;
&#13;
legislative debate, parliaments also offer a                   Non-Quantitative Aspects of Poverty&#13;
&#13;
natural inlet for existing poor people's                Tracking and categorizing citizen complaints.&#13;
&#13;
organizations that might have relevant                  Recording access and security issues raised by&#13;
&#13;
information on poverty in specific regions or            constituents during office hours.&#13;
&#13;
areas. Such groups, who may already be active           Meeting with grass-roots leaders to discuss&#13;
&#13;
in advocating the local government or MPs                communal or village issues.&#13;
&#13;
themselves, could include parent groups,                Listening for reoccurring problems when&#13;
&#13;
housing associations, health organizations, or           communicating with local representatives of&#13;
&#13;
other local issue groups. Asking MPs to be an            organizations, unions, or business.&#13;
&#13;
information channel for groups already active           Observing internal district variations in&#13;
&#13;
in sector-specific areas not only reinforces             infrastructure or access (depending on size of&#13;
&#13;
natural, democratic processes of citizen issue           constituency or circumscription).&#13;
&#13;
aggregation through civic organizations and             Maintaining regular communication with local or&#13;
&#13;
elected representatives, but also makes the              regional CSOs that have issue-specific expertise.&#13;
&#13;
PRSP process more participatory. Access to&#13;
statistical data gathered by local organizations may also make poverty diagnosis more accurate.&#13;
These kinds of outreach activities may be undertaken by individual MPs hoping to ensure that their&#13;
districts are adequately affected by PRSP initiatives, but to cement parliamentary involvement in an&#13;
improved PRSP process, this engagement must become more institutionalized. Appointing a number&#13;
of MPs to the poverty diagnosis working group, or institutionalizing a plenary hearing on the&#13;
findings of the poverty diagnosis report would be one way to formalize the parliament's role in&#13;
poverty diagnosis.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
3. Parliaments and PRSP Development: Pro-Poor Policy Formulation&#13;
&#13;
Direct engagement with legislators in the policy development of the PRSP process can lead to&#13;
greater consensus on poverty reduction strategies and pave the way for smoother implementation&#13;
over time. In addition to enhancing country ownership of the PRSP through inclusion of the structure&#13;
constitutionally responsible for popular representation and relevant legislation, parliamentary&#13;
engagement also provides the PRSP with an existing body of politically active national leaders and&#13;
staff of varying skill levels and interests. Parliamentary committees may be tapped for issue specific&#13;
knowledge or experience; individual MPs may be tasked with hosting public forums to discuss&#13;
policy formation with citizens (especially poorer citizens); and parliamentary leadership could be&#13;
invited to hold public, plenary debates on a draft PRSP, thus testing the document's national&#13;
resonance prior to submission. Further, parliaments, through their committees, caucuses, staff, and&#13;
individual members have the capacity to be involved as a body in prioritization processes for the&#13;
duration of the PRSP development, and thus provide an already existing mechanism for including the&#13;
full spectrum of political actors. Although the depth of a parliament's contribution to the PRSP is&#13;
predicated on its own internal capacity, a legislature's potential to reinforce the medium- to long-&#13;
term sustainability of the PRSP make it a practical partner in the policy formulation phase. This&#13;
legislative engagement may take several forms; a few are detailed as follows.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
8   K.S. Hubli and A. P. Mandaville&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
3.1 Balancing Comprehensive PRSP Priorities&#13;
&#13;
Public or Constituency Outreach&#13;
&#13;
                                                     As outlined in section two, MPs, as well as&#13;
           Outreach to Invite Feedback on            parliamentary issue caucuses, who undertake&#13;
                   PRSP Priorities                   constituency relations activities may be a logical&#13;
     Site visits or road shows to solicit            clearinghouse for regional or rural perceptions of&#13;
      feedback outside the capital.                  poverty and its impact. In countries with&#13;
     Inviting non-urban citizens to attend           longstanding democratic traditions, MPs know&#13;
      "town hall" or village meetings to discuss     that their re-election hinges in part on popular&#13;
      poverty priorities.                            perception of them as individuals able to secure&#13;
     Using constituency offices as information       necessary assistance for their district's&#13;
      centers for PRSP initiatives.                  population. Although this understanding is less&#13;
     Regional public hearings on PRSP                pervasive among MPs in many PRSP countries,&#13;
      priorities.                                    ongoing legislative strengthening programs&#13;
     Committee hearings with NGO testimony           typically strive to reinforce or build MP&#13;
      on sector-specific issues.                     awareness that popular attitudes toward the MPs&#13;
                                                     themselves, or toward their political party, is&#13;
based on representation, service, and the passage of legislation that benefits their home district.&#13;
Where this recognition exists or is being cultivated, MPs have an interest in making sure the needs of&#13;
their voters are addressed in any national poverty reduction program. Consequently, public outreach&#13;
by MPs (as individuals, or as members of such parliamentary groups as party caucuses, issue&#13;
caucuses, or committees) may play a role in&#13;
soliciting and aggregating public input for            MP Outreach to Non-geographic Constituencies&#13;
policy formulation by holding public              Where members of parliament are elected from a single&#13;
meetings or hearings to invite citizen            national party list, an MP's decision to undertake pub-&#13;
feedback on poverty reduction policies.           lic outreach activities is typically motivated by party-&#13;
                                                  interest, rather than geography. This, however, does not&#13;
Although increased constituency outreach          preclude MPs from developing close links with seg-&#13;
by parliamentarians improves the participa-       ments of the population. In many PRSP countries, po-&#13;
tory nature of the PRSP by encouraging citi-      litical party leaders are beginning to recognize the im-&#13;
zens to provide input through a country's         pact that visible, nationally-respected MPs can have on&#13;
existing democratic institutions, one danger      party popularity in subsequent elections and, in some&#13;
is that it may also reinforce certain cultural    cases, have begun to encourage MPs reach out to popu-&#13;
tendencies to view representation largely in      lation groups regarding specific issues. In the long run,&#13;
terms of the representative's ability to win      whether based on self-interest or party-interest, elected&#13;
resources or patronage for his or her particu-    members of parliament benefit from communicating&#13;
lar geographic constituency. In certain coun-     with the electorate regarding the issues that affect them&#13;
tries, elected or appointed officials from a      most. Often these issues are intimately connected to&#13;
particular clan or region may be expected to      national poverty reduction strategies. Further, technical&#13;
assist in securing jobs or benefits for other     assistance geared at enabling newly elected legislators&#13;
members of the group; in other countries,         to design and conduct effective outreach events (such&#13;
substantial contributions from a particular       as trips to specific locations, office hours, or site visits)&#13;
industry or interest group may be seen as a       provides an excellent starting point for capacity build-&#13;
way to obligate the official to use his or her    ing with new or developing parliaments. Facilitating&#13;
position to a group's advantage. While op-        MP communication with the electorate helps to expose&#13;
portunities for parliamentary patronage cer-      new MPs to the most basic aspects of legislative re-&#13;
tainly exist, inviting all MPs to communi-        sponsibilities by ensuring discussion of the issues that&#13;
                                                  most affect citizen's lives.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                Parliaments and the PRSP Process     9&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
cate with their geographic constituency on long-term policy to alleviate chronic economic problems&#13;
is one way to encourage citizens to see parliamentarians as an access point to institutional mecha-&#13;
nisms for change, rather than an individual source of funds or other benefits for personal contacts.&#13;
Moreover, a legislature that is actively involved in poverty policy issues is more likely able to serve&#13;
as a check on ruling party or government patronage. In this way, keeping parliamentarians informed&#13;
about the PRSP so that they are able to speak about it with citizens not only strengthens participatory&#13;
aspects, but encourages transparency and may serve as a first step towards curbing endemic&#13;
corruption.&#13;
&#13;
3.2 Contribution to Sector-Specific Policy Formulation&#13;
&#13;
Each country's PRSP process typically involves the establishment of working groups (or sub-&#13;
commissions) to help develop the government's poverty reduction strategies in specific sectoral&#13;
areas. The results of these working groups are then fed into the I-PRSP or full PRSP document. In&#13;
many countries, MP involvement in the PRSP has tended to be ad-hoc or based on individual interest&#13;
rather than institutional arrangement. To extend the political legitimacy of a country's PRSP and tap&#13;
into issue- or region- specific expertise that MPs may have, parliamentary involvement in PRSP&#13;
mechanisms must be more effectively institutionalized. This could include integration of MPs or&#13;
parliamentary committees into PRSP working groups, the regularization of committee briefings by&#13;
PRSP working group leaders, or the dedication of question time or interpolation to exploring PRSP&#13;
formulation and priorities.&#13;
&#13;
Integration of MPs or Parliamentary Committees into PRSP Working Groups&#13;
&#13;
One logical mechanism for ensuring the PRSP&#13;
process benefits from the involvement of                      Serbia: MPs Form Formal Committee to&#13;
parliamentarians already active in specific sectoral            Consult with PRSP Advisory Board&#13;
areas is to institutionalize a number of positions on     In Serbia and Montenegro, the production of&#13;
each sectoral working group for members of                a PRSP was complicated by the evolution of&#13;
parliament serving on relevant committees or              a federal structure around the two republics.&#13;
representing relevant districts. Such direct              Partly in response to this ongoing&#13;
participation lends electoral legitimacy to working       negotiation, Serbia announced that as part of&#13;
groups otherwise appointed by the executive.              its PRSP process, it would create committee&#13;
                                                          of republic-level parliamentarians who&#13;
Alternatively, where direct MP participation in           would be responsible for providing feedback&#13;
PRSP working groups is not possible, sector-specific      to the PRSP advisory board. In this way,&#13;
parliamentary committees (health, education,              parliamentarians elected to represent the&#13;
finance, etc) can request hearings on                     Serbian electorate were able to play a formal,&#13;
priorities/targets, and/or request periodic (or           structured role in the debates and discussions&#13;
specifically timed) briefings by PRSP working             which informed the poverty reduction&#13;
groups on I-PRSP, priorities, goals, targets, and         strategy.&#13;
indicators. A question and answer period held by the      This formal group of MPs was created as one&#13;
relevant national assembly committees would allow         of five committees designed to provide input&#13;
an opportunity for legislators to provide input into      from key institutional stakeholders in&#13;
the development of poverty reduction strategies. It       Serbia's PRSP. As part of the participatory&#13;
would provide the PRSP working groups additional          process, Serbia created similar committees of&#13;
perspective on potentially controversial issues, as       local government officials, ministerial&#13;
well as offer an early opportunity to cultivate           officials, civil society, and international&#13;
parliamentary support for PRSP priorities.                development partners.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
10   K.S. Hubli and A. P. Mandaville&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Based on briefings by the working groups, committees or committee staff could determine&#13;
appropriate legislative priorities for upcoming parliamentary sessions. By keeping parliamentary&#13;
committees informed about PRSP priorities, working groups encourage a more streamlined&#13;
legislative environment for the passage of key PRSP or PRSP-support legislation. Moreover,&#13;
committee reports on national PRSP progress in light of other information available to sector-&#13;
specific committees could be the basis for a parliamentary contribution to the periodic national&#13;
progress report required by IFI's.&#13;
&#13;
3.3 Parliamentary Review of the Draft PRSP Document&#13;
&#13;
Filling Gaps in the Participatory Process&#13;
&#13;
Although countries are expected to consult with all national stakeholders in the development of a&#13;
PRSP, where parliamentarians believe that a particular actor or group of actors has not been&#13;
adequately consulted, they may be able to facilitate inclusion of inadvertently excluded stakeholders.&#13;
While capacity constraints may prevent many national legislatures from serving as the primary point&#13;
of participatory integration (ie: a legislature with full technical capacity could be relied upon to&#13;
conduct a large number of public hearings to investigate policy options or outcomes), parliaments&#13;
could incrementally expand their role in the consultative process. Gradually expanding activities&#13;
could include public committee hearings, the commissioning of a specific investigation, or tabling of&#13;
a report to reflect input from civic&#13;
actors. By providing an opportunity                         Committees and Caucuses May Provide&#13;
for opposition MPs to participate in                             Supplementary Information&#13;
such activities, the parliament's action      Parliamentary involvement that adds greater transparency may&#13;
may also build consensus on poverty           also contribute supplementary information for consideration&#13;
issues across political divisions. In         during a midpoint report, annual PRSP review, or Joint Staff&#13;
addition to the obvious impact on the         Assessment (JSA). Information brought to light through a&#13;
PRSP's participatory process, such            parliamentary review of any aspect of PRSP development or&#13;
activities could encourage greater            implementation could assist national or external assessment by&#13;
PRSP support from groups with the             providing an additional source of information. Consequently, if&#13;
potential to disrupt implementation           parliaments plan to share the findings of their investigation&#13;
(parties currently in opposition but          with IFI staff in country, this information may be of most use&#13;
with the potential return to power in         prior to the completion of the JSA. Similarly, Ministries may&#13;
the years ahead) thereby promoting            find that parliamentary review of PRSP components serve as a&#13;
sustainability of PRSP strategy itself.       useful inlet for feedback on the impact of PRSP initiatives&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Parliamentary Review of the Draft PRSP&#13;
Document                                                           Parliamentary Mechanisms to Generate&#13;
Aside from the few countries whose constitutions                  Constructive Public Debate on the PRSP&#13;
require the parliament to ratify any multi-year                 Hold time-limited debate on PRSP priorities.&#13;
economic plan, the PRSP process requires no formal              Use parliamentary "Question Time" to request&#13;
parliamentary authorization. However, even where                 PRSP updates.&#13;
not mandated with ratification of economic policy,              Debate and pass a resolution in support of&#13;
parliaments can strengthen the PRSP process                      PRSP sectoral initiatives or priorities.&#13;
through debate and resolution of support for                    Invite PRSP commission staff to brief MPs on&#13;
proposed PRSP priorities. In light of legislatures'              PRSP issues.&#13;
impact on national budget allocations and legislative           Hold committee hearings on sector-specific&#13;
priorities, public parliamentary support for                     objectives or priorities.&#13;
established PRSP priorities could go a long way in              Table a committee report on the impact of a&#13;
establishing national ownership of poverty reduction             particular anti-poverty initiative.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                Parliaments and the PRSP Process          11&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
strategies. By including multiple political parties, an opportunity for time-limited parliamentary&#13;
debate on he PRSP prior to its submission could also strengthen the country's ability to adhere to a&#13;
poverty reduction strategy over time. Finally, even where parliamentary debate regarding the PRSP&#13;
leads to no formal resolution or motion, it would likely foster public awareness and debate about&#13;
various aspects of the PRSP.&#13;
&#13;
     4. Recognizing a Role for Parliaments in PRSP Implementation&#13;
              Budget Allocation, Legislation, and Public Education&#13;
&#13;
Because parliaments are ultimately responsible for passing sound legislation, the national assembly's&#13;
ability to improve PRSP implementation is primarily rooted in aligning national legislation with&#13;
PRSP priorities; in order for countries to implement their poverty reduction strategies, legislatures&#13;
must approve PRSP-compatible budgets and pass PRSP-relevant legislation. Consequently, a&#13;
parliament's ability to evaluate proposed legislation with an eye to PRSP priorities takes on added&#13;
importance in relation to ensuring a results-oriented, comprehensive implementation of the strategy.&#13;
&#13;
4.1 Budget Allocations&#13;
                                                Figure 2. Parliamentary Involvement in Budget and PRSP Cycles&#13;
Because the PRSP sets the policy&#13;
framework for poverty reduction efforts&#13;
and spending, the annual national                     Bud get C ycle                            PRSP cycle&#13;
budget is the single greatest tool for                                 Parliam ents can&#13;
PRSP implementation. In light of this,&#13;
time for a legislative review of the PRSP                   B udget          Ag gr e ga te         Poverty&#13;
                                                                            pu blic input&#13;
should be built-in to the budget process                   P lanning                             A ssess ment&#13;
&#13;
to avoid last minute intra-governmental&#13;
conflict regarding allocations. While&#13;
periodic briefings of parliamentarians or                                                          P overty&#13;
                                                            B udget         D e ba te a nd          P olicy&#13;
committees build consensus among sec-                       Drafting      ide ntify prior ite s&#13;
                                                                                                 Formulation&#13;
tor-specific actors, parliamentary ex-&#13;
amination of the full PRSP may have&#13;
additional benefits. A parliament is                         B udget          Im prove              P RS P&#13;
much more likely to approve a budget                     Implementation    tra ns pa re nc y    Implementation&#13;
that reflects already agreed upon PRSP&#13;
priorities if it has been involved in the&#13;
initial priority setting process; at the                   Monitoring      Ap ply s ta nda r d   Monitoring&#13;
very least, a debate over PRSP priorities                      and            o ve r s ight           and&#13;
allows the government to identify those                    E valuation      m e c ha nis m s      Ev aluation&#13;
&#13;
components which have insufficient po-&#13;
litical support to pass parliamentary&#13;
scrutiny.&#13;
&#13;
            Effective PRSP Budget Analysis by              The impact of sharing PRSP progress with&#13;
                Parliaments is Facilitated by:             the parliament in advance of budget nego-&#13;
     Timely access to PRSP and draft-budget                tiations is directly related to the period of&#13;
     Adequate number of staff                              time allowed for parliamentary analysis of&#13;
     Budgetary analysis training                           the PRSP. To ensure that there is adequate&#13;
     Access to economic analysis                           time for review and feedback, parliaments&#13;
     Computing/ research facilities                        could request reports or briefings on the&#13;
     Coordination between relevant committees&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
12    K.S. Hubli and A. P. Mandaville&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
content of the PRSP prior to its submission as part of the budget approval process. At the same time,&#13;
steps must be taken to ensure that parliamentary committees have adequate staffing and technical&#13;
capacities to engage closely with the more technical aspects of PRSP-specific budget analysis.&#13;
&#13;
4.2 Legislation&#13;
&#13;
In many cases, non-budgetary legislation may be required to implement a full PRSP; thus, PRSP-&#13;
specific assessment of legislation can (and should) occur at multiple levels.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                     Table 1. Ensuring Legislative Compatibility with PRSP Priorities&#13;
&#13;
Level of action    Description of activity                       Can be supported by&#13;
&#13;
                      Debate and approval of the budget          Early involvement in PRSP discussions&#13;
                                                                  Advance notice of PRSP time tables&#13;
Plenary               Debate and passage of legislation to       Facilitating rules of parliamentary&#13;
                        support or implement the PRSP&#13;
                                                                   procedure&#13;
&#13;
                    Coordinate committee member                  Open communication channels between&#13;
                                                                   ministries and committees&#13;
                     participation in sector- specific            Advance notice of PRSP events and&#13;
                     technical events (such as stakeholder&#13;
Sector-Specific                                                    periodic briefing by working groups&#13;
                     workshops or sectoral editorial&#13;
Committee                                                         Technical issue training for committee&#13;
                     boards)&#13;
                    Review ministry-sponsored sectoral            members (eg: health, agriculture)&#13;
                                                                  Adequate numbers of technically trained&#13;
                     legislation against PRSP priorities&#13;
                                                                   committee staff&#13;
&#13;
                    Coordinate review of legislation             Formal creation of a Parliamentary&#13;
                                                                   Committee for Poverty Reduction&#13;
                     specific to the PRSP&#13;
Anti-Poverty        Facilitate involvement of sector-            Leadership and technical skills training&#13;
Committee                                                          for committee members and staff&#13;
                     specific committees or individual            IFI willingness to interact with official&#13;
                     deputies&#13;
                                                                   sub-parliamentary groupings&#13;
&#13;
                                                                  Coordination of PRSP and budget&#13;
Budget or           Conduct public hearing to compare&#13;
                                                                   cycles&#13;
Finance              PRSP priorities with national budget         Technical budget training for MPs and&#13;
Committee            allocations&#13;
                                                                   Staff&#13;
&#13;
                    Distribution of PRSP documents to            Access to information and&#13;
                     relevant committees                           documentation&#13;
Parliamentary       Research and track ongoing PRSP              Staff training on research and other&#13;
Staff                issues/ programs                              technical legislative skills&#13;
                    Summarize PRSP priorities and                May require supplementary staff with&#13;
                     initiatives for review/debate                 sectoral expertise&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Managing Legislation and Legislative Impact Across Sectors&#13;
&#13;
Secondary legislation will often be needed in order to implement different parts of the PRSP. For&#13;
example, a country might identify education as one of its sector priorities, with their PRSP indicating&#13;
that the budget will allocate a series of block grants to local councils to be applied to education needs&#13;
as determined by the local council. If however, decentralization of decision making authority and&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                               Parliaments and the PRSP Process    13&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
financial responsibility for education has not yet occurred, legislation decentralizing these powers is&#13;
necessary before the PRSP can be fully implemented. In addition to decentralization laws,&#13;
parliaments may be required to address labor laws, tax codes, equal rights legislation, or trade&#13;
policies to proceed with PRSP plans. A parliament that has already played an active role in the&#13;
diagnosis and development of its PRSP will be better able to coordinate the passage of such&#13;
legislation.&#13;
&#13;
4.3 Educating the Public on PRSP Processes, Programs, and Impact&#13;
&#13;
As in the policy development phase of the PRSP,&#13;
parliamentary outreach to constituents can be                  Niger: Parliamentary Public Outreach&#13;
mobilized to strengthen implementation by                                on PRSP Processes&#13;
increasing public awareness of PRSP initiatives.        Nigerian legislators' efforts to communicate with&#13;
Such outreach could be approached from a number         the rural poor about poverty reduction processes&#13;
of angles, and would in many cases, fit easily with     and initiatives shows a creative approach to&#13;
outreach activities that MPs or parliamentary sub-      parliamentary involvement in the PRSP. With&#13;
groups have already-existing incentives to              limited rural literacy and nearly prohibitive travel&#13;
conduct.                                                costs, Deputies in Niger have turned to less&#13;
Regular communication with citizens is not only         traditional communications mechanism to reach&#13;
key to popular awareness of and participation in,       out to the public. In mid-2002 and early 2003, a&#13;
PRSP initiatives but also contributes to popular        steering committee of legislators worked together&#13;
trust in democratic institutions by encouraging the     with a national theatre troupe to create and&#13;
perception that elected officials are working on        produce a series of radio plays designed to&#13;
citizens' behalf. Conversely, if deputies participate   inform the audience about the role of the national&#13;
in poverty diagnosis and then do not communicate        assembly in poverty reduction initiatives and the&#13;
the result of citizen's earlier participation or        PRSP. These radio plays, which depicted a&#13;
inform voters about the actions being taken based       Deputy traveling through his constituency and&#13;
on their expressions of concern, citizens will not      explaining various aspects of the PRSP, were&#13;
only avoid the PRSP's participatory elements in         broadcast in multiple national languages with an&#13;
the future, but the failure to respond to voiced        emphasis on reaching rural areas. Deputies later&#13;
concerns will also diminish citizens' faith in          visited some of these constituencies to discuss&#13;
national governing institutions.                        poverty reduction issues and initiatives in person.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
14    K.S. Hubli and A. P. Mandaville&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                 Table 2. Parliamentary Outreach to Educate the Public on PRSP Programs&#13;
&#13;
Objective                           MP or Deputy Activity                     Rationale&#13;
&#13;
                                     Village or town hall meetings           Deputies whose home district&#13;
Geographically targeted public       Direct constituency service hours       have seen an increase in&#13;
education efforts on specific        Joint events on PRSP programs           infrastructure or available&#13;
PRSP priorities and programs                                                  financial support are more&#13;
                                      with local civic organizations&#13;
(eg: local infrastructure project,   Joint events with municipal level       inclined to speak publicly&#13;
pilot micro-credit program)                                                   about PRSP policies and&#13;
                                      officials or administrators&#13;
                                                                              initiatives&#13;
National or regional public          Public service announcements            Deputies elected in a&#13;
education on general PRSP             through various media                   proportional representation&#13;
priorities and large scale           Cooperation with networks of            system are more likely willing&#13;
government initiatives (eg:           regional governing bodies (or           to do extensive public&#13;
national education program,           other participatory mechanisms) to      speaking as it improves their&#13;
new transportation system)            explain new programs                    internal party profile&#13;
Advance public knowledge of          Plenary debate on new legislation&#13;
                                                                              Gradual public education&#13;
new or controversial policies        Committee hearings with NGOs,&#13;
                                                                              helps to avoid extreme public&#13;
necessary for PRSP                    trade unions, etc&#13;
                                                                              response (riots) to introduction&#13;
implementation (ie: price            Media statements by&#13;
                                                                              of less publicly welcome&#13;
deregulation, closure of              parliamentarians in advance of&#13;
                                                                              policies&#13;
defunct industries)                   legislation&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        5. Aligning Parliamentary Oversight Mechanisms with PRSP&#13;
                                 Monitoring and Evaluation&#13;
&#13;
Because the PRSP process is cyclical, several of the&#13;
mechanisms for parliamentary strengthening of the                    Parliamentary Oversight and PRSP&#13;
PRSP during monitoring and evaluation phases are             While effective PRSPs include a plan for ongo-&#13;
quite similar to those applied during poverty                ing monitoring and evaluation, certain parlia-&#13;
diagnosis and PRSP formulation. Information                  mentary practices may be leveraged to&#13;
gleaned in this phase about the impact and                   strengthen in-country monitoring or evaluation&#13;
performance of PRSP initiatives will eventually              capacity.&#13;
become the basis upon which countries adjust                    Parliamentary review or confirmation of key&#13;
poverty reduction strategies, shift resources, or                officials (commissions)&#13;
determine whether priority targets have been met.               Executive updates before committees (can&#13;
Parliaments, already constitutionally charged with               be facilitated through inclusion of reporting&#13;
providing oversight for executive branch                         requirements in PRSP text)&#13;
implementation of legislation and budget policies,              Queries about PRSP initiatives or results&#13;
can be a natural clearinghouse for information on                during regular `question time'&#13;
assessment of PRSP implementation from a variety                Public requests for information from&#13;
of sources. Parliamentary oversight activities may               ministries or other executive bodies&#13;
also strengthen a country's capacity for self                   Committee request for findings of external&#13;
assessment of PRSP implementation by requesting                  auditing bodies&#13;
evidence that the executive is pursuing activities in           Commissioned investigations into lack of&#13;
                                                                 adherence to PRSP priorities&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                Parliaments and the PRSP Process   15&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
keeping with PRSP priorities, or by posing sector-specific questions on the effectiveness of&#13;
particular strategies or activities.&#13;
&#13;
5.1 Committee Hearings on the Impact of PRSP Initiatives&#13;
&#13;
Although statistical data on the impacts of PRSP initiatives is critical to assessing the&#13;
implementation of a country's poverty reduction strategy, non-quantitative elements play a key role&#13;
in evaluating the program's impact on quality of life for the poor. As in the poverty diagnosis phase&#13;
of the PRSP process, one way for parliament to compliment ongoing efforts to gather information&#13;
and monitor changes in the non-quantitative dimensions of poverty would be to solicit input from&#13;
geographically or demographically specific areas through MPs' constituency outreach activities. As&#13;
before, sector specific committees could ask MPs to solicit information on the impact of PRSP&#13;
driven programs through office hours, casework, town hall meetings, surveys, or informal focus&#13;
groups already being conducted, or could look to bring sector-relevant NGOs to testify before&#13;
committees on the results of PRSP priority projects. Bringing citizens' feedback directly into&#13;
parliamentary debates on the results of the year's PRSP implementation not only makes the whole&#13;
process more participatory, but also creates sufficient transparency to allow international partners&#13;
more insight into the soundness of the PRSP as it is being implemented. Further, by setting a&#13;
precedent for legislative investigation into the policy implementation by the executive branch, this&#13;
complementary activity helps to build a check and balance system for more sustainable anti-poverty&#13;
initiatives over time.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Budget, Finance, or Audit Committee Reports&#13;
on Adherence to PRSP Priorities                             Malawi: Civic Testimony Before Budget and&#13;
                                                                         Finance Committee&#13;
Just as parliamentary review of the budget in          In Malawi, Parliamentary interest in monitoring the&#13;
light of PRSP priorities was critical at the           PRSP provided the opportunity for a historic first.&#13;
implementation phase, committee analysis of            On May 6 and 7, 2002 four civil society networks&#13;
sector-specific correlation between the priorities     representing more than 80 Malawian NGOs testi-&#13;
articulated in the PRSP and actual expenditure         fied at a public hearing before the Parliament's&#13;
on line items is a critical part of monitoring         Budget &amp; Finance Committee. These NGO repre-&#13;
implementation of the PRSP. With its mandate           sentatives, the first in Malawi's multi-party history&#13;
to provide oversight for executive branch              to testify before a parliamentary committee, pre-&#13;
implementation, parliament has sufficient              sented documentation and testimony regarding the&#13;
legitimacy to call agencies or ministries to task      delivery of government services in key sectors of&#13;
for excessive or insufficient expenditure levels.      the economy including health, education, and agri-&#13;
Through a series of public reports or hearings,        culture. MPs from the Agriculture, Education, and&#13;
such oversight could become one of the most            Health Committees also attended the hearing. As a&#13;
effective means of strengthening domestic              result, the Committee drew heavily on the findings&#13;
capacity to eradicate patronage and                    of the networks' monitoring activities to table a 54-&#13;
inappropriate use of poverty alleviation funds.        page Pre-Budget Report and issue a Post-Budget&#13;
Development and institutionalization of this           Report tracking expenditures for established priori-&#13;
oversight capacity in parliament could include         ties. These reports not only led to more informed&#13;
hearings with ministries, office of budget             participation by MPs in sectoral committees, but&#13;
management, external auditing agencies (where          also generated significant media coverage, enhanc-&#13;
they exist), local governments, and/or citizen         ing the probability of national public debate.&#13;
monitoring organizations.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
16    K.S. Hubli and A. P. Mandaville&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
5.2 Legislative Review of Annual PRSP Progress Reports&#13;
&#13;
It is expected that an annual progress report will be prepared by countries that are implementing a&#13;
full PRSP. A parliament engaged in even a single phase of the PRSP process  whether that is de-&#13;
                                                   termining the non-quantitative aspects of poverty,&#13;
    Methods for Parliament to Contribute to        establishing legislative priorities, reviewing annual&#13;
         Annual PRSP Progress Reports              budgets, communicating with their constituents&#13;
     Parliamentary committee reports to            about PRSP initiatives, or exercising expenditure&#13;
      PRSP commission                              oversight and project evaluation  would be able to&#13;
     Sector-specific committee hearings on         review annual PRSP reports. In addition to again&#13;
      sectoral PRSP initiatives culminating in     lending greater participation through its&#13;
      pre-report recommendations                   representative nature, it is in these annual reports&#13;
     Plenary review and resolution in support      that adjustments to PRSP priorities or programs are&#13;
      of annual progress report                    made, thus parliamentary review provides an addi-&#13;
     Sub-parliamentary groups to gather civic      tional check on whether pending legislation and&#13;
      input regarding specific sectors             budget allocations are in line with current PRSP&#13;
                                                   priorities. Some thought might also be given to the&#13;
implementation of a system of pre-report recommendations made by committees to the relevant min-&#13;
istries or working groups.&#13;
&#13;
5. 3 Integrating Parliamentarians or Parliamentary Committees into Monitoring and&#13;
Evaluation Groups&#13;
&#13;
As part of the PRSP process, PRSP countries may create Public Expenditure Management (PEM)&#13;
groups or other groups to monitor performance. As with working groups during policy formulation,&#13;
parliamentary interaction with evaluation groups would improve the sustainability of the PRSP&#13;
process by lending the parliament's broader political legitimacy to groups otherwise appointed by the&#13;
executive branch. Here, institutionalized parliamentary interaction with monitoring could take one of&#13;
two forms: assign a pre-determined number of MPs serving on relevant sectoral committees to&#13;
participate as observers in monitoring groups, or, establish a regular schedule on which evaluation&#13;
teams brief relevant committees on their findings. Barring unusual constitutional or other political&#13;
circumstances, the most efficient way of combining PRSP monitoring with parliamentary oversight&#13;
responsibilities would be through an institutionalized schedule of briefings. This practice would also&#13;
encourage transparency of general budget expenditure, again reinforcing domestic checks on&#13;
patronage systems.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
                                                                         Parliaments and the PRSP Process      17&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
        6. Consolidating the Impact of Parliamentary Involvement in&#13;
                                             the PRSP Process&#13;
&#13;
While the national impact of enhanced parliamentary&#13;
involvement in the PRSP will vary from country to                          PRSP Processes May Be Strengthened&#13;
&#13;
country, one means of building on the achievements of                        Through Regional Exchanges on:&#13;
                                                                          Parliamentary public outreach&#13;
a single legislature is through the regional and global                   Improving communication with the ex-&#13;
parliamentary networks. On a regional basis, links                         ecutive branch&#13;
between deputies confronting similar socio-economic                       Coordinating monitoring efforts&#13;
challenges provide an opportunity to share                                Contributing to annual PRSP reviews&#13;
experiences, successes, and lessons learned. More&#13;
globally, parliamentary networks6 offer a means for deputies to survey and discuss universal chal-&#13;
lenges to democratic governance with their peers and colleagues. As a larger number of PRSP coun-&#13;
tries begin to implement and evaluate their own PRSP initiatives, the value of these cross-country&#13;
exchanges will grow.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                    Table 3. Supporting Global or Regional Parliamentary Network Activity&#13;
&#13;
Network Activity                                               May be Supported by&#13;
                                                                Pre-conference technical assistance to relevant&#13;
                                                                 committees or parliamentary sub-groups in-&#13;
                                                                 country&#13;
Regional conferences for legislators on PRSP                    Post-conference consultations with participants&#13;
best practices                                                   on application of shared experiences at home&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                                                Selection of participants in positions to apply&#13;
                                                                 experience&#13;
                                                                Pre-exchange briefings&#13;
                                                                Post-exchange in-country strategy sessions on&#13;
Parliamentary Exchanges                                          application of experience&#13;
                                                                Technical and financial support for in-country&#13;
                                                                 programs based on experience gained out of&#13;
                                                                 country&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
6 For example, the South African Development Council Parliamentary Forum (SADC-PF), the Economic Community Of&#13;
West African States (ECOWAS) Parliament, Inter-Parliamentary Union , the Commonwealth Parliamentary Association,&#13;
etc. In addition to regional and global inter-parliamentary associations, the Parliamentary Network on the World Bank&#13;
(PNoWB) is designed to foster greater parliamentary involvement in international development as a whole.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
Mission of World Bank Institute&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
This mission of WBI is to help World Bank&#13;
&#13;
clients and staff acquire new development&#13;
&#13;
knowledge and skills through a variety of&#13;
&#13;
courses, seminars, and other learning&#13;
&#13;
events. It designs programs on topics&#13;
&#13;
related to economic and social development&#13;
&#13;
for governments, nongovernmental organi-&#13;
&#13;
zations, and other stakeholders. The&#13;
&#13;
Institute produces and disseminates&#13;
&#13;
publications and electronic information&#13;
&#13;
products that support these objectives.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
For information on WBI publications write to:&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Publications&#13;
WBI&#13;
The World Bank&#13;
1818 H Street, NW&#13;
Washington, DC 20433&#13;
Tel: 202-473-6349&#13;
Fax: 202-522-0401&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
Visit us on the World Wide Web at:&#13;
http://www.worldbank.org/wbi&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
SN37231&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="3264151">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2004/01/3264151/parliaments-prsp-process
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2004/01/3264151/parliaments-prsp-process</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2004/01/3264151/parliaments-prsp-process</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2004/04/26/000160016_20040426175045/Rendered/INDEX/286130Parliaments0WBI0WP.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2004/04/26/000160016_20040426175045/Rendered/PDF/286130Parliaments0WBI0WP.pdf</pdfurl>
        <datestored>2004-04-26T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2004-01-01T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Final</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309935</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Parliaments and the PRSP process
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The PRSP (Poverty Reduction Strategy
            Paper) process is continually evolving as countries and
            their development partners learn from early experience. This
            report is designed to assist those involved in poverty
            reduction strategies with identifying and implementing
            activities and programs that will integrate existing
            democratic institutions, namely the national assembly or
            parliament, into poverty reduction efforts, thus
            strengthening the impact and sustainability of each
            country's PRSP. Through analysis, checklists, and
            activity options, the report highlights specific mechanisms
            by which parliaments can strengthen the PRSP process and
            reinforce its positive outcomes though greater involvement
            in poverty diagnosis, policy development, PRSP
            implementation, and evaluation/monitoring. For ease of use,
            it has been organized in keeping with the PRSP cycle.
            Consequently, sections two, three, four, and five address
            opportunities for legislative involvement in poverty
            diagnosis, policy formulation, implementation, and
            monitoring and evaluation, respectively.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Parliaments and the PRSP process
        </docna>
        <display_title>Parliaments and the PRSP process</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/research/2004/01/3264151/parliaments-prsp-process</listing_relative_url>
        <docty>WBI Working Paper</docty>
        <subtopic>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Parliamentary Government,Poverty Assessment,National Governance,Governance Indicators</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Poverty Reduction</teratopic>
        <count>World</count>
        <authors>
            <author>K. Scott Hubli; Alicia P. Mandaville</author>
        </authors>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000160016_20040426175045</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>The World Region,The World Region</admreg>
        <colti>WBI working paper series</colti>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Poverty Reduction</historic_topic>
        <majdocty>Publications &amp; Research</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Poverty mitigation strategies; Parliaments;
            Poverty diagnostics; Policy development; Monitoring &amp;
            evaluation; Policy implementation; Legislative participation
            allocation of resources,authorization,Budget
            Allocations,budget process,budget processes,citizen,citizen
            groups,citizens,civil society,civil war,coalition
            government,Committee
            Hearings,consensus,constituencies,constituency,constituency
            relations,Constituent,constituents,constitution,constitutions,consultative
            process,corruption,country ownership,country
            strategies,decentralization,decision-
            making,democracy,democratic institutions,democratic
            processes,democratic transitions,demographics,development
            partners,districts,donor community,economic
            development,economic factors,economic problems,elected
            representatives,election,elections,electorate,executive
            branch,expenditure,fiscal,geographic spread,government
            officials,income,inflation,institutional
            arrangement,institutional
            stakeholders,institutionalization,legal
            reform,Legislation,Legislative authority,legislative
            bodies,legislative environment,legislative
            structures,legislators,legislature,legislatures,local
            communities,local government,local organizations,members of
            parliament,ministry of Finance,MP,MPs,national
            budget,national economy,national institutions,national
            legislatures,national parliament,national
            parliaments,national poverty,national poverty reduction
            strategies,national poverty reduction
            strategy,nations,opposition
            parties,parliament,Parliamentarians,Parliamentary
            Committees,parliamentary debate,Parliamentary
            Involvement,Parliamentary Mechanisms,Parliamentary
            Network,Parliamentary Oversight,parliamentary
            sessions,parliamentary staff,parliamentary
            systems,Parliaments,participatory methods,participatory
            process,participatory processes,party discipline,policy
            actions,policy decisions,policy development,policy
            framework,policy issues,policy options,policy
            process,political conditions,political development,political
            institutions,political leaders,political
            legitimacy,political parties,political party,political
            representation,poor people,poverty levels,Poverty
            Policy,poverty reduction,poverty reduction policies,poverty
            reduction strategies,Poverty Reduction Strategy,poverty
            strategy,Pro-Poor Policy,Public Debate,Public
            Education,public hearings,representatives,republics,State
            institutions,statistical data,technical assistance,technical
            capacity,technical skills,technical support,transparency
        </keywd>
        <owner>Poverty Reduction &amp; Econ Mng Div (WBIPR)</owner>
        <repnb>28613</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Teaching and Learning</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Competitiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>International Economics and Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Liberalization and Regional Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade Restrictiveness</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade and Integration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Arts and Culture</ml:concept><ml:concept>Education</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environment and Natural Resources</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Trade</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics and Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation and Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Strategy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Alternative Sentencing Options</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Community based Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Correctional Services and Facilities</ml:concept><ml:concept>Corrections</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime Prevention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Crime and Society</ml:concept><ml:concept>Defense Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Detention</ml:concept><ml:concept>Enforcement Policies and Oversight Mechanism</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic</ml:concept><ml:concept>Forensic Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Investigative Task Force Police</ml:concept><ml:concept>Juvenile Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Law Enforcement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Offender Reintegration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Administration and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Police Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Problem solving Policing</ml:concept><ml:concept>Prosecution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Restorative Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Therapeutic Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Assistance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim Services</ml:concept><ml:concept>Victim-Offender Mediation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Asset Recovery</ml:concept><ml:concept>Competitiveness and Competition Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Market Regulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Microeconomic and Market Reforms</ml:concept><ml:concept>Demographics</ml:concept><ml:concept>Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deconcentration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delegation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Devolution</ml:concept><ml:concept>Sub-National Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Subnational Government and Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Analysis &amp; Monitoring</ml:concept><ml:concept>Delivery Units</ml:concept><ml:concept>Grievance Redress</ml:concept><ml:concept>Indicators</ml:concept><ml:concept>M&amp;E</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Measurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Performance Reviews</ml:concept><ml:concept>Rapid Results Approaches</ml:concept><ml:concept>Checks on Executive Power</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Citizen User Satisfaction Survey</ml:concept><ml:concept>Independent Commissions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Ombudsmen</ml:concept><ml:concept>Oversight</ml:concept><ml:concept>Parliament</ml:concept><ml:concept>Procurement Complaints Review Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Supreme Audit Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Civil Society</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Environmental Economics &amp; Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legislation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Media</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction Strategies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Criminal Justice</ml:concept><ml:concept>Copyright</ml:concept><ml:concept>Examinations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Local Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Competition Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Administrative Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Accountability Mechanisms</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions/></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>