<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><ml:doc-envelope xmlns:ml="http://marklogic.com/poolparty/worldbank"><ml:original-txt>                                       (Cr. 342%STP)&#13;
                 Release of the Second Tranche - Full Compliance&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                     I. Background&#13;
&#13;
1. During the period 1998-99, the Government launched an economic reform program&#13;
   despite a difficult political environment. IDA, through two IDFs (Public Resource&#13;
   Management and Administrative Reform), supported the implementation of the first&#13;
   phase of the reform program. Given the encouraging progress, a Public Resource&#13;
   Management Credit was approved by the Board on November                 2, 2000, and&#13;
   provided budgetary support to fill the financial gap for the period 2000-2001,&#13;
   permitting the Government to sustain its reform program.&#13;
&#13;
2. The objective of the Public Resource Management Credit is to assist Sao Tome and&#13;
   Principe in consolidating macroeconomic stability and in gaining competitiveness.&#13;
   The measures supported by the operation are aimed at creating an environment&#13;
   conducive to private sector-led economic growth. Also, by focusing on revenue&#13;
   mobilization and the reallocation of public resources towards education, health, and&#13;
   poverty   reduction programs, this operation seeks to ensure that these key&#13;
   sectors/programs would not suffer from budgetary cuts and would have a direct and&#13;
   positive impact on Sao Tome and Principe's efforts towards poverty reduction.&#13;
&#13;
3  The reform program supported by the Public Resource Management Credit has&#13;
 l&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   three key    components:     (i)  improving    domestic  resource mobilization;   (ii)&#13;
   strengthening public expenditure management; and (iii) continuing implementation&#13;
   of the public     enterprise reform program. The Credit has complemented and&#13;
   deepened actions already agreed under the programs of the IMF, AfDB and EU in&#13;
   the area of public expenditure management.&#13;
&#13;
                  II. Recent Political and Economic Developments&#13;
&#13;
4  The presidential and legislative elections and related political deadlock in 2001 and&#13;
 l&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   2002 led to administrative standstill and slowed the pace of the reform process&#13;
   considerably. In 2003, political in-fighting (January 2003) and political and social&#13;
   unrest (April    riots and July bloodless coup) contributed to a difficult     policy&#13;
   environment. Nonetheless, the implementation of reform has continued, albeit more&#13;
   slowly than envisaged at the time of the credit approval.&#13;
&#13;
5. The developments in the nascent petroleum sector have dominated economic events&#13;
   in 2003. In the first quarter of 2003, the GSTP, using technical assistance funded&#13;
   from the World        Bank PANIC-TA      credit, renegotiated its existing petroleum&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
   contracts with three companies and Nigeria, resulting in more favorable terms. In&#13;
   April 2003, the Joint Zone Administration      (JZA) started the bidding process for&#13;
   exploration of the nine deep sea blocks shared by S%oTome (40 percent) and&#13;
   Nigeria (60 percent). The transparent bidding process closed in late October on a&#13;
   highly successful note, with 33 bids from 22 companies for seven blocks. Sao Tome&#13;
   will receive an approximate US$70-120 millions in the fourth quarter of 2004 in&#13;
   one-off signature bonuses from contracts on these blocks. However, Sgo Tome is&#13;
   not expected to seeits shareof petroleum production revenues before 2010.&#13;
&#13;
6. The GSTP has started to develop a petroleum legal framework in cooperation with&#13;
   the National Assembly and other stakeholders. The Government requested and is&#13;
   receiving technical assistance from the World Bank and UNDP in this effort. The&#13;
   law is expected to be adopted by the National Assembly and promulgated by the&#13;
   President in June 2004. To provide support in this area over the medium term, the&#13;
   World Bank is developing a new three-year TA credit to assist the Government&#13;
   prepare for the new petroleum era economy.&#13;
&#13;
7. Both the World Bank and the I;IF         programs experienced slippages due to the&#13;
   political developments of 2001-2002. The PRGF was suspended and an IMF Staff&#13;
   Monitored Program (SMP) was launched in January 2002. The new Government&#13;
   that was formed in April 2002 committed itself to fiscal discipline and resumed&#13;
   implementation of its reform program. In August 2002, the SMP was extended to&#13;
   end 2002. Overall macroeconomic stability was maintained and performance under&#13;
   the SMP program was broadly satisfactory through end 2002. Real growth in 2001&#13;
   and 2002 reached 4 percent per year, helped by increased competitiveness resulting&#13;
   from a real depreciation and higher international prices for cocoa. Inflation, which&#13;
   stood at 9.5 percent in 2001, fell to 8.9 percent by end 2002.&#13;
&#13;
8. Macroeconomic performance has remained broadly satisfactory in 2003. Real GDP&#13;
   growth in 2003 is estimated to be near 4.5 percent, with end-period inflation close&#13;
   to 10 percent. Broad money grew by 50 percent (including a strong rise in currency&#13;
   in circulation), as a result of a marked increase in demand for transaction balances;&#13;
   net foreign assets rose sharply. The external current account deficit is estimated at&#13;
   45 percent of GDP, reflecting a strong increase in exports and a modest rise in&#13;
   imports. The authorities maintained their flexible exchange rate regime: the real&#13;
   effective exchange rate depreciated by 5 percent during January-October 2003,&#13;
   mitigating the effect on competitiveness of an estimated 11 percent decline in the&#13;
   terms of trade.&#13;
&#13;
9. In 2001-2003, fiscal performance has remained generally on track, although there&#13;
   were problems relating to election expenditures, pressure for civil    service wage&#13;
   increases, and spending increases following        the announcement of petroleum&#13;
   signature bonuses. Tax revenue collections rose from 16.9 percent of GDP in 1999&#13;
   to 18.6 percent in 2001, 19.5 percent of GDP in 2002, and are estimated at 18.6&#13;
   percent in 2003 in the aftermath of the July coup. Total expenditure reached 76.8&#13;
   percent of GDP in 2001 due to election related expenditure, petroleum signature&#13;
   bonuses and a short term loan to the public utility        company. In 2002, total&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                           2&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
    expenditure was 63.5 percent of GDP compared with the programmed 69.7 percent,&#13;
    highlighting the Government's renewed fiscal discipline and commitment to macro-&#13;
    economic stability. The primary fiscal deficit was in line with the macroeconomic&#13;
    program. In fact, total primary balance for 2002 was less than programmed (-4.3&#13;
    percent of GDP vs. the programmed -4.7 percent). Domestic arrears had been&#13;
    cleared by end 2002. For 2003, the primary fiscal deficit, including HIPC-financed&#13;
    social outlays, amounted to 12 percent of GDP. Domestic bank financing of the&#13;
    budget deficit was contained within the program limits.&#13;
&#13;
10.  On the basis of the 2002-2003 track record, understandings were reached with the&#13;
    IMF on a new PRGF-supported program at end June 2003, but the bloodless coup&#13;
    of July 2003 suspended the planned presentation of the new PRGF-supported&#13;
    program. The IMF visited the country in November-December 2003 and is planning&#13;
    to continue discussions on the PRGF-supported program in late June 2004. In&#13;
    addition   to the macroeconomic        performance      being    satisfactory, successful&#13;
    conclusion of the PRGF discussions hinges on the adoption of a satisfactory law on&#13;
    petroleum revenue management that is expected for June 2004 and also on reaching&#13;
    understandings on a medium-term macro-economic framework. In concluding the&#13;
    2003 Article IV consultation on March 17, 2004, 111\4FExecutive Directors noted&#13;
    that Sao Tome and Principe's macroeconomic performance had remained broadly&#13;
    satisfactory, despite a short-lived coup d'etat. They noted the progress in improving&#13;
    public expenditure management, a long-standing concern. The Executive Directors&#13;
    of the IMF endorsed the authorities' strategy of stabilizing the non-oil primary&#13;
    fiscal deficit over the medium term. To help ensure that fiscal policy remains&#13;
    sustainable, Directors stressedthat the deficit should be limited in the long term to&#13;
    the interest and dividend earnings from the future oil fund's accumulated assets.&#13;
    The 2004 budget, as presented to the National Assembly in January 2004, is in line&#13;
    with this approach and consistent with understandings reached with Fund staff last&#13;
    Fall.&#13;
&#13;
11. The implementation of the structural reforms has experienced some delays due to&#13;
    lack of institutional capacity and the political instability the country has experienced&#13;
    in the past three years (five Governments in two years, April 2003 riots, July 2003&#13;
    coup).   However,     some difficult   political   decisions    have been taken     and&#13;
    implemented, including separation of over 300 civil servants in early 2002, holding&#13;
    the line on wage increase demands by the civil service, adoption of a 2003 budget&#13;
    in line with the medium term program of the PRSP, an audit of three Governmental&#13;
    contracts and the adoption of a broadly satisfactory 2004 budget. Furthermore, the&#13;
    Central Bank resolved the situation of the bankrupt Banco Commercial de Ecuador&#13;
    (BCE) by selling it to foreign investors in the first half of 2003.&#13;
&#13;
                 III. Progress in Implementing      the Reform Program&#13;
&#13;
12. The Government recognizes that maintenance of macroeconomic stability is a&#13;
    prerequisite for attaining the higher economic growth essential to reducing poverty.&#13;
    The PRMC has enabled the Government to continue to build on some of the&#13;
    reforms initiated in 1998/99. It also supports the PRSP goals of fostering private&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                            3&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
    sector development and directing funds to the priority sectors (health, education and&#13;
    infrastructure).&#13;
&#13;
13. The Government has shown c,ontinued commitment to its reform program, despite&#13;
    political instabili ty and low institutional capacity leading to slow and at time&#13;
    uneven progress. The positive outcomes of that reform program are reflected by the&#13;
    following:&#13;
&#13;
   *  After an extended participatory and transparent process, the PRSP was officially&#13;
      adopted during a national conference in December 2002 and promulgated by the&#13;
      President in January 2003. It will be officially sent to the World Bank and IMF&#13;
      shortly and presented to the Boards of both institutions in FY05. In the meantime,&#13;
      the 2003 budget already reflected elements of the PRSP. However, limited&#13;
      technical and administrative capacity remains a constraint to the implementation&#13;
      of its development program.&#13;
&#13;
      Actions have been taken to reduce unequal access to public services through the&#13;
      extension of services (especially renovation and building of health centers and&#13;
      schools), supported by donors and the HIPC            Interim Debt Relief.   Public&#13;
      expenditures for economic and social services that benefit the poor were&#13;
      increased. These expenditures included public transport and breakfast for school&#13;
      children that were launched in late 2001. Health and education strategies have&#13;
      been developed, costed and adopted, focusing on primary education and primary&#13;
      health care.&#13;
&#13;
      In public   expenditure management, the Government has been paying close&#13;
      attention to the wage bill, which has been maintained at approximately 9 percent&#13;
      of GDP during 2001-2003. It is working to launch the final phase of unifying&#13;
      civil service and payroll management into one computerized system. It carried out&#13;
      PERs in the health and education sectors in mid 2002 and first quarter of 2003&#13;
      respectively, and has already re-directed budgetary funds toward social sectors.&#13;
      Capital expenditures for health rose from US$2.21 million     in 2002 to US$4.21&#13;
      million in 2003. In education, capital expenditures rose from US$1.45 million in&#13;
      2002 to US$ 3.59 million in 2003. To address its weakness in debt management&#13;
      the Government created a semi-independent agency in the fall of 2003 to update&#13;
      and manage the debt data, analyze debt sustainability and develop a national&#13;
      strategy and criteria for indebtedness beyond HIPC and into the petroleum era.&#13;
      The Government still needs to address the antiquated law and ad hoc procedures&#13;
      relating to public procurement.&#13;
&#13;
   *  Public resource management and expenditure are being strengthened and made&#13;
      transparent. The Government has centralized the Government's revenue and&#13;
      external financial proceeds (except for some grants), and has improved control&#13;
      over extra-budgetary expenditures. It tightened control over budgetary transfers to&#13;
      SOEs. It has improved tax and tariff collection.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
  The reforms at the Finance Directorate have slowly taken shape. There are now&#13;
  three directorates: tax, budget and treasury. All three directorates have received&#13;
  technical assistance from the World Bank and other donors to assist them in&#13;
  capacity building and the reform of their budget related procedures. The budget is&#13;
  prepared following consultation with spending departments, but is still done on a&#13;
  yearly basis instead of within a medium term expenditure framework. The 2003&#13;
  budget, which was presented to the assembly in December 2002, is linked to the&#13;
  policy priorities of the PRSP and the macro-economic targets agreed to with&#13;
  international partners. The Govemrnent has also adopted a broadly satisfactory&#13;
  2004 budget. While       the Government still    lacks the necessary capacity to&#13;
  undertake a thorough internal control of the budgetary process, efforts at&#13;
  improving monitoring are underway: ad hoc a priori and posteriori checks on&#13;
  budget execution have been introduced. Also the Government is working within&#13;
  the framework of the HIPC AAP to improve budget management, including better&#13;
  budget execution and audits. An independent firm was retained in mid-2003 to&#13;
  supervise implementation      and progress of public     investment projects. The&#13;
  Auditor's Office has started its audit work in June 2003.&#13;
&#13;
  The Government has been pursuing its public enterprise privatization program. It&#13;
  liquidated a meat processing enterprise (ENCAR)        and a medicine distribution&#13;
  company (ENAMED)        in 2001. It sold a hotel (Pousada Boa Vista) in April 2003&#13;
  and received one bid for the bankrupt palm-oil company (EMOLVE)          in October&#13;
  2003. As a minority share holder in the national airline company, the GSTP has&#13;
  introduced competition in the national market leading to sharp price decreases,&#13;
  and has decreed that it would sell 1/7thof its sharesto national employees of Air&#13;
  Sao Tome and wishes to adopt an open sky policy. The GSTP is finalizing its&#13;
  withdrawal from a construction material company (Cunha Comes) and continues&#13;
  to   reform   the  water   and electricity   company     (EMAE).    Against    these&#13;
  accomplishments it should be noted that progress in the privatization program has&#13;
  been delayed by a number of factors, including political        and administrative&#13;
  deadlock related to the 2001-2002 electoral period, lack of capacity to assess&#13;
  value of the properties, and lack of investors' interest in the companies being&#13;
  marketed.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
l As part of the reforms intended to improve transparency and governance in the&#13;
  public administration, the Central Bank books are audited externally on a yearly&#13;
  basis and published on the intemet. In an effort to improve the Public Investment&#13;
  Program (PIP) performance (which suffered from low execution rates and no&#13;
  routine coordination with donors up to end 2002) the Government has launched a&#13;
  three-year rolling   PIP.   In  2003, it   has ensured that public       investment&#13;
  programming matches the PRSP priority actions and investment needs. However,&#13;
  donor coordination is still weak. The Ministry of Justice is pursuing a reform plan&#13;
  that includes legal and structural reforms and capacity building&#13;
&#13;
0 The Government has adopted a tourism strategy and is promoting the sector as a&#13;
  major source of economic growth in its poverty reduction strategy. As part of its&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
                                         5&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
        PRSP priority      actions  and rural   strategy, the    Government     is building,&#13;
        rehabilitating and maintaining infrastructure to improve market accessto the rural&#13;
        sector. The pace of other reforms and measures could nonetheless be accelerated.&#13;
        The critical land registration process and other land related legislations have not&#13;
        been undertaken, hampering economic activity such as sales, rental, and use as&#13;
        collateral. The Government recognizes the critical role of extension services and&#13;
        micro-credit in rural development. Faced with a land reform process that has led&#13;
        to land erosion and migration to the cities, the Government is supporting creation&#13;
        of small cooperatives among farmers to provide better extension services and&#13;
        credit.&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
   l    Private sector development (PSD) is considered one of the main pillars of the&#13;
        PRSP. However, Government efforts to improve the legislative, regulatory, fiscal&#13;
        and judicial   environment conducive to private sector development have been&#13;
        uneven. Notable progress has been made in updating laws, providing capacity&#13;
        building to the judiciary,   in developing a new tax and investment law (being&#13;
        discussed in the National Assembly) and in promoting the tourism sector (see&#13;
        above). However, the commercial framework still needs to be improved. The&#13;
        commercial laws are slated to be revised in 2004 together with the civil laws, but&#13;
        there are no plans yet to adopt a competition law or the OHADA      framework. The&#13;
        Government intends to launch a "guichet unique" in 2005 to facilitate registration&#13;
        and launching of businesses, especially foreign investors. However, no action has&#13;
        been taken in this regard yet.    GSTP will still need to adopt a legal business&#13;
        framework such as OHADA to facilitate PSD growth.&#13;
&#13;
14. The progress in the general program, while less than fully satisfactory, has been&#13;
    sufficient to allow tranche release. Progress against specific tranche release criteria as&#13;
    set out in Annex one of the Development Credit Agreement is described below.&#13;
&#13;
   *    Condition    1. Eliminate all ad hoc exemptions.&#13;
&#13;
   This condition     has been met. Elimination   of the ad hoc exemptions took place in&#13;
   2001. Analysis of customs statistics for the first nine months of 2001 suggested a&#13;
   distinct decline in volume of exemptions compared to the past.           No new ad hoc&#13;
   exemptions were granted in 2002 and up to end September 2003. However,&#13;
   exemptions under the law (non ad hoc) increased substantially in 2002.&#13;
&#13;
   a    Condition 2. Make fully operational the SYDONIA          automated system for the&#13;
        assessment of tax bases and the calculation of customs duties.&#13;
&#13;
   This condition has been met. The SYDONIA           system is fully functional. Customs is&#13;
   able to control the calculation of the tariff applicable to imports in a more systematic&#13;
   and efficient manner. A number of Customs professionals have been trained to use&#13;
   the system.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
    *   Condition    3. Introduce the unique taxpayer identification      number system to&#13;
        all revenue agencies to monitor taxpayers compliance.&#13;
&#13;
    This condition    has been met. The Governrnent has introduced a single taxpayer&#13;
    identification number system with 6 digits for the fiscal administration in December&#13;
    2001. The identifier      is functional  since January 2002 and is being used by&#13;
    Government entities such as the Customs, Tax Directorate and Central Bank, and by&#13;
    the private bank (IBSTP). The efficiency of the identification system is expected to be&#13;
    enhanced in the future through an integrated computerized registration system that&#13;
    would correct some problem with multiple entries.&#13;
&#13;
    *   Condition 4. Carry out PERs for the education and health sectors.&#13;
&#13;
   This condition has been met. A draft health PER was provided to the World Bank in&#13;
   August 2002 and a draft education PER in April 2003.&#13;
&#13;
        Condition 5. Implement      a general sales tax.&#13;
&#13;
   This condition     has been met. In 2002, the decree instituting the general services&#13;
   sales tax was published in the official journal and its application decree was adopted.&#13;
   The tax was incorporated into the 2002 budget, but the implementation process met&#13;
   initially with technical difficulties. After addressing the difficulties, the Government&#13;
   implemented the services tax in January 2003. The Government is now further&#13;
   reinforcing tax administration to reduce tax evasion and improve collection rates&#13;
&#13;
                                     IV. CONCLUSION&#13;
&#13;
15. In view of the overall program and progress with the implementation of the program&#13;
    supported by the Credit, and in compliance with the specific conditions of release as&#13;
    described in paragraph 14, the Association has informed            the Borrower of the&#13;
    availability of the second tranche of SDR 1.9 million, US$2.7 million equivalent as of&#13;
   May 3,2004.&#13;
&amp;#12;&#13;
</ml:original-txt><ml:search-metadata><doc id="3420300">
        <url>
            http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2004/05/3420300/sao-tome-principe-public-resource-management-credit-prmc-project-release-second-tranche-full-compliance
        </url>
        <availablein>English</availablein>
        <url_friendly_title>http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/2004/05/3420300/sao-tome-principe-public-resource-management-credit-prmc-project-release-second-tranche-full-compliance</url_friendly_title>
        <new_url>2004/05/3420300/sao-tome-principe-public-resource-management-credit-prmc-project-release-second-tranche-full-compliance</new_url>
        <disclosure_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</disclosure_date>
        <disclosure_type>NA</disclosure_type>
        <ext_pub_date>2010-07-01T00:00:00Z</ext_pub_date>
        <disclstat>Disclosed</disclstat>
        <txturl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2004/05/13/000160016_20040513110308/Rendered/INDEX/28965.txt</txturl>
        <pdfurl>http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/WDSP/IB/2004/05/13/000160016_20040513110308/Rendered/PDF/28965.pdf</pdfurl>
        <credit_no>3429</credit_no>
        <datestored>2004-05-13T00:00:00Z</datestored>
        <docdt>2004-05-06T00:00:00Z</docdt>
        <totvolnb>1</totvolnb>
        <versiontyp>Gray cover</versiontyp>
        <versiontyp_key>1309938</versiontyp_key>
        <volnb>1</volnb>
        <repnme>
            Sao Tome and Principe - Public Resource
            Management Credit (PRMC) Project : release of the Second
            Tranche - full compliance
        </repnme>
        <abstracts>
            The reform program for Sao Tome and
            Principe, supported by the Public Resource Management
            Credit, has three key components: (1) improving domestic
            resource mobilization; (2) strengthening public expenditure
            management; and (3) continuing implementation of the public
            enterprise reform program. The Credit has complemented and
            deepened actions already agreed under the programs of the
            IMF, the African Development Bank and the European Union in
            the area of public expenditure management.  This report
            summarizes progress in the execution of the reform program
            and actions taken by the Government of Sao Tome and Principe
            (GSTP) to meet the specific conditions for the release of
            the second tranche. The report concludes that conditions for
            the release of the second tranche have been met and
            sufficient progress has been made in implementation of the
            overall program of reforms set out in the Letter of
            Development Policy (LDP) despite political instability and
            lack of institutional capacity. In addition, the Government
            is receiving Bank technical assistance in developing
            petroleum revenue legislation and building transparent
            institutional frameworks in the financial and petroleum
            sectors institutional frameworks that would be transparent
            and beneficial to the long term development of the country.
            In light of this performance, this report proposes that the
            second tranche of the Credit, in the amount of SDR 1.9
            million be released for disbursement.
        </abstracts>
        <docna>
            Sao Tome and Principe - Public Resource
            Management Credit (PRMC) Project : release of the Second
            Tranche - full compliance
        </docna>
        <display_title>Sao Tome and Principe - Public
            Resource Management Credit (PRMC) Project : release of the
            Second Tranche - full compliance</display_title>
        <listing_relative_url>/projects/documents/2004/05/3420300/sao-tome-principe-public-resource-management-credit-prmc-project-release-second-tranche-full-compliance</listing_relative_url>
        <projn>ST-Public Resource Management  - Ta -- P073904</projn>
        <docty>Tranche Release Document</docty>
        <subtopic>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation,Environmental Economics &amp; Policies,Public Sector Economics,National Governance,Banks &amp; Banking Reform</subtopic>
        <teratopic>Health, Nutrition and Population</teratopic>
        <count>Sao Tome and Principe</count>
        <geo_region_mdks>
            <geo_region_mdk>World!$!80475</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>Sub-Saharan Africa!$!80473</geo_region_mdk>
            <geo_region_mdk>West Africa!$!80474</geo_region_mdk>
        </geo_region_mdks>
        <entityids>
            <entityid>000160016_20040513110308</entityid>
        </entityids>
        <admreg>Africa,Africa</admreg>
        <subsc>Central government administration</subsc>
        <lang>English</lang>
        <historic_topic>Health, Nutrition and Population</historic_topic>
        <prdln>IBRD/IDA</prdln>
        <sectr>Public Administration, Law, and Justice</sectr>
        <majdocty>Project Documents</majdocty>
        <keywd>
            Tranche releases; Compliance; Reform
            implementation; Conditionality; Institutional capacity;
            Political instability; Petroleum legislation; Transparency
            in governance; Institutional framework; Structural reform;
            Macroeconomic performance; Fiscal performance; Public
            expenditures; Access to services; Public resources management
            administrative capacity,Administrative
            Reform,Air,audits,budget deficit,budget execution,budget
            management,budgetary expenditures,budgetary funds,budgetary
            support,Capital expenditures,civil service,competition
            law,credit approval,Debt,debt management,Debt
            Relief,decree,economic activity,economic growth,economic
            reform,education,electricity,enterprise
            reform,evasion,exchange rate,execution,fiscal,fiscal
            administration,fiscal deficit,fiscal discipline,fiscal
            performance,fiscal policy,foreign assets,foreign
            investors,Government efforts,Government
            entities,health,imports,Inflation,institutional
            capacity,judiciary,laws,legal framework,legislative
            elections,Macroeconomic performance,macroeconomic
            stability,migration,oil,policy environment,political
            instability,primary health care,private
            sector,privatization,public administration,public
            expenditure,public expenditure management,Public
            expenditures,public investment,public procurement,public
            resources,public services,public transport,resource
            mobilization,revenue management,revenue
            mobilization,schools,social sectors,social services,Tax,tax
            administration,Tax revenue,technical assistance,terms of trade,transparency,treasury
        </keywd>
        <owner>AFT: PREM 4 (AFTP4)</owner>
        <lndinstr>
            Technical Assistance Loan
        </lndinstr>
        <geo_regions>
            <geo_region>World</geo_region>
            <geo_region>Sub-Saharan Africa</geo_region>
            <geo_region>West Africa</geo_region>
        </geo_regions>
        <repnb>28965</repnb>
    </doc></ml:search-metadata><ml:annotations><ml:concepts><ml:concept>Economic Policy and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Finance and Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomics and Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Distributional Analysis</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty Reduction and Equity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty and Inequality</ml:concept><ml:concept>General Public Administration Sector</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance and Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Administration</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector and Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protections and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Vulnerability and Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Financial Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Private Sector Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic and Structural Policies</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Growth</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health, Nutrition and Population</ml:concept><ml:concept>Poverty</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Social Protection and Labor</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring and Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Trends, Macroeconomic Variables</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Expenditure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banks</ml:concept><ml:concept>Structural Measures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Structural Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Denationalization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Deregulation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Destatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Divestiture of Ownership</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal &amp; Monetary Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Consolidation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Decentralization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Governance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Governance and Structural Fiscal Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Rules</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Sustainability</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macro-Fiscal Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt Policy and Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Debt Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>HIPC</ml:concept><ml:concept>Efficiency of Public Expenditures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Expenditures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Financial Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Spending</ml:concept><ml:concept>Capital Expenditures</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Sector Investment Plan</ml:concept><ml:concept>Contract Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Governance Institutions</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Arrangements in Public Procurement</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Capacity</ml:concept><ml:concept>Institutional Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Legal Regulatory Framework</ml:concept><ml:concept>State-Society Relations</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wage Setting</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages, Compensation and Benefits</ml:concept><ml:concept>Health Monitoring &amp; Evaluation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Economic Development</ml:concept><ml:concept>Banking</ml:concept><ml:concept>Macroeconomic Performance</ml:concept><ml:concept>Government Expenditure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Central Banking Institutional Set-up</ml:concept><ml:concept>Structural Policy and Reform</ml:concept><ml:concept>Current Account</ml:concept><ml:concept>Privatization</ml:concept><ml:concept>Infrastructure</ml:concept><ml:concept>Inflation</ml:concept><ml:concept>Fiscal Policy</ml:concept><ml:concept>Debt</ml:concept><ml:concept>Heavily Indebted Poor Countries (HIPC)</ml:concept><ml:concept>Managing Public Finances</ml:concept><ml:concept>Public Investment Management</ml:concept><ml:concept>Wages</ml:concept></ml:concepts><ml:geo-regions><ml:geo-region>Africa</ml:geo-region><ml:geo-region>São Tomé and Príncipe</ml:geo-region></ml:geo-regions></ml:annotations></ml:doc-envelope>